<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersDrama PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Drama//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersDrama.dtd" >
%PersDrama;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Trinummus:  The Three Pieces of Money</title>
<author>T. Maccius Plautus</author>
<editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.DLI2;
</titleStmt>
&Perseus.publish;

<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>The Comedies of Plautus</title>
<editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>G. Bell and Sons</publisher>
<date>1912</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction method="silent" status="medium">&Perseus.DE;</correction>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="act"/>
<state n="chunk" unit="scene"/>
<state unit="line"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="de">German</language>
<language id="fr">French</language>
<language id="it">Italian</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change><date>1-Jun-01</date>
<respStmt><name>AEM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
<item>
$Log: pl.trin_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-12-07 18:50:31  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.4  2009/06/17 20:57:56  rsingh04
don't chunk by TLN line cause they don't seem to be correct and cause problems

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 20:50:27  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 16:22:24  packel
new XML version

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:59:51  packel
Converted to XML

Revision 1.14  2003/07/01 22:17:33  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.13  2001/08/21 18:49:31  amahoney
get translator's name into correct place in meta-data, use same form of author as in Latin

Revision 1.12  2001/08/08 17:55:30  amahoney
get rid of the silly italics (marking words that "don't occur" in the Latin)

Revision 1.11  2001/08/03 20:53:28  amahoney
fix stage directions at end of scenes (which had unmatched parentheses
in the original -- very nasty)

Revision 1.10  2001/08/03 20:50:02  amahoney
fix spurious italics in lemmata

Revision 1.9  2001/08/02 21:22:41  amahoney
add header to introduction stuff, to tidy up the tocs

Revision 1.8  2001/08/01 21:34:11  amahoney
use full speaker names

Revision 1.7  2001/08/01 19:16:31  amahoney
get the tln lines in place;  correct funder

Revision 1.6  2001/07/10 21:15:33  amahoney
put a TLN at the start of each scene, and make the scenes match the Latin to facilitate chunking

Revision 1.5  2001/07/05 21:23:36  amahoney
correct citations so we can use both schemes (the one with fewer slots
must always be first), and drop page breaks

Revision 1.4  2001/07/03 18:21:30  amahoney
fix the broken characters

Revision 1.3  2001/06/29 19:04:21  amahoney
tidy up line numbers, making citation scheme match the Latin

Revision 1.2  2001/06/21 17:39:36  amahoney
put in rudimentary line numbers, based on the footnotes

Revision 1.1  2001/06/19 21:34:36  amahoney
now they all parse, and the scenes are correctly identified

</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text lang="en">
<body>

<castList>
<castGroup>
<head>IN THE PROLOGUE.</head>
<castItem type="role"><role>LUXURY.</role></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>POVERTY.</role></castItem>
</castGroup>
<castGroup>
<head>IN THE PLAY.</head>
<castItem type="role"><role>CHARMIDES, </role><roleDesc>an Athenian merchant.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>LESBONICUS, </role><roleDesc>the son of Charmides.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>CALLICLES, </role><roleDesc>a friend of Charmides.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>MEGARONIDES, </role><roleDesc>a friend of Callicles.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>STASIMUS, </role><roleDesc>the servant of Charmides and Lesbonicus.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>PHILTO, </role><roleDesc>a wealthy Athenian,</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>LYSITELES, </role><roleDesc>the son of Philto, and a friend of Lesbonicus.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>A SHARPER.</role></castItem>
</castGroup>
</castList>

<stage>Scene--A Street in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>: the house of CHARMIDES on one side, and that of PHILTO on the other.</stage>

<div1 type="act" n="intro">
<head>Introduction</head>
<div2 type="scene" n="subject">
<head>THE SUBJECT.</head>

<p>CHARMIDES, a wealthy Athenian, his property having been much duninished by the reckless conduct of his son, goes abroad. His dissolute son, Lesbonicus, being left behind at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, consumes the little resources left him, and then puts up his father's house for sale. At his departure, Charmides has entrusted his interests and the care of his son and daughter to his friend Callicles and has also informed him that in his house there is a treasure buried as a reserve against future contingencies. In order that this may not be lost, Cailicles buys the house of Lesbonicus for a small sum. Ignorant of his reason for doing so, his fellow-citizens censure him for his conduct, and accuse him of a breach of good faith in ministering to the extravagance of Lesbonicus by supplying him with money. For this reason Megaronides expostulates with his friend Callicles, and greatly censures him; on which, Callicles, in self-defence, entrusts him with the secret of the treasure. Charmides having left behind him a grown-up daughter in the care of Callicles, Lysiteles, a young man of rank and character, falls in love with her, and through his father, Philto, asks her in marriage. Her brother, Lesbonicus, is not averse to the match, but refuses to let her marry without giving her a portion; and he offers her to Lysiteles, on condition that he will receive as her marriage-portion a piece of land near the city, the sole remnant of his fortune. This, however, Lysiteles refuses to accept. In the mean time, Callicles, at the suggestion of Megaronides, determines to give the young woman a dowry out of the treasure buried in the house which he has bought; but that Lesbonicus may not suspect whence the money really comes, a Sharper is hired, with instructions to pretend that he brings letters from Charmides with a thousand gold pieces as a portion for his daughter when she should marry. It happens, that while the Sharper is on his way with his pretended errand to the abode of Callicles, Charmides, having unexpectedly returned to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is going towards his house. He meets the Sharper, who discloses his errand and attempts to impose upon Charmides, who thereupon discovers himself Charmides then meets his servant Stasimus, who tells him of the purchase of his house by Callicles, whereon he conceives himself to have been betrayed by his friend. Afterwards, on discovering the truth, he praises the fidelity of Callicles, and bestows his daughter on Lysiteles, with a portion of a thousand gold pieces, and, at the intercession of Lysiteles, he forgives his son Lesbonicus, and informs him that he is to be married to the daughter of Callicles.

</p></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="argument">
<head>THE ACROSTIC ARGUMENT. <note anchored="yes" place="inline">[Supposed to have been written by Priscian the Grammarian.]</note></head>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES,</speaker><p> going abroad, entrusts a treasure (<foreign lang="la">Thesaurum</foreign>) secretly hidden, and all his property (<foreign lang="la">Rem</foreign>), to his friend Callicles. He (<foreign lang="la">Istoc</foreign>) being absent, his son wantonly squanders his estate. For (<foreign lang="la">Nam</foreign>) he sells even the house: <foreign lang="la">and</foreign> Callicles makes purchase of it. His sister, a maiden (<foreign lang="la">Virgo</foreign>) without a dowry, is asked <foreign lang="la">in marriage.</foreign> That in a less degree (<foreign lang="la">Minus</foreign>), with censure, Callicles may bestow on her a dowry, he commissions one (<foreign lang="la">Mandat</foreign>) to say that he has brought the gold from her father. When (<foreign lang="la">Ut</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">the Counterfeit</foreign> has reached the house, the old man (<foreign lang="la">Senex</foreign>), Charmides, as he has <foreign lang="la">just</foreign> returned, disappoints him; his children then are married.
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="prologue">
<div2 type="scene" n="0">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LUXURY and POVERTY.<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The Prologue</lemma>:  This Prologue is one of the few figurative ones to be found in the Comedies of Plautus. He appropriately represents Luxury as introducing her daughter Poverty to the abode of the dissipated Lesbonicus. Claudian has a somewhat similar passage in his poem to Rufinus:
<quote lang="la"><l>Et Luxus, populator opum, cui, semper adh&aelig;rens,</l>
<l>Infelix humili gressu comitatur Egestas.</l></quote>
"And Luxury, the waster of wealth, whom, ever attending, wretched Poverty accompanies with humble step." It has been justly observed, that Plautus here avoids a fault which he often falls into, of acquainting the audience with too much of the plot.</note></stage>
<sp><speaker>LUXURY.</speaker><p> Follow me this way, daughter, that you may perform your office.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>POVERTY.</speaker><p> I am following, but I know not what to say will be the end of our journey.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LUXURY.</speaker><p> 'Tis here. See, this is the house. Now go you in.
(<stage>Exit POVERTY, who enters the house of CHARMIDES.</stage>)</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LUXURY.</speaker><p> <stage>to the AUDIENCE</stage>. Now, that no one of you may be mistaken, in a few words I will conduct you into the right path, if, indeed, you promise to listen to me. First, then, I will now tell you who I am, and who she is who has gone in here <stage>pointing to the house</stage>, if you give your attention. In the first place, Plautus has given me the name of Luxury, and then he has willed that this Poverty should be my daughter. But why, at my suggestion, she has just entered here, listen and give attentive ear while I inform you. There is a certain young man who is living in this house; by my assistance he has squandered away his paternal estate. Since I see that there is nothing left for him to support me, I have given him my daughter, together with whom to pass his life. But expect nothing about the plot of this play: the old men who will come hither will disclose the matter to you. The name of this play in the Greek is "The Treasure" [Thesaurus]; Philemon wrote it<milestone n="19" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Philemon wrote it</lemma>:  Not only Philemon, but Menander also, wrote a play, entitled the "Treasure."</note>: Plautus translated it into Latin<milestone n="19" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In Latin</lemma>:  "Barbare" We learn from Festus, and other authors, that the Greeks were in the habit of calling all nations, without exception, but themselves, "barbarians." Hence the present expression, which literally meant into barbarous language."</note>, and gave it the name of "The Three Pieces of Money" [Trinummus]. Now, he begs this of you, that it may be allowed the play to keep that name. Thus much have I to say. Farewell. Attend in silence. <stage>(Exit.)</stage>

</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="1">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="23" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter MEGARONIDES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> To reprove one's friend for a fault that deserves it, is a thankless task; but sometimes 'tis useful and 'tis profitable. Therefore, this day will I soundly reprove my friend for a fault that much deserves it. Unwilling am I, did not my friendship bid me do it. For this faultiness has encroached too much upon good morals, so drooping now are nearly all of them. But while they are in this distempered state, bad morals, in the mean time, have sprung up most plenteously, like well-watered plants; nor is there now anything abundant here but these same bad morals. Of them you may now reap a most plenteous harvest: and here a set of men are making the favour of a few of much more value than that in which they may benefit the many. Thus private interests outdo that which is to the public advantage--interests which in many points are a hindrance, and a nuisance, and cause an obstruction both to private and to public welfare.
</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="39" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter CALLICLES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> <stage>as he enters</stage>. I wish our household God<milestone n="39" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Household God</lemma>:  Literally, "Lar." The Lares were the household Gods, or tutelary Deities of each family. The figures of them were kept, among the Romans, near the hearth, in the "Lararium" which was a recess formed for that purpose, and in which prayers were offered up on rising in the morning. There were both public and private Lares. The latter were by some thought to have been identical with the "Manes," or "shades," of the ancestors of the family occupying the house. The public Lares were the "Urbani," presiding over the cities; "Rustici," over the country; "Compitales," over crossroads; and "Marini," over the sea. Varro tells us that there were 265 stations for the statues of the Lares at the corner of the streets of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. "Lar" was an Etrurian word, signifying "noble," or "lord." The Greeks adorned their household Gods with the leaves of the plane-tree, the Romans with ears of corn. This was especially done on entering a new house, on which the wish was expressed that it might turn out prosperous, lucky, happy, and fortunate to the new occupants. "Quod bonum, faustum, felix, fortunatumque sit." Callicles here expresses this wish on taking possession of the house which he has just bought of Lesbonicus.</note> to be graced with a chaplet. Wife<milestone n="40" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Wife</lemma>:  Being at the door of his house, before shutting it, he calls to his wife within. His kind wish as to the duration of her life he expresses just as he shuts the door.</note> <stage>addressing her within</stage>, pay him due respect, that this dwelling may turn out for us prosperous, lucky, happy, and fortunate; and <stage>in a lower voice</stage> that, as soon as I possibly may, I may see you dead and gone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> This is he who in his old age has become a child<milestone n="43" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Has become a child</lemma>:  He means to say that he has become a boy from the fact of his being in need of correction.</note>--who has been guilty of a fault that deserves correction. I will accost the man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> <stage>looking around</stage>. Whose voice is it that sounds near me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Of one who wishes you well, if you are as I desire you to be; but, if you are otherwise, of one who is your enemy, and is angry with you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Health to you, O my friend and years'-mate! How are you, Megaronides?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> And, i' faith<milestone n="49" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And i' faith</lemma>:  "Hercle," "by Hercules;" "Ecastor," "by Castor "Edepol," "by Pollux," or "by the temple of Pollux," and "Pol," "by Pollux,' were the every-day oaths in the mouths of the Romans, and were used for the purpose of adding weight to the asseverations of the speaker. A literal translation of them throughout this work would hardly be in accordance with the euphony required by the English ear. They are therefore rendered throughout by such expressions as "i' faith," "troth," "by my troth," &amp;c.</note> health to you, Callicles! Are you well? Have you been well?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I am well, and I have been still better.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> And how does your wife do? How is she?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Better than I wish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> 'Tis well, i' faith, for you, that she is alive and well</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Troth, I believe that you are glad if I have any misfortune.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> That which I have, I wish for all my friends as well.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Harkye, how does your wife do?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> She is immortal; she lives, and is likely to live.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I' faith, you tell me good news; and I pray the Gods that, surviving you, she may last out your life.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> By my troth! if indeed she were only married to yourself, I could wish it sincerely.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Do you wish that we should exchange?--that I should take yours, and you mine? I'd be making you not to get a bit the better of the bargain of me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Indeed, I fancy<milestone n="61" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Indeed I fancy</lemma>:  "Neque," which implies a negative, seems to be more in accordance with the sense of the passage than the affirmative "nempe," which is the reading of Ritschel; it has therefore been adopted.</note> you would not be surprising me unawares.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Aye, faith, I should cause you not to be knowing<milestone n="62" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Not to be knowing</lemma>:  That is, "the risk you would run in taking her or your wife."</note> the thing you were about.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Keep what you've got; the evil that we know is the best. But if I were now to take one that I know not, I should not know what to do.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> In good sooth, just as one lives<milestone n="65" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Just as one lives</lemma>:  The meaning of this passage seems to be somewhat obscure, and many of the Editions give this line to Megaronides. It is probable however, that Callicles intends, as a consolation for them both, to say that life itself is a blessing, and that they ought not by unnecessary anxieties to shorten it, but rather to submit with patience to their domestic grievances.</note> a long life, one lives a happy life.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> But give your attention to this, and have done with your joking, for I am come hither to you for a given purpose.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Why have you come?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> That I may rebuke you soundly with many harsh words. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Me, do you say?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Is there any one else here besides you and me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> <stage>looking about</stage>. There is no one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Why, then, do you ask if 'tis you I mean to rebuke? Unless, indeed, you think that I am about to reprove my own self. For if your former principles now flag in you, or if the manners of the age are working a change in your disposition, and if you preserve not those of the olden time, but are catching up these new ones, you will strike all your friends with a malady so direful, that they will turn sick at seeing and hearing you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> How comes it into your mind to utter these expressions?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Because it becomes all good men and all good women to have a care to keep suspicion and guilt away from themselves.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Both cannot be done. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Why so?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Do you ask? I am the keeper of my own heart so as not to admit guilt there; suspicion is centred in the heart of another. For if now I should suspect that you had stolen the crown from the head of <placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName> in the Capitol<milestone n="84" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In the Capitol</lemma>:  Plautus does not much care about anachronism or dramatic precision; though the plot of the play is derived from the Greek, and the scene laid at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he makes frequent reference to Roman localities and manners. It is probable that the expression here employed was proverbial at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, to signify a deed of daring and unscrupulous character. From ancient writers we learn that there was a statue of <placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName> seated in a chariot, placed on the roof of the Capitoline Temple. Tarquinius Priscus employed Etrurian artists to make a statue of pottery for this purpose; and the original chariot, with its four horses, was made of baked clay. In later and more opulent times, the crown placed on the statue was of great value, so much so as to act as a temptation to one Petilius, who attempted to steal it, and being caught in the fact, was afterwards nicknamed "Capitolinus." Mention is again made of this status in the Men&aelig;chmi, act v, sc. b. l. 38.</note>, the statue which stands on the highest summit of the temple; if you had not done so, and still it should please me to suspect you, how could you prevent me from suspecting you? But I am anxious to know what this matter is.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Have you any friend or intimate acquaintance whose judgment is correct?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Troth, I'll tell you without reserve. There are some whom I know to be friends; there are some whom I suspect to be so, but whose dispositions and feelings I am unable to discover, whether they incline to the side of a friend or an enemy; but of my assured friends, you are the most assured. If you know that I have done anything unwittingly or wrongfully, and if you do not accuse me of it, then you yourself will be to blame.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I know it; and if I had come hither to you for any other purpose, you request what is right.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> If you have anything to say, I am waiting for it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Then, first of all, you are badly spoken of in general conversation by the public. Your fellow-citizens are calling you greedy of grovelling gain<milestone n="100" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Greedy of grovelling gain</lemma>:  Plautus makes this into one word 'turpilucricupidum." Probably it was used as a nickname for avaricious persons. It is here attempted to be expressed by an alliteration. <placeName key="tgn,1136756">Thornton</placeName> renders it "Gripeall."</note>; and then, again, there are others who nickname you a vulture<milestone n="101" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A vulture</lemma>:  Both on account of the sordid and greedy habits of that bird, and because, as is stated in the next line, it cares not which side supplies its maw when it follows the course of contending armies.</note>, and say that you care but little whether you devour enemies or fellow-citizens. Since I have heard these things said against you, I have, to my misery, been sadly agitated.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> It is, and it is not, in my power, Megaronides: as to their saying this, that is not in my power; as to their saying this deservedly, that is in my power.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Was this Charmides a friend of yours? <stage>He points to the house of CHARMIDES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> He both is and he was. That you may believe it to be so, I will tell you a circumstance as a proof. For after this son of his had squandered away his fortune, and he saw himself being reduced to poverty, and that his daughter was grown up a young woman, and that she who was both her mother and his own wife was dead; as he himself was about to go hence to Seleueia<milestone n="112" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Hence to <placeName key="tgn,6005333">Seleucia</placeName></lemma>:  There were several cities of this name. The one in <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, a maritime city on the Orontes, near <placeName key="tgn,7002351">Antioch</placeName>, is probably here referred to.</note> he committed to my charge the maiden his daughter, and all his property, and that profligate son. These, I think, he would not have entrusted to me if he had been unfriendly to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> What say you as to the young man, who you see to be thus profligate, and who has been entrusted to your care and confidence? Why do you not reform him? Why do you not train him to frugal habits? It would have been somewhat more just for you to give attention to that matter, if you could have somehow made him a better man, and not for you yourself to be a party to the same disreputable conduct, and share your dishonour with his disgrace?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What have I done?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> That which a bad man would do.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> That is no name of mine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Have you not bought this house from that young man? <stage>A pause.</stage> Why are you silent? This, where you yourself are now living. <stage>He points to the house of CHARMIDES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I did buy it, and I gave the money for it,--forty min&aelig;<milestone n="126" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Forty min&aelig;</lemma>:  Unless he adds the adjective "aurea," "golden," Plautus always means silver "min&aelig;." The "mina" was the sixtieth part of the Attic talent, and contained one hundred "drachm&aelig;," of about ninepence three-farthings each.</note>, to the young man himself, into his own hand.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> You gave the money, do you say?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> 'Twas done; and I am not sorry 'twas done.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I' faith--a young man committed to untrusty keeping. Have you not by these means given him a sword with which to slay himself? For, prithee, what else is it, your giving ready money to a young man who loves women, and weak in intellect, with which to complete his edifice of folly which he had already commenced?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Ought I not to have paid him the money?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> You ought not to have paid him; nor ought you either to have bought anything of or sold anything to him; nor should you have provided him with the means of becoming worse. Have you not taken in the person who was entrusted to you? Have you not driven out of his house the man who entrusted him to you? By my faith, a pretty trust, and a faithful guardianship! Leave him to take care of himself; he would manage his own affairs much better.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> You overpower me, Megaronides, with your accusations, in a manner so strange, that what was privately entrusted to my secrecy, fidelity, and constancy, for me to tell it to no one, nor make it public, the same I am now compelled to entrust to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Whatever you shall entrust to me, you shall take up the same where you have laid it down.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Look round you, then, that no overlooker may be near us <stage>MEGARONIDES looks on every side</stage>; and look around every now and then, I beg of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I am listening if you have aught to say.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> If you will be silent, I will speak. At the time when Charmides set out hence for foreign parts, he showed me a treasure in this house, here in a certain closet---- <stage>He starts as if he hears a noise.</stage> But do look around.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> There is no one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Of Philippean pieces<milestone n="152" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Of Philippean pieces</lemma>:  These were gold coins much in circulation throughout <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, struck by Philip, King of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>.</note> to the number of three thousand. Alone with myself, in tears, he entreated me, by our friendship and by my honour, not to entrust this to his son, nor yet to any one, from whom that might come to his knowledge. Now, if he comes back hither safe, I will restore to him his own. But if anything should happen to him, at all events I have a stock from which to give a marriage-portion to his daughter, who has been entrusted to me, that I may settle her in a condition of life that befits her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> O ye immortal gods! how soon, in a few words, you have made another man of me; I came to you quite a different person. But, as you have begun, proceed further to inform me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What shall I tell you? How that this worthless fellow had almost utterly ruined his caution and my own trustiness and all the secret.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> How so?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Because, while I was in the country for only six days, in my absence and without my knowledge, without consulting me, he advertised with bills<milestone n="168" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Advertised with bills</lemma>:  The method among the Romans of letting, or selling houses, was similar to ours. A ball was fixed upon the house, or some conspicuous place near it, inscribed with "&AElig;des locand&aelig;," "This house to be lot," or "&AElig;des vendund&aelig;," "This house for sale."</note> this house for sale.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> The wolf hungered the more, and opened his mouth the wider; he watched till<milestone n="170" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">He watched till</lemma>:  He alludes to the conduct of Lesbonicus, who watched for the absence of his guardian, Callicles, that he might sell the house. This he would attempt to do, probably, on the plea that his father, not having been heard of for a long time, must be presumed to be dead, and the house has consequently descended to him, as his heir</note> the dog went to sleep; and intended to carry off the whole entire flock.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I' faith, he would have done it, if the dogs had not perceived this in time. But now, in my turn, I wish to ask you this: let me know what it was my duty for me to do. Whether was it right for me to discover the treasure to him, against which very thing his father had cautioned me, or should I have permitted another person to become the owner of this house? Ought that money to have belonged to him who bought the house? In preference, I myself bought the house; I gave the money for the sake of the treasure, that I might deliver it safe to my friend. I have not, then, bought this house either for myself or for my own use; for Charmides have I bought it back again; from my own store have I paid the money. This, whether it has been done rightfully or wrongfully, I own, Megaronides, that I have done. Here, then, are my misdeeds; here, then, is my avarice. Is it for these things that they spread false reports against me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Stay--you have overcome your corrector. You have tied my tongue; there is nothing for me to say in answer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Now I entreat you to aid me with your assistance and counsel, and to share this duty of mine in common with me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I promise you my assistance.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Where, then, will you be a short time hence?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> At home.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Do you wish anything else?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Attend to the trust reposed in you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> That is being carefully done.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> But how say you----?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What do you want?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Where is the young man living now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> This back part<milestone n="194" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The back part</lemma>:  "Posticulum" probably means detached buildings at the back of the house, and within the garden walls, which adjoin the "posticum" or "posticula," the "back door" or "garden-gate."</note> of the building he retained when he sold the house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> That I wanted to know. Now, then, go at once. But what say you, where is the damsel now? She is at your house, I suppose?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> She is so; I take care of her almost as much as of my own daughter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> You act properly.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Before I go away, are you going to ask me anything else?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Farewell. <stage>Exit CALLICLES.</stage> Really, there is nothing more foolish or more stupid, nothing more lying or indeed more tattling, more self-conceited or more forsworn, than those men of this city everlastingly gossiping about, whom they call Busybodies<milestone n="202" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Call Busybodies</lemma>:  The word "Scurra," which is here rendered "busybody," originally meant "a fellow-townsman," well to do in life, and a pleasant companion. In time, however, the word came to have a bad signification attached to it, and to mean an idle fellow, who did nothing but go about cracking his jokes at the expense of others, gossiping, and mischief-making, and at last to signify "a clown," "buffoon," or "mimic" on the stage. These men are most probably termed here "assidui," "everlasting gossipers," from a habit which many people have of making frequent calls on their neighbours, sitting down, and never thinking of taking their departure till they have exhausted all their stock of evil-speaking, lying, and slandering. Gossiping was notoriously the propensity of the Athenians. Numbers did nothing but saunter about the city, and go from spot to spot, with the question <foreign lang="greek">ti kainou=,</foreign> "Any news?" Few will fail to remember the censure of them in the Seventeenth chapter of the Acts of the Apostles, v. 21: "For all the Athenians and strangers which were there spent their time in nothing else, but either to tell, or to hear some new thing."</note>. And thus have I enlisted myself in their ranks together with them; who have been the swallower of the false tales of those who pretend that they know everything, and yet know nothing. They know, forsooth, what each person either has in his mind, or is likely to have; they know what the king whispered in the ear of the queen; they know what Juno talked about in conversation with <placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName>; that which neither is nor is likely to be, do these fellows know. Whether they praise or dispraise any one they please, falsely or truly, they care not a straw, so they know that which they choose to know. All people were in the habit of saying that this Callicles was unworthy of this state, and, himself, to exist, who had despoiled this young man of his property. From the reports of these tale-bearers, in my ignorance I rushed forward to rebuke my guiltless friend. But if the authority was always required from the foundation, upon which they speak of anything they have heard, unless that clearly appeared, the matter ought to be to the peril and loss of the tale-bearer. If this were so, it would be for the public benefit. I would cause those to be but few, who now that which they do not know<milestone n="221" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">They do not know</lemma>:  That is, "who only pretend to know."</note>, and I would make them have their silly chattering more restricted.  <stage>(Exit.)</stage>
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="2">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="223" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYSITELES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I am revolving many things in my mind at once, and much uneasiness do I find in thinking upon them. I tease, and fret, and wear myself out; a mind that enjoins a hard task<milestone n="226" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">That enjoins a hard task</lemma>:  "Exercitor" means the "instructor or "training master" in the Gymnastic exercises. Of course, to beginners, the "exercitores" would be hard task-masters.</note> is now my master. But this thing is not clear to me, nor has it been enough studied by me, which pursuit of these two I should rather follow for myself; which of the two I should think of the greater stability for passing my life therein: whether it were preferable for me to devote myself to love or to aggrandisement; in which alternative there is more enjoyment of life in passing one's days. On this point I am not fully satisfied. But this I think I'll do, that I may weigh both the points together, I must be both judge and culprit in this trial: I'll do so--I like it much. First of all, I will enlarge upon the pursuits of love, how they conduce to one's welfare. Love never expects any but the willing man to throw himself in his toils; these he seeks for, these he follows up, and craftily counsels against their interests. He is a fawning flatterer, a rapacious grappler<milestone n="239" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A rapacious grappler</lemma>: -- "Harpago" means either a "grappling-iron" or a "flesh-hook." It was often made in the form of a hand, with the fingers bent inwards. The grappling-iron was used to throw at the enemy's ship, where it seized the rigging and dragged the vessel within reach, so that it might be easily boarded and destroyed. Cupid is so called here, figuratively, from his insidious approaches, and the difficulty which his victims have in shaking him off</note>, a deceiver, a sweet-tooth, a spoiler, a corrupter of men who court retirement, a pryer into secrets. For he that is in love, soon as ever he has been smitten with the kisses of the object that he loves, forthwith his substance vanishes out of doors and melts away. "Give me this thing<milestone n="244" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Give me this thing</lemma>:  This is supposed to be pronounced in a mincing or affected way, to imitate the wheedling manners of the frail tempter.</note>, my honey, if you love me, if you possibly can." And then this gudgeon says: "O apple of my eye, be it so: both that shall be given you, and still more, if you wish it to be given." Then does she strike while he is wavering<milestone n="247" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">While he is wavering</lemma>:  Literally, "she strikes him as he hangs." Lindemann seems to think that there is a play upon the word "pendentem," which would apply either to the slave, who, according to the barbarous custom of the Romans, was lashed as he hung from the hook to which he was fastened by the hands, or to the lover who is hesitating between assent and refusal; on which she, by her artfulness--"ferit"--"strikes the decisive blow." Terence has the expression "ferior munere," "to strike with a present."</note>; and now she begs for more. Not enough is this evil, unless there is still something more--what to eat, what to drink. A thing that creates<milestone n="250" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A thing that creates</lemma>:  This passage is here read with a period after "comest," and not after "sumpti," as Ritschel's edition has it. This seems more agreeable to the sense of the passage, which is, however, probably in a corrupt state.</note> a further expense, the favour of a night is granted; a whole family is then introduced for her--a wardrobe-woman<milestone n="252" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Wardrobe-woman</lemma>:  The duty of the "vestiplica" would be to fold up and try the clothes of her mistress. These slaves were also called "vestispic&aelig;," and servants "a veste."</note> a perfume-keeper<milestone n="252" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A perfume-keeper</lemma>:  The "unctor" was probably a male slave, whose duty it was to procure and keep the perfumes and unguents for his mistress.</note>, a cofferer, fan-bearers<milestone n="252" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Fan-bearers</lemma>:  Both male and female slaves, and eunuchs, were employed to fan their mistresses. The fans were of elegant form and beautiful colours, and were frequently made of peacocks' feathers, being of a stiff shape, and not pliable, like ours. They were used both for the purpose of cooling the air and driving away flies and gnats.</note>, sandal-bearers<milestone n="252" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Sandal- bearers</lemma>:  The sandal was often one of the most costly articles of the female dress, being much adorned with embroidery and gold. Originally it was worn by both sexes and consisted of a wooden sole, fastened with thongs to the foot. In latter times, its use was confined to females, and a piece of leather covered the toes, while thongs, elegantly decorated, were attached to it. From the present passage it appears that it was the duty of a particular slave to take charge of sandals.</note>, singing-girls, casket-keepers<milestone n="253" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Casket- keepers</lemma>:  The "cistellatrix" probably had charge of the jewel casket of her mistress. The present passage shows in what affluence and splendour some of the courtesans lived in those days.</note>, messengers, news-carriers, so many wasters of his bread and substance. The lover himself, while to them he is complaisant, becomes a beggar. When I revolve these things in my mind, and when I reflect how little one is valued when he is in need; away with you, Love--I like you not--no converse do I hold with you. Although 'tis sweet to feast and to carouse, Love still gives bitters enough to be distasteful. He avoids the Courts<milestone n="261" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Avoids the Courts</lemma>:  Shakspeare has a somewhat similar passage in Romeo and Juliet:
<quote lang="en"><l>"But all so soon as the all cheering sun</l>
<l>Should in the furthest East begin to draw</l>
<l>The shady curtains from Aurora's bed,</l>
<l>Away from light steals home my heavy son,</l>
<l>And private in his chamber pens himself,</l>
<l>Shuts up his windows, locks fair daylight out,</l>
<l>And mates himself an artificial night."</l></quote></note> of justice, he drives away your relations, and drives yourself away from your own contemplation. Nor do men wish that he should be called their friend. In a thousand ways is Love to be held a stranger, to be kept at a distance, and to be wholly abstained from. For he who plunges into love, perishes more dreadfully than if he leapt from a rock. Away with you, Love, if you please; keep your owns<milestone n="266" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Keep your own</lemma>:  This is as much as to say, "I divorce myself from you, and utterly repudiate you." The words "tuas res tibi habeto" were the formula solemnly pronounced among the Romans by the husband in cases of divorce, when he delivered back to the wife her own separate property.</note> property to yourself. Love, never be you a friend of mine; some there are, however, whom, in their misery, you may keep miserable and wretched--those whom you have easily rendered submissive to yourself. My fixed determination is to apply my mind to my advancement in life, although, in that, great labour is undergone by the mind. Good men wish these things for themselves, gain, credit, and honour, glory, and esteem; these are the rewards of the upright. It delights me, then, the more, to live together with the upright rather than with the deceitful promulgators of lies.
</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="276" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter PHILTO.</stage>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> <stage>looking about</stage>. Where has this man betaken himself out of doors from the house?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> <stage>coming up to him</stage>. I am here, father; command me what you will, and I shall cause no delay to you, nor will I hide myself in any skulking-place out of your sight.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> You will be doing what is consonant to the rest of your conduct if you reverence your father. By your duty to me, my son, I wish you, for my sake, not to hold any converse with profligate men, either in the street or in the Forum. I know this age--what its manners are. The bad man wishes the good man to be bad, that he may be like himself. The wicked, the rapacious, the covetous, and the envious, disorder and confound the morals of the age: a crew gaping for gain, they hold the sacred thing as profane--the public advantage as the private emolument. At these things do I grieve, these are the matters that torment me. These things am I constantly repeating both day and night, that you may use due precaution against them. They only deem it right to keep their hands off that which they cannot touch with their hands; as to the rest, seize it, carry it off, keep it, be off and go hide, that is the word with them. These things, when I behold them, draw tears from me, because I have survived to see such a race of men. Why have I not rather descended to the dead<milestone n="291" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To the dead</lemma>:  "Ad plures," "to the many," signifies "the dead, inasmuch as they are more in number than the living. It was probably used as a euphemism, as to make mention of death was considered ominous of ill. Homen in the Odyssey, uses <foreign lang="greek">tous ph eiona\s</foreign> in a similar sense</note> ere this? For these men praise the manners of our ancestors, and defile those same persons whom they commend. With regard, then, to these pursuits, I enjoin you not to taint your disposition with them. Live after my fashion, and according to the ancient manners; what I am prescribing to you, the same do you remember and practise. I have no patience with these fashionable manners, upsetting preconceived notions, with which good men are now disgracing themselves. If you follow these my injunctions to you, many a good maxim will take root in your breast.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> From my earliest youth, even up to this present age, I have always, father, paid all submission to the injunctions you have given. So far as my nature was concerned, I considered that I was free; so far as your injunctions were concerned, I deemed it proper that my mind should pay all submission to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> The man who is struggling with his inclination from his earliest age, whether he ought to prefer to be so, as his inclination thinks it proper that he should be, or whether, rather so as his parents and his relations wish him to be--if his inclination conquers that man, it is all over with him; he is the slave of his inclination and not of himself. But if he conquers his inclination, he truly lives and shall be famed as a conqueror of conquerors. If you have conquered your inclination rather than your inclination you, you have reason to rejoice. 'Tis better by far that you should be such as you ought to be, than such as pleases your inclination. Those who conquer the inclination will ever be esteemed better men than those whom the inclination subdues.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I have ever esteemed these maxims as the shield of my youthful age; never to betake myself to any place where vice was the order of the day<milestone n="317" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Where vice was the order of the day</lemma>:  "Damni conciliabulum." Literally, "the place of counsel for wickedness."</note>, never to go to stroll about at night, nor to take from another that which is his. I have taken all precautions, my father, that I might not cause you uneasiness; I have ever kept your precepts in due preservation<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In due preservation</lemma>:  Buildings were said to be "sarta tecta," "in good repair," when the roof was proof against rain. The expression is here used figuratively, to signify, "I have punctually observed your injunctions."</note> by my own rule of conduct.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> And do you reproach me, because you have acted aright? For yourself have you done so, not for me: my life, indeed, is nearly past<milestone n="319" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Is nearly past</lemma>:  It is worthy of remark that this line is quoted by Cicero in his second Epistle to Brutus: "Sed de hoc tu videris. De me possum dicere idem quod Plautinus pater in Trinummo, 'mihi quidem &aelig;tas acta ferme est.'" "As for that matter, it is your concern. For my own part, I may say with the father in the Trinummus of Plautus, 'my life is nearly past'"</note>; this matter principally concerns your own. Keep on overlaying<milestone n="320" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Keep on overlaying</lemma>:  Philto is most probably alluding to the metaphorical expression, "sarta tecta," used just before by his son; and he tells him that the only way to keep rain from coming in at the roof (that is, to keep evil thoughts out of the mind) is to overlay one good deed with another, just as tile is laid upon tile.</note> good deeds with other good deeds, that the rain may not come through. He is the upright man who is not content with it, however upright and however honest he may chance to be. He who readily gives satisfaction to himself, is not the upright man, nor is he really honest: he who thinks but meanly of himself, in him is there a tendency to well-doing.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> For this reason, father, I have thought that since there is a certain thing that I wish for, I would request it of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> What is it? I am already longing to give assent.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> A young man here, of noble family, my friend and years' mate, who has managed his own affairs but heedlessly and unthinkingly--I wish, father, to do him a service, if you are not unwilling.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> From your own means, I suppose?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> From my own means--for what is yours is mine, and all mine is yours.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> What is he doing? Is he in want?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> He is in want.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Had he property? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> He had.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> How did he lose it? Was he connected with public business<milestone n="331" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With public business</lemma>:  He means by this expression, "has he been farming the taxes or the public lands?" which of course would be a pursuit attended with considerable risk.</note>, or with commercial matters? Had he merchandise or wares to sell, when he lost his property?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> None of these. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> What then?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I' faith, my father, by his good-nature. Besides, to indulge his tastes, he wasted some part of it in luxury.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> By my troth now! a fellow spoken of boldly, and as on familiar terms;--one, indeed, who has never dissipated his fortune by any good means, and is now in want. I cannot brook that, with qualities of that description, he should be your friend.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> 'Tis because he is without any bad disposition that I wish to relieve his wants.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> He deserves ill of a beggar who gives him what to eat or to drink; for he both loses that which he gives and prolongs for the other a life of misery. I do not say this because I am unwilling and would not readily do what you desire; but when I apply these expressions to that same person, I am warning you beforehand, so to have compassion on others, that others may not have to pity you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I am ashamed to desert him, and to deny him aid in his adversity.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I' troth, shame is preferable to repentance by just as many letters<milestone n="345" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">By just as many letters</lemma>:  Commentators differ as to the meaning of this passage, which is somewhat obscure. Philto seems to say that shame before doing an unwise action is every way preferable to repentance after having done it; preferable, indeed, by each individual letter it is composed of, or, as we should say in common parlance, "every inch of it."</note> as it consists of.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> In good sooth, father, by the care of the Gods, and of my forefathers, and your own, I may say that we possess much property, honestly obtained. If you do a service to a friend, it ought not to make you repent that you have done so; it ought rather to cause you shame if you do not do it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> If from great wealth you subtract something, does it become more or less?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Less, father. But do you know what is wont to be repeated to the niggardly citizen<milestone n="350" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Niggardly citizen</lemma>:  "Immunis" means one that does not bear his share in the taxes and tribute of the state, or, in other words, pay his scot and lot. Hence, with an extended signification, it means one that will not out of his abundance assist the distress of others, and who is, consequently, a niggardly and covetous person.</note>? "That which thou hast mayst thou not have, and mayst thou have that misfortune which thou hast not; since thou canst neither endure it to be enjoyed by thyself nor by another."</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I know, indeed, that so it usually is: but, my son, he is the truly niggardly man<milestone n="354" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Truly niggardly man</lemma>:  Philto here alludes to the primary meaning of the word "immunis;" and hints that it may be more properly applied to Lesbonicus, who has reduced himself to poverty by his extravagance, than to himself; inasmuch as he is now perforce 'immunis," not having wherewithal to pay the public dues and taxes.</note> that has nought with which to pay his dues.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> By the care of the Gods, we have, father, both enough for us to enjoy ourselves, and with which to do kind offices to kind-hearted men.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Troth, I am not able to refuse you anything that you; ask of me. Whose poverty do you wish to relieve? Speak out boldly to your father.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> That of this young man Lesbonicus, the son of Charmides, who lives there. <stage>He points to the house of CHARMIDES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Why, hasn't he devoured both what he had, and what he had not<milestone n="360" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">What he had not</lemma>:  That is, by the dishonest expedient of running to debt for it.</note>?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Censure him not, my father: many things happen to a man which he likes, many, too, which he does not like.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Troth, you say falsely, son; and you are doing so now not according to your usual wont. For the prudent man, i' faith, really frames his own fortunes for himself: many things, therefore, do not happen which he does not like, unless he is a bungling workman.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Much labour is requisite for this workmanship in him who seeks to be a clever workman in fashioning his life--but he is still very young.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Not by years but by disposition is wisdom acquired. Age is the relish of wisdom--wisdom is the nutriment of old age. However, come, say what you wish now to give him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Nothing at all, father. Do you only not hinder me from accepting it if he should give anything to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> And will you be relieving his poverty by that, if you shall accept anything of him?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> By that very means, my father.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Faith, I wish that you would instruct me in that method.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Certainly. Do you know of what family he is born?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I know--of an extremely honourable one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> He has a sister--a fine young woman now grown up: I wish, father, to take her without a portion for my wife.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> A wife without a portion?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Just so--your riches saved as well. By these means you will be conferring an extreme favour on him, and in no way could you help him to greater advantage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Am I to suffer you to take a wife without a portion?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> You must suffer it, father; and by these means you will be giving an estimable character to our family.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I could give utterance to many a learned saying, and very fluently too: this old age of mine retains stories of old and ancient times. But, since I see that you are courting friendship and esteem for our family, although I have been opposed to you, I thus give my decision--I will permit you; ask for the girl, and marry her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> May the Gods preserve you to me. But, to this favour add one thing.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> But what is this one thing?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I will tell you. Do you go to him, do you solicit him, and do you ask for her yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Think of that now.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> You will transact it much more speedily: all will be made sure of that you do. One word of yours in this matter will be of more consequence than a hundred of mine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> See, now, how, in my kindness, I have undertaken this matter. My assistance shall be given.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> You really are a kind father. This is the house here he dwells. <stage>He points to the house of CHARMIDES.</stage> Lesbonicus is his name. Mind and attend to the business; I will await you at home. <stage>(Exit.)</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="3">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="392" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>PHILTO, alone.</stage>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> These things are not for the best, nor as I think they ought to be; but still, they are better than that which is downright bad. But this one circumstance consoles myself and my thoughts-namely, that he who counsels in respect to a son nothing else but that which pleases himself alone, only plays the fool; he becomes wretched in mind, and yet he is no nearer bringing it about. He is preparing a very inclement winter for his own old age when he arouses that unseasonable storm. <stage>The door of the house of CHARMIDES opens.</stage> But the house is opened to which I was going; most conveniently, Lesbonicus himself is coming out of doors with his servant. <stage>PHILTO retires to a distance.</stage>
</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="4">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="402" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LESBONICUS and STASIMUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> 'Tis less than fifteen days since you received from Callicles forty min&aelig; for this house; is it not as I say, Stasimus?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> When I consider, I think I remember that it was so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> What has been done with it?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> It has been eaten and drunk up--spent away in unguents, washed away in baths<milestone n="409" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Washed away in baths</lemma>:  This will probably refer, not to the money paid for mere bathing at the public baths, which was a <foreign lang="la">quadrans</foreign>, the smallest Roman coin, but to the expense of erecting private baths, which generally formed a portion of the luxuries of a Roman house. The public baths, however, may have possibly been the scene of much profligacy, and have afforded to the reckless and dissipated ample opportunities for squandering their money. That this may have been the fact, is rendered the more likely when we consider the equivocal signification of the word <foreign lang="la">bagnio</foreign>.</note>. The fishmonger and the baker have carried it off: butchers, too, and cooks, green-grocers, perfumers, and poulterers; 'twas quickly consumed. I' faith! that money was made away with not less speedily than if you were to throw a poppy among the ants.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> By my troth, less has been spent on those items than six min&aelig;?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Besides, what have you given to your mistresses?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> That I am including as well in it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Besides, what have I pilfered of it?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Aye, that item is a very heavy one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> That cannot so appear to you, if you make all due deductions<milestone n="414" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Make all due deductions</lemma>:  "Si sumas." Literally, "if you subtract."</note>, unless you think that your money is everlasting. <stage>Aside.</stage> Too late and unwisely,--a caution that should have been used before,--after he has devoured his substance, he reckons up the account too late.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> The account, however, of this money is by no means clear.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I' faith, the account is very clear: the money's gone<milestone n="419" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The money's gone</lemma>:  Instead of a Latin word, the Greek <foreign lang="greek">oi)/xetai</foreign> is introduced, which means "is gone," or "has vanished." Greek terms were current. at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, just as French words and sentences are imported into our language; indeed, the fashions of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> were very generally set by the Greeks.</note>. Did you not receive forty min&aelig; from Callicles, and did he not receive from you the house in possession?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Very good.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. Troth, I think our neighbour has sold his house<milestone n="422" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Has sold his house</lemma>:  He feels satisfied now that Lysiteles has been correctly informed, and that Lesbonicus really is in difficulties.</note>. When his father shall come from abroad, his place is in the beggar's gate<milestone n="423" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The beggar's gate</lemma>:  He probably alludes to the "Porta Trigemina" at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, which was upon the road to <placeName key="perseus,Ostia">Ostia</placeName>. It received its name from the three twin-born brothers, the Horatii, who passed beneath it when going to fight the Curiatii. This, being one of the largest and most frequented roads in <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, was especially the resort of mendicants; among whom, in the opinion of Philto, the father of Lesbonicus will have to take his place. Some Commentators would read "ponte" instead of "port&acirc;," and they think that the allusion is to the Sublician bridge at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, where we learn from <placeName key="tgn,2652379">Seneca</placeName> and Juvenal that the beggars used to sit and ask alms.</note>, unless, perchance, he should creep into his son's stomach<milestone n="424" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">His son's stomach</lemma>:  He satirically alludes to the reckless conduct of Lesbonicus, who has spent everything to satisfy his love for eating, drinking, and debauchery.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> There were a thousand Olympic drachm&aelig;<milestone n="425" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Olympic drachm&aelig;</lemma>:  As already mentioned, the "drachma" was about ninepence three-farthings in value. As one hundred made a "mina," one fourth of the price received for the house would go to satisfy the banker's claim.</note> paid to the banker<milestone n="426" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To the banker</lemma>:  The "Trapezit&aelig;" were the same as the "Argentarii" at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, who were bankers and money-changers on their own account, while the "Mensarii" transacted business on behalf of the state. Their shops, or offices, were situate around the Forum, and were public property. Their principal business was the exchange of Roman for foreign coin, and the keeping of sums of money for other persons, which were deposited with or without interest, according to agreement. They acted as agents for the sale of estates, and a part of their duty was to test the genuineness of coin, and, in later times, to circulate it from the mint among the people. Lending money at a profit was also part of their business. It is supposed that among the Romans there was a higher and a lower class of "argentarii." The more respectable of them probably held the position of the banker of modern times; while those who did business on a paltry scale, or degraded themselves by usury, were not held in any esteem. Their shops, being public property, were built under the inspection of the Censors, and by them were let to the "argentarii." "Trapezit&aelig;," as they are here called, was properly the Greek name for these persons, who were so styled from the <foreign lang="greek">trapesa,</foreign> or "table," at which they sat. All will remember the "tables of the money-changers" mentioned in the New Testament. The "mensarii" were employed to lend out the public money to borrowers at interest.</note>, which you were owing upon account.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Those, I suppose, that I was security for<milestone n="427" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I was security for</lemma>:  "Spondeo," "I promise," was a term used on many occasions among the Romans, derived from the Greek <foreign lang="greek">spendo/mai,</foreign> "pour out a libation;" the usual mode of ratifying a treaty. Among others, it was pronounced by a person when he became security that another should repay money, as Lesbonicus, to his misfortune, had done in the present instance.</note>?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Say, rather<milestone n="427" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Say, rather</lemma>:  Stasimus will not allow his master to mince the matter in the slightest degree. "Don't say 'I was security for it,' but 'I paid it down.'"</note>, "Those that I paid down"--for that young man whom you used to say<milestone n="428" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">You used to say</lemma>:  He probably alludes to some former occasion, on which his master, having been duped into the belief, was telling him of the extraordinary wealth of his new acquaintance.</note> was so rich.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> It was so done.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Yes, just to be squandered away.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> That was done as well. But I saw him in a pitiable state, and I did have pity on him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> You have pity on others, and you have neither pity nor shame for yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. 'Tis time to accost him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Is this Philto that is coming here? Troth, 'tis he himself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I' faith, I could wish he was my slave, together with his savings<milestone n="434" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With his savings</lemma>:  "Peculium" was the property amassed by a slave out of his savings, which he was permitted to keep as his own. According to the strictness of the law, the "peculium" was the property of the master. Sometimes it was agreed that the slave should purchase his freedom with his "peculium" when it amounted to a certain sum.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Philto right heartily wishes health to both master and servant, Lesbonicus and Stasimus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> May the Gods give you, Philto, whatever you may wish for. How is your son?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> He wishes well to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> In good sooth, he does for me what I do for him in return!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. That phrase, "He wishes well," is worthless, unless a person does well too. I, too, "wish" to be a free man; I wish in vain. He, perhaps, might wish to become frugal; he would wish to no purpose.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> My son has sent me to you to propose an alliance and bond of friendship between himself and your family. He wishes to take your sister for his wife; and I have the same feelings, and I desire it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I really don't understand your ways; amid your prosperity you are laughing at my adversity.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I am a man<milestone n="447" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I am a man</lemma>:  This is somewhat like the celebrated line in Terence:  <quote lang="la">"Homo sum, humani nihil alienum a me puto,"</quote>
"I am a man, nothing that is human do I think unbecoming to me."</note>: you are a man. So may <placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName> love me, I have neither come to laugh at you, nor do I think you deserving of it! But as to what I said, my son begged me to ask for your sister as his wife.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> It is right that I should know the state of my own circumstances. My position is not on an equal footing with yours; seek some other alliance for yourselves.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>to LESBONICUS</stage>. Are you really sound in mind or intellect to refuse this proposal? For I perceive that he has been found for you a very friend in need<milestone n="456" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Friend in need</lemma>:  "Ferentarius," The "ferentarii" were the light-armed troops, who, being unencumbered with heavy armour, were ready to come immediately and opportunely to the assistance of those who were in danger of being overpowered by the army. The word is here used figuratively, to signify "a friend in need."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Get away hence, and go hang yourself<milestone n="457" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And go hang yourself</lemma>:  The word 'dierecte" is supposed to come from an obsolete verb, "dierigo," "to extend out on both sides," and to allude to a punishment inflicted upon slaves, when they were fastened to a stake in the ground, with the arms and legs extended. Applied to a slave, it would be an opprobrious expression, equivalent to "go and be hanged."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Faith, if I should commence to go, you would be forbidding me<milestone n="457" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Be forbidding me</lemma>:  He means, that if he should take his master at his word and go away, he would be the first to stop him.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Unless you want me, Philto, for anything else, I have given you my answer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I trust, Lesbonicus, that you will one day be more obliging to me than I now find you to be. For both to act<milestone n="461" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Both to act</lemma>: -2. The exact meaning of these lines is somewhat obscure. <placeName key="tgn,1136756">Thornton</placeName>'s translation is:
<quote lang="en"><l>Or in word</l>
<l>Or deed to play the trifler would ill suit</l>
<l>One of my years.</l></quote></note> unwisely and to talk unwisely, Lesbonicus, are sometimes neither of them profitable.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Troth, he says what's true.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I will tear out your eye if you add one word.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Troth, but I will talk; for if I may not be allowed to do so as I am, then I will submit to be called the one-eyed man<milestone n="465" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The one-eyed man</lemma>:  He means that he is determined to speak out at all risks, even if his master should be as good as his word, and tear his eye out.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Do you now say this, that your position and means are not on an equal footing with ours?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I do say so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Well, suppose, now, you were to come to a building to a public banquet, and a wealthy man by chance were to come there as your neighbour<milestone n="469" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">As your neighbour</lemma>:  "Par" here means a close neighbour, as reclining next to him on the same "triclinium," or "couch," at the entertainment.</note>. The banquet is set on table, one that they style a public one<milestone n="470" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Style a public one</lemma>:  It is not certain what kind of public banquets are here referred to. Public entertainments were given to the people on the occasion of any public rejoicing: such, for instance, as a triumph, as we learn from Suetonius in his life of Julius C&aelig;sar. They were also given when the tenths were paid to Hercules. The clients, also, of the Patricians were in the habit of giving entertainments to their patrons on festival days, when each client contributed his share in kind; and numerous invitations were given, abundance and hospitality being the order of the day. Sometimes these feasts were held in a temple, and perhaps they are here referred to. There were also frequent entertainments in the "Curi&aelig;," or "Court-houses" of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, at which the "curiales," or men of the "curia," or "ward," met together.</note>. Suppose that dainties were heaped up before him by his dependents, and suppose any-thing pleased you that was so heaped up before him, would you eat, or would you keep your place next to this wealthy man, going without your dinner?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I should eat, unless he were to forbid me doing so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> But I, by my faith, even if he were to forbid me, would eat and cram with both cheeks stuffed out; and what pleased him, that, in especial, would I lay hold of beforehand; nor would I yield to him one jot of my very existence. At table it befits no one to be bashful; for there the decision<milestone n="479" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">There the decision</lemma>:  Scaliger supposes that Stasimus is making a parody on the transaction of business by the Senate, who were said "to give their decisions on matters sacred and human;" and that he means to say that the feast is his Senate-house, and the food are the things sacred and human which he is bound to discuss, without respect for anybody.</note> is about things both divine and human.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> You say what is the fact.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I will tell you without any subterfuge: I would make place for him on the highway, on the footpath, in the canvass for public honors; but as to what concerns the stomach--by my troth, not this much <stage>shows the breadth of his finger-nail</stage>, unless he should first have thrashed me with his fists. With provisions at the present prices, a feast is a fortune without incumbrances<milestone n="484" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Without incumbrances</lemma>:  Every Roman family of consequence was bound to perform particular sacrifices, which were not only ordained by the pontifical laws, but the obligation was also rendered hereditary by the civil law, and ordered to be observed by the law of the Twelve Tables: "Sacra privata perpetua manento," "Let private sacrifices remain perpetual." This law is quoted and commented upon by Cicero in his Second Book on the Laws. He there tells us that "heirs are obliged to continue their sacrifices, be they ever so expensive; and for this reason, as by the above law these sacrifices were to be maintained, no one was presumed to be better able to supply the place of the deceased person than his heir." A property exempt from this necessity, might be truly said to be one without incumbrances.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Always, Lesbonicus, do you take care and think this, that that is the best, according as you yourself are the most deserving: if that you cannot attain to, at least be as near as possible to the most deserving. And now, Lesbonicus, I wish you to grant and accept these terms which I propose, and which I ask of you. The Gods are rich; wealth and station befit the Gods: but we poor mortal beings are, as it were, the salt-cellar<milestone n="492" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The salt-cellar</lemma>:  By this expression, Plautus seems to mean that life is to the body as salt is to flesh; it preserves it from corruption.</note> for the salt of life. The moment that we have breathed forth this, the beggar is held of equal value at <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName><milestone n="494" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName></lemma>:  Acheron was a river of the Brutii in <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>. There was another river of this name in <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>. The word usually denotes one of the rivers of Hell; here it means the Infernal regions themselves.</note> with the most wealthy man when dead.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. It will be a wonder if you don't carry your riches there with you. When you are dead, you may, perhaps, be as good as your name imports<milestone n="496" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">As your name imports</lemma>:  The meaning of Stasimus is--"Perhaps when you are dead, in leaving your property to another, you may really prove yourself the amiable man your name would bespeak you to be;" Philto being derived from the Greek <foreign lang="greek">qile/w,</foreign> "to love."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Now, that you may understand that position and means have no place here, and that we do not undervalue your alliance; I ask for your sister without a marriage-portion. May the matter turn out happily. Do I understand her to be promised? Why are you silent?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> O immortal Gods, what a proposal!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Why don't you say, "May the Gods prosper it, I agree<milestone n="502" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I agree</lemma>:  "Spondeo" was a word in general use to denote that the person entered into a promise or engagement. Being the nearest male relation of the damsel, Philto wishes Lesbonicus to close the matter by saying "spondeo," "I agree to betroth her," which he hesitates to do; on which, Stasimus, alluding to his having been the security for the thousand drachm&aelig;, tells him that he had been ready enough to say "spondeo" when it was not to his advantage; namely, at the time when he aid "spondeo," "I promise," and became the security to the banker for his friend. See Note 1 in page 24.</note>?"</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. Alas! when there was no advantage in the expression, he used to say, "I agree;" now, when there is advantage in it, he is not able to say so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Since you think me, Philto, worthy of an alliance with you, I return you many thanks. But though this fortune of mine has sadly diminished through my folly, I have, Philto, a piece of land near the city here; that I will give as a portion to my sister: for, after all my follies, that alone, besides my existence, is left me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Really I care nothing at all about a portion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I am determined to give her one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>whispers to LESBONICUS</stage>. And are you ready, master, to sever that nurse from us which is supporting us? Take care how you do it. What are we ourselves to eat in future?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> <stage>to STASIMUS</stage>. Once more, will you hold your tongue? Am I to be rendered accountable to you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. We are evidently done for, unless I devise something or other. Philto, I want you. <stage>He remeoves to a distance, and beckons to PHILTO.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> If you wish aught, Stasimus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Step a little this way.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> By all means.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I tell you this in secrecy, that neither he nor any one else may learn it of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Trust me boldly with anything you please.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> By Gods and men I warn you, not to allow that piece of land ever to become yours or your son's. I'll tell you my reasons for this matter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Troth, I should like to hear them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> First of all then, when at any time the ground is being ploughed, in every fifth furrow the oxen die.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Preserve me from it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> The gate of <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName> is in that land of ours. Then the grapes, before they are ripe, hang in a putrid state.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> <stage>in a low voice</stage>. He is persuading the man to something, I think. Although he is a rogue, still he is not unfaithful to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Hear the rest. Besides that, when elsewhere the harvest of wheat is most abundant, there it comes up less by one-fourth than what you have sowed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Ah! bad habits ought to be sown on that spot, if in the sowing they can be killed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> And never is there any person to whom that piece of land belongs, but that his affairs turn out most unfortunate. Of those to whom it has belonged, some have gone away in banishment; some are dead outright; some, again, have hanged themselves. See this man, now, to whom it belongs, how he has been brought to a regular backgammoned state<milestone n="537" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Backgammoned state</lemma>:  "Ad incitas redactus, "brought to a standstill," was a term borrowed from the game of "Duodecim Scripta," or "twelve points," and was applied when one of the parties got all his men on the twelfth point, and, being able to move no further, lost the game in consequence. Probably the game partook of the nature of both backgammon and chess.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Preserve me from this piece of land.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> "Preserve me from it," you would say still more, if you were to hear everything from me. For there every other tree has been blasted with lightning; the hogs die<milestone n="540" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The hogs die</lemma>:  From Pliny the Elder we learn that "angina," or swelling of the throat, was a common distemper among hogs.</note> there most shockingly of inflammation in the throat; the sheep are scabby, as bare of all wool, see, as is this hand of mine. And then, besides, there is not one of the Syrian natives<milestone n="542" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The Syrian natives</lemma>:  He makes mention of the Syrians, because living in a hot climate, they would be most likely to be able to endure extreme heat.</note>, a race which is the most hardy of men, who could exist there for six months; so surely do all die there of the solstitial fever<milestone n="544" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The solstitial fever</lemma>:  He seems to mean, that if a person went to live there at the beginning of the year, he could not possibly live there beyond six months, being sure to die of fever at the time of the Solstice, or Midsummer.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I believe, Stasimus<milestone n="545" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I believe, Stasimus</lemma>:  Philto only says so for peace sake, as no man in his senses was likely to believe a word of it. As he does not want the piece of land for his son, he wishes to make no words about it.</note>, that it is so; but the Campanian<milestone n="545" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">But the Campanian</lemma>:  He just makes this remark casually, probably to show Stasimus that he knows about things in general as well as he does. Some think, however, that he intends to correct Stasimus, and to tell him that even the Campanians, who were considered an effeminate race, could boast of more hardihood than the Syrians.</note> race much outdoes that of the Syrians in hardiness. But, really, that piece of land, as I have heard you describe it, is one to which it were proper for all wicked men to be sent for the public good. Just as they tell of the Islands of the Blest, where all meet together who have passed their lives uprightly: on the other hand, it seems proper that all evildoers should be packed off there, since it is a place of such a character.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> 'Tis a very receptacle of calamity. What need is there of many words? Look for any bad thing whatsoever, there you may find it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> But, i' faith, you may find it there and elsewhere too.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Please, take care not to say that I told you of this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> You have told it me in perfect secrecy.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> For he, indeed <stage>pointing at LESBONICUS</stage>, wishes it to be got rid of from himself, if he can find any one to impose upon<milestone n="558" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To impose upon</lemma>:  "Os quoi sublinat"--literally, "can besmear his face." This expression alludes to the practical joke of making a fool of a person by painting his face while he is asleep.</note> about it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> I' faith, this land shall never become my property.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Aye, if you keep in your senses. <stage>Aside.</stage> I' faith, I have cleverly frightened<milestone n="560" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I have cleverly frightened</lemma>:  As before remarked, he is probably much mistaken in thinking so.</note> the old fellow away from this land; for, if my master had parted with it, there is nothing for us to live upon.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Lesbonicus, I now return to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Tell me, if you please, what has he been saying to you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> What do you suppose? He is a man<milestone n="563" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">He is a man</lemma>:  His meaning seems to be, "he is a man, with feelings like ourselves, and naturally wishes for his freedom,"</note>; he wishes to become a free man, but he has not the money to give.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> And I wish to be rich, but all in vain.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. You might have been, if you had chosen; now, since you have nothing, you cannot be.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> What are you talking about to yourself, Stasimus?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> About that which you were saying just now: if you had chosen formerly, you might have been rich; now you are wishing too late.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> No terms can be come to with me about the marriage-portion; whatever pleases you, do you transact it yourself with my son. Now, I ask for your sister for my son; and may the matter turn out well. What now? are you still considering?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> What--about that matter? Since you will have it so--may the Gods prosper it--I promise her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> Never, by my troth, was a son born so ardently longed for by any one, as was that expression "I promise her," when born for me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> The Gods will prosper all your plans.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>PHILTO</speaker><p> So I wish. Come this way with me, Lesbonicus, that a day may be agreed on for the nuptials, in the presence of Lysiteles: this agreement we will ratify on that same day.  <stage>(Exit PHILTO.)</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Now, Stasimus, go you there <stage>points to the house which he has sold to CALLICLES</stage> to the house of Callicles, to my sister; tell her how this matter has been arranged.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I will go. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> And congratulate my sister.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Very well. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Tell Callicles to meet me----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> But rather do you go now----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> That he may see what is necessary to be done about the portion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do go now. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> For I have determined not to give her without a portion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> But rather do you go now. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> And I will never allow it to be a detriment to her by reason of----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do be off now. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> My recklessness----
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do go now<milestone n="586" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Do go now</lemma>:  Stasimus is continually urging him to follow Philto, and bring the matter to a conclusion, as he fears that so good an opportunity may be lost through his master's habitual carelessness especially as Philto has agreed not to receive the land as a marriage-portion.</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> It seems by no means just, but that, since I have done wrong----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do go now.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> It should be chiefly a detriment to myself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do go now. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> O my father! and shall I ever see you again?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do go now. Go--go now.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I am going. Do you take care of that which I have asked you. I shall be here directly. <stage>(Exit LESBONICUS.)</stage>

<milestone n="591" unit="TLN line"/></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> At length I have prevailed on him to go. In the name of the immortal Gods, i' faith, 'tis a matter well managed by wrongful means of performance, inasmuch as our piece of land is safe; although even now 'tis still a very doubtful matter what may be the result of this affair. But, if the land is parted with, 'tis all over<milestone n="595" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">'Tis all over</lemma>:  He means that he will no longer have any support from his master, and that he will have to turn soldier, and so earn his livelihood.</note> with my neck; I must carry a buckler in foreign lands, a helmet too, and my baggage. He will be running away from the city when the nuptials have been celebrated; he will be going hence to extreme and utter ruin, somewhere or other, to serve as a soldier, either to <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> or to <placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName><milestone n="599" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Atia or to <placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName></lemma>: , Alluding, probably to the wars which were continually occurring between the Greeks and the Persian monarchs, or else to the custom of hiring themselves out as mercenary soldiers, as Xenophon and the ten thousand did to the younger Cyrus.</note>. I will go there <stage>looking at the door of the house bouight by CALLICLES</stage>, where he has ordered me to go, although I detest this house ever since he has driven us out of our abode.  <stage>(Exit into the house of CHARMIDES.)</stage>

</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="3">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="602" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter CALLICLES and STASIMUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> To what effect were you speaking about this, Stasimus?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> That Lesbonicus, the son of my master, has betrothed his sister; in those terms.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> To what person has he betrothed her?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> To Lysiteles, the son of Philto; without a portion, too.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Without a portion, will he marry her into a family so rich<milestone n="605" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Into a family so rich</lemma>:  "In tantas divitias," literally, "into so great wealth."</note>? You are telling me a thing not to be credited.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Why, faith, you would be for never believing. If you don't believe this, at all events I shall be believing----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> That I don't care a fig for your belief.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> How long since, or where, was this matter agreed to?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> On this very spot--here, before his door <stage>pointing to PHILTO'S house</stage>. This moment-like<milestone n="609" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">This moment-like</lemma>:  "Tammodo," He is joking upon the patois of the people of Pr&aelig;neste, who said "tammodo," instead of "modo," "this instant," or "just now." Festus also alludes to this expression, as used by the Pr&aelig;nestines. In the Truculentus, act iii., sc. 2, l. 23, he again takes them off for catting "Ciconia" down to "Conia." Pr&aelig;este was a town of <placeName key="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>, not far from <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. Its present name is <placeName key="tgn,7007001">Palestrina</placeName>.</note>, as the man of Pr&aelig;neste says.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> And has Lesbonicus, amid his ruined fortunes, become so much more frugal than in his prosperous circumstances?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Why, in fact, Philto himself came of his own accord to make the offer for his son.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> <stage>aside.</stage> By my troth, it really will be a disgrace, if a portion is not given to the maiden. In fine, I think, i' faith, that that matter concerns myself. I will go to my corrector, and will ask advice of him. <stage>(Exit.)</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I pretty nearly guess, and I have a strong suspicion, why he makes such speed on this: namely, that he may turn Lesbonicus out of his bit of land, after he has turned him out of his house. O Charmides, my master! since your property here is being torn to pieces in your absence, I wish I could see you return safe, that you might both take vengeance on your enemies, and give the reward to me according as I have behaved, and do behave towards you. 'Tis an extremely difficult thing for a friend to be found really such as the name imports, to whom, when you have entrusted your interests, you may sleep without any care. But lo! I perceive our son-in-law<milestone n="622" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Our son-i-law</lemma>:  He means Lysiteles, the contemplated son-in-law of his master Charmides, whom he has just been apostrophising.</note> coming, together with his neighbour. Something--what, I know not--is wrong between them. They are walking, each with a hasty step; the one is catching the other that is before him by the cloak. They have come to a stop in no very courteous fashion. I'll step aside here a little distance. I have a wish to hear the conversation of these two that are to be connected by marriage. <stage>He retires to a distance.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="627" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYSITELES and LESBONICUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Stay, this moment; don't turn away, and don't hide yourself from me. <stage>He catches hold of his cloak.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p>  <stage>(shaking him off)</stage> Can't you allow me to go whither I was proceeding?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> If, Lesbonicus, it seems to be to your interest, either for your glory or for your honour, I will let you go.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> You are doing a thing that it is very easy to do.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> What is that? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> An injury to a friend.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> It is no way of mine, and I have not learned so to do.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Untaught as you are, how cleverly you do it. What would you have done, if any one had taught you to be thus annoying to me? You, who, when you pretend to be acting kindly to me, use me ill, and are intending evil.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> What!--I? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Yes--you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> How do I use you ill?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Inasmuch as you do that which I do not wish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I wish to consult your advantage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Are you kinder to me than I am to myself? I have sense enough; I see sufficiently well those things that are for my own advantage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> And is it having sense enough to refuse a kindness from a well-wisher?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I reckon it to be no kindness, when it does not please him on whom you are conferring it. I know, and I understand myself what I am doing, and my mind forsakes not its duty; nor will I be driven by your speeches from paying due regard to my own character.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> What do you say? For now I cannot be restrained from saying to you the things which you deserve. Have your forefathers, I pray, so handed down this reputation to you, that you, by your excesses, might lose what before was gained by their merit, and that you might become a bar to the honour of your own posterity? Your father and your grandfather made an easy and a level path for you to attain to honour; whereas you have made it to become a difficult one, by your extreme recklessness and sloth, and your besotted ways. You have made your election, to prefer your passions to virtue. Now, do you suppose that you can cover over your faults by these means? Alas! 'tis impossible. Welcome virtue to your mind, if you please, and expel slothfulness from your heart. Give your attention to your he-friends in the Courts of justice<milestone n="651" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In the Courts of justice</lemma>:  It was the custom of the young men of the Patrician class among the Romans to plead gratuitously for their friends and clients, in the Forum or Court of justice.</note>, and not to the couch of your she-friend, as you are wont to do. And earnestly do I now wish this piece of land to be left to you for this reason, that you may have wherewithal to reform yourself; so that those citizens, whom you have for enemies, may not be able altogether to throw your poverty in your teeth.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> All these things which you have been saying, I know--could even set my seal<milestone n="655" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Set my seal</lemma>:  Affixing the seal to an instrument was then, as now the most solemn way of ratifying it.</note> to them: how I have spoiled my patrimonial estate and the fair fame of my forefathers. I knew how it became me to live; to my misfortune I was not able to act accordingly. Thus, overpowered by the force of passion, inclined to ease, I fell into the snare; and now to you, quite as you deserve, I do return most hearty thanks.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Still, I cannot suffer my labour to be thus lost, and yourself to despise these words; at the same time, it grieves me that you have so little shame. And, in fine, unless you listen to me, and do this that I mention, you yourself will easily lie concealed behind your own self, so that honour cannot find you; when you will wish yourself to be especially distinguished, you will be lying in obscurity. I know right well, for my part, Lesbonicus, your highly ingenuous disposition; I know that of your own accord you have not done wrong, but that it is Love that has blinded your heart; and I myself comprehend all the ways of Love. As the charge of the balista<milestone n="668" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Charge of the balista</lemma>:  The word "balista" here signifies the charge of the military engine known as the "balista." It was used by the ancients for the purpose of discharging stones against the higher part of the walls of besieged places, while the "catapulta" was directed against the lower. The charge of the "balista" varied from two pounds to three hundred-weight.</note> is hurled, so is Love; nothing is there so swift, or that so swiftly flies; he, too, makes the manners of men both foolish and froward<milestone n="669" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Foolish and froward</lemma>:  "Moros." This word is derived from the Greek <foreign lang="greek">mwro\s,</foreign> "foolish." It seems to be used in juxtaposition with "morosos, for the sake of the alliteration.</note>. That which is the most commended pleases him the least<milestone n="670" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pleases him the least</lemma>:  So Shakspeare alludes to the contradictory nature of love in Romeo and Juliet:
<quote lang="la"><l>"Love--heavy lightness! serious vanity!</l>
<l>Misshapen chaos of well-seeming forms."</l></quote></note>; that from which he is dissuaded pleases him. When there is a scarcity, then you long for a thing; when there is an abundance of it, then you don't care for it. The person that warns him off from a thing, the same invites him; he that persuades him to it interdicts him. 'Tis a misfortune of insanity for you to fly to Cupid for refuge. But I advise you again and again to think of this, how you should seek to act. If you attempt to do according as you are now showing signs<milestone n="675" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Are now showing signs</lemma>:  The meaning of this passage is extremely obscure. Perhaps, however, it is this, "If you persist in your extravagance, and are resolved to part with this land, the very last of your possessions, you will prove the conflagration and ruin of your family. Then you will be seeking a remedy--water with which to quench it. When you have got this remedy, as you cleverly suppose, in going abroad to fight and earn glory, you will ply it with such zeal, that you will overdo it, and, in getting killed yourself, will thereby quench the last spark on which the very existence of your house depended." Or this Lesbonicus says, though not carrying on the metaphor in the same sense, "I will find means, even amid the enemy, to render my name illustrious, for there the fire may be found which is to keep my family from becoming extinguished."</note>, you will cause the conflagration of your family; and then, in consequence, you will have a desire for water with which to quench this conflagration of your family. And if you should obtain it, just as lovers are subtle in their devices, you will not leave even one spark with which your family may brighten up.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> 'Tis easy to be found: fire is granted, even though you should ask it of a foe. But you, by your reproof, are urging me from my faults to a viler course. You are persuading me to give you my sister without a portion. But it does not become me, who have misused so great a patrimony, to be still in affluent circumstances, and to be possessing land, but her to be in want, so as with good reason to detest me. Never will he be respected by others who makes himself despised by his own relatives. As I said, I will do; I do not wish you to be in doubt any longer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> And is it so much preferable that for your sister's sake you should incur poverty, and that I should possess that piece of land rather than yourself, who ought to be upholding your own walls?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I do not wish you so much to have regard to myself, in order that you may relieve my poverty, as that in my neediness I may not become disgraced: that people may not spread about this report of me, that I gave my own sister without a portion to you, rather in concubinage<milestone n="690" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Rather in concubinage</lemma>:  His pride is hurt at the idea of his sister being married without a portion, and thereby losing one of the distinctive marks between a wife and a mistress. It was considered a disgraceful thing for a remain to be given in marriage without a portion, however small.</note> than in marriage. Who would be said to be more dishonorable than I? The spreading of this report might do credit to you, but it would defile me, if you were to marry her without a portion. For you it would be a gain of reputation, for me it would be something for people to throw in my teeth.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Why so? Do you suppose<milestone n="695" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Do you suppose</lemma>:  Lysiteles says, satirically, and rather unkindly, it would seem, "What, do you suppose that, if I accept this piece of land of you, you will attain the Dictatorship as the reward of your high spirit?' The Dictatorshiip was the highest honour in the Roman Republic.</note> that you will become Dictator if I accept the land of you?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I neither wish, nor require, nor do I think so; but still, to be mindful of his duty, is true honour to an upright man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> For my part, I know you, how you are disposed in mind; I see it, I discover it, I apprehend. You are doing this, that when you have formed an alliance between us, and when you have given up this piece of land, and have nothing here with which to support life, in beggary you may fly from the city, in exile you may desert your country, your kindred, your connexions, your friends,--the nuptials once over. People would suppose that you were frightened hence by my means, and through my cupidity. Do not fancy in your mind that I will act so as to allow that to happen.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>advanccing</stage>. Well, I cannot but exclaim, "Well done, well done, Lysiteles, encore<milestone n="705" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Encore</lemma>:  <foreign lang="greek">*pali\n.</foreign> This Greek word was no doubt used by the Romans just as we employ the French word "encore." In a similar manner it was probably used in the theatres, the usage of which is here figuratively referred to.</note>." Easily do you win the victory; the other is conquered: your performance is superior. This one <stage>pointing to LYSITELES</stage> acts better in character, and composes better lines<milestone n="707" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Composes better lines</lemma>:  In the line before, he alludes to the contest of the Comic poets for the prize of Comedy, to be decided according to the merits of their respective plays. As the poets were often the actors of their plays, he addresses them in this line in the latter capacity. Then, in the next line, he refers to the custom of the Romans in early times of training slaves as actors, where, if they did not please the spectators, they were taken off the stage and fined or beaten for their carelessness.</note>. By reason of your folly do you still dispute it? Stand in awe of the fine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> What means this interruption of yours, or your intrusion here upon our conversation?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> The same way that I came here I'll get me gone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Step this way home with me, Lysiteles; there we will talk at length about these matters.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I am not in the habit of doing anything in secret. Just as my feelings are I will speak out. If your sister, as I think it right, is thus given to me in marriage without a portion, and if you are not about to go away hence, that which shall be mine, the same shall be yours. But if you are minded otherwise, may that which you do turn out for you for the best. I will never be your friend on any other terms; such is my determination. <stage>(Exit LESBONICUS, followed by LYSITELES.)</stage>

<milestone n="717" unit="TLN line"/></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Faith, he's off. D'ye hear--Lysiteles? I want you. He's off as well. Stasimus, you remain alone. What am I now to do, but to buckle up my baggage and sling my buckler on my back<milestone n="719" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">On my back</lemma>:  When marching, the "clypeus," or "shield," was slung on the back of the soldier. The "sarcina," or "baggage," probably resembled our knapsack.</note>, and order soles to be fastened<milestone n="720" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Soles to be fastened</lemma>:  The "soccus" was a slipper or low shoe, which did not fit closely, and was not fastened by a tie. These were worn both by men and women, and especially by Comic actors. His meaning probably is, that he will be obliged to have high heels and thick soles put to his shoes, so as to turn them into "calig&aelig;," the heavy kind of shoes worn by the Roman soldiers.</note> beneath my shoes? There is no staying now. I see that no long time hence I shall be a soldier's drudge. And when my master has thrown himself into the pay<milestone n="722" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Into the pay</lemma>:  "In saginam," means "for his food;" as what we technically call "the mess" was provided for the soldier by those who hired him The term "sagina" is found especially applied to the victuals of the gladiators, who were trained up and dieted on all kinds of nourishing food for the purpose of adding to their strength, and thereby heightening interest attendant on their combats.</note> of some potentate, I guess that among the greatest warriors he will prove a brave<milestone n="723" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Prove a brave</lemma>:  In this line and the next he is witty upon the sorry figure which he fancies Lesbonicus will make in the field of battle.</note>--hand at running away, and that there he will capture the spoil, who-shall come to attack my master. I myself, the moment that I shall have assumed my bow and quiver and arrows, and the helmet on my head, shall-go to sleep very quietly in my tent. I'll be off to the Forum; I'll ask that talent<milestone n="727" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Ask that talent</lemma>:  Many a truth is said in jest, and perhaps part of this talent is the fruit of the theft which he seems in joke only to admit in l. 414; as some Commentators have remarked, where was Stasimus, a slave, to get so much money as a talent, more than 200 &pound;? As, however, in other respects, he seems to have been a faithful servant, let us in charity suppose that he cams honestly by his talent, and that it was his fairly acquired "peculium"</note> back of the person to whom I lent it six days since, that I may have some provision for the journey to carry with me. <stage>(Exit.)</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="3">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="729" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter MEGARONIDES and CALLICLES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> According as you relate the matter to me, Callicles, it really can by no means be but that a portion must be given to the girl.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Why, troth, it would hardly be honestly done on my part, if I were to allow her to contract a marriage without a portion, when I have her property in my possession at home. * * * * *</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> * * * * A portion is ready at your house; unless you like to wait until her brother has disposed of her in marriage without a portion. After that, you might go to Philto yourself, and might say that you present her with a portion, and that you do it on account of your intimacy with her father. But I dread this, lest that offer might bring you into crimination and disgrace with the public. They would say that you were so kind to the girl not without some good reason; that the dowry which you presented her was given you by her father; they would think that you were portioning her out of that, and that you had not kept it safe for her just as it was given, and that you had withheld some part. Now, if you wish to await the return of Charmides, the time is very long; meanwhile, the inclination to marry her may leave this Lysiteles; this proposal, too, is quite a first-rate one for her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> All these very same things suggest themselves to my mind.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Consider if you think this more feasible and more to the purpose: go to the young man himself, and tell him how the matter really stands.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Should I now discover the treasure to a young man, ill-regulated, and brimful of passion and of wantonness? No, faith, most assuredly, by no means. For I know, beyond a doubt, that he would devour even all that spot where it is buried. I fear to dig for it, lest he should hear the noise; lest, too, he might trace out the matter itself, if I should say I will give her a portion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> By what method, then, can the portion be secretly taken out?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Until an opportunity can be found for that business, I would, in the meanwhile, ask for a loan of the money from some friend or other.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Can it be obtained from some friend or other?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> It can. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Nonsense; you'll certainly meet with this answer at once: "O, upon my faith, I really have not anything that I can lend you."</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Troth, I would rather they would tell me the truth than lend me the money with a bad grace.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> But consider this plan, if it pleases you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What is the plan? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I have found out a clever plan, as I think.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What is it? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Let some person, now, be hired, of an appearance as much unknown as possible, such as has not been often seen. Let this person be dressed up to the life after a foreign fashion, just as though he were a foreigner.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What is he to understand that he must do after that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> It is necessary for him to be some lying, deceiving, impudent fellow--a lounger from the Forum.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> And what then, after that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Let him come to the young man as though from Seleucia, from his father; let him pronounce his salutation to him in the words of his father, say that he is prospering in business, and is alive and well, and that he will be shortly coming back again. Let him bring two letters; let us seal these, as though they are from his father. Let him give the one to him, and let him say that he wishes to give the other to yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Go on, and tell me still further.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Let him say that he is bringing some gold as a marriage-portion from her father for the girl, and that his father has requested him to deliver it to you. Do you understand me now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Pretty nearly; and I listen with great satisfaction.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Then, in consequence, you will finally give the gold to the young man when the girl shall be given in marriage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Troth, 'tis very cleverly contrived.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> By this means, when you have dug up the treasure, you will have removed all cause for suspicion from the young man. He will think that the gold has been brought to you from his father; whereas, you will be taking it from the treasure.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Very cleverly and fairly contrived; although I am ashamed, at this time of life, for me to be playing a double part. But when he shall bring the letters sealed, don't you suppose that the young man will then recollect the impression of his father's signet<milestone n="789" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">His father's signet</lemma>:  The custom of wearing rings among the Romans was said to have been derived from the Sabines. The stones set in them were generally engraved with some design, and they were universally used by both Greeks and Romans for the purpose of a seal. So common was the practice among the Greeks, that Solon made a very wholesome law which forbade engravers to keep the form of a seal which they had sold. In some rings the seal was cut in the metal itself. The designs engraved on rings were various; sometimes portraits of ancestors or friends, and sometimes subjects connected with the mythology or the worship of the Gods. The onyx was the stone most frequently used in rings. The genuineness of a letter was tested, not by the signature, but by the seal appended to it; hence the anxiety of Callicles on the present occasion.</note>?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Will you be silent now? Reasons innumerable may be found for that circumstance. That which he used to have he has lost, and he has since had another new one made. Then, if he should bring them not sealed at all, this might be said,--that they had been unsealed for him by the custom-house officers<milestone n="794" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The custom-house officers</lemma>:  The "portitores" were the officers who collected the "portorium," or "import duty," on goods brought from foreign countries. These "portitores," to whom it was frequently farmed, greatly annoyed the merchants by their unfair conduct and arbitrary proceedings. At Rome, all commodities, including slaves, which were imported for the purpose of selling again, were subject to the "portorium." The present instance is an illustration of the license of their proceedings, for we can hardly suppose that they were entitled as of right to break open the seals of letters from foreign countries.</note>, and had been examined. On matters of this kind, however, 'tis mere idleness to spend the day in talk; although a long discussion might be spun out. Go now, at once, privately to the treasure; send to a distance the men-servants and the maids; and--do you hear?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What is it? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> Take care that you conceal this matter from that same wife of yours as well; for, i' faith, there is never any subject which they can be silent upon. Why are you standing now? Why don't you take yourself off hence, and bestir yourself? Open the treasure, take thence as much gold as is requisite for this purpose; at once close it up again, but secretly, as I have enjoined you; turn all out of the house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I will do so. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> But, really, we are continuing too long a discourse; we are wasting the day, whereas there is need now of all expedition. There is nothing for you to fear about the seal; trust me for that. This is a clever excuse to give, as I mentioned, that they have been looked at by the officers. In fine, don't you see the time of day? What do you think of him being of such a nature and disposition? He is drunk already; anything you like may be proved for him. Besides, what is the greatest point of all, this person will say that he brings, and not that he applies for, money.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Now, that's enough.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I am now going to hire a sharper<milestone n="815" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A sharper</lemma>:  "Sycophanta." At an early period there was a law at Athens against the exportation of figs. In spite, however, of prohibitions and penalties; the fig-growers persisted in exporting the fruit. To inform the authorities against the practice was deemed mean and vexatious, so the statute came in time to be looked upon as obsolete. Hence, the term <foreign lang="greek">dukofantei=n,</foreign> "to inform relative to the exportation of figs," came to be applied to all mean and dishonest accusations. In time, the word "sycophant" came to be applied to a man who was a cunning and villanous character, and who, as it has been justly observed, in Dr Smith's Dictionary, was "a happy compound of the common barretor, informer, pettifogger, busybody, rogue, liar, and slanderer." In fact, he was such a person as we mean by the epithet "swindler" or "sharper." Information being encouraged by the policy of Athens, and the informer gaining half the reward, it was upon this honourable calling that the "sycophant&aelig;" in general thrived They were ready, however, for any other job, however dishonorable, and perjury would not be declined by them if they could obtain their price. They would, consequently be much in the neighbourhood of the Courts of justice; and the Forum, as in the present instance, would not be an unlikely place to meet with them.</note> from the Forum, and then I will seal the two letters; and I'll send him thither <stage>pointing to the house of CHARMIDES</stage>, well tutored in his part, to this young man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I am going in-doors then to my duty in consequence. Do you see about this matter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MEGARONIDES</speaker><p> I'll take care it's done in the very cleverest style. <stage>(Exeunt.)</stage>

</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="4">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="820" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter CHARMIDES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> To Neptune, potent o'er the deep and most powerful, the brother of &aelig;thereal Jove, joyously and sincerely do I proffer praise, and return my grateful thanks; to the salt waves, too, with whom lay supreme power over myself,--one, too, that existed over my property and my life, --inasmuch as from their realms they have returned me safe and sound even to my own native city. And, Neptune, before the other Deities, do I both give and return to you extreme thanks. For all people talk of you as being cruel and severe, of voracious habits, filthy, unsightly, unendurable, and outrageous; on the other hand, I have experienced your kindly aid. For, in good sooth, I have found you mild and merciful upon the deep, even to that degree that I wished. This commendation, too, I had already heard with these ears before of you among men,--that you were accustomed to spare the poor, and to depress and overawe the rich. Adieu! I commend you; you know how to treat men properly, according as is just. This is worthy of the Gods; they should ever prove benignant to the needy; to men of high station, quite otherwise. Trusty have you proved, though they are in the habit of saying that you cannot be trusted. For, without you, it would have happened, I am very sure, that on the deep your attendants would have shockingly torn in pieces and rent asunder wretched me, and, together with me, my property as well, in every direction throughout the azure surface of ocean. But just now, like raging dogs, and no otherwise, did the winds in hurricane beset the ship; storms and waves, and raging squalls were about to roar, to break the mast, to bear down the yards, to split the sails; had not your favouring kindness been nigh at hand. Have done with me, if you please; henceforth have I now determined to give myself up to ease; enough have I got. With what pains have I struggled, while I was acquiring riches for my son. But who is this<milestone n="840" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">But who is this</lemma>:  It seems at first sight rather absurd that Charmides, who has just returned from a voyage, should wait in the street to gossip with a stranger who is coming towards him; but we must remember that he sees that the fellow is making straight for his house, and his curiosity is excited by that fact, combined with the very extraordinary dress which Megaronides has hired for him from the playhouse, and has thereby probably much overdone the character which he is intended to represent.</note> that is coming up the street with his new-fangled garb and appearance? I' faith, though I wish to be at home, I'll wait awhile; at the same time, I will give my attention to see what business this fellow is about. <stage>He retires aside.</stage>
</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="843" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter the SHARPER.</stage>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> To this day I give the name of "The Festival of the Three Pieces" (Trinummus); for, on this day, have I let out my services in a cheating scheme for three pieces of money. I am just arrived from Seleucia, Macedonia, Asia, and Arabia,--places which I never visited either with my eye or with my foot. See now, what business poverty brings upon the man that is wretchedly destitute; inasmuch as I am now obliged, for the sake of three pieces of money, to say that I received these letters from a certain person, about whom I don't know, nor have I ever known, who the man is, nor do I know this for certain, whether he was ever born or not.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Faith, this fellow's surely of the mushroom genus; he covers himself entirely with his top.<milestone n="851" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With his top</lemma>:  The Sharper, as personating a foreigner, has on a "petasus," or hat with very wide brims, extending straight out on each side. For this reason Charmides wittily compares him to a mushroom--all head. The "causia" was a similar hat worn by the Macedonians, with the brims turned up at the sides.</note> The countenance of the fellow appears to be Illyrian; he comes, too, in that garb.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> He who hired me, when he had hired me, took me to his house; he told me what he wanted to be done; he taught and showed me beforehand how I was to do everything. If, then, I should add anything more, my employer will on that account the better forward his plan through me. As he dressed me out, so am I now equipped; his money did that. He himself borrowed my costume, at his own risk, from the theatrical wardrobe<milestone n="858" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The theatrical wardrobe</lemma>:  "Chorego"--literally, "from the Choregus." It was the duty of this person at Athens to provide the Choruses for tragedies and comedies, the Lyric Choruses of men and boys, the dancers for the Pyrrhic dance, the Cyclic Choruses, and the Choruses of flute-players for the religious festivals of Athens. He also had to provide the Chorus with the requisite dresses, wreaths, and masks--whence the application to him on the present occasion.</note>; if I shall be able, now, to impose on this man through my garb, I will give him occasion clearly to find that I am a very trickster.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. The more I look at him, the less does the appearance of the fellow please me. 'Tis a wonder if that fellow there is not either a night-robber<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A night-robber</lemma>:  "Dormitator" seems to mean a thief, who slept during the day and pursued his avocations by night. "Sector zonarius" is a "cutter of girdles," similar to our "cutpurse." It was the custom of persons of the middle and lower classes to wear their purses suspended from the "zona," or "girdle," round the waist; and sometimes they used the folds of the girdle itself for the purpose of depositing their money therein.</note> or a cutpurse. He is viewing the locality; he is looking around him and surveying the houses; troth, I think he is reconnoitring the spot for him to come and rob bye and bye. I have a still greater desire to watch what he is about: I'll give attention to this matter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> This employer of mine pointed out these localities to me; at this house are my devices to be put in practice. I'll knock at the door.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Surely this fellow is making in a straight line for my house; i' faith, I think I shall have to keep watch this night of my arrival.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> <stage>knocks at the door of the house of CHARMIDES</stage>. Open this door!--open it! Hallo, there! who now has the care of this door<milestone n="870" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Care of this door</lemma>:  It was not the usage to enter a house without giving notice to those within. This was done among the Spartans by shouting, while the Athenians, and other nations, either used the knocker of the door or rapped with the knuckles or a stick. In the houses of the rich a porter was always in attendance to open the door. He was commonly a slave or eunuch, and was, among the Romans, chained to his post. A dog was also in general chained near the entrance, and the warning, "Cave canem," "Beware of the dog," was sometimes written near the door.</note>?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>coming up to him</stage>. Young man, what do you want? hat is it you wish? Why are you knocking at this door?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Eh! old gentleman; I am inquiring here for a young man named Lesbonicus, where in this quarter he lives --and likewise for another person, with such white hairs on his head as yours; he that gave me these letters said his name was Callicles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. In fact, this fellow is looking for my own son Lesbonicus and my friend Callicles, to whom I entrusted both my children and my property.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Let me know, respected sir<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Respected sir</lemma>: "Pater," literally. "father."</note>, if you are acquainted with it, where these persons live.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Why are you inquiring for them? Or who are you?--Or whence are you?--Or whence do you cone?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> I gave the return correctly to the Censor<milestone n="879" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To the Censor</lemma>:  "Juratori." It was the duty of the Censor, among the Romans, to make these inquiries of every person when taking the Census. As the Censors were bound by an oath to the faithful discharge of their duties they were, in common with all persons so bound, called "juratores," "oathsmen." The Sharper gives Charmides an impudent answer, saying that he has answered the Censor on these points, and that is enough.</note>, when I was questioned by him----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> * * * *</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> You ask a number of things in the same breath; I know not which in especial to inform you upon. If you will ask each thing singly, and in a quiet manner, I'll both let you know my name, and my business, and my travels.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I'll do as you desire. Come then; in the first place, tell me your name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> You begin by demanding an arduous task.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> How so?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Because, respected sir, if you were to begin before daylight, i' faith, to commence at the first part of my name<milestone n="855" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Beginning of my name</lemma>:  He probably alludes to his varied calling, commensurate with everything in the line of roguery. See the Note to line 815.</note>, 'twould be the dead of the night before you could get to the end of it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> According to your story, a person should have a long journey's provision crammed tightly in for your name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> I have another name somewhat less,--about the size of a wine-casks<milestone n="888" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Size of a wine cask</lemma>:  He alludes, probably, to the "amphora," or large earthen jar, in which wine was kept. This was, perhaps, a cant saying, just as if we should say, "As little as a hogshead."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What is this name of yours, young man?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> "Hush," that's my name<milestone n="889" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">"Hush," that is my name</lemma>:  "Pax." This word was used to enjoin silence, like our word "Hush," or "Whist." He seems to allude to his own thieving avocation, which often required him to be as mute as a mouse. Some of the editions nave "tax," as though from "tango," "to prig," or "steal." This, Thornton renders "Touchit."</note>; that's my every-day one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I' faith, 'tis a scampish name; just as though<milestone n="891" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Just as though</lemma>:  This passage is of obscure signification. A note of exclamation ought to be inserted after "pax," and then the meaning of the old man seems to be, that, as in conversation a stop is instantly put to the discourse on saying "hush!" so, if anything is entrusted to him, it is as easily done for (periisse), and that it vanishes the instant you call him by his name. Thin is the explanation given by Lindemann. Ritschel reads "pax," but most of the old Commentators have "tax," which seems the more probable reading. The passage is thus rendered in Thornton's translation:
<quote lang="en"><sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><l>'Tis Touchit;--that, sir, is my name.</l>
<l>A common one.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><l> A very knavish name:</l>
<l>As though you meant to say if anything</l>
<l>Was trusted to you, touch it, and 'tis gone.</l></sp></quote></note> you were to say, "Hush," if I were confiding anything to you, and then it is at an end forthwith. <stage>Aside.</stage> This fellow is evidently a sharper. What say you, young man----?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> What is it now? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Speak out; what do these persons owe you whom you are seeking?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> The father of this young man, Lesbonicus, delivered to me these two letters; he is a friend of mine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. I have now caught him in the fact; he says that I gave him the letters. I will have some fine sport with the fellow.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> As I have begun, if you will give attention, I will say on.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I'll give you my attention.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> He bade me give this letter to his son, Lesbonicus, and this other one, as well, he bade me give to his friend Callicles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. Troth, but since he is acting the impostor, I, on the other hand, have an inclination to act the cheat as well. Where was he himself?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> He was carrying on his business prosperously.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> But where? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> At Seleucia.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> * * * * * And did you receive these from himself?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> With his own hands he himself delivered them into my hands.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Of what appearance is this person?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> He is a person somewhere about half a foot taller than you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. This is an odd matter, if in fact I am taller when absent than when present. Do you know this person?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> You are asking me a ridiculous question; together with him I was in the habit of taking my meals.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What is his name?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> One, i' faith, that belongs to an honorable man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I would like to hear it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Troth, his name <stage>hesitating</stage>--his--his-- <stage>Aside.</stage> Woe to unfortunate me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What's the matter? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Unguardedly, I this moment swallowed the name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I like not the man that has his friends shut up within his teeth.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> And yet this moment 'twas dwelling on the very edge of my lips.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. I've come to-day in good time before this fellow.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. To my sorrow I'm caught in the fact.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Have you now recollected the name?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> 'Fore Gods and men, i' faith, I'm ashamed of myself</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> See, now, how well you know this man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> As well as my own self. This is in the habit of happening: the thing you are holding in your hand, and seeing with your eyes, that same you are looking for as lost. I'll recollect it letter by letter. C is the beginning of the name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Is it Callias? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> No: it isn't that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Callippus? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> It isn't that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Callidemides? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> It isn't that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Callinicus? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> No: it isn't that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Or is it Callimachus?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> 'Tis in vain you suggest; and, i' faith, I really don't care one fillip about it, since I recollect enough myself for my own purpose.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> But there are many people here of the name of Lesbonicus; unless you tell me the name of his father, I cannot show you these persons whom you are looking for. What is it like? Perhaps we can find it out by guessing.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> It is something like this: Char----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Chares? Or Charicles? Or is it Charmides?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Ah! that's he; may the Deities confound him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I have said to you once before already * * * * that it is proper for you rather to speak well of a man that is your friend, than to curse him.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Isn't it the fact<milestone n="925" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Isn't it the fact</lemma>:  He alludes to his having forgotten the confounded name, which was on the very tip of his tongue.</note> that this most worthless fellow has lain perdu between my lips and my teeth?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Don't you be cursing an absent friend.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Why, then, did this most rascally fellow hide himself away from me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> If you had only called him, he would have answered to his name. But where is he himself now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Troth, I left him at Rhadama<milestone n="928" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><p><lemma targOrder="U">At Rhadama</lemma>:  Rhadama is a fictitious name--pure gibberish.</p>
<p>Cercopia" is a preferable reading to "Cecropia," which was an epithet of Athens, itself supposed to be the scene of the Comedy. The other word would imply some unknown region, called "Apeland," as the Sharper's only aim is to impose upon the credulity of Charmides, and to hinder him from asking unseasonable questions. He coins the word upon the spur of the moment, though there really were the "Ape Islands," or the isles of Pithecus&aelig;, off the coast of Campania. They are mentioned by Ovid, in the 14th book of the Metamorphoses, l. 291: "For the father of the Gods, once abhorring the frauds and perjuries of the Cercropians, and the crimes of the fraudulent race, changed these men into ugly animals; that these same beings might be able to appear unlike men and yet like them. He both contracted their limbs and flattened their noses, bent back from their foreheads; and he furrowed their faces with the wrinkles of old age; and he sent them into this spot with the whole of their bodies covered with long yellow hair. Moreover, he first took away from them the use of language and of their tongues, made for dreadful perjury; he only allowed them to be able to complain with a harsh jabbering."</p></note>, in the isle of Apeland.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> * * * * * <stage>aside</stage>. What person is there a greater simpleton than I, who myself am making inquiries where I am? But it is by no means unimportant to this present purpose. What do you say as----?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> What now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I ask you this. What places have you visited?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Places exceedingly wonderful in astonishing ways.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I should like to hear about them, unless it is inconvenient.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Really I quite long to tell you. First of all we were conveyed to Pontus, to the land of Arabia<milestone n="933" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Land of Arabia</lemma>:  He gets out of depth directly he leaves imaginary places and touches on real countries. He makes Arabia to be in Pontus, while they were realy about two thousand miles asunder</note>.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> How now; is Arabia then in Pontus?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> It is. Not that Arabia where frankincense is produced, but where the wormwood grows<milestone n="935" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Wormwood grows</lemma>:  If he really refers here to Pontus. he accidentally hits upon the truth. Ovid, when in banishment there, says, in the Tristia, B. v. El. 13, l. 21, "Let the white wormwood first be wanting in the freezing Pontus." The Sharper tries to correct himself by saying he means another Arabia, and not the one generally known, where the frankincense grows.</note>, and the wild marjoram which the poultry love.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. An extremely ingenious knave this. But the greater simpleton I, to be asking of this fellow from what place I have come back, a thing which I know, and he does not know; except that I have a mind to try how he will get out of it at last. But what say you further? Whither did you go next from thence?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> If you give me your attention, I will tell you. To the source of the river which arises out of the heavens, from beneath the throne of Jupiter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Beneath the throne of Jupiter?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Yes: I say so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Out of the heavens?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Aye, out of the very middle.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> How now; and did you ascend even to the heavens?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Yes: we were carried in a little skiff<milestone n="942" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In a little skiff</lemma>:  "Horiola," or "horia," was a small skiff or smack used by fishermen.</note> right on, up the river, against the tide.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> And did you see Jupiter as well?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> The other Gods said that he had gone to his country-house, to dole out the victuals for his slaves. Then, after that----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Then after that--I don't want you to relate anything more.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Troth, I'm silent, if it's troublesome.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Why, no decent person<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">No decent person</lemma>:  He is supposed covertly to allude to the disgraceful story at Ganymede being carried off by the eagle to minister to the lust of Jupiter.</note> ought to tell it, who has gone from the earth to heaven.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> I'll leave you, as I see you wish it. But point me out these persons whom I am looking for, and to whom I must deliver these letters.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What say you? If now perchance you were to see Charmides himself, him, I mean, who you say gave you these letters, would you know the man?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> By my troth now, do you take me to be a brute beast, who really am not able to recognise the person with whom I have been spending my life? And would he have been such a fool as to entrust to me a thousand Philippean pieces, which gold he bade me carry to his son, and to his friend Callicles, to whom he said that he had entrusted his affairs? Would he have entrusted them to me if he had not known me, and I him, very intimately?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. I really have a longing now to swindle this swindler, if I can cozen him out of these thousand Philippean pieces which he has said that I have given to him. A person, that I know not who he is, and have never beheld him with my eyes before this day, should I be entrusting gold to him? A man, to whom, if his life were at stake, I would not entrust a dump of lead. This fellow must be adroitly dealt with by me. Hallo! Mister Hush, I want three words with you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Even three hundred, if you like.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Have you that gold which you received from Charmides?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Yes, and Philippeans, too, counted out on the table with his own hand, a thousand pieces.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> You received it, you mean, from Charmides himself?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> 'Twere a wonder if I had received it of his father, or of his grandfather, who are dead.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Then, young man, hand me over this gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> <stage>staring at him</stage>. What gold am I to give you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> That which you have owned you received from me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Received from you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Yes, I say so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Who are you? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I am Charmides, who gave you the thousand pieces of money.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> I' faith, you are not he; and this day, you never shall be he, for this gold, at any rate. Away with you, if you please, you impostor! <stage>Aside.</stage> You are trying to cheat the cheater.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I am Charmides. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> I' faith, you are so to no purpose, for I carry<milestone n="973" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">For I carry</lemma>:  He takes the other to be as great a rogue as himself and means, that his being Charmides only depended on whether he himself admitted that he was in possession of the gold of Charmides.</note> no gold. Right cleverly were you down upon me, at the very nick of time. After I said that I was bringing the gold, that instant you became Charmides. Before I made mention of the gold, you were not he. It won't do. Just, therefore, in such manner as you Charmidised yourself, do you again un-Charmidise yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Who am I, then, if in fact I am not he who I really am?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> What matters that to me? So long as you are not he whom I do not choose you to be, you may be who you like, for what I care. Just now, you were not he who you were, now you are become he who then you were not.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Come, despatch, if you are going to do it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> What am I to do?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Give me back the gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> You are dreaming, old gentleman.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Did you own that Charmides delivered the gold to you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Yes--in writing<milestone n="982" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Yes, in writing</lemma>:  This, of course, was the fact, as Megaronides and Callicles would know better than entrust the fellow with any money. It probably means that he was entrusted with a letter to Callicles, enclosing a counterfeit bill at sight, or order on the Athenian bankers for payment of a thousand Philippeans to Callicles. This, Callicles was to show to Lesbonicus, to put him off the scent as to the treasure whence the money really was taken. The Sharper has told Charmides that he has the money with him, merely by way of boasting of his trustworthy character.</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Are you making haste or not, you night-robber, to be off with all speed this very instant from this neighbourhood, before I order you to be soundly cudgelled on the spot?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> For what reason? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Because I am that self-same Charmides about whom you have been thus lying, and who you said gave the letters to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> How now; prithee, are you really he?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I really am he. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Say you so, pray? Are you really he himself?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I do say so. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Are you his own self?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> His own self, I say. I am Charmides.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> And are you then his own self?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> His own very self. Begone hence out of my sight.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Since you really have made your appearance here thus late, you shall be beaten both at my own award<milestone n="990" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At my own award</lemma>:  He means to tell Charmides, that by delaying his return thus late, he has spoilt his prospect of a lucrative job; and he then adds, that he deserves a thrashing, equally with the actor who came on the stage too late. The actors in early times, being often slaves, were liable to punishment if they offended the audience. The &AElig;diles were the officers under whose superintendence the plays were performed; and probably with them lay the decision whether the actor should be punished for coining late on the stage, after he had been pronounced deserving of it in the opinion (arbitratus) of the spectators. See the Note to l. 707.</note> and that of the new &AElig;diles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> And are you abusing me as well?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A SHARPER.</speaker><p> Yes; seeing that you have arrived in safety<milestone n="991" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Have arrived in safety</lemma>:  "Advenis." After this word, Callicles might suppose that the Sharper is going to congratulate him in the uenal terms on his safe arrival; but, instead of that, the fellow pauses, and then finishes with a malediction.</note>, may the Gods confound me, if I care a straw for you, had you perished first. I have received the money for this job; you, I devote to bad luck. But who you are, or who you are not, I care not one jot. I'll go and carry word<milestone n="995" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Go and carry word</lemma>:  To tell him that he has given the three pieces to no purpose, for the real Charmides has made his appearance, and has completely spoiled the plot.</note> to him who gave me the three pieces, that he may know that he has thrown them away. I'm off. Live with a curse, and fare you ill; may all the Gods confound you, Charmides, for coming from abroad<milestone n="997" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From abroad</lemma>:  This scene is replete with true comic spirst It has been supposed by some that the disgrace of the pedant in Shakspeare's Taming of the Shrew, and his assuming the name and character of Vincentio, were suggested by this scene. A similar incident is met with in the old play of Albumazar act iv., sc. 3. and most probably it was borrowed from the present passage.</note>. <stage>(Exit.)</stage>

<milestone n="988" unit="TLN line"/></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Since this fellow has gone, at last a time and opportunity seem to have arrived for speaking out without restraint. Already does this sting pierce my breast--what business he could have before my house? For these letters summon apprehensions into my heart; those thousand pieces, too--what purpose they were to serve. I' faith, a bell<milestone n="1004" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I' faith, a bell</lemma>:  He aptly compares the worthless fellow to a bell, and then shrewdly judges that a bell cannot ring unless it is put in motion by somebody.</note> is never rung for no purpose; unless some one handles it or moves it, 'tis mute, 'tis dumb. But who is this, that is beginning to run this way along the street? I should like to observe what he is about. I'll step aside this way. <stage>He retires aside.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="3">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1008" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter STASIMUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. Stasimus, make you haste with all speed; away with you to your master's house, lest on a sudden, through your folly, fears should arise for your shoulder-blades<milestone n="1009" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">For your shoulder-blades</lemma>:  The slaves among the Romans were whipped most unmercifully with the "flagellum," a whip, to the handle of which a lash was fastened, made of cords or thongs of leather, especially from the ox's hide. It was often knotted with bones, or pieces of bronze, or terminated by hooks, and was then not inaptly termed "a scorpion." The infliction of punishment with this on the naked back was sometimes fatal, and was carried into execution by a class of slaves who were called "lorarii."</note>. Quicken your pace, make haste; 'tis now a long while since you left the house. If you shall be absent when inquired after by your master, take you care, please, that the smacks of the bull's-hide<milestone n="1011" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Smacks of the bull's-hide</lemma>:  "Cottabus" was a game played by the Sicilians and Greeks, in which the players had in turn to throw wine out of a goblet into a metal basin at a certain distance, in such a way as not to spill any of the wine. The methods in which the game was played are stated with precision in an able article in Dr. Smith's Dictionary. As one of the merits of the game was that the wine thrown should in its fall produce the strongest and most pat sound, Stasimus here calls the smacks of the whip on his back so many "<foreign lang="la">bubuli cottabi</foreign>," "ox-hide smacks."</note> don't clatter thick upon you. Don't you cease running. See now, Stasimus, what a worthless fellow you are; and isn't it the fact that you have forgotten your ring<milestone n="1014" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Forgotten your ring</lemma>:  We learn from C&aelig;lius Rhodiginus that "condalium" was a peculiar kind of ring worn by slaves.</note> at the liquor- shop<milestone n="1013" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At the liquor-shop</lemma>:  The "thermopolia" are supposed to have been the same as the "popin&aelig;," shops where drinks and ready-dressed provisions were sold. They were very numerous throughout Italy. The keepers of them were called "pop&aelig;." In the present instance we learn what kind of people visited them, and Cicero tells us that they were frequented by the slaves and the lower orders. They sat on stools or benches, while they drank "calda," or "calida," "mulled wine," which was always kept hot. It was probably mixed with spices, and was the favourite drink of the lower classes. It was measured out in "poteria," "draughts," which are here mentioned; and which formed, probably, about a moderate cupful. Claudius commanded the "thermopolia" to be closed at one period of his reign.</note> after you have been washing your throat with warm drink? Turn about, and run back now, to seek it, while the thing has but just happened.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Whoever he is, his throat is his taskmaster<milestone n="1016" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">His throat is his taskmaster</lemma>:  He has overheard what Stasimus has said about warming his throat in l. 1014; and, talking to himself, he remarks that his throat will be the cause of his learning how to run, as he warms his throat, gets drunk, loses his ring, runs homeward, and then runs back to find it.</note>; that teaches this fellow the art of running.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> What, good-for-nothing fellow, are you not ashamed of yourself? having lost your memory after only three cups? And really, because you were there drinking together with such honest fellows, who could keep their hands off<milestone n="1019" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Would keep their hands off</lemma>:  There is no doubt that this is intended to be said satirically.</note> the property of another without difficulty;--is it among such men that you expect you may recover your ring? Chiruchus was there, Cerconicus, Crimnus, Cricolabus, Collabus<milestone n="1021" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Cricolabus, Collabus</lemma>:  These are either nicknames, or, possibly, names really given to slaves, as in all ages and countries masters have especially tried to show their wit in naming their slaves.</note>, whipped-necks<milestone n="1022" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Whipped-necks</lemma>:  "Collicrepid&aelig;" and "Cruricrepid&aelig;" were probably cant terms for slaves, who carried the marks of punishment on their necks and legs. "Crepid&aelig;" is from the verb "crepo," to "crack," and alludes to the sound of the lashes. "Ferriterius" was a slave who bore the marks of the chain with which he had been fastened for refractory conduct, while "mastigia" was a name given to a slave who had passed the ordeal of flogging. A liquor-shop was a likely place for the resort of worthless and refractory slaves.</note>, whipped-legs, iron-rubbers, whipped-knaves. By my faith, any one of these could steal the sole of his shoe from a running footman<milestone n="1023" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From a running footman</lemma>:  "Cursores" were slaves who ran before the carriage of their masters for the same purpose as our outriders. Perhaps, however, this is not the meaning of the word here, as the name was given to all slaves whom their masters employed in carrying letters and messages. Stasimus hints by this that his boon companions were not only very expert at thieving, but that they would prey inst as readily on a fellow-slave as any other person.</note>.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. So may the Gods love me, a finished thief.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Why should I go seek what is gone for ever? Unless I would bestow my pains, too, by way of addition over and above to my loss. Why, then, don't you consider that what is gone is gone? Tack about, then<milestone n="1026" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Tack about, then</lemma>:  "Cape vorsoriam" was a sea-phrase, meaning "'turn," or "tack about;" as "vorsoria" was the name of the rope by which the sail was turned from one direction to another</note>. Betake yourself back to your master.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. This fellow is no runaway; he remembers his home.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I wish that the old-fashioned ways of old-fashioned days, and the old-fashioned thriftiness, were in greater esteem here, rather than these bad ways.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Immortal Gods! this man really is beginning to talk of noble doings! He longs for the old-fashioned ways; know that he loves the old-fashioned ways, after the fashion of our forefathers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> For, now-a-days, men's manners reckon of no value what is proper, except what is agreable. Ambition now is sanctioned by usage, and is free from the laws. By usage, people have the license to throw away their shields, and to run away from the enemy. To seek honor thereby in place of disgrace is the usage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. A shameless usage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Now-a-days, 'tis the usage to neglect the brave.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Aye, 'tis really shocking.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> The public manners have now got the laws in their power; to them they are more submissive than are parents to their children<milestone n="1038" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Parents to their children</lemma>:  This is said satirically in reference to the corruptness of the age, in which all the relations and duties of life were turned upside down.</note>. In their misery, these laws are even hung up<milestone n="1039" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Are even hung up</lemma>:  He alludes to the custom among the Romans of writing or engraving the laws and ordinances on wood or brass, and hanging them up for public inspection upon pegs or rails in the Capitol, Forum, and Curi&aelig;, or Court-houses.</note> against the wall with iron nails, where it had been much more becoming for bad ways to be fixed up.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. I'd like to go up and accost this person; but I listen to him with much pleasure, and I'm afraid, if I address him, that he may begin to talk on some other subject.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> And, for these ways, there is nothing rendered sacred by the law. The laws are subservient to usage; but these habits are hastening to sweep away both what is sacred and what is public property.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. By my troth, 'twere right for some great calamity to befal these bad customs.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Ought not this state of things to be publicly censured? For this kind of men are the enemies of all persons, and do an injury to the entire people. By a non-observance of their own honour, they likewise destroy all trust even in those who merit it not; inasmuch as people form an estimate of the disposition of these from the disposition of those fellows. If you lend<milestone n="1050" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">If you lend</lemma>:  Stasimus has experienced this, and has applied for the talent which he lent, but in rain; unless, indeed, his meaning is that he got back the talent, but lost his friend. Shakspeare has a somewhat similar passage in Hamlet:
<quote lang="en"><l>Neither a borrower nor a lender be;</l>
<l> For loan oft loseth both itself and friend.</l></quote></note> a person any money, it becomes lost for any purpose as one's own. When you ask for it back again, you may find a friend made an enemy by your kindness. If you begin to press still further, the option of two things ensues--either you must part with that which you have entrusted, or else you must lose that friend. As to how this suggests itself to me, I have by actual experience been lately put in mind of it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Surely this is my servant Stasimus?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> For as to him to whom I lent the talent, I bought myself an enemy with my talent, and sold my friend. But I am too great a simpleton to be attending to public matters rather than (what's my immediate interest) obtain safety for my back. I'll go home. <stage>Moves as if going.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Hallo, you! Stop, this instant! Harkye; hallo, you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I'll not stop. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I want you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> What if I myself don't want you to want me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Why, Stasimus, you are behaving very rudely.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> 'Twere better for you to buy some one to give your commands to.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I' faith, I have bought one, and paid the money, too. But if he is not obedient to my orders, what ani I to do?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Give him a severe punishment.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> You give good advice; I am resolved to do so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Unless, indeed, you are under obligations to him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> If he is a deserving person, I am under obligations to him; but if he is otherwise, I'll do as you advise me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> What matters it to me whether you have good or lad slaves?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Because you have a share in this matter both of the good and of the bad.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> The one share I leave to yourself; the other share, that in the good, do you set down<milestone n="1067" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Do you set down</lemma>:  "Appone." This word is used figuratively, it being employed to mean, in mercantile matters, "to set down to one's account." So Horace says:
<quote lang="la"><l>Qnem sors dierum cumque dabit, lucro</l>
<l> Appone----</l></quote>
"Whatever lot each day shall bring, set that down as clear gain." This, we may here observe, is a similar sentiment to that conveyed in the remark of Callicles, L. 65.</note> to my account.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> If you shall prove deserving, it shall be so. Look back at me--I am Charmides.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Ha! what person is it that has made mention of that most worthy man?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> 'Tis that most worthy man himself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> O seas, earth, heavens, by my trust in you--do I see quite clearly with my eyes? Is this he, or is it not? 'Tis he! 'Tis certainly he; 'tis he beyond a doubt! O my most earnestly wished-for master, health to you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Health to you, too, Stasimus!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> That you are safe and sound, I----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> <stage>interruptitng him</stage>. I know it, and I believe you. But wave the rest; answer me this; how are my children, my son and daughter, whom I left here?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> They are alive, and well.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Both of them, say you? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Both of them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> The Gods willed me to be safe and preserved from dangners. The rest that I want to know I will inquire about in-doors at my leisure. Let us go in-doors; follow me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Where are you going now? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Where else but to my house?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do you suppose that we are living here?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Why, where else should I suppose?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Now---- </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What about "now?"</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> This house is not our own.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What is it I hear from you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Your son has sold this house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I'm ruined. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> For silver min&aelig;; ready money counted out.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> How many? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Forty.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I'm undone. Who has purchased it?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Callicles, to whom you entrusted your affairs; he has removed here to live, and has turned us out of doors.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Where is my son now living?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Here, in these back buildings. <stage>Points to the side of the house.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I'm utterly undone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I thought that this would be distressing to you when you heard of it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> To my sorrow, amid extreme dangers I have been borne over vast oceans, with the peril of my life I have preserved myself among robbers full many in number, and I have returned safe. Now, to my misery, I am here undone by reason of those same persons for whose sake I have been struggling at this time of life Grief is depriving me of my senses. Support me, Stasimus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Do you wish me to fetch you some water?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> When my fortunes were in their mortal struggle, then was it befitting that water should be sprinkled<milestone n="1092" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Should be sprinkled</lemma>:  His meaning is, "you should have beer as ready to give your assistance at the time when my fortunes were in their death- struggle through the conduct of my son Lesbonicus."</note> upon them.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="4">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1093" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter CALLICLES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What noise is this that I hear before my house?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> O Callicles! O Callicles! O Callicles! to what sort of friend have I entrusted my property?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> To one good, and faithful, and trusty, and of strict integrity. Health to you, and I rejoice that you have arrived safe and sound<milestone n="1097" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Safe and sound</lemma>:  The lines after this, enclosed in brackets, are supplied by Ritschel in Latin verse, to supply the "lacuna" here, where it is clear that some part of the play has been lost. They are cleverly composed, and do great credit to his ingenuity.</note>.
<gap/></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> How, health to me? Troth, I have no patience with such health. This I wish to know; how have you kept your trust, who, without my knowledge, have utterly destroyed my property and my children that I entrusted to you and committed to your charge when going hence abroad?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I don't think that it is fair, when you don't understand the matter, to censure your old friend with harsh words. For you are both mistaken and you are doing me a very great injustice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Have you not bought this house which you came out of just now, and driven thence my son Lesbonicus? Is this so as I say, or is it not? Answer me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I myself did buy the house; I bought it that I might keep it for you. And without that it would have happened that your son would have sold it to another person; and then you would have lost both it and that treasure together, which, concealed there, you had entrusted to my charge. See, I restore it safe to you; for you did I buy it, not for myself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Prithee, what do you say? By my trust in Gods and men, you make me suddenly to be quite ashamed of my error in speaking unkindly to my friend in return for his services.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> How, then; do you now think that I am trusty and faithful?]</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I do think so,, if all these matters are so as you relate them. But what means<milestone n="1099" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">But what means</lemma>:  As he has been interrupted while digging up the treasure, it is probable that he has run out with his sleeves tucked up. and perhaps with the spade in his hand, which causes Charmides to make the present inquiry.</note> this garb of yours?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I'll tell you. I was digging up the treasure indoors, as a marriage-portion to be given to your daughter. But I will relate to you both this and the rest in the house. Follow me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Stasimus. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> Well!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Run with all haste to the Pir&aelig;us<milestone n="1103" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The Pir&aelig;us</lemma>: -- The Pir&aelig;us was the main harbour of Athens, with which it was connected by long walls.</note>, and make but one run of it. There you will at once see the ship, on board of which I was carried hither. Bid Sagario take care that the things are brought which I enjoined him, and do you go together with them. The duty has been already paid<milestone n="1107" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Been already paid</lemma>: -- Among the Romans, merchandise which a person brought with him from abroad for his own use was in general exempt from "portorium," or import duty; but this was not the case if it belonged rather to the luxuries than the necessaries of life.</note> to the custom-house officer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I make no delay. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Get you gone with all speed; and be back directly.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> I am both there and here in an instant.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> <stage>to CHARMIDES.</stage> Do you follow me this way indoors. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I follow. <stage>(Exeunt CALLICLES and CHARMIDES into the house.)</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>STASIMUS</speaker><p> This man alone has remained a firm friend to my master; nor has he allowed his mind to swerve from unshaken fidelity, although I believe that he has undergone many troubles, by reason of the property and the children of my master. Still, this person, as I suspect, alone has maintained his fidelity. <stage>(Exit.)</stage>

</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="5">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1115" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYSITELES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> This individual<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">This individual</lemma>: -- He is speaking of himself in the third person, and is congratulating himself on his being about to obtain the hand of the daughter of Charmides.</note> is the very first of all men; excelling all in pleasures and delights. So truly do the blessings which I desire befal me, that whatever I undertake is brought about, and constantly succeeds: so does one delight succeed other delights. Just now, Stasimus, the servant of Lesbonicus, came to me at home. He told me that his master, Charmides, had arrived here from abroad. Now he must be forthwith waited upon by me, that the father may prove a more sure foundation in that matter on which I have treated with his son. I'll go. But this door, with its creaking, inopportunely causes me delay. <stage>He retires to a distance.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1125" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter CHARMIDES and CALLICLES.</stage>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> There never was, nor will there be, nor yet do I think that there is a person upon the earth, whose fidelity and constancy towards his friend equals yours. For without you, it would have been that he would have ousted me out of this house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> If I have in any way acted well towards my friend, or have faithfully consulted his advantage, I seem not to be deserving of praise, but I think I am free from fault. For a benefit which is conferred on a man for his own, at once is lost to the giver; what is given only as a loan, the same there is a right to ask back, whenever you please.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> 'Tis so as you say. But I cannot sufficiently-wonder at this, that he has betrothed his sister into a family so influential.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Aye; to Lysiteles, the son of Philto.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Why, he is mentioning my name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> He has got into a most worthy family.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Why do I hesitate to address these persons? But still, I think, I may wait awhile; for something is going to be said to the purpose about this matter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> O---- </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> What's the matter?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I forgot just now to tell you of it in-doors. Au I was coming hither, a while ago, a certain swindling fellow met me--a very finished sharper. He told me that he was carrying a thousand gold pieces, of my giving, to you and my son Lesbonicus; a fellow, that I know not who he was, nor have I ever seen him anywhere before. But why do you laugh?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> He came by my directions, as though he was one bringing the gold from you to me, to give as a portion to your daughter; that your son, when I should give it to her from my own hands, might suppose that it had been brought from you, and that he might not anyhow be enabled to discover the fact itself--that your treasure was in my possession, and demand it of me<milestone n="1146" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And demand it of me</lemma>: -- On the supposition of his father's death, the laws would probably have decreed it to him as his father's heir.</note>, as having belonged to his father, by the public laws.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Cleverly contrived, i' troth. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Megaronides, a common well-wisher of yours and mine, planned this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Well, I applaud his device, and approve of it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> <stage>behind</stage>. Why, in my foolishness, while I fear to interrupt their discourse, am I standing here alone, and am not forwarding the business that I was intending to trans act? I will accost these persons. <stage>He advances.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Who is this person that is coming this way towards us?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> <stage>going up to CHARMIDES</stage>. Lysiteles salutes his father-in-law Charmides.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> May the Gods grant you, Lysiteles, whatever you may desire.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Am I not worthy of a salutation?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Yes; health to you, Callicles. It is right that I should give him the preference: the tunic is nearer<milestone n="1154" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The tunic is nearer</lemma>: -- This was, perhaps, a proverbial saying, used when a preference was expressed. Of course he would pay more respect to his anticipated father-in-law than to an ordinary friend. The "tumca" supplied the place of the shirt of modern times.</note> the skin than the cloak.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> I trust that the Gods may direct your plans aright.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I hear that my daughter has been betrothed to you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Unless you are unwilling. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Nay, I am not unwilling.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Do you, then, promise your daughter for my wife?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I promise a thousand gold Philippean pieces, as well, for a portion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I care nothing about a portion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> If she pleases you, the portion which she presents to you must be pleased as well. In fine, the object which you desire you shall not have, unless you shall take that which you do not desire.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> <stage>to LYSITELES</stage>. He asks but justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> He shall obtain it, you the advocate and the judge. On these conditions, do you engage that your daughter shall be given to me as my wife?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> I do promise her. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> And I promise her likewise.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> O save you, my connexions by marriage. <stage>He embraces them.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> But, in good sooth, there are some matters on account of which I still am angry with you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> What have I done? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Because you have allowed my son to become dissolute.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Had that been done by my consent, there would have been cause for you to blame me. * * * * * But allow me to obtain of you this one thing which I entreat?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> What is it? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> You shall know. If he has done anything imprudently, that you will dismiss it all from your mind. Why do you shake your head?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> My heart is tortured, and I fear----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> What is it now? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Because he is such as I would that he was not,--by that am I tortured. I fear that if I refuse you what you ask of me, you may suppose that I am indifferent towards you. I won't make difficulties, however; I will do as you wish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> You are a worthy man. I am going to call him out. <stage>He goes to the door of the house of CHARMIDES</stage>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> 'Tis a shocking thing if one is not allowed to punish bad deserts just as they merit.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> <stage>knocking at the door</stage>. Open the door, open quickly, and call Lesbonicus out of doors, if he is at home. The occasion is very sudden, therefore I wish him to come to me with all haste.

<milestone n="1176" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LESBONICUS from the house.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> What person has been calling me out of doors with so loud a knocking?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> 'Tis your well.wisher and friend</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Is all quite right?--tell me.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> All's well. I am glad to say that your father has returned from abroad.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Who says so? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> I.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Have you seen him? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYSITELES</speaker><p> Aye, and you yourself may see him too. <stage>He points to CHARMIDES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> O my father, my father, blessings on you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Many blessings on you, my son.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> If, father, any trouble<milestone n="1181" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">If, father, any trouble</lemma>: --  Lesbonicus seems to be about to apologise to Charmides for any trouble he may have given him, but, as the old man has already agreed to forgive him at the intercession of Lysiteles, he will not allow a word more to be said about it.</note>---- </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Have no fear, nothing has happened. My affairs prosperously managed, I have returned safe. If you are only wishful to be steady, that daughter of Callicles has been promised you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> I will marry both her, father, and any one else besides that you shall bid me</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> Although I have been angry with you, one misery<milestone n="1185" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">One misery</lemma>: -- The old gentleman tells his son that he will be quite sufficiently punished for his faults by having one wife. It is either said as a joke in a bantering way, or else it means, that, what will be a great punishment to him, he must now reform his mode of life, for common decency sake and out of respect to his wife.</note>, in fact, is more than enough for one man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CALLICLES</speaker><p> Nay, rather, 'twere too little for him; for if he were to marry a hundred wives for his sins, it were too little.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> But henceforth, in future, I will be steady.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> So you say; if you will only do it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LESBONICUS</speaker><p> Is there any reason why I should not bring my wife home to-morrow?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>CHARMIDES</speaker><p> 'Tis very good. And you, Lysiteles, be ready to be married the day after to-morrow.
<stage>A COMEDIAN.</stage></p>
<p>Give your applause<milestone n="1189" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Give your applause</lemma>: -- <foreign lang="la">Plaudite</foreign>. Literally, "clap your hands." Ritschel, on a full examination of the MSS., comes to the conclusion that this was said, not, as is generally thought by one of the characters in the play, but by one of the actors or singers, probably, of the Chorus, who commenced their song the moment the play was finished. All the applause bestowed on the writer and the actors seems to have been usually reserved for the end of the play.</note>.
</p></sp></div2></div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
