<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>

<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
<author>Hyperides</author>
&responsibility;
&fund.AnnCPB;
</titleStmt>
<extent>about 195Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
	<monogr>
		<author>Hyperides</author><title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>
	
		<imprint><publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher><date>1962</date></imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="speech"/>
<state unit="section"/>
<state unit="fragment"/>
</refsDecl>

<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2" n="speech=5">
<state unit="speech"/>
<state unit="fragment"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date>May 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>June 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>4/30/93</date><respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>add refdecl, changed some of the FRAG attributes that had commentary in them, made notes have a space after them.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<div1 n="1" type="speech">
<head>In Defence of Lycophron</head><p>
    <milestone unit="fragment" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . each man in private and in public life,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Blass, comparing <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.1">Aeschin. 3.1</bibl>, conjectured the sense to be: &ldquo;I come before you now having put my trust both in the gods, on whom you all rely in private and in public life, and also in the law, etc.&rdquo;</note>  and also in the law and in the oath which bids you give an equal hearing to the prosecution and to the defence.
<milestone unit="fragment" n="2"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . to conduct the prosecution,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense is no doubt: &ldquo;Since you allowed my opponents to conduct the prosecution as they wished, allow me also a fair hearing in my defence.&rdquo;</note> allow me also in the same way to follow out, so far as I am able, the line of defence which I have chosen.  I must ask you all, while I am speaking, to refrain from interrupting me with: &ldquo;Why are you telling us this?&rdquo; And do not add anything of your own to the prosecution's argument; rather &lt;attend&gt; to the defence . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="3"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . nor is it true that the law, while allowing freedom to join in the prosecution of men on trial, denies the right to share in their defence.  I do not intend to waste words before coming to the point, and shall therefore proceed to the actual defence, after praying the gods to help me and bring me safely through the present trial and requesting you, gentlemen of the jury, first . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="3a"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . either the betrayal of dockyards, the burning of public buildings, or the seizure of the Acropolis . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="4"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . Euphemus . . . first . . . when the husband died . . . of <placeName key="tgn,7012055">Phlya</placeName> . . . from him . . . that the woman . . . he had left his wife with child, which did not entail any breach of the law.  But if their interpretation of this story tallied with that given by Ariston in the impeachment, they<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The reference seems to be to those relatives due to benefit by the will in the event of the child's death.  See Introduction.</note>  should not surely have prevented the nearest relatives from ejecting Euphemus.  They ought to have let them do so.  Whereas now, by behaving as they did, they have by their own action furnished evidence that the charge against me is false.  Besides, is it not strange that if anything had happened to the child at birth, or after, they would have adhered firmly to this will, in which . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="4a"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . nor is it possible for him to deny his own handwriting
<milestone unit="fragment" n="4b"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . to be sluggish. . . 
<milestone unit="section" n="1"/>. . . and he had Ariston's slaves in his works.  This fact he confirmed for you himself<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The subject is probably Theomnestus.</note>  in court when Ariston was bringing an action against Archestratides.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing is known of this man.  He may be the Archestratides against whom Hyperides composed a speech.  Compare <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 52">Hyp. Fr. 52.</bibl></note>
<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Let me explain the kind of method which this man Ariston employs.  He issues a summons against everyone he meets, accusing and prosecuting those who do not give him money, but letting go all who are willing to pay.  He gives the money to Theomnestus who takes it and buys slaves, providing Ariston with a livelihood, as is done for pirates, and paying him an obol a day for each slave, to enable him to continue permanently as a false informer.
<milestone unit="section" n="3"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When considering the matter, gentlemen of the jury, we ought to begin with the charges which my accusers themselves brought against me at the outset in the Assembly.  My relatives communicated the impeachment to me by letter, and also the charges which they made against me in the Assembly when they brought the impeachment in.  Among these was recorded a statement of Lycurgus, who claimed to have been told by the relatives that during the wedding of Charippus to the woman I followed and tried to persuade her to reserve herself and have nothing to do with Charippus.
<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Let me now repeat to you the answer which I gave to the relatives and also to my own relations directly I arrived, namely this.  If these accusations are true, I agree to having done all the other things set down in the impeachment.  But they are false, as is surely obvious to everyone.
<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>For who is there in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> so uncritical as to believe these allegations?  There must have been attenders, gentlemen of the jury, with the carriage that conveyed the bride: first a muleteer and a guide, and then her escort of boys, and also Dioxippus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For Dioxippus, the athlete who accompanied Alexander to <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> &lpar;<bibl n="Diod. 17.100">Diod. Sic. 17.100.2</bibl>&rpar;, see Introduction to the speech.</note> For he was in attendance, too, since she was a widow being given away in marriage.
<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Was I then so utterly senseless, do you think, that with all those other people in the procession, as well as Dioxippus and Euphraeus his fellow-wrestler, both acknowledged to be the strongest men in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, I had the impudence to pass such comments on a free woman, in the hearing of everyone, and was not afraid of being strangled on the spot?  Would anyone have listened to such remarks about his sister as these men accuse me of having made, without killing the speaker?
<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>And to crown it all, as I said just now, are we to conclude that Charippus was so completely obtuse that he was still prepared to marry her, although in the first place she said beforehand, according to their story, that she was pledged to me and in the second place he heard me encouraging her to keep the promises she had made?  Do you think that the mad Orestes, or Margites,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Margites, the hero of an old comic epic early attributed to Homer, came to be regarded as the typification of a fool.</note> the greatest fool of all time, would act like that?
<milestone unit="section" n="8"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But then, in my opinion, gentlemen of the jury, the prosecutors in a trial have many advantages over the defendants.  For them the case involves no risk,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the importance of this statement for determining the date of the speech see Introduction.</note> and so they are free to talk and lie to their heart's content, while the men on trial are afraid and so forget to mention a great deal, even of what they have really done.
<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Also, accusers, speaking first, do not confine themselves to putting the just arguments which support their case, but trump up baseless slanders about the accused and so deprive them of the means of defence.  The latter are thus affected in one of two ways.  Either they defend themselves against the extraneous charges and fall short in the relevant parts of their defence, or else they forget the accusations which have just been made, and so leave the jury with the impression that these are true.
<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>In addition to this the accusers create a prejudice against the advocates for the defence and distort the case of the accused himself; which is what Ariston here attempted to do, when speaking for the prosecution, since he does not even allow me to benefit from those who come forward to help me intending to share in my defence.  What reason is there why they should not?  Is it not right that men on trial should be supported by their relatives and friends?  Or is there any custom in the city more democratic<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Compare <bibl n="Hyp. 4.11">Hyp. 4.11</bibl>.</note> than that which permits citizens capable of public-speaking to assist those who are incapable when they are in trouble?
<milestone unit="section" n="11"/>But you, Ariston, have not merely discussed my advocates; you even determine my own arguments and tell the jury what they must listen to, what line of defence they must prescribe for me, and what they must not tolerate.  Surely it is most unfair that after conducting the prosecution as you wanted you should rob me of my defence, because you know already the honest answers I can offer to your lies.
    <milestone unit="section" n="12"/>And you accuse me in the impeachment of undermining the democracy by breaking the laws; but you override every law yourself, by presenting an impeachment in a case where the laws require a public charge before the Thesmothetae.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A list of offences for which impeachments were appropriate is given in <bibl n="Hyp. 4.8">Hyp. 4.8</bibl>.  The Thesmothetae were concerned mainly with crimes directed against the state, but they also dealt with cases of assault and adultery &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">u(/bris</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">moixei/a</foreign>&rpar;.  See <bibl n="Hyp. 4.6">Hyp. 4.6</bibl> and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 59">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 59</bibl>.</note> Your object was to run no risk in bringing in the action and also to have the opportunity of writing tragic phrases<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For this use of the noun <foreign lang="greek">tragw|di/a</foreign> compare <bibl n="Hyp. 4.26">Hyp. 4.26</bibl>.  The verb <foreign lang="greek">tragw|de/w</foreign> is used with a similar sense by Demosthenes &lpar;e.g. <bibl n="Dem. 18.13">Dem. 18. 13</bibl>&rpar;.</note> in the impeachment, such as you have written now, protesting that I am making many women grow old unmarried in their homes and many live illegally with men unsuited for them.
<milestone unit="section" n="13"/>The fact is that you can instance no other woman in the city whom I have wronged in this way, and as for the subject of your present charge, what view did you take of her?  Was she right to live with Charippus, an Athenian citizen who was her husband; or was she growing old unmarried in her home,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This passage is not very clearly expressed in the Greek.  Lycophron is answering the charge that he causes women &lpar;a&rpar; to grow old unmarried; &lpar;b&rpar; to live with the wrong men.  Taking these points in the reverse order he retorts by asking whether in the present case the woman is &lpar;b&rpar; doing wrong by living with her legal husband or &lpar;a&rpar; growing old unmarried.  In view of the words <foreign lang="greek">ou)prosh/kei</foreign> in &sect; l2 above, a negative before <foreign lang="greek">prodh/kein</foreign> would make the sense of what follows much clearer.  Kirchhoff's suggested emendation is therefore rather tempting.</note> she who was married at once, as soon as Euphemus supplied a talent of silver as a dowry, obviously with no ulterior motive but simply out of kindness?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Probably Ariston had alleged that Euphemus was acting in collusion with Lycophron, but we have no details.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="14"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>So Ariston may say whatever he pleases, gentlemen of the jury, and invent lies against me, but surely your verdict upon me must be based, not on the slanders of the prosecutor, but on a review of the whole of my life.  No one in the city, whether good or bad, can deceive the community in which you live.  Indeed the most reliable testimonial of character which a man can have is his past career, especially in refuting charges like the present.
<milestone unit="section" n="15"/>Where the crime is one which can be committed at any time during a man's life it should be considered in the light of the particular accusation made.  But adultery is a practice which no man can begin after fifty.  Either he has been a loose-liver for a long lime&mdash;and let these men prove that that is true of me&mdash;or else the charge may be presumed false.
<milestone unit="section" n="16"/>Now I, gentlemen of the jury, have lived with you in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> all my life.  I have never been subjected to any discreditable charge, nor have I brought an accusation against another citizen.  I have not been defendant or prosecutor in any lawsuit, but have always been a keen horsebreeder, consistently overtaxing my strength and my resources.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Horsebreeding, which was carried on either for war or racing, was sometimes frowned on as a mark of wealth and ostentation.  &lpar;Compare <bibl n="Lyc. 1.139">Lyc. 1.139</bibl>. &rpar;.  But here, though he admits extravagance, Lycophron is simply claiming to be doing his duty as a knight.</note> I have been crowned for bravery by the order of knights and by my colleagues in office.
    <milestone unit="section" n="17"/>For you appointed me, gentlemen of the jury, first as Phylarch and later as Cavalry Leader at <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The ten phylarchs, one from each tribe, commanded the cavalry of their own tribe under the hipparchs.  Of these there were two elected from the whole people.  One of them was appointed to command a body of Athenian cavalry in <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>, after the Athenians gained control of the island by the Peace of Antalcidas in <date value="-387">387</date> B.C.  Compare <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 61.6">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 6l. 6</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 4.27">Dem. 4. 27</bibl>;<title>CIA</title>2. 14 and 593.</note> I held the command there for two years, the only cavalry leader who has ever done so, and prolonged my stay for a third, as I did not wish, in exacting the pay for the horsemen rashly, to burden citizens in financial straits.
<milestone unit="section" n="18"/>During that time no one there brought an action against me, either private or public.  In fact I was crowned three times by the inhabitants of Hephaestia and as many times more by those of Myrine.  These facts should satisfy you, in the present trial, that the charges against me are false.  No man can be good in <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> if he is bad in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and you had no poor opinion of me when you dispatched me there and made me responsible for two of your own cities.
<milestone unit="section" n="19"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Well, gentlemen of the jury, you have heard virtually all that I had to say in my own defence.  The prosecutor, who is an experienced speaker and used to frequent litigation, summoned advocates<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The chief of these advocates was the orator Lycurgus.  See Introduction to the speech.</note> to help him in unjustly ruining a citizen.  So I too am asking you, most earnestly, for your authority to summon my advocates in this important case, and I beg you to give a sympathetic hearing to any of my relatives or friends who can help me.
<milestone unit="section" n="20"/>I am a fellow-citizen of yours, an amateur unused to speaking, on trial now with the risk not only of losing my life&mdash;a minor consideration to men with a proper sense of values&mdash;but also of being cast out after death, without even the prospect of a grave in my own country.  So if you will give the word, gentlemen of the jury, I will call an advocate.  Will you please come up, Theophilus, and say what you can in my defence?  The jury ask you to do so.</p></div1>
<div1 n="1a" type="speech">
<head>Second Speech in Defence of Lycophron</head><p>
<milestone unit="fragment" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As for his digging through the wall to have intercourse with the woman: that is quite incredible.  For the accuser<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Presumably Ariston.</note> has not shown either that he fell out with the people who had previously been serving him and readily submitting to any orders he gave them, or that they had a quarrel with him and so refused their services, thus inducing Lycophron to dig through the wall, as their persons were no longer . . . would not have dug through the wall.  Why should a man who was not pressed for time and had the chance both of receiving news from her and giving his own messages and . . . and . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Evidently the invalid husband's name was given here, but it cannot be restored with certainty.</note> never forbade him &lpar;?&rpar; the house.  Besides, it is almost out of the question for her servants to have quarrelled with him.  Which one of them could have grown so rash as to withhold either his messages to her or hers to him, for reasons of personal spite?  For the danger was imminent, if . . . what these men assumed.  In actual fact they saw their master in an extremely weak condition and had their mistress, the future ruler of the household, constantly before their eyes as a reminder that, if he died, they would be punished in return for what they had done against her wishes.  It is therefore incredible that Lycophron dug through the wall; nor was he accustomed, as the accuser claims, to converse with the servants.  What reason would he have had for doing so?  Why should they have quarrelled with him, whom, as their mistress grew more favorably disposed to him . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="5"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>What then are the proofs on which he bases his demand to the jury to condemn Lycophron?  He actually bases it on the evidence of his kinsmen by marriage, Anaschetus, Theomnestus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For Theomnestus compare <bibl n="hyp. 1.2">Hyp. 1. 2.</bibl></note> and Criton; and it would be as well for you, gentlemen of the jury,. to examine it carefully.  For the whole accusation . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="13"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . that &lsqb;when he was about to marry?&lsqb; his sister to Charippus, Dioxippus went away to <placeName key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> where he was to win a crown for his city, but that meanwhile Lycophron sent letters saying . . .</p></div1>
<div1 n="2" type="Speech">
<head>Against Philippides</head><p>
<milestone unit="fragment" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . in a free city furthering the interests of tyrants . . . towards slavery . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="6"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . was responsible for actions which did credit to the city and to <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The subject is perhaps <placeName key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName>, an Athenian commander who was often praised in this way.  Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.14">Din. 1. 14</bibl> and note.</note> Therefore both here and everywhere else he was paid the highest honors . . . rightly . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="8"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . we must thank Alexander on account of those who died . . . but I think. . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="10"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Moreover these men trample on the people in their misfortune, and for this reason they deserve your hatred far more.  For just as human bodies need most care when they are sick, so it is with cities, which need most attention in times of misfortune.  To these men  ?&rpar; only . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="11"/>. . . [Very fragmentary.]
<milestone unit="fragment" n="15a"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . each of them gives, one in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, another in <placeName key="perseus,Tanagra">Tanagra</placeName> . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="15b"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Or that they do not pray for the overthrow of all that is left in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, when they are deriving profits from the cities that are being destroyed?  Or that, while they wish you to spend your lives in fear and danger . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="21"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Unimpressive in person on account of his thinness.
<milestone unit="section" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . make accusations.  And they make it clear that even when they were friends of the Lacedaemonians<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Hyperides may be alluding to the period from 378 to <date value="-371">371</date> B.C., when <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> were at war with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>.</note> their speeches were prompted not by love for them but by hatred of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and a willingness to flatter those whose power at any time threatened you.
    <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>And when the power recently shifted from them to Philip they then chose to flatter him and Democrates of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Democrates of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> was a politician whom Aeschines mentions &lpar;<bibl n="Aeschin. 2.17">Aeschin. 2. 17</bibl>;cf. <bibl n="Isaeus 6.22">Isaeus 6. 22</bibl>&rpar;.  He had quite a reputation for wit and some of his sayings are preserved.  As a descendant of one of the tyrant-slayers, probably of Aristogiton, who appears to have been a member of the tribe <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName>, he enjoyed free meals in the Prytaneum, a privilege to which apparently only the eldest of each line was entitled &lpar;<title>CIA</title>1.8; 2. 240&rpar;.</note> who never leaves their sides . . . makes jokes on the city's misfortunes, abusing you in the market place by day and then coming at evening to dine at your table.  And yet you, Democrates, are the one person who has no right to say a single hard word against the state, for two reasons:
    <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>first because you needed no one but yourself to show you that the city is grateful to her benefactors, you who now enjoy the honors for services which other men once rendered; and secondly because the people drew up a law forbidding anyone to speak ill of Harmodius and Aristogeiton or sing disparaging songs about them.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Harmodius and Aristogiton are mentioned again in <bibl n="Hyp. 6. 39">Hyp. 6. 39</bibl>.  This particular privilege is not elsewhere recorded.</note> It is therefore scandalous that, though the people saw fit to prevent even a drunken man from abusing your ancestors, you should be speaking ill of the state even when you are sober.
    <milestone unit="section" n="4"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I have a few more points to make, gentlemen of the jury, and after summing up my argument will leave the platform.  The case in which you are going to vote is an indictment for the proposing of illegal measures and the decree under consideration is one congratulating presidents.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In the 4th century B.C. the chairman of the <foreign lang="greek">pruta/neis</foreign> appointed these presidents by lot, one from each tribe except that to which he himself belonged, for each meeting of the Council or Assembly.  After their appointment he drew lots among them for their chairman &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">e)pista/ths</foreign>&rpar;.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.104">Aeschin. 1. 104</bibl>, <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.39">Aeschin. 3. 39</bibl>, and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 44.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 44. 2</bibl>.&rpar;</note> Presidents should observe the law during their period of office.  These men have broken it.  As evidence for both these facts you heard the actual laws read.
<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>The sequel now rests with you.  For you will make it plain whether you are going to punish the proposers of illegal measures or whether you intend to grant those honors, which till now have been paid to your benefactors, to presidents whose conduct is not lawful; and that too when you have sworn to observe the laws in giving your vote.  There is, however, one argument open to them, namely that the people were compelled to pass the votes of honor.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">i. e., the votes of honor for certain Macedonians.  Hyperides agrees that it may have been impossible to avoid passing the votes of honor, but that there was no need to congratulate the presidents for having done so.</note> Even this cannot possibly mislead you; for it cannot be said that we were under any compulsion to crown the presidents.
<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Moreover the defendant has himself made your decision easy, since he stated in writing his reasons for crowning them.  They had, he said, been just towards the Athenian people and observed the laws during their office.  That is a statement for which you must now summon him to answer.  And you, Philippides, show us that what you assumed about the presidents in your decree is true and you will be acquitted.
<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>But if you think that your usual vulgarity and joking will secure your pardon in court or win from these men any indulgence or sympathy to which you are not entitled, you are a fool and very far from the mark.  You see, you laid up popularity for yourself, not in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but elsewhere.  You thought fit to cringe before those whom the people feared rather than before the men who now have power to save you.
<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>You have concluded that one person will be immortal,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This passage is important for determining the date of the speech.  It has been held, e. g., by <placeName key="tgn,1029705">Kenyon</placeName>, that the remark is a gibe, in which there would be no point unless Philip were already dead.  But the use of the perfect tense &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">u(pei/lhfas</foreign>&rpar; seems to imply that he was still living when Hyperides spoke, or had only just been killed.</note> yet you sentenced to death a city as old as ours, never realizing the simple fact that no tyrant has yet risen from the dead, while many cities, though utterly destroyed, have come again to power.  You and your party took no account of the history of the Thirty or of the city's triumph over her assailants from without and those within her walls who joined in the attack upon her.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The reference is to the return of the democrats to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in <date value="-403">403</date> B.C., under Thrasybulus, who had to contend both with the Spartans under Lysander and with the Thirty.</note> It was well known that you were all watching the city's fortunes, waiting for the chance to say or do something against the people.
    <milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Will you dare then presently to mention opportunities, when the opportunities you sought were for the city's ruin?  Have you brought your children with you into court, Philippides?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the bringing of children into court compare <bibl n="Hyp. 4.41">Hyp. 4.41</bibl>.</note> Are you going to bring them soon on to the platform and so claim pity from the jury?  You have no right to pity.  When others felt compassion for the city's misfortunes, you and your like were exulting over her.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">At the time of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> &lpar;<date value="-338">338</date> B.C.&rpar;.</note> They had resolved to save <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in a spirit which ill deserved the fate they met.  But you, who are unjustly bringing <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> into the depths of shame, deserve the punishment you are now about.to suffer.
<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Why should you spare this man, gentlemen?  Because he is a democrat?  Why, you are well aware that he has chosen to be the slave of tyrants and is ready on the other hand to give the people orders.  Would it be because he is a good man?  No; for you twice condemned him as a criminal.  True, you may say, but he is useful.  Granted; but if you use a man whom you are known to have condemned as wicked, it will appear either that your judgements are wrong or that you welcome wicked men.  It is not therefore right to take upon yourselves this man's misdeeds.  On the contrary: the transgressor must be punished.
    <milestone unit="section" n="11"/>And if anyone comes forward with the plea that he has twice before been convicted for illegal proposals and that therefore you should acquit him,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The penalties for illegal proposals and for giving false witness seem to have been  the same, although the exact rules governing them in the 4th century B.C. are not quite clear.  In the 5th century a man three times convicted of false witness was automatically disfranchised &lpar;See <bibl n="Andoc. 1.74">Andoc. 1.74</bibl>&rpar;, and the present passage suggests that in the 4th century too a third conviction led to partial <foreign lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign>.  &lpar;Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 51.12">Dem. 51.12</bibl> and <bibl n="Plat. Laws 937">Plat. Laws. 937 c</bibl>, evidently inspired by current Athenian practice.&rpar;  The actual penalty seems to have been a fine; but if this was not paid the prosecutor had the right to enforce the judgement by a suit of ejection&lpar;<foreign lang="greek">di/kh e)cou/lhs</foreign>&rpar; and thus partially disfranchise the culprit.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Isoc. 16.47">Isoc. 16. 47</bibl>.&rpar;  When orators speak as if <foreign lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign> were inevitable after any conviction they are probably exaggerating.</note> please do just the opposite, and that for two reasons.  In the first place it is a piece of good fortune, when a man is known to have proposed illegal measures, that you should catch him coming up for trial a third time.  He is not a good man and need not be spared as such.  Indeed you should rid yourselves of him as quickly as you can, since he has twice already proved his character to you.
<milestone unit="section" n="12"/>And secondly, compare the case of false witness.  If people have been twice convicted of this, you have allowed them to refrain from giving evidence a third time, even of events at which they have themselves been present, so that, if anyone is disfranchised, responsibility shall rest, not on the people, but on the man himself, for continuing to bear false witness.  Similarly men convicted of illegal proposals need not bring forward proposals in future.  If they do they are clearly actuated by some private motive.  So that people of this type deserve punishment, not pity.
<milestone unit="section" n="13"/>I do not wish to speak too long after setting myself as a limit an amphora of water in the clock; so the clerk will read you the indictment again.  And now bear in mind the accusations and the laws which you heard read and bring in a verdict that will be just and also expedient for yourselves.</p></div1>
<div1 n="3" type="speech">
<head>Against Athenogenes</head><p>
<milestone unit="section" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When I told her what had happened and explained that Athenogenes was rude to me and unwilling to come to any reasonable agreement, she said that he was always like that and told me not to worry, as she would support me in everything herself.
<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Her manner when she said this could not have been more sincere, and she took the most solemn oaths to prove that she was thinking only of my welfare and was telling me the plain truth.  So, to be quite honest with you, gentlemen of the jury, I took her at her word.  That is how love, I suppose, upsets a man's natural balance when it takes a woman as its ally.  She, at any rate, by this act of wholesale trickery pocketed, as a reward for her kindness, a further three hundred drachmas, ostensibly to buy a girl.
<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Perhaps there is nothing very surprising, gentlemen of the jury, in my having been taken in like this by Antigone, a woman who was, I am told, the most gifted courtesan of her time and who has continued to practise as a procuress . . . has ruined the house of . . . of the deme Chollidae which was equal to any.  And yet if that was how she behaved on her own, what do you think her plans are now when she has taken Athenogenes into partnership, who is a speechwriter, a man of affairs and, most significant of all, an Egyptian?
    <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>At all events, to make a long story short, she finally sent for me again later and said that after a long talk with Athenogenes she had with difficulty managed to persuade him to release Midas and both his sons for me for forty minas.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This was a high price for three slaves.  Demosthenes tells us that the total cost of his father's fifty-two slaves &lpar;thirty-two swordsmiths and twenty couchmakers&rpar; was 230 minas, i.e., an average of just under eight pounds per head.  &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 27.9">Dem. 27. 9</bibl>.&rpar;</note> She told me to produce the money as quickly as I could before Athenogenes changed his mind on any point.
<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>After I had collected it from every source and been a nuisance to my friends I deposited the forty minas in the bank and came to Antigone.  She brought us both together, Athenogenes and myself, and after reconciling us asked us to treat each other as friends in future.  I consented to this and Athenogenes, the defendant, replied that I had Antigone to thank for what had passed.  &ldquo;And now,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;I will show you how well I am going to treat you for her sake.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the explanation of this offer see Introduction.</note> You are going to put down the money,&rdquo; he went on, &ldquo;for the liberation of Midas and his sons.  Instead I will sell them to you formally as your own, so that no one shall interfere with, or seduce the boy, and also so that the slaves themselves shall abstain from being troublesome, for fear of the consequences.
<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>But this is the chief advantage: under the present arrangement they would think that it was I who had freed them; whereas, if you buy them formally first and then liberate them afterwards at your leisure, they will be doubly grateful to you.  However,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;you will become responsible for what money they owe: a debt for some sweet oil to Pancalus and Procles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The name is given as Polycles in &sect; 10.</note> and any other sums which customers have invested in the perfumery in the ordinary course.  It is a trifling amount and much more than counterbalanced by the stocks in the shop, sweet oil, scent-boxes, myrrh&rdquo; &lpar;and he mentioned the names of some other things&rpar;, &ldquo;which will easily cover all the debts.&rdquo;
<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>There, so it seems, gentlemen of the jury, lay the catch, the real point of the elaborate plot.  For if I used the money to buy their freedom I was simply losing whatever I gave him without suffering any serious harm.  But if I bought them formally and agreed to take over their debts assuming, since I had no previous information, that these were negligible, he meant to set all his creditors and contributors<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">I.e., friends who had made loans to the business.  The money would be repaid in instalments free of interest. Cf. &sect;&sect; 9 and 11.</note> on me, using the agreement as a trap.
<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>And that is just what he did.  For when I accepted his proposals he immediately took a document from his lap and began to read the contents, which were the text of an agreement with me.  I listened to it being read, but my attention was concentrated on completing the business I had come for.  He sealed the agreement directly in the same house, so that no one with any interest in me should hear the contents, and added with my name that of Nicon of Cephisia.
<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>We went to the perfumery and deposited the document with Lysicles of Leuconoe, and I put down the forty minas and so made the purchase.  When this was settled I was visited by the creditors, to whom Midas owed money, and the contributors too, who talked things over with me.  In three months all the debts had been declared, with the result that, including repayment of contributions, I owed, as I said just now, about five talents.
<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>When I realized what a plight I was in, at long last I called together my friends and relatives and we read the copy of the agreement in which the names of Pancalus and Polycles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The name is given as Procles in &sect; 6.  It is not known which is the correct form.</note> were expressly written with the statement that certain sums were owing to them for sweet oil.  These were small amounts, and they were justified in saying that the oil in the shop was equal in value to the money.  But the majority of the debts, including the largest, were not given specifically; they were mentioned as an unimportant item in a sort of footnote which ran:
<milestone unit="section" n="11"/>&ldquo;and any debt which Midas may owe to any other person.&rdquo;  Of the contributions one was noted of which three instalments for repayment were still outstanding.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See &sect; 7, note.</note> This was given in the name of Dicaeocrates.  But the others, on the strength of which Midas had acquired everything and which were of recent date, were not entered by him in the agreement but kept secret.
<milestone unit="section" n="12"/>On thinking it over we decided to go to Athenogenes and broach the matter.  We found him near the perfume stalls and asked him whether he was not ashamed of being a liar and trapping us with the agreement by not declaring the debts beforehand.  He replied that he did not know what debts we meant and that we made no impression on him; he had in safe-keeping a document relating to me which covered the transaction.  A crowd gathered and overheard the incident, as our altercation took place in the market.  Although they gave him a slating and told us to arrest him summarily as a kidnapper,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Summary arrest &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">a)pagwgh/</foreign>&rpar;  by which the injured party seized the criminal and took him before the magistrate, could be used against various types of offender, e.g., thieves and kidnappers.  Athenogenes was not actually a kidnapper, but he was driving a man to debt, which, though it did not lead to enslavement, might result in total <foreign lang="greek">atimi/a</foreign>.</note> we thought it best not to do so.  Instead we summoned him before you, as the law permits.  First of all then, the clerk shall read you the agreement; for you shall have the actual text of the document as evidence of the plot, for which Athenogenes and no other is to blame.  Read the agreement.<quote type="Agreement"></quote>
<milestone unit="section" n="13"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Well, gentlemen of the jury, you have heard the facts in detail.  But Athenogenes will presently tell you that in law whatever agreements one man makes with another are binding.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This law is quoted elsewhere,e.g., by <bibl n="Dem. 47.77">Dem. 47.77</bibl>.</note> Yes, my friend, just agreements.  But if they are unjust, the opposite is true: the law forbids that they be binding.  I will quote the laws themselves to make this clearer to you.  For you have reduced me to such a state of fear lest I shall be ruined by you and your craftiness that I have been searching the laws night and day and studying them to the neglect of everything else.
    <milestone unit="section" n="14"/>The first law, then, stipulates that people shall not tell lies in the market, which seems to me a most admirable provision.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The first of these two laws cited by the plaintiff is mentioned also by <bibl n="Dem. 20.9">Dem. 20.9</bibl>.  It was enforced by the ten agoranomoi, whose duty it was to guard against fraud in all questions of purchase.  See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 51">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 51</bibl>.  For the second law compare <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.249">Aeschin. 3.249</bibl> and <bibl n="Plat. Laws 915c">Plat. Laws. 915 c.</bibl></note> Yet you lied in the middle of the market when you made the agreement to defraud me.  But if you show that you declared to me beforehand the contributions and the debts, or that you wrote in the agreement the names of those whose existence I later discovered, I have no quarrel with you; I admit that I owe the money.
<milestone unit="section" n="15"/>After this there is a second law, covering agreements between individuals, which states that whenever anyone sells a slave, he must declare in advance any physical disability from which the man suffers.  Otherwise the slave in question can be returned to the vendor.  And yet if a slave can be returned simply because of some weakness due to mischance which the master keeps secret at the time of the sale, how can you fail to take the responsibility for the crimes which you deliberately planned?  But the epileptic slave does not involve the buyer in fresh expense, whereas Midas, whom you sold to me, has even lost my friends' money.
    <milestone unit="section" n="16"/>Consider the legal position, Athenogenes, as regards free persons as well as slaves.  No doubt you know as everyone does that the children of married women are legitimate.  Yet the mere act of betrothing a woman on the part of a father or brother was not enough for the lawmaker.  On the contrary, he wrote expressly in the law<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This law is mentioned by Demosthenes &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 44.49">Dem. 44.49</bibl>&rpar; and quoted in <bibl n="Dem. 46.18">Dem. 46.18</bibl>, from which the text is here reconstructed.</note> : &ldquo;whomsoever any man has lawfully betrothed as wife, her children shall be legitimate&rdquo;; not: &ldquo;if any man has betrothed some other woman on the pretence that she is his daughter.&rdquo;  He lays it down that just betrothals shall be valid and unjust ones invalid.
    <milestone unit="section" n="17"/>Moreover the law dealing with wills is very similar to this.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This law is quoted in <bibl n="Dem. 46.14">Dem.  46.14</bibl>.  Compare <bibl n="Isaeus 6.10">Isaeus 6.10</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 35">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 35</bibl>.  As Colin points out, the comparison between <foreign lang="greek">sunqh=kai</foreign> &lpar;an agreement  and <foreign lang="greek">diaqh/lkh</foreign>  a will&rpar; seems closer in Greek than in English.</note> It allows a man to bequeath his property as he wishes unless he is affected by old age, illness or insanity, and provided he is not influenced by a woman or imprisoned or otherwise coerced.  But if even our own personal property cannot be administered according to an unjust will, surely Athenogenes who is disposing of my property through his agreement cannot enforce such terms.
<milestone unit="section" n="18"/>Apparently if a man respects the wishes of his own wife in making his will it will be invalid.  Then must I, who was influenced by the mistress of Athenogenes, accept the contract and be ruined too,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The argument is rather condensed; the contrast is this: A will may be otherwise just and yet it becomes invalid when made under the influence of a wife.  Therefore, a fortiori, this contract becomes invalid because &lpar;1&rpar; it was not just in other respects, &lpar;2&rpar; it was made under the influence of a woman less reputable than a wife.</note> even though I can claim the very powerful help of the law, having been compelled by these people to conclude the agreement?  Do you insist on the agreement when you and your mistress laid a trap for me to get it signed?  In circumstances where the laws relating to conspiracy proclaim that you are guilty, are you expecting actually to make a profit?  You were not content with the forty minas for the perfumery.  No; you robbed me of a further five talents as though I were caught . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The exact words cannot be restored but the sense is: &ldquo;It is absurd for Athenogenes, a shrewd business man, to plead ignorance, when I with no experience of the market discovered the facts so soon without effort.&rdquo;</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="19"/>the affairs of the market, but by simply waiting I discovered all the debts and loans in three months.  Whereas this man had two generations of perfume sellers behind him; he used to sit in the market every day, was the owner of three stalls and had accounts submitted to him monthly and still he did not know his debts.  Though an expert in other matters he was a complete simpleton in dealing with his slave, and though he knew, apparently, of some of the debts, he pleads ignorance of others&mdash;to suit his convenience.
<milestone unit="section" n="20"/>In using an argument like this, gentlemen of the jury, he is accusing, not excusing, himself, since he is admitting that I need not pay the debts.  For if he says that he did not know the full amount owing, surely he cannot claim that he informed me of the debts beforehand; and I am not bound to pay those of which the seller did not notify me.  You knew that Midas owed this money, Athenogenes, as I think we all realize for several reasons, and chiefly because you summoned Nicon to give security for me<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This passage was restored by Blass, partly following Revillout, to give the following meaning: &ldquo; . . . because you summoned Nicon to give security for me, knowing that I could not meet the debts alone without his help.  And indeed I cannot, but I want to get to grips with this claim of yours that you did not know who had invested what sums, or what the individual debts were.  Let us consider it in this way.&rdquo;  For Nicon see &sect; 8.</note> . . .
<milestone unit="section" n="21"/>in this way.  If ignorance prevented you from informing me in advance of all the debts, and if I thought when I concluded the agreement that your statement covered them all, which of us has to pay them?  The subsequent purchaser, or the man who owned the business originally, when the money was borrowed?  Personally I think that you are liable.  But if it turns out that we disagree on this, let the law be our arbiter, which was made neither by lovers nor men with designs on other people's property but by that great democrat Solon.
    <milestone unit="section" n="22"/>He knew that sales are constantly taking place in the city and passed a law, which everyone admits to be just, stating that any offences or crimes committed by a slave shall be the responsibility of the master who owns him at the time.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This law, which does not seem to be mentioned elsewhere, is not strictly applicable here, since the plaintiff had agreed in his contract to assume responsibility for Midas's debts.  However, it was a fair law, and if Athenogenes had not intended to take advantage of the plaintiff he would have been willing to observe it.  <foreign lang="greek">zhmi/an e)rga/zesqai</foreign>, which appears to be an old legal phrase, is variously understood.  Other interpretations than that adopted in the translation are: &lpar;1&rpar; to incur loss, &lpar;2&rpar; to incur a fine.</note> This is only fair; for if a slave gains any success or brings in earnings, his owner enjoys the benefits.  But you ignore the law and talk about agreements being broken.  Solon did not consider that a decree, even when constitutionally proposed, should override the law.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This provision of Solon is mentioned by <bibl n="Andoc. 1.87">Andoc. 1.87</bibl> and by <bibl n="Dem. 23.87">Dem. 23.87</bibl>.</note> Yet you maintain that even unjust agreements take precedence over all the laws.
<milestone unit="section" n="23"/>Besides this, gentlemen of the jury, he was saying to my father and my other relatives that . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense evidently is: &ldquo;that he offered me the one boy as a present and asked me to leave Midas.&rdquo;Cf.&sect; 27.</note> telling me to leave Midas for him instead of buying him, but that I refused and wanted to buy them all.  I gather that he is even going to mention these points to you with the idea of convincing you of his moderation, if you please.  He must think that he is going to address a set of fools who will not realize his effrontery.
<milestone unit="section" n="24"/>You must hear what happened; for you will see that it fits in with the rest of their plot.  He sent me the boy, whom I mentioned just now, with the message that he could not stay with me unless I freed his father and brother.  When I had already agreed to put down the money for the three of them, Athenogenes approached some of my friends and said:
<milestone unit="section" n="25"/>&ldquo;Why does Epicrates want to give himself extra trouble when he could take the boy and use . . .?&rdquo;
<milestone unit="section" n="26"/>I am not a seller of perfume<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The general sense of this mutilated passage is restored by Colin, in his translation, as follows: &ldquo;Despite his dishonest purpose, I accepted his word, and when he offered me the boy, raised no objection over the price.  I thus agreed to pay 40 minas, but I now find I must produce five talents for a perfumery in which I have no interest.&rdquo;</note> and I do not practise any other trade.  I simply farm the property which my father gave me, and I was landed in the purchase by these people.  Which is more probable, Athenogenes, that I set my heart on your trade in which I was not proficient, or that you and your mistress had designs on my money?  Personally, I think that you are indicated.  Therefore, gentlemen of the jury, you could fairly excuse me for being cheated by . . . and for having had the misfortune to fall in with a man like this, but to Athenogenes . . .
<milestone unit="section" n="27"/>all to be mine and the profits of the fraud to be his.  . . . that I took Midas . . . whom he says he was reluctant to let go.  But for the boy whom, we are told, he originally offered me for nothing, he has now been paid a far higher price than he is worth; and yet in the end the boy will not be my property but will be freed on the strength of your verdict.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The point of this remark is not clear.  The plaintiff might mean that if he wins his case the boy will be freed, since he never intended to buy him as a slave; but the following sentence suggests that he has in mind at present the consequences of his condemnation.</note>
    <milestone unit="section" n="28"/>However I do not think myself that in addition to my other troubles I deserve to be disfranchised by Athenogenes.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Disfranchisement could only follow upon condemnation if the plaintiff failed to obtain one-fifth of the votes and so became liable to pay <foreign lang="greek">e)pwbeli/a</foreign>,i.e.,  compensation to Athenogenes at the rate of one-sixth of the sum in question.  On failure to pay this he would become liable to prosecution again &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">di/kh e)cou/lhs</foreign>&rpar; and if condemned would have to pay a fine to the state too.  Finally as a state debtor he would be liable to loss of civic rights &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign>&rpar;.  The payment of <foreign lang="greek">e)pwbeli/a</foreign> certainly obtained in mercantile, and some other cases, and probably in cases of damage also.  See <bibl n="Andoc. 1.73">Andoc. 1.73</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 21.44">Dem. 21.44</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 27.67">Dem. 27.67</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 28.21">Dem. 28.21</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 47.64">Dem. 47.64</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.163">Aeschin. 1.163</bibl>.</note> For I should be receiving harsh treatment indeed, gentlemen of the jury, if . . . of the metics to come unguarded.
<milestone unit="section" n="29"/>During the war against Philip he left the city just before the battle and did not serve with you at <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.  Instead, he moved to <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, disregarding the law<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This law, which is not mentioned by any other writer appears to be the same as the one subsequently read out &lpar;&sect; 33&rpar; which forbade resident aliens to emigrate in time of war.  It is not clear, however, why the clause quoted here should relate to an attempted return on the part of the lawbreaker rather than to his actual departure.  If the plaintiff is making a valid point we must assume that the law existed before the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, since it was then that Athenogenes left <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.  If so, it must have applied to resident aliens only &lpar;as indeed appears from &sect; 33 to have been the case&rpar; for had it applied to citizens, Lycurgus would surely have mentioned it in his speech against Leocrates, as he was there concerned with just this question.  It is possible, however, that Hyperides is alluding to some provision which did not come into force until the time of emergency after <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, but is attempting to impose on the ignorance of his hearers.</note> which says that a man who moves in wartime shall be indicted and summarily arrested if he returns.  The reason for the move, it seems, was this: he thought that the city of <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> would survive, whereas he had passed a sentence of death on ours.  His daughters whom he had brought up in the prosperity which you provided . . . he married off . . . with the intention of returning later to carry on his business when peace was established.
<milestone unit="section" n="30"/>. . .
<milestone unit="section" n="31"/>after disregarding the agreement which we all make with the state, he insists on his private contract with me, as if anyone would believe that a man who made light of his duty to you would have cared about his obligations to me.  He is so degraded and so true to type wherever he is, that even after his arrival at <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> when they had made him a citizen he became the tool of Mnesias the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Mnesias the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> is mentioned as a traitor by Demosthenes.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Dem. 18.295">Dem. 18.295</bibl>, where, however, the name is spelt <foreign lang="greek">*mnase/as</foreign>.&rpar;</note> and, after being made a magistrate by him, expelled the citizens from the city.  The men themselves will bear witness to this; for they are here in exile.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">As these men were still in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Alexander's decree of <date value="-424">424</date> B.C., providing that exiles should return, cannot yet have been issued.  Hence we have a terminus ante quem for the speech.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="32"/>And you, gentlemen of the jury, took them in when they were banished; you made them citizens and granted them a share of all your privileges.  Remembering, after more than a hundred and fifty years,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The Athenians sent women and children to <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> before the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Cic. Off. 3.11.48">Cic. de Offic. 3. 11.48</bibl>.&rpar;  Hence we have a rough terminus post quem for the speech.</note> the help they gave you against the barbarian, you felt that when men had been of service to you in times of danger you should protect them in their misfortune.  But this abandoned wretch, who forsook you and was enrolled at <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, engaged in nothing that was worthy either of the constitution or the spirit of that city.  He treated those who had welcomed him so cruelly that . . . in the Assembly . . . fled.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense appears to be, as Colin suggests, that he was accused in the Assemhly of the Troezenians, and, fearing punishment, fled back to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="33"/>To prove that what I say is true the clerk will read you first the law, which forbids metics to move in war time, then the evidence of the Troezenians and also the Troezenians' decree passed by them in honor of your city, in return for which you welcomed them and made them citizens.  Read.<quote type="Law. Evidence. Decree"></quote>
<milestone unit="section" n="34"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now take the evidence of the father-in-law<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Revillout suggests that the defendant called for the father-in-law to give evidence that Athenogenes had been lavishing all his money on Antigone.</note> . . .
<milestone unit="section" n="35"/>the way in which Athenogenes has plotted against me and also his behavior towards you.  If a man has been vicious in his private life and given up hope of his city's safety; if he has deserted you and expelled the citizens from the town of his adoption, will you not punish him when he is in your power?
<milestone unit="section" n="36"/>For my part, gentlemen of the jury, I beg you most earnestly to show me mercy.  Remember in this trial that you ought to have pity . . . suffer nothing if he is convicted . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="1"/>...</p></div1>
<div1 n="4" type="Speech">
<head>In Defence of Euxenippus</head><p>
    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Personally, gentlemen of the jury, as I was just saying to those seated beside me,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The opening words are the same as those of the speech against Demosthenes.</note> I am surprised that you are not tired by now of this kind of impeachment.  At one time the men impeached before you were Timomachus, Leosthenes, Callistratus, Philon of Anaea, Theotimus who lost <placeName key="perseus,Sestos">Sestos</placeName>, and others of the same type.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Timomachus was an Athenian general who failed in his command against Cotys of <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> &lpar;c. <date value="-361">361</date> B.C.&rpar;, and on his return to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> was condemned either to death or to a heavy fine.  See <bibl n="Dem. 19.180">Dem. 19.180</bibl>, and the scholiast on <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.56">Aeschin. 1.56</bibl>.  Leosthenes, who led an Athenian fleet against Alexander of Pherae &lpar;c. <date value="-361">361</date> B.C.&rpar;, lost five triremes, was condemned to death at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and went into exile.  See <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.124">Aeschin. 2.124</bibl>, and <bibl n="Diod. 15.95">Diod. Sic. 15.95.2</bibl>.  For Callistratus, a prominent orator, exiled at about the same time and later put to death, see <bibl n="Lyc. 1.93">Lyc. 1.93</bibl>.  Theotimus, also about the year 361, was impeached for losing <placeName key="perseus,Sestos">Sestos</placeName> to Cotys.  Of PhiIon nothing further is known.</note> Some were accused of betraying ships, others of giving up Athenian cities, and another, an orator, of speaking against the people's interests.
<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Though there were five of them, not one waited to be tried; they left the city of their own accord and went into exile.  The same is true of many others who were impeached.  In fact it was a rare thing to see anyone subjected to impeachment appearing in court.  So serious and so notorious were the crimes which at that time led to an impeachment.  But the present practice in the city is utterly absurd.
<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Diognides and Antidorus the metic are impeached on a charge of hiring out flute-girls at a higher price than that fixed by law, Agasicles of <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Agasicles, according to Harpocration and Suidas &lpar;sv. <foreign lang="greek">*)agasiklh=s</foreign>&rpar;, though an alien, bribed the people of Halimus to enroll him in their deme.  The former adds that Dinarchus wrote a speech prosecuting him for this.  See <bibl n="Din. Fr. 7">Din. Fr. 7</bibl>.</note> because he was registered in Halimus, and Euxenippus because of the dreams which he claims to have had; though surely not one of these charges has anything to do with the impeachment law.
<milestone unit="section" n="4"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>And yet in public trials, gentlemen of the jury, the jury should refuse to listen to the details of the prosecution until they have first considered the point at issue, and also the written statement of the accused, to see if the pleas are legally valid.  It is certainly wrong to maintain, as Polyeuctus did in his speech for the prosecution, that defendants should not insist on the impeachment law; which lays it down that impeachments shall be reserved for the orators themselves, when they speak against the interests of the people, but shall not apply to every Athenian.
<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>With me this law would have first claim to notice; and a point, I think, which should be dwelt on as much as any, is how to ensure that the laws in a democracy are binding and that impeachments and other actions brought into court are legally valid.  It was with this in view that you made separate laws covering individually all offences committed in the city.
    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Suppose someone commits a religious offence.  There is the method of public prosecution before the King-Archon.  Or he maltreats his parents.  The Archon presides over his case.  Someone makes illegal proposals in the city.  There is the board of Thesmothetae ready.  Perhaps he does something involving summary arrest.  You have the authority of the Eleven.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The King-Archon, who supervised all religious ceremonies of state, judged all cases connected with religion, while the Archon himself dealt with family law.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57.2</bibl> and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 56.6">Aristot. Ath. Pol.  56.6</bibl>.&rpar;  For the Thesmothetae compare <bibl n="Hyp. 1.12">Hyp. 1.12</bibl> and note.  Summary arrest could be legally employed against three classes of criminal.  Of these, two were tried by the Eleven and one by the Thesmothetae.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 52.1">Aristot. Ath. Po1. 52.1</bibl>.&rpar;</note> Similarly, to deal with every other offence you have established laws, offices, and courts appropriate to each.
<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>In what cases then do you think impeachments should be used?  Your answer has already been embodied in detail in the law, so as to leave no room for doubt.  &ldquo;If any person,&rdquo; it says, &ldquo;seeks to overthrow the democracy of the Athenians.&rdquo;  Naturally, gentlemen of the jury; for a charge like that admits of no excuse from anyone nor of an oath for postponement.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A man due to be tried could offer the court an excuse &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">skh=fis</foreign>&rpar; and provide a second party to take an oath &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">u(pwmosi/a</foreign>&rpar; that this excuse was true.  In such cases the jury might grant a postponement.</note> It should come directly into court.
<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>&ldquo;Or if he attends a meeting in any place with intent to undermine the democracy, or forms a political society; or if anyone betrays a city, or ships, or any land, or naval force, or being an orator, makes speeches contrary to the interests of the Athenian people, receiving bribes.&rdquo;  The opening provisions of the law were made applicable by you to the entire citizen body, since those are offences which anyone might commit; but the latter part is directed against the orators themselves, in whose hands the proposing of measures rests.
<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>You would have been insane if you had framed the law in any other way; if, when the orators enjoy both the honors and the profits of speaking, you had exposed the ordinary citizen to the risks that go with them.  Nevertheless, Polyeuctus is bold enough to assert, though he is bringing in an impeachment, that defendants must not make use of the impeachment law.
<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>All other prosecutors who think it necessary, when speaking first, to steal the defendants' arguments from them encourage the jury to refuse to listen to any defendant who does not keep within the scope of the law, to challenge his statements and tell the clerk to read the law.  The opposite is true of you: it is recourse to law of which you think you should deprive Euxenippus in his defence.
    <milestone unit="section" n="11"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You also maintain that no one should even help him or be his advocate, and you exhort the jury to refuse a hearing to those who come up to speak.  And yet, of the many good institutions of the city, what is better or more democratic<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Compare <bibl n="Hyp. 1.10">Hyp. 1.10</bibl>.</note> than our custom, when some private person is facing the danger of a trial and cannot conduct his own defence, of allowing any citizen who wishes to come forward to help him and give the jury a fair statement of the case?
    <milestone unit="section" n="12"/>You will claim, no doubt, that you have never worked on such a principle.  Yet when you were prosecuted by Alexander of Oeon,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing further is known of this trial.  For other occasions on which Hyperides opposed Polyeuctus compare <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 24">Hyp. Fr. 24</bibl> and<bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 25">Hyp. Fr. 25</bibl>.</note> you asked for ten advocates from the tribe Aegeis, and I was one of them, chosen by yourself.  You also summoned men from other tribes into the court to help you.  But why should I mention other instances?  Take your handling of the present trial.  Did you not make as many accusations as you wished?  Did you not call Lycurgus to join you in the prosecution, a speaker who is the equal of any in the city and who has the reputation among these gentlemen of being sound and honorable?
<milestone unit="section" n="13"/>If you then, as a defendant, may summon advocates, or as a prosecutor may bring in co-prosecutors&mdash;you who are not merely capable of speaking for yourself but well able to give a whole city trouble&mdash;is Euxenippus, because he is not a professional speaker and is now advanced in years, even to be denied the help of friends and relatives, on pain of their being abused by you?
<milestone unit="section" n="14"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Yes; for in the words of your indictment, his conduct has been scandalous and deserves the death penalty.  Gentlemen of the jury, will you please review it and scrutinize it point by point?  The people ordered Euxenippus, as one of three, to lie down in the temple; and he tells us that he fell asleep and had a dream which he reported to them.  If you assumed, Polyeuctus, that this was true and that he reported to the people what he actually saw in his sleep, why is he to blame for notifying the Athenians of the commands which the god had been giving him?
<milestone unit="section" n="15"/>If on the other hand, as you now maintain, you thought that he misrepresented the god and, out of partiality for certain persons, had made a false report to the people, rather than propose a decree disputing the dream you ought to have sent to <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, as the previous speaker said, and inquired the truth from the god.  But instead of doing that, you proposed a decree, entirely conceived by yourself,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">I follow Colin's interpretation of the word <foreign lang="greek">au)totelh/s</foreign> in this passage, although it was often used technically to describe a decree laid before the people without previous consideration by the Council &lpar;see <bibl n="Hsch. a.8474.1">Hesychius, sv. <foreign lang="greek">au)totele/s yh/fisma</foreign></bibl>&rpar;.</note> against two tribes, a measure not only most unjust but self-contradictory also.  This was what caused your conviction for illegal proposals.  It was not the fault of Euxenippus.
<milestone unit="section" n="16"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Let us consider it in this way.  The tribes, formed into groups of two, shared out the mountains in Oropus awarded to them by the people.  This mountain fell to the lot of Acamantis and Hippothoontis.  You proposed that these tribes should restore the mountain to Amphiaraus and the price of produce from it which they had sold; your reason being that the fifty boundary officials had selected it beforehand and set it apart for the god, and that the two tribes had no right to be holding it.
<milestone unit="section" n="17"/>A little later in the same decree you propose that the eight tribes shall provide compensation and pay it to the other two so that they shall not suffer unfairly.  But if the mountain really belonged to the two tribes and you tried to take it from them, surely we are entitled to be angry.  Alternatively, if they had no right to be occupying it and it belonged to the god, why were you proposing that the other tribes should actually pay them compensation?  They should have been well content that when restoring the property of the god they did not also pay a fine in cash.
<milestone unit="section" n="18"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>These proposals, when examined in court, were considered unsatisfactory, and the jury condemned you.  So if you had been acquitted in your trial, Euxenippus would not have misrepresented the god: because you happened to be convicted, must ruin fall on him?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Apparently it was loss of prestige which caused Polyeuctus to be resentful against Euxenippus, since the actual fine was negligible.</note> And when you, who proposed a decree like that, were fined a mere twenty-five drachmas, is the man who lay down in the temple at the people's request even to be refused a grave in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>?
<milestone unit="section" n="19"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Yes, you say; for he committed a serious crime in regard to the cup which he allowed Olympias to dedicate to the statue of Health.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Olympias, mother of Alexander the Great, was sent by him about <date value="-331">331</date> B.C. to <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>, where her brother Alexander was king.  On the death of the latter she became regent for the young prince Neoptolemus and so controlled Molossia, which had been attached to the kingdom by Philip in <date value="-343">343</date> B.C.  The statue of Health stood on the Acropolis.  &lpar;See <bibl n="Paus. 1.23.5">Paus. 1.23.5</bibl>.&rpar;  It is not known how Euxenippus was connected with this affair.</note> You think that if you bring her name irrelevantly into the case to serve your own ends and accuse Euxenippus of deceitful flattery, you will bring down the jury's hatred and anger upon him.  The thing to do, my friend, is not to use the name of Olympias and Alexander in the hope of harming some citizen.
<milestone unit="section" n="20"/>Wait till they send the Athenian people some injunctions which are unjust or inappropriate.  Then is the time for you to get up and oppose them in the interests of your city, disputing the cause of justice with their envoys and resorting to the Congress of the Greeks<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The Congress, which united all Greek states except <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, was founded by Philip after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> in <date value="-338">338</date> B.C.</note> as the champion of your country.  But you never stood up or spoke about them there; it is only here that you hate Olympias
<milestone unit="section" n="21"/>so that you can ruin Euxenippus by alleging that he flatters her and the Macedonians.  If you show us that he has ever been to <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> or entertained any of the people in his own home, that he knows a Macedonian intimately or meets any of them; if you prove that he has said one word about such matters, either in a shop or in the market or anywhere else, instead of quietly and modestly minding his own business as much as any other citizen, the jury may do what they like with him.
<milestone unit="section" n="22"/>For if these charges of yours were true, not only you but everyone else in the city would know the facts, as is the case with all the others who speak or act in the interests of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>.  Their conduct is no secret.  The rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, even the schoolchildren, know the orators who take Macedonian money and the other persons who put up Macedonian visitors, either secretly making them welcome or going into the streets to meet them when they arrive.  You will not see Euxenippus classed with a single one of these men anywhere.
<milestone unit="section" n="23"/>But you do not prosecute or bring to trial any of the people who are universally known to be doing these things, and yet you accuse Euxenippus of flattery when his manner of life disproves the charge.  And yet if you had any sense, you would neither be blaming Euxenippus for the dedication of the cup nor have made any further mention of the affair, since it is impolitic to do so.  Why is that?  Will you please listen, gentlemen of the jury, to the account which I am going to give?
<milestone unit="section" n="24"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Olympias has made complaints against you about the incident at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName> was, second to <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, the most famous oracle of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.  Dione, a consort of Zeus, was often worshipped in his temples.</note> complaints which are unfair, as I have twice already proved in the Assembly before yourselves and the rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.  I explained to her envoys that the charges she brings against the city are not justified.  For Zeus of <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> commanded you through the oracle to embellish the statue of Dione.
<milestone unit="section" n="25"/>You made a face as beautiful as you could, together with all the other appropriate parts; and having prepared a great deal of expensive finery for the goddess and dispatched envoys with a sacrifice at great expense, you embellished the statue of Dione in a manner worthy of yourselves and of the goddess.  These measures brought you the complaints of Olympias, who said in her letters that the country of Molossia, in which the temple stands, belonged to her, and that therefore we had no right to interfere with anything there at all.
<milestone unit="section" n="26"/>Now if you decide that the incidents relating to the cup constitute an offence, we are in a sense condemning ourselves as being wrong in what we did at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>.  But if we acquiesce in what has been done we shall have taken away her right to these theatrical complaints and accusations.  For I presume that when Olympias can furnish ornaments for shrines in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> we may safely do so at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>, particularly when the god demands it.
<milestone unit="section" n="27"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>However, it seems to me, Polyeuctus, that there is nothing which you would not use as grounds for an accusation.  But from the time when you decided to play a part in public life, for which I admit you are well fitted, you should not have prosecuted private individuals or made them the victims of your impudence.  Wait for an orator to commit a crime and then prosecute him, or for a general to do wrong and then impeach him.  These are the men who have power to harm the city, all of them who choose to do so, not Euxenippus or any member of this jury.
    <milestone unit="section" n="28"/>It is not as if I were prescribing one line of conduct for you having followed another in my own public life.  I myself never in my life prosecuted any private citizen, and there are some whom before now I have done my best to help.  What men, then, have I prosecuted and brought to trial?  Aristophon of Hazenia,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Of the three orators here mentioned Aristophon was prosecuted by Hyperides in <date value="-362">362</date> B.C., Diopithes at an unknown date, and Philocrates in 343.  See further, notes on <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 17">Hyp. Fr. 17</bibl>,<bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 15">Hyp. Fr. 15</bibl>, and <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 16">Hyp. Fr. 16</bibl>.</note> now a most influential person in public life&mdash;he was acquitted in this court by two votes only;
<milestone unit="section" n="29"/>Diopithes of Sphettus, thought to be the most formidable man in the city; Philocrates of Hagnus, whose political career has been marked by the utmost daring and wantonness.  I prosecuted that man for his services to Philip against <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and secured his conviction in court.  The impeachment which I drew up was just and in accordance with the law, referring to him as &ldquo;an orator giving counsel against the best interests of the people and receiving money and gifts from those working against them.&rdquo;
<milestone unit="section" n="30"/>Even so I was not satisfied to bring in the impeachment before I had added underneath: &ldquo;These proposals he made against the best interests of the people, because he had taken bribes.&rdquo;  And I wrote his decree underneath.  And again I added: &ldquo;These further proposals he made against the best interests of the people, because he had taken bribes.&rdquo;  And I wrote the decree alongside.  Indeed this statement is written down five or six times in my speech; for I thought that I must make the trial and the prosecution just.  But you could not include in your impeachment the things which you allege Euxenippus to have said against the best interests of the people.  Yet, though he is a private citizen, by your mode of prosecution you class him as an orator.
<milestone unit="section" n="31"/>After a scanty reference to the defendant's written statement you are now bringing fresh charges and incriminations against him, mentioning, amongst other similar allegations, that he tried to marry his daughter to Philocles, that he undertook an arbitration for Demotion, and other similar charges.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing is known of Philocles and the reference to Demotion is obscure.  He was clearly an unpopular character, perhaps the parasite feeder satirized by comedians &lpar;see <bibl n="Ath. 6.243">Athen. 6.243</bibl> b&rpar;.  The translation of the phrase <foreign lang="greek">*dhmoti/wnos di/aitan e)/laben</foreign> is doubtful; it might mean: &ldquo;adopted the method of life of Demotion.&rdquo;</note> Your intention is that, if the defence neglect the main indictment and deal with the irrelevant allegations, the jury shall interrupt them by calling: &ldquo;Why do you tell us this?&rdquo; and if they ignore the additional points entirely their case shall be weakened.  For any charge that is not refuted is left to be fastened on by the anger of the jury.
<milestone unit="section" n="32"/>The most outrageous feature of your speech was the fact that often during the argument you let fall the remark&mdash;you thought that your motive in doing so passed unnoticed, though it was obvious&mdash;that Euxenippus was rich, and again, a little later, that he had amassed great wealth dishonestly.  It has surely nothing to do with this case whether he is a man of large means or small, and to raise the matter is malicious and implies an unfair assumption regarding the jury, namely that they would base their verdict on other considerations than the point at issue and the question whether the man on trial is offending against you or not.
<milestone unit="section" n="33"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You do not realize, Polyeuctus, it seems to me, you and those who share your views, that there is not in the world a single democracy or monarch or race more magnanimous than the Athenian people, and that it does not forsake those citizens who are maligned by others, whether singly or in numbers, but supports them.
<milestone unit="section" n="34"/>Let me give an instance.  When Tisis of Agryle brought in an inventory of the estate of Euthycrates, amounting to more than sixty talents, on the grounds of its being public property, and again later promised to bring in an inventory of the estate of Philip and Nausicles saying that they had made their money from unregistered mines, this jury were so far from approving such a suggestion or coveting the property of others that they immediately disfranchised the man who tried to slander the accused and did not award him a fifth part of the votes.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">No other details are known of the cases mentioned here.  An Epicrates of <placeName key="perseus,Pallene">Pallene</placeName> is known to have been trierarch in <date value="-342">342</date> B.C. &lpar;IG. 2.803 e&rpar;, and may be the man referred to in connection with the second of the two trials.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="35"/>Or take a recent instance, if you like, the verdict given by the jury last month, surely a most commendable decision.  I refer to the case of Lysander, who reported that the mine of Epicrates of <placeName key="perseus,Pallene">Pallene</placeName> had been bored beyond the boundaries.  It had already been worked for three years and virtually the richest men in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had shares in it.  Lysander promised to secure three hundred talents for the city, since that, he claimed, was the sum which they had made from the mine.
<milestone unit="section" n="36"/>In spite of this the jury were governed, not by the accusers promises, but by the claims of justice.  They decided that the mine was within its proper limits, and in one and the same verdict assured the safety of the men's estates and guaranteed their working of the mine for the remainder of the period.  That is why the excavation of new mines, neglected previously because men were afraid, is now in progress, and the city's revenues from these are again being increased, revenues which some of our orators impaired by misleading the people and subjecting the mine-workers to tribute.
<milestone unit="section" n="37"/>The good citizen, gentlemen of the jury, is not a man to make some small additions to the public funds in ways which cause an ultimate loss, nor one who, by dishonestly producing an immediate profit, cuts off the city's lawful source of revenue.  On the contrary, he is the man who is anxious to keep what will be profitable to the city in the future, to preserve agreement among the citizens and safeguard your reputation.  There are some who disregard these things.  By taking money from contractors they claim that they are providing revenue, although it is the lack of it that they are really causing in the city.  For when anxiety is attached to earning and saving, who will want to take the risk?
<milestone unit="section" n="38"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now perhaps it is not easy to prevent these men from acting as they do; but you, gentlemen of the jury, have saved many other citizens who were unjustly brought to trial. Then help Euxenippus in the same way, rather than desert him over a trivial matter, and in an impeachment like the present: an impeachment to which he is not liable, which has been framed in defiance of the laws, and which moreover has been partly invalidated by the prosecutor himself.
<milestone unit="section" n="39"/>For Polyeuctus has impeached Euxenippus for speaking against the best interests of the people of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, being in receipt of money and gifts from those acting against the people of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.  Now if he were arguing that there were men outside the city with whom Euxenippus was co-operating on receipt of bribes, he would then be able to say that, since these persons could not be punished, their servants in the city must be brought to justice.  But, in fact, he says that it is from Athenians that Euxenippus has had the gifts.  For shame, sir; when you have here in the city the men who act against the people, do you let them be and choose instead to harass Euxenippus?
<milestone unit="section" n="40"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I will say a few words more about the vote which you are going to give and then leave the platform.  When about to go to the ballot, gentlemen of the jury, tell the clerk to read you the impeachment, the impeachment law and the oath sworn by jurymen.  Dispense with the arguments of us all let the impeachment and the laws govern your decision and give whatever verdict you consider to be just and in keeping with your oath.
<milestone unit="section" n="41"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>And now, Euxenippus, I have done all in my power to help you.  It remains for you to ask the jury's permission to summon your friends and bring your children to the bar.</p></div1>
<div1 n="5" type="Speech">
<head>Against Demosthenes</head><p>
<milestone unit="fragment" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Personally, gentlemen of the jury, as I was just saying to those seated beside me, what surprises me is this.  Is it really true that Demosthenes, unlike any other man in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is exempt from the laws which enforce an agreement made by a person against his own interests?  Is he unaffected by the people's decrees, which you have sworn to observe in voting, decrees which were proposed, not by any of his enemies, but by Demosthenes himself, and which the people carried on his motion, almost as though he deliberately sought to destroy himself . . . and yet the just verdict, gentlemen of the jury, is, as I see it, simple: it is in our favor against Demosthenes.  In private suits differences are often settled by challenge, and that is how this affair also has been settled.  Look at it in this way, gentlemen.  The people accused you, Demosthenes, of having accepted twenty talents illegally, against the interests of the state.  You denied having done so and drew up a challenge, which you laid before the people in the form of a decree entrusting the matter on which you were accused to the council of the Areopagus. . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="2"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . and you malign the Areopagus and publish challenges, in which you ask how you came by the gold, who gave it you, and where.  Perhaps you will end by asking what you used it for after you obtained it, as though you were demanding a banker's statement from the Areopagus.  I, on the other hand, should like to know from you why the council of the Areopagus said . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="3"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . the reports.  On the contrary they have shown, as you will recognize, an exceptionally democratic spirit in handling the affair.  They reported the guilty 
persons; even this was not done from choice but in answer to repeated pressure from the people; and they did not undertake to punish them on their own responsibility but rightly left it to you, with whom the 
final authority rests.  It is not only his own trial which Demosthenes has in mind when he determines to mislead you by abusing the report; he wishes also to frustrate all the other prosecutions which the city has in hand.  That is a point to be carefully borne in mind and you must not be deceived by the 
defendant's argument.  For these reports concerning the money of Harpalus have all been drawn up by the Areopagus on an equal footing.  They are the same for all the accused.  In no case has the council added the reason why it publishes a particular name.  It stated summarily how much money each man had received, adding that he was 
liable for that amount.  Is Demosthenes to have more weight with you than the report given against him? . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense of the missing words appears to be: &ldquo;If you discredit the report, you thereby admit that no one took the money, and all the others are acquitted.&rdquo;</note> For of course this argument, if it protects Demosthenes, will also protect the rest.  The sum on which you are pronouncing 
judgement is not twenty, but four hundred,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The figure mentioned later, in column 10, is 350 talents, which is confirmed by <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 1.1">Pseudo-Plut. Dem. 846 B</bibl>.  Hence Boeckh suggested the reading 400 in this passage, on the grounds that Hyperides would be more likely to exaggerate than otherwise.</note> talents.  
You are judging all the crimes, not one.  For your mad conduct, Demosthenes, has made you champion of all these criminals, foremost in danger as you are in impudence.  In my opinion the fact that you took the gold is proved to the jury well enough by your being condemned by the council to which you entrusted 
yourself. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Although the missing Greek words cannot be restored with certainty, the sense appears to be: &ldquo;I shall now produce the evidence relating to the gold which you previously accepted, and, as I said, explain why you took the money 
and for what reasons you disgraced the whole city.&rdquo;</note> When Harpalus arrived in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, gentlemen of the jury, and the envoys from Philoxenus demanding him were, at the same time, brought into the Assembly, Demosthenes came forward and made a long speech in which he argued that it was not right for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to surrender Harpalus to the envoys from Philoxenus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Philoxenus, one of Alexander's generals, was governor of 
<placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> at the time.</note> and that Alexander must not be left with any cause for complaint, on his account, against the people; the safest course for the city was to guard the money and the person of Harpalus, and to take up all the money, with which Harpalus had entered <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, to the Acropolis on the following day, while Harpalus himself should announce then and there how much money there was.  His real purpose, it seems, was not simply 
to learn the figure, but to find out from how large a sum he was to collect his commission.  Sitting below in his usual place in the niche,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">It is not known what niche is meant.  It may have been a cutting in the side of the Pnyx. The word <foreign lang="greek">katatomh/</foreign> is cited by Harpocration as occurring in this speech.</note> he told Mnesitheus the dancer to ask Harpalus how much money there would be to take up to the 
Acropolis.  The answer given was seven hundred talents. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In the missing lines Hyperides probably explained that the Assembly was then dismissed and not summoned again until the following day, when the money had been paid over.  <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 1.1">Pseudo-Plut. Dem. 846 B</bibl>, says that Demosthenes was accused of having taken bribes because he had not reported the amount of money brought to the Acropolis or the 
carelessness of those in charge of it.</note> He had told you himself in the Assembly that that was the correct figure; and yet when the total brought up to the Acropolis was three hundred and fifty talents instead of seven hundred, having by then received his twenty, he did not utter a word. . . .  After saying before the Assembly that there were seven hundred talents you now bring up 
    half. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense of the mutilated column 11 appears to be: &ldquo;You did not reflect that if the whole amount originally mentioned was not taken up to the Acropolis someone must have embezzled.  You were interested solely in your own fee; for you cannot persuade us that you received nothing when we know that Demades was paid 5000 staters.&rdquo;  For the bribe paid to Demades see <bibl n="Din. 1.89">Din. 1.89</bibl>.</note> Harpalus 
would not have bought . . . nor would the city be exposed to accusation and reproach.  But of all these things, Demosthenes . . .  It was you who decreed that a guard should be posted over the person of Harpalus.  Yet when it relaxed its vigilance you did not try to restore it, and after it was disbanded you did not prosecute those responsible.  I suppose you went unpaid for your shrewd handling of the crisis?  If Harpalus distributed his gold among the lesser 
orators, who had nothing to give but noise and shouting, what of you who control our whole policy?  Did he pass you over?  That is incredible.  So supreme is the contempt, gentlemen of the jury, with which Demosthenes has treated the affair, or to be quite frank, you and the laws, that at the outset, it seems, he admitted having taken the money but said that he had used it on your behalf and had borrowed it free of 
interest<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">There does not seem to be an exact parallel for this use of the word <foreign lang="greek">prodanei/zomai</foreign> and there are two possible interpretations.  &lpar;1&rpar; The active <foreign lang="greek">prodanei/zw</foreign> apparently has the sense of &ldquo;lend without interest&rdquo; in Pseudo-Plut. Lives of the Ten Orators 852 B, and in <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 16">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 16</bibl>.  If the 
translation given above is correct, Demosthenes claimed to have borrowed the money from Harpalus and to have advanced it to the Athenian people.  &lpar;2&rpar; On the other hand the noun <foreign lang="greek">prodaneisth/s</foreign> is used in a Delian inscription with the sense of &ldquo;one who borrows for another.&rdquo;  On this analogy we might translate <foreign lang="greek">prodaneisme/nos</foreign> as &ldquo;having 
    borrowed for the people.&rdquo;  Demosthenes would thus be claiming to have acted as an intermediary in accepting a loan from Harpalus to the state.</note> for the Theoric fund.  Cnosion<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cnosion, a boy with whom Demosthenes was friendly, is mentioned also by <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.149">Aeschin. 2.149</bibl>, and by the scholiast on that passage.</note> and his other friends went about saying that Demosthenes would be compelled by his accusers to publish facts which he wished kept secret and to admit that he had borrowed the money free of interest for the state to meet expenses of government.  Since the anger of those of you who heard this statement was greatly increased by these aspersions cast on your democracy, on the grounds that he was not content to have taken 
bribes himself but thought fit to infect the people too . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The gist of the missing lines was probably that Demosthenes changed his tactics and began to plead a different excuse.</note> speaking and complaining that the Areopagus was seeking favor with Alexander and for that reason wanted to destroy him.  As if you did not all know that no one destroys the kind of man who can be bought.  On the contrary, it is the opponent who can be neither persuaded nor corrupted with bribes that men contrive to be rid of by any means in their power.  There is some likelihood, it seems, that you, Demosthenes, are deaf to prayers and not to be persuaded into taking bribes?  Do not imagine, gentlemen, that only trivial matters are affected by the venal conduct of these men.  For it is no secret that all who conspire for power in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> secure the smaller cities by force of arms and the larger ones by buying the influential citizens in them; and we know that Philip reached the height he did because, at the outset, he sent money to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, and the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and those with power in the cities and authority. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The words &ldquo;he bribed&rdquo; should probably be added to complete the sense.</note>
    <milestone unit="fragment" n="4"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . you tell us marvellous stories, little thinking that your conduct is no secret; you professed to be supporting the people's interests but were clearly speaking on behalf of Alexander.  Personally I believe that even in the past everyone knew that you acted in this way over the Thebans, and over all the rest, and that you appropriated money, which was sent from <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> to buy help,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.10">Din. 1.10</bibl>, note and <bibl n="Din. 1.18">Din. 1.18-22</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.239">Aeschin. 3.239-240</bibl>.  Demosthenes was said by his opponents to have accepted money from <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> for use against <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>, but to have withheld it when Alexander destroyed <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C.</note> for your own personal use, spending most of it; and now you engage in sea commerce and make bottomry loans, and having bought a house . . . you do not live in the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> but have your anchorage outside the city.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The house in the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> is mentioned by <bibl n="Din. 1.69">Din. 1.69</bibl>; and <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.209">Aeschin. 3. 209</bibl> uses these exact words.</note> A popular leader worthy of the name should be the savior of his country, not a deserter.  When Harpalus recently descended on <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> so suddenly that he took everyone by surprise, he found affairs in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and in the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in this condition owing to the arrival of Nicanor with the orders which he brought from Alexander relating to the exiles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><bibl n="Din. 1.82">Din. 1.82</bibl> also refers to this event, which took place in <date value="-324">324</date> B.C.  Nicanor, the son-in-law of Aristotle, was sent by Alexander to <placeName key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> to proclaim his demand for the return to their cities of all Greek exiles except the Thebans.</note> and to the . . . of the Achaean, Arcadian, and Boeotian Leagues. . . .  You have contrived this situation by means of your decree, because you arrested Harpalus.  You have induced the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> to send envoys to Alexander, since they have no other recourse, and have prevented all the satraps, who by themselves would willingly have joined forces with us, each with money and all the troops at his disposal, not merely from revolting from him, by your detention of Harpalus, but also . . . each of them . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The general sense appears to be: &ldquo;All the satraps united with Alexander.  You yourself are now a supporter of his and have your agents with every important Macedonian.&rdquo;</note>
    <milestone unit="fragment" n="5"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . sent by Demosthenes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Sauppe suspected that the man here referred to was Aristion of <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, a friend of Demosthenes who, according to >Harpocration &lpar;s. v. <foreign lang="greek">*)aristi/wn</foreign>&rpar;, was mentioned in this speech and was sent by Demosthenes to Hephaestion in order to reach an understanding with him.  For Callias and Taurosthenes of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName> compare <bibl n="Din. 1.44">Din. 1.44</bibl> and note.</note> and with Olympias Callias the Chalcidian, the brother of Taurosthenes.  For these men were made Athenian citizens on the motion of Demosthenes and they are his special agents.  Naturally enough; for being perpetually unstable himself, I suppose he might well have friends from the Euripus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A comparison between the Euripus, a very changeable strait, and the character of Callias is made also by <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.90">Aeschin. 3.90</bibl>.</note> Will you dare then presently to speak to me of friendship . . . you yourself broke up that friendship when you accepted bribes against your country and made a change of front.  You made yourself a laughing stock and brought disgrace on those who had ever shared your policy in former years.  When we might have gained the highest distinction in public life and been accompanied for the remainder of our lives by the best of reputations, you frustrated all these hopes, and you are not ashamed, even at your age,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Demosthenes was just over sixty.</note> to be tried by youths for bribery.  And yet the positions ought to be reversed: your generation ought to be training the younger orators, reproving and punishing any over-impetuous action.  But the fact is just the opposite: the youths are taking to task the men of over sixty.  Therefore, gentlemen of the jury, you have a right to feel resentful towards Demosthenes; for after gaining a tolerable reputation and great riches, all through you, even on the threshold of old age he has no loyalty to his country.  But you used to be ashamed . . . the Greeks who were standing round, when you passed sentence on certain persons, to think that such popular leaders and generals and guardians of your affairs . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense of this passage is probably: &ldquo;Since you condemned such generals as Timotheus, though you shrank from doing so, you should not hesitate to condemn Demosthenes.&rdquo;  Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.16">Din. 1.16</bibl>.</note>
    <milestone unit="fragment" n="6"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . For to take money is not so serious as to take it from the wrong source, and the private individuals who took the gold are not so culpable as the orators and generals.  Why is that?  Because the private individuals were given the money by Harpalus for safe-keeping, but the generals and orators have accepted it with some policy in view.  The laws prescribe that ordinary offenders shall pay a simple fine but that men accepting bribes shall pay ten times the usual sum.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The term <foreign lang="greek">a)dikei=n</foreign> seems to be used in this context to describe the milder breaches of the law, and is used in the same sense by <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 54.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 54.2</bibl>, where <foreign lang="greek">kle/ptein, dw=ra, lamba/nein</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">a)dikei=n</foreign> are distinguished as punishable with a tenfold fine, a tenfold fine, and a simple fine respectively.  Dinarchus is misleading when he refers &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 1.60">Din. 1.60</bibl>&rpar; to a double fine.  A simple fine was doubled only when it was not paid up within a fixed time.</note> Therefore, just as we can lawfully fix the penalty for these men, so also . . . from you against them. . . .  It is as I said in the Assembly.  You give full permission, gentlemen of the jury, to the orators and generals to reap substantial rewards.  It is not the laws which grant them this privilege but your tolerance and generosity.  But on one point you insist: your interests must be furthered, not opposed, with the money they receive.  Now Demosthenes and Demades, from actual decrees passed in the city and from proxenies, have each received, I believe, more than sixty talents, quite apart from the Persian funds and money sent from Alexander.  If neither of these sources suffices for them, and they have now accepted bribes which threaten the city's life itself, can we doubt our right to punish them?  Suppose that one of you, mere private individuals, during the tenure of some office, makes a mistake through ignorance or inexperience; he will be overwhelmed in court by the eloquence of these men and will either lose his life or be banished from his country.  Shall they themselves, after harming the city on such a scale, escape unscathed?  <placeName key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName> of Paeania took theoric money for his son who was abroad.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><placeName key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName> is perhaps the banker to whom Dinarchus refers &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 1.43">Din. 1.43</bibl>&rpar;, and the incident which he mentions later in the speech &lpar;i. 56&rpar; is possibly the same as that to which Hyperides is alluding here, though according to Dinarchus it was the Areopagus who accused the culprit.  Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.56">Din. 1.56</bibl>, note.  The story of Aristomachus is not known.</note> He was prosecuted for it by these men in court, and though he asked your pardon, had to pay a talent, all for taking five drachmas.  Aristomachus also, because, on becoming principal of the Academy, he transferred a spade from the wrestling school to his own garden near by and used it and . . .
    <milestone unit="fragment" n="7"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . However during the period which followed<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Hyperides is referring to the period which followed <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, and the statesman in question is Lycurgus.  Demosthenes also speaks of the number of trials which took place at this time &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 18.249">Dem. 18.249</bibl>&rpar;.  Hyperides himself was prosecuted by Aristogiton.  Compare <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 18">Hyp. Fr. 18</bibl> and note.</note> the people did not forbid us to approach them or to discuss with them; instead they used us as counsellors and advisers . . . and elected him next . . . as treasurer with full control of their finances, considering, quite rightly, that we owed him a debt of gratitude.  Later, too, though we were often brought to trial on the strength of that policy and the war itself, these men did not vote against us once but brought us safely through everything; and one could not have a more impressive, or a surer sign of popular favor. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense of the mutilated passage beginning with the words <foreign lang="greek">kai\ gra/yai</foreign> has been restored by Blass and Colin as follows: &ldquo;Although you, Demosthenes, dared to propose the death penalty for yourself if the council reported that you had received anything from Harpalus, when it made its report and you were ipso facto convicted by the terms of the decree, these gentlemen did not take account of the circumstance but allowed you a special trial.  For the people have always behaved in such a way towards us orators, etc.&rdquo;</note> the people so behaved that though deprived themselves by fortune of their crown of glory, they did not take from us the wreath which they had granted.  When the people have acted thus towards us should we not render them all due service, and if need be die for them?  I believe we should, but you, against the people . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense appears to be: &ldquo;You oppose the people and forget that there are men who wish to serve their own country instead of other people's.  You have continued to be disloyal and to display your eloquence.&rdquo;</note> benefits.  For them to serve their own, and not some other's country . . . you have continued to display the power of your eloquence.  When you thought that the Areopagus would report those who had the gold you became hostile and created a disturbance in the city so as to obstruct the inquiry.  But when the Areopagus postponed its statement on the grounds that it had not yet discovered the truth, you conceded in the Assembly that Alexander might be the son of Zeus and Poseidon too if he wished . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.94">Din. 1.94</bibl></note> wished . . . to set up a statue of Alexander, the king and god invincible . . . Olympias . . . announced to the people . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="8"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . of the charges and made a proclamation about them.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Dinarchus makes no clear reference to this proclamation.  Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.4">Din. 1.4</bibl>.</note> And they, instead of returning what they had received and being quit of the affair, were proposing penalties and inquiries directed against themselves.  How ought we to treat men who began by doing wrong and taking bribes and then, when exemption was offered them, did not give back the gold?  Should we let them go unpunished?  No; for it would be a shameful thing, gentlemen of the jury, to jeopardize the safety of the city because of charges brought against individual men.  You cannot acquit these men themselves unless you are willing also to assume responsibility for their crimes. . . .  Then do not indulge their love of gain, gentlemen of the jury, at the expense of your own security.  Do not let your motive for making war be love of sordid gain; let it be rather a wish for a more creditable record and a change to better fortunes. . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="9"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . on behalf of them . . . we made peace.  . . . to be rendered to it by each of us.  The prosecuting in court and the exposing of those who had received the money and taken bribes against their country it allotted to us, the chosen accusers.  The reporting of the names of the recipients it assigned to the Areopagus, who gave these men's names to the people.  Punishment of the criminals . . . to you . . . the Areopagus.  If the vote goes contrary to law or justice, that is a responsibility, gentlemen of the jury, which will rest with you.  You must all therefore . . . the safety of the city and the good fortune which in other ways you all enjoy in this country both collectively and individually.  Remember the tombs of your ancestors and punish the offenders in the interests of the whole city.  Do not allow their plausibility in argument . . . the men who have taken bribes against their country and defied the laws.  And do not let the tears of Hagnonides<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Hagnonides, who is described by Plutarch as a sycophant, and against whom, if Reiske's emendation is correct, Dinarchus composed a speech, was probably acquitted.  He fled from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> after the Lamian war but later returned and was condemned to death.  Compare <bibl n="Din. Fr. 9">Din. Fr. 9</bibl>; <bibl n="Plut. Phoc. 38">Plut. Phoc. 38</bibl>.</note> affect you.  Remember this . . . but this man would have no right to shed tears, any more than pirates who cry upon the wheel when they need not have embarked in the boat.  The same is true of Demosthenes.  What excuse will he have for tears when he need not have accepted . . .
<milestone unit="fragment" n="a"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But you call upon the younger men, though you used to abuse and insult them with the name of wine-swillers.
<milestone unit="fragment" n="b"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Anyone who drank rather freely used to vex you.
<milestone unit="fragment" n="c"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Not even within a limited time.
<milestone unit="fragment" n="d"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Cowardly.</p></div1>
<div1 n="6" type="speech">
<head>Funeral Speech</head><p>
<milestone unit="section" n="1"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The words to be pronounced above this grave, a tribute to Leosthenes the general and the others who have perished with him in the war, for the courage they have shown, have as their witness time itself . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The missing words were restored by Sudhaus so as to give the following sense: &ldquo;. . . time itself which holds the record of their deeds.  For no man known during the history of the world has seen in any land a nobler choice than this or better men, etc.&rdquo;</note> nor better men than these now dead nor more resplendent actions.  Indeed my greatest doubt today is lest my speech may prove unworthy of their exploits.
<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>I am, however, taking heart in this assurance: that what I leave unsaid will be supplied by you who hear me; for my listeners will be no random audience but the persons who themselves have witnessed the actions of these men.
<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>While praise is due to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for her policy, for choosing as she did a course not only ranking with her past achievements but even surpassing them in pride and honor, and to the fallen also for their gallantry in battle, for proving worthy of their forbears' valor, to Leosthenes the general it is doubly due; the city's guide in framing her decision, he was besides the citizens' commander in the field.
<milestone unit="section" n="4"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>In the case of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to recount in detail the benefits which she has previously conferred upon the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> would be a task too great to compass in the time we have, nor is the occasion one for lengthy speaking.  Indeed it is not easy for a single man, faced with so many noble actions, to recall the full story to your minds.  I shall, however, venture one general comment on her.
<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Compare her with the sun which visits the whole world and duly separates the seasons, disposing all things for the best, with provision, where men are virtuous and prudent, for their birth and nurture, the crops and all the other needs of life; for so our city never fails to punish the wicked, help the just, mete out to all men fairness in place of wrong, and at her individual peril and expense assure the Greeks a common safety.
<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>To deal with the achievements of the city as a whole is, as I said before, a task which I shall not attempt, and I will here confine myself to Leosthenes and his companions.  At what point, then, shall I take up the story?  What shall I mention first?  Shall I trace the ancestry of each?
<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>To do so would, I think, be foolish.  Granted, if one is praising men of a different stamp, such as have gathered from diverse places into the city which they inhabit, each contributing his lineage to the common stock, then one must trace their separate ancestry.  But from one who speaks of Athenians, born of their own country and sharing a lineage of unrivalled purity, a eulogy of the descent of each must surely be superfluous.
<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>Am I then to touch upon their education, and, as other speakers often do, remind you how as children they were reared and trained in strict self-discipline?  None of us, I think, is unaware that our aim in training children is to convert them into valiant men; and that men who have proved of exceptional courage in war were well brought up in childhood needs no stressing.
<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>The simplest course, I think, will be to tell you of their courage under arms, revealing them as authors of many benefits conferred upon their country and the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.  First I shall take the general, as is his due.
<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>For Leosthenes perceived that the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> was humiliated and . . . cowed, corrupted by men who were accepting bribes from Philip and Alexander against their native countries.  He realized that our city stood in need of a commander, and <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> herself of a city, able to assume the leadership, and he gave himself to his country and the city to the Greeks, in the cause of freedom.
<milestone unit="section" n="11"/>After raising a mercenary force he took command of the citizen army and defeated the first opponents of Greek freedom, the Boeotians, Macedonians and Euboeans, together with their other allies, in battle in <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="12"/>Thence he advanced to Pylae<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In fact Leosthenes seems to have occupied <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName> before his victory in <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>.</note> and occupied the pass through which, in bygone days as well, barbarians marched against the Greeks.  He thus prevented the inroad of Antipater into <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and overtaking him in that vicinity, defeated him in battle and shut him into <placeName key="perseus,Lamia">Lamia</placeName>, which he then besieged.
<milestone unit="section" n="13"/>The Thessalians, Phocians, Aetolians, and all the other peoples of the region, he made his allies, bringing under his control, by their own consent, the men whom Philip and Alexander gloried in controlling against their wish.  The circumstances subject to his will he mastered, but fate he could not overpower.
<milestone unit="section" n="14"/>Leosthenes must have first claim upon our gratitude for ever, not only for the acts performed by him, but also for the later battle, fought after his death, and for those other triumphs which the Greeks have gained in this campaign.  For on the foundations laid by Leosthenes the subsequent success of his survivors rests.
<milestone unit="section" n="15"/>Let no one fancy that I disregard the other citizens and keep my eulogy for him alone.  The praise bestowed upon Leosthenes for these engagements is in fact a tribute to the rest.  For though sound strategy depends upon the leader, success in battle is ensured by those who are prepared to risk their lives; and therefore, in the praise that I bestow upon the victory gained, I shall be commending not merely the leadership of Leosthenes but the courage of his comrades too.
<milestone unit="section" n="16"/>For who could rightly grudge his praise to those of our citizens who fell in this campaign, who gave their lives for the freedom of the Greeks, convinced that the surest proof of their desire to guarantee the liberty of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> was to die in battle for her?
<milestone unit="section" n="17"/>One circumstance did much to reinforce their purpose as champions of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>: the fact that the earlier battle was fought in <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The points which Hyperides makes in this and in the following section will not bear examination.  For &lpar;1&rpar; the first victory was gained in the territory of <placeName key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName>, not within sight of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>; &lpar;2&rpar; the second battle was probably fought near <placeName key="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName> in <placeName key="perseus,Trachis">Trachis</placeName>, and its site could not be seen from <placeName key="perseus,Anthela">Anthela</placeName> where the Amphictyonic council met.  Moreover, the council met there only once a year and could hardly be called representative of the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.</note> They saw that the city of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> had been tragically annihilated from the face of the earth, that its citadel was garrisoned by the Macedonians, and that the persons of its inhabitants were in slavery, while others parcelled out the land among themselves.  And so these threats, revealed before their eyes, gave them an undaunted courage to meet danger gladly.
<milestone unit="section" n="18"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Yet the action fought near Pylae and <placeName key="perseus,Lamia">Lamia</placeName> has proved to be as glorious for them as the conflict in <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>, not solely through the circumstances of victory in the field, over Antipater and his allies, but on the grounds of situation also.  The fact that this has been the battle's site will mean that all the Greeks, repairing twice a year to the council of the Amphictyones, will witness their achievements; for by the very act of gathering in that spot they will recall the valor of these men.
<milestone unit="section" n="19"/>Never before did men strive for a nobler cause, either against stronger adversaries or with fewer friends, convinced that valor gave strength and courage superiority as no mere numbers could.  Liberty they gave us as an offering for all to share, but the honor of their deeds they have bestowed upon their country as a wreath for her alone.
<milestone unit="section" n="20"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now we might well reflect what, in our opinion, the outcome would have been, had these men failed to do their duty in the struggle.  Must we not suppose that the whole world would be under one master, and <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> compelled to tolerate his whim as law?  In short that Macedonian arrogance, and not the power of justice, would lord it among every people. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Various attempts have been made to restore this corrupt passage, from which some words seem to have dropped out, but none is wholly satisfactory.  In any case the sense appears to be that outrages on women, girls, and children would continue without pause in every city.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="21"/>The practices which even now we have to countenance are proof enough: sacrifices being made to men; images, altars, and temples carefully perfected in their honor, while those of the gods are neglected, and we ourselves are forced to honor as heroes the servants of these people.
<milestone unit="section" n="22"/>If reverence for the gods has been removed by Macedonian insolence, what fate must we conclude would have befallen the rules of conduct towards man?  Would they not have been utterly discounted?  The more terrible therefore we think the consequences would have been, the greater must be the praise which we believe the dead have earned.
<milestone unit="section" n="23"/>For no campaign has better shown the courage of the soldiers than this last, when they had daily to be arrayed for combat, to fight, on but one expedition, more battles than the combats which any soldier of the past endured,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The exaggeration of this remark has led some editors to doubt the reading.</note> and face extreme severities of weather and many hard privations in the daily needs of life with an endurance almost beyond description.
<milestone unit="section" n="24"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Such trials Leosthenes induced the citizens to brave undaunted, and they gave up their persons gladly to share the struggle with so great a leader.  Should they not then be counted fortunate in their display of valor rather than unfortunate in their sacrifice of life?  For in exchange for a mortal body they gained undying glory, safeguarding by their personal courage the universal liberty of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The Greek words which follow here cannot be translated as they stand.  Fritzsche's emendation probably restores the correct sense, namely: &ldquo;Nothing brings complete happiness without self-government.&rdquo;  But the Greek wording is uncertain.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="25"/>If men are to be happy, the voice of law, and not a ruler's threats, must reign supreme; if they are free, no groundless charge, but only proof of guilt, must cause them apprehension; nor must the safety of our citizens depend on those who slander them and truckle to their masters but on the force of law alone.
<milestone unit="section" n="26"/>Such were the aims with which these men accepted labor upon labor, and with the dangers of the passing hour dispelled the terrors which the whole future held for citizens and Greeks, sacrificing their lives that others might live well.
<milestone unit="section" n="27"/>To them we owe it that fathers have grown famous, and mothers looked up to in the city, that sisters, through the benefit of law, have made, and will make, marriages worthy of them, that children too will find a passport to the people's hearts in these men's valor; these men who, far from dying&mdash;death is no word to use where lives are lost, as theirs were, for a noble cause&mdash;have passed from this existence to an eternal state.
<milestone unit="section" n="28"/>For if the fact of death, to others a most grievous ill, has brought to them great benefits, are we not wrong indeed to count them wretched or to conclude that they have left the realm of life?  Should we not rather say they have been born anew, a nobler birth than the first?  Mere children then, they had no understanding, but now they have been born as valiant men.
<milestone unit="section" n="29"/>Formerly they stood in need of time and many dangers to reveal their courage; now, with that courage as a base, they have become known to all, to be remembered for their valor.
<milestone unit="section" n="30"/>On what occasion shall we fail to recollect the prowess of these men, in what place fail to see them win their due of emulation and the highest praise?  What if the city prospers?  Surely the successes, which they have earned, will bring their praises, and none other's, to our lips and to our memories.  Shall we then forget them in times of personal satisfaction?  We cannot; for it is through their valor that we shall have the safe enjoyment of those moments.
<milestone unit="section" n="31"/>Will there be men of any age who will not count them blessed?  What of the older generation, who think that through the efforts of these men they have been placed in safety and will pass the rest of their lives free from dread?   Consider their compeers . . .<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense is supplied by <placeName key="tgn,1029705">Kenyon</placeName> as follows: &ldquo;To them it has been given, because these died in battle, to enjoy their lives in honor and safety.&rdquo;</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="32"/>Think, too, of the younger men and boys.  Will they not envy their death and strive themselves to take as an example these men's lives, in place of which they have left behind their valor?
<milestone unit="section" n="33"/>Ought we then to count them happy in so great an honor?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The missing passage from <foreign lang="greek">h)/ ti/nes</foreign> to <foreign lang="greek">tw=| pole/mw|</foreign> has been tentatively restored by Blass and <placeName key="tgn,1029705">Kenyon</placeName> to give the following sense: &ldquo;Neither poets nor philosophers will be in want of words or song in which to celebrate their deeds to <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.  Surely this expedition will be more famed in every land than that which overthrew the Phrygians.  Throughout all time in every part of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> these exploits will be praised in verse and song.  Leosthenes himself and those who perished with him in the war will have a double claim to be revered.&rdquo;</note> . . .
<milestone unit="section" n="34"/>For if it is for pleasure that men recall such feats of courage, what could be more pleasing to Greeks than the praise of those who gave them freedom from the Macedonian yoke?  Or if it is desire for profit that prompts such recollections, what speech could be of greater profit to the hearts of those about to hear it than one which is to honor courage and brave men?
<milestone unit="section" n="35"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>With us and all mankind, it is clear, in the light of these reflections, that their fame is now assured, but what of the lower world?  Who, we may well ask ourselves, are waiting there to welcome the leader of these men?  Are we not convinced that we should see, greeting Leosthenes with wonder, those of the so-called demi-gods who sailed against <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>: heroes whom he so far excelled, though his exploits were akin to theirs, that they with all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> at their side took but one city, while he with his native town alone brought low the whole power which held <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> beneath its sway?
<milestone unit="section" n="36"/>They championed one lone woman wronged, but he staved off from all Greek women the violence coming upon them, aided by these men who now are being buried with him.
<milestone unit="section" n="37"/>Remember the figures who,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This sentence is awkward in Greek because, though <foreign lang="greek">tw=n gegenhme/nown</foreign> is genitive, dependent on <foreign lang="greek">u(pere/sxen</foreign>, the writer has inserted <foreign lang="greek">w(=n</foreign> which is not needed.  The diffculty can be avoided by placing a comma after <foreign lang="greek">a)ndrw=n</foreign> and the full stop after <foreign lang="greek">diapepragme/nwn</foreign>, but then <foreign lang="greek">le/gw dh\</foreign> makes an abrupt beginning to the new sentence.</note> born after the heroes of old, yet rivalled their deeds of valor, the followers of Miltiades and Themistocles, and those others who, by freeing <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, brought honor to their country and glory to their lives;
<milestone unit="section" n="38"/>whom Leosthenes so far outdid in bravery and counsel, that where they beat back the barbarian power as it advanced, he even forestalled its onslaught.  They saw a struggle with the foe in their own land, but he defeated his opponents on the foe's own soil.
    <milestone unit="section" n="39"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Those too, I fancy, who gave the people the surest token of their mutual friendship, Harmodius and Aristogiton,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense appears to be that they regard no one as so suitable to rank with themselves as Leosthenes and his comrades.  Harmodius and Aristogiton, who in <date value="-514">514</date> B.C. plotted to assassinate the two sons of Pisistratus, and after killing one, Hipparchus, were captured and put to death, were later looked upon as liberators of the city.  They and their descendants, who enjoyed special privileges, are not infrequently referred to by the orators.  Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.63">Din. 1.63</bibl> and <bibl n="Din. 1.101">Din. 1.101</bibl>; <bibl n="Hyp. 2.3">Hyp. 2.3</bibl>.</note> do not regard . . . as Leosthenes and his comrades in arms; nor are there any with whom they would rather hold converse in the lower world than these.  We need not wonder; for what these men did was no less a task than theirs; it was indeed, if judgement must be passed, a greater service still.  Those two brought low the tyrants of their country, these the masters of the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="40"/>Noble indeed beyond our dreams was the courage these men attained, honorable and magnificent the choice they made.  How supreme was the valor, the heroism in times of peril, which they, dedicating to the universal liberty of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> . . .
<milestone unit="section" n="41"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It is hard no doubt to offer consolation to those borne down with griefs like these.  For sorrows are not stilled by word or law; only the individual's temper, and the measure of his feeling for the dead, can set the limit to his mourning.  Yet we must take heart, and restricting our grief as best we may, bear in our minds, with the thought of death, the glorious name which the fallen have left behind them.
<milestone unit="section" n="42"/>For though their fate deserves our tears, their conduct claims the highest praise.  Though they have failed to reach old age in life, they have achieved a fame which knows no age, and have attained the height of satisfaction.  For all who were childless at their death the praises of the Greeks will be immortal children.  For all who have children alive the goodwill of their country will be the children's guardian.
<milestone unit="section" n="43"/>And furthermore, if death means non-existence, they have been released from sickness and from grief, and from the other ills which vex our human life.  But if in Hades we are conscious still and cared for by some god, as we are led to think, then surely those who defended the worship of the gods, when it was being overthrown, must receive from him the greatest care of all. . . .</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
