<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersVerse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Verse//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersVerse.dtd" >
%PersVerse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Carmina</title>
				<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
				<author n="Catul.">C. Valerius Catullus</author>
				<editor role="editor" n="Smithers">Leonard C. Smithers</editor> &responsibility;
                &fund.NEH; </titleStmt>
			<extent>about 130Kb</extent> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Catullus</author>
						<title>The Carmina of Gaius Valerius Catullus.</title>
						<editor role="editor">Leonard C. Smithers</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Smithers.</publisher>
							<date>1894</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="OCLC">878062</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<step delim="." refunit="poem" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)"/>
				<step refunit="line" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE UNIT line N %2)"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>

		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>Jan 1998</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>WM</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>public domain text of Burton translation scanned and proofread by RO, WM, JB,
                    RC; prose text modernized and corrected to ET Merrill text.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>3 August 1999</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>David Smith</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cat.smithers_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.4  2010-07-06 16:02:34  rsingh04
fixed CVS log keyword some more

Revision 1.3  2010/07/06 15:59:28  rsingh04
fixed CVS log keyword

Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:24 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.5 2008/11/14 21:10:45 lcerrato 
changed author name to make consistent 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:37:59 packel 
fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:16 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:56:09 packel 
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:30:44 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.4 2003/07/01 22:14:50 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.3 2000/03/04 20:34:08 dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.2 2000/01/20 01:04:58 dasmith 
Added missing poem number. 

Revision 1.1 1999/08/03 21:02:50 textgod
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="1">
				<p>To whom inscribe my charming new book&mdash;just out and with ashen pumice
                    polished? <persName><surname>Cornelius</surname></persName>, to you! for you
                    used to deem my triflings of account, and at a time when you alone of Italians
                    dared unfold the ages' abstract in three chronicles&mdash;learned, by
                    <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>!&mdash;and most
                    laboriously written. Therefore take this booklet, such as it is, and, O Virgin
                    Patroness, may it outlive generations more than one.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="2">
				<p>Sparrow, darling of my girl, with which she plays, which she presses to her
                    bosom, to whom she gives her fingertip, arousing sharp bites as he seeks after
                    it, when gleaming with desire of me she jests a light joke of it, so that, I
                    think, it is a solace for her pain when the heavy burning is at rest. Could I
                    but play with you just as she does and lighten the sad cares of mind.<gap/>This
                    was as pleasing to me as the golden apple was to the fleet footed girl, which
                    unloosed her girdle long-time fastened.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="3">
				<p>O mourn, you Loves and Cupids, and all men of gracious mind. Dead is the sparrow
                    of my girl, sparrow, darling of my girl, which she loved more than her eyes; for
                    it was sweet as honey, and its mistress knew it as well as a girl knows her own
                    mother. Nor did it move from her lap, but hopping round first one side then the
                    other, to its mistress alone it continually chirped. Now it fares along that
                    path of shadows from where nothing may ever return. May evil befall you, savage
                    glooms of Orcus, which swallow up all things of fairness: which have snatched
                    away from me the comely sparrow. O wretched deed! O hapless sparrow! Now on your
                    account my girl's sweet eyes, swollen, redden with tear-drops.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="4">
				<p>That pinnace which you see, my friends, says that it was the speediest of boats,
                    that it could gain the lead of any craft skimming the surface, whether the task
                    were to fly with oarblades or sail. And she denies that the shore of the
                    menacing Adriatic denies this, or the <placeName key="tgn,7011270">Cyclades</placeName> awkward &lsqb;to navigate&rsqb;, or noble
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> and bristling Thracian
                    Propontis, or the frim Pontic gulf, where she afterwards was a pinnace,
                    beforehand was bearded forest; and often on Cytorus' ridge she gave out a
                    rustling with speaking foliage. And you, Pontic Amastris, and to boxwood bearing
                    Cytorus, the pinnace declares that this was and is most well-known to you; she
                    says that from its origin it stood upon your topmost peak, dipped its oars in
                    your waters, and bore its master from there through so many seas lacking
                    self-control, whether the wind called from port or starboard or whether
                    favorable Jove fell on both the sheets at once; and nor were any vows
                    &lsqb;from stress of storm&rsqb; made be her to shore-gods, when she
                    came from the most distant sea to this glassy lake. But these things were of
                    before: now laid away, she grows old in peace and dedicates herself to you, twin
                    Castor, and to Castor's twin.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="5">
				<p>Let us live, my Lesbia, and let us love, and count all the rumors of stearn old
                    men at a penny's fee. Suns can set and rise again: we when once our brief light
                    has set must sleep through a perpetual night. Give me a thousand kisses, and
                    then a hundred, then another thousand, then a second hundred, then another
                    thousand without resting, then a hundred. Then, when we have made many
                    thousands, we will confuse the count lest we know the numbering, so that no one
                    can cast an evil eye on us through knowing the number of our kisses.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="6">
				<p>Flavius, you would speak of your sweetheart to Catullus, and you could not keep
                    silent, were she not both ill-mannered and ungraceful. In truth you affect I
                    know not what hot-blooded whore you love: this you are ashamed to confess. For
                    your couch, fragrant with garlands and Syrian unguent, in no way mute cries out
                    that you do not lie alone at night, and also the pillow and bolsters indented
                    here and there, and the creakings and joggings of the quivering bed: unless you
                    can silence these, nothing and again nothing avails you to hide your affairs.
                    And why? You would not display such love-weary loins unless occupied in some
                    tomfoolery. Therefore, whatever you have for good or ill, tell us! I want to
                    call you and your loves to heaven in charming verse.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="7">
				<p>You ask, how many kisses of yours, Lesbia, may be enough and to spare for me. As
                    the countless Libyan sands which strew asafoetida-bearing <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName> between the oracle of sweltering Jove
                    and the sacred tomb of ancient Battus, or as the many stars, when night is
                    silent, look upon the furtive loves of mortals, to kiss you with kisses of so
                    great a number is enough and to spare for passion-driven Catullus: so many that
                    prying eyes may not avail to number, nor ill tongues to bewitch.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="8">
				<p>Unhappy Catullus, cease your trifling and what you see lost, know to be lost.
                    Once bright days used to shine on you when you used to go wherever your girl led
                    you, loved by us as never a girl will ever be loved. There those many joys
                    occured which you did wish, nor was the girl unwilling. In truth bright days
                    used once to shine on you. Now she no longer wants you: you too, powerless to
                    avail, must not want her, do not pursue her retreating, do not live unhappy, but
                    with firm-set mind endure, harden yourself. Farewell, girl! now Catullus hardens
                    himself, he will not seek you, will not ask you since you are unwilling. But you
                    will be pained, when you are not asked. Faithless, go your way! what manner of
                    life remains to you? who now will visit you? who find you beautiful? whom will
                    you love now? whose will you be called? whom will you kiss? whose lips will you
                    bite? But you, Catullus, remain firm in your hardness.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="9">
				<p>Veranius, standing in the front of all my friends, had I three hundred thousand
                    of them, have you come home to your Penates, your longing brothers and your aged
                    mother? You have come back. O joyful news to me! I'll see you safe and sound,
                    and hear you speak of regions, deeds, and peoples Iberian, as is your manner;
                    and reclining over your neck shall kiss your laughing mouth and eyes. Of all men
                    most full of bliss, who is more happy or more blissful than I?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="10">
				<p>Varus drew me off from the Forum where I was passing the time to see his lover: a
                    professional, as it seemed to me at first sight, neither inelegant nor lacking
                    good looks. When we came in, we fell to discussing various subjects, among
                    which, how was <placeName key="tgn,7016608">Bithynia</placeName> now, how things
                    had gone there, and whether I had made any money there. I replied what was true,
                    that neither ourselves nor the praetors nor their company had brought away
                    anything whereby to flaunt a better-scented hair-do, especially as our praetor,
                    who boned us all, didn't care a hair for his company. "But surely," she said,
                    "you got some men to bear your litter, for they are said to grow there?" I, to
                    make myself appear to the girl as one of the fortunate, "No," I say, "it did not
                    go that badly with me, ill as the province turned out, that I could not procure
                    eight strapping men to bear me. (But not a single one was mine either here or
                    there who could hoist on his neck the fractured foot of my old bedstead). And
                    she, like the saucy tramp she was, "Please, Catullus," says she, "lend me those
                    bearers for a short time, for I want to ride to the shrine of Serapis." "Hold
                    it!" say I to the girl, "when I said I had this, my mind slipped; my friend,
                    Cinna Gaius, he provided himself with these. In truth, whether his or
                    mine&mdash;what is it to me? I use them as though I had paid for them. But
                    you are awfully crude and a bother, not through you am I to be careless."</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="11">
				<p>Furius and Aurelius, comrades of Catullus, whether he forces his way to furthest
                        <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> where the shore is lashed by
                    the far-echoing waves of the Dawn, or whether to the land of the Hyrcanians or
                    soft Arabs, or whether to the land of the Sacians or quiver-bearing Parthians,
                    or where the seven-mouthed <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> colors
                    the sea, or whether he traverses the lofty <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName>, gazing at the monuments of mighty Caesar, the Gallic
                    Rhine, the shuddering water and remotest Britons, prepared to attempt all these
                    things at once, whatever the will of the heavenly gods may
                    bear,&mdash;repeat to my girl a few words, though they are not at all good.
                    May she live and flourish with her fornicators, and may she hold three hundred
                    at once in her embrace, loving not one in truth, but bursting again and again
                    the guts of all: nor may she look back upon my love as before, which by her
                    lapse has fallen, just as a flower on the meadow's edge, after the touch of the
                    passing plough.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="12">
				<p>Marrucinius Asinius, you do not use your left hand nicely amid the jests and
                    wine: you make off with the napkins of the careless. Do you think this is witty?
                    It escapes you, fool, how coarse a thing and unbecoming it is! Don't you believe
                    me? Believe your brother Pollio who would willingly give a talent to divert you
                    from your thefts: for he is a lad skilled in pleasantries and clever talk.
                    Therefore, either expect three hundred hendecasyllables, or return me my napkin
                    which I esteem, not for its value but as a pledge of remembrance from my
                    comrade. For Fabullus and Veranius sent me napkins as a gift from Iberian
                    Saetabis; these I must love even as I do Veraniolus and Fabullus.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="13">
				<p>You will feast well with me, my Fabullus, in a few days, if the gods favour you,
                    provided you bring here with you a good and great feast, not forgetting a
                    radiant girl and wine and wit and all kinds of laughter. Provided, I say, you
                    bring them here, our charming friend, you will feast well: for your Catullus'
                    purse is full with cobwebs. But in return you will receive a pure love, or what
                    is sweeter or more elegant: for I will give you an unguent which the Venuses and
                    Cupids gave to my girl, which, when you smell it, you will entreat the gods to
                    make you, Fabullus, all Nose!</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="14">
				<p>If I did not love you more than my eyes, most delightful Calvus, for your gift I
                    should hate you with Vatinian hatred. For what have I done or what have I said
                    that you should torment me so vilely with these poets? May the gods give that
                    client of yours ills enough, who sent you so many scoundrels! Yet if, as I
                    suspect, Sulla, the litterateur, gives you this new and care-picked gift, it is
                    not ill to me, but well and beatific, that your labors [in his cause] are not
                    made light of. Great gods, what a horrible and accursed book which&mdash;if
                    you please!&mdash;you have sent to your Catullus, that he might die of
                    boredom the livelong day in the Saturnalia, choicest of days! No, no, my joker,
                    you will not get off so easily: for at dawn I will haste to the booksellers'
                    cases; the Caesii, the Aquini, Suffenus, every poisonous rubbish will I collect
                    that I may repay you with these tortures. Meantime farewell! be gone from here,
                    where an ill foot brought you, pests of the period, most wretched of poets.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="14b">
				<p>If by chance you ever should be readers of my triflings and you will not quake to
                    lay your hands upon us<gap/></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="15">
				<p>I commend myself and my lover to you, Aurelius. I come with a modest request
                    that,&mdash;if you longed for anything with your heart which you desired
                    chaste and untouched&mdash;you will preserve my boy's chastity
                    from&mdash;I do not say from the people: I fear not at all those who hurry
                    along the thoroughfares here and there occupied on their own business: in truth,
                    my fear is from you and your penis, pestilent to boys fair and to foul. Set it
                    in motion where you please, as you please, as much as you want, outdoors
                    wherever you find the opportunity: for this one object I make an exception, to
                    my thought a reasonable request. But if your infatuation and senseless passion
                    push you forward, scoundrel, to a crime so great as to assail our head with your
                    snares, ah!, then an evil fate will make you suffer, when, with feet taut bound,
                    radishes and mullets will pierce through the open hole.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="16">
				<p>I will make you my boys and bone you, sexually submissive Aurelius and Furius the
                    sodomite, who think, because my verses are voluptuous, that I am not chaste
                    enough. For it is right that a poet be chaste himself; it is not at all
                    necessary for his verses to be. My verses, in a word, may have a spice and
                    charm, if they are voluptuous and not chaste enough, and because they are sexy
                    and can arouse&mdash;I do not say boys&mdash;but this hairy pair who
                    can't shake their stiffies. Because you have read of many thousand kisses, do
                    you think me less a man? I will make you my boys and bone you!</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="17">
				<p>O <persName><surname>Colonia</surname></persName>, you who long to play on a
                    long bridge and have it readied to dance on, but fear the shaky legs of the
                    little bridge standing on second-hand sticks, lest it tumble flat in the deep
                    swamp; let the bridge be as good as you desire, on which even the Salian dances
                    may be undertaken: for which give to me, <persName><surname>Colonia</surname></persName>, the gift of greatest laughter. I want a certain
                    townsman of mine to go head over heels from your bridge into the mud, in truth
                    where the brimming, stinking swamp is darkest and an especially deep-sunk mire.
                    He's the biggest ass of a man, lacking the sense of a two-year-old dozing in his
                    father's cradling arm. Although a girl is wedded to him flushed with
                    springtide's bloom (and a girl more dainty than a tender kid needs to be watched
                    with keener diligence than the lush-black grape-bunch), he leaves her to play as
                    she wants, cares not a single hair, nor troubles himself with marital office,
                    but lies like an alder tree felled by a Ligurian hatchet in a ditch, as aware of
                    everything as though no woman were anywhere. Such is my thick-headed friend! he
                    sees not, he hears not. He also knows not who he is himself, or whether he is or
                    is not. Now I want to chuck him head first from your bridge, if it is possible
                    to suddenly rouse this sleepy dullard and to leave behind in the heavy mud his
                    sluggish spirit, as does a mule its iron shoe in the sticky mire.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="18">
				<p>= Anth. Lat. <date value="1700">1700</date></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="19">
				<p>= Anth. Lat. <date value="1699">1699</date></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="20">
				<p>= Anth. Lat. <date value="1698">1698</date></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="21">
				<p>Aurelius, father of hunger, in ages past in time now present and in future years
                    yet to come, you long to make my lover your boy. And you do not operate
                    secretly: for you are with him, you joke together, closely sticking at his side
                    you try every means. In vain: for, though you plot against me, I'll tag you
                    first with a boning.&mdash; Now if you were satisfied, I would be silent:
                    but what irks me is that my boy, ah me! must learn to starve and thirst with
                    you. Therefore, desist, while you may with modesty, lest you reach the
                    end,&mdash;but by being boned.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="22">
				<p>That Suffenus, Varus, whom you know well, is a man fair spoken, witty and urbane,
                    and one who makes lengthy verses. I think he has written at full length ten
                    thousand or more, nor are they set down, as commonly, on scraped parchment:
                    regal paper, new boards, new bosses, straps, red parchment, the whole thing
                    ruled with the lead and smoothed off with the pumice. But when you read these,
                    that refined and urbane Suffenus seems on the contrary to be a mere goatherd or
                    ditch-digger, so great and shocking is the change. What can we think of this?
                    The same man, who just now seemed a man-about-town, or if anything could be more
                    polished than that, is stupider than the stupid countryside as soon as he
                    touches poetry, and nor is the same man ever as happy as when he is writing
                    poetry&mdash;so greatly is he pleased with himself, so much does he admire
                    himself. Still, we are all the same and are deceived, nor is there any man in
                    whom you can not see a Suffenus in some one point. Each of us has his assigned
                    delusion: but we see not what's in the wallet on our back.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="23">
				<p>Furius, you who have neither a slave, nor a coffer, nor a bug, nor a spider, nor
                    fire, but have both a father and a step-mother whose teeth can munch up even
                    flints,&mdash;you live finely with your father, and with your father's
                    wooden spouse. And no wonder: for you are all in good health, finely you digest,
                    you fear nothing, not arson, not the fall of your house, not impious thefts, not
                    plots of poison, no perilous happenings whatsoever. And you have bodies drier
                    than horn (or if there is anything more arid still, parched by sun, frost, and
                    famine. So why is it not happy and well with you? Sweat is a stranger to you,
                    absent also are saliva, phlegm, and evil nose-snot. Add to this cleanliness the
                    thing that's still more cleanly, that your backside is purer than a salt-cellar,
                    nor do you crap ten times in the whole year, and then it is harder than beans
                    and pebbles; and if you rub and crumble it in your hands, you can't ever dirty a
                    finger. Spurn not hese goodly gifts and favours, Furius, nor think lightly of
                    them; and stop always begging for a hundred sesterces: for you are happy
                    enough!</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="24">
				<p>O you who are the little flower of Juventian race, not only of these now living,
                    but of those that were before and also of those that will be in the coming
                    years, I'd rather that you had given the wealth of Midas to that man who owns
                    neither a slave nor coffer, than that you should suffer yourself to be loved by
                    him. "What?" you ask. "Isn't he a fine looking man?" He is; but this fine
                    looking man has neither a slave nor coffer. Slight and make light of this as you
                    please: nevertheless, he has neither a slave nor coffer.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="25">
				<p>Thallus you sodomite, softer than rabbit's fur, or goose's marrow, or an ear
                    lobe, or an old man's drooping penis, and the cobwebs there; again Thallus
                    greedier than the driving storm, when &dagger;the ram shows them off their
                    guard&dagger;, give me back my mantle which you have swooped down upon, and
                    the Saetaban napkin and Thynian tablets which, idiot, you openly parade as
                    though they were heirlooms. Now unglue these from your nails and return them,
                    lest the stinging scourge shamefully score your downy little butt and delicate
                    little hands, and you unaccustomedly heave and toss like a tiny boat surprised
                    on the vast sea by a raging storm.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="26">
				<p>Furius, your little house is pitted not against the southern breeze nor the
                    western wind nor cruel Boreas nor sunny east, but fifteen thousand two hundred
                    sesterces. O horrible and baleful wind.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="27">
				<p>Boy cupbearer of old Falernian, pour me more pungent cups as bids the laws of
                    Postumia, mistress of the feast, drunker than a drunken grape. But off with you,
                    as far as you please, crystal waters, bane of wine, depart you to the sober:
                    here the Thyonian juice is pure.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="28">
				<p>Piso's Company, a penniless staff, with lightweight knapsacks, scantly packed,
                    most dear Veranius you, and my Fabullus too, how goes it with you? Have you
                    borne frost and famine enough with that sot? Which in your tablets
                    appear&mdash;the profits or expenses? So with me, who when I followed a
                    praetor, inscribed more gifts than gains. "0 Memmius, well and slowly did you
                    bone me, supine, day by day, with the whole of that beam." But, from what I see,
                    in like case you have been; for you have been crammed with no smaller a poker.
                    Courting friends of high rank! But may the gods and goddesses heap ill upon you
                    disgraces to Romulus and Remus.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="29">
				<p>Who can see this, who can stand it, save the shameless, the glutton, and gambler,
                    that Mamurra Mentula should possess what long-haired <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> had and remotest <placeName key="tgn,7008653">Britain</placeName> had before? You sodomite Romulus, will
                    you see this and bear it? Then you are shameless, a glutton and a gambler. And
                    will he now, proud and overflowing, saunter over each one's bed, like a little
                    white dove or an Adonis? You sodomite Romulus, will you see this and bear it?
                    Then you are shameless, a glutton and a gambler. For such a name, Generalissimo,
                    have you been to the furthest island of the west, that this love-weary Mentula
                    of yours should squander twenty or thirty million? What is it but a skewed
                    liberality? Perhaps he spent too little, or perhaps he was washed clean? First
                    he wasted his patrimony; second the loot from <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>; then third the loot from <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, which even the goldbearing <placeName key="tgn,7016546">Tagus</placeName> knows. Now he is feared by Gauls and <placeName key="tgn,7008653">Britain</placeName>. Why do you indulge this scoundrel?
                    What can he do but devour well-fattened inheritances? Was it for such a name,
                    &dagger; most wealthy father-in-law and son-in-law, that you have destroyed
                    everything?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="30">
				<p>Alfenus, unmindful and unfaithful to your comrades true, is there now no pity in
                    you, hard of heart, for your sweet loving friend? Do you betray me now, and not
                    hesitate to play me false now, dishonourable one? Yet the irreverent deeds of
                    traitorous men do not please the dwellers in heaven: this you take no heed of,
                    leaving me wretched among my ills. Tell me, ah, what may men do, or in whom may
                    they have their trust? Surely you used to bid me entrust my soul to you, unfair,
                    drawing my affections to yourself, as though all were safely mine. Yet now you
                    withdraw yourself, and all your purposeless words and deeds you suffer the winds
                    and airy clouds to bear away. If you have forgotten, yet the gods remember,
                    Faith remembers, and in time to come will make you regret your doing.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="31">
				<p><placeName key="tgn,7005771">Sirmio</placeName>! Eyelet of islands and
                    peninsulas, which each Neptune holds whether in limpid lakes or on the wide sea,
                    how gladly and how happily do I see you again, scarcely believing that I've left
                    behind Thynia and the Bithynian plains, and that I gaze on you safe and sound. O
                    what greater blessing than cares released, when the mind casts down its burden,
                    and when wearied with the toil of travel we reach our hearth, and rest in the
                    long-for bed. This and only this repays our numerous labors. Hail, lovely
                        <placeName key="tgn,7005771">Sirmio</placeName>, and rejoice in your master;
                    and rejoice, you waves of the Lybian lake; laugh, you laughters echoing from my
                    home.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="32">
				<p>Please, my sweet Ipsithilla, my delight, my charmer: order me to come to you at
                    noon. And if you should order this, it will be useful if no one makes fast the
                    outer door [against me], and don't be minded to go out, but stay at home and
                    prepare for us nine continuous love-makings. In truth if you are minded, give
                    the order at once: for breakfast over, I lie supine and ripe, poking through
                    both tunic and cloak.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="33">
				<p>0 best of the thieves of the baths, Vibennius the father, and his sexually
                    submissive son (for the father is the filthier with the right hand, the son is
                    the greedier with the backside), why don't you go into exile and to hellish
                    shores, seeing that the father's plunder is known to the people, and that, son,
                    you cannot sell your hairy butt for one cent?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="34">
				<p>We, upright maids and youths, are in Diana's care: upright youths and maids, we
                    sing Diana. 0 Latonia, progeny great of greatest Jove, whom your mother bore
                    beneath Delian olive, that you might be queen of lofty mounts, of foliaged
                    groves, of remote glens, and of winding streams. You are called Juno Lucina by
                    the mother in the pangs of childbirth, you are named potent Trivia and
                        <persName><surname>Luna</surname></persName> with an ill-got light. You,
                    Goddess, with monthly march measuring the yearly course, glut with produce the
                    rustic roofs of the farmer. Be you hallowed by whatever name you prefer; and
                    cherish, with your good aid, as you are accustomed, the ancient race of
                    Romulus.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="35">
				<p>Paper, I would like you say to that sweet poet, my comrade, Caecilius, that he
                    come to <placeName key="perseus,Verona">Verona</placeName>, quitting New Comum's
                    city-walls and Larius' shore; for I want him to receive certain thoughts from a
                    friend of his and mine. Therefore, if he is wise, he'll devour the way, although
                    a bright-hued girl a thousand times calls him back when he goes, and flinging
                    both arms around his neck asks him to delay&mdash;she who now, if truth is
                    reported to me, is undone with immoderate love of him. For, since the time she
                    read the beginning of his <title>Mistress of Dindymus</title>, flames have been
                    devouring the innermost marrow of the poor little girl. I forgive you, girl,
                    more learned than the Sapphic muse: for charmingly has the Great Mother been
                    begun by Caecilius.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="36">
				<p>Volusius' <title>Annals</title>, defiled sheets, fulfil a vow for my girl: for
                    she vowed to sacred Venus and to Cupid that if I were reunited to her, and I
                    desisted hurling savage iambics, she would give the choicest writings of the
                    worst poet to the slow-footed god to be burned with ill-omened wood. And the
                    wretched girl saw herself vow this to the gods in jest. Now, O Creation of the
                    pale blue sea, you who dwell in sacred <placeName key="tgn,7002336">Idalium</placeName> and in storm-beaten <placeName key="perseus,Urium">Urium</placeName>, and foster <placeName key="perseus,Ancona">Ancona</placeName> and reedy <placeName key="perseus,Amathus">Amathus</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidos</placeName> and
                    Golgos and <placeName key="tgn,7010750">Dyrrhachium</placeName>, the tavern of
                    the Adriatic, accept and acknowledge this vow if it lacks neither grace nor
                    charm. But meantime, off with you to the flames, crammed with boorish speech and
                    vapid, <title>Annals</title> of Volusius, defiled sheets.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="37">
				<p>Tavern of lust and you, its tentmates (at ninth pillar from the Cap-donned
                    Brothers), do you think that you alone have mentules, that it is allowed to you
                    alone to have sex with whatever may be feminine, and to think the rest are
                    goats? But, because you sit, tasteless, hundred or maybe two hundred in a row,
                    do you think I would not dare to bone you entire two hundred loungers at once!
                    Just think it! for I'll scrawl dirty pictures all over the front of your tavern.
                    For my girl, who has fled from my embrace, she whom I loved as none will be
                    loved, for whom I fought fierce fights, has seated herself here. All of you,
                    good men and rich, and also (0 cursed shame) all of you piddling back-alley
                    fornicators, are making love to her; and you above all, Egnatius, one of the
                    long-haired race, the son of Celtiberia full of rabbits, whose quality is
                    stamped by dense-grown beard, and teeth scrubbed with Spanish urine.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="38">
				<p>It is ill, Cornificius, with your Catullus, it is ill, by Hercules, and most
                    unbearably; and greater, greater ill, each day and hour! And you, what solace do
                    you give, even the tiniest, the lightest, by your words? I'm angry with you. Is
                    my love worth this? Yet one little message would cheer me, though more full of
                    sadness than the tears of Simonides.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="39">
				<p>Egnatius, who has shiny, white teeth, grins forever everywhere. If he is in
                    court, when counsel excites tears, he grins. If he be at funeral pyre where one
                    mourns a son devoted, where a bereft mother's tears stream for her only son, he
                    grins. Whatever it may be, wherever he is, whatever may happen, he grins. Such
                    an ill habit has he&mdash;neither in good taste, I suppose, nor refined.
                    Therefore take note from me, my good Egnatius. Whether you are from the city or
                        <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> or Tiburtine, or a thrifty
                    Umbrian or a fat Etruscan, or a dark, toothy Lanuvian, or Transpadine (to touch
                    upon my own folk also), or whoever of those who cleanly wash their teeth, still
                    I wish you wouldn't grin forever everywhere; for nothing is more senseless than
                    senseless giggling. Now you're a Celtiberian: and in the Celtiberian land early
                    in the morning they piss and scrub their teeth and pinky gums with it, so that
                    the higher the polish on your teeth, the more it proclaims that you have drunk
                    your piss.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="40">
				<p>What ill-set mind, poor little Ravidus, thrusts you headlong at my iambics? What
                    god, none advocate of good for you, stirs you to a senseless quarrel? That you
                    may be in the people's mouth? What do you want? Do you want to be famous, no
                    matter in what way? You will be, but by our long-drawn vengeance, since you
                    wanted to love my lover.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="41">
				<p>Ameana, a love-worn girl, asks me for a whole ten thousand, that girl with an
                    ugly little nose, wench of the bankrupt Formian. You near of kin in whose care
                    the girl is, summon both friends and doctors: for the girl is not sane, and is
                    not accustomed to ask her mirror how she looks.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="42">
				<p>O come, all ye hendecasyllables, as many as you are, from every part, all of you,
                    as many soever as you be! A filthy whore thinks that I am a joke, and says she
                    won't return to me your writing tablets, if you can stand it. Let's pursue her,
                    and claim them back. "Who is she?" you ask. That one, whom you see strutting
                    disgracefully, grinning with annoyance like a mime with a face like a Gallic
                    puppy. Surround her, and claim them back. "Filthy whore, give back the writing
                    tablets; give back, filthy whore, the writing tablets." You don't give two
                    cents? You slime, you whorehouse, or if you could be anything even more
                    loathsome! But you mustn't think that this is enough. For if nothing else we can
                    extort a blush on your brazened bitch's face. We'll yell again in heightened
                    voice, "Filthy whore, give back the writing tablets; give back, filthy whore,
                    the writing tablets." But we do no good, she isn't moved. We must change our
                    approach and our tune, if you can make further progress&mdash;"Chaste and
                    honest, give back our writing tablets."</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="43">
				<p>Hail, girl with nose not the smallest, and with foot not lovely, and with eyes
                    not black, and with fingers not long, and with mouth not dry and with tongue not
                    so very elegant, the wench of the bankrupt Formian. And the province declares
                    you to be lovely? With you our Lesbia is to be compared? O generation witless
                    and unmannerly!</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="44">
				<p>O, Homestead of ours, whether <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> or
                    Tiburtine (for people in whose heart it is not to wound Catullus declare you
                    Tiburtine, but those in whose heart it is, will wager anything you're <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName>) but whether <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> or more truly Tiburtine, I was glad to
                    be within your rural country-home, and to cast off an ill cough from my chest,
                    which&mdash;not unearned&mdash;my belly granted me, for grasping after
                    luxurious meals. For, while I want to be Sestius' guest, I read his defence
                    against the plaintiff Antius, crammed with venom and pestilence. Hence a chill
                    heavy rheum and fitful cough shook me continually until I fled to your asylum,
                    and brought me back to health with rest and nettle-broth. Therefore, refreshed,
                    I give you utmost thanks, that you have not avenged my fault. Nor do I pray now
                    for anything but that, if I should retake Sestius' abominable script, its chill
                    may bring a cold and cough to Sestius himself; and he invites me [to dinner]
                    whenever I read one of his bad books.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="45">
				<p>Septimius, holding his lover Acme in his lap, says, "My Acme, if I do not love
                    you to death, and am not prepared to love you constantly all the years in time
                    to come, as much and the most as one can who is desperately in love&mdash;
                    alone in <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName> or in torrid <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> may I come face to face with a grey-eyed
                    lion." When he said this, Love, leftwards as before, with approbation rightwards
                    sneezed. Then Acme slightly bending back her head, and kissed the intoxicated
                    eyes of her sweet boy with her rose-red lips. "So," she said, "my life,
                    Septimillus, we shall serve this lord alone from now on, as greater, keener fire
                    burns the more amid my soft marrow." When she said this, Love, leftwards as
                    before, with approbation rightwards sneezed. Now made complete under good
                    auspices, with mutual minds they love and are loved. Poor little Septimius wants
                    Acme alone more than [the wealth of] the <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> or <placeName key="tgn,7008653">Britain</placeName>: in
                    Septimius alone the faithful Acme takes delight and pleasure. Whoever has seen
                    happier people, whoever a more propitious Love?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="46">
				<p>Now spring brings back mild breezes without cold, now heaven's equinoctial fury
                    falls silent at Zephyr's pleasant breezes. Let the Phrygian meadows be left
                    behind, Catullus, and the teeming fields of sun-scorched <placeName key="tgn,7008773">Nicaea</placeName>: let us fly to the glorious cities of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>. Now my palpitating soul longs
                    to wander, now happy in their zeal my feet grow strong. O sweet band of
                    comrades, fare you well, whom various roads in different directions carry back
                    all at once setting out far from home.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="47">
				<p>Porcius and Socration, the two left hands of Piso, scurf and hunger of the world,
                    has that verpus Priapus placed you before my Veraniolus and Fabullus? Do you
                    spend the day luxuriously in expensive feasts? Do my comrades seek out dinner
                    invitations the cross-roads?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="48">
				<p>If someone let me kiss continually your honey-sweet eyes, Juventius, continually
                    I'd kiss even to three hundred thousand kisses, nor ever should I seem on the
                    verge of having enough, not even if the crop of our kisses should be thicker
                    than dried wheat sheaves.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="49">
				<p>Most eloquent of Romulus' descendancy&mdash;as many as there are, who have
                    been, 0 Marcus Tullius, and who will be after in other years&mdash;to you
                    Catullus gives his greatest gratitude, the worst poet of all by as much as you
                    are the best advocate of all.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="50">
				<p>Yesterday, Licinius, in leisure much we played upon my tablets, as became us, men
                    of fancy. Each jotting verses in turn played first in this meter then in that,
                    exchanging mutual epigrams amid jokes and wine. But I departed from there,
                    afire, Licinius, with your wit and charm, so that food was useless to my
                    wretched self; nor could sleep close my eyes in quiet, but all over the bed in
                    restless fury did I toss, longing to behold daylight that I might speak with
                    you, and again we might be together. But afterwards, when my limbs, weakened by
                    my restless labours, lay stretched in semi-death upon the bed, I made this poem
                    for you, my delight, from which you will perceive my pain. Now beware of
                    presumptuousness, and beware of rejecting our pleadings, I pray you, apple of my
                    eye, lest Nemesis exact her dues from you. She is a forceful Goddess; beware her
                    wrath.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="51">
				<p>He seems to me to be equal to a god, he, if such were lawful, to surpass the
                    gods, who sitting across from you again and again gazes on you, and listens to
                    you sweetly laughting, which snatchs away from sombre me my every sense: for the
                    instant I glance on you, Lesbia, nothing is left to me [of voice], but my tongue
                    is numbed, a keen-edged flame spreads through my limbs, with sound self-caused
                    my twin ears sing, and my eyes are enwrapped with night. Leisure, Catullus, to
                    you is hurtful: in leisure beyond measure do you exult and pass your life.
                    Leisure first ruined rulers and prosperous cities.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="52">
				<p>What is it, Catullus, why delay your death? Nonius the tumor is seated in the
                    curule chair, Vatinius lies his way to the consulship: what is it, Catullus, why
                    delay your death?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="53">
				<p>I just had to laugh at someone in the crowded court who, when with admirable art
                    my Calvus had set forth Vatinius' crimes, with hands uplifted in admiration thus
                    spoke: "Great Gods, the fluent little Salaputian!"</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="54">
				<p>Otho's tiny little head is<gap/>the master's uncouth half-soaped legs, Libo's
                    light and delicate wind<gap/>if not all things I wish would displease you and
                    Fuficius, that warmed-over old man<gap/>again you will be enraged at my
                    undeserving iambics, Generalissimo.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="55">
				<p>We beg, if maybe it's not too much trouble, you'll show us where your haunt may
                    be. We looked for you in the smaller Campus, for you in the Circus, for you in
                    every bookshop, for you in <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>'s
                    holy temple. My friend, on Magnus' promenade I grabbed every girl I saw whose
                    looks were unruffled, and at the same time I demanded loudly, "Give me back
                    Camerius, you wretched girls." One of them, drawing back her naked<gap/> "Look!
                    he's hiding here between my rosey-red nipples!" But bearing with you is a labor
                    of <persName><surname>Hercules</surname></persName> now. Do you deny that you
                    bear yourself in such great arrogance, my friend? Tell us where you will be,
                    declare it boldly, give up the secret, trust it to the light. What, do the
                    milk-white maidens detain you? If you hold your tongue closed up in your mouth,
                    you squander Love's every fruit: for <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName> joys in words and talk. Yet if you wish, you may bar your
                    palate, as long as you are a partner of true love.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="56">
				<p>O thing ridiculous, <persName><surname>Cato</surname></persName>, and funny, and
                    worthy of your ears and of your laughter. Laugh, <persName><surname>Cato</surname></persName>, the more you love Catullus: the thing is ridiculous and
                    too funny. Just now I caught a boy a-thrusting in a girl: and, so please you,
                    Dione, for lack of a weapon I slayed him with my own rigidity.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="57">
				<p>Beautifully it fits the shameless sodomites, Mamurra and sexually submissive
                    Caesar. It's no wonder: they share like stains&mdash;the one from the City,
                    the other, Formian&mdash;which stay deep-marked and they can not be washed
                    off. Debauched twins each, both learned, both in one bed, one not more than the
                    other the greater greedier adulterer, allied rivals of the girls. Beautifully it
                    fits the shameless sodomites.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="58">
				<p>0 Caelius, our <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName>, that <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName>, the self-same Lesbia whom Catullus
                    loved more than himself and all his own, now at the cross-roads and in the
                    alleyways husks off the high-spirited descendants of <persName><surname>Remus</surname></persName>.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="58b">
				<p>Not if I were molded into the Cretan guard, not if I were born with Pegasean
                    wing, or I Ladas, or Perseus with winged foot, or Rhesus' swift and snowy team:
                    add to these the feathery-footed and winged ones, ask at the same time the
                    course of the winds: which bound up, Camerius, you name as mine; yet exhausted
                    in my every marrow and with many a faintness consumed, I would be in my quest
                    for you, my friend.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="59">
				<p>Rufa of <placeName key="tgn,7010649">Bononia</placeName> blows Rufulus, she the
                    wife of Menenius. Often you have seen her among the tombs, snatching her meal
                    from the funeral pyre. When she chases after the bread which has rolled from the
                    fire, she is buffeted by the half-shaven cremator.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="60">
				<p>Did a lioness of the Libyan mountains beget you, or Scylla yelping from her
                    lowmost groin with mind so harsh and loathsome, that you have contempt for a
                    suppliant's voice in his last calamity? ah, heart overgreatly cruel.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="61">
				<p>You who dwell on Helicon Hill, sprung from Urania, who carry off the gentle
                    virgin to her mate, O Hymenaeus Hymen, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>Twine round your temples sweet-smelling flowers of marjoram; put on your
                    gold-tinted veil; lighthearted here, come here, bearing on snowy foot the
                    golden-yellow sandal:</p>
				<p>And afire with the joyous day, chanting wedding melodies with ringing voice,
                    strike the ground with your feet, with your hand swing aloft the torch of
                    pine.</p>
				<p>For Vinia&mdash;fair as <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName>
                    dwelling in <placeName key="tgn,7002336">Idalium</placeName> when came to the
                    Phrygian judge&mdash;a virgin fair, weds Manlius amid happy auspices.</p>
				<p>She, bright-shining as the Asian myrtle florid in its branches, which the
                    Hamadryads nurture for their pleasure with besprinkled dew.</p>
				<p>So come then! convey your approach here, leaving the Aonian cave in cliffs of
                        <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName>, over which flows the
                    chilling stream of Aganippe.</p>
				<p>And summon homewards the mistress, eager for her new husband, firm-prisoning her
                    soul in love; as tight-clasping ivy, wandering here and there, wraps the tree
                    around.</p>
				<p>And also you, upright virgins, for whom a like day is nearing, chant in cadence,
                    singing &ldquo;O Hymenaeus Hymen, O Hymen Hymenaeus!&rdquo;</p>
				<p>That more freely, hearing himself to his duty called, will he bear here his
                    presence, Lord of honorable love, uniter of true lovers.</p>
				<p>What god is worthier to be sought by anxious lovers? Whom of the celestials do
                    men worship more greatly? O Hymenaeus Hymen, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>You for his young the trembling father beseeches, for you virgins unclasp the
                    belt from their breasts, for you the fearful bridegroom harkens with eager
                    ear.</p>
				<p>You deliver into the hands of the untamed youth that flower-like maiden, taken
                    from her mother's bosom, O Hymenaeus Hymen, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>Without you Venus can do nothing suitable that good repute sanctions; but she
                    can, with you willing. Who dares to be compared with such a god?</p>
				<p>Without you, no house can produce heirs, no parent be surrounded by offspring;
                    but they can, with you willing. Who dares to be compared with such a god?</p>
				<p>And lacking your rites no land can give protection to its territory; but it can,
                    with you willing. Who dares to be compared with such a god?</p>
				<p>Unbolt, open the gates: the virgin is here. See how the torches shake their
                    gleaming locks? <gap/></p>
				<milestone n="80" unit="line"/>
				<p><gap/>Her natural modesty detains her: hearing this the more, she weeps because
                    she must go.</p>
				<p>Cease your tears. For you there is no peril, Aurunculeia, that any woman more
                    beauteous will ever see the light of day coming from Ocean.</p>
				<p>You are like the hyacinth flower, which stands aloft amid varied riches of its
                    master's garden. But you delay, day slips by: advance, new bride.</p>
				<p>Advance, new bride, it it now seems right, and listen to our speech. See how the
                    torches shake their glittering tresses: advance, new bride.</p>
				<p>Nor is your man a fickle husband, given to ill adulteries, seeking shameless
                    acts, ever wishing to lie away from your soft breasts,</p>
				<p>But as the lithe vine among neighbouring trees doth cling, so shall he be
                    enclasped in your embrace. But day slips by: advance, new bride.</p>
				<p>O nuptial couch which for all<gap/><milestone n="115" unit="line"/>with feet of
                    ivory white.</p>
				<p>What joys are coming to your man in fleeting night, in noon of day, let him
                    rejoice! but day slips by: advance, new bride.</p>
				<p>Raise high, O boys, the torches: I see the gleaming veil approach. Come, chant in
                    cadence, &ldquo;O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus.&rdquo;</p>
				<p>Nor longer silent is lewd Fescinnine jest, nor, favorite, hearing your master's
                    love has flown, deny the nuts to the boys.</p>
				<p>Give nuts to the boys, O listless favorite; long enough have you played nuts: now
                    you must serve Talassius. O favorite, give the nuts!</p>
				<p>The country wives were dirt to you, O favorite, but yesterday: now the barber
                    shaves your face. Wretched, wretched favorite, give the nuts.</p>
				<p>They will say when the bridegroom has been annointed that you can scarce abstain
                    from your hairless boys: butabstain! O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen
                    Hymenaeus.</p>
				<p>We know that these delights were known to you only when lawful: but to the wedded
                    these same no more are lawful. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>You also, bride, what your husband seeks beware of denying, lest he go elsewhere
                    in its search. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>Look, your husband's home is yours, influential and goodly, allow it to serve you
                    (O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!)</p>
				<p>Until white-haired old age, shaking your trembling brow, nods assent to
                    everything. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>Bring with good omen your golden feet across the threshold, and go through the
                    polished doorway. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>Look! your husband alone within, lying on Tyrian couch, all-expectant waits for
                    you. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>No less than in yours, in his breast burns an inmost flame, but more deeply
                    inward. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus!</p>
				<p>Release the maiden's slender arm, boy with crimson-bordered toga: now let her
                    approach her husband's couch. O Hymen Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus.</p>
				<p>You good women of fair renown to aged spouses, put the maiden to bed. O Hymen
                    Hymenaeus io, O Hymen Hymenaeus.</p>
				<p>Now you may come, bridegroom: your wife is in the bedroom, with face brightly
                    blushing as white parthenice amid ruddy poppies.</p>
				<p>But, bridegroom (so help me the heaven-dwellers) in no way less beautiful are
                    you, nor does Venus slight you. But the day slips by: on! do not delay.</p>
				<p>You have not delayed for long, now you are coming. Kindly Venus will help you,
                    since what you desire you take publicly, and do not conceal true love.</p>
				<p>Whoever wishes to keep count of your many thousand games, first let him make an
                    accounting of the number of <placeName key="tgn,2086787">Africa</placeName>'s
                    sands and the glittering stars.</p>
				<p>Play as you like, and speedily give heirs. It does not become so old a name to
                    without children, but from similar stock always to be generated.</p>
				<p>A little Torquatus I wish, from his mother's lap reaching out his dainty hands,
                    and smiling sweetly at his father with lips apart.</p>
				<p>May he be like his father <persName><surname>Manlius</surname></persName>, and
                    easily acknowledged by every stranger, and by his face point out his mother's
                    faithfulness.</p>
				<p>May such praise confirm his birth from true mother, such fame as rests only with
                    Telemachus from best of mothers, Penelope.</p>
				<p>Close the doors, virgins: enough we've played. But, fair bride and groom, live
                    you well, and diligently fulfil the office of vigorous youth.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="62">
				<p/>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Youths</speaker>
					<p><persName><surname>Vesper</surname></persName> is here: youths, arise.
                        <persName><surname>Vesper</surname></persName> at last has just borne
                        aloft in the heavens his long awaited light. Now it is time to arise, now to
                        leave the luxurious tables, now will come the virgin, now will be sung the
                        Hymenaeus. Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Maidens</speaker>
					<p>Unwedded girls, do you see the youths? Arise in response: so it must be that
                        the Star of Eve displays its Oetaean fires. Surely it is thus; see how
                        fleetly they have leapt forth? Nor without intent have they leapt forth;
                        what they will sing, it is our task to surpass. Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen
                        come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Youths</speaker>
					<p>For us, comrades, the palm of victory is not easily acquired; see how the
                        girls rehearse what they planned. They do not plan in vain, what they have
                        may be memorable. No wonder: for inwardly they toil with whole of their
                        minds. Our minds are parted in one direction, our ears in another:
                        rightfully therefore we shall be surpassed, for victory loves solicitude. So
                        then, at least now focus your attention: now they begin to sing, now we
                        shall have to respond. Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Maidens</speaker>
					<p><persName><surname>Hesperus</surname></persName>! what crueler star is borne
                        aloft in the heavens? you who could pluck a maid from her mother's embrace,
                        pluck a clinging maid from her mother's embrace, and could give the chaste
                        girl to a burning youth. What more cruel could victors accomplish in
                        vanquished city? Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Youths</speaker>
					<p><persName><surname>Hesperus</surname></persName>! what more delightful star
                        shines in the heavens? you who strengthen with your flame the marriage
                        betrothals which husbands pledge, and which the fathers pledged before, and
                        they are not joined before your flame is borne aloft. What more wished for
                        do the gods give than that happy hour? Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O
                        Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Maidens</speaker>
					<p><persName><surname>Hesperus</surname></persName>, comrades, has stolen one
                        girl away from us,<gap/>&lsqb;Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O
                        Hymenaeus!&rsqb;</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Youths</speaker>
					<p>For at your approach a guard always keeps watch. Thieves lie in wait by
                        night, often on your return with your name changed, <persName><surname>Hesperus</surname></persName>, you catch the same men. Yet it
                        pleases the unwedded girls to criticize you with false complaints. But what
                        if they criticize the one whom with silent mind they long for? Hymen O
                        Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Maidens</speaker>
					<p>As grows the hidden flower in a walled garden, unknown to cattle, uprooted by
                        no plow, which the breezes caress, the sun strengthens, and the rain gives
                        growth: many boys and many girls have longed for it: this same flower when
                        plucked by a delicate fingernail sheds its blossoms: no boys and no girls
                        long for it: so the virgin, while she stays untouched, so long is she dear
                        to her own; when she has lost her chaste flower from her body profaned, she
                        does not remain a delight for the boys,she beauteous, nor is she dear to the
                        girls. Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Youths</speaker>
					<p>As the widowed vine which grows in naked field never uplifts itself, never
                        ripens a mellow grape, but bending prone beneath the weight of its tender
                        body now and again its highmost shoot touches with its root; this no farmer,
                        no oxen will cultivate: but if this same chance to be joined with marital
                        elm, many farmers, many oxen will cultivate it: so the virgin, while she
                        stays untouched, so long does she age, uncultivated; but when she obtains
                        fitting union at the right time, dearer is she to her husband and less of a
                        trouble to her father. Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Youths and Maidens</speaker>
					<p>Even you, virgin, do not struggle against such a mate. It is improper to
                        struggle with him to whom your father has handed you over, your father
                        himself together with your mother whom you must obey. Your maidenhead is not
                        wholly yours, in part it is your parents': a third part is your father's, a
                        third part is given to your mother, a third alone is yours: be unwilling to
                        struggle against two, who to their son-in-law their rights together with
                        dowry have given. Hymen O Hymenaeus, Hymen come O Hymenaeus!</p>
				</sp>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="63">
				<p>Over the vast main borne by swift-sailing ship, Attis, as with hasty hurried foot
                    he reached the Phrygian wood and gained the tree-girt gloomy sanctuary of the
                    Goddess, there roused by rabid rage and mind astray, with sharp-edged flint
                    downwards dashed his burden of virility. Then as he felt his limbs were left
                    without their manhood, and the fresh-spilt blood staining the soil, with
                    bloodless hand she hastily took a tambour light to hold, your taborine, Cybele,
                    your initiate rite, and with feeble fingers beating the hollowed bullock's back,
                    she rose up quivering thus to chant to her companions.</p>
				<p>&ldquo;Haste you together, she-priests, to Cybele's dense woods, together
                    haste, you vagrant herd of the dame Dindymene, you who inclining towards strange
                    places as exiles, following in my footsteps, led by me, comrades, you who have
                    faced the ravening sea and truculent main, and have castrated your bodies in
                    your utmost hate of <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName>, make glad
                    our mistress speedily with your minds' mad wanderings. Let dull delay depart
                    from your thoughts, together haste you, follow to the Phrygian home of Cybele,
                    to the Phrygian woods of the Goddess, where sounds the cymbal's voice, where the
                    tambour resounds, where the Phrygian flutist pipes deep notes on the curved
                    reed, where the ivy-clad Maenades furiously toss their heads, where they enact
                    their sacred orgies with shrill-sounding ululations, where that wandering band
                    of the Goddess flits about: there it is meet to hasten with hurried mystic
                    dance.&rdquo;</p>
				<p>When Attis, spurious woman, had thus chanted to her comity, the chorus
                    straightway shrills with trembling tongues, the light tambour booms, the concave
                    cymbals clang, and the troop swiftly hastes with rapid feet to verdurous Ida.
                    Then raging wildly, breathless, wandering, with brain distraught, hurries Attis
                    with her tambour, their leader through dense woods, like an untamed heifer
                    shunning the burden of the yoke: and the swift Gallae press behind their
                    speedy-footed leader. So when the home of Cybele they reach, wearied out with
                    excess of toil and lack of food they fall in slumber. Sluggish sleep shrouds
                    their eyes drooping with faintness, and raging fury leaves their minds to quiet
                    ease.</p>
				<p>But when the sun with radiant eyes from face of gold glanced over the white
                    heavens, the firm soil, and the savage sea, and drove away the glooms of night
                    with his brisk and clamorous team, then sleep fast-flying quickly sped away from
                    wakening Attis, and goddess Pasithea received Somnus in her panting bosom. Then
                    when from quiet rest torn, her delirium over, Attis at once recalled to mind her
                    deed, and with lucid thought saw what she had lost, and where she stood, with
                    heaving heart she backwards traced her steps to the landing-place. There, gazing
                    over the vast main with tear-filled eyes, with saddened voice in tristful
                    soliloquy thus did she lament her land:</p>
				<p>&ldquo;Mother-land, my creatress, mother-land, my begetter, which full sadly
                    I'm forsaking, as runaway serfs do from their lords, to the woods of Ida I have
                    hasted on foot, to stay amid snow and icy dens of beasts, and to wander through
                    their hidden lurking-places full of fury. Where, or in what part, mother-land,
                    may I imagine that you are? My very eyeball craves to fix its glance towards
                    you, while for a brief space my mind is freed from wild ravings. And must I
                    wander over these woods far from my home? From country, goods, friends, and
                    parents, must I be parted? Leave the forum, the palaestra, the race-course, and
                    gymnasium? Wretched, wretched soul, it is yours to grieve for ever and ever. For
                    what shape is there, whose kind I have not worn? I (now a woman), I a man, a
                    stripling, and a lad; I was the gymnasium's flower, I was the pride of the oiled
                    wrestlers: my gates, my friendly threshold, were crowded, my home was decked
                    with floral garlands, when I used to leave my couch at sunrise. Now will I live
                    a ministrant of gods and slave to Cybele? I a Maenad, I a part of me, I a
                    sterile trunk! Must I range over the snow-clad spots of verdurous Ida, and wear
                    out my life beneath lofty Phrygian peaks, where stay the sylvan-seeking stag and
                    woodland-wandering boar? Now, now, I grieve the deed I've done; now, now, do I
                    repent!&rdquo;</p>
				<p>As the swift sound left those rosy lips, borne by new messenger to gods' twinned
                    ears, Cybele, unloosing her lions from their joined yoke, and goading, the
                    left-hand foe of the herd, thus speaks: &ldquo;Come,&rdquo; she says,
                    &ldquo;to work, you fierce one, cause a madness urge him on, let a fury
                    prick him onwards till he returns through our woods, he who over-rashly seeks to
                    fly from my empire. On! thrash your flanks with your tail, endure your strokes;
                    make the whole place re-echo with roar of your bellowings; wildly toss your
                    tawny mane about your nervous neck.&rdquo; Thus ireful Cybele spoke and
                    loosed the yoke with her hand. The monster, self-exciting, to rapid wrath spurs
                    his heart, he rushes, he roars, he bursts through the brake with heedless tread.
                    But when he gained the humid verge of the foam-flecked shore, and spied the
                    womanish Attis near the opal sea, he made a bound: the witless wretch fled into
                    the wild wood: there throughout the space of her whole life a bondsmaid did she
                    stay. Great Goddess, Goddess Cybele, Goddess Dame of Dindymus, far from my home
                    may all your anger be, 0 mistress: urge others to such actions, to madness
                    others hound.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="64">
				<p>Pines once sprung from <placeName key="tgn,2096449">Pelion</placeName>'s peak
                    floated, it is said, through liquid billows of <placeName key="tgn,2065560">Neptune</placeName> to the flowing <placeName key="tgn,7012263">Phasis</placeName> and the Aeetaean territory, when the picked youth, the
                    vigour of <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> manhood seeking to
                    carry away the Golden Fleece from <placeName key="tgn,7016642">Colchis</placeName>, dared to skim over salt seas in a swift-sailing ship,
                    sweeping the blue-green ocean with paddles shaped from fir-wood. That goddess
                    who guards the castles in topmost parts of the towns herself fashioned the car,
                    scudding with lightest of winds, uniting the interweaved pines unto the curving
                    keel. That goddess first instructed untaught Amphitrite with sailing. Scarce had
                    it split with its stem the windy waves, and the billow vexed with oars had
                    whitened into foam, when arose from the swirl of the hoary eddies the faces of
                    sea-dwelling Nereids wondering at the marvel. And then on that propitious day
                    mortal eyes gazed on sea-nymphs with naked bodies bare to the breasts
                    outstanding from the foamy swirl. Then it is said Peleus burned with desire for
                    Thetis, then Thetis despised not mortal marriage, then Thetis' sire himself
                    sanctioned her joining to Peleus. O heroes, born in the time of joyfuller ages,
                    hail! sprung from the gods, good progeny of mothers, hail! and may you be
                    favourably inclined. I'll address you often in my song, you too I'll approach,
                    Peleus, pillar of <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, so
                    increased in importance by your fortunate wedding-torches, to whom <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName> himself, the sire of the gods himself,
                    yielded up his beloved. Did not Thetis embrace you, she most winsome of Nereids
                    born? Did not Tethys consent that you should lead home her grandchild, and
                    Oceanus too, whose waters enfold the total globe? When in full course of time
                    the longed-for day had dawned, all <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> assembled and thronged his home, a gladsome company
                    overspreading the halls: they bear gifts to the fore, and their joy in their
                    faces they show. Scyros remains a desert, they leave Phthiotic Tempe, Crannon's
                    homes, and the fortressed walls of Larissa; at Pharsalia they gather, beneath
                    Pharsalian roofs they throng. None tills the soil, the heifers' necks grow
                    softened, the trailing vine is not cleansed by the curved rake-prongs, nor does
                    the bull tear up the clods with the prone-bending plowblade, nor does the sickle
                    prune the shade of the spreading tree-branches, squalid rust steals over the
                    neglected plows.</p>
				<p>But this mansion, throughout its innermost recesses of opulent royalty, glitters
                    with gleaming gold and with silver. Ivory makes white the seats; goblets glint
                    on the boards; the whole house delights in the splendour of royal treasure.
                    Placed in the midst of the mansion is the bridal bed of the goddess, made glossy
                    with Indian tusks and covered with purple, tinted with the shell-fish's rosy
                    dye. This tapestry embroidered with figures of men of ancient time portrays with
                    admirable art the heroes' valour. For looking forth from Dia's beach, resounding
                    with crashing of breakers, Ariadne watches Theseus moving from sight with his
                    swift fleet, her heart swelling with raging passion, and she does not yet
                    believe she sees what she sees, as, newly-awakened from her deceptive sleep, she
                    perceives herself, deserted and woeful, on the lonely shore. But the heedless
                    youth, flying away, beats the waves with his oars, leaving his perjured vows to
                    the gusty gales. In the dim distance from amidst the sea-weed, the daughter of
                    Minos with sorrowful eyes, like a stone-carved Bacchante, gazes afar, alas!
                    gazes after him, heaving with great waves of grief. No longer does the fragile
                    fillet bind her yellow locks, no more with light veil is her hidden bosom
                    covered, no more with rounded zone the milky breasts are clasped; fallen down
                    from her body everything is scattered here and there, and the salt waves toy
                    with them in front of her very feet. But neither on fillet nor floating veil,
                    but on you, Theseus, in their stead, was she musing: on you she bent her heart,
                    her thoughts, her love-lorn mind. Ah, woeful one, with sorrows unending
                    distraught, Erycina sows thorny cares deep in your bosom, since that time when
                    Theseus fierce in his vigor set out from the curved bay of <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, and gained the Gortynian roofs of
                    the iniquitous ruler.</p>
				<p>For it is said that once, constrained by the cruelest plague to expiate the
                    slaughter of Androgeos, Cecropia used to give both chosen youths and the pick of
                    the unmarried maidens as a feast to the Minotaur. When thus his strait walls
                    with ills were vexed, Theseus with free will preferred to yield up his body for
                    adored <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> rather than such
                    Cecropian corpses be carried to <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>
                    unobsequied. And therefore borne in a speedy craft by favouring breezes, he came
                    to the imperious Minos and his superb seat. Instantly with longing glance the
                    royal virgin saw him, she whom the chaste couch breathing out sweetest of scents
                    cradled in her mother's tender enfoldings, like the myrtle which the rivers of
                    Eurotas produce, or the many-tinted blooms opening with the springtide's
                    breezes, she bent not her flashing eyes away from him, until the flame spread
                    through her whole body, and burned into her innermost marrow. Ah, hard of heart,
                    urging with misery to madness, O holy boy, who mingles men's cares and their
                    joys, and you queen of Golgos and of foliaged <placeName key="tgn,7002336">Idalium</placeName>, on what waves did you heave the mind-kindled maid,
                    sighing often for the golden-haired guest! What dreads she bore in her swooning
                    soul! How often did she grow sallower in sheen than gold! When craving to
                    contend against the savage monster, Theseus faced death or the palm of
                    praise.</p>
				<milestone n="103" unit="line"/>
				<p>Then gifts to the gods not unpleasing, not idly given, with promise from
                    tight-closed lips did she address her vows. For as an oak waving its boughs on
                    Taurus' top, or a coniferous pine with sweating stem, is uprooted by savage
                    storm, twisting its trunk with its blast (dragged from its roots prone it falls
                    afar, breaking all in the line of its fall) so did Theseus fling down the
                    conquered body of the brute, tossing its horns in vain towards the skies. Thence
                    backwards he retraced his steps amidst great laud, guiding his errant footsteps
                    by means of a tenuous thread, lest when coming out from tortuous labyrinthines
                    his efforts be frustrated by unobservant wandering. But why, turned aside from
                    my first story, should I recount more, how the daughter fleeing her father's
                    face, her sister's embrace, and even her mother's, who despairingly bemoaned her
                    lost daughter, preferred to all these the sweet love of Theseus; or how borne by
                    their boat to the spumy shores of Dia she came; or how her husband with
                    unmemoried breast forsaking her, left her bound in the shadows of sleep? And
                    oft, so it is said, with her heart burning with fury she poured out clarion
                    cries from depths of her bosom, then sadly scaled the rugged mounts, whence she
                    could cast her glance over the vast seething ocean, then ran into the opposing
                    billows of the heaving sea, raising from her bared legs her clinging raiment,
                    and in uttermost plight of woe with tear-stained face and chilly sobs she spoke
                    thus:&mdash;</p>
				<p>&ldquo;Is it thus, O perfidious, when dragged from my motherland's shores, is
                    it thus, O false Theseus, that you leave me on this desolate strand? thus do you
                    depart unmindful of slighted godheads, bearing home your perjured vows? Was no
                    thought able to bend the intent of your ruthless mind? had you no clemency
                    there, that your pitiless bowels might show me compassion? But these were not
                    the promises you gave me idly of old, this was not what you bade me hope for,
                    but the blithe bride-bed, hymenaeal happiness: all empty air, blown away by the
                    breezes. Now, now, let no woman give credence to man's oath, let none hope for
                    faithful vows from mankind; for while their eager desire strives for its end,
                    nothing fear they to swear, nothing of promises forbear they: but instantly
                    their lusting thoughts are satiate with lewdness, nothing of speech they
                    remember, nothing of perjuries care. In truth I snatched you from the midst of
                    the whirlpool of death, preferring to suffer the loss of a brother rather than
                    fail your need in the supreme hour, O ingrate. For which I shall be a gift as
                    prey to be rent by wild beasts and the carrion-fowl, nor dead shall I be placed
                    in the earth, covered with funeral mound. What lioness bore you beneath lonely
                    crag? What sea conceived and spued you from its foamy crest? What Syrtis, what
                    grasping Scylla, what vast Charybdis? O you repayer with such rewards for your
                    sweet life! If it was not your heart's wish to yoke with me, through holding in
                    horror the dread decrees of my stern sire, yet you could have led me to your
                    home, where as your handmaid I might have served you with cheerful service,
                    laving your snowy feet with clear water, or spreading the purple coverlet over
                    your couch. Yet why, distraught with woe, do I vainly lament to the unknowing
                    winds, which unfurnished with sense, can neither hear uttered complaints nor can
                    return them? For now he has sped away into the midst of the seas, nor does any
                    mortal appear along this desolate seaboard. Thus with overweening scorn bitter
                    Fate in my extreme hour even grudges ears to my complaints. All-powerful
                    Jupiter! would that in old time the Cecropian ships had not touched at the
                    Gnossan shores, nor that the false mariner, bearing the direful ransom to the
                    unquelled bull, had bound his ropes to <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, nor that yonder wretch hiding ruthless designs beneath
                    sweet seemings had reposed as a guest in our halls! For whither may I flee? in
                    what hope, O lost one, take refuge? Shall I climb the Idomenean crags? but the
                    truculent sea stretching far off with its whirlings of waters separates us. Dare
                    I hope for help from my father, whom I deserted to follow a youth besprinkled
                    with my brother's blood? Can I crave comfort from the care of a faithful
                    husband, who is fleeing with yielding oars, encurving amidst whirling waters? If
                    I turn from the beach there is no roof in this tenantless island, no way shows a
                    passage, circled by waves of the sea; no way of flight, no hope; all denotes
                    dumbness, desolation, and death. Nevertheless my eyes shall not be dimmed in
                    death, nor my senses secede from my spent frame, until I have besought from the
                    gods a just penalty for my betrayal, and implored the faith of the celestials
                    with my last breath. Wherefore you requiters of men's deeds with avenging pains,
                    O Eumenides, whose front enwreathed with serpent-locks blazons the wrath exhaled
                    from your bosom, come here, here, listen to my complaint, which I, sad wretch,
                    am urged to outpour from my innermost marrow, helpless, burning, and blind with
                    frenzied fury. And since in truth they spring from the very depths of my heart,
                    be unwilling to allow my agony to pass unheeded, but with such mind as Theseus
                    forsook me, with like mind, O goddesses, may he bring evil on himself and on his
                    kin.&rdquo;</p>
				<milestone n="202" unit="line"/>
				<p>After she had poured forth these words from her grief-laden bosom, distractedly
                    clamouring for requital against his heartless deeds, the celestial ruler
                    assented with almighty nod, at whose motion the earth and the shuddering waters
                    quaked, and the world of glittering stars quivered. But Theseus, self-blinded
                    with mental mist, let slip from forgetful breast all those injunctions which
                    until then he had held firmly in mind, nor bore aloft sweet signals to his sad
                    sire, showing himself safe when in sight of Erectheus' haven. For it is said
                    that before, when Aegeus entrusted his son to the winds, on leaving the walls of
                    the chaste goddess's city, he gave these commands to the youth with his parting
                    embrace:</p>
				<p>&ldquo;O my only son, far dearer to me than long life, lately restored to me
                    at extreme end of my years, O son whom I am forced to send off to a doubtful
                    hazard, since my ill fate and your ardent valour snatch you from me unwilling,
                    whose dim eyes are not yet sated with my son's dear form: nor gladly and with
                    joyous breast do I send you, nor will I suffer you to bear signs of helpful
                    fortune, but first from my breast many a complaint will I express, sullying my
                    grey hairs with dust and ashes, and then will I hang dusky sails to the swaying
                    mast, so that our sorrow and burning of mind are shown by rusty-dark Iberian
                    canvas. Yet if the dweller on holy Itone, who deigns to defend our race and
                    Erectheus' dwellings, grant you to besprinkle your right hand in the bull's
                    blood, then see that in very truth these commandments deep-stored in your
                    heart's memory do flourish, nor any time deface them. As soon as your eyes shall
                    see our cliffs, lower their gloomy clothing from every yard, and let the twisted
                    cordage bear aloft snowy sails, where resplendent shall shine bright topmast
                    spars, so that, immediately discerning, I may know with gladness and lightness
                    of heart that in prosperous hour you are returned to my face.&rdquo;</p>
				<p>These charges, at first held in constant mind, from Theseus slipped away as
                    clouds are impelled by the breath of the winds from the ethereal peak of a
                    snow-clad mount. But as his father sought the castle's turrets as watchplace,
                    dimming his anxious eyes with continual weeping, when first he spied the
                    discoloured canvas, flung himself headlong from the top of the crags, believing
                    Theseus lost by harsh fate. Thus as he entered the grief-stricken house, his
                    paternal roof, Theseus savage with slaughter met with like grief as that which
                    with unmemoried mind he had dealt to Minos' daughter: while she gazed with
                    grieving at his disappearing keel, turned over a tumult of cares in her wounded
                    spirit.</p>
				<p>But on another part &lsqb;of the tapestry&rsqb; swift hastened the
                    flushed Iacchus with his train of Satyrs and Nisa-begot Sileni, seeking you,
                    Ariadne, and aflame with love for you.<gap/>These scattered all around, an
                    inspired band, rushed madly with mind all distraught, ranting
                    &ldquo;Euhoe,&rdquo; with tossing of heads &ldquo;Euhoe.&rdquo;
                    Some with womanish hands shook thyrsi with wreath-covered points; some tossed
                    limbs of a rended steer; some girded themselves with writhed snakes; some
                    enacted obscure orgies with deep chests, orgies of which the profane vainly
                    crave a hearing; others beat the tambours with outstretched palms, or from the
                    burnished brass provoked shrill tinklings, blew raucous-sounding blasts from
                    many horns, and the barbarous pipe droned forth horrible song. With luxury of
                    such figures was the coverlet adorned, enwrapping the bed with its mantling
                    embrace.</p>
				<p>After the Thessalian youth were sated with the desire of gazing, they began to
                    give way to the sacred gods. Hence, as with his morning's breath brushing the
                    still sea Zephyrus makes the sloping billows uprise, when Aurora mounts beneath
                    the threshold of the wandering sun, and the waves move forth slowly at first
                    with the breeze's gentle motion (plashing with the sound as of low laughter),
                    but after, as the wind swells, more and more frequent they crowd and gleam in
                    the purple light as they float away,&mdash;so quitting the royal vestibule
                    the folk left, each to his home with steps wandering hither and thither.</p>
				<p>After their departure, Chiron came, chief from the summit of <placeName key="tgn,2096449">Pelion</placeName>, the bearer of sylvan spoil: for
                    whatever the fields bear, what the Thessalian land on its high hills breeds, and
                    what flowers the fecund air of warm Favonius begets near the running streams,
                    these did he bear enwreathed into blended garlands wherewith the house rippled
                    with laughter, caressed by the grateful odor.</p>
				<p>Speedily Penios stands present, for a time leaving his verdant <placeName key="tgn,7014367">Tempe</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7014367">Tempe</placeName> whose overhanging trees encircle, to the <placeName key="tgn,2292724">Dorian</placeName> choirs, damsels Magnesian, to frequent;
                    nor empty-handed,&mdash;for he has borne here lofty beeches uprooted and the
                    tall laurel with straight stem, nor lacks he the nodding plane and the lithe
                    sister of flame-wrapt Phaethon and the aerial cypress. These wreathed in line
                    did he place around the palace so that the vestibule might grow green sheltered
                    with soft fronds.</p>
				<p>After him follows Prometheus of inventive mind, bearing diminishing traces of his
                    ancient punishment, which once he had suffered, with his limbs confined by
                    chains hanging from the rugged Scythian crags. Then came the sire of gods from
                    heaven with his holy consort and offspring, leaving you alone, Phoebus, with
                    your twin-sister the fosterer of the mountains of Idrus: for equally with
                    yourself did your sister disdain Peleus nor was she willing to honour the
                    wedding torches of Thetis. After they had reclined their snow-white forms along
                    the seats, tables were loaded on high with food of various kinds.</p>
				<milestone n="305" unit="line"/>
				<p>In the meantime with shaking bodies and infirm gesture the Parcae began to intone
                    their truth-naming chant. Their trembling frames were enwrapped around with
                    white garments, encircled with a purple border at their heels, snowy fillets
                    bound each aged brow, and their hands pursued their never-ending toil, as of
                    custom. The left hand bore the distaff enwrapped in soft wool, the right hand
                    lightly withdrawing the threads with upturned fingers shaped them, then twisting
                    them with the prone thumb it turned the balanced spindle with well-polished
                    whirl. And then with a pluck of their tooth the work was always made even, and
                    the bitten wool-shreds adhered to their dried lips, which shreds at first had
                    stood out from the fine thread. And in front of their feet wicker baskets of
                    osier twigs took charge of the soft white woolly fleece. These, with
                    clear-sounding voice, as they combed out the wool, out-poured fates of such kind
                    in sacred song, in song which no age yet to come could tax with untruth.</p>
				<p>&ldquo;O with great virtues augmenting your exceeding honour, mainstay of
                        <placeName key="tgn,2316645">Emathia</placeName>, most famous in your issue,
                    receive what the sisters make known to you on this happy day, a truth-naming
                    oracle! But run, you spindles, drawing the thread which the fates follow, run,
                    spindles! &ldquo;Now Hesperus will come to you bearing what is longed for by
                    bridegrooms, with that fortunate star will your bride come, who steeps your soul
                    with the sway of softening love, and prepares with you to conjoin in languorous
                    slumber, spreading her smooth arms beneath your sinewy neck. Run, drawing the
                    thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;No house ever yet enclosed such loves, no love
                    bound lovers with such pact, as abides with Thetis, as is the concord of Peleus.
                    Run, drawing the thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;To you will Achilles be born,
                    a stranger to fear, to his foes known not by his back, but by his strong breast,
                    who, often the victor in the uncertain struggle of the foot-race, will outrun
                    the fire-fleet footsteps of the speedy doe. Run, drawing the thread, run,
                    spindles! &ldquo;None in war with him may compare as a hero, when the
                    Phrygian streams trickle with Trojan blood, and when besieging the walls of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName> with a long, drawn-out warfare
                    perjured Pelops' third heir lays that city waste. Run, drawing the thread, run,
                    spindles! &ldquo;Often will mothers attest over funeral-rites of their sons
                    his glorious acts and illustrious deeds, when the white locks from their heads
                    are unloosed amid ashes, and they bruise their discoloured breasts with feeble
                    fists. Run, drawing the thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;For as the reaper,
                    plucking off the dense wheat-ears before their time, mows the harvest yellowed
                    beneath ardent sun, so will he cast prostrate the corpses of <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>'s sons with grim swords. Run, drawing the
                    thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;His great valour will be attested by
                    Scamander's wave, which ever pours itself into the swift <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>, narrowing its course with
                    slaughtered heaps of corpses he shall make tepid its deep stream by mingling
                    warm blood with the water. Run, drawing the thread, run, spindles!
                    &ldquo;And finally she will be a witness: the captive-maid handed to death,
                    when the heaped-up tomb of earth built in lofty mound receives the snowy limbs
                    of the stricken virgin. Run, drawing the thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;For
                    instantly fortune will give the means to the war-worn Greeks to break <persName><surname>Neptune</surname></persName>'s stone bonds of the Dardanian city,
                    the tall tomb shall be made dank with Polyxena's blood, who as the victim
                    succumbing beneath two-edged sword, with yielding knees shall fall forward a
                    headless corpse. Run, drawing the thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;Come then!
                    Conjoin in the longed-for delights of your love. Let the bridegroom receive his
                    goddess in felicitous compact; let the bride be given to her eager husband. Run,
                    drawing the thread, run, spindles! &ldquo;Neither will the nurse returning
                    with morning light succeed in circling her neck with last night's thread.
                    &lsqb;Run, drawing the thread, run, spindles!&rsqb;, nor need her
                    solicitous mother fear that sad discord will cause a parted bed for her
                    daughter, nor need she cease to hope for dear grandchildren. Run, drawing the
                    thread, run, spindles!&rdquo;</p>
				<p>With such soothsaying songs of yore did the Parcae chant from divine breast the
                    felicitous fate of Peleus. For previously the heaven-dwellers used to visit the
                    chaste homes of heroes and to show themselves in mortal assembly when their
                    worship had not yet been scorned. Often the father of the gods, resting in his
                    glorious temple, when on the festal days his annual rites appeared, gazed on a
                    hundred bulls strewn prone on the earth. Often wandering <placeName key="tgn,2032614">Liber</placeName> on topmost summit of <placeName key="tgn,2113566">Parnassus</placeName> led his howling Thyiads with loosely
                    tossed locks, when the Delphians tumultuously trooping from the whole of their
                    city joyously acclaimed the god with smoking altars. Often in lethal strife of
                    war, Mavors, or swift Triton's queen, or the Rhamnusian virgin, in person did
                    exhort armed bodies of men. But after the earth was infected with heinous crime,
                    and each one banished justice from their grasping mind, and brothers steeped
                    their hands in fraternal blood, the son ceased grieving over departed parents,
                    the sire craved for the funeral rites of his first-born that freely he might
                    take of the flower of unwedded step-mother, the unholy mother, lying under her
                    unknowing son, did not fear to sully her household gods with dishonor:
                    everything licit and lawless commingled with mad infamy turned away from us the
                    just-seeing mind of the gods. Wherefore neither do they deign to appear at such
                    assemblies, nor will they permit themselves to be met in the daylight.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="65">
				<p>Though outspent with care and unceasing grief, I am withdrawn, Ortalus, from the
                    learned Virgins, nor is my soul's mind able to bring forth the sweet fruit of
                    the Muses (so much does it waver amidst ills: for but lately the wave of the
                    Lethean stream washes with its flow the poor, pale foot of my brother, whom the
                    land of <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName> crushes beneath the
                    Rhoetean shore, stolen from our eyes. &lsqb;Never again will I hear you
                    speak,&rsqb; never again, O brother, more lovable than life, will I see you.
                    But surely I will always love you, always will I sing elegies made gloomy by
                    your death, such as the Daulian bird pipes beneath densest shades of foliage,
                    lamenting the lot of slain Itys.&mdash;Yet amidst sorrows so deep, O
                    Ortalus, I send you these verses recast from Battiades, lest by chance you
                    should think that your words have slipped from my mind, entrusted to the
                    wandering winds, as it was with that apple, sent as furtive love-token by the
                    wooer, which leapt out from the virgin's chaste bosom; for the hapless girl
                    forgot she had placed it beneath her soft robe&mdash;when she starts at her
                    mother's approach, out it is shaken: and down it rolls headlong to the ground,
                    while a tell-tale flush bears witness to the girl's distress.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="66">
				<p>He who scanned all the lights of the great firmament, who ascertained the rising
                    and the setting of the stars, how the flaming splendour of the swift sun was
                    darkened, how the planets disappear at certain seasons, how sweet love with
                    stealth detaining Trivia beneath the Latmian crags draws her away from her airy
                    circuit: he that same Conon saw me, a lock of hair from <persName><surname>Berenice</surname></persName>'s head, in the celestial light,
                    gleaming brightly, which she outstretching graceful arms promised to all of the
                    gods, when the king, magnified by his recent marriage, had gone to lay waste the
                    Assyrian borders, bearing the sweet traces of nightly contests, in which he had
                    borne away her virginal spoils. Is <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName> abhorred by new brides? And are the parents' joys turned
                    aside by feigned tears, which they shed copiously within the threshold of the
                    bedchamber? Their groans are untrue, by the gods I swear! This my queen taught
                    me by her many lamentings, when her bridegroom set out for stern warfare. Yet,
                    when deserted, you did not grieve the widowed couch, did you, but the tearful
                    separation from a dear brother? How care consumed your marrow, sad deep within!
                    Such that, your whole bosom being agitated, and your senses being snatched from
                    you, your mind wandered! But in truth I have known you great of heart ever since
                    you were a little maiden. Have you forgotten that noble deed, by which you
                    gained a royal marriage, than which none dared other deeds bolder? Yet what
                    grieving words you spoke when bidding your bridegroom farewell! <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>! how often with sad hand &lsqb;you
                    wiped&rsqb; your eyes! What mighty god changed you? Was it that lovers are
                    unwilling to be long absent from their dear one's body? Then did you promise me
                    to the whole of the gods on your sweet consort's behalf, not without blood of
                    oxen, if he should be granted safe return. In no long time he added captive
                        <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName> to the Egyptian territory. For
                    these reasons I, bestowed amidst the celestial host, by a new gift fulfil your
                    ancient vow. Unwillingly, O queen, did I quit your brow, unwillingly: I swear to
                    you and to your head; if anyone swears lightly, may he bear a suitable penalty:
                    but who may claim himself equal to steel? Even that mountain was swept away, the
                    greatest on earth, over which Thia's illustrious progeny passed, when the Medes
                    created a new sea, and the barbarian youth sailed its fleet through the middle
                    of <placeName key="tgn,7002722">Athos</placeName>. What can locks of hair do,
                    when such things yield to iron? <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>! may the whole race of the Chalybes perish, and whoever
                    first began to seek the veins beneath the earth and invent the hardness of iron!
                    Just before severance my sister locks were mourning my fate, when Ethiop
                    Memnon's brother, the winged steed, beating the air with fluttering wings,
                    appeared before Locrian Arsinoe, and he bearing me up, flies through aethereal
                    shadows and lays me in the chaste bosom of <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName>. Zephyritis herself had dispatched him as her servant, a
                    Greek settler on the Canopian shores. For it was the wish of many gods that the
                    golden crown from Ariadne's temples stay fixed, not alone in heaven's light, but
                    that we also should gleam, the spoils dedicated from your golden-yellow head;
                    when moist with weeping I entered the temples of the gods, the goddess placed
                    me, a new star, among the ancient ones. For touching the Virgin's and the cruel
                    Lion's gleams, hard by Lycaonian Callisto, I turn westwards, a guide before the
                    slow-moving Bootes who barely sinks into the vast ocean. But although the
                    footsteps of the gods press upon me in the night, and the daytime restores me to
                    the white-haired Tethys, (grant me your grace to speak thus, O Rhamnusian
                    virgin, for I will not hide the truth through any fear, even if the stars revile
                    me with ill words, yet I will unfold the pent-up feelings from truthful breast)
                    I am not so much rejoiced at these things as I am tortured by being forever
                    parted, parted from my lady's head, with whom I, in all ointments having not a
                    share, drank many thousands when she was still a virgin.</p>
				<p>Now do you, whom the gladsome light of the wedding torches has joined, yield not
                    your bodies to your desiring husbands nor throw aside your robes and bare your
                    nipples, before your onyx cup brings me delightful gifts, your onyx, you who
                    seek the dues of chaste marriage-bed. But she who gives herself to foul
                    adultery, ah! may the light-lying dust responselessly drink her vile gifts, for
                    I seek no offerings from folk that do ill. But rather, O brides, may concord
                    always be yours, and constant love ever dwell in your homes. But when you, O
                    queen, while gazing at the stars, will propitiate the goddess <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName> with festal torch lights, let not me,
                    your own, be left lacking of unguent, but rather gladden me with large gifts.
                    Why do the stars hold me back? would that I become a royal tress, that Orion
                    might gleam next to Aquarius.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="67">
				<p/>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Catullus</speaker>
					<p>O dear in thought to the sweet husband, dear in thought to his sire, hail!
                        and may Jove augment his good grace to you, Door! which of old, they say,
                        did serve Balbus benignly, while the old man held his home here; and which
                        on the contrary, so it is said, did serve grudgingly after the old man was
                        stretched stark, you doing service to the bride. Come, tell us why you are
                        reported to be changed and to have renounced your ancient faithfulness to
                        your lord?</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Door</speaker>
					<p>No, (so may I please Caecilius to whom I am now made over!) it is not my
                        fault, although it is said so to be, nor may anyone impute any crime to me;
                        albeit the fabling tongues of folk make it so, who, whenever anything is
                        found not well done, all clamor at me: &ldquo;Door, yours is the
                        blame!&rdquo;</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Catullus</speaker>
					<p>It is not enough for you to say this by words merely, but so to act that
                        everyone may feel it and see it.</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Door</speaker>
					<p>In what way can I? No one questions or troubles to know.</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Catullus</speaker>
					<p>We are wishful: be not doubtful to tell us.</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Door</speaker>
					<p>First then, the virgin (so they called her!) who was handed to us was
                        spurious. Her husband was not the first to touch her, he whose little
                        dagger, hanging more limply than the tender beet, never raised itself to the
                        middle of his tunic: but his father is said to have violated his son's bed
                        and to have polluted the unhappy house, either because his lewd mind blazed
                        with blind lust, or because his impotent son was sprung from sterile seed,
                        and therefore one greater of nerve than he was needed, who could unloose the
                        virgin's belt.</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Catullus</speaker>
					<p>You tell of an excellent parent marvellous in piety, who himself urinated in
                        the womb of his son!</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Door</speaker>
					<p>But <placeName key="tgn,7005764">Brixia</placeName> says that she has
                        knowledge of not only this, placed beneath the Cycnean peak, through which
                        the golden-hued Mella flows with its gentle current, <placeName key="tgn,7005764">Brixia</placeName>, beloved mother of my <placeName key="perseus,Verona">Verona</placeName>. For she talks of the loves of
                        Postumius and of Cornelius, with whom that one committed foul adultery.</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Catullus</speaker>
					<p>Someone might say here: &ldquo;How do know you these things, O door? you
                        who are never allowed absence from your lord's threshold, nor may hear
                        folk's gossip, but fixed to this beam are accustomed only to open or to shut
                        the house!&rdquo;</p>
				</sp>
				<sp>
					<speaker>Door</speaker>
					<p>Often have I heard her talking with hushed voice, when alone with her serving
                        girls, about her iniquities, quoting by name those whom we have spoken of,
                        for she did not expect me to be gifted with either tongue or ear. Moreover
                        she added a certain one whose name I'm unwilling to speak, lest he uplift
                        his red eyebrows. He is a lanky fellow, against whom some time ago was
                        brought a grave law-suit over the spurious child-birth of a lying belly.</p>
				</sp>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="68">
				<p>Because you, oppressed by fortune and bitter calamity, sent me this letter
                    written with tears, that I might bear up shipwrecked you tossed by the foaming
                    waves of the sea, and restore you from the threshold of death; you whom neither
                    sacred Venus suffers to repose in soft slumber, desolate on a lonely couch, nor
                    do the Muses divert with the sweet song of ancient poets, while your anxious
                    mind keeps watch:&mdash;I am grateful that you call me your friend, and seek
                    here the gifts of the Muses and of Venus. But so that my troubles may not be
                    unknown to you, Manlius, and so that you not think that I hate the duty of host,
                    hear how I myself am engulfed in the waves of fortune, and do not further seek
                    joyful gifts from a wretched one. In that time when the white toga was first
                    handed to me, and my flowering age was passing its delightful spring, much and
                    enough did I sport: nor was the goddess unknown to us who mixes bitter-sweet
                    with our cares. But my brother's death plunged all this pursuit into mourning. O
                    brother, taken from my unhappy self; you by your dying have broken my ease, O
                    brother; all our house is buried with you; with you have perished the whole of
                    our joys, which your sweet love nourished in your lifetime. With your loss, I
                    have dismissed wholly from mind these studies and every delight of mind. So
                    then, because you write, &ldquo;it is shameful for Catullus to be at
                        <placeName key="tgn,7003262">Verona</placeName>, because here someone of the
                    better sort warms up his frigid limbs on a desolate couch;&ldquo; that,
                    Manlius, is not shameful; rather it is a sorrow. Therefore, forgive me if I do
                    not bestow on you these gifts which grief has snatched from me, because I am
                    unable. For the fact that there is no great store of writings with me arises
                    from this, that we live at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>: there
                    is my home, there is my hall, there my time is passed; here but one of my
                    book-cases follows me. As it is thus, I would not want you to think that we do
                    this from ill-will or with a mind not open enough, because ample store is not
                    forthcoming to either of your desires: of my own accord would I grant both, had
                    I the wherewithal.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="68b">
				<milestone n="41" unit="line"/>
				<p>I cannot conceal, goddesses, in what way Allius has aided me, or with how many
                    good services he has assisted me, lest the flight of time through ages of
                    forgetfulness cover with night's blindness this care of his. But I shall tell it
                    to you, and you in time to come declare it to many yousands, and make this
                    paper, grown old, speak of it<gap/>And let him be more and more noted when dead,
                    nor let the spider aloft, weaving her thin-drawn web, carry on her work over the
                    neglected name of Allius. For you know what anxiety of mind twofold Amathusia
                    gave me, and in what manner she overthrew me, when I was burning like the
                    Trinacrian rocks, or the Malian fount in Oetaean Thermopylae; and my sorrowful
                    eyes did not cease to dissolve with continual weeping, or did my cheeks to be
                    dampened with sad showers. As the transparent stream gushes forth from the
                    moss-grown rock on the airy crest of the mountain, which, when it has rolled
                    headlong prone down the valley, softly wends its way through the midst of the
                    populous parts, sweet solace to the wayfarer sweating with weariness, when the
                    oppressive heat cracks the burnt-up fields agape: or, as to sailors
                    tempest-tossed in black whirlpool, there comes a favourable and a gently-moving
                    breeze, implored by prayer now to Pollux, now to Castor: of such kind was
                    Allius' help to us. He laid open my closed field with a wide path; he gave us a
                    home and he gave it to our mistress, in which we both might exercise our loves
                    in common. There with gracious gait my bright-hued goddess betook herself, and
                    pressed her shining sole on the worn threshold with creaking sandal; as once
                    came Laodamia, flaming with love for her husband, to the home of
                    Protesilaus,&mdash;a home begun in vain&mdash;not yet had a victim
                    appeased the lords of the heavens with sacred blood. May nothing please me
                    overmuch, Rhamnusian virgin, that is undertaken rashly against the will of those
                    lords! How the thirsty altar craves the pious blood Laodamia was taught by the
                    loss of her husband, being compelled to abandon the neck of her new spouse
                    before one winter and another had come, in whose long nights she might sate her
                    eager passion, so she could live despite her broken marriage-yoke. The Parcae
                    decreed that this would not be long distant, if her husband went a soldier to
                    the walls of <placeName key="tgn,7002329">Ilium</placeName>. For then with
                    Helen's rape <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> had begun to summon
                    the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> chiefs to itself; <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> (accursed!) the common grave of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> and of <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, the bitter ashes of heroes and of every noble deed, that
                    also lamentably brought death to our brother. O brother taken from unhappy me! O
                    delightful light taken from an unhappy brother! together with you is buried all
                    our house, together with you have perished all our joys, which your sweet love
                    nurtured during life. Whom now so far away <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, obscene, baleful <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, an alien land, holds in far-distant soil laid not among
                    familiar tombs or near the ashes of his kindred. There, it is said, hastening
                    together from all parts, the Greek youth forsook their hearths and homes, lest
                    <persName><surname>Paris</surname></persName> enjoy his abducted trollop
                    with freedom and leisure in a peaceful bed. Such then was your case, loveliest
                    Laodamia, to be bereft of husband sweeter than life and breath; the tide of love
                    swallowing you in so great a current bore you off into its steep abyss, as the
                    Greeks say Pheneus near Cyllene drains off the soil from the rich swampland.
                    Once the falsely-born son of Amphitryon is heard to have dug this soil, having
                    cut through the marrow of the mountain, at the time when he knocked down the
                    Stymphalian monsters with sure arrows at the command of his inferior lord, so
                    that the gate of heaven might be pressed by a greater number of deities, and
                    Hebe might not remain in long virginity. But deeper than that abyss was your
                    deep love which taught you then, untamed, to bear the yoke. For not as dear to
                    the parent consumed with age is the head of the late-born grandchild an only
                    daughter rears, who, &lsqb;an heir&rsqb; found at last for the ancestral
                    wealth, scarcely having brought his name into the public records, casts off the
                    impious joys of mocking kinsmen and stirs away the vulture from the whitened
                    head; nor so much does any dove rejoice in her snow-white consort, which they
                    say is always plucking kisses with her nibbling beak: more shamelessly than a
                    woman who is especially passionate. But you alone surpassed the great frenzies
                    of these, when you were once united to your yellow-haired husband. Worthy to
                    yield to her in no respect or in little, my light brought herself into my
                    embrace, round whom Cupid, often running here and there, gleamed radiantly in
                    his saffron tunic. Although she is not content with Catullus alone, we will bear
                    the rare intrigues of our coy lady, lest we may be too much a bother, after the
                    manner of fools. Often even Juno, greatest of heaven-dwellers, boiled with
                    flaring wrath at her husband's fault, knowing the many intrigues of passionate
                    Jove. Yet it is not fair to compare men with the gods<gap/>bear up the
                    ungrateful burden of a trembling father. After all she was not handed to me by a
                    father's right hand when she came to my house fragrant with Assyrian perfume,
                    but she gave me her stolen favors in the wondrous night, taken away from the
                    embrace of her own husband. Therefore it is enough if to us alone she gives that
                    day which she marks with a whiter stone.</p>
				<p>This gift to you, Allius, completed in what verse I can, is in return for many
                    services, so that this day and that, and other and other of days may not touch
                    your name with flaking rust. To this the gods will add the many gifts, which
                    Themis once used to bring to the pious of old. May you be happy, both you and
                    your life's-love together, and your home in which we have sported, and its
                    mistress, and he who first gave us earth takes it away, from whom all my good
                    fortunes were first born, and lastly she whose very self is dearer to me than
                    all these,&mdash;my light, who living, living is sweet to me.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="69">
				<p>Don't wonder why no woman, Rufus, wants to place her tender thigh beneath you,
                    not even if you tempt her with the gift of a rare robe or with the delights of a
                    crystal-clear gem. A certain ill tale injures you, that you bear housed in the
                    valley of your armpits a grim goat. This everyone fears. It's no wonder: for it
                    is an exceeding ill beast, with whom no fair girl will sleep. Therefore, either
                    murder that cruel plague of their noses, or cease to marvel, "Why do they
                    fly?"</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="70">
				<p>No one, says my lady, would she rather wed than myself, not even if <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName> himself sought her. Thus she says! but
                    what a woman says to a desirous lover ought fitly to be written on the breezes
                    and in running waters.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="71">
				<p>If ever anyone was deservedly cursed with an atrocious goat-stench from armpits,
                    or if limping gout did justly gnaw one, it is your rival, who occupies himself
                    with your love, and who wondrously has obtained each these ills from you. For as
                    often as he takes his pleasure, he just as often takes vengeance on both;
                    herself he prostrates by his stink, he is slain by his gout.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="72">
				<p>Once you used to say you knew only Catullus, <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName>, that you would not hold Jove before me. I loved you
                    then, not only as a fellow his mistress, but as a father loves his own sons and
                    sons-in-law. Now I do know you: so if I burn at greater cost, you are
                    nevertheless to me far viler and of lighter thought. How can this be? you ask.
                    Because such wrongs drive a lover to love the more, but less to respect.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="73">
				<p>Cease to wish you well deserve anything from anyone, or to think anyone can
                    become pious. All things are unpleasant, it is of no avail to have done deeds of
                    kindness, but rather it wearies me, wearies me and proves the greater ill: so
                    with me, whom no one oppresses more heavily nor more bitterly than he who a
                    little while ago held me his one and only friend.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="74">
				<p>Gellius had heard that his uncle used to scold anyone who spoke of or practised
                    the delights of love. That this should not happen to him, he kneaded deeply his
                    uncle's wife herself, and turned his uncle into a Harpocrates. He did whatever
                    he wanted; for now, even if he boned his uncle, the uncle wouldn't say a
                    word.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="75">
				<p>Now is my mind brought down to this point, my <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName>, by your fault, and has so lost itself by its devotion,
                    that now it cannot wish you well, were you to become most perfect, nor can it
                    cease to love you, whatever you do.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="76">
				<p>If there is any pleasure in a man's recalling the good deeds of the past, when he
                    knows that he is pious and has not violated any sacred trust or abused the
                    divinity of the gods to deceive men in any pact, great store of joys awaits you
                    during your length of years, Catullus, from this thankless love of yours. For
                    whatever people can say or do well for someone, such have been your sayings and
                    your doings, and all your confidences have been squandered on a thankless mind.
                    So then why do you torture yourself further? Why don't you strengthen your
                    resolve and lead yourself out of this and, since the gods are unwilling, stop
                    being miserable? It is difficult suddenly to set aside a love of long standing;
                    it is difficult, this is true, no matter how you do it. This is your one
                    salvation, this you must fight to the finish; you must do it, whether it is
                    possible or impossible. O gods, if it is in you to have pity, or if ever you
                    brought help to men in death's very extremity, look on pitiful me, and if I have
                    lived my life with purity, snatch from me this canker and pest! Ah! like a
                    numbness creeping through my inmost veins it has cast out every happiness from
                    my breast. Now I no longer pray that she may love me in return, or (what is not
                    possible) that she should become chaste: I wish but for health and to cast aside
                    this foul disease. O gods, grant me this in return for my piety.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="77">
				<p><persName><surname>Rufus</surname></persName>, believed by me a friend, in vain
                    and worthlessly, (in vain? yes, and in fact at an ill and grievous price) you
                    have thus stolen upon me, and burning my innards, ah! snatched from wretched me
                    all our good? you have snatched it, alas, you cruel venom of our life! alas, you
                    plague of our friendship. </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="78">
				<p>Gallus has brothers, one of whom has a most charming spouse, the other a charming
                    son. Gallus is a nice man: for he joins together their sweet loves, so that the
                    nice girl beds with the the nice boy. Gallus is a foolish man not to see that he
                    is himself a husband who as an uncle shows how to cuckold an uncle.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="78b">
				<p><gap/>But now I grieve that the pure kisses of a pure girl have mingled with your
                    filthy spit. But in truth you will not come off with impunity; for every age
                    will know you, and Old Lady Fame will tell who you are.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="79">
				<p>Lesbius is handsome: why not so? whom <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName> prefers to you, Catullus, and to your whole family. Yet
                    this handsome one can sell Catullus and his family if he can find three
                    acquaintances he can gain greet with a kiss.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="80">
				<p>What shall I say, Gellius, how those rosy-red lips have become whiter than winter
                    snow, when you leave home in the morning and when the eighth hour stirs you from
                    a gentle nap amid the long day? Something is certain: perhaps Rumor whispers
                    true that you are devouring the well-grown tenseness of a man's middle? So for
                    certain it must be! the ruptured guts of poor little Victor and your lips marked
                    with what was lately-drained cry it aloud.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="81">
				<p>Could no one in this great people, Juventius, be a nice man you could fall in
                    love with except for this guest of yours, paler than a gilded statue, from the
                    dying town of <placeName key="tgn,7003991">Pisaurum</placeName>? He who now has
                    your heart, whom you dare to place before us; and you know not what crime you
                    commit.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="82">
				<p>Quintius, if you want Catullus to owe you his eyes, or another thing dearer than
                    his eyes, if such there is, do not snatch from him what is much dearer to him
                    than his eyes, or what is dearer than his eyes.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="83">
				<p><persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName> in her husband's presence says
                    the utmost ill about me: this gives the fool the greatest pleasure. Mule, you
                    perceive nothing! If she had forgotten about us and were silent, she would be
                    all right: now becasuse she snarls and scolds, not only does she remember, but,
                    what is far more to the point, she is angry. That is, she is enflamed and is
                    speaking.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="84">
				<p>Chommodious Arrius would say, whenever he wanted to say commodious, and for
                    insidious hinsidious, and then hoped that he had spoken with accent wondrous
                    fine, when aspirating hinsidious to the full of his lungs. I believe that his
                    mother, his free uncle, his maternal grandfather and grandmother all spoke thus.
                    When he was sent to <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, everyone's
                    ears were rested, hearing these words spoken smoothly and slightly, nor after
                    that did folk fear such words from him, when suddenly is brought the horrible
                    news that th' Ionian waves, after Arrius had come there, no longer are Ionian,
                    but are now the Hionian Hocean.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="85">
				<p>I hate and I love. Why I do this, perhaps you ask. I know not, but I feel it
                    happening and I am tortured.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="86">
				<p>Quintia is lovely to many; to me she is radiant, tall, and straight. Each of
                    these qualities I grant, but deny the whole of these is loveliness: for there is
                    no charm, not a grain of salt in so great a body. <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName> is lovely, for not only is the whole of her most
                    beautiful, but she has stolen all the Venus-charm from everybody together.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="87">
				<p>No woman can say truly that she has been loved as much as you, <persName><surname>Lesbia</surname></persName>, have been loved by me: no trust in any
                    pact has ever been found so great as was that on my part in the love of you.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="88">
				<p>What is he doing, Gellius, who has an itch with mother and sister and stays up
                    all night with tunics cast aside? What is he doing, who does not allow his uncle
                    to be a husband? Do you know the weight of crime he undertakes? He undertakes, O
                    Gellius, so much as neither furthest Tethys nor Oceanus, father of nymphs, can
                    cleanse: for there is no crime which can go further, not even if with lowered
                    head he swallowed himself.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="89">
				<p>Gellius is thin: why not? He who lives with so good a mother, so healthy and so
                    beauteous a sister, and who has such a good uncle, and a worldfull of girl
                    cousins, why would he cease to be skinny? who if he touched nothing but what is
                    not lawful to touch&mdash;you will find ample reason why he is skinny.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="90">
				<p>Let there be born a Magus from the unspeakable coupling of Gellius and his
                    mother, and let him learn the Persian art of divination. For if <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>'s impious religion is true, a pleasing
                    Magus ought to be begotten from a mother and son, so that, when the chant has
                    been learned, he may worship gods while melting the fat innards in the sacred
                    flame.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="91">
				<p>For no other reason, Gellius, did I hope for your faith to me in this our
                    unhappy, this our desperate love, not because I knew you well or thought you
                    constant or able to restrain your mind from a shameless act), but because I saw
                    this girl whose love kept knawing at me was neither your mother nor your sister.
                    And although I have had many mutual dealings with you, I did not believe this
                    case to be enough cause for you. You considered it enough: so great is your joy
                    in every kind of wrongdoing in which there is some vice.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="92">
				<p>Lesbia forever speaks ill of me nor is ever silent about me: I'll be damned if
                    Lesbia doesn't love me! By what sign? because mine are just the same: I
                    exsecrate her constantly, yet may I be damned if I do not love her in sober
                    truth.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="93">
				<p>I am not over anxious, Caesar, to please you greatly, or to know whether you are
                    a white or a black man.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="94">
				<p>Mentula fornicates. Of course a mentule fornicates! This is what they
                    say&mdash;the pot itself gathers the vegetables.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="95">
				<p>My Cinna's <title>Zmyrna</title> finally, after the ninth harvest it was begun,
                    and after the ninth winter it was published, when Hortensius meanwhile five
                    hundred thousand &lsqb;lines&rsqb; in one &lsqb;year&rsqb;<gap/>
                    <title>Zmyrna</title> will be sent to the curving waves of innermost Satrachus,
                    hoary ages will roll out <title>Zmyrna</title> long hence. But Volusius'
                        <title>Annals</title> will die at <placeName key="tgn,7003085">Padua</placeName> itself, and will often furnish loose wrappings for
                    mackerel. May the short works of my comrade remain in my heart; as for the
                    people, let them rejoice in bloated Antimachus.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="96">
				<p>Calvus, if anything pleasing or welcome from our grief can have an effect on
                    silent graves, then with its longing we renew old loves and weep friendships
                    once lost, surely Quintilia does not mourn her premature death as much as she
                    rejoices in your love.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="97">
				<p>So may the Gods love me, I did not think it made any difference whether I smelled
                    Aemilius' mouth or his arse. In no respect is the latter cleaner, the former
                    filthier; as a matter of fact, his backside is cleaner and better&mdash;for
                    it comes without teeth. His mouth has teeth a foot and a half long, gums truly
                    like an old wagon-box, and besides, he usually has a maw like the split twat of
                    a she-mule pissing in the summer heat. This man has sex with many girls, and
                    makes himself out to be charming, and is not condemned to the mill &lsqb;to
                    drive&rsqb; the mule? Any girl who would touch him we would think could lick
                    the arse of a diseased hangman.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="98">
				<p>What can be said to you, if to anyone, stinking Victius, is said to wind bags and
                    fools. For with that tongue, if the occasion should arise, you could lick arses
                    and farmers' boots. If you want to destroy us altogether, Victius, yawn: you
                    will accomplish what you want altogether.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="99">
				<p>I stole from you, while you were playing, honeyed Juventius, a kiss sweeter than
                    sweet ambrosia. But I bore it off not unpunished; for more than an hour I
                    remember I was nailed to the top of a cross, while I purged myself &lsqb;for
                    my crime&rsqb; to you, nor could any tears in the least remove your cruelty.
                    For as soon as it was done, you washed your lips with many drops, and wiped them
                    off with every finger, lest anything contracted from our mouth remain, as though
                    it were the filthy spittle of a piss-wet whore. Besides, you have handed
                    wretched me over to spiteful Love, nor have you ceased to torture me in every
                    way, so that for me that kiss is now changed from ambrosia to be harsher than
                    harsh hellebore. Since you award such punishment to wretched lover, never more
                    after this will I steal kisses.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="100">
				<p>Caelius and Quintius, the flower of the Veronese youth, madly in love with
                    Aufilenus, madly in love with Aufilena&mdash;the one with the brother; the
                    other with the sister. This is, as one would say, true brotherhood and sweet
                    friendship. To whom shall I incline the more? Caelius, to you; for your single
                    devotion to us was shown by its deeds, when the raging flame scorched my marrow.
                    Be happy, Caelius, be potent in love.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="101">
				<p>Through many nations and through many seas borne, I come, brother, for these sad
                    funeral rites, that I may give the last gifts to the dead, and may vainly speak
                    to your silent ashes, since fortune has taken yourself away from me. Ah, poor
                    brother, undeservedly snatched from me. But now receive these gifts, which have
                    been handed down in the ancient manner of ancestors, the sad gifts to the grave,
                    drenched with a brother's tears, and for ever, brother, hail and farewell.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="102">
				<p>If anything was entrusted in a pledge of silence by a friend whose inmost loyalty
                    of spirit is known, you will find that I am one of those rightfully devoted,
                    Cornelius, and think that I have become a Harpocrates.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="103">
				<p>Come, Silo, either return me my ten thousand sesterces, and then be to your
                    content surly and boorish: or, if you like the money, please stop being a
                    pimp&mdash;and being surly and boorish.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="104">
				<p>Do you believe that I could curse my life, she who is dearer to me than are both
                    my eyes? I could not, nor if I could, would my love be so desperate: but you and
                        <placeName key="tgn,1090192">Tappo</placeName> make a monstrosity out of
                    everything.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="105">
				<p>Mentula tries to climb Mount Pimpla: the Muses with their forks chuck him
                    headlong down.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="106">
				<p>When you see an auctioneer with a comely lad, what do believe other than that he
                    longs to sell himself?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="107">
				<p>If ever something happens that you long for and want and is unhoped for, this is
                    genuinely pleasing to the soul. And thus is it pleasing to us and far dearer
                    than gold, that you have returned, Lesbia, to longing me, you have returned to
                    me, longing and without hope, you brought yourself back to us. O day of whiter
                    note! Who lives more happily than I alone, or who can name things greater to be
                    wished for in this life?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="108">
				<p>If, Cominius, by the judgment of the people your white hair made filthy by
                    unclean practices should perish, to be sure I do not doubt that first your
                    tongue, hostile to goodness, cut out, will be given to the greedy vulture, the
                    crow will gorge your eyes, gouged out, down his black throat, the dogs will
                    gorge down your entrails, the wolves your remaining members.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="109">
				<p>My life, you declare to me that this love of ours will be an everlasting joy
                    between us. Great Gods! grant that she may promise truly, and say this in
                    sincerity and from her soul, and that through all our lives we may be allowed to
                    prolong together this bond of holy friendship.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="110">
				<p>Aufilena, good professional girls are always praised: they receive their pay for
                    what they intend to do. Because you promised me&mdash;which was a
                    lie&mdash;you are unprofessional; because you do not give and often bring
                    &lsqb;home the pay&rsqb;, you do wrong. Either to do it is honest, or
                    not to have promised was chaste, Aufilena: but to steal what was given by
                    deceiving, proves you worse than the greedy whore who prostitutes herself with
                    her whole body.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="111">
				<p>Aufilena, that a bride live content in her husband alone is praise of exceptional
                    praise: but it is preferable to lie beneath any lover you choose, rather than as
                    mother to bring forth brothers &lsqb;cousins&rsqb; out of your
                    uncle.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="112">
				<p>He is a lot of man, <persName><surname>Naso</surname></persName>, and he who
                    descends with you is not a lot of man: <persName><surname>Naso</surname></persName> you are a lot&mdash;and sexually submissive.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="113">
				<p>In the first consulate of Pompey, Cinna, two used to frequent Mucilla: now again
                    made consul, the two remain, but to each one has accrued a thousand. The seed of
                    adultery is fruitful.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="114">
				<p>With his estate not falsely is Mentula of <placeName key="tgn,7004029">Firmum</placeName> said to be rich, which has everything in it of such
                    excellence, game preserves of every kind, fish, meadows, plowland and beasts. In
                    vain: the yield is overcome by the expense. Therefore I grant that he is rich,
                    while everything is lacking. Let us praise the estate, while its owner is a
                    needy man.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="115">
				<p>Mentula has something like thirty acres of meadow land, forty under cultivation:
                    the rest are as the sea. Why can he not surpass Croesus in wealth, he who in one
                    estate possesses so much? Meadow, arable land, immense woods, and open fields
                    and marshes, even to the uttermost north and to the Ocean sea! All things great
                    are here, yet is the owner most great beyond all; not a man, but in truth a
                    mentule mighty, menacing!</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Poem" n="116">
				<p>Often seeking, my mind hunting how I could send to studious you the poems of
                    Battiades, whereby I might soften you towards us, and you might not try to send
                    hostile weapons at my head all the time&mdash;I see now that this effort was
                    undertaken by me in vain, Gellius, and that our prayers to this end were of no
                    avail. Your weapons against us we will ward off with our cloak; but, transfixed
                    with ours, you will pay the punishment.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
