<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Maxime cum principbus philosopho esse diserendum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.115">
      <body>
         <head>That a philosopher ought chiefly to converse with great men.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
               <p>This epistolary discourse was wrote against an ill-bred sort of philosophers who neither would take the charge of education of great persons themselves, nor would suffer others to do it. Tho' the author seems here only to vindicate his friend, it is in truth an apology for himself, who bred up an emperor, and spent most part of his time (to good purpose) in the greatest court in the world. This and several other of his moral discourses seems to be hastily dictated, so that there is no great choice in his words or measure in his periods, or strict method in the whole. However, the treasure of ancient learning and good sense which is to be found in him, as it was frequently made use of by the most eloquent Greek Fathers, so is it sufficient to recommend his works to all lovers of learning and good manners. (K. C.)</p>
				           <p>Much of this version is a mere paraphrase. (G.)</p>
            </note>
         </head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
               <pb id="v.2.p.368"/> THE resolution which you have taken to enter into
				the friendship and familiarity of Sorcanus, that by the
				frequent opportunities of conversing with him you may
				cultivate and improve a soil which gives such early promises of a plentiful harvest, is an undertaking which will
				not only oblige his relations and friends, but redound very
				much to the advantage of the public; and (notwithstanding the peevish censures of some morose or ignorant
				people) it is so far from being an argument of an aspiring
				and vain-glorious temper, that it shows you to be a lover
				of virtue and good manners, and a zealous promoter of
				the common interest of mankind.</p>
            <p>They themselves are rather to be accused of an indirect
					but more vehement sort of ambition, who would not upon
					any terms be found in the company ar so much as be seen
					to give a civil salute to a person of quality. For how unreasonable would it be to enforce a well-disposed young
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.369"/>
					
					gentleman, and one who needs the direction of a wise governor, to such complaints as these: <q direct="unspecified">Would that I might
						change myself from a Pericles or a Cato to a cobbler like
						Simon or a grammarian like Dionysius, that I might like
						them have the conversation of such a man as Socrates,
						enjoy his company, and hear his instructive lessons of
						morality.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So far, I am sure, was Aristo of Chios from being of
					their humor, that when he was censured for exposing and
					prostituting the dignity of philosophy by his freedom to
					all comers, he answered, that he could wish that Nature
					had given understanding to wild beasts, that they too
					might be capable of being his hearers. Shall we then
					deny that privilege to men of interest and power, which
					this good man would have communicated (if it had been
					possible) to the brute beasts? But these men have taken
					a false notion of philosophy, they make it much like the
					art of statuary, whose business it is to carve out a lifeless
					image in the most exact figure and proportions, and then
					to raise it upon its pedestal, where it is to continue for
					ever. The true philosophy is of a quite different nature;
					it is a spring and principle of motion wherever it comes;
					it makes men active and industrious, it sets every wheel
					and faculty a going, it stores our minds with axioms and
					rules by which to make a sound judgment, it determines
					the will to the choice of what is honorable and just; and
					it wings all our faculties to the swiftest prosecution of it.
					It is accompanied with an elevation and nobleness of mind,
					joined with a coolness and sweetness of behavior, and
					backed with a becoming assurance and inflexible resolution. And from this diffusiveness of the nature of good
					it follows, that the best and most accomplished men are
					inclined to converse with persons of the highest condition. Indeed a physician, if he have any good nature
					and sense of honor, would be more ready to cure an eye
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.370"/>
					
					which is to see and watch for a great many thousands,
					than that of a private person; how much more then
					ought a philosopher to form and fashion, to rectify and
					cure the soul of such a one, who is (if I may so express
					it) to inform the body politic,&mdash;who is to think and understand for so many others, to be in so great measure
					the rule of reason, the standard of law, and model of behavior, by which all the rest will square and direct their
					actions? Suppose a man to have a talent at finding out
					springs and contriving of aqueducts (a piece of skill for
					which Hercules and other of the ancients are much celebrated in history), surely he could not so satisfactorily
					employ himself in sinking a well or deriving water to
					some private seat or contemptible cottage, as in supplying
					conduits to some fair and populous city, in relieving an army
					just perishing with thirst, or in refreshing and adorning
					with fountains and cool streams the beautiful gardens of
					some glorious monarch. There is a passage of Homer
					very pertinent to this purpose, in which he calls Minos
					<foreign lang="greek">*dio\s mega/lou o)aristh/n</foreign>, which, as Plato interprets it, signifies
					<hi rend="italics">the disciple and companion of Jupiter.</hi> For it were beneath his dignity indeed to teach private men, such as
					care only for a family or indulge their useless speculations; but kings are scholars worthy the tuition of a God,
					who, when they are well advised, just, good. and magnanimous, never fail to procure the peace and prosperity of
					all their subjects. The naturalists tell us that the eryngium hath such a property with it, that if one of the
					flock do but taste it, all the rest will stand stock still in
					the same place till the shepherd hath taken it out of its
					mouth. Such quickness of action does it have, pervading and spreading itself over every thing that is near it,
					as if it were fire. The effects of philosophy, however.
					are different according to the difference of inclinations in
					men. If indeed it lights on one who loves a dull and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.371"/>
					
					inactive sort of life, that makes himself the centre and
					the little conveniences of life the circumference of all his
					thoughts, such a one does contract the sphere of her activity, so that having only made easy and comfortable the
					life of a single person, it fails and dies with him; but
					when it finds a man of a ruling genius, one fitted for conversation and able to grapple with the difficulties of public business, if it once possess him with principles of
					honesty, honor, and religion, it takes a compendious
					method, by doing good to one, to oblige a great part
					of mankind. Such was the effect of the conversation
					of Anaxagoras with Pericles, of Plato with Dion, and
					of Pythagoras with the principal statesmen of all Italy.
					Cato himself took a voyage, when he had the concern
					of an expedition lying upon him, to see and hear Athenodorus; and Scipio sent for Panaetius, when he was
					commissioned by the senate <q direct="unspecified">to take a survey alike of
						the outrages and the good order which were practised in
						their provinces,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XVII. 487</note> as Posidonius observes. Now what a
					pretty sort of return would it have been in Panaetius to
					send word back,&mdash;<q direct="unspecified">If indeed you were in a private capacity, John a Nokes or John a Stiles, that had a mind
						to get into some obscure corner or cell, to state cases and
						resolve syllogisms, I should very gladly have accepted
						your invitation; but now, because you are the son of
						Paulus Aemilius who was twice consul, and grandson of
						that Scipio who was surnamed from his conquest of Hannibal and Africa, I cannot with honor hold any conversation with you!</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>The objections which they bring from the two kinds
				of discourse, one of which is mental, the other expressed
				in words or interpretative of the former, are so stale and
				pedantical, that they are best answered by laughter or
				silence; and we merely quote the old saying, <q direct="unspecified">I knew
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.372"/>
					
					this before Theognis was born.</q> However, thus much
				shall be said, that the end of them both is friendship,&mdash;in the first case with ourselves, in the second case with
				another. For he that hath attained to virtue by the
				methods of philosophy hath his mind all in tune and
				good temper; he is not struck with those reproaches of
				conscience, which cause the acutest sense of pain and are
				the natural punishments of our follies; but he enjoys (the
				great prerogative of a good man) to be always easy and
				in amity with himself.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No factious lusts reason's just power control,
				</l>
                     <l>Nor kindle civil discord in his soul.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>His passion does not stand in defiance to his reason, nor
					do his reasonings cross and thwart one the other, but
					he is always consistent with himself. But the very joys
					of wicked men are tumultuary and confused, like those
					who dwell in the borders of two great empires at variance, always insecure, and in perpetual alarms; whilst a
					good man enjoys an uninterrupted peace and serenity of
					mind, which excels the other not only in duration, but in
					sense of pleasure too. As for the other sort of discourse,
					that which consists in expression of itself to others, Pindar says very well, that it was not mercenary in old time,
					nor indeed is it so now; but by the baseness and ambition of a few it is made use of to serve their poor secular
					interests. For if the poets represent Venus herself as
					much offended with those who make a trade and traffic
					of the passion of love, how much more reasonably may
					we suppose that Urania and Clio and Calliope have an
					indignation against those who set learning and philosophy
					to sale? Certainly the gifts and endowments of the Muses
					ought to be privileged from such mean considerations.</p>
            <p>If indeed some have made fame and reputation one of
					the ends of their studies, they used it only as an instrument
					to get friends; since we find by common observation that
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.373"/>
					
					men praise only those whom they love. If they sought its
					own praise, they were as much mistaken as Ixion when he
					embraced a cloud instead of Juno; for there is nothing so
					fleeting, so changeable, and so inconstant as popular applause; it is but a pompous shadow, and hath no manner
					of solidity and duration in it. But a wise man, if he design to engage in business and matters of state, will so far
					aim at fame and popularity as that he may be better enabled to benefit others; for it is a difficult and very unpleasant task to do good to those who are disaffected to our
					persons. It is the good opinion men have of us which
					disposes men to give credit to our doctrine. As light is a
					greater good to those who see others by it than to those
					who only are seen, so is honor of a greater benefit to those
					who behold it than to those whose glory is beheld. But
					even one who withdraws himself from the noise of the
					world, who loves privacy and indulges his own thoughts,
					will show that respect to the good word of the people which
					Hippolytus did to Venus,&mdash;though he abstain from her
					mysteries, he will pay his devotions at a distance;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 102</note> but he
					will not be so cynical and sullen as not to hear with gladness the commendations of virtuous men like himself; he
					will neither engage himself in a restless pursuit of wealth,
					interest, or honor, nor will he on the other hand be so rustic
					and insensible as to refuse them in a moderate degree,
					when they fairly come in his way; in like manner he will
					not court and follow handsome and beautiful youth, but
					will rather choose such as are of a teachable disposition,
					of a gentle behavior, and lovers of learning. The charms
					and graces of youth will not make a philosopher shy of
					their conversation, when the endowments of their minds
					are answerable to the features of their bodies. The case
					is the same when greatness of place and fortune concur
					with a well-disposed mind in the same person; he will not
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.374"/>
					
					therefore forbear loving and respecting such a one, nor be
					afraid of the name of a courtier, nor think it a curse that
					such attendance and dependence should be his fate.
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>They that strive most Dame Venus to eschew
					</l>
                     <l>Do fault as much as they who her pursue.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Veiled Hippolytus of Euripides, Frag. 431.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The application is easy to the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>A philosopher therefore, if he is of a retired humor, will
					not shun such persons; while one who generously designs
					his studies for the public advantage will cheerfully embrace
					their advances of friendship, will not force them after a
					troublesome manner to hear him, will lay aside his scholastical terms and distinctions, and will rejoice to discourse and
					pass his time with them when they are willing and disposed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I plough the spacious Berecynthian fields,
			</l>
                     <l>Full six days' journey wide,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Niobe of Aeschylus, Frag. 153.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>says one boastingly in the poet; the same man, if he were
					as much a lover of mankind as of husbandry, would much
					rather bestow his pains on such a farm, the fruits of which
					would serve a great number, than to be always dressing
					the olive-yard of some cynical malecontent, which, when
					all was done, would scarce yield oil enough to dress a salad
					or to supply his lamp in the long winter evenings. Epicurus himself, who places happiness in the profoundest quiet
					and sluggish inactivity, as the only secure harbor from the
					storms of this troublesome world, could not but confess
					that it is both more noble and delightful to do than to receive a kindness;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Almost the same words with those of our Saviour, It is more blessed to give than to receive. So that a man can scarcely be a true Epicurean without practising some of the maxims of Christianity.</note> for there is nothing which produces so
					humane and genuine a sort of pleasure as that of doing
					good. He who first gave the names to the three Graces well
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.375"/>
					
					understood this, for they all signify delectation and joy,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aglaia, Euphrosyne, and Thalia</note>
					and these surely are far greater and purer in him who does
					the good turn. This is so evidently true, that we all receive good turns blushing and with some confusion, but
					we are always gay and well pleased when we are conferring
					one.</p>
            <p>If then it is so pleasant to do good to a few, how are
					their hearts dilated with joy who are benefactors to whole
					cities, provinces, and kingdoms? And such benefactors
					are they who instil good principles into those upon whom
					so many millions do depend. On the other hand, those
					who debauch the minds of great men&mdash;as sycophants,
					false informers, and flatterers, worse than both, manifestly
					do&mdash;are the centre of all the curses of a nation, as men
					who do not only infuse deadly poison into the cistern of a
					private house, but into the public springs of which so many
					thousands are to drink. The people therefore laughed at
					the hangers-on of Callias, whom, as Eupolis says, neither
					fire nor brass nor steel could keep from supping with him;
					but as for the favorites of those execrable tyrants Apollodorus, Phalaris, and Dionysius, they racked them, they
					flayed them alive, they roasted them at slow fires, they
					looked on them as the very pests of society and disgraces
					of human nature; for to debauch a simple person is indeed
					an ill thing, but to corrupt a prince is an infinite mischief.
					In like manner, he who instructs an ordinary man makes him
					to pass his life decently and with comfort; but he who
					instructs a prince, by correcting his errors and clearing his
					understanding, is a philosopher for the public, by rectifying the very mould and model by which whole nations are
					formed and regulated. It is the custom of all nations to
					pay a peculiar honor and deference to their priests; and
					the reason of it is, because they do not only pray for good
					things for themselves, their own families and friends, but
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.376"/>
					
					for whole communities, for the whole state of mankind.
					Yet we are not so fond as to think that the priests cause
					the Gods to be givers of good things, or inspire a vein of
					beneficence into them; but they only make their supplications to a being which of itself is inclinable to answer
					their requests. But in this a good tutor hath the privilege
					above the priests,&mdash;he effectually renders a prince more
					disposed to actions of justice, moderation, and mercy, and
					therefore hath a greater satisfaction of mind when he reflects upon it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>For my own part, I cannot but think that an ordinary
				mechanic&mdash;for instance, a maker of musical instruments
				&mdash;would be much more attentive and pleased at his work,
				if he knew that his harp would be touched by the famous
				Amphion, and in his hand serve for the builder of Thebes,
				or if that Thales had bespoke it, who was so great a master
				that by the force of his music he pacified a popular tumult
				amongst the Lacedaemonians. A good-natured shipwright
				would ply his work more heartily, if he were making the
				steerage for the admiral galley of Themistocles when he
				fought for the liberty of Greece, or of Pompey when he
				went on his expedition against the pirates: what ecstasy
				of delight then must a philosopher be in, when he reflects
				that his scholar is a man of authority, a prince or great
				potentate, that he is employed in so public a work, giving
				laws to him who is to give laws to a whole nation, who is
				to punish vice, and to reward the virtuous with riches and
				honor? The builder of the Argo certainly would have
				been mightily pleased, if he had known what noble mariners were to row in his ship, and that at last she should be
				translated into heaven; and a carpenter would not be half
				so much pleased to make a coach or plough, as to make
				the tablets on which Solon's laws were to be engraved. In
				like manner the discourses and rules of philosophy, being
				once deeply stamped and imprinted on the minds of great
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.377"/>
				
				personages, will stick so close, that the prince shall seem
				no other than justice incarnate and animated law. This
				was the design of Plato's voyage into Sicily,&mdash;he hoped
				that the lectures of his philosophy would serve for laws to
				Dionysius, and bring his affairs again into a good posture.
				But the soul of that unfortunate prince was like paper
				scribbled all over with the characters of vice; its piercing
				and corroding quality had stained quite through, and sunk
				into the very substance of his soul. Whereas, if such
				persons are to profit by sage lessons, they must be taken
				when they are at full speed.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>