<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De esu carnium II</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.132">
      <body>
         <head>Of eating of flesh: Tract II.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Reason persuades us now to return with fresh cogitations and dispositions to what we left cold yesterday of
				our discourse about flesh-eating. It is indeed a hard and
				a difficult task to undertake (as Cato once said) to dispute
				with men's bellies, that have no ears; since most have
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.11"/>
				
				already drunk that draught of custom, which is like that
				of Circe,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of groans and frauds and sorcery replete.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. X. 234.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And it is no easy task to pull out the hook of flesh-eating from the jaws of such as lave gorged themselves
					with luxury and are (as it were) nailed down with it. It
					would indeed be a good action, if as the Egyptians draw
					out the stomach of a dead body, and cut it open and
					expose it to the sun, as the only cause of all its evil
					actions, so we could, by cutting out our gluttony and
					blood-shedding, purify and cleanse the remainder of our
					lives. For the stomach itself is not guilty of bloodshed,
					but is involuntarily polluted by our intemperance. But if
					this may not be, and we are ashamed by reason of custom
					to live unblamably, let us at least sin with discretion. Let
					us eat flesh; but let it be for hunger and not for wantonness. Let us kill an animal; but let us do it with sorrow
					and pity, and not abusing and tormenting it, as many nowadays are used to do, while some run red-hot spits through
					the bodies of swine, that by the tincture of the quenched iron
					the blood may be to that degree mortified, that it may
					sweeten and soften the flesh in its circulation; others
					jump and stamp upon the udders of sows that are ready
					to pig, that so they may trample into one mass, (O Piacular
					Jupiter!) in the very pangs of delivery, blood, milk, and
					the corruption of the crushed and mangled young ones,
					and so eat the most inflamed part of the animal; others
					sew up the eyes of cranes and swans, and so shut them up
					in darkness to be fattened, and then souse up their flesh
					with certain monstrous mixtures and pickles.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>By all which it is most manifest, that it is not for
				nourishment, or want, or any necessity, but for mere gluttony, wantonness, and expensiveness, that they make a
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.12"/>
				
				pleasure of villany. Just as it happens in persons who
				cannot satiate their intemperance upon women, and having
				made trial of every thing else and falling into vagaries, at
				last attempt things not to be mentioned; even so inordinateness in feeding, when it hath once passed the bounds
				of nature and necessity, studies at last to diversify the lusts
				of its intemperate appetite by cruelty and villany. For
				the senses, when they once quit their natural measures,
				sympathize with each other in their distempers, and are
				enticed by each other to the same consent and intemperance. Thus a distempered ear first debauched music, the
				soft and effeminate notes of which provoke immodest
				touches and lascivious tickling. These things first taught
				the eye not to delight in Pyrrhic dances, gesticulations of
				hands, or elegant pantomimes, nor in statues and fine
				paintings; but to reckon the slaughtering and death of
				mankind and wounds and duels the most sumptuous of
				shows and spectacles. Thus unlawful tables are accompanied with intemperate copulations, with unmusician-like
				balls, and theatres become monstrous through shameful
				songs and rehearsals; and barbarous and brutish shows
				are again accompanied with an unrelenting temper and
				savage cruelty towards mankind. Hence it was that the
				divine Lycurgus in his Three Books of Laws gave orders
				that the doors and ridges of men's houses should be made
				with a saw and an axe, and that no other instrument should
				so much as be brought to any house. Not that he did
				hereby intend to declare war against augers and planes
				and other instruments of finer work; but because he very
				well knew that with such tools as these you will never
				bring into your house a gilded couch, and that you will
				never attempt to bring into a slender cottage either silver
				tables, purple carpets, or costly stones; but that a plain
				supper and a homely dinner must accompany such a house,
				couch, table, and cup. The beginning of a vicious diet is
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.13"/>
				
				presently followed by all sorts of luxury and expensiveness,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ev'n as a mare is by her thirsty colt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>And what meal is not expensive? That for which no
				animal is put to death. Shall we reckon a soul to be a
				small expense. I will not say perhaps of a mother, or a
				father, or of some friend, or child, as Empedocles did; but
				one participating of feeling, of seeing, of hearing, of imagination, and of intellection; which each animal hath received from Nature for the acquiring of what is agreeable
				to it, and the avoiding what is disagreeable. Do but consider this with yourself now, which sort of philosophers
				render us most tame and civil, they who bid people to feed
				on their children, friends, fathers, and wives, when they are
				dead; or Pythagoras and Empedocles, that accustom men
				to be just towards even the other members of the creation.
				You laugh at a man that will not eat a sheep: but we
				(they will say again)&mdash;when we see you cutting off the
				parts of your dead father or mother, and sending it to your
				absent friends, and calling upon and inviting your present
				friends to eat the rest freely and heartily&mdash;shall we not
				smile? Nay, peradventure we offend at this instant time
				while we touch these books, without having first cleansed
				our hands, eyes, feet, and ears; if it be not (by Jupiter) a
				sufficient purgation of them to have discoursed of these
				matters in potable and fresh language (as Plato speaketh),
				thereby washing off the brackishness of hearing. Now if
				a man should set these books and discourses in opposition
				to each other, he will find that the philosophy of the one
				sort suits with the Scythians, Sogdians, and Melanchlaenians, of whom Herodotus's relation is scarce believed;
				but the sentiments of Pythagoras and Empedocles were the
				laws and customs of the ancient Grecians.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Who then were the first authors of this opinion, that
				we owe no justice to dumb animals?
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.14"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who first beat out accursed steel,
					</l>
                     <l>And made the laboring ox a knife to feel.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In the very same manner oppressors and tyrants begin first
					to shed blood. For example, the first man that the Athenians ever put to death was one of the basest of all knaves,
					whom all thought deserving of death; after him they put
					to death a second and a third. After this, being now accustomed to blood, they patiently saw Niceratus the son of
					Nicias, and their own general Theramenes, and Polemarchus the philosopher suffer death. Even so, in the beginning, some wild and mischievous beast was killed and eaten,
					and then some little bird or fish was entrapped. And the
					love of slaughter, being first experimented and exercised
					in these, at last passed even to the laboring ox, and the
					sheep that clothes us, and to the poor cock that keeps
					the house; until by little and little, unsatiableness being
					strengthened by use, men came to the slaughter of men,
					to bloodshed and wars. Now even if one cannot demonstrate and make out, that souls in their regenerations make
					a promiscuous use of all bodies, and that that which is now
					rational will at another time be irrational, and that again
					tame which is now wild,&mdash;for that Nature changes and
					transmutes every thing,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With different fleshy coats new clothing all,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>this thing should be sufficient to change and reclaim men,
					that it is a savage and intemperate habit, that it brings sickness and heaviness upon the body, and that it inclines the
					mind the more brutishly to bloodshed and destruction, when
					we have once accustomed ourselves neither to entertain a
					guest nor keep a wedding nor to treat our friends without
					blood and slaughter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>And if what is argued about the return of souls into
				bodies is not of force enough to beget faith, yet methinks
				the very uncertainty of the thing should fill us with apprehension and fear. Suppose, for instance, one should in
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.15"/>
				
				some night engagement run on with his drawn sword upon
				one that had fallen down and covered his body with his
				arms, and should in the mean time hear one say, that he
				was not very sure, but that he fancied and believed, that
				the party lying there was his own son, brother, father, or
				tent-companion; which were more advisable, think you,&mdash;
				to hearken to a false suggestion, and so to let go an enemy
				under the notion of a friend, or to slight an authority not
				sufficient to beget faith, and to slay a friend instead of a
				foe? This you will all say would be insupportable. Do
				but consider the famous Merope in the tragedy, who taking
				up a hatchet, and lifting it at her son's head, whom she
				took for her son's murderer, speaks thus as she was ready
				to give the fatal blow,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Villain, this pious blow shall cleave thy head;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Cresphontes, Frag. 457.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>what a bustle she raises in the whole theatre while she
					raises herself to give the blow, and what a fear they are
					all in, lest she should prevent the old man that comes to
					stop her hand, and should wound the youth. Now if another old man should stand by her and say, <q direct="unspecified">Strike, it is
						thy enemy,</q> and this, <q direct="unspecified">Hold, it is thy son;</q> which, think
					you, would be the greater injustice, to omit the punishing
					of an enemy for the sake of one's child, or to suffer one's
					self to be so transported with anger at an enemy as to kill
					one's child? Since then neither hatred nor wrath nor any
					revenge nor fear for ourselves carries us to the slaughter
					of a beast, but the poor sacrifice stands with an inclined
					neck, only to satisfy thy lust and pleasure, and then one
					philosopher stands by and tells thee, <q direct="unspecified">Cut him down, it is
						but an unreasonable animal,</q> and another cries, <q direct="unspecified">Hold,
							what if there should be the soul of some kinsman or God
							inclosed in him</q>&mdash;good Gods! is there the like danger
					if I refuse to eat flesh, as if I for want of faith murder my
					child or some other friend?</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.16"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>The Stoics' way of reasoning upon this subject of flesh-eating is no way equal nor consonant with themselves.
				Who is this that hath so many mouths for his belly and the
				kitchen? Whence comes it to pass, that they so very
				much womanize and reproach pleasure, as a thing that they
				will not allow to be either good or preferable, or so much
				as agreeable, and yet all on a sudden become so zealous
				advocates for pleasures? It were indeed but a reasonable
				consequence of their doctrine, that, since they banish perfumes and cakes from their banquets, they should be much
				more averse to blood and to flesh. But now, just as if they
				would reduce their philosophy to their day-books, they
				lessen the expenses of their suppers in certain unnecessary
				and needless matters, but the untamed and murderous part
				of their expense they nothing boggle at. <q direct="unspecified">Well! What
					then?</q> say they. <q direct="unspecified">We have nothing to do with brute
						beasts.</q> Nor have you any with perfumes, nor with foreign sauces, may some one answer; therefore expel these
				from your banquets, if you are driving out every thing
				that is both useless and needless.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Let us therefore in the next place consider, whether
				we owe any justice to the brute beasts. Neither shall we
				handle this point artificially, or like subtle sophisters, but
				by casting our eye into our own breasts, and conversing with
				ourselves as men, we will weigh and examine the whole
				matter. . .</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>