<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De liberis educandis</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1927</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v1.p.3"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>THE EDUCATION OF CHILDREN (DE LIBERIS EDUCANDIS) <lb/>Introduction</head>
            <p>It is generally believed that the essay which stands first in the collected
					works of Plutarch cannot have been written by him. The arguments against the
					genuineness of the essay, based both on external and internal evidence, are
					too long to be repeated here, but they may be found in Wyttenbach's edition
					vol. vi. pp. 29-64.</p>
            <p>The essay, however, is interesting in itself, since it reflects in many ways
					the educational conditions of its time. Frankly recognizing the difference
					in natural endowments, the author insists on the great benefits which
					inevitably come from training. Physical training is of course required, and
					military training is held to be most important for preparing men to win in
					battle. A knowledge of philosophy is the final goal of education.</p>
            <p>The invectives against the indifference of parents about the education of
					their children, and their unwillingness to pay adequate salaries so as to
					secure men of character as teachers, may have the same familiar ring two
					thousand years hence.</p>
            <p>Finally, a word is added on the excesses of young men, and a warning against
					flatterers,—suggested perhaps by Plutarch's essay devoted to that
					subject.</p>
            <pb id="v1.p.5"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Let us consider what may be said of the education of free-born children, and
					what advantages they should enjoy to give them a sound character when they
					grow up. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>It is perhaps better to begin with their parentage first ; and I should
					advise those desirous of becoming fathers of notable offspring to abstain
					from random cohabitation with women; I mean with such women as courtesans
					and concubines. For those who are not well-born, whether on the father's or
					the mother's side, have an indelible disgrace in their low birth, which
					accompanies them throughout their lives, and offers to anyone desiring to
					use it a ready subject of reproach and insult. Wise was the poet who
					declares: <quote rend="blockquote">The home's foundation being wrongly laid,
						The offspring needs must be unfortunate.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hercules Furens</hi>, 1261.</note>
               </quote> A
					goodly treasure, then, is honourable birth, and such a man may speak his
					mind freely, a thing which should be held of the highest account by those
					who wish to have issue lawfully begotten. In the nature of things, the
					spirits of those whose blood is base or counterfeit are constantly being
					brought down and humbled, and quite rightly does the poet declare: <pb id="v1.p.7"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">A man, though bold, is made a slave whene'er He
						learns his mother's or his sire's disgrace.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus</hi>, 424.</note>
               </quote> Children of
					distinguished parents are, of course, correspondingly full of exultation and
					pride. At all events, they say that Cleophantus, the son of Themistocles,
					often declared to many persons, that whatever he desired was always agreed
					to by the Athenian people; for whatever he wished his mother also wished;
					whatever his mother wished Themistocles also wished; and whatever
					Themistocles wished all the Athenians wished. It is very proper also to
					bestow a word of praise on the Spartans for the noble spirit they showed in
					fining their king, Archidamus, because he had permitted himself to take to
					wife a woman short of stature, the reason they gave being that he proposed
					to supply them not with kings but with kinglets. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>In this connexion we should speak of a matter which has not been overlooked
					by our predecessors. What is this? It is that husbands who approach their
					wives for the sake of issue should do so only when they have either not
					taken any wine at all, or at any rate, a very moderate portion. For children
					whose fathers have chanced to beget them in drunkenness are wont to be fond
					of wine, and to be given to excessive drinking. Wherefore Diogenes,
					observing an emotional and crack-brained youth, said, <q direct="unspecified">Young man, your
						father must have been drunk when he begot you !</q> So much for my
					views on the subject of birth. We must now speak of education. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>As a general statement, the same assertion may be made in regard to moral
					excellence that we <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Hippolytus, 424.</note>
					          <pb id="v1.p.9"/> are in the habit of making in regard to the arts and
					sciences, namely, that there must be a concurrence of three things in order
					to produce perfectly right action, and these are: nature, reason, and habit.
					By reason I mean the act of learning, and by habit constant practice. The
					first beginnings come from nature, advancement from learning, the practical
					use from continued repetition, and the culmination from all combined; but so
					far as any one of these is wanting, the moral excellence must, to this
					extent, be crippled. For nature without learning is a blind thing, and
					learning without nature is an imperfect thing, and practice without both is
					an ineffective thing. Just as in farming, first of all the soil must be
					good, secondly, the husbandman skilful, and thirdly, the seed sound, so,
					after the same manner, nature is like to the soil, the teacher to the
					farmer, and the verbal counsels and precepts like to the seed. I should
					strenuously insist that all three qualities met together and formed a
					perfect union in the souls of those men who are celebrated among all
					mankind,—Pythagoras, Socrates, Plato, and all who have attained an
					ever-living fame. </p>
            <p> Now it is a fortunate thing and a token of divine love if ever a heavenly
					power has bestowed all these qualities on any one man ; but if anybody
					imagines that those not endowed with natural gifts, who yet have the chance
					to learn and to apply themselves in the right way to the attaining of
					virtue, cannot repair the want of their nature and advance so far as in them
					lies, let him know that he is in great, or rather total, error. For
					indifference ruins a good natural endowment, but instruction amends a poor
					one; easy things escape the careless, but difficult <pb id="v1.p.11"/>
					things are conquered by careful application. One may understand how
					effective and how productive a thing is application and hard work, if he
					only direct his attention to many effects that are daily observed. For drops
					of water make hollows in rocks, steel and bronze are worn away by the touch
					of hands, and rims of chariot-wheels once bent by dint of labour, cannot, no
					matter what be done, recover their original lines. The bent staves which
					actors use it is impossible to straighten; indeed the unnatural shape has,
					through labour, come to predominate over the natural. And are these the only
					things which clearly show the potency of diligence? No, but myriads upon
					myriads. A piece of land is good by nature, but without care it grows waste,
					and the better it is by nature, so much the more is it spoiled by neglect if
					it be not worked. Another piece is forbidding and rougher than land should
					be, but, if it be tilled, straightway it produces noble crops. What trees if
					they are neglected do not grow crooked and prove unfruitful? Yet if they
					receive right culture, they become fruitful, and bring their fruit to
					maturity. What bodily strength is not impaired and finally ruined by neglect
					and luxury and ill condition? On the other hand, what weak physique does not
					show a very great improvement in strength if men exercise and train
					themselves? What horses if they are well broken when young do not become
					obedient to their riders, whereas if they are left unbroken they turn out
					stubborn and restive? Why wonder at other instances, seeing as we do that
					many of the wildest animals are made tame and used to their labours? <pb id="v1.p.13"/> Well did the Thessalian say, when asked who were the most
					pacific of the Thessalians, <q direct="unspecified">Those who are just returning from
						war.</q> But why discuss the matter at length ? For character is
					habit long continued, and if one were to call the virtues of character the
					virtues of habit, he would not seem to go far astray. I will cite but one
					more example on this point and then I shall desist from discussing it
					further. Lycurgus, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 225 F.</note> the lawgiver of the Spartans, took two
					puppies of the same litter, and reared them in quite different ways, so that
					from the one he produced a mischievous and greedy cur, and from the other a
					dog able to follow a scent and to hunt. And then at a time when the Spartans
					were gathered together, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Men of Sparta, of a truth habit and
						training and teaching and guidance in living are a great influence
						toward engendering excellence, and I will make this evident to you at
						once.</q> Thereupon producing the two dogs, he let them loose,
					putting down directly in front of them a dish of food and a hare. The one
					dog rushed after the hare, and the other made for the dish. While the
					Spartans were as yet unable to make out what import he gave to this, and
					with what intent he was exhibiting the dogs, he said, <q direct="unspecified">These dogs are
						both of the same litter, but they have received a different bringing-up,
						with the result that the one has turned out a glutton and the other a
						hunter.</q> In regard to habits and manner of life let this suffice.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Next in order comes the subject of feeding. Mothers ought, I should say,
					themselves to feed their infants and nurse them themselves. For they will
					feed them with a livelier affection and greater <pb id="v1.p.15"/> care, as
					loving them inwardly, and, according to the proverb, to their finger-tips.
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">So Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Ad fam.</hi>, i. 6 <q direct="unspecified">a teneris
						unguiculis</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> J. C. Rolfe in <hi rend="italics">Proceedings of Amer. Phil. Assoc.</hi>, July 1903, p.
						55.</note> But the goodwill of foster-mothers and nursemaids is
					insincere and forced, since they love for pay. Nature too makes clear the
					fact that mothers should themselves nurse and feed what they have brought
					into the world, since it is for this purpose that she has provided for every
					animal which gives birth to young a source of food in its milk. Wise also is
					her forethought; for she has fashioned women's breasts double, so that, if
					there be twins, they may have a double source of nutrition. Yet apart from
					all this, mothers would come to be more kindly disposed towards their
					children, and more inclined to show them affection. Not unnaturally either,
					I swear; for this fellowship in feeding is a bond that knits kindliness
					together. Yes, even the brute beasts, when dragged away from their
					companions in feeding, evidently miss them. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, ii. l. 28. <hi rend="italics">Cf.
						Memorabilia</hi>, ii. 3. 4.</note> So, as I have said, mothers must
					endeavour, if possible, to nurse their children themselves; but if they are
					unable to do this, either because of bodily weakness (for such a thing can
					happen) or because they are in haste to bear more children, yet
					foster-mothers and nursemaids are not to be selected at random, but as good
					ones as possible must be chosen; and, first of all, in character they must
					be Greek. For just as it is necessary, immediately after birth, to begin to
					mould the limbs of the children's bodies in order that these may grow
					straight and without deformity, so, in the same fashion, it is fitting from
					the beginning to regulate the characters of children. For youth <pb id="v1.p.17"/> is impressionable and plastic, and while such minds are
					still tender lessons are infused deeply into them ; but anything which has
					become hard is with difficulty softened. For just as seals leave their
					impression in soft wax, so are lessons impressed upon the minds of children
					while they are young. And, as it seems to me, Plato, that remarkable man,
					quite properly advises <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 377 E.</note> nurses, even in telling stories to children, not to
					choose at random, lest haply their minds be filled at the outset with
					foolishness and corruption. Phocylides, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poetae Lyrici Graeci, ii. 448 (frag. 13).</hi>
               </note> too, the poet, appears to give
					admirable advice in saying : <quote rend="blockquote">Should teach while still a child The tale of
						noble deeds.</quote> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Now there is another point which should not be omitted, that in choosing the
					younger slaves, who are to be the servants and companions of young masters,
					those should be sought out who are, first and foremost, sound in character,
					who are Greeks as well, and distinct of speech, so that the children may not
					be contaminated by barbarians and persons of low character, and so take on
					some of their commonness. The proverb-makers say, and quite to the point,
					<q direct="unspecified">If you dwell with a lame man, you will learn to limp.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>When now they attain to an age to be put under the charge of attendants, then
					especially great care must be taken in the appointment of these, so as not
					to entrust one's children inadvertently to slaves taken in war or to
					barbarians or to those who are unstable. Nowadays, the common practice of
					many persons is more than ridiculous ; for some of their trustworthy slaves
					they appoint to manage their farms, others they make masters of their <pb id="v1.p.19"/> ships, others their factors, others they make
					housestewards, and some even money-lenders; but any slave whom they find to
					be a wine-bibber and a glutton, and useless for any kind of business, to him
					they bring their sons and put them in his charge. But the good attendant
					ought to be a man of such nature as was Phoenix, the attendant of Achilles. </p>
            <p> I come now to a point which is more important and weighty than anything I
					have said so far. Teachers must be sought for the children who are free from
					scandal in their lives, who are unimpeachable in their manners, and in
					experience the very best that may be found. For to receive a proper
					education is the source and root of all goodness. As husbandmen place stakes
					beside the young plants, so do competent teachers with all care set their
					precepts and exhortations beside the young, in order that their characters
					may grow to be upright. Nowadays there are some fathers who deserve utter
					contempt, who, before examining those who are going to teach, either because
					of ignorance, or sometimes because of inexperience, hand over their children
					to untried and untrustworthy men. And this is not so ridiculous if their
					action is due to inexperience, but there is another case which is absurd to
					the last degree. What is this ? Why, sometimes even with knowledge and with
					information from others, who tell them of the inexperience and even of the
					depravity of certain teachers, they nevertheless entrust their children to
					them ; some yield to the flatteries of those who would please them, and
					there are those who do it as a favour to insistent friends. Their action
					resembles that of a person, who, if he were afflicted with bodily disease,
					<pb id="v1.p.21"/> should reject that man who by his knowledge might be
					able to save his life, and, as a favour to a friend, should prefer one who
					by his inexperience might cause his death ; or again that of a person who
					should dismiss a most excellent shipmaster, and accept the very worst
					because of a friend's insistence. Heaven help us ! Does a man who bears the
					name of father think more of gratifying those who ask favours than he thinks
					of the education of his children ? And did not Socrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cleitophon</hi>, 407 A.</note> of old often say
					very fittingly, that if it were in any way possible one should go up to the
					loftiest part of the city and cry aloud, <q direct="unspecified">Men, whither is your course
						taking you, who give all possible attention to the acquiring of money
						but give small thought to your sons to whom ye are to leave it ?</q>
					To this I should like to add that such fathers act nearly as one would act
					who should give thought to his shoe but pay no regard to his foot. Many
					fathers, however, go so far in their devotion to money as well as in
					animosity toward their children, that in order to avoid paying a larger fee,
					they select as teachers for their children men who are not worth any wage at
					all—looking for ignorance, which is cheap enough. Wherefore Aristippus not
					inelegantly, in fact very cleverly, rebuked a father who was devoid both of
					mind and sense. For when a man asked him what fee he should require for
					teaching his child, Aristippus replied, <q direct="unspecified">A thousand drachmas</q>
					; but when the other exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">Great Heavens ! what an excessive
						demand ! I can buy a slave for a thousand,</q> Aristippus retorted,
					<q direct="unspecified">Then you will have two slaves, your son and the one you
						buy.</q> And, in general, 
					<pb id="v1.p.23"/> is it not absurd for people to accustom children to take
					their food with their right hand, and, if one puts out his left, to rebuke
					him, and yet to take no forethought that they shall hear right and proper
					words of instruction ? </p>
            <p> Now I will tell what happens to these admirable fathers when they have badly
					brought up and badly educated their sons. When their sons are enrolled in
					the ranks of men, and disdain the sane and orderly life, and throw
					themselves headlong into disorderly and slavish pleasures, then, when it is
					of no use, the fathers regret that they have been false to their duty in the
					education of their sons, being now distressed at their wrongdoing. For some
					of them take up with flatterers and parasites, abominable men of obscure
					origin, corrupters and spoilers of youth, and others buy the freedom of
					courtesans and prostitutes, proud and sumptuous in expense ; still others
					give themselves up to the pleasures of the table, while others come to wreck
					in dice and revels, and some finally take to the wilder forms of evildoing,
					such as adultery and bacchanalian routs, ready to pay with life itself for a
					single pleasure. But if these men had become conversant with the higher
					education, they perhaps would not have allowed themselves to be dominated by
					such practices, and they would at least have become acquainted with the
					precept <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The explanation may be found in the <hi rend="italics">Palatine Anthology</hi>, v. No. 301 (the <hi rend="italics">Greek Anthology</hi>, in the L.C.L. vol. i. p. 291, No. 302), or in Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1044 B, or in Athenaeus, iv. 48 (p. 158 F). </note> of Diogenes, who with coarseness of speech, but with substantial
					truth, advises and says, <q direct="unspecified">Go into any brothel to learn that there is
						no difference between what costs money and what costs nothing.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Briefly, then, I say (an oracle one might properly 
					<pb id="v1.p.25"/> call it, rather than advice) that, to sum up, the
					beginning, the middle, and end in all these matters is good education and
					proper training ; and it is this, I say, which leads on and helps towards
					moral excellence and towards happiness. And, in comparison with this, all
					other advantages are human, and trivial, and not worth our serious concern.
					Good birth is a fine thing, but it is an advantage which must be credited to
					one's ancestors. Wealth is held in esteem, but it is a chattel of fortune,
					since oftentime she takes it away from those who possess it, and brings and
					presents it to those who do not expect it. Besides, great wealth is the very
					mark for those who aim their shafts at the purse— rascally slaves and
					blackmailers ; and above all, even the vilest may possess it. Repute,
					moreover, is imposing, but unstable. Beauty is highly prized, but
					short-lived. Health is a valued possession, but inconstant. Strength is much
					admired, but it falls an easy prey to disease and old age. And, in general,
					if anybody prides himself wholly upon the strength of his body, let him know
					that he is sadly mistaken in judgement. For how small is man's strength
					compared with the power of other living creatures! I mean, for instance,
					elephants and bulls and lions. But learning, of all things in this world, is
					alone immortal and divine. Two elements in man's nature are supreme over
					all—mind and reason. The mind exercises control over reason, and reason is
					the servant of the mind, unassailable by fortune, impregnable to calumny,
					uncorrupted by disease, unimpaired by old age. For the mind alone grows
					young with increase of years, and time, which takes away all things else,
					but adds wisdom <pb id="v1.p.27"/> to old age. War, again, like a torrent,
					sweeps everything away and carries everything along in its current, but
					learning alone it cannot take away. It seems to me that Stilpo, the
					philosopher of Megara, made an answer worth recording, at the time when
					Demetrius, having reduced the people of that city to slavery and razed its
					buildings, asked him whether perchance he had lost anything ; but Stilpo
					replied : <q direct="unspecified">No, indeed, for war cannot make spoil of virtue.</q>
					In full accord and harmony with this appears the reply of Socrates.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Gorgias</hi>, 470 E; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 12.</note> For he,
					when someone (I think it was Gorgias) asked him what notion he had regarding
					the great king, and whether he thought him happy, said, <q direct="unspecified">I do not
						know how he stands in the matter of righteousness and
						learning,</q>—his thought being that happiness depends upon these and
					not upon accidental advantages. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Just as I advise people to make nothing of more immediate importance than the
					education of their children, so again I say they ought to cling to the
					uncorrupted and sound education, and to withdraw their sons as far away as
					possible from the nonsense of ostentatious public discourse. For to please
					the multitude is to displease the wise. And Euripides bears witness to my
					words when he says : <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus</hi>, 986.</note> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">I have no gift to reason with a crowd ; I'm wiser
						with my friends and fewer folk. And this is just; since those the wise hold
						cheap Are better tuned to speak before a crowd.</quote> I observe that those who
					practise speaking in a way to catch the favour of the vulgar herd also turn
					
					<pb id="v1.p.29"/> out in general to be incontinent in their lives and fond
					of pleasure. And this surely is to be expected ; for if, in providing
					pleasure for others, they disregard what is honourable, they would be slow
					to place that which is upright and sound above the gratification of their
					own pleasures and luxurious tastes, and slow to pursue the temperate course
					instead of the agreeable. Moreover, why should children [be taught such a
					way of speaking] ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The lacuna in the MSS. probably had something to this effect.</note> For it is a good thing not to say or do anything at
					random, and according to the proverb, <q direct="unspecified">Good things are hard.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi> 257 E.</note>
					Speeches made offhand display a large measure of readiness and facility,
					being characteristic of persons who know not where should be the beginning
					or where the end. But, apart from all other errors, those who speak on the
					impulse of the moment fall into a dreadful disregard of limit and into
					loquacity. Reflexion on the other hand prevents a discourse from exceeding
					the due limits of proportion. Pericles, <q direct="unspecified">as the story has been handed
						down for us to hear,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi> 23 (<hi rend="italics">Against Aristocrates</hi>), 66, p. 641.</note> though called upon by the people,
					oftentimes did not heed their summons, saying that he was unprepared. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pericles</hi>, chap. 7 (155 <hi rend="italics">ad fin</hi>).</note> In
					like manner also Demosthenes, who was an ardent follower of Pericles'
					political policy, when the Athenians called upon him to give his counsel,
					resisted, saying, <q direct="unspecified">I have not prepared myself.</q> This, perhaps,
					is an unauthentic and fictitious tradition; but in his speech against
					Meidias <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi> 21, (<hi rend="italics">Against Meidias</hi>), 191, p. 576.</note> he presents clearly the helpfulness of reflection. At any rate he
					says, <q direct="unspecified">Men of Athens, I say I have given much thought 
						<pb id="v1.p.31"/> to this matter, and I could not deny that I have also
						rehearsed my speech to the best of my ability ; for I should be a
						miserable wretch, if, in view of his past and present treatment of me, I
						had paid no attention to what I was going to say to you about
						it.</q> But I, for my part, would not assert that readiness of
					speech is to be utterly rejected, or again that it should not be used in its
					proper place, but that it is to be used like a drug, with caution. Indeed
					until one arrives at man's estate I do not think it right that he should
					speak at all offhand, but when he shall have firmly established his powers,
					then, if the occasion invite, it is fitting for him to exercise some freedom
					in his speech. For just as those who have been in fetters for a long time,
					even if later they be set free, yet, because of the long-continued
					habituation to their bonds, are not able to walk freely, and are not sure on
					their feet, so is it with those who for a long time have kept their speech
					under close restraint : if ever it becomes necessary to speak offhand, they
					nevertheless keep to the same type of expression as before. But to allow
					those who are still young to speak extempore stands responsible for the
					worst sort of rambling talk. They tell the story of a wretched painter, who,
					exhibiting to Apelles a painting, said, <q direct="unspecified">This I have only this moment
						painted.</q> Whereupon Apelles replied, <q direct="unspecified">Even should you not
							say so, yet I know that it was painted hastily, and I only wonder that
							you have not painted more of like sort.</q>
				        </p>
            <p> I advise then (for I return now to my original theme) that, as one should
					always be careful to avoid the theatrical and melodramatic style, so, on the
					other hand, one should exercise the same caution <pb id="v1.p.33"/> to avoid
					triviality and vulgarity in style ; for a turgid diction is unfitted for a
					man in public life, and a barren style is too unimpressive ; but as the body
					ought to be not merely healthy but also sturdy, so also speech should be not
					merely free from fault but vigorous too. For the cautious is merely
					commended, but the audacious is admired as well. It so happens that I
					entertain the same opinion also in regard to mental disposition. For a man
					should not be bold, on the one hand, or, on the other, pusillanimous and
					cowering, since the one resolves itself into impudence, and the other into
					servility. Always to pursue the middle course in everything is artistic and
					in good taste. </p>
            <p> While I am still dwelling upon my own opinion in regard to education, I
					desire to say that in the first place a discourse composed of a series of
					short sentences I regard as no small proof of lack of culture ; in the
					second place I think that in practice such discourse soon palls, and in
					every case it causes impatience; for monotony is in everything tiresome and
					repellent, but variety is agreeable, as it is in everything else, as, for
					example, in entertainments that appeal to the eye or the ear. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Now the free-born child should not be allowed to go without some knowledge,
					both through hearing and observation, of every branch also of what is called
					general education ; yet these he should learn only incidentally, just to get
					a taste of them, as it were (for perfection in everything is impossible),
					but philosophy he should honour above all else. I can perhaps make my
					opinion clear by means of a figure : for example, it is a fine thing to
					voyage about and view many cities, but profitable to dwell <pb id="v1.p.35"/> only in the best one. And it was a clever saying of Bion, the
					philosopher, that, just as the suitors, not being able to approach Penelope,
					consorted with her maid-servants, so also do those who are not able to
					attain to philosophy wear themselves to a shadow over the other kinds of
					education which have no value. Wherefore it is necessary to make philosophy
					as it were the head and front of all education. For as regards the care of
					the body men have discovered two sciences, the medical and the gymnastic, of
					which the one implants health, the other sturdiness, in the body ; but for
					the illnesses and affections of the mind philosophy alone is the remedy. For
					through philosophy and in company with philosophy it is possible to attain
					knowledge of what is honourable and what is shameful, what is just and what
					is unjust, what, in brief, is to be chosen and what to be avoided, how a man
					must bear himself in his relations with the gods, with his parents, with his
					elders, with the laws, with strangers, with those in authority, with
					friends, with women, with children, with servants ; that one ought to
					reverence the gods, to honour one's parents, to respect ones elders, to be
					obedient to the laws, to yield to those in authority, to love one's friends,
					to be chaste with women, to be affectionate with children, and not to be
					overbearing with slaves; and, most important of all, not to be over joyful
					at success or overmuch distressed at misfortune, nor to be dissolute in
					pleasures, nor impulsive and brutish in temper. These things I regard as
					pre-eminent among all the advantages which accrue from philosophy. For to
					have a generous heart in prosperity shows a man, to excite no envy withal
					shows <pb id="v1.p.37"/> a disciplined nature ; to rule pleasure by reason
					marks the wise man, and not every man can master his passion. But I regard
					as perfect, so far as men can be, those who are able to combine and mingle
					political capacity with philosophy ; and I am inclined to think that these
					are secure in the possession of two things which are of the greatest good: a
					life useful to the world in their public position, and the calm and
					untroubled life in their pursuit of philosophy. For there are three forms of
					life, of which the first is the practical life, the second the contemplative
					life, and the third the life of enjoyment. The last, which is dissolute and
					enslaved to pleasure, is bestial and mean, but the contemplative life, which
					falls short in practice, is not useful, while the practical life which has
					no portion in philosophy, is without culture or taste. One must try, then,
					as well as one can, both to take part in public life, and to lay hold of
					philosophy so far as the opportunity is granted. Such was the life of
					Pericles as a public man, such was Archytas of Tarentum, such was Dion of
					Syracuse, such was Epaminondas of Thebes, of whom the next to the last was
					the associate of Plato. </p>
            <p> In regard to education I do not know why it is necessary to take the time to
					say more ; but in addition to the foregoing, it is useful, or rather it is
					necessary, not to be indifferent about acquiring the works of earlier
					writers, but to make a collection of these, like a set of tools in farming.
					For the corresponding tool of education is the use of books, and by their
					means it has come to pass that we are able to study knowledge at its source.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>It is not proper, either, to overlook the exercise <pb id="v1.p.39"/> of the
					body, but we should send the children to the trainer's and cultivate
					adequately this side of education with all diligence, not merely for the
					sake of gracefulness of body but also with an eye to strength ; for
					sturdiness of body in childhood is the foundation of a hale old age. Just as
					in fair weather, then, one ought to prepare for storm, so also in youth one
					should store up discipline and self-restraint as a provision for old age.
					But the amount of bodily exercise should be so limited as not to be a drain
					on the children and make them too tired to study; for, according to Plato, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 537 B.</note>
					sleep and weariness are the enemies of learning. But why do I introduce this
					subject here ? Just because I am anxious to say that which is of greater
					importance than all the rest: it is for the contests of war that boys must
					be practised, by exercising themselves in throwing the javelin, shooting
					with the bow, and in hunting. <q direct="unspecified">For the goods of the vanquished
					</q> in battle <q direct="unspecified">are prizes offered to the victors.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, ii. 3. 2.</note> War
					has no place for a bodily condition produced by an indoor life, and a
					slenderly built soldier accustomed to military exercises forces his way
					through the masses of fleshy athletes. </p>
            <p> But perchance someone may say, <q direct="unspecified">What is this ? You, who have promised
					to give directions in regard to the education of free-born children, are
					now evidently disregarding the education of the poor children of the
					common people, and you acknowledge that you are offering your
					suggestions for the rich only.</q> To these it is not difficult to
					make reply. My dearest wish would be that my scheme 
					<pb id="v1.p.41"/> of education should be generally useful; but if some,
					being needy in their private circumstances, shall be unable to avail
					themselves of my directions, let them lay the blame therefor upon fortune
					and not upon him who gives this counsel. Even the poor must endeavour, as
					well as they can, to provide the best education for their children, but, if
					that be impossible, then they must avail themselves of that which is within
					their means. I have burdened the discussion with this minor matter so as to
					connect therewith in due order the other topics which tend toward the right
					education of the young. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>This also I assert, that children ought to be led to honourable practices by
					means of encouragement and reasoning, and most certainly not by blows or
					ill-treatment, for it surely is agreed that these are fitting rather for
					slaves than for the freeborn ; for so they grow numb and shudder at their
					tasks, partly from the pain of the blows, partly from the degradation.
					Praise and reproof are more helpful for the free-born than any sort of
					ill-usage, since the praise incites them toward what is honourable, and
					reproof keeps them from what is disgraceful. </p>
            <p> But rebukes and praise should be used alternately and in a variety of ways ;
					it is well to choose some time when the children are full of confidence to
					put them to shame by rebuke, and then in turn to cheer them up by praises,
					and to imitate the nurses, who, when they have made their babies cry, in
					turn offer them the breast for comfort. Moreover in praising them it is
					essential not to excite and puff them up, for they are made conceited and
					spoiled by excess of praise. <pb id="v1.p.43"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>In my time I have seen fathers in whom excessive affection had become the
					cause of no affection. What is it that I mean to say, in order that by the
					example I give I may make my argument more luminous ? It is this : in their
					eagerness that their children may the sooner rank first in everything, they
					lay upon them unreasonable tasks, which the children find themselves unable
					to perform, and so come to grief; besides, being depressed by their
					unfortunate experiences, they do not respond to the instruction which they
					receive. For, just as plants are nourished by moderate applications of
					water, but are drowned by many in succession, in the same fashion the mind
					is made to grow by properly adapted tasks, but is submerged by those which
					are excessive. Children must be given some breathing-space from continued
					tasks, for we must bear in mind that our whole life is divided between
					relaxation and application. For this reason there have been created not only
					waking hours but also sleep, not only war but also peace, not only storm but
					also fair weather, not only periods of vigorous activity but also holidays.
					In short, rest gives relish to labour. We may observe that this holds true
					not merely in the case of living creatures, but also in the case of
					inanimate things, for we unstring bows and lyres that we may be able to
					tighten them again. The body, generally speaking, is maintained by hunger
					and its satisfaction, and the mind by relaxation and labour. </p>
            <p> It is right to rebuke some fathers who, after entrusting their sons to
					attendants and masters, do not themselves take cognizance at all of their
					instruction by means of their own eyes or their own <pb id="v1.p.45"/> ears.
					Herein they most fail in their duty; for they ought themselves every few
					days to test their children, and not rest their hopes upon the disposition
					of a hired person; for even those persons will devote more attention to the
					children if they know they must from time to time render an account. And in
					this connexion there is point as well as wit in the remark of the groom who
					said that nothing makes the horse so fat as the king's eye.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Oeconomicus</hi>, 12. 20.</note> 
            </p>
            <p> Above all, the memory of children should be trained and exercised ; for this
					is, as it were, a storehouse of learning ; and it is for this reason that
					the mythologists have made Memory the mother of the Muses, thereby
					intimating by an allegory that there is nothing in the world like memory for
					creating and fostering. This, then, is to be trained in either case, whether
					one's children be naturally gifted with a good memory, or, on the contrary,
					forgetful. For we shall thus strengthen nature's generous endowment, and
					thus fill out her deficiency ; and while the first class of children will
					excel others, the second class will excel their former selves. The saying of
					Hesiod <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 361; <q direct="unspecified">Many a little makes a mickle.</q>
               </note> is admirably put: <quote rend="blockquote">If even small upon the small you place And do this
						oft, the whole will soon be great.</quote> Nor should parents forget that those
					branches of instruction which involve memory make no small contribution, not
					merely to education, but also to the practical activities of life ; for the
					memory of past activities serves as a pattern of good counsel for the
					future. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Moreover, one's sons are to be kept from foul 
					<pb id="v1.p.47"/> language ; for, according to Democritus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmete der Vorsokratiker</hi>, ii. p. 87.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">A word
						is a deed's shadow.</q> Then, too, proper measures must be taken to
					ensure that they shall be tactful and courteous in their address ; for
					nothing is so deservedly disliked as tactless characters. Besides, children
					may avoid getting themselves disliked by their associates if they do not
					prove totally unyielding in discussions. For it is a fine thing to
					understand, not only how to gain the victory, but also how to submit to
					defeat, in cases where victory is injurious ; for there is really such a
					thing as a <q direct="unspecified">Cadmean victory.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A victory which (like a Pyrrhic victory) is disastrous to the victor. The reference is to the combat between Eteocles and Polyneices, the two sons of Oedipus. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 488 A and Herodotus, i. 166.</note> As a witness of this I may
					quote Euripides the wise, who says: <quote rend="blockquote">When of two speakers one is growing
						wroth, Wiser is he that yields in argument.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Protesilaus</hi>; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 654.</note>
               </quote> 
            </p>
            <p> We must now lay down some rules of conduct which the young should follow no
					less but even more than those previously given. These are: To practise the
					simple life, to hold the tongue in check, to conquer anger, to control the
					hands. We must consider the importance of each of these ; and they will be
					more intelligible if based on examples. </p>
            <p> So, to begin with the last, some men by putting their hands to wrongful
					gains have upset the good repute of their earlier lives. Witness the case of
					Gylippus, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is told in detail by Plutarch in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. 16 (p. 442).</note> the Spartan, who was forced into exile because he had secretly
					unsewed the bags of money. 
					<pb id="v1.p.49"/>
				        </p>
            <p> Again, an unruffled temper is certainly the mark of a wise man. Thus
					Socrates once, when a bold and impudent youth had kicked him, observed that
					the bystanders were so indignant and so violently moved as to wish to follow
					up the offender ; but he only said : <q direct="unspecified">If an ass had kicked me, should
						you have thought it proper to kick him in return ?</q> That youth,
					however, did not by any means get off scot-free, but as everybody jeered at
					him, and nicknamed him <q direct="unspecified">Kicker,</q> he ended by hanging himself. </p>
            <p> And when Aristophanes brought out the Clouds, and heaped all manner of abuse
					upon Socrates in every possible way, one of those who had been present said
					to Socrates, <q direct="unspecified">Are you not indignant, Socrates, that he used you as he
						did in the play ?</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">No indeed,</q> he replied; <q direct="unspecified">when they break a jest upon
						me in the theatre I feel as if I were at a big party of good
						friends.</q> What Archytas of Tarentum and Plato did will be seen to
					be closely akin to this. For Archytas, on his return from the war (where he
					had been general) found his land gone to waste. He summoned his overseer and
					said, <q direct="unspecified">You should be sorry for this, if I were not in too great a
						temper.</q> And Plato, provoked at a gluttonous and impudent slave,
					called his sister's son, Speusippus, and said as he withdrew, <q direct="unspecified">Beat
						this fellow, for I am too much provoked.</q> But it may be urged
					that such actions are difficult and hard to imitate. I know that myself. But
					the effort must be made, by employing the actions of such men as standards
					as far as possible, to abate a great part of our unbridled and furious
					temper; for in other respects also we are not comparable with them either in
					<pb id="v1.p.51"/> experience or in magnanimity. Yet we, no less than
					they, feeling ourselves to be the high priests of God's mysteries and
					torch-bearers of wisdom, do attempt, so far as lies in our power, to imitate
					and to get a little taste of such conduct for ourselves. </p>
            <p> The control of the tongue, then, still remains to be discussed of the topics
					I suggested. If anybody has the notion that this is a slight and
					insignificant matter, he is very far from the truth. For timely silence is a
					wise thing, and better than any speech. And this is the reason, as it
					appears to me, why the men of olden time established the rites of initiation
					into the mysteries, that we, by becoming accustomed to keep silence there,
					may transfer that fear which we learned from the divine secrets to the safe
					keeping of the secrets of men. For, again, nobody was ever sorry because he
					kept silent, but hundreds because they talked. Again, the word unspoken can
					easily be uttered later; but the spoken word cannot possibly be recalled. I
					have heard of countless men who have fallen into the greatest misfortunes
					through intemperate speech. Of these I shall mention one or two as typical
					and omit the rest. When Ptolemy Philadelphus married his sister Arsinoe,
					Sotades <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, xiv. 13 (p. 620 F).</note> said, <quote rend="blockquote">'Tis wrong for you to try to spur that mare,</quote> and thereafter
					he rotted in prison for many years; and so suffered condign punishment for
					his untimely talking, and to make other men laugh he sorrowed a long time
					himself. A story to match and couple with this, and much more dreadful, is
					what the sophist Theocritus said and suffered. Alexander 
					<pb id="v1.p.53"/> had bidden the Greeks to make ready crimson robes so that
					on his return he might offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving for his victory in
					the war against the barbarians, and all the states had to pay a polltax in
					money, when Theocritus remarked, <q direct="unspecified">Before this I used to be in doubt,
						but now I know for a certainty that this is Homer's ' Crimson Death.'
					</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> v. 83, and elsewhere.</note> And thereby he made an enemy of Alexander. And Antigonus, king of
					the Macedonians, who was blind of one eye, he drove to immoderate anger by
					reproaching him with his disfigurement. For Antigonus sent his chief cook,
					Eutropion, who had been an officer in his army, to Theocritus, and insisted
					that Theocritus should come to him and engage him in discussion. When
					Eutropion delivered his message to Theocritus, coming several times for the
					purpose, the latter said, <q direct="unspecified">I know very well that you want to serve me
						up raw to your Cyclops,</q> twitting the one for being disfigured
					and the other for being now a cook. <q direct="unspecified">Then you shall not keep your
						head on,</q> said Eutropion, <q direct="unspecified">but you shall pay the penalty
							for this reckless talk and madness of yours.</q> He thereupon
					reported the remark to the king, who sent and had Theocritus put to death. </p>
            <p> But besides all this, we should, as a most sacred duty, accustom children to
					speak the truth. For lying is fit for slaves only, and deserves to be hated
					of all men, and even in decent slaves it is not to be condoned. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>So far I have felt no doubt or even hesitation in saying what I have said
					about the decorous conduct and modest behaviour of the young ; but in regard
					to the topic now to be introduced I am of two opinions and two minds, and I
					incline now <pb id="v1.p.55"/> this way, now that, as though on a balance,
					being unable to settle down on either side ; and a feeling of great
					reluctance possesses me, whether to introduce or to avoid the subject. Still
					I must venture to speak of it. What is it then ? It is the question whether
					boys' admirers are to be permitted to associate with them and pass their
					time with them, or whether, on the contrary, they should be kept away and
					driven off from association with the youth. For when I have regard to those
					uncompromising fathers, harsh and surly in their manner, who think the
					society of admirers an intolerable outrage to their sons, I feel cautious
					about standing as its sponsor and advocate. But again, when I think of
					Socrates, Plato, Xenophon, Aeschines, Cebes, and that whole band of men who
					sanctioned affection between men, and thus guided the youth onward to
					learning, leadership, and virtuous conduct, I am of a different mind again,
					and am inclined to emulate their example. Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Theseus</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 388.</note> gives testimony in
					their favour when he says : Among mankind another love exists, That of an
					upright, chaste, and noble soul. Nor may we omit the remark of Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 468 B.</note>
					wherein jest and seriousness are combined. For he says that those who have
					acquitted themselves nobly ought to have the right to kiss any fair one they
					please. Now we ought indeed to drive away those whose desire is for mere
					outward beauty, but to admit without reserve those who are lovers of the
					soul. And while the sort of love prevailing at Thebes and in Elis is to be
					avoided, as well as the so-called 
					<pb id="v1.p.57"/> kidnapping in Crete, that which is found at Athens and in
					Lacedaemon is to be emulated. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>In this matter each man may be allowed such opinion as accords with his own
					convictions. But now that I have spoken of the orderly and decorous
					behaviour of children, I shall next pass to the period of adolescence, and
					say a very few words about it. I have often expressed my utter
					disapprobation of men who have been responsible for the introduction of
					depraved habits. For, while it is true that they have put attendants and
					teachers in charge of their children, they nevertheless have allowed the
					impetuosity of youth to range unrestrained, when they ought, on the
					contrary, to have exercised greater caution and watchfulness over them when
					they were young men than when they were children. For who is not aware that
					the faults of children are trivial and altogether corrigible —heedlessness,
					perhaps, towards their attendants, or deceiving and refusing to mind their
					teachers ? But the iniquities of early manhood are often monstrous and
					wicked—unlimited gluttony, theft of parents' money, gambling, revels,
					drinking-bouts, love affairs with young girls, and corruption of married
					women. The impulses of young men should therefore be kept fettered and
					restrained by careful supervision. For life's prime is prodigal in its
					pleasures, restive, and in need of a curb, so that parents who do not take
					hold of the reins with firm hand at this period of life, are manifestly, by
					their folly, giving to their sons licence for wrongdoing. Wise fathers
					ought, therefore, especially during this time, to be vigilant and alert, and
					to bring the young men to reason by instruction, by threats, <pb id="v1.p.59"/> by entreaties, by pointing out examples of men who
					through love of pleasure have become involved in misfortunes, and of those
					who, through their steadfastness, have gained for themselves approval and
					good repute. For these two things—hope of reward and fear of punishment—are,
					as it were, the elements of virtue. For the one renders men more eager for
					honourable pursuits while the other makes them averse to base actions. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>It should be the general rule to keep the young away from any association
					with base men ; for they carry away something of their badness. This duty
					Pythagoras <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, x. 77 (p. 452 D); Iamblichus, <hi rend="italics">Protrept.</hi> chap. 21 (pp. 131-160); Diogenes Laertius, viii. 1, 17-18; and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Numa</hi>, chap. 14 (69 C).</note> also has enjoined in the form of allegories which I shall now
					quote and explain. For they contribute no small influence towards the
					acquisition of virtue. For example : </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not taste of black-tails <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The name of a fish.</note> ;</q> that is, <q direct="unspecified">Do not
						spend your time with men of black character, because of their
						malevolence.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not step over the beam of a balance</q>; that is, one should
					give greatest heed to justice and not transgress it. </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not sit on a peck measure</q> ; as much as to say that we
					should avoid idleness and have forethought for providing our daily bread. </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not give your hand to everybody</q> ; instead of, <q direct="unspecified">Do
						not make friends too readily.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not wear a tight ring</q> ; means that one should live his
					life unhampered, and not subject it to any bond. </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not poke a fire with steel</q> ; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 281 A and 354 E, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Numa</hi>, chap. 14 (69 C) where Plutarch has <q direct="unspecified">with a sword.</q>
               </note> instead of, 
					<pb id="v1.p.61"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not provoke an angry man.</q> Indeed, it is wrong to do so,
					and we should yield to men who are in a temper. </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not eat your heart</q> ; as much as to say, <q direct="unspecified">Do not
						injure your soul by wasting it with worries.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Abstain from beans</q> ; means that a man should keep out of
					politics, for beans were used in earlier times for voting upon the removal
					of magistrates from office. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A form of recall (<foreign lang="greek">a)poxeirotoni/a</foreign>); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, chap. 61.</note> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Do not put food into a slop-pail</q> ; signifies that it is not
					fitting to put clever speech into a base mind. For speech is the food of
					thought, and baseness in men makes it unclean. </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not turn back on reaching the boundaries</q> ; that is, when
					people are about to die and see the boundary of their life close at hand,
					they should bear all this with serenity and not be faint-hearted. </p>
            <p> I return to the subject suggested at the beginning of the chapter. As I said
					there, the young should be kept away from every sort of base men, and most
					of all from flatterers. Let me repeat here what I say over and over again to
					many fathers: There is no class of persons more pernicious than flatterers,
					nor any that more surely and quickly gives youth a nasty tumble. They
					utterly ruin both fathers and sons, bringing to sorrow the old age of those
					and the youth of these, and dangling pleasure as an irresistible lure to get
					their advice taken. To sons who are to inherit wealth fathers commend
					sobriety, flatterers drinking to excess ; fathers commend self-restraint,
					flatterers profligacy ; fathers 
					<pb id="v1.p.63"/> frugality, flatterers extravagance ; fathers industry,
					flatterers indolence, saying, <q direct="unspecified">All life is but a moment. We must
						live, not merely exist.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apparently adapted from some comedy; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 643.</note> Why should we give a thought to your father's
						threats ? He's an old twaddler with one foot already in the grave, and
						before long we'll take his coffin on our shoulders and carry him
						out.</q> Another of them posts a drab in the young man's path, or
					prostitutes a married woman for him, and spoils and wastes the father's
					provision for old age. Detestable is their whole tribe, pretenders of
					friendship, without a vestige of honest speech, flatterers of the rich but
					despisers of the poor, addressing themselves with instinctive art to the
					young, grinning broadly when their patrons laugh, spurious claimants to any
					spirit, and bastard members of human life, subsisting at the beck and nod of
					the wealthy ; free-born by freak of fortune, but slaves by choice. Whenever
					they are not treated with insult, they feel themselves insulted because then
					they do not fulfil the purpose for which they are kept. So if any father is
					concerned for the good upbringing of his children, he must drive away these
					detestable creatures, and quite as much must he drive away schoolmates who
					show depravity, for these also are capable of corrupting the most likely
					natures. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Now all these rules concern honour and good profit, but what follows concerns
					human nature. Take the fathers again : I do not think they should be utterly
					harsh and austere in their nature, but they should in many cases concede
					some shortcomings to the younger person, and remind themselves that they
					once were young. As physicians, by mixing bitter drugs with sweet syrups,
					have <pb id="v1.p.65"/> found that the agreeable taste gains access for what
					is beneficial, so fathers should combine the abruptness of their rebukes
					with mildness, and at one time grant some licence to the desires of their
					children, and slacken the reins a little, and then at another time draw them
					tight again. Most desirable is it that they should bear misdeeds with
					serenity, but if that be impossible, yet, if they be on occasion angered,
					they should quickly cool down. For it is better that a father should be
					quick-tempered than sullen, since a hostile and irreconcilable spirit is no
					small proof of animosity towards one's children. It is a good thing also to
					pretend not to know of some shortcomings, and to turn the old man's dull eye
					and dull ear to what they do, and seeing, not to see, and, hearing, not to
					hear, sometimes, what goes on. Our friends' shortcomings we bear with: why
					should it be surprising that we bear with our children's ? Though our slaves
					often suffer from a headache in the morning, we do not force them to confess
					a debauch. <q direct="unspecified">You were niggardly once; well, now be liberal. You were
						indignant once; well, pardon now. He tricked you once with the help of a
						slave; restrain your anger. He once took away a yoke of cattle from the
						field, he once came home with breath reeking from yesterday's debauch;
						ignore it. Or smelling of perfume; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Evidence that the young man had been out in mixed company.</note> do not say a word.</q> In this
					fashion is restive youth gradually broken to harness. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>An effort should be made to yoke in marriage those who cannot resist their
					desires, and who are deaf to admonitions. For marriage is the most secure
					bond for youth. One should, however, betroth to his sons women who are not
					greatly <pb id="v1.p.67"/> above them either in birth or wealth. The maxim
					<q direct="unspecified">Keep to your own place</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The figure is said to be derived from the laguage of boys whipping tops. It is attributed to Pittachus by Diogenes Laertius, i. 4. 8; <hi rend="italics">cf. The Palatine Anthology</hi>, vii. 89 (in L.C.L. <hi rend="italics">The Greek Anthology</hi>, vol. ii. p. 63). A similar expression (from the race-track) may be found in Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Clouds</hi>, 25.</note> is wise, since those who take
					to wife women far above themselves unwittingly become not the husbands of
					their wives, but the slaves of their wives' dowries. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>I will add but little more and then conclude my suggestions. Fathers ought
					above all, by not misbehaving and by doing as they ought to do, to make
					themselves a manifest example to their children, so that the latter, by
					looking at their fathers' lives as at a mirror, may be deterred from
					disgraceful deeds and words. For those who are themselves involved in the
					same errors as those for which they rebuke their erring sons, unwittingly
					accuse themselves in their sons' name. If the life they lead is wholly bad,
					they are not free to admonish even their slaves, let alone their sons.
					Besides, they are likely to become counsellors and instructors to their sons
					in their wrongdoing. For, wherever old men are lacking in decency, young men
					too are sure to be most shameless. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 729 C; also cited or referred to by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 71 B, 144 F and 272 C.</note> 
            </p>
            <p> We must endeavour, therefore, to employ every proper device for the
					discipline of our children, emulating the example of Eurydice, who, although
					she was an Illyrian and an utter barbarian, yet late in life took up
					education in the interest of her children's studies. The inscription which
					she dedicated to the Muses sufficiently attests her love for her children :
					
					<pb id="v1.p.69"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Eurydice of Hierapolis Made to the Muses this her
						offering When she had gained her soul's desire to learn. Mother of young and
						lusty sons was she, And by her diligence attained to learn Letters, wherein
						lies buried all our lore.</quote> 
            </p>
            <p>Now to put into effect all the suggestions which I have given is the province
					of prayer, perhaps, or exhortation. And even to follow zealously the
					majority of them demands good fortune and much careful attention, but to
					accomplish this lies within the capability of man. </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>