<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">An Recte Dictum Sit Latenter Esse Vivendum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text n="tlg-0007.141">
      <body>
         <head>Whether 'twere rightly said, live concealed.</head>
         <pb id="v.3.p.3"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>IT is sure, he that said it had no mind to live concealed, for he spoke it out of a design of being taken
				notice of for his very saying it, as if he saw deeper into
				things than every vulgar eye, and of purchasing to himself a reputation, how unjustly soever, by inveigling others
				into obscurity and retirement. But the poet says right:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I hate the man who makes pretence to wit,
				</l>
                     <l>Yet in his own concerns waives using it.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides, Frag. 897.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For they tell us of one Philoxenus the son of Eryxis,
					and Gnatho the Sicilian, who were so over greedy after
					any dainties set before them, that they would blow their
					nose in the dish, whereby, turning the stomachs of the
					other guests, they themselves went away fuller crammed
					with the rarities. Thus fares it with all those whose appetite is always lusting and insatiate after glory. They
					bespatter the repute of others, as their rivals in honor,
					that they themselves may advance smoothly to it and
					without a rub. They do like watermen, who look astern
					while they row the boat ahead, still so managing the
					strokes of the oar that the vessel may make on to its
					port. So these men who recommend to us such kind of
					precepts row hard after glory, but with their face another
					way. To what purpose else need this have been said?&mdash;why committed to writing and handed down to posterity?
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.4"/>
					
					Would he live incognito to his contemporaries, who is so
					eager to be known to succeeding ages?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But besides, doth not the thing itself sound ill, to
				bid you keep all your lifetime out of the world's eye, as
				if you had rifled the sepulchres of the dead, or done
				such like detestable villany which you should hide for?
				What! is it grown a crime to live, unless you can keep all
				others from knowing you do so? For my part, I should
				pronounce that even an ill-liver ought not to withdraw
				himself from the converse of others. No; let him be
				known, let him be reclaimed, let him repent; so that, if
				you have any stock of virtue, let it not lie unemployed, or
				if you have been viciously bent, do not by flying the means
				continue unreclaimed and uncured. Point me out therefore and distinguish me the man to whom you adopt this
				admonition. If to one devoid of sense, goodness, or wit,
				it is like one that should caution a person under a fever or
				raving madness not to let it be known where he is, for fear
				the physicians should find him, but rather to skulk in
				some dark corner, where he and his diseases may escape
				discovery. So you who labor under that pernicious, that
				scarce curable disease, wickedness, are by parity of reason
				bid to conceal your vices, your envyings, your superstitions,
				like some disorderly or feverous pulse, for fear of falling
				into the hands of them who might prescribe well to you
				and set you to rights again. Whereas, alas! in the days
				of remote antiquity, men exhibited the sick to public view,
				when every charitable passenger who had labored himself
				under the like malady, or had experienced a remedy on them
				that did, communicated to the diseased all the receipts he
				knew; thus, say they, skill in physic was patched up by
				multiplied experiments, and grew to a mighty art. At the
				same rate ought all the infirmities of a dissolute life, all
				the irregular passions of the soul, to be laid open to the
				view of all, and undergo the touch of every skilful hand,
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.5"/>
				
				that all who examine into the temper may be able to
				prescribe accordingly. For instance, doth anger transport you? The advice in that case is, Shun the occasions
				of it. Doth jealousy torment you? Take this or that
				course. Art thou love-sick? It hath been my own case
				and infirmity to be so too; but I saw the folly of it, I repented, I grew wiser. But for those that lie, denying,
				hiding, mincing, and palliating their vices, it makes them
				but take the deeper dye, it rivets their faults into them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Again, if on the other hand this advice be calculated
				for the owners of worth and virtue, if they must be condemned to privacy and live unknown to the world, you do
				in effect bid Epaminondas lay down his arms, you bid Lycurgus rescind his laws, you bid Thrasybulus spare the
				tyrants, in a word, you bid Pythagoras forbear his instructions, and Socrates his reasonings and discourses; nay,
				you lay injunctions chiefly upon yourself, Epicurus, not
				to maintain that epistolary correspondence with your Asiatic
				friends, not to entertain your Egyptian visitants, not to be
				tutor to the youth of Lampsacus, not to present and send
				about your books to women as well as men, out of an
				ostentation of some wisdom in yourself more than vulgar,
				not to leave such particular directions about your funeral
				And in fine, to what purpose, Epicurus, did you keep a
				public table? Why that concourse of friends, that resort
				of fair young men, at your doors? Why so many thousand lines so elaborately composed and writ upon Metrodorus, Aristobulus, and Chaeredemus, that death itself
				might not rob us of them; if virtue must be doomed to oblivion, art to idleness and inactivity, philosophy to silence,
				and all a man's happiness must be forgotten?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>But if indeed, in the state of life we are under, you
				will needs seclude us from all knowledge and acquaintance
				with the world (as men shut light from their entertainments
				and drinking-bouts, for which they set the night apart), let
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.6"/>
				
				it be only such who make it the whole business of life to
				heap pleasure upon pleasure; let such live recluses all
				their days. Were I, in truth, to wanton away my days in
				the arms of your miss Hedeia, or spend them with Leontium, another dear of yours,&mdash;were I to bid defiance to
				virtue, or to place all that's good in the gratification of
				the flesh or the ticklings of a sensual pleasure,&mdash;these
				accursed actions and rites would need darkness and an
				eternal night to veil them; and may they ever be doomed
				to oblivion and obscurity. But what should they hide their
				heads for, who with regard to the works of nature own
				and magnify a God, who celebrate his justice and providence, who in point of morality are due observers of the
				law, promoters of society and community among all men,
				and lovers of the public-weal, and who in the administration
				thereof prefer the common good before private advantage?
				Why should such men cloister up themselves, and live recluses from the world? For would you have them out of
				the way, for fear they should set a good example, and allure others to virtue out of emulation of the precedent? If
				Themistocles's valor had been unknown at Athens, Greece
				had never given Xerxes that repulse. Had not Camillus
				shown himself in defence of the Romans, their city Rome
				had no longer stood. Sicily had not recovered her liberty,
				had Plato been a stranger to Dion. Truly (in my mind)
				to be known to the world under some eminent character
				not only carries a reputation with it, but makes the virtues
				in us become practical like light, which renders us not
				only visible but useful to others. Epaminondas, during the
				first forty years of his life, in which no notice was taken of
				him, was an useless citizen to Thebes; but afterwards, when
				he had once gained credit and the government amongst the
				Thebans, he both rescued them from present destruction,
				and freed even Greece herself from imminent slavery, exhibiting (like light, which is in its own nature glorious, and
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.7"/>
				
				to others beneficial at the same time) a valor seasonably
				active and serviceable to his country, yet interwoven with
				his own laurels. For
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">Virtue, like finest brass, by use grows bright.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, Frag. 779.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And not our houses alone, when (as Sophocles has it) they
					stand long untenanted, run the faster to ruin; but men's
					natural parts, lying unemployed for lack of acquaintance
					with the world, contract a kind of filth or rust and craziness thereby. For sottish ease, and a life wholly sedentary
					and given up to idleness, spoil and debilitate not only the
					body but the soul too. And as close waters shadowed over
					by bordering trees, and stagnated in default of springs to
					supply current and motion to them, become foul and corrupt; so, methinks, is it with the innate faculties of a
					dull unstirring soul,&mdash;whatever usefulness, whatever seeds
					of good she may have latent in her, yet when she puts
					not these powers into action, when once they stagnate,
					they lose their vigor and run to decay.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>See you not how on night's approach a sluggish
				drowsiness oft-times seizes the body, and sloth and inactiveness surprise the soul, and she finds herself heavy and
				quite unfit for action? Have you not then observed how
				a man's reason (like fire scarce visible and just going out)
				retires into itself, and how by reason of its inactivity and
				dulness it is gently agitated by divers fantastical imaginations, so that nothing remains but some obscure indications
				that the man is alive.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But when the orient sun brings back the day,
				</l>
                     <l>It chases night and dreamy sleep away.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>It doth, as it were, bring the world together again, and
					with his returned light call up and excite all mankind to
					thought and action; and, as Democritus tells us, men setting themselves every new-spring day to endeavors of
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.8"/>
					
					mutual beneficence and service one towards another, as if
					they were fastened in the straitest tie together, do all of
					them, some from one, some from another quarter of the
					world, rouse up and awake to action.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>For my own part, I am fully persuaded that life itself,
				and our being born at the rate we are, and the origin we
				share in common with all mankind, were vouchsafed us by
				God to the intent we should be known to one another.
				It is true, whilst man, in that little part of him, his soul,
				lies struggling and scattered in the vast womb of the
				universe, he is an obscure and unknown being; but, when
				once he gets hither into this world and puts a body on, he
				grows illustrious, and from an obscure becomes a conspicuous being; from an hidden, an apparent one. For
				knowledge does not lead to essence (or being), as some
				maintain; but the essence of things rather conducts us
				into the knowledge and understanding thereof. For the
				birth or generation of individuals gives not any being
				to them which they had not before, but brings that individual into view; as also the corruption or death of
				any creature is not its annihilation or reduction into mere
				nothing, but rather a sending the dissolved being into an
				invisible state. Hence is it that many persons (conformably to their ancient country laws), taking the Sun to be
				Apollo, gave him the names of Delius and Pythius (that is,
				conspicuous and known). But for him, be he either God
				or Daemon, who hath dominion over the opposite portion,
				the infernal regions, they call him Hades (that is, invisible),
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">Emperor of gloomy night and lazy sleep,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>for that at our death and dissolution we pass into a state
					of invisibility and beyond the reach of mortal eyes. I am
					indeed of opinion, that the ancients called man Phos (that
					is, light), because from the affinity of their natures strong
					desires are bred in mankind of continually seeing and
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.9"/>
					
					being seen to each other. Nay, some philosophers hold
					the soul itself to be essentially light; which they would
					prove by this among other arguments, that nothing is so
					insupportable to the mind of man as ignorance and obscurity. Whatever is destitute of light she avoids, and
					darkness, the harbor of fears and suspicions, is uneasy to
					her; whereas, on the other hand, light is so delicious, so
					desirable a thing, that without that, and wrapped in darkness, none of the delectables in nature are pleasing to her.
					This makes all our very pleasures, all our diversions and
					enjoyments, charming and grateful to us, like some universal relishing ingredients mixed with the others to make
					them palatable. But he that casts himself into obscure
					retirements, he that sits surrounded in darkness and buries
					himself alive, seems, in my mind, to repine at his own
					birth and grudge he ever had a being.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>And yet it is certain, in the regions prepared for
				pious souls, they conserve not only an existence in (or
				agreeable to) nature, but are encircled with glory.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There the sun with glorious ray,
				</l>
                     <l>Chasing shady night away,
				</l>
                     <l>Makes an everlasting day;
				</l>
                     <l>Where souls in fields of purple roses play;
				</l>
                     <l>Others in verdant plains disport,
				</l>
                     <l>Crowned with trees of every sort,
				</l>
                     <l>Trees that never fruit do bear,
				</l>
                     <l>But always in the blossom are.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Pindar.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The rivers there without rude murmurs gently glide, and
					there they meet and bear each other company, passing
					away their time in commemorating and running over things
					past and present.</p>
            <p>A third state there is of them who have led vicious and
					wicked lives, which precipitates souls into a kind of hell
					and miserable abyss,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where sluggish streams of sable night
					</l>
                     <l>Spout floods of darkness infinite.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Pindar.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This is the receptacle of the tormented; here lie they hid
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.10"/>
					
					under the veils of eternal ignorance and oblivion. For
					vultures do not everlastingly gorge themselves upon the
					liver of a wicked man, exposed by angry Gods upon the
					earth, as poets fondly feign of Prometheus. For either
					rottenness or the funeral pile hath consumed that long ago.
					Nor do the bodies of the tormented undergo (as Sisyphus
					is fabled to do) the toil and pressure of weighty burdens;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">For strength no longer flesh and bone sustains.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 219.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>There are no reliques of the body in dead men which
					stripes and tortures can make impressions on; but in very
					truth the sole punishment of ill-livers is an inglorious
					obscurity, or a final abolition, which through oblivion hurls
					and plunges them into deplorable rivers, bottomless seas,
					and a dark abyss, involving all in uselessness and inactivity,
					absolute ignorance and obscurity, as their last and eternal
					doom.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>