<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De unius in republica dominatione</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold North Fowler</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.10.p.303"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>ON MONARCHY, DEMOCRACY, AND OLIGARCHY (DE UNIUS IN REPUBLICA DOMINATIONE, POPULARI STATU, ET PAUCORUM IMPERIO)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					This essay is evidently only a fragment, as Wyttenbach long ago pointed out. The opening words
					indicate that the author delivers it as an address
					before an audience to which he has spoken on the
					day before, but nothing further is known about the
					circumstances. Few scholars now believe that the
					author is Plutarch, though who the writer was is not
					known. The substance of the fragment is derived
					chiefly from the <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi> of Plato.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.305"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Now as I was myself bringing before this company as a court of judgement the talk that I presented to you yesterday, I thought I heard, while
					wide awake, not in a dream,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xix. 547.</note> Political Wisdom
					saying :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Golden foundation is wrought for canticles sacred,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Frag. 194 (206), p. 465 ed. Schroeder.</note>
               </quote>
					so the speech, which exhorts and encourages you to
					enter political life has been laid as a basis. <q direct="unspecified">Come,
						let us now build walls,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi>
               </note> building upon the exhortation the teaching which is due. And it is due to
					anyone who has received the exhortation and the
					impulse to engage in public affairs that he next
					hear and receive precepts of statecraft by the use of
					which he will, so far as is humanly possible, be of
					service to the people and at the same time manage
					his own affairs with safety and rightful honour. But
					as a step towards that which follows and a consequence of that which has been said, we must consider
					what is the best form of government. For just as
					there are numerous modes of life for a man, so the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.307"/>
					
					
					government (<hi rend="italics">politeia</hi>) is the life of a people, and
					therefore it is essential for us to take the best form
					of it; for of all forms the statesman will choose the
					best or, if he cannot obtain that, then the one of
					all the rest which is most like it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Now the word <hi rend="italics">politeia</hi> (citizenship) is defined
					also as <q direct="unspecified">having a share of the rights in a State,</q> as
					we say the Megarians voted Alexander the <hi rend="italics">politeia</hi>
					(citizenship) ; and when he made fun of their eagerness, they told him that up to that time they had
					conferred citizenship upon Heracles only and now
					upon himself. Then Alexander was astonished and
					accepted the gift, thinking that its rarity gave it
					value. But the life of a statesman, a man who
					is occupied in public affairs, is also called <hi rend="italics">politeia</hi>
					(statecraft) ; as, for example, we commend the
					<hi rend="italics">politeia</hi> (statecraft) of Pericles and of Bias, but condemn that of Hyperbolus and Cleon. And some
					people even call a single brilliant act for the public
					benefit a <hi rend="italics">politeia</hi> (politic act), such, for example, as a
					gift of money, the ending of a war, the introduction
					of a bill in parliament; and accordingly we say
					nowadays that so-and-so has performed a <hi rend="italics">politeia</hi>
					if he happens to have put through some needed
					public measure.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Besides all these, <hi rend="italics">politeia</hi> is defined as an order
					and constitution of a State, which directs its affairs;
					and accordingly they say that there are three
					<hi rend="italics">politeiae</hi> (forms of government), monarchy, oligarchy,
					and democracy, a comparison of which is given by
					Herodotus in his third book.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, iii. 80-84.</note> They appear to be
					the most typical forms ; for the others, as happens in
					musical scales when the strings of the primary notes
					are relaxed or tightened, turn out to be errors
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.309"/>
					
					
					and corruptions through deficiency or excess. Of
					these forms of government, which have achieved
					the widest and greatest power in their periods of
					dominion, the Persians received as their lot royalty
					absolute and irresponsible, the Spartans oligarchy
					aristocratic and uncontrolled, the Athenians democracy self-governing and undiluted. When these
					forms are not hit exactly, their perversions and
					exaggerations are what are called (1) tyranny, (2)
					the predominance of great families,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Politics</hi>, iv. 4. 1 on <foreign lang="greek">dunastei/a</foreign>.</note> (3) or mob-rule : that is, (1) when royalty breeds violence and
					irresponsible action; (2) oligarchy, arrogance and
					presumptuousness; (3) democracy breeds anarchy,
					equality, excess, and all of them folly.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>So, just as a real musician will make use of
					every instrument harmoniously, adapting it skilfully
					and striking each one with regard to its natural
					tunefulness, and yet, following Plato's advice,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 399 c, d.</note> will
					give up guitars, banjoes, psalteries with their many
					sounds, harps and string triangles and prefer the
					lyre and the cithara ; in the same way the real
					statesman will manage successfully the oligarchy
					that Lycurgus established at Sparta, adapting to
					himself the colleagues who have equal power and
					honour and quietly forcing them to do his will;
					he will also get on well in a democracy with its many
					sounds and strings by loosening the strings in some
					matters of government and tightening them in
					others, relaxing at the proper time and then again
					holding fast mightily, knowing how to resist the
					masses and to hold his ground against them. But
					if he were given the choice among governments,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.311"/>
					
					
					like so many tools, he would follow Plato's advice
					and choose no other than monarchy, the only one
					which is able to sustain that top note of virtue,
					high in the highest sense, and never let it be
					tuned down under compulsion or expediency. For
					the other forms of government in a certain sense,
					although controlled by the statesman, control him,
					and although carried along by him, carry him along,
					since he has no firmly established strength to oppose
					those from whom his strength is derived, but is often
					compelled to exclaim in the words of Aeschylus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 107, no. 359; <hi rend="italics">Life of Demetrius</hi>, chap. xxxv.</note>
					which Demetrius the City-stormer employed against
					Fortune after he had lost his hegemony,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Thou fanst my flame, methinks thou burnst me up.</quote>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>