<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Consolatio ad Apollonium</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1928</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.105"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>A LETTER OF CONDOLENCE TO APOLLONIUS (CONSOLATIO AD APOLLONIUM) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>The Letter of Condolence to Apollonius, into which quotations from earlier
					authors have been emptied from the sack rather than scattered by hand, has
					in comparatively recent years fallen under suspicion as being perhaps not
					the work of Plutarch. The suspicion rests mainly on two grounds, the unusual
					length of the quotations, and certain incongruities of style. The latter may
					here be briefly dismissed with the remark that for every departure from
					accepted Plutarchean style a striking instance of conformity to his style
					may be cited, so that no very positive results are to be obtained in this
					way. The case is much the same with the quotations. Many of them are
					unusually long, although not longer than we find in other authors. Some of
					them, for example Euripides, Suppliants 1110 and 1112 (Plut. 110c), show an
					accuracy of ms. tradition so far superior that the reading given by Plutarch
					is commonly adopted by editors of Euripides in preference to the traditional
					reading of the mss. of Euripides. On the other hand, the quotation from
					Plato, Gorgias 523 a (Plut. 120 e), shows many minor variations from our
					text of Plato ; some of these are interesting in themselves, but none of
					them really disturbs the meaning of the passage. </p>
            <p>We learn from the letter almost nothing about <pb id="v.2.p.106"/> Apollonius
					and his departed son, and hardly more about Plutarch. It lacks the intimate
					touch of a similar letter which was written by Plutarch to his wife
					(Moralia, 608 a). Indeed we cannot be wholly sure that the boy was called
					Apollonius after his father, for one stroke of the pen to change the
					accusative to a vocative (121 e) would cause his name to disappear entirely. </p>
            <p>The title of the letter is not found in Lamprias' list of Plutarch's works,
					nevertheless we have reference to it at a comparatively early date. </p>
            <p>Some striking similarities between the letter and Cicero's Tusculan
					Disputations are doubtless to be explained by derivation from a common
					source, and this source was doubtless in large part the works of the
					Academic philosopher Crantor. </p>
            <p>In the absence of actual knowledge it is convenient to assume an hypothesis
					(as in the realm of science one speaks of <q direct="unspecified">atoms</q> or <q direct="unspecified">
						ions</q> or of the electric <q direct="unspecified">current</q>). If we assume
					that this is the original rough draft of the letter which was to be sent to
					Apollonius, nearly everything can be made to square with the hypothesis. In
					selecting some of the quotations Plutarch had put down enough of the
					context, so that later the lines he might finally choose to insert could be
					smoothly interwoven with the text, and the text itself was no doubt to be
					subjected to further polish. </p>
            <p>However, we may be profoundly grateful for the collection of extracts
					included in the letter, and, if the hypothesis be right, we may also be
					grateful for this glimpse of Plutarch's methods of composition. </p>
            <p>We must bear in mind that this particular form of literary composition had
					developed a style of its <pb id="v.2.p.107"/> own, the earliest example
					perhaps being the Axiochus (of Plato ?), and we have records of many more
					now lost. Among the Romans also this form of composition was popular, and
					several examples may be found in the works of Seneca. </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.109"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Even before this time, Apollonius, I felt for you in your sorrow and trouble,
					when I heard of the untimely passing from life of your son, who was very
					dear to us all&mdash;a youth who was altogether decorous and modest, and
					unusually observant of the demands of religion and justice both toward the
					gods and toward his parents and friends. In those days, close upon the time
					of his death, to visit you and urge you to bear your present lot as a mortal
					man should would have been unsuitable, when you were prostrated in both body
					and soul by the unexpected calamity ; and, besides, I could not help sharing
					in your feeling. For even the best of physicians do not at once apply the
					remedy of medicines against acute attacks of suppurating humours, but allow
					the painfulness of the inflammation, without the application of external
					medicaments, to attain some assuagement of itself.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, 29
						(63), and Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Letters</hi>, v. 16.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Now since time, which is wont to assuage all things, has intervened since the
					calamity, and your present condition seems to demand the aid of your
					friends, I have conceived it to be proper to communicate to you some words
					that can give comfort, for <pb id="v.2.p.111"/> the mitigation of grief and
					the termination of mournful and vain lamentations. For <quote rend="blockquote">Words are physicians for an ailing mind, When at the
						fitting time one soothes the heart.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Prometheus Bound</hi>, 379.</note>
               </quote> Since, according to
					the wise Euripides,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>,
						Euripides, No. 962. The last two lines are cited <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> 69 D.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">For divers ills are remedies diverse : The kindly
						speech of friends for one in grief, And admonitions when one plays the
						fool.</quote> Indeed, though there are many emotions that aifect the
					soul, yet grief, from its nature, is the most cruel of all. They say :
					<quote rend="blockquote">To many there doth come because of grief
						Insanity and ills incurable, And some for grief have ended their own
						life.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Philemon; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 512, Philemon, No.
							106, where additional lines are given.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>The pain and pang felt at the death of a son has in itself good cause to
					awaken grief, which is only natural, and over it we have no control. For I,
					for my part, cannot concur with those who extol that harsh and callous
					indifference, which is both impossible and unprofitable.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan
						Disputations</hi>, iii. 6 (12).</note> For this will rob us of the
					kindly feeling which comes from mutual affection and which above all else we
					must conserve. But to be carried beyond all bounds and to help in
					exaggerating our griefs I say is contrary to nature, and results from our
					depraved ideas. Therefore this also must be dismissed as injurious and
					depraved and most unbecoming to right-minded men, but a moderate indulgence
					<pb id="v.2.p.113"/> in grief is not to be disapproved. <q direct="unspecified">Pray
						that we be not ill,</q> says Crantor <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Philos. Graec.</hi> iii.
							p. 146; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, iii. 6
							(12).</note> of the Academy, <q direct="unspecified">but if we be ill, pray that
								sensation be left us, whether one of our members be cut off or torn
								out.</q> For this insensibility to pain <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Such Stoicism was
									required by the stricter Stoic school, but the philosophers of the
									Academy would have none of it.</note> is attained by man only at a great
					price ; for in the former case, we may suppose, it is the body which has
					been brutalized into such insensibility, but in the latter case the soul.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Reason therefore requires that men of understanding should be neither
					indifferent in such calamities nor extravagantly affected ; for the one
					course is unfeeling and brutal, the other lax and effeminate. Sensible is he
					who keeps within appropriate bounds and is able to bear judiciously both the
					agreeable and the grievous in his lot, and who has made up his mind
					beforehand to conform uncomplainingly and obediently to the dispensation of
					things ; just as in a democracy there is an allotment of offices, and he who
					draws the lot holds office, while he who fails to do so must bear his
					fortune without taking offence. For those who cannot do this would be unable
					sensibly and soberly to abide good fortune either. </p>
            <p>Among the felicitous utterances the following piece of advice is to the
					point: <quote rend="blockquote">Let no success be so unusual That it excite
						in you too great a pride, Nor abject be in turn, if ill betide ; But
						ever be the same ; preserve unchanged Your nature, like to gold when
						tried by fire.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play of Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
							Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 963.</note>
               </quote> It is the mark of
					educated and disciplined men to <pb id="v.2.p.115"/> keep the same habit of
					mind toward seeming prosperity, and nobly to maintain a becoming attitude
					toward adversity. For it is the task of rational prudence, either to be on
					guard against evil as it approaches, or, if it have already happened, to
					rectify it or to minimize it or to provide oneself with a virile and noble
					patience to endure it. For wisdom deals also with the good, in a fourfold
					way&mdash; either acquiring a store of goods, or conserving them, or
					adding to them, or using them judiciously. These are the laws of wisdom and
					of the other virtues, and they must be followed for better fortune or for
					worse. For <quote rend="blockquote">No man exists who's blest in
						everything,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Stheneboea</hi> of
							Euripides, <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> No. 661.</note>
               </quote> and
					truly <quote rend="blockquote">What thou must do cannot be made &amp;ldquo;must
						not.&amp;rdquo;
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck,
							<hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespot. No.
							368.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>For as there are in plants at one time seasons of fruitage and at another
					time seasons of unfruitfulness, and in animals at one time fecundity and at
					another time barrenness, and on the sea both fair weather and storm, so also
					in life many diverse circumstances occur which bring about a reversal of
					human fortunes. As one contemplates these reversals he might say not
					inappropriately : <quote rend="blockquote">Not for good and no ill came thy
						life from thy sire, Agamemnon, but joy Thou shalt find interwoven with
						grief; For a mortal thou art. Though against thy desire Yet the plans of
						the gods will so have it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Iphigenia
							at Aulis</hi>, 29; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 33
							E.</note>
               </quote> and the words of Menander <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 155,
								No. 531, and Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi> (in L.C.L.), p.
								478.</note>: <pb id="v.2.p.117"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">If you alone, young master, at your birth Had
						gained the right to do whate'er you would Throughout your life, and ever
						be in luck, And if some god agreed to this with you, Then you have right
						to feel aggrieved. He has Deceived and strangely treated you. But if
						Upon the selfsame terms as we, you drew The primal breath of universal
						life (To speak you somewhat in the tragic style), You must endure this
						better, and use sense. To sum up all I say, you are a man, Than which no
						thing that lives can swifter be Exalted high and straight brought low
						again. And rightly so; for though of puny frame, He yet doth handle many
						vast affairs, And, falling, ruins great prosperity. But you, young
						master, have not forfeited Surpassing good, and these your present ills
						But moderate are ; so bear without excess What Fortune may hereafter
						bring to you.</quote> But, in spite of this condition of affairs, some
					persons, through their foolishness, are so silly and conceited, that, when
					only a little exalted, either because of abundance of money, or importance
					of office, or petty political preferments, or because of position and
					repute, they threaten and insult those in lower station, not bearing in mind
					the uncertainty and inconstancy of fortune, nor yet the fact that the lofty
					is easily brought low and the humble in turn is exalted, transposed by the
					swift-moving changes of fortune. Therefore to try to find any constancy in
					what is inconstant is a trait of people who do not rightly reason about the
					circumstances of life. For <pb id="v.2.p.119"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">The wheel goes round, and of the rim now one And
						now another part is at the top.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. p.
							740.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Reason is the best remedy for the cure of grief, reason and the preparedness
					through reason for all the changes of life. For one ought to realize, not
					merely that he himself is mortal by nature, but also that he is allotted to
					a life that is mortal and to conditions which readily reverse themselves.
					For men's bodies are indeed mortal, lasting but a day, and mortal is all
					that they experience and suffer, and, in a word, everything in life ; and
					all this <quote rend="blockquote">May not be escaped nor avoided by
						mortals<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xii.
							326.</note>
               </quote> at all, but <quote rend="blockquote">The depths of
								unseen Tartarus hold you fast by hardforged necessities,</quote> as
					Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 207 (ed. Christ).</note>
					says. Whence Demetrius of Phalerum was quite right when, in reference to a
					saying of Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 558.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">Wealth is inconstant, lasting but a
						day,</quote> and also : <quote rend="blockquote">Small things may cause
							an overthrow ; one day Puts down the mighty and exalts the low,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See
								note <hi rend="italics">a</hi> on next page.</note>
               </quote> he said
					that it was almost all admirably put, but it would have been better if he
					had said not <q direct="unspecified">one day,</q> but <q direct="unspecified">one second of
						time.</q>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.121"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Alike the cycle of earth's fruitful plants And
						mortal men. For some life grows apace, While others perish and are
						gathered home.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Both this and the preceding quotation are from the
							<hi rend="italics">Ino</hi> of Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
							Euripides, Nos. 420 and 415, where additional lines are
							given.</note>
               </quote> And elsewhere Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Pyth.</hi> viii. 135.</note> says : Somebody? Nobody? Which is
					which ? A dream of a shadow is man. Very vividly and skilfully did he use
					this extravagance of expression in making clear the life of mankind. For
					what is feebler than a shadow ? And a dream of it!&mdash;that is
					something which defies any clear description. In similar strain Crantor,
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag.
						Philos. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 147.</note> endeavouring to comfort
					Hippocles upon the death of his children, says : <q direct="unspecified">All our ancient
						philosophy states this and urges it upon us ; and though there be
						therein other things which we do not accept, yet at any rate the
						statement that life is oftentimes toilsome and hard is only too true.
						For even if it is not so by nature, yet through our own selves it has
						reached this state of corruption. From a distant time, yes from the
						beginning, this uncertain fortune has attended us and to no good end,
						and even at our birth there is conjoined with us a portion of evil in
						everything. For the very seed of our life, since it is mortal,
						participates in this causation, and from this there steal upon us
						defectiveness of soul, diseases of body, loss of friends by death, and
						the common portion of mortals.</q> For what reason have we turned
					our thoughts in this direction? It is that we may know that misfortune is
					nothing novel for man, but that we all have <pb id="v.2.p.123"/> had the
					same experience of it. For Theophrastus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 73 (ed. Wimmer).</note>
					says : <q direct="unspecified">Fortune is heedless, and she has a wonderful power to take
						away the fruits of our labours and to overturn our seeming tranquillity,
						and for doing this she has no fixed season.</q> These matters, and
					others like them, it is easy for each man to reason out for himself, and to
					learn them from wise men of old besides ; of whom the first is the divine
					Homer, who said <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xviii. 130.</note>: <quote rend="blockquote">Nothing more wretched than man doth the earth support
						on its bosom, Never, he says to himself, shall he suffer from evil
						hereafter, Never, so long as the gods give him strength and his knees
						are still nimble; Then when the blessed gods bring upon him grievous
						affliction, Still he endures his misfortune, reluctant but steadfast in
						spirit.</quote> And: <quote rend="blockquote">Such is the mood of the
							men who here on the earth are abiding, E'en as the day which the father
							of men and of gods brings upon them.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>
								xviii. 136.</note>
               </quote> And in another place : <quote rend="blockquote">Great-hearted son of Tydeus, why do you ask of my
									fathers ? As is the race of the leaves, such too is that of all mortals.
									Some of the leaves doth the wind scatter earthward, and others the
									forest Budding puts forth in profusion, and springtime is coming upon
									us. Thus is man's race: one enters on life, and another's life
									ceases.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 145.</note>
               </quote>
					That he has admirably made use of this image of human life is clear from
					what he says in another place, in these words : <pb id="v.2.p.125"/> To
					fight for the sake of mortals <quote rend="blockquote">Wretched, who like to
						the leaves, at the one time all ardent Come to their fitting perfection,
						and eat of the fruit of their acres; Then again helpless they perish,
						nor is there aught that can help them.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>
							xxi. 463.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>Pausanias, king of the Lacedaemonians, who persistently boasted of his own
					exploits, mockingly urged the lyric poet Simonides to rehearse for him some
					wise saying, whereupon the poet, being fully cognizant of his conceit,
					advised him to remember that he was only human.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, ix.
						21.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>Philip, the king of the Macedonians, happened to have three pieces of good
					news reported to him all at once : the first, that he was victor at the
					Olympic games in the race of the four-horse chariots ; the second, that
					Parmenio, his general, had vanquished the Dardanians in battle, and the
					third, that Olympias had borne him a male child ; whereupon, stretching out
					his hands toward the heavens, he said: <q direct="unspecified">O God, offset all this by
						some moderate misfortune !</q> For he well knew that in cases of
					great prosperity fortune is wont to be jealous.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.
						Moralia</hi> 177 C and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
							Alexander</hi>, chap. iii. (p. 666 A).</note>
				        </p>
            <p>While Theramenes, who afterwards became one of the Thirty Tyrants at Athens,
					was dining with several others, the house, in which they were, collapsed,
					and he was the only one to escape death ; but as he was being congratulated
					by everybody, he raised his voice and exclaimed in a loud tone, <q direct="unspecified">O
						Fortune, for what occasion are you reserving me ?</q> And not long
					afterward he came to his end by torture at the hands of his fellow
					tyrants.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">He was condemned to drink hemlock, according to the usual
						tradition; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, ii. 3. 54-56, and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia
							Historia</hi>, ix. 21.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.127"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>The Poet <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 522; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 20 F
					and 22 B.</note> is regarded as extraordinarily successful in bestowing
					consolation, where he represents Achilles as speaking to Priam, who has come
					to ransom Hector, as follows : <quote rend="blockquote">Come then and rest
						on a seat; let us suffer our sorrows to slumber Quietly now in our
						bosoms, in spite of our woeful afflictions ; Nothing is ever
						accomplished by yielding to chill lamentation. Thus, then, the gods have
						spun the fate of unhappy mortals, Ever to live in distress, but
						themselves are free from all trouble. Fixed on Zeus' floor two massive
						urns stand for ever, Filled with gifts of all ills that he gives, and
						another <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Such is the meaning of the passage as here quoted from
							Homer; but in two other places (<hi rend="italics">De audiendis
								poetis</hi>, 24 B, and <hi rend="italics">De exilio</hi>, 600 D)
							Plutarch follows Plato (<hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, p. 379 D),
							who wrote <foreign lang="greek">khrw=n e)/mpleioi, o( me\n e)sqlw=n
								au)tar o( deilw=n</foreign>, thus making one urn of evil and one
							of good. Metrical considerations make it more than probable that the
							line found in Plato was not taken from Homer, but it is only fair to
							say that these considerations could have had no weight with
							Plutarch.</note> of blessings ; He on whom Zeus, god of thunder,
						bestows their contents commingled Sometimes meets with the good, and
						again he meets only with evil. Him upon whom he bestows what is baneful
						he makes wholly wretched ; Ravenous hunger drives him o'er the earth's
						goodly bosom, Hither and thither he goes, unhonoured of gods or of
						mortals.</quote> Hesiod, who, although he proclaimed himself the
					disciple of the Muses, is nevertheless second to Homer in reputation as well
					as in time, also confines the evils in a great urn and represents Pandora as
					opening it and scattering the host of them over the whole land and sea. His
					words <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 94; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 115 A and 127
						D.</note> are as follows : <quote rend="blockquote">Then with her hands
							did the woman, uplifting the urn's massive cover, Let them go as they
							would ; and on men she brought woeful afflictions. <pb id="v.2.p.129"/>
							Hope alone where it was, with its place of abode yet undamaged, Under
							the rim of the urn still tarried ; nor into the open Winged its way
							forth; for before it escaped she had put on the cover. More are the woes
							unnumbered among men now freely ranging. Full is the land now of evils,
							and full of them too is the ocean ; Illnesses come upon men in the
							daytime, and others at nighttime ; Hither and thither they go, of
							themselves bringing evils to mortals ; Silent they go, since the wisdom
							of Zeus has deprived them of voices.</quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Closely allied with this are the following words of the comic poet
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Philemon, in the <hi rend="italics">Sardius; cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 497, Philemon, No.
						73.</note> spoken with reference to those whose grief over such
					calamities is excessive : If only tears were remedy for ills, And he who
					weeps obtained surcease of woe, Then we should purchase tears by giving
					gold. But as it is, events that come to pass, My master, do not mind nor
					heed these things, But, whether you shed tears or not, pursue The even tenor
					of their way. What then Do we accomplish by our weeping ? Naught. But as the
					trees have fruit, grief has these tears. And Dictys, who is trying to
					console Dana&euml; in her excessive grief, says : <quote rend="blockquote">Think you that Hades minds your moans at all, And will
						send back your child if you will groan ? Desist. By viewing close your
						neighbour's ills You might be more composed,&mdash;if you reflect
						How many mortals have to toil in bonds, <pb id="v.2.p.131"/> How many
						reft of children face old age, And others still who from a prosperous
						reign Sink down to nothing. This you ought to heed.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Dictys</hi> of Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>,
							Euripides, No. 332.</note>
               </quote> For he bids her to think of the
					lot of those who are equally unfortunate or even more unfortunate than
					herself, with the idea that her grief will be lightened. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>In this connexion might be adduced the utterance of Socrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not
					original with Socrates, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Herodotus, vii. 152;
					attributed to Solon by Valerius Maximus, vii. 2, ext. 2.</note> which
					suggests that if we were all to bring our misfortunes into a common store,
					so that each person should receive an equal share in the distribution, the
					majority would be glad to take up their own and depart. </p>
            <p>The poet Antimachus, also, employed a similar method. For after the death of
					his wife, Lyde, whom he loved very dearly, he composed, as a consolation for
					his grief, the elegy called Lyde, in which he enumerated the misfortunes of
					the heroes, and thus made his own grief less by means of others' ills. So it
					is clear that he who tries to console a person in grief, and demonstrates
					that the calamity is one which is common to many, and less than the
					calamities which have befallen others, changes the opinion of the one in
					grief and gives him a similar conviction&mdash; that his calamity is
					really less than he supposed it to be. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Aeschylus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Aeschylus, No. 353.</note>
					seems admirably to rebuke those who think that death is an evil. He says :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Men are not right in hating Death, which is The
						greatest succour from our many ills.</quote> In imitation of Aeschylus
					some one else has said : <pb id="v.2.p.133"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">O Death, healing physician, come.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Somewhat
						similar to a line from the <hi rend="italics">Philoctetes</hi> of
						Aeschylus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Aeschylus, No. 255.</note>
               </quote> For
					it is indeed true that <quote rend="blockquote">A harbour from all distress
						is Hades.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No.
							369.</note>
               </quote> For it is a magnificent thing to be able to say
					with undaunted conviction : <quote rend="blockquote">What man who recks not
						death can be a slave?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play of Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
							Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 958, and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 34 B.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">With Hades' help shadows I do not fear.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
								Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No. 370.</note>
               </quote> For what is there
					cruel or so very distressing in being dead ? It may be that the phenomenon
					of death, from being too familiar and natural to us, seems somehow, under
					changed circumstances, to be painful, though I know not why. For what wonder
					if the separable be separated, if the soluble be dissolved, if the
					combustible be consumed, and the corruptible be corrupted ? For at what time
					is death not existent in our very selves ? As Heracleitus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der
						Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 95, No. 88.</note> says : <q direct="unspecified">Living
							and dead are potentially the same thing, and so too waking and sleeping,
							and young and old ; for the latter revert to the former, and the former
							in turn to the latter.</q> For as one is able from the same clay to
					model figures of living things and to obliterate them, and again to model
					and obliterate, and alternately to repeat these operations without ceasing,
					so Nature, using the same material, a long time ago raised up our
					forefathers, and then in close succession to them created our fathers, and
					then ourselves, and <pb id="v.2.p.135"/> later will create others and still
					others in a neverending cycle ; and the stream of generation, thus flowing
					onward perpetually, will never stop, and so likewise its counterpart,
					flowing in the opposite direction&mdash;which is the stream of
					destruction, whether it be designated by the poets as Acheron or as Cocytus.
					The same agency which at the first showed us the light of the sun brings
					also the darkness of Hades. May not the air surrounding us serve to
					symbolize this, causing as it does day and night alternately, which bring us
					life and death, and sleep and waking ? Wherefore it is said that life is a
					debt to destiny, the idea being that the loan which our forefathers
					contracted is to be repaid by us. This debt we ought to discharge cheerfully
					and without bemoaning whenever the lender asks for payment; for in this way
					we should show ourselves to be most honourable men. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>I imagine also that it was because Nature saw the indefiniteness and the
					brevity of life that she caused the time allowed us before death to be kept
					from us. And it is better so; for if we knew this beforehand, some persons
					would be utterly wasted by griefs before their time, and would be dead long
					before they died. Observe too the painfulness of life, and the exhaustion
					caused by many cares ; if we should wish to enumerate all these, we should
					too readily condemn life, and we should confirm the opinion which now
					prevails in the minds of some that it is better to be dead than to live.
					Simonides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii.,
						Simonides, No. 39.</note> at any rate says : <quote rend="blockquote">Petty indeed is men's strength ; All their strivings are vain ; Toil
							upon toil in a life of no length. <pb id="v.2.p.137"/> Death hovers over
							them all, Death which is foreordained. Equal the share by the brave is
							attained In death with the base.</quote> And Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Pyth.</hi>iii. 82; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Homer,
								<hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 527, quoted <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> 105 C.</note> says : <quote rend="blockquote">A pair of
									miseries with each good The deathless gods mete out to mortal man. The
									foolish cannot bear them as they should.</quote> And Sophocles
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">T.G.F.</hi>, Sophocles, No. 761.</note> says : <quote rend="blockquote">Mourn you a mortal if he's passed away, Not knowing if
						the future brings him gain ?</quote> And Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Alcestis</hi>, 780.</note> says : <quote rend="blockquote">Know you the nature of this mortal world ? I wot not.
							For whence could you ? But hear me. By all mankind is owed a debt to
							death, And not a single man can be assured If he shall live throughout
							the coming day. For Fortune's movements are inscrutable.</quote> Since,
					then, the life of men is such as these poets say it is, surely it is more
					fitting to felicitate those who have been released from their servitude in
					it than to pity them and bewail them, as the majority do through ignorance.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Socrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, p. 40 C.</note> said
					that death resembles either a very deep sleep or a long and distant journey,
					or, thirdly, a sort of destruction and extinction of both the body and the
					soul, but that by no one of these possibilities is it an evil. Each of these
					conceptions he pursued further, and the first one first. For if <pb id="v.2.p.139"/> death is a sleep, and there is nothing evil in the
					state of those who sleep, it is evident that there is likewise nothing evil
					in the state of those who are dead. Nay, what need is there even to state
					that the deepest sleep is indeed the sweetest ? For the fact is of itself
					patent to all men, and Homer <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xiii.
						80.</note> bears witness by saying regarding it: <quote rend="blockquote">Slumber the deepest and sweetest, and nearest to death
							in its semblance.</quote> In another place <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiv. 231.</note> also he says : <quote rend="blockquote">Here she chanced to encounter the brother of Death, which is
								Slumber,</quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Slumber and Death, the
									twin brothers,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 672,
										682.</note>
               </quote> thereby indicating their similarity in appearance,
					for twins show most similarity. And again somewhere <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 241.</note> he says that death is a <q direct="unspecified">brazen
						sleep,</q> in allusion to our insensibility in it. And not
					inelegantly did the man <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mnesimachus. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Kock,
						<hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 422, Mnesimachus, No.
						11. Initiation into the lesser mysteries (celebrated at Agrae, near
						Athens, in March) was required before one could be admitted to the great
						Eleusinian festival in September.</note> seem to put the case who called
					<q direct="unspecified">sleep the Lesser Mysteries of death</q>; for sleep is really
					a preparatory rite for death. Very wise was the remark of the cynic
					Diogenes, who, when he had sunk into slumber and was about to depart this
					life, was roused by his physician, who inquired if anything distressed him.
					<q direct="unspecified">Nothing,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">for the one brother merely
						forestalls the other.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> a similar
							remark attributed to Gorgias of Leontini in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, ii. 35.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>If death indeed resembles a journey, even so <pb id="v.2.p.141"/> it is not
					an evil. On the contrary, it may even be a good. For to pass one's time
					unenslaved by the flesh and its emotions, by which the mind is distracted
					and tainted with human folly, would be a blessed piece of good fortune.
					<q direct="unspecified">For the body,</q> says Plato, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, p. 66 B.</note>
					          <q direct="unspecified">in countless ways leaves us no leisure because of its necessary care
						and feeding. Moreover, if any diseases invade it, they hinder our
						pursuit of reality, and it fills us with lusts and desires and fears and
						all manner of fancies and folly, so that, as the saying goes, because of
						it we really have no opportunity to think seriously of anything. It is a
						fact that wars and strifes and battles are brought about by nothing else
						except the body and its desires ; for all wars are waged for the
						acquisition of property, and property we are forced to acquire because
						of the body, since we are slaves in its service ; and the result is
						that, because of these things, we have no leisure for study. And the
						worst of all is, that even if we do gain some leisure from the demands
						of the body, and turn to the consideration of some subject, yet at every
						point in our investigation the body forces itself in, and causes tumult
						and confusion, and disconcerts us, so that on account of it we are
						unable to discern the truth. Nay, the fact has been thoroughly
						demonstrated to us that, if we are ever going to have any pure
						knowledge, we must divest ourselves of the body, and with the soul
						itself observe the realities. And, as it appears, we shall possess what
						we desire and what we profess to long for&mdash;and that is
						wisdom&mdash;only, as our reasoning shows, after we are dead, but
						not <pb id="v.2.p.143"/> while we are alive. For if it is impossible in
						company with the body to have any pure knowledge, then one of two things
						is true : either it is not possible to attain knowledge anywhere, or
						else only after death. For then the soul will be quite by itself,
						separate from the body, but before that time never. And so, while we
						live, we shall, as it appears, be nearest to knowledge if, as far as
						possible, we have no association or communion with the body, except such
						as absolute necessity requires, and if we do not taint ourselves with
						its nature, but keep ourselves pure of it until such time as God himself
						shall release us. And thus, being rid of the irrationality of the body,
						we shall, in all likelihood, be in the company of others in like state,
						and we shall behold with our own eyes the pure and absolute, which is
						the truth ; since for the impure to touch the pure may well be against
						the divine ordinance.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>So, even if it be likely that death transports us into another place, it is
					not an evil ; for it may possibly prove to be a good, as Plato has shown.
					Wherefore very wonderful were the words which Socrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, p. 29 A.</note> uttered before his
					judges, to this effect: <q direct="unspecified">To be afraid of death, Sirs, is nothing else
						than to seem to be wise when one is not; for it is to seem to know what
						one does not know. For in regard to death nobody knows even whether it
						happens to be for mankind the greatest of all good things, yet they fear
						it as if they knew well that it is the greatest of evils.</q> From
					this view it seems that the poet does not dissent who says : <pb id="v.2.p.145"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Let none fear death, which is release from
						toils,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No.
							371.</note>
               </quote> &mdash;ay, and from the greatest of evils as
					well. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>It is said that the Deity also bears witness to this. For tradition tells us
					that many for their righteousness have gained this gift from the gods. Most
					of these I shall pass over, having regard to due proportion in my
					composition; but I shall mention the most conspicuous, whose story is on the
					lips of all men. </p>
            <p>First I shall relate for you the tale of Cleobis and Biton, the Argive
					youths.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>Herodotus, i. 31, and
						Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, Frag. in vol. vii. p. 126
						Bernardakis.</note> They say that their mother was priestess of Hera,
					and when the time had come for her to go up to the temple, and the mules
					that always drew her wagon were late in arriving, and the hour was pressing,
					these young men put themselves to the wagon and drew their mother to the
					temple ; and she, overjoyed at the devotion of her sons, prayed that the
					best boon that man can receive be given them by the goddess. They then lay
					down to sleep and never arose again, the goddess granting them death as a
					reward for their devotion. </p>
            <p>Of Agamedes and Trophonius, Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Frag.</hi> 2
					of Pindar (ed. Christ).</note> says that after building the temple at
					Delphi they asked Apollo for a reward, and he promised them to make payment
					on the seventh day, bidding them in the meantime to eat, drink, and be
					merry. They did what was commanded, and on the evening of the seventh day
					lay down to sleep and their life came to an end. </p>
            <p>It is said that Pindar himself enjoined upon the <pb id="v.2.p.147"/>
					deputies of the Boeotians who were sent to consult the god that they should
					inquire, <q direct="unspecified">What is the best thing for mankind ?</q> and the
					prophetic priestess made answer, that he himself could not be ignorant of it
					if the story which had been written about Trophonius and Agamedes were his ;
					but if he desired to learn it by experience, it should be made manifest to
					him within a short time. As a result of this inquiry Pindar inferred that he
					should expect death, and after a short time his end came. </p>
            <p>They say that the following incident happened to the Italian
					Euthyno&uuml;s.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story comes from Crantor's <hi rend="italics">Consolatio</hi>, according to Cicero.</note> He was
					the son of Elysius, of Terina, a man foremost among the people there in
					virtue, wealth, and repute, and Euthyno&uuml;s came to his end suddenly
					from some unknown cause. Now it occurred to Elysius, as it might have
					occurred to anybody else, that his son had perhaps died of poisoning; for he
					was his only heir to a large property and estate. Being in perplexity as to
					how he might put his suspicions to the test, he visited a place where the
					spirits of the dead are conjured up, and having offered the preliminary
					sacrifice prescribed by custom, he lay down to sleep in the place, and had
					this vision. It seemed that his own father came to him, and that on seeing
					his father he related to him what had happened touching his son, and begged
					and besought his help to discover the man who was responsible for his son's
					death. And his father said, <q direct="unspecified">It is for this that I am come. Take from
						this person here what he brings for you, and from this you will learn
						about everything over which you are now grieving.</q> The person
					whom he indicated was a young man who followed him, resembling his son
					Euthyno&uuml;s and close to him in years and stature. <pb id="v.2.p.149"/> So Elysius asked who he was ; and he said, <q direct="unspecified">I am the ghost of your
						son,</q> and with these words he handed him a paper. This Elysius
					opened and saw written there these three lines : <quote rend="blockquote">Verily somehow the minds of men in ignorance wander; Dead now
						Euthyno&uuml;s lies ; destiny so has decreed. Not for himself was it
						good that he live, nor yet for his parents.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Philos. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 148; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan
							Disputations,</hi> i. 48 (115).</note>
               </quote> Such, you
					observe, is the purport of the tales recorded in ancient writers. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>If, however, death is really a complete destruction and dissolution of both
					body and soul (for this was the third of Socrates' conjectures), even so it
					is not an evil. For, according to him, there ensues a sort of insensibility
					and a liberation from all pain and anxiety. For just as no good can attach
					to us in such a state, so also can no evil; for just as the good, from its
					nature, can exist only in the case of that which is and has substantiality,
					so it is also with the evil. But in the case of that which is not, but has
					been removed from the sphere of being, neither of them can have any real
					existence. Now those who have died return to the same state in which they
					were before birth ; therefore, as nothing was either good or evil for us
					before birth, even so will it be with us after death. And just as all events
					before our lifetime were nothing to us, even so will all events subsequent
					to our lifetime be nothing to us. For in reality <pb id="v.2.p.151"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">No suffering affects the dead,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Philoctetes</hi> of Aeschylus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>,
						Aeschylus, No. 255.</note>
               </quote> since <quote rend="blockquote">Not to be born I count the same as death.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Trojan Women</hi>, 636.</note>
               </quote> For the
					condition after the end of life is the same as that before birth. But do you
					imagine that there is a difference between not being born at all, and being
					born and then passing away? Surely not, unless you assume also that there is
					a difference in a house or a garment of ours after its destruction, as
					compared with the time when it had not yet been fashioned. But if there is
					no difference in these cases, it is evident that there is no difference in
					the case of death, either, as compared with the condition before birth.
					Arcesilaus puts the matter neatly : <q direct="unspecified">This that we call an evil,
						death, is the only one of the supposed evils which, when present, has
						never caused anybody any pain, but causes pain when it is not present
						but merely expected.</q> As a matter of fact, many people, because
					of their utter fatuity and their false opinion regarding death, die in their
					effort to keep from dying.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 107, A <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note> Excellently does
					Epicharmus<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 122.</note>
					put it: <quote rend="blockquote">To be and not to be hath been his
						fate;</quote> once more <quote rend="blockquote">Gone is he whence he
							came, earth back to earth, The soul on high. What here is evil ?
							Naught.</quote> Cresphontes in some play of Euripides,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <hi rend="italics">Cresphontes; cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
								Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 450.</note> speaking of Heracles,
					says : <quote rend="blockquote">For if he dwells beneath the depths of earth
						'Mid lifeless shades, his vigour would be naught.</quote>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.153"/> This you might rewrite and say, <quote rend="blockquote">For if he dwells beneath the depths of earth 'Mid
						lifeless shades, his dolour would be naught.</quote> Noble also is the
					Spartan song<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi>iii. p.
						662.</note>: <quote rend="blockquote">Here now are we ; before us others
							throve, and others still straightway, But we shall never live to see
							their day ;</quote> and again : <quote rend="blockquote">Those who have
								died and who counted no honour the living or dying, Only to consummate
								both nobly were honour for them.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iii.
									p. 516; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pelopidas</hi>. chap. i. (p. 278 A).</note>
               </quote>
					Excellently does Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Suppliants</hi>,
						1109.</note> say of those who patiently endure long illnesses : <quote rend="blockquote">I hate the men who would prolong their lives By foods
							and drinks and charms of magic art, Perverting nature's course to keep
							off death ; They ought, when they no longer serve the land, To quit this
							life, and clear the way for youth.</quote> And Merope <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Referred to
								the <hi rend="italics">Cresphontes</hi> of Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>,
								Euripides, No. 454.</note> stirs the theatres by expressing manly
					sentiments when she speaks the following words : <quote rend="blockquote">Not mine the only children who have died, Nor I the only woman robbed
						of spouse ; Others as well as I have drunk life's dregs.</quote> With
					this the following might be appropriately combined : <pb id="v.2.p.155"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Where now are all those things magnificentGreat
						Croesus, lord of Lydia ? Xerxes, too, Who yoked the sullen neck of
						Hellespont ? Gone all to Hades and Oblivion's house,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author
							unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
								Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No. 372, and Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p.
							739.</note>
               </quote> and their wealth perished with their bodies. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">True,</q> it may be said, <q direct="unspecified">but an untimely death moves
					most people to mourning and lamentation.</q> Yet, even for this,
					words of consolation are so readily found that they have been perceived by
					even uninspired poets, and comfort has been had from them. Observe what one
					of the comic poets <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 429, Adespota, No.
						116.</note> says on this subject to a man who is grieving for an
					untimely death : <quote rend="blockquote">Then if you knew that, had he
						lived this life, Which he did not live, Fate had favoured him, His death
						was not well timed ; but if again This life had brought some ill
						incurable, Then Death perhaps were kindlier than you.</quote> Since,
					then, it is uncertain whether or not it was profitable for him that he
					rested from his labours, forsaking this life and released from greater ills,
					we ought not to bear it so grievously as though we had lost all that we
					thought we should gain from him. Not ill considered, evidently, is the
					comfort which Amphiaraus in the poem offers to the mother of Archemorus, who
					is greatly affected because her son came to his end in his infancy long
					before his time. For he says : <quote rend="blockquote">There is no man that
						does not suffer ill; Man buries children, and begets yet more, <pb id="v.2.p.157"/> And dies himself. Men are distressed at this,
						Committing earth to earth. But Fate decrees That life be garnered like
						the ripened grain, That one shall live and one shall pass from life.
						What need to grieve at this, which Nature says Must be the constant
						cycle of all life ? In what must be there's naught that man need
						dread.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Hypsipyle</hi> of Euripides;
							<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
								Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 757.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>In general everyone ought to hold the conviction, if he seriously reviews the
					facts both by himself and in the company of another, that not the longest
					life is the best, but the most efficient. For it is not the man who has
					played the lyre the most, or made the most speeches, or piloted the most
					ships, who is commended, but he who has done these things excellently.
					Excellence is not to be ascribed to length of time, but to worth and timely
					fitness. For these have come to be regarded as tokens of good fortune and of
					divine favour. It is for this reason, at any rate, that the poets have
					traditionally represented those of the heroes who were preeminent and sprung
					from the gods as quitting this life before old age, like him Who to the
					heart of great Zeus and Apollo was held to be dearest, Loved with exceeding
					great love ; but of eld he reached not the threshold.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xv. 245.</note> For we everywhere observe
					that it is a happy use of opportunity, rather than a happy old age, that
					wins the highest place.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Marcus Antoninus,
						24. 1, and Seneca, <hi rend="italics">Epist.</hi> 93. 2.</note> For of
					trees and plants the best are those that in a brief time produce the most
					crops of fruit, and the best of animals are those from which in no long time
					we have the greatest service toward our livelihood. The terms <q direct="unspecified">long
					</q> and <q direct="unspecified">short</q> obviously appear to lose their
					difference if we fix <pb id="v.2.p.159"/> our gaze on eternity. For a
					thousand or ten thousand years, according to Simonides, are but a vague
					second of time, or rather the smallest fraction of a second. Take the case
					of those creatures which they relate exist on the shores of the Black
					Sea,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Hist. animal.</hi> v. 19. 3f.
						(copied by Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, xi. 36 (43)).
						<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De nat.
							animal.</hi> v. 43; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan
								Disputations</hi>, i. 39 (94).</note> and have an existence of only
					one day, being born in the morning, reaching the prime of life at mid-day,
					and toward evening growing old and ending their existence ; would there not
					be in those creatures this same feeling which prevails with us, if each of
					them had within him a human soul and power to reason, and would not the same
					relative conditions obviously obtain there, so that those who departed this
					life before mid-day would cause lamentation and tears, while those who lived
					through the day would be accounted altogether happy ? The measure of life is
					its excellence, not its length in years. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>We must regard as vain and foolish such exclamations as these : <q direct="unspecified">But
					he ought not to have been snatched away while young !</q> For who
					may say what ought to be ? Many other things, of which one may say <q direct="unspecified">
						they ought not to have been done,</q> have been done, and are done,
					and will be done over and over again. For we have come into this world, not
					to make laws for its governance, but to obey the commandments of the gods
					who preside over the universe, and the decrees of Fate or Providence. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>But do those who mourn for the untimely dead, mourn on their own account or
					on account of the departed ? If on their own account, because they have been
					cut off from some gratification or profit or comfort in old age, which they
					might have expected from the dead, then is their excuse for grieving wholly
					<pb id="v.2.p.161"/> selfish; for it will be plain that they mourn, not
					for them, but for their services. But if they mourn on account of the dead,
					then if they will fix their attention on the fact that the dead are in no
					evil state, they will rid themselves of grief by following that wise and
					ancient admonition to magnify the good and to minimize and lessen the evil.
					If, then, mourning is a good, we ought to enlarge and magnify it in every
					way. But if, as the truth is, we admit it to be an evil, we ought to
					minimize and reduce it, and as far as possible to efface it. </p>
            <p>That this is easy is plainly to be seen from the following sort of
					consolation. They say that one of the ancient philosophers visited
					Arsino&euml;, the queen, who was mourning for her son, and made use of
					this story,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi> 609 F, where the idea
						is attributed to Aesop.</note> saying that at the time Zeus was
					distributing to the deities their honours. Mourning did not happen to be
					present, but arrived after the distribution had been made. But when she said
					it was only right that some honour be given to her also, Zeus, being
					perplexed, since all the honours had been used up, finally gave her that
					honour which is paid in the case of those who have died&mdash;tears and
					griefs. Just as the other deities, therefore, are fond of those by whom they
					are honoured, so also is Mourning. <q direct="unspecified">Therefore, Madame, if you treat
						her with disrespect, she will not come near you; but if she is strictly
						honoured by you with the honours which were conceded to her, namely
						griefs and lamentations, she will love you and affectionately will be
						ever with you, provided only she be constantly honoured by you.</q>
					Admirably, it appears, he succeeded, by this story, in convincing the woman
					and in alleviating her mourning and lamentations. <pb id="v.2.p.163"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>In general one might say to the man who mourns, <q direct="unspecified">Shall you at some
					time cease to take this to heart, or shall you feel that you must grieve
					always every day of your life ? For if you purpose to remain always in
					this extreme state of affliction, you will bring complete wretchedness
					and the most bitter misery upon yourself by the ignobleness and
					cowardice of your soul. But if you intend some time to change your
					attitude, why do you not change it at once and extricate yourself from
					this misfortune ? Give attention now to those arguments by the use of
					which, as time goes on, your release shall be accomplished, and relieve
					yourself now of your sad condition. For in the case of bodily
					afflictions the quickest way of relief is the better. Therefore concede
					now to reason and education what you surely will later concede to time,
					and release yourself from your troubles.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">But I cannot,</q> he says, <q direct="unspecified">for I never expected or looked
					for this experience.</q> But you ought to have looked for it, and to
					have previously pronounced judgement on human affairs for their uncertainty
					and fatuity, and then you would not now have been taken off your guard as by
					enemies suddenly come upon you. Admirably does Theseus in Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In
						an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> Euripides, No. 964 D; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the translation by Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan
							Disputations</hi>, iii. 14 (29).</note> appear to have prepared
					himself for such crises, for he says : <quote rend="blockquote">But I have
						learned this from a certain sage, And on these cares and troubles set my
						mind, And on myself laid exile from my land And early deaths and other
						forms of ills, <pb id="v.2.p.165"/> That if I suffer aught my fancy saw,
						It should not, coming newly, hurt the more.</quote> But the more ignoble
					and untutored sometimes cannot even recall themselves to the consideration
					of anything seemly and profitable, but go out of their way to find extremes
					of wretchedness, even to punishing their innocent body and to forcing the
					unafflicted, as Achaeus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
						Frag.</hi> p. 757, Achaeus, No. 45.</note> says, to join in their
					grief. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Wherefore very excellently Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from the <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, p. 604 B.</note> appears to advise us
					<q direct="unspecified">in</q> such <q direct="unspecified">misfortunes to maintain a calm demeanour,
						since neither the evil nor the good in them is at all plain, and since
						no advance is made by the man who takes things much to heart. For grief
						stands in the way of sane counsel about an event and prevents one from
						arranging his affairs with relation to what has befallen, as a player
						does at a throw of the dice, in whatever way reason may convince him
						would be best. We ought not, therefore, when we have fallen to act like
						children and hold on to the injured place and scream, but we should
						accustom our soul speedily to concern itself with curing the injury and
						raising up the fallen, and we should put away lamentation by remedial
						art.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>They say that the lawgiver of the Lyclans <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
					Valerius Maximus, ii. 6. 13.</note> ordered his citizens, whenever they
					mourned, to clothe themselves first in women's garments and then to mourn,
					wishing to make it clear that mourning is womanish and unbecoming to
					decorous men who lay claim to the education of the free-born. Yes, mourning
					is verily feminine, and weak, and ignoble, since <pb id="v.2.p.167"/> women
					are more given to it than men, and barbarians more than Greeks, and inferior
					men more than better men ; and of the barbarians themselves, not the most
					noble, Celts and Galatians, and all who by nature are filled with a more
					manly spirit, but rather, if such there are, the Egyptians and Syrians and
					Lydians and all those who are like them. For it is recorded that some of
					these go down into pits and remain there for several days, not desiring even
					to behold the light of the sun since the deceased also is bereft of it. At
					any rate the tragic poet Ion,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
						Frag.</hi> p. 743, Ion, No. 54.</note> who was not without knowledge
					of the foolishness of these peoples, has represented a woman as saying :
					<quote rend="blockquote">The nurse of lusty children I have come, To
						supplicate you, from the mourning pits.</quote> And some of the
					barbarians even cut off parts of their bodies, their noses and ears, and
					mutilate other portions of their bodies also, thinking to gratify the dead
					by abandoning that moderation of feeling which Nature enjoins in such cases.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But I dare say that, in answer to this, some may assert their belief that
					there need not be mourning for every death, but only for untimely deaths,
					because of the failure of the dead to gain what are commonly held to be the
					advantages of life, such as marriage, education, manhood, citizenship, or
					public office (for these are the considerations, they say, which most cause
					grief to those who suffer misfortune through untimely deaths, since they are
					robbed of their hope out of due time) ; but they do not realize that the
					untimely death shows no disparity if it be considered with reference to the
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, Trag. Graec. Frag. p. 743, Ion, No. 54.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.169"/> common lot of man. For just as when it has been decided
					to migrate to a new fatherland, and the journey is compulsory for all, and
					none by entreaty can escape it, some go on ahead and others follow after,
					but all come to the same place; in the same manner, of all who are
					journeying toward Destiny those who come more tardily have no advantage over
					those who arrive earlier. If it be true that untimely death is an evil, the
					most untimely would be that of infants and children, and still more that of
					the newly born. But such deaths we bear easily and cheerfully, but the
					deaths of those who have already lived some time with distress and mourning
					because of our fanciful notion, born of vain hopes, since we have come to
					feel quite assured of the continued tarrying with us of persons who have
					lived so long. But if the years of man's life were but twenty, we should
					feel that he who passed away at fifteen had not died untimely, but that he
					had already attained an adequate measure of age, while the man who had
					completed the prescribed period of twenty years, or who had come close to
					the count of twenty years, we should assuredly deem happy as having lived
					through a most blessed and perfect life. But if the length of life were two
					hundred years, we should certainly feel that he who came to his end at one
					hundred was cut off untimely, and we should betake ours elves to wailing and
					lamentation. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>It is evident, therefore, that even the death which we call untimely readily
					admits of consolation, both for these reasons and for those previously
					given. For in fact Tro&iuml;lus shed fewer tears than did Priam; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A
						saying of Callimachus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 93 (39); Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 211 A.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.171"/> and if Priam had died earlier, while his kingdom and
					his great prosperity were at their height, he would not have used such sad
					words as he did in his conversation with his own son Hector, when he advised
					him to withdraw from the battle with Achilles ; he says: <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxii. 56.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Come then within the walled city, my son, so to
						save from destruction All of the men and the women of Troy, nor afford a
						great triumph Unto the offspring of Peleus, and forfeit the years of
						your lifetime. Also for me have compassion, ill-starred, while yet I
						have feeling ; Hapless I am ; on the threshold of eld will the Father,
						descended from Cronus, Make me to perish in pitiful doom, after visions
						of evils, Sons being slain and our daughters as well being dragged to be
						captives, Chambers of treasure all wantonly plundered and poor little
						children Dashed to the earth in the terrible strife by the merciless
						foeman, Wives of my sons being dragged by the ravishing hands of
						Achaeans. Me, last of all, at the very front doors shall the dogs tear
						to pieces, Ravening, eager for blood, when a foeman wielding his weapon,
						Keen-edged of bronze, by a stroke or a throw, takes the life from my
						body. Yet when the dogs bring defilement on hair and on beard that is
						hoary, And on the body as well of an old man slain by the foeman, This
						is the saddest of sights ever seen by us unhappy mortals. Thus did the
						old man speak, and his hoary locks plucked by the handful, Tearing his
						hair from his head, but he moved not the spirit of Hector.</quote> Since
					you have, then, so very many examples <pb id="v.2.p.173"/> regarding the
					matter, bear in mind the fact that death relieves not a few persons from
					great and grievous ills which, if they had lived on, they would surely have
					experienced. But, out of regard for the due proportions of my argument, I
					omit these, contenting myself with what has been said touching the
					wrongfulness of being carried away beyond natural and moderate bounds to
					futile mourning and ignoble lamentation. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Crantor <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Philor. Graec.</hi> iii. p.
					149.</note> says that not being to blame for one's unhappy state is no
					small alleviation for misfortunes ; but I should say that it surpasses all
					others as a remedy for the cure of grief. But affection and love for the
					departed does not consist in distressing ourselves, but in benefiting the
					beloved one; and a benefit for those who have been taken away is the honour
					paid to them through keeping their memory green. For no good man, after he
					is dead, is deserving of lamentations, but of hymns and songs of joy ; not
					of mourning, but of an honourable memory ; not of sorrowing tears, but of
					offerings of sacrifice,&mdash;if the departed one is now a partaker in
					some life more divine, relieved of servitude to the body, and of these
					everlasting cares and misfortunes which those who have received a mortal
					life as their portion are constrained to undergo until such time as they
					shall complete their allotted earthly existence, which Nature has not given
					to us for eternity; but she has distributed to us severally the apportioned
					amount in accordance with the laws of fate. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Wherefore, over those who die men of good sense ought not to be carried away
					by sorrow beyond the natural and moderate limit of grief, which so affects
					the soul, into useless and barbarian <pb id="v.2.p.175"/> mourning, and they
					ought not to wait for that outcome which has already been the lot of many in
					the past, the result of which is that they terminate their own lives in
					misery before they have put off their mourning, and gain nothing but a
					forlorn burial in their garments of sorrow, as their woes and the ills born
					of their unreasonableness follow them to the grave, so that one might utter
					over them the verse of Homer : <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Combined from <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiii. 109, and <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> i. 423 (=<hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xviii. 306).</note> While they were weeping
					and wailing black darkness descended upon them. </p>
            <p>We should therefore often hold converse with ourselves after this fashion and
					say : <q direct="unspecified">What ? Shall we some day cease grieving, or shall we consort
						with unceasing misery to the very end of our life ?</q> For to
					regard our mourning as unending is the mark of the most extreme foolishness,
					especially when we observe how those who have been in the deepest grief and
					greatest mourning often become most cheerful under the influence of time,
					and at the very tombs where they gave violent expression to their grief by
					wailing and beating their breasts, they arrange most elaborate banquets with
					musicians and all the other forms of diversion. It is accordingly the mark
					of a madman thus to assume that he shall keep his mourning permanently. If,
					however, men should reason that mourning will come to an end after some
					particular event, they might go on and reason that it will come to an end
					when time, forsooth, has produced some effect ; for not even God can undo
					what has been done. So, then, that which in the present instance has come to
					pass contrary to our expectation and contrary to our opinion has only
					demonstrated what is wont, through <pb id="v.2.p.177"/> the very course of
					events, to happen in the case of many men. What then ? Are we unable,
					through reason, to learn this fact and draw the conclusion, that <quote rend="blockquote">Full is the earth now of evils, and full of them too
						is the ocean,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 101;
							<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 105 E <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
               </quote> and also this : <quote rend="blockquote">Such woes of woes for mortal men, And round about the Fates throng
								close; There is no vacant pathway for the air ?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown
									lyric poet; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 689.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Not merely now, but long ago, as Crantor <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Philos. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 149.</note> says, the lot of man
					has been bewailed by many wise men, who have felt that life is a punishment
					and that for man to be born at all is the greatest calamity. Aristotle
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 48 (114), and Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> No. 44 Rose.</note> says that Silenus when
					he was captured declared this to Midas. It is better to quote the very words
					of the philosopher. He says, in the work which is entitled Eudemus, or Of
					the Soul, the following : <q direct="unspecified">' Wherefore, O best and blessedest of all,
						in addition to believing that those who have ended this life are blessed
						and happy, we also think that to say anything false or slanderous
						against them is impious, from our feeling that it is directed against
						those who have already become our betters and superiors. And this is
						such an old and ancient belief with us that no one knows at all either
						the beginning of the time or the name of the person who first
						promulgated it, but it continues to be a fixed belief for all
						time.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Antigone</hi> 466.</note>
						            <pb id="v.2.p.179"/> And in addition to this you observe how the saying,
						which is on the lips of all men, has been passed from mouth to mouth for
						many years.' ' What is this ?' said he. And the other, again taking up
						the discourse, said : ' That not to be born is the best of all, and that
						to be dead is better than to live. And the proof that this is so has
						been given to many men by the deity. So, for example, they say that
						Silenus, after the hunt in which Midas of yore had captured him, when
						Midas questioned and inquired of him what is the best thing for mankind
						and what is the most preferable of all things, was at first unwilling to
						teli, but maintained a stubborn silence. But when at last, by employing
						every device, Midas induced him to say something to him, Silenus, forced
						to speak, said : <q direct="unspecified">Ephemeral offspring of a travailing genius and
							of harsh fortune, why do you force me to speak what it were better
							for you men not to know ? For a life spent in ignorance of one's own
							woes is most free from grief. But for men it is utterly impossible
							that they should obtain the best thing of all, or even have any
							share in its nature (for the best thing for all men and women is not
							to be born) ; however, the next best thing to this, and the first of
							those to which man can attain, but nevertheless only the second
							best, is, after being born, to die as quickly as possible.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Theognis, 425; Bacchylidies, v. 160;
							Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oed. Col.</hi> 1225; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 48 (115).</note>
						It is evident, therefore, that he made this declaration with the
						conviction that the existence after death is better than that in life.'
					</q> One might cite thousands and thousands of examples under this same
					head, but there is no need to be prolix. <pb id="v.2.p.181"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>We ought not, therefore, to lament those who die young on the ground that
					they have been deprived of those things which in a long life are accounted
					good ; for this is uncertain, as we have often said&mdash;whether the
					things of which they have been deprived are good or evil; for the evils are
					much the more numerous. And whereas we acquire the good things only with
					difficulty and at the expense of many anxieties, the evils we acquire very
					easily. For they say that the latter are compact and conjoined, and are
					brought together by many influences, while the good things are disjoined,
					and hardly manage to unite towards the very end of life. We therefore
					resemble men who have forgotten, not merely, as Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from
						the <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 555.</note> says, that <quote rend="blockquote">Mortals are not the owners of their wealth,</quote>
					but also that they do not own a single one of human possessions. Wherefore
					we must say in regard to all things that <quote rend="blockquote">We keep
						and care for that which is the gods', And when they will they take it
						back again.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 556.</note>
               </quote> We
					ought not, therefore, to bear it with bad grace if the gods make demand upon
					us for what they have loaned us for a short time.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cebes, <hi rend="italics">Tabula</hi>, xxxi., and Cicero,
						<hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 39 (93).</note>
					For even the bankers, as we are in the habit of saying frequently, when
					demand is made upon them for the return of deposits, do not chafe at the
					repayment, if they be honourable men. To those who do not make repayment
					with good grace one might fairly say, <q direct="unspecified">Have you forgotten that you
						accepted this on condition that you should return it ?</q> Quite
					parallel is the lot of all mortals. For we hold our life, as it were, on
					deposit from the gods, who have compelled us to accept the account, and
					there is no fixed time for <pb id="v.2.p.183"/> its return, just as with the
					bankers and their deposits, but it is uncertain when the depositor will
					demand payment. If a man, therefore, is exceedingly indignant, either when
					he himself is about to die, or when his children have died, must he not
					manifestly have forgotten that he is but human and the father of children
					who are mortal ? For it is not characteristic of a man of sense to be
					unaware of the fact that man is a mortal creature, and that he is born to
					die. At any rate, if Niobe of the fable had had this conception ready at
					hand, that even the woman who, <quote rend="blockquote">Laden with the happy
						burden Of sweet life and growing children, Looks upon the pleasant
						sunlight,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown poet; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>
							Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No.
							373, and Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p.
							720.</note>
               </quote> must die, she would not have been so resentful
					as to wish to abandon life on account of the magnitude of her misfortune,
					and to implore the gods that she herself might be hurried to the most awful
					perdition. </p>
            <p>There are two of the inscriptions at Delphi <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
					Plato, <hi rend="italics">Protagoras</hi>, p. 343 B, and <hi rend="italics">Charmides</hi>, p. 165 A; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rheoric</hi>, ii. 12, 14; Pausanias, x. 24, 1;
					Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 167 B, 385 D, and 511 B, and
					<hi rend="italics">De vita et poesi Homeri</hi>, 151.</note> which
					are most indispensable to living. These are : <q direct="unspecified">Know thyself</q>
					and <q direct="unspecified">Avoid extremes,</q> for on these two commandments hang all
					the rest. These two are in harmony and agreement with each other, and the
					one seems to be made as clear as possible through the other. For in
					self-knowledge is included the avoidance of extremes, and in the latter is
					included self-knowledge. Therefore Ion <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
						Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 743, Ion, No. 55.</note> speaks of the former
					as follows : <quote rend="blockquote">Not much to say is &amp;ldquo;Know
						thyself&amp;rdquo; ; to do This, Zeus alone of gods doth
						understand.</quote>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.185"/> And, of the other, Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 216 (Christ).</note> says : <quote rend="blockquote">The
						wise have landed with exceeding praise the words &amp;ldquo;Avoid
							extremes.&amp;rdquo;
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>If, then, one keeps these in mind as god-given injunctions, he will be able
					easily to adapt them to all the circumstances of life, and to bear with such
					circumstances intelligently, by being heedful of his own nature, and
					heedful, in whatever may befall him, not to go beyond the limit of
					propriety, either in being elated to boastfulness or in being humbled and
					cast down to wailings and lamentations, through weakness of the spirit and
					the fear of death which is implanted in us as a result of our ignorance of
					what is wont to happen in life in accordance with the decree of necessity or
					destiny. Excellent is the advice which the Pythagoreans <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Carmina Aurea</hi>, 17.</note> gave, saying : <quote rend="blockquote">Whatsoe'er woes by the gods' dispensation all mortals
						must suffer, What be the fate you must bear, you should bear it and not
						be indignant.</quote> And the tragic poet Aeschylus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to
							Euripides by Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, cviii. 43;
							<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
								Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 1078.</note> says : <quote rend="blockquote">It is the mark of just and knowing men In woes to feel
									no anger at the gods;</quote> and Euripides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play;
										<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi>,
										Euripides, No. 965.</note>: <quote rend="blockquote">Of mortals he who
											yields to fate we think Is wise and knows the ways of Providence
											;</quote> and in another place <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Melanippe; cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi>,
												Euripides, No. 505.</note> he says : <pb id="v.2.p.187"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Of mortals he who bears his lot aright To me seems
						noblest and of soundest sense.</quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Most people grumble about everything, and have a feeling that everything
					which happens to them contrary to their expectations is brought about
					through the spite of Fortune and the divine powers. Therefore they wail at
					everything, and groan, and curse their luck. To them one might say in
					retort: <quote rend="blockquote">God is no bane to you ; 'tis you
						yourself,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Tyrannus</hi>,
							379.</note>
               </quote> you and your foolish and distorted notions due
					to your lack of education. It is because of this fallacious and deluded
					notion that men cry out against any sort of death. If a man die while on a
					journey, they groan over him and say : <quote rend="blockquote">Wretched his
						fate ; not for him shall his father or much revered mother Close his
						dear eyelids in death.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi.
							452.</note>
               </quote> But if he die in his own land with his parents
					at his bedside, they deplore his being snatched from their arms and leaving
					them the memory of the painful sight. If he die in silence without uttering
					a word about anything, they say amid their tears : <quote rend="blockquote">No, not a word did you say to me, which for the weight of its meaning
						Ever might dwell in my mind.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>xxiv. 744.</note>
               </quote> But if he talked a little at the
					time of his death, they keep his words always before their mind as a sort of
					kindling for their grief. If he die suddenly, they deplore his death,
					saying, <q direct="unspecified">He was snatched away</q> ; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, Oedipus
						Tyrannus, 379. b Homer, Il. xi. 452. c Homer, Il. xxiv. 744.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.189"/> but if he lingered long, they complain that he wasted
					away and suffered before he died. Any pretext is sufficient to arouse grief
					and lamentations. This movement the poets initiated, and especially the
					first of them, Homer,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiii. 222, and xvii. 37.</note> who says : <quote rend="blockquote">E'en as a father laments as the pyre of
						his dead son he kindles, Wedded not long; by his death he brought woe to his
						unhappy parents. Not to be told is the mourning and grief that he caused for
						his parents.</quote> And yet so far it is not evident that the father is justified
					in bewailing thus. But note this next line : <quote rend="blockquote">Only and darlingest son, who is
						heir to his many possessions.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 482.</note>
               </quote> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>For who knows but that God, having a fatherly care for the human race, and
					foreseeing future events, early removes some persons from life untimely?
					Wherefore we must believe that they undergo nothing that should be avoided.
					(For <quote rend="blockquote">In what must be, there's naught that men need dread,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Hypsipyle</hi> of Euripides, quoted <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 110 F.</note>
               </quote> nor in any of
					those events which come to pass in accordance with the postulates or the
					logical deductions of reason), both because the great majority of deaths
					forestall other and greater troubles and because it were better for some not
					to be born even, for others to die at the very moment of birth, for others
					after they have gone on in life a little way, and for still others while
					they are in their full vigour. Toward all such deaths we should maintain a
					cheerful frame of mind, since we know that we cannot escape 
					<pb id="v.2.p.191"/> destiny. It is the mark of educated men to take it for
					granted that those who seem to have been deprived of life untimely have but
					forestalled us for a brief time; for the longest life is short and momentary
					in comparison with eternity. And we know, too, that many who have protracted
					their period of mourning have, after no long time, followed their lamented
					friends, without having gained any advantage from their mourning, but only
					useless torment by their misery. </p>
            <p>Since the time of sojourn in life is very brief, we ought not, in unkempt
					grief and utterly wretched mourning, to ruin our lives by racking ourselves
					with mental anguish and bodily torments, but to turn to the better and more
					human course, by striving earnestly to converse with men who will not, for
					flattery, grieve with us and arouse our sorrows, but will endeavour to
					dispel our griefs through noble and dignified consolation. We should hearken
					to Homer and keep in mind those lines of his <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 486.</note> which Hector spoke to
					Andromache, endeavouring, in his turn, to comfort her : <quote rend="blockquote">Dearest, you seem
						much excited; be not overtroubled in spirit; No man beyond what is fated
						shall send me in death unto Hades. For not a man among mortals, I say, has
						escaped what is destined, Neither the base nor the noble, when once he has
						entered life's pathway.</quote> Of this destiny the poet elsewhere <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>xx. 128.</note> says : <quote rend="blockquote">When from
							his mother he came, in the thread of his life Fate entwined it.</quote>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.193"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Keeping these things before our mind, we shall rid ourselves of the useless
					and vain extremes of mourning, since the time remaining of our life is
					altogether short. We must therefore be chary of it, so that we may live it
					in cheerfulness of spirit and without the disturbance of mournful griefs, by
					giving up the outward signs of sorrow and by bethinking ourselves of the
					care of our bodies and the welfare of those who live with us. It is a good
					thing also to call to mind the arguments which most likely we have sometimes
					employed with relatives or friends <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, iii. 29-30 (71-74).</note> who found themselves in similar
					calamities, when we tried to comfort them and to persuade them to bear the
					usual happenings of life in the usual way and a man's lot like a man; and it
					is a good thing, too, not to put ourselves in the position of being able to
					help others to find relief from grief, but ourselves to have no profit in
					recalling the means through which we must cure the soul's
					distress&mdash;<q direct="unspecified">by healing remedies of
						reason</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Agamemnon,</hi>, 848.</note>&mdash;since we should postpone anything else rather than
					the putting aside of grief. And yet one poet <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 414.</note> says that the man who in any
					matter <q direct="unspecified">puts off till to-morrow</q> is <q direct="unspecified">wrestling with
						destruction</q>&mdash;a proverb which is repeated among all men.
					Much more, I think, is this true of the man who puts over to a future time
					the experiences which his soul finds so troublesome and so hard to face.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>It is a good thing, too, to contemplate those men who nobly and high-mindedly
					and calmly have been resigned to the deaths which have befallen their
					sons&mdash;Anaxagoras of Clazomenae, Demosthenes of Athens, Dion of
					Syracuse, King Antigonus, and very 
					<pb id="v.2.p.195"/> many others among men both of earlier times and of our
					own day. </p>
            <p>Of these, Anaxagoras,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 2; Galen, v. p. 418 (ed. Kuhn); Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, iii. 14 (30) and 24 (58); Valerius Maximus, v 10. ext. 3.</note> according to the traditional story, was talking about
					natural philosophy in conversation with his friends, when he heard from one
					of the messengers, who were sent to bring him the news, of the end which had
					befallen his son. He stopped for a moment and then said to those present,
					<q direct="unspecified">I knew that I had begotten a son who was mortal.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>Pericles,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pericles</hi>, chap. xxxvi. (p. 172 c); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, ix. 6; Valerius Maximus, v. 10, ext. 1.</note> who was called <q direct="unspecified">the Olympian</q> because of his
					surpassing power of reasoning and of understanding, learned that both his
					sons, Paralus and Xanthippus, had passed from life. Protagoras describes his
					conduct in these words : <q direct="unspecified">His sons were comely youths, but though
						they died within seven days of each other, he bore their deaths without
						repining. For he continued to hold to that serenity from which day by
						day he added greatly to his credit of being blest by Fortune and
						untroubled by sorrow, and to his high repute with the people at large.
						For each and every man, as he beheld Pericles bearing his sorrows so
						stoutly, felt that he was high-minded and manful and his own superior,
						being only too well aware of what would be his own helplessness under
						such circumstances. For Pericles, immediately after the tidings about
						his two sons, none the less placed the garland upon his head, according
						to the time-honoured custom at Athens, and, clad in garb of white,
						harangued the people, 
						<pb id="v.2.p.197"/> 'taking lead in good counsel,' <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 273.</note> and inspiriting
						the Athenians to war.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>Xenophon, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 3; Diogenes Laertius, ii. 54; Valerius Maximus, v. 10, ext. 2.</note> the follower of Socrates, was once offering sacrifice when he
					learned from the messengers who had come from the field of battle that his
					son Gryllus had met his death while fighting. He took the garland from his
					head and questioned them as to how he had died. When the messengers reported
					that he died nobly, displaying the greatest valour and after slaying many of
					the enemy, Xenophon was completely silent for a few moments while mastering
					his emotion by the power of reason, and then, replacing the gai'land, he
					completed the sacrifice, remarking to the messengers, <q direct="unspecified">I prayed to
						the gods, not that my son should be immortal or even long of life (for
						it is not clear whether it be of advantage so), but that he should be
						brave and patriotic ; and so it has come to pass.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>Dion <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Dion</hi>, chap. lv. (p. 982 c): Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 4.</note> of Syracuse was sitting in consultation with his friends, when there
					arose, in the house a commotion and a great screaming, and upon inquiring
					the cause and hearing what had happened&mdash;that his son had fallen
					from the roof and been killed&mdash;he was not at all disconcerted, but
					commanded the corpse to be given over to the women for the usual preparation
					for burial, and he himself did not leave off the discussion in which he was
					engaged. </p>
            <p>His example, they say, Demosthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, chap. xxii. (p. 855 D), and Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, iii. 26 (63).</note> the orator emulated when he lost his only
					and much-loved daughter, of whom Aeschines, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or. iii. (<hi rend="italics">Against Ctesiphon</hi>) 77 (p. 64).</note> thinking to reproach 
					<pb id="v.2.p.199"/> Demosthenes, speaks as follows : <q direct="unspecified">On the seventh
						day after his daughter's death, before he had mourned for her or
						performed the customary rites, putting on a garland and resuming his
						white apparel, he offered a sacrifice in public and violated all custom,
						when he had lost, poor wretch, his only daughter, who was the first
						child to address him as father.</q> So then Aeschines, purposing,
					after the manner of the political speaker, to reproach him, rehearsed these
					facts, being quite unaware that thereby he was really commending
					Demosthenes, who put aside his grief, and displayed his patriotism in
					preference to his feelings for his kindred. </p>
            <p>Antigonus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Antigonus Gonatas; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 5.</note> the king, on learning of the death of his son Alcyoneus, which had
					occurred in the line of battle, gazed proudly upon the messengers who had
					brought news of the calamity, and, after waiting for a moment, said, bowing
					his head, <q direct="unspecified">Not so very early, Alcyoneus, have you departed this life,
						since you always rushed so recklessly against the enemy without a
						thought either of your own safety or of my counsels.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>The whole world wonders at these men and admires them for their nobility of
					mind, but others have not the ability to imitate them in practice because of
					that weakness of spirit which results from lack of education. But although
					there are so many examples, which have been handed down to us through both
					Greek and Roman history, of men who have behaved nobly and honourably at the
					deaths of their relatives, yet what has been said will suffice to induce you
					to put aside mourning, which is the most distressing of all things, and also
					the fruit <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Antigonus Gonatas; cf. Aelian, Varia Historia, iii.
						5.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.201"/> less pain, which serves no useful purpose, involved in
					mourning. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>The fact that those who excel in virtues pass on to their fate while young,
					as though beloved of the gods, I have already called to your attention in an
					earlier part <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">111 B <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>
               </note> of my letter, and I shall endeavour at this time to touch upon
					it very briefly, merely adding my testimony to that which has been so well
					said by Menander <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Double Deceiver</hi>: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 36, Menander, No. 125, and Allinson's <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi> (L.C.L.), p. 345. The sentiment is found many times in other writers, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plautus, <hi rend="italics">Bacch.</hi> iv. 7. 18 <q direct="unspecified">quem di diligunt adulescens moritur.</q>
               </note> : <quote rend="blockquote">Whom the gods love dies young.</quote> But perhaps, my dearest
					Apollonius, you would say in retort that your young son had been placed
					under the special care of Apollo and the Fates, and that it should have been
					you who, on departing this life, received the last offices from him, after
					he had come to full manhood ; for this, you say, is in accordance with
					nature. Yes, in accordance with your nature, no doubt, and mine, and that of
					mankind in general, but not in accordance with the Providence which presides
					over all or with the universal dispensation. But for that boy, now among the
					blessed, it was not in accordance with nature that he should tarry beyond
					the time allotted to him for life on this earth, but that, after fulfilling
					this term with due obedience, he should set forth to meet his fate, which
					was already (to use his own words <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> his dying words, <q direct="unspecified">Fate summons me</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the dying words of Alcestis, <q direct="unspecified">Charon summons me,</q> Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Alcestis</hi>, 254, and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 115 A.</note>) summoning him to himself. <q direct="unspecified">But he
						died untimely.</q> Yes, but for this very reason his lot is happier,
					and he is spared many evils ; for Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 966.</note> says : 
					<pb id="v.2.p.203"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Life bears the name of life, being but toil.</quote> But he, in
					the most blooming period of his years, has departed early, a perfect youth,
					envied and admired by all who knew him. He was fond of his father and mother
					and his relatives and friends, or, to put it in a word, he loved his fellow
					men ; he respected the elderly among his friends as fathers, he was
					affectionate towards his companions and familiar friends, he honoured his
					teachers, and was most kind toward strangers and citizens, gentle with all
					and beloved of all, both because of his charm of appearance and because of
					his affable kindliness. </p>
            <p>Ah well, but he, bearing with him the fair and fitting fame of your
					righteousness and his own conjoined, has departed early to eternity from out
					this mortal life, as from an evening party, before falling into any such
					grossness of conduct as is wont to be the concomitant of a long old age. And
					if the account of the ancient poets and philosophers is true, as it most
					likely is, and so there is for those of the departed who have been righteous
					a certain honour and preferment, as is said, and a place set apart in which
					their souls pass their existence, then you ought to be of good hope for your
					dear departed son that he will be reckoned among their number and will be
					with them. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>These are the words of the melic poet Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 129 (ed. Christ); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also the two lines quoted in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 17 C, and the amplification of these lines which Plutarch gives in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1130 C.</note> regarding the righteous in the
					other world : <quote rend="blockquote">For them doth the strength of the sun shine below, While night
						all the earth doth overstrow. 
						<pb id="v.2.p.205"/> In meadows of roses their suburbs lie, Roses all tinged
						with a crimson dye. They are shaded by trees that incense bear, And trees
						with golden fruit so fair. Some with horses and sports of might, Others in
						music and draughts delight. Happiness there grows ever apace, Perfumes are
						wafted o'er the loved place, As the incense they strew where the gods'
						altars are And the fire that consumes it is seen from afar.</quote> And a little
					farther on, in another lament for the dead, speaking of the soul, he says <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi>131 (ed. Christ); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Romulus</hi>, xxviii. (p. 35 D).</note>
					: <quote rend="blockquote">In happy fate they all <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The line is incomplete, lacking a finite verb.</note> Were freed by death from labour's thrall. Man's
						body follows at the beck of death O'ermastering. Alive is left The image of
						the stature that he gained, Since this alone is from the gods obtained. It
						sleeps while limbs move to and fro, But, while we sleep, in dreams doth show
						The choice we cannot disregard Between the pleasant and the hard.</quote> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>The divine Plato has said a good deal in his treatise On the Soul about its
					immortality, and not a little also in the Republic and Meno and Gorgias, and
					here and there in his other dialogues. What is said in the dialogue On the
					Soul I will copy, with comments, and send you separately, as you desired.
					But for the present occasion these words, which were spoken 
					<pb id="v.2.p.207"/> to Callicles the Athenian, the friend and disciple of
					Gorgias the orator, are timely and profitable. They say that Socrates,
					according to Plato's account,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Gorgias</hi>, p. 523 A.</note> says : <q direct="unspecified">Listen to a very beautiful
						story, which you, I imagine, will regard as a myth, but which I regard
						as a story; for what I am going to say I shall relate as true. As Homer <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xv. 187.</note>
						tells the tale, Zeus, Poseidon, and Pluto divided the kingdom when they
						received it from their father. Now this was the custom regarding men
						even in the time of Cronus, and it has persisted among the gods to this
						day&mdash;that the man who has passed through life justly and in
						holiness shall, at his death, depart to the Islands of the Blest and
						dwell in all happiness beyond the reach of evil, while he who has lived
						an unjust and godless life shall go to the prison-house of justice and
						punishment, which they call Tartarus. The judges of these men, in the
						time of Cronus and in the early days of Zeus's dominion, were living,
						and judged the living, giving judgement on the day when the men were
						about to die. As time went on, for some reason the cases were not
						decided well. Accordingly Pluto and the supervisors in the Islands of
						the Blest went to Zeus and said to him that there kept coming to them at
						both places inadmissible persons. ' Very well,' said Zeus, ' then I
						shall put a stop to this proceeding. The judgements are now rendered
						poorly ; for,' said he, ' those who are judged are judged with a
						covering on them, since they are judged while alive, and so,' he
						continued, a good 
						<pb id="v.2.p.209"/> many perhaps who have base souls are clad with
						beautiful bodies and ancestry and riches, and, when the judgement takes
						place, many come to testify for them that they have lived righteously.
						So not only are the judges disconcerted by these things, but at the same
						time they themselves sit in judgement with a covering on them, having
						before their own souls, like a veil, their eyes and ears and their whole
						body. All these things come between, both their own covering and that of
						those who are being judged. In the first place, then, all their
						foreknowledge of death must be ended ; for now they have foreknowledge
						of it. So Prometheus has been told to put an end to this. Secondly, they
						must be judged divested of all these things ; for they must be judged
						after they have died. The judge also must be naked, and dead, that he
						may view with his very soul the very soul of every man instantly after
						he has died, and isolated from all his kin, having left behind on earth
						all earthly adornments, so that his judgement may be just. I, therefore,
						realizing this situation sooner than you, have made my own sons judges,
						two from Asia&mdash;Minos and Rhadamanthysand one from
						EuropeAeacus. These, then, as soon as they have died, shall sit in
						judgement in the meadow at the parting of the ways whence the two roads
						lead, the one to the Islands of the Blest and the other to Tartarus. The
						people of Asia shall Rhadamanthys judge, while Aeacus shall judge the
						people of Europe; and to Minos I shall give the prerogative of
						pronouncing final judgement in case the other 
						<pb id="v.2.p.211"/> two be in any doubt, in order that the decision in
						regard to the route which men must take shall be as just as possible.'
						This, Callicles, is what I have heard, and believe to be true ; and from
						these words I draw the following inferencethat death is, as it seems
						to me, nothing else than the severing of two things, soul and body, from
						each other.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Having collected and put together these extracts, my dearest Apollonius, with
					great diligence, I have completed this letter of condolence to you, which is
					most needful to enable you to put aside your present grief and to put an end
					to mourning, which is the most distressing of all things. In it is included
					also for your son, Apollonius, a youth so very dear to the gods, a fitting
					tribute, which is much coveted by the sanctified&mdash;a tribute due to
					his honourable memory and to his fair fame, which will endure for time
					eternal. You will do well, therefore, to be persuaded by reason, and, as a
					favour to your dear departed son, to turn from your unprofitable distress
					and desolation, which affect both body and soul, and to go back to your
					accustomed and natural course of life. Forasmuch as your son, while he was
					living among us, was sorry to see either you or his mother downcast, even
					so, now that he is with the gods and is feasting with them, he would not be
					well satisfied with your present course of life. Resume, therefore, the
					spirit of a brave-hearted and high-minded man who loves his offspring, and
					set free from all this wretchedness both yourself, the mother of the youth,
					and your relatives and friends, as you may do by pursuing a more tranquil
					form of life, which will be most gratifying both to your son and to all of
					us who are concerned for you, as we rightly should be. </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>