<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De cohibenda ira</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.095">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.33"/>
         <head>Concerning the cure of anger: a dialogue.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>SYLLA. Those painters, O Fundanus, in my opinion do
				very wisely, who never finish any piece at the first sitting,
				but take a review of it at some convenient distance of time;
				because the eye, being relieved for a time, renews its power
				by making frequent and fresh judgments, and becomes able
				to observe many small and critical differences which continual poring and familiarity would prevent it from noticing. Now, because it cannot be that a man should stand
				off from himself and interrupt his consciousness, and then
				after some interval return to accost himself again (which is
				one principal reason why a man is a worse judge of himself than of other men), the next best course that a man
				can take will be to inspect his friends after some time
				of absence, and also to offer himself to their examination,
				not to see whether he be grown old on the sudden, or
				whether the habit of his body be become better or worse
				than it was before, but that they may take notice of his
				manner and behavior, whether in that time he hath made
				any advance in goodness, or gained ground of his vices.
				Wherefore, being after two years' absence returned to
				Rome, and having since conversed with thee here again
				for these five months, I think it no great matter of wonder
				that those good qualities which, by the advantage of a
				good natural disposition, you were formerly possessed of
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.34"/>
				
				have in this time received so considerable an increase.
				But truly, when I behold how that vehement and fiery disposition which you had to anger is now through the conduct of reason become so gentle and tractable, my mind
				prompts me to say, with Homer,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>O wonder! how much gentler is he grown!</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. XXII. 378.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nor hath this gentleness produced in thee any laziness
					or irresolution; but, like cultivation in the earth, it hath
					caused an evenness and a profundity very effectual unto
					fruitful action, instead of thy former vehemency and over-eagerness. And therefore it is evident that thy former
					proneness to anger hath not been withered in thee by any
					decay of vigor which age might have effected, or spontaneously; but that it hath been cured by making use of some
					mollifying precepts.</p>
            <p>And indeed, to tell you the truth, when I heard our
					friend Eros say the same thing, I had a suspicion that he
					did not report the thing as it was, but that out of mere
					good-will he testified those things of you which ought to
					be found in every good and virtuous man. And yet you
					know he cannot be easily induced to depart from what he
					judges to be true, in order to favor any man. But now,
					truly, as I acquit him of having therein made any false
					report of thee, so I desire thee, being now at leisure from
					thy journey, to declare unto us the means and (as it were)
					the medicine, by use whereof thou hast brought thy mind to
					be thus manageable and natural, thus gentle and obedient
					unto reason.</p>
            <p>FUNDANUS. But in the mean while, O most kind Sylla,
					you had best beware, lest you also through affection and
					friendship may be somewhat careless in making an estimate of my affairs. For Eros, having himself also a mind
					oft-times unable to keep its ground and to contain itself
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.35"/>
					
					within that obedience which Homer mentions, but subject
					to be exasperated through an hatred of men's wickedness,
					may perhaps think I am grown more mild; just as in
					music, when the key is changed, that note which before
					was the base becomes a higher note with respect to others which are now below it.</p>
            <p>SYLLA. Neither of these is so, Fundanus; but, I pray
					you, gratify us all by granting the request I made.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>FUNDANUS. This then, O Sylla, is one of those
				excellent rules given by Musonius which I bear in memory,&mdash;that those who would be in sound health must physic
				themselves all their lives. Now I do not think that reason
				cures, like hellebore, by purging out itself together with
				the disease it cures, but by keeping possession of the soul,
				and so governing and guarding its judgments. For the
				power of reason is not like drugs, but like wholesome food;
				and, with the assistance of a good natural disposition, it
				produceth a healthful constitution in all with whom it hath
				become familiar.</p>
            <p>And as for those good exhortations and admonitions
					which are applied to passions while they swell and are at
					their height, they work but slowly and with small success;
					and they differ in nothing from those strong-smelling things,
					which indeed do serve to put those that have the falling
					sickness upon their legs again after they are fallen, but
					are not able to remove the disease. For whereas other
					passions, even when they are in their ruff and acme, do in
					some sort yield and admit reason into the soul, which
					comes to help it from without; anger does not, as Melanthius says,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Displace the mind, and then act dismal things;</l>
               </quote>
					
					but it absolutely turns the mind out of doors, and bolts
					the door against it; and, like those who burn their houses
					and themselves within them, it makes all things within full
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.36"/>
					
					of confusion, smoke, and noise, so that the soul can neither
					see nor hear any thing that might relieve it. Wherefore
					sooner will an empty ship in a storm at sea admit of a pilot
					from without, than a man tossed with anger and rage
					listen to the advice of another, unless he have his own
					reason first prepared to entertain it.</p>
            <p>But as those who expect to be besieged are wont to
					gather together and lay in provisions of such things as
					they are like to need, not trusting to hopes of relief
					from without, so ought it to be our special concern to fetch
					in from philosophy such foreign helps as it affords against
					anger, and to store them up in the soul beforehand, seeing
					that it will not be so easy a matter to provide ourselves
					when the time is come for using them. For either the soul
					cannot hear what is spoken without, by reason of the
					tumult, unless it have its own reason (like the director of
					the rowers in a ship) ready to entertain and understand
					whatsoever precept shall be given; or, if it do chance to
					hear, yet will it be ready to despise what is patiently and
					mildly offered, and to be exasperated by what shall be
					pressed upon it with more vehemency. For, since wrath
					is proud and self-conceited, and utterly averse from compliance with others, like a fortified and guarded tyranny, that
					which is to overthrow it must be bred within it and be of
					its own household.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Now the continuance of anger and frequent fits of it
				produce an evil habit in the soul called wrathfulness, or a
				propensity to be angry, which oft-times ends in choleric
				temper, bitterness, and moroseness. Then the mind becomes ulcerated, peevish, and querulous, and like a thin,
				weak plate of iron, receives impression and is wounded by
				even the least occurrence; but when the judgment presently seizes upon wrathful ebullitions and suppresses them,
				it not only works a cure for the present, but renders the
				soul firm and not so liable to such impressions for the future.
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.37"/>
				
				 And truly, when I myself had twice or thrice made
				a resolute resistance unto anger, the like befell me that did
				the Thebans; who, having once foiled the Lacedaemonians,
				that before that time had held themselves invincible, never
				after lost so much as one battle which they fought against
				them. For I became fully assured in my mind, that anger
				might be overcome by the use of reason. And I perceived
				that it might not only be quieted by the sprinkling of cold
				water, as Aristotle relates, but also be extinguished by putting one into a flight. Yea, according to Homer, many
				men have had their anger melted and dissipated by sudden
				surprise of joy. So that I came to this firm resolution,
				that this passion is not altogether incurable to such as are
				but willing to be cured; since the beginnings and occasions of it are not always great or forcible; but a scoff, or
				a jest, or the laughing at one, or a nod only, or some other
				matter of no great importance, will put many men into a
				passion. Thus Helen, by addressing her niece in the
				words beginning,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>O my Electra, now a virgin stale,</l>
               </quote>
				
				provoked her to make this nipping return:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thou'rt wise too late, thou shouldst have kept at home.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Eurip. Orestes, 72 and 99.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				And so did Callisthenes provoke Alexander by saying,
				when the great bowl was going round, I will not drink so
				deep in honor of Alexander, as to make work for Aesculapius.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>As therefore it is an easy matter to stop the fire that
				is kindled only in hare's wool, candle-wick, or a little chaff,
				but if it have once taken hold of matter that hath solidity
				and thickness, it soon inflames and consumes, as Aeschylus
				says,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>With youthful vigor the carpenter's lofty work;</l>
               </quote>
				
				so he that observes anger while it is in its beginning, and
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.38"/>
				
				sees it by degrees smoking and taking fire from some
				speech or chaff-like scurrility, need take no great pains to
				extinguish it, but oftentimes can put an end to it only by
				silence or neglect. For as he that adds no fuel to the fire
				hath already as good as put it out, so he that doth not feed
				anger at the first, nor blow the fire in himself, hath prevented and destroyed it. Wherefore Hieronymus, although
				he taught many other useful things, yet hath given me no
				satisfaction in saying that anger is not perceptible in its
				birth, by reason of its suddenness, but only after its birth
				and while it lives; for there is no other passion, while it is
				gathering and stirring up, which hath its rise and increase
				so conspicuous and observable. This is very skilfully
				taught by Homer, by making Achilles suddenly surprised
				with grief as soon as ever the word fell on his ear, saying
				of him,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>This said, a sable cloud of grief covered him o'er;</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. XVII. 591.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				but making Agamemnon grow angry slowly and need many
				words to inflame him, so that, if these had been stopped
				and forbidden when they began, the contest had never
				grown to that degree and greatness which it did. Wherefore Socrates, as oft as he perceived any fierceness of spirit
				to rise within him towards any of his friends, setting himself like a promontory to break the waves, would speak
				with a lower voice, bear a smiling countenance, and look
				with a more gentle eye; and thus, by bending the other way
				and moving contrary to the passion, he kept himself from
				falling or being worsted.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>For the first way, my friend, to suppress anger, as
				you would a tyrant, is not to obey or yield to it when it
				commands us to speak high, to look fiercely, and to beat
				ourselves; but to be quiet, and not increase the passion, as
				we do a disease, by impatient tossing and crying out. It is
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.39"/>
				
				true that lovers' practices, such as revelling, singing, crowning the door with garlands, have a kind of alleviation in
				them which is neither rude nor unpleasing:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Coming, I asked not who or whose she was,</l>
					             <l>But kissed her door full sweetly,&mdash;that I wot;</l>
					             <l>If this be sin, to sin I can but choose.</l>
               </quote>
				
				So the weeping and lamentation which we permit in mourners doubtless carry forth much of the grief together with
				the tears. But anger, quite on the contrary, is more inflamed by what the angry persons say or do.</p>
            <p>The best course then is for a man to compose himself,
					or else to run away and hide himself and retreat into quiet,
					as into an haven, as if he perceived a fit of epilepsy coming on, lest he fall, or rather fall upon others; and truly
					we do most and most frequently fall upon our friends.
					For we neither love all, nor envy all, nor fear all men;
					but there is nothing untouched and unset upon by anger.
					We are angry with our foes and with our friends; with our
					own children and our parents; nay, with the Gods above,
					and the very beasts below us, and instruments that have no
					life, as Thamyras was,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>His horn, though bound with gold, he brake in's ire,</l>
						            <l>He brake his melodious and well-strung lyre;</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>From the Thamyras of Sophocles, Frag. 224.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					and Pandarus, wishing a curse upon himself if he did not
					burn his bow,
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>First broken by his hands.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. V. 216</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					But Xerxes dealt blows and marks of his displeasure to
					the sea itself, and sent his letters to the mountain in the
					style ensuing: <q direct="unspecified">O thou wretched Athos, whose top now
						reaches to the skies, I charge thee, put not in the way of
						my works stones too big and difficult to be wrought. If
						thou do, I will cut thee into pieces, and cast thee into the
						sea.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For anger hath many terrible effects, and many also that
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.40"/>
					
					are ridiculous; and therefore of all passions, this of anger
					is most hated and most contemned, and it is good to consider it in both respects.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>I therefore, whether rightly or not I know not,
				began this cure with learning the nature of anger by beholding it in other men, as the Lacedaemonians learned what
				drunkenness was by seeing it in the Helots. And, in the
				first place, as Hippocrates said that that was the most dangerous disease which made the sick man's countenance
				most unlike to what it was, so I observed that men transported with anger also exceedingly change their visage,
				color, gait, and voice. Accordingly I formed a kind of
				image of that passion to myself, withal conceiving great in
				dignation against myself if I should at any time appear to
				my friends, or to my wife and daughters, so terrible and discomposed, not only with so wild and strange a look, but also
				with so fierce and harsh a voice, as I had met with in some
				others of my acquaintance, who by reason of anger were
				not able to observe either good manners or countenance or
				graceful speech, or even their persuasiveness and affability
				in conversation.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Caius Gracchus, the orator, being of a rugged
					disposition and a passionate kind of speaker, had a pipe
					made for him, such as musicians use to vary their voice
					higher or lower by degrees; and with this pipe his servant stood behind him while he pronounced, and gave him
					a mild and gentle note, whereby he took him down from
					his loudness, and took off the harshness and angriness of
					his voice, assuaging and charming the anger of the orator,
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>As their shrill wax-joined reed who herds do keep</l>
						            <l>Sounds forth sweet measures, which invite to sleep.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Aesch. Prometheus, 574.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					For my own part, had I a careful and pleasant companion who would show me my angry face in a glass, I should
					not at all take it ill. In like manner, some are wont to
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.41"/>
					
					have a looking-glass held to them after they have bathed,
					though to little purpose; but to behold one's self unnaturally
					disguised and disordered will conduce not a little to the
					impeachment of anger. For those who delight in pleasant fables tell us, that Minerva herself, playing on a pipe,
					was thus admonished by a satyr:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>That look becomes you not, lay down your pipes,</l>
						            <l>And take your arms, and set your cheeks to rights;</l>
               </quote>
					
					but would not regard it; yet, when by chance she beheld
					the mien of her countenance in a river, she was moved with
					indignation, and cast her pipes away; and yet here art had
					the delight of melody to comfort her for the deformity.
					And Marsyas, as it seems, did with a kind of muzzle and
					mouth-piece restrain by force the too horrible eruption of
					his breath when he played, and so corrected and concealed
					the distortion of his visage:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>With shining gold he girt his temples rough,</l>
						            <l>And his wide mouth with thongs that tied behind.</l>
               </quote>
					
					Now anger doth swell and puff up the countenance very indecently, and sends forth a yet more indecent and unpleasant
					voice,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Moving the heart-strings, which should be at rest.</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For when the sea is tossed and troubled with winds,
					and casts up moss and sea-weed, they say it is purged; but
					those impure, bitter, and vain words which anger throws up
					when the soul has become a kind of whirlpool, defile the
					speakers, in the first place, and fill them with dishonor, arguing them to have always had such things in them and
					to be full of them, only now they are discovered to have them
					by their anger. So for a mere word, the lightest of things (as
					Plato says), they undergo the heaviest of punishments, being
					ever after accounted enemies, evil speakers, and of a malignant disposition.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>While now I see all this and bear it in mind, the
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.42"/>
				
				thought occurs to me, and I naturally consider by myself,
				that as it is good for one in a fever, so much better is it for
				one in anger, to have his tongue soft and smooth. For if
				the tongue in a fever be unnaturally affected, it is indeed an
				evil symptom, but not a cause of harm; but when the
				tongue of angry men becomes rough and foul, and breaks
				out into absurd speeches, it produces insults which work irreconcilable hatred, and proves that a poisonous malevolence lies festering within. For wine does not make men
				vent any thing so impure and odious as anger doth; and,
				besides, what proceeds from wine is matter for jest and
				laughter, but that from anger is mixed with gall and bitterness. And he that is silent in his cups is counted a burthen,
				and a bore to the company, whereas in anger there is
				nothing more commended than peace and silence; as
				Sappho adviseth,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>When anger once is spread within thy breast,</l>
					             <l>Shut up thy tongue, that vainly barking beast.</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Nor doth the constant observation of ourselves in
				anger minister these things only to our consideration, but
				it also gives us to understand another natural property of
				anger, how disingenuous and unmanly a thing it is, and
				how far from true wisdom and greatness of mind. Yet the
				vulgar account the angry man's turbulence to be his activity,
				his loud threats to argue boldness, and his refractoriness
				strength; as also some mistake his cruelty for an undertaking of great matters, his implacableness for a firmness
				of resolution, and his morosity for an hatred of that which
				is evil. For, in truth, both the deeds and motions and the
				whole mien of angry men do accuse them of much littleness and infirmity, not only when they vex little children,
				scold silly women, and think dogs and horses and asses
				worthy of their anger and deserving to be punished (as
				Ctesiphon the Pancratiast, who vouchsafed to kick the ass
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.43"/>
				
				that had kicked him first); but even in their tyrannical
				slaughters, their mean-spiritedness appearing in their
				bitterness, and their suffering exhibited outwardly in their
				actions, are but like to the biting of serpents who, when
				they themselves become burnt and full of pain, violently
				thrust the venom that inflames them from themselves into
				those that have hurt them. For as a great blow causes a
				great swelling in the flesh, so in the softest souls the giving
				way to a passion for hurting others, like a stroke on the
				soul, doth make it to swell with anger; and all the more,
				the greater is its weakness.</p>
            <p>For this cause it is that women are more apt to be angry
					than men are, and sick persons than the healthful, and old
					men than those who are in their perfect age and strength,
					and men in misery than such as prosper. For the covetous
					man is most prone to be angry with his steward, the glutton
					with his cook, the jealous man with his wife, the vainglorious person with him that speaks ill of him; but of all
					men there are none so exceedingly disposed to be angry as
					those who are ambitious of honor, and affect to carry on a
					faction in a city, which (according to Pindar) is but a
					splendid vexation. In like manner, from the great grief
					and suffering of the soul, through weakness especially, there
					ariseth anger, which is not like the nerves of the soul (as
					one spake), but like its straining and convulsive motions
					when it vehemently stirs itself up in its desires and endeavors of revenge.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Indeed such evil examples as these afford us speculations which are necessary, though not pleasant. But now,
				from those who have carried themselves mildly and gently
				in their anger, I shall present you with most excellent
				sayings and beautiful contemplations; and I begin to contemn such as say, You have wronged a man inded, and is
				a man to bear this?&mdash;Stamp on his neck, tread him down
				in the dirt,&mdash;and such like provoking speeches, whereby
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.44"/>
				
				 some do very unhandsomely translate and remove anger
				from the women's to the men's apartment. For fortitude,
				which in other respects agrees with justice, seems only to
				disagree in respect of mildness, which she claims as more
				properly her own. For it sometimes befalls even worser
				men to bear rule over those who are better than themselves; but to erect a trophy in the soul against anger
				(which Heraclitus says it is an hard thing to fight against,
				because whatever it resolves to have, it buys at no less a
				price than the soul itself) is that which none but a great
				and victorious power is able to achieve, since that alone
				can bind and curb the passions by its decrees, as with
				nerves and tendons.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I always strive to collect and read not only
					the sayings and deeds of philosophers, who (wise men say)
					had no gall in them, but especially those of kings and
					tyrants. Of this sort was the saying of Antigonus to his
					soldiers, when, as some were reviling him near his tent,
					supposing that he had not heard them, he stretched his
					staff out of the tent, and said: What! will you not stand
					somewhere farther off, while you revile me? So was that
					of Arcadio the Achaean, who was ever speaking ill of Philip,
					exhorting men to flee
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Till they should come where none would Philip know.</l>
               </quote>
					
					When afterwards by some accident he appeared in Macedonia, Philip's friends were of opinion that he ought
					not to be suffered, but be punished; but Philip meeting
					him and speaking courteously to him, and then sending
					him gifts, particularly such as were wont to be given to
					strangers, bade him learn for the time to come what to
					speak of him to the Greeks. And when all testified that
					the man was become a great praiser of Philip, even to admiration, You see, said Philip, I am a better physician
					than you. And when he had been reproached at the
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.45"/>
					
					Olympic solemnities, and some said it was fit to make the
					Grecians smart and rue it for reviling Philip, who had
					dealt well with them, What then, said he, will they do,
					if I make them smart? Those things also which Pisistratus did to Thrasybulus, and Porsena to Mutius, were
					bravely done; and so was that of Magas to Philemon, for
					having been by him exposed to laughter in a comedy on
					the public stage, in these words:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Magas, the king hath sent thee letters:</l>
						            <l>Unhappy Magas, thou dost know no letters.</l>
               </quote>
					
					And having taken Philemon as he was by a tempest cast
					on shore at Paraetonium, he commanded a soldier only to
					touch his neck with his naked sword and to go quietly away;
					and then having sent him a ball and huckle-bones, as if he
					were a child that wanted understanding, he dismissed him.
					Ptolemy was once jeering a grammarian for his want of
					learning, and asked him who was the father of Peleus: I
					will answer you (quoth he) if you will tell me first who was
					the father of Lagus. This jeer gave the king a rub for
					the obscurity of his birth, whereat all were moved with
					indignation, as a thing not to be endured. But, said Ptolemy, if it is not fit for a king to be jeered, then no more
					is it fit for him to jeer others. But Alexander was more
					severe than he was wont in his carriage towards Calisthenes
					and Clitus. Wherefore Porus, being taken captive by
					him, desired him to treat him like a king; and when
					Alexander asked him if he desired no more, he answered,
					When I say like a king, I have comprised all. And hence
					it is that they call the king of the Gods Meilichius, while
					the Athenians, I think, call him Maimactes; but the office
					of punishing they ascribe to the Furies and evil Genii,
					never giving it the epithet of divine or heavenly.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>As therefore one said of Philip, when he razed the
				city of Olynthus, But he is not able to build such another
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.46"/>
				
				city; so may it be said to anger, Thou canst overthrow, and
				destroy, and cut down; but to restore, to save, to spare, and
				to bear with, is the work of gentleness and moderation, of a
				Camillus, a Metellus, an Aristides, and a Socrates; but to
				strike the sting into one and to bite is the part of pismires
				and horse-flies. And truly, while I well consider revenge, I
				find that the way which anger takes for it proves for the
				most part ineffectual, being spent in biting the lips, gnashing the teeth, vain assaults, and railings full of silly threats;
				and then it acts like children in a race, who, for want of
				governing themselves, tumble down ridiculously before
				they come to the goal towards which they are hastening. Hence that Rhodian said not amiss to the servant
				of the Roman general, who spake loudly and fiercely to
				him, It matters not much what thou sayest, but what this
				your master in silence thinks. And Sophocles, having introduced Neoptolemus and Eurypylus in full armor, gave
				a high commendation of them when he said,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Into the hosts of brazen-armed men</l>
					             <l>Each boldly charged, but ne'er reviled his foe.</l>
               </quote>
				
				Some indeed of the barbarians poison their swords; but
				true valor has no need of choler, as being dipped in reason;
				but anger and fury are weak and easily broken. Wherefore the Lacedaemonians are wont by the sounding of
				pipes to take off the edge of anger from their soldiers,
				when they fight; and before they go to battle, to sacrifice
				to the Muses, that they may have the steady use of their
				reason; and when they have put their enemies to flight,
				they pursue them not, but sound a retreat (as it were) to
				their wrath, which, like a short dagger, can easily be handled and drawn back. But anger makes slaughter of thousands before it can avenge itself, as it did of Cyrus and
				Pelopidas the Theban. Agathocles, being reviled by some
				whom he besieged, bore it with mildness; and when one
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.47"/>
				
				said to him, O Potter, whence wilt thou have pay for thy
				mercenary soldiers? he answered with laughter, From
				your city, if I can take it. And when some onefrom the
				wall derided Antigonus for his deformity, he answered, I
				thought surely I had a handsome face: and when he had
				taken the city, he sold those for slaves who had scoffed at
				him, protesting that, if they reviled him so again, he would
				call them to account before their masters.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, I observe that hunters and orators are wont
					to be much foiled by anger. Aristotle reports that the
					friends of Satyrus once stopped his ears with wax, when
					he was to plead a cause, that so he might not confound
					the matter through anger at the revilings of his enemies.
					Do we not ourselves oftentimes miss of punishing an
					offending servant, because he runs away from us in fright
					when he hears our threatening words? That therefore
					which nurses say to little children&mdash;Do not cry, and thou
					shalt have it&mdash;may not unfitly be applied to our mind
					when angry. Be not hasty, neither speak too loud, nor be
					too urgent, and so what you desire will be sooner and
					better accomplished. For as a father, when he sees his
					son about to cleave or cut something with an hatchet,
					takes the hatchet himself and doth it for him; so one
					taking the work of revenge out of the hand of anger doth
					himself, without danger or hurt, yea, with profit also,
					inflict punishment on him that deserves it, and not on himself instead of him, as anger oft-times doth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Now, whereas all passions do stand in need of discipline, which by exercise tames and subdues their unreasonableness and stubbornness, there is none about which
				we have more need to be exercised in reference to servants
				than that of anger. For neither do we envy nor fear them,
				nor have we any competition for honor with them; but we
				have frequent fits of anger with them, which case many
				offences and errors, by reason of the very power possessed
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.48"/>
				
				by us as masters, and which bring us easily to the ground,
				as if we stood in a slippery place with no one standing by
				to save us. For it is impossible to keep an irresponsible
				power from offending in the excitement of passion, unless
				we gird up that great power with gentleness, and can slight
				the frequent speeches of wife and friends accusing us of
				remissness. And indeed I myself have by nothing more
				than by such speeches been incensed against my servants,
				as if they were spoiled for want of beating. And truly it
				was late before I came to understand, that it was better
				that servants should be something the worse by indulgence,
				than that one should distort himself through wrath and bitterness for the amendment of others. And secondly, observing that many by this very impunity have been brought to
				be ashamed to be wicked, and have begun their change to
				virtue more from being pardoned than from being punished, and that they have obeyed some upon their nod only,
				peaceably, and more willingly than they have done others
				with all their beating and scourging, I became persuaded
				of this, that reason was fitter to govern with than anger.
				For it is not as the poet said,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Wherever fear is, there is modesty;</l>
               </quote>
				
				but, on the contrary, it is in the modest that that fear is bred
				which produces moderation, whereas continual and unmerciful beating doth not make men repent of doing evil, but only
				devise plans for doing it without being detected. And in
				the third place I always remember and consider with myself, that as he who taught us the art of shooting did not
				forbid us to shoot, but only to shoot amiss, so no more can
				it be any hindrance from punishing to teach us how we
				may do it seasonably and moderately, with benefit and
				decency. I therefore strive to put away anger, especially
				by not denying the punished a liberty to plead for themselves, but granting them an hearing. For time gives a
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.49"/>
				
				breathing-space unto passion, and a delay which mitigates
				and dissolves it; and a man's judgment in the mean while
				finds out both a becoming manner and a proportionable
				measure of punishing. And moreover hereby, he that is
				punished hath not any pretence left him to object against
				the correction given him, if he is punished not out of
				anger, but being first himself convinced of his fault. And
				finally we are here saved from the greatest disgrace of all,
				for by this means the servant will not seem to speak more
				just things than his master.</p>
            <p>As therefore Phocion after the death of Alexander, to
					hinder the Athenians from rising too soon or believing it
					too hastily, said: O Athenians, if he is dead to-day, he
					will be so to-morrow, and on the next day after that;
					in like manner do I judge one ought to suggest to himself,
					who through anger is making haste to punish: If it is
					true to-day that he hath thus wronged thee, it will be true
					to-morrow, and on the next day, also. Nor will there any
					inconvenience follow upon the deferring of his punishment
					for a while; but if he be punished all in haste, he will ever
					after seem to have been innocent, as it hath oftentimes fallen
					out heretofore. For which of us all is so cruel as to torment
					or scourge a servant because, five or ten days before, he burnt
					the meat, or overturned the table, or did not soon enough
					what he was bidden? And yet it is for just such things as
					these, while they are fresh and newly done, that we are so
					disordered, and become cruel and implacable. For as
					bodies through a mist, so actions through anger seem greater
					than they are. Wherefore we ought speedily to recall
					such considerations as these are to our mind; and when
					we are unquestionably out of passion, if then to a pure and
					composed reason the deed do appear to be wicked, we ought
					to animadvert, and no longer neglect or abstain from punishment, as if we had lost our appetite for it. For there is
					nothing to which we can more justly impute men's punishing
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.50"/>
					
					 others in their anger, than to a habit of not punishing
					them when their anger is over, but growing remiss, and
					doing like lazy mariners, who in fair weather keep loitering within the haven, and then put themselves in danger
					by setting sail when the wind blows strong. So we likewise, condemning the remissness and over-calmness of our
					reason in punishing, make haste to do it while our anger is
					up, pushing us forward like a dangerous wind.</p>
            <p>He that useth food doth it to gratify his hunger, which
					is natural; but he that inflicts punishment should do it
					without either hungering or thirsting after it, not needing
					anger, like sauce, to whet him on to punish; but when
					he is farthest off from desiring it, then he should do it
					as a deed of necessity under the guidance of reason.
					And though Aristotle reports, that in his time servants
					in Etruria were wont to be scourged while the music
					played, yet they who punish others ought not to be carried
					on with a desire of punishing, as of a thing they delight in,
					nor to rejoice when they punish, and then repent of it when
					they have done,&mdash;whereof the first is savage, the last
					womanish; but, without either sorrow or pleasure, they
					should inflict just punishment when reason is free to judge,
					leaving no pretence for anger to intermeddle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>But this perhaps may seem to be not a cure of
				anger, but only a thrusting by and avoiding of such miscarriages as some men fall into when they are angry. And
				yet, as Hieronymus tells us, although the swelling of the
				spleen is but a symptom of the fever, the assuaging thereof
				abates the disease. But, considering well the origin of
				anger itself, I have observed that divers men fall into
				anger for different causes; and yet in the minds of all
				of them was probably an opinion of being despised and
				neglected. We must therefore assist those who would
				avoid anger, by removing the act which roused their anger
				as far as possible from all suspicion of contempt or insult,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.51"/>
				
				and by imputing it rather to folly or necessity or disorder
				of mind, or to the misadventure of those that did it. Thus
				Sophocles in Antigone:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The best resolved mind in misery</l>
					             <l>Can't keep its ground, but suffers ecstasy.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Soph. Antig. 563.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And so Agamemnon, ascribing to Ate the taking away of
					Briseis, adds:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Since I so foolish was as thee to wrong,</l>
						            <l>I'll please thee now, and give thee splendid gifts.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. XIX. 138.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For supplication is an act of one who is far from contemning; and when he that hath done an injury appears
					submissive, he thereby removes all suspicion of contempt.
					But he that is moved to anger must not expect or wait for
					such a submission, but must rather take to himself the
					saying of Diogenes, who, when one said to him, They deride thee, O Diogenes, made answer, But I am not derided;
					and he must not think himself contemned, but rather himself contemn that man that offends him, as one acting out
					of weakness or error, rashness or carelessness, rudeness or
					dotage, or childishness. But, above all, we must bear with
					our servants and friends herein; for surely they do not
					despise us as being impotent or slothful, but they think less
					of us by reason of our very moderation or good-will
					towards them, some because we are gentle, others because we are loving towards them. But now, alas!
					out of a surmise that we are contemned, we not only
					become exasperated against our wives, our servants, and
					friends, but we oftentimes fall out also with drunken innkeepers, and mariners and ostlers, and all out of a suspicion
					that they despise us. Yea, we quarrel with dogs because
					they bark at us, and asses if they chance to rush against
					us; like him who was going to beat a driver of asses, but
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.52"/>
					
					when the latter cried out, I am an Athenian, fell to beating
					the ass, saying, Thou surely art not an Athenian too, and
					so accosted him with many a bastinado.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>And especially self-love and morosity, together with
				luxury and effeminacy, breed in us long and frequent fits of
				anger, which by little and little are gathered together into
				our souls, like a swarm of bees or wasps. Wherefore there
				is nothing more conducing to a gentle behavior towards our
				wife and servants and friends than contentedness and simplicity, if we can be satisfied with what we have, and not
				stand in need of many superfluities. Whereas the man
				described in the poet,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Who never is content with boiled or roast,</l>
					             <l>Nor likes his meat, what way soever drest,&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
				
				who can never drink unless he have snow by him, or eat
				bread if it be bought in the market, or taste victuals out of
				a mean or earthen vessel, or sleep on a bed unless it be
				swelled and puffed up with feathers, like to the sea when it is
				heaved up from the bottom; but who with cudgels and
				blows, with running, calling, and sweating doth hasten his
				servitors that wait at table, as if they were sent for plasters
				for some inflamed ulcer, he being slave to a weak, morose,
				and fault-finding style of life,&mdash;doth, as it were by a continual cough or many buffetings, breed in himself, before he is
				aware, an ulcerous and defluxive disposition unto anger.
				And therefore the body is to be accustomed to contentment
				by frugality, and so be made sufficient for itself. For they
				who need but few things are not disappointed of many; and
				it is no hard matter, beginning with our food, to accept
				quietly whatever is sent to us, and not by being angry and
				querulous at every thing, to entertain ourselves and our
				friends with the most unpleasant dish of all, which is
				anger. And surely
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Than that supper nought can more unpleasant be,</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Odyss. XX. 892.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				           <pb id="v.1.p.53"/>
				
				where the servants are beaten and the wife railed at, because
				something is burnt or smoked or not salt enough, or
				because the bread is too cold. Arcesilaus was once entertaining his friends and some strangers at a feast; the
				supper was set on the board, but there wanted bread, the
				servants having, it seems, neglected to buy any. Now, on
				such an occasion, which of us would not have rent the very
				walls with outcries? But he smiling said only: What a
				fine thing it is for a philosopher to be a jolly feaster!
				Once also when Socrates took Euthydemus from the wrestling-house home with him to supper, his wife Xanthippe
				fell upon him in a pelting chase, scolding him, and in conclusion overthrew the table. Whereupon Euthydemus rose
				up and went his way, being very much troubled at what
				had happened. But Socrates said to him: Did not a hen
				at your house the other day come flying in, and do the like?
				and yet I was not troubled at it. For friends are to be
				entertained by good-nature, by smiles, and by a hospitable
				welcome; not by knitting brows, or by striking horror and
				trembling into those that serve.</p>
            <p>We must also accustom ourselves to the use of any cups
					indifferently, and not to use one rather than another, as
					some are wont to single some one cup out of many (as they
					say Marius used to do) or else a drinking-horn, and to
					drink out of none but that; and they do the same with
					oil-glasses and brushes, affecting one above all the rest, and
					when any one of these chances to be broken or lost, then
					they take it heinously, and punish severely those that did it.
					And therefore he that is prone to be angry should refrain
					from such things as are rare and curiously wrought, such
					as cups and seals and precious stones; for such things distract a man by their loss more than cheap and ordinary
					things are apt to do. Wherefore when Nero had made an
					octagonal tent, a wonderful spectacle for cost and beauty,
					Seneca said to him: You have proved yourself to be a
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.54"/>
					
					poor man; for if you chance to lose this, you cannot tell
					where to get such another. And indeed it so fell out that
					the ship was sunk, and this tent was lost with it. But Nero,
					remembering the words of Seneca, bore the loss of it with
					greater moderation.</p>
            <p>But this contentedness in other matters doth make a
					man good-tempered and gentle towards his servants; and
					if towards servants, then doubtless towards friends and subjects also. We see also that newly bought servants enquire
					concerning him that bought them, not whether he be superstitious or envious, but whether he be an angry man or
					not; and that universally, neither men can endure their
					wives, though chaste, nor women their husbands, though
					kind, if they be ill-tempered withal; nor friends the conversation of one another. And so neither wedlock nor
					friendship with anger is to be endured; but if anger be
					away, even drunkenness itself is counted a light matter.
					For the ferule of Bacchus is a sufficient chastiser of a
					drunken man, if the addition of anger do not change the
					God of wine from Lyaeus and Choraeus (the looser of cares
					and the leader of dances) to the savage and furious deity.
					And Anticyra (with its hellebore) is of itself able to cure
					simple madness; but madness mixed with anger furnishes
					matter for tragedies and dismal stories.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Neither ought any, even in their playing and jesting,
				to give way to their anger, for it turns good-will into hatred;
				nor when they are disputing, for it turns a desire of knowing truth into a love of contention; nor when they sit in
				judgment, for it adds violence to authority; nor when they
				are teaching, for it dulls the learner, and breeds in him a
				hatred of all learning; nor if they be in prosperity, for it
				increases envy; nor if in adversity, for it makes them to be
				unpitied, if they are morose and apt to quarrel with those
				who commiserate them, as Priam did:&mdash;
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.55"/>
				
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Be gone, ye upbraiding scoundrels, haven't ye at home</l>
					             <l>Enough, that to help bear my grief ye come?</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. XXIV. 239.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>On the other hand, good temper doth remedy some
					things, put an ornament upon others, and sweeten others;
					and it wholly overcomes all anger and moroseness by gentleness. As may be seen in that excellent example of
					Euclid, who, when his brother had said in a quarrel,
					Let me perish if I be not avenged of you, replied, And
					let me perish if I do not persuade you into a better mind;
					and by so saying he straightway diverted him from his
					purpose, and changed his mind. And Polemon, being
					reviled by one that loved precious stones well and was even
					sick with the love of costly signets, answered nothing, but
					noticed one of the signets which the man wore, and looked
					wistfully upon it. Whereat the man being pleased said:
					Not so, Polemon, but look upon it in the sunshine, and
					it will appear much better to you. And Aristippus,
					when there happened to be a falling out between him and
					Aeschines, and one said to him, O Aristippus, what is
					now become of the friendship that was between you two?
					answered, It is asleep, but I will go and awaken it.
					Then coming to Aeschines, he said to him, What? dost
					thou take me to be so utterly wretched and incurable
					as not to be worth thy admonition? No wonder, said
					Aeschines, if thou, by nature so excelling me in every
					thing, didst here also discern before me what was right
					and fitting to be done.
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>A woman's, nay a little child's soft hand,</l>
						            <l>With gentle stroking easier doth command,</l>
						            <l>And make the bristling boar to couch and fall,</l>
						            <l>Than any boisterous wrestler of them all.</l>
               </quote>
					
					But we that can tame wild beasts and make them gentle,
					carrying young wolves and the whelps of lions in our
					arms, do in a fit of anger cast our own children, friends,
					and companions out of our embraces; and we let loose our
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.56"/>
					
					wrath like a wild beast upon our servants and fellow-citizens. And we but poorly disguise our rage when we give
					it the specious name of zeal against wickedness; and it is
					with this, I suppose, as with other passions and diseases of
					the soul,&mdash;although we call one forethought, another liberality, another piety, we cannot so acquit and clear ourselves
					of any of them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>And as Zeno has said that the seed was a mixture
				drawn from all the powers of the soul, in like manner anger seems to be a kind of universal seed extracted from all
				the passions. For it is taken from grief and pleasure and
				insolence; and then from envy it hath the evil property of
				rejoicing at another's adversity; and it is even worse than
				murder itself, for it doth not strive to free itself from suffering, but to bring mischief to itself, if it may thereby but
				do another man an evil turn. And it hath the most odious
				kind of desire inbred in it, if the appetite for grieving and
				hurting another may be called a desire.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, when we go to the houses of drunkards, we
					may hear a wench playing the flute betimes in the morning, and behold there, as one said, the muddy dregs of
					wine, and scattered fragments of garlands, and servants
					drunk at the door; and the marks of angry and surly men
					may be read in the faces, brands, and fetters of the servants.
					<q direct="unspecified">But lamentation is the only bard that is always to be heard
						beneath the roof</q> of the angry man, while his stewards are
					beaten and his maid-servants tormented; so that the spectators, in the midst of their mirth and delight, cannot but
					pity those sad effects of anger.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>And even those who, out of a real hatred of wickedness, often happen to be surprised with anger, can abate
				the excess and vehemence of it so soon as they give up
				their excessive confidence in those with whom they converse. For of all causes this doth most increase anger,
				when one proves to be wicked whom we took for a good
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.57"/>
				
				man, or when one who we thought had loved us falls into
				some difference and chiding with us.</p>
            <p>As for my own disposition, thou knowest very well with
					how strong inclinations it is carried to show kindness to
					men and to confide in them; and therefore, like those who
					miss their step and tread on nothing, when I most of all
					trust to men's love and, as it were, prop myself up with it,
					I do then most of all miscarry, and, finding myself disappointed, am troubled at it. And indeed I should never
					succeed in freeing myself from this too great eagerness
					and forwardness in my love; but against excessive confidence perhaps I can make use of Plato's caution for a
					bridle. For he said that he so commended Helicon, the
					mathematician, because he thought him a naturally versatile animal; but that he had a jealousy of those who had
					been well educated in the city, lest, being men and the
					offspring of men, they should in something or other discover the infirmity of their nature. But when Sophocles
					says, If you search the deeds of mortals, you will find
					the most are base, he seems to insult and disparage us
					over much. Still even such a harsh and censorious judgment as this may make us more moderate in our anger;
					for it is the sudden and the unexpected which do most
					drive us to frenzy. But we ought, as Panaetius somewhere
					said, to imitate Anaxagoras; and as he said upon the death
					of his son, I knew before that I had begotten but a mortal,
					so should every one of us use expressions like these of
					those offences which stir up to anger: I knew, when I
					bought my servant, that I was not buying a philosopher;
					I knew that I did not get a friend that had no passions; I
					knew that I had a wife that was but a woman. But if
					every one would always repeat the question of Plato to
					himself, But am not I perhaps such a one myself? and
					turn his reason from abroad to look into himself, and put
					restraint upon his reprehension of others, he would not
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.58"/>
					
					make so much use of his hatred of evil in reproving other
					men seeing himself to stand in need of great indulgence.
					But now every one of us, when he is angry and punishing,
					can bring the words of Aristides and of Cato: Do not steal,
					Do not lie, and Why are ye so slothful? And, what is
					most truly shameful of all, we do in our anger reprove
					others for being angry, and what was done amiss through
					anger we punish in our passion, therein not acting like
					physicians, who
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Purge bitter choler with a bitter pill,</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Sophocles, Frag. 769</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					but rather increasing and exasperating the disease which
					we pretend to cure.</p>
            <p>While therefore I am thus reasoning with myself, I endeavor also to abate something of my curiosity; because
					for any one over curiously to enquire and pry into every
					thing, and to make a public business of every employment
					of a servant, every action of a friend, every pastime of a
					son, every whispering of a wife, causes great and long and
					daily fits of anger, whereof the product and issue is a
					peevish and morose disposition. Wherefore God, as Euripides says,
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Affairs of greatest weight himself directeth,</l>
						            <l>But matters small to Fortune he committeth.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Euripides, Frag. 964.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					But I think a prudent man ought not to commit any thing
					at all to Fortune, nor to neglect any thing, but to trust and
					commit some things to his wife, some things to his servants,
					and some things to his friends (as a prince to certain vicegerents and accountants and administrators), while he himself is employing his reason about the weightiest matters,
					and those of greatest concern.</p>
            <p>For as small letters hurt the sight, so do small matters
					him that is too much intent upon them; they vex and stir
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.59"/>
					
					up anger, which begets an evil habit in him in, reference
					to greater affairs. But above all the rest, I look on that
					of Empedocles as a divine thing, <q direct="unspecified">To fast from evil.</q>
					And I commended also those vows and professions made
					in prayers, as things neither indecent in themselves nor
					unbecoming a philosopher,&mdash;for a whole year to abstain
					from venery and wine, serving God with temperance all
					the while; or else again, for a certain time to abstain from
					lying, minding and watching over ourselves, that we speak
					nothing but what is true, either in earnest or in jest. After
					the manner of these vows then I made my own, supposing
					it would be no less acceptable to God and sacred than
					theirs; and I set myself first to observe a few sacred days
					also, wherein I would abstain from being angry, as if it
					were from being drunk or from drinking wine, celebrating
					a kind of Nephalia and Melisponda<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Nephalia</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">nh/fw,</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">to be sober</hi>) were wineless offerings, like those to the Eumen.
						ides. See Aesch. Eumen. 107: <foreign lang="greek">*xoa/s t' a)oi/nous, nhfa/lia meili/gmata.</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Melisponda</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">me/li</foreign>)
						were offerings of honey. (G.)</note> with respect to my
					anger. Then, making trial of myself little by little for a
					month or two, I by this means in time made some good
					progress unto further patience in bearing evils, diligently
					observing and keeping myself courteous in language and
					behavior, free from anger, and pure from all wicked words
					and absurd actions, and from passion, which for a little
					(and that no grateful) pleasure brings with itself great
					perturbations and shameful repentance. Whence experience, not without some divine assistance, hath, I suppose,
					made it evident that that was a very true judgment and
					assertion, that this courteous, gentle, and kindly disposition
					and behavior is not so acceptable, so pleasing, and so delightful to any of those with whom we converse, as it is to
					those that have it.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>