<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De Alexandri magni fortuna aut virtute</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.4.p.380"/>
            <head>ON THE FORTUNE OR THE
					VIRTUE OF ALEXANDER
					(DE ALEXANDRI MAGNI FORTUNA
					AUT VIRTUTE)
					I AND II</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
               <p>
						Again we have epideictic orations similar to the
						preceding and the following essays, and the conclusion again is abrupt, as if the speaker had been
						obliged to stop after a certain period of time had
						elapsed. Note, however, the very considerable difference in length between the first and the second part
						of the present work.
					</p>
               <p>We know nothing of the circumstances under
						which these orations were delivered, but it is quite
						possible that they were spoken at Rome to show the
						Romans what an educated Greek could do in the
						treatment of a controversial subject.
					</p>
               <p>The first oration deals mainly with the manner in
						which Fortune used Alexander ; but much is also
						said of the manner in which he met the buffetings of
						Fortune and rose superior to them. In the second
						oration Fortune is by no means neglected, but rather
						more is said of Alexander's Virtue ; thus it is not
						surprising to find in Lamprias's list of Plutarch's
						works two entries : the first, No. 176, <hi rend="italics">Alexander's
						Fortune</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">*peri\ th=s *)aleca/ndrou tu/xhs</foreign>) and the second,
						No. 186, <hi rend="italics">Alexander's Virtue</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">*peri\ th=s *)aleca/ndrou a)reth=s</foreign>).
					</p>
               <p>Much that is included here is found also in
						Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, in Arrian's <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>,
						and in other writers cited in the notes.
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.381"/>
						
					          </p>
               <p>The genuineness of the tradition which ascribes
						these works to Plutarch (for the attribution had been
						attacked by A. Sch&auml;fer and by L. Weber) has been
						brilliantly vindicated by W. Nachst&auml;dt in his dissertation, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarchi Declamationibus quae sunt De
						Alexandri Fortuna (Berliner Beitr&auml;ge f&uuml;r klassischen
						Philologie</hi>, ii.), Karl Vogt, Berlin, 1895. This excellent work also contains a discussion of many of the
						problems which confront the editor of these essays
						and has been of great service.
					</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.4.p.383"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>This is Fortune's discourse, who declares that
						Alexander is her own characteristic handiwork, and
						hers alone. But some rejoinder must be made on
						behalf of philosophy, or rather on Alexander's behalf,
						who would be vexed and indignant if he should be
						thought to have received as a pure gift, even at the
						hands of Fortune, the supremacy which he won at the
						price of much blood and of wounds that followed one
						after another ; and
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Many a night did he spend without sleeping,
						</l>
                     <l>Many a blood-stained day did he pass amid combats
						unceasing,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 325-326.</note>
                     </l>
                  </quote>
						against irresistible forces and innumerable tribes,
						against impassable rivers and mountain fastnesses
						whose summit no arrow could reach, furthered by
						wise counsels, steadfast purpose, manly courage, and
						a prudent heart.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>I think that if Fortune should try to inscribe her
						name on his successes, he would say to her, <q direct="unspecified">Slander
							not my virtues, nor take away my fair fame by detraction. Darius was your handiwork : he who was
							
							<pb id="v.4.p.385"/>
							
							a slave and courier of the king,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 340 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xviii. (674 d). Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xii. 43, says that he was a slave; and Strabo, xv. 3. 24, Diodorus, xvii. 5, say that he was not of the royal family.</note> him did you make
							the mighty lord of Persia ; and Sardar Lapalus, upon
							whose head you placed the royal diadem, though he
							spent his days in carding purple wool.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 336 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> But I,
							through my victory at Arbela,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">331 b.c.</note> went up to Susa,
							and Cilicia<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The battle of Issus, 333 b.c.</note> opened the way for me into the broad
							land of Egypt; but to Cilicia I came by way of the
							Granicus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">334 b.c.</note> which I crossed, using as a bridge the dead
							bodies of Mithridates and Spithridates. Adorn yourself, proud Fortune, and vaunt your dominion over
							kings that never felt a wound nor shed a drop of blood.
							For they have been Fortune's favourites, men such
							as Ochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Artaxerxes III. (358-338 b.c.).</note> was and Artaxerses, whom at the very hour
							of their birth you placed upon the throne of Cyrus.
							But my body bears many a token of an opposing
							Fortune and no ally of mine. First, among the
							Illyrians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This wound is elsewhere unknown to history. For the wounds of Alexander see the excellent tables of Nachst&auml;dt, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 38-44.</note> my head was wounded by a stone and my
							neck by a cudgel. Then at the Granicus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 341 a-c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xvi. (673 a); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, i. 15. 7; Diodorus, xvii. 20.</note> my head
							was cut open by an enemy's dagger, at Issus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">By Darius, according to Chares (341 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xx. (675 f)); but this is unknown to Arrian, Diodorus, Curtius, and Justin.</note> my
							thigh was pierced by the sword. Next at Gaza<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text is probably corrupt; in Curtius, iv. 6, we hear of two wounds, and they are quite different ones. One wound is reported in 341 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxv. (679 b); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 27. 2.</note> my
							ankle was wounded by an arrow, my shoulder was
							dislocated, and I whirled heavily round and round.
							Then at Maracandaf<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 341 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iii. 30. 11; Curitus, vii. 6.</note> the bone of my leg was split open
							by an arrow. There awaited me towards the last also
							the buffetings I received among the Indians and the
							
							<pb id="v.4.p.387"/>
							
							violence of famines.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxvi. (702 a-b); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vi. 24-25.</note> Among the Aspasians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf. Ibid.</hi>, iv. 23. 3; Curitus, viii. 3.</note> my
							shoulder was wounded by an arrow, and among the
							Gandridae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nothing is known of this wound.</note> my leg. Among the Mallians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 341 c, 343 e ff., <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxiii. (700 b ff.); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vi. 9, 10; Diodorus, xvii. 98; Curtius, ix. 4, 5; Strabo, xv. 1. 33.</note> the shaft
							of an arrow sank deep into my breast and buried
							its steel; and I was struck in the neck by a cudgel,
							when the scaling-ladders which we had moved up to
							the walls were battered down ; and Fortune cooped
							me up alone, favouring ignoble barbarians and not
							illustrious adversaries with such an exploit. But
							if Ptolemy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Peucestas in <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, and in Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>.</note> had not held his shield above me, and
							Limnaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Leonnatus according to Arrian (<hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vi. 10. 2).</note> taking his stand before me had not fallen, a
							target for ten thousand shafts, and if my Macedonians
							had not overthrown the wall with spirit and main
							force, then that nameless village in a foreign land
							must needs have become the tomb of Alexander.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Moreover, there were the trials of the campaign
						itself : storms, droughts, deep rivers, the heights of
						the Birdless Rock,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 181 c; Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iv. 28; Diodorus, xvii. 85. Sir Aurel Stein has identified Aornos with the plateau of Pir-s'ar (<hi rend="italics">On Alexander's Track to the Indus</hi>, Macmillan, 1929).</note> the monstrous shapes of savage
						beasts, an uncivilized manner of life, the constant succession of petty kings and their repeated treachery.
						Then there were also the difficulties before his expedition:<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xi. (670 b).</note> Greece was still gasping over Philip's
						wars ; Thebes, staggering to her feet after her fall,
						was shaking the dust of Chaeroneia from her arms,
						and Athens was stretching forth a helping hand to
						join with Thebes. All Macedonia was festering with
						revolt and looking toward Amyntas and the children
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.389"/>
						
						of A&euml;ropus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Very little is known of this faction. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, xiv. 37 and 89. Amyntas later joined Darius and met his death soon after the battle of Issus.</note>; the Illyrians were again rebelling, and
						trouble with the Scythians was impending for their
						Macedonian neighbours, who were in the throes of
						political change ; Persian gold flowed freely through
						the hands of the popular leaders everywhere, and
						helped to rouse the Peloponnesus ; Philip's treasuries
						were bare of money, and in addition there was owing a
						loan of two hundred talents<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">£40,000 or $200,000.</note> (as Onesicritus records).
						In such poverty<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the varying accounts of the wealth and forces of Alexander <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 342 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xv. (672 a); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, i. 11. 3; and Alexander's own account, according to Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vii. 9. 6 ff.</note> and in circumstances fraught with
						such uncertainty, a stripling, scarcely older than a
						boy, had the daring to hope for Babylon and Susa ;
						nay more, to conceive the project of dominion over
						all the world, relying only on the thirty thousand
						foot and four thousand cavalry which were his ; for,
						according to Aristobulus, that was the full extent of
						their number. But King Ptolemy puts them at
						thirty thousand foot and five thousand horse, Anaximenes at forty-three thousand foot, fifty-five hundred
						horse. And the great and glorious war-chest which
						Fortune had ready for him was only seventy talents,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">£14,000 or $70,000.</note>
						as Aristobulus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 342 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> says, though Duris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 472.</note> says it was provision for only thirty days.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Was, then, Alexander ill-advised and precipitate
						in setting forth with such humble resources to
						acquire so vast an empire? By no means. For who
						has ever put forth with greater or fairer equipment
						than he : greatness of soul, keen intelligence, selfrestraint, and manly courage, with which Philosophy
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.391"/>
						
						herself provided him for his campaign? Yes, the
						equipment that he had from Aristotle his teacher
						when he crossed over into Asia was more than what
						he had from his father Philip. But although we
						believe those who record that Alexander once said
						that the <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chaps. viii. (p. 668 d) and xxvi. (679 c-d); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, vii. 29. 108.</note> and the <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi> accompanied him as
						equipment for his campaigns, since we hold Homer
						in reverence, yet are we to contemn anyone who
						asserts that the works of Homer accompanied him
						as a consolation after toil and as a pastime for sweet
						hours of leisure, but that his true equipment was
						philosophic teaching, and treatises on Fearlessness
						and Courage, and Self-restraint also, and Greatness
						of Soul? For of course it is obvious that Alexander
						wrote nothing on the subject of either syllogisms or
						axioms, nor did he have the opportunity of sharing
						the walks in the Lyceum,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, of occupying himself with Peripatetic (Aristotelian) philosophy.</note> or of discussing propositions
						in the Academy. For it is by these criteria that those
						define philosophy who regard it as a theoretical rather
						than a practical pursuit. And yet even Pythagoras
						wrote nothing at all, nor did Socrates, nor Arcesilaus,
						nor Carneades, who were all most notable among philosophers. Nor were these philosophers continuously
						occupied with such tremendous wars, nor with spreading civilization among foreign princes, nor in establishing Grecian cities among savage nations, nor
						did they go on and on, instructing lawless and
						ignorant tribes in the principles of law and peace ;
						but, even though they had leisure, they relinquished
						the writing of philosophy to sophists. Whence,
						then, comes our belief that they were true philosophers? Surely from what they said, or from the
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.393"/>
						
						manner of life which they led, or from the principles
						which they taught. By these criteria let Alexander
						also be judged ! For from his words, from his deeds,
						and from the instruction which he imparted, it will be
						seen that he was indeed a philosopher.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>And first, if you will, consider a matter entirely
						contrary to the general belief, and compare Alexander's pupils with those of Plato and Socrates.
						Plato and Socrates taught pupils of splendid natural
						endowment who spoke the same language ; so that,
						even if the pupils understood nothing else, at least
						they understood the Greek tongue. And even so,
						Plato and Socrates did not win over many. But their
						pupils, such as Critias and Alcibiades and Cleitophon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is interesting to note that dialogues bearing the names of all these pupils have been handed down to us under the name of Plato, although some of them are thought to be spurious.</note>
						were prone to spew the good word forth, as a horse
						the curbing bit, and turned them to other ways.
					</p>
               <p>But if you examine the results of Alexander's instruction, you will see that he educated the Hyrcanians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wyttenbach in sadness doubts whether these ethnological remarks are the fruit of any research on the part of Plutarch. But they probably derive from a hazy recollection of such passages as Herodotus, i. 216 (of the Massagetae). Note, however, that Strabo supports Plutarch on this custom of the Persians (xv. 3. 20), which is easily explained by the fact that the young king inherited his father's harem as well as his father's stable, and that the father's younger wives furnished the beginning of the son's harem. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Trachiniae</hi>, 1221-1251. For other pleasant customs of the Hyrcanians <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 499 d.</note> to respect the marriage bond, and taught
						the Arachosians to till the soil, and persuaded the
						Sogdians to support their parents, not to kill them,
						and the Persians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wyttenbach in sadness doubts whether these ethnological remarks are the fruit of any research on the part of Plutarch. But they probably derive from a hazy recollection of such passages as Herodotus, i. 216 (of the Massagetae). Note, however, that Strabo supports Plutarch on this custom of the Persians (xv. 3. 20), which is easily explained by the fact that the young king inherited his father's harem as well as his father's stable, and that the father's younger wives furnished the beginning of the son's harem. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Trachiniae</hi>, 1221-1251. For other pleasant customs of the Hyrcanians <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 499 d.</note> to revere their mothers and not to
						take them in wedlock. O wondrous power of Philosophic Instruction, that brought the Indians to worship Greek gods, and the Scythians to bury their
						dead, not to devour them ! We admire Carneades'
						power, which made Cleitomachus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, iv. 67; Athenaeus, 402 c.</note> formerly called
						Hasdrubal, and a Carthaginian by birth, adopt
						Greek ways. We admire the character of Zeno, which
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.395"/>
						
						persuaded Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diogenes, from Seleucia in Mesopotamia (Strabo, xvi. 1. 16; Diogenes Laertius, vi. 81), was said to have been a pupil of Chrysippus, and thus was converted to the inheritance of Zeno, Stoicism.</note> the Babylonian to be a philosopher. But when Alexander was civilizing Asia,
						Homer was commonly read, and the children of the
						Persians, of the Susianians, and of the Gedrosians
						learned to chant, the tragedies of Sophocles and
						Euripides.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. viii. (p. 668 e).</note> And although Socrates, when tried on
						the charge of introducing foreign deities,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, 24 b; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Memorabilia</hi>, i. 1. 1.</note> lost his
						cause to the informers who infested Athens, yet
						through Alexander Bactria and the Caucasus learned
						to revere the gods of the Greeks. Plato wrote a book
						on the One Ideal Constitution, but because of its
						forbidding character he could not persuade anyone
						to adopt it; but Alexander established more than
						seventy cities among savage tribes, and sowed all
						Asia with Grecian magistracies, and thus overcame its
						uncivilized and brutish manner of living. Although
						few of us read Plato's <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, yet hundreds of thousands
						have made use of Alexander's laws, and continue to
						use them. Those who were vanquished by Alexander
						are happier than those who escaped his hand; for these
						had no one to put an end to the wretchedness of their
						existence, while the victor compelled those others to
						lead a happy life. Therefore it is even more just
						to apply Themistocles' saying<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 185 f, and the note there.</note> to the nations conquered by Alexander. For, when Themistocles in
						exile had obtained great gifts from Artaxerxes, and
						had received three cities to pay him tribute, one to
						supply his bread, another his wine, and a third his
						meat, he exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">My children, we should be
							ruined now, had we not been ruined before.</q> Thus
						Alexander's new subjects would not have been
						civilized, had they not been vanquished; Egypt
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.397"/>
						
						would not have its Alexandria, nor Mesopotamia its
						Seleuceia, nor Sogdiana its Prophthasia, nor India
						its Bucephalia, nor the Caucasus a Greek city<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Alexandria-in-the-Caucasus: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iii. 28. 4; iv. 22. 4; v. 1. 5; Curtius, vii. 3. 23; Diodorus, xvii. 83. 1.</note> hard
						by; for by the founding of cities in these places
						savagery was extinguished and the worse element,
						gaining familiarity with the better, changed under
						its influence. If, then, philosophers take the greatest
						pride in civilizing and rendering adaptable the intractable and untutored elements in human character,
						and if Alexander has been shown to have changed the
						savage natures of countless tribes, it is with good
						reason that he should be regarded as a very great
						philosopher.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>Moreover, the much-admired <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Cambridge Ancient History</hi>, vol. vii. p. 225; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 653 e; <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, xxxi. (59 a); Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Legibus</hi>, i. 7-11 (21-32): <hi rend="italics">De Officiis</hi>, i. 7 (22); Diogenes Laertius, vii. 32-34, 121, 129, 131.</note> of Zeno,
						the founder of the Stoic sect, may be summed up in
						this one main principle : that all the inhabitants of
						this world of ours should not live differentiated by
						their respective rules of justice into separate cities
						and communities, but that we should consider all men
						to be of one community and one polity, and that we
						should have a common life and an order common to
						us all, even as a herd that feeds together and shares
						the pasturage of a common field. This Zeno wrote,
						giving shape to a dream or, as it were, shadowy
						picture of a well-ordered and philosophic commonwealth ; but it was Alexander who gave effect to the
						idea. For Alexander did not follow Aristotle's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle's name is not elsewhere linked with this advice; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Strabo, i. 4. 9 (p. 66), or Aristotle, Frag. 658 (ed. V. Rose).</note> advice
						to treat the Greeks as if he were their leader, and
						other peoples as if he were their master ; to have
						regard for the Greeks as for friends and kindred, but
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.399"/>
						
						to conduct himself toward other peoples as though
						they were plants or animals; for to do so would
						have been to cumber his leadership with numerous
						battles and banishments and festering seditions.
						But, as he believed that he carne as a heaven-sent
						governor to all, and as a mediator for the whole
						world, those whom he could not persuade to unite
						with him, he conquered by force of arms, and he
						brought together into one body all men everywhere,
						uniting and mixing in one great loving-cup, as it
						were, men's lives, their characters, their marriages,
						their very habits of life.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vii. 11. 8-9.</note> He bade them all consider
						as their fatherland the whole inhabited earth, as their
						stronghold and protection his camp, as akin to them
						all good men, and as foreigners only the wicked ;
						they should not distinguish between Grecian and
						foreigner by Grecian cloak and targe, or scimitar
						and jacket; but the distinguishing mark of the
						Grecian should be seen in virtue, and that of the
						foreigner in iniquity ; clothing and food, marriage
						and manner of life they should regard as common to
						all, being blended into one by ties of blood and
						children.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>Now Demaratus the Corinthian, one of Philip's
						intimate friends,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 70 c; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. ix. (669 c).</note> when he had seen Alexander in
						Susa, exclaimed with tears of joy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> chaps. xxxvii. (687 a), lvi. (696 f); <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesila&uuml;s, chap. xv. (604 a).</hi>
                  </note> that all the
						Greeks who had died before that hour had been
						deprived of a great joy, since they had not seen
						Alexander seated on the throne of Darius. But I
						swear that for my part I feel no envy because of this
						spectacle toward them that saw it, for it was but the
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.401"/>
						
						handiwork of Fortune, and the lot of other kings as
						well. But methinks I would gladly have been a
						witness of that fair and holy marriage-rite, when he
						brought together in one golden-canopied tent an
						hundred Persian brides and an hundred Macedonian
						and Greek bridegrooms, united at a common hearth
						and board.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxx. (703 e); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vii. 4; Diodorus, xvii. 107. 6; Athenaeus, 538 b-e; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, viii. 7; but the number is not elsewhere given as 100.</note> He himself, crowned with garlands, was
						the first to raise the marriage hymn as though he were
						singing a song of truest friendship over the union of
						the two greatest and most mighty peoples ; for he, of
						one maid the bridegroom, and at the same time of all
						the brides the escort, as a father and sponsor united
						them in the bonds of wedlock. Indeed at this sight
						I should have cried out for joy, <q direct="unspecified">O dullard Xerxes,
							stupid fool that spent so much fruitless toil to bridge
							the Hellespont! This is the way that wise kings join
							Asia with Europe ; it is not by beams nor rafts, nor by
							lifeless and unfeeling bonds, but by the ties of lawful
							love and chaste nuptials and mutual joy in children
							that they join the nations together.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>Considering carefully this order of affairs,
						Alexander did not favour the Median raiment, but
						preferred the Persian, for it was much more simple
						than the Median. Since he deprecated the unusual
						and theatrical varieties of foreign adornment, such
						as the tiara and the full-sleeved jacket and trousers,
						he wore a composite dress adapted from both
						Persian and Macedonian fashion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xlv. (690 e-691 a); Diodorus, xvii. 77.</note> as Eratosthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably in the treatise referred to by Strabo, i. 4. 9 (p. 66).</note>
						has recorded. As a philosopher what he wore was
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.403"/>
						
						a matter of indifference, but as sovereign of both
						nations and benevolent king he strove to acquire the
						goodwill of the conquered by showing respect for
						their apparel, so that they might continue constant
						in loving the Macedonians as rulers, and might
						not feel hate toward them as enemies. Conversely
						it were the mark of an unwise and vainglorious
						mind to admire greatly a cloak of uniform colour
						and to be displeased by a tunic with a purple
						border, or again to disdain those things and to be
						struck with admiration for these, holding stubbornly,
						in the manner of an unreasoning child, to the raiment
						in which the custom of his country, like a nurse, had
						attired him. When men hunt wild animals, they put
						on the skins of deer, and when they go to catch birds,
						they dress in tunics adorned with plumes and feathers;
						they are careful not to be seen by bulls when they
						have on red garments, nor by elephants when
						dressed in white;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 144 d.</note> for these animals are provoked
						and made savage by the sight of these particular
						colours. But if a great king, in taming and mollifying
						headstrong and warring nations, just as in dealing
						with animals, succeeded in soothing and stilling them
						by wearing a garb familiar to them and by following
						their wonted manner of life, thereby conciliating
						their rough natures and smoothing their sullen
						brows, can men impeach him? Must they not
						rather wonder at his wisdom, since by but a slight
						alteration of his apparel he made himself the popular
						leader of all Asia, conquering their bodies by his
						arms, but winning over their souls by his apparel?
						And yet men marvel at the disciple of Socrates,
						Aristippus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Horace, <hi rend="italics">Epistles</hi>, i. 17. 23-29 <q direct="unspecified">
                        <foreign lang="la">personamque feret non inconcinnus utramque</foreign>.</q>
                  </note> that whether he wore a threadbare
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.405"/>
						
						cloak or a fine Milesian robe he retained his gentility
						in either ; but they impeach Alexander because,
						although paying due respect to his own national
						dress, he did not disdain that of his conquered subjects in establishing the beginnings of a vast empire.
						For he did not overrun Asia like a robber nor was he
						minded to tear and rend it, as if it were booty and
						plunder bestowed by unexpected good fortune, after
						the manner in which Hannibal later descended upon
						Italy, or as earlier the Treres<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, i. 3. 21; xi. 8. 4.</note> descended upon Ionia
						and the Scythians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, i. 15, 103-106.</note> upon Media. But Alexander
						desired to render all upon earth subject to one law of
						reason and one form of government and to reveal all
						men as one people, and to this purpose he made
						himself conform. But if the deity that sent down
						Alexander's soul into this world of ours had not
						recalled him quickly, one law would govern all mankind, and they all would look toward one rule of
						justice as though toward a common source of light.
						But as it is, that part of the world which has not
						looked upon Alexander has remained without sunlight.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>Therefore, in the first place, the very plan and
						design of Alexander's expedition commends the man
						as a philosopher in his purpose not to win for himself
						luxury and extravagant living, but to win for all men
						concord and peace and community of interests.
					</p>
               <p>And, in the second place, let us examine his
						sayings too, since it is by their utterances<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 172 d.</note> that the
						souls of other kings and potentates also best reveal
						their characters. The elder Antigonus remarked to a
						certain sophist who put in his hands a treatise on
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.407"/>
						
						justice, <q direct="unspecified">You are a fool to say anything about justice
							when you see me smiting other peoples cities.</q>
						The despot Dionysius remarked that one should trick
						children with dice, but men with oaths.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed elsewhere to Lysander: <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 229 b, and the note (Vol. III. p. 373).</note> Upon the
						tomb of Sardanapalus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Palatine Anthology</hi>, vii. 325; xvi. 27: a full list of citations portraying Sardanapalus in ancient popular philosophy is given by W. Capelle, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, lx. p. 394; see also W. Headlam, <hi rend="italics">Journal of Philosophy</hi>, xxvi. p. 98.</note> is written.
						<quote rend="blockquote">These are still mine - what I ate, and my wanton love - frolics.</quote>
						Who would not own that by these several sayings are
						revealed Sardanapalus's love of pleasure, Dionysius's
						impiety, and Antigonus's injustice and greed? But
						if you subtract from Alexander's sayings his crown,
						his relationship with Ammon, and his noble birth, they
						will appear to you as the utterances of a Socrates or
						a Plato or a Pythagoras. Let us, then, pay no heed
						to the proud boasts which the poets inscribed upon his
						portraits and statues, studying, as they were, to
						portray, not Alexander's moderation, but his power :
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Eager to speak seems the statue of bronze, up to Zeus as
						</l>
                     <l>it gazes :
						&amp;ldquo;Earth I have set under foot; Zeus, keep Olympus
							yourself.&amp;rdquo;
                     <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                           <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 335 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; T. Preger, <hi rend="italics">Inscriptiones Graecae Metricae</hi> (1891), pp. 183-187. The epigram is more completely given in the <hi rend="italics">Anthology</hi>, xvi. 120, where it is attributed to Archela&uuml;s or Asclepiades. Probably, as Ouvre has seen, it belongs to the latter.</note>
                     </l>
                  </quote>
						And another man makes Alexander say, <q direct="unspecified">I am the
							son of Zeus.</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxvii. (680 f).</note> These expressions, then, as I have
						said, the poets addressed to Alexander in flattery of
						his good fortune.
					</p>
               <p>But of the genuine sayings of Alexander we might
						first review those of his youth. Since he was the
						swiftest of foot of all the young men of his age,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 179 d; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. iv. (666 d).</note> his
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.409"/>
						
						comrades urged him to enter the Olympic games.
						He asked if the competitors were kings, and when his
						friends replied that they were not, he said that the
						contest was unfair, for it was one in which a victory
						would be over commoners, but a defeat would be the
						defeat of a king.
					</p>
               <p>When the thigh of his father Philip had been
						pierced by a spear in battle with the Triballians, and
						Philip, although he escaped with his life, was vexed
						with his lameness, Alexander said, <q direct="unspecified">Be of good
							cheer, father, and go on your way rejoicing, that at
							each step you may recall your valour.</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to a Spartan woman in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 241 e, where see the note.</note> Are not
						these the words of a truly philosophic spirit which,
						because of its rapture for noble things, already
						revolts against mere physical encumbrances? How,
						then, think you, did he glory in his own wounds, remembering by each part of his body affected a nation
						overcome, a victory won, the capture of cities, the
						surrender of kings? He did not cover over nor hide
						his scars, but bore them with him openly as symbolic
						representations, graven on his body, of virtue and
						manly courage.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>And in the same spirit if ever there chanced to
						be in hours of ease or at a banquet a comparison of
						the verses of Homer, each man choosing his favourite
						line, Alexander always judged this verse to be the
						greatest of all:
						<quote rend="blockquote">Both things is he: both a goodly king and a warrior
						mighty.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, iii. 179; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Memorabilia</hi>, iii. 2. 2.</note>
                  </quote>
						This praise, which at the time it was written another
						had received, Alexander conceived to be a law for
						himself, so that he said of Homer that in this same
						verse he had honoured the manly courage of Agamemnon
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.411"/>
						
						and prophesied that of Alexander. Accordingly when he had crossed the Hellespont, he went
						to see the site of Troy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xv. (672 b); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, ix. 38.</note> imagining to himself the
						heroic deeds enacted there ; and when one of the
						natives of the country promised to give him the lyre
						of Paris, if he wished it, Alexander said, <q direct="unspecified">Of his
							lyre I have no need ; for I already possess Achilles'
							lyre to the accompaniment of which, as he rested
							from his labours,
							<quote rend="blockquote">he sang the famed deeds of heroes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 189.</note>
                     </quote>
							But the lyre of Paris gave forth an altogether weak
							and womanish strain to accompany his love songs.</q>
						Thus it is the mark of a truly philosophic soul to be in
						love with wisdom and to admire wise men most of all,
						and this was more characteristic of Alexander than of
						any other king. His attitude toward Aristotle has
						already been stated<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">327 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chaps. vii., viii. (668 a-f).</note>; and it is recorded by several
						authors that he considered the musician Anaxarchus
						the most valuable of all his friends, that he gave ten
						thousand gold pieces to Pyrrhon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Adversus Mathematicos</hi>, i. 282.</note> of Elis the first
						time he met him, that he sent to Xenocrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 333 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 181 e.</note> the
						friend of Plato, fifty talents as a gift, and that he
						made Onesicritus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xiv. (671 d); Diogenes Laertius, vi. 32; Valerius Maximus, iv. 3. 4; Juvenal, xiv. 311-314. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 782 a-b.</note> the pupil of Diogenes the Cynic,
						chief pilot of his fleet.
					</p>
               <p>But when he came to talk with Diogenes g himself
						in Corinth, he was so awed and astounded with the
						life and the worth of the man that often, when remembrance of the philosopher came to him, he would
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.413"/>
						
						say, <q direct="unspecified">If I were not Alexander,I should be Diogenes,</q>
						that is to say: <q direct="unspecified">If I did not actively practise philosophy, I should apply myself to its theoretical pursuit.</q> He did not say, <q direct="unspecified">If I were not a king, I
							should be Diogenes,</q> nor <q direct="unspecified">If I were not rich and
								an Argead</q> ; for he did not rank Fortune above
						Wisdom, nor a crown and royal purple above the
						philosopher's wallet and threadbare gown. But he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">If I were not Alexander, I should be Diogenes</q>;
						that is to say: <q direct="unspecified">If it were not my purpose to combine
							foreign things with things Greek, to traverse and
							civilize every continent, to search out the uttermost
							parts of land and sea, to push the bounds of
							Macedonia to the farthest Ocean, and to disseminate and shower the blessings of Greek justice
							and peace over every nation, I should not be content
							to sit quietly in the luxury of idle power, but I should
							emulate the frugality of Diogenes. But as things
							are, forgive me, Diogenes, that I imitate Heracles,
							and emulate Perseus, and follow in the footsteps of
							Dionysus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iv. 10. 6; <hi rend="italics">Rhein. Mus.</hi> liv. 470.</note>the divine author and progenitor of my
							family,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 326 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and desire that victorious Greeks should
							dance again in India and revive the memory of the
							Bacchic revels among the savage mountain tribes
							beyond the Caucasus. Even there it is said that
							there are certain holy men, a law unto themselves,
							who follow a rigid gymnosophy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chaps. lxiv., lxv. (700 f-701 f) for Alexander's dealing with the Gymnosophists.</note> and give all their
							time to God ; they are more frugal than Diogenes
							since they have no need of a wallet. For they do
							not store up food, since they have it ever fresh
							and green from the earth; the flowing rivers give
							them drink and they have fallen leaves and grassy
							
							<pb id="v.4.p.415"/>
							
							earth to lie upon. Because of me even those faraway sages shall come to know of Diogenes, and he
							of them. And I also, like Diogenes, must alter the
							standard of coinage<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, vi. 20, 21.</note> and stamp foreign states with
							the impress of Greek government.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>Very well. Do Alexander's actions, then, reveal the caprice of Fortune, the violence of war, the
						might of conquest, or do they rather reveal the great
						courage and justice, the great restraint and mildness
						together with the decorous behaviour and intelligence,
						of one who did all things with sober and sane judgement? For, by Heaven, it is impossible for me to
						distinguish his several actions and say that this betokens his courage, this his humanity, this his selfcontrol, but everything he did seems the combined
						product of all the virtues ; for he confirms the truth
						of that principle of the Stoics which declares that
						every act which the wise man performs is an activity
						in accord with every virtue ; and although, as it
						appears, one particular virtue performs the chief role
						in every act, yet it but heartens on the other virtues
						and directs them toward the goal. Certainly one
						may observe that in Alexander the warlike is also
						humane, the mild also manly, the liberal provident,
						the irascible placable, the amatory temperate, his
						relaxation not idle, and his labours not without
						recreation. Who but he combined festivals with wars,
						campaigns with revels, Bacchic rites and weddings
						and nuptial songs with sieges and battle-fields?
						Who was ever more hostile to wrongdoers or kinder
						to the unfortunate? Who more stern to his opponents
						or more indulgent to petitioners?
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.417"/>
						
						It occurs to me to introduce here an incident
						touching Porus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 181 e, and 458 b; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lx. (669 c); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, v. 19. 2.</note> For when Porus was brought as a
						captive before Alexander, the conqueror asked how
						he should treat him. <q direct="unspecified">Like a king, Alexander,</q> said
						Porus. When Alexander asked again if there were
						nothing else, <q direct="unspecified">No,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">for everything is
							included in that word.</q> And it naturally occurs to
						me also to exclaim over each of Alexander's deeds,
						<q direct="unspecified">Like a philosopher !</q> For in this is included
						everything. He became enamoured of Roxan&ecirc;,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 338 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xlvii. (691 e); Arrian, iv. 19; Curtius, viii. 4.</note> the
						daughter of Oxyartes, as she danced among the
						captive maidens ; yet he did not offer any violence to
						her, but made her his wife. <q direct="unspecified">Like a philosopher!</q>
						When he saw Darius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xliii. (690 b).</note> pierced through by javelins,
						he did not offer sacrifice nor raise the paean of
						victory to indicate that the long war had come to an
						end ; but he took off his own cloak and threw it over
						the corpse as though to conceal the divine retribution that waits upon the lot of kings. <q direct="unspecified">Like a
							philosopher!</q> Once when he was reading a confidential letter from his mother, and Hephaestion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 180 d, and the note.</note>
						who, as it happened, was sitting beside him, was
						quite openly reading it too, Alexander did not
						stop him, but merely placed his own signet-ring on
						Hephaestion's lips, sealing them to silence with
						a friend's confidence. <q direct="unspecified">Like a philosopher !</q> For
						if these actions be not those of a philosopher, what
						others are?
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>But let us compare the actions of men who
						are admitted to be philosophers. Socrates forbore
						when Alcibiades<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 218 c; Diogenes Laertius, ii. 31.</note> spent the night with him. But when
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.419"/>
						
						Philoxenus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1099 d; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxii. (676 f).</note> the governor of the coast-lands of Asia
						Minor, wrote to Alexander that there was in Ionia a
						youth, the like of whom for bloom and beauty did not
						exist, and inquired in his letter whether he should
						send the boy on to him. Alexander wrote bitterly in
						reply, <q direct="unspecified">Vilest of men, what deed of this sort have
							you ever been privy to in my past that now you
							would flatter me with the offer of such pleasures?</q>
						We admire Xenocrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 331 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> because he would not accept
						the gift of fifty talents which Alexander sent him.
						But shall we not admire the giving of it? Or do we
						think that he who does not welcome a gift and he
						who bestows it are not at one in their contempt for
						money? Because of philosophy Xenocrates had no
						need of wealth and because of philosophy Alexander
						had need of wealth that he might lavish it upon such
						men. How many times has Alexander said this
						when forcing an attack amid a shower of missiles?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Alexander's remark that he needed money to give to others may be compared to the remark which Plutarch quotes in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lx. (698 e), when Alexander was risking his life in crossing the swollen Hydaspes: <q direct="unspecified">O Athenians, can you possibly believe what dangers I undergo, to win good repute among you?</q> Others think that the remark has been lost from the mss.</note>
						And yet we believe that all men are endowed with
						the capacity to form right judgements. For Nature
						of herself is prone to lead men toward the Good.
						But philosophers differ from common persons in
						having their powers of judgement strong and firm to
						face danger, since the common man is not fortified by
						conceptions such as these : <q direct="unspecified">Best is one omen</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xii. 243 <foreign lang="greek">ei(=s oi)wno\s a)/ristos a)munesqai peri\ pa/trhs</foreign>.</note> and
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.421"/>
						
						            <q direct="unspecified">Death is the end for all men</q>;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 166 f; Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">De Corona</hi>, 97. W. Cr&ouml;nert, in a review of Bell-Crum, <hi rend="italics">A Greek-Coptic Glossary</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Gnomon</hi>, ii. p. 657), reconstructs, from the words of the Testament of the High Priest Fl. Phoebammon, trimeters of an Euripidean flavour:
                     <foreign lang="greek"> 
                     <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>pe/ras de\ panto\s tou= brothsi/ou ge/nous </l>
                     <l>o( qa/natos ou)de\ dunato/n e)stin e)kfugei=n</l>.</quote></foreign>
                      More likely here, however, would be such a line as                       
                      <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l><foreign lang="greek">o( qa/nato/s e)sq' a(/pasin a)nqrw/pois pe/ras</foreign></l>.</quote> 
                        Plutarch and Demosthenes may both be quoting from something of the sort.</note> but crises destroy
						all his calculations in the face of danger, and the
						fantastic imaginings of perils close at hand dispel his
						powers of judgement. For not only does <q direct="unspecified">fear,</q> as
						Thucydides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucydides, ii. 87.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">drive out memory,</q> but it also
						drives out every purpose and ambition and impulse,
						unless philosophy has drawn her cords about them.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.4.p.423"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Yesterday we forgot, it seems, to remark that
						the age of Alexander had the good fortune to produce both many artistic achievements and many men
						of great talent. Perhaps, however, this was not part
						of Alexander's good fortune, but rather that of the
						artists, to have obtained as witness and spectator of
						their achievements the man who was both best able
						to judge of their success and to reward them most
						liberally. At any rate, it is said that, when Archestratus, a poet of a later age, who, though an accomplished writer, was passing his days in poverty and
						neglect, someone remarked to him, <q direct="unspecified">If you had
							been born in Alexander's time, for every verse he
							would have given you a Cyprus or a Phoenicia.</q>
						And I think that the foremost of the artists of that
						age became so, not because they lived in Alexander's
						day, but through what Alexander did for them.
						For a good climate and a lightness of the surrounding air produces a bountiful harvest; and
						likewise the favour, esteem, and benignity shown
						by a king evokes a rich increase in the arts and in
						men of talent. And, conversely, through jealousy
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.425"/>
						
						and parsimony or emulous rivalry on the part of
						monarchs all artistic production is quenched and
						perishes.
					</p>
               <p>Thus the despot Dionysius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 41 d-e.</note> as the story goes,
						while listening to a celebrated harper, engaged to
						give him a talent.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">£200, or $1000.</note> Next day, when the man asked
						for the fulfilment of the promise, Dionysius said,
						<q direct="unspecified">Yesterday I was delighted with your performance,
							and during the time that you were singing I also
							delighted you with hopes ! The result is that at that
							very time you were receiving full pay for the pleasure
							you gave by having your pleasure too!</q>
						Alexander,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Pelopidas</hi>, xxix. (293 f); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xiv. 40.</note> the tyrant of Pherae (this last should
						be his only appellation ; he should not be permitted
						to disgrace the name of Alexander), as he watched
						a tragic actor, felt himself much moved to pity
						through enjoyment of the acting. He jumped up,
						therefore, and left the theatre at a rapid pace, exclaiming that it would be a dreadful thing, if, when
						he was slaughtering so many citizens, he should be
						seen to weep over the sufferings of Hecuba and
						Polyxena. And he came near visiting punishment
						upon the actor because the man had softened his
						heart, as iron in the fire.
					</p>
               <p>Archela&uuml;s<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 177 b, and the note.</note> was thought to be somewhat niggardly
						in his favours, and Timotheus liked to hint at this by
						often chanting this refrain :
						<quote rend="blockquote">Over the earth-born silver you rave.</quote>
						But Archela&uuml;s, with some wit, chanted in reply :
						<quote rend="blockquote">That, however, is what you crave.</quote>
						
						            <pb id="v.4.p.427"/>
						
					          </p>
               <p>Ateas, the Scythian king, took the flute-player
						Ismenias captive, and ordered him to play at a
						banquet. The rest were delighted, and applauded,
						but Ateas swore his horse's neighing was sweeter to
						his ear.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 174 f, and the note.</note> So far from the Muses' habitation did he
						allow his ears to dwell, and his soul he kept in the
						mangers,better attuned to hear, not horses' neigh,but
						asses ' bray ! At the court of monarchs such as these
						what advancement or esteem could there be for Art,
						or for Poetry and Music of excellence? Nor, again,
						could artistic endeavour flourish at the court of those
						who wish to be rival performers in these arts, and
						thus through malice and ill-will suppress the true
						artists. Such a prince was Dionysius (to use him
						again as an example), who threw the poet Philoxenus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 471 e; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 22 (63); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xii. 44; Diodorus, xv. 6.</note>
						into the stone-quarries ; for when Dionysius ordered
						him to correct a tragedy of his, Philoxenus cancelled
						the whole piece from the very beginning to the final
						flourish.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <hi rend="italics">coronis</hi> at the end of the roll.</note>
					          </p>
               <p>Philip also was in these matters somewhat more
						petty and childish than became him, since he had
						acquired his knowledge late in life. Thus they tell
						the tale that Philip<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 67 f, 179 b, 634 d.</note> once argued with a certain
						harp-player about the technique of his instrument,
						and even thought he was confuting the man; but
						the harp-player smiled gently and said, <q direct="unspecified">God forbid,
							your Majesty, that you should ever fall so low as to
							know more of these matters than I.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>But Alexander, knowing well in what matters
						he should be merely a spectator and listener, and in
						what he should play the chief role, trained himself
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.429"/>
						
						always to be formidable in arms, and. in the words of
						Aeschylus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 317 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note>
						            <quote rend="blockquote">Sturdy contender in arms, baleful to all that oppose.</quote>
						This art he inherited from his ancestors, the
						Aeacidae, and from Heracles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. ii. (665 b).</note>; but upon the other
						arts he freely bestowed honour without jealousy
						according to their worth and artistic excellence ; but
						he was not so easily carried away by the pleasure
						they give him as to try to imitate them. The tragic
						actors of his time were the group that centred
						about Thettalus and Athenodorus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> chap. xxix. (681 d).</note> At the contest
						of these two, the kings of Cyprus defrayed the
						expenses of the performance and Alexander's most
						celebrated generals served as judges. When Athenodorus won, <q direct="unspecified">I would rather,</q> said Alexander, <q direct="unspecified">have
							lost half my kingdom than see Thettalus defeated.</q>
						However, he did not intercede with the judges nor
						find fault with the judgement, since he felt that,
						while he must be superior to all men, yet he must
						submit to Justice.
					</p>
               <p>The comic actors of his time were the group that
						centred about Lycon of Scarpheia.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> chap. xxix. (681 d).</note> When Lycon
						inserted in one of his comedies a begging verse,
						Alexander laughed and gave him ten talents.
					</p>
               <p>Various harp-players also were his friends, among
						them Aristonicus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iv. 16. 7.</note> who came to Alexander's aid in
						a certain battle, and was slain fighting gloriously.
						Therefore Alexander ordered to be made and set up
						at Delphi a bronze statue of him, with lyre in hand
						and spear advanced ; thereby he not only honoured
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.431"/>
						
						this particular man, but also paid tribute to Music
						herself, in the belief that she is a creator of true
						men and, in particular, that she filis with inspiration
						and impetuousness those who are truly her fosterchildren. For once Upon a time, when Antigenides
						was playing on his flute the Chariot Song,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1133 e (= Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, i. pp. 4-8). See also Dio Chrysostom, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi> i. 1-2, where Timotheus is the flute-player and the tune the Orthian.</note> Alexander
						became so transported, and his spirit so inflamed by
						the strains, that he leapt up and laid hands upon
						the weapons that lay near, and thus confirmed the
						testimony of the Spartans who used to sing,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to Alcman in <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xxi. (53 d); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 51, or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, i. p. 90.</note>
						            <quote rend="blockquote">The noble playing of the lyre is meet to match the sword.</quote>
					          </p>
               <p>Apelles the painter and Lysippus the sculptor also
						lived in the time of Alexander. The former painted
						<q direct="unspecified">Alexander wielding the Thunderbolt</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. iv. (666 b); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, xxxv. 10 (92).</note> so vividly
						and with so natural an expression, that men said that,
						of the two Alexanders, Alexander, son of Philip, was
						invincible, but the Alexander of Apelles was inimitable. And when Lysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. iv. (666 b).</note> modelled his first statue
						of Alexander which represented him looking up
						with his face turned towards the heavens (as indeed
						Alexander often did look, with a slight inclination of
						his head to one side<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. ibid.</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 53 d.</note>),someone engraved these verses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 331 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note>
						on the statue, not without some plausibility,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Eager to speak seems the statue of bronze, up to Zeus as
						it gazes :
						</l>
                     <l>
                     &amp;ldquo;Earth I have set under foot: Zeus, keep Olympus
							yourself!&amp;rdquo;
                  </l>
                  </quote>
						
						            <pb id="v.4.p.433"/>
						
						Wherefore Alexander gave orders that Lysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, vii. 37 (125); Horace, <hi rend="italics">Epistles</hi>, ii. 1. 240; Valerius Maximus, viii. 11. 2; Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, i. 16. 4.</note>
						only should make statues of him. For Lysippus was,
						it seemed, the only one that revealed in the bronze
						Alexander's character and in moulding his form
						portrayed also his virtues. The others wished to
						imitate the flexing of his neck and the melting and
						liquid softness of his eyes, but were unable to preserve his virile and leonine expression.
					</p>
               <p>Among the other artists at his court was Stasicrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxxii. (705 a): the man is called Deinocrates by Vitruvius, ii. praef.; and Cheirocrates by the mss. of Strabo, xiv. 1. 23.</note>
						the master-sculptor, not seeking to make something
						flowery or pleasant or lifelike to look upon, but employing a magnificence in workmanship and design
						worthy of a king's munificence. He followed
						Alexander into Asia and found fault with the
						paintings, sculptures, and moulded likenesses that
						had been made of him, on the ground that they
						were the works of timid and ignoble artists. <q direct="unspecified">But
							I, your Majesty,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">have conceived the
								project of placing your likeness in living and imperishable material, with roots that are everlasting
								and weight immovable and unshakable. For Mount
								Athos in Thrace, in that part where is its highest and
								most conspicuous summit, has well-proportioned surfaces and heights, limbs and joints and proportions that
								suggest the human form. When it has been properly
								carved and worked into shape, it can be called
								Alexander's statue, and Alexander's statue it will
								be ; with its base set in the sea, in its left hand it will
								encompass and hold a city peopled with ten thousand
								
								<pb id="v.4.p.435"/>
								
								inhabitants, and with its right pour from a bowl of libation an ever-flowing river down into the sea. But as
								for gold and bronze, ivory, wooden timbers, and dyes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The reference is to the chryselephantine statues of Pheidias and his school with their inner frame-work of timbers, and painted without.</note>
								which make those paltry images that can be bought and
								sold, stolen, or melted down, let us reject them all!</q>
						Alexander listened to his words and admired but declined with thanks the lofty designs and the boldness of
						the artist. <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> said he, &ldquo;let Athos remain as it is.
						It is enough that it be the memorial of the arrogance
						of one king<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xerxes' canal; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 342 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; but my imprint the Caucasus shall
						show and the Emodian<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A range of north-western India, the Prakrit Haimota; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Indica</hi>, 2. 3; 6. 4; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, vi. 17 (56).</note> range and the Tana&iuml;s and the
						Caspian Sea ; these will be the image of my deeds.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>But imagine, pray, that such a work had been
						completed and made evident to men's eyes. Is there
						anyone who could look upon it and suppose that
						the form, the arrangement, and the appearance were
						created by Fortune and Accident? No one, I think.
						What of Apelles' <q direct="unspecified">Wielder of the Thunderbolt</q>?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 335 a, <hi rend="italics">supra, Moralia</hi> 360 d.</note>
						What of the statue which takes its name from the
						Spear?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 335 a, <hi rend="italics">supra, Moralia</hi>, 360 d.</note> Shall we admit, then, that greatness in a
						statue cannot, without the help of Art,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 99 b-c.</note> be created
						by Fortune's profuse provision of gold and bronze and
						ivory and much rich material, but is it possible that a
						great man, or rather the greatest man of all that have
						ever lived, without the help of Virtue, was perfected
						through Fortunes supplying him with arms and
						money, foot and horse? But for him who has not
						learned how to use these things they are a danger,
						not a strength and enrichment, but a means of
						proving his weakness and pettiness. For Antisthenes
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.437"/>
						
						was right when he said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, lix. 41 (Hense, vol. iv. p. 362).</note> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">We should pray that our
							enemies be provided with all good things, except courage ; for thus these good things will belong, not to their
							owners, but to those that conquer them.</q> Therefore
						they say that Nature also for defence has caused horns,
						wonderful for their size and jagged points, to grow
						upon the deer, the most cowardly of all animals ; and
						therein does Nature teach us that strength and arms
						are of no benefit to such as have not the courage to
						stand their ground. Thus also Fortune, by frequently
						bestowing on cowards and fools military forces and
						dominions, in which they disgrace themselves, emblazons and commends Virtue as the one quality
						that constitutes the greatness and beauty of man.
						For if indeed, as Epicharmus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An oft-quoted line. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> G. Kaibel, <hi rend="italics">Comicorum Graec. Frag.</hi> i. 137, Epicharmus, no. 249; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 98 c, with the note; also Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disp.</hi> i. 20 (46); Maximus Tyrius, xi. 10.</note> says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Mind has sight and Mind has hearing;</quote>
						but
						<quote rend="blockquote">All things else are deaf and blind;</quote>
						then it happens that these are really lacking in reason.
						For our perceptive faculties seem to respond to their
						own special stimuli; but the fact that it is mind which
						aids us and mind which emblazons our deeds, and it is
						mind that conquers and overpowers and plays the
						monarch, and that <q direct="unspecified">all things else,</q> since they are
						<q direct="unspecified">blind and deaf</q> and soulless, mislead and burden
						and disgrace their possessors, if Virtue be not
						present,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Menexenus</hi>, 246 e.</note> is a truth which may be gleaned from
						history.
					</p>
               <p>Now of the two monarchs Semiramis and Sardanapalus, in whose hands were placed the same power
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.439"/>
						
						and dominion, Semiramis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, ii. 4-20; Justin, i. 2.</note> though a woman, equipped
						great expeditions, armed her ranks, established the
						Babylonian Empire, and sailed about the Persian
						Gulf subduing the Ethiopians and Arabs. But
						Sardanapalus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 326 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Diodorus, ii. 21. 8 ff; Athenaeus, 528 f; W. K. Prentice, in <hi rend="italics">Trans. Amer. Phil. Assoc.</hi> liv. (1923) p. 79: but the theory rightly set forth, there, that this description comes from Ctesias's <hi rend="italics">Persica</hi>, is as old as Hemsterhuys; see Wyttenbach's note on this passage.</note> though born a man, spent his days at
						home carding purple wool, sitting with his knees drawn
						up in front of him among his concubines ; and when
						he died, they made a stone statue of him dancing
						in a barbaric fashion and apparently snapping its
						fingers above its head. They engraved upon it :
						<q direct="unspecified">Eat, drink, and sport with love ; all else is naught.</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on 330 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					          </p>
               <p>When Crates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 401 a; Athenaeus, 591 b; Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, vi. 39 (vol. iii. p. 296 Hense).</note> saw a golden statue of Phryn&ecirc; the
						courtesan standing at Delphi, he cried out that it
						stood there as a monument to Greek licentiousness ;
						and thus if one examine either the life or the tomb
						of Sardanapalus (for I think there is no difference
						between them), one would say that they are a
						monument to the bounty of Fortune. But if this
						be so, shall we allow Fortune to lay hold upon
						Alexander after Sardanapalus, and to lay claim to
						Alexander's greatness and power? For what greater
						gift did she bestow on him than those which other
						monarchs received at her hands : arms, horses,
						missiles, money, guardsmen? Let Fortune endeavour to make an Aridaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 337 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> great by these, if
						she can, or an Ochus or Oarses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 337 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> or Tigranes the
						Armenian, or the Bithynian Nicomedes. Of these
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.441"/>
						
						Tigranes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Pompey</hi>, chap. xxxiii. (637 a); <hi rend="italics">Comp. of Cimon and Lucullus</hi>, iii. (522 e); Velleius Paterculus, ii. 37; Valerius Maximus, v. 1. 10.</note> cast down his crown before the feet of
						Pompey and ignominiously received back his kingdom,
						which had become the spoil of war. But Nicomedes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch has confused Nicomedes with his father Prusias; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Polybius, xxx. 19; Livy, xlv. 44; Diodorus, xxxi. 15; Appian, <hi rend="italics">Mithridatica</hi>, 2.</note>
						shaved his head and put on the freedman's cap and
						proclaimed himself an emancipated slave of the
						Roman people.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Shall we say, then, that Fortune makes men
						petty, timid, and abject in spirit? Yet it is not
						right for anyone to charge baseness to misfortune,
						or courage and intelligence to good fortune ; but
						Fortune was magnified by Alexander's reign, for in
						him she was illustrious, invincible, magnanimous,
						inoffensive, and humane. Then, immediately after
						Alexander's decease, Leosthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The saying is elsewhere attributed to Demades; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 181 f, and the note.</note> said that his
						forces, as they wandered here and there and fell foul
						of their own efforts, were like the Cyclops after his
						blinding, groping about everywhere with his hands,
						which were directed at no certain goal; even thus
						did that vast throng roam about with no safe footing,
						blundering through want of a leader. Or rather, in
						the manner of dead bodies, after the soul departs,
						when they are no longer held together by natural
						forces, but undergo dispersion and dissolution, and
						finally are dissipated and disappear altogether ; even
						so Alexander's forces, having lost him, maintained a
						gasping, agitated, and fevered existence through men
						like Perdiccas, Meleager, Seleucus, and Antigonus,
						who, as it were, provided still a warm breath of life
						and blood that still pulsed and circulated. But at
						length the host wasted away and perished, generating
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.443"/>
						
						about itself maggots, as it were, of ignoble kings and
						rulers in their last death-struggle. This, then, it is
						likely that Alexander himself meant when he rebuked
						Hephaestion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xlvii. (691 f-692 a).</note> for quarrelling with Craterus: <q direct="unspecified">What</q>
						said he, <q direct="unspecified">will be your power and your achievements
							if someone deprive you of Alexander?</q> Rut I, for
						my part, shall not hesitate to say this very thing to
						the Fortune that presided over Alexander's career :
						<q direct="unspecified">What is your greatness or your repute? Where is
							your power or your invincibility, if someone deprive
							you of Alexander?</q> That is to say, <q direct="unspecified">If someone
								deprive you of your skill in arms, your munificent
								use of riches, your self-restraint in expending them,
								your boldness against your foes in battle, your mildness toward the vanquished? Make another great,
								if you can ; but one that shall not be generous with
								his substance, nor court danger in the front ranks, nor
								give honour to his friends, nor feel pity for his captives, nor be temperate in his pleasures, nor sleepless
								in crises, nor placable in his victories, nor humane
								amid his successes. What man is great in the
								exercise of power, if folly and wickedness attend
								him? Take away virtue from the fortunate man
								and in everything he is petty ; in acts of generosity,
								through parsimony ; in hard tasks, through softness ;
								in religion, through superstition; towards the good,
								through envy; among men, through cowardice ;
								among women, through wantonness.</q> Just as
						inexpert artisans, who construct large pedestals for
						petty offerings, make the smallness of the offerings
						noticeable, so Fortune, whenever she elevates a
						petty character by acts that have a certain pomp
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.445"/>
						
						and circumstance, makes the more conspicuous and
						disgraceful the blundering and instability that result
						from a shallow character.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>Wherefore greatness lies, not in the possession
						of good things, but in our use of them, since even
						infant children inherit their fathers' kingdoms and
						dominions, even as Charillus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. iii. (41 a).</note> whom Lycurgus carried
						in his swaddling-clothes into the common dining-hall
						and proclaimed king of Sparta in place of himself.
						Assuredly it was not the child who was great, but he
						who surrendered to the child its paternal rights, and
						did not keep them for himself nor take them away.
					</p>
               <p>But who could have made Aridaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 791 e.</note> great, whom,
						differing no whit from a child, only that his swaddlingclothes were royal purple, Meleager set on the throne
						of Alexander? And indeed it was well that he did
						so, that for a few days it might be observed how it
						is that men rule by right of virtue and how by gift
						of Fortune. For in succession to a real competitor
						for sovereignty Meleager introduced a mere actor,
						or rather, did a mute figure wearing a crown parade
						across the stage, as it were, of the inhabited world.
						<quote rend="blockquote">Even a woman can carry a burden if a man impose it
						upon her.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Knights</hi>, 1056; see Rogers's note <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </quote>
						Conversely, however, one might affirm that it lies
						within the strength of even a woman or a child to
						take up and impose the gifts of power and wealth
						and sovereignty. The eunuch Bagoas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 14. 5; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, vi. 8; Diodorus, xvii. 5.</note> took up the
						kingship of Persia and bestowed it upon Oarses and
						Darius.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 326 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> But the ability to sustain and administer
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.447"/>
						
						great authority when one has once received it, and
						not to be crushed or turned from ones purpose by
						the weight and the magnitude of one's activities, is
						the mark of a man who possesses virtue, sense, and
						intelligence. This virtue Alexander possessed, whom
						some accuse of drunkenness and a passion for wine I
						Rut he was truly a great man, for in his conduct of
						affairs he was sober, nor was he made drunk nor led to
						revelling by authority and power ; but others, when
						they get but a small portion, or even a taste, of power
						are unable to control themselves :
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Bad men, when gorged with wealth, or chancing on
						</l>
                     <l>Some honours in the State, caper and prance
						</l>
                     <l>When luck, unhoped for, to their house has come.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From a much longer fragment of Euripides' <hi rend="italics">Erechtheus</hi>; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 471, Euripides, no. 362, 29-31.</note>
                     </l>
                  </quote>
						Cleitus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, xviii. 15. 9. 72.</note> when he had scuttled three or four Greek
						triremes at Amorgos, caused himself to be proclaimed
						Poseidon and carried a trident. Demetrius, to whom
						Fortune added the little that she was able to subtract
						from Alexander's power, allowed himself to be called
						<q direct="unspecified">The Heaven-descended,</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">Avatar,</q> he that desceds from Heaven (in thunder and lightning), a common title of Zeus; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Demetrius</hi>, chaps. x., xi. (893 d, e).</note> and the subject states
						did not send ambassadors to him, but <q direct="unspecified">Sacred
							Deputies,</q> and his replies they spoke of as <q direct="unspecified">Oracles.</q>
						Lysimacho, who obtained possession of the regions
						adjoining Thrace, the mere outskirts of the kingdom
						of Alexander, as it were, reached such a pitch of
						arrogance and boldness as to say, <q direct="unspecified">The Byzantines
							now come to me when I am touching Heaven with
							my spear.</q> But Pasiades of Byzantium, who was
						present, said, <q direct="unspecified">Let us be off, lest he make a hole
							in the sky with his spear-point!</q>
						
						            <pb id="v.4.p.449"/>
						
					          </p>
               <p>And yet why should anyone mention these men
						who might have some legitimate ground for pride
						because of Alexander, when even Clearchus, after he
						became despot of Heracleia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In Pontus: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 526.</note> used to carry a thunderbolt,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> a <hi rend="italics">skepton</hi>, instead of <hi rend="italics">skeptron</hi>, <q direct="unspecified">sceptre.</q>
                  </note> and named one of his sons Thunderer? And
						Dionysius the younger styled himself the son of
						Apollo in the inscription :
						<quote rend="blockquote">Sprung from a Dorian mother by union with Phoebus
						Apollo.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 324.</note>
                  </quote>
						And Dionysius's father killed ten thousand or more
						citizens, and, led on by envy, betrayed his brother
						to the enemy, nor could he wait for his already aged
						mother to die a few days later, but strangled her<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xiii. 45.</note>;
						yet in one of his tragedies he wrote these words<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 797, Dionysius, no. 7.</note>:
						<quote rend="blockquote">The mother of foul wrong is tyranny !</quote>
						Notwithstanding, of his daughters he named one
						Virtue, another Temperance, a third Justice.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Dion</hi>, chap. vi. (960 c).</note> And
						yet other persons publicly styled themselves Benefactors,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably Ptolemy Euergetes II. Physcon (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Athenaeus xii. 549 d), rather than Philopater (<hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 56 e, Polybius v. 34), is alluded to.</note> Conquerors, Saviours, or The Great; but
						no one would be able to tell the tale of their
						marriages one after another, like the matings of
						horses, as they spent their days with no restraint
						amid herds of women, their corruption of boys, their
						beating of drums in the company of emasculated
						men, their daily dicing, their flute-playing in the
						public theatres, the night that was too short for
						them at their dinners, and the day at their breakfasts.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>But Alexander took his breakfast at daybreak
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.451"/>
						
						seated<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxiii. (677 d).</note>; he dined late in the evening ; he drank
						only after sacrificing to the gods ; he played dice
						with Medius when he had a fever<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> chap. lxxvi. (706 d).</note>; he played games
						while travelling, at the same time also learning to
						wield a bow and mount a chariot. For himself he
						married Roxan&ecirc;,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 332 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> the only woman he ever loved;
						but Stateira,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxx. (703 e); Diodorus, xvii. 107; Justin, xii. 10.</note> the daughter of Darius, he married
						for imperial and political reasons, since the union
						of the two races was highly advantageous. But
						as for the other Persian women, he was as much
						their superior in self-control as in valour he was
						superior to Persian men. For he looked at no
						woman against her will<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 97 d, 522 a; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxi. (676 f).</note> and those that he looked
						at he passed by more readily than those that he
						did not look at; and although he bore himself
						humanely toward all other persons, it was toward fair
						youth alone that he conducted himself haughtily.
						He would not listen to a single word in praise of the
						beauty of the wife<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> chap. xxii. (677 a); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iv. 20; Athenaeus, xiii. 603 c; Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, iv. 10.</note> of Darius, who was a very handsome woman; but when she died, he graced her
						funeral with such a royal pomp and bewailed her death
						so feelingly that his self-control was questioned amid
						his display of humanity, and his goodness incurred the
						charge of wrongdoing. For Darius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxx. (682 c-d).</note> was disturbed
						by suspicion of Alexander's power and youth ; for he
						also was still one of those who believed Alexander's
						victory to be through Fortune. But when he had
						tested the matter from every angle, and recognized the truth, <q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">the lot of the
							Persians is not so utterly wretched, nor will anyone
							say that we are altogether cowardly or unmanly in
							
							<pb id="v.4.p.453"/>
							
							that we have been overcome by such a man. But
							for my part I pray the gods for fair fortune and for
							might in war, that I may surpass Alexander in bestowing favours ; and I am possessed by an ambitious
							and emulous desire to prove myself more humane
							than Alexander. But if my power be spent, do thou,
							O Zeus, ancestral god of the Persians, and ye other
							gods that guard our kingship, grant that none other
							than Alexander take his seat upon the throne of
							Cyrus.</q> This was Darius's way of adopting Alexander,
						invoking the gods as witnesses.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>Thus do men prevail through Virtue. Ascribe
						to Fortune, if you will, Arbela and the Cilician
						victory and his other deeds of violence and war :
						Fortune battered down the walls of Tyre<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxv. (679 a); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 23.</note> for him ;
						Fortune opened the way to Egypt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 326 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; through Fortune Halicarnassus fell, and Miletus was captured,
						and Mazaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iii. 7. 2.</note> left the Euphrates unguarded, and the
						Babylonian plain was strewn with corpses. But at
						least it was not in any way Fortune's gift that he was
						temperate, nor was it because of Fortune that he was
						self-controlled, nor did Fortune lock his soul and keep
						it impregnable to pleasure and invulnerable to desire ; in fact, these were the qualities by which he
						defeated Darius himself. The rest were but defeats
						of arms and horses, battles, slaughters, and routs of
						men. But the truly great and indisputable defeat
						Darius suffered : he yielded in virtue and greatness
						of soul, in prowess and Justice, and marvelled at
						Alexander's invincibility in pleasure, in toil, in the
						bestowal of favours. It is true that Tarrias,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Tarrias is elsewhere unknown; the stories here related of him are told of Antigenes in <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxx. (703 e-f).</note> son of
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.455"/>
						
						Deinomenes, and Antigenes of Pallen&ecirc;, and Philo t as,
						the son of Parinenion, were also invincible at least
						amid shields, pikes, battle-cries, and the clash of
						arms; but towards pleasures and women and gold
						and silver they were no better than their captives. In fact, when Alexander was freeing the
						Macedonians from debt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 343 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vii. 5. 1-3.</note> and paying creditors for
						everybody, Tarrias said falsely that he was a debtor,
						and produced at the bank a person who asserted that
						he was Tarrias s creditor ; later, when he was detected,
						he was ready to commit suicide had not Alexander,
						coming to know of this, exculpated him, and allowed
						him to keep the money ; for the king remembered
						that when Philip was assaulting Perinthus, Tarrias,
						although his eye was pierced by a missile, would not
						submit nor suffer the shaft to be extracted until they
						had routed the enemy.
					</p>
               <p>Antigenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 181 a; but told of Eurylochus in <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xli. (689 b).</note> joined himself with those who were
						being sent back to Macedonia because of sickness or
						wounds,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxxi. (704 b).</note> and had himself enrolled among them ; but
						when, however, it was discovered that he had nothing
						wrong with him, but was feigning some infirmity, and
						it was seen that he was a stout fighting man whose
						body was covered with wounds, the matter vexed
						Alexander. When he asked the reason for such
						conduct, Antigenes confessed that he was in love
						with Telesippa, and was accompanying her to the sea,
						since he could not be left behind if she went away.
						<q direct="unspecified">Whose is she?</q> asked Alexander, <q direct="unspecified">and to whom
							must we speak?</q> Antigenes replied that she was
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.457"/>
						
						free-born. <q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said Alexander, <q direct="unspecified">let us persuade her with promises and presents to remain behind.</q> So ready was he with an excuse for every
						lover rather than for himself.
					</p>
               <p>And further, Philotas,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chaps. xlviii., xlix. (692 a-693 a).</note> the son of Parmenion, had
						in his licentiousness the nurse, as it were, of all his
						ills. For among the captives taken at Damascus
						was a courtesan from Pella, by name Antigona. Ere
						this she had crossed over to Samothrace, and there
						had been taken captive by Autophradates. She was
						comely enough to look upon and, after Philotas had
						attached himself to her, she had complete possession of him. Indeed that man of iron<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Doric form suggests quotation from some poem or drama.</note> was so
						softened that he was not in control of his reasoning
						powers amid his pleasures, but unlocked and brought
						forth many of his secrets for the woman : <q direct="unspecified">What
							was that famed Philip, were it not for Parmenion?
							What was this Alexander, were it not for Philotas?
							Where his Ammon, and where his serpents,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A reference, perhaps, to Ammon (<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> Zeus) in the form of a serpent, seen with Olympias, as told in <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. iii. (665 d); or perhaps to the expedition to the oracle of Ammon, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iii. 3. 5.</note> if we do
							not wish it so?</q> These words Antigona reported to
						an intimate friend of hers among the women, and
						she reported them to Craterus ; Craterus brought
						Antigona herself secretly to Alexander, who did not
						touch her person, but restrained himself and, working
						secretly through her, he discovered the whole of
						Philotas's plans. And for a period of more than seven
						years Alexander never revealed his suspicion ; not in
						his cups, the reputed drunkard I not in anger, this
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.459"/>
						
						man of fiery temper! not to a friend, this man who
						trusted Hephaestion in everything and shared everything with him! In fact it is recorded<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 333 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that once,
						when he had broken the seal of a confidential letter
						from his mother and was reading it silently<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">Silently,</q> for reading was generally done aloud.</note> to himself, Hephaestion quietly put his head beside Alexander's and read the letter with him; Alexander
						could not bear to stop him, but took off his ring and
						placed the seal on Hephaestion's lips.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>But one might grow weary in the enumeration
						of these matters by which Alexander is shown to have
						made the most honourable and the most regal use of
						his authority. And even though he became great
						through Fortune, he is even greater in that he made
						good use of his Fortune. And the more we praise
						his Fortune the more shall we exalt his Virtue by
						reason of which he became worthy of his Fortune.
					</p>
               <p>Now, however, I shall proceed at once to the first
						steps in his advancement and the beginnings of his
						power, and I shall examine in those matters the role
						played by Fortune, by reason of which men assert
						that Alexander became great through the instrumentality of Fortune. In Heaven's name ! Why
						do they not assert this of one that never felt a wound
						nor lost a drop of blood nor ever served in Avar, whom
						the neighing of a horse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, iii. 84 ff.</note> placed upon the throne of
						Cyrus, even as the first Darius, the son of Hystaspes?
						Or of Xerxes, whom a king, flattered by his wife, as
						Darius was flattered by Atossa,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vii. 3.</note> set upon the throne?
						Did the royal diadem come to Alexander's doors, as
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.461"/>
						
						to Oarses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Artaxerxes: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 336 e, 337 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, <hi rend="italics">Life of Artaxerxes</hi>, chap. i. (1012 a): Reiske conjectured <foreign lang="greek">*)/arsh|</foreign> from Diodorus, xvii. 5, which may be right. But Bagoas also put Darius III. on the throne of Persia. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 326 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> through the machinations of Bagoas, who
						stripped from him the garb of a courier and put upon
						him the royal raiment and the tiara that ever stands
						erect<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the upright tiara <hi rend="italics">cf. e.g.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 5. 23; <hi rend="italics">Life of Themistocles</hi>, chap. xxix. (126 e); <hi rend="italics">Life of Artaxerxes</hi>, chaps. xxvi., xxviii. (1024 e, 1025 e).</note>? Was he suddenly and unexpectedly chosen
						by lot and thus carne to rule the inhabited world,
						as at Athens the Thesmothetae and Archons attain
						their office?
					</p>
               <p>Would you learn how it is that men come to the
						throne by choice of Fortune? Once upon a time
						among the Argives the family of Heracleidae became
						extinct, from which family it was their ancestral
						custom to select the Argive kings. When in their
						search they made inquiry of the god at Delphi, he
						replied that an eagle would show them , and a few
						days later an eagle appeared on high and, swooping
						down, alighted on the house of Aegon, and Aegon was
						chosen king.
					</p>
               <p>Again in Paphos when the reigning king was
						seen to be unjust and wicked. Alexander expelled
						him and searched for another, since the family of
						Cinyradae appeared to be already passing away or
						extinct. However, they told him that there still
						survived one poor and obscure person, who eked out
						a forsaken existence in a certain garden. Men were
						sent to fetch him and, when they arrived, he was
						found watering his garden-plots ; and he was much
						perturbed when the soldiers laid hands on him and
						ordered him to come with them. He was brought
						before Alexander and, dressed as he was in a single
						cheap garment, he was proclaimed king, and received
						the royal purple, and became one of those who are
						styled the king's <q direct="unspecified">Companions.</q> His name was
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.463"/>
						
						Abdalonymus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cobet's conjecture (Abdalonymus for Aralynomus) is only very partially supported by Diodorus, xvii. 46. 47. But <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the references <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi> in Fischer's ed. (Leipzig 1906), especially Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, iv. 1. 19.</note> Thus does shifting Fortune create
						kings, change their raiment, and quickly and easily
						alter the status of men who cxpect nothing of the sort,
						and do not even hope for it.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>But what greatness did Alexander acquire beyond his just merits, what without sweat, what without blood, what without a price, what without labour?
						He drank rivers fouled with blood, crossed streams
						bridged by dead bodies, through hunger ate the first
						grass that he saw, dug through nations buried in deep
						snow<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, xvii. 82; Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, v. 3.</note> and cities built beneath the earth, sailed over
						a battling sea<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vi. 19; Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, ix. 9.</note>; and as he traversed the parching
						strands of Gedrosia and Arachosia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxvi. (702 a); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vi. 22 ff; Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, ix. 10.</note> it was in the sea,
						not on the land, that first he saw a living plant.
					</p>
               <p>If to Fortune, as to a human being, one might
						present Frankness in Alexander's behalf, would she
						not say, &ldquo;When and where did you ever vouchsafe a
						way for the exploits of Alexander? What fortress
						did he ever capture by your help without the shedding
						of blood? What city unguarded or what regiment
						unarmed did you deliver into his hands? What king
						was found to be indolent, or what general negligent,
						or what watchman asleep at the gate? But no
						river was easy to cross, no storm was moderate, no
						summer's heat was without torment. Betake yourself to Antiochus, the son of Seleucus, or to Artaxerxes, the brother of Cyrus ; depart to Ptolemy
						Philadelphus ! Their fathers, while yet alive, proclaimed
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.465"/>
						
						them kings ; they won battles that did not
						cost a tear ; they made merry all their lives in processions and theatres; and every one of them, because of good fortune, grew old upon the throne.
					</p>
               <p>&ldquo;But in the case of Alexander, though I were to
						mention nothing else, behold his body gashed with
						wounds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the wounds of Alexander see the note on 327 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, with the work of Nachst&auml;dt there referred to.</note> from tip to toe, bruised all over, smitten at
						the hands of his enemies
						<quote rend="blockquote">Now with the spear, now the sword, now with mighty
						masses of boulders.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 265, 541.</note>
                  </quote>
						On the banks of the Granicus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 327 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the notes.</note> his helmet was cleft
						through to his scalp by a sword ; at Gaza his shoulder
						was wounded by a missile ; at Maracanda his shin
						was so torn by an arrow that by the force of the blow
						the larger bone was broken and extruded. Somewhere in Hyrcania his neck was smitten by a stone,
						whereby his sight was dimmed, and for many days
						he was haunted by the fear of blindness. Among the
						Assacenians his ankle was wounded by an Indian
						arrow ; that was the time when he smilingly said to
						his flatterers, &lsquo;this that you see is blood, not
						<quote rend="blockquote">Ichor, that which flows from the wounds of the blessed
						immortals.&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> v. 340; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 180 e and the note.</note>
                  </quote>
						At Issus he was wounded in the thigh with a sword,
						as Chares<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xx. (675 e-f).</note> states, by Darius the king, who had come
						into hand-to-hand conflict with him. Alexander
						himself wrote of this simply, and with complete truth,
						in a letter to Antipater : &lsquo;I myself happened,&rsquo; he
						writes, &lsquo;to be wounded in the thigh by a dagger.
						But nothing untoward resulted from the blow either
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.467"/>
						
						immediately or later.&rsquo; Among the Mallians he was
						wounded in the breast by an arrow three feet long,
						which penetrated his breastplate, and someone rode
						up under him, arid struck him in the neck, as Aristobulus relates. When he had crossed the Taiiais
						against the Scythians and had routed them, he
						pursued them on horseback an hundred and fifty
						stades, though he was grievously distressed with
						diarrhoea.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xlv. (691 a); Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iv. 4. 9; Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, vii. 9, 13.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">Well done. Fortune ! You exalt Alexander
						and make him great by running him through from
						every side, by making him lose his footing, by laying
						open every portion of his body. Not like Athena
						before Menela&uuml;s<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 129.</note> did you guide the missile to the
						stoutest parts of his armour, and by breastplate, belt,
						and kilt take away the intensity of the blow, which
						only grazed his body with force enough to cause blood
						to flow ; but you exposed to the missiles the vital
						portions of Alexander's body unprotected, you drove
						home the blows through his very bones, you circled
						about his body, you laid siege to his eyes and his feet,
						you hindered him in pursuing his foes, you endeavoured to strip him of his victories, you upset his
						expectations.</q>
					          </p>
               <p>No other king seems to me to have felt the hand
						of Fortune more heavily upon him, even though
						on many it has fallen harshly and malignantly. But
						like a thunderbolt it cut down the other rulers,
						and destroyed them ; toward Alexander, however,
						Fortune's ill-will became but contentious and quarrelsome and hard to overpower, even as it was toward
						Heracles. For what manner of Typhons or monstrous
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.469"/>
						
						giants did she not raise up to oppose him? Whom
						of his foes did she not fortify with a vast supply of
						weapons or deep rivers or jagged cliffs or the might
						of beasts from foreign lands<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably elephants.</note>? But if Alexander's
						thought had not been set on high emprise, if it had
						not derived its impelling force from great Virtue, and
						had not refused to submit to defeat in its wrestling
						with Fortune, would he not have grown tired and
						weary of marshalling and arming his forces, weary
						of his sieges and pursuits amid unnumbered revolts,
						desertions, and riots of subject peoples, defections of
						kings, against Bactria, Maracanda, Sogdiana, as if
						he were cutting off the heads of a hydra which ever
						grew again in renewed wars among these faithless
						and conspiring peoples? 
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>I shall be thought to be making a strange statement, yet what I shall say is true : it was because of
						Fortune that Alexander all but lost the repute of being
						the son of Ammon! For what offspring of the gods
						could have toiled through such hazardous, toilsome,
						and painful Labours save only Heracles, the son of
						Zeus? But it was one arrogant man who imposed
						upon Heracles the task of capturing lions, of pursuing
						wild boars, of frightening off birds so that he might
						not have time to go about performing greater deeds,
						such as punishing men like Antaeus and stopping
						creatures like Busiris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 315 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 857 a.</note> from their abominable murders.
						But upon Alexander it was Virtue who laid the kingly
						and god-like Labour, the end and aim of which
						was not gold, carried about by countless camels, nor
						Persian luxury, banquets, and women, nor the wine
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.471"/>
						
						of Chalybon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A city in Syria; for the wine <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Strabo, xv. 3. 22 (p. 735); Athenaeus, 28 d; Suidas and Hesychius, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi>
                  </note> nor the fish of Hyrcanis,, but to order
						all men by one law and to render them submissive to
						one rule and accustomed to one manner of life. The
						desire which he cherished to accomplish this task
						was implanted in him from childhood, and was fostered
						and increased with the years that passed. Once,
						when ambassadors carne from the Persian king to
						Philip, who was not at home, Alexander, while he
						entertained them hospitably,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. v. (666 e-f).</note> asked ho childish
						questions, as the others did, about the vine of gold,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, vii. 1. 38; Diodorus, xix. 48.</note>
						or the Hanging Gardens, or how the Great King was
						arrayed ; but he was completely engrossed with the
						most vital concerns of the dominion, asking how large
						was the Persian army; where the king stationed
						himself in battle (even as the famed Odysseus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 407.</note> asked
						<quote rend="blockquote">Where are his arms that he wields in the battle, and where
						are his horses?);</quote>
						and which roads were the shortest for travellers going inland from the sea - so that the strangers were
						astounded and said, <q direct="unspecified">This boy is a &lsquo;great king&rsquo;;
							our king is only wealthy.</q> But after Philip's end,
						when Alexander was eager to cross over and, already
						absorbed in his hopes and preparations, was hastening
						to gain a hold upon Asia, Fortune, seizing upon him,
						blocked his way, turned him about, dragged him
						back, and surrounded him with countless distractions
						and delays. First she threw into the utmost commotion the barbarian elements among his neighbours,
						and contrived wars with the Illyrians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 327 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and Triballians.
						By these wars he was drawn from his Asiatic projects
						as far away as the portion of Scythia that lies along
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.473"/>
						
						the Danube ; when, by sundry manoeuvres, he had
						subjugated all this territory with much danger and
						great struggles, he was again eager and in haste for
						the crossing. Again, however, Fortune stirred up
						Thebes against him, and thrust in his pathway a war
						with Greeks, and the dread necessity of punishing, by
						means of slaughter and fire and sword, men that
						were his kith and kin,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Heracles, a reputed ancestor of the Macedonian kings, was born in Thebes.</note> a necessity which had a most
						unpleasant ending.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The sack of Thebes and the enslaving of most of the surviving inhabitants; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xi. (670 e), and Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, i. 8-9.</note>
					          </p>
               <p>After this he crossed with provision for thirty days,
						as Phylarchus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cited on the authority of Duris in 327 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> relates ; but Aristobulus says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 327 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> with
						seventy talents. He divided the greater part of his
						possessions at home and his royal revenues among his
						friends ; Perdiccas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xv. (672 b).</note> alone would take nothing when
						Alexander offered, but asked, <q direct="unspecified">What, are you leaving
							for yourself, Alexander?</q> And when Alexander
						replied, <q direct="unspecified">High hopes !</q>, <q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said Perdiccas,
						<q direct="unspecified">we also shall share in these ; for it is not right to
							take your possessions, but right to wait in expectation of those of Darius.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>What, then, were the hopes on which Alexander
						relied when he crossed into Asia? Not a force
						counted by means of a wall that would hold a city
						of 10,000 men,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xerxes counted his army, according to Herodotus vii. 60, by causing 10,000 men to fall in as compactly as possible; then a low wall was built around them; they then marched out, others marched in until the whole host (1,700,000 foot soldies) had been counted.</note> nor fleets that sailed through mountains,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">By Xerxes' canal through Athos: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 335 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Herodotus, vii. 22, 23.</note> nor scourges or fetters, insane and barbaric implements for chastising the sea<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Again referring to Xerxes; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Herodotus, vii. 35.</note>; but externally they
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.475"/>
						
						were the great ambition in his little army, mutual
						rivalry of hot youth, competition for repute and
						excellence among his Companions. And within himself he had his own high hopes, reverence for the
						gods, fidelity toward his friends, frugality, self-control,
						experience, fearlessness toward death, high courage,
						humanity, affability, integrity of character, constancy
						in counsel, quickness in execution, the height of good
						repute, and a disposition to gain his end in everything
						honourable. For not appropriately nor convincingly
						did Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, ii. 478-479.</note> employ a combination of three similes
						in his comparison describing the fair appearance of
						Agamemnon:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Like in his eyes and his head unto Zeus who delighteth in
						thunder,
						</l>
                     <l>Like unto Ares in waist, and in breadth of his chest to
						Poseidon.</l>
                  </quote>
						But if the god who begat Alexander made his
						natural endowment an harmoniously joined combination of many virtues, may we not say that he
						possessed the high spirit of Cyrus, the discretion of
						Agesila&uuml;s, the intelligence of Themistocles,the experience of Philip, the daring of Brasidas, the eloquence
						and statesmanship of Pericles? And, to compare him
						with the men of still more ancient days, he was more
						self-restrained than Agamemnon ; for Agamemnon
						set a captive woman<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Chryseis: <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, i. 113.</note> above his wedded wife,but Alexander, even before his marriage, kept aloof from his
						captives. He was more magnanimous than Achilles ;
						for Achilles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxiv. 552-600.</note> gave back the body of Hector for a
						small ransom, but Alexander buried Darius at great
						expense ; Achilles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xix. 140-147.</note> when he had become reconciled,
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.477"/>
						
						accepted gifts and recompense from his friends to
						requite him for ceasing from his Wrath, but Alexander
						enriched his enemies by conquering them. He was
						more reverent than Diomedes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, v. 335-352, 855-861.</note>; for Diomedes was
						ready to fight with gods, but Alexander believed the
						gods to be the authors of all success. He was more
						deeply mourned by his relatives than was Odysseus ;
						for Odysseus'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, xi. 202-203.</note> mother died of grief, but the mother<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sisygambis, the mother of Darius: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diodorus, xvii. 118. 3; Justin, xiii. 1; Quintus Curtius, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Alexandri</hi>, x. 5. 21.</note>
						of Alexander's foe, for the goodwill she bore him,
						shared his death.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>In short, if Solon's statesmanship also was
						due to Fortune, and if Miltiades' generalship, and
						Aristeides'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 97 c.</note> justice were but the result of Fortune,
						then surely there is no work of Virtue in these men,
						but it is a name only, talk based on appearance,
						pervading their lives to no purpose, a figment of the
						sophists and legislators. But if every one of these
						men and of others like them became poor or rich,
						weak or strong, ugly or handsome, lived to a ripe old
						age or met an untimely death through Fortune, or if
						each one of them proved himself a great general, a
						great lawgiver, or great in government and statesmanship through Virtue and Reason, then consider
						Alexander and compare him with them all. Solon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 828 f; <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, chaps. xv., xvi. (86 d, 87 d); Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, 10. 1.</note>
						brought about a cancellation of debts in Athens which
						he called the <q direct="unspecified">Relief from Burdens</q> (Seisachtheia);
						but Alexander himself paid the debts which his men
						owed to their creditors.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 339 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note> Pericles collected tribute from
						the Greeks and with the money adorned the Acropolis
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.479"/>
						
						with temples ; but Alexander captured the riches of
						barbarians and sent them to Greece with orders that
						ten thousand talents<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">£2,000,000 or $10,000,000.</note> be used to construct temples
						for the gods.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, xviii. 4. 4.</note> Brasidas's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, ii. 25. 2.</note> dash along the shore to
						Methon&ecirc; through the armed host of the enemy amid
						showers of missiles made him renowned in Greece ;
						but that daring leap of Alexander in the country of
						the Oxydrachae,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Mallians: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 327 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> incredible to them that hear of it
						and fearful to them that saw it, when he hurled
						himself down from the walls into the midst of the
						enemy, who received him with spears and arrows
						and naked swords-with what may one compare it,
						save with the levin bolt that breaks and flashes in
						the midst of a hurricane, like the apparition of Phoebus
						that darted down to earth,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> perhaps Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xv. 237; iv. 75-80.</note> gleaming round about
						with flaming armour. The enemy at first were amazed
						and affrighted and retired with trembling fear ; but
						a moment later, when they saw that he was but one
						man attacking many, they made a stand against him.
					</p>
               <p>There indeed Fortune made manifest great and
						splendid results of her kindliness toward Alexander,
						when she cast him into an insignificant foreign town
						and shut him in and fenced him round about! And
						when his men wTere earnestly trying to bring help
						from without and were attempting to scale the wails,
						Fortune, by breaking and shattering their ladders,
						took away their foothold and hurled them from the
						walls. And of the three<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">327 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxiii. (700 c) mention only two; but Plutarch here seems to follow the authority used by Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vi. 10, who gives the number as three; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also 344 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> men who alone were quick
						enough to grasp the wall and, throwing themselves
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.481"/>
						
						down inside, to take their stand beside the king,
						Fortune straightway snatched up one and made away
						with him before he could strike a blow ; and a second,
						pierced through by many arrows, was only so far from
						death that he could see and perceive his king's danger.
						But the charges and shouting of the Macedonians
						were unavailing for they had no machines nor siege
						engines with them ; but in their zeal they tried to
						hack the walls with their swords, and were forced to
						break them off with their bare hands, and all but
						bite their way through.
					</p>
               <p>But the king, who was Fortune's favourite, and was
						always guarded and personally protected by her, was
						caught within like a wild beast in the toils, alone and
						without succour ; nor was he struggling for Susa or
						Babylon, nor to capture Bactriaj nor to vanquish the
						great Porus ; for in great and glorious conflicts, even
						though men fail, disgrace, at least, can find no place.
						But so contentious and malicious was Fortune, so
						greatly did she favour barbarians and hate Alexander, that she tried to destroy not only his body and
						his life, but also, in so far as she could, to destroy his
						repute and to wipe out his fair fame. For it were not
						a terrible thing for Alexander to fall and lie buried
						beside the Euphrates or the Hydaspes, nor ignoble
						to meet death by coming into close combat with
						Darius or in confronting the horses and swords and
						battle-axes of the Persians as they fought to defend
						their king, nor to be overthrown while he bestrode
						the walls of Babylon and to fall from his high hope.
						Thus fell Pelopidas and Epameinondas ; their death
						was a death belonging to Virtue, not to misfortune,
						engaged as they were in such a high emprise. But
						of what sort was the deed of Fortune, who is now
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.483"/>
						
						under scrutiny? Was it not that on the farthest outposts of a land beside a foreign river within the walls
						of an obscure hamlet, which surrounded and hid away.
						from sight the lord and master of the inhabited world,
						he should perish, smitten and stricken by ignominious
						weapons and whatever else lay at hand? For his head
						was wounded through his helmet by an axe, and someone shot an arrow through his breastplate so that it
						penetrated the bones of his breast and was lodged
						there firmly, while the shaft protruded and hampered
						him and the iron point was four fingers broad and five
						fingers long.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch the rhetorician increases by one finger's-breadth the dimensions of the arrow-point which are given by Plutarch the biographer in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxiii. (700 e).</note> But - the extreme of all the dangers
						he confronted - while he was defending himself
						against those who attacked him in front, the archer
						who shot him had plucked up courage to approach
						him with a sword, but Alexander with his dagger
						was too quick for the man and knocked him down
						and killed him ; but while he was thus occupied,
						someone ran out from a mill, and gave him a blow
						on the neck with a cudgel from behind ; this confused his senses, and his head swam. But Virtue
						was by his side and in him she engendered daring,
						and in his companions strength and zeal. For men
						like Limnaeus and Ptolemy and Leonnatus and all
						those who had surmounted the wall or had broken
						through it took their stand before him and were a
						bulwark of Virtue, exposing their bodies in the face
						of the foe and even their lives for the goodwill and
						love they bore their king. Surely it is not due to
						Fortune that the companions of good kings risk their
						lives and willingly die for them ; but this they do
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.485"/>
						
						through a passion for Virtue, even as bees, as if under
						the spell of love-charms, approach and closely surround their sovereign.
					</p>
               <p>What spectator, then, who might without danger to
						himself have been present at that scene, would not
						exclaim that he was witnessing the mighty contest
						of Fortune and Virtue ; that through Fortune the
						foreign host was prevailing beyond its deserts, but
						through Virtue the Greeks were holding out beyond
						their ability? And if the enemy gains the upper hand,
						this will be the work of Fortune or of some jealous
						deity or of divine retribution ; but if the Greeks
						prevail, it will be Virtue and daring, friendship and
						fidelity, that will win the guerdon of victory? These
						were, in fact, the only support that Alexander had
						with him at this time, since Fortune had put a barrier
						between him and the rest of his forces and equipment, fleets, horse, and camp.
					</p>
               <p>Finally, the Macedonians routed the barbarians,
						and, when they had fallen, pulled down their city on
						their heads. But this was no help to Alexander ; for
						he had been hurried from the field, arrow and all, and
						he had the shaft in his vitals ; the arrow was as a
						bond or bolt holding his breastplate to his body. And
						when they tried forcibly to pull it out of the wound
						by the roots, as it were, the iron would not budge,
						since it was lodged in the bony part of the breast
						in front of the heart. They did not dare to saw
						off the protruding portion of the shaft, since they
						were afraid that the bone might be split by the
						jarring and cause excruciating pain, and that an internal haemorrhage might result. But when Alexander perceived their great perplexity and hesitation,
						he himself tried with his dagger to cut off the arrow
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.487"/>
						
						close to his breastplate ; but his hand was unsteady
						and affected by a torpid languor from the inflammation of the wound. Accordingly with encouraging
						words he urged those that were unwounded to take
						hold and not to be afraid; and he railed at some
						who were weeping and could not control themselves,
						others he branded as deserters, since they had not
						the courage to Come to his assistance. And he cried
						aloud to his Companions, <q direct="unspecified">Let no one be fainthearted even for my sake ! For it will not be believed
							that I do not fear death, if you fear death for me !</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Some think the narrative closes abruptly, and that it should have been continued to include at least Alexander's recovery, but the Greeks did not always insist on a happy ending narrated in full.</note>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>