<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De fato</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.108">
      <body>
         <head>Of fate.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
               <q direct="unspecified">This little Treatise is so pitiously tome, maimed, and dismembred thorowout,
				that a man may sooner divine and guess thereat (as I have done) than translate it.
				I beseech the readers therefore, to hold me excused, in case I neither please my
				selfe, nor content them, in that which I have written.</q>&mdash;HOLLAND.</note>
         </head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.293"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="0">
            <p>I will endeavor, my dearest Piso, to send you my
				opinion concerning Fate, written with all the clearness
				and compendiousness I am capable of; since you, who are
				not ignorant how cautious I am of writing, have thought
				fit to make it the subject of your request.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>You are first then to know that this word Fate is
				spoken and understood two manner of ways; the one as
				it is an energy, the other as it is a substance. First therefore, as it is an action, Plato<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato, Phaedrus, p. 248 C; Timaeus, p. 41 E; Republic, X. p. 617 D.</note> has under a type described
				it, saying thus in his dialogue entitled Phaedrus: <q direct="unspecified">And
					this is a sanction of Adrastea (or an inevitable ordinance),
					that whatever soul being an attendant on God,</q> &amp;c. And
				in his treatise called Timaeus: <q direct="unspecified">The laws which God in
					the nature of the universe has established for immortal
					souls.</q> And in his book of a Commonweal he calls Fate
				<q direct="unspecified">the speech of the virgin Lachesis, who is the daughter
					of Necessity.</q> By which sentences he not tragically but
				theologically shows us what his sentiments are in this
				matter. Now if any one, translating the fore-cited passages, would have them expressed in more familiar terms,
				the description in Phaedrus may be thus explained: That
				Fate is a divine sentence, intransgressible because its cause
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.294"/>
				
				cannot be divested or hindered. And according to what
				he has said in his Timaeus, it is a law ensuing on the
				nature of the universe, according to which all things that
				are done are transacted. For this does Lachesis effect,
				who is indeed the daughter of Necessity,&mdash;as we have both
				already related, and shall yet better understand by that
				which will be said in the progress of our discourse. Thus
				you see what Fate is, when it is taken for an action.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But as it is a substance, it seems to be the universal
				soul of the world, and admits of a threefold distribution;
				the first destiny being that which errs not; the second,
				that which is thought to err; and the third that which,
				being under the heaven, is conversant about the earth.
				Of these, the highest is called Clotho, the next Atropos,
				and the lowest, Lachesis; who, receiving the celestial influences and efficacies of her sisters, transmits and fastens
				them to the terrestrial things which are under her government. Thus have we declared briefly what is to be said
				of Fate, taken as a substance; what it is, what are its parts,
				after what manner it is, how it is ordained, and how it
				stands, both in respect to itself and to us. But as to the
				particularities of these things, there is another fable in his
				Commonweal, by which they are in some measure covertly
				insinuated, and we ourselves have, in the best manner we
				can, endeavored to explain them to you.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>But we now once again turn our discourse to Fate, as
				it is an energy. For concerning this it is that there are so
				many natural, moral, and logical questions. Having therefore already in some sort sufficiently defined what it is, we
				are now in the next place to say something of its quality,
				although it may to many seem absurd. I say then that
				Fate, though comprehending as it were in a circle the infinity of all those things which are and have been from
				infinite times and shall be to infinite ages, is not in itself
				infinite, but determinate and finite; for neither law, reason,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.295"/>
				
				nor any other divine thing can be infinite. And this you
				will the better understand, if you consider the total revolution and the whole time in which the revolutions of the
				eight circles (that is, of the eight spheres of the fixed stars,
				sun, moon, and five planets), having (as Timaeus<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Tim. p. 39 D.</note> says)
				finished their course, return to one and the same point,
				being measured by the circle of the Same, which goes
				always after one manner. For in this order, which is
				finite and determinate, shall all things (which, as well in
				heaven as in earth, consist by necessity from above) be reduced to the same situation, and restored again to their
				first beginning. Wherefore the habitude of heaven alone,
				being thus ordained in all things, as well in regard of itself
				as of the earth and all terrestrial matters, shall again (after
				long revolutions) one day return; and those things that in
				order follow after, and being linked together in a continuity
				are maintained in their course, shall be present, every one
				of them by necessity bringing what is its own. But for
				the better clearing of this matter, let us understand that
				whatever is in us or about us is not wrought by the course
				of the heavens and heavenly influences, as being entirely
				the efficient cause both of my writing what I now write,
				and of your doing also what you at present do, and in the
				same manner as you do it. Hereafter then, when the same
				cause shall return, we shall do the same things we now do,
				and in the same manner, and shall again become the same
				men; and so it will be with all others. And that which
				follows after shall also happen by the following cause; and
				in brief, all things that shall happen in the whole and in
				every one of these universal revolutions shall again become
				the same. By this it appears (as we have said before) that
				Fate, being in some sort infinite, is nevertheless determinate
				and finite; and it may be also in some sort seen and comprehended, as we have farther said, that it is as it were a
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.296"/>
				
				circle. For as a motion of a circle is a circle, and the time
				that measures it is also a circle; so the order of things
				which are done and happen in a circle may be justly
				esteemed and called a circle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>This therefore, though there should be nothing else,
				almost shows us what sort of thing Fate is; but not particularly or in every respect. What kind of thing then is
				it in its own form? It is, as far as one can compare it,
				like to the civil or politic law. For first it commands the
				most part of things at least, if not all, conditionally; and
				then it comprises (as far as is possible for it) all things that
				belong to the public in general; and the better to make
				you understand both the one and the other, we must
				specify them by an example. The civil law speaks and
				ordains in general of a valiant man, and also of a deserter
				and a coward; and in the same manner of others. Now
				this is not to make the law speak of this or that man in
				particular, but principally to propose such things as are
				universal or general, and consequently such as fall under
				them. For we may very well say, that it is legal to reward
				this man for having demeaned himself valiantly, and to
				punish that man for flying from his colors; because the
				law has virtually&mdash;though not in express terms and particularly yet in such general ones as they are comprehended under,&mdash;so determined of them. As the law (if
				I may so speak) of physicians and masters of corporal
				exercises potentially comprehends particular and special
				things within the general; so the law of Nature, determining first and principally general matters, secondarily and
				consequently determines such as are particular. Thus,
				general things being decreed by Fate, particular and individual things may also in some sort be said to be so, because they are so by consequence with the general. But
				perhaps some one of those who more accurately examine
				and more subtly search into these things may say, on the
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.297"/>
				
				contrary, that particular and individual things precede the
				composition of general things, and that the general exist
				only for the particular, since that for which another thing
				is always goes before that which is for it. Nevertheless,
				this is not the proper place to treat of this difficulty, but
				it is to be remitted to another. However, that Fate comprehends not all things clearly and expressly, but only such
				as are universal and general, let it pass for resolved on at
				present, as well for what we have already said a little before, as for what we shall say hereafter. For that which
				is finite and determinate, agreeing properly with divine
				Providence, is seen more in universal and general things
				than in particular; such therefore is the divine law, and
				also the civil; but infinity consists in particulars and individuals.</p>
            <p>After this we are to declare what this term <q direct="unspecified">conditionally</q> means; for it is to be thought that Fate is also some
					such thing. That then is said to be conditionally, which
					is supposed to exist not of itself or absolutely, but as
					really dependent upon and joined to another; which signifies a suit and consequence. <q direct="unspecified">And this is the sanction
						of Adrastea (or an inevitable ordinance), that whatever
						soul, being an attendant on God, shall see any thing of
						truth, shall till another revolution be exempt from punishment; and if it is always able to do the same, it shall
						never suffer any damage.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is the whole passage from Plato's Phaedrus, p. 248 C, of which part is
							quoted in &sect; 1. (G.)</note> This is said both conditionally and also universally. Now that Fate is some such
					thing is clearly manifest, as well from its substance as
					from its name. For it is called <foreign lang="greek">ei(marme/nh</foreign> as being <foreign lang="greek">ei)rome/nh,</foreign>
					that is, dependent and linked; and it is a sanction or law,
					because things are therein ordained and disposed consequentially, as is usual in civil government.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>We ought in the next place to consider and treat of
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.298"/>
				
				mutual relation and affection; that is, what reference and
				respect Fate has to divine Providence, what to Fortune,
				what also to <q direct="unspecified">that which is in our power,</q> what to contingent and other such like things; and furthermore we are
				to determine, how far and in what it is true or false that
				all things happen and are done by and according to Fate.
				For if the meaning is, that all things are comprehended
				and contained in Fate, it must be granted that this proposition is true; and if any would farther have it so understood, that all things which are done amongst men, on
				earth, and in heaven are placed in Fate, let this also pass
				as granted for the present. But if (as the expression seems
				rather to imply) the <q direct="unspecified">being done according to Fate</q> signifies not all things, but only that which is an immediate
				consequent of Fate, then it must not be said that all things
				happen and are done by and according to Fate, though all
				things are so according to Fate as to be comprised in it.
				For all things that the law comprehends and of which it
				speaks are not legal or according to law; for it comprehends treason, it treats of the cowardly running away from
				one's colors in time of battle, of adultery, and many other
				such like things, of which it cannot be said that any one
				of them is lawful. Neither indeed can I affirm of the performing a valorous act in war, the killing of a tyrant, or
				the doing any other virtuous deed, that it is legal; because that only is proper to be called legal, which is commanded by the law. Now if the law commands these
				things, how can they avoid being rebels against the law
				and transgressors of it, who neither perform valiant feats
				of arms, kill tyrants, nor do any other such remarkable
				acts of virtue? And if they are transgressors of the law,
				why is it not just they should be punished? But if this
				is not reasonable, it must then be also confessed that these
				things are not legal or according to law; but that legal
				and according to law is only that which is particularly prescribed
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.299"/>
				
				 and expressly commanded by the law, in any action
				whatsoever. In like manner, those things only are fatal
				and according to Fate, which are the consequences of
				causes preceding in the divine disposition. So that Fate
				indeed comprehends all things which are done; yet many
				of those things that are comprehended in it, and almost all
				that precede, should not (to speak properly) be pronounced
				to be fatal or according to Fate.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>These things being so, we are next in order to show,
				how <q direct="unspecified">that which is in our power</q> (or free will), Fortune,
				possible, contingent, and other like things which are placed
				among the antecedent causes, can consist with Fate, and
				Fate with them; for Fate, as it seems, comprehends all
				things, and yet all these things will not happen by necessity, but every one of them according to the principle of its
				nature. Now the nature of the possible is to presubsist,
				as the genus, and to go before the contingent; and the
				contingent, as the matter and subject, is to be presupposed
				to free will; and our free will ought as a master to make use
				of the contingent; and Fortune comes in by the side of
				free will, through the property of the contingent of inclining
				to either part. Now you will more easily apprehend what
				has been said, if you shall consider that every thing which
				is generated, and the generation itself, is not done without
				a generative faculty or power, and the power is not without a substance. As for example, neither the generation
				of man, nor that which is generated, is without a power;
				but this power is about man, and man himself is the substance. Now the power or faculty is between the substance, which is the powerful, and the generation and the
				thing generated, which are both possibles. There being
				then these three things, the power, the powerful, and the
				possible; before the power can exist, the powerful must
				of necessity be presupposed as its subject, and the power
				must also necessarily subsist before the possible. By this
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.300"/>
				
				deduction then may in some measure be understood what
				is meant by possible; which may be grossly defined as
				<q direct="unspecified">that which power is able to produce;</q> or yet more
				exactly, if to this same there be added, <q direct="unspecified">provided there
					be nothing from without to hinder or obstruct it.</q> Now
				of possible things there are some which can never be
				hindered, as are those in heaven, to wit, the rising and
				setting of the stars, and the like to these; but others may
				indeed be hindered, as are the most part of human things,
				and many also of those which are done in the air. The
				first, as being done by necessity, are called necessary; the
				others, which may fall one way or other, are called contingent; and they may both thus be described. The
				necessary possible is that whose contrary is impossible;
				and the contingent possible is that whose contrary is also
				possible. For that the sun should set is a thing both
				necessary and possible, forasmuch as it is contrary to this
				that the sun should not set, which is impossible; but that,
				when the sun is set, there should be rain or not rain, both
				the one and the other is possible and contingent. And
				the again of things contingent, some happen oftener,
				others rarely and not so often, others fall out equally or
				indifferently, as well the one way as the other, even as it
				happens. Now it is manifest that those are contrary to
				one another,&mdash;to wit, those which fall out oftener and
				those which happen but seldom,&mdash;and they both for the
				most part depend on Nature; but that which happens
				equally, as much one way as another, depends on ourselves. For that under the Dog it should be either hot or
				cold, the one oftener, the other seldomer, are both things
				subject to Nature; but to walk and not to walk, and all
				such things of which both the one and the other are submitted to the free will of man, are said to be in us and our
				election; but rather more generally to be in us. For there
				are two sorts of this <q direct="unspecified">being in our power;</q> the one of
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.301"/>
				
				which proceeds from some sudden passion and motion
				of the mind, as from anger or pleasure; the other from
				the discourse and judgment of reason, which may properly
				be said to be in our election. And some reason there is
				to believe that this possible and contingent is the same
				thing with that which is said to be in us and according to
				our free will, although differently named. For in respect
				to the future, it is styled possible and contingent; and in
				respect of the present, it is named <q direct="unspecified">in our power</q> and
				<q direct="unspecified">in our free will.</q> So that these things may thus be defined: The contingent is that which is itself&mdash;as well
				as its contrary&mdash;possible; and <q direct="unspecified">that which is in our
					power</q> is one part of the contingent, to wit, that which
				now takes place according to our will. Thus have we in
				a manner declared, that the possible in the order of Nature
				precedes the contingent, and that the contingent subsists
				before free will; as also what each of them is, whence
				they are so named, and what are the qualities adjoined or
				appertaining to them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>It now remains, that we treat of Fortune and casual
				adventure, and whatever else is to be considered with them.
				It is therefore certain that Fortune is a cause. Now of
				causes, some are causes by themselves, and others by accident. Thus for example, the proper cause by itself of an
				house or a ship is the art of the mason, the carpenter, or
				the shipwright; but causes by accident are music, geometry, and whatever else may happen to be joined with the
				art of building houses or ships, in respect either of the
				body, the soul, or any exterior thing. Whence it appears,
				that the cause by itself must needs be determinate and
				one; but the causes by accident are never one and the
				same, but infinite and undetermined. For many&mdash;nay, infinite&mdash;accidents, wholly different one from the other, may
				be in one and the same subject. Now the cause by accident, when it is found in a thing which not merely is done
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.302"/>
				
				for some end but has in it free will and election, is then
				called Fortune; as is the finding a treasure while one is
				digging a hole to plant a tree, or the doing or suffering
				some extraordinary thing whilst one is flying, following, or
				otherwise walking, or only turning about, provided it be
				not for the sake of that which happens, but for some other
				intention. Hence it is, that some of the ancients have declared Fortune to be a cause unknown, that cannot be foreseen by the human reason. But according to the Platonics,
				who have approached yet nearer to the true reason of it,
				it is thus defined: Fortune is a cause by accident, in those
				things which are done for some end, and which are of our
				election. And afterwards they add, that it is unforeseen
				and unknown to the human reason; although that which
				is rare and strange appears also by the same means to be
				in this kind of cause by accident. But what this is, if it
				is not sufficiently evidenced by the oppositions and disputations made against it, will at least most clearly be seen
				by what is written in Plato's Phaedo, where you will find
				these words:</p>
            <p>PHAED. Have you not heard how and in what manner the judgment passed? ECH. Yes indeed; for there
					came one and told us of it. At which we wondered very
					much that, the judgment having been given long before,
					it seems that he died a great while after. And what,
					Phaedo, might be the cause of it? PHAED. It was a fortune which happened to him, Echecrates. For it chanced
					that, the day before the judgment, the stern of the galley
					which the Athenians send every year to the isle of Delos
					was crowned.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Phaedo, p. 58 A.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In which discourse it is to be observed, that the expression <hi rend="italics">happened to him</hi> is not simply to be understood by
					<hi rend="italics">was done</hi> or <hi rend="italics">came to pass,</hi> but it much rather regards
					what befell him through the concurrence of many causes
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.303"/>
					
					together, one being done with regard to another. For the
					priest crowned the ship and adorned it with garlands for
					another end and intention, and not for the sake of Socrates; and the judges also had for some other cause condemned him. But the event was strange, and of such a
					nature that it might seem to have been effected by the
					providence of some human creature, or rather of some
					superior powers. And so much may suffice to show with
					what Fortune must of necessity subsist, and that there must
					be first some subject of such things as are in our free
					will: its effect is, moreover, like itself called Fortune.</p>
            <p>But chance or casual adventure is of a larger extent
					than Fortune; which it comprehends, and also several
					other things which may of their own nature happen sometimes one way, sometimes another. And this, as it appears by the derivation of its name, which is in Greek
					<foreign lang="greek">au)to/maton,</foreign> chance, is that which happens of itself, when that
					which is ordinary happens not, but another thing in its
					place; such as cold in the dog-days seems to be; for it
					is sometimes then cold. ... Once for all, as <q direct="unspecified">that which
						is in our power</q> is a part of the contingent, so Fortune is
					a part of chance or casual adventure; and both the two
					events are conjoined and dependent on the one and the
					other, to wit, chance on contingent, and Fortune on <q direct="unspecified">that
						which is in our power,</q>&mdash;and yet not on all, but on what
					is in our election, as we have already said. Wherefore
					chance is common to things inanimate, as well as to those
					which are animated; whereas Fortune is proper to man
					only, who has his actions voluntary. And an argument of
					this is, that to be fortunate and to be happy are thought
					to be one and the same thing. Now happiness is a certain well-doing, and well-doing is proper only to man, and
					to him perfect.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>These then are the things which are comprised in
				Fate, to wit, contingent, possible, election, <q direct="unspecified">that which is
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.304"/>
					
					in our power,</q> Fortune, chance, and their adjuncts, as are
				the things signified by the words <hi rend="italics">perhaps</hi> and <hi rend="italics">peradventure;</hi> all which indeed are contained in Fate, yet none of
				them is fatal. It now remains, that we discourse of divine Providence, and show how it comprehends even Fate
				itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>The supreme therefore and first Providence is the
				understanding or (if you had rather) the will of the first
				and sovereign God, doing good to every thing that is in
				the world, by which all divine things have universally and
				throughout been most excellently and most wisely ordained and disposed. The second Providence is that of
				the second Gods, who go through the heaven, by which
				temporal and mortal things are orderly and regularly generated, and which pertains to the continuation and preservation of every kind. The third may probably be called
				the Providence and procuration of the Daemons, which, being placed on the earth, are the guardians and overseers
				of human actions. This threefold Providence therefore
				being seen, of which the first and supreme is chiefly and
				principally so named, we shall not be afraid to say, although we may in this seem to contradict the sentiments
				of some philosophers, that all things are done by Fate and
				by Providence, but not also by Nature. But some are done
				according to Providence,&mdash;these according to one, those
				according to another,&mdash;and some according to Fate; and
				Fate is altogether according to Providence, while Providence
				is in no wise according to Fate. But let this discourse be
				understood of the first and supreme Providence. Now
				that which is done according to another, whatever it is,
				is always posterior to that according to which it is done;
				as that which is according to the law is after the law, and
				that which is according to Nature is after Nature, so that
				which is according to Fate is after Fate, and must consequently be more new and modern. Wherefore supreme
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.305"/>
				
				Providence is the most ancient of all things, except him
				whose will or understanding it is, to wit, the sovereign author, maker, and father of all things. <q direct="unspecified">Let us
					therefore,</q> says Timaeus, <q direct="unspecified">discourse for what cause the
						Creator made and framed this machine of the universe.
						He was good, and in him that is good there can never be
						imprinted or engendered any envy against any thing. Being therefore wholly free from this, he desired that all
						things should, as far as it is possible, resemble himself.
						He therefore, who admits this to have been chiefly the
						principal original of the generation and creation of the
						world, as it has been delivered to us by wise men, receives
						that which is most right. For God, who desired that all
						things should be good, and nothing, as far as possibly might
						be, evil, taking thus all that was visible,&mdash;restless as it was,
						and moving rashly and confusedly,&mdash;reduced it from disorder to order, esteeming the one to be altogether better than
						the other. For it neither was nor is convenient for him
						who is in all perfection good, to make any thing that
						should not be very excellent and beautiful.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Timaeus, p. 29 D.</note> This, therefore, and all that follows, even to his disputation concerning human souls, is to be understood of the first Providence,
				which in the beginning constituted all things. Afterwards
				he speaks thus: <q direct="unspecified">Having framed the universe, he ordained souls equal in number to the stars, and distributed
					to each of them one; and having set them, as it were, in
					a chariot, showed the nature of the universe, and appointed
					them the laws of Fate.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Timaeus, p. 41 D.</note> Who then will not believe, that
				by these words he expressly and manifestly declares Fate
				to be, as it were, a foundation and political constitution of
				laws, fitted for the souls of men? Of which he afterwards renders the cause.</p>
            <p>As for the second Providence, he thus in a manner explains it, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Having prescribed them all these laws,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.306"/>
					
					to the end that, if there should afterwards happen any
					fault, he might be exempt from being the cause of any of
					their evil, he dispersed some of them upon the earth, some
					into the moon, and some into the other instruments of
					time. And after this dispersion, he gave in charge to the
					young Gods the making of human bodies, and the making
					up and adding whatever was wanting and deficient in
					human souls; and after they had perfected whatever is
					adherent and consequent to this, they should rule and
					govern, in the best manner they possibly could, this mortal
					creature, so far as it should not be the cause of its own
					evils.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Timaeus, p. 42 D.</note> For by these words, <q direct="unspecified">that he might be exempt
						from being the cause of any of their evil,</q> he most clearly
					signifies the cause of Fate; and the order and office of
					the young Gods manifests the second Providence; and it
					seems also in some sort to have touched a little upon the
					third, if he therefore established laws and ordinances that
					he might be exempt from being the cause of any of their
					evil. For God, who is free from all evil, has no need of
					laws or Fate; but every one of these petty Gods, drawn
					on by the providence of him who has engendered them,
					performs what belongs to his office. Now that this is true
					and agreeable to the opinion of Plato, these words of the
					lawgiver, spoken by him in his Book of Laws, seems to
					me to give sufficient testimony: <q direct="unspecified">If there were any man
						so sufficient by Nature, being by divine Fortune happily
						engendered and born, that he could comprehend this, he
						would have no need of laws to command him. For there
						is not any law or ordinance more worthy and powerful
						than knowledge; nor is it fitting that Mind, provided it
						be truly and really free by Nature, should be a subject or
						slave to any one, but it ought to command all.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Laws, IX. p. 875 C.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>I therefore do for mine own part thus understand
				and interpret this sentence of Plato. There being a threefold
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.307"/>
				
				 Providence, the first, as having engendered Fate, does
				in some sort comprehend it; the second, having been engendered with Fate, is with it totally comprehended and
				embraced by the first; the third, as having been engendered after Fate, is comprehended by it in the same manner
				as are free will and Fortune, as we have already said.
				<q direct="unspecified">For they whom the assistance of a Daemon's power does
					aid in their intercourse with me</q> says Socrates, declaring
				to Theages what is the almost inevitable ordinance of
				Adrastea <q direct="unspecified">are those whom you also mean; for they grow
					and come forward with speed.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Theages, p. 129 E.</note> In which words, what
				he says of a Daemon's aiding some is to be ascribed to the
				third Providence, and the growing and coming forward
				with speed, to Fate. In brief, it is not obscure or doubtful
				but that this also is a kind of Fate. And perhaps it may
				be found much more probable that the second Providence
				is also comprehended under Fate, and indeed all things
				that are done; since Fate, as a substance, has been rightly
				divided by us into three parts, and the fable of the chain
				comprehends the revolutions of the heavens in the number
				and rank of those things which happen conditionally. But
				concerning these things I will not much contend, to wit,
				whether they should be called conditional, or rather conjoined with Fate, the precedent cause and commander of
				Fate being also fatal.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Our opinion then, to speak compendiously, is such.
				But the contrary sentiment does not only include all things
				in Fate, but affirms them all to be done by and according
				to Fate. It accords indeed in all things to the other (the
				Stoic) doctrine; and that which accords to it, 'tis clear, is
				the same thing with it. In this discourse therefore we
				have first spoken of the contingent; secondly, of <q direct="unspecified">that
					which is in our power;</q> thirdly, of Fortune and chance,
				and whatever depends on them; fourthly, of praise, blame,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.308"/>
				
				and whatever depends on them; the fifth and last of all
				may be said to be prayers to the Gods, with their services
				and ceremonies.</p>
            <p>For the rest, as to those which are called idle and reaping arguments, and that which is named the argument
					against destiny, they are indeed but vain subtleties and
					captious sophisms, according to this discourse. But according to the contrary opinion, the first and principal conclusion seems to be, that there is nothing done without a
					cause, but that all things depend upon antecedent causes;
					the second, that the world is governed by Nature, and that
					it conspires, consents, and is compatible with itself; the
					third seems rather to be testimonies,&mdash;of which the first
					is divination, approved by all sorts of people, as being
					truly in God; the second is the equanimity and patience
					of wise men, who take mildly and bear patiently whatever
					befalls, as happening by divine ordinance and as it ought;
					the third is the speech so common and usual in every
					one's mouth, to wit, that every proposition is true or false.
					Thus have we contracted this discourse into a small number of short articles, that we might in few words comprehend the whole matter of Fate; into which a scrutiny
					ought to be made, and the reasons of both opinions to be
					weighed with a most exact balance. But we shall hereafter come to discuss particulars.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>