<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De invidia et odio</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.105">
      <body>
         <head>Of envy and hatred.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.95"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Envy and hatred are passions so like each other that
				they are often taken for the same. And generally, vice has
				(as it were) many hooks, whereby it gives unto those passions that hang thereto many opportunities to be twisted
				and entangled with one another; for as differing diseases
				of the body agree in many like causes and effects, so do the
				disturbance of the mind. He who is in prosperity is
				equally an occasion of grief to the envious and to the malicious man; therefore we look upon benevolence, which is
				a willing our neighbor's good, as an opposite to both envy
				and hatred, and fancy these two to be the same because
				they have a contrary purpose to that of love. But their
				resemblances make them not so much one as their unlikeness makes them distinct. Therefore we endeavor to describe
				each of them apart, beginning at the original of either
				passion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Hatred proceeds from an opinion that the person we
				hate is evil, if not generally so, at least in particular to us.
				For they who think themselves injured are apt to hate the
				author of their wrong; yea, even those who are reputed
				injurious or malicious to others than ourselves we usually
				nauseate and abhor. But envy has only one sort of object,
				the felicity of others. Whence it becomes infinite, and,
				like an evil or diseased eye, is offended with every thing
				that is bright. On the other hand, hatred is always determined by the subject it adheres to.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.96"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Secondly, hatred may be conceived even against brutes;
				for there are some men who have an antipathy to cats or
				beetles or toads or serpents. Germanicus could endure
				neither the crowing nor the sight of a cock; and the Persian Magi were killers of mice, as creatures which they
				both hated themselves and accounted odious to God. In
				like manner also all the Arabians and Ethiopians abhor
				them. But envy is purely a human passion, and directed
				only against man.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Envy is not likely to be found among brutes, whose
				fancies are not moved by the apprehensions of each other's
				good or evil; neither can they be spirited with the notions
				of glorious or dishonorable, by which envy is chiefly stirred
				up. Yet they have mutual hatred; they kill each other,
				and wage most incredible wars. The eagles and the
				dragons fight, the crows and the owls, yea, the little titmouse and linnet; insomuch that it is said, the very blood
				of these creatures, when slain, will by no means be mixed;
				but though you would temper them together, they will
				immediately separate again. The lion also vehemently
				hates the cock, and the elephant the hog; but this probably proceeds from fear; for what they fear, the same are
				they inclined to hate.</p>
            <p>We see then herein a great difference betwixt envy and
					hate, that the one is natural to brutes, but they are not at
					all capable of the other.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Further, envy is always unjust; for none wrong by
				being happy, and upon this sole account they are envied.
				But hatred is often just; for there are some men so much
				to be avoided and disliked, that we should judge those
				worthy to be hated themselves who do not shun and detest
				them. And of this it is no weak evidence, that many will
				acknowledge they hate, but none will confess they envy;
				and hatred of the evil is registered amongst laudable
				things.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.97"/>
            <p>Therefore, as some were commending Charillus, the
					nephew of Lycurgus and king of Sparta, for his universally mild and gentle disposition,&mdash;How, answered his
					colleague, can Charillus be a virtuous person, who is pleasing even to the vicious? So the poet too, when he had
					variously and with an infinite curiosity described the deformities of Thersites's body, easily couched all the baseness
					of his manners in a word,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">Most hateful to Achilles and Ulysses too;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>for to be an enemy to the good is the greatest extravagance
					of vice.</p>
            <p>Men will deny the envy; and when it is alleged, will
					feign a thousand excuses, pretending they were angry, or
					that they feared or hated the person, cloaking envy with
					the name of any passion they can think of, and concealing
					it as the most loathsome sickness of the soul.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Moreover, these disturbances of the mind, like plants,
				must be nourished and augmented by the same roots from
				which they spring; therefore hatred increases as the persons hated grow worse, while envy swells bigger as the
				envied rise higher in the true braveries of virtue. Upon
				this consideration Themistocles, whilst he was yet young,
				said that he had done nothing gallant, for he was not yet
				envied. And we know that, as the cantharis is most busy
				with ripe fruits and roses in their beauty, so envy is most
				employed about the eminently good and those who are
				glorious in their places and esteem.</p>
            <p>Again, extreme badness makes hatred more vehement
					and bitter. The Athenians therefore had so utter an abhorrence of those who accused Socrates, that they would
					neither lend them fire, nor answer them any question, nor
					wash with them in the same water, but commanded the
					servants to pour it out as polluted; till these sycophants,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.98"/>
					
					no longer able to bear up under the pressure of this hatred,
					put an end to their own lives.</p>
            <p>Yet envy often gives place to the splendor of a matchless
					prosperity. For it is not likely that any envied Alexander
					or Cyrus, when they arrived at the height of their conquests
					and became lords of all. But as the sun, where he passes
					highest and sends down his beams most directly, has none
					or very little shadow, so they who are exalted to the meridian of fortune, shining aloof over the head of envy, have
					scarce any thing of their brightness eclipsed, while envy
					retires, being driven away by the brightness overspreading it.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, hatred is not vanquished by the greatness and glory of its objects. For though Alexander had
					not one to envy him, yet he had many haters, by whose
					treacheries at last he fell. So, on the other side, misfortunes cause envy to cease, but take not enmity away; for
					men will be malicious even toward abject enemies, but none
					envy the distressed. However, what was said by one of
					our Sophists, that the envious are tenderly inclinable to
					pity, is true; and in this appears a great unlikeness of
					these passions, that hatred leaves neither the happy nor
					the miserable, but envy becomes languid when its object
					has either prosperity or adversity in excess.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>We shall better understand this from the poising
				them together.</p>
            <p>Men let go their enmity and hatred, when either they
					are persuaded they were not injured at all, or if they now
					believe them to be good whom before they hated as evil,
					or, lastly, when they are appeased by the insinuations of a
					benefit received. For as Thucydides saith, A later service
					or good turn, if it be done at the right moment, will take
					away the ill resenting of a former fault, though this was
					greater than the recompense.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucyd. I. 42.</note>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.99"/>
            <p>Yet the first of these removes not envy, for men will
					persist in this vice, though they know they are not wronged;
					and the two latter (the esteem or credit of a person, and
					the bestowing a favor) do exasperate it more. For they
					most envy the virtuous, as those who are in possession of
					the chiefest good; and when they receive a kindness from
					any in prosperity, it is with reluctance, as though they
					grudged then not only the power but the will of conferring
					it; the one of which comes from their happy fortune, the
					other from their virtue. Both are good. Therefore envy
					is an entirely distinct affection from hatred, since, as we see,
					the very things that appease the one only rouse and exasperate the other.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Now let us consider a little the inclination and bent
				of either passion.</p>
            <p>The design of hatred is to endamage; and hence they
					define it, an insidious desire and purpose of doing hurt.
					But envy aims not at this. Many envy their familiars and
					kinsfolk, but have no thoughts of their ruin nor of so much
					as bringing any troubles upon them; only their felicity is
					a burden. Though they will perhaps diminish their glory
					and splendor what they can, yet they endeavor not their
					utter subversion; being, as it were, content to pull down
					so much only of an high stately house as hindered the
					light and obscured them with too great a shade.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>