<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Placita Philosophorum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Pseudo-Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="book"/>
            <state unit="chapter"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0094.003">
      <body>
         <head>Of those sentiments concerning nature with which philosophers were delighted.</head>
         <div1 type="book" n="1">
            <head>Book 1</head>
            <pb id="v.3.p.104"/>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="0">
               <p>IT being our determination to discourse of Natural Philosophy, we judge it necessary, in the first place and chiefly,
						to divide the body of philosophy into its proper members,
						that we may know what is that which is called philosophy,
						and what part of it is physical, or the explanation of natural things. The Stoics affirm that wisdom is the knowledge of things human and divine; that philosophy is the
						exercise of that art which is expedient to this knowledge;
						that virtue is the sole and sovereign art which is thus expedient; and this distributes itself into three general parts,
						&mdash;natural, moral, and logical. By which just reason (they
						say) philosophy is tripartite; of which one is natural, the
						other moral, the third logical. The natural is when our
						enquiries are concerning the world and all things contained in it; the ethical is the employment of our minds in
						those things which concern the manners of man's life; the
						logical (which they also call dialectical) regulates our conversation with others in speaking. Aristotle, Theophrastus, and after them almost all the Peripatetics give the following division of philosophy. It is absolutely requisite
						that the complete person be contemplator of things which
						have a being, and the practiser of those things which are
						decent; and this easily appears by the following instances.
						If the question be proposed, whether the sun, which is so
						conspicuous to us, be informed with a soul or inanimate,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.105"/>
						
						he that makes this disquisition is the thinking man; for
						he proceeds no farther than to consider the nature of that
						thing which is proposed. Likewise, if the question be
						proposed, whether the world be infinite, or whether beyond the system of this world there is any real being, all
						these things are the objects about which the understanding of man is conversant. But if these be the questions,
						&mdash;what measures must be taken to compose the well ordered life of man, what are the best methods to govern
						and educate children, or what are the exact rules whereby
						sovereigns may command and establish laws,&mdash;all these
						queries are proposed for the sole end of action, and the
						man conversant therein is the moral and practical man.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter I.
						<lb/> WHAT IS NATURE?</head>
               <p>SINCE we have undertaken to make a diligent search
						into Nature, I cannot but conclude it necessary to declare
						what Nature is. It is very absurd to attempt a discourse
						of the essence of natural things, and not to understand
						what is the power and sphere of Nature. If Aristotle be
						credited, Nature is the principle of motion and rest, in
						that thing in which it exists principally and not by accident. For all things that are conspicuous to our eyes,
						which are neither fortuitous nor necessary, nor have a
						divine original, nor acknowledge any such like cause, are
						called natural and enjoy their proper nature. Of this sort
						are earth, fire, water, air, plants, animals; to these may be
						added all things produced from them, such as showers,
						hail, thunders, hurricanes, and winds. All these confess
						they had a beginning, none of these were from eternity, but
						had something as the origin of them; and likewise animals
						and plants have a principle whence they are produced.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.106"/>
						
						But Nature, which in all these things hath the priority, is
						the principle not only of motion but of repose; whatsoever enjoys the principle of motion, the same has a possibility to find a dissolution. Therefore on this account it is
						that Nature is the principle of motion and rest.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter II.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN A PRINCIPLE AND AN ELEMENT?</head>
               <p>THE followers of Aristotle and Plato conclude that the
						elements are discriminated from a principle. Thales the
						Milesian supposeth that a principle and the elements are
						one and the same thing, but it is evident that they vastly
						differ one from another. For the elements are things
						compounded; but we do pronounce that principles admit not of a composition, nor are the effects of any other
						being. Those which we call elements are earth, water,
						air, and fire. But we term those principles which have
						nothing precedent to them out of which they are produced;
						for otherwise not these themselves, but rather those things
						whereof they are produced, would be the principles.
						Now there are some things which have a pre-existence
						to earth and water, from which they are begotten; to wit,
						matter, which is without form or shape; then form, which
						we call <foreign lang="greek">e)ntele/xeia</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">actuality</hi>); and lastly, privation. Thales
						therefore is very peccant, by affirming that water is both
						an element and a principle.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter III.
						<lb/> OF PRINCIPLES, AND WHAT THEY ARE.</head>
               <p>THALES the Milesian doth affirm that water is the principle whence all things in the universe spring. This
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.107"/>
						
						person appears to be the first of philosophers; from
						him the Ionic sect took its denomination, for there are
						many families and successions amongst philosophers. After
						he had professed philosophy in Egypt, when he was very
						old, he returned to Miletus. He pronounced, that all things
						had their original from water, and into water all things are
						resolved. His first reason was, that whatsoever was the
						prolific seed of all animals was a principle, and that is
						moist; so that it is probable that all things receive their
						original from humidity. His second reason was, that all
						plants are nourished and fructified by that thing which is
						moist, of which being deprived they wither away. Thirdly,
						that that fire of which the sun and stars are made is nourished by watery exhalations,&mdash;yea, and the world itself;
						which moved Homer to sing that the generation of it was
						from water:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>The ocean is
						</l>
                        <l>Of all things the kind genesis.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIV. 246.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Anaximander, who himself was a Milesian, assigns the
						principle of all things to the Infinite, from whence all things
						flow, and into the same are corrupted; hence it is that infinite worlds are framed, and those vanish again into that
						whence they have their original. And thus he farther
						proceeds, For what other reason is there of an Infinite
						but this, that there may be nothing deficient as to the generation or subsistence of what is in nature? There is his
						error, that he doth not acquaint us what this Infinite is,
						whether it be air, or water, or earth, or any other such
						like body. Besides he is peccant, in that, giving us the
						material cause, he is silent as to the efficient cause of beings;
						for this thing which he makes his Infinite can be nothing
						but matter; but operation cannot take place in the sphere
						of matter, except an efficient cause be annexed.</p>
               <p>Anaximenes his fellow-citizen pronounceth, that air is the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.108"/>
						
						principle of all beings; from it all receive their original,
						and into it all return. He affirms that our soul is nothing
						but air; it is that which constitutes and preserves; the
						whole world is invested with spirit and air. For spirit
						and air are synonymous. This person is in this deficient,
						that he concludes that of pure air, which is a simple body
						and is made of one only form, all animals are composed.
						It is not possible to think that a single principle should be
						the matter of all things, from whence they receive their
						subsistence; besides this there must be an operating cause.
						Silver (for example) is not of itself sufficient to frame a
						drinking cup; an operator also is required, which is the
						silversmith. The like may be applied to vessels made of
						wood, brass, or any other material.</p>
               <p>Anaxagoras the Clazomenian asserted Homoeomeries
						(or parts similar or homogeneous) to be the original cause
						of all beings; it seemed to him impossible that any thing
						could arise of nothing or be resolved into nothing. Let
						us therefore instance in nourishment, which appears simple and uniform, such as bread which we owe to Ceres,
						and water which we drink. Of this very nutriment, our
						hair, our veins, our arteries, nerves, bones, and all our
						other parts are nourished. These things thus being performed, it must be granted that the nourishment which is
						received by us contains all those things by which these
						parts of us are increased. In it there are those particles
						which are producers of blood, bones, nerves, and all other
						parts; which particles (as he thought) reason discovers
						for us. For it is not necessary that we should reduce all
						things under the objects of sense; for bread and water are
						fitted to the senses, yet in them there are those particles
						latent which are discoverable only by reason. It being
						therefore evident that there are particles in the nourishment similar to what is produced thereby, he terms these
						homogeneous parts, averring that they are the principles
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.109"/>
						
						of beings. Matter is according to him these similar parts,
						and the efficient cause is a Mind, which orders all things
						that have an existence. Thus he begins his discourse:
						<q direct="unspecified">All things were confused one among another; but Mind
							divided and reduced them to order.</q> In this he is to be
						commended, that he yokes together matter and an intellectual agent.</p>
               <p>Archelaus the son of Apollodorus, the Athenian, pronounceth, that the principles of all things have their original from an infinite air rarefied or condensed. Air rarefied
						is fire, condensed is water.</p>
               <p>These philosophers, the followers of Thales, succeeding
						one another, made up that sect which takes to itself the
						denomination of the Ionic.</p>
               <p>Pythagoras the Samian, the son of Mnesarchus, from
						another origin deduces the principles of all things; it was
						he who first gave philosophy its name. He assigns the first
						principles to be numbers, and those symmetries resulting
						from them which he styles harmonies; and the result of
						both combined he terms elements, called geometrical.
						Again, he enumerates unity and the indefinite binary number amongst the principles. One of these principles tends
						to an efficient and forming cause, which is Mind, and that
						is God; the other to the passive and material part, and
						that is the visible world. Moreover the nature of number (he saith) consists in the ten; for all people, whether
						Grecians or barbarians, reckon from one to ten, and thence
						return to one again. Farther he avers the virtue of ten
						consists in the quaternion; the reason whereof is this,&mdash;
						if any person reckon from one, and by addition place his
						numbers so as to take in the quaternary, he shall complete
						the number ten; if he exceed the four, he shall go beyond
						the ten; for one, two, three, and four being cast up together
						make up ten. The nature of numbers, therefore, if we regard
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.110"/>
						
						 the units, resteth in the ten; but if we regard its
						power, in the four. Therefore the Pythagoreans say that
						their most sacred oath is by that God who delivered to
						them the quaternary.
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>By th' founder of the sacred number four,
						</l>
                        <l>Eternal Nature's font and root, they swore.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Of this number the soul of man is composed; for mind,
						knowledge, opinion, and sense are the four that complete
						the soul, from which all sciences, all arts, all rational faculties derive themselves. For what our mind perceives, it
						perceives after the manner of a thing that is one, the soul
						itself being a unity; as for instance, a multitude of persons are not the object of our sense nor are comprehended
						by us, for they are infinite; our understanding gives the general notion of <hi rend="italics">a man,</hi> in which all individuals agree. The
						number of individuals is infinite; the generic or specific
						nature of all being is a unit, or to be apprehended as one
						only thing; from this one conception we give the genuine
						measures of all existence, and therefore we affirm that a
						certain class of beings are rational and discoursive beings.
						But when we come to give the nature of a horse, it is that
						animal which neighs; and this being common to all horses,
						it is manifest that the understanding, which hath such like
						conceptions, is in its nature unity. The number which
						is called the infinite binary must needs be science; in
						every demonstration or belief belonging to science, and in
						every syllogism, we draw that conclusion which is the
						question doubted of, from those propositions which are by
						all granted, by which means another proposition is demonstrated. The comprehension of these we call knowledge;
						for which reason science is the binary number. But
						opinion is the ternary; for that rationally follows from comprehension. The objects of opinion are many things, and
						the ternary number denotes a multitude, as <q direct="unspecified">Thrice happy
							Grecians;</q> for which reason Pythagoras admits the ternary.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.111"/>
						
						 This sect of philosophers is called the Italic, by
						reason Pythagoras opened his school in Italy; his hatred
						of the tyranny of Polycrates enforced him to leave his native country Samos.</p>
               <p>Heraclitus and Hippasus of Metapontum suppose that
						fire gives the origination to all beings, that they all flow
						from fire, and in fire they all conclude; for of fire when
						first quenched the world was constituted. The first part of
						the world, being most condensed and contracted within
						itself, made the earth; but part of that earth being loosened and made thin by fire, water was produced; afterwards this water being exhaled and rarefied into vapors
						became air; after all this the world itself, and all other
						corporeal beings, shall be dissolved by fire in the universal
						conflagration. By them therefore it appears that fire is
						what gives beginning to all things, and is that in which all
						things receive their period.</p>
               <p>Epicurus the son of Neocles, the Athenian, his philosophical sentiments being the same with those of Democritus, affirms that the principles of all being are bodies
						which are perceptible only by reason; they admit not of
						a vacuity, nor of any original, but being of a self-existence
						are eternal and incorruptible; they are not liable to any
						diminution, they are indestructible, nor is it possible for
						them to receive any transformation of parts, or admit of any
						alterations; of these reason only is the discoverer; they
						are in a perpetual motion in vacuity, and by means of the
						empty space; for the vacuum itself is infinite, and the
						bodies that move in it are infinite. Those bodies acknowledge these three accidents, figure, magnitude, and gravity.
						Democritus acknowledged but two, magnitude and figure.
						Epicurus added the third, to wit, gravity; for he pronounced that it is necessary that bodies receive their motion from that impression which springs from gravity,
						otherwise they could not be moved. The figures of atoms
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.112"/>
						
						cannot be apprehended by our senses, but they are not
						infinite. These figures are neither hooked nor trident-shaped nor ring-shaped, such figures as these being easily
						broken; but the atoms are impassible, impenetrable; they
						have indeed figures proper to themselves, which are discovered only by reason. It is called an atom, by reason
						not of its smallness but of its indivisibility; in it no vacuity, no passible affection is to be found. And that there
						is an atom is perfectly clear; for there are elements which
						have a perpetual duration, and there are animals which
						admit of a vacuity, and there is a unity.</p>
               <p>Empedocles the Agrigentine, the son of Meton, affirms
						that there are four elements, fire, air, earth, and water, and
						two powers which bear the greatest command in nature,
						concord and discord, of which one is the union, the other
						the division of beings. Thus he sings,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mark the four roots of all created things:&mdash;
						</l>
                        <l>Bright shining Jove, Juno that giveth life,
						</l>
                        <l>Pluto beneath the earth, and Nestis who
						</l>
                        <l>Doth with her tears supply the mortal fount.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>By Jupiter he means fire and aether, by Juno that gives
						life he means the air, by Pluto the earth, by Nestis and
						the fountain of all mortals (as it were) seed and water.</p>
               <p>Socrates the son of Sophroniscus, and Plato son of Ariston, both natives of Athens, entertain the same opinion
						concerning the universe; for they suppose three principles,
						God, matter, and the idea. God is the universal understanding; matter is that which is the first substratum, accommodated for the generation and corruption of beings;
						the idea is an incorporeal essence, existing in the cogitations and apprehensions of God; for God is the soul and
						mind of the world.</p>
               <p>Aristotle the son of Nichomachus, the Stagirite, constitutes three principles; Entelecheia (which is the same with
						form), matter, and privation. He acknowledges four elements,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.113"/>
						
						 and adds a certain fifth body, which is ethereal and
						not obnoxious to mutation.</p>
               <p>Zeno son of Mnaseas, the native of Citium, avers these
						principles to be God and matter, the first of which is the
						efficient cause, the other the passible and receptive. Four
						elements he likewise confesses.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter IV.
						<lb/> HOW WAS THIS WORLD COMPOSED IN THAT ORDER AND AFTER THAT MANNER IT IS?</head>
               <p>THE world being broken and confused, after this manner it was reduced into figure and composure as now it is.
						The insectible bodies or atoms, by a wild and fortuitous motion, without any governing power, incessantly and swiftly
						were hurried one amongst another, many bodies being
						jumbled together; upon this account they have a diversity
						in the figures and magnitude. These therefore being so
						jumbled together, those bodies which were the greatest
						and heaviest sank into the lowest place; they that were
						of a lesser magnitude, being round, smooth, and slippery,
						meeting with those heavier bodies were easily broken into
						pieces, and were carried into higher places. But when that
						force whereby these variously figured particles fought with
						and struck one another, and forced the lighter upwards,
						did cease, and there was no farther power left to drive them
						into superior regions, yet they were wholly hindered from
						descending downwards, and were compelled to reside in
						those places capable to receive them; and these were the
						heavenly spaces, unto which a multitude of these little bodies were whirled, and these being thus shivered fell into
						coherence and mutual embraces, and by this means the
						heaven was produced. Then a various and great multitude
						of atoms enjoying the same nature, as it is before asserted,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.114"/>
						
						being hurried aloft, did form the stars. The multitude
						of these exhaled bodies, having struck and broke the air
						in shivers, forced a passage through it; this being converted into wind invested the stars, as it moved, and whirled
						them about, by which means to this present time that circulary motion which these stars have in the heavens is
						maintained. Much after the same manner the earth was
						made; for by those little particles whose gravity made
						them to reside in the lower places the earth was formed.
						The heaven, fire, and air were constituted of those particles which were carried aloft. But a great deal of matter
						remaining in the earth, this being condensed by the forcible driving of the winds and the breathings from the stars,
						every little part and form of it was broken in pieces, which
						produced the element of water; but this being fluidly disposed did run into those places which were hollow, and
						these places were those that were capable to receive and
						protect it; or else the water, subsisting by itself, did make
						the lower places hollow. After this manner the principal
						parts of the world were constituted.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter V.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE UNIVERSE IS ONE.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics pronounce that the world is one thing, and
						this they say is the universe and is corporeal.</p>
               <p>Empedocles's opinion is, that the world is one; yet by no
						means the system of this world must be styled the universe,
						but that it is a small part of it, and the remainder is idle
						matter.</p>
               <p>What to Plato seems the truest he thus declares, that
						there is one world, and that world is the universe; and
						this he endeavors to evince by three arguments. First,
						that the world could not be complete and perfect, if it did
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.115"/>
						
						not within itself include all beings. Secondly, nor could it
						give the true resemblance of its original and exemplar, if
						it were not the one only begotten thing. Thirdly, it could
						not be incorruptible, if there were any being out of its
						compass to whose power it might be obnoxious. But to
						Plato it may be thus returned. First, that the world is not
						complete and perfect, nor doth it contain all things within
						itself. And if man is a perfect being, yet he doth not encompass all things. Secondly, that there are many exemplars and originals of statues, houses, and pictures. Thirdly,
						how is the world perfect, if any thing beyond it is possible
						to be moved about it? But the world is not incorruptible,
						nor can it be so conceived, because it had an original.</p>
               <p>To Metrodorus it seems absurd, that in a large field one
						only stalk should grow, and in an infinite space one only
						world exist; and that this universe is infinite is manifest
						by this, that there are causes infinite. Now if this world
						were finite and the causes which produced it infinite,
						it is necessary that the worlds likewise be infinite; for
						where all causes do concur, there the effects also must
						appear, let the causes be what they will, either atoms or
						elements.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter VI.
						<lb/> WHENCE DID MEN OBTAIN THE KNOWLEDGE OF THE EXISTENCE AND ESSENCE OF A DEITY?</head>
               <p>THE Stoics thus define the essence of a God. It is a
						spirit intellectual and fiery, which acknowledges no shape,
						but is continually changed into what it pleases, and assimilates itself to all things. The knowledge of this Deity
						they first received from the pulchritude of those things
						which so visibly appeared to us; for they concluded that
						nothing beauteous could casually or fortuitously be formed,
						but that it was framed from the art of a great understanding
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.116"/>
						
						 that produced the world. That the world is very resplendent is made perspicuous from the figure, the color,
						the magnitude of it, and likewise from the wonderful variety of those stars which adorn this world. The world is
						spherical; the orbicular hath the pre-eminence above all
						other figures, for being round itself it hath its parts likewise round. (On this account, according to Plato, the understanding, which is the most sacred part of man, is in
						the head.) The color of it is most beauteous; for it is
						painted with blue; which, though little blacker than purple, yet hath such a shining quality, that by reason of the
						vehement efficacy of its color it cuts through such an interval of air; whence it is that at so great a distance the
						heavens are to be contemplated. And in this very greatness of the world the beauty of it appears. View all
						things: that which contains the rest carries a beauty with
						it, as an animal or a tree. Also all things which are visible to us accomplish the beauty of the world. The oblique circle called the Zodiac in the heaven is with
						different images painted and distinguished:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>There's Cancer, Leo, Virgo, and the Claws;
						</l>
                        <l>Scorpio, Arcitenens, and Capricorn;
						</l>
                        <l>Amphora, Pisces, then the Ram, and Bull;
						</l>
                        <l>The lovely pair of Brothers next succeed.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Aratus.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>There are a thousand others that give us the suitable
						reflections of the beauty of the world. Thus Euripides:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>The starry splendor of the skies,
						</l>
                        <l>The wondrous work of that most wise
						</l>
                        <l>Creator, Time.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Elsewhere quoted in a long passage from the Sisyphus of Critias. See Nauck, p 598. (G.)</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>From this the knowledge of a God is conveyed to man;
						that the sun, the moon, and the rest of the stars, being carried under the earth, rise again in their proper color, magnitude, place, and times. Therefore they who by tradition
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.117"/>
						
						delivered to us the knowledge and veneration of the Gods
						did it by these three manner of ways:&mdash;first, from Nature;
						secondly, from fables; thirdly, from the testimony given by
						the laws of commonwealths. Philosophers taught the natural way; poets, the fabulous; and the political way is
						received from the constitutions of each commonwealth.
						All sorts of this learning are distinguished into these seven
						parts. The first is from things that are conspicuous, and
						the observation of those bodies which are in places superior to us. To men the heavenly bodies that are so visible
						did give the knowledge of the Deity; when they contemplated that they are the causes of so great an harmony, that
						they regulate day and night, winter and summer, by their
						rising and setting, and likewise considered those things
						which by their influences in the earth do receive a being
						and do likewise fructify. It was manifest to men that the
						Heaven was the father of those things, and the Earth the
						mother; that the Heaven was the father is clear, since
						from the heavens there is the pouring down of waters,
						which have their spermatic faculty; the Earth the mother,
						because she receives them and brings forth. Likewise men
						considering that the stars are running (<foreign lang="greek">qe/ontes</foreign>) in a perpetual motion, that the sun and moon give us the power to
						view and contemplate (<foreign lang="greek">qewrei=n</foreign>), they call them all Gods
						(<foreign lang="greek">qeou/s</foreign>).</p>
               <p>In the second and third place, they thus distinguished
						the Deities into those which are beneficial and those that
						are injurious to mankind. Those which are beneficial they
						call Jupiter, Juno, Mercury, Ceres; those who are mischievous the Dirae, Furies, and Mars. These, which threaten
						dangers and violence, men endeavor to appease and conciliate by sacred rites. The fourth and the fifth order of
						Gods they assign to things and passions; to passions, Love,
						Venus, and Desire; the Deities that preside over things,
						Hope, Justice, and Eunomia.</p>
               <pb id="v.3.p.118"/>
               <p>The sixth order of deities are those made by the poets;
						Hesiod, willing to find out a father for those Gods that
						acknowledge an original, invented their progenitors,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hyperion, Coeus, and Iapetus,
						</l>
                        <l>With Creius;</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Theogony, 134.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>upon which account this is called the fabulous. The
						seventh rank of the deities added to the rest are those
						which, by their beneficence to mankind, were honored with
						a divine worship, though they were born of mortal race;
						of this sort were Hercules, Castor and Pollux, and Bacchus.
						These are reputed to be of a human species; for of all beings that which is divine is most excellent, and man
						amongst all animals is adorned with the greatest beauty,
						and is also the best, being distinguished by virtue above
						the rest because of his intellect: therefore it was thought
						that those who were admirable for goodness should resemble that which is the best and most beautiful.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter VII.
						<lb/> WHAT IS GOD ?</head>
               <p>SOME of the philosophers, such as Diagoras the Melian,
						Theodorus the Cyrenean, and Euemerus the Tegeatan, did
						unanimously deny there were any Gods; and Callimachus
						the Cyrenean discovered his mind touching Euemerus in
						these Iambic verses, thus writing:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>To th' ante-mural temple flock apace,
						</l>
                        <l>Where he that long ago composed of brass</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">According to Bentley, <q direct="unspecified">Panchaean Jove.</q> See Diodorus, VI. Frag. 2; and
							Bentley's note to Callimachus, Frag. 86. (G.)</note>
                        <l>Great Jupiter, Thrasonic old bald pate,
							</l>
                        <l>Now writes his impious books,&mdash;a boastful ass!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>meaning books which denote there are no Gods. Euripides the tragedian durst not openly declare his sentiment;
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.119"/>
						
						the court of Areopagus terrified him. Yet he sufficiently
						manifested his thoughts by this method. He presented in
						his tragedy Sisyphus, the first and great patron of this
						opinion, and introduced himself as one agreeing with
						him:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Disorder in those days did domineer,
						</l>
                        <l>And brutal power kept the world in fear.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwards by the sanction of laws wickedness was suppressed; but by reason that laws could prohibit only public villanies, yet could not hinder many persons from acting
						secret impieties, some wise persons gave this advice, that
						we ought to blind truth with lying disguises, and to persuade men that there is a God:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>There's an eternal God does hear and see
						</l>
                        <l>And understand every impiety;
						</l>
                        <l>Though it in dark recess or thought committed be.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>But this poetical fable ought to be rejected, he thought,
						together with Callimachus, who thus saith:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>If you believe a God, it must be meant
						</l>
                        <l>That you conceive this God omnipotent.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>But God cannot do every thing; for, if it were so, then
						God could make snow black, and the fire cold, and him that
						is in a posture of sitting to be upright, and so on the contrary. The brave-speaking Plato pronounceth that God
						formed the world after his own image; but this smells rank
						of the old dotages, old comic poets would say; for how
						did God, casting his eye upon himself, frame this universe ?
						Or how can God be spherical, and not be inferior to
						man?</p>
               <p>Anaxagoras avers that bodies did consist from all eternity, but the divine intellect did reduce them into their
						proper orders, and effected the origination of all beings.
						Plato did not suppose that the primary bodies had their
						consistence and repose, but that they were moved confusedly and in disorder; but God, knowing that order was
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.120"/>
						
						better than confusion, did digest them into the best methods. Both these were equally peccant; for both suppose
						God to be the great moderator of human affairs, and for
						that cause to have formed this present world; when it is
						apparent that an immortal and blessed being, replenished
						with all his glorious excellencies, and not at all obnoxious
						to any sort of evil, but being wholly occupied with his
						own felicity and immortality, would not employ himself
						with the concerns of men; for certainly miserable is the
						being which, like a laborer or artificer, is molested by the
						troubles and cares which the forming and governing of
						this world must give him. Add to this, that the God
						whom these men profess was either not at all existing previous to this present world (when bodies were either
						reposed or in a disordered motion), or that then God did
						either sleep, or else was in a perpetual watchfulness, or
						that he did neither of these. Now neither the first nor
						the second can be entertained, because they suppose God
						to be eternal; if God from eternity was in a continual
						sleep, he was in an eternal death,&mdash;and what is death but
						an eternal sleep?&mdash;but no sleep can affect a Deity, for the
						immortality of God and alliance to death are vastly different. But if God was in a continual vigilance, either there
						was something wanting to make him happy, or else his
						beatitude was perfectly complete; but according to neither
						of these can God be said to be blessed; not according to
						the first, for if there be any deficiency there is no perfect
						bliss; not according to the second, for, if there be nothing
						wanting to the felicity of God, it must be a useless enterprise for him to busy himself in human affairs. And how
						can it be supposed that God administers by his own providence human concerns, when to vain and trifling persons
						prosperous things happen, to great and high adverse?
						Agamemnon was both
						<quote rend="blockquote">A virtuous prince, for warlike acts renowned,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. III. 173.</note>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <pb id="v.3.p.121"/>
               <p>and by an adulterer and adulteress was vanquished and
						perfidiously slain. Hercules, after he had freed the life
						of man from many things that were pernicious to it, perished by the witchcraft and poison of Deianira.</p>
               <p>Thales said that the intelligence of the world was God.</p>
               <p>Anaximander concluded that the stars were heavenly
						Deities.</p>
               <p>Democritus said that God, being a globe of fire, is intelligence and the soul of the world.</p>
               <p>Pythagoras says that, of his principles, unity is God; and
						the perfect good, which is indeed the nature of a unity, is
						mind itself; but the binary number, which is infinite, is a
						devil, and in its own nature evil,&mdash;about which the multitude of material beings, and this world which is the object
						of our eyes, are conversant.</p>
               <p>Socrates and Plato agree that God is that which is one,
						hath its original from its own self, is of a singular subsistence, is one only being perfectly good; all these various names signifying goodness do all centre in mind; hence
						God is to be understood as that mind and intellect, which
						is a separate idea, that is to say, pure and unmixed of all
						matter, and not twisted with any thing obnoxious to
						passions.</p>
               <p>Aristotle's sentiment is, that God hath his residence in
						superior regions, and hath placed his throne in the sphere
						of the universe, and is a separate idea; which sphere is an
						ethereal body, which is by him styled the fifth essence or
						quintessence. For there is a division of the universe into
						spheres, which are contiguous by their nature but appear to
						reason to be separated; and he concludes that each of the
						spheres is an animal, composed of a body and soul; the
						body of them is ethereal, moved orbicularly, the soul is
						the rational form, which is unmoved, and yet is the cause
						that the sphere is actually in motion.</p>
               <p>The Stoics affirm that God is a thing more common and
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.122"/>
						
						obvious, and is a mechanic fire which every way spreads
						itself to produce the world; it contains in itself all seminal
						virtues, and by this means all things by a fatal necessity
						were produced. This spirit, passing through the whole
						world, received various names from the mutations in the
						matter through which it ran in its journey. God therefore
						is the world, the stars, the earth, and (highest of all) the
						supreme mind in the heavens.</p>
               <p>In the judgment of Epicurus all the Gods are anthropomorphites, or have the shape of men; but they are perceptible only by reason, for their nature admits of no other
						manner of being apprehended, their parts being so small
						and fine that they give no corporeal representations. The
						same Epicurus asserts that there are four other natural
						beings which are immortal: of this sort are atoms, the
						vacuum, the infinite, and the similar parts; and these last
						are called Homoeomeries and likewise elements.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter VIII.
						<lb/> OF THOSE THAT ARE CALLED GENIUSES AND HEROES.</head>
               <p>HAVING treated of the essence of the deities in a just
						order, it follows that we discourse of daemons and heroes.
						Thales, Pythagoras, Plato, and the Stoics do conclude that
						daemons are essences which are endowed with souls; that
						the heroes are the souls separated from their bodies, some
						are good, some are bad; the good are those whose souls
						are good, the evil those whose souls are wicked. All this
						is rejected by Epicurus.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter IX.
						<lb/> OF MATTER.</head>
               <p>MATTER is that first being which is substrate for generation, corruption, and all other alterations.</p>
               <pb id="v.3.p.123"/>
               <p>The disciples of Thales and Pythagoras, with the Stoics,
						are of opinion that matter is changeable, mutable, convertible, and sliding through all things.</p>
               <p>The followers of Democritus aver that the vacuum, the
						atom, and the incorporeal substance are the first beings,
						and not obnoxious to passions.</p>
               <p>Aristotle and Plato affirm that matter is of that species
						which is corporeal, void of any form, species, figure, and
						quality, but apt to receive all forms, that she may be the
						nurse, the mother, and origin of all other beings. But they
						that do say that water, earth, air, and fire are matter do
						likewise say that matter cannot be without form, but conclude it is a body; but they that say that individual particles and atoms are matter do say that matter is without
						form.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter X.
						<lb/> OF IDEAS.</head>
               <p>AN idea is a being incorporeal, which has no subsistence
						by itself, but gives figure and form unto shapeless matter,
						and becomes the cause of its manifestation.</p>
               <p>Socrates and Plato conjecture that these ideas are essences separate from matter, having their existence in the
						understanding and fancy of the Deity, that is, of mind.</p>
               <p>Aristotle objected not to forms and ideas; but he doth
						not believe them separated from matter, or patterns of
						what God has made.</p>
               <p>Those Stoics, that are of the school of Zeno, profess that
						ideas are nothing else but the conceptions of our own
						mind.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter XI.
						<lb/> OF CAUSES.</head>
               <p>A CAUSE is that by which any thing is produced, or by
						which any thing is effected.</p>
               <pb id="v.3.p.124"/>
               <p>Plato gives this triple division of causes,&mdash;the material,
						the efficient, and the final cause; the principal cause he
						judges to be the efficient, which is the mind and intellect.</p>
               <p>Pythagoras and Aristotle judge the first causes are incorporeal beings, but those that are causes by accident or
						participation become corporeal substances; by this means
						the world is corporeal.</p>
               <p>The Stoics grant that all causes are corporeal, inasmuch
						as they are breath.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter XII.
						<lb/> OF BODIES.</head>
               <p>A BODY is that being which hath these three dimensions,
						breadth, depth, and length ;&mdash;or a bulk which makes a sensible resistance;&mdash;or whatsoever of its own nature possesseth a place.</p>
               <p>Plato saith that it is neither heavy nor light in its own
						nature, when it exists in its own place; but being in the
						place where another should be, then it has an inclination
						by which it tends to gravity or levity.</p>
               <p>Aristotle saith that, if we simply consider things in their
						own nature, the earth only is to be judged heavy, and fire
						light; but air and water are sometimes heavy and sometimes light.</p>
               <p>The Stoics think that of the four elements two are light,
						fire and air; two ponderous, earth and water; that which
						is naturally light doth by its own nature, not by any inclination, recede from its own centre; but that which is
						heavy doth by its own nature tend to its centre; for the
						centre is not a heavy thing of itself.</p>
               <p>Epicurus thinks that bodies are not to be limited; but
						the first bodies, which are simple bodies, and all those
						composed of them, all acknowledge gravity; that all atoms
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.125"/>
						
						are moved, some perpendicularly, some obliquely; some
						are carried aloft either by direct impulse or with vibrations.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="13">
               <head>Chapter XIII.
						<lb/> OF THOSE THINGS THAT ARE LEAST IN NATURE.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES, precedent to the four elements, introduceth
						the most minute bodies which resemble elements; but
						they did exist before the elements, having similar parts
						and orbicular.</p>
               <p>Heraclitus brings in the smallest fragments, and those
						indivisible.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="14">
               <head>Chapter XIV.
						<lb/> OF FIGURES.</head>
               <p>A FIGURE is the exterior appearance, the circumscription, and the boundary of a body.</p>
               <p>The Pythagoreans say that the bodies of the four elements are spherical, fire being in the supremest place only
						excepted, whose figure is conical.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="15">
               <head>Chapter XV.
						<lb/> OF COLORS.</head>
               <p>COLOR is the visible quality of a body.</p>
               <p>The Pythagoreans called color the outward appearance
						of a body. Empedocles, that which is consentaneous to
						the passages of the eye. Plato, that they are fires emitted
						from bodies, which have parts harmonious for the sight.
						Zeno the Stoic, that colors are the first figurations of matter. The Pythagoreans, that colors are of four sorts,
						white and black, red and pale; and they derive the variety
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.126"/>
						
						of colors from the diversity of the elements, and that seen
						in animals also from the variety of food and the air in
						which they live and are bred.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="16">
               <head>Chapter XVI.
						<lb/> OF THE DIVISION OF BODIES.</head>
               <p>THE disciples of Thales and Pythagoras grant that all
						bodies are passible and divisible unto infinity. Others
						hold that atoms and indivisible parts are there fixed, and
						admit not of a division into infinity. Aristotle, that all
						bodies are potentially but not actually divisible into infinity.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="17">
               <head>Chapter XVII.
						<lb/> HOW BODIES ARE MIXED AND CONTEMPERATED ONE WITH ANOTHER.</head>
               <p>THE ancient philosophers held that the mixture of elements proceeded from the alteration of qualities; but the
						disciples of Anaxagoras and Democritus say it is done by
						apposition. Empedocles composes the elements of still
						smaller bulks, those which are the most minute and may
						be termed the elements of elements. Plato assigns three
						bodies (but he will not allow these to be elements, nor properly so called), air, fire, and water, which are mutable into
						one another; but the earth is mutable into none of these.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="18">
               <head>Chapter XVIII.
						<lb/> OF A VACUUM.</head>
               <p>ALL the natural philosophers from Thales to Plato rejected a vacuum. Empedocles says that there is nothing
						of a vacuity in nature, nor any thing superabundant. Leucippus,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.127"/>
						
						 Democritus, Demetrius, Metrodorus, Epicurus, that
						the atoms are infinite in number; and that a vacuum is
						infinite in magnitude. The Stoics, that within the compass
						of the world there is no vacuum, but beyond it the vacuum
						is infinite. Aristotle,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">We should probably here read <q direct="unspecified">Pythagoras.</q> (G.)</note> that the vacuum beyond the world
						is so great that the heaven has liberty to breathe into it,
						for the heaven is fiery.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="19">
               <head>Chapter XIX.
						<lb/> OF PLACE.</head>
               <p>PLATO, to define place, calls it that thing which in its
						own bosom receives forms and ideas; by which metaphor
						he signifies matter, being (as it were) a nurse or receptacle
						of beings. Aristotle, that it is the ultimate superficies of
						the circumambient body, contiguous to that which it doth
						encompass.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="20">
               <head>Chapter XX.
						<lb/> OF SPACE.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics and Epicureans make a place, a vacuum, and
						a space to differ. A vacuum is that which is void of any
						thing that may be called a body; place is that which is possessed by a body; a space that which is partly filled with
						a body, as a cask with wine.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="21">
               <head>Chapter XXI.
						<lb/> OF TIME.</head>
               <p>IN the sense of Pythagoras, time is that sphere which
						encompasses the world. Plato says that it is a movable
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.128"/>
						
						image of eternity, or the interval of the world's motion.
						Eratosthenes, that it is the solar motion.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="22">
               <head>Chapter XXII.
						<lb/> OF THE ESSENCE AND NATURE OF TIME.</head>
               <p>PLATO says that the heavenly motion is time. Most of the
						Stoics affirm that motion itself is time. Most philosophers
						think that time had no beginning; Plato, that time had
						only an ideal beginning.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="23">
               <head>Chapter XXIII.
						<lb/> OF MOTION.</head>
               <p>PLATO and Pythagoras say that motion is a change and
						alteration in matter. Aristotle, that it is the actual operation of that which may be moved. Democritus, that there
						is but one sort of motion, and it is that which is vibratory.
						Epicurus, that there are two species of motion, one perpendicular, and the other oblique. Herophilus, that one
						species of motion is obvious only to reason, the other to
						sense. Heraclitus utterly denies that there is any thing of
						quiet or repose in nature; for that is the state of the dead;
						one sort of motion is eternal, which he assigns to beings
						eternal, the other perishable, to those things which are perishable.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="24">
               <head>Chapter XXIV.
						<lb/> OF GENERATION AND CORRUPTION.</head>
               <p>PARMENIDES, Melissus, and Zeno deny that there are any
						such things as generation and corruption, for they suppose
						that the universe is unmovable. Empedocles, Epicurus, and
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.129"/>
						
						other philosophers that combine in this, that the world is
						framed of small corporeal particles meeting together, affirm
						that corruption and generation are not so properly to be accepted; but there are conjunctions and separations, which do
						not consist in any alteration according to their qualities, but
						are made according to quantity by coalition or disjunction.
						Pythagoras, and all those who take for granted that matter
						is subject to mutation, say that generation and corruption
						are to be accepted in their proper sense, and that they are
						accomplished by the alteration, mutation, and dissolution
						of elements.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="25">
               <head>Chapter XXV.
						<lb/> OF NECESSITY.</head>
               <p>THALES says that necessity is omnipotent, and that it exerciseth an empire over every thing. Pythagoras, that the
						world is invested by necessity. Parmenides and Democritus, that there is nothing in the world but what is necessarily, and that this same necessity is otherwise called fate,
						justice, providence, and the architect of the world.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="26">
               <head>Chapter XXVI.
						<lb/> OF THE NATURE OF NECESSITY.</head>
               <p>PLATO distinguisheth and refers some things to Providence, others to necessity. Empedocles makes the nature
						of necessity to be that cause which employs principles and
						elements. Democritus makes it to be a resistance, impulse,
						and force of matter. Plato sometimes says that necessity
						is matter; at other times, that it is the habitude or respect
						of the efficient cause towards matter.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.130"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="27">
               <head>Chapter XXVII.
						<lb/> OF DESTINY OR FATE.</head>
               <p>HERACLITUS, who attributes all things to fate, makes necessity to be the same thing with it. Plato admits of a
						necessity in the minds and the actions of men, but yet he
						introduceth a cause which flows from ourselves. The Stoics,
						in this agreeing with Plato, say that necessity is a cause invincible and violent; that fate is the ordered complication
						of causes, in which there is an intexture of those things
						which proceed from our own determination, so that some
						things are to be attributed to fate, others not.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="28">
               <head>Chapter XXVIII.
						<lb/> OF THE NATURE OF FATE.</head>
               <p>ACCORDING to Heraclitus, the essence of fate is a certain
						reason which penetrates the substance of all being; and
						this is an ethereal body, containing in itself that seminal
						faculty which gives an original to every being in the universe. Plato declares that it is the eternal reason and the
						eternal law of the nature of the universe. Chrysippus,
						that it is a spiritual faculty, which in due order doth manage and rule the universe. Again, in his book styled the
						Definitions, that fate is the reason of the world, or that it
						is that law whereby Providence rules and administers every
						thing that is in the world; or it is that reason by which
						all things past have been, all things present are, and all
						things future will be. The Stoics say that it is a chain of
						causes, that is, it is an order and connection of causes which
						cannot be resisted. Posidonius, that it is a being the third
						in degree from Jupiter; the first of beings is Jupiter, the
						second nature, and the third fate.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.131"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="29">
               <head>Chapter XXIX.
						<lb/> OF FORTUNE.</head>
               <p>PLATO says, that it is an accidental cause and a casual consequence in things which proceed from the election and
						counsel of men. Aristotle, that it is an accidental cause in
						those things which are done by an impulse to a certain end;
						and this cause is uncertain and unstable: there is a great deal
						of difference betwixt that which flows from chance and that
						which falls out by Fortune; for that which is fortuitous admits also of chance, and belongs to things practical; but
						what is by chance cannot be also by Fortune, for it belongs
						to things without action: Fortune, moreover, belongs to rational beings, but chance to rational and irrational beings
						alike, and even to inanimate things. Epicurus, that it is
						a cause not always consistent, but various as to persons,
						times, and manners. Anaxagoras and the Stoics, that it is
						that cause which human reason cannot comprehend; for
						there are some things which proceed from necessity, some
						things from Fate, some from choice and free-will, some
						from Fortune, some from chance.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="30">
               <head>Chapter XXX.
						<lb/> OF NATURE.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES believes that Nature is nothing else but the
						mixture and separation of the elements; for thus he writes
						in the first book of his natural philosophy:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nature gives neither life nor death,
						</l>
                        <l>Mutation makes us die or breathe.
						</l>
                        <l>The elements first are mixed, then all
						</l>
                        <l>Do separate: this mortals Nature call.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <pb id="v.3.p.132"/>
               <p>Anaxagoras is of the same opinion, that Nature is coalition
						and separation, that is, generation and corruption.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="book" n="2">
            <head>Book 2.</head>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="0">
               <p>HAVING finished my dissertation concerning principles
						and elements and those things which chiefly appertain to
						them, I will turn my pen to discourse of those things
						which are produced by them, and will take my beginning
						from the world, which contains and encompasseth all
						beings.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter I.
						<lb/> OF THE WORLD.</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS was the first philosopher that gave the
						name of <foreign lang="greek">xo/smos</foreign> to the world, from the order and beauty
						of it; for so that word signifies. Thales and his followers
						say the world is one. Democritus, Epicurus, and their
						scholar Metrodorus affirm that there are infinite worlds
						in an infinite space, for that infinite vacuum in its whole
						extent contains them. Empedocles, that the circle which
						the sun makes in its motion circumscribes the world, and
						that circle is the utmost bound of the world. Seleucus,
						that the world knows no limits. Diogenes, that the universe is infinite, but this world is finite. The Stoics make
						a difference between that which is called the universe, and
						that which is called the whole world;&mdash;the universe is
						the infinite space considered with the vacuum, the vacuity
						being removed gives the right conception of the world; so
						that the universe and the world are not the same thing.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.133"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter II.
						<lb/> OF THE FIGURE OF THE WORLD.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that the figure of the world is spherical,
						others that it is conical, others oval. Epicurus, that the
						figure of the world may be globular, or that it may admit
						of other shapes.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter III.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE WORLD BE AN ANIMAL.</head>
               <p>DEMOCRITUS, Epicurus, and those philosophers who introduced atoms and a vacuum, affirm that the world is not an
						animal, nor governed by any wise Providence, but that it is
						managed by a nature which is void of reason. All the other
						philosophers affirm that the world is informed with a soul,
						and governed by reason and Providence. Aristotle is excepted, who is somewhat different; he is of opinion, that
						the whole world is not acted by a soul in every part of it,
						nor hath it any sensitive, rational, or intellectual faculties,
						nor is it guided by reason and Providence in every part of
						it; of all which the heavenly bodies are made partakers,
						for the circumambient spheres are animated and are living
						beings; but those things which are about the earth are
						void of those endowments; and though those terrestrial
						bodies are of an orderly disposition, yet that is casual and
						not primogenial.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter IV.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE WORLD IS ETERNAL AND INCORRUPTIBLE.</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS [and Plato], with the Stoics, affirm that the
						world was framed by God, and being corporeal is obvious
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.134"/>
						
						to the senses, and in its own nature is obnoxious to destruction; but it shall never perish, it being preserved by
						the providence of God. Epicurus, that the world had a
						beginning, and so shall have an end, as plants and animals
						have. Xenophanes, that the world never had a beginning,
						is eternal and incorruptible. Aristotle, that the part of
						the world which is sublunary is obnoxious to change, and
						there terrestrial beings find a decay.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter V.
						<lb/> WHENCE DOES THE WORLD RECEIVE ITS NUTRIMENT?</head>
               <p>ARISTOTLE says that, if the world be nourished, it will
						likewise be dissolved; but it requires no aliment, and will
						therefore be eternal. Plato, that this very world prepares
						for itself a nutriment, by the alteration of those things
						which are corruptible in it. Philolaus believes that a destruction happens to the world in two ways; either by
						fire falling from heaven, or by the lunary water being
						poured down through the whirling of the air; and the
						exhalations proceeding from thence are the aliment of
						the world.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter VI.
						<lb/> FROM WHAT ELEMENT GOD DID BEGIN TO RAISE THE FABRIC OF THE WORLD.</head>
               <p>THE natural philosophers pronounce that the forming of
						this world took its original from the earth, it being its centre, for the centre is the principal part of the globe.
						Pythagoras, from the fire and the fifth element. Empedocles determines, that the first and principal element
						separated from the rest was the ether, then fire, after that
						the earth, which earth being strongly compacted by the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.135"/>
						
						force of a violent revolution, water springs from it, the
						exhalations of which water produce the air; the heaven
						took its origin from the ether, and fire gave a being to
						the sun; those things that belong to the earth are condensed from the remainders. Plato, that the visible world
						was framed after the exemplar of the intellectual world;
						the soul of the visible world was first produced, then the
						corporeal figure, first that which came from fire and earth,
						afterwards that which came from air and water. Pythagoras, that the world was formed of five solid figures which
						are called mathematical; the earth was produced by the
						cube, the fire by the pyramid, the air by the octahedron,
						the water by the icosahedron, and the globe of the universe by the dodecahedron. In all these Plato hath the
						same sentiments with Pythagoras.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter VII.
						<lb/> IN WHAT FORM AND ORDER THE WORLD WAS COMPOSED.</head>
               <p>PARMENIDES believes that there are small coronets alternately twisted one within another, some made up of a thin,
						others of a condensed matter; and there are others between them mixed mutually together of light and of
						darkness, and about them all there is a solid substance,
						which like a firm wall surrounds these coronets. Leucippus and Democritus wrap the world round about, as with
						a garment and membrane. Epicurus says that that which
						bounds some worlds is thin, and that which limits others
						is gross and condensed; and of these worlds some are in
						motion, others are fixed. Plato, that fire takes the first
						place in the world, the second the ether, after that the
						air, under that the water; the last place the earth possesseth: sometimes he puts the ether and the fire in the
						same place. Aristotle gives the first place to the ether, as
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.136"/>
						
						that which is impassible, it being a kind of fifth body;
						after which he placeth those that are passible, fire, air, and
						water, and last of all the earth. To those bodies that are
						accounted celestial he assigns a motion that is circular, but
						to those that are seated under them, if they be light bodies,
						an ascending, if heavy, a descending motion. Empedocles,
						that the places of the elements are not always fixed and
						determined, but they all succeed one another in their
						respective stations.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter VIII.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE CAUSE OF THE WORLD'S INCLINATION.</head>
               <p>DIOGENES and Anaxagoras affirm that, after the world
						was composed and the earth had produced living creatures,
						the world out of its own propensity made an inclination
						towards the south. Perhaps this may be attributed to a
						wise Providence (they say), that thereby some parts of the
						world may be habitable, others uninhabitable, according as
						the various climates are affected with a rigorous cold, or a
						scorching heat, or a just temperament of cold and heat.
						Empedocles, that the air yielding to the impetuous force
						of the solar rays, the pole received an inclination; whereby the northern parts were exalted and the southern depressed, by which means the whole world received its
						inclination.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter IX.
						<lb/> OF THAT THING WHICH IS BEYOND THE WORLD, AND WHETHER IT BE A VACUUM OR NOT.</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS and his followers say that beyond the world
						there is a vacuum, into which and out of which the world
						hath its respiration. The Stoics, that there is a vacuum
						into which the infinite world by a conflagration shall be
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.137"/>
						
						dissolved. Posidonius, not an infinite vacuum, but as much
						as suffices for the dissolution of the world; and this he
						asserts in his first book concerning the Vacuum. Aristotle
						affirms, that there is no vacuum. Plato concludes that
						neither within nor without the world there is any vacuum.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter X.
						<lb/> WHAT PARTS OF THE WORLD ARE ON THE RIGHT HAND, AND WHAT PARTS ARE ON THE LEFT.</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS, Plato, and Aristotle say that the eastern
						parts of the world, from whence motion commences, are of
						the right, those of the western are of the left-hand of the
						world. Empedocles, that those that are of the right-hand
						are towards the summer solstice, those of the left towards
						the winter solstice.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter XI.
						<lb/> OF HEAVEN, WHAT IS ITS NATURE AND ESSENCE.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMENES declares that the circumference of heaven
						is the limit of the earth's revolution. Empedocles, that
						the heaven is a solid substance, and hath the form and
						hardness of crystal, it being composed of the air compacted by fire, and that in both hemispheres it invests the
						elements of air and fire. Aristotle, that it is formed by
						the fifth body, and by the mixture of extreme heat and
						cold
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter XII.
						<lb/> INTO HOW MANY CIRCLES IS THE HEAVEN DISTINGUISHED; OR, OF THE DIVISION OF HEAVEN.</head>
               <p>THALES, Pythagoras, and the followers of Pythagoras do
						distribute the universal globe of heaven into five circles,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.138"/>
						
						which they denominate zones; one of which is called the
						arctic circle, which is always conspicuous to us, another is
						the summer tropic, another is the equinoctial, another is
						the winter tropic, another is the antarctic circle, which
						is always invisible. The circle called the zodiac is placed
						under the three that are in the midst, and lies obliquely,
						gently touching them all. Likewise, they are all cut in
						right angles by the meridian, which runs from pole to pole.
						It is supposed that Pythagoras made the first discovery of
						the obliquity of the zodiac, but one Oenopides of Chios
						challenges to himself the invention of it.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="13">
               <head>Chapter XIII.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE ESSENCE OF THE STARS, AND HOW THEY ARE COMPOSED.</head>
               <p>THALES believes that they are globes of earth set on fire.
						Empedocles, that they are fiery bodies arising from that
						fire which the ether embraced within itself, and did shatter in pieces when the elements were first separated one
						from another. Anaxagoras, that the circumambient ether
						is of a fiery substance, which, by a vehement force in its
						whirling about, did tear stones from the earth, and by its
						own power set them on fire, and establish them as stars
						in the heavens. Diogenes thinks they resemble pumice
						stones, and that they are the breathings of the world; again
						he supposeth that there are some invisible stones, which
						sometimes fall from heaven upon the earth, and are there
						quenched; as it happened at Aegos-potami, where a stony
						star resembling fire did fall. Empedocles, that the fixed
						stars are fastened to the crystal, but the planets are
						loosened. Plato, that the stars for the most part are of a
						fiery nature, but they are made partakers of another element, with which they are mixed after the resemblance of
						glue. Xenophanes, that they are composed of inflamed
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.139"/>
						
						clouds, which in the daytime are quenched, and in the
						night are kindled again. The like we see in coals; for
						the rising and setting of the stars is nothing else but the
						quenching and kindling of them. Heraclides and the
						Pythagoreans, that every star is a world in an infinite ether,
						and itself encompasseth air, earth, and ether; this opinion
						is current among the followers of Orpheus, for they suppose that each of the stars does make a world. Epicurus
						condemns none of these opinions, for he embraces any
						thing that is possible.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="14">
               <head>Chapter XIV.
						<lb/> OF WHAT FIGURE THE STARS ARE.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that the stars are of a circular form, like
						the sun, the moon, and the world. Cleanthes, that they
						are of a conical figure. Anaximenes, that they are fastened as nails in the crystalline firmament; some others,
						that they are fiery plates of gold, resembling pictures.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="15">
               <head>Chapter XV.
						<lb/> OF THE ORDER AND PLACE OF THE STARS.</head>
               <p>XENOCRATES says that the stars are moved in one and
						the same superficies. The other Stoics say that they are
						moved in various superficies, some being superior, others
						inferior. Democritus, that the fixed stars are in the highest place; after those the planets; after which the sun,
						Venus, and the moon, in their order. Plato, that the first
						after the fixed stars that makes its appearance is Phaenon,
						the star of Saturn; the second Pha&euml;ton, the star of Jupiter; the third the fiery, which is the star of Mars; the
						fourth the morning star, which is the star of Venus;
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.140"/>
						
						the fifth the shining star, and that is the star of Mercury;
						in the sixth place is the sun, in the seventh the moon. Plato
						and some of the mathematicians conspire in the same
						opinion; others place the sun as the centre of the planets.
						Anaximander, Metrodorus of Chios, and Crates assign to
						the sun the superior place, after him they place the moon,
						after them the fixed stars and planets.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="16">
               <head>Chapter XVI.
						<lb/> OF THE MOTION AND CIRCULATION OF THE STARS.</head>
               <p>ANAXAGORAS, Democritus, and Cleanthes say that all the
						stars have their motion from east to west. Alcmaeon
						and the mathematicians, that the planets have a contrary
						motion to the fixed stars, and in opposition to them are
						carried from the west to the east. Anaximander, that
						they are moved by those circles and spheres on which they
						are placed. Anaximenes, that they are turned under and
						about the earth. Plato and the mathematicians, that the
						sun, Venus, and Mercury have equal measures in their
						motions.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="17">
               <head>Chapter XVII.
						<lb/> WHENCE DO THE STARS RECEIVE THEIR LIGHT?</head>
               <p>METRODORUS says that all the fixed stars derive their light
						from the sun. Heraclitus and the Stoics, that earthly
						exhalations are those by which the stars are nourished.
						Aristotle, that the heavenly bodies require no nutriment,
						for they being eternal cannot be obnoxious to corruption.
						Plato and the Stoics, that the whole world and the stars
						are fed by the same things.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.141"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="18">
               <head>Chapter XVIII.
						<lb/> WHAT ARE THOSE STARS WHICH ARE CALLED THE DIOSCURI, THE TWINS, OR CASTOR AND POLLUX?</head>
               <p>XENOPHANES says that those which appear as stars in
						the tops of ships are little clouds shining by their peculiar motion. Metrodorus, that the eyes of frighted and
						astonished people emit those lights which are called the
						Twins.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="19">
               <head>Chapter XIX.
						<lb/> HOW STARS PROGNOSTICATE, AND WHAT IS THE CAUSE OF WINTER AND SUMMER.</head>
               <p>PLATO says that the summer and winter indications proceed from the rising and setting of the stars, that is, from
						the rising and setting of the sun, the moon, and the fixed
						stars. Anaximenes, that the others in this are not at all
						concerned, but that it is wholly performed by the sun.
						Eudoxus and Aratus assign it in common to all the stars,
						for thus Aratus sings:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thund'ring Jove stars in heaven hath fixed,
						</l>
                        <l>And them in such beauteous order mixed,
						</l>
                        <l>Which yearly future things predict.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="20">
               <head>Chapter XX.
						<lb/> OF THE ESSENCE OF THE SUN.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER says, that the sun is a circle eight and
						twenty times bigger than the earth, and has a circumference which very much resembles that of a chariot-wheel,
						which is hollow and full of fire; the fire of which appears
						to us through its mouth, as by a hole in a pipe; and this
						is the sun. Xenophanes, that the sun is constituted of
						small bodies of fire compact together and raised from a
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.142"/>
						
						moist exhalation, which collected together make the body
						of the sun; or that it is a cloud enfired. The Stoics, that
						it is an intelligent flame proceeding from the sea. Plato,
						that it is composed of abundance of fire. Anaxagoras,
						Democritus, and Metrodorus, that it is an enfired stone, or
						a burning mass. Aristotle, that it is a sphere formed out
						of the fifth body. Philolaus the Pythagorean, that the
						sun shines as crystal, which receives its splendor from the
						fire of the world and so reflecteth its light upon us; so
						that first, the body of fire which is celestial belongs
						to the sun; and secondly, the fiery reflection that proceeds from it, in the form of a mirror; and lastly, the
						light which is spread upon us by way of reflection from
						that mirror; and this last we call the sun, which is (as it
						were) an image of an image. Empedocles, that there are
						two suns; the one the prototype, which is a fire placed in
						the other hemisphere, which it totally fills, and is always
						ordered in a direct opposition to the reflection of its own
						light; and the sun which is visible to us, formed by the
						reflection of that splendor in the other hemisphere (which
						is filled with air mixed with heat), the light reflected from
						the circular sun in the opposite hemisphere falling upon
						the crystalline sun; and this reflection is carried round
						with the motion of the fiery sun. To give briefly the
						full sense, the sun is nothing else but the light and brightness of that fire which encompasseth the earth. Epicurus,
						that it is an earthy bulk well compacted, with hollow
						passages like a pumice-stone or a sponge, which is kindled
						by fire.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="21">
               <head>Chapter XXI.
						<lb/> OF THE MAGNITUDE OF THE SUN.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER says, that the sun itself in greatness is
						equal to the earth, but that the circle from whence it
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.143"/>
						
						receives its respiration and in which it is moved is seven
						and twenty times larger than the earth. Anaxagoras, that
						it is far greater than Peloponnesus. Heraclitus, that it
						is no broader than a man's foot. Epicurus, that he equally
						embraceth all the foresaid opinions,&mdash;that the sun may
						be of magnitude as it appears, or it may be somewhat
						greater or somewhat less.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="22">
               <head>Chapter XXII.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE FIGURE OR SHAPE OF THE SUN.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMENES affirms that in its dilatation it resembles a
						leaf. Heraclitus, that it hath the shape of a boat, and is
						somewhat crooked. The Stoics, that it is spherical, and it
						is of the same figure with the world and the stars. Epicurus, that the recited dogmas may be defended.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="23">
               <head>Chapter XXIII.
						<lb/> OF THE TURNING AND RETURNING OF THE SUN, OR THE SUMMER AND WINTER SOLSTICE.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMENES thinks that the stars are forced by a condensed and resisting air. Anaxagoras, by the repelling
						force of the northern air, which is violently pushed on by
						the sun, and thus rendered more condensed and powerful.
						Empedocles, that the sun is hindered from a continual direct course by its spherical vehicle and by the two circular
						tropics. Diogenes, that the sun, when it comes to its utmost
						declination, is extinguished, a rigorous cold damping the
						heat. The Stoics, that the sun maintains its course only
						through that space in which its aliment is seated, let it be
						the ocean or the earth; by the exhalations proceeding from
						these it is nourished. Plato, Pythagoras, and Aristotle, that
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.144"/>
						
						the sun receives a transverse motion from the obliquity of
						the zodiac, which is guarded by the tropics; all these the
						globe clearly manifests.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="24">
               <head>Chapter XXIV.
						<lb/> OF THE ECLIPSES OF THE SUN.</head>
               <p>THALES was the first who affirmed that the eclipse of the
						sun was caused by the moon's running in a perpendicular
						line between it and the earth; for the moon in its own nature is terrestrial. And by mirrors it is made perspicuous
						that, when the sun is eclipsed, the moon is in a direct line
						below it. Anaximander, that the sun is eclipsed when the
						fiery mouth of it is stopped and hindered from expiration.
						Heraclitus, that it is after the manner of the turning of a
						boat, when the concave appears uppermost to our sight,
						and the convex nethermost. Xenophanes, that the sun is
						eclipsed when it is extinguished; and that a new sun is
						created to rise in the east. He gives a farther account of
						an eclipse-of the sun which remained for a whole month,
						and again of a total eclipse which changed the day into
						night. Some say that the cause of an eclipse is the invisible concourse of condensed clouds which cover the orb of
						the sun. Aristarchus placeth the sun amongst the fixed
						stars, and believeth that the earth [the moon?] is moved
						about the sun, and that by its inclination and vergency it
						intercepts its light and shadows its orb. Xenophanes, that
						there are many suns and many moons, according as the
						earth is distinguished by climates, circles, and zones. At
						some certain times the orb of the sun, falling upon some
						part of the world which is uninhabited, wanders in a
						vacuum and becomes eclipsed. The same person affirms
						that the sun, proceeding in its motion in the infinite space,
						appears to us to move orbicularly, receiving that representation from its infinite distance from us.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.145"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="25">
               <head>Chapter XXV.
						<lb/> OF THE ESSENCE OF THE MOON.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER affirms that the circle of the moon is nineteen times bigger than the earth, and resembles the sun, its
						orb being full of fire; and it suffers an eclipse when the
						wheel turneth,&mdash;which he describes by the divers turnings
						of a chariot-wheel, in the midst of it there being a hollow
						replenished with fire, which hath but one way of expiration. Xenophanes, that it is a condensed cloud. The
						Stoics, that it is mixed of fire and air. Plato, that it is
						a body of the greatest part earthy. Anaxagoras and
						Democritus, that it is a solid, condensed, and fiery body, in
						which there are champaign countries, mountains, and valleys. Heraclitus, that it is an earth covered with a cloud.
						Pythagoras, that the body of the moon was of a nature
						like a mirror.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="26">
               <head>Chapter XXVI.
						<lb/> OF THE MAGNITUDE OF THE MOON.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics declare, that in magnitude it exceeds the
						earth, as the sun itself doth. Parmenides, that it is equal
						to the sun, from whom it receives its light.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="27">
               <head>Chapter XXVII.
						<lb/> OF THE FIGURE OF THE MOON.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics believe that it is of the same figure with the
						sun, spherical. Empedocles, that the figure of it resembles
						a quoit. Heraclitus, a boat. Others, a cylinder.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="28">
               <head>Chapter XXVIII.
						<lb/> FROM WHENCE IS IT THAT THE MOON RECEIVES HER LIGHT?</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER thinks that she gives light to herself, but
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.146"/>
						
						it is very slender and faint. Antiphon, that the moon shines
						by its own proper light; but when it absconds itself; the
						solar beams darting on it obscure it. Thus it naturally happens, that a more vehement light puts out a weaker; the
						same is seen in other stars. Thales and his followers, that
						the moon borrows all her light of the sun. Heraclitus,
						that the sun and moon are after the same manner affected;
						in their configurations both are shaped like boats, and are
						made conspicuous to us, receiving their light from moist exhalations. The sun appears to us more refulgent, by reason
						it is moved in a clearer and purer air; the moon appears
						more duskish, it being carried in an air more troubled and
						gross.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="29">
               <head>Chapter XXIX.
						<lb/> OF THE ECLIPSE OF THE MOON.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMENES believes that the mouth of the hollow wheel,
						about which the moon is turned, being stopped is the cause
						of, an eclipse. Berosus, that it proceeds from the turning
						of the dark side of the lunar orb towards us. Heraclitus,
						that it is performed just after the manner of a boat turned
						upside downwards. Some of the Pythagoreans say, that
						the splendor arises from the earth, its obstruction from the
						Antichthon (or <hi rend="italics">counter-earth</hi>). Some of the later philosophers, that there is such a distribution of the lunar flame,
						that it gradually and in a just order burns until it be full
						moon; in like manner, that this fire decays by degrees,
						until its conjunction with the sun totally extinguisheth it.
						Plato, Aristotle, the Stoics, and all the mathematicians
						agree in this, that the obscurity with which the moon is
						every month affected ariseth from a conjunction with the
						sun, by whose more resplendent beams she is darkened;
						and the moon is then eclipsed when she falls upon the
						shadow of the earth, the earth interposing between the sun
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.147"/>
						
						and moon, or (to speak more properly) the earth intercepting the light of the moon.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="30">
               <head>Chapter XXX.
						<lb/> OF THE PHASES OF THE MOON, OR THE LUNAR ASPECTS; OR HOW IT COMES TO PASS THAT THE MOON APPEARS TO US TERRESTRIAL.</head>
               <p>THE Pythagoreans say, that the moon appears to us terraneous, by reason it is inhabited as our earth is, and in it
						there are animals of a larger size and plants of a rarer
						beauty than our globe affords; that the animals in their
						virtue and energy are fifteen degrees superior to ours;
						that they emit nothing excrementitious; and that the days
						are fifteen times longer. Anaxagoras, that the reason of
						the inequality ariseth from the commixture of things earthy
						and cold; and that fiery and caliginous matter is jumbled
						together, whereby the moon is said to be a star of a counterfeit aspect. The Stoics, that by reason of the diversity
						of her substance the composition of her body is subject
						to corruption.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="31">
               <head>Chapter XXXI.
						<lb/> HOW FAR THE MOON IS REMOVED FROM THE SUN.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES affirms, that the distance of the moon from
						the sun is double her remoteness from the earth. The
						mathematicians, that her distance from the sun is eighteen
						times her distance from the earth. Eratosthenes, that the
						sun is remote from the earth seven hundred and eighty
						thousand furlongs.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="32">
               <head>Chapter XXXII.
						<lb/> OF THE YEAR, AND HOW MANY CIRCULATIONS MAKE UP THE GREAT YEAR OF EVERY PLANET.</head>
               <p>THE year of Saturn is completed when he has had his
						circulation in the space of thirty solar years; of Jupiter
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.148"/>
						
						in twelve; of Mars in two, of the sun in twelve months;
						in so many Mercury and Venus, the spaces of their circulation being equal; of the moon in thirty days, in which
						time her course from her prime to her conjunction is finished. As to the great year, some make it to consist of
						eight years solar, some of nineteen, others of fifty-nine.
						Heraclitus, of eighteen thousand. Diogenes, of three hundred and sixty-five such years as Heraclitus assigns. Others
						there are who lengthen it to seven thousand seven hundred
						and seventy-seven years.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="book" n="3">
            <head>Book 3.</head>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="0">
               <p>IN my two precedent treatises having in due order taken
						a compendious view and given an account of the celestial
						bodies, and of the moon which divides between them and
						the terrestrial, I must now convert my pen to discourse in
						this third book of Meteors, which are beings above the
						earth and below the moon, and are extended to the site
						and position of the earth, which is supposed to be the
						centre of the sphere of this world; and from thence will
						I take my beginning.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter I.
						<lb/> OF THE GALAXY, OR THE MILKY WAY.</head>
               <p>IT is a cloudy circle, which continually appears in the
						air, and by reason of the whiteness of its colors is called
						the galaxy, or the milky way. Some of the Pythagoreans say that, when Pha&euml;ton set the world on fire, a star
						falling from its own place in its circular passage through
						the region caused an inflammation. Others say that originally it was the first course of the sun; others, that it is an
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.149"/>
						
						image as in a looking-glass, occasioned by the sun's reflecting its beams towards the heavens, and this appears in the
						clouds and in the rainbow. Metrodorus, that it is merely
						the solar course, or the motion of the sun in its own
						circle. Parmenides, that the mixture of a thick and thin
						substance gives it a color which resembles milk. Anaxagoras, that the sun moving under the earth and not being
						able to enlighten every place, the shadow of the earth,
						being cast upon the part of the heavens, makes the galaxy.
						Democritus, that it is the splendor which ariseth from the
						coalition of many small bodies, which, being firmly united
						amongst themselves, do mutually enlighten one another.
						Aristotle, that it is the inflammation of dry, copious, and
						coherent exhalations, by which the fiery train, whose seat
						is beneath the ether and the planets, is produced. Posidonius, that it is a combination of fire, of rarer substance
						than the stars, but denser than light.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter II.
						<lb/> OF COMETS AND SHOOTING FIRES, AND THOSE WHICH RESEMBLE BEAMS.</head>
               <p>SOME of the Pythagoreans say, that a comet is one of
						those stars which do not always appear, but after they
						have run through their determined course, they then rise
						and are visible to us. Others, that it is the reflection of our
						sight upon the sun, which gives the resemblance of comets
						much after the same manner as images are reflected in mirrors. Anaxagoras and Democritus, that two or more stars
						being in conjunction by their united light make a comet.
						Aristotle, that it is a fiery coalition of dry exhalations.
						Strato, that it is the light of the star darting through a
						thick cloud that hath invested it; this is seen in light
						shining through lanterns. Heraclides, native of Pontus,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.150"/>
						
						that it is a lofty cloud inflamed by a sublime fire. The
						like causes he assigns to the bearded comet, to those circles
						that arc seen about the sun or stars, or those meteors which
						resemble pillars or beams, and all others which are of this
						kind. This way unanimously go all the Peripatetics, believing that these meteors, being formed by the clouds, do
						differ according to their various configurations. Epigenes,
						that a comet arises from an elevation of spirit or wind,
						mixed with an earthy substance and set on fire. Bo&euml;thus,
						that it is a phantasy presented to us by inflamed air. Diogenes, that comets are stars. Anaxagoras, that those
						styled shooting stars fall down from the ether like sparks,
						and therefore are soon extinguished. Metrodorus, that it
						is a forcible illapse of the sun upon clouds which makes
						them to sparkle as fire. Xenophanes, that all such fiery
						meteors are nothing else but the conglomeration of the
						enfired clouds, and the flashing motions of them.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter III.
						<lb/> OF VIOLENT ERUPTION OF FIRE OUT OF THE CLOUDS. OF LIGHTNING. OF THUNDER. OF HURRICANES. OF WHIRLWINDS.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER affirms that all these are produced by the
						wind after this manner: the wind being enclosed by condensed clouds, by reason of its minuteness and lightness it
						violently endeavors to make its passage; and in breaking
						through the cloud it gives the noise; and the rending the
						cloud, because of the blackness of it, gives a resplendent
						flame. Metrodorus, that when the wind falls upon a cloud
						whose densing firmly compacts it, by breaking the cloud it
						causeth a great noise, and by striking and rending the cloud
						it gives the flame; and in the swiftness of its motion, the
						sun imparting heat to it, it throws out the thunderbolt. The
						weak declining of the thunderbolt ends in a violent tempest.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.151"/>
						
						Anaxagoras, that when heat and cold meet and are mixed
						together (that is, ethereal parts with airy), thereby a great
						noise of thunder is produced, and the color seen against
						the blackness of the cloud causes the flashing of fire; the
						full and great splendor is lightning, the more enlarged and
						embodied fire becomes a whirlwind, the cloudiness of it
						gives the hurricane. The Stoics, that thunder is the clashing of clouds one upon another, the flash of lightning is their
						fiery inflammation; their more rapid splendor is the thunderbolt, the faint and weak the whirlwind. Aristotle, that
						all these proceed from dry exhalations, which, if they meet
						with moist vapors, force their passage, and the breaking
						of them gives the noise of thunder; they, being very dry,
						take fire and make lightning; tempests and hurricanes
						arise from the plenitude of matter which each draw to
						themselves, the hotter parts attracted make the whirlwinds,
						the duller the tempests.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter IV.
						<lb/> OF CLOUDS, RAIN, SNOW, AND HAIL.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMENES thinks that by the air being very much condensed clouds are formed; this air being more compacted,
						rain is compressed through it; when water in its falling
						down freezeth, then snow is generated; when it is encompassed with a moist air, it is hail. Metrodorus, that a cloud
						is composed of a watery exhalation carried into a higher
						place. Epicurus, that they are made of vapors; and that
						hail and rain are formed in a round figure, being in their
						long descent pressed upon by the circumambient air.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter V.
						<lb/> OF THE RAINBOW.</head>
               <p>THOSE things which affect the air in the superior places
						of it are of two sorts. Some have a real subsistence, such
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.152"/>
						
						are rain and hail; others not. Those which enjoy not a
						proper subsistence are only in appearance; of this sort is
						the rainbow. Thus the continent to us that sail seems to
						be in motion.</p>
               <p>Plato says, that men admiring it feigned that it took
						origination from one Thaumas, which word signifies admiration. Homer says:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Jove paints the rainbow with a purple dye,
						</l>
                        <l>Alluring man to cast his wandering eye.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVII. 547.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Others therefore fabled that the bow hath a head like a
						bull, by which it swallows up rivers.</p>
               <p>But what is the cause of the rainbow? It is evident that
						what apparent things we see come to our eyes in right or
						in crooked lines, or by reflection: these last are incorporeal
						and to sense obscure, but to reason they are obvious. Those
						which are seen in right lines are those which we see through
						the air or horn or transparent stones, for all the parts of
						these things are very fine and tenuious; but those which
						appear in crooked lines are in water, the thickness of
						the water presenting them bended to our sight. This is the
						reason that oars in themselves straight, when put into the
						sea, appear to us crooked. The third manner of our seeing is by reflection, and this is perspicuous by mirrors.
						After this third sort the rainbow is affected. We conceive
						it is a moist exhalation converted into a cloud, and in a
						short space it is dissolved into small and moist drops.
						The sun declining towards the west, it will necessarily follow that the whole bow is seen opposite to the sun; for
						the eye being directed to those drops receives a reflection,
						and by this means the bow is formed. The eye doth not
						consider the figure and form, but the color of these drops;
						the first of which colors is a shining red, the second a
						purple, the third is blue and green. Let us consider
						whether the reason of this shining red color be the splendor
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.153"/>
						
						of the sun falling upon these small drops, the whole body
						of light being reflected, by which this bright red color is
						produced; the second part being troubled, and the light
						languishing in the drops, the color becomes purple (for the
						purple is the faint red); but the third part, being more
						and more troubled, is changed into the green color. And
						this is proved by other effects of Nature; if any one shall
						put water in his mouth and spit it out so opposite to the
						sun that its rays may be reflected on the drops, he shall
						see the resemblance of a rainbow; the same appears to
						men that are blear-eyed, when they fix their watery eyes
						upon a candle.</p>
               <p>Anaximenes thinks the bow is thus formed; the sun
						casting its splendor upon a thick, black, and gross cloud,
						and the rays not being in a capacity to penetrate beyond
						the superficies. Anaxagoras, that, the solar rays being reflected from a condensed cloud, the sun being placed directly opposite to it forms the bow after the mode of the
						repercussion of a mirror; after the same manner he assigns the natural cause of the Parhelia or mock-suns, which
						are often seen in Pontus. Metrodorus, that when the sun
						casts its splendor through a cloud, the cloud gives itself a
						blue, and the light a red color.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter VI.
						<lb/> OF METEORS WHICH RESEMBLE RODS, OR OF RODS.</head>
               <p>THESE rods and the mock-suns are constituted of a double nature, a real subsistence, and a mere appearance;&mdash;
						of a real subsistence, because the clouds are the object of
						our eyes; of a mere appearance, for their proper color is
						not seen, but that which is adventitious. The like affections, natural and. adventitious, in all such things do
						happen.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.154"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter VII.
						<lb/> OF WINDS.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER believes that wind is a fluid air, the sun
						putting into motion or melting the moist subtle parts of it.
						The Stoics, that all winds are a flowing air, and from the
						diversity of the regions whence they have their origin receive their denomination; as, from darkness and the west
						the western wind ; from the sun and its rising the eastern;
						from the north the northern, and from the south the southern winds. Metrodorus, that moist vapors heated by the
						sun are the cause of the impetuousness of violent winds.
						The Etesian, or those winds which annually commence
						about the rising of the Little Dog, the air about the northern pole being more compacted, blow vehemently following
						the sun when he returns from the summer solstice.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter VIII.
						<lb/> OF WINTER AND SUMMER.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES and the Stoics believe that winter is caused
						by the thickness of the air prevailing and mounting upwards; and summer by fire, it falling downwards.</p>
               <p>This description being given by me of Meteors, or
						those things that are above us, I must pass to those things
						which are terrestrial.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter IX.
						<lb/> OF THE EARTH, WHAT IS ITS NATURE AND MAGNITUDE.</head>
               <p>THALES and his followers say that there is but one earth.
						Hicetes the Pythagorean, that there are two earths, this
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.155"/>
						
						and the Antichthon, or the earth opposite to it. The
						Stoics, that this earth is one, and that finite and limited.
						Xenophanes, that the earth, being compacted of fire and
						air, in its lowest parts hath laid a foundation in an infinite
						depth. Metrodorus, that the earth is mere sediment and
						dregs of water, as the sun is of the air.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter X.
						<lb/> OF THE FIGURE OF THE EARTH.</head>
               <p>THALES, the Stoics, and their followers say that the earth
						is globular. Anaximander, that it resembles a smooth
						stony pillar. Anaximenes, that it hath the shape of a
						table. Leucippus, of a drum. Democritus, that it is like
						a quoit in its surface, and hollow in the middle.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter XI.
						<lb/> OF THE SITE AND POSITION OF THE EARTH.</head>
               <p>THE disciples of Thales say that the earth is the centre of the universe. Xenophanes, that it is first, being
						rooted in the infinite space. Philolaus the Pythagorean
						gives to fire the middle place, and this is the hearth-fire of
						the universe; the second place to the Antichthon; the third
						to that earth which we inhabit, which is seated in opposition unto and whirled about the opposite,&mdash;which is the
						reason that those which inhabit that earth cannot be seen
						by us. Parmenides was the first that confined the habitable world to the two solstitial (or temperate) zones.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter XII.
						<lb/> OF THE INCLINATION OF THE EARTH.</head>
               <p>LEUCIPPUS affirms that the earth vergeth towards the
						southern parts, by reason of the thinness and fineness that
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.156"/>
						
						is in the south ; the northern parts are more compacted,
						they being congealed by a rigorous cold, but those parts of
						the world that are opposite are enfired. Democritus, because, the southern parts of the atmosphere being the
						weaker, the earth as it enlarges bends towards the south;
						the northern parts are of an unequal, the southern of an
						equal temperament; and this is the reason that the earth
						bends towards those parts where the earth is laden with
						fruits and its own increase.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="13">
               <head>Chapter XIII.
						<lb/> OF THE MOTION OF THE EARTH.</head>
               <p>MOST of the philosophers say that the earth remains
						fixed in the same place. Philolaus the Pythagorean, that
						it is moved about the element of fire, in an oblique circle,
						after the same manner of motion that the sun and moon
						have. Heraclides of Pontus and Ecphantus the Pythagorean
						assign a motion to the earth, but not progressive, but after
						the manner of a wheel being carried on its own axis ; thus
						the earth (they say) turns itself upon its own centre from
						west to east. Democritus, that when the earth was first
						formed it had a motion, the parts of it being small and
						light; but in process of time the parts of it were condensed,
						so that by its own weight it was poised and fixed.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="14">
               <head>Chapter XIV.
						<lb/> INTO HOW MANY ZONES IS THE EARTH DIVIDED?</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS says that, as the celestial sphere is distributed into five zones, into the same number is the
						terrestrial; which zones are the arctic and antarctic,
						the summer and winter tropics (or temperate zones), and
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.157"/>
						
						the equinoctial; the middle of which zones equally divides
						the earth and constitutes the torrid zone; but that part
						which is in the middle of the summer and winter tropics
						is habitable, by reason the air is there temperate.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="15">
               <head>Chapter XV.
						<lb/> OF EARTHQUAKES.</head>
               <p>THALES and Democritus assign the cause of earthquakes
						to water. The Stoics say that it is a moist vapor contained
						in the earth, making an irruption into the air, that makes
						the earthquake. Anaximenes, that the dryness and rarety
						of the earth are the cause of earthquakes, the one of
						which is produced by extreme drought, the other by immoderate showers. Anaxagoras, that the air endeavoring
						to make a passage out of the earth, meeting with a thick
						superficies, is not able to force its way, and so shakes the
						circumambient earth with a trembling. Aristotle, that
						a cold vapor encompassing every part of the earth prohibits
						the evacuation of vapors; for those which are hot, being
						in themselves light, endeavor to force a passage upwards,
						by which means the dry exhalations, being left in the
						earth, use their utmost endeavor to make a passage out,
						and being wedged in, they suffer various circumvolutions
						and shake the earth. Metrodorus, that whatsoever is in its
						own place is incapable of notion, except it be pressed
						upon or drawn by the operation of another body; the
						earth being so seated cannot naturally be removed, yet
						divers parts and places of the earth may move one upon
						another. Parmenides and Democritus, that the earth
						being so equally poised hath no sufficient cause why it
						should incline rather to one side than to the other; so
						that it may be shaken, but cannot be removed. Anaximenes, that the earth by reason of its latitude is borne
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.158"/>
						
						upon the air which presseth upon it. Others opine
						that the earth swims upon the waters, as boards and
						broad planks, and by that reason is moved. Plato,
						that motion is by six manner of ways, upwards, downwards, on the right-hand and on the left, behind and
						before; therefore it is not possible that the earth should
						be moved in any of these modes, for it is altogether seated
						in the lowest place; it therefore cannot receive a motion,
						since there is nothing about it so peculiar as to make it
						incline any way; but some parts of it are so rare and thin
						that they are capable of motion. Epicurus, that the possibility of the earth's motion ariseth from a thick and
						aqueous air beneath the earth, which may, by moving
						or pushing it, be capable of its quaking; or that being so
						compassed, and having many passages, it is shaken by the
						wind which is dispersed through the hollow dens of it.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="16">
               <head>Chapter XVI.
						<lb/> OF THE SEA, AND HOW IT IS COMPOSED, AND HOW IT BECOMES TO THE TASTE BITTER.</head>
               <p>ANAXIMANDER affirms that the sea is the remainder of the
						primogenial humidity, the greatest part of which being
						dried up by the fire, the influence of the great heat altered
						its quality. Anaxagoras, that in the beginning water
						did not flow, but was as a standing pool; and that it was
						burnt by the motion of the sun about it, by which the oily
						part of the water being exhaled, the residue became salt
						and bitter. Empedocles, that the sea is the sweat of the
						earth burnt by the sun. Antiphon, that the sweat of that
						which was hot was separated from the other parts which
						were moist; these by seething and boiling became bitter,
						as happens in all sweats. Metrodorus, that the sea was
						strained through the earth, and retained some part of the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.159"/>
						
						density thereof; the same is observed in all those things
						which are strained through ashes. The schools of Plato,
						that the element of water being compacted by the rigor of
						the air became sweet, but that part which was exhaled
						from the earth, being enfired, became of a brackish taste.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="17">
               <head>Chapter XVII.
						<lb/> OF TIDES, OR OF THE EBBING AND FLOWING OF THE SEA.</head>
               <p>ARISTOTLE and Heraclides say, they proceed from the
						sun, which moves and whirls about the winds; and these
						falling with a violence upon the Atlantic, it is pressed and
						swells by them, by which means the sea flows; and their
						impression ceasing, the sea retracts, hence they ebb.
						Pytheas the Massilian, that the fulness of the moon gives the
						flow, the wane the ebb. Plato attributes it all to a certain
						oscillation of the sea, which by means of a mouth or orifice
						causes the alternate ebb and flow; and by this means the
						seas do rise and flow contrarily. Timaeus believes that
						those rivers which fall from the mountains of the Celtic
						Gaul into the Atlantic produce a tide. For upon their entering upon that sea, they violently press upon it, and so
						cause the flow; but they disemboguing themselves, there
						is a cessation of the impetuousness, by which means the
						ebb is produced. Seleucus the mathematician attributes a
						motion to the earth; and thus he pronounceth that the
						moon in its circumlation meets and repels the earth in its
						motion; between these two, the earth and the moon, there
						is a vehement wind raised and intercepted, which rushes
						upon the Atlantic Ocean, and gives us a probable argument
						that it is the cause the sea is troubled and moved.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.160"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="18">
               <head>Chapter XVIII.
						<lb/> OF THE HALO, OR A CIRCLE ABOUT A STAR.</head>
               <p>THE halo or circle is thus formed. A thick and dark air
						intervening between the moon or any other star and our
						eye, by which means our sight is dilated and reflected.
						when now our sight is incident upon the outward circumference of the orb of that star, there presently seems a
						circle to appear. This circle thus appearing is called the
						<foreign lang="greek">a(/lws</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">halo;</hi> and there is constantly such a circle seen by
						us, when such a density of sight happens.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="book" n="4">
            <head>Book 4.</head>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="0">
               <p>HAVING taken a survey of the general parts of the world,
						I will take a view of the particular members of it.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter I.
						<lb/> OF THE OVERFLOWING OF THE NILE.</head>
               <p>THALES conjectures that the Etesian or anniversary northern winds blowing strongly against Egypt heighten the
						swelling of the Nile, the mouth of that river being obstructed by the force of the sea rushing into it. Euthymenes the Massilian concludes that the Nile is filled by the
						ocean and that sea which is outward from it, this being
						naturally sweet. Anaxagoras, that the snow in Ethiopia
						which is frozen in winter is melted in summer, and this
						makes the inundation. Democritus, that the snows which
						are in the northern climates when the sun enters the summer solstice are dissolved and diffused; from those vapors
						clouds are compacted, and these are forcibly driven by the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.161"/>
						
						Etesian winds into the southern parts and into Egypt, from
						whence violent showers are poured; and by this means the
						fens of Egypt are filled with water, and the river Nile hath
						its inundation. Herodotus the historian, that the waters of
						the Nile receive from their fountain an equal portion of
						water in winter and in summer; but in winter the water
						appears less, because the sun, making its approach nearer
						to Egypt, draws up the rivers of that country into exhalations. Ephorus the historiographer, that in summer all
						Egypt seems to be melted and sweats itself into water, to
						which the thin and sandy soils of Arabia and Lybia contribute. Endoxus relates that the Egyptian priests affirm
						that, when it is summer to us who dwell under the northern tropic, it is winter with them that inhabit under the
						southern tropic; by this means there is a various contrariety and opposition of the seasons in the year, which cause
						such showers to fall as make the water to overflow the
						banks of the Nile and diffuse itself throughout all Egypt.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter II.
						<lb/> OF THE SOUL.</head>
               <p>THALES first pronounced that the soul is that being which
						is in a perpetual motion, or that whose motion proceeds
						from itself. Pythagoras, that it is a number moving itself;
						he takes a number to be the same thing with a mind.
						Plato, that it is an intellectual substance moving itself, and
						that motion is in a numerical harmony. Aristotle, that it
						is the first actuality (<foreign lang="greek">e)ntele/xeia</foreign>) of a natural organical
						body which has life potentially; and this actuality must
						be understood to be the same thing with energy or operation. Dicaearchus, that it is the harmony of the four elements. Asclepiades the physician, that it is the concurrent
						exercitation of the senses.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.162"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter III.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE SOUL BE A BODY, AND WHAT IS THE NATURE AND ESSENCE OF IT.</head>
               <p>ALL those that have been named by me do affirm that
						the soul itself is incorporeal, and by its own nature is in a
						perpetual motion, and in its own essence is an intelligent
						substance, and the actuality of a natural organical body
						which has life. The followers of Anaxagoras, that it is
						airy and a body. The Stoics, that it is a hot breath. Democritus, that it is a fiery composition of things which are
						perceptible by reason, the same having their forms spherical
						and without an inflaming faculty; and it is a body. Epicurus, that it is constituted of four qualities, of a fiery
						quality, of an aerial quality, a pneumatical, and of a fourth
						quality which hath no name, but it contains the virtue of
						the sense. Heraclitus, that the soul of the world is the
						exhalation which proceeds from the moist parts of it; but
						the soul of animals, arising from exhalations that are exterior and from those that are within them, is homogeneous
						to it.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter IV.
						<lb/> OF THE PARTS OF THE SOUL.</head>
               <p>PLATO and Pythagoras, according to their former account
						distribute the soul into two parts, the rational and irrational. By a more accurate and strict account the soul is
						branched into three parts; they divide the unreasonable
						part into the concupiscible and the irascible. The Stoics
						say the soul is constituted of eight parts; five of which
						are the senses, hearing, seeing, tasting, touching, smelling,
						the sixth is the faculty of speaking, the seventh of generating, the eighth of commanding; this is the principal of all,
						by which all the other are guided and ordered in their
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.163"/>
						
						proper organs, as we see the arms of a polypus aptly disposed. Democritus and Epicurus divide the soul into two
						parts, the rational, which hath its residence in the breast,
						and the irrational, which is diffused through the whole
						structure of the body. Democritus, that the quality of the
						soul is communicated to every thing, yea, to the dead
						corpses; for they are partakers of heat and some sense,
						when the most of both is expired out of them.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter V.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE PRINCIPAL PART OF THE SOUL, AND IN WHAT PART OF THE BODY IT RESIDES.</head>
               <p>PLATO and Democritus place its residence in the whole
						head. Strato, in that part of the forehead where the eyebrows are separated. Erasistratus, in the Epikranis, or membrane which involves the brain. Herophilus, in that sinus
						of the brain which is the basis of it. Parmenides, in the
						whole breast; which opinion is embraced by Epicurus.
						The Stoics are generally of this opinion, that the seat of
						the soul is throughout the heart, or in the spirit which is
						about it. Diogenes, in the arterial ventricle of the heart,
						which is also filled with vital spirit. Empedocles, in the
						mass of the blood. There are that say it is in the neck
						of the heart, others in the pericardium, others in the midriff. Certain of the Neoterics, that the seat of the soul is
						extended from the head to the diaphragm. Pythagoras,
						that the animal part of the soul resides in the heart, the
						intellectual in the head.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter VI.
						<lb/> OF THE MOTION OF THE SOUL.</head>
               <p>PLATO believes that the soul is in perpetual motion, but
						that the mind is immovable with respect to motion from
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.164"/>
						
						place to place. Aristotle, that the soul is not naturally
						moved, but its motion is accidental, resembling that which
						is in the forms of bodies.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter VII.
						<lb/> OF THE SOUL'S IMMORTALITY.</head>
               <p>PLATO and Pythagoras say that the soul is immortal;
						when it departs out of the body, it retreats to the soul of
						the world, which is a being of the same nature with it.
						The Stoics, when the souls leave the bodies, they are carried to divers places; the souls of the unlearned and
						ignorant descend to the coagmentation of earthly things,
						but the learned and vigorous endure till the general fire.
						Epicurus and Democritus, the soul is mortal, and it perisheth with the body. Plato and Pythagoras, that part of
						the soul of man which is rational is eternal; for though
						it be not God, yet it is the product of an eternal Deity;
						but that part of the soul which is divested of reason dies.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter VIII.
						<lb/> OF THE SENSES, AND OF THOSE THINGS WHICH ARE OBJECTS OF THE SENSES.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics give this definition of sense: Sense is the
						apprehension or comprehension of an object by means of
						an organ. There are several ways of expressing what
						sense is; it is either a habit, a faculty, an operation, or
						an imagination which apprehends by means of an organ
						of sense,&mdash;and also the eighth principal thing, from
						whence the senses are derived. The instruments of sense
						are intelligent spirits, which from the said commanding
						part reach unto all the organs of the body. Epicurus,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.165"/>
						
						that sense is a faculty, and that which is perceived by the
						sense is the product of it; so that sense hath a double
						acceptation,&mdash;sense which is the faculty, and the thing
						received by the sense, which is the effect. Plato, that
						sense is that commerce which the soul and body have
						with those things that are exterior to them; the power of
						which is from the soul, the organ by which is from the
						body; but both of them apprehend exterior objects by
						means of the imagination. Leucippus and Democritus,
						that sense and intelligence arise from external images;
						so neither of them can operate without the assistance of
						an image falling upon us.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter IX.
						<lb/> WHETHER WHAT APPEARS TO OUR SENSES AND IMAGINATIONS BE TRUE OR NOT.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that what the senses represent is true;
						what the imagination, is partly false, partly true. Epicurus, that every impression which either the sense or
						fancy gives us is true, but of those things that fall
						under the account of opinion, some are true, some false:
						sense gives us a false representation of those things only
						which are the objects of our understanding; but the fancy
						gives us a double error, both of things sensible and things
						intellectual. Empedocles and Heraclides, that the senses
						perceive by a just accommodation of the pores in every
						case; every thing that is perceived by the sense being congruously adapted to its proper organ.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter X.
						<lb/> HOW MANY SENSES ARE THERE?</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that there are five senses properly so
						called, seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, and touching.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.166"/>
						
						Aristotle indeed doth not add a sixth sense; but he assigns
						a common sense, which is the judge of all compounded
						species; into this each sense casts its proper representation, in which is discovered a transition of one thing into
						another, like as we see in figure and motion where there
						is a change of one into another. Democritus, that there
						are several species of senses, which appertain to beings
						destitute of reason, to the Gods, and to wise men.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter XI.
						<lb/> HOW THE ACTIONS OF THE SENSES, THE CONCEPTIONS OF OUR MINDS, AND THE HABIT OF OUR REASON ARE FORMED.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics affirm that every man, as soon as he is born,
						has the principal and commanding part of his soul, which
						is in him like a sheet of writing-paper, to which he commits all his notions. The first manner of his inscribing is
						by denoting those notions which flow from the senses.
						Suppose it be of a thing that is white; when the present
						sense of it is vanished, there is yet retained the remembrance; when many memorative notions of the same similitude do concur, then he is said to have an experience;
						for experience is nothing else but the abundance of
						notions that are of the same form met together. Some
						of these notions are naturally begotten according to the
						aforesaid manner, without the assistance of art; the others
						are produced by discipline, learning, and industry; these
						only are properly called notions, the others are prenotions. But reason, which gives us the denomination of
						rational, is completed by prenotions in the first seven
						years. The conception of the mind is the vision that the
						intelligence of a rational animal hath received; when that
						vision falls upon the rational soul, then it is called the
						conception of the mind, for it hath derived its name from
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.167"/>
						
						the mind (<foreign lang="greek">e)nno/hma</foreign> from <foreign lang="greek">nou=s</foreign>). Therefore these visions are
						not to be found in any other animals; they are appropriated only to Gods and to us men. If these we consider
						generally, they are phantasms; if specifically, they are
						notions. As pence or staters, if you consider them according to their own value, are merely pence and staters;
						but if you give them as a price for a naval voyage, they
						are called not merely pence, &amp;c., but your fraught.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter XII.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN IMAGINATION (<foreign lang="greek">fantasi/a</foreign>),
						IMAGINABLE (<foreign lang="greek">fantasto/n</foreign>), FANCY (<foreign lang="greek">fantastiko/n</foreign>), AND
						PHANTOM (<foreign lang="greek">fa/ntasma</foreign>)?</head>
               <p>CHRYSIPPUS affirms, these four are different one from
						another. Imagination (he says) is that passion raised in
						the soul which discovers itself and that which was the
						efficient of it; for example, after the eye hath looked upon
						a thing that is white, the sight of which produceth in the
						mind a certain impression, this gives us reason to conclude
						that the object of this impression is white, which affecteth
						us. So is it with touching and smelling.</p>
               <p>Phantasy or imagination is denominated from <foreign lang="greek">fw=s</foreign>, which
						denotes light; for as light discovers itself and all other
						things which it illuminates, so this imagination discovers
						itself and that which is the cause of it. The imaginable is
						the efficient cause of imagination; as any thing that is
						white, or any thing that is cold, or every thing that may
						make an impression upon the imagination. Fancy is a
						vain impulse upon the mind of man, proceeding from nothing which is really imaginable; this is experienced in those
						that whirl about their idle hands and fight with shadows;
						for to the imagination there is always some real imaginable thing presented, which is the efficient cause of it; but
						to the fancy nothing. A phantom is that to which we are
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.168"/>
						
						led by such a fanciful and vain attraction; this is to be
						seen in melancholy and distracted persons. Of this
						sort was Orestes in the tragedy, pronouncing these words:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mother, these maids with horror me affright;
						</l>
                        <l>Oh hurl them not, I pray, into my sight!
						</l>
                        <l>They're smeared with blood, and cruel, dragon-like,
						</l>
                        <l>Skipping about with deadly fury strike.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>These rave as frantic persons, they see nothing, and yet
						imagine they see. Thence Electra thus returns to him:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>O wretched man, securely sleep in bed;
						</l>
                        <l>Nothing thou seest, thy fancy's vainly led.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orestes, 255.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>After the same manner Theoclymenus in Homer.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="13">
               <head>Chapter XIII.
						<lb/> OF OUR SIGHT, AND BY WHAT MEANS WE SEE.</head>
               <p>DEMOCRITUS and Epicurus suppose that sight is caused
						by the insinuation of little images into the visive organ,
						and by the entrance of certain rays which return to the eye
						after striking upon the object. Empedocles supposes that
						images are mixed with the rays of the eye; these he styles
						the rays of images. Hipparchus, that the visual rays extend from both the eyes to the superficies of bodies, and give
						to the sight the apprehension of those same bodies, after
						the same manner in which the hand touching the extremity of bodies gives the sense of feeling. Plato, that the
						sight is the splendor of united rays; there is a light which
						reaches some distance from the eyes into a congruous air,
						and there is likewise a light emitted from bodies, which
						meets and is joined with the fiery visual light in the intermediate air (which is liquid and mutable); and the conjunction of these rays gives the sense of seeing. This is
						Plato's corradiancy, or splendor of united rays.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.169"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="14">
               <head>Chapter XIV.
						<lb/> OF THOSE IMAGES WHICH ARE PRESENTED TO OUR EYES IN MIRRORS.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES says that these images are caused by certain
						effluvias which, meeting together and insisting upon the
						superficies of the mirror, are perfected by that fiery quality
						emitted by the said mirror, which transmutes withal the air
						that surrounds it. Democritus and Epicurus, that the
						specular appearances are formed by the subsistence of the
						images which flow from our eyes; these fall upon the mirror and remain, while the light rebounds to the eye. The
						followers of Pythagoras explain it by the reflection of
						the sight; for our sight being extended (as it were) to the
						brass, and meeting with the smooth dense surface thereof
						it is struck back, and caused to return upon itself: the
						same appears in the hand, when it is stretched out and
						then brought back again to the shoulder. Any one
						may apply these instances to explain the manner of seeing.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="15">
               <head>Chapter XV.
						<lb/> WHETHER DARKNESS CAN BE VISIBLE TO US.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that darkness is seen by us, for out of our
						eyes there issues out some light into it; and our eyes do
						not impose upon us, for they really perceive there is darkness. Chrysippus says that we see darkness by the striking of the intermediate air; for the visual spirits which
						proceed from the principal part of the soul and reach to
						the ball of the eye pierce this air, which, after they have
						made those strokes upon it, presses conically on the surrounding air, where this is homogeneous. For from the
						eyes those rays are poured forth which are neither black
						nor cloudy. Upon this account darkness is visible to us.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.170"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="16">
               <head>Chapter XVI.
						<lb/> OF HEARING.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES says that hearing is formed by the insidency
						of the air upon the spiral, which it is said hangs within
						the ear as a bell, and is beat upon by the air. Alcmaeon,
						that the vacuity that is within the ear makes us to have
						the sense of hearing, for the air forcing a vacuum gives the
						sound; every inanity affords a ringing. Diogenes, the air
						which is in the head, being struck upon by the voice, gives
						the hearing. Plato and his followers, the air which exists
						in the head being struck upon, is reflected to the principal
						part of the soul, and this causeth the sense of hearing.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="17">
               <head>Chapter XVII.
						<lb/> OF SMELLING.</head>
               <p>ALCMAEON believes that the principal part of the soul,
						residing in the brain, draws to itself odors by respiration.
						Empedocles, that scents insert themselves into the breathing of the lungs; for, when there is a great difficulty in
						breathing, odors are not perceived by reason of the sharpness; and this we experience in those who have the defluxion of rheum.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="18">
               <head>Chapter XVIII.
						<lb/> OF TASTE.</head>
               <p>ALCMAEON says that a moist warmth in the tongue, joined
						with the softness of it, gives the difference of taste. Diogenes, that by the softness and sponginess of the tongue,
						and because the veins of the body are joined in it, tastes
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.171"/>
						
						are diffused by the tongue; for they are attracted from it
						to that sense and to the commanding part of the soul, as
						from a sponge.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="19">
               <head>Chapter XIX.
						<lb/> OF THE VOICE.</head>
               <p>PLATO thus defines a voice,&mdash;that it is a breath drawn
						by the mind through the mouth, and a blow given to the
						air and through the ear, brain, and blood transmitted to
						the soul. Voice is abusively attributed to irrational and
						inanimate beings; thus we improperly call the neighing
						of horses or any other sound by the name of voice. But
						properly a voice (<foreign lang="greek">fwnh/</foreign>) is an articulate sound, which
						illustrates (<foreign lang="greek">fwti/zei</foreign>) the understanding of man. Epicurus
						says that it is an efflux emitted from things that are
						vocal, or that give sounds or great noises; this is broken
						into those fragments which are after the same configuration. Like figures are round figures with round, and
						irregular and triangular with those of the same nature.
						These falling upon the ears produce the sense of hearing.
						This is seen in leaking vessels, and in fullers when they
						fan or blow their cloths.</p>
               <p>Democritus, that the air is broken into bodies of similar
						configuration, and these are rolled up and down with the
						fragments of the voice; as it is proverbially said, One
						daw lights with another, or, God always brings like to like.
						Thus we see upon the shore, that stones like to one another
						are found in the same place, in one place the long-shaped,
						in another the round are seen. So in sieves, things that are
						of the same form meet together, but those that are different are divided; as pulse and beans falling from the same
						sieve are separated one from another. To this it may be
						objected: How can some fragments of air fill a theatre in
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.172"/>
						
						which there is an infinite company of persons ? The Stoics,
						that the air is not composed of small fragments, but is a
						continued body and nowhere admits a vacuum; and being
						struck with the breath, it is infinitely moved in waves and
						in right circles, until it fill that air which invests it; as we
						see in a fish-pool which we smite by a falling stone cast
						upon it; yet the air is moved spherically, the water orbicularly. Anaxagoras says a voice is then formed, when upon
						a solid air the breath is incident, which being repercussed
						is carried to the ears; after the same manner the echo is
						produced.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="20">
               <head>Chapter XX.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE VOICE IS INCORPOREAL. WHAT IS IT THAT GIVES THE ECHO?</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS, Plato, and Aristotle say that the voice is
						incorporeal; for it is not the air that makes the voice, but
						the figure which compasseth the air and its superficies,
						having received a stroke, give the voice. But every superficies of itself is incorporeal. True it is that it moveth
						with the body, but of itself it hath no body; as we perceive in a staff that is bended, the matter only admits of
						an inflection, while the superficies doth not. According to
						the Stoics, a voice is corporeal, since every thing that is an
						agent or operates is a body; a voice acts and operates, for
						we hear it and are sensible of it; for it falls and makes an
						impression on the ear, as a seal of a ring gives its similitude upon the wax. Moreover, every thing that creates a
						delight or molestation is a body; harmonious music affects
						with delight, but discord is tiresome. And every thing that
						is moved is a body; and the voice moves, and having its
						illapse upon smooth places is reflected, as when a ball is
						cast against a wall it rebounds. A voice spoken in the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.173"/>
						
						Egyptian pyramids is so broken, that it gives four or five
						echoes.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="21">
               <head>Chapter XXI.
						<lb/> BY WHAT MEANS THE SOUL IS SENSIBLE, AND WHAT IS THE PRINCIPAL AND COMMANDING PART OF IT.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that the highest part of the soul is the
						commanding part of it: this is the cause of sense, imagination, consents, and desires; and this we call the rational
						part. From this principal and commander there are produced seven parts of the soul, which are spread through
						the body, as the seven arms in a polypus. Of these seven
						parts, five are assigned to the senses, seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, touching. Sight is a spirit which is extended
						from the commanding part to the eyes; hearing is that
						spirit which from the principal reacheth to the ears ; smelling a spirit drawn from the principal to the nostrils; tasting a spirit extended from the principal to the tongue;
						touching is a spirit which from the principal is drawn to
						the extremity of those bodies which are obnoxious to a
						sensible touch. Of the rest, the one called the spermatical is a spirit which reacheth from the principal to the
						generating vessels; the other, which is the vocal and termed
						the voice, is a spirit extended from the principal to the
						throat, tongue, and other proper organs of speaking. And
						this principal part itself hath that place in our spherical
						head which God hath in the world.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="22">
               <head>Chapter XXII.
						<lb/> OF RESPIRATION OR BREATHING.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES thinks, that the first breath the first animal
						drew was when the moisture in unborn infants was separated,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.174"/>
						
						 and by that means an entrance was given to the external air into the gaping vessels, the moisture in them
						being evacuated. After this the natural heat, in a violent
						force pressing upon the external air for a passage, begets
						an expiration; but this heat returning to the inward parts,
						and the air giving way to it, causeth an inspiration. The
						respiration that now is arises when the blood is carried to
						the exterior surface, and by this fluxion drives the airy substance through the nostrils; thus in its recess it causeth
						expiration, but the air being again forced into those places
						which are emptied of blood, it causeth an inspiration. To
						evince which, he proposeth the instance of a water-clock,
						which gives the account of time by the running of water.</p>
               <p>Asclepiades supposeth the lungs to be in the manner of
						a tunnel, and maketh the cause of breathing to be the
						fineness of the inward parts of the breast; for thither the
						outward air which is more gross hastens, but is forced backward, the breast not being capable either to receive or want
						it. But there being always some of the more tenuous parts
						of the air left, so that all of it is not exploded, to that
						which there remains the more ponderous external air with
						equal violence is forced; and this he compares to cupping-glasses. All spontaneous breathings are formed by the
						contracting of the smaller pores of the lungs, and to the
						closing up of the pipes in the neck; for these are at our
						command.</p>
               <p>Herophilus attributes a moving faculty to the nerves,
						arteries, and muscles, but believes that the lungs are affected only with a natural desire of enlarging and contracting themselves. Farther, there is the first operation of the
						lungs by attraction of the outward air, which is drawn in
						because of the abundance of the external air. Next to
						this, there is a second natural appetite of the lungs; the
						breast, pouring in upon itself the breath, and being filled, is
						no longer able to make an attraction, and throws the superfluity
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.175"/>
						
						 of it upon the lungs, whereby it is in turn sent
						forth by way of expiration; the parts of the body mutually
						concurring to this function by the alternate participation
						of fulness and emptiness. So that to lungs pertain four
						motions;&mdash;first, when the lungs receive the outward air;
						secondly, when the outward air thus entertained is transmitted to the breast; thirdly, when the lungs again receive
						that air which they imparted to the breast; fourthly, when
						this air then received from the breast is thrown outwards.
						Of these four motions two are dilatations, one when the
						lungs attract the external air, another when the breast dischargeth itself of it upon the lungs; two are contractions,
						one when the breast draws into itself the air, the second
						when it expels this which was insinuated into it. The
						breast admits only of two motions;&mdash;of dilatation, when
						it draws from the lungs the breath, and of contraction,
						when it returns what it did receive.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="23">
               <head>Chapter XXIII.
						<lb/> OF THE PASSIONS OF THE BODY, AND WHETHER THE SOUL HATH A SYMPATHETICAL CONDOLENCY WITH IT.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics say that all the passions are seated in those
						parts of the body which are affected, the senses have their
						residence in the commanding part of the soul. Epicurus,
						that all the passions and all the senses are in those parts
						which are affected, but the commanding part is subject to
						no passion. Strato, that all the passions and senses of the
						soul are in the rational or commanding part of it, and are
						not fixed in those places which are affected; for in this
						part patience takes its residence, and this is apparent in
						terrible and dolorous things, as also in timorous and valiant
						persons.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.3.p.176"/>
         <div1 type="book" n="5">
            <head>Book 5.</head>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter I.
						<lb/> OF DIVINATION.</head>
               <p>PLATO and the Stoics introduce divination as a divine
						enthusiasm, the soul itself being of a divine constitution, and this prophetic faculty being an inspiration, or
						an illapse of the divine knowledge into man; and sc
						likewise they explain interpretation by dreams. And these
						same admit many divisions of the art of divination. Xenophanes and Epicurus utterly refuse any such art of foretelling future contingencies. Pythagoras rejects all manner
						of divination which is by sacrifices. Aristotle and Dicaearchus admit only these two kinds of it, a fury by a divine
						inspiration, and dreams; they deny the immortality of the
						soul, yet they affirm that the mind of man hath a participation of something that is divine.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter II.
						<lb/> WHENCE DREAMS DO ARISE.</head>
               <p>DEMOCRITUS says that dreams are formed by the illapse
						of adventitious representations. Strato, that the irrational
						part of the soul in sleep becoming more sensible is moved
						by the rational part of it. Herophilus, that dreams which
						are caused by divine instinct have a necessary cause; but
						dreams which have their origin from a natural cause arise
						from the soul's forming within itself the images of those
						things which are convenient for it, and which will happen;
						those dreams which are of a constitution mixed of both
						these have their origin from the fortuitous appulse of
						images, as when we see those things which please us;
						thus it happens many times to those persons who in
						their sleep imagine they embrace their mistresses.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.177"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter III.
						<lb/> OF THE NATURE OF GENERATIVE SEED.</head>
               <p>ARISTOTLE says, that seed is that thing which contains in
						itself a power of moving, whereby it is enabled to produce
						a being like unto that from whence it was emitted. Pythagoras, that seed is the sediment of that which nourisheth
						us, the froth of the purest blood, of the same nature as
						the blood and marrow of our bodies. Alcmaeon, that it is
						a part of the brain. Plato, that it is the deflux of the
						spinal marrow. Epicurus, that it is a fragment torn from
						the body and soul. Democritus, that it proceeds from all
						the parts of the body, and chiefly from the principal parts.
						as the flesh and muscles.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter IV.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE SPERM BE A BODY.</head>
               <p>LEUCIPPUS and Zeno say, that it is a body and a fragment of the soul. Pythagoras, Plato, and Aristotle, that
						the spermatic faculty is incorporeal, as the mind is which
						moves the body; but the effused matter is corporeal. Strato
						and Democritus, that the very power is a body; for it is
						like spirit.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter V.
						<lb/> WHETHER WOMEN DO GIVE A SPERMATIC EMISSION AS MEN DO.</head>
               <p>PYTHAGORAS, Epicurus, and Democritus say, that women
						have a seminal projection, but their spermatic vessels are
						inverted; and it is this that makes them have a venereal
						appetite. Aristotle and Plato, that they emit a material
						moisture, as sweat we see produced by exercise and labor;
						but that moisture has no spermatic power. Hippo, that
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.178"/>
						
						women have a seminal emission, but not after the mode
						of men; it contributes nothing to generation, for it falls
						without the matrix; and therefore some women without
						coition, especially widows, give the seed. The same also
						asserts that from men the bones, from women the flesh
						proceeds.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter VI.
						<lb/> HOW IT IS THAT CONCEPTIONS ARE MADE.</head>
               <p>ARISTOTLE says, that conception takes place when the
						womb is drawn forward by the natural purgation, and
						the monthly terms attract from the whole bulk part of the
						purest blood, and this is met by the genital seed of man.
						On the contrary, there is a failure by the impurity and
						inflation of the womb, by the passions of fear and grief, by
						the weakness of women, or the decay of strength in men.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter VII.
						<lb/> AFTER WHAT MANNER MALES AND FEMALES ARE GENERATED</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES affirms, that heat and cold give the difference in the generation of males and females. Hence is
						it, as histories acquaint us, that the first men had their
						original from the earth in the eastern and southern parts,
						and the first females in the northern parts thereof. Parmenides is of opinion perfectly contrariant. He affirms
						that men first sprouted out of the northern earth, for their
						bodies are more dense; women out of the southern, for
						theirs are more rare and fine. Hippo, that the more compacted and strong sperm, and the more fluid and weak,
						discriminate the sexes. Anaxagoras and Parmenides, that
						the seed of the man is naturally cast from his right side
						into the right side of the womb, or from the left side of
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.179"/>
						
						the man into the left side of the womb; when there is an
						alteration in this course of nature, females are generated.
						Cleophanes, whom Aristotle makes mention of, assigns the
						generation of men to the right testicle, of women to the
						left. Leucippus gives the reason of it to the alteration or
						diversity of parts, according to which the man hath a yard,
						the female the matrix; as to any other reason he is silent.
						Democritus, that the parts which are common to both
						sexes are engendered indifferently by one or the other;
						but the peculiar parts by the one that is more prevalent.
						Hippo, that if the spermatic faculty be more effectual, the
						male, if the nutritive aliment, the female is generated.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter VIII.
						<lb/> BY WHAT MEANS IT IS THAT MONSTROUS BIRTHS ARE EFFECTED.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES believes that monsters receive their origination from the abundance or defect of seed, or from its
						division into parts which are superabundant, or from some
						perturbation in the motion, or else that there is an error by
						a lapse into an improper receptacle; and thus he presumes
						he hath given all the causes of monstrous conceptions.
						Strato, that it comes from addition, subtraction, or transposition of the seed, or the distension or inflation of the
						matrix. And some physicians say that the matrix suffers
						distortion, being distended with wind.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter IX.
						<lb/> HOW IT COMES TO PASS THAT A WOMAN'S TOO FREQUENT CONVERSATION WITH A MAN HINDERS CONCEPTION.</head>
               <p>DIOCLES the physician says that either no genital sperm
						is projected, or, if there be, it is in a less quantity than
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.180"/>
						
						nature requires, or there is no prolific faculty in it; or
						there is a deficiency of a due proportion of heat, cold,
						moisture, and dryness; or there is a resolution of the
						generative parts. The Stoics attribute sterility to the
						obliquity of the yard, by which means it is not able to
						ejaculate in a due manner, or to the unproportionable magnitude of the parts, the matrix being so contracted as not
						to be in a capacity to receive. Erasistratus assigns it to
						the womb's being more callous or more carneous, thinner
						or smaller, than nature does require.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter X.
						<lb/> WHENCE IT IS THAT ONE BIRTH GIVES TWO OR THREE CHILDREN.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES affirms, that the superabundance of sperm
						and the division of it causes the bringing forth of two or
						three infants. Asclepiades, that it is performed from the
						excellent quality of the sperm, after the manner that
						from the root of one barleycorn two or three stalks do
						grow; sperm that is of this quality is the most prolific.
						Erasistratus, that superfetation may happen to women as
						to irrational creatures; for, if the womb be well purged
						and very clean, then there may be divers births. The
						Stoics, that it ariseth from the various receptacles that are
						in the womb: when the seed illapses into the first and
						second of them at once, then there are conceptions upon
						conception; and so two or three infants are born.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter XI.
						<lb/> WHENCE IT IS THAT CHILDREN REPRESENT THEIR PARENTS AND PRO- GENITORS.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES says, that the similitude of children to their
						parents proceeds from the vigorous prevalency of the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.181"/>
						
						generating sperm; the dissimilitude from the evaporation
						of the natural heat contained in the same. Parmenides,
						that when the sperm descends from the right side of the
						womb, then the infant gives the resemblance of the father;
						if from the left, it is stamped with the similitude of the
						mother. The Stoics, that the whole body and soul give
						the sperm; and hence arise the resemblances in the
						characters and figures of the children, as a painter in his
						copy imitates the colors which are in the picture before
						him. Women have a concurrent emission of seed; if the
						feminine seed have the predominancy, then the child
						resembles the mother; if the masculine, the father.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter XII.
						<lb/> HOW IT COMES TO PASS THAT CHILDREN HAVE A GREATER SIMILITUDE WITH STRANGERS THAN WITH THEIR PARENTS.</head>
               <p>THE greatest part of physicians affirm, that this happens casually and fortuitously; for, when the sperm of the
						man and woman is too much refrigerated, then children
						carry a dissimilitude to their parents. Empedocles, that a
						woman's imagination when she conceives impresses a shape
						upon the infant; for women have been enamored with
						images and statues, and the children which were born of
						them gave their similitudes. The Stoics, that the resemblances flow from the sympathy and consent of minds, by
						the insertion of effluvias and rays, not of images or pictures.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="13">
               <head>Chapter XIII.
						<lb/> WHENCE ARISETH BARRENNESS IN WOMEN, AND IMPOTENCY IN MEN?</head>
               <p>THE physicians maintain, that sterility in women may
						arise from the womb; for if it be after any ways thus
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.182"/>
						
						affected, there will be barrenness,&mdash;if it be more condensed, or more spongy, or more hardened, or more
						callous, or more carneous; or it may be from low spirits,
						or from an atrophy or vicious distemper of body; or, lastly,
						it may arise from a twisted or distorted configuration.
						Diocles holds that the sterility in men ariseth from some
						of these causes,&mdash;either that they cannot at all ejaculate
						any sperm, or if they do, it is less than nature doth require,
						or else there is no generative faculty in the sperm, or the
						genital members are flagging; or from the obliquity of
						the yard. The Stoics attribute the cause of sterility to the
						contrariant qualities and dispositions of those who lie with
						one another; but if it chance that these persons are
						separated, and there happen a conjunction of those who
						are of a suitable temperament, then there is a commixture
						according to nature, and by this means an infant is formed.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="14">
               <head>Chapter XIV.
						<lb/> HOW IT COMES TO PASS THAT MULES ARE BARREN.</head>
               <p>ALCMAEON says, that the barrenness of the male mules
						ariseth from the thinness of the genital sperm, that is, the
						seed is too chill; the female mules are barren, for their
						womb does not open its mouth (as he expresses it). Empedocles, the matrix of the mule is so small, so depressed, so narrow, so invertedly growing to the belly,
						that the sperm cannot be regularly cast into it, and if it
						could, there would be no capacity to receive it. Diocles
						concurs in this opinion with him; for, saith he, in our
						anatomical dissection of mules we have seen that their
						matrices are of such configurations; and it is possible that
						there may be the same reason why some women are barren.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.183"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="15">
               <head>Chapter XV.
						<lb/> WHETHER THE INFANT IN THE MOTHER'S WOMB BE AN ANIMAL.</head>
               <p>PLATO says, that the embryo is an animal; for, being
						contained in the mother's womb, motion and aliment are
						imparted to it. The Stoics say that it is not an animal,
						but to be accounted part of the mother's belly; like as we
						see the fruit of trees is esteemed part of the trees, until it
						be full ripe; then it falls and ceaseth to belong to the tree;
						and thus it is with the embryo. Empedocles, that the embryo is not an animal, yet whilst it remains in the belly it
						breathes. The first breath that it draws as an animal is
						when the infant is newly born; then the child having its
						moisture separated, the extraneous air making an entrance
						into the empty places, a respiration is caused in the infant
						by the empty vessels receiving of it. Diogenes, that infants
						are bred in the matrix inanimate, yet they have a natural
						heat; but presently, when the infant is cast into the open
						air, its heat draws air into the lungs, and so it becomes an
						animal. Herophilus acknowledgeth that infants have a
						natural, but not a respiratory motion, and that the nerves
						are the cause of that motion; that then they become
						animals, when being first born they suck in something of
						the air.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="16">
               <head>Chapter XVI.
						<lb/> HOW EMBRYOS ARE NOURISHED, OR HOW THE INFANT IN THE BELLY RECEIVES ITS ALIMENT.</head>
               <p>DEMOCRITUS and Epicurus say, that the embryos in the
						womb receive their aliment by the mouth, for we perceive,
						as soon as ever the infant is born, it applies its mouth to
						the breast; in the wombs of women (our understanding
						concludes) there are little dugs, and the embryos have
						small mouths by which they receive their nutriment. The
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.184"/>
						
						Stoics, that by the secundines and navel they partake of
						aliment, and therefore the midwife instantly after their
						birth binds the navel, and opens the infant's mouth, that it
						may receive another sort of aliment. Alcmaeon, that they
						receive their nourishment from every part of the body; as
						a sponge sucks in water.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="17">
               <head>Chapter XVII.
						<lb/> WHAT PART OF THE BODY IS FIRST FORMED IN THE WOMB.</head>
               <p>THE Stoics believe that the greater part is formed at
						the same time. Aristotle, as the keel of a ship is first
						made, so the first part that is formed is the loins. Alcmaeon, the head, for that is the commanding and the principal part of the body. The physicians, the heart, in
						which are the veins and arteries. Some think the great
						toe is first formed; others affirm the navel.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="18">
               <head>Chapter XVIII.
						<lb/> WHENCE IS IT THAT INFANTS BORN IN THE SEVENTH MONTH ARE BORN ALIVE.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES says, that when the human race took first
						its original from the earth, the sun was so slow in its
						motion that then one day in its length was equal to ten
						months, as now they are; in process of time one day
						became as long as seven months are; and there is the
						reason that those infants which are born at the end of
						seven months or ten months are born alive, the course
						of nature so disposing that the infant shall be brought to
						maturity in one day after that night in which it is begotten.
						Timaeus says, that we count not ten months but nine, by
						reason that we reckon the first conception from the retention
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.185"/>
						
						 of the menstruas; and so it may generally pass for
						seven months when really there are not seven; for it sometimes happens that even after conception a woman is
						purged in some degree. Polybus, Diocles, and the Empirics acknowledge that the eighth month gives a vital birth to
						the infant, though the life of it is more faint and languid;
						many therefore we see born in that month die out of
						mere weakness. Though we see many born in that month
						arrive at the state of man, yet (they affirm) if children be
						born in that month, none are willing to rear them.</p>
               <p>Aristotle and Hippocrates, that if the womb is grown
						full in seven months, then the child falls from the mother
						and is born alive; but if it falls from her but is not
						properly nourished, the navel being weak on account of
						the heavy burden of the infant, then it doth not thrive;
						but if the infant continues nine months in the womb, and
						then breaks forth from the woman, it is entire and perfect.
						Polybus, that a hundred and eighty-two days and a half
						suffice for the bringing forth of a living child; that is,
						six months, in which space of time the sun moves from
						one tropic to the other; and this is called seven months,
						for the days which are overplus in the sixth are accounted
						to give the seventh month. Those children which are
						born in the eighth month cannot live, for, the infant then
						falling from the womb, the navel, which is the cause of
						nourishment, is thereby too much stretched; and is the
						reason that the infant languishes and hath an atrophy.
						The astrologers, that eight months are enemies to every
						birth, seven are friends and kind to it. The signs of the
						zodiac are then enemies, when they fall upon those stars
						which are lords of houses; whatever infant is then born
						will have a life short and unfortunate. Those signs of
						the zodiac which are malevolent and injurious to generation are those pairs of which the last is reckoned the
						eighth from the first, as the first and the eighth, the second
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.186"/>
						
						and the ninth, &amp;c.; so is the Ram unsociable with Scorpio,
						the Bull with Sagittarius, the Twins with the Goat, the
						Crab with Aquarius, the Lion with Pisces, the Virgin with
						the Ram. Upon this reason those infants that are born in
						the seventh or tenth months are like to live, but those
						in the eighth month will die.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="19">
               <head>Chapter XIX.
						<lb/> OF THE GENERATION OF ANIMALS, HOW ANIMALS ARE BEGOTTEN, AND WHETHER THEY ARE OBNOXIOUS TO CORRUPTION.</head>
               <p>THOSE philosophers who entertain the opinion that the
						world had an original do likewise assert that all animals
						are generated and corruptible. The followers of Epicurus,
						who gives an eternity to the world, affirm the generation
						of animals ariseth from the various permutation of parts
						mutually among themselves, for they are parts of this
						world. With them Anaxagoras and Euripides concur:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>For nothing dies,
						</l>
                        <l>But different changes give their various forms.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Anaximander's opinion is, that the first animals were generated in moisture, and were enclosed in bark on which
						thorns grew; but in process of time they came upon dry
						land, and this thorny bark with which they were covered
						being broken, they lived for a short space of time. Empedocles says, that the first generation of animals and
						plants was by no means completed, for the parts were
						disjoined and would not admit of a union; the second
						preparation for their being generated was when their parts
						were united and appeared in the form of images; the
						third preparation for generation was when their parts mutually amongst themselves gave a being to one another;
						the fourth, when there was no longer a mixture of similar
						elements (like earth and water), but a union of animals
						among themselves,&mdash;in some the nourishment being made
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.187"/>
						
						dense, in others female beauty provoking a lust of spermatic motion. All sorts of animals are discriminated by
						their proper temperament and constitution; some are carried by a proper appetite and inclination to water; some,
						which partake of a more fiery quality, to breathe in the
						air; those that are heavier incline to the earth; but those
						animals whose parts are of a just and equal temperament
						are fitted equally for all places.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="20">
               <head>Chapter XX.
						<lb/> HOW MANY SPECIES OF ANIMALS THERE ARE, AND WHETHER ALL ANIMALS HAVE THE ENDOWMENTS OF SENSE AND REASON.</head>
               <p>THERE is a certain treatise of Aristotle, in which animals
						are distributed into four kinds, terrestrial, aqueous, fowl,
						and heavenly; and he calls the stars and the world also
						animals, yea, and God himself he defines to be an animal
						endowed with reason and immortal. Democritus and Epicurus esteem all animals rational which have their residence in the heavens. Anaxagoras says that animals have
						only that reason which is operative, but not that which is
						passive, which is justly styled the interpreter of the mind,
						and is like the mind itself. Pythagoras and Plato, that the
						souls of all those who are styled brutes are rational; but
						by the evil constitution of their bodies, and because they
						have a want of a discoursive faculty, they do not act rationally. This is manifested in apes and dogs, which have
						voice but not speech. Diogenes, that this sort of animals
						are partakers of intelligence and air, but by reason of the
						density in some parts of them, and by the superfluity of
						moisture in others, they enjoy neither understanding nor
						sense; but they are affected as madmen are, the commanding rational part being defectuous and impeached.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.188"/>
						
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="21">
               <head>Chapter XXI.
						<lb/> WHAT TIME IS REQUIRED TO SHAPE THE PARTS OF ANIMALS IN THE WOMB.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES believes, that the joints of men begin to be
						formed from the thirty-sixth day, and their shape is
						completed in the nine and fortieth. Asclepiades, that
						male embryos, by reason of a greater natural heat, have
						their joints begun to be formed in the twenty-sixth day,&mdash;
						many even sooner,&mdash;and that they are completed in all
						their parts on the fiftieth day; the parts of the females
						are articulated in two months, but by the defect of heat are
						not consummated till the fourth; but the members of
						brutes are completed at various times, according to the
						commixture of the elements of which they consist.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="22">
               <head>Chapter XXII.
						<lb/> OF WHAT ELEMENTS EACH OF THE MEMBERS OF US MEN IS COMPOSED.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES says, that the fleshy parts of us are constituted by the contemperation of the four elements in us;
						earth and fire mixed with a double proportion of water make
						the nerves; but when it happens that the nerves are refrigerated where they meet the air, then the nails are made;
						the bones are produced by two parts of water and the same
						of air, with four parts of fire and the same of earth, duly
						mixed together; sweat and tears flow from the liquefaction
						of these bodies of ours.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="23">
               <head>Chapter XXIII.
						<lb/> WHAT ARE THE CAUSES OF SLEEP AND DEATH?</head>
               <p>ALCMAEON says, that sleep is caused when the blood retreats to the concourse of the veins, but when the blood
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.189"/>
						
						diffuses itself, then we awake; and when there is a total
						retirement of the blood, then men die. Empedocles, that
						a moderate cooling of the blood causeth sleep, but a total
						remotion of heat from blood causeth death. Diogenes, that
						when all the blood is so diffused as that it fills all the veins,
						and forces the air contained in them to the back and to the
						belly that is below it, the breast being thereby more heated,
						thence sleep arises; but if every thing that is airy in the
						breast forsakes the veins, then death succeeds. Plato and
						the Stoics, that sleep ariseth from the relaxation of the
						sensitive spirit, it not receiving such total remission as if
						it fell to the earth, but so that that spirit is carried
						about the intestine parts of the eyebrows, in which the
						principal part has its residence; but when there is a total
						remission of the sensitive spirit, then death ensues.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="24">
               <head>Chapter XXIV.
						<lb/> WHEN AND FROM WHENCE THE PERFECTION OF A MAN COMMENCES.</head>
               <p>HERACLITUS and the Stoics say, that men begin their
						completeness when the second septenary of years begins,
						about which time the seminal serum is emitted. Trees
						first begin their perfection when they give their seeds; till
						then they are immature, imperfect, and unfruitful. After
						the same manner a man is completed in the second septenary of years, and is capable of learning what is good and
						evil, and of discipline therein.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="25">
               <head>Chapter XXV.
						<lb/> WHETHER SLEEP OR DEATH APPERTAINS TO THE SOUL OR BODY.</head>
               <p>ARISTOTLE'S opinion is, that both the soul and body sleep;
						and this proceeds from the moisture in the breast, which
						doth steam and arise in the manner of a vapor into the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.190"/>
						
						head, and from the aliment in the stomach, whose natural
						heat is cooled in the heart. Death is the perfect refrigeration of all heat in the body; but death is only of the body,
						and not of the soul, for the soul is immortal. Anaxagoras
						thinks, that sleep makes the operations of the body to
						cease; it is a corporeal passion and affects not the soul.
						Death is the separation of the soul from the body. Leucippus, that sleep is only of the body; but when the
						smaller particles cause immoderate evaporation from the
						soul's heat, this makes death; but these affections of death
						and sleep are of the body, not of the soul. Empedocles,
						that death is nothing else but separation of those fiery parts
						by which man is composed, and according to this sentiment
						both body and soul die; but sleep is only a smaller separation of the fiery qualities.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="26">
               <head>Chapter XXVI.
						<lb/> HOW PLANTS GROW, AND WHETHER THEY ARE ANIMALS.</head>
               <p>PLATO and Empedocles believe, that plants are animals,
						and are informed with a soul; of this there are clear arguments, for they have tossing and shaking, and their
						branches are extended; when the woodmen bend them
						they yield, but they return to their former straightness and
						strength again when they are let loose, and even draw up
						weights that are laid upon them. Aristotle doth grant that
						they live, but not that they are animals; for animals are
						affected with appetite, sense, and reason. The Stoics and
						Epicureans deny that they are informed with a soul; by
						reason that all sorts of animals have either sense, appetite,
						or reason; but plants move fortuitously, and not by means
						of any soul. Empedocles, that the first of all animals
						were trees, and they sprang from the earth before the sun
						in its glory enriched the world, and before day and night
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.191"/>
						
						were distinguished; but by the harmony which is in their
						constitution they partake of a masculine and feminine
						nature; and they increase by that heat which is exalted out
						of the earth, so that they are parts belonging to it, as
						embryos in the womb are parts of the womb. Fruits in
						plants are excrescences proceeding from water and fire;
						but the plants which have a deficiency of water, when this
						is dried up by the heat of summer, lose their leaves; whereas
						they that have plenty thereof keep their leaves on still, as
						the olive, laurel, and palm. The differences of their moisture and juice arise from the difference of particles and
						various other causes, and they are discriminated by the various particles that feed them. And this is apparent in
						vines; for the excellence of wine flows not from the difference in the vines, but from the soil from whence they receive their nutriment.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="27">
               <head>Chapter XXVII.
						<lb/> OF NOURISHMENT AND GROWTH.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES believes, that animals are nourished by the
						remaining in them of that which is proper to their own
						nature; they are augmented by the application of heat; and
						the subtraction of either of these makes them to languish
						and decay. The stature of men in this present age, if compared with the magnitude of those men which were first
						produced, is no other than a mere infancy.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="28">
               <head>Chapter XXVIII.
						<lb/> WHENCE IT IS THAT IN ANIMALS THERE ARE APPETITES AND PLEASURES.</head>
               <p>EMPEDOCLES says that the want of those elements which
						compose animals gives to them appetite, and pleasures
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.192"/>
						
						spring from humidity. As to the motions of dangers and
						such like things, as perturbations, &amp;c....
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="29">
               <head>Chapter XXIX.
						<lb/> WHAT IS THE CAUSE OF A FEVER, OR WHETHER IT IS AN AFFECTION OF THE BODY ANNEXED TO A PRIMARY PASSION.</head>
               <p>ERASISTRATUS gives this definition of a fever: A fever
						is a quick motion of blood, not produced by our consent,
						which enters into the vessels proper unto the vital spirits.
						This we see in the sea; it is in a serene calm when nothing disturbs it, but is in motion when a violent preternatural wind blows upon it, and then it rageth and is circled
						with waves. After this manner it is in the body of man;
						when the blood is in a nimble agitation, then it falls upon
						those vessels in which the spirits are, and there being in
						an extraordinary heat, it fires the whole body. The opinion that a fever is an appendix to a preceding affection
						pleaseth him. Diodes proceeds after this manner: Those
						things which are internal and latent are manifested by
						those which externally break forth and appear; and it is
						clear to us that a fever is annexed to certain outward
						affections, for example, to wounds, inflaming tumors, inguinary abscesses.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="30">
               <head>Chapter XXX.
						<lb/> OF HEALTH, SICKNESS, AND OLD AGE.</head>
               <p>ALCMAEON says that the preserver of health is an equal
						proportion of the qualities of heat, moisture, cold, dryness,
						bitterness, sweetness, and the other qualities; on the contrary, the prevailing empire of one above the rest is the
						cause of diseases and author of destruction. The efficient
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.193"/>
						
						cause of disease is the excess of heat or cold, the material
						cause is superabundance or defect, the place is the blood
						or brain. But health is the harmonious commixture of the
						elements. Diodes, that sickness for the most part proceeds from the irregular disposition of the elements in the
						body, for that makes an ill habit or constitution of it.
						Erasistratus, that sickness is caused by the excess of food,
						indigestion, and corruptions; on the contrary, health is the
						moderation of the diet, and the taking that which is convenient and sufficient for us. It is the unanimous opinion
						of the Stoics that the want of heat brings old age, for (they
						say) those persons in whom heat more abounds live the
						longer. Asclepiades, that the Ethiopians soon grow old,
						and at thirty years of age are ancient men, their bodies
						being excessively heated and scorched by the sun; in
						Britain persons live a hundred and twenty years, on account
						of the coldness of the country, and because the people
						contain the fiery element within their bodies; for the bodies
						of the Ethiopians are more fine and thin, because they are
						relaxed by the sun's heat, while they who live in northern
						countries have a contrary state of their bodies, for they are
						condensed and robust, and by consequence live the longer.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>