<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quaestiones Graecae</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.4.p.174"/>
            <head>THE GREEK QUESTIONS
					(QUAESTIONES GRAECAE)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>In the <hi rend="italics">Greek Questions</hi>, as in the <hi rend="italics">Roman Questions</hi>,
					Plutarch endeavours to give the reason or explanation
					of fifty-nine matters concerned with Greek life. The
					vast majority of them are customs or names and, as
					the explanations are usually historical, they often go
					back to very early times. A full commentary may
					be found in W. R. Halliday, <hi rend="italics">The Greek Questions of
					Plutarch</hi> (Oxford, 1928), an excellent work, embodying
					also much of the modern speculation in regard to
					primitive religion.
				</p>
            <p>The sources for the information contained in this
					essay seem to be somewhat varied, but there is little
					doubt that Aristotle's account of the numerous <hi rend="italics">Greek
					Constitutions</hi> was Plutarch's principal source. The
					matter is treated at length by Halliday.
				</p>
            <p>J. J. Hartman (<hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi>, xii. p. 216, or <hi rend="italics">De
					Plutarcho scriptore et philosophos</hi> p. 139) is the only
					modern scholar who has doubted the authenticity of
					the attribution to Plutarch of this work<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">
                     <foreign lang="la">Sed praeterea totus liber mera est doctrinae ostentatio, . . . Chaeronensi metium medico prorsus indigna</foreign>.</q>
               </note>; the author
					was not primarily interested in ethical matters,
					according to Hartman, and hence cannot be Plutarch.
					J. B. Titchener<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">The ms. Tradition of Plutarch's Aetia Graeca and Aetia Romana</hi> (Urbana, Illinois, 1924), p. 9.</note> has promised a discussion of this
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.175"/>
					
					matter, but stylistic considerations alone seem to
					make it uncertain whether the work is correctly
					attributed to Plutarch.
				</p>
            <p>A few of the topics treated in the <hi rend="italics">Greek Questions</hi>
					appear also in other works of Plutarch, but the
					number naturally is not large.
				</p>
            <p>The ms. tradition is good; the few difficulties
					found are generally with single words.
				</p>
            <p>The work is No. 166 in Lamprias's list of Plutarch's
					works, where the title is given as <foreign lang="greek">*ai)ti/ai *(ellh/nwn</foreign>.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.4.p.177"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Who were the <q direct="unspecified">dusty-feet</q> and the <q direct="unspecified">directors</q>
					in Epidaurus?
				</p>
            <p>There were one hundred and eighty men who
					directed the State. From these they used to elect
					councillors whom they called <q direct="unspecified">directors.</q> But the
					majority of the populace spent their life in the coun
					try. They were called <q direct="unspecified">dusty-feet</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This was the serf-class liberated by the tyrants: <hi rend="italics">cf. Cambridge Ancient History</hi>, vol. iii. p. 554.</note> since, as one
					may conjecture, they were recognized by their dust-covered feet whenever they carne down to the city.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Who was the <q direct="unspecified">woman that rode on a donkey</q>
					at Cumae?
				</p>
            <p>Any woman taken in adultery they used to bring
					into the market-place and set her on a certam stone
					in plain sight of everyone. In like manner they then
					proceeded to mount her upon a donkey , and when she
					had been led about the circuit of the entire city, she
					was required again to take her stand upon the same
					stone, and for the rest of her life to continue in disgrace, bearing the name <q direct="unspecified">donkey-rider.</q> After this
					ceremony they believed that the stone was unclean
					and they used ritually to purify it.
				</p>
            <p>The citizens of Cumae had also a certain office
					called the Guards. The man who held this office
					used to watch the prison most of the time, but he
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.179"/>
					
					came to the nocturnal assemblies of the council and
					led out the kings by the hand and kept them out,
					until by secret ballot the council had decided on
					their case, whether they had done wrong or no.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Who is She that Kindles the Fire (hypekkaustria)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">W. R. Halliday, in <hi rend="italics">Harvard Studies in Classical Philology</hi>, xxxvi. 165-177, suggests that <q direct="unspecified">cohen</q> (= priest) may be contained in this word.</note> among the people of Soli?
				</p>
            <p>This is the name which they give to the priestess of
					Athena because she performs certain sacrifices and
					ceremonies to avert evil.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Who were the Forgetful Ones (<hi rend="italics">Amnemones</hi>) at
					Cnidus, and who was the Dismisser<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Grote thus connected <hi rend="italics">aphester</hi> with the Spartan <hi rend="italics">apostater</hi> of <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. vi. (43 c); but the matter is very doubtful; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> van Herwerden, <hi rend="italics">Lex. Supp. Graec.</hi>
               </note> (<hi rend="italics">Aphester</hi>)?
				</p>
            <p>They were wont to employ sixty men chosen from
					the nobles, and appointed for life, as overseers and
					preliminary advisers in matters of the greatest importance. They were called the Forgetful Ones, one
					might conjecture, because they could not be held to
					account for their actions ; unless, indeed, it was because they were men who remembered many things.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the <hi rend="italics">lucus a non lucendo</hi> principle, as Halliday well suggests; or else <foreign lang="greek">a)m</foreign>-<foreign lang="greek">mnh/mones</foreign>, as van Herwerden supposes.</note>
					He who asked them their opinions was the Dismisser.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Who are the <q direct="unspecified">good</q> among the Arcadians and
					the Spartans?
				</p>
            <p>When the Spartans had come to terms with the
					Tegeans, they made a treaty and set up in common
					a pillar by the Alpheius. On this, among other
					matters, was inscribed : <q direct="unspecified">The Messenians must be
						expelled from the country ; it shall not be lawful to
						make men good.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 
                  <foreign lang="greek">xrhote\ xai=re</foreign> on Greek tombstones.</note> Aristotle,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 592 (V. Rose); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 277 b-c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> then, in explaining
					this, states that it means that no one shall be put
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.181"/>
					
					to death because of assistance given to the Spartan
					party in Tegea.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Who is <q direct="unspecified">he that selects barley</q> (<hi rend="italics">krithologos</hi>)
					among the Opuntians?
				</p>
            <p>For sacrifices of very ancient origin most of the
					Greeks used to employ barley, which the citizens
					offered as first-fruits of the harvest. Accordingly
					they called the officer who presided at the sacrifices
					and brought these first-fruits the Barley-selector.
					They had two priests : one appointed for sacrifices to
					the gods, the other for sacrifices to the spirits.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>What were the <q direct="unspecified">floating clouds</q>?
				</p>
            <p>They used to call clouds <q direct="unspecified">floating</q> which particularly threatened rain and were in constant motion, as
					Theophrastus has stated in the fourth book of his
					<hi rend="italics">Meteorology</hi>. The passage reads thus : <q direct="unspecified">Since also
						these floating clouds and these compact clouds, which
						are immovable and very white in colour, exhibit a
						certain difference of substance which is filled neither
						with water nor with wind.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Who is the <q direct="unspecified">near-dweller</q> (<hi rend="italics">platioiketas</hi>) among
					the Boeotians?
				</p>
            <p>This is the name they give in the Aeolian dialect
					to persons who dwell in the next house or occupy
					adjoining property, signifying that they hold land
					near at hand. I shall add one phrase from the Edict
					of the Guardians of the Law, although there are
					several more . . .<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The copyist seems to have omitted the quotation.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Who is the Consecrator (<hi rend="italics">hosioter</hi>) among the
					Delphians and why do they call one of the months
					<q direct="unspecified">Bysios</q>?
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.183"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>They call the victim that is sacrificed Consecrator
					whenever an Holy One<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 365 a, 437 a.</note> is appointed. There are five
					Holy Ones, who hold office for life ; they do a great
					many things with the co-operation of the oracle-interpreters and with them take part in the holy
					rites, since they are thought to have descended from
					Deucalion.
				</p>
            <p>The month <q direct="unspecified">Bysios,</q> as many think, is the month of
					growth (<hi rend="italics">physios</hi>) ; for it begins the spring and during
					it many plants spring up and come into bloom. But
					this is not the truth of the matter, for Delphians do
					not use <hi rend="italics">b</hi> in place of <hi rend="italics">ph</hi> (as Macedonians do who say
					<q direct="unspecified">Bilip</q> and <q direct="unspecified">balacros</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Beronic&ecirc;</q>), but in
					place of <hi rend="italics">p</hi>; thus they naturally say <q direct="unspecified">broceed</q> for
					<q direct="unspecified">proceed</q> and <q direct="unspecified">bainful</q> for <q direct="unspecified">painful.</q> Accordingly <q direct="unspecified">Bysios</q> is <q direct="unspecified">pysios,</q> the month of oracular
					inquiry, in which men ask questions and obtain responses from the god ; for this is the legitimate and
					traditional procedure. In this month, then, oracles
					used to be given and the seventh day of this month
					they consider the birthday of the god.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 717 d; for the connexion of the number seven with the birth of Apollo see Callimachus, <hi rend="italics">Hymn</hi> iv. 251 ff.</note> They call
					this day the day of Many Utterances (<hi rend="italics">Polyphtho&ouml;s</hi>)
					not because they then bake cakes (<hi rend="italics">phtho&iuml;s</hi>),<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, 647 d, 502 b.</note> but
					because it is a day when many inquire of the god
					and receive many oracles. For only recently have
					monthly oracles been given out to inquirers ; formerly
					the prophetic priestess was wont to give responses
					but once a year on this day, as Callisthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der griech. Hist.</hi> 124 f 49.</note> and
					Anaxandrides have recorded.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>What is the <q direct="unspecified">sheep-escaper</q>?
				</p>
            <p>It is one of the small plants that grow close to the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.185"/>
					
					ground, whose shoots the grazing animals attack,
					cutting off the tops and injuring them and so spoiling
					the growth. But when these plants grow up and
					gain some size and escape injury from the flocks
					which graze upon them, then they are called <q direct="unspecified">sheep-escapers.</q> The evidence for this is Aeschylus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 123, Aeschylus, Frag. 447.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Who are the <q direct="unspecified">Men repulsed by slings</q>?
				</p>
            <p>Men from Eretria used to inhabit the island of
					Corcyra. But Charicrates sailed thither from Corinth
					with an army and defeated them in war; so the
					Eretrians embarked in their ships and sailed back
					home. Their fellow-citizens, however, having learned
					of the matter before their arrival, barred their return
					to the country and prevented them from disembarking by showering upon them missiles from slings.
					Since the exiles were unable either to persuade or to
					overcome their fellow-citizens, who were numerous
					and inexorable, they sailed to Thrace and occupied
					a territory in which, according to tradition, Methon,
					the ancestor of Orpheus, had formerly lived. So the
					Eretrians named their city Methon&ecirc;, but they were
					also named by their neighbours the <q direct="unspecified">Men repulsed
						by slings.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Who was <q direct="unspecified">Charilla</q> among the Delphians?
				</p>
            <p>The Delphians celebrate three festivals one after
					the other which occur every eight<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 421 c.</note> years, the first of
					which they call Septerion, the second Hero&iuml;s, and the
					third Charilla.
				</p>
            <p>Now the Septerion seems to be a representation of
					Apollo's fight with the Python and the flight to Temp&ecirc;
					and pursuit that followed the battle.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 421 c.</note> Some indeed
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.187"/>
					
					affirm that Apollo fled because he desired purification as a consequence of the slaughter he had done,
					others that he was following the wounded Python
					as he fled along the road which we now call the Sacred
					Way, and was only a little late for the monster's
					death ; for he overtook him when he had just died
					from the effects of the wound and had been buried
					by his son, whose name, as they say, was Aix. The
					Septerion, then, is a representation of these matters
					or certain matters of a similar nature.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 418 a-b; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 1, for this festival.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>The greater part of the Hero&iuml;s has a secret import which the Thyiads<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 249 e-f.</note> know ; but from the portions
					of the rites that are performed in public one might
					conjecture that it represents the evocation of Semele.
				</p>
            <p>The story of Charilla which they relate is somewhat
					as follows : A famine following a drought oppressed
					the Delphians, and they came to the palace of their
					king with their wives and children and made supplication. The king gave portions of barley and
					legumes to the more notable citizens, for there was
					not enough for all. But when an orphaned girl, who
					was still but a small child, approached him and importuned him, he struck her with his sandal and cast
					the sandal in her face. But, although the girl was
					poverty-stricken and without protectors, she was not
					ignoble in character ; and when she had withdrawn,
					she took off her girdle and hanged herself. As
					the famine increased and diseases also were added
					thereto, the prophetic priestess gave an oracle to the
					king that he must appease Charilla, the maiden
					who had slain herself. Accordingly, when they had
					discovered with some difficulty that this was the name
					of the child who had been struck, they performed
					a certain sacrificial rite combined with purification,
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.189"/>
					
					which even now they continue to perform every
					eight years. For the king sits in state and gives a
					portion of barley-meal and legumes to everyone,
					alien and citizen alike, and a doll-like image of
					Charilla is brought thither. When, accordingly, all
					have received a portion, the king strikes the image
					with his sandal. The leader of the Thyiads picks up
					the image and bears it to a certain place which is full
					of chasms ; there they tie a rope round the neck of
					the image and bury it in the place where they buried
					Charilla after she had hanged herself.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>What is the <q direct="unspecified">beggar's meat</q> among the
					Aenianians?
				</p>
            <p>There have been several migrations of the Aenianians. For first, when they inhabited the region
					about the Dotian plain, they were expelled by the
					Lapiths to Aethicia.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 297 b-c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> From there they proceeded
					to take possession of the region of Molossia about
					the river Auas, from which they received the name
					Parauaei. After this they took possession of Cirrha.
					There, when they had stoned to death Oenoclus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 297 b-c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					their king, at the command of the god, they descended to the country about the Inachus, which was
					inhabited by Inachians and Achaeans. Since an
					oracle had declared that if the Inachians gave away
					any part of their country, they should lose it all, and
					that if the Aenianians received any part of the land
					from willing givers, they should gain possession of it,
					Temon, a notable man among the Aenianians, donned
					rags and wallet and came to the Inachians in the
					guise of a beggar. In scorn and mockery their king
					gave him a clod of earth, which Temon accepted,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.191"/>
					
					placed within his wallet, and was evidently satisfied with the gift; for he straightway withdrew
					without asking for anything more. The Inachian
					elders were astonished, but, recalling the oracle,
					they went to the king and told him not to make light
					of the fellow nor to let him get away. Temon, then,
					perceiving their intent, hastened his flight and made
					his escape after vowing a hecatomb to Apollo.
				</p>
            <p>After this affair the two kings engaged in single
					combat, and Phemius, king of the Aenianians, observing the Inachian king, Hyperochus, advancing
					to meet him accompanied by a dog, said that Hyperochus was acting unfairly in bringing on a second
					combatant. But while Hyperochus was driving
					off the dog and had his back turned, Phemius hit
					him with a stone and killed him. The Aenianians
					gained possession of the country, driving out the
					Inachians together with the Achaeans, and they
					revere that stone as sacred, and sacrifice to it and
					cover it round about with the fat of the sacrificial
					victim ; and whenever they pay the hecatomb to
					Apollo, they sacrifice a bull to Zeus ; and they set
					aside a select portion of the flesh for the descendants
					of Temon, and this they call the <q direct="unspecified">beggar's meat.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Who are the <q direct="unspecified">Coliadae</q> among the inhabitants of Ithaca and what is the <hi rend="italics">phagilos</hi>?
				</p>
            <p>After the slaughter of the suitors the relatives
					of the dead men rose up against Odysseus; but
					Neoptolemus was sent for by both parties to act as
					arbiter.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Epitome</hi>, vii. 40.</note> He adjudged that Odysseus should depart
					from the country and be exiled for homicide from
					Cephallenia, Zacynthus, and Ithaca ; and that the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.193"/>
					
					companions and the relatives of the suitors should
					recompense Odysseus each year for the injuries
					which they had done to his estate. Odysseus accordingly departed to Italy ; but the recompense he
					formally transferred to his son, and ordered the inhabitants of Ithaca to pay it to him. The recompense consisted of barley, wine, honeycombs,
					olive-oil, salt, and beasts for sacrifice that were older
					than <hi rend="italics">phagiloi</hi>; according to Aristotle's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 507 (ed. V. Rose).</note> statement,
					a lamb is a <hi rend="italics">phagilos</hi>. Now Telemachus bestowed
					freedom upon Eumaeus and his associates, and incorporated them among the citizens ; and the clan
					of the Coliadae is descended from Eumaeus, and that
					of the Bucolidae from Philoetius.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eumaeus was the swineherd and Philoetius the cowherd of Odysseus.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>What is <q direct="unspecified">the wooden dog</q> among the Locrians?
				</p>
            <p>Locrus was the son of Physcius, the son of Amphictyon. The son of Locrus and Caby&ecirc; was
					Opus. His father quarrelled with Opus and taking
					many of the citizens with him he went to seek an
					oracle concerning a colony. The god told him to
					found a city where he should chance to be bitten by a
					wooden dog, and, as he was crossing to the other sea,
					he trod upon a dog-brier.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, 70 c-d.</note> Greatly troubled by the
					wound, he spent several days there, during which he
					explored the country and founded the cities Physcus
					and Oeantheia and the other cities which the so-called
					Ozolian Locrians inhabited.
				</p>
            <p>Some say that the Locrians are called Ozolian
					because of Nessus ; others say that it is because of the
					serpent Python, since their bodies were washed up
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.195"/>
					
					by the sea and rotted away in the country of the
					Locrians. But some say that these men wear fleeces
					and goatskins and for the most part spend their time
					with herds of goats, and thus became evil-smelling.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, x. 38.</note>
					But some, on the contrary, assert that, since the
					country has many flowers, it acquired its name from
					sweet odour. Among these is also Archytas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Powell, <hi rend="italics">Collectanea Alexandrina</hi>, p. 23.</note> of
					Amphissa, for he has written thus :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lovely Macyna, wreathed with clusters of grapes and
					fragrant with perfume.</quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>What is it that the Megarians call <hi rend="italics">aphabroma</hi>?
				</p>
            <p>When Nisus, from whom Nisaea acquired its name,
					was king, he took a wife from Boeotia, Habrot&ecirc;,
					daughter of Onchestus, the sister of Megareus, a
					woman who, as it appears, was both exceptionally
					intelligent and remarkably discreet. When she died,
					the Megarians mourned her with one accord, and
					Nisus, wishing that her memory and her repute should
					be established everlastingly, ordered the women of
					the city to wear the garment that she used to wear ;
					and because of her he called the garment <hi rend="italics">aphabroma</hi>. Even the god seems to have furthered the
					repute of this woman, for often, when the Megarian
					women wished to make a change in their raiment,
					he prevented them by an oracle.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>What is the <q direct="unspecified">spear-friend</q>?
				</p>
            <p>In days of old the Megarid used to be settled
					iri village communities with the citizens divided
					into five groups. They were called Herae&iuml;s, Pirae&iuml;s,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.197"/>
					
					Megareis, Cynosureis, and Tripodiscioi. Although
					the Corinthians brought about a civil war among
					them, for the Corinthians were ever plotting to get
					Megara under their control, none the less, because of
					their fair-mindedness, they conducted their wars in a
					civilized and a kinsmanly way. For no one did any
					harm at all to the men working in the fields, and when
					anyone was captured, he but needed to pay a certain
					specified ransom ; this his captors received after they
					had set him free, and did not collect it earlier ; but
					he who took a prisoner conducted the man to his
					house and, after sharing with him salt and food,
					sent him home. He, accordingly, who brought his
					ransom, was highly regarded and continued thenceforward to be a friend of his captor ; and, as a
					consequence of his capture by the spear, he was now
					called <q direct="unspecified">spear-friend.</q> But any one who failed to pay
					the ransom was held in disrepute as dishonest and
					faithless, not only among his enemies, but also among
					his fellow-citizens.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>What is <q direct="unspecified">return-interest</q>?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 304 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>When the Megarians had expelled Theagenes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, i. 126.</note>
					their despot, for a short time they were sober and
					sensible in their government. But later when the
					popular leaders poured a full and heady draught of
					freedom for them, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 562 d.</note> says, they were completely corrupted and, among their shocking acts of
					misconduct toward the wealthy, the poor would enter
					their homes and insist upon being entertained and
					banqueted sumptuously. But if they did not receive
					what they demanded, they would treat all the household with violence and insult. Finally they enacted
					a decree whereby they received back again the
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.199"/>
					
					interest which they chanced to have paid to their
					creditors, calling the measure <q direct="unspecified">return-interest.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Which is the Anthedon to which the utterance
					of the prophetic priestess refers :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Drink wine turbid with lees, since thou dwellest not
					in Anthedon,</quote>
					for Anthedon in Boeotia is not rich in wine?
				</p>
            <p>In days of old they used to call Calaureia by the
					name of Eiren&ecirc;, from the woman Eiren&ecirc; who, as
					legend has it, was born of Poseidon and Melantheia,
					the daughter of the Alpheius. But later, when the
					companions of Anthus and Hypera settled there, they
					called the island Anthedonia and Hypereia. According to Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 597 (ed. V. Rose); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Frag. 596 and Athenaeus, 31 b-c.</note> the oracle ran as follows :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Drink wine turbid with lees, since thou dwellest not
					in Anthedon,
					</l>
                  <l>No, nor in Hypera holy ; for wine without lees thou
					didst drink there.</l>
               </quote>
					This, then, is Aristotle's version. But Mnasigeiton
					says that Anthus, the brother of Hypera, disappeared
					from home while he was still a child, and that Hypera,
					while she was wandering about in search of him, came
					to Pherae to the house of Acastus, where it chanced
					that Anthus was the slave appointed to be cupbearer.
					While they were feasting the boy recognized his
					sister, as he was bearing her cup to her, and said
					to her softly
					<quote rend="blockquote">Drink wine turbid with lees, since thou dwellest not
					in Anthedon,</quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.201"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>What is it that is called in Prien&ecirc; <q direct="unspecified">the darkness
					by the Oak</q>?
				</p>
            <p>When the Samians and the Prienians were at war
					with each other, on the other occasions they suffered
					injuries and inflicted injuries to a moderate degree
					only ; but when a great battle took place, the people
					of Prien&ecirc; slew one thousand Samians. Six years later
					they engaged the Milesians at a place called the
					Oak, and lost practically all the best and the foremost
					of their citizens. At this time also the sage Bias was
					sent on an embassy from Prien&ecirc; to Samos and won
					high repute. For the women of Prien&ecirc; this was a
					cruel experience and a pitiable calamity, and it
					became established as a curse and an oath in the
					most important matters to swear by <q direct="unspecified">the darkness
						by the Oak,</q> because of the fact that there their
					sons, their fathers, and their husbands had been
					slaughtered.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, Frag. 576 (ed. V. Rose).</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Who are they that are called <q direct="unspecified">burners</q> among
					the Cretans?
				</p>
            <p>They relate that the Tyrrhenians who, at the time
					when they inhabited Lemnos and Imbros, carried
					off the daughters and wives of the Athenians from
					Brauron, later, when they had been expelled from
					there, came to Sparta and consorted with the women
					of the country even to the begetting of children.
					But again, as the result of suspicions and false accusations, they were forced to leave the Spartan
					country. With their children and wives they
					effected a landing in Crete with Pollis and Delphus
					as their leaders.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 247 a-f, and the note there (Vol. III. p. 496).</note> There, while they were fighting
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.203"/>
					
					the possessors of the island, they suffered many of
					the men who had been slain in the battles to lie unburied, because at first they had no leisure to bury
					them because of the war and the danger, and later
					because they shrank from touching corpses that had
					been decomposed and putrefied by the lapse of
					time. Accordingly Foliis devised certain honours,
					privileges, and immunities, and some of these he
					bestowed on the priests of the gods, others upon
					them that buried the dead. These honours he put
					in the keeping of the spirits of the underworld in
					order that they might continue for ever irrevocable.
					The one class received the name of priests, and the
					other that of <q direct="unspecified">burners.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>Then Pollis made a division by lot with Delphus,
					and they governed separate and independent states ;
					and, along with other humane provisions which they
					enjoyed, they had freedom from the injuries which
					the other Cretans are wont to inflict upon one
					another through stealthy plundering and pillaging.
					For to the Tyrrhenian communities they do no
					injury, nor do they steal anything from them or
					dispossess them of anything.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>What is the <q direct="unspecified">Children's Tomb</q> among the
					Chalcidians?
				</p>
            <p>Cothus and Aeolus, the sons of Xuthus, carne to
					Euboea to dwell at a time when the Aeolians possessed the greater part of the island. It had been
					prophesied to Cothus that he should have great
					success and get the better of his enemies if he
					bought the land. When he had landed on the island
					with a few men, he encountered little children playing by the sea. So he joined in their play, and
					in a kindly spirit showed them many playthings
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.205"/>
					
					from foreign lands. But when he saw that the
					children were desirous of having them for their own,
					he refused to give them unless he too should receive
					some earth from the children. So they picked up
					some from the ground and gave it to Cothus, and
					then, taking the playthings, departed. But the
					Aeolians discovered what had happened, arid, when
					their enemies sailed against them, they made away
					with the children under stress of anger and grief.
					The children were buried beside the road which
					leads from the city to the Euripus, and the place
					is called the Children's Tomb.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Who is the <q direct="unspecified">Associate-founder</q> (<hi rend="italics">mixarchagetas</hi>)
					at Argos, and who are the <q direct="unspecified">Averters</q> (<hi rend="italics">elasioi</hi>)?
				</p>
            <p>They call Castor the Associate-founder, and think
					that he is buried in Argive territory, but Poly deuces
					they reverence as one of the Olympians. Persons
					who have the reputed ability to turn away attacks
					of epilepsy they call Avertere, and these are thought
					to be of the descendants of Alexida, the daughter of
					Amphiara&uuml;s.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>What is that which is called an <hi rend="italics">enknisma</hi> (a
					roast) among the Argives?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iv. p. 498.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>It is the custom for those who have lost a relative
					or an intimate friend to sacrifice to Apollo<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For <q direct="unspecified">Apollo</q> Halliday suggests with some plausibility <q direct="unspecified">Pluto</q>; but Apollo, as the god who cleanses from pollution (<foreign lang="greek">kaqa/rsios</foreign>), is almost a commonplace in Greek literature.</note> immediately after the mourning, and again thirty days later
					to Hermes. For they believe that, just as the earth
					receives the bodies of the dead, even so Hermes
					receives their souls. They give barley to the priest
					of Apollo and receive some meat of the sacrificial
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.207"/>
					
					victim ; and when they have put out their fire, since
					they believe it to be polluted, and have relighted it
					from the hearth of others, they proceed to roast
					this flesh which they call <hi rend="italics">enknisma</hi>.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>What is an <hi rend="italics">alastor</hi>, an <hi rend="italics">aliterios</hi>, a <hi rend="italics">palamnaeos</hi>?
				</p>
            <p>We certainly must not believe those who say that
					persons who, during a famine set a watch upon the
					miller and plunder him are called <hi rend="italics">aliterioi</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 523 a-b.</note> But
					he who has done unforgettable (<hi rend="italics">alesta</hi>) things,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 418 b.</note>
					things that will be remembered for a long time, is
					called <hi rend="italics">alastor</hi>; and he whom it were well to avoid
					(<hi rend="italics">aleuasthai</hi>) and to guard against because of his
					wickedness is called <hi rend="italics">aliterios</hi>. These things, according to the statement of Socrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Socrates of Argos; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> v. p. 498.</note> they have
					written on tablets of bronze.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>What is the intent of the custom by which
					the maidens who serve as an escort for the men who
					lead the bull from Aenis to Cassiopaea chant until
					they reach the boundary,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Never may ye return to the well-loved soil of your homeland?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xviii. 148 (= xix. 298).</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>When the Aenianians had been driven out of their
					country by the Lapiths,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 293 f-294 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> they dwelt first of all
					about Aethicia, and later about Molossia and Cassiopaea. But, since they had no benefit from the
					country, and, in addition, had to deal with ungentle
					peoples on their borders, they came to the Cirrhaean
					plain under the leadership of Oenoclus, their king.
					But great droughts befell them there, and, as it is
					related, in accordance with an oracle they stoned
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.209"/>
					
					Oenoclus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 293 f-294 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> Then they wandered on and came to
					this country which they now possess, a goodly
					country, productive of all manner of crops ; wherefore it is with good reason that they pray to the gods
					that they may not return again to their ancient
					fatherland, but may remain here in prosperity.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Why is it that among the Rhodians a herald
					does not enter the shrine of the hero Ocridion?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because Ochimus affianced his daughter
					Cydipp&ecirc; to Ocridion? But Cercaphus, who was the
					brother of Ochimus, was in love with the maiden and
					persuaded the herald (for it used to be the custom
					to use heralds to fetch the brides), when he should
					receive Cydipp&ecirc;, to bring her to him. When this
					had been accomplished, Cercaphus fled with the
					maiden ; but later, when Ochimus had grown old,
					Cercaphus returned to his home again. But the
					custom became established among the Rhodians that
					a herald should not approach the shrine of Ocridion
					because of the wrong that had been done.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Why is it that among the inhabitants of
					Tenedos a flute-player may not enter the; shrine of
					Tenes, nor may anyone mention Achilles' name
					within the shrine?
				</p>
            <p>Is it that, when Tenes' stepmother<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Epitome</hi>, iii. 23-26, with Frazer's notes (L.C.L. vol. ii. pp. 193 ff.).</note> falsely accused
					him of wishing to lie with her, Molpus the flute-player
					bore false witness against him, and because of this it
					came about that Tenes had to flee to Tenedos with
					his sister? But as for Achilles, it is said that his
					mother Thetis straitly forbade him to kill Tenes, since
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.211"/>
					
					Tenes was honoured by Apollo; and she commissioned
					one of the servants to be on guard, and to remind
					Achilles lest he should unwittingly slay Tenes. But
					when Achilles was overrunning Tenedos and was
					pursuing Tenes' sister, who was a beautiful maiden.
					Tenes met him and defended his sister ; and she
					escaped, though Tenes was slain. When he had
					fallen. Achilles recognized him, and slew the servant because he had, although present, not reminded
					him; and he buried Tenes where his shrine now
					stands and neither does a flute-player enter it nor is
					Achilles mentioned there by name.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Who is the <q direct="unspecified">Seller</q> among the Epidamnians?
				</p>
            <p>The Epidamnians were neighbours of the Illyrians
					and perceived that such of their citizens as associated
					with the Illyrians were becoming corrupted ; and,
					since they feared a revolution, they used to select one
					of the most reputable of their fellow-citizens each
					year to conduct such commercial dealings and barters.
					This man visited the barbarians and provided them
					with a market and an opportunity for all the citizens
					to display what they had to sell: thus he was called
					the <q direct="unspecified">Seller.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>What is the <q direct="unspecified">Beach of Araenus</q> in Thrace?
				</p>
            <p>When the Andrians and Chalcidians sailed to
					Thrace to settle there, they jointly seized the city of
					San&ecirc;, which was betrayed to them; but when they
					learned that the barbarians had abandoned Acanthus,
					they sent out two scouts. When these were approaching the city, they perceived that the enemy
					had all fled ; so the Chalcidian ran forward to take
					possession of the city for Chalcis, but the Andrian,
					since he could not cover the distance so rapidly as
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.213"/>
					
					his rival, hurled his spear, and when it was firmly
					implanted in the city gates, he called out in a loud
					voice that by his spear the city had been taken into
					prior possession for the children of the Andrians. As
					a result of this a dispute arose, and, without going
					to war, they agreed to make use of Erythraeans,
					Samians, and Parians as arbitrators concerning the
					whole matter. But when the Erythraeans and the
					Samians gave their vote in favour of the Andrians,
					and the Parians in favour of the Chalcidians, the
					Andrians, in the neighbourhood of this place, made
					a solemn vow against the Parians that they would
					never give a woman in marriage to the Parians nor
					take one from them. And for this reason they called
					the place the Beach of Araenus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch, or his source, imagined that this meant <q direct="unspecified">Beach of Vowing.</q>
               </note> although it had
					formerly been named the Serpent's Beach.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>Why is it that at the Thesmophoria the Eretrian
					women cook their meat, not by fire, but by the
					rays of the sun ; and why do they not call upon
					Calligeneia?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The name of the third and last day of this festival at Athens; probably also a cult title applied to some goddess, perhaps to Demeter.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>Is it because it happened that the captive women
					whom Agamemnon was bringing home from Troy
					were celebrating the Thesmophoria at this place,
					but when conditions for sailing suddenly appeared
					favourable, they put out to sea leaving behind them
					the sacrifice uncompleted?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Who are the Perpetual Sailors among the
					Milesians?
				</p>
            <p>When the despots associated with Thoas and
					Damasenor had been overthrown, two political parties
					came into control of the city, one of which was called
					Plutis, the other Cheiromacha.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Capital and Labour.</q>
               </note> When, accordingly,
					the men of influence gained the upper hand and
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.215"/>
					
					brought matters into the control of their party, they
					used to deliberate about matters of the greatest
					importance by embarking in their ships and putting
					out to a considerable distance from the land. But
					when they had come to a final decision, they sailed
					back ; and because of this they acquired the appellation of Perpetual Sailors.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>Why do the Chalcidians call the neighbourhood
					of the Beacon <q direct="unspecified">the Young Men's Club</q>?
				</p>
            <p>They relate that Nauplius, when he was being
					pursued by the Achaeans, came as a suppliant to the
					Chalcidians ; and on the one hand he defended himself in regard to the indictment brought against
					him, and on the other hand brought a counter-charge
					against the Achaeans. The Chalcidians had no intention of surrendering him ; but, since they were
					afraid that he might be slain by treachery, they gave
					him a guard of young men in the prime of their youth
					and stationed them in this place, where they lived
					together and at the same time served as a guard for
					Nauplius.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>Who was the man that slew an ox for<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Possibly <q direct="unspecified">sacrificed an ox to his benefactor</q>; but an animal sacrifice to a living man seems incredible.</note> his
					benefactor?
				</p>
            <p>Anchored off the island of Ithaca was a pirate
					vessel in which there chanced to be an old man with
					earthenware jars containing pitch. By chance a
					ferryman of Ithaca, by name Pyrrhi as, put off to the
					ship and rescued the old man without asking for any
					reward, but because he had been persuaded by the
					old man and pitied him. He did, however, accept
					some of the jars, for the old man bade him do so.
					But when the pirates had departed and there was
					nothing to fear, the old man led Pyrrhias to the jars,
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.217"/>
					
					and in them showed him much gold and silver mixed
					with the pitch. So Pyrrhias, suddenly becoming
					rich, treated the old man well in various ways, and
					also slew an ox for him. Wherefore men make use
					of this as a proverbial expression : <q direct="unspecified">No one but
						Pyrrhias has slain an ox for his benefactor.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>Why was it the custom for the Bottiaean
					maidens to chant as they danced, <q direct="unspecified">Let us go to
						Athens<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch (<hi rend="italics">Life of Theseus</hi>, chap. xvi. p. 6 e ff.) states that his source for this is Aristotle's <hi rend="italics">Constitution of the Bottiaeans</hi> (Frag. 485 (ed. V. Rose)); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi> (in L.C.L. iii. 540).</note>
               </q>?
				</p>
            <p>They relate that the Cretans in accordance with a
					vow sent a consecrated offering of men to Delphi ;
					but the men who had been sent, when they saw that
					there was no abundance there, set out from Delphi
					to found a colony. They settled first in Iapygia, but
					later occupied this region of Thrace. There were
					some Athenians included among them ; fer it appears
					that Minos did not destroy the young persons whom
					the Athenians sent him for tribute, but kept them
					by him as servants. Accordingly, some who were
					descended from these Athenians and had come to be
					considered Cretans were included in this company
					sent to Delphi. Wherefore the daughters of the
					Bottiaeans, in remembrance of their lineage, were
					wont to sing in their festivals, <q direct="unspecified">Let us go to Athens.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>Why is it that the women of the Eleans, when
					they sing hymns to Dionysus, call upon him to come
					to them <q direct="unspecified">with the foot of a bull</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For Dionysus as a bull <hi rend="italics">cf. e.g.</hi> Athenaeus 35 e, 38 e.</note>? The hymn<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text is uncertain; Hartman has attempted a reconstruction in <hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi>, xli. 217; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also the other references in E. Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, ii. p. 206. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 364 f; Pausanias, vi. 26. 1; Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 656, or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi> (L.C.L. iii. 510).</note> runs
					as follows :
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.219"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Come, O hero Dionysus,
					</l>
                  <l>To thy Elean holy
					</l>
                  <l>Temple, with the Graces,
					</l>
                  <l>To thy temple
					</l>
                  <l>With thy bull's foot hasting.</l>
               </quote>
					Then they chant twice the refrain : <q direct="unspecified">O worthy bull.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>Is it because some address the god as <q direct="unspecified">kine-born</q>
					or as <q direct="unspecified">bull</q>? Or by <q direct="unspecified">ox-foot</q> do they mean <q direct="unspecified">with
						thy mighty foot</q> even as the Poet used <q direct="unspecified">ox-eyed</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 551 and often.</note>
					to signify <q direct="unspecified">large-eyed,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">bully</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">bouga/ios</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiii. 824: <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xviii. 79.</note> for <q direct="unspecified">loudmouthed</q>?
				</p>
            <p>Or is it rather because the foot of the bull is harmless, but the part that bears horns is harmful, and
					thus they call upon the god to come in a gentle and
					painless manner?
				</p>
            <p>Or is it because many believe that the god was the
					pioneer in both ploughing and sowing?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Why do the people of Tanagra have before
					their city an Achilleum, that is, a place bearing this
					name? For it is related that Achilles actually had
					more enmity than friendship for the city, since he
					carried off Stratonic&ecirc;, the mother of Poemander, and
					slew Acestor, the son of Ephippus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A grandson of Poemander.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>While the territory of Tanagra was still inhabited
					in village communities, Poemander, the father of
					Ephippus, had been besieged by the Achaeans in the
					place called Stephon, because of his unwillingness
					to join their expedition.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Against Troy.</note> But he abandoned that
					stronghold by night and fortified Poemandria.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, ix. 20. 1.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.221"/>
					
					Polycrithus the master-builder, however, who was
					present, spoke slightingly of the fortifications and, in
					derision, leaped over the moat. Poemander was enraged and hastened to throw at him a great stone
					which had been hidden there from ancient days, set
					aside for use in the ritual of the Nyctelia.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These rites resembled those of the rending and resurrection of Osiris; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi> 367 f.</note> This stone
					Poemander snatched up in his ignorance, and hurled.
					He missed Polycrithus, but slew his son Leucippus. According to the law, therefore, he had to
					depart from Boeotia and become a suppliant at a
					stranger's hearth. But this was not easy, since the
					Achaeans had invaded the territory of Tanagra. Accordingly he sent his son Ephippus to appeal to
					Achilles. Ephippus, by his persuasive words, brought
					to his father Achilles, as well as Tlepolemus, the son
					of Heracles, and Penele&ouml;s, the son of Hippalcmas, all
					of them interrelated. Poemander was escorted by
					them to Chalcis, and there at the house of Elephenor
					he was purified of the murder. Therefore he honoured
					these heroes and set apart sacred precincts for them
					all, and of these the precinct of Achilles has still kept
					its name.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>Who are the <q direct="unspecified">Psoloeis</q> and who the <q direct="unspecified">Oleiae</q>
					among the Boeotians?
				</p>
            <p>They relate that the daughters of Minyas, Leucipp&ecirc;
					and Arsino&ecirc; and Alcatho&ecirc;, becoming insane, conceived a craving for human flesh, and drew lots for
					their children.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 42; Antonius Liberalis, <hi rend="italics">Metamorphoses</hi>, x. Ovid's account (<hi rend="italics">Met.</hi> iv. 1. ff.; 389 ff.) is rather different and omits the murder of Hippasus.</note> The lot fell upon Leucippe to contribute her son Hippasus to be torn to pieces, and
					their husbands, who put on ill-favoured garments for
					very grief and sorrow, were called <q direct="unspecified">Grimy</q> (<hi rend="italics">Psoloeis</hi>);
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.223"/>
					
					but the Minyads themselves were called <q direct="unspecified">Oleiae,</q>
					that is to say, &lsquo;Murderesses.&rsquo; And even to-day
					the people of Orchomenus give this name to the
					women descended from this family ; and every year,
					at the festival of Agrionia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 717 a; 291 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> there takes place a flight
					and pursuit of them by the priest of Dionysus with
					sword in hand. Any one of them that he catches he
					may kill, and in my time the priest Zo&iuml;lus killed one
					of them. But this resulted in no benefit for the
					people of Orchomenus ; but Zo&iuml;lus fell sick from some
					slight sore and, when the wound had festered for a
					long time, he died. The people of Orchomenus also
					found themselves involved in some suits for damages
					and adverse judgements ; wherefore they transferred
					the priesthood from Zo&iuml;lus's family and chose the
					best man from all the citizens to fili the office.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>Why do the Arcadians stone persons who
					voluntarily enter the Lycaeon ; but if such persons
					enter through ignorance, they send them away to
					Eleutherae?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because they were released and set free that
					this story gained credence, and is the expression <q direct="unspecified">to
						Free Town</q> (<hi rend="italics">Eleutherae</hi>) of the same sort as <q direct="unspecified">to
							the land of Sans Souci</q> and <q direct="unspecified">you will come to the
								Seat of Satisfaction</q>?
				</p>
            <p>Or is it in accordance with the legend, since
					Eleuther and Lebadus were the only sons of Lycaon
					that had no share in the abomination prepared for
					Zeus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The serving of human flesh. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Metamorphoses</hi>, i. 163 ff. and Frazer's note on Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi> iii. 8. 1 (L.C.L. vol. i. pp. 390 ff.).</note> but instead they fled to Boeotia, and there
					is community of citizenship between the people of
					Lebadeia and the Arcadians, and do they accordingly
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.225"/>
					
					send away to Eleutherae those who involuntarily
					enter the inviolate sanctuary of Zeus?
				</p>
            <p>Or is it as Architimus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> vol. iv. p. 317.</note> relates in his <hi rend="italics">Arcadian
					History</hi>, that certain men who entered through ignorance were handed over by the Arcadians to the
					Phliasians, and by the Phliasians to the Megarians,
					and, as they were being conducted from Megara to
					Thebes, they were stopped near Eleutherae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A town in Attica not far from the borders of Boeotia.</note> by rain
					and thunder and other signs from heaven? Whence,
					in fact, some assert that the place acquired the name
					of Eleutherae.
				</p>
            <p>The tale, however, that no shadow is cast by a
					person who enters the Lycaeon is not true, although
					it has acquired widespread credence.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, viii. 38. 6; Polybius, xvi. 12. 7, whose source is Theopompus.</note> Is it because
					the air turns to clouds, and lowers darkly upon those
					who enter? Or is it because he that enters is condemned to death, and the followers of Pythagoras
					declare that the spirits of the dead cast no shadow,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 564 d. See also Dante, <hi rend="italics">Purgatorio</hi>, iii. 25-30, 94-97.</note>
					neither do they blink? Or is it because it is the sun
					which causes shadow, but the law deprives him that
					enters of the sunlight?
				</p>
            <p>This too they relate allegorically : he that enters is
					called a <q direct="unspecified">deer.</q> Wherefore, when Cantharion the
					Arcadian deserted to the Eleans while they were at
					war with the Arcadians, and with his booty crossed
					the inviolate sanctuary, even though he fled to Sparta
					after peace had been made, the Spartans surrendered
					him to the Arcadians, since the god ordered them to
					give back <q direct="unspecified">the deer.</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.227"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>Who was the hero Eunostus in Tanagra, and
					why may no women enter his grove?
				</p>
            <p>Eunostus was the son of Elieus, who was the son of
					Cephisus, and Scias. They relate that he acquired
					his name because he was brought up by the nymph
					Eunosta. Handsome and righteous as he was, he was
					no less virtuous and ascetic. They say that Ochn&ecirc;,
					his cousin, one of the daughters of Colonus, became
					enamoured of him ; but when Eunostus repulsed her
					advances and, after upbraiding her, departed to
					accuse her to her brothers, the maiden forestalled
					him by doing this very thing against him. She incited
					her brothers, Echemus, Leon, and Bucolus, to kill
					Eunostus, saying that he had consorted with her
					by force. They, accordingly, lay in ambush for the
					young man and slew him. Then Elieus put them in
					bonds ; but Ochn&ecirc; repented, and was filled with
					trepidation and, wishing to free herself from the
					torments caused by her love, and also feeling pity for
					her brothers, reported the whole truth to Elieus, and
					he to Colonus. And when Colonus had given judgement, Ochn&ecirc;'s brothers were banished, and she
					threw herself from a precipice, as Myrtis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, iii. p. 3.</note> the lyric
					poetess of Anthedon, has related.
				</p>
            <p>But the shrine and the grove of Eunostus were
					so strictly guarded against entry and approach by
					women that, often, when earthquakes or droughts
					or other signs from heaven occurred, the people
					of Tanagra were wont to search diligently and to
					be greatly concerned lest any woman might have
					approached the place undetected ; and some relate,
					among them Cleidamus, a man of prominence, that
					Eunostus met them on his way to the sea to bathe
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.229"/>
					
					because a woman had set foot within the sacred
					precinct. And Diocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 78.</note> also, in his treatise upon the
					<hi rend="italics">Shrines of Heroes</hi>, quotes a decree of the people of
					Tanagra concerning the matters which Cleidamus
					reported.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>From what cause was a river in Boeotia in the
					vicinity of Eleon called Scamander?
				</p>
            <p>De&iuml;machus, the son of Eleon and a companion of
					Heracles, took part in the expedition against Troy.
					But since, as it appears, the war was dragging on, he
					welcomed to his quarters Glaucia, the daughter of
					Scamander, who had fallen in love with him, and
					got her with child ; then he himself fell in fighting
					against the Trojans. But Glaucia, fearing detection,
					fled for refuge, and told Heracles of her love and
					of her association with De&iuml;machus. And he, both
					through pity for the woman, and for j oy that the stock
					of a brave man who was his close friend should thus
					survive, took Glaucia oil board his fleet; and when
					she gave birth to a son, he brought both the child and
					the mother, and delivered them to Eleon in Boeotia.
					The child was named Scamander, and he became the
					king of the country; and he named the Inachus river
					Scamander after himself, and the stream near by he
					called Glaucia from his mother. The spring Acidusa
					he named after his wife ; and from her he had three
					daughters whom even to this day they honour under
					the name of the <q direct="unspecified">Maidens.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>Whence arose the proverbial saying, <q direct="unspecified">This is
					valid</q>?
				</p>
            <p>When Deinon of Tarentum, a brave soldier, was
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.231"/>
					
					general, his fellow-citizens voted to reject a certain
					proposal of his. When the herald reported the prevailing majority, he held up his right hand and said,
					<q direct="unspecified">But this is stronger.</q> This is Theophrastus's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 133 (ed. Wimmer).</note>
					version of the story ; but Apollodorus has a supplementary version, that when the herald of the
					Tarentines proclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">These are in the majority</q>
					Deinon said, <q direct="unspecified">But these are better !</q> and validated
					the vote of the minority.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>For what reason was the city of the Ithacans
					called Alalcomenae?
				</p>
            <p>Because Anticleia, while yet a virgin, was violated
					by Sisyphus and conceived Odysseus. This is related
					by several authorities<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Philoctetes</hi>, 417, with Jebb's note; Frag. 567 (ed. Pearson), with the note.</note>; but Ister<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> i. p. 426.</note> of Alexandria in
					his <hi rend="italics">Commentaries</hi> has in addition recorded that when
					Anticlea had been given in marriage to La&euml;rtes and
					was being conducted to his home, she gave birth to
					Odysseus near the Alalcomenium in Boeotia. And
					for this reason, as though referring the name to that
					of a mother-city, he states that the city in Ithaca
					acquired its name.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>Who were the <q direct="unspecified">solitary eaters</q> in Aegina?
				</p>
            <p>Of the Aeginetans who were engaged in the war
					against Troy many perished in the battles there, but
					even more were destroyed by the storm on the returnvoyage. So there were but few who survived, and
					when their relatives had welcomed them home, and
					observed that the other citizens were in mourning
					and sorrow, they deemed it proper neither to rejoice
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.233"/>
					
					nor to sacrifice to the gods openly ; but secretly and
					separately in their own houses they received with
					feasting and good cheer those who had reached home
					in safety. They themselves waited upon their fathers
					and kinsmen, their brothers and relatives, and no one
					outside the family was allowed to enter. It is, then,
					in imitation of this that they hold a sacrifice to
					Poseidon, which is called <hi rend="italics">thiasoi</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Club-dinner.</note> in which they
					feast by themselves in silence for sixteen days, and no
					slave is present. Then, when they have celebrated
					the Aphrodisia, they terminate the festival. For this
					reason they are called <q direct="unspecified">solitary eaters.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>Why is it that the statue of the Labrandean
					Zeus in Caria is fashioned holding an axe, but not a
					sceptre or a thunderbolt?
				</p>
            <p>Because when Heracles had slain Hippolyt&ecirc;, together with her other arms he took her axe and gave
					it as a present to Omphal&ecirc;. The Lydian kings who
					succeeded Omphal&ecirc; used to carry it as a part of
					the sacred regalia, handing it down one to the other
					until it carne to Candaules. He deemed it of little
					worth and gave it to one of his Companions<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Technically a Hellenistic court office, but Plutarch seems to assume such a relation in early Lydian history.</note> to carry.
					But when Gyges<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The many ancient variants of the Gyges legend are collected and discussed by K. F. Smith, <hi rend="italics">American Jour. Phil.</hi>, 1902 pp. 261 ff., 362 ff.; 1920, pp. 1 ff.</note> revolted and was at war with
					Candaules, Arselis carne from Mylasa with an army
					as an ally for Gyges and slew both Candaules and his
					Companion and brought the axe to Caria together
					with the other spoils. He therefore constructed a
					statue of Zeus and placed the axe in its hand, and
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.235"/>
					
					called the god Labrandeus ; for the Lydialis call the
					axe <hi rend="italics">labrys</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One is reminded of the many representations of the double axe on Cretan monuments.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>Why is it that the people of Tralles call vetch
					<q direct="unspecified">purifier</q> and make particular use of it for expiations and purifications?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because the Leleges and Minyae in days of old
					drove them out and took possession of their city and
					their land, and because later the Trallians returned
					and prevailed, and as many of the Leleges as had not
					been slain nor had fled away, but had been left behind
					there because of their destitution and weakness - of
					these they took no account either of their life or of their
					death, and they established a law that any Trallian
					who killed a Miriyan or a Lelegian should be free
					from pollution when he had measured out a bushel of
					vetch to the relatives of the murdered man?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>Why is there a proverb among the Eleans <q direct="unspecified">to
					suffer more terribly than Sambicus</q>?
				</p>
            <p>The story is told that a certain Sambicus, an Elean,
					at the head of a numerous group of confederates, cut
					many pieces from the bronze votive statues in Olympia
					and sold them, and finally he despoiled the shrine of
					Artemis the Guardian. This is in Elis and is called
					the Aristarcheum. Immediately, then, after this
					sacrilege, he was caught and tortured for a year,
					being interrogated about each of his confederates in
					turn ; and in this manner he died and the proverb
					arose from his sufferings.
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.237"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>Why at Sparta is a shrine of Odysseus built
					near the shrine of the daughters of Leucippus?
				</p>
            <p>Erginus, one of the descendants of Diomedes, was
					persuaded by Temenus to steal the Palladium from
					Argos ; this he did with the knowledge and help
					of Leagrus, who was one of Temenus's friends. But
					later Leagrus became incensed at Temenus and removed to Sparta, taking the Palladium with him. The
					Spartan kings received it eagerly, and gave it a place
					near the shrine of the daughters of Leucippus, and
					they sent to Delphi to obtain an oracle concerning its
					safety and preservation. When the god gave oracle
					that one of those who had purloined the Palladium
					should be made its guardian, the Spartans constructed
					there the shrine of Odysseus, especially since, because of his marriage with Penelop&ecirc;,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The daughter of the Spartan Icarius.</note> they reckoned
					that this hero had close relations with their city.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>Why is it the custom for the women of Chalcedon, whenever they encounter strange men, and
					especially officials, to veil one cheek?
				</p>
            <p>The Chalcedonians were involved in a war against
					the Bithyniae, to which they were provoked by all
					kinds of reasons. When Zeipoetes became king of
					Bithynia, the Chalcedonians, in full force and with the
					addition of Thracian allies, devastated the country
					with fire and sword. When Zeipoetes attacked them
					near the so-called Phalion, they fought badly through
					rashness and lack of discipline, and lost over eight
					thousand soldiers. It was only because Zeipoetes
					granted an armistice to please the Byzantines that
					they were not completely annihilated at that time.
					Since, then, there was a great scarcity of men
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.239"/>
					
					throughout the city, most of the women were forced
					to consort with freedmen and resident aliens. But
					those women who preferred to have no husband at
					all rather than a marriage of this sort, themselves
					conducted whatever business they needed to transact
					with the judges or the officials, drawing aside one part
					of the veil that covered their faces. And the married
					women, for very shame, followed the example of
					these, who, they felt, were better than themselves,
					and also changed to a similar custom.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>Why is it that the Argives drive their sheep
					to the precinct of Agenor when they wish to mate
					them?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because Agenor took most excellent care of his
					sheep and acquired more flocks than any other king?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="51">
            <p>Why is it that Argive children in a certain
					festival call themselves, in jest, <q direct="unspecified">Pear-throwers</q>?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because the first men that were led down by
					Inachus from the mountains to the plain lived, as they
					say, on wild pears? They also say that wild pears
					were first discovered by the Greeks in the Peloponnesus at a time when that country was still called
					Apia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, ii. 5. 7; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 39.</note> wherefore wild pears were named <hi rend="italics">apioi</hi>.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="52">
            <p>What is the reason why the Eleans lead their
					mares outside the boundaries of their country to mate
					them with asses?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, iv. 30; Pausanias, v. 5. 2; 9. 2; mules were not bred in Elis because of a curse, and this, seemingly, should be the meaning here; but the corruption in the text of one word, which should have designated asses, has made the mules somewhat dubious.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>Is it because of all kings Oenoma&uuml;s was the most
					fond of horses, and, since he particularly loved
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.241"/>
					
					this animal, he laid many terrible curses upon any
					that should thus mate horses in Elis ; and it is in fear
					of that curse that they endeavour to keep clear of it?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="53">
            <p>Why was it the custom among the Cnossians
					for those who borrowed money to snatch it?
				</p>
            <p>Was it that if they defaulted they might be liable
					to the charge of violence, and so be punished the
					more?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="54">
            <p>What is the reason why in Samos they invoke
					the Aphrodit&ecirc; of Dexicreon?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because a sorcerer Dexicreon, making use of
					a rite of purification, freed the women of Samos
					from the unbridled licentiousness in which they indulged because of their great luxury and wantonness?
				</p>
            <p>Or is it because Dexicreon was a shipmaster and
					sailed to Cyprus on a trading voyage, and, when he
					was about to freight his ship, Aphrodit&ecirc; bade him
					put into it water and nothing else, and set sail as
					quickly as possible? He obeyed and, putting much
					water aboard the ship, sailed away ; after a time the
					wind died down and the ship was becalmed in the
					open sea. To the other merchants and shipmasters,
					who were athirst, he sold the water and amassed
					much money. Wherefore he fashioned an image of
					the goddess and called it by his own name. If this
					is really true, it appears that the goddess wished not
					to make one man rich, but to save the lives of many
					through one man.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="55">
            <p>Why is it that whenever the Samians are engaged in sacrificing to Hermes the Giver of Joy they
					allow whoever so desires to steal from them and filch
					their clothes?
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.243"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>Because in obedience to an oracle they changed
					their abode from Samos to Mycal&ecirc; and supported
					themselves by piracy there for ten years ; and after
					this they sailed again to Samos and overcame their
					enemies.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="56">
            <p>From what does the place Panhaema on the
					island of Samos derive its name?
				</p>
            <p>Is it because the Amazons sailed from the country
					of the Ephesians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, vii. 2. 7.</note> across to Samos when they were
					endeavouring to escape from Dionysus? But he built
					boats and crossed over and, joining battle, slew many
					of them near this place, which the spectators in
					amazement called Panhaema<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Allblood.</q>
               </note> because of the vast
					quantity of blood shed there. And of the elephants<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wilamowitz and Halliday emend to <foreign lang="greek">e)lefa/ntwn</foreign>. This has, at first view, some plausibility, but completely lacks corroborative evidence. Nonnus, <hi rend="italics">Dionysiaca</hi>, xxvi. 326 ff. is not by any means parallel.</note>
					some are said to have been slain near Phloeum, and
					their bones are pointed out there ; but some relate
					that Phloeum also was cleft by them as they uttered
					a loud and piercing cry.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="57">
            <p>For what reason is the great hall in Samos
					called the Hall of Fetters?
				</p>
            <p>After the murder of Demoteles and the dissolution
					of his monarchic government the Land-owners<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucydides, viii. 21, recounts the later struggles of the Land-owners and the People.</note> controlled the State, and at this time the Megarians
					made an expedition against the Perinthians, who
					were colonists of the Samians ; as it is related, they
					brought with them fetters for their captives. When
					the Land-owners learned of this, they dispatched aid
					to the Perinthians with all speed, appointing nine
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.245"/>
					
					generals and manning thirty ships. Two of these
					ships, as they were sailing out, were destroyed by a
					thunderbolt in front of the harbour ; but the generals
					kept on with the others, defeated the Megarians, and
					took six hundred of them alive. Elated by their
					victory, they conceived the proj ect of overthrowing
					the oligarchy of the Land-owners at home. Now
					the officials in charge of the government had provided
					an occasion for undertaking this, by writing to the
					generals to bring back the captive Megarians bound
					in their own fetters. The generals, accordingly,
					took the letter, and secretly showed it to certain
					of the Megarians and persuaded them to join with
					themselves and free the city. When they took
					counsel together concerning the deed, they decided
					to knock loose the rings that fastened the fetters, and
					in this condition to put them on the legs of the
					Megarians, holding them up with thongs to their
					girdles, so that the fetters might not slip down
					and fall off when their legs became relaxed in
					walking. Having thus equipped the men and given
					a sword to each, they sailed back to Samos and disembarked, and there they led the Megarians through
					the market-place to the council-chamber, where practically all the Land-owners were sitting together.
					Then, at a given signal, the Megarians fell upon
					them and slew them. When the city had thus been
					freed, they made citizens of those Megarians who
					so desired ; and they constructed a great building
					and dedicated the fetters there ; and from this the
					building was called the Hall of Fetters.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="58">
            <p>Why is it that among the Coans the priest of
					Heracles at Antimacheia dons a woman's garb, and
					
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.247"/>
					
					fastens upon his head a woman's head-dress before
					he begins the sacrifice?
				</p>
            <p>Heracles, putting out with his six ships from Troy,
					encountered a storm ; and when his other ships had
					been destroyed, with the only one remaining he was
					driven by the gale to Cos. He was cast ashore upon
					the Laceter, as the place is called, with nothing
					salvaged save his arms and his men. Now he
					happened upon some sheep and asked for one ram
					from the shepherd. This man, whose name was
					Antagoras, was in the prime of bodily strength, and
					bade Heracles wrestle with him ; if Heracles could
					throw him, he might carry off the ram. And when
					Heracles grappled with him, the Meropes came to the
					aid of Antagoras, and the Greeks to help Heracles,
					and they were soon engaged in a mighty battle. In
					the struggle it is said that Heracles, being exhausted
					by the multitude of his adversaries, fled to the house
					of a Thracian woman ; there, disguising himself in
					feminine garb, he managed to escape detection.
					But later, when he had overcome the Meropes in
					another encounter, and had been purified, he married Chalciop&ecirc; and assumed a gay-coloured raiment.
					Wherefore the priest sacrifices on the spot where it
					came about that the battle was fought, and bridegrooms wear feminine raiment when they welcome
					their brides.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="59">
            <p>Whence came the clan of <q direct="unspecified">Wagon-rollers</q>
					among the Megarians?
				</p>
            <p>In the time of the unbridled democracy which
					brought about both the return-interest<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 295 c-d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and the
					temple sacrilege, a sacred mission of Peloponnesians
					passed through the Megarid, on its way to Delphi and
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.249"/>
					
					had encamped, as chance dictated, in their wagons,
					with their wives and children, in Aegeiri beside the
					lake. But the boldest spirits among the Megarians,
					inflamed with wine, in their insolence and savagery
					rolled back the wagons and pushed them into the
					lake, so that many members of the mission were
					drowned. Now because of the unsettled state of
					their government the Megarians took no notice of
					the crime; but the Amphictyonic Assembly, since the
					mission was sacred, took cognizance of the matter
					and punished some of the guilty men with banishment and others with death. The descendants of
					these men were called <q direct="unspecified">Wagon-rollers.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>