<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Amatoriae narrationes</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold North Fowler</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.10.p.3"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="intro">
            <head>LOVE STORIES (AMATORIAE NARRATIONES)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					These five short stories are interesting to the modern
					reader chiefly as examples of the kind of tale which
					appealed to the readers of Plutarch's time ; for they
					were probably written during his lifetime, though
					not by him. In style and content they differ greatly
					from his genuine works. The elements of passion
					and of sentimental love are made to appear important in them rather on account of their dire
					consequences than for their own sake.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.5"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>I</head>
            <p>
					At Haliartus, in Boeotia, there was a girl of remarkable beauty, named Aristocleia, the daughter
					of Theophanes. She was wooed by Strato of Orchomenus and Callisthenes of Haliartus. Strato was
					the richer and was rather the more violently in love
					with the maiden ; for he had seen her in Lebadeia
					bathing at the fountain called Hercyn&ecirc; in preparation for carrying a basket<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Processions were common in Greek worship, and often young women, chosen usually for their good birth and their beauty, formed part of them, carrying baskets in which were offerings or utensils for use in sacrifices.</note> in a sacred procession
					in honour of Zeus the King. But Callisthenes had
					the advantage, for he was a blood-relation of the girl.
					Theophanes was much perplexed about the matter,
					for he was afraid of Strato, who excelled nearly all
					the Boeotians in wealth and in family connexions,
					and he wished to submit the choice to Trophonius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A hero whose oracular shrine was at Lebadeia.</note>
					but Strato had been persuaded by the maiden's
					servants that she was more inclined towards him,
					so he asked that the choice be left to the bride-to-be
					herself. But when Theophanes in the presence of
					everyone asked the maiden, and she chose Callisthenes, it was plain at once that Strato found the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.7"/>
					
					
					slight hard to bear. But he let two days go by and
					came to Theophanes and Callisthenes asking that
					the friendship between him and them be preserved,
					even though he had been deprived of the marriage
					by some jealous divinity. And they approved of
					what he said, so that they even invited him to the
					wedding-feast. But before he came he got ready
					a crowd of his friends and a considerable number
					of servants, who were scattered among the others
					present and were not noticed ; but when the girl
					went, according to the ancestral custom, to the spring
					called Cissoessa to make the preliminary sacrifice
					to the nymphs, then his men who were in ambush
					all rushed out at once and seized her. Strato
					also had hold of the maiden ; and naturally Callisthenes and his supporters in turn took hold of her and
					held on until, although they did not know it at the
					time, she died in their hands as they pulled against
					each other. Callisthenes immediately disappeared,
					whether by committing suicide or by going away
					as an exile from Boeotia ; at any rate nobody could
					tell what had happened to him. But Strato slew
					himself in sight of all upon the body of the maiden.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>II</head>
            <p>
					A man named Pheidon, who was striving to
					make himself ruler of the Peloponnesians and wished
					his own native city of Argos to be the leader of all
					the other states, plotted first against the Corinthians. He sent and asked of them the thousand
					young men who were the best in vigour and valour ;
					and they sent the thousand, putting Dexander in
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.9"/>
					
					
					command of them. Now Pheidon intended to make
					an onslaught upon these young men, that Corinth
					might be weakened and he might have the city in
					his power, for he considered that it would be the
					most advantageous bulwark of the whole Peloponnesus, and he confided this matter to some of his
					friends, among whom was Habron. Now he was a
					friend of Dexander and told him of the plot, so before
					the onslaught was made the thousand young men
					escaped safely to Corinth ; but Pheidon tried to
					discover the betrayer of his plot and searched for him
					with , great care. So Hatron was frightened and
					fled to Corinth with his wife and his servants, settling
					in Melissus, a village in Corinthian territory. There
					he begot a son whom he called Melissus from the
					name of the place. This Melissus had a son named
					Actaeon, the handsomest and most modest youth
					of his age, who had many lovers, chief of whom was
					Archias, of the family of the Heracleidae, in wealth
					and general influence the most outstanding man in
					Corinth. Now when he could not gain the boy by
					persuasion, he determined to carry him off by force.
					So he got together a crowd of friends and servants,
					went as in a drunken frolic to the house of Melissus,
					and tried to take the boy away. But his father and
					his friends resisted, the neighbours also ran out and
					pulled against the assailants, and so Actaeon was
					pulled to pieces and killed ; the assailants thereupon went away. But Melissus took his son's body
					and exhibited it in the market-place of the Corinthians, demanding the punishment of the men who
					had done the deed ; but the Corinthians merely pitied
					him and did nothing further. So, being unsuccessful,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.11"/>
					
					
					he went away and waited for the Isthmian
					festival,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The famous Isthmian games in honour of Poseidon, for victors in which Pindar composed some of his odes.</note> when he went up upon the temple of
					Poseidon, shouted accusations against the Bacchiadae,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The noble family which ruled Corinth in the eighth and seventh centuries b.c. Periander is its most famous member.</note> and reminded the people of his father Habron's
					benefactions, whereupon, calling upon the gods to
					avenge him, he threw himself down from the rocks.
					Not long afterwards the city was afflicted by drought
					and pestilence, and when the Corinthians consulted
					the oracle concerning relief, the god replied that the
					wrath of Poseidon would not relax until they inflicted punishment for the death of Actaeon. Archias
					knew of this, for he was himself one of those sent to
					consult the oracle, and voluntarily rgfrained from
					returning to Corinth. Instead he sailed to Sicily and
					founded Syracuse. There he became the father of
					two daughters, Ortygia and Syracusa, and was
					treacherously murdered by Telephus, who had been
					his beloved and had sailed with him to Sicily in
					command of a ship.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>III</head>
            <p>
					There was a poor man named Scedasus who lived
					at Leuctra ; that is a village of the country of the
					Thespians. This man had two daughters, called
					Hippo and Miletia, or, as some say, Theano and
					Euxipp&ecirc;. Now Scedasus was a worthy man and
					friendly to strangers, though he was not very well
					off. So when two Spartan youths came to his house
					he received them gladly. They fell in love with the
					maidens, but were restrained from overboldness by
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.13"/>
					
					
					the worthy character of Scedasus, and the next day
					went away to Delphi, for that was the place for which
					they were bound. And when they had consulted the
					god about the matters which concerned them, they
					went back again towards home, and passing through
					Boeotia they stopped again at the house of Scedasus.
					Now he, as it happened, was not at Leuctra ; but his
					daughters, in accordance with their usual custom,
					received the strangers, who, finding the maidens unprotected, ravished them ; and then, seeing that they
					were exceedingly distressed by the violent wrong they
					had suffered, they killed them, threw their bodies
					into a well, and went away. When Scedasus came
					home, he missed the girls, but found everything that
					he had left in the house undisturbed, and so he did
					not know what to make of it all until, because his dog
					kept whimpering and often running up to him and
					from him to the well, he guessed the truth, and so
					drew up the bodies of his daughters. And finding
					out from his neighbours that on the previous day they
					had seen going into his house the Lacedaemonians
					who had been entertained there shortly before, he
					guessed that they had done the deed, because during
					their previous visit they had constantly been praising
					the girls and talking of the happiness of their future
					husbands.
				</p>
            <p>
					Scedasus set out for Lacedaemon to see the ephors,
					and when he was in the territory of Argos night came
					upon him, so he put up at an inn, and at the same
					inn was another elderly man, a native of the city of
					Oreus in the territory of Hestiaea. Scedasus heard
					him groaning and uttering curses against the Lacedaemonians, so he asked him what harm the Lacedaemonians had done him. Then he proceeded to
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.15"/>
					
					
					tell that he was a subject of Sparta and that Aristodemus, who had been sent by the Lacedaemonians
					to Oreus as governor, had shown himself very lawless
					and cruel. <q direct="unspecified">For,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">he fell in love with my
						young son and, when he could not gain him by persuasion, he tried to take him from the palaestra by
						force. But the teacher of gymnastics interfered, and
						many young fellows came out to help, so for the time
						being Aristodemus went away ; but the next day he
						manned a ship of war, seized the boy, sailed from
						Oreus to the opposite shore, and tried to rape him ;
						then when the boy would not submit, he cut his
						throat and killed him, after which he went back to
						Oreus and gave a dinner-party. But as for me,</q> he
					said, <q direct="unspecified">I learned of the deed, performed the funeral
						rites over the body, then went to Sparta and had an
						audience with the ephors ; but they paid no attention
						to me.</q> When Scedasus heard this he was disheartened, for he suspected that the Spartans would
					pay no attention to him either ; and he in turn
					told the stranger of his own misfortune. Then the
					stranger advised him not even to go to see the ephors,
					but to turn back to Boeotia and build his daughters'
					tomb. Scedasus, however, did not take this advice,
					but went to Sparta and spoke with the ephors. They
					paid no attention to him, so he hurried to the kings,
					and from them he went up to every one of the citizens
					and told his tale of woe. And when nothing did any
					good, he ran through the midst of the city stretching
					up his hands towards the sun, and again he beat upon
					the ground and summoned up the Erinyes, and finally
					he put an end to his life.
				</p>
            <p>
					Later, however, the Lacedaemonians certainly paid
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.17"/>
					
					
					the penalty. For when they were rulers of all the
					Greeks and had placed their garrisons in the cities,
					Epaminondas the Theban first slaughtered the
					garrison of the Lacedaemonians in his own city, and
					when thereupon the Lacedaemonians made war upon
					the Thebans, the latter met them at Leuctra,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A village in Boeotia. The battle, which ended the Spartan hegemony, took place in 371 b.c.</note> thinking it a place of good omen, because at an earlier time
					they had gained their freedom there, when Amphictyon, having been driven into exile by Sthenelus,
					came to the city of the Thebans and, finding them
					tributaries of the Chalcidians, freed them from the
					tribute by killing Chalcodon, king of the Euboeans.
					Now it happened that the utter defeat of the Lacedaemonians took place precisely in the vicinity of the
					tombstone of the daughters of Scedasus. And the
					story goes that before the battle Pelopidas, one of
					the generals of the Theban army, was disturbed by
					some omens which were considered unfavourable and
					that in his sleep Scedasus came and stood over him
					and told him to be of good courage, for the Lacedaemonians were coming to Leuctra to pay the penalty
					to him and his daughters ; and he enjoined upon him
					one day before fighting the Lacedaemonians to make
					ready a white colt and sacrifice it at the tomb of the
					maidens. So Pelopidas, while the Lacedaemonians
					were still in camp at Tegea, sent some men to Leuctra
					to find out about this tomb, and when he learned about
					it from the inhabitants of the place, he led out his
					army with confidence and was victorious.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.19"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>IV</head>
            <p>
					Phocus was by birth a Boeotian, for he was from
					the town of Glisas, and he was the father of Callirrho&ecirc;,
					who excelled in beauty and modesty. She was wooed
					by thirty young men, the most highly esteemed in
					Boeotia ; but Phocus found one reason after another
					for putting off her marriage, for he was afraid that
					violence would be done to him<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> by the disappointed suitors.</note>; at last, however,
					he yielded to their demands, but asked to leave
					the choice to the Pythian oracle. The suitors were
					incensed by the proposal, rushed upon Phocus, and
					killed him. In the confusion the maiden got away
					and fled through the country, but the young men
					pursued her. She came upon some farmers making
					a threshing-floor, and found safety with them, for the
					farmers hid her in the grain, and so her pursuers
					passed by. But she waited in safety until the festival
					of the Pamboeotia, when she went to Coroneia, took
					her seat on the altar of Athena Itonia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The cult of Athena Itonia was brought to Boeotia by the Ionians when they were driven out by the Thessalians. Her sanctuary near Coroneia was the place of the Pamboeotia, the festival of the united Boeotians.</note> and told of
					the lawless act of the suitors, giving the name and
					birthplace of each. So the Boeotians pitied the maid
					and were angry with the young men. When they
					learned of this, they fled for refuge to Orchomenus,
					and when the Orchomenians refused to receive them,
					they forced their way into Hippotae, a village lying
					on the slope of Mount Helicon between Thisbe and
					Coroneia. There they were received. Then the
					Thebans sent and demanded the slayers of Phocus,
					and when the people of Hippotae refused to deliver
					them, the Thebans, along with the rest of the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.21"/>
					
					
					Boeotians, took the field under the command of
					Phoedus, who at that time administered the government of Thebes. They besieged the village, which
					was well fortified, and when they had overcome the
					inhabitants by thirst, they took the murderers and
					stoned them to death and made slaves of the
					villagers; then they pulled down the walls and the
					houses and divided the land between the people of
					Thisb&ecirc; and of Coroneia. It is said that in the night,
					before the capture of Hippotae, there was heard
					many times from Helicon a voice of someone saying
					<q direct="unspecified">I am here,</q> and that the thirty suitors recognized
					the voice as that of Phocus. It is said also that on
					the day when they were stoned to death the old
					man's monument at Glisas ran with saffron ; and
					that as Phoedus, the ruler and general of the
					Thebans, was returning from the battle, he received
					the news of the birth of a daughter and, thinking
					it of good omen, he named her Nicostrata.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">She of the conquering host.</q>
               </note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>V</head>
            <p>
					Alcippus was a Lacedaemonian by birth; he
					married Damocrita and became the father of two
					daughters. Now since he was a most excellent
					counsellor to the state and conducted affairs to the
					satisfaction of the Lacedaemonians, he was envied
					by his political opponents, who misled the ephors by
					false statements to the effect that Alcippus wished
					to destroy the constitution, and they thereby brought
					about his exile. So he departed from Sparta, but
					wher his wife Damocrita, with their daughters,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.23"/>
					
					
					wished to follow her husband, she was prevented
					from doing so, and moreover his property was confiscated, that the girls might not be provided with
					dowries. And when even so there were some suitors
					who wooed the girls on account of their father's high
					character, his enemies got a bill passed, forbidding
					anyone to woo the girls, saying that their mother
					Damocrita had often prayed that her daughters
					might speedily bear sons who should grow up to be
					their father's avengers. Damocrita, being harassed
					on all sides, waited for a general festival in which
					married women along with unmarried girls, slaves,
					and infant children took part, and the wives of those
					in authority passed the whole night in a great hall
					by themselves. Then she buckled a sword about
					her waist, took the girls, and went by night into the
					sacred place, waiting for the moment when all the
					women were performing the mysteries in the hall.
					Then, after the entrances had all been closed, she
					heaped a great quantity of wood against the doors
					(this had been prepared by the othei's for the sacrifice
					belonging to the festival) and set it on fire. And
					when the men came running up to save their wives,
					Damocrita killed her daughters with the sword and
					then herself over their dead bodies. But the Lacedaemonians, not knowing how to vent their anger, threw
					the bodies of Damocrita and her daughters out beyond
					the boundaries ; and they say that because the god
					was offended by this the great earthquake<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably the earthquake of 464 b.c. is meant.</note> came
					upon the Lacedaemonians.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>