<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De primo frigido</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1957</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.12.p.227"/>
            <head>ON THE PRINCIPLE OF COLD (DE PRIMO FRIGIDO) <lb/> INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					This little essay, or open letter to Favorinus, is not
					written in a controversial spirit, though a few sharp
					comments are made from time to time. Having
					established (chapters 5-7) that an element of Cold
					really exists, Plutarch proceeds to consider what that
					element may be. Since fire is obviously excluded,
					can it be air, as the Stoics believe (8-12), or water,
					as Empedocles, and an early Peripatetic, Strato, hold
					(13-16) ? Or, indeed, may it be earth itself (17-22) ?
					This latter opinion is apparently put forward by
					Plutarch as an original contribution to theoretical
					physics and there is no reason to believe it is not his.
					The essay closes, however, with a recommendation
					to scepticism,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See J. Schr&ouml;ter, <hi rend="italics">Plutarchs Stellung zur Skepsis</hi> (Greifswald, 1911), pp. 23 and 40. He compares other recomendations to the suspension of judgement, such as <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 430 f - 431 a. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Hartman, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, pp. 253 f.</note> so that our author may not have regarded his attempted proof as cogent, as indeed it is
					not.
				</p>
            <p>
					The work was probably written in Delphi (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 953
					c-d and e) after a.d. 107-(949 e, note) and addressed
					to the young philosopher Favorinus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the details see Ziegler's article on Plutarch in Pauly-Wissowa, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, col. 675.</note> the great lover
					of Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 734 f), who is also a speaker in
					<hi rend="italics">Symposiacs</hi>, viii. IO. Though Favorinus was in all
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.228"/>
					
					likelihood some twenty years younger than Plutarch,
					the two men dedicated several works to each other.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lamprias cat. 132: Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Letter to Favorinus on Friendship</hi> (or <hi rend="italics">The Use of Friends</hi>); Galen, <hi rend="italics">de Opt. Doctr.</hi> (i. 41 K): Favorinus's <hi rend="italics">Plutarch, or On the Academic Disposition</hi>. See also Suidas, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi> 
                  <foreign lang="greek">*fabwri=nos</foreign>.</note>
					In the present essay it is, perhaps, odd that of the
					three quotations from Aristotle one is a rebuke (950
					b), one is apparently a partial miscitation (948 a, note),
					while the third is of no importance. No doubt it is in
					virtue of Favorinus' youth that his idol is treated so
					lightly, and that the sceptical note is sounded so
					firmly at the end. The young Peripatetic was also
					quoted by Plutarch (for partial refutation) in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi>
					271 c ; but Plutarch (if Tarn<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Alexander the Great</hi>, ii. 298 f.</note> and others are right)
					became much more favourable to Peripatetics later
					in his life (e.g. in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>).
				</p>
            <p>
					Bernardakis s text of this work is one of his most
					unsatisfactory ; even for an <hi rend="italics">editio minor</hi> it is careless
					and confused to a deplorable extent. Nor are the
					means of correcting and supplementing it at hand,
					the fifth Teubner volume being still, one fears, in
					the remote future. Then, too. the only photographs
					available were those of E and Β. which are not likely
					to add much to our knowledge.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the recent brisk controversy as to their relationship: Manton, <hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> xliii (1949), pp. 97-104; Hubert, <hi rend="italics">Rhein. Mus.</hi> xciii (1950), pp. 330-336; Einarson and De Lacy, <hi rend="italics">Class. Phil.</hi> xlvi (1951), p. 110, n. 56; Flaceliere, ed. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Amatorius</hi>, pp. 35 ff. The evidence in this essay, for what it may be worth, seems to make it unlikely that B was here copied from either E or an immediate descendant; they both appear to go back to a common ancestor, perhaps through several intermediaries: see, <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>, 951 a, b, d, 953 e. See now Cherniss <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, pp. 27, note <hi rend="italics">a</hi>; 31, 32.</note> Consequently the
					only course that seemed prudent was to return to
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.229"/>
					
					Wyttenbach wherever there was a reasonable doubt.
					Bernardakis has been tacitly corrected (or altered,
					whichever it may be) in a good many places. This
					has been done consistently when both E and <foreign lang="greek">Β</foreign>
					agree with Wyttenbach's and Hutten's silence ; Bernardakis's silence, unfortunately, appears to have no
					significance.
				</p>
            <p>
					The work is no. 90 in the catalogue of Lamprias.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.231"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Is there, then, Favorinus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the introduction to this essay.</note> an active principle or
					substance of Cold (as fire is of Heat) through the
					presence of which and through participation in which
					everything else becomes cold? Or is coldness rather
					a negation of warmth, as they say darkness is of light
					and rest of motion? Cold, indeed, seems to have the
					quality of being stationary, as heat has that of motion;
					while the cooling off of hot things is not caused by the
					presence of any force,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As, for instance, the force of fire.</note> but merely by the displacement of heat, for it can be seen to depart completely
					at the same time as the remainder cools off. The
					steam, for example, which boiling water emits, is
					expelled in company with the departing heat; that
					is why the amount becomes less by cooling off; for
					this removes the heat and nothing else takes its place.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>First of all, must we not be wary of one point in
					this argument ? It eliminates many obvious forces
					by considering them not to be qualities or properties,
					but merely the negation of qualities or properties,
					weight being the negation of lightness and hardness
					that of softness, black that of white, and bitter that
					of sweet, and so in any other case where there is a
					natural opposition of forces rather than a relation
					of positive and negative. Another point is that all
					negation is inert and unproductive : blindness, for
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.233"/>
					
					example, and deafness, silence or death. Here you
					have the defection of a definite form and the annihilation of a reality, not something that is in itself a part
					of nature or reality. It is the nature of coldness,
					however, to produce affects and alterations in bodies
					that it enters no less than those caused by heat.
					Many objects can be frozen solid, or become condensed or made viscous, by cold.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As steam is condensed and oil becomes viscous.</note> Moreover, the
					property whereby coldness promotes rest and resists
					motion is not inert, but acts by pressure and resistance. being constrictive and preservative because of
					its strength. This explains how, though negation is a
					disappearance and departure of the contrary force,
					many things may yet become<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The verb is ambiguous: <q direct="unspecified">become cold</q> or <q direct="unspecified">dry</q> or perhaps <q direct="unspecified">congealed.</q>
               </note> cold while all the time
					containing within themselves considerable warmth.
					There are even some objects which cold solidifies and
					consolidates the more readily the hotter they are :
					steel, for example, plunged in water. The Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 1052 f; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 134, 222; and see Hartman's explanation, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, p. 566. Von Arnim thinks that the next five chapters also contain Stoic material.</note> also
					affirm that in the bodies of infant children the breath is
					tempered by cooling and, from being a physical substance, becomes a soul. This, however, is debatable ;
					yet since there are many other effects which may be
					seen to be produced through the agency of cold, we
					are not justified in regarding it as a negation.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Besides, a negation does not permit degrees of
					less or more. Surely nobody will affirm that one blind
					man is blinder than another, or one dumb man more
					silent than another, or one corpse deader than its
					fellow ; but among cold things there is a wide range
					of deviation from much to little, from very cold to not
					very, and, generally speaking, in degrees of intensity
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.235"/>
					
					and remission, just as there is in hot things. This
					occurs because the matter involved is in different cases
					acted upon by the opposing forces with more or less
					intensity ; it thus exhibits degrees of one or the other,
					and so of hot and cold. There is, in fact, no such
					thing as a blending of positive qualities with negative
					ones, nor may any positive force accept the assault
					of the negation that corresponds to it or take it into
					partnership ; instead it gives place to it. Now hot
					things do admit a blending with cold up to a point,
					just as do black with white, high notes with low, sweet
					tastes with sour ; and this harmonious association
					of colours and sounds, drugs and sauces, produces
					many combinations that are pleasant and grateful
					to the senses.
				</p>
            <p>
					For the opposition of a negation to a positive
					quality is an irreconcilable hostility, since the existence of the one is the annihilation of the other. The
					other opposition, however, of positive forces, if it
					occurs in due measure, is often operative in the arts,
					and very often indeed in various phenomena of
					nature, especially in connexion with the weather
					and the seasons and those matters from which the
					god derives his title of harmonizer and musician,
					because he organizes and regulates them. He does
					not receive these names merely for bringing sounds
					of high and low pitch, or black and white colours, into
					harmonious fellowship, but because he has authority
					over the association and disunion of heat and cold in
					the universe, to see that they observe due measure
					in their combination and separation, and because, by
					eliminating the excess of either, he brings both into
					proper order.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Furthermore, we find that cold can be perceived
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.237"/>
					
					as well as heat; but mere negation cannot be seen or
					heard or touched or recognized by the other senses.
					Perception, in fact, must be of something existent;
					but where nothing existent is observed, privation may
					be inferred, being the negation of existence, as blindness is of sight, silence of sound, void and emptiness
					of matter. We cannot perceive a void by touch ; but
					where no matter can be touched, void is inferred.
					Nor can we hear silence ; yet, even though we hear
					nothing, we infer silence. Nor, in the same way, is
					sense active when things are unseen or bare<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As, when a hill has been stripped of timber, you cannot see the trees.</note>; there
					is, rather, inference from the negation of perception.
					If, therefore, cold were a privation of warmth, we
					ought not to be able to feel it, but only to infer it
					from the deficiency in warmth ; but if cold is perceived by the contraction and condensation of our
					flesh (just as heat is by the warming and loosening
					of it), clearly there is some special first principle and
					source of coldness, just as there is of heat.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>And yet another point: privation of any sort is
					something simple and uncomplicated, whereas substances have many differences and powers. Silence,
					for example, is of only one kind, while sound varies,
					sometimes annoying, at other times delighting, the
					perception. Both colours and figures show the same
					variation, for they produce different effects on different occasions when they meet the eye ; but that
					which cannot be touched and is without colour or any
					quality whatever, admits no difference, but is always
					the same.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Is cold, then, so like this sort of privation that
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.239"/>
					
					it produces no effects that differ ? Or is the contrary
					true : Do not great and useful pleasures accrue to
					our bodies from the presence of cold, as well as mighty
					detriments and pains and depressions, before which
					the heat does not always depart and quit the field ?
					Often, rather, though cut off within, it makes a stand
					and gives battle. This struggle of hot and cold is
					called shivering or shaking ; and if heat is overcome,
					freezing and torpor set in ; but if cold is defeated,
					there is diffused through the body a relaxed and
					pleasantly warm sensation which Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See, <hi rend="italics">e.g., Odyssey</hi>, vi. 156; <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxiii. 598, 600; and <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 454 d, 735 f.</note> calls <q direct="unspecified">to
						be aglow.</q> Surely these facts are obvious to everyone ; and it is chiefly by these effects that cold is
					shown to be in opposition to heat, not as a negation
					or privation, but as one substance or one state<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Heat, for example, may be said to be a <q direct="unspecified">state</q> or condition of metal.</note> to
					another : it is not a mere destruction or abolition of
					heat, but a positive substance or force. Otherwise
					we might just as well exclude winter from the list
					of seasons or the northerly blasts from that of winds,
					on the pretext that they are only a deficiency of hot
					weather or southerly gales and have no proper origin
					of their own.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Furthermore, given four primary bodies in the
					universe<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, pp. 315 ff., Empedocles, frag. B 17. The doctrine is clearly stated by, for example, Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ii. 10. The author of the <hi rend="italics">Epinomis</hi> (981 c) adds a fifth element, aether (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 951 d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>).</note> which, because of their quantity, simplicity, and potentiality, most judges regard as being
					the elements or first principles of everything else - 
					I mean fire, water, air, and earth - the number of
					primary, simple qualities must be the same. And
					what should these be but warmth and cold, dryness
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.241"/>
					
					and moisture, which by their very nature cause all
					the elements to act and be acted upon?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Post translates his emendation: <q direct="unspecified">by which all things are qualified through the natural action of the elements,</q> pointing out that elements have nothing but size, shape, and motion. Fire causes heat, but its atoms are not themselves hot.</note> Just as in
					grammar we have elements long and short and in
					music elements high and low in pitch - and in neither
					case is one element merely a negation of the other - 
					so also in physical bodies we must assume an elementary opposition of wet to dry and cold to hot, and
					in this way we shall be faithful both to logic and to
					experience. Or are we, as old Anaximenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 95; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diller, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, lxvii, pp. 35 f.</note> maintained, to leave neither hot nor cold in the realm of
					being, but to treat them as states belonging equally
					to any matter and occurring as a result of changes
					within it ? He affirms, in fact, that anything which
					undergoes contraction and condensation of matter
					is cold, while anything that suffers rarefaction and
					distention - this comes close to his own phrasing - is
					hot. So there is no contradiction in the remark that
					the man blew both hot and cold,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aesop's <hi rend="italics">Fables</hi> (no. 60 in Chambry's Bude edition, vol. i, pp. 131 ff.), where the satyr renounces friendship with the man because the latter blows both hot and cold through the same mouth.</note> for breath grows
					cold when it is compressed and condensed by the lips ;
					but when it is expelled from the mouth left slack, it
					becomes hot through rarefaction. Aristotle,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the note on 950 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>) <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, xxxiv. 7 (964 a 10 ff.); contrast Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 79 a-c.</note> however, holds that in this Anaximenes was mistaken :
					when the mouth is slack, what is exhaled is warm air
					from our own bodies ; but when we compress the
					lips and blow, it is not air from ourselves, but the cold
					air in front of the mouth that is propelled forward and
					makes contact.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.243"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Perhaps we should now leave the question
					whether heat and cold are substances ; if so, let us
					advance the argument to the next point and inquire
					what sort of substance coldness has, and what is its
					first principle and nature. Now those who affirm
					that there are certain uneven, triangular formations
					in our bodies<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 53 c, 54 b-c.</note> and that shivering and trembling,
					shuddering and the like manifestations, proceed from
					this rough irregularity, even if they are wrong in the
					particulars, at least derive the first principle from
					the proper place ; for the investigation should begin,
					as it were from the very hearth,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or, perhaps, <q direct="unspecified">with Hestia,</q> as the first principle of the cosmos (see, for example, Ritter, on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 247 a, pp. 123-124 of his edition). This passage is somewhat obscurely quoted below in 954 f. There were already three different interpretations known to the scholiast on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Euthyphro</hi>, 3 a (p. 2, ed. Greene).</note> from the substance
					of all things. This is, it would seem, the great difference between a philosopher and a physician or a
					farmer or a flute-player ; for the latter are content
					to examine the causes most remote from the first
					cause, since as soon as the most immediate cause of
					an effect is grasped - that fever is brought about by
					exertion or an overflow of blood, that rusting of grain
					is caused by days of blazing sun after a rain, that a
					low note is produced by the angle and construction
					of the pipes - that is enough to enable a technician
					to do his proper job. But when the natural philosopher sets out to find the truth as a matter of speculative knowledge, the discovery of immediate causes
					is not the end, but the beginning of his journey to
					the first and highest causes. This is the reason why
					Plato and Democritus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wyttenbach suggested <q direct="unspecified">Xenocrates</q> for <q direct="unspecified">Democritus</q> in this passage, which may be right, though his proposal is not considered by either Mullach or Heinze.</note> when they were inquiring
					into the causes of heat and heaviness, were right not
					to stop their investigation with earth and fire, but
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.245"/>
					
					to go on carrying back sensible phenomena to rational
					origins until they reached, as it were, the minimum
					number of seeds.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Nevertheless it is better for us first to attack
					things perceptible to the senses,in which Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 319, frag. B 21, part of which is quoted below in 949 f.</note>
					and Strato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Fritz Wehrli, <hi rend="italics">Die Schule des Aristoteles</hi>, Part V. frag. 49.</note> and the Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 952 c, 1053 f; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 140 f.</note> locate the substances
					that underlie the qualities, the Stoics ascribing the
					primordially cold to the air, Empedocles and Strato
					to water ; and someone else may, perhaps, be found
					to affirm that earth is the original substance of coldness.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As Plutarch himself: see below, 952 c ff. (chapters 17-22).</note> But let us examine Stoic doctrine before the
					others.
				</p>
            <p>
					Since fire is not only warm but bright, the opposite
					natural entity (they say) must be both cold and dark :
					as gloomy is the opposite of bright, so is cold of hot.
					Besides, as darkness confounds the sight, so cold
					confuses the sense of touch. Heat, on the other hand,
					transmits the sensation of touching, as brightness
					does that of seeing. It follows, then, that in nature
					the primordially dark is also the primordially cold ;
					and that it is air which is primordially dark does not,
					in fact, escape the notice of the poets since they use
					the term <q direct="unspecified">air</q> for <q direct="unspecified">darkness</q>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thick air lay all about the ships, nor could
					</l>
                  <l>The moon shine forth from heaven.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, ix. 144-145. Words for <q direct="unspecified">air</q> in Homer often mean <q direct="unspecified">mist</q> or <q direct="unspecified">fog.</q>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And another instance :
					<quote rend="blockquote">So clad in air they visit all the earth.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 255.</note>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.247"/>
					
					And another:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The air at once he scattered and dispelled the mist;
					</l>
                  <l>The sun shone forth and all the battle carne in view.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xvii. 649-650.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					They also call the lightless air <hi rend="italics">knephas</hi>, being as it
					were, <hi rend="italics">kenon phaous</hi> 
               <q direct="unspecified">void of light</q> ; and collected
					and condensed air has been termed <hi rend="italics">nephos</hi> 
               <q direct="unspecified">cloud</q>
					because it is a negation of light.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch's etymologies here are no more scientific or convincing than those to be found in his <hi rend="italics">Roman Questions</hi>, L.C.L. vol. iv, pp. 6-171.</note> Flecks in the sky
					and mist and fog and anything else that does not
					provide a transparent medium for light to reach our
					senses are merely variations of air ; and its invisible
					and colourless part is called Hades and Acheron.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Invisible</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 953 a below and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 403 a ff.; <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 81 c-d and contrast <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 942 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; <q direct="unspecified">colourless,</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">achroston, Acheron. Cf.</hi> L. Parmentier, <q direct="unspecified">Recherches sur le traite d'Isis et d'Osiris de Plut.,</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Mem. Acad. Belg.</hi> ii. 2 (1912/13), pp. 71 ff.</note> In
					the same way, then, as air is dark when light is gone,
					so when heat departs the residue is cold air and
					nothing else. And this is the reason why it has been
					termed Tartarus because of its coldness. Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 119; contrast Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 112 a ff.</note>
					makes this obvious when he writes <q direct="unspecified">murky Tartarus</q> ; and to shake and shiver with cold is to
					<q direct="unspecified">tartarize.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Servius on Vergil, <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi> vi. 577.</note> Such, then, is the reason for these
					names.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Since corruption, in each case, is a change of
					the things that are corrupted into their opposites,
					let us see whether the saying holds good that <q direct="unspecified">the
						death of fire is the birth of air.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 168, Heraclitus, frag. 76 (frag. 25, ed. Bywater, p. 11). <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 392 c-d.</note> Fire, indeed,
					perishes like a living creature,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 281 f, 702 e-f; 703 b.</note> being either extinguished by main force or dying out of itself. Now
					if it is extinguished, that makes the change of fire
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.249"/>
					
					into air more conspicuous. Smoke, in fact, is a form
					of air, as is reek and exhalation, which, to quote
					Pindar,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Isth.</hi> iv. 112.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Stabs at the air with unctuous smoke.</quote>
					Nevertheless, even when fire goes out for lack of
					nourishment, one may see, as for instance in the case
					of lamps, the apex of the flame passing off into murky,
					dusky air. Moreover, the vapour ascending from our
					bodies when, after a bath or sweat, cold water is
					poured on them, sufficiently illustrates the change
					of heat, as it perishes, into the air ; and this implies
					that it is the natural opposite of fire. From this the
					Stoics drew the conclusion that air was primordially
					dark and cold.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Moreover, freezing, which is the most extreme
					and violent effect of cold in bodies, is a condition
					of water, but a function of air. For water of itself is
					fluid, uncongealed and not cohesive ; but when it is
					compressed by air because of its cold state, it becomes
					taut and compact. This is the reason for the saying<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Included without authority among Callimachus's fragments (787 = anon. 384) by Schneider, but rejected by Pfeiffer.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">If Southwind challenges North, instantly snow will appear.</quote>
					For after the Southwind has collected the moisture
					as raw material, the Boreal air takes over and congeals it. This is particularly evident in snowfields :
					when they have discharged a preliminary exhalation
					of air that is thin and cold, they melt.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 691 f and Hubert's references <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
               </note> Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 212, ed. Rose and <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 695 d.</note>
					also declares that whetstones of lead will melt and
					become fluid in the wintertime through excess of cold
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.251"/>
					
					when no water is anywhere near them ; it seems
					probable that the air with its coldness forces the
					bodies together until it crushes and breaks them.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There is here probably a confusion of lead and tin, for both of which the term <hi rend="italics">stannum</hi> is used in Latin. Tin is reduced to powder by severe cold, owing to transformation to its allotrope. In [Aristotle], <hi rend="italics">De Mir. Ausc.</hi> 50 (p. 257, L.C.L.) the more nearly correct statement appears that tin melts in severe cold. This note is due to the suggestion of O. T. Benfey of Haverford College.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Furthermore, portions of water will freeze
					sooner than the spring from which they are drawn,
					for the air more readily masters the smaller amount.
					If you will draw from a well cold water in a jar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably Plutarch is thinking of a jar of porous earthenware, such as are commonly used to cool water in the Near East.</note> and
					let it down again into the well in such a way that the
					jar does not touch the water, but is suspended in the
					air, and if you wait a short time, you will find that the
					water has become colder.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 b-e.</note> This is very good evidence
					that the First Cause of coldness is not water but air.
					Certainly, none of the great rivers freezes through
					its entire depth ; for the air does not penetrate down
					into the whole, but merely renders stationary as
					much as, by contact and proximity, it includes within
					the range of its coldness. And this is the reason why
					barbarians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Thracians, according to 968 f ff. <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 103; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 24; xiv. 26.</note> do not cross frozen rivers until they have
					tried them out with foxes : if the ice is not thick, but
					merely superficial, the foxes perceive this by the
					sound of the current running underneath and return
					to the bank. Some even catch fish by weakening and
					softening the ice with hot water - enough of the ice,
					at least, to admit their lines ; so the cold has no effect
					at a depth. Yet the water near the surface undergoes
					so great a change through freezing that ships are
					crushed by it when it is forced in on itself and squeezed
					tight, as those relate who recently passed the winter
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.253"/>
					
					with Caesar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably the reference is to Trajan and the Second Dacian War (a.d. 105-107). Plutarch's intimate friends, Sosius Senecio, is known to have taken part in it.</note> on the Danube. Nevertheless, what
					happens in our own case is ample testimony : after
					warm baths and sweats we are cooler, since our bodies
					are relaxed and porous, so that we take in a good deal
					of cold along with the air.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 c-d.</note> The same thing happens
					to water, too : it freezes faster when it has first been
					heated, thus becoming more susceptible to air ; and
					those who draw off boiling water and suspend it in
					the air do this, surely, only to secure the admixture
					of great quantities of air.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 c-d.</note> So now, Favorinus, the
					argument that attributes the primal force of cold to
					the air depends on such plausibilities as these.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>But the argument which attributes it to water
					finds in the same way facts to support it; Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 319, frag. B 21, lines 3 and 5. Plutarch apparently used a version different from those known to Aristotle and Simplicius. The evidence is complicated and may be consulted in Diels-Kranz. On Empedocles' meaning see Cherniss, <hi rend="italics">Aristotle's Criticism of the Presocratics</hi>, p. 110.</note> says something like this :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Behold the sun, everywhere bright and warm;
					</l>
                  <l>And then the rain, to all men dark and cold.</l>
               </quote>
					By thus setting cold against hot, as he does dark
					against bright, he has given us to understand that
					dark and cold belong to the same substance, as do
					also bright and hot. And our senses bear witness
					that darkness is an attribute of water, not of air, since
					nothing, to put it simply, is blackened by air and
					everything is by water.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 364 b.</note> For if you throw the whitest
					wool or the whitest garment into water, it will come
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.255"/>
					
					out black and it will remain black until the moisture
					is evaporated by heat or is squeezed out by some sort
					of wringing or pressure. When a patch of ground is
					sprinkled, the spots which are covered by the drops
					turn black, but the rest remains as it was. In fact,
					of water itself the deepest looks the darkest because
					there is so much of it, while those parts that lie near
					the air flash and sparkle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 952 f <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; and of the other liquids
					oil is the most transparent, as containing the most
					air. A proof of this is its lightness, by reason of which
					it maintains itself on the surface of all other things,
					buoyed up by the air.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 696 b, 702 b.</note> If it is sprinkled upon the
					waves, it will calm the sea, not because it is so smooth
					that the winds slip off it, as Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, 961 a 23 ff., though this work is surely not by Aristotle in the form in which it has come down to us.</note> affirmed ; but
					because the waves are dissipated when they are
					struck by any moist substance. But it is peculiar to
					oil that it provides light and sight at the bottom since
					the moist elements are interspersed with air ; it is,
					in fact, not only on the surface that it provides light
					for those who pass the night at sea ; it does so also
					for sponge-divers<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 981 e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 638 ff.</note> below the surface when it is blown
					out of their mouths. Air, therefore, has no greater
					proportion of darkness than water has, and it has
					less cold. Certainly oil, which has more air than any
					other moist substance, is least cold; and when it
					freezes, it forms a soft jelly : the air that is intermixed
					does not permit it to freeze hard. They dip needles,
					iron clasps, and all delicate artifacts in oil rather than
					in water, fearing that the water's excessive frigidity
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.257"/>
					
					may distort them. It is, in fact, fairer to judge the
					argument by this evidence than by that of colour,
					since snow and hail and ice are at their brightest when
					they are coldest. Moreover, pitch is both hotter and
					darker than honey.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>I am surprised, nevertheless, when those who
					maintain that the air is cold because it is dark do not
					perceive that others think it must be hot because it
					is light. For darkness is not so closely connected and
					akin to cold as heaviness and stability are ; many
					things, in fact, which have no heat are bright, but
					nothing cold is buoyant, light, and soaring. Why,
					the very clouds, as long as they are akin to the substance of air, float aloft; but as soon as they change to
					moisture, they fall at once and lose their lightness no
					less than their warmth as coldness grows within them.
					Contrariwise, when heat supervenes, they reverse
					the movement again, for their substance begins to
					soar as soon as it has changed to air.
				</p>
            <p>
					Nor is the argument from destruction true either ;
					for when anything is destroyed, it does not perish by
					becoming its opposite, though it does perish by the
					action of its opposite, as fire, for instance, is changed
					by water into air. For of water Aeschylus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> pp. 107-108, frag. 360.</note> speaks
					in tragic style, but accurately, as
					<quote rend="blockquote">The riot-quelling justicer of fire.</quote>
					And when Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxi. 330-383; 435-469. The river is the Xanthus.</note> matched Hephaestus against the
					river and Apollo against Poseidon in the battle, he
					did it rather as a philosopher than as a poet. And
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.259"/>
					
					Archilochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, i. 237, frag. 86; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi> (L.C.L.), ii, p. 146, frag. 93; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 1070 a, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demetrius</hi>, 35 (905 e).</note> expressed himself well on a woman
					who was of two minds :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>With guileful thoughts she bore
					</l>
                  <l>In one hand water, in the other fire.</l>
               </quote>
					Among the Persians it was the most compelling plea
					to gain an end, one which would admit no refusal, if
					the suppliant took fire, stood in a river, and threatened
					that if he lost his suit, he would drop the fire into the
					water. Now he got what he asked, but though he
					did so, he was punished for the threat, on the ground
					that it was contrary to law and against nature. Again,
					the familiar proverb that is on everyone's lips,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But, curiously enough, not to be found in the <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi Graeci</hi>, as edited by Leutsch and Schneidewin.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">to
						mix fire with water,</q> as an example of the impossible,
					seems to bear witness that water is hostile to fire,
					which is destroyed by it and so is punished by being
					extinguished<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the quotation from Aeschylus <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 950 e.</note>; it is not so affected by air, which, on
					the contrary, supports fire and welcomes it in its
					changed form. For if anything into which the thing
					destroyed changes is its opposite, why will fire, any
					more than water, seem opposite to air ? For air
					changes into water by condensation, and into fire by
					rarefaction just as, on the other hand, water vanishes
					into air by rarefaction, but into earth by condensation.
					Now these processes take place, in my opinion, not
					because these elements are contrary or hostile to one
					another, but because they are in close affinity and relationship. But my opponents,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably those who, in 950 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, claim that air is cold because it is dark.</note> whichever way they
					state their case, ruin their proof. Certainly it is perfectly
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.261"/>
					
					absurd for them to say that water is frozen by air
					when they have never seen air itself freezing. For
					clouds, mists, and flecks in the sky are not congelations, but condensations and thickenings of air that is
					moist and vaporous. But waterless, dry air never
					admits loss of heat to the point where such a change
					might occur. There are, in fact, mountains which do
					not know clouds or dew or mist because their peaks
					reach a region of pure air that has no humidity at all.
					From this fact it is especially obvious that it is the
					condensation and density below that contribute to air
					the cold, moist element that is found in combination
					with it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>It is reasonable that the lower portion of large
					rivers should not freeze ; for the upper portion, being
					frozen, does not transmit the exhalation which is,
					accordingly, shut in and turned back, and so provides
					heat for the deep waters. A demonstration of this
					is the fact that when the ice melts again a great
					quantity of vapour rises from the waters. This is also
					the reason why the bodies of animals are warmer in
					the winter, because the heat is driven inwards by the
					cold from without and they keep it within them.
				</p>
            <p>
					Now drawing off water and suspending it in the
					air<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 949 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 690 b-e.</note> not only takes away its warmth, but its coldness
					also; those, therefore, who want a very cold drink
					take care not to disturb the snowpacks<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 691 c - 692 a for snow packed in chaff and the like.</note> or the wet
					matter that is formed from them by compression,
					for movement expels both heat and cold.
				</p>
            <p>
					That such a function of cold belongs not to air, but
					to water, may be demonstrated as follows from a fresh
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.263"/>
					
					start. In the first place, it is improbable that air,
					which lies adjacent to the aether<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the difference between <hi rend="italics">aer</hi> and <hi rend="italics">aether</hi> see the lucid discussion of Guthrie, <hi rend="italics">The Greeks and their Gods</hi>, pp. 207 f.</note> and touches and is
					touched by the revolving fiery substance, should have
					a force that is contrary to that of aether. For one
					thing, it is impossible for two substances whose boundaries touch and are contiguous not to be acted upon
					by each other - and if acted upon, for the weaker not
					to be contaminated by the force that resides in the
					stronger. Nor is it reasonable to suppose that Nature
					has placed side by side destroyer and victim, as though
					she were the author of strife and dissension, not of
					union and harmony. She does, indeed, make use of
					opposites to constitute the universe ; yet she does
					not employ them without a tempering element, or
					where they will collide. She disposes them rather
					so that a space is skipped and an inserted strip duly
					assigned whereby they will not destroy one another,
					but may enjoy communication and co-operation. And
					this strip is occupied by air, suffused as it is through
					a space under the fire<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, the aether. See also Cherniss, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 126.</note> between it and water. It
					makes distribution both ways and receives contributions from both, being itself neither hot nor cold, but
					a blending and union of the two. When these are so
					fused, they meet without injury and the fused matter
					sends forth or takes to itself the opposing extremes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Heat and cold.</note>
					without violence.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Then, too, air is everywhere equal; though
					neither winter nor cold is identical everywhere. It
					is no accident that some parts of the world are cold
					and damp, while others are hot and dry ; it is due
					to the existence of a single substance that includes
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.265"/>
					
					coldness and wetness in one. The greater part of
					Africa is hot and without water ; while those who
					have travelled through Scythia, Thrace, and Pontus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch may be thinking of the old kingdom of Pontus, which included tracts south, east, and north of the Black Sea.</note>
					report that these regions have great lakes or marshes
					and are traversed by many deep rivers. As for the
					regions that lie between, those that are near lakes
					and marshes are especially cold because of the exhalations from the water, Posidonius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The fragment has not yet been numbered in L. Edelstein's forthcoming collection; for the literature see <hi rend="italics">A.J.P.</hi> lvii (1936), p. 301 and n. 61.</note> then, in
					affirming that the freshness and moistness of marsh
					air is the reason for the cold, has done nothing to
					disturb the plausibility of the argument; he has,
					rather, made it more plausible. For fresh air would
					not always seem colder if cold did not take its origin
					from moisture. So Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, v. 469.</note> spoke more truly when
					he affirmed
					<quote rend="blockquote">The river-air blows chill before the dawn,</quote>
					thereby indicating the source of coldness.
				</p>
            <p>
					Our senses, moreover, often deceive us and we
					imagine, when we touch cold garments or cold wool,
					that we are touching moist objects : this is because
					wet and cold have a common substance and their
					natures have a close affinity and relationship. In very
					cold climates the low temperature often breaks
					vessels whether they are of bronze or of clay - not,
					of course, when they are empty, but only when they
					are full and the water exerts pressure by means of
					its coldness. Theophrastus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The fragment is apparently omitted by Wimmer.</note> to be sure, declares that
					the air breaks these vessels, using the liquid as a
					spike. But take care<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This seems to be addressed to Favorinus's Peripatetic sympathies.</note> that there isn't more wit than
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.267"/>
					
					truth in such a remark! For if it were so, vessels full
					of pitch or of milk would more readily be broken by
					the air.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, than those full of water.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Water, however, seems to be cold of itself, and
					primordially so. It is the antithesis, in its coldness,
					to the heat of fire, just as in its wetness to the dryness
					of fire, and in its heaviness to the other's lightness.
					To sum up : fire is of a disintegrating and separative
					nature, while water is adhesive and retentive, holding
					and gluing together by means of its moistness.
					Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 318, frag. B 19. Plutarch seems to have mistaken Empedocles' meaning, though some would invoke frag. B 34. In general, while Plutarch is said to have written ten books on Empedocles (Lamprias catalogue no. 43), he does not seek the difficult poet's meaning very carefully.</note> alluded to this, when, as often as he
					mentioned them, he termed Fire a <q direct="unspecified">Destructive
						Strife</q> and Water <q direct="unspecified">Tenacious Love.</q> For the
					nourishment of fire is that which can be changed
					into fire and only things that have affinity and a
					close relationship to it can be so changed ; while
					its opposites, like water, are not easily changed to
					fire. Water itself is practically incombustible, and it
					renders matter such as damp grass and moist timber
					very hard to consume ; the greenness in them produces a dusky, dull flame because, by dint of cold, it
					struggles against heat as against its natural enemy.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Now you must pursue the subject by comparing
					these arguments with those of my opponents. For
					Chrysippus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, p. 140; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 1053 e.</note> thinking that the air is primordially
					cold because it is also dark, merely mentioned those
					who affirm that water is at a greater distance from the
					aether<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 951 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> than is air ; and, wishing to make them some
					answer, he said, <q direct="unspecified">If so, we might as well declare that
						even earth is primordially cold because it is at the
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.269"/>
						
						greatest distance from the aether</q> - tossing off this
					argument as if it were utterly inadmissible and absurd.
					But I have a mind to maintain the thesis that earth
					too is not destitute of probable and convincing arguments, and I shall start with the one that Chrysippus
					has found most serviceable for air. And what is this ?
					Why, that it is primordially dark and cold. For if he
					takes these two pairs of opposing forces and assumes
					that one must of necessity accompany the other,
					there are, surely, innumerable oppositions and antipathies between the aether and the earth with which
					one might suppose this to be consistent. For it
					is not only opposed as heavy to light and as moving
					by gravity downwards, not upwards, or as dense
					to rare or as slow and stable to mobile and active,
					but as heaviest to lightest and as densest to rarest
					and, finally, as immovable of itself to self-moving,
					and as occupying the central position in the universe
					to revolving forever around a centre. It is not absurd,
					then, if oppositions so numerous and important carry
					with them the opposition of cold and heat as well.
					<q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> Chrysippus may say, <q direct="unspecified">but fire is bright.</q>
					Is not the earth, then, dark ? Why, it is the darkest
					and most unilluminated of all things. Certainly air
					is first of all to participate in light; it is instantly
					altered and when it is saturated, it distributes
					illumination everywhere, lending itself to light as a
					body in which to reside. For when the sun arises,
					as one of the dithyrambic writers<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, ii. 302; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi> (L.C.L.), iii, p. 460 (adespota no. 95).</note> has said,
					<quote rend="blockquote">It straightway fills the mighty home of the air-borne winds.</quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.271"/>
					
					Next the air, moving downward, infuses a part of its
					brightness into the lakes and the sea, and the depths
					of the rivers flash brightly,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Prometheus</hi>, 90, and 950 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> to the extent that air
					is able to penetrate them. Of all bodies only the
					earth remains constantly without light, impenetrable
					to the illumination of sun or moon ; yet it is warmed
					by them and permits the heat to sink in and warm
					it up to a slight depth. But because it is solid, earth
					does not give passage to light, but is encircled by
					light on its surface only, while the inner parts are
					called Darkness and Chaos and Hades<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Invisible Place, according to the etymology adopted above in 948 f.</note> - so that
					Erebus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 125. The original meaning of Erebus is actually <q direct="unspecified">darkness</q>.</note> turns out to be the subterranean and interior
					darkness. Then, too, the poets tell us that Night
					was born of Earth<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 331, Empedocles, frag. B 48; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 1006 f.</note> and mathematicians demonstrate
					that night is the shadow of Earth blocking the light
					of the sun. The air, indeed, is saturated with darkness by the earth, just as it is with light by the sun.
					The unlighted portion of the air is the area of night,
					amounting to the space occupied by the earth's
					shadow. This is the reason why men make use of the
					air out of doors even when it is night, as well as many
					beasts which do their pasturing in the darkness, since
					it retains some vestiges of light and dispersed glimmerings of radiance ; but the house-bound man who
					is under a roof is utterly blind and without light
					inasmuch as there the earth envelops him from all
					directions. Whole skins, furthermore, and horns of
					animals do not let light pass through them because
					of their solidity ; yet if sections are sawed off and
					polished, they become translucent when once the
					air has been mixed with them. It is also my opinion
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.273"/>
					
					that the earth is called black by the poets,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, ii. 699; Alcman, 36 (Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, i, p. 76; Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, ii. 27); Sappho, 38 (Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> i, p. 208).</note> whenever
					they have occasion to do so, because of its murky and
					lightless characteristics. The result, then, of these
					considerations is that the much-prized antithesis of
					light and darkness belongs to earth rather than to air.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>This, however, has no relevance to the question
					under discussion ; for it has been shown that there
					are many cold objects which are bright and many
					hot which are dull and dark. Yet there are qualities
					more closely connected that belong to coldness :
					heaviness, stability, solidity, and resistance to change.
					Air has no part at all in them, while earth has a greater
					share in all of them than water has. Cold, moreover,
					is perceptibly one of the hardest of things and it
					makes things hard and unyielding. Theophrastus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 184 Wimmer.</note>
					for instance, tells us that when frozen fish are dropped
					on the ground, they are broken and smashed to bits
					just like objects of glass or earthenware. And at
					Delphi you yourself heard, in the case of those who
					climbed Parnassus to rescue the Thyiades<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Thyiades were Attic women, devotees of Dionysus, who went every other year to Delphi to join in the midwinter festival. See Guthrie, <hi rend="italics">The Greeks and their Gods</hi>, p. 178.) The rites must have involved considerable discomfort and even risk, as Dodds says (edition of Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Bacchae</hi>, p. xi).</note> when
					they were trapped by a fierce gale and snowstorm,
					that their capes were frozen so stiff and wooden that
					when they were opened out, they broke and split
					apart. Excessive cold, because of its hardness and
					immobility, also stiffens the muscles and renders the
					tongue speechless, for it congeals the moist and
					tender parts of the body.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.275"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>In view of these considerations, regard the
					facts in the following light : every force, presumably,
					whenever it prevails, by a law of nature changes and
					turns into itself whatever it overcomes. What is
					mastered by heat is reduced to flames, what is
					mastered by wind turns to air ; and anything that
					falls into the water, unless it gets out quickly, dissolves and liquefies. It follows, then, that whatever
					is completely frozen must turn into primordial cold.
					Now freezing is extreme refrigeration that terminates
					in a complete alteration and petrifaction when, since
					the cold has obtained complete mastery, the moist
					elements are frozen solid and the heat is squeezed
					out. This is the reason why the earth at its bottommost point is practically all solid frost and ice. For
					there undiluted and unmitigated cold abides at bay,
					thrust back to the point farthest removed from the
					flaming aether.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 951 d above.</note> As for these features that are
					visible, cliffs and crags and rocks, Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 296, frag. A 69; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 691 b and Hubert's references <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
               </note> thinks
					that they have been fixed in place and are upheld by
					resting on the fire that burns in the depths of the
					earth ; but the indications are rather that all these
					things from which the heat was squeezed out and
					evaporated were completely frozen by the cold ; and
					for this reason they are called <hi rend="italics">pagoi</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Crags and rocks are called <hi rend="italics">pagoi</hi> (as the Areo-pagus, <q direct="unspecified">Mars Hill,</q> at Athens), which Plutarch correctly connects with the verb meaning <q direct="unspecified">freeze</q> or <q direct="unspecified">solidify</q> and uses to confute Empedocles.</note> So also the
					peaks<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch is speaking of volcanoes like Aetna with a lava bed on top.</note> of many of them have a black crust where the
					heat has been expelled and have the appearance of
					debris from a conflagration. For the cold freezes
					substances to a varying degree, but hardest those of
					which it is naturally a primary constituent. Thus, if
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.277"/>
					
					it is the nature of heat to lighten, the lightest object
					will have most heat, and if it is the nature of humidity
					to soften, the softest will have the most humidity ;
					so, if it is also true that the nature of cold is to harden,
					then it must also follow that the hardest object will
					have the most cold - that is to say, just as the earth
					has. But what is coldest by nature is surely also
					primarily cold, so that the earth is in fact cold both
					primordially and naturally ; and, of course, this is
					obvious even to the senses. Mud, in fact, is a colder
					thing than water ; and men extinguish a fire by
					dumping earth upon it. Blacksmiths, when their iron
					becomes fiery and begins to melt, sprinkle on it marble
					chips and gypsum to check and cool it off before it
					melts too much. It is also true that dust cools the
					bodies of athletes and dries up their sweat.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>And what is the meaning of our demand for
					a yearly change of habitation ? In winter we retreat
					to the loftiest parts of our houses, those farthest from
					the earth, while in summer we require the lower parts,
					submerging ourselves and going in quest of comfortable retreats, as we make the best of a life in the
					embrace of mother earth. Since we do this, are we
					not guided to the earth by our perception of its coldness ? Do we not acknowledge it as the natural seat
					of primordial cold ? And surely our living by the sea
					in the winter is, in a way, an escape from the earth,
					since we abandon the land as far as possible because
					of the frost and wrap ourselves in salt sea air because
					it is warm. Then again, in the summer by reason of
					the heat, we long for the earth-born, upland air, not
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.279"/>
					
					because it is itself chilly, but because it has sprung
					from the naturally and primordially cold and has been
					imbued with its earthy power, as steel is tempered
					by being plunged in water.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 433 a and 946 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> And of flowing waters,
					also, the coldest are those that fall from rocks or
					mountains, and of well waters the deepest are the
					coldest; the air from outside does not, in the case
					of these wells, affect the water, so deep are they,
					while any such streams burst forth through pure unmixed earth, like the one at Taenarum,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch knew that the mouth of Hades was at Taenarum (Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Pythian</hi>, iv. 44) and transferred the Styx to that place. For its water see Frazer on Pausanias, viii. 18. 4. According to Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 158 (ed. Keller) no receptacle except one of horn can contain the water; he adds, <q direct="unspecified">All that taste of it die.</q>
               </note> which they
					call the water of Styx : it flows from the rock in a
					trickle, but so cold that no vessel except an ass's hoof
					can contain it - all others it bursts and breaks apart.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>We are, further, informed by physicians that
					generically earth is by nature astringent and cold,
					and they enumerate many metals that provide a
					styptic, staying effect for medicinal use. The element
					of earth is not sharp or mobile or slender or priekly
					or soft or ductile, but solid and compact like a cube.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 288 e and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 55 d-e.</note>
					This is how it came to have weight; and the cold,
					which is its true power, by thickening, compressing,
					and squeezing out the humidity of bodies, induces
					shivering and shaking through its inequality<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 948 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; and
					if it becomes complete master and expels or extinguishes all the heat, it fixes the body in a frozen
					and corpselike condition. This is the reason why
					earth does not burn at all, or burns only grudgingly
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.281"/>
					
					and with difficulty. Air, on the other hand, often
					shoots forth flames from itself and, turning into fire,
					makes streams and flashes of lightning. Heat feeds
					on moisture,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 649 b, 687 a, 696 b; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Metaphysics</hi>, A 3 (983 b 23 ff.); Pseudo-Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, 949 b 29.</note> for it is not the solid part of wood,
					but the damp part, that is combustible ; and when
					this is distilled, the solid, dry part remains behind,
					reduced to ashes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 696 b.</note> Those who emulously strive to
					prove that this too is changed and consumed, sprinkling it, perhaps, with oil or kneading it with suet and
					setting it alight, accomplish nothing ; for when the
					oily part is consumed, the earthy remains as a permanent residue, do what they may. Not only, therefore, because the earth is physically immovable from
					its station, but also because it is unalterable in essence, it was quite appropriately called Hestia<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 247 a and 948 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> with the note. For earth as Hestia see also Dio Chrys. xxxvi. 46 (L.C.L.) with Crosby's note; Dion. Hal. ii. 66. 3; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Fasti</hi>, vi. 267; Koster, <hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi>, Suppl. iii (1951), p. 7, n. 6.</note> by
					the ancients - in as much as she <q direct="unspecified">remains in the home
						of the gods</q> - because of its stationary and compact
					nature ; and coldness is what binds it together, as
					Archela&uuml;s<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">5</hi>, ii, p. 48.</note> the natural philosopher declared, since
					nothing can relax or soften it, as a substance that is
					subject to heating or warming might be loosened.
				</p>
            <p>
					As for those who suppose that they feel cold air and
					water, but are less sensible of earth's coldness, what
					they perceive is that portion of earth which is closest
					to them and has come to be a medley, a congeries,
					abounding in air and water, sun and heat. There is
					no difference between such people and those who
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.283"/>
					
					declare that the aether<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 951 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> is not naturally and primordially hot, but rather that scalding water or red
					hot iron are - because they can feel and touch these,
					but are unable to touch and feel the primordially
					pure and heavenly fire. Nor likewise are these
					persons able to touch and feel the earth at its bottommost, which is what we particularly mean by earth - 
					earth set off alone by itself, without admixture of any
					other element. But we can see a sample of such
					earthiness in that statement about the cliffs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 954 c-d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that
					display from deep down so intense a cold that it can
					scarcely be endured. Then, too. those who want a
					colder drink throw pebbles into the water,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 f - 691 c.</note> which
					becomes thicker and denser through the coldness that
					streams upward, fresh and undiluted, from the stones.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>We must, therefore, believe that the reason
					why ancient learned men held that there is no commerce between earthly and celestial things was not
					that they distinguished up and down by relative
					position, as we do in the case of scales ; but rather
					it was the difference in powers that led them to assign
					such things as are hot and bright, swift and buoyant,
					to the eternal and imperishable part of nature, while
					darkness and cold and slowness they considered the
					unhappy heritage of transitory and submerged beings.
					Then too, the body of a living creature, as long as it;
					breathes and flourishes, does, as the poets say, enjoy
					both warmth and life<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps some such passage as Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxii. 363 is meant.</note>; but when these forsake it
					and it is abandoned in the realm of earth alone,
					immediately frigidity and congelation seize upon it,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.285"/>
					
					since warmth naturally resides in anything else rather
					than in the earthy.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Compare these statements, Favorinus, with the
					pronouncements of others ; and if these notions of
					mine are neither less probable nor much more plausible than those of others, say farewell to dogma, being
					convinced as you are that it is more philosophic to
					suspend judgement when the truth is obscure than
					to take sides.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the introduction to this essay.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>