<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De garrulitate</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.101">
      <body>
         <head>Of garrulity, or talkativeness</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.220"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>IT is a troublesome and difficult task that philosophy
				undertakes in going about to cure the disease, or rather
				itch, of intemperate rating. For that words, which are
				the sole remedy against it, require attention; but they who
				are given to prate will hear nobody, as being a sort of
				people that love to be always talking themselves. So that
				the principal vice of loquacious persons is this, that their
				ears are stopped to every thing else but their own impertinencies; which I take to be a wilful deafness in men,
				controlling and contradicting Nature, that has given us two
				ears, though but one tongue. Therefore it was that Euripides spoke very right to a certain stupid hearer of his:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Impossible it is to fill that brain,
				</l>
                     <l>That in a moment lets out all again;
				</l>
                     <l>'Tis but the words of wisdom to unfold
				</l>
                     <l>Unto a fool, whose skull will nothing hold.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Frag. 891.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>More justly and truly might I say to an idle prate-too-fast,
					or rather concerning such a fellow:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In vain I seek to fill thy sieve-like brain,
					</l>
                     <l>That in a moment lets out all again;
					</l>
                     <l>Infusing wisdom into such a skull
					</l>
                     <l>As leaks so fast, it never will be full.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Much more may he be said to spill his instructions over
					(rather than pour them into) a man, who is always talking
					to those that do not hear, and never hears when others
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.221"/>
					
					talk. For so soon as a wise man has uttered any thing, be
					it never so short, garrulity swallows it forthwith like the
					sea, and throws it up again threefold, with the violence of
					a swelling tide. Such was the portico at Olympia, called
					Heptaphonos, by the reverberation of one single voice
					causing no less than seven distinct echoes. And in like
					manner, if the least word light into the ears of an impertinent babbler, presently all the room rings with it, and he
					makes such a din,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>That soon the jangling noise untunes the strings
					</l>
                     <l>Of minds sedately fixt on better things.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Insomuch that we may say, that the conduits and conveyances of their hearing reach not to the souls, but only to
					their tongues. Therefore it is that other people retain
					what is spoken to them; whereas, whatever is said to talkative people runs through them as through a cullender;
					and then they run about from place to place, like empty
					vessels void of sense or wit, but making a hideous noise.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>However, in hopes that there is yet some room left
				to try an experiment for the cure of this distemper, let us
				begin with this golden sentence to the impertinent prater
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be silent, boy, and thou wilt find i' th' end,
				</l>
                     <l>What benefits on silent lips attend.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Aleadae of Sophocles, Frag. 79.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Among these benefits two of the first and chiefest are to
					hear and to be heard. To neither of which can these
					talkative companions ever attain; so unhappy they are
					still to meet with disappointments, though they desire a
					thing never so much. For as for those other distempers
					of the soul, such as avarice, ambition, and exorbitant love
					of pleasure, they have this happiness, to enjoy what they
					so eagerly covet. But this is that which most afflicts these
					idle rattlers, that being desirous of nothing more than
					of company that will hear them prate, they can never meet
					with it, in regard that all men avoid their society; and
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.222"/>
					
					whether sitting in a knot together or walking, so soon as
					they behold a prattler advancing towards them, they presently give warning to each other and adjourn to another
					place. And as, when there happens a deep silence in any
					assembly, so that all the company seems to be mute, we
					say that Mercury is got among them; so when a fool, full
					of noise and talk, enters into any room where friends and
					acquaintance are met to discourse or else to feast and be
					merry, all people are hushed of a sudden, as afraid of giving him any occasion to set his tongue upon the career.
					But if he once begin to open his mouth, up they rise and
					away they trip, like seamen foreseeing a sudden storm and
					rolling of the waves, when they hear <q direct="unspecified">the north wind begin to whistle from some adjoining promontory,</q> and hastening into harbor. Whence it comes to pass, that he
					never can meet with any that are willing either to eat or
					drink or lodge with him in the same room, either upon the
					road or upon a voyage, unless constrained thereto by necessity. For so importunate he is in all places, that sometimes he will pull you by the coat, sometimes by the beard,
					and sometimes be hunching your sides, to make you speak.
					How highly then are to be prized a swift pair of legs, according to the saying of Archilochus! Nay, by Jove, it
					was the opinion of wise Aristotle himself. For he being
					perplexed with an egregious prater, and tired out with his
					absurd stories and idle repetitions of, <q direct="unspecified">And is not this a
						wonderful thing, Aristotle?</q>&mdash;No wonder at all, said he,
					is this; but if a man should stand still to hear you prate
					thus, who had legs to run away, that were a wonder indeed.
					To another of the same stamp that, after a long tale of a
					roasted horse, excused himself by saying that he was afraid
					he had tired him with his prolixity; No, upon my word,
					quoth the philosopher, for I never minded what you said.
					On the other side, should it so fall out that there was no
					avoiding the vexation of one of these chattering fops, Nature
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.223"/>
					
					 has afforded us this happiness, that it is in the power
					of the soul to lend the outward ears of the body, to endure
					the brunt of the noise, while she retires to the remoter
					apartments of the mind, and there employs herself in better and more useful thoughts. By which means those
					sonorous babblers are at the same time disappointed, as
					well of auditors, as of people that believe what they say.
					All men look upon their vain babbling with the same opinion that they have of the seed of people insatiably addicted
					to the use of women; for as the one is barren and useless
					for generation, so is the other void of the end of discourse,
					altogether frivolous and impertinent.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>And yet there is no member of human bodies that
				Nature has so strongly enclosed within a double fortification, as the tongue, entrenched within with a barricado of
				sharp teeth, to the end that, if it refuses to obey and keep
				silent when reason <q direct="unspecified">presses the glittering reins</q> within,
				we should fix our teeth in it till the blood comes, rather
				than suffer the inordinate and unseasonable din. For, according to the saying of Euripides,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our miseries do not spring
				</l>
                     <l>From houses wanting locks or bolts;
				</l>
                     <l>But from unbridled tongues,
				</l>
                     <l>Ill used by prating fools and dolts.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, I must tell you, that they who think that houses
					without doors, and purses without strings, are of no use to
					their masters, yet at the same time set neither fence nor
					door before their lips, but suffer a continual torrent of vain
					and idle discourse to flow through them, like the perpetual flux of water through the mouth of the Pontic sea, seem
					to me to have the least esteem for human speech of all
					men in the world. Whence it comes to pass that they
					never gain belief, which is the end of all discourse. For
					the main scope and intention of all men that speak is to
					
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Eurip. Bacchae, 385.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.224"/>
					
					gain a belief of what they utter with those that hear them;
					whereas talkative noise-makers are never believed, let
					them speak never so much truth. For as wheat, when
					crowded into a musty vessel, is found to exceed in measure, but to be unwholesome for use; so the discourse of a
					loquacious person swells and enlarges itself with lies and
					falsehood, but in the mean time it loses all force of persuasion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Then again, there is no man of modesty and civility but would be careful of preserving himself from
				drunkenness. For anger, as some are of opinion, is
				the next neighbor to madness, while drunkenness doth
				dwell in the very same house with it; or rather, drunkenness is madness itself, inferior to it in continuance of time,
				yet far exceeding it as it is voluntary, since it is a madness
				of our own choice. Now there is nothing for which drunkenness is so much abominated and decried, as for that
				it is the cause of inordinate and unlimited babbling and
				prating.
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Heated with wine, the man at other times
				</l>
                     <l>Both wise and grave sings loose and wanton rhymes;
				</l>
                     <l>lie minds not loud indecent laughter then,
				</l>
                     <l>Nor mimic dancing, scorned by sober men.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Odyss. XIV. 464.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet both singing, laughing, and dancing are all but
					trifles to that which follows, the consequences of which
					are oft-times fatal:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He blurts those secrets forth, which once revealed,
					</l>
                     <l>Too late he wishes they had been concealed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This is that which oftentimes proves dangerous, if not
					terrible, to the discoverer. And who knows but that the
					poet might here design to resolve a question much disputed among philosophers,&mdash;that is to say, what the difference is between being tipsy and stark drunk,&mdash;by
					attributing to the former only mirth and jollity of humor,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.225"/>
					
					but branding the latter with the foul reproach of noxious
					babbling? For, according to the proverb,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What the sober heart conceals,
					</l>
                     <l>That the drunken heart reveals.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it is reported of Bias, that sitting very silent at
					a compotation, drinking only when it came to his turn, and
					being laughed at by one whose tongue ran at random, who
					for his silence called him mope and fool, he made this reply: Find me out that fool, said he, that e'er could hold
					his tongue in his cups.</p>
            <p>A citizen of Athens, having invited the king of Persia's
					ambassadors to a magnificent feast, at their request gave
					the same invitation to the most eminent philosophers in
					the city, to bear them company. Now, when all the rest
					were propounding of themes, and raising arguments pro
					and con, and others were maintaining of paradoxes to show
					their wit and learning, only Zeno sat still, so reserved and
					mute that the ambassadors took notice of it; and thereupon, after they thought they had opened his heart with
					two or three lusty brimmers, Pray tell us, Zeno, said they,
					what report we shall make concerning thee to our master?
					To whom Zeno: Nothing more, said he, but that there
					was an old man at Athens that could hold his tongue in
					the midst of his cups. Such profound and divine mysterious virtues are silence and sobriety; whereas drunkenness
					is loquacious, void of reason and understanding, and
					therefore full of jangling and impertinent tautologies.
					Wherefore the philosophers, when they come to define
					drunkenness, call it <q direct="unspecified">vain talk over wine.</q> So that drinking is not condemned, provided a man keep himself within
					the bounds of silence; only vain and silly discourse makes
					wine-bibbing to be drunkenness. He then that is drunk
					talks idly over his wine; but the babbler does it everywhere,&mdash;in the market-place, at the theatre, in the public
					walks, as well by night as by day. If he be a physician,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.226"/>
					
					certainly he is more troublesome than the disease; if your
					companion in a voyage, more insupportable than the
					qualms occasioned by the tumbling of the sea. If he
					praise thee, his panegyric is more offensive than the
					reproaches of another. It is a greater pleasure to
					converse with vicious men, so they be discreet in their language, than with twaddlers, though never so honest. Therefore Nestor in Sophocles, desirous to appease exasperated
					Ajax, mildly thus rebuked him:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I blame thee not, for though thy words are ill,
					</l>
                     <l>Thy deeds bespeak thee brave and valiant still.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Sophocles Frag. 770.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But there is not the same excuse to be made for a vain
					babbling fellow; for the ill government of his tongue corrupts and vitiates all the merits of his actions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Lysias had given to a certain accused criminal an
				oration of his own writing. He, having read it several
				times over, came to Lysias very much dejected, and told
				him that, upon his first perusal of it, it seemed to him
				to be a most admirable piece; but after he had read it
				three or four times over, he could see nothing in it but
				what was very dull and insipid. To whom Lysias, smiling: What, said he, is not once enough to speak it before
				the judges? And yet do but consider the persuasive eloquence and grace that is in Lysias's writing, and then I
				may be bold to affirm,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>That no man living e'er was favored more
				</l>
                     <l>By sacred Muse that violet garlands wore.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Certain it is that, of all the commendations that were ever
					given to Homer, this is the truest, that he alone avoided
					being irksome to his readers, as one that was always new
					and still flourishing, as it were in the prime of poetic
					beauty. And yet in speaking thus of himself,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I hate vain repetitions, fondly made,
					</l>
                     <l>Of what has been already plainly said,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XII. 452.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.227"/>
            <p>he shows how careful he is to shun that satiety which, as
					it were, lies in wait for all speech, alluring the ear from
					one relation into another, and still recreating the reader
					with fresh variety, in such a manner that he never thinks
					himself satisfied. Whereas men that let their tongues
					run at random rend and tear the ears with their tautologies, like those that, after writing-tables have been newly
					cleansed and wiped, deface them again with their impertinent scrawls and scratches.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>And therefore we would have them to remember this
				in the first place, that, as they who constrain men to guzzle down wine unmixed with water, and to excess, are the
				occasion that what was bestowed at first on men as a blessing, to excite mirth and rejoice the heart, becomes a mischief, creating sadness and causing drunkenness; so they
				that make an ill and inconsiderate use of speech, which is
				the most delightful means of human converse, render it
				both troublesome and unsociable, molesting those whom
				they think to gratify, derided by those whose esteem and
				admiration they covet, and offensive to such whose love
				and friendship they seek. And therefore, as he may be
				truly said to be no favorite of Venus, who with the girdle
				of the Goddess, wherein are all manner of allurements,
				drives and chases away his familiar acquaintance from his
				society ; so he that vexes others with his loose and extravagant talk may be as truly said to be a rustic, wanting altogether education and breeding.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Now then, among all other passions and maladies,
				some are dangerous, others hateful, and others ridiculous;
				but in foolish prating all these inconveniences concur. Praters are derided when they make relations of
				common matters; they are hated for bringing unwelcome
				tidings; they are in danger for divulging of secrets.
				Whereas Anarcharsis, being feasted by Solon, was esteemed a wise man, for that, as he lay asleep after the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.228"/>
				
				banquet was over, he was seen with his left hand over his
				privy parts, and his right hand laid upon his mouth; deeming, as indeed he rightly believed, that his tongue required
				the stronger curb. For though it would be a hard task to
				reckon up how many men have perished through the venereal intemperance, yet I dare say it would be almost as
				difficult to tell how many cities and States have been demolished and totally subverted by the inconsiderate blurting out of a secret.</p>
            <p>Sylla besieged Athens at a time when it was certain that
					he could not lie long before the city, by reason that other
					affairs and troubles called him another way. For on the
					one side, Mithridates ravaged Asia; on the other, Marius's
					party had made themselves masters of Rome. But it happened, that certain old fellows being met together in a
					barber's shop, among other discourse, blabbed it out, that
					the Heptachalcon was ill guarded, and that the city was in
					great danger of a surprise in that part. Which being
					overheard and reported to Sylla by certain of his spies, he
					presently brought all his forces on that side, and about
					midnight, after a sharp assault, entered the city with his
					whole army, and it was a thousand to one but that he had
					laid it in ashes. However, he filled it with the carcasses
					of the slain, and made the Ceramicus run with blood;
					being highly incensed against the Athenians, more for their
					reproachful language than their military opposition. For
					they had abused both him and his wife Metella, getting up
					upon the walls and calling him <q direct="unspecified">mulberry strewed with
						dust meal,</q> with many other provoking scoffs of the same
					nature; and merely for a few words&mdash;which, as Plato
					observes, are the lightest things in the world&mdash;they drew
					upon their heads the severest punishment.</p>
            <p>The tongue of one man prevented Rome from recovering
					her freedom by the destruction of Nero. For there was
					but one night to pass before Nero was to be murdered on
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.229"/>
					
					the morrow, all things being ready prepared and agreed on
					for that purpose. But in the mean time it happened that
					he who had undertaken to execute the act, as he was going
					to the theatre, seeing one of those poor creatures that
					were bound and pinioned, just ready to be led before Nero,
					and hearing the fellow bewail his hard fortune, gathered
					up close to him, and whispered the poor fellow in the ear:
					Pray only, honest friend, said he, that thou mayest but
					escape this day; to-morrow thou shalt give me thanks.
					Presently the fellow taking hold of this enigmatical speech,
					and calling to mind the vulgar saying, that he is a fool
					who lets slip a bird in the hand for a bird in the bush,
					preferred the surer to the juster way of saving himself,
					and presently declared to Nero what that man had whispered in his ear. Immediately the whisperer was laid hold
					of, and hurried away to the place of torture, where by
					racking, searing, and scourging he was constrained, poor
					miserable creature, to confess that by force which before
					he had discovered without any compulsion at all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Zeno, that he might not be compelled by the tortures
				of his body to betray, against his will, the secrets entrusted
				in his breast, bit off his tongue, and spit it in the tyrant's
				face. Notorious also was the example of Leaena, and
				signal the reward which she had for being true to her trust
				and constant in her taciturnity. She was a courtesan with
				whom Harmodius and Aristogiton were very familiar;
				and for that reason they had imparted to her the great
				hopes which they had upon the success of the conspiracy
				against the tyrants, wherein they were so deeply engaged;
				while she on the other side, having drunk freely of the
				noble cup of love, had been initiated into their secrets
				through the God of Love; and she failed not of her vow.
				For the two paramours being taken and put to death after
				they had failed in their enterprise, she was also apprehended
				and put to the torture, to force out of her a discovery of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.230"/>
				
				the rest of the accomplices; but all the torments and extremities they could exercise upon her body could not
				prevail to make her discover so much as one person;
				whereby she manifested to the world that the two gentlemen, her friends, had done nothing misbecoming their
				descent, in having bestowed their affections upon such a
				woman. For this reason the Athenians, as a monument
				of her virtue, set up a lioness (which the name Leaena
				signifies) in brass, without a tongue, just at the entrance
				into the Acropolis; by the stomachful courage of that
				beast signifying to posterity the invincible resolution of
				the woman; and by making it without a tongue, denoting
				her constancy in keeping the secret with which she was
				entrusted. For never any word spoken did so much good,
				as many locked up in silence. Thus at one time or other
				a man may utter what heretofore has been kept a secret;
				but when a secret is once blurted forth, it can never be
				recalled; for it flies abroad, and spreads in a moment far
				and near. And hence it is that we have men to teach us
				to speak, but the Gods are they that teach us silence;
				silence being the first thing commanded upon our first initiation into their divine ceremonies and sacred mysteries.
				And therefore it is that Homer makes Ulysses, whose eloquence was so charming, to be the most silent of men; and
				the same virtue he also attributes to his son, to his wife,
				and also to his nurse. For thus you hear her speaking:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Safe, as in hardened steel or sturdy oak,
				</l>
                     <l>Within my breast these secrets will I lock.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Ulysses himself, sitting by Penelope before he discovered himself, is thus brought in:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>His weeping wife with pity he beheld,
					</l>
                     <l>Although not willing yet to be revealed.
					</l>
                     <l>lie would not move his eyes, but kept them fast,
					</l>
                     <l>Like horn or steel within his eyebrows placed.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIX. 494 and 204.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.231"/>
            <p>So powerfully possessed with continence were both his
					tongue and lips; and having all the rest of his members so
					obedient and subject to his reason, he commanded his eye
					not to weep, his tongue not to speak a word, and his heart
					neither to pant nor tremble.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>So was his suffering heart confined
					</l>
                     <l>To give obedience to his mind;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XX. 23.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>his reason penetrating even to those inward motions, and
					subduing to itself the blood and vital spirits. Such were
					many of the rest of his followers. For though they were
					dragged and haled by Polyphemus, and had their heads
					dashed against the ground, they would not confess a word
					concerning their lord and master Ulysses, nor discover the
					long piece of wood that was put in the fire and prepared
					to put out his eye; but rather suffered themselves to be
					devoured raw than to disclose any one of their master's
					secrets; which was an example of fidelity and reservedness
					not to be paralleled. Pittacus therefore did very well,
					who, when the king of Egypt sent him an oblation-beast,
					and ordered him to take out and set apart the best and
					worst piece of it, pulled out the tongue and sent to him,
					as being the instrument of many good things as well as
					the instrument of the greatest evils in the world.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Ino therefore, in Euripides, frankly extolling herself,
				says:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know both when and where my tongue to hold,
				</l>
                     <l>And when with safety to be freely bold.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Ino, Frag. 417.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For they that are brought up under a truly generous and
					royal education learn first to be silent, and then to talk.
					And therefore King Antigonus, when his son asked him
					when they should discamp, replied, What! art thou afraid
					of being the only man that shall not hear the trumpet?
					So loath was he to trust him with a secret, to whom he
					was to leave his kingdom; teaching him thereby, when he
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.232"/>
					
					came to command another day, to be no less wary and
					sparing of his speech. Metellus also, that old soldier,
					being asked some such question about the intended march
					of his army, If I thought, said he, that my shirt were
					privy to this secret, I would pull it off and throw it into
					the fire. Eumenes also, when he heard that Craterus was
					marching with his forces against him, said not a word of
					it to his best friend, but gave out all along that it was
					Neoptolemus; for him his soldiers contemned, but they
					admired Craterus's fame and virtue; but nobody knew the
					truth but Eumenes himself. Thereupon joining battle, the
					victory fell to their side, and they slew Craterus, not knowing whom he was till they found him among the slain. So
					cunningly did taciturnity manage this combat, and conceal
					so great an adversary; so that the friends of Eumenes
					admired rather than reproved him for not telling them
					beforehand. For indeed, should a man be blamed in such
					a case, it is better for him to be accused after victory obtained by his distrust, than to be obliged to blame others
					after an overthrow because he has been too easy to impart
					his secrets.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Nay, what man is he that dares take upon him the
				freedom to blame another for not keeping the secret which
				he himself has revealed to him? For if the secret ought
				not to have been divulged, it was ill done to break it to
				another; but if, after thou hast let it go from thyself, thou
				wouldst have another keep it in, surely it is a great argument that thou hast more confidence in another than in
				thyself; for, if he be like thyself, thou art deservedly
				lost; if better, then thou art miraculously saved, as having
				met with a person more faithful to thee than thou art to
				thy own interest. But thou wilt say, he is my friend.
				Very good: yet this friend of mine had another, in whom
				he might confide as much as I did in him; and in like
				manner his friend another, to the end of the chapter.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.233"/>
				
				And thus the secret gains ground, and spreads itself by
				multiplication of babbling. For as a unit never exceeds
				its bounds, but always remains one, and is therefore called
				a unit; but the next is two, which contains the unlimited
				principle of diversity,&mdash;for it straightway departs from
				out of itself (as it were) and by doubling turns to a plurality,&mdash;so speech abiding in the first person's thoughts
				may truly be called a secret; but being communicated to
				another, it presently changes its name into common rumor.
				This is the reason that Homer gives to words the epithet
				of winged; for he that lets a bird go out of his hand
				does not easily catch her again; neither is it possible for a
				man to recall and cage again in his breast a word let slip
				from his mouth;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Euripides, Frag. 1031.</note> for with light wings it fetches many a
				compass, and flutters about from one quarter to another in
				a moment. The course of a ship may well be stayed by
				cables and anchors, which else would spoon away before a
				fresh gale of wind; but there is no fist riding or anchor-hold for speech, when once let loose as from a harbor;
				but being whirled away with a sonorous noise and loud
				echo, it carries off and plunges the unwary babbler into
				some fatal danger.
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For soon a little spark of fire, let fly,
				</l>
                     <l>May kindle Ida's wool, so thick and high
				</l>
                     <l>What one man to his seeming fiend lets go,
				</l>
                     <l>Whole cities may with ease enquire and know.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Ino, Frag. 415.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>The Senate of Rome had been debating among
				themselves a certain piece of secrecy for several days,
				which caused the matter to be so much the more suspected
				and listened after. Whereupon a certain Roman lady,
				discreet enough in other things, but yet a woman, laid at
				her husband day and night, and mournfully importuned
				him what the secret might be. Oaths, you may be sure,
				she was ready to make, and to curse herself if ever she
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.234"/>
				
				revealed whatever he should tell; nor was she wanting in
				tears, and many moist complaints of her being a woman
				so little to be trusted by a husband. The Roman thus
				beset, yet willing in some measure to make trial of her
				fidelity and convince her of her folly, Thou hast overcome
				me, wife, said he, and now I'll tell thee a most dreadful
				and prodigious thing. We were advertised by the priests,
				that a lark was seen flying in the air, with a golden helmet
				upon her head and a spear in one of her claws; now we
				are consulting with the augurs or soothsayers about this
				portent, whether it be good or bad. But keep it to thyself, for it may be of great concernment for the commonwealth. Having so said, he walked forth toward the
				market-place. No sooner was he gone, but his wife
				caught hold of the first of her maids that entered the
				room, and then striking her breast and tearing her hair,
				Woe is me, said she, for my poor husband and dearest country ! What will become of us?&mdash;prompting the maid, as
				if she were desirous that she should say to her, Why?
				What is the matter, mistress? Upon which she presently
				unfolded all that her husband had told her; nay, she forgot not the common burden with which all twattle-baskets
				conclude their stories; But, hussy, said she, for your life,
				be sure you say not a word of this to any soul living. The
				wench was no sooner got out of her mistress's sight, but
				meeting with one of her fellow-servants that had little to
				do, to her she unbosoms herself; she, big with the news,
				with no less speed runs away to her sweetheart, who was
				come to give her a visit, and without any more to do tells
				him all. By this means the story flew about the marketplace before the first deviser of it could get thither. Presently one of his acquaintance meeting him asked, Did ye
				come straight from your house? Without stop or stay,
				replied the other. And did ye hear nothing? says his
				friend. Why? quoth the other, Is there any news? Oh!
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.235"/>
				
				quoth his friend, a lark has been seen flying in the air,
				with a golden helmet upon her head and a spear in her
				claw, and the Senate is summoned to consult about it.
				Upon which the gentleman, smiling: God a mercy, wife,
				quoth he, for being so nimble! One would have thought
				I might have got into the market-place before a story so
				lately told thee; but I see 'twas not to be done. Thereupon meeting with some of the senators, he soon delivered
				them out of their pain. However, being resolved to take
				a slight revenge of his wife, making haste home, Wife,
				said he, thou hast undone me; for it is found out that the
				great secret I told thee was first divulged out of my house;
				and now must I be banished from my native country for
				your wicked gaggling tongue. At first his wife would
				have denied the matter, and put it off from her husband
				by telling him there were three hundred more besides
				himself that heard the thing, and why might not one of
				those divulge it as well as he? But he bade her never tell
				him of three hundred more, and told her it was an invention of his own framing to try her and to avoid her importunity. Thus this Roman safely and cautiously made the
				experiment of his wife's ability to keep a secret; as when
				we pour into a cracked and leaky vessel, not wine nor oil,
				but water only.</p>
            <p>But Fulvius, one of Augustus Caesar's minions and
					favorites, once heard the emperor deploring the desolation
					of his family, in regard his two grandchildren by his
					daughter were both dead, and Postumius, who only remained alive, upon an accusation charged against him was
					confined to banishment, so that he was forced to set up his
					wife's son to succeed him in the empire, yet upon more
					compassionate thoughts, signifying his determination to
					recall Postumius from exile. This Fulvius hearing related
					the whole to his wife, and she to Livia. Livia sharply
					expostulated the matter with Caesar; wherefore, seeing he
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.236"/>
					
					had projected the thing so long before, he did not send for
					his daughter's son at first, but exposed her to the hatred
					and revenge of him that he had determined to be his successor. The next morning Fulvius coming into Augustus's
					presence, and saluting him with Hail, O Caesar! Caesar
					retorted upon him, God send thee more wit, Fulvius. He,
					presently apprehending the meaning of the repartee, made
					haste home again; and calling for his wife, Caesar understands, said he. that I have discovered his secret counsels,
					and therefore I am resolved to lay violent hands upon myself. And justly too, said she, thou dost deserve to die,
					since having lived so long with me, thou didst not know
					the lavishness of my tongue, and how unable I was to
					keep a secret. However, suffer me to die first. And with
					that, snatching the sword out of her husband's hands, she
					slew herself before his face.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Truly therefore was it said by Philippides the comedian, who being courteously and familiarly asked by King
				Lysimachus, what he should bestow upon him of all the
				treasure that he had, made answer, Any thing, O King, but
				your secrets.</p>
            <p>But there is another vice no less mischievous that attends
					garrulity, called Curiosity. For there are a sort of people
					that desire to hear a great deal of news, that they may
					have matter enough to tattle abroad; and these are the
					most diligent in the world to pry and dive into the secrets
					of others, that they may enlarge and aggravate their own
					loquacity with new stories and fooleries. And then they
					are like children, that neither can endure to hold the ice in
					their hands nor will let it go ; or rather they may be said
					to lodge other men's secrets in their bosoms, like so many
					serpents, which they are not able to keep there long, because they eat their way through. It is said that the fish
					called the sea-needle and vipers rive asunder and burst
					themselves when they bring forth; in like manner, secrets,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.237"/>
					
					dropping from the mouths of those that cannot contain
					them, destroy and overthrow the revealers. Seleucus Callinicus, having lost his whole army in a battle fought with
					the Galatians, threw off his royal diadem, and flew away
					full speed on a horse with three or four attendants, wandering through by-roads and deserts, till at last he began to
					faint for want of food. At length coming to a certain
					countryman's house, and finding the owner himself within,
					he asked him for a little bread and water; which the
					countryman not only readily fetched him, but what else his
					ground would afford he very liberally and plentifully set
					before the king and his companions, making them all as
					heartily welcome as it was possible for him to do. At
					length, in the midst of their cheer, he knew the king's
					face. This overjoyed the man to such a degree,&mdash;that he
					should have the happiness to relieve the king in his necessity,&mdash;that he was not able to contain himself or dissemble his knowledge of the king; but after he had rode a
					little way with him and came to take his leave; Farewell,
					King Seleucus, said the poor man. But then the king,
					stretching forth his right hand and pulling his host to his
					breast, as if he had intended to kiss him, nodded to one
					of his followers to strike off the countryman's head with
					his sword.
					<quote rend="blockquote">E'en while he speaks, his head rolls in the dust.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. X. 457.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas if he could but have held his peace and mastered
					his tongue for a little while, till the king, as afterwards he
					did, had recovered his good fortune and grandeur, he had
					been doubtless better rewarded for his silence than he was
					for his hospitality. And yet this poor man had some
					colorable excuse for letting his tongue at liberty; that is to
					say, his hopes, and the kindness he had done the king.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>But most of your twattlers, without any cause or
				pretence at all, destroy themselves; as it happened when
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.238"/>
				
				certain fellows began to talk pretty freely in a barber's
				shop concerning the tyranny of Dionysius, that it was as
				secure and inexpugnable as a rock of adamant: I wonder,
				quoth the barber, laughing, that you should talk these
				things before me concerning Dionysius, whose throat is
				almost every day under my razor. Which scurrilous freedom of the barber being related to the tyrant, he caused
				him forthwith to be crucified. And indeed the generality
				of barbers are a prating generation of men; in regard the
				most loquacious praters usually resort to their shops, and
				there sit prattling; from whence the barbers also learn an
				ill habit of twattling. Pleasant therefore was the answer
				of Archelaus to the barber who, after he had cast the linen
				toilet about his shoulders, put this question to him, How
				shall I trim your majesty; In silence, quoth the king. It
				was a barber that first reported the news of the great overthrow which the Athenians received in Sicily; for being
				the first that heard the relation of it in the Piraeus, from a
				servant of one of those who had escaped out of the battle,
				he presently left his shop at sixes and sevens, and flew into
				the city as fast as his heels could carry him,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For fear some other should the honor claim
				</l>
                     <l>Of being first, when he but second came.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">I. XXII. 207.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now you may be sure that the first spreader of this news
					caused a great hubbub in the city, insomuch that the people, thronging together in the market-place, made diligent
					enquiry for the first divulger. Presently the barber was
					brought by head and shoulders to the crowd, and examined;
					but he could give no account of his author, only one that
					he never saw or knew in his life before had told him the
					news. Which so incensed the multitude, that they immediately cried out, To the rack with the traitor, tie the
					lying rascal neck and heels together. This is a mere story
					of the rogue's own making. Who heard it? Who gave
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.239"/>
					
					any credit to it beside himself? At the same instant the
					wheel was brought out, and the poor barber stretched upon
					it,&mdash;not to his ease, you may be sure. And then it was,
					and not before, that the news of the defeat was confirmed
					by several that had made a hard shift to escape the slaughter. Upon which the people scattered every one to his
					own home, to make their private lamentation for their particular losses, leaving the unfortunate barber bound fast to
					the wheel; in which condition he continued till late in the
					evening, before he was let loose. Nor would this reform
					the impertinent fool; for no sooner was he at liberty but
					he would needs be enquiring of the executioner, what
					news, and what was reported of the manner of Nicias the
					general's being slain. So inexpugnable and incorrigible a
					vice is loquacity, gotten by custom and ill habit, that they
					cannot leave it off, though they were sure to be hanged.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>And yet we find that people have the same antipathy against divulgers of bad tidings, as they that drink
				bitter and distasteful potions have against the cups wherein they drank them. Elegant therefore is the dispute in
				Sophocles between the messenger and Creon:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>MESSENGER. By what I tell and what you hear,
				</l>
                     <l>Do I offend your heart or ear?</l>
                  </lg>
					             <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>CREON. Why so inquisitive to sound
					</l>
                     <l>My grief, and search the painful wound?</l>
                  </lg>
					             <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>MESSENGER. My news afflicts thy ears, I find,
					</l>
                     <l>But 'tis the fact torments thy mind.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Antigone, 317.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they that bring us bad tidings are as bad as they
					who are the authors of our misery; and yet there is
					no restraining or correcting the tongue that will run at
					random.</p>
            <p>It happened that the temple of Minerva in Lacedaemon
					called Chalcioecus was robbed, and nothing but an earthen
					pitcher left behind; which caused a great concourse of
					people, where every one spent his verdict about the empty
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.240"/>
					
					pitcher. Gentlemen, says one, pray give me leave to tell
					ye my opinion concerning this pitcher. I am apt to believe, that these sacrilegious villains, before they ventured
					upon so dangerous an attempt, drank each of them a
					draught of hemlock juice, and then brought wine along
					with them in this pitcher; to the end that, if it were their
					good hap to escape without being apprehended, they might
					soon dissolve and extinguish the strength and vigor of the
					venom by the force of the wine unmixed and pure; but if
					they should be surprised and taken in the fact, that then
					they might die without feeling any pain under the torture
					of the rack. Having thus said, the people, observing so
					much forecast and contrivance in the thing, would not be
					persuaded that any man could have such ready thoughts
					upon a bare conjecture, but that he must know it to be so.
					Thereupon, immediately gathering about him, one asked
					who he was; another, who knew him; a third, how he
					came to be so much a philosopher. And at length, they
					did so sift and canvass and fetch him about, that the
					fellow confessed himself to be one of those that committed the sacrilege.</p>
            <p>And were not they who murdered the poet Ibycus discovered after the same manner, as they sat in the theatre?
					For as they were sitting there under the open sky to behold the public pastimes, they observed a flock of cranes
					flying over their heads; upon which they whispered merrily one to another, Look, yonder are the revengers of
					Ibycus's death. Which words being overheard by some
					that sat next them,&mdash;in regard that Ibycus had been long
					missing but could not be found, though diligent search had
					been made after him,&mdash;they presently gave information
					of what they had heard to the magistrates. By whom
					being examined and convicted, they suffered condign punishment, though not betrayed by the cranes, but by the
					incontinency of their own tongues, and by an avenging
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.241"/>
					
					Erinnys hovering over their heads and constraining them
					to confess the murder. For as in the body, wounded and
					diseased members draw to themselves the vicious humors
					of the neighboring parts; in like manner, the unruly
					tongues of babblers, infested (as it were) with inflammations where a sort of feverish pulses continually lie beating, will be always drawing to themselves something of
					the secret and private concerns of other men. And therefore the tongue ought to be environed with reason, as with
					a rampart perpetually lying before it, like a mound, to
					stop the overflowing and slippery exuberance of impertinent talk; that we may not seem to be more silly than
					geese, which, when they take their flight out of Cilicia
					over the mountain Taurus, which abounds with eagles, are
					reported to carry every one a good big stone in their bills,
					instead of a bridle or barricade, to restrain their gaggling.
					By which means they cross those hideous forests in the
					night-time undiscovered.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Now then if the question should be asked, Which
				are the worst and most pernicious sort of people? I do not
				believe there is any man that would omit to name a traitor.
				By treason it was that Euthycrates covered the uppermost
				story of his house with Macedonian timber, according to
				the report of Demosthenes; that Philocrates, having received a good sum of money, spent it upon whores and
				fish; and that Euphorbus and Philagrus, who betrayed
				Eretria, were so well rewarded by the king with ample
				Possessions. But a prattler is a sort of traitor that no
				man needs to hire, for that he offers himself officiously
				and of his own accord. Nor does he betray to the enemy
				either horse or walls; but whatever he knows of public
				or private concerns requiring the greatest secrecy, that he
				discloses, whether it be in courts of judicature, in conspiracies, or management of state affairs, 'tis all one; he
				expects not so much as the reward of being thanked for
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.242"/>
				
				his pains; nay, rather he will return thanks to them that
				give him audience. And therefore what was said upon a
				certain spendthrift that rashly and without any discretion
				wasted his own estate by his lavish prodigality to others,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou art not liberal; 'tis a disease
				</l>
                     <l>Of vainly giving, which does thee possess;
				</l>
                     <l>'Tis all to please thyself, what thou dost give,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Epicharmus.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>may well be retorted upon a common prattler:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou art no friend, nor dost to me impart,
					</l>
                     <l>For friendship's sake, the secrets of thy heart;
					</l>
                     <l>But as thy tongue has neither bolt nor lock,
					</l>
                     <l>'Tis thy disease, that thou delight'st to talk.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Nor would I have the reader think that what has
				hitherto been said has been discoursed so much to blame as
				to cure that vicious and infectious malady of loquaciousness.
				For though we surmount and vanquish the vices of the mind
				by judgment and exercise, yet must the judgment precede.
				For no man will accustom himself to avoid and, as it were,
				to extirpate out of his soul those vices, unless he first
				abominate them. Nor can we ever detest those evil habits
				of the mind as we ought to do, but when we rightly judge
				by reason's light of the prejudice they do us, and the ignominy we sustain thereby. For example, we consider and
				find that these profuse babblers, desirous of being beloved, are universally hated; while they study to gratify,
				they become troublesome; while they seek to be admired,
				they are derided. If they aim at profit, they lose all their
				labor; in short, they injure their friends, advantage their
				enemies, and undo themselves. And therefore the first
				remedy and cure for this spreading malady will be this, to
				reckon up all the shameful infamies and disasters that
				attend it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>The second remedy is to take into serious consideration the practice of the opposite virtue, by always hearing,
				remembering, and having ready at hand the due praises
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.243"/>
				
				and encomiums of reservedness and taciturnity, together
				with the majesty, sanctimony, and mysterious profoundness
				of silence. Let them consider how much more beloved, how
				much more admired, how far they are reputed to excel in
				prudence, who deliver their minds in few words, roundly
				and sententiously, and contract a great deal of sense within
				a small compass of speech, than such as fly out into voluminous language, and suffer their tongues to run before
				their wit. The former are those whom Plato so much
				praises, and likens unto skilful archers, darting forth their
				sentences thick and close, as it were crisped and curled
				one within another. To this same shrewdness of expression Lycurgus accustomed his fellow-citizens from their
				childhood by the exercise of silence, contracting and thickening their discourse into a compendious delivery. For as
				the Celtiberians make steel of iron by burying it in the
				ground, thereby to refine it from the gross and earthy part,
				so the Laconic way of speech has nothing of bark upon it,
				but by cutting off all superfluity of words, it becomes steeled
				and sharpened to pierce the understanding of the hearers.
				So their consciousness of language, so ready to turn the
				edge to all manner of questions, became natural by their
				extraordinary practice of silence. And therefore it would
				be very expedient for persons so much given to talk, always
				to have before their eyes the short and pithy sayings of
				those people, were it only to let them see the force and
				gravity which they contain. For example: The Lacedaemonians to Philip; Dionysius in Corinth. And when
				Philip wrote thus to the Spartans: If once I enter into
				your territories, I will destroy ye all, never to rise again;
				they answered him with the single word, If. To King
				Demetrius exclaiming in a great rage, What! have the
				Spartans sent me but one ambassador? the ambassador
				nothing terrified replied, Yes; one to one. Certainly they
				that spoke short and concisely were much admired by the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.244"/>
				
				ancients. Therefore the Amphictyons gave order, not that
				the Iliad or the Odyssey or Pindar's paeans should be
				written upon Pythian Apollo's temple; but Know thyself; Nothing too much; Give sureties, and mischief is at
				hand. So much did they admire conciseness of speech,
				comprehending full sense in so much brevity, made solid
				as it were by the force of a hammer. Does not the Deity
				himself study compendious utterance in the delivery of his
				oracles? Is he not therefore called Loxias,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The name <hi rend="italics">Loxias</hi> is usually derived from <foreign lang="greek">loco/s</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">indirect.</hi> (G.)</note> because he
				avoids rather loquacity than obscurity? Are not they that
				signify their meaning by certain signs, without words, in
				great admiration and highly applauded Thus Heraclitus,
				being desired by his fellow-citizens to give them his opinion concerning Concord, ascended the public pulpit, and
				taking a cup of cold water into his hand, first sprinkled it
				with a little flour, then stirring it with a sprig of pennyroyal, drank it off, and so came don again; intimating thereby, that if men would but be contented with what was next
				at hand, without longing after dainties and superfluities, it
				would be an easy thing for cities to live in peace and concord one with another.</p>
            <p>Scilurus, king of the Scythians, left fourscore sons behind him ; who, when he found the hour of death approaching, ordered them to bring him a bundle of small javelins,
					and then commanded every one singly to try whether lie
					could break the bundle, as it was, tied up altogether; which
					when they told him it was impossible for them to do, he
					drew out the javelins one by one, and brake them all himself with case ; thereby declaring that, so long as they kept
					together united and in concord, their force would be invincible, but that by disunion and discord they would
					enfeeble each other, and render their dominion of small
					continuance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>He then, that by often repeating and reflection shall
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.245"/>
				
				enure himself to such precedents as these, may in time perhaps be more delighted with these short and conclusive
				apophthegms than with the exorbitances of loose and lavish discourse. For my own part, I must acknowledge that
				I am not a little ashamed of myself, when I call to mind that
				same domestic servant of whom I am now going to speak,
				and consider how great a thing it is to advise before a man
				speaks, and then to be able to maintain and stick to what
				he has resolved upon.</p>
            <p>Pupius Piso, the rhetorician, being unwilling to be disturbed with much talk, gave orders to his servants to answer
					to such questions only as he should ask them, and say no
					more. Then having a design to give an entertainment to
					Clodius, at that time magistrate, he ordered him to be invited, and provided a splendid banquet for him, as in all probability he could do no less. At the time appointed several
					other guests appeared, only they waited for Clodius's coming,
					who tarried much longer than was expected; so that Piso
					sent his servant several times to him, to know whether he
					would be pleased to come to supper or no. Now when it
					grew late and Piso despaired of his coming, What! said he
					to his servant, did you call him? Yes, replied the servant.
					Why then does he not come away? Because he told me
					he would not come. Why did you not tell me so before?
					Because, sir, you never asked me the question. This was a
					Roman servant. But an Athenian servant, while he is
					digging and delving, will give his master an account of the
					articles and capitulations in a treaty of peace. So strangely
					does custom prevail in all things, of which let us now discourse.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>For there is no curb or bridle that can tame or restrain a libertine tongue; only custom must vanquish that
				disease. First therefore, when there are many questions
				propounded in the company where thou art, accustom thyself
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.246"/>
				
				 to silence till all the rest have refused to give an
				answer. For, as Sophocles observes,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Although in racing swiftness is required,
				</l>
                     <l>In counselling there's no such haste desired;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>no more do speech and answer aim at the same mark with
					running. For it is the business of a racer to get the
					start of him that contends with him; but if another man
					gives a sufficient answer, there needs no more than to commend and approve what he says, and so gain the reputation
					of a candid person. If not, then to tell wherein the other
					failed and to supply the defect will neither be unseasonable
					nor a thing that can justly merit distaste. But above all
					things, let us take special heed, when another is asked a
					question, that we do not chop in to prevent his returning
					an answer. And perhaps it is as little commendable, when
					a question is asked of another, to put him by, and under
					take the solution of what is demanded ourselves. For
					thereby we seem to intimate that the person to whom the
					question was put was not able to resolve it, and that the
					propounder had not discretion sufficient to know of whom
					to ask it. Besides, such a malapert forwardness in answering is not only indecent, but injurious and affrontive.
					For he that prevents the person to whom the question is
					put in returning his answer, would in effect insinuate a
					What need had you to ask of him?&mdash;What can he say to
					it?&mdash;When I am in presence, no man ought to be asked
					those questions but myself. And yet many times we put
					questions to some people, not for want of an answer, but
					only to minister occasion of discourse to provoke them to
					familiarity, and to have the pleasure of their wit and conversation, as Socrates was wont to challenge Theaetetus
					and Charmides. Therefore to prevent another in returning
					his answers, to abstract his ears, and draw off his cogitations from another to himself, is the same thing as to run
					and salute a man who designs to be saluted by somebody
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.247"/>
					
					else, or to divert his eyes upon ourselves which were already fixed upon another; considering that if he to whom
					the question is put refuse to return an answer, it is but
					decent for a man to contain himself, and by an answer
					accommodate to the will of the propounder, modestly and
					respectfully to put in, as if it had been at the request or
					in the behalf of the other. For they that are asked a
					question, if they fail in their answer, are justly to be pardoned; but he that voluntarily presumes to answer for
					another gives distaste, let his answer be never so rational;
					but if he mistake, he is derided by all the company.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>The second point of exercise, in reference to our
				own answering of questions, wherein a man that is given
				to talk ought to be extremely careful, is first of all not to
				be over-hasty in his answers to such as provoke him to
				talk on purpose to make themselves merry and to put an
				affront upon him. For some there are who, not out of
				any desire to be satisfied, but merely to pass away the
				time, study certain questions, and then propound them to
				persons which they know love to multiply words, on purpose to make themselves sport. Such men therefore ought
				to take heed how they run headlong and leap into discourse, as if they were glad of the occasion, and to consider the behavior of the propounder and the benefit and
				usefulness of the question. When we find that the propounder is really desirous to be informed, it is convenient
				then for a man to bethink himself awhile, and make some
				pause between the question and the answer; to the end
				that the proposer, if he pleases to make any additions to
				his proposal, may have time to do it, and himself a convenient space to consider what answer to make, for fear of
				running at random and stifling the question before it be
				fully propounded, or of giving one answer for another for
				want of considering what he ought to say,&mdash;which is the
				effect of an over-hasty zeal to be talking. True it is,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.248"/>
				
				indeed, that the Pythian priestess was wont to give her
				oracular answers at the very instant, and sometimes before
				the question was propounded. For that the Deity whom
				she serves
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Both understands the mute that cannot speak,
				</l>
                     <l>And hears the silent e'er his mind he break.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Herod. I. 47.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But it behooves a man that would return a pertinent answer, to stay till he rightly apprehend the sense and understand the intent of him that propounds the question, lest
					he may happen to make good the proverb,
					<quote rend="blockquote">A rake we called for; they refused a bowl.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, we must subdue this inordinate and insatiate greediness of having all the talk, that it may not seem as if we
					had some old flux of humors impostumated about the
					tongue, which we were willing to have lanced and let
					out by a question. Socrates therefore, though never so
					thirsty after violent exercise, never would allow himself the
					liberty to drink, till he had drawn one bucket of water
					and poured it out upon the ground; to the end he might
					accustom his sensual appetite to attend reason's appointment.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Now therefore we come to understand that there
				are three sorts of answers to questions, the necessary, the
				polite, and the superfluous. For example, if a man should
				ask whether Socrates is within, the other, if he were in an
				ill-humor or not disposed to make many words, would
				answer, Not within; or if he intended to be more Laconic,
				he would cut off <q direct="unspecified">within,</q> and reply briefly, No. Thus
				the Lacedaemonians, when Philip sent them an epistle, to
				know whether or not they would admit him into their
				city, vouchsafed him no other answer than only No, fairly
				written in large letters upon a sheet of paper. Another
				that would answer more courteously would say: He is not
				within; he is gone among the bankers; and perhaps he
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.249"/>
				
				would add, Where he expects some friends. But a superfluous prater, if he chance to have read Antimachus of
				Colophon, would reply: He is not within; but is gone
				among the bankers, in expectation to meet certain Ionian
				friends, who are recommended to him in a letter from Alcibiades, who lives at Miletus with Tissaphernes, one of
				the great king of Persia's lieutenant-generals, who formerly assisted the Lacedaemonians, but is now, by the
				solicitation of Alcibiades, in league with the Athenians;
				for Alcibiades, being desirous to return to his own country,
				has prevailed with Tissaphernes to change his mind and
				join with the Athenians. And thus perhaps you shall have
				him run on and repeat the whole eighth book of Thucydides, and overwhelm a man with his impertinent
				discourse, till he has taken Miletus, and banished Alcibiades a second time. Herein therefore ought a man
				chiefly to restrain the profuseness of his language, by
				following the footsteps of the question, and circumscribing
				the answer, as it were, within a circle proportionable to
				the benefit which the propounder proposes to make of
				his question. It is reported of Carneades, that before he
				was well known in the world, while he was disputing in
				the Gymnasium, the president of the place sent him an
				admonition to moderate his voice (for he naturally spoke
				very deep and loud); in answer to which he desired the
				president to send him a gauge for his voice, when the president not improperly made answer: Let that be the person
				who disputes with thee. In like manner, the intent of
				the propounder ought to be the rule and measure of the
				answer.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Moreover, as Socrates was wont to say, that those
				meats were chiefly to be abstained from which allured men
				to eat when they were not a-hungry, and those drinks to
				be refrained that invited men to drink when they were not
				a-dry; so it would behoove a man that is lavish of his
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.250"/>
				
				tongue, to be afraid of those discourses and themes wherein he most delights and makes it his business to be most
				prolix, and whenever he perceives them flowing in upon
				him, to resist them to the utmost of his power. For example, your martial men are always talking of sieges and
				battles, and the great poet often introduces Nestor boasting
				of his own achievements and feats of arms. The same
				disease is incident to noted pleaders at the bar, and accompanies such as have unexpectedly risen to be the favorites
				of great princes. For such will be always up with their
				stories,&mdash;how they were introduced at first, how they
				ascended by degrees, how they got the better in such a
				case, what arguments they used in such a case, and lastly
				how they were hummed up and applauded in court. For
				to say truth, gladness and joy are much more loquacious
				than the sleeplessness so often feigned in their comedies,
				rousing up and still refreshing itself with new relations;
				and therefore they are prone to fall into such stories upon
				the least occasion given. For not only
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where the body most is pained,
				</l>
                     <l>There the patient lays his hand;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but pleasure also has a voice within itself, and leads the
					tongue about to be a support to the memory. So lovers
					spend the greatest part of their time in songs and sonnets,
					to refresh their memories with the representations of their
					mistresses; concerning which amours of theirs, when companions are wanting, they frequently discourse with things
					that are void of life. Thus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O dearest bed, whereon we wont to rest;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O blessed lamp divine,&mdash;for surely thee
					</l>
                     <l>Bacchis believes some mighty Deity,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>Surely the greatest of the Gods thou art,
					</l>
                     <l>If she so wills who does possess my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed it may well be said, that a loose-tongued fellow is no more, in respect of his discourse, than a white
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.251"/>
					
					line struck with chalk upon white marble. For in regard
					there are several subjects of discourse, and many men are
					more subject to some than to others, it behooves every
					one to be on his guard especially against these, and to suppress them in such a manner that the delight which they
					take therein may not decoy them into their beloved prolixity and profuseness of words. The same inclination to
					overshoot themselves in prattling appears in such as are
					prone to that kind of discourses wherein they suppose
					themselves to excel others, either in habit or experience.
					For such a one, being as well a lover of himself as ambitious of glory,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The chiefest part of all the day doth spend,
					</l>
                     <l>Himself to pass and others to transcend.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Antiope of Euripides, Frag. 183.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For example, he that reads much endeavors to excel in
					history; the grammarian, in the artificial couching of
					words; the traveller is full of his geography. But all
					these surplusages are to be avoided with great caution,
					lest men, intoxicated therewith, grow fond of their old infirmities, and return to their former freaks, like beasts that
					cannot be driven from their haunts. Cyrus therefore, yet
					a young stripling, was most worthy of admiration, who
					would never challenge his equals and playfellows to any
					exercise wherein he excelled, but to such only wherein he
					knew himself to be inferior; unwilling that they should
					fret for the loss of the prize which he was sure to win,
					and loath to lose what he could himself gain from the
					others' better skill.</p>
            <p>On the other side, the profuse talker is of such a disposition that, if any discourse happen from which he might
					be able to learn something and inform his ignorance, that
					he refuses and rejects, nor can you hire him even to hold
					his tongue; but after his rolling and restless fancy has
					mustered up some few obsolete and all-to-be-tattered rhapsodies
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.252"/>
					
					 to supply his vanity, out he flings them, as if he
					were master of all the knowledge in the world. Just like
					one amongst us who, having read two or three of Ephorus's
					books, tired all men's ears, and spoiled and brake up all
					the feasts and societies wherever he came, with his continual relations of the battle of Leuctra and the consequences of it; by which means he got himself a nickname,
					and every one called him Epaminondas.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But this is one of the least inconveniences of this
				infirmity ; and indeed we ought to make it one step towards
				the cure, to turn this violent vein of twattling upon such
				subjects as those. For such a loquacity is less a nuisance
				when it superabounds in what belongs to humane literature. It would be well also that the sort of people who
				are addicted to this vice should accustom themselves to
				write upon some subject or other, and to dispute of certain
				questions apart. For Antipater the Stoic, as we may
				probably conjecture, either not being able or else unwilling
				to come into dispute with Carneades, vehemently inveighing against the Stoics, declined to meet him fairly in the
				schools, yet would be always writing answers against him;
				and because he filled whole volumes full of contradictory
				arguments, and still opposed him with assertions that only
				made a noise, he was called Calamoboas, as one that made
				a great clamor with his pen to no purpose. So it is very
				probable that such fighting with their own shadows, and
				exclaiming one against another apart by themselves, driving
				and restraining them from the multitude, would render
				them gradually more tolerable and sociable in civil company; as curs, after they have once discharged their fury
				upon sticks and stones, become less fierce towards men.
				It would be always of great importance to them to converse with their superiors and elders; for that the awful
				reverence and respect which they bear to their dignity and
				gravity may accustom them in time to silence.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.253"/>
            <p>And it would be evermore expedient to intermix and involve with these exercises this manner of ratiocination
					with ourselves, before we speak, and at the very moment
					that the words are ready to break out of our mouths:
					What is this which I would say, that presses so hard to be
					gone? For what reason would this tongue of mine so fain
					be talking? What good shall I get by speaking, What
					mischief shall I incur by holding my peace? For we are
					not to case and discharge ourselves of our words, as if they
					were a heavy burthen that overloaded us; for speech remains as well when uttered as before; but men either
					speak in behalf of themselves when some necessity compels them, or for the benefit of those that hear them, or
					else to recreate one another with the delights of converse,
					on purpose to mitigate and render more savory, as with
					salt, the toils of our daily employments. But if there be
					nothing profitable in speaking, nothing necessary to them
					that hear what is said, nothing of satisfaction or delight,
					what need is there it should be spoken? For words may
					be in vain and to no purpose, as well as deeds. But after
					and above all that has been said, we ought always to bear
					in remembrance, and always to have at our tongue's end,
					that saying of Simonides, that he had often repented him
					of talking, but never of keeping silent. Then as for exercise, we must believe it to be a matter of great importance, as being that which overcomes and masters all things;
					considering what watchful care and even toil and labor
					men will undergo to get rid of an old cough or hiccough.
					But silence and taciturnity not only never cause a dry
					throat, as Hippocrates observes, but are altogether free
					from pain and sorrow.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>