<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aquane an ignis sit utilior</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1957</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>WHETHER FIRE OR WATER IS MORE USEFUL (AQUANE AN IGNIS UTILIOR) <lb/> INTRODUCTION</head>
            <pb id="v.12.p.288"/>
            <p>
					There seems to be no reason to discuss this little work
					in detail, since F. H. Sandbach<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> xxxiii (1939), pp. 198-202. G. Kowolski, <hi rend="italics">De Plut. scriptorum iuvenilium colore rhetorico</hi>, Cracow, 1918, pp. 258 ff., also denied the authenticity.</note> has shown conclusively that it cannot be genuine. Still more might
					be added to his proofs, sound and thorough as they
					are ; but this is not the place to slay the slain. It is
					the more to be regretted that Ziegler, in the article
					on Plutarch in Pauly-Wissowa, <hi rend="italics">Realencyclop&auml;die</hi>, has
					not had access to Sandbach's work,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is very puzzling since Ziegler later (936) cites the same article as authoritative on rhythmical matters.</note> though he does
					refer to Xylander's athetesis, only to reject it, and
					might have mentioned Meziriacus' as well.
				</p>
            <p>
					Sandbach well observes : <q direct="unspecified">To write an exercise
						on the comparative utility of fire and water may
						seem so difficult to us moderns who do not have such
						tasks as part of our education, that we do not recognize how badly the topic is here handled. . . . While
						it is possible that Plutarch wrote this work as a parody,
						or when a schoolboy, or under some strange circumstances, yet . . . the most probable view is that a
						miserable sophistical exercise on the subject <hi rend="italics">Whether
						fire or water is more useful</hi> was fathered on the author
						of a diversion entitled <hi rend="italics">Whether land- or water-animals
						aire more intelligent</hi>, just as the <hi rend="italics">Consolatio ad Apollonium</hi>
						
						            <pb id="v.12.p.289"/>
						
						was ascribed to the author of a consolation addressed
						to his wife, or the <hi rend="italics">Lives of the Ten Orators</hi> to the author
						of some more famous biographies.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The text is extremely bad, as may be seen by
					examining Wegehaupt's topheavy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wegehaupt collated some 34 mss. for his edition, all of which he cites separately.</note> apparatus in
					<foreign lang="greek">*xa/rites</foreign> 
               <hi rend="italics">f&uuml;r Friedrich Leo</hi> (Berlin, Weidmann, 1911)?
					pp. 158-169- It is possible, to be sure, that part at
					least of the difficulty of the text is due to the author.
					Less emendation than that admitted here might not
					seriously damage what is irreparable nonsense in any
					case. Some attempt has been made to reproduce the
					childish style of the original.
				</p>
            <p>
					The work is no. 206 in the catalogue of Lamprias.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The new Teubner edition of this and the following essays appeared while this volume was in proof, so that only the most necessary changes and corrections could be made. In this essay (since Wegehaupt's edition was already available) they have not been so plentiful as in the subsequent ones, for which Hubert has now provided the first truly critical edition that these works have ever had.</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.12.p.291"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">Water is best, but gold is a flaming fire,</quote>
					says Pindar.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Olympians</hi>, i. 1.</note> He, therefore, bluntly assigns the
					second place to fire; and Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 116.</note> agrees with him
					in the words
					<quote rend="blockquote">And first of all came Chaos into being;</quote>
					for most people believe that this is his name for water
					because it flows (<hi rend="italics">chysis</hi>).<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Etymologizing (as in Mor. 948 e-f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>) <hi rend="italics">chaos</hi> from <hi rend="italics">chysis</hi>, <q direct="unspecified">diffusion of liquid.</q>
               </note> Yet the balance of witnesses on both sides seems to be equal. There are,
					in fact, some<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Stoics; <hi rend="italics">cf., e.g.,</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> i, p. 27 (Zeno, frag. 98); <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 1053 a-b; 1067 a; 1077 b.</note> who state that fire is the first principle
					of the universe and, like a seed, creates everything out
					of itself and receives all things into itself when the
					conflagration occurs.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the Universal Conflagration of the Stoics see von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> ii, pp. 183 ff.; on that of Heraclitus, Cherniss, <hi rend="italics">Aristotle's Criticism of the Presocratics</hi>, p. 29, n. 108.</note> Ignoring the authors, let us
					examine the arguments on both sides and see where
					they will lead us.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Is not that element the more useful of which
					most of all, everywhere, invariably, we stand in need
					as a household tool and, I swear, a friend, ready to
					help us at any time, in any emergency ? Yet fire is
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.293"/>
					
					not always useful; sometimes, indeed, we find it too
					much and interrupt our use of it. But water is used
					both winter and summer, sick and well, night and
					day : there is no time when a man does not need it.
					That, of course, is the reason why the dead are called
					<hi rend="italics">alibantes</hi>, meaning that they are without <hi rend="italics">libas</hi>, <q direct="unspecified">moisture,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 736 a; Galen, <hi rend="italics">De Temperament</hi>, i. 3 (i, p. 522 K.).</note> and for lack of that deprived of life. Man
					has often existed without fire, but without water
					never. Besides, that which, from the beginning,
					was coincidental with the inception of man is more
					useful than that which was discovered later ; for it
					is obvious that Nature bestowed the one as vitally
					necessary, while the other was brought to light by
					luck or contrivance for a superfluous use. Now, none
					may tell of a time when water was unknown to man,
					nor is any god or hero said to be its discoverer ; it
					was, in fact, at hand instantly when man appeared
					and was itself the cause of his appearance. But the
					use of fire, they say,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As, <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>, Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Prometheus</hi>, 254. The following words in lozenge brackets are conjecturally supplied.</note> was discovered only a day or
					twro ago by Prometheus ; (consequently all our preceding life was deprived of) fire, though it was not
					without water. And that this is no poetic fiction is
					proved by present modes of living ; for there are
					certain races of man who live without fire, with no
					house or hearth, under the open sky. And Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This anecdote is told with rather more point and relevance in 995 c-d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					the Cynic reduced the use of fire to a minimum, so
					that he even swallowed a squid raw, remarking,
					<q direct="unspecified">Thus, gentlemen, do I risk my life for you.</q> But
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.295"/>
					
					without water no one ever thought it good, or even
					possible, to live.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>And why do I split hairs by discussing merely
					human nature ? For though there are many, or
					rather countless, sorts of creatures, man is practically
					the only one that knows the use of fire, while all the
					others live and feed without it: they subsist, whether
					they range abroad or fly or crawl, upon roots or produce or flesh, all without fire ; but without water no
					creature of the sea or land or air ever existed. For
					even flesh-eating animals, some of which Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 3 (601 b).</note>
					says do not drink, nevertheless keep alive by using
					the fluids in the flesh. That element, therefore,
					without which no living nature can subsist or endure
					is the more useful.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Let us pass from the people who use fire to the
					things that we use, namely plants and produce,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">This must be one of the most remarkable transitions in literature</q> (Sandbach, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 200).</note> of
					which some are completely devoid of heat, while
					others have an infinitesimal and uncertain amount.
					Moisture, however, is the element in nature that
					makes them all burgeon, growing and bearing fruit.
					And why should I enumerate honey and wine and
					oil and all the rest that come to us from the vintage,
					the milking of herds, or taking off of honey - and it
					is obvious where they belong<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, they must be classed as liquids.</note> - when even wheat
					itself, though it is classed as a dry food, moves into
					the category of liquids by alteration, fermentation,
					and deliquescence?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 968 a <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; here, however, the author seems to be talking about beer.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Moreover, what is never detrimental is more
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.297"/>
					
					useful. Now fire, when it forms a stream, is most
					destructive ; but the nature of water is never harmful.
					Then again, of two elements that is more beneficial
					which is cheaper and provides its help without any
					preparation. Now the use of fire requires a supply
					of fuel, for which reason rich people have more of
					it than poor, and kings than private persons ; but
					water has another merit in service to man, that of
					equality, with no discrimination. For it needs no
					tools or implements, being a self-sufficient, self-fulfilling good.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Then too, that which by multiplication destroys
					its own contribution is the less useful. Such a thing
					is fire which, like an all-devouring beast, consumes
					everything near, so that it is useful rather by skilful
					handling and craft and moderation in use than by
					its own nature ; but water is never dangerous.
					Further, of two things the one which may be joined
					with its fellow is more useful. Now fire does not admit
					moisture and is of no use when in conjunction with
					it; but water is of service when combined with fire,
					for hot water is healing and well adapted to medicinal
					purposes. A watery fire you will never see ; but
					water is as useful to mankind when hot as when cold.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Furthermore, though there are but four elements,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 948 d above; in 729 b the sea is called the <q direct="unspecified">naturally hostile element.</q>
               </note> water provides from itself a fifth, so to say,
					the sea, one no less beneficial than the others, especially for commerce among other things. This element,
					therefore, when our life was savage and unsociable,
					linked it together and made it complete, redressing
					defects by mutual assistance and exchange and so
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.299"/>
					
					bringing about co-operation and friendship. Now
					Heraclitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i. 173, frag. B 99. In <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 98 c a fuller and more appropriate version is given; but see now H. Fr&auml;nkel, <hi rend="italics">Wege und Formen</hi>, p. 270 and n. 1.</note> declares, <q direct="unspecified">If there were no sun, it would
						be perpetual night</q> ; in the same way we may say
					that if there were no sea, man would be the most
					savage and destitute of all creatures. But as it is,
					the sea brought the Greeks the vine from India, from
					Greece transmitted the use of grain across the sea,
					from Phoenicia imported letters as a memorial
					against forgetfulness,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Euripides, frag. 578 (p. 542 Nauck).</note> thus preventing the greater
					part of mankind from being wineless, grainless, and
					unlettered. How, then, should water not be more
					useful when it has the advantage over fire of one more
					element?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For this delightful absurdity see Sandbach, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 199, n. 4.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>What could anyone find to say on the other side
					from this point on ? This, that God, the master workman, had as material four elements from which to
					construct the universe. Among these, again, there
					is a simple mutual distinction, namely, that earth
					and water are a foundation at the bottom of the
					universe, being, like raw material, the substance of
					which things are constructed and moulded, having
					just so much form and organization, and indeed of
					capacity for growth and procreation, as is imparted
					to them by the other elements, air and fire, which
					are makers and artisans and rouse them, lying lifeless
					as they were until then, to the act of creation. Between these two, again, fire and air, there is the distinction that fire assumes the rule and leadership.
					This is clear by induction<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Possibly; but the argument hardly demonstrates this. The text is corrupt and a different solution than that adopted here is proposed by M. Adler (<hi rend="italics">Wien. Stud.</hi> xxxi. 308).</note>: earth without warmth
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.301"/>
					
					is barren and unfruitful, but fire, when it takes
					possession and inflames, causes it to swell to the
					point of generation ; and it is impossible to find anyother reason why rocks and the bare bones of mountains are barren except that they have either no part
					at all, or very little share, in fire.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>And, in general, water is so far from being selfsufficient for the preservation or generation of other
					things that the want of fire is water's destruction.
					For heat maintains everything in its proper being and
					keeps it in its proper substance, water itself as well
					as everything else. When fire withdraws and fails,
					water putrefies : the dearth of heat is the death and
					destruction of water. It is, of course, marsh waters
					and such as are stagnant, some too that have drained
					into depressions with no outlet, that are bad<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, <q direct="unspecified">salt,</q> as, for example, the Dead Sea.</note> and
					finally putrefy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 1129 d, 725 d; Athenaeus, 46 b-c.</note> because they have very little motion,
					which preserves everything by stirring up its heat.
					This is the reason why we commonly say that those
					waters are <q direct="unspecified">living</q> which have most motion and
					the strongest current; the heat is maintained by
					their motion. How, then, should that not be the more
					useful of two things which has provided what is
					necessary for the other's existence, as fire does for
					water ? And surely that is the more useful, the lack
					of which, if it be entirely taken away, causes the
					living creature to die. For it is obvious that anything
					without which a creature cannot live must have been
					a necessary cause of its existence, while it did exist.
					Now even corpses have moisture which does not
					entirely vanish ; otherwise dead bodies would not
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.303"/>
					
					putrefy, since putrefaction is not a change from dry
					to moist, but rather a corruption of the moisture in
					flesh. Death, then, is nothing but the total disappearance of heat and so dead men are extremely cold ;
					if you attack them with a razor-blade, you will blunt
					the edge of it through excess of cold. In the living
					creature itself, too, the parts that have the least heat
					are the least sensitive, like bones and hair and the
					parts that are a long way from the heart. And, in
					general, the presence of fire makes a greater difference<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or adopting Schultz's (<hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xlvi. 632) emendation: <q direct="unspecified">the difference between living and non-living comes from the presence of fire</q>; but the text is hopelessly corrupt.</note> than that of moisture ; for it is not mere
					moisture that produces plants and fruits, but warm
					moisture ; cold water, of course, is either less productive or not productive at all. Yet if by its own
					nature water were fruitful, it would always bear fruit
					by itself b ; but on the contrary it is even harmful.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>To begin again : for the use of fire as fire we
					do not need water ; on the contrary, it would be in
					our way since it extinguishes and destroys it. But
					in most circumstances it is impossible to use water
					without fire. When water is heated, it is more useful ;
					otherwise it is harmful. And it is heat which has
					made the sea more beneficial, its waters being warmer,
					since it differs from other waters in no other respect.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This sentence was transferred here from the following chapter by Wegehaupt.</note>
					So that of two things, that is better which of itself
					lends us its use without need of the other. Besides,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.305"/>
					
					water is solely beneficial to the touch, when you wash
					or bathe in it; but fire is profitable to all the senses.
					It can, in fact, both be touched and seen from a
					distance, so that in addition to its other uses, there
					is also its variegated character.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The order of the sentences in this chapter, in addition to its many other corruptions, has been badly disturbed.</note> For to say that man ever exists without fire
					is absurd, nor can he exist at all without it; but
					there are differences in kind as in other things. As
					for men who have no need of fire from without, they
					have this experience not because they do not need it,
					but because their own heat more than suffices. This
					must be predicated also of other animals which do
					not need fire.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This clause was transferred here by the editor from 958 c <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> at the end of the paragraph.</note> So that in this respect, too, the use
					of fire is probably superior. Water is never in such
					a condition as to need no external support, but fire
					is self-sufficient because of its great excellence. As,
					then, a general is better who manages the affairs of
					his city so that it needs no allies from without, so
					also an element is superior which does not often need
					external assistance.
				</p>
            <p>
					Yet, to take the opposite point of view, that is more
					useful which we alone make great use of, since by
					the powers of our reason we are able to choose what
					is better. For what is more useful and more profitable
					to man than reason ? But brute beasts do not have
					it. What then ? Is what has been discovered by the
					foresight of our better part for this reason less useful ?
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.307"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And since we have arrived at this point in our
					argument: What is more profitable to life than Art ?
					And it was fire that discovered and still preserves all
					the arts. That is why they make Hephaestus the
					first of artificers. Man has been granted but a little
					time to live and, as Ariston<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> i. p. 90, frag. 403; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Nicomachean Ethics</hi>, i. 13. 12 (1102 b 7).</note> says, sleep, like a taxcollector, takes away half of that. But I would rather
					say that it is a question of darkness ; for although
					a man might stay awake all night, yet no good would
					come of his wakefulness if fire did not give him the
					benefits of day and remove the difference between
					day and night.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A very corrupt passage. Adler's reconstruction (<hi rend="italics">Wien. Stud.</hi> xxxi. 308), with additions by Post, has been followed.</note> If, then, there is nothing more
					advantageous to man than life and life is many times
					increased by fire, how should fire not be the most
					useful of all things ?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>And, to be sure, will not that be the most
					advantageous of which each of the senses has the
					greatest proportion? Do you not perceive, then,
					that there is no one of the senses which uses moisture
					by itself without an admixture of air or fire ; and that
					every sense partakes of fire inasmuch as it supplies
					the vital energy ; and especially that sight, the
					keenest of the physical senses,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 250 d; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 654 d-e, 681 e.</note> is an ignited mass
					of fire<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 196, 199; but Post believes the words may mean <q direct="unspecified">a chain of fire</q> linking the eye with its object.</note> and is that which has made us believe<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is the visible heavens and their fire that make us believe by <q direct="unspecified">declaring the glory</q> of the celestial gods. See A. S. Pease, <q direct="unspecified">Caeli Enarrant,</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Harvard Theological Review</hi>, xxxiv (1941), pp. 163-200.</note> in the
					gods ? And further, through sight, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 47 a-b.</note> says,
					we are able to conform our souls to the movements
					of the celestial bodies.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>