<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Ad principem ineruditum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.116">
      <body>
         <head>A discourse to an unlearned prince.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.323"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>PLATO, being desired by the Cyreneans to prescribe to
				them good laws and to settle their government, refused to
				do it, saying that it was a hard matter to give them any
				law whilst they enjoyed so much prosperity, since nothing
				is so fierce, arrogant, and untamable, as a man that thinks
				himself to be in a happy condition. Wherefore it is very
				difficult to give counsel to princes in matters of government; for they fear to receive advice as a thing seeming to
				command them, lest the force of reason should seem to
				lessen their power, by obliging it to submit to truth. And
				they consider not the saying of Theopompus, king of
				Sparta, who, being the first in that country that joined
				the Ephori with the Kings, was reproached by his wife,
				because by this means he would leave the kingdom to his
				children less than he found it; to whom he replied, that
				he should render it so much the greater, the firmer it was.
				For, by holding the reins of government somewhat loose,
				he avoided envy and danger; nevertheless, since he permitted the stream of his power to flow so freely into other
				channels, what he gave to them must needs be a loss to
				himself. Though philosophy possessing a prince as his
				assistant and keeper, by taking away the dangerous part of
				fulness of power (as if it were fulness of body), leaves
				the sound part.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But many kings and princes foolishly imitate those
				unskilful statuaries who think to make their images look
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.324"/>
				
				great and fierce if they make them much straddling, with
				distended arms, and open mouth. After the same manner
				they, by the grave tone of their voice, stern countenance,
				morose behavior, and living apart from all society, would
				affect a kind of majestic grandeur, not unlike those statues
				that without seem to be of an heroic and divine form. but
				within are filled with nothing but earth, stone and lead;&mdash;with this only difference, that the weight of these massy
				bodies renders them stable and unmovable; whereas unlearned princes, by their internal ignorance, are often
				shaken and overthrown, and in regard they do not build
				their power on a true basis and foundation, they fall together with it. For, as it is necessary at first that the rule
				itself should be right and straight, before those things that
				are applied to it can be rectified and made like unto it; so
				a potentate ought in the first place to learn how to govern
				his own passions and to endue his mind with a tincture of
				princely virtues, and afterwards to make his subjects conformable to his example. For it is not the property of one
				that is ready to fall himself to hinder another from tripping, nor of one that is rude and illiterate to instruct the
				ignorant; neither can a person govern that is under no
				government. But most men, being deceived by a false
				opinion, esteem it the chiefest good in ruling to be subject
				to no authority; and thus the Persian king accounted
				all his servants and slaves except his wife, whose master
				he ought more especially to have been.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Who then shall have power to govern a prince?
				The law, without doubt; which (as Pindar saith) is the
				king of mortal and immortal beings; which is not written
				without in books nor engraven on wood or stone, but is a
				clear reason imprinted in the heart, always residing and
				watching therein, and never suffering the mind to be without government. The king of Persia indeed commanded
				one of his lords that lay in the same chamber to attend
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.325"/>
				
				him every morning, and to sound these words in his ears:
				Arise, O king! and take care of those affairs and duties
				that Oromasdes requires of thee. But a wise and prudent.
				prince hath such a monitor within his breast as always
				prompts and admonishes him to the same effect. It was a
				saying of Polemon, that Love was the minister of the Gods,
				appointed to take care of the education of youth; but it
				might be more truly affirmed, that princes are the administrators of the divine power, for the safety and protection
				of mankind, to distribute part of those goods that God bestows on men, and to reserve part for themselves.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dost thou behold the vast and azure sky,
				</l>
                     <l>How in its liquid arms the earth doth lie?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Frag. 935.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The air indeed disperses the first principles of convenient
					seeds, but the earth causeth them to spring forth; some
					grow and thrive by the means of moderate and refreshing
					showers, some delight in gentle breezes of wind, and some
					are cherished by the influences of the moon and stars;
					but it is the sun that perfects and beautifies all, inspiring
					them with the principle of mutual sympathy and love.
					Nevertheless, all these so many and so great benefits, that
					are the effects of the divine munificence and liberality,
					cannot be enjoyed or duly made use of, without a law, justice, and a prince; for justice is the end of the law, the
					law is the prince's work, and the prince is the image of
					God, that disposeth all things. He doth not stand in need
					of a Phidias, a Polycletus, or a Myro; but by the practice
					of virtue makes himself most like the divine nature, and
					becomes a most delectable object to God and man. For
					as God hath placed the sun and moon in heaven, as manifest tokens of his power and glory, so the majesty of a
					prince is resplendent on earth, as he is his representative
					and vicegerent,
					
					Who doth like God most righteous laws dispense.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIX. 109.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.326"/>
					
					I mean such a one as believes that the likeness of God is
					found in wisdom and understanding, not in the sceptre, the
					thunderbolt, or the trident, with which symbols of Deity
					some have vainly caused themselves to be carved or painted, thereby exposing their egregious folly to the world, in
					affecting that which they are not able to attain to. For
					God cannot but be incensed against those that presume to
					imitate him in producing thunder, lightnings, and sunbeams; but if any strive to emulate his goodness and
					mercy, being well pleased with their endeavors, he will
					assist them, and will endue them with his order, justice,
					truth, and gentleness, than which nothing can be more
					sacred and pure,&mdash;not fire, not light, nor the course of
					the sun, not the rising and setting of the stars, nor even
					eternity and immortality itself. For God is not only happy
					by reason of the duration of his being, but because of the
					excellency of his virtue; this is properly divine and transcendent, and that is also good which is governed by it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Anaxarchus endeavoring to comfort Alexander, who
				was very much afflicted for the murder he had committed
				on the person of Clitus, told him, that justice and right
				sat as assistants by the throne of Jupiter, so that whatsoever was done by a king might be accounted lawful and
				just; but by this means he indiscreetly prevented his repentance, and encouraged him to attempt the committing
				the like crimes again. But if we may be permitted to
				guess at these matters, Jupiter hath not Justice for an assessor or counsellor, but is himself Justice and Right, and
				the original and perfection of all laws. Therefore the
				ancients devised and taught these things, that they might
				thereby show that even Jupiter himself could not rule well
				without Justice; for she is (according to Hesiod) a pure and
				undefiled virgin, and the companion of Modesty, Reverence,
				Chastity, and Simplicity; hence kings are called <q direct="unspecified">reverent,</q> for they ought to be most reverent who fear least.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.327"/>
				
				But a prince ought to be more afraid of doing than of suffering ill; for the former is the cause of the other; and
				this is a noble and generous sort of fear, well becoming a
				prince, to be solicitous lest any harm should befall his subjects unawares:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As faithful dogs, surprised with sudden fear,
				</l>
                     <l>When once they see the savage beasts appear,
				</l>
                     <l>Not of themselves, but of their flocks take care.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. X. 183.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Epaminondas, when on a certain festival day the Thebans
					gave themselves up wholly to drinking and carousing, went
					about alone and viewed the arsenal and the walls of the
					city, saying, that he was sober and vigilant that others
					might have liberty to be drunk and to sleep. And Cato
					at Utica, when he had called together by proclamation all
					his soldiers that had escaped the slaughter to the seaside,
					caused them to embark in ships; and having prayed for
					their prosperous voyage, returned home and killed himself, leaving an example to princes, whom they ought to
					fear and what they ought to contemn. On the other hand,
					Clearchus, king of Pontus, creeping into a chest, slept
					therein like a snake. And Aristodemus lay with his concubine in a bed placed in an upper room over a trap-door,
					her mother removing the ladder as soon as they were got
					up, and bringing it again in the morning. How then,
					think you, did he fear to be seen in the theatre, in the
					judgment-hall, in the court, or at a feast, who had turned
					his bed-chamber into a prison? For indeed good princes
					are possessed with fear for their subjects, but tyrants with
					fear of them; insomuch that their timorousness increaseth
					with their power, since the more people they have under
					their dominion, so much the more objects they see of dread
					and terror.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Neither is it probable or convenient (as some philosophers affirm) that God should be mingled together with
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.328"/>
				
				matter that is altogether passive, and with things obnoxious to innumerable necessities, chances, and mutations;
				but to us he seems to be placed somewhere above with the
				eternal nature that always operates after the same manner; and proceeding (as Plato saith) on sacred foundations,
				according to nature, he brings his works to perfection.
				And as he hath placed the sun in the firmament, as a clear
				image of his most sacred and glorious essence, in which,
				as in a mirror, he exhibits himself to the contemplation of
				wise men; so in like manner, the splendor of justice that
				appears in some cities is a kind of representation of the
				divine wisdom, which happy and prudent persons describe
				by the help of philosophy, conforming themselves to those
				things which are of a most sublime and excellent nature.
				It is certain that this disposition of mind cannot be attained but by the doctrine of philosophy; otherwise we
				shall lie under the same circumstances as Alexander, who
				seeing Diogenes at Corinth, and being astonished at his
				ingenuity and majestic gravity, let fall this expression:
				If I were not Alexander, I would choose to be Diogenes.
				For being almost oppressed with the weight of his own
				grandeur and power, which are the impediments of virtue
				and ease, he seemed to envy the happiness of a threadbare
				cloak and pouch, with which the Cynic rendered himself
				as invincible as he could be with all his armor, horses, and
				pikes. However, he had an opportunity to philosophize
				and to become Diogenes in his mind, though he remained
				Alexander in his outward state and condition, and he might
				more easily be Diogenes, because he was Alexander; forasmuch as to keep the vessel of his prosperous fortune
				steady, which was tossed with the winds and waves, he
				stood in need of a good quantity of ballast and of a skilful pilot.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Amongst the mean and inferior sort of people, folly
				mingled with weakness is destitute of an ability to do mischief;
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.329"/>
				
				 and the mind is vexed and distracted by it, as a
				distempered brain is with troublesome dreams, insomuch
				that it hath not strength enough to execute what it desires.
				But power joined with a corrupt and depraved inclination
				adds the fuel of madness to the fire of the passions. So
				true is that saying of Dionysius, who declared, that he
				then chiefly enjoyed his authority, when he speedily performed what he designed. But herein lies the greatest
				danger, lest he that is able to do all things that he desires
				should desire those things that he ought not
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">The word's no sooner said, but th' act is done.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIX. 242.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Vice, being furnished with wheels by power, sets all the
					faculties of the soul in a violent fermentation; of anger it
					makes murder, of love adultery, and of covetousness the
					confiscation of other men's goods.
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">The word's no sooner said,&mdash;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>but the offender is executed; a suspicion arises,&mdash;the
					accused person is put to death. And as naturalists affirm,
					that the lightning breaks forth after the thunder as the
					blood follows the wound, but is seen first, since whilst the
					ear expects the sound the eye discerns the light; so under
					some governments the punishments precede the accusation,
					and the condemnation prevents the proving of the crime.
					Under such circumstances,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No human soul such license can withstand,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>As anchors strive in vain to hold in sand,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>unless this exorbitant power be restrained and kept within
					its due bounds by the force of sound reason. Therefore a
					prince ought to imitate the sun, which being come to its
					greatest height in the northern signs, moves slowest, whereby he renders his course the more safe.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>For it is not possible that the vices and faults of persons in authority can be concealed in obscurity. But as
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.330"/>
				
				people that are troubled with the falling-sickness, if they
				walk about in a high place, are seized with a giddiness in
				the head and a dimness in the sight, which are the usual
				symptoms of that disease; so Fortune, when she hath a
				little exalted illiterate and foolish men with riches, glory,
				or authority, suddenly hastens their ruin. And as amongst
				empty vessels it cannot easily be discerned which are whole
				and which are leaky, but by the pouring in of any liquor;
				so corrupt and exulcerated minds, after the infusion of
				power, are not able to contain it, but immediately overflow
				with concupiscence, anger, arrogance, and folly. And what
				need is there of mentioning these particulars, since the
				least faults and miscarriages of renowned and famous men
				lie under the lash of slander and calumny? Cimon was
				accused for being too much addicted to the drinking of
				wine, Scipio was blamed for delighting in immoderate
				sleep, and Lucullus for making too liberal and costly entertainments....</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>