<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Praecepta gerendae reipublicae</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold North Fowler</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.10.p.156"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>PRECEPTS OF STATECRAFT (PRAECEPTA GERENDAE REIPUBLICAE)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					This essay is addressed to Menemachus, a young
					man who has asked Plutarch for advice concerning
					public life. Nothing further is known of the young
					man, except that Pardalas of Sardis is mentioned as
					his fellow-citizen (813 f ; 825 d) ; but some of those
					to whom Plutarch's various essays are addressed
					are known to be real persons, and it is, therefore,
					probable that Menemachus also actually existed.
					Plutarch held at different times various public offices,
					and moreover he was highly regarded by his fellowcitizens and many others as a guide, philosopher,
					and friend; it is, therefore, not unnatural that a
					young man who was thinldng of entering upon a
					political career should appeal to him for advice and
					counsel, though it is also possible that Plutarch wrote
					the essay without being asked to do so and addressed
					it to Menemachus merely as a matter of form.
				</p>
            <p>
					There is nothing profoundly philosophical and very
					little purely theoretical to be found here. Greece,
					like most of the known world, was a part of the
					Roman Empire, and the exercise of statecraft on
					a large scale was virtually limited to Romans. The
					ancient Greek city-states retained, however, their
					local self-government, subject to the supervision of
					the proconsul; they could enter into agreements
					with each other, and could send envoys to Rome if
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.157"/>
					
					occasion arose. A man could, therefore, find useful
					and honourable occupation in public life, as Plutarch
					himself did. Although he frequently uses the great
					men of the great days of Greece as examples, Plutarch
					gives the sort of advice which would be useful to
					one engaged insuch political activity as was open to
					a Greek in his time. Some of his advice is applicable
					only to his own times and its conditions, but the
					politician or statesman of any age may recognize
					many of his precepts as common sense, the application of which is limited to no time or place. The
					essay is, then, of interest, not only because it throws
					a sidelight upon the conditions in Greece in Plutarch's
					time, but also on account of its own inherent value.
				</p>
            <p>
					The reference to troubles which took place <q direct="unspecified">recently under Domitian</q> (815 d, Chapter 19) may
					indicate that the essay was written not long after
					a.d. 96, the date of Domitian's death.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.159"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>If, Menemachus, it is suitable to apply to anything at all the saying
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>No one of all the Achaeans finds fault with the words thou
					hast uttered,
					</l>
                  <l>Nor will oppose them in speech; and yet thou hast reached
					no conclusion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 55; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 795 b.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					it may be applied to those philosophers who urge
					people to take lessons from them, but give no real
					instruction or advice ; for they are like those who
					trim the lamps, but fail to pour in oil. Therefore,
					seeing that the desire has been aroused in you a
					<quote rend="blockquote">Speaker of speeches to be, and also a doer of actions<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 443; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 795 e.</note>
               </quote>
					in your native State, as befits your noble birth, since
					you have not time to gain an understanding of a
					philosopher's life in the open among affairs of State
					and public conflicts or to be a spectator of examples
					worked out in deed, not merely in word, and since
					you ask for some precepts of statecraft, I think it is
					not at all fitting that I should refuse, and I pray that
					the result may be worthy of your zeal and of my goodwill ; and, as you requested, I have made use of a
					rather large variety of examples.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>First, then, at the base of political activity there
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.161"/>
					
					
					must be, as a firm and strong foundation, a choice of
					policy arising from judgement and reason, not from
					mere impulse due to empty opinion or contentiousness or lack of other activities. For just as those who
					have no useful occupation at home spend most of
					their time in the market-place, even if there is nothing
					they need there, just so some men, because they have
					no business of their own that is worth serious attention, throw themselves into public affairs, treating
					political activity as a pastime, and many who have
					become engaged in public affairs by chance and have
					had enough of them are no longer able to retire from
					them without difficulty ; they are in the same predicament as persons who have gone aboard a vessel
					to be rocked a bit and then have been driven out into
					the open sea ; they turn their gaze outside, seasick
					and much disturbed, but obliged to stay where they
					are and endure their present plight.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Over the bright calm sea
					</l>
                  <l>The fair-faced loves went past them to the mad
					</l>
                  <l>Outrage of the ship's oars that plough the deep.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 396, ascribed to Simonides.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					These men cast the greatest discredit upon public
					life by regretting their course and being unhappy
					when, after hoping for glory, they have fallen into
					disgrace or, after expecting to be feared by others on
					account of their power, they are drawn into affairs
					which involve dangers and popular disorders. But the
					man who has entered upon public life from conviction
					and reasoning, as the activity most befitting him and
					most honourable, is not frightened by any of these
					things, nor is his conviction changed. For neither is
					it right to enter upon public life as a gainful trade, as
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.163"/>
					
					
					Stratocles and Dromocleides and their set used to
					invite each other to come to the golden harvest (for
					so they called the orators' platform in jest) ; nor
					ought we to enter upon it as if wTe were suddenly
					seized by an onset of strong emotion, as Gaius
					Gracchus did, who, when his brother's misfortunes
					were still fresh, withdrew so far as possible from public
					affairs and then, inflamed by anger because certain
					persons insulted and reviled him, rushed into public
					life. And although he was quickly satiated with
					public affairs and fame, yet when he tried to stop and
					wished for a change and a quiet life, he found that
					his power was too great to be laid down but before
					he could lay it down he perished. And those who
					make themselves up for political competition or
					the race for glory, as actors do for the stage, must
					necessarily regret their action, since they must either
					serve those whom they think they should rule or
					offend those whom they wish to please. On the contrary, I believe that those who, like men who fall into
					a well, stumble into public life by mere chance and
					unexpectedly must be cast into confusion and regret
					their course, whereas those who enter into it quietly,
					as the result of preparation and reflection, will be
					moderate in their conduct of affairs and will not be
					discomposed by anything, inasmuch as they have
					honour itself and nothing else as the purpose of their
					actions.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>So, after thus determining their choice in their
					own minds and making it invariable and unchangeable, statesmen must apply themselves to the understanding of the character of the citizens, which shows
					itself as in the highest degree a compound of all their
					individual characters and is powerful. For any attempt
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.165"/>
					
					
					on the part of the statesman to produce by himself
					at the very outset a change of character and nature
					in the people will not easily succeed, nor is it safe,
					but it is a matter that requires a long space of time
					and great power. But just as wine is at first controlled
					by the character of the drinker but gradually, as it
					warms his whole body and becomes mingled therewith, itself forms the drinker's character and changes
					him, just so the statesman, until he has by his reputation and by public confidence in him built up his
					leadership, must accommodate himself to the people's
					character as he finds it and make that the object of
					his efforts, knowing by what things the people is
					naturally pleased and led. For example, the Athenian
					populace is easily moved to anger, easily turned to
					pity, more willing to suspect quickly than to be informed at leisure ; as they are readier to help humble
					persons of no reputation, so they welcome and especially esteem facetious and amusing speeches; while they
					take most delight in those who praise them, they are
					least inclined to be angry with those who make fun of
					them; they are terrible even to their chief magistrates,
					then kindly even to their enemies. Quite different is
					the character of the Carthaginian people ; it is bitter,
					sullen, subservient to their magistrates, harsh to
					their subjects, most abject when afraid, most savage
					when enraged, stubborn in adhering to its decisions,
					disagreeable and hard in its attitude towards playfulness and urbanity. Never would these people, if a
					Cleon had asked them to postpone the meeting of the
					assembly on the ground that he had made sacrifice
					and had guests to entertain,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story of the adjournment of the assembly is told by Plutarch in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Nicias</hi>, chap. vii. p. 527.</note> have adjourned the
					meeting amid laughter and the clapping of hands ;
					nor would they, when a quail escaped from Alcibiades'
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.167"/>
					
					
					cloak while he was speaking, have joined eagerly
					in hunting it down and then have given it back to
					him<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Life of Alcibiades</hi>, chap. x. p. 195.</note>; no, they would have put them both to death
					for their insolence and their flippancy, seeing that
					they banished Hanno on the charge of aspiring to be
					tyrant, because he used a lion on his campaigns to
					carry his luggage ! And I do not believe that the
					Thebans either, if they had obtained control of their
					enemies' letters, would have refrained from reading
					them, as the Athenians, when they captured Philip's
					mail-carriers with a letter addressed to Olympias,
					refrained from breaking the seal and making
					known an affectionate private message of an absent
					husband to his wife. Nor, on the other hand,
					do I believe that the Athenians would have borne
					with good temper the contemptuous pride of Epameinondas, when he refused to reply to the accusation
					against him but rose from his seat and went out from
					the theatre through the assembly to the gymnasium.
					And I think, too, that the Spartans would have been
					far from enduring the insolence and buffoonery of
					Stratocles, who persuaded the Athenians to make
					sacrifices on the ground that they had won a
					victory, and then, after a true report of their
					defeat had been received, when they were angry
					with him, asked the people what wrong he had
					done them seeing that, thanks to him, they had
					been happy for three days.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Demetrius</hi>, chap. xi.</note> Now court flatterers,
					like bird-catchers, by imitating the voices of kings
					and assimilating themselves to them, insinuate themselves deeply into their good graces and decoy them
					by deceit; but for the statesman it is fitting, not to
					imitate the character of his people, but to understand
					it and to employ for each type those means by
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.169"/>
					
					
					which it can be brought under his control. For
					ignorance of their characters leads to no less serious
					mistakes and failures in free States than in the
					friendships of kings.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>So, then, the statesman who already has attained
					to power and has won the people's confidence should
					try to train the character of the citizens, leading
					them gently towards that which is better and treating them with mildness; for it is a difficult task to
					change the multitude. But do you yourself, since you
					are henceforth to live as on an open stage, educate
					your character and put it in order ; and if it is not
					easy wholly to banish evil from the soul, at any rate
					remove and repress those faults which are most
					flourishing and conspicuous. For you know the
					story that Themistocles, when he was thinking of
					entering upon public life, withdrew from drinking-parties and carousals ; he was wakeful at night, was
					sober and deeply thoughtful, explaining to his friends
					that Miltiades' trophy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Militiades was the victorious general at Marathon, 490 b.c.</note> would not let him sleep.
					And Pericles also changed his personal habits of
					life, so that he walked slowly, spoke gently, always
					showed a composed countenance, kept his hand
					under his cloak, and trod only one path - that which
					led to the assembly and the senate. For a populace
					is not a simple and easy thing for any chance person
					to subject to that control which is salutary ; but one
					must be satisfied if the multitude accept authority
					without shying, like a suspicious and capricious beast,
					at face or voice. Since, then, the statesman must
					not treat even these matters carelessly, ought he to
					neglect the things which affect his life and character,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.171"/>
					
					
					that they may be clear of blame and ill report of
					every kind ? For not only are men in public life
					held responsible for their public words and actions,
					but people busy themselves with all their concerns :
					dinner, love affair, marriage, amusement, and every
					serious interest. What need is there, for instance,
					to speak of Alcibiades, who, though he was most
					active of all the citizens in public affairs and was
					undefeated as general, was ruined by his audacious
					and dissolute habits in private life, and, because
					of his extravagance and lack of restraint, deprived
					the State of the benefit of his other good qualities ?
					Why, the Athenians blamed Cimon for wine-drinking,
					and the Romans, having nothing else to say, blamed
					Scipio<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 972 f.</note> for sleeping ; and the enemies of Pompey the
					Great, observing that he scratched his head with
					one finger, reviled him for it.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 89 e, with note <hi rend="italics">a</hi> in Babbitt's translation (L.C.L.), where the habit is spoken of as a mark of effeminacy and licentiousness.</note> For, just as a mole
					or a wart on the face is more unpleasant than brandmarks, mutilations, or scars on other parts of the
					body, so small faults appear great when observed in
					the lives of leaders and statesmen on account of the
					opinion which the majority has of governing and
					public office, regarding it as a great thing which
					ought to be clean of all eccentricities and errors.
					With good reason, therefore, did Livius Drusus the
					tribune gain inreputation because, when many parts of
					his house were exposed to the view of his neighbours
					and an artisan promised to turn them the other way
					and change their position for only five talents,
					Drusus replied, <q direct="unspecified">Take ten and make the whole
						house open to view, that all the citizens may see
						how I live.</q> For he was a man of temperate and
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.173"/>
					
					
					well-ordered life. And perhaps he had no need of
					that exposure to the public view ; for the people
					see through the characters, counsels, acts, and lives
					of public men, even those that seem to be very
					thickly cloaked ; they love and admire one man and
					dislike and despise another quite as much for his
					private as for his public practices.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> you say, <q direct="unspecified">do not States put in office
						men who live licentiously and wantonly?</q> They
					do, and pregnant women often long for stones, and
					seasick persons for salt pickles and the like, which
					then a little later they spew out and detest. So the
					people of democracies, because of the luxury of their
					own lives or through sheer perversity, or for lack of
					better leaders, make use of those who happen to
					turn up, though they loathe and despise them, then
					take pleasure in hearing such things said about them
					as the comic poet Plato puts into the mouth of the
					People itself:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Take, take my hand as quickly as you can;
					</l>
                  <l>I'm going to choose Agyrrhius general<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. p. 652, no. 185; on Agyrrhius <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Plutus</hi>, 176.</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					and again, when he makes the People ask for a basin
					and a feather in order to vomit and then say,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Beside my platform Mantias takes his stand,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the same play as the preceding.</note>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">It feeds foul Cephalus, most hateful pest.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the same play as the preceding.</note>
               </quote>
					And the Roman people, when Carbo promised
					something and confirmed his promise with an oath
					and a curse, unanimously took a counter-oath that
					it did not trust him. And at Lacedaemon, when a
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.175"/>
					
					
					dissolute man named Demosthenes made a desirable
					motion, the people rejected it, but the ephors chose
					by lot one of the elders and told him to make that
					same motion, in order that it might be made acceptable to the people, thus pouring, as it were, from a
					dirty vessel into a clean one. So great is the importance, in a free State, of confidence or lack of
					confidence in a man's character.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>However, we should not on this account neglect
					the charm and power of eloquence and ascribe everything to virtue, but, considering oratory to be, not
					the creator of persuasion but certainly its coworker, we should correct Menander's line,
					<quote rend="blockquote">The speaker's nature, not his speech, persuades,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 135, no. 472.</note>
               </quote>
					for both his nature and his speech do so ; unless,
					indeed, one is to affirm that just as the helmsman, not
					the tiller, steers the ship, and the rider, not the rein,
					turns the horse, so political virtue, employing, not
					speech, but the speaker's character as tiller or rein,
					sways a State, laying hold of it and directing it, as
					it were, from the stern, which is, in fact, as Plato
					says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Critias</hi>, 109 c <q direct="unspecified">only it was not our bodies that they [the gods] constrained by bodily force, like shepherds guiding ther flocks by stroke of staff, but they directed from the stern, where the living creature is easiest to turn about (<foreign lang="greek">h(=| ma/lista eu)/strofon zw=|on</foreign>), laying hold on the soul by persuasion, as by a rudder, according to their own disposition</q> (trans. R. G. Bury in L.C.L.).</note> the easiest way of turning an animal about.
					For those great and, as Homer calls them, <q direct="unspecified">Zeus-descended</q> kings pad themselves out with purple
					robes and sceptres and guards and divine oracles,
					and although they enslaved the multitude by their
					grandeur, as if they were superior beings, they
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.177"/>
					
					
					wished nevertheless to be <q direct="unspecified">speakers of words</q> and
					they did not neglect the charm of speech,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Nor the assemblies in which men make themselves greatly distinguished,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 441.</note>
               </quote>
					and they worshipped not only Zeus of the Council,
					Ares Enyalius, and Athena of War, but they invoked
					also Calliop&ecirc;,
					<quote rend="blockquote">who accompanies reverend monarchs,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Theog.</hi> 80.</note>
               </quote>
					softening by persuasion and overcoming by charms
					the fierce and violent spirit of the people. How,
					then, is it possible that a private person of ordinary
					costume and mien who wishes to lead a State may
					gain power and rule the multitude unless he possesses persuasion and attractive speech ? Now the
					pilots of ships employ others to give orders to the
					rowers, but the statesman needs to have in himself
					the mind that steers and also in himself the speech
					that gives orders, that he may not require some
					other man's voice and be obliged to say, as Iphicrates
					did when defeated through the eloquence of Aristophon's orators, <q direct="unspecified">My opponents' actor is better,
						but superior my play,</q> and may not often need those
					lines of Euripides,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Oh that the seed of wretched men were mute,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 678, no. 987.</note>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Ah, would that deeds of men possessed a voice,
					</l>
                  <l>That clever speakers might become as naught<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 494, no. 439, from the first <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus</hi>.</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.179"/>
					
					
					for these sayings ought perhaps to be granted as
					a refuge to Alcamenes, Nesiotes, Ictinus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Alcamenes and Nesiotes were sculptors of the fifth century b.c. Ictinus was architect of the Parthenon.</note> and all
					artisans and craftsmen if they take an oath that
					they are no speakers ; as once at Athens, when two
					architects were being questioned with a view to a
					public work, one of them, a wheedling and elegant
					speaker, moved the people by declaiming a prepared
					speech about the construction of it, but the other,
					who was a better architect but lacked the power of
					speech, came forward and said : <q direct="unspecified">Men of Athens,
						what he has said, I will do.</q> For, as Sophocles
					says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 309, no. 760, perhaps from the satyr drama <hi rend="italics">Pandora</hi>.</note> only those are servants of the goddess of
					artistry who <q direct="unspecified">on the anvil with a heavy hammer</q>
					and with blows work the yielding and inanimate
					material of their art. But the spokesman for
					Athena of the City and Themis of Counsel,
					<quote rend="blockquote">She who dismisses assemblies of men and who also
					convenes them,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> ii. 69.</note>
               </quote>
					employing speech as his only instrument, moulding
					and adapting some things and softening and smoothing off those which are hindrances to his work, such
					as would be knots in wood or flaws in iron,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Sophist</hi>, 267 e.</note> is an
					ornament to the city. For this reason the government in Pericles' time was <q direct="unspecified">in name,</q> as Thucydides says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucydides, ii. 65. 8.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">a democracy, but in fact the rule of
						the foremost man,</q> because of his power of speech.
					For Cimon also was a good man, as were Ephialtes
					and Thucydides, but when the last named was asked
					by Archidamus King of the Spartans whether he
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.181"/>
					
					
					or Pericles was the better wrestler, he replied,
					<q direct="unspecified">Nobody can tell; for whenever I throw him in
						wrestling, he says he was not thrown and wins by
						persuading the onlookers.</q> And this brought not
					only reputation to Pericles but safety to the State;
					for while it was swayed by him it preserved its
					existing prosperity and refrained from foreign entanglements. But Nicias, whose policy was the
					same, but who lacked such power of persuasion and
					tried to rein in the people with speech as easy as a
					snaffle, could not restrain or master it, but against
					his will went off to Sicily on its back and together
					with it came a cropper. The wolf, they say, cannot
					be held by the ears ; but one must lead a people or
					a State chiefly by the ears, not, as some do who have
					no practice in speaking and seek uncultured and inartistic holds upon the people, pulling them by the
					belly by means of banquets or gifts of money or
					arranging ballet-dances or gladiatorial shows, by
					which they lead the common people or rather curry
					favour with them, tor leadership of a people is
					leadership of those who are persuaded by speech;
					but enticing the mob by such means as have just
					been mentioned is exactly like catching and herding
					irrational beasts.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>The speech of the statesman, however, must not
					be juvenile and theatrical, as if he were making a
					speech for show and weaving a garland of delicate
					and flowery words ; on the other hand it must not,
					as Pytheas said of the speech of Demosthenes,
					smell of the lamp and elaborate literary labour,
					with sharp arguments and with periods precisely
					measured by rule and compass. No, just as musicians
					demand that the touch upon the strings exhibit feeling,
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.183"/>
					
					
					not mere technique, so the speech of the statesman, counsellor, and ruler must not exhibit shrewdness or subtlety, and it must not be to his credit to
					speak fluently or artistically or distributively,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These seem to be somewhat technical words employed by the rhetoricians.</note> but
					his speech must be full of unaffected character,
					true high-mindedness, a father's frankness, foresight, and thoughtful concern for others. His
					speech must also have, in a good cause, a charm
					that pleases and a winning persuasiveness; in addition to nobility of purpose it must possess grace
					arising from stately diction and appropriate and
					persuasive thoughts. And political oratory, much
					more than that used in a court of law, admits
					maxims, historical and mythical tales, and metaphors,
					by means of which those who employ them sparingly
					and at the proper moment move their audiences
					exceedingly ; as did he who said <q direct="unspecified">Do not make
						Hellas one-eyed,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, iii. 1017, p. 1411 a; said by the Athenian orator Leptines, in opposing the destruction of Sparta, one of the <q direct="unspecified">eyes of Greece.</q>
               </note> and Demades when he said he
					was <q direct="unspecified">governing the wreck of the State,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Phocion</hi>, chap. i.</note> and
					Archilochus saying
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Nor let the stone of Tantalus
					</l>
                  <l>Hang o'er the head of this our isle,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 396.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					and Pericles when he bade the Athenians to remove
					<q direct="unspecified">the eyesore of the Peiraeus,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Pericles</hi>, chap. viii. The references is to Aegina, whose thriving commerce threatened the prosperity of the Peiraeus.</note> and Phocion when
					he said with reference to the victory of Leosthenes
					that the furlong race of the war was good, but he
					was fearful about the long-distance race.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Phocion</hi>, chap. xxiii.</note> And, in
					general, loftiness and grandeur of style are more
					fitting for political speech ; examples are the
					<hi rend="italics">Philippics</hi> and among the speeches in Thucydides
					that of the ephor Sthenela&iuml;das, that of King Archidamns
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.185"/>
					
					
					at Plataea, and that of Pericles after the
					pestilence.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucydides, i. 86; ii. 72; ii. 60.</note> But as for the rhetorical efforts and
					grand periods of Ephorus, Theopompus, and Anaximenes, which they deliver after they have armed
					and drawn up the armies, it can be said of them,
					<quote rend="blockquote">None talks so foolishly when near the steel.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 441, l. 22; from the <hi rend="italics">Autolycus</hi> of Euripides.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>It is true, however, that derision and ridicule
					are sometimes proper parts of the statesman's
					speech if employed, not as insults or buffoonery,
					but for needful reproof and disparagement. That
					sort of thing is most laudable in rejoinders and
					replies ; for when employed of set purpose and
					without provocation, it makes the speaker appear
					to be a clown and carries with it a suspicion of malice,
					such as was attached to the ridicule in the speeches
					of Cicero, Cato the Elder, and Aristotle's pupil
					Euxithe&uuml;s, all of whom frequently employed ridicule
					without previous provocation. But for one who
					employs it in self-defence the occasion makes it
					pardonable and at the same time pleasing, as when
					Demosthenes, in reply to a man who was suspected
					of being a thief and who mocked him for writing at
					night, said, <q direct="unspecified">I am aware that I offend you by keeping a light burning,</q> and to Demades who shouted,
					<q direct="unspecified">Demosthenes would correct <hi rend="italics">me</hi> - &lsquo;the sow correcting Athena,&rsquo;</q> he replied, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, your Athena
						was caught in adultery last year!</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These two retorts are recorded by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, chap. xi. p. 851. The second obviously refers to misconduct on the part of Demades. <q direct="unspecified">The sow (teaches or contends with) Athena</q> was a proverbial expression; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Theocritus, <hi rend="italics">Idyl</hi>, v. 23. As <hi rend="italics">sus (docet) Minervam</hi> the proverb was current in Latin; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Festus, p. 310 M&uuml;ller, p. 408 Lindsay; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Ad Familiares</hi>, ix. 18. 3; <hi rend="italics">Academica</hi>, i. 4. 18; <hi rend="italics">De Oratore</hi>, ii. 57. 233.</note> Witty too was
					Xenaenetus's rejoinder to the citizens who reviled
					him for running away when he was general, <q direct="unspecified">Yes,
						
						<pb id="v.10.p.187"/>
						
						
						to keep you company, my dears.</q> But in jesting
					one must guard against going too far and against
					offending one's hearers by jesting at the wrong
					moment or making the speaker appear ignoble and
					mean-spirited, as Democrates did ; for he went up
					into the assembly and said that he, like the State,
					had little strength but much bluster, and at the time
					of the disaster at Chaeroneia he came forward among
					the people and said, <q direct="unspecified">I wish the State had not met
						with so great a misfortune as to make you listen even
						to me as adviser,</q> for this remark showed him to be
					mean-spirited, the other to be crazy, and neither is
					becoming to a statesman. But in Phocion conciseness of speech was admired. At any rate Polyeuctus
					declared that Demosthenes was the greatest orator,
					but Phocion the cleverest in speaking, because his
					speech contained the most meaning in the fewest
					words. And Demosthenes, though he despised
					the other orators, used to say when Phocion rose to
					speak, <q direct="unspecified">The cleaver of my speeches is getting up.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Most of all, then, try to employ in addressing
					the people well-considered, not empty, speech, and
					to use precaution, knowing that even the great
					Pericles used to pray before making a public speech
					that no single utterance foreign to the matter in
					hand might occur to him. But nevertheless the
					orator must always keep his speech nimble and in
					good practice for making apt rejoinders ; for occasions
					arise quickly and often bring with them in public
					affairs sudden developments. That is why Demosthenes was inferior to many, as they say, because
					he drew back and hesitated when the occasion called
					for the opposite course. And Theophrastus tells us
					that Alcibiades,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alcibiades</hi>, chap. x.</note> because he planned, not only to say
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.189"/>
					
					
					the right thing, but to say it in the right way, often
					while actually speaking would search for words
					and arrange them into sentences, thereby causing
					hesitation and failure. But the man who is so
					moved by the events which take place and the
					opportunities which offer themselves that he springs
					to his feet is the one who most thrills the crowd,
					attracts it, and carries it with him. So it was, for
					example, with Leo<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The name Leo, <q direct="unspecified">lion,</q> made the little man seem ridiculous.</note> of Byzantium ; he once came to
					address the Athenians when they were in political
					discord, and when they laughed at him because he
					was a little man, he said, <q direct="unspecified">What if you should see
						my wife, who hardly comes up to my knee?</q>
					Then when they laughed louder, <q direct="unspecified">And yet,</q> he
					said, <q direct="unspecified">little as we are, when we quarrel with each
						other, the city of Byzantium is not big enough to
						hold us.</q> So also when Pytheas the orator was
					speaking in opposition to the granting of honours to
					Alexander and someone said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Do you, at
						your age, dare to speak on such important matters?</q>
					he replied: <q direct="unspecified">And yet Alexander is younger than I,
						and you are voting to make him a god.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>And the statesman must bring to the struggle
					of statecraft - a struggle which is not unimportant,
					but calls for all one's fighting power - speech which
					is severely trained in firmness of voice and strength
					of lungs, that he may not be frequently so weary
					and burnt out as to be defeated by some
					<quote rend="blockquote">Rapacious bawler with a torrent's voice.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Knights</hi>, 137. The reference is to Cleon.</note>
               </quote>
					Cato, when he had no hope of winning his cause by
					persuasion because the popular assembly or the
					senate was gained over beforehand by favours and
					interests, used to get up and speak the whole day,
						
					<pb id="v.10.p.191"/>
					
					
					thus destroying his opponents' opportunity. On the
					subject, then, of the preparation of one's speech and
					the way to use it these remarks are enough for one
					who has the ability to go on and discover the conclusions to be drawn from them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>There are two entrances to public life and two
					paths leading to it: one the quick and brilliant
					road to reputation, by no means without risk, the
					other more prosaic and slower, but safer. For some
					men launch out at once into political life with some
					conspicuous, great, and daring action, like men who
					launch a vessel from a promontory that juts out into
					the sea ; they think Pindar is right in saying
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To a work's beginning we needs must set
					</l>
                  <l>A front that shines afar,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Ol.</hi> vi. 4. The translation is adapted from that of Sir John Sandys (L.C.L.).</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					for the masses are more ready to accept the beginner
					because they are so palled and surfeited with those
					to whom they are accustomed, just as spectators
					at a show are glad to accept a new performer ;
					and authority and power that has a brilliant and
					rapid growth takes envy's breath away. For, as
					Ariston says, fire does not cause smoke, nor reputation
					envy, if it blazes up quickly at the start, but those
					who grow great gradually and slowly are attacked
					one from one side, another from another ; hence
					many men before coming to full bloom as public
					speakers have withered away. But if, as is said of
					Ladas,
					<quote rend="blockquote">The noise o' the barrier's fall was in his ears<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Paton's translation (in L.C.L.) of the phrase in <hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi> xi. 86 on Pericles, quoted from the earlier epigram on Ladas, a famous runner of Sparta. The sudden cutting or loosening of the taut rope stretched across the starting-line was accompanied by an audible sound. See E. N. Gardiner, <hi rend="italics">Jour. Hell. Studies</hi> xxiii. p. 262.</note>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.193"/>
					
					
					even when he has been crowned for Ms brilliant
					success on an embassy, for a notable triumph, or for
					achievement as a general, in such instances neither
					those who envy a man nor those who despise him
					have so much power as before. In this way Aratus
					arrived at fame, beginning his public life with the
					destruction of the tyrant Nicocles ; so Alcibiades, by
					making the Mantinean alliance against the Lacedaemonians. Pompey demanded a triumph although
					he had not yet been admitted to the senate, and
					when Sulla voted against it, he said, <q direct="unspecified">More worship
						the rising than the setting sun</q> ; and Sulla, when
					he heard this, withdrew his opposition. And take
					the case of Cornelius Scipio ; it was not because of
					any chance beginning that the Roman people suddenly and contrary to law appointed him consul
					when he wTas a candidate for the aedileship, but
					rather because they admired his victorious single
					combat in Iberia when he was a mere youth, and his
					deeds a little later at Carthage as military tribune,
					about which Cato the Elder exclaimed
					<quote rend="blockquote">He and he only has sense, the rest are mere flickering
					shadows.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xi. 495 (slightly changed).</note>
               </quote>
					Nowadays, then, when the affairs of the cities no
					longer include leadership in wars, nor the overthrowing of tyrannies, nor acts of alliances, what
					opening for a conspicuous and brilliant public career
					could a young man find ? There remain the public
					lawsuits and embassies to the Emperor, which demand a man of ardent temperament and one who
					possesses both courage and intellect. But there are
					many excellent lines of endeavour that are neglected
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.195"/>
					
					
					in our cities which a man may take up, and also
					many practices resulting from evil custom, that have
					insinuated themselves to the shame or injury of the
					city, which a man may remove, and thus turn them
					to account for himself. Indeed in past times a just
					verdict gained in a great suit, or good faith in acting
					as advocate for a weak client against a powerful
					opponent, or boldness of speech in behalf of the right
					against a wicked ruler, has opened to some men a
					glorious entrance into public life. And not a few
					also have grown great through the enemies they have
					made by attacking men whose position made them
					enviable or caused them to be feared ; for when
					such a man is overthrown his power passes at once,
					and with better reputation, to the man who overcame him. For attacking, through motives of envy,
					a good man who, on account of his virtue, is leader
					of the state, as Pericles was attacked by Simmias,
					Themistocles by Alcmeon, Pompey by Clodius, and
					Epameinondas by Menecleides the orator, is neither
					conducive to a good reputation nor advantageous in
					any other way ; for when the people have committed
					a wrong against a good man and then (which happens
					quickly) repent of their anger, they think the easiest
					way to excuse themselves for this offence is the most
					just, namely, to destroy the man who was the
					author of it and persuaded them to commit it. On
					the other hand, to revolt against a bad man who by
					shameless audacity and cunning has made the city
					subject to himself, such as Cleon and Cleophon were
					at Athens, and to pull him down and humble him
					provides a glorious entrance upon the stage of public
					life. And I am not ignorant of the fact that some
					men by curtailing the power of an oppressive and
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.197"/>
					
					
					oligarchical senate, as Ephialtes did at Athens and
					Phormio at Elis, have gained at the same time both
					power and glory ; but to one who is just entering
					upon public life there is a great risk in this. Therefore
					Solon made a better beginning, when the State was
					divided into three factions called the Diacrians (<q direct="unspecified">hillfolk</q>), the Pedieans (<q direct="unspecified">plainsfolk</q>), and the Paralians
					(<q direct="unspecified">coastfolk</q>) ; for he entangled himself with none of
					them, but acted for all in common and said and did
					everything to bring about concord among them, so
					that he was chosen lawgiver to reconcile their differences and in this way established his rule.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, chap. v.</note> So many,
					then, and of such kinds are the more conspicuous
					ways of entering upon a public career.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But the safe and leisurely way has been chosen by
					many famous men - Aristeides, Phocion, Pammenes
					the Theban, Lucullus at Rome, Cato, the Lacedaemonian Agesila&uuml;s. For just as ivy rises by twining
					itself about a strong tree, so each of these men,
					by attaching himself while still young to an older man
					and while still obscure to a man of reputation, being
					gradually raised up under the shelter of his power
					and growing great with him, fixed himself firmly and
					rooted himself in the affairs of State. For Aristeides
					was made great by Cleisthenes, Phocion by Chabrias,
					Lucullus by Sulla, Cato by Maximus, Epameinondas
					aided Pammenes, and Lysander Agesila&uuml;s. But
					Agesila&uuml;s through untimely ambition and jealousy of
					Lysander's reputation insulted and quickly cast aside
					the guide of his actions ; but the others in noble and
					statesmanlike fashion cherished their teachers until
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.199"/>
					
					
					the end and joined in honouring them, enhancing
					in turn with their own radiance, and illuminating,
					like the heavenly bodies that face the sun, that which
					caused themselves to shine. Certainly Scipio's detractors said that he was the actor, but his friend
					Laelius the real author of his deeds; Laelius, however,
					was not puffed up by any of those sayings but continued
					always eagerly to exalt Scipio's virtue and renown.
					And Pompey's friend Afranius, even though he was
					of humble station, nevertheless expected to be
					elected consul, but when Pompey favoured other
					candidates, he relinquished his ambition, saying that
					gaining the consulship would be to him not so much
					glorious as painful and troublesome, if it were against
					Pompey's will and without his co-operation ; and so
					after waiting only one year he both gained the office
					and retained the friendship.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Pompey</hi>, chap. xliv., where another story concerning the friendship of Pompey for Afranius is told.</note> Those who are thus
					led to renown by the hand of others gain favour
					with many, and at the same time, if anything unpleasant happens, are less disliked ; and that is why
					Philip advised Alexander to gain friends as long as
					he could while another man was king by having
					pleasant intercourse with others and maintaining
					friendly relations with them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>But anyone who is entering upon a public
					career should choose as his leader a man who is not
					merely of established reputation and powerful, but
					one who is all this on account of real worth. For
					just as not every tree will accept and support the
					grape-vine which entwines itself about it, but some
					trees stifle and ruin its growth, so in States, the men
					who are not lovers of what is noble, but merely
					lovers of honours and of office, do not afford young
					men opportunities for public activities, but through
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.201"/>
					
					
					envy repress them and, to speak figuratively, wither
					them up by depriving them of glory, their natural
					nourishment. So Marius, after having achieved
					many successes in Libya and again in Gaul with the
					help of Sulla, ceased to employ him and cast him off,
					being angered by his growth in power, but using the
					incident of the seal as a pretext. For Sulla, when
					Marius was general and he was quaestor<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Equivalent here to adjutant.</note> in Libya,
					was sent by Marius to Bocchus and took Jugurtha
					prisoner ; and being a young man who had just
					had his first taste of glory, he did not bear his good
					fortune with moderation, but had a seal engraved
					with a representation of his deed - Jugurtha surrendering to him - and wore it.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Marius</hi>, chap. x., and <hi rend="italics">Life of Sulla</hi>, chap. iii.</note> Marius threw this
					up against him and cast him off. And Sulla, transferring his allegiance to Catulus and Metellus,
					worthy men and opposed to Marius, quickly drove
					Marius out and broke his power in the civil war
					after he had almost overthrown Rome. Sulla,
					however, exalted Pompey from the time of his
					youth, rising up and uncovering his head when
					he came near ; and also by giving the other young
					men opportunities for acts of leadership and even
					by urging some on against their will, he filled his
					armies with ambition and eagerness ; and he gained
					power over them all by wishing to be, not the only
					great man, but first and greatest among many
					great ones. Such, then, are the men to whom young
					statesmen should attach themselves and cling closely,
					not snatching glory away from them, like Aesop's
					wren who was carried up on the eagle's shoulders,
					then suddenly flew out and got ahead of him, but
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.203"/>
					
					
					receiving it from them in goodwill and friendship,
					knowing that no one can ever command well who
					has not first learned rightly to obey, as Plato says.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 762 e.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Next after this comes the decision to be made
					concerning friends, and here we approve neither the
					idea of Themistocles nor that of Cleon. For Cleon,
					when he first decided to take up political life, brought
					his friends together and renounced his friendship
					with them as something which ofter weakens and
					perverts the right and just choice of policy in political
					life. But he would have done better if he had cast
					out from his soul avarice and love of strife and had
					cleansed himself of envy and malice ; for the State
					needs, not men who have no friends or comrades,
					but good and self-controlled men. As it was, he
					drove away his friends,
					<quote rend="blockquote">But a hundred heads of cursed flatterers circling fawned<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Peace</hi>, 756. The poet refers to Cleon.</note>
               </quote>
					about him, as the comic poets say ; and being rough
					and harsh to the better classes he in turn subjected
					himself to the multitude in order to win its favour,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Its old age tending, dosing it with pay,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Nicias</hi>, chap. ii. p. 524. A parody by an unknown comic poet (unless it be by Aristophanes) of a line from the <hi rend="italics">Peleus</hi> of Sophocles, Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> 447, p. 239. See Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 400.</note>
               </quote>
					and making the basest and most unsound element
					of the people his associates against ;he best. But
					Themistocles on the other hand, when someone said
					that he would govern well if he showed himself
					equally impartial to all, replied : <q direct="unspecified">May I never
						
						<pb id="v.10.p.205"/>
						
						
						take my seat on such a throne that my friends shall
						not have more from me than those who are not my
						friends !</q> He also was wrong; for he put the government under pledge to his friendship, subordinating
					the affairs of the community and the public to private
					favours and interests. And yet when Simonides
					asked for something that was not just, he said to
					him : <q direct="unspecified">Neither is he a good poet who sings contrary to metre, nor is he an equitable ruler who
						grants favours contrary to law.</q> For truly it is an
					outrageous and abominable thing if a pilot selects
					sailors and a ship-captain selects a pilot
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Well knowing how at the stern to hold steady the tiller and
					also
					</l>
                  <l>How to stretch taut the yard ropes when rises the onrushing
					tempest,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Callimachus, Frag. 382, p. 787, ed. Schneider.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					and an architect chooses subordinates and handicraftsmen who will not spoil his work but will co-operate to perfect it, whereas the statesman, who is,
					as Pindar says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Frag. 57, p. 403 Schroeder.</note> the best of craftsmen and the maker
					of lawfulness and justice, does not immediately
					choose friends whose convictions are I ke his own,
					who will aid him and share his enthusiasm for what
					is noble, but rather those who are always wrongfully
					and by violent means trying to divert him to various
					other uses. Such a statesman will be found to be
					no better than a builder or a carpenter who through
					ignorance and error makes use of such squares and
					rulers and levels as are sure to make his work crooked.
					For friends are the living and thinking tools of the
					statesman, and he ought not to slip with them when
					they go wrong, but he must be on the watch that
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.207"/>
					
					
					they do not err even through ignorance. In fact,
					it was this that disgraced Solon and brought him
					into disrepute among the citizens ; for when he
					made up his mind to lighten debts and to introduce
					the Seisachtheia<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The cancellation of debts was one of the chief features of Solon's reorganization of the government of Athens in the sixth century b.c. The popular term means <q direct="unspecified">shaking off burdens.</q> This incident is discussed by Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, chap. vi., where Solon's innocence of wrongdoing is maintained.</note> (that was the nickname for the
					cancellation of debts), he told his friends about
					it, and they did a very wrong thing ; they secretly
					borrowed a great deal of money before the law was
					published, and a little later, after its publication,
					they were found to have bought splendid houses
					and much land with the money they had borrowed,
					and Solon, who was wronged, was accused of sharing
					in their wrongdoing. Agesila&uuml;s, too, showed himself very weak and poor-spirited in dealing with his
					friends' solicitations and, like Pegasus in Euripides'
					drama,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Crouched down and yielded more if more he wished,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Bellerophon</hi>, Frag. 309, p. 451 Nauck. Quoted in part, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 529 e.</note>
               </quote>
					and by too great eagerness in aiding them when in
					misfortunes he made himself seem like them in wrongdoing ; for example, when Phoebidas was on trial
					for seizing the Cadmeia without orders, he got him off
					by saying that such things were bound to happen of
					their own accord ; and when Sphodrias was being
					tried for an illegal and frightful act (for he had invaded Attica when the Athenians were friends and
					allies), he brought about his acquittal, being softened
					by the amorous pleadings of his son. And a note of
					his to a certain ruler is quoted as follows : <q direct="unspecified">If Nicias
						is innocent, let him go ; if he is guilty, let him go for
						my sake; anyway, let him go.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 209 f.</note> But Phocion did
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.209"/>
					
					
					not even appear in support of his son-in-law Charicles
					when he was accused in connexion with the Harpalus
					affair ; he merely said : <q direct="unspecified">I made you my son-in-law
						for nothing but what is right</q> and went away. And
					Timoleon of Corinth,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Timoleon</hi>, chaps. iv., v., pp. 237, 238.</note> when he was unable either by
					instruction or by entreaty to make his brother give up
					his tyranny, joined with those who destroyed him. For
					a statesman ought, by stopping short of being a party
					to perjury, not to be a <q direct="unspecified">friend as far as the altar,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A proverbial expression (Latin <hi rend="italics">usque ad aras</hi>) equivalent to out <q direct="unspecified">to the bitter end</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 531 d.</note>
					as Pericles once said, but only so far as conforms to any
					law, equity, or advantage the neglect of which leads
					to great public injury, as did the failure to punish
					Sphodrias and Phoebidas, for they did a great deal to
					make Sparta enter into the Leuctrian war. For the
					principles that govern a statesman's conduct do not
					force him to act with severity against the moderate
					errors of his friends ; on the contrary, they make it
					possible for him, after he has once made the chief
					public interests safe, out of his abundant resources to
					assist his friends, take his stand beside them, and help
					them out of their troubles. And there are also favours
					which arouse no ill-will, such as aiding a friend to
					gain an office, putting into his hands some honourable
					administrative function or some friendly foreign
					mission, for example one which includes honours to a
					ruler or negotiations with a State concerning friendship and concord ; and if some public activity be
					laborious, but conspicuous and important, the statesman can first appoint himself to the post and then
					choose his friend as assistant, just as Diomedes
					did :
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.211"/>
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>So if you tell me myself to choose another as comrade,
					</l>
                  <l>How in that case could I e'er be forgetful of godlike
					Odysseus?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 242.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And Odysseus again fittingly returns the compliment:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Now these horses, old sir, these new ones, of which thou
					inquirest,
					</l>
                  <l>Thracian they are, but their master was slain by the brave
					Diomedes,
					</l>
                  <l>Slain and beside him his comrades, twelve comrades and
					all of the noblest.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 558.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					For such concession to one's friends adorns those
					who give praise no less than those who receive it;
					but self-conceit, says Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Letters</hi>, iv. 321 b.</note> dwells with loneliness.
					Then, besides, a man ought to ascribe to his friends a
					share in his own good and kindly acts of favour ; he
					should tell those who have been benefited to praise and
					show them affection as the originators and advisers of
					the favours. But base and absurd requests he should
					reject, not harshly but gently, informing the askers
					by way of consolation that the requests are not in
					accord with their own excellence and reputation.
					Epameinondas exemplifies this most admirably: after
					refusing to let the pedlar out of prison at Pelopidas's
					request and then letting him out a little later when
					his mistress asked it, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Favours of that sort,
						Pelopidas, are fit for courtesans to receive, but not
						for generals.</q> But Cato acted harshly and arbitrarily
					when he was quaestor, and Catulus the censor, one of
					his most intimate friends, asked for the acquittal of a
					man who was being tried, by saying : <q direct="unspecified">It is a disgrace that you, whose duty it is to train us young
						men to honourable conduct, have to be thrown out
						by our servants.</q> For he might, while refusing the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.213"/>
					
					
					favour in fact, have avoided harshness and bitterness of speech, by producing the impression that
					the offensive quality of his action was not due to
					his own will, but was forced upon him by law and
					justice. There ai'e also in public life ways which
					are not dishonourable of helping friends who need
					money to acquire it; as, for example, when after
					the battle Themistocles saw a corpse wearing a
					golden bracelet and necklace, he himself passed
					it by, but turned to his friend and said, <q direct="unspecified">Take
						these things, for you are not, as I am, Themistocles.</q>
					For the administration of affairs frequently gives the
					man in public life this sort of chance to help his
					friends ; for not every man is a Menemachus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The friend to whom this essay is addressed.</note> Hand
					over to one friend a case at law which will bring in
					a good fee as advocate in a just cause, to another
					introduce a rich man who needs legal oversight and
					protection, and help another to get some profitable
					contract or lease. Epameinondas even told a friend
					to go to a certain rich man and ask for a talent,
					saying that it was he who bade him give it; and when
					the man who had been asked for it came and asked
					him the reason, he replied : <q direct="unspecified">Because this man is a
						good man and poor, but you are rich since you have
						appropriated much of the State's wealth.</q> And
					Xenophon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Ages.</hi> 4.</note> says that Agesilaiis delighted in enriching
					his friends, he being himself above money.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>But since, to quote Simonides,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 418, no. 68.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">all larks must
					grow a crest,</q> and every public career bears its crop
					of enmities and disagreements, the public man must
					give especial consideration to these matters. So
					most people commend Themistocles and Aristeides
					who, whenever they went on an embassy or in command
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.215"/>
					
					
					of an army, laid down their private enmity at
					the frontier, then took it up again later. And some
					people also are immensely pleased by the conduct of
					Cretinas of Magnesia. He was a political opponent
					of Hermeias, a man who was not powerful but was
					of ambitious spirit and brilliant mind, and when the
					Mithridatic war broke out, seeing that the State was
					in danger, he told Hermeias to take over the command and manage affairs, while he himself withdrew ;
					or, if Hermeias wished him to be general, then
					Hermeias should remove himself, that they might
					not by ambitious strife with one another destroy the
					State. The challenge pleased Hermeias, and saying
					that Cretinas was more versed in war than himself,
					he went away with his wife and children. And as he
					was departing Cretinas escorted him, first giving him
					out of his own means such things as were more useful
					to exiles than to people besieged in a city, after which
					by his excellent military leadership he saved the State
					unexpectedly when it was on the brink of destruction.
					For if it is a noble thing and the mark of an exalted
					spirit to exclaim
					<quote rend="blockquote">I love my children, but I love my country more,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 918, no. 411. Probably from the <hi rend="italics">Erechtheus</hi> of Euripides and spoken by Praxithes, wife of Erechtheus.</note>
               </quote>
					would it not have been easier for each of them to say,
					<q direct="unspecified">I hate so-and-so and wish to do him harm, but
						I love my country more</q>? For to be unwilling to
					make peace with a personal enemy for the sake of
					those things for which we ought even to give up a
					friend is shockingly uncivilized and as low as the
					beasts. Certamly Phoeion and Cato and their like
					acted much better, for they would allow no personal
					enmity to have any bearing whatsoever upon political
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.217"/>
					
					
					differences, but were stern and inexorable only in
					public contests against sacrificing what was for the
					common good ; yet in private matters they treated
					kindly and without anger their political opponents.
					For the statesman should not regard any fellow-citizen as an enemy, unless some man, such as
					Aristion, Nabis, or Catiline, should appear who is
					a pest and a running sore to the State. Those who
					are in other ways out of harmony he should, like a
					skilful musician, bring into unison by gently tightening or relaxing the strings of his control, not attacking angrily and insultingly those who err, but making
					an appeal designed rather to make a moral impression, as Homer does :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Truly, my friend, I did think you surpassed other men in
					your wisdom<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xvii. 171.</note>;</quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Knowledge thou hast to devise other speech that is better
					than this was.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 358.</note>
               </quote>
					But if they say or do anything good, he should not
					be vexed by their honours, nor should he be sparing
					of complimentary words for their good actions ; for
					if we act in this way our blame, where it is needed,
					will be thought justified, and we shall make them
					dislike evil by exalting virtue and showing through
					comparison that good actions are more worthy and
					fitting than the other kind. And I think also that the
					statesman should give testimony in just causes even
					for his opponents, should aid them in court against
					the malicious prosecutors, and should discredit
					calumnies about them if such accusations are alien
					to the principles they profess ; just as the infamous
					Nero, a little before he put Thrasea to death, whom he
					hated and feared intensely, nevertheless when someone
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.219"/>
					
					
					accused him of a bad and unjust decision in court,
					said : <q direct="unspecified">I wish Thrasea were as good a friend to me
						as he is a most excellent judge.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					And it is not a bad method for confounding persons
					of a different kind, men who are naturally vicious and
					prone to evil conduct, to mention to them some
					enemy of theirs who is of finer character and to say :
					<q direct="unspecified">He would not have said that or done that.</q> And
					some men, too, when they do wrong, should be reminded of their excellent fathers, as Homer says :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Truly not much like his sire is the son who was gotten by
					Tydeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> v. 800, referring to Diomedes.</note>;</quote>
					And Appius, when competing with Scipio Africanus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Scipio Africanus the younger (185-129 b.c.) was the son of Lucius Aemilius Paulus.</note>
					in the elections, said : <q direct="unspecified">O Paulus, how you would
						groan in the lower world if you saw that when your
						son was standing for the censorship Philonicus the
						publican acted as his bodyguard!</q> Such sayings
					serve at once to rebuke wrongdoers and to add
					lustre to those who administer the rebuke. And
					the Nestor of Sophocles, too, made a statesmanlike
					reply when reviled by Ajax :
					<quote rend="blockquote">I blame thee not; for good thy acts, though ill thy speech.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 312, no. 771.</note>
               </quote>
					And Cato, although he had opposed Pompey in the
					violent measures which he and Caesar applied to the
					State, when war broke out between them advised
					handing over the leadership to Pompey, saying :
					<q direct="unspecified">The men who can bring about great evils can also
						end them.</q> For blame wThich is mingled with praise
					and contains nothing insulting but merely frankness
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.221"/>
					
					
					of speech, and arouses not anger but a pricking of
					the conscience and repentance, appears both kindly
					and healing ; but abusive speech is not at all fitting
					for statesmen. Observe the things that were said
					by Demosthenes against Aeschines and by Aeschines
					against him and again those which Hypereides
					wrote against Demades, and ask yourself if a Solon
					or a Pericles or Lycurgus the Lacedaemonian or
					Pittacus the Lesbian would have said them. And
					yet even Demosthenes employs abuse only in his
					speeches before a court of law ; the Philippics are
					free from all jeering and scurrility. For such things
					bring disgrace upon the speakers rather than upon
					those spoken of, and moreover they bring confusion
					into the conduct of affairs and they disturb councils
					and assemblies. Therefore Phocion did well when
					he stopped speaking and yielded the floor to a man
					who was reviling him, and then, when the fellow had
					at last become silent, came forward again saying :
					<q direct="unspecified">Well, then, about the cavalry and the heavy
						infantry you have heard already ; it remains for me
						to discuss the light infantry and the targeteers.</q>
					But since many men find it hard to endure that sort
					of thing quietly, and abusive speakers are often,
					and not without general benefit, made to shut their
					mouths by the retorts they evoke, let the reply
					be brief in wording, showing no temper and no
					extreme rancour, but urbanity mingled with playfulness and grace which somehow or other has a sting
					in it. Retorts which turn his own words back upon
					the speaker are especially good in this way. For
					just as things which are thrown and return to the
					thrower seem to do this because they are driven
					back by some force and firmness of that against
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.223"/>
					
					
					which they are thrown, so that which is spoken seems
					through the force and intellect of him who has been
					abused to turn back upon those who uttered the
					abuse. For example, the retort of Epameinondas
					to Callistratus, who reproached the Thebans and the
					Argives because Oedipus killed his f ither and Orestes
					killed his mother : <q direct="unspecified">When we had driven out the
						doers of those deeds, you took them in,</q> and that of
					Antalcidas the Spartan to the Athenian who said
					<q direct="unspecified">We have often chased you away from the Cephissus,</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Yes, but we have never had to chase you from the
						Eurotas.</q> And Phocion also made a witty retort,
					when, after Demades had screamed <q direct="unspecified">The Athenians
						will put you to death,</q> he replied, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, if they are
							crazy ; but you are the one whom t ley will execute,
							if they are sane.</q> And Crassus the orator, when
					Domitius said to him, <q direct="unspecified">It was you. was it not, who
						wept when a lamprey died that you kept in a tank ?</q>
					retorted with the question, <q direct="unspecified">It was you, was it not,
						who buried three wives without shedding a tear?</q>
					Apt replies of this sort, however, ;ire of some use
					also in life in general.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>There are men who enter upon every kind of
					public service, as Cato did, claiming that the good
					citizen ought, so far as in him lies, tc omit no trouble
					or diligence ; and they commend Epameinondas
					because, when through envy and is an insult he
					had been appointed <hi rend="italics">telmarch</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">No such official as <hi rend="italics">telearchos</hi> is mentioned elsewhere, and the word itself describes no function. On the other hand, <hi rend="italics">telmarchos</hi> or <hi rend="italics">telmatarchos</hi>, conjectured independently by Winckelmann and van Herwerden, although not found elsewhere, gives a meaning which accords with Plutarch's description, <q direct="unspecified">official of stagnant pools,</q> or a special kind of collector of refuse and other nuisances from the streets, very like the <hi rend="italics">koprologoi</hi> of Athens.</note> by the Thebans, he did
					not neglect his duties, but saying thit not only does
					the office distinguish the man, but also the man the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.225"/>
					
					
					office, he advanced the <hi rend="italics">telmarchy</hi> to a position of
					great consideration and dignity, though previously
					it had been nothing but a sort of supervision of the
					alleys for the removal of dung and the draining off of
					water in the streets. And no doubt I myself seem
					ridiculous to visitors in our town when I am seen
					in public, as I often am, engaged in such matters.
					But I am helped by the remark of Antisthenes which
					has been handed down to memory ; for when someone expressed surprise that he himself carried a dried
					fish through the market-place, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, but
						it's for myself</q> ; but I, on the other hand, say to
					those who criticize me for standing and watching tiles
					being measured or concrete or stones being delivered,
					that I attend to these things, not for myself, but for
					my native place. Yes, for there are many other
					things in regard to which a man would be petty and
					sordid who managed them for himself and attended
					to them for his own sake, but if he does it for the
					public and for the State's sake, he is not ignoble, on
					the contrary his attention to duty and his zeal are
					all the greater when applied to little things. But
					there are others who think the conduct of Pericles
					was more dignified and splendid, one of whom is
					Critolaiis the Peripatetic, who clsims that just as
					the Salaminia and the Paralus, ships at Athens, were
					not sent out to sea for every service, but only for
					necessary and important missions, so the statesman
					should employ himself for the most momentous and
					important matters, as does the King of the Universe,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>For God great things doth take in hand,
					</l>
                  <l>But small tilings passing by he leaves to chance,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 675, no. 974. From an unknown play, quoted also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 464 a.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					according to Euripides,
					<pb id="v.10.p.227"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>
					Neither do we commend the ambition and contentiousness of Theagenes who, after being victorious,
					not only in the circuit of festivals,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Refers to the four great festivals: the Olympic, the Pythian, the Isthmian, and the Nemean games.</note> but in many other
					contests besides, not only in the pancratium, but
					also in boxing and long-distance running,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The length was twenty stadia, slightly more than two and a quarter miles.</note> at last,
					when at certain commemorative funeral ceremonies
					he was partaking of the feast to honour the deceased
					as a hero, and all present had, as was the custom,
					their several portions already set before them, sprang
					up and performed a whole pancratium, as if it were
					wrong for anyone else to be a victor when he was
					present; for he had collected by such means twelve
					hundred head-bands, most of which might be regarded as rubbish. Now there is no difference
					between him and those who strip for every political
					activity ; they soon cause themselves to be criticized
					by the multitude ; they become unpopular and arouse
					envy when they are successful, but joy when they
					meet with failure ; and that which was admired in
					them when they began to hold office results at last
					in mockery and ridicule. Such are the lines :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Metiochus, you see, is general, Metiochi s inspects the roads,
					</l>
                  <l>Metiochus inspects the bread, and Metiochus inspects the
					flour,
					</l>
                  <l>Metiochus takes care of all things, Metiochus will come to
					grief.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From a poet of the Old Comedy, Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 629, no. 1325.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					He was one of Pericles' followers and seems to have
					used the power gained through him in such a way
					as to arouse odium and disgust. Far the statesman
					ought, as they say, to find the people fond of him
					when he comes to them and to leave a longing for
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.229"/>
					
					
					him when he is not there ; which Scipio Africanus
					accomplished by spending much of his time in the
					country, thereby at one and the same time removing
					the weight of envy and giving a breathing-space to
					those who thought they were oppressed by his glory.
					But Timesias of Clazomenae was in other respects
					a good man in his service to the State, but by doing
					everything himself he had aroused rancour and
					hatred ; but of this he was unaware until the following incident took place : - Some boys were knocking
					a knuckle-bone out of a hole when he was passing by ;
					and some of them said it was still in the hole, but
					the boy who had struck at it said : <q direct="unspecified">I'd like to knock
						the brains out of Timesias as truly as this has been
						knocked out of the hole.</q> Timesias, hearing this
					and understanding that dislike of him had permeated
					all the people, returned home and told his wife what
					had happened; and directing her to pack up and follow
					him, he went immediately away from his house and
					out from the city. And it appears that Themistocles,
					when he met with some such treatment from the
					Athenians, said, <q direct="unspecified">Why, my dear people, are you
						tired of receiving repeated benefits?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Now of such sayings some are well said, others are
					not. For so far as goodwill and solicitude for the
					common weal are concerned, a statesman should not
					hold aloof from any part of public affairs, but should
					pay attention to them all and infoim himself about
					all details ; nor should he, as the ship's gear called
					sacred<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Meaning the largest anchor, held in reserve and used only in a crisis; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> below, 815 d and Lucian, <hi rend="italics">Iuppiter Tragoedus</hi>, chap. li. and scholium.</note> is stowed apart, hold himself aloof, waiting
					for the extreme necessities and fortunes of the State;
					but just as pilots do some things wit i their own hands
					but perform other duties by means of different
					instruments operated by different agents, thus giving
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.231"/>
					
					
					a turn or a twist to the instruments while they sit
					apart, and they make use of sailors, look-out men,
					and boatswains, some of whom they often call to
					the stern and entrust with the tiller, just so it
					is fitting that the statesman should yield office to
					others and should invite them to the orators' platform in a gracious and kindly manner, and he should
					not try to administer all the affairs of the State by
					his own speeches, decrees, and actions, but should
					have good, trustworthy men and employ each of
					them for each particular service according to his fitness. So Pericles made use of Menippus for the
					position of general, humbled the Council of the
					Areopagus by means of Ephialtes, passed the decree
					against the Megarians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Passed in 432 b.c. excluding Megara from commerce with Athens and her allies.</note> by means of Charinus, and
					sent Lampon out as founder of Thurii. For, when
					power seems to be distributed among many, not
					only does the weight of hatreds and enmities become
					less troublesome, but there is also greater efficiency
					in the conduct of affairs. For just as the division of
					the hand into fingers does not make it weak, but
					renders it a more skillful instrument for use, so the
					statesman who gives to others a share in the government makes action more effective by co-operation.
					But he who through insatiable greed of fame or power
					puts the whole burden of the State upon himself and
					sets himself even to tasks for which he is not fitted
					by nature or by training (as Cleon set himself to
					leading armies, Philopoemen to commanding ships,
					and Hannibal to haranguing the people) - such a
					man has no excuse when he makes mistakes, but
					will have to hear Euripides quoted to boot,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>A joiner thou, yet didst a task essay
					</l>
                  <l>That was no carpentry.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 678, no. 988.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.233"/>
					
					
					So, being no persuasive speaker, you went on an
					embassy, or being easy-going you undertook administration, being ignorant of accounting you were treasurer, or when old and feeble you took command of an
					army. Rut Pericles divided the power with Cimon so
					that he should himself be ruler in the city and Cimon
					should man the ships and wage war against the barbarians ; for one of them was more gifted for civic
					government, the other for war. And Eubulus the
					Anaphlystian also is commended because, although
					few men enjoyed so much confidence and power as
					he, yet he administered none of the Hellenic affairs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Negotiations with other Greek states.</note>
					and did not take the post of general, but applied
					himself to the finances, increased the revenues, and
					did the State much good thereby. But Iphicrates
					was jeered at when he did exercises in speaking at
					his home in the presence of many hearers ; for even
					if he had been a good speaker, and not, as he was, a
					poor one, he ought to have been contented with glory
					in arms and to have left the school to the sophists.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>But since there is in every democracy a spirit
					of malice and fault-finding directed against men in
					public life, and they suspect that many desirable
					measures, if there is no party opposition and no expression of dissent, are done by conspiracy, and this
					subjects a man's associations and friends to calumny,
					statesmen ought not to let any real enmity or
					disagreement against themselves subsist, as Onomademus the popular leader of the Chians did when,
					after his victory in the factional strife, he refused
					to have all his opponents banished from the city,
					<q direct="unspecified">that we may not,</q> he said <q direct="unspecified">begin to quarrel with
						our friends when we have altogether got rid of our
						enemies.</q> Now that was silly ; but when the populace
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.235"/>
					
					
					are suspicious about some important and salutary
					measure, the statesmen when they come to the
					assembly ought not all to express the same opinion,
					as if by previous agreement, but two or three of the
					friends should dissent and quietly speak on the other
					side, then change their position as if they had been
					convinced ; for in this way they draw the people
					along with them, since they appear to be influenced
					only by the public advantage. In small matters,
					however, which do not amount to much, it is not a
					bad thing to let one's friends really disagree, each
					following his own reasoning, that in matters of the
					highest importance their agreement upon the best
					policy may not seem to be prearranged.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Now the statesman is always by nature ruler
					of the State, like the leader<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greeks did not know that the most important bee in the hive was female - the queen bee.</note> bee in the hive, and bearing this in mind he ought to keep public matters in
					his own hands ; but offices which are called <q direct="unspecified">authorities</q> and are elective he ought not to seek too
					eagerly or often, for love of office is neither dignified
					nor popular ; nor should he refuse them, if the people
					offer them and call him to them in accordance with
					the law, but even if they be too small for a man
					of his reputation, he should accept them and exercise them with zeal; for it is right that men who
					are adorned with the highest offices should in turn
					adorn the lesser, and that statesmen should show
					moderation, giving up and yielding some part of the
					weightier offices, such as the generalship at Athens,
					the prytany at Rhodes, and the Boeotarchy here,
					and should add to the minor offices dignity and
					grandeur, that we may not be despised in connexion
					with the latter, nor envied on account of the former.
					And when entering upon any office whatsoever, you
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.237"/>
					
					
					must not only call to mind those considerations of
					which Pericles reminded himself when he assumed
					the cloak of a general: <q direct="unspecified">Take care, Pericles ;
						you are ruling free men, you are ruling Greeks,
						Athenian citizens,</q> but you must also say to yourself:
					<q direct="unspecified">You who rule are a subject, ruling a State controlled by proconsuls, the agents of Caesar ; &lsquo;these
						are not the spearmen of the plain,&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Trachiniae</hi>, 1058.</note> nor is this
						ancient Sardis, nor the famed Lydian power.</q> You
					should arrange your cloak more carefully and from
					the office of the generals keep your eyes upon the
					orators' platform, and not have great pride or confidence in your crown, since you see the boots of
					Roman soldiers just above your head. No, you
					should imitate the actors, who, while putting into
					the performance their own passion, character, and
					reputation, yet listen to the prompter and do not
					go beyond the degree of liberty in rhythms and
					metres permitted by those in authority over them.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In Greece of Plutarch's time <q direct="unspecified">those in authority</q> in political matters were the Romans.</note>
					For to fail in one's part in public life brings not
					mere hissing or catcalls or stamping of feet, but
					many have experienced
					<quote rend="blockquote">The dread chastiser, axe that cleaves the neck,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 918, no. 412; from an unknown play.</note>
               </quote>
					as did your countryman Pardalas and his followers
					when they forgot their proper limitations. And
					many another, banished to an island, has become, as
					Solon says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 34.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Pholegandrian or Sicinete,
					</l>
                  <l>No more Athenian, having changed his home.</l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.239"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>
					Furthermore when we see little children trying
					playfully to bind their fathers' shoes on their feet
					or fit their crowns upon their heads, we only laugh,
					but the officials in the cities, when they foolishly urge
					the people to imitate the deeds, ideals, and actions
					of their ancestors, however unsuitable they may be
					to the present times and conditions, stir up the
					common folk and, though what they do is laughable, what is done to them is no laughing matter,
					unless they are merely treated with utter contempt.
					Indeed there are many acts of the Greeks of former
					times by recounting which the statesman can mould
					and correct the characters of our contemporaries,
					for example, at Athens by calling to mind, not
					deeds in war, but such things as the decree of amnesty
					after the downfall of the Thirty Tyrants, the fining
					of Phrynichus for presenting in a tragedy the capture
					of Miletus, their decking their heads with garlands
					when Cassander refounded Thebes ; how, when they
					heard of the clubbing at Argos, in which the Argives
					killed fifteen hundred of their own citizens, they
					decreed that an expiatory sacrifice be carried about
					in the assembly ; and how, when they were searching the houses at the time of Harpalus's frauds,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Thirty Tyrants at Athens were overthrown in 403 b.c.; Phrynichus presented the tragedy shortly after Miletus was captured by the Persians in 494 b.c.; Cassander refounded Thebes in 316-315 b.c., ten years after its destruction by Alexander; the clubbing of aristocrats at Argos by the mob took place in 370 b.c.; Harpalus, Alexander's treasurer, brought to Athens in 329 b.c. funds stolen from Alexander and was supposed to have bribed many prominent Athenians, one of whom was Demosthenes.</note> they
					passed by only one, that of a newly married man.
					By emulating acts like these it is even now possible
					to resemble our ancestors, but Marathon, the
					Eurymedon, Plataea, and all the other examples
					which make the common folk vainly to swell with
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.241"/>
					
					
					pride and kick up their heels, should be left to the
					schools of the sophists.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>And not only should the statesman show himself and his native State blameless towards our
					rulers,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Romans.</note> but he should also have always a friend
					among the men of high station who have the greatest
					power as a firm bulwark, so to speak, of his administration ; for the Romans themselves are most eager
					to promote the political interests of their friends ;
					and it is a fine thing also, when we gain advantage
					from the friendship of great men, to turn it to the
					welfare of our community, as Polybius and Panaetius,
					through Scipio's goodwill towards them, conferred
					great benefits upon their native States.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Arcadia and Rhodes respectively. Polybius was a statesman and historian, Panaetius a Stoic philosopher.</note> And Caesar,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Augustus Caesar is meant. For a further account of his treatment of Areius see <hi rend="italics">Life of Antony</hi>, chap. lxxx.</note>
					when he took Alexandria, drove into the city holding
					Areius by the hand and conversing with him only of
					all his friends, then said to the Alexandrians, who
					were expecting the most extreme measures and were
					begging for mercy, that he pardoned them on account
					of the greatness of their city and for the sake of its
					founder Alexander, <q direct="unspecified">and thirdly,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">as a
						favour to my friend here.</q> Is there any comparison
					between such a favour and the procuratorships and
					governorships of provinces from which many talents
					may be gained and in pursuit of which most public
					men grow old haunting the doors of other men's
					houses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This refers to the Roman custom of greeting at the front door.</note> and leaving their own affairs uncared for ?
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.243"/>
					
					
					Or should we correct Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides in <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 524 f. represents Eteocles as saying - <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l><foreign lang="greek">ei)/per ga\r a)dikei=n xrh/, turanni/dos pe/ri </foreign></l><l><foreign lang="greek">ka/lliston a)dikei=n</foreign>.</l></quote>
                  <p/>
                  <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>If wrong be ever right, for the throne's sake </l>
                     <l>Were wrong most right. (Way's translation.)</l>
                  </quote> If Plutarch quotes this passage, correcting it to suit his purpose, he simply substitutes <foreign lang="greek">a)grupnei=n</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">a)dikei=n</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">patri/dos</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">turanni/dos</foreign>. And the sentiment about equality, as the basis of true friendship, seems to be an echo of 535 f. of the same play. This method of dealing with passages from the poets is not infrequently employed by Plutarch.</note> when he chants
					the sentiment that if a man must spend sleepless
					nights and haunt another mans court and subject
					himself to an intimacy with a great man, it is best to
					do so for the sake of his native land, but otherwise
					it is best to welcome and hold fast friendships based
					on equality and justice ?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>However, the statesman, while making his
					native State readily obedient to its sovereigns, must
					not further humble it ; nor, when the leg has been
					fettered, go on and subject the neck to the yoke, as
					some do who, by referring everything, great or small,
					to the sovereigns, bring the reproach of slavery upon
					their country, or rather wholly destroy its constitutional government,making it dazed, timid, and powerless in everything. For just as those who have become accustomed neither to dine nor to bathe except
					by the physician's orders do not even enjoy that
					degree of health which nature grants them, so those
					who invite the sovereign's decision on every decree,
					meeting of a council, granting of a privilege,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This doubtless refers to honorary citizenship, crowns, statues, and the like.</note> or
					administrative measure, force their sovereign to be
					their master more than he desires. And the cause of
					this is chiefly the greed and contentiousness of the
					foremost citizens ; for either, in cases in which they
					are injuring their inferiors, they force them into
					exile from the State, or, in matters concerning which
					they differ among themselves, since they are unwilling
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.245"/>
					
					
					to occupy an inferior position among their
					fellow-citizens, they call in those who are mightier;
					and as a result senate, popular assembly, courts, and
					the entire local government lose their authority. But
					the statesman should soothe the ordinary citizens by
					granting them equality and the powerful by concessions in return, thus keeping them within the
					bounds of the local government and solving their
					difficulties as if they were diseases, making for
					them, as it were, a sort of secret political medicine; he will prefer to be himself defeated among
					his fellow-citizens rather than to be successful by
					outraging and destroying the principles of justice
					in his own city and he will beg everyone else to do
					likewise, and will teach them how great an evil is
					contentiousness. But as it is, not only do they not
					make honourable and gracious compromises with their
					fellow-citizens and tribesmen<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The citizens of most ancient states were divided into tribes or clans.</note> at home and with their
					neighbours and colleagues in office, but they carry
					their dissensions outside to the doors of professional
					orators and put them in the hands of lawyers, to their
					own great injury and disgrace. For when physicians
					cannot entirely eradicate diseases, they turn them
					outwards to the surface of the body ; but the statesman, if he cannot keep the State entirely free from
					troubles, will at any rate try to cure and control whatever disturbs it and causes sedition, keeping it meanwhile hidden within the State, so that it may have
					as little need as possible of physicians and medicine
					drawn from outside. For the policy of the statesman should be that which holds fast to security and
					avoids the tumultuous and mad impulse of empty
					opinion, as has been said. In his disposition, however, high spirit and
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.247"/>
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>courage must be, full of daring,
					</l>
                  <l>Dauntless, and such as inspires all men who for weal of
					their country
					</l>
                  <l>'Gainst men of hostile intent<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvii. 156 ff.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					and against difficult conditions and times stand
					firm in resistance and struggle to the end. For
					he must not create storms himself, and yet he
					must not desert the State when storms fall upon
					it; he must not stir up the State and make it reel
					perilously, but when it is reeling and in danger, he
					must come to its assistance and employ his frankness of speech as a sacred anchor<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note on 812 b above.</note> heaved over in
					the greatest perils. Such were the troubles which
					overtook the Pergamenes under Nero and the
					Rhodians recently under Domitian and the Thessalians earlier under Augustus, when they burned
					Petraeus alive.
					<quote rend="blockquote">Then slumb'ring thou never wouldst see him,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 223. Spoken of Agamemnon.</note>
               </quote>
					nor cowering in fear, the man who is really a statesman, nor would you see him throwing blame upon
					others and putting himself out of danger, but you
					will see him serving on embassies, sailing the seas and
					saying first not only
					<quote rend="blockquote">Here we have come, the slayers; avert thou the plague, O
					Apollo,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Callimachus, p. 787 ed. Schneider.</note>
               </quote>
					but, even though he had no part in the wrongdoing
					of the people, taking dangers upon himself in their
					behalf. For this is noble ; and besides being noble,
					one man's excellence and wisdom by arousing admiration has often mitigated anger which has been
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.249"/>
					
					
					aroused against the whole people and has dissipated
					the threatened terror and bitterness. Something
					of that sort seems to have happened to the Persian
					king in the case of Boulis and Sperchis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story of these two is told in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 235 f, 236.</note> the Spartans,
					and happened to Pompey in the case of Sthenno,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 203 d, where the name is Sthennius, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Pompey</hi>, chap. x.</note>
					when, as he was going to punish the Mamertines
					for revolting, Sthenno told him that he would be
					doing wrong if he should destroy many innocent
					men for the fault of one ; for, he said, it was he
					himself who had caused the city to revolt by persuading his friends and compelling his enemies.
					This so affected Pompey that he let the city go
					unpunished and also treated Sthenno kindly. But
					Sulla's guest-friend, practising virtue of the same
					sort but not having to do with the same sort of man,
					met with a noble end. For when Sulla, after the
					capture of Praenest&ecirc;, was going to slaughter all the
					rest of the citizens but was letting that one man go
					on account of his guest-friendship, he declared that
					he would not be indebted for his life to the slayer
					of his fatherland, and then mingled with his fellow-citizens and was cut down with them. However, we
					must pray to be spared such crises and must hope
					for better things.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>And deeming every public office to be something great and sacred, we must also pay the
					highest honour to one who holds an office ; but
					the honour of an office resides in concord and
					friendship with one's colleagues much more than
					in crowns and a purple-bordered robe. But those
					who consider that serving together in a campaign or
					in the school for young citizens<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Athenian youths from eighteen to twenty years of age were called <hi rend="italics">ephebi</hi>. For one year they were trained chiefly in gymnastics and military drill, then for a year they served as guards on the frontier. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, chap. xlii.</note> is the beginning
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.251"/>
					
					
					of friendship, but regard joint service in the generalship or other office as the cause of enmity, have
					failed to avoid one of the three evils ; for either
					they regard their colleagues as their equals and
					are themselves factious, or they envy them as their
					superiors, or despise them as their inferiors. But
					a man ought to conciliate his superior, add prestige
					to his inferior, honour his equal, and be affable and
					friendly to all, considering that they have been made
					<quote rend="blockquote">Friends, not of festive board,</quote>
					nor of tankard,
					<quote rend="blockquote">nor of fireside's cheer,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apparently a quotation from a comedy. See Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 495.</note>
               </quote>
					but all alike by vote of the people, and that they
					bear goodwill toward one another as a heritage, so to
					speak, from their fatherland. At any rate Scipio was
					criticized in Rome because, when he entertained his
					friends at the dedication of the temple of Hercules, he
					did not include his colleague Mummius ; for even if
					in general the two men did not consider themselves
					friends, on such occasions they usually thought it
					proper to show honour and friendliness to each other
					on account of their office. Inasmuch, therefore, as
					the omission of so slight an act of courtesy brought a
					reputation for haughtiness to Scipio, a man in other
					respects admirable, how can anyone be considered
					honourable and fair-minded who detracts from the
					dignity of a colleague in office, or maliciously flouts
					him by actions which reveal ambitious rivalry, or
					is so self-willed that he arrogates and annexes to
					himself everything, in short, at the expense of his
					colleague ? I recollect that when I was still a
					young man I was sent with another as envoy to
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.253"/>
					
					
					the proconsul; the other man was somehow left
					behind ; I alone met the proconsul and accomplished
					the business. Now when I came back and was
					to make the report of our mission, my father left
					his seat and told me in private not to say <q direct="unspecified">I went,</q>
					but <q direct="unspecified">we went,</q> not <q direct="unspecified">I said,</q> but <q direct="unspecified">we said,</q> and in
					all other ways to associate my colleague in a joint
					report. For that sort of thing is not only honourable
					and kind, but it also takes the sting out of any envy
					of our reputation. And therefore great men ascribe
					to God and to Fortune a share in their successes,
					as Timoleon, who put down the tyrannies in Sicily,
					founded a sanctuary of Automatia (Chance) ; and
					Python, when he was admired and honoured by the
					Athenians for slaying Cotys, said <q direct="unspecified">God did this,
						borrowing from me the hand that did the deed.</q>
					And Theopompus, King of the Lacedaemonians,
					replied to the man who said that Sparta was preserved because the kings were fitted to rule, <q direct="unspecified">No,
						it is rather because the people are fitted to obey.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Now both of these arise from each other.
					Most people say and believe that it is the business
					of political teaching to cause men to be good subjects ; for, they say, the subject class is in every
					State larger than the ruling class; and each official
					rules but a short time, whereas he is ruled all the
					time, if he is a citizen of a democracy ; so that it is
					a most excellent and useful thing to learn to obey
					those in authority, even if they happen to be deficient in power and reputation. For it is absurd
					that in a tragedy the chief actor, even though he is
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.255"/>
					
					
					a Theodorus or a Polus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theodorus and Polus were famous actors at Athens in the fourth century b.c. See J. B. O'Connor, <hi rend="italics">Chapters in the History of Actors and Acting in Ancient Greece</hi>, pp. 100, 128. The terms <foreign lang="greek">tragw|do/s</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">kwmw|do/s</foreign> were used for actors who had been assigned to the highest rank and were privileged to bring out old plays at the festivals, and they stand in sharp contrast to the <q direct="unspecified">hireling</q> actors, usually referred to after Demosthenes' time as <q direct="unspecified">tritagonists,</q> to whom were often given the <q direct="unspecified">third-class</q> roles of kings; see <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> chap. i.</note> often makes his entrance
					after a hireling who takes third-class parts and addresses him in humble fashion, just because the
					latter wears the diadem and sceptre, but that in real
					affairs and in government the rich and famous man
					belittles and despises the official who is plebeian and
					poor, thereby using his own high standing to insult
					and destroy that of the State, instead of enhancing
					it rather and adding to the office the esteem and
					power derived from himself. So at Sparta the kings
					gave precedence to the ephors, and if any other
					Spartan was summoned, he did not walk slowly in
					obeying the summons, but by running eagerly at
					full speed through the market-place they exhibited
					to their fellow-citizens their spirit of obedience,
					rejoicing in paying honour to their rulers. They
					did not behave like some uncultured and unmannerly
					persons who, as if swaggering in the excess of their
					own power, abuse the umpires at the games, revile
					the choregi at the Dionysiac festival, and jeer at
					generals and gymnasiarchs, not knowing and not
					understanding that it is often more glorious to pay
					honour than to receive it. For to a man who has
					great power in the State greater distinction accrues
					through serving in the bodyguard and the escort of
					an official than through being so served and escorted
					by him, or rather the latter brings him dislike and
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.257"/>
					
					
					envy, but the former brings true reputation, that
					which comes from goodwill; and by being seen
					sometimes at the official's door, by greeting him
					first, and by putting him in the middle place<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Cicero</hi>, chap. ii., <q direct="unspecified">Cicero placed in their midst, as a mark of honour,</q> Perrin's translation, L.C.L.</note> in
					walking a man adds lustre to the State without
					taking anything from himself.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>And it is also a service to the people sometimes to endure the evil speech and anger of a man
					in office, repeating to oneself either the words of
					Diomedes :
					<quote rend="blockquote">For unto him will accrue mighty glory,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 415.</note>
               </quote>
					or the saying of Demosthenes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, xxi. (<hi rend="italics">Against Meidias</hi>) 524. Meidias had insulted Demosthenes in public when Demosthenes was choregus, officially appointed to bear the expense of a chorus.</note> that now he is not
					only Demosthenes, but also one of the thesmothetae,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The thesmothetae were the six junior archons at Athens. Their chief duty was supervision of the courts of law.</note>
					or a choregus, or the wearer of a crown.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The stephanephori were officials whose duties varied in different cities. At Athens they were concerned with public festivals.</note> We should,
					therefore, put off our requital to the right time ;
					for then either we shall attack him after his term of
					office is ended or in the delay our gain will be the
					cessation of anger.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>One should, however, always vie with every
					official in zeal, forethought for the common good,
					and wisdom ; if they are worthy men, by voluntarily
					suggesting and pointing out the things to be done
					and allowing them to make use of well-considered
					ideas and to be held in high esteem because they
					are benefactors of the community. But if there is
					in them any reluctance, delay, or ill-will as to putting
					such suggestions into effect, then a man ought to
					come forward of himself and address the people, and
					he should not neglect or slight the public interests
					on the ground that because someone else is in office
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.259"/>
					
					
					it is not proper for him to meddle and mix in the
					administration of affairs. For the law always gives
					the first rank in the government to him who does
					what is right and recognizes what is advantageous.
					<q direct="unspecified">Now there was,</q> says he,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The author of the <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>. But Plutarch may have written <foreign lang="greek">fhsi\n au)to/s</foreign>.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">in the army a man
						named Xenophon, neither a general nor a captain,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Anab.</hi> iii. 1. 4.</note>
					but by perceiving what was needed and daring to do
					it he put himself in command and saved the Greeks.
					And of Philopoemen's deeds the most brilliant is
					this, that when Nabis had taken Messen&ecirc;, and the
					general of the Achaeans was so cowardly that he
					would not go to the assistance of the place, he himself with the most eager patriots set out and took
					the city without any decree of the council. Certainly
					it is well to make innovations, not for the sake of
					small or casual matters, but in cases of necessity,
					as Philopoemen did, or for glorious causes, as Epameinondas did when contrary to the law he added
					four months to the Boeotarchy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Boeotarchy was the chief office of the Boeotian confederacy. Its term was one year.</note> in which time he
					invaded Laconia and carried out his measures at
					Messen&ecirc;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These measures included the freeing of Messenia from Spartan domination and the founding of the city of Messen&ecirc;.</note>; so that if any accusation or blame be
					brought against us on this account we may have
					necessity as our defence against the charge, or the
					greatness and glory of the action as a consolation for
					the risk.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>A saying of Jason, monarch of the Thessalians,
					is recorded, which he always used to repeat whenever he was taking violent and annoying measures
					against individuals: <q direct="unspecified">It is inevitable that those
						should act unjustly in small matters who wish to
						act justly in great matters.</q> That is recognized
					at once as the saying of a despot; but this is a more
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.261"/>
					
					
					statesmanlike precept: <q direct="unspecified">Win the favour of the
						people by giving way in small things in order that
						in greater matters you may oppose them stubbornly
						and thus prevent them from committing errors.</q>
					For a man who is always very exact and strenuous
					about everything, not giving way or yielding at all,
					but always harsh and inexorable, gets the people
					into the habit of opposing him and being out of
					temper with him ;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>But he should let the sheet
					</l>
                  <l>Run out a bit before the waves' great force,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 918, no. 413.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					sometimes by giving way and playing graciously
					with them himself, as at sacrifices, public games,
					and spectacles in the theatre, and sometimes by pretending not to see or hear their errors, just as we
					treat the errors of the young people in a family,
					in order that the force of his rebukes and outspoken
					criticism - like that of a medicine - may not become
					exhausted or stale, but may in matters of greater
					importance, retaining its full strength and its credit,
					take a stronger hold upon the people and sting
					them into obedience. Alexander, for example, when
					he heard that his sister had had intercourse with a
					handsome young man, did not burst into a rage,
					but merely remarked that she also ought to be
					allowed to get some enjoyment out of her royal
					station. In making such concessions he did not
					act rightly or in a manner worthy of himself; for
					the weakening of a throne and outrageous conduct
					should not be regarded as mere enjoyment. But to
					the people the statesman will, so far as is possible,
					permit no outrageous conduct towards the citizens,
					no confiscation of others' property, nor distribution
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.263"/>
					
					
					of public funds, but by persuasion, arguments, and
					threats he will oppose to the bitter end desires of
					that sort, by nourishing and increasing which Cleon
					and his partizans produced in the State, as Plato
					says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 552 c, d.</note> a swarm of drones with stings. But if the
					people, taking an ancestral festival or the worship
					of some god as a pretext, are bent upon some public
					spectacle or a slight distribution of funds, or a gift
					for the general good or some lavish show prompted
					by private ambition, for such purposes let them reap
					the benefit both of their generosity and of their
					prosperity. Why, among the public acts of Pericles
					and of Demetrius are many of that sort, and Cimon
					beautified the market-place by planting plane-trees
					and laying out walks. And Cato, seeing that the
					people was being greatly stirred up by Caesar in the
					affair of Catiline and was dangerously inclined towards
					a revolution, persuaded the senate to vote a dole to
					the poor, and the giving of this halted the disturbance and ended the uprising. For just as a physician,
					after drawing off a great deal of infected blood,
					supplies a little harmless nourishment, so the statesman, after doing away with something big which
					was discreditable or harmful, appeases the spirit of
					discontent and fault-finding by some slight and kindly
					act of favour.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>It is also expedient to divert the people's
					interest to other useful things, as Demades did when
					he had the revenues of the State in his charge ; for
					when the people were eager to send out triremes to
					aid those who were in revolt against Alexander,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 330 b.c. King Agis of Sparta headed the revolt.</note> and
					were urging him to furnish funds, <q direct="unspecified">You have,</q> he
					said, <q direct="unspecified">funds available, for I have made preparations
						
						<pb id="v.10.p.265"/>
						
						
						for the Pitcher Festival<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The second day of the <hi rend="italics">Anthesteria</hi>, a three-day festival in worship of Dionysus, held in early spring at Athens.</note> so that each of you is to
						receive a half-mina, but if you had rather apply
						the funds to this other purpose, use your own money
						for the festival.</q> And in this way, since they gave
					up the expedition in order not to lose the distribution of money, he removed any ground of complaint
					on Alexander's part against the people of Athens.
					For there are many unprofitable measures which
					the statesman cannot avert by direct means, but
					he must use some sort of roundabout and circuitous
					methods, such as Phocion employed when ordered
					at an inopportune time to invade Boeotia. He
					immediately issued a proclamation<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Phocion</hi>, chap. xxiv.</note> calling all those
					from the age of military service up to sixty years to
					join the ranks, and when the older men made a
					violent protest, he said : <q direct="unspecified">What is there terrible
						about it ? For I, your general, who am eighty years
						old, shall be with you.</q> So in this way we should
					prevent inopportune embassies by listing among the
					envoys many who are not qualified to go, and useless
					construction by calling for contributions, and improper lawsuits and missions abroad by ordering the
					parties to appear in court together and together to go
					abroad on the missions. And those who propose such
					measures and incite the people to adopt them should
					be the first to be haled into court and made to take
					the responsibility for putting them into effect; for so
					they will either draw back and appear to be themselves nullifying the measure or they will stick to it
					and share its unpleasant features.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>When, however, something important and useful but requiring much conflict and serious effort is
					to be accomplished, then try to select from among
					your friends those who are most powerful, or from
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.267"/>
					
					
					among the most powerful those who are easiest to
					get along with ; for they are least likely to act
					against you and most likely to work with you, since
					they possess wisdom without contentiousness. And,
					moreover, you should know your own nature and
					choose for any purpose for which you are naturally
					less fitted than others, men who are more able rather
					than men like yourself, as Diomedes chose to go with
					him on the scouting expedition the man of prudence
					and passed over the men of courage.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 243. He chose Odysseus.</note> For actions
					are thus more equally balanced, and contention does
					not arise among men whose ambitions proceed from
					different virtues and abilities. So, if you are not a
					good speaker, take an orator as your assistant in a
					lawsuit or your colleague in an embassy, as Pelopidas
					took Epameinondas ; and if, like Callicratidas, you
					are too lofty of speech and not persuasive in addressing the masses, choose a man who is winning in his
					speech and conciliatory ; and if you are physically
					weak and incapable of hard work, choose a man
					who is fond of labour and strong, as Nicias chose
					Lamachus. For on this principle Geryon would have
					been enviable for having many legs, arms, and eyes,
					if he had directed them all by one mind. But statesmen, by uniting for one purpose not only men's
					persons and funds, but also their fortunes, abilities,
					and virtues, if they are in agreement, can gain
					greater reputation in connexion with the same action
					than by other means, not behaving like the Argonauts,
					who left Heracles behind and then were forced to
					work through the women's quarters<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This refers to Jason's seduction of Medea.</note> and use magic
					and drugs to save themselves and steal the golden
					fleece.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.269"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>
					When entering some sanctuaries men leave their
					gold outside ; but iron, one may say, they do not
					at all carry into any sanctuary. And since the
					orators' platform is a sanctuary common to Zeus the
					Counsellor and the Protector of Cities, to Themis
					and to Justice, do you strip off all love of wealth
					and of money, as you would iron full of rust<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 609 a.</note> and
					a disease of the soul, cast them straightway at the
					beginning into the market-place of hucksters and
					money-lenders,
					<quote rend="blockquote">and turning your back depart from them,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> v. 350.</note>
               </quote>
					believing that a man who makes money out of public
					funds is stealing from sanctuaries, from tombs, from
					his friends, through treason and by false testimony,
					that he is an untrustworthy adviser, a perjured judge,
					a venal magistrate, in brief not free from any kind
					of iniquity. And therefore there is no need of
					saying much about these evils.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>But ambition, although it is a more pretentious word than <q direct="unspecified">covetousness,</q> is no less pernicious in the State ; for there is more daring in it;
					since it is innate, not in slothful and abject spirits,
					but in the most vigorous and impetuous, and the
					surge which comes from the masses, raising it on
					the crest of the wave and sweeping it along by shouts
					of praise, often makes it unrestrained and unmanageable. Therefore, just as Plato said<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 416 e.</note> that young
					people should be told from childhood that it is not
					proper for them to wear gold on their persons or to
					possess it, since they have a gold of their own
					mingled in their souls, - a figurative reference, I
					believe, to the virtue derived by descent, which
					permeates their natures, - so let us moderate our
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.271"/>
					
					
					ambition, saying that we have in ourselves honour,
					a gold uncorrupted, undefiled, and unpolluted by
					envy and fault-finding, which increases along with
					reasoning and the contemplation of our acts and
					public measures. Therefore we have no need of
					honours painted, modelled, or cast in bronze, in
					which even that which is admired is really the work
					of another ; for the person who receives praise is
					not the man for whom the <q direct="unspecified">trumpeter</q> or the
					<q direct="unspecified">doryphorus,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Two famous statues. The doryphorus (spear-bearer) was by Polycleitus.</note> for example, was made, but the man
					by whom it was made. Cato, Rome then beginning
					to be full of portrait statues, refused to let one be
					made of himself, saying, <q direct="unspecified">I prefer to have people
						ask why there is not a statue of me rather than why
						there is one.</q> Such honours do indeed arouse envy,
					and the people think that they are themselves under
					obligations to men who have not received them, but
					that those who have received them are oppressors of
					the people, as men who demand payment for their
					services. Therefore, just as a man who has sailed
					past the Syrtis and is then capsized at the channel
					has done nothing so very great or glorious, so the
					man who has watched over the treasury and the
					public revenue, but is then found wanting in the
					presidency or the prytany, is indeed dashed against
					a lofty promontory, but gets a ducking all the same.
					No, that man is the best who wants no such things
					and even avoids and refuses them when offered.
					But if it is not easy to reject some favour or some
					kindly sentiment of the people, when it is so inclined, for men engaged in a political struggle for
					which the prize is not money or gifts, but which is
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.273"/>
					
					
					a truly sacred contest worthy of a crown,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The prizes at the Olympic, Pythian, Isthmian, and Nemean games were crowns of wild olive, laurel, pine, and parsley respectively.</note> a mere
					inscription suffices, a tablet, a decree, or a green
					branch such as Epimenides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Epimenides of Crete was called in by the Athenians, apparently not far from 500 b.c., to purify the city of a pestilence.</note> received from the
					Acropolis after purifying the city. And Anaxagoras,
					giving up the honours which had been granted him,
					requested that on the day of his death the children
					be allowed to play and be free from their lessons.
					And to the seven Persians who killed the magi the
					privilege was granted that they and their descendants
					should wear their headdress tilted forward over the
					forehead ; for they made this, so it appears, their
					secret sign when they undertook their act. And
					there is something that indicates public spirit, too,
					about the honour received by Pittacus ; for, when
					he was told to take as much as he wished of the land
					which he had gained for the citizens, he took only as
					much as he could throw a javelin over. And the
					Roman Codes received as much as he - and he was
					lame-could plough around in one day. For the
					honour should not be payment for the action, but a
					symbol, that it may last for a long time, as those just
					mentioned have lasted. But of all the three hundred statues of Demetrius of Phalerum not one
					acquired rust or dirt; they were all destroyed while
					he was still living ; and those of Demades were
					melted down into chamber-pots. Things like that
					have happened to many honours, they having become
					offensive, not only because the recipient was worthless, but also because the gift bestowed was too
					great. And therefore the best and surest way to
					ensure the duration of honours is to reduce their
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.275"/>
					
					
					cost but those which are great and top-heavy and
					weighty are, like ill-proportioned statues, quickly
					overturned.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>And I now give the name <q direct="unspecified">honours</q> to those
					which the multitude, to quote Empedocles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Phil. Graec.</hi> i. p. 3, 112.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Do not call as is right; and I, too, myself follow custom.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Quoted with slightly different wording by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1113 b.</note>
               </quote>
					For the statesman will not despise the true honour
					and favour founded upon the goodwill and disposition of those who remember his actions, nor will he
					disdain reputation and avoid <q direct="unspecified">pleasing his neighbours,</q> as Democritus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Phil. Graec.</hi> i. p. 355.</note> demanded. For not even the
					greeting of dogs nor the affection of horses is to be
					spurned by huntsmen and horse-trainers, but it is
					both advantageous and pleasant to instil into animals
					which are brought up with us and live with us such a
					disposition towards us as was exhibited by the dog of
					Lysimachus and as the poet tells us that Achilles'
					horses felt towards Patroclus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xix. 404 ff.; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal</hi>. vi. 25.</note> And I believe even
					bees would come off better if they would only welcome and placate their keepers and attendants instead of stinging them and making them angry. But
					as it is, people punish bees with smoke and lead
					unruly horses and runaway dogs by force of bits and
					dog-collars ; but nothing makes a man willingly tractable and gentle to another man except trust in his
					goodwill and belief in his nobility and justice. And
					therefore Demosthenes is right<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, vi. (second <hi rend="italics">Philippic</hi>) 24.</note> in declaring that the
					greatest safeguard States possess against tyrants is
					distrust; for that part of the soul with which we
					trust is most easily taken captive. Therefore just as
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.277"/>
					
					
					Cassandra's prophetic power was useless to the
					citizens because she was held in no esteem, <q direct="unspecified">For
						God,</q> she says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>has made me prophesy in vain,
						</l>
                     <l>And those who suffer or have suffered woes
						</l>
                     <l>Have called me &lsquo;wise&rsquo;; but ere they suffer, &lsquo;mad,&rsquo;</l>
                  </quote>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 919, no. 414. From an unknown play.</note>
               </quote>
					so the trust which the citizens reposed in Archytas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Archytas of Tarentum was a statesman, Pythagorean philosopher, and mathematician. He was seven times general and never defeated. He lived in the fourth century b.c. and was a friend of Plato.</note>
					and their goodwill towards Battus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably Battus III. of Cyrene is meant, under whom the constitution of the city was reformed about the middle of the sixth century b.c.</note> was, on account
					of their reputation, of great advantage to those who
					made use of them. The first and most important
					advantage inherent in the reputation of statesmen is
					this : the trust in them which affords them an entrance
					into public affairs ; and the second is that the goodwill of the multitude is a weapon of defence for the
					good against the slanderous and wicked,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>as when a mother
					</l>
                  <l>Wards off a fly from her child when he lieth asleep in
					sweet slumber,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 130.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					keeping off envy and in the matter of power making
					the low-born equal to the nobles, the poor to the
					rich, and the private citizen to the office-holders ;
					and in short, when truth and virtue are added to it,
					such goodwill is a steady fair wind wafting a man into
					political office. Now consider the contrary disposition
					and learn of it by examples. For the men of Italy
					Violated the daughters and the wife of Dionysius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Dionysius II. of Syracuse; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Timoleon</hi>, chap. xiii., and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Var. Hist.</hi> vi. 12.</note>
					killed them, and then burned their bodies and scattered the ashes from a boat over the sea. But when
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.279"/>
					
					
					a certain man named Menander, who had been a
					good king of the Bactrians, died in camp, the cities
					celebrated his funeral as usual in other respects, but
					in respect to his remains they put forth rival claims
					and only with difficulty came to terms, agreeing that
					they should divide the ashes equally and go away
					and should erect monuments to him in all their cities.
					But, on the other hand, the Agrigentines, when they
					had got rid of Phalaris, decreed that no one should
					wear a grey cloak; for the tyrant's servants had worn
					grey garments. But the Persians, because Cyrus
					was hook-nosed, even to this day love hook-nosed
					men and consider them the most handsome.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>So of all kinds of love that which is engendered
					in states and peoples for an individual because of his
					virtue is at once the strongest and the most divine ;
					but those falsely named and falsely attested honours
					which are derived from giving theatrical performances, making distributions of money, or offering
					gladiatorial shows, are like harlots' flatteries, since
					the masses always smile upon him who gives to them
					and does them favours, granting him an ephemeral
					and uncertain reputation. And so he who first said
					that the people was ruined by the first man who
					bought its favour was well aware that the multitude
					loses its strength when it succumbs to bribe-taking;
					but those also who give such bribes should bear in
					mind that they are destroying themselves when they
					purchase reputation by great expenditures, thus
					making the multitude strong and bold in the thought
					that they have power to give and take away something important.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>We ought not, however, on this account to be
					niggardly as to the customary public contributions,
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.281"/>
					
					
					if we are in prosperous circumstances ; since the
					masses are more hostile to a rich man who does not
					give them a share of his private possessions than to
					a poor man who steals from the public funds, for
					they think the former's conduct is due to arrogance
					and contempt of them, but the latter's to necessity.
					First, then, let the gifts be made without bargaining for anything ; for so they surprise and overcome
					the recipients more completely ; and secondly they
					should be given on some occasion which offers a good
					and excellent pretext, one which is connected with
					the worship of a god and leads the people to piety ;
					for at the same time there springs up in the minds of
					the masses a strong disposition to believe that the
					deity is great and majestic, when they see the men
					whom they themselves honour and regard as great
					so liberally and zealously vying with each other in
					honouring the divinity. Therefore, just as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 398 e.</note>
					withheld the Lydian and the Ionian musical modes
					from the education of the young, because the one
					arouses that part of the soul which is inclined towards
					mourning and grief and the other strengthens that
					part which readily slips into pleasures and grows
					wanton, so you must, if possible, remove from the
					State all those free exhibitions which excite and
					nourish the murderous and brutal or the scurrilous
					and licentious spirit, or if you cannot do that, avoid
					them and oppose the multitude when they demand
					them. But always make the objects of your expenditures useful and moderate, having as their
					purpose either what is good or what is necessary,
					or at any rate what is pleasant and agreeable without
					anything harmful or outrageous in it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>But if your property is moderate and in relation
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.283"/>
					
					
					to your needs strictly circumscribed <q direct="unspecified">as by
						centre and radius,</q> it is neither ignoble nor humiliating at all to confess your poverty and to withdraw
					from among those who have the means for public expenditures, instead of borrowing money and making
					yourself at once a pitiful and a ridiculous object in
					the matter of your public contributions ; for men
					are plainly seen to lack resources when they keep
					annoying their friends or truckling to money-lenders ;
					so that it is not reputation or power, but rather
					shame and contempt, which they acquire by such
					expenditures. And therefore it is always desirable
					in connexion with such things to remember Lamachus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lamachus was an Athenian general who was killed in the battle at the Anapus near Syracuse in 414 b.c.</note> and Phocion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Phocion was a famous Athenian general in the fourth century b.c. He was elected general forty-five times. He was virtual ruler of Athens when Antipater was in power, but in 318 b.c. was tried and executed by the Athenians. Soon after that a public burial and a statue were decreed for him. The story told here is found also in the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, p. 533 a.</note>; for the latter, when the
					Athenians at a sacrifice called upon him to contribute
					and repeatedly raised a clamour, said, <q direct="unspecified">I should be
						ashamed if I gave you a contribution and did not
						pay Callicles here what I owe him,</q> pointing to his
					money-lender. And Lamachus always, when he was
					general, entered in his accounts money for shoes and
					a cloak for himself. And when Hermon tried to
					avoid office on the plea of poverty, the Thessalians
					voted to give him a flask<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">About six pints.</note> of wine monthly and a
					measure<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">About a bushel and a half.</note> of meal every four days. So it is not
					ignoble to confess poverty, and poor men, if by
					reason of their virtue they enjoy freedom of speech
					and public confidence, have no less influence in their
					cities than those who give public entertainments and
					exhibitions. The statesman must, then, do his best
					to control himself in such matters and not go down
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.285"/>
					
					
					into the plain on foot to fight with cavalry; if he
					is poor, he must not produce foot-races, theatrical
					shows, and banquets in competition with the rich for
					reputation and power, but he should vie with those
					who try always to lead the State on the strength of
					virtue and wisdom, combined with reason, for in such
					are found not only nobility and dignity but also the
					power to win and attract the people, a thing <q direct="unspecified">more
						desirable than gold coins of Croesus.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pollux, iii. 87, ix. 85, but, as Bernardakis suggests, Plutarch may have added the word for <q direct="unspecified">more desirable,</q> in which case there is here no real quotation.</note> For the
					good man is neither presumptuous nor offensive,
					and the prudent man is not over-blunt in speech,
					nor does he
					<quote rend="blockquote">Walk with a mien his townsmen bitter find,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 919, no. 415.</note>
               </quote>
					but in the first place he is affable and generally accessible and approachable for all, keeping his house
					always unlocked as a harbour of refuge for those in
					need, and showing his solicitude and friendliness, not
					only by acts of service, but also by sharing the griefs
					of those who fail and the joys of those who succeed;
					and he is in no way disagreeable or offensive by
					reason of the number of the servants who attend him
					at the bath or by appropriating seats at the theatre,
					nor is he conspicuous for invidious exhibitions of
					luxury and extravagance ; but he is on an equal
					level with others in his clothing and daily life, in
					the bringing up of his children and as regards the
					servants who wait upon his wife, as one who wishes
					to live like the masses and be friendly with them.
					And, moreover, he shows himself a kindly counsellor,
					an advocate who accepts no fee, and a kind-hearted
					conciliator when husbands are at variance with their
					wives or friends with one another. He spends no
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.287"/>
					
					
					small part of the day engaged in the public business
					on the orators' platform of the senate or the assembly, and thenceforth all the rest of his life he
					<quote rend="blockquote">Draws to himself as north-east wind draws clouds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 853, no. 75; Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 612, no. 1229. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 88 f, uses the same simile, and this line is quoted as a proverb by Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Meteor.</hi> 364 b 13.</note>
               </quote>
					services and commissions from every quarter. But
					since he is always devoting his thoughts to the public
					weal and regards public office as his life and his
					work, not, like most people, as an interruption to
					leisure and a compulsory expense, - by all these and
					similar qualities he turns and attracts the people
					towards himself, for they see that the flatteries and
					enticements of others are spurious and counterfeit
					when compared with his care and forethought.
					The flatterers of Demetrius would not address the
					other monarchs as kings, but called Seleucus <q direct="unspecified">Ruler
						of Elephants</q> and Lysimachus <q direct="unspecified">Guardian of the
							Treasure</q> and Ptolemy <q direct="unspecified">Admiral of the Fleet</q>
					and Agathocles <q direct="unspecified">Lord of the Isles</q> ; but the
					multitude, even if at first they reject the good and
					wise man, afterwards, when they have become acquainted with his truthfulness and his character,
					consider him alone a statesmanlike, public-spirited
					man and a ruler, whereas they consider and call the
					others, one a provider of choruses, one a giver of
					banquets, and one a director of athletics. Then,
					just as at banquets, though Callias or Alcibiades
					pay the bill, it is Socrates to whom they listen,
					and Socrates on whom all eyes are turned, so in
					States in which the conditions are sound Ismenias
					makes contributions, Lichas gives dinners, and
					Niceratus provides choruses, but it is Epameinondas,
					Aristeides, and Lysander who are the rulers, public
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.289"/>
					
					
					men, and generals. So, observing these things, we
					must not be humiliated or overwhelmed by the
					reputation with the masses gained from theatres,
					kitchens, and assembly-halls, remembering that it
					lasts but a short time and ends the minute the
					gladiatorial and dramatic shows are over, since
					there is nothing honourable or dignified in it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Now those who are skilled in tending and
					keeping bees think that the hive which hums loudest
					and is most full of noise is thriving and in good condition ; but he to whom God has given the care of
					the rational and political swarm will judge of its
					happiness chiefly by the quietness and tranquillity
					of the people ; he will accept and imitate to the best
					of his ability the other precepts of Solon, but will
					wonder in great perplexity why that great man
					prescribed that in case of factional disorder whoever
					joined neither faction should be deprived of civic
					rights. For in a body afflicted with disease the
					beginning of a change to health does not come from
					the diseased parts, but it comes when the condition
					in the healthy parts gains strength and drives out
					that which is contrary to nature ; and in a people
					afflicted with faction, if it is not dangerous and destructive but is destined to cease sometime, there
					must be a strong, permanent, and permeating admixture of sanity and soundness ; for to this element
					there flows from the men of understanding that which
					is akin to it, and then it permeates the part which is
					diseased ; but States which have fallen into complete
					disorder are utterly ruined unless they meet with
					some external necessity and chastisement and
					are thus forcibly compelled by their misfortunes to
					be reasonable. Yet certainly it is not fitting in time
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.291"/>
					
					
					of disorder to sit without feeling or grief, singing
					the praises of your own impassiveness and of the inactive and blessed life,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This refers to the doctrine held by the Epicurean and Sceptic Schools of philosophy that the perfect state is that of complete tranquillity.</note> and rejoicing in the follies
					of others ; on the contrary, at such times you should
					by all means put on the buskin of Theramenes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theramenes was prominent in the oligarchy at Athens in 411 b.c., but later turned against his former associates. In 404 b.c. he was elected one of the <q direct="unspecified">Thirty Tyrants,</q> but tried to restrain his colleagues and was put to death by them. He was nicknames Cothurnus because the buskin could be worn on either foot, as he was a member of each party in turn (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">turncoat</q>). Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, 28. 5. praises him as a patriot.</note>
					conversing with both parties and joining neither ; for
					you will appear to be, not an outsider by not joining
					in wrongdoing, but a common partisan of all by
					coming to their aid ; and your not sharing in their
					misfortunes will not arouse envy, if it is plain that
					you sympathize with all alike. But the best thing is
					to see to it in advance that factional discord shall never
					arise among them and to regard this as the greatest
					and noblest function of what may be called the art
					of statesmanship. For observe that of the greatest
					blessings which States can enjoy, - peace, liberty,
					plenty, abundance of men, and concord, - so far
					as peace is concerned the peoples have no need of
					statesmanship at present; for all war, both Greek
					and foreign,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the phrase <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thucydides, ii. 364.</note> has been banished from among us
					and has disappeared ; and of liberty the peoples
					have as great a share as our rulers grant them, and
					perhaps more would not be better for them ; but
					bounteous productiveness of the soil, kindly tempering of the seasons, that wives may bear <q direct="unspecified">children
						like to their sires,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 233.</note> and that the offspring may live
					in safety - these things the wise man will ask the
					gods in his prayers to grant his fellow-citizens.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.293"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>
					There remains, then, for the statesman, of those
					activities which fall within his province, only this - and it is the equal of any of the other blessings : - always to instil concord and friendship in those who
					dwell together with him and to remove strifes, discords, and all enmity. He will talk, as in the case
					of quarrels among friends, first with the persons
					who think they are the more aggrieved, and will
					appear to share their feeling of wrong and anger,
					then he will try in this way to mollify them and teach
					them that those who let wrongs go unheeded are
					superior to those who are quarrelsome and try to
					compel and overcome others, not only in reasonableness and character, but also in wisdom and greatness
					of spirit, and that by yielding in a small thing they
					gain their point in the best and most important
					matters. Then he will instruct his people both
					individually and collectively and will call attention
					to the weak condition of Greek affairs, in which it is
					best for wise men to accept one advantage - a life
					of harmony and quiet - since fortune has left us no
					prize open for competition. For what dominion,
					what glory is there for those who are victorious ?
					What sort of power is it which a small edict of a
					proconsul may annul or transfer to another man and
					which, even if it last, has nothing in it seriously worth
					while ? But just as a conflagration does not often
					begin in sacred or public places, but some lamp left
					neglected in a house or some burnt rubbish causes
					a great flame and works public destruction, so disorder in a State is not always kindled by contentions
					about public matters, but frequently differences
					arising from private affairs and offences pass thence
					into public life and throw the whole State into confusion.
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.295"/>
					
					
					Therefore it behoves the statesman above
					all things to remedy or prevent these, that some of
					them may not arise at all and some may be quickly
					ended and others may not grow great and extend
					to public interests, but may remain merely among
					the persons who are at odds with one another. He
					should do this by noticing himself and pointing out
					to others that private troubles become the causes
					of public ones and small troubles of great ones, if
					they are overlooked and do not in the beginning
					receive treatment or soothing counsel.
				</p>
            <p>
					For example, at Delphi the greatest insurrection
					is said to have been caused by Crates, whose daughter
					was to be married to Orsila&uuml;s, the son of Phalis ; but
					then, when at the betrothal the mixing-bowl broke in
					the middle of its own accord, Orsila&uuml;s regarded that
					as an omen, left his bride, and went away with his
					father. But Crates a little later, secretly putting
					a sacred object of gold into their possession while
					they were sacrificing, caused Orsila&uuml;s and his brother
					to be hurled over the precipice without trial and
					later slew some of their friends and relatives when
					they were suppliants in the sanctuary of Athena-before-the-Temple. But after many such things
					had taken place the Delphians put Crates and his
					fellow-partisans to death, and with their property,
					which had been declared accursed, they built the
					lower temples. And at Syracuse there were two
					young men, intimate friends, one of whom, being
					entrusted with his friend's beloved for safe-keeping,
					seduced him while the other was away; then the
					latter, as if to repay outrage with outrage, committed adultery with the offender's wife. Thereupon
					one of the elder men came forward in the senate and
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.297"/>
					
					
					moved that both be banished before the State reap
					the result and be infected with enmity through
					them. His motion, however, was not carried, and
					from this beginning disorder arose which caused
					great disasters and overthrew the most excellent
					government. And indeed you yourself also no
					doubt have excellent examples at home in the enmity
					of Pardalas and Tyrrhenus, which came near to destroying Sardis by involving the State in rebellion
					and war as the result of petty private matters.
				</p>
            <p>
					Therefore the statesman should not despise such
					offences as may, like diseases in a person, spread
					quickly, but he should take hold of them, suppress
					them, and cure them. For by attention, as Cato
					says, the great is made small and the small is reduced to nothing. And for this there is no more
					persuasive device than for the statesman to show
					himself in his private differences mild and conciliatory,
					persisting without anger in his original reasons for
					disagreement, and treating no one with contentiousness, anger, or any other passion which injects harsha
					ness and bitterness into unavoidable disputes. For
					we put soft gloves on the hands of those who compete
					in the boxing-school, that the contest may not have
					a fatal result, its blows being soft and not painful;
					and in law-suits against one's fellow-citizens it is
					better to treat the causes of disagreement pure and
					simple in one's pleading, and not, by sharpening
					and poisoning matters, as if they were darts or
					arrows, with bad words, malice, and threats, to make
					them incurable, great, and of public importance.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.299"/>
					
					
					For a man who proceeds in this way towards those
					with whom he himself has to do will find that others
					also yield to him ; and rivalries affecting public
					interests, if private enmities are done away with,
					become of slight importance and do no serious or
					incurable harm.
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>