<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De fortuna</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1928</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.73"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>CHANCE (DE FORTUNA) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p> In default of any information regarding Plutarch's short essay on Chance, we
					can only guess that it may have been delivered as a lecture, although
					Hartman denies such a possibility. The arguing of such subjects has always
					had a certain attraction for mankind until comparatively recent times, but
					the development of a more exact knowledge regarding psychology has in later
					years checked such discussions. Yet a knowledge of psychology will not
					detract from the interest and enjoyment of anyone who will read this essay.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.75"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">Man's ways are chance and not sagacity.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Chaeremon: Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>p. 782. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 9 (25).</note>
               </quote> Is it true also that man's ways are
					not justice either, or equality, or self-control, or decorum, but was it the
					result of chance and because of chance that Aristeides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Aristides</hi>, chap. xxv. (p. 334 B).</note> persevered in his
					poverty when he could have made himself master of great wealth, and that
					Scipio, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 200 B.</note> having captured Carthage, neither took nor saw any of the spoil ?
					Was it the result of chance and because of chance that Philocrates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, Or. xix. (<hi rend="italics">De falsa legatione</hi>), 229 (p. 412). The money was the price of treason according to Demosthenes.</note> having
					received money from Philip, <q direct="unspecified">proceeded to spend it on trulls and
						trout,</q> and was it due to chance that Lasthenes and Euthycrates
					lost Olynthus, <q direct="unspecified">measuring happiness by their bellies and the most
						shameless deeds</q> ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, Or. xviii. (<hi rend="italics">De corona</hi>), 296 (p. 324). These men also Demosthenes puts in his list of traitors.</note> Was it the result of chance that
					Alexander,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxi. (p. 676 B ff.).</note> the son of Philip, forbore to touch the captive women himself
					and punished those who offered them insult, and, on the other hand, was it
					because the Alexander who was the son of Priam yielded to the dictates of an
					evil genius or of chance that he lay with the wife of his host, and by her
					abduction filled two of our three continents with war and woes ? For if
					these things happen because 
					<pb id="v.2.p.77"/> of chance, what is to hinder our saying that cats,
					goats, and apes because of chance are given over to greediness, lustfulness,
					and mischievous tricks ? </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>If self-control, justice, and bravery exist, how is it possible to reason
					that intelligence does not exist ; and if intelligence exists, must not
					sagacity exist also ? For self-control is a kind of intelligence, they say,
					and justice requires the presence of intelligence.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 441 A and 1034 C.</note> Or rather, that
					particular sagacity and intelligence which render men virtuous in the midst
					of pleasures we call continence and self-control, in perils and labours we
					call it perseverance and fortitude, in private dealings and in public life
					we call it equity and justice. Wherefore, if we impute the works of sagacity
					to chance, let the works of justice and of self-control be also ascribed to
					chance, and, by Heaven, let thieving, stealing purses, and licentious living
					all be ascribed to chance, and let us abandon all our reasoning processes
					and resign ourselves to chance, to be driven and carried, as dust or rubbish
					by a violent wind, hither and thither. If, then, sagacity does not exist, it
					is a fair inference that there can be no sagacious planning about what is to
					be done, and no consideration or searching for what is to the best
					advantage, but Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Tyrannus</hi>, 110.</note> indulged in idle talk when he said : <quote rend="blockquote">Whatever is
						pursued May be achieved ; neglected it escapes;</quote> and so too in another place
					where he tries to distinguish different classes of actions : What can be
					taught I learn ; what can be found I seek ; but God I ask to answer prayer.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play of Sophocles; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Sophocles, No. 759.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.2.p.79"/> For what is there which can be found out or learned by
					mankind if the issue of all things is determined by chance ? And what
					deliberative assembly of a State can there be which is not abolished, or
					advisory council of a king which is not dissolved, if all things are under
					the dominion of chance, which we reproach for being blind because we, like
					blind men, stumble against it ?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Kock. <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 121, Menander, No. 417.</note> How can we help doing so when we pluck out
					sagacity, as it were our own eyes, and take as our guide in life a blind
					leader ? </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Yet, suppose someone among us should say that the act of seeing is chance and
					not vision nor the use of <q direct="unspecified">light-bringing orbs,</q> as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 45 B.</note>
					calls the eyes, and that the act of hearing is chance and not a faculty
					apperceptive of a vibration in the air which is carried onward through ear
					and brain.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 67 B.</note> If such were the case, it were well for us, as it appears, to
					beware of trusting our senses ! But, as a matter of fact, Nature has
					conferred upon us sight, hearing, taste, smell, and our other members and
					their faculties to be ministers of sagacity and intelligence, and <quote rend="blockquote">Mind has
						sight and mind has hearing ; all the rest is deaf and blind.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Epicharmus; cited by Plutarch also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 33 B and 961 A. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 123.</note>
               </quote> Precisely as
					would be our case if the sun did not exist, and we, for all the other stars,
					should be passing our life in a continual night, as Heracleitus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i, p. 97; Bywater, p. 13. A slightly different version of the saying is given by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 957 A.</note> affirms, so
					man, for all his senses, had he not mind and reason, would not differ at all
					in his life from the brutes. 
					<pb id="v.2.p.81"/> But as it is, we excel them and have power over them,
					not from chance or accidentally, but the cause thereof is Prometheus, or, in
					other words, the power to think and reason, <quote rend="blockquote">Which gives the foal of horse
						and ass, and get Of bull, to serve us and assume our tasks,</quote> as Aeschylus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Prometheus Unbound</hi> of Aeschylus; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Aeschylus, No. 194. The lines are again quoted by Plutarch <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 964 F.</note>
					puts it. Certainly, in so far as chance and nature's endowment at birth are
					concerned, the great majority of brute animals are better off than man. For
					some are armed with horns, or teeth, or stings, and Empedocles says, <quote rend="blockquote">But as
						for hedgehogs Growing upon their backs sharp darts of spines stand
						bristling,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker, i. p. 252.</hi>
                  </note>
               </quote> and still others are shod and clad with scales or hair, with
					claws or horny hoofs. Man alone, as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Protagoras</hi>, 321 C.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">naked, unarmed,
						with feet unshod, and with no bed to lie in,</q> has been abandoned
					by Nature. <quote rend="blockquote">Yet by one gift all this she mitigates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown, but perhaps Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,</hi>Adespota, No. 367; cited again by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 959 D.</note>
               </quote> the gift of reasoning,
					diligence, and forethought. <quote rend="blockquote">Slight, of a truth, is the strength of man ; and
						yet By his mind's resourcefulness Doth he subjugate the monsters Of the
						deep, and the purposes Of the denizens of earth and air.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Aeolus</hi> of Euripides; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 27.</note>
               </quote> Horses are the
					lightest and swiftest of foot, yet they run for man. The dog is pugnacious
					and 
					<pb id="v.2.p.83"/> spirited, yet it watches over man. Fish is most savoury,
					and the pig very fat, yet for man they are nourishing and appetizing food.
					What is bigger than an elephant or more terrible to behold ? But even this
					creature has been made the plaything of man, and a spectacle at public
					gatherings, and it learns to posture and dance and kneel.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch has several good stories about elephants in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 968 ff.</note> Such
					presentations are not without their use ; indeed, they serve a purpose in
					that we may learn to what heights man's intelligence raises him, above what
					it places him, and how he is master of all things, and in every way
					superior. <quote rend="blockquote">No, we are not invincible either in boxing or wrestling, Nor are
						we swift in the race.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> viii. 246.</note>
               </quote> Indeed, in all these matters we are not so fortunate
					as the animals ; yet we make use of experience, memory, wisdom, and skill,
					as Anaxagoras <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 409.</note> says, which are ours, and ours only, and we take their honey,
					and milk them, and carry and lead them at will, taking entire control over
					them. In all this, therefore, there is no element of chance at all, but
					solely and wholly sagacity and forethought. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Moreover, under the head of <q direct="unspecified">man's ways</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the first line of chap. i. <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note> would fall, no doubt,
					the activities of carpenters, copper-smiths, builders, and statuaries,
					wherein we see nothing brought to a successful conclusion accidentally or as
					it chances. That chance may sometimes contribute slightly to their success, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Epicurus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the quotation in Diogenes Laertius, x. 144.</note>
					but 
					<pb id="v.2.p.85"/> that the arts through themselves bring to perfection the
					most and greatest of their works, is plainly suggested by this poet: <quote rend="blockquote">Into
						the highway come, all craftsmen folk, Who worship Labour, stern-eyed child
						of Zeus, With sacred baskets placed about.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps from Sophocles; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Sophocles, No. 760. <foreign lang="greek">)*erga/nh</foreign> is an epithet applied to Athena as patron of the arts.</note>
               </quote> For the arts have Labour, that
					is Athena, and not Chance as their coadjutor. Of just one artist, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nealces, according to Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xxxv. 36 (104). Dio Chrysostom (<hi rend="italics">Or.</hi> lxiii. 4) says it was Apelles, and Valerius Maximus (viii. 11. 7) says <q direct="unspecified">a famous painter.</q>
               </note> however,
					it is related that in painting a horse he had succeeded in nearly every
					respect in the drawing and colours, but the frothy appearance of the foam
					from champing the bit, and the rush of the foamflecked breath, he had tried
					again and again to paint, but without success, and each time had wiped it
					out, until finally, in a rage, he threw his sponge just as it was, full of
					pigments, at the canvas, and this, as it struck, transferred its contents in
					some amazing manner to the canvas, and effected the desired result. This is
					the only recorded instance of a technical achievement due to chance. Rulers,
					weights, measures, and numbers are everywhere in use, so that the random and
					haphazard may find no place in any production. Indeed, the arts are said to
					be minor forms of intelligence, or rather offshoots of intelligence, and
					detached fragments of it interspersed amid life's common necessities, as it
					is said in the allegory regarding fire, that it was divided into portions by
					Prometheus and scattered some here and some there. For thus, when
					intelligence is finely broken and divided, small portions and fragments of
					it have gone to their several stations. 
					<pb id="v.2.p.87"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>It is therefore amazing how, if the arts have no need of chance to accomplish
					their own ends, the greatest and most perfect art of all, the consummation
					of the high repute and esteem to which man can attain, can count for nothing
					! But in the tightening and loosening of strings there is involved a certain
					sagacity, which men call music, and also in the preparation of food, to
					which we give the name of cookery, and in the cleaning of clothes, which we
					call fulling ; and we teach our children to put on their shoes and clothes,
					and to take their meat with the right hand and hold their bread in the left,
					on the assumption that even these things do not come by chance, but require
					oversight and attention.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 5 A and 440 A.</note> But can it be that those things which are most
					important and most essential for happiness do not call for intelligence, nor
					have any part in the processes of reason and forethought ? But nobody wets
					clay with water and leaves it, assuming that by chance and accidentally
					there will be bricks, nor after providing himself with wool and leather does
					he sit down with a prayer to Chance that they turn into a cloak and shoes
					for him ; and when a man has amassed much gold and silver and a multitude of
					slaves, and has surrounded himself with spacious suites of rooms, and, in
					addition, has furnished them with costly couches and tables,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 100 C, <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
               </note> does he
					imagine that these things, without the presence of intelligence in himself,
					will be happiness and a blissful life, free from grief and secure from
					change ? </p>
            <p> Somebody asked Iphicrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This story also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 187 B and 440 B.</note> the general, as though undertaking to expose him,
					who he was, since he was <q direct="unspecified">neither a man-at-arms, nor archer, nor
						targeteer</q> ; and he answered, <q direct="unspecified">I am the man who <pb id="v.2.p.89"/> commands and makes use of all these.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Intelligence is not gold or silver or repute or wealth or health or strength
					or beauty. What then is it ? It is the something which is able to make good
					use of all these, and something through whose agency each of these is made
					pleasant, noteworthy, and profitable. Without it they are unserviceable,
					fruitless, and harmful, and they burden and disgrace their possessor. It is
					surely excellent advice that Hesiod's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 86.</note> Prometheus gives to Epimetheus :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Never to welcome Any gifts from Zeus of Olympus, but always return them,</quote>
					meaning the gifts of chance and external advantages; as if he were advising
					him not to play the flute if ignorant of music, nor to read if illiterate,
					nor to ride if unused to horses, thus advising him not to hold public office
					if a fool, nor to be rich if miserly, nor to marry if ruled by a woman. For
					not only is it true, as Demosthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Olynthiac</hi>I. 23.</note> has said, that <q direct="unspecified">undeserved
						success becomes a source of misconception for fools,</q> but
					undeserved good fortune also becomes a source of misery for the unthinking.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>