<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De tuenda sanitate praecepta</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1928</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.214"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>ADVICE ABOUT KEEPING WELL (DE TUENDA SANITATE PRAECEPTA) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>Plutarch had more than a casual interest in medicine, for, besides this essay
					on keeping well, his other works abound in references to the behaviour of
					the sick and their treatment, and the medical practices of his day. Long
					before the time of Plutarch the art of medicine, always empirical, had been
					put on a solid foundation, and the acute observations of Hippocrates and his
					school had been set down in writing ; and this body of Hippocratic medical
					writings, along with others, was in circulation, and had undoubtedly been
					read by Plutarch. </p>
            <p>That medicine has made very great advances since Plutarch's time is, of
					course, self-evident; <q direct="unspecified">aseptic,</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">antiseptic,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">sterilize</q> are now household
					words, and the germ theory of disease has, in recent times, shed light on
					much which before was dark. But Plutarch is not dealing with the technical
					side of medicine ; he is only giving some common-sense advice on rational
					living, and much that he has to say in regard to rest, exercise, and diet is
					in accord with the best medical practice of the present day. In fact, it is
					doubtful if any physician would take exception to anything that Plutarch
					advises (his advice is meant for men whose work is done with their heads
					rather than their hands), and one might name men in public life to-day, well
					on in years, who have followed many of his suggestions, unwittingly, no
					doubt, but to their own advantage. </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.215"/>
            <p>The essay seems, at the first glance, to be put in the form of a dialogue,
					but it is about as much of a dialogue as Quiller-Couch's Foe-Farrell. The
					dialogue form is merely a literary subterfuge to present an essay in a
					slightly more attractive form, and the third person of the dialogue, only
					occasionally recalled to the reader by the parsimonious interjection of
					<q direct="unspecified">he said,</q> may be presumed to be Plutarch, the author. The
					two speakers in the brief dialogue at the beginning of the essay are
					Moschion, a physician, whom Plutarch introduces also into the Symposiacs
					(Moralia, 658 a), and Zeuxippus, a friend of Plutarch's, who is introduced
					also as a speaking character in two other essays of Plutarch's (Moralia, 748
					e and 1086 c), besides being mentioned several times in other essays. </p>
            <p>That the essay was written some time after a.d. 81 is clear from the
					reference to the death of the Roman Emperor Titus (123 d). </p>
            <p>The title of the essay is included in Lamprias' list of Plutarch's works, and
					Stobaeus, in his Florilegium, has several quotations from it, sometimes with
					a slightly different reading, but none of these readings changes the meaning
					of the passage at all, and rarely is one to be preferred to the reading
					found in the mss. of Plutarch (see Vol. I. Introd. p. xxi). </p>
            <p>Indeed, the text of this essay has suffered more at the hands of modern
					editors than from the ancient copyists, for a glance at the foot-notes
					inBernardakis's edition will show that the gratuitous and unnecessary
					changes introduced into the text by modern editors outnumber their
					corrections of the minor errors in spelling, and the like, made by the
					ancient copyists. </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.217"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Moschion. So, Zeuxippus, yesterday you drove away Glaucus, the physician,
					when he wished to join in your philosophical discussions. </p>
            <p>Zeuxippus. No, my dear Moschion, I did not drive him away, nor did he wish to
					join in philosophical discussion, but I avoided him and feared giving an
					opening to a man fond of contention. In medicine the man is, as Homer <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 514.</note> puts
					it, Worth many others together, but he is not kindly disposed towards
					philosophy, and there is always a certain harshness and ill-nature inherent
					in his remarks. And just then he was coming at us full tilt, crying out,
					even before he came near us, that it was no small or suitable task,
					amounting in fact to a confusion of all bounds, which had been boldly
					assumed by us in discussing a healthful manner of living. For he asserted
					that the subjects of philosophy and medicine are as <q direct="unspecified">far
						remote</q> from each other as <q direct="unspecified">are the boundaries of</q>
					any <q direct="unspecified">Mysians and Phrygians</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Proverbial; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No. 560.</note> ; and thereupon, as he had at
					the tip of his tongue some statements of ours, which, though not very
					carefully formulated, are certainly not without utility, he proceeded to
					tear them to pieces. </p>
            <p>Moschion. Well, in this and in other matters, <pb id="v.2.p.219"/> Zeuxippus,
					I should be very glad to be your attentive listener. </p>
            <p>Zeuxippus. That is because you, Moschion, have a natural gift for philosophy,
					and you feel incensed at the philosopher who does not take an interest in
					medicine, and you are indignant that such a man should imagine it more
					becoming for him, in the eyes of mankind, to profess some knowledge of
					geometry, logical discussion, and music, than to desire to seek out and know
					<quote rend="blockquote">All that of evil and good may have chanced to betide in the dwelling <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv, 392.</note>
               </quote> which
					is his own body. And yet you will see a larger number of spectators in the
					theatres where money to pay for admission is distributed to those who gather
					together, as at Athens ; and of the liberal arts medicine is inferior to
					none in elegance, distinction, and the satisfaction which it yields, and it
					gives to its students admission to something of very great
					importance&mdash;the preservation of their life and health.
					Consequently, the charge of trespass ought not to lie against philosophers
					if they discuss matters of health, but rather should they be blamed if they
					do not consider it their duty to abolish all boundarylines altogether, and
					to make a single field, as it were, of all honourable studies, and therein
					to cultivate them in common, thus aiming in their discussion at both the
					pleasant and the essential. </p>
            <p>Moschion. Well, Zeuxippus, let us say no more about Glaucus, who is so
					self-important that he wants to be a law unto himself, needing no help from
					philosophy ; but do you tell us in detail the whole discussion ; or, if you
					prefer, just those statements <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, Od. iv. 392.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.221"/> which you first referred to as not altogether carefully
					formulated, which you say Glaucus seized upon. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Zeuxippus. Well, our companion <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch himself presumably.</note> asserted that he had heard somebody say that
					keeping the hands always warm, and never allowing them to get cold, is in no
					small measure conducive to health, and, conversely, the chilling of the
					extremities, by concentrating the warmth in the interior of the body,
					creates, as it were, a habit or a predisposition towards feverishness ; and
					for a man to divert the substances in his body toward the surface, and to
					conduct and distribute them, along with the warmth, to all parts of his body
					, is healthful. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 635 C.</note> If therefore we happen to be doing something with our hands
					and using them, the motion itself brings the warmth to these parts, and
					keeps it there ; but when not engaged in such activities we must by no means
					allow the cold to find lodgement in our extremities. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>This, then, was one of the things ridiculed. The second, I think, concerned
					the food which you people serve to the sick. For he urged that we should
					partake of it and taste it from time to time, and get ourselves used to it
					in time of health, and not abhor and detest such a regimen, like little
					children, but gradually make it familiar and congenial to our appetites, so
					that in sickness we may not be disaffected over our fare as if it were so
					much medicine, and may not show impatience at receiving something simple,
					unappetising, and savourless. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 661 B.</note> For this reason, too, omitting the bath now
					and then before going to a meal is not a thing to be avoided, nor drinking
					only water when wine is at hand, nor drinking anything lukewarm in the
					summer-time when there is snow on the table ; and while dismissing <pb id="v.2.p.223"/> once for all time the ostentatious and studied
					abstinence from such things and the bragging over it, we should silently, by
					our own selves, habituate the appetite to be obedient to expediency with all
					serenity, and long beforehand we must rid our soul of its squeamishness in
					times of sickness about such trifles, and its lamentation thereat, as it
					deplores how it has been driven away from great and fond pleasures to an
					ignoble and humiliating way of living. </p>
            <p>Well has it been said, <q direct="unspecified">Choose the life that is best, and constant
					habit will make it pleasant,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A precept of Pythagoras according to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 466 F, and other writers who quote it; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 602 B.</note> and, in particular, it is
					profitable for a man, experimenting with each several department of life and
					especially with those which have to do with the practices which affect the
					body, to inculcate a fixed habit during periods of soundest health, so thus
					to make these things agreeable, familiar, and congenial to his nature, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, p. 797 E.</note>
					bearing in mind how some men feel and act in times of sickness, being angry
					and fretful when hot water and gruel, or plain bread, is served to them,
					calling these things abominable and unpleasant, and abominable and
					hard-hearted also those who would force such things upon them. A bath has
					proved to be the death of many men who at the outset had not much the matter
					with them, save only that they could not and would not bear to taste food
					unless they had first had their bath ; of whom Titus the Emperor <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There are varying accounts regarding the manner of Titus's death, poisoning or drowning being also alleged.</note> was one,
					as those who attended him in his illness affirm. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Something, moreover, was said to this effect, that, while the less expensive
					things are always more healthful for the body, we ought especially to guard
					against excess in eating and drinking, and against <pb id="v.2.p.225"/> all
					self-indulgence when we have immediately on hand some festival or a visit
					from friends, or when we are expecting an entertainment of some king or high
					official with its unavoidable social engagements ; and thus we should, as it
					were, in fair weather make our body trim and buoyant against the oncoming
					wind and wave. It is indeed a hard task, in the midst of company and good
					cheer, to keep to moderation and one's habits and at the same time to avoid
					the extreme disagreeableness which makes one appear offensive and tiresome
					to the whole company. Therefore, to avoid adding fire to fire (as the
					proverb has it),<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The proverb may be found in Plato's <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, p. 666 A, and often repeated in other writers.</note> and gorging to gorging, and strong drink to strong drink,
					we ought with all seriousness to imitate the polite joke of Philip. It was
					in this wise <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 178 D, and referred to, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 707 B.</note> : A man had invited Philip to dinner in the country, assuming
					that he had but a few with him, but when later the host saw Philip bringing
					a great company, no great preparations having been made, he was much
					perturbed . Philip, becoming aware of the situation, sent word privately to
					each of his friends to <q direct="unspecified">leave room for cake.</q> They, following
					the advice, and looking for more to come, ate sparingly of what was before
					them, and so the dinner was ample for all. In this manner, then, we ought to
					prepare ourselves in anticipation of our imperative round of social
					engagements by keeping room in the body for elaborate dishes and pastry,
					and, I dare to say it, for indulgence in strong drink also, by bringing to
					these things an appetite fresh and willing. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>If, however, such imperative occasions suddenly confront us when we are
					overloaded and in no condition for taking part&mdash;if, for instance,
					we receive an invitation from a high official, or guests appear, so <pb id="v.2.p.227"/> that we are constrained by a false sense of shame to
					join company with men who are in fit condition and to drink with
					them&mdash;then especially, in order to combat <q direct="unspecified">shame which works
						mischief for men</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The reference may be to Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 45 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days,</hi> 318).</note> (or rather I would call it shamefacedness),
					we should summon to our defence the words which Creon speaks <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Medea</hi>, 290, quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 530 C.</note> in the
					tragedy : <quote rend="blockquote">'Twere better, friend, to gain your hatred now Than be
						soft-hearted and lament anon.</quote> For to be so afraid of being thought ill-bred
					as to plunge oneself into a pleurisy or brain-fever is proof that one is in
					very truth ill-bred, possessed of neither sense nor the reason which knows
					how to consort with men without the wine-glass and the savour of food.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 612 F.</note> For
					a request to be excused, if characterized by cleverness and wit, is no less
					agreeable than joining in the round of gaiety ; and if a man provides a
					banquet in the same spirit in which he provides a burnt-offering which it is
					forbidden to taste, and personally abstains when the wine-cup and the table
					are before him, at the same time volunteering cheerfully some playful
					allusion to himself, he will create a pleasanter impression than the man who
					gets drunk and gormandizes for company. Of the men of earlier times he <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumable Plutarch again.</note>
					mentioned Alexander,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxxv. (p. 706 C); Diodorus, xvii. 117; Athenaeus, 434 C; Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, vii. 25. 1; Quintus Curtius, x. 4; Justin, xii. 13.</note> who, after a prolonged debauch, was ashamed to say no
					to the challenges of Medius, and abandoned himself to a fresh round of hard
					drinking, which cost him his life; and of the men of our time he mentioned
					Regulus the prize-fighter. For when Titus Caesar called him to the bath at
					daybreak, 
					<pb id="v.2.p.229"/> he came and bathed with him, took but one drink, they
					say, and died immediately from a stroke of apoplexy. </p>
            <p>These are the teachings which Glaucus in derision quoted aggressively to us
					as pedantic. The rest he was not eager to hear, nor we to tell him. But I
					beg that you will examine each of the several statements. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>First there is Socrates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Memorabilia</hi>, i. 3. 6; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 513 C, 521 E, and 661 F.</note> who, in urging us to be on our guard against such
					things to eat as persuade us to eat when we are not hungry, and such things
					to drink as persuade us to drink when we are not thirsty, did not absolutely
					forbid the use of these things ; but he was instructing us to use them only
					if we needed them, and to make the pleasure in them serve our necessity,
					just as our statesmen do who turn to military uses their funds for
					amusements.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps a reference to Demosthenes, lix. 4, which says that in time of war all surplus funds are to be devoted to the army.</note> For that which is pleasant, in so far as it is a nutritive
					element, is congenial to our nature, and it is by remaining still hungry
					that we ought to get enjoyment from the necessary or the pleasant foods ;
					but we should not stir up in ourselves a second and separate set of
					appetites after we have appeased the usual ones. And here is another
					consideration. Just as Socrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, ii. 17-20; again referred to <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, 130 E and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 711 E.</note> found dancing a not unpleasant exercise,
					so the man for whom pastry and sweets serve as a meal and as food suffers
					less injury. But when a man has satisfied the moderate demands of his
					nature, and has had his fill, he ought to exercise the very greatest
					vigilance against helping himself to such things. And in such matters, while
					we should be on guard against love of pleasure and gluttony, yet we should
					be no less on guard against vulgarity and love of notoriety. For these
					latter often help to persuade people to eat <pb id="v.2.p.231"/> something
					when they are not hungry, and to drink when they are not thirsty,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi>, 124 D.</note> by
					suggesting utterly sordid and cheap conceits&mdash;that it is absurd not
					to take advantage of the presence of some rare and expensive thing, as, for
					example, sow's udder,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the cruelties practised in the preparation of this highly esteemed delicacy see Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 997 A.</note> Italian mushrooms, Samian cake, or snow in Egypt. For
					things of this sort do indeed often induce people to use what is renowned
					and rare, since they are led on by empty repute as by an attractive savour,
					and compel their body to do its share, although it feels no need, so that
					they may have a tale to tell to others, and may be envied for their
					enjoyment of things so hard to obtain and so uncommon. Quite similar is
					their behaviour toward notorious women. There are times when they repose in
					quiet with their own wives who are both lovely and loving, but when they
					have paid money to a Phryne or a La&iuml;s, although their body is in
					sorry state and is inclined to shirk its task, they rouse it forthwith to
					action, and call in licentiousness to minister to pleasure, all because of
					empty repute. In fact, Phryne herself, in her advancing years, said that she
					got a better price for her remnants because of her repute. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>It is a great marvel if we get off unscathed, when we concede to the body
					only as much of pleasures as Nature in her need finds a place for, but still
					more so when we battle with it vigorously to thwart its appetites, and keep
					putting them off, and finally consent to some negotiation with such as will
					not be denied, or, as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The quotation does not appear in Plato, but Plutarch is probably summing up from memory an account of a contest with the passions such as may be found, for example, in the <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, pp. 254 ff.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">yield when the body bites and
						strains.</q> But when the case is reversed, 
					<pb id="v.2.p.233"/> and the desires descend from the mind to the body and
					force it to be subservient to the mind's emotions, and to join in their
					excitements, there is no way to prevent their leaving as a residue the most
					violent and serious injuries as the aftermath of feeble and evanescent
					pleasures. Least of all ought the body to be stirred to pleasures by the
					mind's desire, since such an origin is unnatural. Just as tickling the
					arm-pits so affects the mind as to produce laughter which is not natural, or
					even mild or happy, but convulsive and harsh, so whatsoever pleasures the
					body achieves through being prodded and disturbed by the mind are deranging
					and disturbing and foreign to Nature. Whenever, then, someone of those rare
					and notorious means of enjoyment is afforded us, we ought to take more pride
					in abstinence than in enjoyment, remembering that just as Simonides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated in more or less similar form, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 10 F and 514 F.</note> used
					to say that he had never been sorry for having kept silent, but many a time
					for having spoken, so we have never been sorry either for having put a
					dainty to one side, or for having drunk water instead of Falernian wine, but
					the opposite ; not only ought Nature not to be forced, but if anything of
					this sort is offered her even when she has need of it, the appetite ought to
					be often diverted from it towards the plain and familiar food for the sake
					of habituation and training. <quote rend="blockquote">If one must needs do wrong,</quote> are the words of
					the Theban,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eteocles in the <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi> of Euripides, i. 524; quoted by Plutarch also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 18 D.</note> who is not correct in saying, far best it were <quote rend="blockquote">To do it for a
						kingdom's sake.</quote> 
					          <pb id="v.2.p.235"/> But we can improve on this by saying that if we must
					needs seek repute in such matters as food and drink, <q direct="unspecified">far best it
						were</q> by continence for the sake of health. Nevertheless
					stinginess and greediness constrain some persons, who repress and reduce
					their desires in their own homes, to stuff themselves and enjoy themselves
					with expensive things at others' houses as though they were engaged in
					ruthless foraging in an enemy's country ; then they go away much indisposed,
					and for the next day they have an attack of indigestion to pay for their
					insatiable appetite. So Crates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> ii. p. 670, Crates, No. 10 or Diels, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Phil. Frag.</hi> p. 219, Crates, No. 6</note> thinking that luxury and extravagance were
					as much to blame as anything for the growth of civil discords and the rule
					of despots in states, humorously advised : <quote rend="blockquote">Do not, by always making our fare
						more ample than lentils, Throw us all into discord.</quote> And let everybody exhort
					himself <q direct="unspecified">not to make his fare always more ample than lentils,</q>
					and by all means not to proceed beyond cress and olives to croquettes and
					fish, and by overeating throw <q direct="unspecified">his body into discord,</q> that is
					to say, into derangements and diarrhoeas. For the inexpensive things keep
					the appetite to its natural limits of moderation, but the arts of the chefs
					and their trained helpers, and, in the words of the comic poet,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 435.</note> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">These
						knavish dainties and these complex foods,</quote> are constantly advancing and
					enlarging the bounds of enjoyment, and altering our ideas of what is good
					for us. I do not know how it is that, while we loathe and detest women who
					contrive philters and magic to use upon their husbands, we entrust <pb id="v.2.p.237"/> our food and provisions to hirelings and slaves to be
					all but bewitched and drugged. If the saying of Arcesilaus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 705 E, in a slightly different form. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aulus Gellius, iii. 5.</note> addressed to
					the adulterous and licentious appears too bitter, to the effect that ' it
					makes no difference whether a man practises lewdness in the front parlour or
					in the back hall,' yet it is not without its application to our subject. For
					in very truth, what difference does it make whether a man employ
					aphrodisiacs to stir and excite licentiousness for the purposes of pleasure,
					or whether he stimulate his taste by odours and sauces to require, like the
					itch, continual scratchings and ticklings ? </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>At some other time, then, it may be that we shall have to speak against
					pleasures, and show what an intrinsic beauty and dignity belongs to
					continence ; but the present discourse is on the side of many pleasures and
					great. For diseases do not take from us and spoil for us so many of our
					enterprises or hopes or travels or pastimes as they do of our pleasures.
					Hence contempt for health is least profitable for those who make pleasure
					their chief aim. For infirmities allow many persons to be philosophers, or
					actually even generals or kings, but the pleasures and enjoyments of the
					body in some cases do not come to life at all in time of disease, and those
					that come to life yield but a brief part of what they properly should, and
					even that is not pure, but contaminated with much that is foreign, and
					marked, as it were, by the beatings of surge and storm. For it is not true
					that In well-gorged bodies Love resides,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The sentiment is probably taken from Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 895, and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 917 B.</note> but rather in serenity and
					calmness of the flesh does 
					<pb id="v.2.p.239"/> love find its end in pleasure, as also do eating and
					drinking ; and health affords to pleasures, as calm weather to the
					halcyons,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia animalium</hi>, v. 8; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 982 F.</note> a safe and lovely nesting and hatching of their young. Prodicus
					seems to have put the matter very neatly in saying that fire is the best of
					sauces <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to Evenus in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 50 A 697 D, and 1010 C.</note> ; but one might more truly speak of health as being the most divine
					and agreeable sauce. For boiled, baked, or fried foods afford no proper
					pleasure or even gratification to those who are suffering from disease,
					debauch, or nausea, while a clean and unspoiled appetite makes everything,
					to a sound body, pleasant and <q direct="unspecified">eagerly craved,</q> as Homer has
					said,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> viii. 164. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also 101 C <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>&mdash;that is, agreeable. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>As Demades used to say that the Athenians, who were for making war in season
					and out of season, never voted for peace save when wearing black, so we
					never give a thought to a plain and restrained way of living except when
					using enemas and poultices. But when we find ourselves in this plight we try
					hard to stifle the thought of our wrongdoings, setting ourselves against
					their remembrance, and, as is the way of most people who object to this or
					that air or this or that locality as insalubrious when they say that they
					dread travelling, we exclude our intemperance and self-indulgence from the
					cause of our illness. Nay, we should recall how Lysimachus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">202 B.C.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 183 E and 555 D. Lysimachus was one of the successors of Alexander the Great.</note> among the Getae
					was constrained by thirst to surrender himself and the army with him as
					prisoners of war, and afterwards as he drank cold water exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">
						My God, for what a brief pleasure have I thrown 
						<pb id="v.2.p.241"/> away great prosperity !</q> And in the same
					way we ought in our attacks of illness to remember that for a cold drink, an
					ill-timed bath, or a social party, we have spoiled many of our pleasures and
					have ruined many an honourable enterprise and delightful recreation. For the
					sting caused by such reflections keeps the memory raw, so that, like a scar
					that remains when the body is in health, it makes us more circumspect about
					our way of living. For the healthy body will not, to any immoderate extent,
					breed desires that are vehement, intractable, unwonted, and hard to
					dispossess ; nay, we can boldly and confidently oppose the appetites which
					would fain go beyond all bounds and assault our enjoyments, knowing that
					their whining and whimpering is a trivial and childish manifestation, and
					that later, when the table is removed, they will cease repining and make no
					complaint nor feel themselves aggrieved, but, on the contrary, untainted and
					cheerful rather than dulled and nauseated by over-indulgence, await the
					morrow. The remark which Timotheus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That this story had acquired almost a fixed phraseology in the source from which Plutarch took it may be seen by comparing this passage and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 686 A, Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, ii. 18, Athenaeus, p. 419 d, and Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 35 (100).</note> made, the day after he had dined with
					Plato at the Academy on the simple fare of the scholar, is in point here :
					<q direct="unspecified">Those who dine with Plato,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">get on
						pleasantly the next day also.</q> And it is reported that Alexander
					said <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 180 A, 1099 C, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxii. (p. 677 B).</note> when he discharged the chefs of Ada that he had better ones always to
					take with him&mdash;his night marches for breakfast, and for dinner his
					frugal breakfast. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>I am not unaware that men contract fevers 
					<pb id="v.2.p.243"/> because of fatigue and extremes of heat and cold ; but
					just as the scents of flowers are weak by themselves, whereas, when they are
					mixed with oil, they acquire strength and intensity, so a great mass of food
					to start with provides substance and body, as it were, for the causes and
					sources of disease that come from the outside. Without such material none of
					these things would cause any trouble, but they would readily fade away and
					be dissipated, if clear blood and an unpolluted spirit are at hand to meet
					the disturbance ; but in a mass of superfluous food a sort of turbulent
					sediment, as it were, is stirred up, which makes everything foul and hard to
					manage and hard to get rid of. Therefore we must not act like those much
					admired (!) ship-masters who for greed take on a big cargo, and thenceforth
					are continually engaged in baling out the sea-water. So we must not stuff
					and overload our body, and afterwards employ purgatives and injections, but
					rather keep it all the time trim, so that, if ever it suffer depression, it
					shall, owing to its buoyancy, bob up again like a cork. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>We ought to take special precautions in the case of premonitory symptoms and
					sensations. For what Hesiod has said <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 104, quoted more fully <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 105 E.</note> of the illnesses that go hither and
					thither assailing mankind is not true of all, that <quote rend="blockquote">Silent they go, since the
						wisdom of Zeus has deprived them of voices,</quote> but most of them have as their
					harbingers, forerunners, and heralds, attacks of indigestion and lassitude.
					<q direct="unspecified">Feelings of heaviness or of fatigue,</q> says Hippocrates, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Aphorisms</hi>, ii. 5 (ed. Chartier, 38, 43, Kuhn, iii. p. 712).</note>
					          <q direct="unspecified">when due to no external cause, 
						<pb id="v.2.p.245"/> indicate disease,</q> since, presumably, the
					spirit about the nerves is subjected to tension and pressure owing to
					fullness within the body. Nevertheless, some men, although their body itself
					all but resists and would fain drag them to their beds and their rest, are
					led by gluttony and self-indulgence to rush off to the baths and eagerly to
					join in the drinking-bouts, as if they were laying in provisions for a siege
					and were fearful lest the fever seize them before they have had luncheon.
					Others, less gross than these, are not indeed caught in this folly, but very
					stupidly, just because they are ashamed to admit having a headache or
					indigestion, and to keep their clothes on all day, when a crowd on their way
					to the gymnasium invite them to come along, they get up and go, strip with
					the others, and go through the same exercises as do those who are in sound
					health. But as for the majority, Hope, backed by a proverb which well
					accords with incontinence and weakness of purpose, persuades and induces
					them to get up and go recklessly to their accustomed haunts, thinking to
					expel and dispel wine with wine, and headache with headache.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Similia similibus curentur.</q> The proverb as not been handed down in this form, but Plutarch may have in mind the proverb found in Pollux, ix. 120 (see Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 500, and his notes, especially the reference to Athenaeus, 44 a): <q direct="unspecified">Nail with nail and peg with peg</q> (a man drives out). Sligtly different versions may be found in Leutsch and Schneidewin, <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi Graeci</hi>, ii. pp. 116 and 171.</note> Against this
					hope should be set Cato's caution which that grand old man phrased in this
					way <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 825 D.</note> : <q direct="unspecified">Make the great small, and abolish the small altogether
					</q> ; also the thought that it is better to submit patiently to fasting
					and resting with nothing to show for it, rather than to take any chances by
					rushing pell-mell to a bath or a dinner. For if there 
					<pb id="v.2.p.247"/> is anything the matter with us, failure to take proper
					precaution and to put a check on ourselves will do us harm ; and if nothing
					is the matter, it will do no harm for the body to be subjected to some
					restrictions and cleared of some of its encumbrances. But that childish
					person who is afraid to let his friends and servants discover that he is in
					a state of discomfort from excessive eating or drinking, will, if he is
					ashamed to admit having indigestion to-day, tomorrow admit having diarrhoea
					or fever or gripes. The shame of want makes want a shame to bear,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play of Menander; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 220.</note> but much
					more is it a shame to bear indigestion, overloading, and over-fullness in a
					body which is dragged to the bath like a rotten and leaky boat into the sea.
					For just exactly as some persons, when they are voyaging and a storm is
					raging, are ashamed to tarry on shore, and so they put out to sea, and then
					are in most shameful case, shrieking and sea-sick, so those who regard it as
					ignoble, amidst suspicious premonitory symptoms of their body, to spend one
					day in bed, and not to take their meals at table, keep to their bed most
					shamefully for many days, under purging and poulticing, servile and
					attentive to physicians, asking for wine or cold water, and suffering
					themselves to do and to utter many extravagant and ignoble things because of
					their distress and fear. </p>
            <p>Moreover, it is well that those who because of pleasures fail in
					self-control, and give way to their desires or are carried away by them,
					should be instructed and reminded that pleasures derive most of their
					satisfaction from the body; </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>and as the Spartans give to the cook vinegar and salt only, 
					<pb id="v.2.p.249"/> bidding him seek whatever else he needs in the
					slaughtered animal itself,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A humorous turn is given to this custom in the anecdote related by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 995 B.</note> so in the body are the best of sauces for
					whatever is served, if so be that it is served to a body which is healthy
					and clean. For everything of this sort is <q direct="unspecified">sweet</q> or <q direct="unspecified">
						costly</q> irrespectively of the user and by itself, but Nature
					decrees that it becomes <q direct="unspecified">pleasant</q> only in and in connexion
					with the person that is pleased and is in harmony with Nature; but in those
					who are captious or suffering from a debauch, or are in a bad way, all
					things lose their intrinsic agreeableness and freshness. Therefore there is
					no need to look to see whether the fish be fresh, the bread white, the bath
					warm, or the girl shapely, but a man should look to himself to see whether
					he be not nauseated, feculent, stale, or in any way upset. Otherwise, just
					as drunken revellers who force their way into a house of mourning provide no
					cheerfulness or pleasure, but only cause weeping and wailing, so in a body
					that is in a bad condition and out of harmony with Nature, the pleasures of
					love, elaborate food, baths and wine, when combined with such elements in
					the body as are unsettled and tainted, set up phlegm and bile and bring on
					an upset, besides being unduly exciting, while they yield no pleasure to
					speak of, nor any enjoyment like what we expected. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>The very exact mode of living, <q direct="unspecified">exact to a hair's breadth,</q> to
					use the popular expression,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on 86 A in Vol. I.</note> puts the body in a timorous and precarious
					state, and abridges the self-respect of the soul itself, so that it comes to
					look askance at every activity, and to no less 
					<pb id="v.2.p.251"/> a degree at spending any time or participating at all
					in pleasures or labours, and goes at no undertaking with readiness and
					confidence. A man ought to handle his body like the sail of a ship, and
					neither lower and reduce it much when no cloud is in sight, nor be slack and
					careless in managing it when he comes to suspect something is wrong, but he
					should rather ease the body off and lighten its load, as has already been
					said, and not wait for indigestions and diarrhoeas, nor heightened
					temperatures nor fits of drowsiness. And yet some people wait until a fever
					is already at their doors and then, being as excited as if a message or a
					summons to court had come, just manage to restrict themselves ; whereas they
					ought, while these things are still afar off, to be cautious <quote rend="blockquote">Before the
						storm, as though along the strand The North wind blew.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, ii. p. 88.</note>
               </quote> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>For it is absurd to give careful heed to the croaking of ravens, the clucking
					of hens, and <q direct="unspecified">swine m their wild excitement over bedding,</q>b as
					Democritusc put it, making signs of winds and rains out of these, and at the
					same time not to forestall nor take precaution against the stirrings, the
					ups and downs, and the premonitory symptoms in the body, and not to hold
					these to be signs of a storm that is going to take place in one's self, and
					is just about to break. Wherefore not merely in the matter of food and
					exercise do we need to keep watch of our body, to see whether, contrary to
					its habits, it takes to these reluctantly and without zest, or at another
					time is thirsty and hungry in an unnatural way, but also, in the matter of
					sleep, to beware of lack of 
					<pb id="v.2.p.253"/> continuity and of evenness, marked by irregularities
					and sharp interruptions, and to beware also of the abnormal in dreams,
					which, if so be that our visions are improper or unwonted, argues an
					over-abundance or concretion of humours, or a disturbance of spirit within
					us. And also the emotions of the soul have often given warning that the body
					is perilously near disease. For instance, irrational discouragements and
					fears take possession of people oftentimes from no apparent cause, and
					suddenly extinguish their hopes ; in temper they become irascible, sharp,
					and pained at trifles, and they are tearful and dismayed whenever bad
					vapours and bitter exhalations encounter and unite with the <q direct="unspecified">
						rotations of the soul,</q> as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 47 D.</note> has it. Therefore those to whom
					such things happen have need to consider and to remember that, if the cause
					is not one which concerns the spirit, it is one which concerns the body, and
					that it needs reducing or toning down. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>It is very profitable when visiting sick friends to inquire of them the
					causes of their illness, not by talking pedantically and officiously about
					stoppages, irruptions, and trite generalities, and incidentally displaying
					some acquaintance with medical terminology and literature, but by listening
					in no perfunctory way to these homely and common details of overeating,
					exposure to the sun, fatigue, sleeplessness, and especially the manner of
					living which the man was following when he fell sick of the fever. Then,
					like Plato, who, on his way home, was accustomed to say on the subject of
					others' faults, <q direct="unspecified">Am not I too possibly like them ?</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 40 D, 88 E, and 463 E.</note> a man
					ought to correct in himself the faults he observes in his neighbours, and be
					watchful and mindful not to become involved in <pb id="v.2.p.255"/> the same
					difficulties, and be himself compelled to take to his bed, and there give
					voice to his yearnings for precious health, but rather, when another is
					undergoing this experience, he will impress upon himself how valuable a
					thing is health, and that he ought to try to preserve this by giving heed to
					himself, and by being frugal. It is not a bad thing, either, to take a look
					at our own way of living ; for if we have been engaged in a bout of drinking
					and eating, or in some hardships and other irregularities, and the body
					presents no suspicious or premonitory symptoms, nevertheless we ought to be
					watchful of ourselves and forestall any trouble by means of rest and quiet
					when fresh from the pleasures of love, or when fatigued ; also by drinking
					water after the free use of wine and after social gaiety, and especially,
					after indulging in a heavy diet of meat or multifarious foods, to eat
					lightly, and leave no mass of superfluous residue in the body. For these
					very things are of themselves the causes of many diseases, and they add
					material and potency to the other causes.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 732 E.</note> Wherefore it has been very well
					said, <q direct="unspecified">Eating not unto satiety, labouring not unto weariness, and
						observance of chastity, are the most healthful things.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably based on Hippocrates: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Hippocrates, <hi rend="italics">Epidemics</hi>, vi. 4. 20 (ed. Chartier, 9, 500, Khn, iii. p. 605).</note> For
					incontinence, by undermining especially the powers by which the food is
					assimilated, causes further superfluity and overcrowding. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Let us now take up each topic anew once more; and in the first place, on the
					subject of exercises suitable for scholars, we beg to remark that one might
					follow the example of the man who, by saying that he had nothing to write
					for people dwelling by the sea on the subject of ships, showed clearly that
					they were in use ; and so in the same way one <pb id="v.2.p.257"/> might say
					that he was not writing for scholars on the subject of exercise. For it is
					wonderful what an exercise is the daily use of the voice in speaking aloud,
					conducing, not only to health, but also to strength&mdash;not the
					strength of the wrestler which lays on flesh and makes the exterior solid
					like the walls of a building, but a strength which engenders an
					all-pervasive vigour and a real energy in the most vital and dominant parts.
					That breathing gives strength the athletic trainers make clear in telling
					the athletes to brace themselves against the rubbing and stop their breath
					meantime, and keep tense the portions of the body that are being kneaded and
					massaged. Now the voice is a movement of the breath, and if it be given
					vigour, not in the throat, but, as it were, at its source in the lungs, it
					increases the warmth, tones down the blood, clears out every vein, opens
					every artery, and does not permit of any concretion or solidifying of
					superfluous fluid like a sediment to take place in the containing organs
					which take over and digest the food. For this reason we ought especially to
					make ourselves habituated and used to this exercise by continual speaking,
					or, if there be any suspicion that our body is not quite up to the mark or
					is somewhat fatigued, then by reading aloud or declaiming. For reading
					stands in the same relation to discussion as riding in a carriage to active
					exercise, and as though upon the vehicle of another's words it moves softly,
					and carries the voice gently this way and that. But discussion adds
					contention and vehemence, as the mind joins in the encounter along with the
					body. We must, however, be cautious about passionate and convulsive
					vociferations. For 
					<pb id="v.2.p.259"/> spasmodic expulsion and straining of the breath
					produces ruptures and sprains. </p>
            <p>After reading or discussion, before going to walk, one should make use of
					rubbing with oil in a warm room to render the flesh supple, extending the
					massage so far as practicable to the inward parts, and gently equalizing the
					vital spirit and diffusing it into the extremities. Let the limits of the
					amount of this rubbing be what is agreeable to the senses and not
					discomforting. For the man who thus composes the inward disquiet and tension
					in his vital spirit manages the superfluous in his body without discomfort,
					and if unfavourable weather or some engagement prevent his going to walk, it
					does not matter, for Nature has received her proper due. Wherefore neither
					travelling nor stopping at an inn ought to be made an excuse for silence,
					nor even if everybody there deride one. For where it is not disgraceful to
					eat it is certainly not disgraceful to take exercise; nay, it is more
					disgraceful to feel timid and embarrassed before sailors, muleteers, and
					innkeepers, who do not deride the man who plays ball and goes through the
					movements of sparring alone, but the man who speaks, even though in his
					exercises he instruct, question, learn, and use his memory. Socrates said <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Symposium, 2. 18.</hi>
               </note>
					that for a man's movements in dancing a room that would accommodate seven
					persons at dinner was large enough to take exercise in, but for a man who
					takes his exercise through singing or speaking every place affords him
					adequate room for this exercise both when standing up and when lying down.
					But we must observe this one caution&mdash;not to strain our voices too
					hard
					<pb id="v.2.p.261"/> when we are conscious of a fullness, venery, or
					fatigue. This is the experience of many of the public speakers and sophists,
					some of whom are led on by repute and ambition, others on account of
					emoluments or political rivalries, to competition in excess of what is best
					for them. Our Niger, when he was giving public lectures in Galatia, happened
					to swallow a fish bone. But, as another sophist from abroad had made his
					appearance and was lecturing, Niger, dreading to give the impression that he
					had yielded to his rival, still lectured although the bone was sticking in
					his throat; unable to bear the distress from the great and stubborn
					inflammation that arose, he submitted to a deep incision from the outside,
					and through the opening the bone was removed ; but the place grew sore and
					purulent and caused his death. But comment on these matters may well be
					postponed to a later occasion. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, 135 D.</note> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>To take a cold bath after exercising is ostentatious and juvenile rather than
					healthful. For the power of resistance to external influences and the
					hardiness which it seems to create in the body really produces a more evil
					effect on the inward parts by stopping up the pores, causing the fluids to
					collect together, and condensing the exudations which are always wanting to
					be released and dispersed. Besides, those who insist upon taking cold baths
					have to make a further change into that exact and strictly ordered way of
					living which we are trying to avoid, and they have to be always taking heed
					not to transgress this, since every shortcoming is at once bitterly brought
					to book. On the other hand, warm baths have much to offer by way of excuse.
					For they do not detract so much from vigour and strength as <pb id="v.2.p.263"/> they help towards health by rendering the food yielding
					and soft for the digestion, and by providing for the painless dispersion of
					whatever escapes digestion, at least if it do not remain altogether crude
					and high up, and soothing any latent feelings of fatigue. However, when
					Nature affords us a sense of a moderate and comfortable condition in our
					body, the bath had better be left alone. A gentle rubbing with oil beside a
					fire is better, if the body require warming, for it can take for itself the
					requisite amount of such warmth ; but the sun permits the use of its warmth
					at neither higher nor lower temperature than is determined by the
					temperature of the air. So much will suffice in regard to exercise. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Coming now to the subject of food, if there be anything helpful in my earlier
					suggestions as to how we may beguile and pacify our appetites, we must give
					some further advice regarding what comes next; but if it be difficult to
					manage a belly that has been set free, as it were from bondage, and to
					wrangle with it when it has no ears to hear, as Cato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same remark is found in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 198 D, 996 D, and <hi rend="italics">Life of M. Cato</hi>, chap. viii. (p. 340 A).</note> used to say, we must
					contrive by means of the character of our food to make the quantity less
					burdensome ; and of the solid and very nourishing foods, things, for
					example, like meat and cheese, dried figs and boiled eggs, one may partake
					if he helps himself cautiously (for it is hard work to decline all the
					time), but should stick to the thin and light things, such as most of the
					garden stuff, birds, and such fish as have not much fat. For it is possible
					by partaking of these things both to gratify the appetites and not oppress
					the body. Especially to be feared are indigestions <pb id="v.2.p.265"/>
					arising from meats <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is worth while to compare Plutarch's essays on eating meat, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 993 A-999 B.</note> ; for they are depressing at the outset, and a
					pernicious residue from them remains behind. It is best to accustom the body
					not to require meat in addition to other food. For the earth yields in
					abundance many things not only for nourishment but also for comfort and
					enjoyment, some of which it grants to our use just as they are with no
					trouble on our part, while others we may make savoury by all sorts of
					combination and preparation. But since custom has become a sort of unnatural
					second nature, our use of meat should not be for the satisfaction of
					appetite, as is the case with wolves or lions ; but while we may put it in
					as a sort of prop and support of our diet, we should use other foods and
					relishes which for the body are more in accord with nature and less dulling
					to the reasoning faculty, which, as it were, is kindled from plain and light
					substances. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Of the liquids milk ought not to be used as a beverage but as a food
					possessing solid and nourishing power. With regard to wine we ought to talk
					as does Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, No. 967. The sentiment is a favourite one with Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>, for example, <hi rend="italics">Iphigeneia at Aulis</hi>, 543-557; <hi rend="italics">Medea</hi> 627-634; <hi rend="italics">Helena</hi>, 1105.</note> with regard to Love : <quote rend="blockquote">May est thou be mine, but moderate
						be, I pray, yet ne'er abandon me.</quote> For wine is the most beneficial of
					beverages, the pleasantest of medicines, and the least cloying of appetizing
					things, provided that there is a happy combination of it with the occasion
					as well as with water. Water, not only the water that is mixed with <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">b
						From an unknown play: cf. Nauck, Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides, No. 967.
						The sentiment is a favourite one with Euripides ; cf., for example,
						Iphigeneia at Aulis, 543-557; Medea, 627-634; Helena, 1105.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.267"/> the wine, but that which is drunk by itself in the
					interim between the draughts of the mixture, makes the mixture more
					innocent. One ought to accustom oneself, therefore, in the course of the
					daily routine to partake of two or three glasses of water, thus both making
					the potency of the wine milder, and making the drinking of water habitual
					with the body, so that, whenever it comes to be in need of water, it may not
					feel strange towards the drink, and refuse it. For the fact is that some
					people feel most impelled towards wine when the drink which they most need
					is water. For after being exposed to the sun, and again when chilled, and
					after speaking more earnestly and thinking more intently than usual, and, in
					general, after exertions and strivings, they think they ought to drink wine,
					feeling that Nature requires for the body some comfort and change after
					labours. But Nature does not require comfort, if comfort is only a name for
					self-indulgence, but she does require a change, a change which puts the body
					in a state midway between pleasure and pain. Therefore in such circumstances
					there should not only be some reduction in food, but wine should be either
					altogether eliminated or else partaken of between times very diluted and
					practically engulfed by the drinking of water. For wine, being truculent and
					keen, intensifies the disturbances of the body, and exacerbates and
					irritates the contused parts, which are in need of the comfort and
					alleviation that water best supplies. For if, in spite of the fact that we
					are not thirsty, we drink hot water after undergoing exertion, strain, or
					heat, we are sensible of a relaxing and soothing effect within us; for the
					aqueous fluid is mild and does not quicken the pulse, <pb id="v.2.p.269"/>
					whereas that of wine has great impetuosity and a potency that is not kindly
					or humanely disposed toward recent affections. As for the acerbities and
					bitterness which some say fasting engenders in the body , if anybody fears
					them, or if, childlike, he thinks it a dreadful thing not to have a meal
					served before the fever which he suspects is coming, the drinking of water
					is a very fitting middle course. In fact we frequently make to Dionysus
					himself offerings which include no wine, thus habituating ourselves quite
					properly not to be always looking for strong drink. Minos, too, because of
					grief, abolished the flute and garland from the sacrifice.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi>, iii. 15. 7.</note> Yet we know that
					a grieving soul is not affected either by garlands or by flute. But no one's
					body is so strong that wine, thrust upon it when it is disturbed and
					feverish, does it no harm. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>The Lydians, they say, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, i. 94.</note> in a time of famine, alternately spent one day in
					regaling themselves with food, and the next in jollity and games of chance.
					But in the case of a scholarly and cultivated man, on an occasion which
					requires a later dinner than usual, a mathematical problem on hand, or some
					pamphlet or musical instrument, will not permit him to be harried by his
					belly ; on the contrary, he will steadily turn away and transfer his
					thoughts from the table to these other things, and scare away his appetites,
					like Harpies, by means of the Muses. Does not the Scythian,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demetrius</hi>, chap. xix. (p. 897 C).</note> while he is
					drinking, ofttimes put his hand to his bow, and twang the string, thus
					summoning back his senses which are being unstrung by the liquor ; and shall
					a Greek man be afraid of those who deride him when by letters and books he
					endeavours quietly to ease and relax an unfeeling <pb id="v.2.p.271"/> and
					inexorable desire? When the young men described by Menander <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p 183, No. 607. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 706 B.</note> were, as they
					were drinking, insidiously beset by the pimp, who introduced some handsome
					and high-priced concubines, each one of them (as he says), <quote rend="blockquote">Bent down his
						head and munched his own dessert,</quote> being on his guard and afraid to look at
					them. But scholars have many fair and pleasant outlooks and diversions, if
					so be they can in no other way keep under control the canine and bestial
					element in their appetites when at table. The utterances of athletic
					trainers and the talk of teachers of gymnastics, who assert on every
					occasion that scholarly conversation at dinner spoils the food and makes the
					head heavy, are to be feared only when we propose to solve the Indian
					problem or to discuss determinants <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These are both thought to be logical fallacies of the type of Achilles and the tortoise, or the <q direct="unspecified">Liar.</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1070 C.</note> during dinner. The leaf-bud at the top
					of the date-palm is sweet, but they say that it brings on a violent headache
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 3. 15.</note> ; and an exercise in logic is by no means a <q direct="unspecified">sweet morsel</q>
					          <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 124 (ed. Christ).</note> to top off a dinner, but, on the contrary, it is quite likely to bring on
					a headache, and is extremely fatiguing as well. But if they will not allow
					us to start any other inquiry or scholarly discussion,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi> 612 F, where this topic is treated more fully.</note> or to read while at
					dinner any of those things which, besides being beautiful and useful,
					contain also the element of pleasurable allurement and sweetness, we shall
					bid them not to bother us, but to take themselves off, and in the training
					grounds and buildings to engage in such talk with the athletes, whom they
					have torn from their books, 
					<pb id="v.2.p.273"/> and by accustoming them to spend the whole day in
					jesting and scurrility, have, as the clever Ariston said, made them as
					glossy and blockish as the pillars in a gymnasium. But as for ourselves, we
					shall follow the advice of the physicians who recommend always to let some
					time intervene between dinner and sleep, and not, after jumbling our
					victuals into our body and oppressing our spirit, to hinder our digestion at
					once with the food that is still unassimilated and fermenting, but rather to
					provide for it some respite and relaxation ; just as those who think it is
					the right thing to keep their bodies moving after dinner do not do this by
					means of foot-races and strenuous boxing and wrestling, but by gentle
					walking and decorous dancing, so we shall hold that we ought not to distract
					our minds after dinner either with business or cares or pseudo-learned
					disputations, which have as their goal an ostentatious or stirring rivalry.
					But many of the problems of natural science are light and enticing, and
					there are many stories which contain ethical considerations and the <q direct="unspecified">
						soul's satisfaction,</q> as Homer has phrased this, and nothing
					repellent. The spending of time over questions of history and poetry some
					persons, not unpleasingly, have called a second repast <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi> 672 E.</note> for men of
					scholarship and culture. There are also inoffensive stories and fables, and
					it is less onerous to exchange opinions about a flute and a lyre than to
					listen to the sound of the lyre and the 
					<pb id="v.2.p.275"/> flute itself. The length of time for this is such as
					the digestion needs to assert itself and gain the upper hand over the food
					as it is gradually absorbed and begins to agree with us. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Aristotle holds <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 224 (233 in Rose's edition).</note>that walking about on the part of those who have just dined
					revives the bodily warmth, while sleep, if they go to sleep at once,
					smothers it; but others hold that quiet improves the digestive faculties,
					while movement disturbs the processes of assimilation; and this has
					persuaded some to walk about immediately after dinner, and others to remain
					quiet. In view of the two opinions a man might appear properly to attain
					both results who after dinner keeps his body warm and quiet, and does not
					let his mind sink at once into sleep and idleness, but, as has been
					previously suggested, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi> 130 A-E.</note> lightly diverts and enlivens his spirits by talking
					himself and listening to another on one of the numerous topics which are
					agreeable and not acrimonious or depressing. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>The use of emetics and cathartics, abominable <q direct="unspecified">comforts for an
					overloaded stomach,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Critias, p. 115 B.</hi>
               </note> ought never, except under the stress of
					great necessity, to be inaugurated, as is the way of most people, who fill
					up their bodies for the sake of emptying them, and then empty them for the
					sake of filling them up again, thus transgressing against nature, and are
					vexed no less at their fullness than at their emptiness&mdash;or,
					better, they are utterly depressed over their fullness, as being a hindrance
					to enjoyment, but set about bringing on emptiness with the idea of making
					room always for pleasures. The harmfulness in all this is manifest; for both
					procedures give rise to disorders and convulsive movements in the <pb id="v.2.p.277"/> body. What is peculiarly bad in the use of an emetic is
					that it increases and fosters an insatiate greediness. For the feelings of
					hunger become rough and turbulent, like rivers that are interrupted in their
					course, and they gulp the food down violently, always ravening and
					resembling not appetites that need victuals, but inflammations that need
					medicines and poultices. For this reason the pleasures that lay hold upon
					such persons are swift in their action and imperfect, and attended by much
					palpitation and agitation while being experienced, and these are succeeded
					by distensions and sharp pains in the passages, and retention of gases,
					which cannot wait for the natural movements, but stay in the upper part of
					the body as in water-logged ships which require the jettisoning of their
					cargo, not merely of their surplus. The violent disturbances lower down in
					the bowels resulting from medication, by decomposing and liquefying the
					existing contents, increase rather than relieve the overcrowding. Just
					imagine that anybody , feeling much troubled at the crowd of Greeks living
					in his city, should fill up the city with Arab and Scythian immigrants ! Yet
					it is just this radical mistake that some people make in connexion with the
					expulsion of the surplus of habitual and familiar foods, when they introduce
					into the body from the outside Cnidian berries, scammony, or other
					incongruous and drastic agents, which have more need of being purged away
					than power of purging our nature. It is best, therefore, by moderate and
					temperate living to make the body constantly selfsufficient and well
					adjusted as regards filling the stomach and emptying it. </p>
            <p>If ever absolute necessity befall us, vomiting <pb id="v.2.p.279"/> should be
					induced without medication and a great ado, and without causing any
					disturbance beyond merely avoiding indigestion by at once allowing the
					excess to be peacefully ejected. Just as linen cleansed with lye and washing
					powders wears out faster than that washed in plenty of water, so vomitings
					with drugs maltreat and ruin the body. If the bowels are getting sluggish,
					there is no medicine like some sorts of food that afford a mild stimulus to
					the inclinations and gently dissolve the cause of trouble. Experience with
					these is familiar to all, and their use is not attended by discomfort. But
					if it will not yield to these, the drinking of water for several days, or
					fasting, or an enema, should be tried next rather than disturbing and
					pernicious dosing to which most people hurriedly resort, after the manner of
					licentious women who employ drugs and instruments to produce abortion for
					the sake of the enjoyment of conceiving again. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But we need say no more about this class of persons. However, to speak once
					again of those too exact persons who interject set periods of fasting
					according to a fixed schedule, they are wrong in teaching their nature to
					feel a need of restraint when not in need of it, and in making necessary the
					unnecessary retrenchment at a time which makes demand for what is
					customarily required. It is better to apply such discipline to the body with
					a certain freedom, and, if there be no premonitory or suspicious symptoms,
					to keep, as has been already suggested,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi>, 128 E.</note> our general mode of life responsive
					to changes so as to meet whatever may befall it, and not to let it be
					enslaved or bound to one formula of life, which has trained itself to be
					guided by certain <pb id="v.2.p.281"/> seasons, or numbers, or schedules.
					For it is not safe, nor easy, nor befitting a citizen or a man, but like the
					life of an oyster or the trunk of a tree&mdash;this immutability and
					forced compliance in the matter of food and abstinence, movement and rest;
					it is fitting only for men who have reduced and restricted themselves to a
					retired, idle, solitary, friendless, and inglorious life, far removed from
					the duties of citizenship. <q direct="unspecified">No,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">it fits not
						with my opinion.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A paraphrase of Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 108.</note> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>For health is not to be purchased by idleness and inactivity, which are the
					greatest evils attendant on sickness, and the man who thinks to conserve his
					health by uselessness and ease does not differ from him who guards his eyes
					by not seeing, and his voice by not speaking. For a man in good health could
					not devote himself to any better object than to numerous humane activities.
					Least of all is it to be assumed that laziness is healthful, if it destroys
					what health aims at; and it is not true either that inactive people are more
					healthy. For Xenocrates did not keep in better health than Phocion, nor
					Theophrastus than Demetrius, and the running away from every activity that
					smacked of ambition did not help Epicurus and his followers at all to attain
					their much-talked-of condition of perfect bodily health. But we ought, by
					attention to other details, to preserve the natural constitution of our
					bodies, recognizing that every life has room for both disease and health. </p>
            <p>However, our friend said that to men in public life should be given advice
					opposite to that which Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not extant in Plato's writings, but a faint suggestion of the idea may be found in <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, p. 643 B.</note> 
					          <pb id="v.2.p.283"/> used to give to the young men. For the philosopher, as
					he took his leave after the exercise, was in the habit of saying, <q direct="unspecified">Be
						sure, my boys, that you store up the lesson of this hour of leisure for
						some good end.</q> But we would advise those who take part in the
					government to employ their active labours for good and necessary ends, and
					not subject their bodies to stress on account of small and paltry matters,
					as is the way of most people, who make themselves miserable over incidental
					things, and wear themselves out with loss of sleep, going to this place and
					that place, and running about, all for no useful or decent purpose, but only
					from a spirit of insolence, envy, or rivalry against others, or in the
					pursuit of unprofitable and empty repute. It was in special reference to
					such people, as I think, that Demolitus said,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Philos. Graec.</hi> i. p. 342; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, ii. p. 91.</note> that, if the body were to
					enter suit against the soul for cruel and abusive treatment, the soul would
					not be acquitted. Perhaps, too, there is some truth in what Theophrastus
					said,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This and the preceding quotation are given in greatly amplified form in Fragment i, 2 of <hi rend="italics">De anima</hi> (vol. vii. p. 2 of Bernardakis's edition of the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>).</note> in his metaphorical statement, that the soul pays a high rental to
					the body. At any rate, the body reaps the fruit of more evils from the soul
					than the soul from the body, inasmuch as the soul uses the body
					unreasonably, and the body does not get the care that it deserves. For
					whenever the soul is occupied with its own emotions, strivings, and
					concerns, it is prodigal of the body. I do not know what possessed Jason <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Despot of Pherae; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the note <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> on 89 C. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also for the sentiment Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 817 F, and Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, i. 12; also <hi rend="italics">The Epistle to the Romans</hi>, iii. 8 and vi. 1.</note>
					to say : <q direct="unspecified">We must do wrong in small ways for the sake of doing right
						in large ways.</q> But we, with good reason, would advise the man in
					public life to be indifferent to small things, and to take his ease and give
					himself 
					<pb id="v.2.p.285"/> plenty of rest while attending to them, if, when he
					comes to honourable and important activities, he wishes to have his body not
					worn by drudging, nor dull, nor on the point of giving out, but refreshed by
					quiet, like a ship in the dock ; so that when the soul again points the way
					to needful activities, it May run like weanling colt beside its dam.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi>ii. p. 738, Simonides of Amorgus, No. 5; repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 84 D, 446 E, 790 F, and in a fragment quoted by Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, cxv. 18.</note> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Therefore, when circumstances afford us opportunity, we should give ourselves
					a chance to recuperate, and to this end we should not grudge to our body
					either sleep or luncheon or ease, which is the mean between indulgence and
					discomfort,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An adumbration of the Aristotelian doctrine that virtue is a mean.</note> nor observe the sort of limit that most people observe whereby
					they wear out their body, like steel that is being tempered, by the changes
					to which they subject it; whenever the body has been strained and oppressed
					by much hard work, it is once more softened and relaxed immoderately in
					pleasures, and again, as the next step, while it is still flaccid and
					relaxed from venery and wine, it is coerced into going to the Forum or to
					Court or into some business requiring fervent and intense application.
					Heracleitus, suffering from dropsy, bade his physician to <q direct="unspecified">bring on a
						drought to follow the wet spell</q>;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. pp. 67-68.</note> but most people are completely
					in error, inasmuch as, when they are in the midst of exertions, labours, and
					deprivations, they are most inclined to surrender their bodies to pleasures
					to be made languid and relaxed, and then, after their pleasures, bending
					them, as it were, into place, and stretching them tight again. 
					<pb id="v.2.p.287"/> For Nature does not require any such form of
					compensation in the case of the body. But, on the other hand, in the soul
					the licentious and unmannerly element, immediately after undergoing
					hardships, is carried away, as sailors are, by wantonness to pleasures and
					enjoyments, and, after the pleasures, it is again coerced to tasks and
					business ; and the result is that it does not allow Nature to attain the
					composure and calm which she needs most, but deranges and disturbs her
					because of this irregularity. But people who have sense are least given to
					proffering pleasures to the body when it is busied with labours. For they
					have absolutely no need, nor even recollection, of such things, inasmuch as
					they are keeping their thoughts intent on the good to be accomplished by
					their activity ; and by the joy or earnestness in their souls they
					completely dwarf their other desires. There is a jocose remark attributed to
					Epameinondas in regard to a good man who fell ill and died about the time of
					the battle of Leuctra : <q direct="unspecified">Great Heavens ! How did he find time to die
						when there was so much going on ?</q> This may be repeated with
					truth in the case of a man who has in hand some public activity or
					philosophic meditation: <q direct="unspecified">What time has this man now for indigestion or
						drunkenness or carnal desires ?</q> But when such men find
					themselves again at leisure following upon their activities, they compose
					and rest their bodies, guarding against and avoiding useless toils, and more
					especially unnecessary pleasures, on the ground that they are inimical to
					Nature. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>I have heard that Tiberius Caesar once said that a man over sixty who holds
					out his hand to a physician is ridiculous.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 794 B; Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Annals</hi>, vi. 46.</note> To me that seems a pretty <pb id="v.2.p.289"/> strong statement, but this does seem to be true, that
					each person ought neither to be unacquainted with the peculiarities of his
					own pulse (for there are many individual diversities), nor ignorant of any
					idiosyncrasy which his body has in regard to temperature and dryness,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 735 F.</note> and
					what things in actual practice have proved to be beneficial or detrimental
					to it. For the man has no perception regarding himself, and is but a blind
					and deaf tenant in his own body, who gets his knowledge of these matters
					from another, and must inquire of his physician whether his health is better
					in summer or winter, whether he can more easily tolerate liquid or solid
					foods, and whether his pulse is naturally fast or slow. For it is useful and
					easy for us to know things of this sort, since we have daily experience and
					association with them. </p>
            <p>In regard to food and drink it is expedient to note what kinds are wholesome
					rather than what are pleasant, and to be better acquainted with those that
					are good in the stomach rather than in the mouth, and those that do not
					disturb the digestion rather than those that greatly tickle the palate. For
					to inquire of a physician what is hard or easy for oneself to digest, and
					what is constipating or laxative, is no less disgraceful than to inquire
					what is sweet and what is bitter and what is sour. But nowadays people
					correct the chefs, being expert at detecting what dish has in it more
					sweetening or salt or sourness than is proper ; but they do not themselves
					know what, when taken into their own bodies, will be light and painless and
					beneficial. Therefore, a mistake is not often made in seasoning a soup at
					their houses, but by their vile and pernicious seasoning of themselves every
					day they provide a plentiful business <pb id="v.2.p.291"/> for the
					physicians. Now such persons do not regard the sweetest soup as the best,
					but they mix in also bitter and pungent flavourings ; on the other hand,
					they inject into the body numerous cloying pleasures, partly from ignorance,
					and partly because they do not remember that to whatever is healthful and
					beneficial nature adds a pleasure which causes neither pain nor repentance.
					But we must keep in mind both those things that are congenial and suitable
					to the body, and, conversely, as changes attendant on the season occur and
					different circumstances arise, we should, in full knowledge of the facts,
					suitably adjust our mode of living to each. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Now as to various difficulties, due to observance of petty detail and to lack
					of freedom, which most men encounter&mdash;men who are engaged in the
					toilsome business of harvesting and caring for their crops and by sleepless
					nights and running hither and thither bring to light the latent infirmities
					of their bodies&mdash;there is no good reason to fear that such will be
					experienced by scholars and men in public life, with reference to whom our
					discussion has taken its present form ; but these must guard against another
					and more subtle kind of pettiness that inheres in letters and learning, an
					influence which compels them to be unsparing and careless of their body, so
					that they oftentimes, when the body is ready to succumb, will not surrender,
					but will force the mortal to be partner with the immortal, and the
					earth-born with the celestial, in rivalry and achievement. Then later, to
					quote the words of the ox to his fellow-servant the camel, who was unwilling
					to lighten his burden : <q direct="unspecified">Well, before long you will be carrying me as
						well as all this load</q> (as actually <pb id="v.2.p.293"/>
					resulted when the ox fell dead).<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aesop's <hi rend="italics">Fables</hi>, No. 125.</note>And this is just what happens to the mind
					: if it is unwilling to relax a little and give up to the body in distress
					and need, a little later a fever or a vertigo attacks it, and it is
					compelled to give up its books and discussions and studies, and share with
					the body its sickness and weariness. Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 88 B.</note> was right, therefore, in
					advising that there should be no movement of the body without the mind or of
					the mind without the body, but that we should preserve, as it were, the even
					balance of a well-matched team ; when the body shares most in the work and
					weariness of the mind we should repay it by giving it the most care and
					attention, and we should feel that of the good gifts which fair and lovely
					Health bestows the fairest is the unhampered opportunity to get and to use
					virtue both in words and in deeds. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cf. Aesop's Fables No. 125. b
						Timaeus, p. 88 b.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>