<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>

<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Twelve Years (English). Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Demades</author> &responsibility; &fund.AnnCPB; </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 21Kb</extent> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demades</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                <state unit="speech"/>
                <state unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="en">English </language>
                <language id="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>May 1992</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>W. Merrill</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>June 1992</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>W. Merrill</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Checkmark</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="speech" n="1">
                <head>On the Twelve Years</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The laws have
                    given you the right, Athenians, to acquit or punish men on trial. A doctor
                    cannot treat his patients skilfully if he has not discerned the cause of the
                    disease, nor can a member of a jury give a fair vote unless he has followed
                    intelligently the rights and wrongs of the case. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    />Since I have myself become exposed to the full hatred of the orators, I am
                    asking not only for divine assistance but for your help also. For they are
                    casting aspersions on my personal history, thinking to undermine your confidence
                    in my speech. I am of no consequence whether alive or dead; for what do the
                    Athenians care if Demades is lost to them, too? No soldier will shed tears over
                    my death&mdash;&lpar;How could he, when war brings him advancement and
                    peace destroys his livelihood?&rpar;; but it will be lamented by the farmer,
                    the sailor, and everyone who has enjoyed the peaceful life with which I
                    fortified <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, encircling its
                    boundaries, not with stone, but with the safety of the city. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>In many cases, gentlemen of the jury, when men are serving
                    as judges they are seriously misled. For, just as a complaint of the eyes, by
                    confusing the vision, prevents a man from seeing what lies before him, so an
                    unjust speech, insinuating itself into the minds of the jury, prevents them in
                    their anger from perceiving the truth. You should therefore exercise more care
                    in dealing with the accused than with the plaintiffs. For the latter, by virtue
                    of speaking first, have the jury in the mood which suits them, while the former
                    are compelled to plead their cause to judges already prejudiced by anger.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Now, if you hold me liable for the charges,
                    condemn me out of hand; I ask no pardon. But if, on considerations of justice,
                    law, and expediency, I prove to be innocent of these charges, do not leave me to
                    the savagery of my prosecutors. If my death will contribute in the least, as
                    these men say, to the common safety, I am ready to die. For it is a noble thing
                    to win public esteem by the loss of one's own life, so long as it is given in
                    answer to the country's need and not the argument of these accusers. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>I entreat you by the gods, Athenians, give me free
                    scope to explain to you my claims to fair treatment. I have, I believe, the
                    power even to be of assistance to others, but on this occasion fear restrains my
                    speech. Apart from that I am not afraid that the facts will convict me; all I
                    fear is my opponents' slander which, instead of bringing wrongdoers to justice,
                    attaches to any with a reputation as an orator or statesman. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>The hopes I place in you are justified; for the sympathy of
                    his hearers, when it is ranged on the side of justice, is no small factor in
                    securing the acquittal of the accused. If I gain this I shall rebut all the
                    calumnies; without it neither speech nor laws, nor the light of facts, can save
                    a man unjustly brought to trial. I need not remind you that numerous prosecutors
                    on many occasions in the past have, on the strength of their pleas, been thought
                    to be urging a just case, but after a comparison with the defence they have been
                    found to be themselves speaking falsely and I am convinced that my accusers now
                    will have the same experience, if you consent to grant me a favorable hearing.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As they
                    attempted to question the rest of my administration, I wish to make a few points
                    in connexion with it and then to pass on to the remainder of my defence in order
                    to prove their dishonesty to you. I am the son of Demeas, Athenians, as the
                    elder ones among you know, and the early part of my life I lived as best I
                    could, neither doing harm to the community nor troubling any individual in the
                    city. I merely persisted in trying, by my own efforts, to better my humble
                    position. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Penury may involve inconvenience and
                    hardship but it carries with it no discredit, since poverty is frequently, I
                    imagine, a mark not of weakness of character but of sheer misfortune. When I
                    entered public life I did not concentrate on lawsuits or the perquisites to be
                    derived from writing speeches but on speaking freely from the platform, a
                    practice which makes the lives of orators dangerous but holds out the clearest
                    opportunities of success, if men are careful<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                            ><foreign lang="greek">eu)laboume/nois</foreign>, too, clearly refers to
                        the hearers, not to the orators, an therefore the sense is the same as that
                        given by the words <foreign lang="greek">eu)labw=s a)krowme/nois</foreign>,
                        even if we do not adopt that emendation.</note>; for, though they succumb to
                    the speaker, their country's safety must not also fall a victim. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/>I have, to bear me out, the burial of a thousand
                        Athenians<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">It is said that after <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> in <date value="-338">338</date>
                        B.C. Philip was insulting his prisoners, until Demades, by his frank speech,
                        won him over to a better attitude towards <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName>. Cf. <bibl n="Diod. 16.87">Dio. Sic.
                        16.87</bibl>.</note> performed by the hands of our adversaries, hands which
                    I won over from enmity to friendship towards the dead. Then, on coming to the
                    fore in public life, I proposed the peace. I admit it. I proposed honors to
                    Philip. I do not deny it. By making these proposals I gained for you two
                    thousand captives free of ransom, a thousand Athenian dead, for whom no herald
                    had to ask, and Oropus without an embassy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>The
                    hand that wrote them was constrained, not by Macedonian gifts, as my accusers
                    falsely allege, but by the need of the moment, the interest of my country, and
                    the generosity of the king. For he entered the war as our foe but emerged from
                    the struggle as a friend, awarding to the vanquished the prize of the victors.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Again, there came a second crisis for the
                    city; for I deliberately ignore the intervening dangers. All other inhabitants
                    of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> were promoting Alexander to
                    the rank of leader, and by remoulding him in their decrees they raised the
                    aspirations of a young and ambitious man to an excessive pitch. We and the
                    Spartans remained, with neither revenues nor armaments nor regiments of infantry
                    to be the bulwark of our safety, yet fortified by a great desire, though our
                    power was small and humble. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>The Spartans had
                    been deprived of their strength by the battle of Leuctra<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n=">Din. 1.73">Din. 1.73</bibl>, note.</note>, and
                    the Eurotas, which had never yet heard an enemy trumpet, saw Boeotians camping
                    in <placeName key="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName>. For the Theban had cut off
                    the bloom of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, enveloping in
                    ashes the flower of her young men, the established boundaries of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName>. Our own resources were spent with war
                    and the hopes of the survivors were oppressed by the fate of the dead.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>The Thebans were suffering the closest
                    restriction in the Macedonian garrison<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">i.e. the
                        garrison established in the Cadmea by Philip after <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.</note> which bound their hands
                    together and had even deprived them of their freedom of speech. Time buried the
                    power of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> with the body of
                    Epaminonidas. The Macedonians had reached their full strength, and in their
                    aspirations Fortune was already leading them across the sea against the throne
                    and treasuries of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/>Then too Demosthenes decided upon war, offering to
                    his compatriots counsel which, though seemingly prudent, was in reality fraught
                    with danger.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">After the accession of Alexander in
                            <date value="-336">336</date> B.C. Demosthenes proposed a decree to
                        honor Philip's murderer, and war was imminent. But in the same year, when
                        Alexander entered <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>,
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> retracted. Demades
                        apparently negotiated the ensuing agreement, but we have no other evidence
                        to confirm the statement made in this passage.</note> When the enemy was
                    encamped near <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and the country
                    was being confined in the town, when the city, worthy to be striven for and
                    marvelled at by all, was being filled like a stable with oxen, sheep and flocks
                    and there was no hope of help from any quarter, I proposed the peace. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/>I admit it and I maintain that it is an honorable and
                    expedient course to have taken. For it is better to shun the cloud as it
                    approaches than to be swept away in the rush of the flood. I ask, Athenians,
                    that the grief occasioned by events shall not engender in you any bitterness
                    against me. For I have no mastery over Fortune; it is Fortune which controls
                    life and gives it its danger. The counsellor, like the doctor, must not take
                    blame for the disease; he must be thanked for the cure. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/>Discount, therefore, what happened from extraneous causes
                    and simply examine my policy naked in the light of facts. To resume then: after
                    this the city was exposed to a third and paramount danger, not this time sent by
                    Fortune but brought on us by the politicians of the day.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">The reference is to the events leading up to the destruction
                        of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> in <date value="-335"
                            >335</date> B.C., after which Demades interceded with Alexander on
                        behalf of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. See <bibl
                            n="Din. 1.10">Din. 1.10</bibl>, note.</note>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>I would ask you to recall their conduct when
                    Demosthenes and Lycurgus, side by side in their speeches, were defeating the
                    Macedonians among the Triballi and almost exhibited the body of Alexander on the
                    platform for us to see; when, in the Assembly, they calmed the Theban exiles,
                    who were present, with specious words and spurred on their minds to conceive a
                    hope of freedom, protesting that I was gloomy and over pessimistic since I did
                    not approve . . . <milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para"
                        ed="P"/>There is bitterness in the voice of truth, when the speaker with
                    simple frankness takes away the expectation of great successes: while pleasant
                    words, though they are false, convince those who hear them. <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The danger was expected to
                    reach <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>In a short time the
                    Macedonian spearheads had already closed on <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
                        >Attica</placeName>, and now that the catastrophe was on our borders and
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> was cowering we had need to
                    soothe and tame the anger of the king, which had been roused against our people.
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It is not
                    the giving of the bribe that distresses us but the action of the man who takes
                    it, if it is directed against our interests. <milestone n="22" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>With these words he raises the firebrand of
                    war and the enemy encamps at the gates. <milestone n="23" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>He decided the war with bloodshed.
                        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>My purpose
                    is not to get gold, as these men falsely allege; it is this. <milestone n="25"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . had suspicion as an
                    ally. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>If only
                    the Thebans had possessed a Demades; for <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName> would then be still a city. Now it is but the site of a
                    city, a remnant of catastrophe, razed to its foundations by enemy hands.
                        <milestone n="27" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It was not
                    honorable to admit enemy blood and Macedonian fire into <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> nor to be silent and endure the sight
                    of the city sinking like a ship. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>But the cowardly politicians, leading out the flower of
                    the city to <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>, led them to a
                    graveyard. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It
                    is with peace, not argument, that we must counter the Macedonian phalanx; for
                    argument lacks power to take effect when urged by men whose strength is less
                    than their desire. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para"
                        ed="P"/>The anger of those who have been wronged is appeased whenever he who
                    is to blame refrains from contentiousness and lets the party wronged judge for
                    himself the kindness he will show. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>They entombed the envoys in a well,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">For the well-known story of the envoys of Darius, whom the
                        Spartans threw into a well and the Athenians into a pit, see <bibl
                            n="Hdt. 7.133">Hdt. 7.133</bibl></note> noble in so far as they stood by
                    their resolution, but impious in the execution of the punishment. <milestone
                        n="32" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/><placeName
                        key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> was worn out with difficulties.
                        <milestone n="33" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"
                    />Demosthenes, bitter sycophant that he is, by the cleverness of his words
                    distorted the fact and showed it in a bad light. <milestone n="34"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>They came to realize clearly
                    the changeability of the politician's life, the uncertainty of the future, the
                    variety of fortune's changes, and the difficulty of gauging the crises that hold
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in their grip. Therefore the
                    law which they intended to direct against others . . . <milestone n="35"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It was not I that advised
                    this course: my country, the occasion, the circumstances themselves, thought fit
                    to use my voice to put the measures into effect. It Is unjust therefore that an
                    adviser should be held accountable for circumstances and for events whose
                    outcome rested with fortune. <milestone n="36" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>Killed by his own hand he departed this life. <milestone
                        n="37" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The daughters of
                        Erechtheus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the story of the daughters
                        of Erechtheus see <bibl n="Lyc. 1.98">Lyc. 98</bibl> and note.</note> by
                    nobility of virtue, triumphed over the woman's weakness in their hearts the
                    frailty of their nature was made virile by devotion to the soil that reared
                    them. <milestone n="38" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Old men
                    shrink from death in the sunset of life. <milestone n="39" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . lit up <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName> with the fire of war. <milestone n="40" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>A word, if rashly uttered, will sharpen the
                    sword of war, and yet, if skilfully chosen, it will blunt the spear even though
                    it is already whetted. There is more speed in management than in force.
                        <milestone n="41" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The
                    barbarian accepted the statement but did not probe its meaning. For his ears
                    interpreted the message to conform with his own pleasure rather than with the
                    truth. But this was no idle speech, for deeds followed hard upon it. <milestone
                        n="42" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Force does not enable
                    a man to master even the smallest things. It was inventiveness and system that
                    made him yoke the ox to the plough for the tilling of the land, bridle the
                    horse, set a rider on the elephant, and cross the boundless sea in boats of
                    wood. The engineer and craftsman of all these things is mind, and we must use it
                    as our guide, not always seeking to follow the subtleties of our own plans but
                    rather the natural changes of events. This was the method by which I tamed
                    Alexander, like some fearful beast, with flattering words and made him tractable
                    for the future. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"
                    />A manly utterance and a frankness worthy of the name Athenian. <milestone
                        n="44" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I hate the popular
                    leaders because they disturb the people and shatter the peace, the fruit of my
                    administration, with a decree in favour of war. <milestone n="45" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Our ancestors left <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and held the sea as a city, and the
                    naval disaster shattered the land army also. <milestone n="46" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Freedom is not on guard against a spy.
                        <milestone n="47" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The changes
                    to which events are subject are treacherous and unceasing. <milestone n="48"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>For it is by a resolution of
                    goodwill that the altar of immortality has been erected.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Apparently a reference to the deification of Alexander in
                            <date value="-324">324</date> B.C.</note>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You will set
                    over them time speaking as a herald. <milestone n="50" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Alexander who framed his hopes to gain
                    world dominion. <milestone n="51" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"
                    />Demosthenes, a little man made up of syllables and a tongue. <milestone n="52"
                        unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>For those words as it were
                    lulled to sleep the king's anger. <milestone n="53" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>For the powers of the city and the pride of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> were still at their height, and fortune
                    favoured the people. But now every element of value in the political world has
                    been ostracized and the cities' hamstrings removed men's lives have inclined to
                    relaxation and luxury, the means of concord are no longer there, and the hopes
                    of our friends have proved vain. <milestone n="54" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>War, like a cloud, was threatening <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> from every quarter, suppressing my
                    right to speak my mind in the assembly and taking away all power of free and
                    noble utterance. <milestone n="55" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"
                    />Examine the truth in the light of events and do not give more weight to false
                    charges than to accepted facts. <milestone n="56" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . by the course of events proclaims the fire of war.
                    This letter of Alexander's broke my purpose.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                        >Perhaps Alexander's letter demanding triremes from <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> &lpar;see <bibl
                            n="Plut. Phoc. 21">Plut. Phoc. 21</bibl>&rpar;.</note> This letter,
                    embracing war in characters of ink, almost seized me by the hand and roused me.
                    It travelled through my thoughts and did not let me rest in peace; for the
                    danger was at our gates. <milestone n="57" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/>My diplomacy and the clamor that greeted it combined to
                    set the city on the watch, saved <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>
                    from being swamped from every side as by a wave and turned the army in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> against the Persians.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">After the fall of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C.</note>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Fear of war,
                    like darkness, does not present the same aspect when it confronts us as when it
                    has been averted. <milestone n="59" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para"
                        ed="P"/>It seems, therefore, the harshest imaginable rule that a man should
                    be held accountable in time of peace for his administration during war. For
                    every critic judges it with reference to the present calm, not to the danger
                    that is over. And yet, if we make no allowance for the crisis, we are removing
                    too the justification for the action. <milestone n="60" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Each offence is dealt with in its own
                    particular way some call for the council of the Areopagus, some for lesser
                    courts, others for the Heliaea. All these are distinguished in name,
                    circumstance, time, penalty, procedure, and in the number of the jury.
                        <milestone n="61" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Those who
                    malign me are making unwarranted accusations. They do not charge me with
                    plotting, for their villainy is bound by no oath. But the jury's judgement is
                    governed by an oath. <milestone n="62" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para"
                        ed="P"/>An unjust trial differs from an unjust punishment only in name.
                        <milestone n="63" unit="section"/><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>They think
                    that they will plunge me below the surface. <milestone n="64" unit="section"
                        /><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It is not right that the saving of a man in
                    danger should provide fuel for the malicious charges of those who have abandoned
                    all principle, nor that an accusation based on stories should be held stronger
                    than a defence grounded on facts. <milestone n="65" unit="section"/><milestone
                        unit="para" ed="P"/><placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> has lost
                    an eye in the destruction of the Thebans' city.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
