<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Airs Waters Places, introduction</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb id="p.66"/>
			<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>INTRODUCTION</head>
				<p>No ancient critic appears to have doubted the
					authenticity of this work, and only Haller among
					the moderns has rejected it.</p>
				<p>It is divided roughly into two parts. The first
					(Chapters I-XI) deals chiefly with the effects of
					climate and situation upon health ; the second
					(XII-XXIV) deals chiefly with the effects of climate
					upon character. At the end of XII a portion has
					been lost dealing with the Egyptians and Libyans.</p>
				<p>The style of the book has the dignified restraint
					which we associate with the Hippocratic group of
					treatises. In tone it is strikingly dogmatic, conclusions
					being enunciated without the evidence upon
					which they are based. Modern physicians are
					sceptical about many of these conclusions while
					fully recognizing the value of the principle that
					geographical conditions and climate influence health.</p>
				<p>The second part of the work is scarcely medical
					at all, but rather ethnographical. It bears a close
					resemblance to certain parts of Herodotus, but lacks
					the graceful <hi rend="ital">bonhomie</hi> which is so characteristic of
					the latter writer. Indeed it is hard not to see a
					close connection between the account of the impotent
					effeminates of Chapter XXII and the <foreign lang="greek">E)NA/REES2</foreign>
					of Herodotus I. 105.</p>
				<pb id="p.67"/>
				<p><hi rend="center">MSS. <hi rend="sc">AND</hi> E<hi rend="sc">DITIONS</hi>.</hi></p>
					<p>T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> chief MSS. are V and R, the latter being
						a fifteenth-century MS. at Rome called <hi rend="ital">Codex
							Barberinus.</hi> To these must be added the readings
						of a MS. called by K&eacute;hlewein b, which is now lost,
						but its readings have been noted by Gadaldinus of
						Venice. There are two Paris MSS. worth noticing.
						One (2255 or E) divides the treatise into two parts,
						and the other (7027) is a Latin translation which
						sometimes helps in the reconstruction of the text.</p>
					<p>The work has often been edited. The earliest
						edition was published at Venice in 1497, and there
						were at least ten others during the sixteenth
						century.<note>See Littr&eacute;, II. 9, 10.</note> The best edition is that of Coray (2 vols.,
						Paris, 1800). Though verbose it is both scholarly
						and medically accurate, Coray being a Greek by
						birth, a medical man by training, and a scholar by
						inclination.</p>
					<p>There are English translations by Peter Low
						(London, 1597), John Moffat (London, 1788), Francis
						Clifton (London, 1734), and, of course, Francis
						Adams (London, 1849).</p>
					<p>The following table, taken from Aetius III. 164,
						may prove useful in determining the periods of the
						year mentioned in the Hippocratic writings.</p>
					<p>March 23 . . <foreign lang="greek">I)S1HMERI/A E)ARINH/</foreign>.</p>
					<p>April 1 . . <foreign lang="greek">AI( PLHIA/DES2 A)KRO/NUXOI FAI/NONTAI</foreign>.</p>
					<p>April 19 . . <foreign lang="greek">AI( PLHIA/DES2 E(S1PE/PIOI KRU/PTONTAI</foreign>.</p>
					<p>April 21 . . <foreign lang="greek">AI( PLHIA/DES2 A)MA H(LI/OU A)NATOLH=|
						E)PITE/LLOUS1I</foreign>.</p>
					<p>May 7 . . . <foreign lang="greek">AI( PLHIA/DES2 E(W=(AI FAI/NONTAI</foreign> (heliacal
						rising).</p>
					<pb id="p.68"/>
					<p>June 6 . . . <foreign lang="greek">A)RKTOU=ROS2 DU/NEI</foreign>.</p>
					<p>June 25 . . <foreign lang="greek">TROPAI\ QERINAI/</foreign>.</p>
					<p>July 19 . . <foreign lang="greek">O( KU/WN EW=(OS2 E)PITE/LLEI</foreign>.</p>
					<p>September 17 <foreign lang="greek">A)RKTOU=ROS2 E)PITE/LLEI</foreign> (heliacal rising).</p>
					<p>September 25 <foreign lang="greek">I)S1HMERI/A FQINOPWRINH/</foreign>.</p>
					<p>November 6 <foreign lang="greek">AI( PLHIA/DES E(W=(AI DU/NOUS1I</foreign> (cosmic
						setting).</p>
					<p>December 23 <foreign lang="greek">TROPAI\ XEIMERINAI/</foreign>.</p>
					<p>February 25 <foreign lang="greek">A)RKTOU=ROS2 E(S1PE/RIOS2 E)PITE/LLEI KAI\</foreign>
						(26) <foreign lang="greek">XELIDO/NES2 PE/TONTAI KAI\ FAI/NONTAI</foreign>.</p>
					<p>Spring began with the equinox, but was often
						popularly dated from the appearance of swallows
						and the acronychal rising of Arcturus in February.
						The heliacal rising of the Pleiades marked the
						beginning of summer, which ended with that of
						Arcturus, an event nearly coinciding with the
						autumnal equinox. Finally, winter began with the
						cosmic setting of the Pleiades.</p>
					<p>A star is said to rise heliacally when it gets far
						enough in front of the sun to be visible before
						dawn. It sets cosmically when it gets so much
						further in advance as to be first seen setting in the
						west before dawn. The acronychal is the evening
						rising of a star, when it is visible all night, and
						contrasts with the heliacal, or morning, rising, when
						it soon disappears in the sun's rays.</p>
					<p>Galen, in his commentary on the third section of
						<hi rend="ital">Aphorisms</hi>, implies that there are two meanings of
						<foreign lang="greek">METABOLAI\ TW=N W(RE/WN</foreign>, a common term in <hi rend="ital">Airs Waters
							Places :</hi></p>
					<p>(1) the actual changes from season to season ;</p>
					<pb id="p.69"/>
					<p>(2) sharp contrasts of weather during the
						seasons.</p>
					<p>It is clear from the passages in <hi rend="ital">Airs Waters Places</hi>
						where the phrase occurs that it may have either
						meaning. The notion underlying it is that of
						violent change in the weather.</p>
					<p>The reader should note the meanings of the
						following :</p>
					<p>(1) "between the winter rising of the sun and
						the winter setting," <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> roughly E.S.E.
						to W.S.W.;</p>
					<p>(2) "between the summer setting and the
						summer rising," <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> roughly W.N.W. to
						E.N.E.;</p>
					<p>(3) "between the summer and winter risings,"
						<hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> roughly E.N.E. to E.S.E.</p>
					<p>The exact number of degrees is a question of
						latitude. The directions given above are roughly
						correct for the Mediterranean area.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>