<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Oath, introduction</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>Introduction</head>
				<p>O<hi rend="sc">F</hi> all the Hippocratic writings the <hi rend="ital">Oath,</hi> in spite
					of its shortness, is perhaps the most interesting to
					the general reader and also to the modern medical
					man. Whatever its origin, it is a landmark in the
					ethics of medicine.</p>
				<p>Yet its exact relationship to the history of
					medicine is unknown, and apparently, in our present
					state of knowledge, unknowable. The student must,
					at every stage of the inquiry, confess his ignorance.
					What is the date of the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> ? Is it mutilated or
					interpolated ? Who took the oath, all practitioners
					or only those belonging to a guild ? What binding
					force had it beyond its moral sanction ? Above all,
					was it ever a reality or merely a " counsel of perfection" ?
					To all these questions the honest inquirer
					can only say that for certain he knows
					nothing.</p>
				<p>Such being the case it is most important to
					realize clearly what actually is known. In the
					first place, the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> was admitted to be genuinely
					Hippocratic by Erotian.</p>
				<p>As to internal evidence, the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi>, besides binding
					all who take it to certain moral rules of practice,
					makes them also promise to act in a certain manner
					towards co-practitioners.</p>
				<p>The taker of the oath--</p>
				<p>(1) Will treat the children of his teacher as
					though they were his brothers ;</p>
				<pb id="p.292"/>
				<p>(2) Will " share his livelihood" with his teacher,
					and, in case of necessity, relieve his financial
					distress ;</p>
				<p>(3) Will teach his teacher's children " without fee
					or indenture" ;</p>
				<p>(4) Will give full instruction to his own children,
					to those of his teacher, to students who have taken
					the oath and signed the indenture, and to no others.</p>
				<p>We cannot be sure what this indenture (<foreign lang="greek">S1UGGRAFH/</foreign>)
					was. The word occurs again in the very first
					sentence, " I will carry out this oath and this indenture."
					One might suppose from these two
					occurrences of <foreign lang="greek">S1UGGRAFH/</foreign> that they both refer to the
					same document, and that the document is what we
					call the <hi rend="ital">Oath.</hi> If this view be taken, our present document
					must be a composite piece, consisting of both
					oath and indenture, and that it is the second component
					that the students paying no fee are excused
					from signing, for nobody would suppose that these
					had not to take the oath to uphold a high moral
					standard.</p>
				<p>It must be confessed that to separate <foreign lang="greek">S1UGGRAFH/</foreign>
					from <foreign lang="greek">O(/RKOS2</foreign> would not be difficult, as the former
					would include merely those articles which concerned
					master and pupil, <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> the latter's promise of financial
					aid to his teacher and of instruction to his teacher's
					children.</p>
				<p>The difficulty in this view is that the vague
					promises <foreign lang="greek">*BI/OU KOINW/S1ES1QAI</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">KAI\ *XREW=N *XRHI+/ZONTI
						META/DOS1IN
						POIH/S1ES1QAI</foreign>, do not read like a legal <foreign lang="greek">S1UGGRAFH/</foreign>, such as
					is implied in the words <foreign lang="greek">A)/NEU MIS1QOU= KAI\ S1UGGRAFH=S2</foreign>.
					They are not definite enough, and there is no
					mention of a specific <foreign lang="greek">MIS1QO/S2</foreign>. Indeed, such clauses</p>
				<pb id="p.293"/>
				<p>could never be enforced ; if they could have been,
					and if a physician had one or two rich pupils, his
					financial position would have been enviable. A
					share in the livelihood of rich men, relief when in
					need of money, free education for children--these
					advantages would make it superfluous, not to say
					unjust, to require any <foreign lang="greek">MIS1QO/S2</foreign> in addition.</p>
				<p>It may well be that the <foreign lang="greek">S1UGGRAFH/</foreign> of <foreign lang="greek">A)/NEU MIS1QOU=
					KAI\ S1UGGRAFH=S2</foreign> was a private agreement between
					teacher and taught, quite distinct from the present
					document, in which case <foreign lang="greek">S1UGGRAFH\N TH/NDE</foreign> will refer
					either to such an agreement appended to the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi>,
					or more probably to the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> itself, which might be
					called a <foreign lang="greek">S1NGGRAFH/</foreign> in the wider and vaguer sense
					of that term, though it is not precise enough for
					the legal indenture.</p>
				<p>Some scholars regard the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> as the test required
					by the Asclepiad Guild. The document, however,
					does not contain a single word which supports this
					contention. It binds the student to his master and
					his master's family, not to a guild or corporation.
					But if the Hippocratic oath ever was a real force
					in the history of medicine, it must have had the
					united support of the most influential physicians.
					Whether this union was that of something approximating
					to a guild we cannot say.</p>
				<p>The <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> contains a sentence which has long
					proved a stumbling-block. It is :--<foreign lang="greek">OU) TEME/W DE\ OU)DE\
						MH\N LIQIW=NTAS2</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">E)KXWRH/S1W DE\ E)RGA/TH|S1IN A)NDRA/S1I PRH/CIOS2
							TH=S1DE</foreign>. If these words are the genuine reading, they
					can only mean that the taker of the oath promises
					not to operate even for stone, but to leave operations
					for such as are craftsmen therein. It has seemed
					an insuperable difficulty that nowhere in the Hippocratic</p>
				<pb id="p.294"/>
				<p>collection is it implied that the physician must
					not operate, nor is any mention made of <foreign lang="greek">E)RGA/TAI
						A)/NDRES2</foreign> who made a profession of operating. On the
					contrary, as Littr&eacute; points out in his introduction
					to the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi>, the Hippocratic writers appear to perform
					operations without fear or scruple. Gomperz,
					in a note to the first volume of <hi rend="ital">Greek Thinkers</hi>,
					suggests that the words hide a reference to castration.
					A glance at Littr&eacute;'s introduction shows that
					the suggestion is by no means new, and a belief in
					its truth underlies Reinhold's unhappy emendation
					to <foreign lang="greek">OU)DE\ MH\ E)N H(LIKI/H| E)O/NTAS2</foreign>. A reference to castration
					would clear away the difficulty that a promise not to
					operate is out of place between two promises to
					abstain from moral offences, for castration was
					always an abomination to a Greek. But to leave
					the abominable thing to the <foreign lang="greek">E)RGA/TAI</foreign> is condoning a
					felony or worse, and, moreover, the qualification is
					quite uncalled for. The whole tone of the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi>
					would require " I will not castrate" without
					qualification.</p>
				<p>One might be tempted to say that the promise
					not to operate was intended to hold only during the
					noviciate of the learner were there anything in the
					text to support this view. But although the oath
					would have been stultified if it had not been taken
					at the beginning of the medical course,<note>Of course an ancient
						physician did not graduate in the
						modern sense of the term. The distinction between a qualified
						practitioner and one unqualified was not a well-defined
						line. A man was an <foreign lang="greek">I)HTRO/S2</foreign> as soon as he had learnt enough
						to be of any use at all.</note> there is
					nothing in the text implying that any of its clauses
					were only temporarily binding. So the historian is</p>
				<pb id="p.295"/>
				<p>forced back upon the view that the clause, even if
					not strictly speaking an interpolation, applied only
					to a section of the medical world, or only to a
					particular period, when it was considered degrading
					to a master physician to operate with his own
					hands, and the correct course was to leave the use
					of the knife to inferior assistants acting under
					instruction.</p>
				<p>Knowing as little as we do, it is perhaps permissible
					to use the constructive imagination to frame
					an hypothesis which in broad outline at least is not
					inconsistent with the <hi rend="ital">data</hi> before us.</p>
				<p>From the <hi rend="ital">Protagoras</hi> we learn that Hippocrates
					himself was ready to train physicians for a fee, and
					there is no reason to suppose that the practice was
					unusual. Some sort of bond between teacher and
					taught would naturally be drawn up, and a set form
					of words would evolve itself embodying those clauses
					which had as their object the maintenance of medical
					probity and honour. These might well contain
					promises to the teacher couched in extravagant
					language if taken literally, but which were intended
					to be interpreted in the spirit rather than in the
					letter.<note>Compare modern interpretations of marriage vows.</note> Such
					may have been the nucleus of the
					Hippocratic <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi>, and a copy would not unnaturally
					be found in the library of the medical school at Cos.
					But there is nothing in the evidence to lead us to
					suppose that a stereotyped form was universal, or
					that clauses were not added or taken away at various
					places and at various times. One writer in the
					<hi rend="ital">Corpus</hi>, the author of the work <hi rend="ital">Nature of the Child</hi>,
					unblushingly violates the spirit, if not the letter, of
					the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> by attempting to produce abortion in a</p>
				<pb id="p.296"/>
				<p>singular and disgusting manner.<note>13, Littr&eacute;, vii. 490.</note> So
					some physicians
					did not feel bound by all the clauses, and
					some may not have felt bound by any. We may
					suppose, however, that no respectable physician
					would act contrary to most of the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi>, even if he
					were ignorant of its existence. The clause forbidding
					operative surgery may be an addition of late
					but uncertain date.<note>It is possible that the degradation of surgery
						did not
						take place until Christian times (see Galen x. 454, 455),
						and the sentence of the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> may well be very late indeed.
						The <foreign lang="greek">MH\N</foreign> in <foreign lang="greek">OU)O(/E\ MH\N LIQIW=NTAS2</foreign> will strike scholars as
						strange.</note></p>
				<p>But the interest of the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> does not lie in its
					baffling problems. These may never be solved, but
					the little document is nevertheless a priceless possession.
					Here we have committed to writing those
					noble rules, loyal obedience to which has raised the
					calling of a physician to be the highest of all the
					professions. The writer, like other Hippocratics,
					uses to describe the profession a word which, in
					Greek philosophy, and especially in Plato, has a
					rather derogatory meaning. Medicine is " my art"
					(<foreign lang="greek">TE/XNH</foreign>) in the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> ; elsewhere, with glorious arrogance,
					it is " the art." " The art is long ; life is
					short," says the first <hi rend="ital">Aphorism.</hi> Many years later,
					the writer of <hi rend="ital">Precepts</hi> declared that " where the love
					of man is, there is the love of the art." That
					medicine is an art (the thesis of <hi rend="ital">The Art</hi>), a difficult
					art, and one inseparable from the highest
					morality and the love of humanity, is the great
					lesson to us of the Hippocratic writings. The true
					physician is <hi rend="ital">vir bonus sanandi peritus.</hi></p>
				<p>The chief MSS. containing the <hi rend="ital">Oath</hi> are V and M.</p>
				<pb id="p.297"/>
				<p>The chief editions are--</p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Serment d'Hippocrate pr&eacute;c&eacute;d&eacute; d'une notice sur les
					serments en m&eacute;decine.</hi> J. R. Duval. Paris, 1818.</p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Hippocrate : Le Serment</hi>, etc. Ch. V. Daremberg.
					Paris, 1843.</p>
				<p>See also--</p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Super locum Hippocratis in Iureiurando maxime
				vexatum meditationes.</hi> Fr. Boerner, Lips. 1751.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>