<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Nutriment, introduction</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>INTRODUCTION</head>
				<p>T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> treatise <hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> is unique. It deals with
					an interesting subject in an unusual manner, and, in
					spite of the limitations of Greek physiology, many
					valuable and interesting views are set forth.</p>
				<p>Heraclitus held that matter is, like a stream, in a
					state of continuous change. His system contained
					other hypotheses,<note>Some perhaps (<hi rend="ital">e. g.</hi> the union of opposites)
						being more
						fundamental.</note> but this was the most fruitful,
					and the one which commended itself most to his
					followers and to his successors.</p>
				<p>A later Heraclitean, whether a professional doctor
					or not is uncertain, applied the theory of perpetual
					change to the assimilation of food by a living
					organism, and <hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> is the result. He has
					copied the aphoristic<note>It is interesting to note that the aphoristic
						style, which
						is a great aid to memory, came into vogue at a time when
						text-books first became necessary. It has its modern analogue
						in the "crammer's" analysis.</note> style and manner of his
					master, as well as the obscurity, with considerable
					success, and whole paragraphs might well be genuine
					fragments of Heraclitus.</p>
				<p>The author's idea of digestion is far from easy to
					follow.</p>
				<p>Apparently nutritive food is supposed to be dissolved
					in moisture, and thus to be carried to every part
					of the body, assimilating itself to bone, flesh, and so</p>
				<pb id="p.338"/>
				<p>on, as it comes into contact with them. Air (breath)
					also is regarded as food, passing through the arteries
					from the heart, while the blood passes through the
					veins from the liver. But the function of blood is
					not understood ; blood is, like milk, "what is left
					over" (<foreign lang="greek">PLEONAS1MO/S2</foreign>) when nourishment has taken
					place. Neither is the function of the heart understood,
					and its relation to the lungs is never
					mentioned.</p>
				<p>The aspect of nutrition which appeals most to the
					writer is the combination of unity and multiplicity
					which it exhibits. Food is one ; yet it has the
					power of becoming many things. Similarly the
					animal organism is one, with many parts vitally
					connected with the whole, so that they act in
					complete sympathy with it and with one another.</p>
				<p>Food, says the writer, has "power" (<foreign lang="greek">DU/NAMIS2</foreign>), and
					so has the body. This "power" seems to be the sum
					total of its properties, although these are not yet
					regarded as abstractions. It is one and many ; one
					in its essence, many in its manifestations. But
					"power" in its various forms is manifested only in
					relationship to other things ; it is not independent,
					being latent until called into action by a suitable
					environment. In modern language, the author feels
					that qualities are relations. Wine is good (or bad)
					in certain circumstances ; so is milk and all other
					foods. All things are good or bad <foreign lang="greek">PRO/S2 TI</foreign> (Chapters
					XIX and XLIV).</p>
				<p>This theory of <foreign lang="greek">DU/NAMIS2</foreign> with its insistence upon
					relativity helps in assigning a date to the document.
					A similar account of <foreign lang="greek">DU/NAMIS2</foreign> is given in <hi rend="ital">Ancient
						Medicine</hi>, the date of which is approximately 420 <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi>
					The theory of relativity, implied in the doctrine of</p>
				<pb id="p.339"/>
				<p>Heraclitus, was fully developed in one direction by
					Protagoras, who regarded knowledge as conditioned
					by (<hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> relative to) the percipient being. In
					<hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> relativity is made to apply, not merely to
					the knowledge of properties, but to the properties
					themselves. Such an extension of the doctrine
					would probably be made somewhat later than the
					time of Protagoras, and we may with some confidence
					suppose that the author wrote about 400 <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi></p>
				<p>The first chapter of <hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> distinguishes <foreign lang="greek">GE/NOS2</foreign>
					from <foreign lang="greek">EI)=DOS2</foreign> after the Aristotelian manner. A similar
					distinction occurs in the <hi rend="ital">Parmenides</hi> of Plato, and it
					need not prevent us from assigning a date as early as
					the end of the fifth century <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi></p>
				<p>In Chapter XLVIII mention is made of pulses,
					supposed to be the first occasion of such mention in
					Greek literature.<note>See Sir Clifford Allbutt, <hi rend="ital">Greek Medicine in
						Rome</hi>, Chapter
						XIII, for the ancient doctrines about pulses. It is most
						remarkable that before about 340 <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi> their great importance
						was not realised.</note> This fact, again, is no argument
					against an early date. The reference is quite
					general, and amounts to no more than the knowledge,
					to be found in several places in the Hippocratic
					<hi rend="ital">Corpus</hi>,<note>See Littr&eacute;'s index, <hi rend="ital">s.v. battements.</hi></note> that
					violent pulsations (of the
					temples and so forth) are characteristic of certain
					acute diseases.</p>
				<p>It should be noticed that the doctrine of <foreign lang="greek">DU/NAMIS2</foreign>
					described above is inconsistent with a post-Aristotelian
					date. Aristotle's doctrine is obviously a
					development of it, and it is clear how the earlier
					doctrine prepares the way for the later.</p>
				<p>The Heraclitean love of anthithesis results in</p>
				<pb id="p.340"/>
				<p>many purely verbal contrasts, which render more
					obscure the natural obscurities of this little tract.
					Indeed the reader is often forced to the conclusion
					that the writer wished so to express himself that
					more than one interpretation might legitimately be
					put upon his words. In my paraphrase I have tried
					to give the most obvious meaning, although I have
					often felt that other meanings are almost equally
					possible.<note>I wish to point out that Chapters I, III, V and VI are
						up to the present unsolved mysteries. Incidentally, I should
						like to mention that Chapter I shows that the history of the
						word <foreign lang="greek">EI)=DOS2</foreign> is not so simple as Professor A. E. Taylor makes
						out in <hi rend="ital">Varia Socratica.</hi></note></p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> is more important as a philosophical
					than as a medical document. The teaching of
					Heraclitus did not die out with his death ; he had
					followers who emended and developed his theories,
					and one of these wrote <hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> to bring a branch
					of physiology into the domain of philosophy. The
					tract is a striking proof of the difficulty of uniting
					philosophy and science, and of pursuing the latter
					on the methods of the former. Incidentally one may
					notice that it belongs to the period of eclecticism
					and reaction which followed the development of
					atomism.<note>See Burnet, <hi rend="ital">Early Greek Philosophy</hi>, Chapter
						X.</note></p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> was accepted as a genuine work of
					Hippocrates by Erotian, and a mutilated commentary
					on it passes under the name of Galen. Aulus
					Gellius (III. xvi), quotes it as a work of Hippocrates.
					There was another tradition in antiquity, referred to
					in two Paris MSS., that <hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> was the work of
					Thessalus or of Herophilus. It is easy to understand
					how some found a difficulty in ascribing to the</p>
				<pb id="p.341"/>
				<p>author of <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> such a dissimilar book ; indeed
					it is likely that the chief reason for assigning it to
					Hippocrates was its superficial likeness to <hi rend="ital">Aphorisms.</hi></p>
				<p><hi rend="center">MSS. <hi rend="sc">AND</hi> E<hi rend="sc">DITIONS</hi>.</hi></p>
				<p>The chief MSS. are A and M. <hi rend="ital">Nutriment</hi> was
					edited several times in the sixteenth century, and
					interesting remarks on it are to be found in the
					following :</p>
				<p>J. Bernays, <hi rend="ital">Heraklitische Briefe.</hi></p>
				<p>A. Patin, <hi rend="ital">Quellenstudien zu Heraklit.</hi></p>
				<p>See also Mewaldt in <hi rend="ital">Hermes,</hi> xliv. 121, and,
					for Heracliteanism in the <hi rend="ital">Corpus,</hi> C. Fredrich,
					<hi rend="ital">Hippokratische Untersuchungen.</hi></p>
				<pb id="p.343"/>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>