<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Precepts, introduction</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>INTRODUCTION</head>
				<p>I<hi rend="sc">T</hi> is with considerable misgiving that I have
					included this work as a kind of appendix to the first
					volume of the Hippocratic collection. In the first
					place there is not yet available the material necessary
					for a really satisfactory restoration of the text.
					Furthermore, the editors have generally neglected
					it. Littr&eacute; reserved it for his ninth and last volume
					of text and translation, and by the time he reached
					it even his untiring energy was beginning to flag ;
					his edition is hasty, erratic and in places unintelligible.
					Ermerins gives over the task in despair, and
					leaves whole chapters untranslated.</p>
				<p>In spite of all these things I have determined to
					include <hi rend="ital">Precepts,</hi> because it illustrates so well the
					characteristics of many parts of the Hippocratic
					collection, and the problems that face both editors
					and translators. It forms also a complete contrast
					to the nucleus of Hippocratic writings composing
					the rest of the first volume.</p>
				<p>(1) Like <hi rend="ital">Humours</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Nutriment,</hi> it is obscure to a
					degree.</p>
				<p>(2) It is, like so many Hippocratic works, a <hi rend="ital">cento.</hi>
					Beginning and end are quite unconnected with
					the main portion of the book, and the main
					portion itself is a series of rather disconnected
					remarks.</p>
				<pb id="p.306"/>
				<p>(3) It has, like <hi rend="ital">Ancient Medicine, Nutriment, Nature
					of Man, Airs, Regimen I.,</hi> a close relationship
					to philosophy.</p>
				<p>(4) It shows, I think conclusively, the wide period
					covered by the Hippocratic collection.</p>
				<p>No reader can fail to notice that, short as it is, the
					work is a <hi rend="ital">cento</hi> with three main divisions.</p>
				<p>(1) Chapters I and II defend the principle that
					medicine must be based upon observed fact
					and not on any plausible but fallacious hypothesis
					(<foreign lang="greek">E)K PIQANH=S2 A)NAPLA/S1IOS2 LO/GOU</foreign>). The writer
					uses language remarkably similar to that
					attributed to Epicurus by Diogenes Laertius.
					I must quote two passages from the latter.</p>
				<p>(<hi rend="ital">a</hi>) <foreign lang="greek">KAI\ GA\R KAI\ E)PI/NOIAI PA=S1AI A)PO\ TW=N AI)S1QH/S1EWN
					GEGO/NAS1I KATA/ TE PERI/PTWS1IN KAI\ A)NALOGI/AN KAI\
					O(MOIO/THTA KAI\ S1N/NQES1IN</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">S1UMBALLOME/NOU TI KAI\ TOU=
						LOGIS1MOU=</foreign>. . . . <foreign lang="greek">TH\N DE\ PRO/LHYIN LE/GOUS1IN OI(ONEI\
							KATA/LHYIN</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">H)\ DO/CAN O)RQH/N</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">H)\ E)/NNOIAN</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">H)\
								KAQOLIKH\N
								NO/HS1IN E)NAPOKEIME/NHN</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">TOU=T' E)S1TI MNH/MHN TOU= POLLA/KIS2
									E)/CWQEN FANE/NTOS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p>D. L., X. 20, 21, 32, 33.</p>
				<p>(<hi rend="ital">b</hi>) <foreign lang="greek">A)LLA\ MH\N U(POLHPTE/ON KAI\ TH\N TW=N A)NQRW/PWN
					FU/S1IN POLLA\ KAI\ PANTOI=A U(PO\ TW=N AU)TH\N PERIES1TW/TWN
					PRAGMA/TWN DIDAXQH=NAI/ TE KAI\ A)NAGKAS1QH=NAI: TO\N
					DE\ LOGIS1MO\N TA\ U(PO\ TAU/THS2 PAREGGUHQE/NTA KAI\
					U)/S1TERON E)PAKRIBOU=N</foreign>.</p>
				<p>D. L., X. 24, 75.</p>
				<p>There are also several occurrences of the Epicurean
					word <foreign lang="greek">E)NARGH/S2</foreign>. The similarities are far too close to
					be accidental.</p>
				<pb id="p.307"/>
				<p>(2) Chapters III-XIII contain remarks on medical
					etiquette, fees, patients' whims, quacks, consultants,
					lecturing to large audiences, late
					learners. These remarks are sometimes connected,
					but follow no plan.</p>
				<p>(3) Chapter XIV contains a few disconnected remarks
					on illnesses and invalids.</p>
				<p>So the work as a whole shows no signs of a prearranged
					plan. It is disjointed and formless. As
					far as subject-matter is concerned, the three parts
					distinguished above ought to be classed under
					separate branches of medicine :--</p>
				<p>(1) This belongs to the theory of medicine, or
					rather to the theory of science generally.</p>
				<p>(2) This belongs on the whole to etiquette
					(<foreign lang="greek">EU)S1XHMOS1U/NH</foreign>).</p>
				<p>(3) This consists merely of a few disconnected
					hints. Littr&eacute; justly says of it (IX. 248): " J'y
					vois done une de ces intercalations que les
					copistes se permettaient quelquefois &eacute; la fin
					d'un trait&eacute;, soit, comme dit Galien, pour grossir
					le volume, soit pour placer quelque fragment
					qu'on ne savait ou mettre, et qui, autrement,
					s'en allait perdu."</p>
				<p>Yet it is remarkable that there is a certain style
					common to all three parts which points to the conclusion
					that the compiler, whoever he was, was no
					mere " paste-and-scissors " man, but an author who
					stamped his characteristics even on his borrowings.
					This style is marked by a studied aphoristic brevity
					combined with a genius for choosing out-of-the-way
					terms and expressions. It so happens that in addition
					the author appears to have been an imperfect</p>
				<pb id="p.308"/>
				<p>Greek scholar. It is indeed hard to believe that he
					was writing his mother tongue.</p>
				<p>I am ready to admit that a more perfect recension
					of the MSS. will prove that certain of these vagaries
					are merely errors of the copyists, but when considered
					together they are too numerous and too
					strange to be explained in this way. A few examples
					only shall be chosen.</p>
				<p>Chapter I. <foreign lang="greek">H)\N TA\ E)PI/XEIRA E)KOMI/ZONTO</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" II. <foreign lang="greek">MH\ EI)/H E)PAU/RAS1QAI</foreign>, " perhaps it is impossible
					to gain " (see <hi rend="ital">Oath,</hi> p. 300,
					1. 33).</p>
				<p>" IV. <foreign lang="greek">PARAINE/S1IOS2 D' A)\N KAI\ TOU=TO E)PIDEHQEI/H TH=S2
					QEWRI/HS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">NOU/S1OU GA\R TAXUTH\S2 KAIRO\N MH\ DIDOU=S1A
					K.T.L.</foreign></p>
				<p>" VI. <foreign lang="greek">H)\N DE\ KAIRO\S2 EI)/H</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">H)S1QHME/NOI TO\ PA/QOS2 MH\ E)O\N E)N A)S1FALEI/H</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" VII. <foreign lang="greek">MH\ E)GKEXEIRIKO/TES2</foreign>, " because they have
					not entrusted."</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">DEO/MENOI TH\N U(GIEINH\N DIA/QES1IN</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" VIII. <foreign lang="greek">E)PINE/MHS1IN KE/XRHNTAI</foreign> [an emendation
					of Coray].</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">O)\ A)\N E)RE/W</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" IX. <foreign lang="greek">S1U\N TH= OU)S1I/H</foreign> == <foreign lang="greek">TH=S2 OU)S1I/HS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">OU) DIAMARTH/S1EI</foreign> (3rd person singular).</p>
				<p>" XIII. <foreign lang="greek">O(/POI A)\N KAI\ E)PIS1TATH/S1AIMI</foreign>.</p>
				<p>Notice in particular that <foreign lang="greek">MH/</foreign> is ousting <foreign lang="greek">OU)</foreign>. This is a
					sure sign of late date.</p>
				<p>Words and expressions that occur only in late
					Greek, or are used in a strange sense, are fairly
					common, and there appear to be a few <foreign lang="greek">A(/PAC LEGO/MENA</foreign>.</p>
				<pb id="p.309"/>
				<p>Chapter I. <foreign lang="greek">KATAFORH/</foreign> == deducing.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">PROPAQH/S2</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" II. <foreign lang="greek">PERI\ TAU=TA GI/GNES1QAI</foreign> == to be occupied
					with.</p>
				<p>" IV. <foreign lang="greek">PROMU/S1S1EIN</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" V. <foreign lang="greek">H)DELFIS1ME/NOS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" VI. <foreign lang="greek">EU)DOKI/H</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" VII. <foreign lang="greek">E)K PODO/S2</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">KATAXLIDA=N</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">DIANTLI/ZES1QAI</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" VIII. <foreign lang="greek">KATAS1ILLAI/NW</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" IX. <foreign lang="greek">MINU/QHMA</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" X. <foreign lang="greek">EU)XARI/H</foreign> (if this reading be correct),
					or <foreign lang="greek">EU)XARIS1TI/H</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" XII. <foreign lang="greek">I(S1TORIEUME/NHN</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">MATAIOKOPI/H</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" XIII. <foreign lang="greek">FILALUS1TH/S2</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">DIAZHLEU/OMAI</foreign>.</p>
				<p>" XIV. <foreign lang="greek">S1UMPA/QHS1IS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">S1UMPA/QEIA</foreign>.</p>
				<p><foreign lang="greek">U(POPARAI/THS1IS2</foreign> (if this reading be
					correct).</p>
				<p>The aphoristic style, which appears to have been
					popular among medical writers (<hi rend="ital">Coan Prenotions,
						Prorrhctic I., Aphorisms, Nutriment</hi>) tended to become
					oracular and obscure. The writer of <hi rend="ital">Precepts</hi> seems
					to have gone out of his way to wrap up his meaning
					in unusual diction, which is often almost unintelligible.
					He is fond of allusive, metaphorical language,
					which savours sometimes of the lyric poets.</p>
				<p>In spite of his weaknesses as an author, and they
					are many, he is a man of sound common sense. I
					would note in particular his insisting upon reasoning</p>
				<pb id="p.310"/>
				<p>from accurately observed facts only, and upon the
					necessity of not worrying the patient about fees,
					and his pungent criticisms of quacks, their dupes,
					and all " late-learners."</p>
				<p>There is something about the style which is
					reminiscent of Latin, particularly <foreign lang="greek">PARAINE/S1IOS2 TOU=TO</foreign>
					in Chapter IV, meaning " this piece of advice," and
					perhaps the future in Chapter V with imperatival
					sense.<note>Since I wrote the above my attention has been called to
						<foreign lang="greek">S1TENW=N E)/NDOS1IN</foreign> in Chapter VII. The word <foreign lang="greek">S1TENW=N</foreign> looks
						like
						<hi rend="ital">angustiarum.</hi></note> The perfect tense too is commonly used for
					the aorist. One would be tempted to regard the
					author as a Roman who wrote in Greek an essay,
					compiled from Epicurean literature and fairly sound
					medical sources, were it not for two scholia, one
					discovered by Daremberg and the other in the MS.
					Vaticanus gr. 277. The latter quotes a great part
					of Erotian's explanation of <foreign lang="greek">FLEDONW/DEA</foreign> as a comment
					upon <hi rend="ital">Precepts</hi> VII.,where our MSS. now have <foreign lang="greek">FQOGGW/DEA</foreign>
					or <foreign lang="greek">FQEGGW/DEA</foreign>. In other words, the treatise appears
					to have been known to Erotian, or to the authorities
					used by Erotian, as an Hippocratic work. Daremberg<note>See <hi rend="ital">Notices et
						extraits des manuscrits m&eacute;dicaux grecs, latins
						et fran&eacute;ais des principales biblioth&eacute;ques de l'Europe,</hi> pp.
						200-203.</note>
					discovered in a Vatican MS. a gloss from
					which it appears that Galen commented on <hi rend="ital">Precepts,</hi>
					and that Archigenes (a physician of the early second
					century <hi rend="sc">A.D.</hi>) and Chrysippus the Stoic commented
					on the distinction between <foreign lang="greek">KAIRO/S2</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">XRO/NOS2</foreign> with
					which <hi rend="ital">Precepts</hi> opens.</p>
				<p>Even if we allow full weight to this evidence of</p>
				<pb id="p.311"/>
				<p>early authorship, we need conclude no more than
					that Chrysippus knew the originals from which the
					compilation was made--indeed he must have been
					well acquainted with the Epicurean original of
					Chapters I and II. There is nothing in the evidence
					to prevent our taking <hi rend="ital">Precepts</hi> to be a <hi rend="ital">cento</hi> from
					good sources made by a late writer not perfectly
					familiar with Greek. Somehow it became incorporated
					in a collection of Hippocratic writings,
					probably a little-known one, as none of the ancient
					" lists " of Hippocratic works includes <hi rend="ital">Precepts.</hi>
					There was no generally accepted canon, and a work
					of unknown or uncertain authorship might easily
					find its way into the Hippocratic collection in one
					or other of the great libraries.</p>
				<p>Although linguistic difficulties obscure the details,
					the reader will be interested in the picture of medical
					practice in antiquity. The " late-learner " covering
					up his mistakes in a flood of medical jargon will
					suggest the doctors of Moli&eacute;re. The public lectures,
					with quotations from poetry, are the exact counterpart
					of modern advertisements of patent medicines.</p>
				<p><hi rend="center">MSS. <hi rend="sc">AND</hi> E<hi rend="sc">DITIONS</hi>.</hi></p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Precepts</hi> is found in several of the Paris manuscripts
					and in M.<note>There is no good <hi rend="ital">apparatus criticus.</hi> I have tried
						to
						infer from Littr&eacute;'s " vulgate " and Ermerins' text what is
						the reading of the majority of the manuscripts, and it is
						generally this reading which I denote by " MSS." Only
						more careful examination of the actual manuscripts can
						show how far I am justified in so doing.</note> There have been so far as I
					know
					no separate editions and no translations into English.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>