<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Ancient Medicine, introduction</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>INTRODUCTION</head>
				<p>A<hi rend="sc">MONG</hi> ancient writers Erotian is the only one
					who expressly ascribes this little treatise to Hippocrates
					himself. Modern critics generally regard it as
					old, but as not by Hippocrates, the chief exception
					being Littr&eacute;. Adams is uncertain, but is inclined to
					think that Hippocrates was not the author.</p>
				<p>Thus the external evidence in support of the view
					that Hippocrates was the author of this treatise is very
					slight indeed. The internal evidence is considerably
					stronger.</p>
				<p>(1) The writer, like Hippocrates,<note>By "Hippocrates" is meant the
					writer of <hi rend="ital">Prognostic</hi>,
					of <hi rend="ital">Regimen in Acute Diseases</hi>, and of <hi rend="ital">Epidemics, I., III.</hi></note>
					holds that
					health is caused by a "coction" of the "humours."</p>
				<p>(2) He recognises the importance of "critical"
					days in an illness.</p>
				<p>(3) He holds that medical science is founded on
					observation and reasoning, not on speculation.</p>
				<p>(4) He attaches great importance to the use of
					"slops" of various degrees of consistency.</p>
				<p>All these doctrines are in conformity with the
					views expounded in the works assigned to Hippocrates.
					On the other hand, no stress is laid upon
					prognosis, which Hippocrates considered of primary
					importance. Again, it would be impossible to show
					from the works of Hippocrates that the father of</p>
				<pb id="p.4"/>
				<p>medicine thought little of the power of heat and
					cold in producing health or disease ; our author,
					however, rates them very low. Moreover, like the
					Pythagorean physician Alcmaeon, he holds that
					there is an indefinite number of "opposites," the
					harmony or <hi rend="ital">crasis</hi> of which produces health. The
					historical Hippocrates is said to have reduced the
					number of the humours to four, although I can find
					no trace of this limitation to four in any treatise
					earlier than the one on the <hi rend="ital">Nature of Man</hi>, which
					is not generally considered authentic.</p>
				<p>It may be said that, were the external evidence
					stronger, the treatise would be accepted as an
					authentic work of Hippocrates.</p>
				<p>Littr&eacute;<note>i. pp. 294-310. Gomperz is inclined to support this
					view.</note> argues that the well-known passage in the
					<hi rend="ital">Phaedrus</hi>,<note>270, C. D. Littr&eacute;'s discussion of the sentence
						<foreign lang="greek">TO\ TOI/NUN
							PERI\ FU/S1EWS2 S1KO/PEI TI/ POTE LE/GEi *(IPPOKRA/THS2 TE KAI\ O(
							O)RQO\S2
							LO/GOS2</foreign>, to show that it does not refer to any actual words of
						Hippocrates, is, of course, quite beside the mark. The
						sentence means "what H. and right reason mean by <foreign lang="greek">PERI\
							*FU/S1EWS2</foreign>."</note> where "Hippocrates the Asclepiad" is
					mentioned as holding a theory that a knowledge
					of the human body is impossible without a knowledge
					of the universe--interpreted to mean an examination
					of the <foreign lang="greek">DU/NAMIS2</foreign> (or <foreign lang="greek">DUNA/MEIS2</foreign>) of a body
					according to its inter-relations with other things--refers
					to Chapter XX of the <foreign lang="greek">PERI\ A)RXAI/HS2 I)HTRIKH=S2</foreign>,
					and not, as Galen maintains, to the treatise <hi rend="ital">On the
						Nature of Man.</hi> Littr&eacute;<note>pp. 314, 315.</note> also points out that a
					passage
					in our treatise<note>Chapter X.</note> is very similar to one in <hi rend="ital">Regimen
						in
						Acute Diseases</hi>, the authenticity of which is undoubted.</p>
				<pb id="p.5"/>
				<p>Littr&eacute; may have shown that there is a resemblance
					to our author in the <hi rend="ital">Phaedrus</hi> passage. Resemblances,
					however, show merely that the writer was
					Hippocratic, not that he was Hippocrates.</p>
				<p>The reference, in Chapter XV, to participation
					(<foreign lang="greek">KOINNWEI=I</foreign>) in <foreign lang="greek">EI)/DH</foreign> and to "absolute existences" (<foreign lang="greek">AU)TO/
						TI E)*F' E(WUTOU=</foreign>) might lead a critic to infer that the
					writer lived in the age of Plato. But there are two
					insuperable difficulties to this hypothesis. One is
					that in Chapter XX the word <foreign lang="greek">S1O*FIS1TH/S2</foreign> is used in its
					early sense of "philosopher," which implies that
					the writer lived before Plato attached to the word
					the dishonourable meaning it has in later Greek.
					The other is that the writer attacks the intrusion of
					philosophic speculation into the science of medicine,
					and the speculation he has constantly in mind, as
					being, apparently, the most influential in his day, is
					that of Empedocles,<note>Or possibly that of the Milesian school with its
						doctrine of
						opposites, of which opposites the Empedoclean "roots" are
						four, definitely corporealised.</note> who is actually mentioned in
					Chapter XX as a typical writer <foreign lang="greek">PERI\ *FU/S1EWS2</foreign>. There is
					a sentence in Chapter XIV which closely resembles,
					in both thought and diction, the fragments of Anaxagoras.<note><foreign lang="greek">O/(TAN
						DE/ TI TOU/TWN A)POKRIQH= KAI\ AU)TO\ E)*F) E(WUTOU= GE/NHTAI</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">TO/TE
							KAI\ *FANERO/N E)S1TI KAI\ LUPEI= TO\N A)/NQRWPON</foreign>.</note>
					It certainly looks as though the writer of
					<hi rend="ital">Ancient Medicine</hi> was not unfamiliar with the works
					of this philosopher. All this evidence tends to fix
					the date as approximately 430-420 <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi>, and to
					suggest as the writer either Hippocrates or a very
					capable supporter of the medical school of which
					Hippocrates was a contemporary member.</p>
				<p>The author of <hi rend="ital">Ancient Medicine</hi> in Chapter II asserts</p>
				<pb id="p.6"/>
				<p>that empiric medicine was in his day an old art, and
					that the attempt to foist the method of philosophy
					upon it was comparatively modern. He is obviously
					correct. Hippocratic science must have been the
					ripe fruit of a long period of active inquiry ;
					philosophy began early in the sixth century <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi>,
					and it was late in that century that medicine
					and philosophy were combined in the persons of
					prominent Pythagoreans.<note>See Burnet, <hi rend="ital">Early Greek Philosophy</hi>,
						pp. 223-226 for
						Alcmaeon, and pp. 339-341 for the later Pythagoreans.</note> It was only
					natural that,
					as the main interest of philosophy shifted from
					cosmology to biology, philosophy should occupy
					itself with medical problems. The union was closest
					in Empedocles, thinker, seer, and "medicine-man,"
					but by the end of the fifth century philosophy
					had discarded medicine, although to its great loss
					medicine did not discard philosophy.<note>See especially Burnet, <hi rend="ital">op.
						cit.</hi> pp. 234-235.</note></p>
				<p>Several recent critics, notably Professor A. E.
					Taylor,<note><hi rend="ital">Varia Socratica</hi>, pp. 74-78 and 214-218.</note> have
					pointed out the importance of this
					little work in the history of thought. It has even
					been urged that it proves that the technical phrases,
					and perhaps the doctrine also, of the theory of
					Ideas, usually ascribed to Plato, were well-known
					to educated men a generation at least before Plato.
					The language used in Chapter XV is, indeed,
					strikingly like the terminology of Plato, far too
					much so to be a mere coincidence.</p>
				<p>However this may be, it is plain that in the fifth
					century <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi> there were thinkers, holding principles
					nearly akin to those of modern science, who were
					violently opposed to the application of philosophic</p>
				<pb id="p.7"/>
				<p>procedure to science. This procedure the writer
					calls the method of <foreign lang="greek">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign>. The student of Plato
					is at once reminded of the <hi rend="ital">Phaedo, Republic</hi>, and
					<hi rend="ital">Sophist</hi>, in which dialogues a theory of knowledge
					is expounded which is stated to be the best possible
					method of inquiry until the Ideas have been apprehended.
					It should be noticed that a <foreign lang="greek">U(PO/QES1IS2</foreign> is
					something very different from a modern scientific
					hypothesis. The latter is a summary of observed
					phenomena, intended to explain them by pointing
					out their causal relationship. The former is not a
					summary of phenomena ; it is a postulate, intended
					to be accepted, not as an explanation, but as a foundation
					(<foreign lang="greek">U(PO-TI/QHMI</foreign>) upon which to build a superstructure.
					An hypothesis must by tested by further
					appeals to sense-experience ; a <foreign lang="greek">U(PO/QES1IS2</foreign> must not be
					so tested, it must be taken for granted as an obvious
					truth. Plato would have nothing to do with appeals
					to sense-experience. According to him, if a <foreign lang="greek">U(PO/QES1IS2</foreign>
					is not accepted, it must be abandoned, and a more
					general <foreign lang="greek">U(PO/QES1IS2</foreign> postulated, until one is reached to
					which the opponent agrees.<note><hi rend="ital">Phaedo</hi>, 101 D, E.</note> The writer
					of <hi rend="ital">Ancient
						Medicine</hi> suggests,<note>Chapter I. The language of the author is more
							than a
							little sarcastic.</note> as the proper sphere of <foreign lang="greek">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign>,
					the celestial regions and those beneath the earth.
					Here, among <foreign lang="greek">TA\ A)*FANE/A TE KAI\ A)POREO/MENA</foreign>, where we
					have no means of applying a satisfactory test, where
					in fact sense-perception fails us, is the proper place
					for <foreign lang="greek">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign>. He would exclude them all from
					medicine, but he is constantly suggesting what we
					moderns call "hypotheses." The best examples of
					<foreign lang="greek">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign> are the axioms and postulates of geometry.</p>
				<pb id="p.8"/>
				<p>These are not tested or proved ; they are assumed,
					and upon the assumptions a whole science is built.</p>
				<p>In place of <foreign lang="greek">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign> the author of <hi rend="ital">Ancient Medicine</hi>
					relies, as a modern scientific thinker relies, on careful
					observation and critical examination<note><foreign lang="greek">LOGIS1MW=|</foreign>, Chapter
						XII.</note> of phenomena,
					hoping thereby to reach, not the complete and perfect
					knowledge Plato hoped to attain through his
					Ideas, but an approximation to truth.<note><foreign lang="greek">EI) MH\ E)/XEI PERI\
						PA/NTA
						A)KRI/BEIAN</foreign>, <foreign lang="greek">A)LLA\ POLU\ MA=LLON DIA\ TO\
							E)LLU\S2 O*IMAI TOU= A)TREKES1TA/TOU DU/NAS1QAI H)/KEIN</foreign>. <hi rend="ital">Ibid.</hi>
						The forty-two
						clinical histories, given in the <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> of Hippocrates,
						are excellent examples of the observation which the Hippocratic
						school considered the only foundation of science.</note></p>
				<p>So the two methods, that of Greek philosophy and
					that of modern science, stand face to face. The
					struggle between them was, for the time being, short.
					Medicine, almost the only branch of Greek science
					scientifically studied, was worsted in the fight, and
					medical science gradually degenerated from rational
					treatment to wild speculation and even quackery
					and superstition.<note>See E. T. Withington, in <hi rend="ital">Malaria and Greek
						History</hi>, by
						W. H. S. Jones and E. T. Withington.</note> The transcendant genius of Plato,
					strong in that very power of persuasion the use of
					which he so much deprecated, won the day. The
					philosophic fervour which longed with passionate
					desire for unchangeable reality, that felt a lofty contempt
					for the material world with its ever-shifting
					phenomena, that aspired to rise to a heavenly region
					where changeless Ideas might be apprehended by pure
					intelligence purged from every bodily taint, was more
					than a match for the humble researches of men who
					wished to relieve human suffering by a patient study
					of those very phenomena that Plato held of no account.</p>
				<pb id="p.9"/>
				<p>So for centuries philosophy flourished and science
					languished, in spite of Aristotle, Euclid and Archimedes.</p>
				<p><hi rend="center">A<hi rend="sc">NALYSIS</hi>.</hi></p>
				<p>(1) The rejection of <foreign lang="greek">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign> and the defence of
					the old method in medicine (Ch. I-III).</p>
				<p>(2) The origin of medicine, and its connection
					with the art of dieting (III-XII).</p>
				<p>(3) The comparative unimportance of the four
					"opposites" in health and disease (XIII-XV).</p>
				<p>(4) The importance of certain secretions as compared
					with heat and cold (XVI-XIX).</p>
				<p>(5) The correct method of studying medicine
					(XX-XXIV).</p>
				<p><hi rend="center">T<hi rend="sc">EXT, ETC.</hi></hi></p>
				<p>There has never been published any separate
					edition of this treatise, but of course it is included
					in all the great editions of Hippocrates. Not much
					was done to improve the text before Littr&eacute;, who
					seems to have bestowed care and thought upon the
					little book. The edition of K&eacute;hlewein introduced
					a radical reformation of the pseudo-ionic forms that
					disfigured earlier texts, and also several improvements
					in detail, but his changes are not always happy.</p>
				<p>The chief manuscript authority is A,<note>Called by Littr&eacute; 2253.</note>
					which seems
					infinitely superior to all the others. The next most
					important manuscript is M, the others being of very
					little help.</p>
				<p>In this edition I have kept closely to the spelling
					of K&eacute;hlewein, but the text itself is my own. It</p>
				<pb id="p.10"/>
				<p>follows the MS. A very closely, but on several
					occasions I have accepted (with acknowledgements)
					the emendations of Coray, Reinhold, Ermerins,
					Littr&eacute;, Diels and K&eacute;hlewein. One passage I have
					rejected on my own authority, and in another I
					have presented a new combination of readings which
					I think restores sense out of nonsense. I have
					generally noted readings only when the choice makes
					a decided difference to the translation.</p>
				<p>The translator is often perplexed how to render
					semi-technical words which belong to a time when
					the ideas underlying them were in a transition stage,
					or when ideas were current which the progress of
					time has destroyed. "Hot" and "cold" were no
					longer bodies, but they were not yet qualities. As
					Professor Taylor<note><hi rend="ital">Loc. cit.</hi></note> shows, the word <foreign lang="greek">EI)DOS2</foreign>
					is most
					elusive, referring to the form, appearance, structure
					of a thing, the physique of persons, etc., and yet it is
					becoming capable of being applied to immaterial
					reality. There are about half a dozen words to
					describe the process which we describe by the single
					word "digestion."<note>In deference to authority I translate
						<foreign lang="greek">A)PALLA/S1S1EIN</foreign> in
						Chapters X and XX "come off" well or ill. But I am almost
						convinced that in both cases the word means "to get rid of
						food," "to digest." Compare Chapter III, p. 18, l. 32.</note> These nice
					distinctions must be
					lost in an English version. The most difficult word
					of all is perhaps <foreign lang="greek">DU/NAMIS2</foreign>. Scientific thought in the
					fifth century <hi rend="sc">B.C.</hi> held that certain constituents of
					the body, and indeed of the material world generally,
					manifested themselves to our senses and feelings in
					certain ways. These are their <foreign lang="greek">DUNA/MEIS2</foreign>, "powers,"
					or, as we may sometimes translate, "properties,"</p>
				<pb id="p.11"/>
				<p>"characteristics," "effects." Almost equally difficult
					is the word <foreign lang="greek">*FU/S1IS2</foreign>. This appears sometimes to have
					the meaning which Professor Burnet shows it has in
					early philosophy, "primordial matter," "primitive
					element or elements," the "stuff" of which the
					world is made. Often, again, it has its later meaning,
					"nature," while sometimes the two senses are
					combined or confused. In all these cases perfect
					consistency of rendering can only be achieved by
					sacrificing the thought. In my work I have been
					constantly impressed, and depressed, by the truth
					of the proverb, "Translators are traitors."</p>
				<pb id="p.13"/>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>