<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Consipiracy of Catiline</title>
<author>Sallust</author>
<editor role="editor">John Selby Watson</editor>
&responsibility;
</titleStmt>
&Perseus.publish;

<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Conspiracy of Catiline</title>
<author>Sallust</author>
<editor role="transl">Rev. John Selby Watson, M.A.</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>New York and London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
<date>1899</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction method="silent" status="medium">&Perseus.OCR;</correction>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="chapter"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="de">German</language>
<language id="fr">French</language>
<language id="it">Italian</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change><date>27 March 2002</date>
<respStmt><name>Claire Zietz</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
<item>
$Log: sallust.catil_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-12-07 22:06:05  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status.  split up Plutarch/plut_gk.xml into separate files and gave them their own doc ids.

Revision 1.7  2009/09/10 20:43:58  rsingh04
changed chunking scheme from section to chapter so it will line up with latin versions

Revision 1.6  2006/09/14 15:36:50  gcrane
small fixes

Revision 1.5  2006/05/05 17:38:37  packel
fixed date tags

Revision 1.4  2006/02/10 20:50:44  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.3  2006/01/31 14:47:39  gcrane
typo

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 16:25:53  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:00:20  packel
Converted to XML

Revision 1.9  2004/11/02 15:34:17  gcrane
typos

Revision 1.8  2004/10/06 21:10:08  packel
proofed through ch. 22

Revision 1.7  2004/09/20 15:51:20  packel
fixed various typos, esp. in the Greek and Latin in the notes, through ch. 12

Revision 1.6  2004/09/10 13:21:22  mimno
changed oeligs to aeligs

Revision 1.5  2004/09/09 15:23:36  gcrane
typos and some tagging

Revision 1.4  2004/07/22 19:59:02  mimno
added P4 declarations

Revision 1.3  2004/07/20 12:40:20  mimno
removed subdoc elements

Revision 1.2  2003/05/12 16:07:38  mimno
small changes

Revision 1.1  2003/02/05 21:33:04  mimno
first valid sgml version

</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
<text lang="en">
<body>
<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>BIOGRAPHICAL NOTICE OF SALLUST.</head>
<p>SALLUST was born at <placeName key="perseus,Amiternum">Amiternum</placeName>, a town in the <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> territory, on the first of October,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Euseb. Chron.</note> in the year six hundred and sixty-six<note anchored="yes" place="foot"><placeName key="tgn,1002284">Clinton</placeName>, Fast. Rom.</note> from the foundation of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, eighty-seven years before Christ, and in the seventh consulship of Marius.</p>
<p>The name of his father was Caius Sallustius;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">De Brosses, Vie de Sall., &sect; 2; Glandorp. Onomast.</note> that of his mother is unknown. His family was thought by Crinitus, and some others, to have been patrician, but by <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>, and most of the later critics, is pronounced to have been plebeian, because he held the office of tribune of the people, because lie makes observations unfavorable to the nobility in his writings, and because his grandson, according to Tacitus,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ann., iii. 30.</note> was only of equestrian rank.</p>
<p>The ingenuity of criticism has been exercised in determining whether his name should be written with a double or single l. Jerome Wolfius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Apud Voss.</note> and <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>, are in favor of the single letter, depending chiefly on inscriptions, and on the presumption that the name is derived from <foreign lang="la">salus</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">sal</foreign>. But inscriptions vary; the etymology of the word is uncertain, and to derive it from <foreign lang="la">sal</foreign> would authorize either mode of spelling. All the Latin authors, both in prose and poetry, have the name with the double letter, and it seems better, as Vossius<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Vit. Sall.</note> remarks, to adhere to their practice. Among the Greeks, Dion and Eusebius have the single letter; in some other writers it is found doubled.</p>
<p>Another question raised respecting his name, is whether he <pb n="x"/>should be called <foreign lang="la">Sallustius Crispus</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">Crispus Sallustius.</foreign> The latter mode is adopted by Le Clerc, Cortius, Havercamp, and some other critics; but De Brosses<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Vie de Sall., &sect; 1.</note> argues conclusively in favor of the former method; as Sallustius, from its termination, is evidently the name of the family or <foreign lang="la">gens;</foreign> and Crispus, which denotes <foreign lang="la">quelque habitude du corps,</foreign> only a surname to distinguish one of its branches. <foreign lang="la">Crispus Sallustius</foreign> is found, indeed, in manuscripts; and, according to Cortius, in the best; but on what reasonable grounds can it be justified? It was perhaps adopted by some copyist front the ode of <placeName key="tgn,2028398">Horace</placeName><note anchored="yes" place="foot">Od., ii. 2, 3.</note> addressed to Sallist's nephew, and inconsiderately continued by his successors.</p>
<p>He was removed early in life to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, that he might be educated under Atteius Pr&aelig;textatus, a celebrated grammarian of that age, who styled himself Philologus, and who was afterward tutor to Asinius Pollio.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Suet. de Ill. Gramm., c. 10.</note> Atteius treated Sallust with very great distinction.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ibid.</note></p>
<p>He may be supposed to have soon grown conscious of his powers;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Sall. Ep. to C&aelig;s., i. 10.</note> and appears at an early period of his life to have devoted himself to study, with an intention to distinguish himself in history.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Cat., c. 3.</note></p>
<p>His devotion to literature, however, was not so great as to detain him from indulgence in pleasure; for he became, if we allow any credit to the old declaimer, infamous, <foreign lang="la">&aelig;tatis tirocinio,</foreign> for debauchery and extravagance. He took possession of his father's house in his father's lifetime, and sold it; an act by which he brought his father to the grave; and he was twice, for some misconduct, arraigned before the magistrates, and escaped on both occasions only through the perjury of his judges.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Cic. in Sall., c. 5.</note></p>
<p>When we cite this rhetorician, we must not forget that we cite an anonymous reviler, yet we must suppose with <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>, and with Meisner, the German translator of Sallust, that we quote a writer who grounded his invectives on reports and opinions current at the time in which he lived.</p>
<p>Sallust next thought of aspiring to political distinction;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Cat., c. 3.</note> but <pb n="xi"/>"the usual method of attaining notice," says De Brosses,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Vie de Sal., c. 3.</note> "which was to secure friends and clients by pleading the causes of individuals at the bar, he seems not to have adopted;" since, as is known, no orations spoken' by him are in existence, and, as is thought, no mention is made of such orations in any other author.</p>
<p>Mention, however, is made of orations of Sallust, at whatever time delivered, in the well-known passage of <placeName key="tgn,1002883">Seneca</placeName> the rhetorician.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pr&aelig;f. in Controv., 1. iii., p. 231, ed. Par. <date value="1607">1607</date>.</note> When <placeName key="tgn,1002883">Seneca</placeName> inquired of Cassius Severus, why he, who was so eminent in pleading important causes, displayed so little talent in pronouncing fictitious declamations, the orator replied, <quote lang="la">Quod in me miraris, pene omnibus evenit, etc. Orationes Sallustii in honorem historiarum leguntur.</quote> "What you think extraordinary in me, is common to all men of ability. The greatest geniuses, to whom I am conscious of my great inferiority, have generally excelled only in one species of composition. The felicity of <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName> in poetry deserted him in prose; the eloquence of <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName>'s orations is not to be found in his verses; and the speeches of Sallust are read only as a foil to his histories." The speeches which are here meant, are not, as has been generally imagined, those inserted in the histories, but others, which Sallust had spoken. This view of the passage was first taken by Antonius Augustinus, and communicated by him to Schottus, who mentioned it in his annotations on <placeName key="tgn,1002883">Seneca</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">P. 234, ed. Par. <date value="1607">1607</date>.</note></p>
<p>But by whatever means he secured support, he had at length sufficient interest to obtain a qu&aelig;storship;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Cic., in Sall., c. 5.</note> the tenure of which gave him admission into the senate. It would appear that he was about thirty-one years of age when he attained this honor.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Adam's Rom. antiquities, p. 4.</note></p>
<p>It must have been about this period that his adventure with Fausta, the daughter of Sylla and wife of <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName>, occurred, of which a short account is given by Aulus Gellius<note anchored="yes" place="foot">xvii. 18.</note> in an extract from Varro. The English reader may take it in the version of Beloe : "Marcus Varro, a man of great authority and weight in his writings and life, in his publication entitled 'Pius,' or 'De Pace,' <pb n="xii"/>records that Caius Sallust, the author of that grave and serious composition (<foreign lang="la">seri&aelig; illius et sever&aelig; orationis</foreign>), in which he has exercised the severity of the censorial office, in taking cognizance of crimes, being taken by Ann&aelig;us <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName> in adultery, was well scourged, and, after paying a sum of money, dismissed." The same story is told, on the authority of Asconius Pedianus the biographer of Sallust, by Acro and Porphyrio, the scholiasts on Horace, who, they think, had it in his mind when he wrote the words, <quote lang="la">Ille flagellis ad mortem c&aelig;sus.</quote><note anchored="yes" place="foot">Sat., i. 2, 41.</note> Servius, also, in his note on <foreign lang="la">Quique ob adulterium c&aelig;si,</foreign> in the sixth book of the &AElig;neid,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ver. 612.</note> tells a like tale, adding that Sallust entered the house in the habit of a slave, and was caught in that disguise by <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName>.</p>
<p>Such being the case, it is not wonderful that when Sallust entered on his tribuneship of the people, to which lie was elected in the year of the city seven hundred, he seized an opportunity which occurred of being revenged on <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName>, who had shortly before killed Clodius. He joined with his colleagues, Pompeins Rufus and Plancus, in inflaming the populace, and charging Milo with premeditated hostility.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ascon. Pedian. in Cic. Orat. pro Milo., c. 17; Cic. Mil., c. 5.</note> They intimidated <placeName key="tgn,2115507">Cicero</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName>'s advocate, insinuating that he had planned the assassination;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ascon. Pedian. in Cic. Mil., c. 18.</note> and the matter ended in <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName>'s banishment.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Dion. Cap., lib. xl.</note> During the progress of the trial, however, it is said that Sallust abated his hostility to <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,2115507">Cicero</placeName>, and even became friendly with them.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ascon. Ped. <foreign lang="la">ubi supra.</foreign></note> How this reconciliation was effected, does not appear; but it seems certain that <placeName key="tgn,2115507">Cicero</placeName>, when he attacked Plancus, Sallust's colleague, for exciting the populace to turbulence, left Sallust himself unmolested.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ascon. Ped. in Cic. Mil., c. 85.</note></p>
<p>Unmolested, however, lie did not long remain; for in the year of the city seven hundred and four, in the censorship of Appius Claudius Pulcher, and Lucius Calpurnius Piso, Appius, actuated by two motives, one of which was to serve Pompey, by excluding from the senate such as were hostile to him,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Dion. Cap., xl. 63.</note> and the other to throw into the shade his own private irregularities by <pb n="xiii"/>an ostentatious discharge of his public duties,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Cic. Ep. ad Fam., viii. 14.</note> expelled Sallust from the senate on pretence that he was a flagrantly immoral character.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Dion., ib.</note></p>
<p>But Appius, by this proceeding, instead of serving Pompey, served C&aelig;sar; for many who had previously been favorable to Pompey, or had continued neutral, betook themselves immediately to C&aelig;sar's camp; in the number of whom was Sallust.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Cic. in Sail., c. 6. <placeName key="tgn,2062904">Gerlach</placeName>, Vit. Sall., p. 7.</note></p>
<p>His attendance on C&aelig;sar did not go unrewarded; for when C&aelig;sar returned from <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, after his victory over Afranius and Petreius, he restored Sallust, with others under similar circumstances,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Suet. J. C&aelig;s., c. 41.</note> to his seat in the senate; and as it was not usual for a senator, who had been degraded from his rank, to be reinstated in it without being at the same time elected to an office, he was again made qu&aelig;stor,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Cic., c. 6, 8.</note> or, as <placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName> thinks, pr&aelig;tor.</p>
<p>He was then intrusted with some military command, and sent into <placeName key="tgn,7016683">Illyria</placeName>, where, as Orosius<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Lib., vi. 15. Gerlach, Vit. Sall., p. 7.</note> states, he was one of those that were defeated by the Pomnpeian leaders Octavius and Libo.</p>
<p>Afterward, when the war in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> was finished, but while the remains of Pompey's army, headed by Scipio and Cato, were still menacing hostilities in <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, Sallust, with the title of pr&aelig;tor, was directed to conduct against them a body of troops from <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" place="foot"><placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName>. <placeName key="tgn,2224859">Cass</placeName>., xlii. 52.</note> But Sallust was intrusted with more than he was able to perform. The soldiers mutinied on the coast, compelled him to flee, and hurried away to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, putting to death two senators in their way., It was on this occasion that C&aelig;sar humbled them by addressing them as <foreign lang="la">Quirites</foreign> instead of <foreign lang="la">commilitones.</foreign><note anchored="yes" place="foot"><placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName>., ib. Appian. B. C., ii. 92. Plut. in C&aelig;s. Suet. J. C&aelig;s., c. 10.</note></p>
<p>Sallust was then reinstated in command, and was sent, during the African war, to the island of <placeName key="tgn,7006523">Cercina</placeName>, to bring off a quantity of corn that had been deposited there by the enemy; a commission which he successfully executed.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Hirt. B. A., c. 8, 24.</note></p>
<p>Whether he performed any other service for C&aelig;sar in this <pb n="xiv"/>war, we have no account; but C&aelig;sar, when it was ended, thought him a person of such consequence, that he gave him the government of <placeName key="tgn,7016752">Numidia</placeName>, with the title of pro-consul. "He received the province from C&aelig;sar," says <placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName>, "nominally to govern it, but in reality to ravage and plunder it." Whether such was C&aelig;sar's intention or not, it is generally believed that he enriched himself by the spoil of it to the greatest possible extent.<note anchored="yes" place="foot"><placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName>., xliii. 9. Pseudo-Cic., c. 7.</note></p>
<p>When his term of office, which seems to have been only a year, was expired, he "appeared at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>," says the declaimer, "like a man enriched in a dream." But the Numidians followed him, and accused him of extortion; a charge front which he was only acquitted through the interposition of C&aelig;sar,<note anchored="yes" place="foot"><placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName>., xliii. 9.</note> to whom he is said to have presented a bribe.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Cic., c. 7.</note></p>
<p>The trial had not been long concluded when C&aelig;sar was assassinated, and Sallust, being thus deprived of his patron, seems to have withdrawn entirely from public life. He purchased a large tract of ground on the Quirinal hill, where he erected a splendid mansion, and laid out those magnificent gardens of which so much has been related. Their extent must have been vast, if De Brosses, who visited the spot in <date value="1739">1739</date>, obtained any just notion of it.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">De Brosses, &OElig;uv. de Sall., vol. iii., p. 363.</note> But some have thought them much smaller. He had also a country-house at <placeName key="perseus,Tibur">Tibur</placeName>, which had belonged to Julius C&aelig;sar.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pseudo-Cic., c. 7.</note></p>
<p>It was during this period of retirement, as is supposed, that he married Terentia, the divorced wife of Cicero, if, indeed, he married her at all; for their union rests on no very strong testimony.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Hieronym. adv. Jovin., i. 48. Gerlach, vol. ii., p. 8. De Brosses, tom. iii. p. 355. Le Clerc, Vit. Sall.</note></p>
<p>It was at this time, too, it would appear, that he commenced the composition of history, with a view to the perpetuation of his name; for he entered on it, lie says, when his mind was free from "hope, fear, or political partisanship;"<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Cat., c. 4.</note> and to no other time of his life are such expressions applicable. <placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName> seems to have supposed <pb n="xv"/>that he appeared as a historian before he went to <placeName key="tgn,7016752">Numidia</placeName>, but is in all probability mistaken.</p>
<p>Sallust died on the thirteenth of May, in the year of the city seven hundred and eighteen, in the fifty-second year of his age,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Euseb. Chron. <placeName key="tgn,2244545">Clinton</placeName>, Fasti.</note> leaving his grand-nephew, Gains Sallustius Crispus, whom want of children had induced him to adopt, heir to all his possessions. His gardens, some years after his death, became imperial property.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">See De Brosses, tom. iii. p. 368.</note></p>
<p>Such were the events, as far as we learn, of the life of Sallust; and such is the notion which the voice of antiquity teaches us to form of his moral character. In modern times, some attempts have been made to prove that he was less vicious than he was anciently represented.</p>
<p>Among those who have attempted to clear him of the charges usually brought against hin, are Miller,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">C. Sallustius Crispus, <placeName key="tgn,7012329">Leipzig</placeName>, <date value="1817">1817</date>.</note> Wieland,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ad. Hor. Sat., i. 2, 48.</note> and Roos;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Einige Bemerk, ub. den Moral Char. des Sallust. <foreign lang="de">Prog. Giessen.,</foreign> <date value="1788">1788</date>, 4to. See Frotscher's note on Le Clerc's Life of Sall., init.</note> who are strenuously opposed by Gerlach<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Vit. Sall., p. 9, seq.</note> and Loebell.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Zur Beurtheilung des Sall., <placeName key="tgn,7007601">Breslau</placeName>, <date value="1818">1818</date>.</note> The points on which his champions chiefly endeavor to defend him, are the adventure with Fausta, and the spoliation of <placeName key="tgn,7016752">Numidia</placeName>. Of the three, Miller is the most enterprising. With regard to the affair of Fausta, he sets himself boldly to impugn the authority of Varro or Gellius, on which it chiefly rests; and his reasoning is as follows: That such writers as Gellius are not always to be trusted; that Gellius often quoted from memory; that he cites old authors on the testimony of later authors; that he speaks of Varro, <quote lang="la">fide homo mult&acirc; et gravis,</quote> as if he were a cotemporary that needed commendation, not the well-known Varro whose character was established; that the Varro of Gellius may therefore be a later Varro, whose book, "Pius," or "De Pace," may have been about Antoninus Pius, under whom Gellius lived, and who may have been utterly mistaken in what he said of Sallust; and that, consequently, the passage in Gellius is to be suspected. Respecting the plunder of <placeName key="tgn,7016752">Numidia</placeName>, his arguments are, that the <pb n="xvi"/>province was given to Sallust to spoil, not for himself, but for C&aelig;sar; that of the money obtained from it, the chief part was given to C&aelig;sar; and that, consequently, C&aelig;sar, not Sallust, is to bear the blame for what was done.</p>
<p>But such conjectures produce no more impression on the mind of a reader than <placeName key="tgn,7000667">Walpole</placeName>'s " Historic Doubts" concerning Richard the Third. They suggest something that may have been, but bring no proof of what actually was; they may be allowed to be ingenious, but the general voice of history is still believed. To all M&uuml;ller's suggestions Gerlach exclaims, <quote lang="la">Credat Jud&aelig;us!</quote> Were there, in the pages of antiquity, a single record or remark favorable to the moral character of Sallust, there would then be a <foreign lang="fr">point d'appui</foreign> from which to commence an attack on what is said against him; but the case, alas! is exactly the reverse; wherever Sallust is characterized as a man, he is characterized unfavorably.</p>
<p>His writings consisted of his narratives of the Conspiracy of Catiline and the War with Jugurtha, and of a History of <placeName key="tgn,7000874">Rome</placeName> in five books, extending from the death of Sylla to the beginning of the Mithridatic war. The Catiline and Jugurtha have reached us entire; but of the History there now remain only four speeches, two letters, and a number of smaller fragments preserved among the grammarians. That he was not the author of the Epistles to C&aelig;sar, the reader will find satisfactorily shown in the remarks prefixed to the translation of them in the present volume.</p>
<p>Sallust is supposed to have formed his style on that of Thucydides;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Vell. Pat., i. 36.</note> but he has far excelled his model, if not in energy, certainly in conciseness and perspicuity, of expression. "The speeches of Thucydides," says Cicero,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Orat., c. 9.</note> "contain so many dark and intricate passages, that they are scarcely understood." No such complaint can be made of any part of the writings of Sallust. "From any sentence in Thucydides," says <placeName key="tgn,2652379">Seneca</placeName> the rhetorician,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Controvers., iv. 24.</note> "however remarkable for its conciseness, if a word or two be taken away, the sense will remain, if not equally ornate, yet equally entire; but from the periods of Sallust nothing can be <pb n="xvii"/>deducted without detriment to the meaning." <quote lang="la">Apud eruditas aures,</quote> says Quintilian,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Inst. Or., x. 1.</note> <quote lang="la">nihil potest esse perfectius.</quote></p>
<p>The defects of his style are, that he wants the <foreign lang="la">flumen orationis</foreign> so much admired in Livy and Herodotus;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Monboddo, Origin and Prog. of Language, vol. ii. p. 200.</note> that his transitions are often abrupt; and that he too much affects antique phraseology.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Quint. Inst. Or., viii. 3.</note> But no writer can combine qualities that are incompatible. He is justly preferred by Quintilian<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Inst. Or., ii. 5.</note> to Livy, and well merits the praise given him by Tacitus<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ann., iii. 30.</note> and Martial,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">xiv. 191.</note> of being <quote lang="la">rerum Romanarum florentissimus auctor,</quote> and <quote lang="la">Roman&acirc; primus in histori&acirc;.</quote></p>
<p>Of the numerous editions of Sallust, that of Cortius, which appeared at <placeName key="tgn,7012329">Leipsic</placeName> in <date value="1724">1724</date>, and has been often reprinted, long indisputably held the first rank. But Cortius, as an editor, was somewhat too fond of expelling from his text all words that he could possibly pronounce superfluous; and succeeding editors, as Gerlach (Basil. <date value="1823">1823</date>), Kritz (<placeName key="tgn,7012329">Leipsic</placeName>, 1834), and Dietsch (<placeName key="tgn,7012329">Leipsic</placeName>, 1846), have judiciously restored many words that he had discarded, and produced texts more acceptable in many respects to the generality of students.</p>
<p>Sallust has been many times translated into English. The versions most deserving notice are those of <placeName key="tgn,1050708">Gordon</placeName> (<date value="1744">1744</date>), Rose (<date value="1751">1751</date>), Murphy (<date value="1809">1809</date>), and Peacock (<date value="1845">1845</date>.) <placeName key="tgn,1050708">Gordon</placeName> has vigor, but wants polish; Rose is close and faithful but often dry and hard; Murphy is sprightly, but verbose and licentious, qualities in which his admirer, Sir Henry Steuart (<date value="1806">1806</date>), went audaciously beyond him; Mr. Peacock's translation is equally faithful with that of Rose, and far exceeds it in general ease and agreeableness of style.

<pb n="1"/></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="1">
<p> IT becomes all men, who desire to excel other animals,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">I. Desire to excel other animals] <quote lang="la">Sese student pr&aelig;stare ceteris animalibus.</quote> The pronoun, which was usually omitted, is, says Cortius, not without its force; for it is equivalent to <foreign lang="la">ut ipsi: student ut ipsi pr&aelig;stent.</foreign> In support of his opinion he quotes, with other passages, Plaut. Asinar. i. 3, 31: <foreign lang="la">Vult placere sese amic&aelig;,</foreign> i.e. <foreign lang="la">vult ut ipse amic&aelig; placeat;</foreign> and <bibl>C&aelig;lius Antipater apud Festum in "Topper,"</bibl> <foreign lang="la">Ita uti sese quisque vobis studeat &aelig;mulari,</foreign> i.e. <foreign lang="la">studeat ut ipse &aelig;muletur.</foreign> This explanation is approved by Bernouf. Cortius might have added Cat. 7: <foreign lang="la">sese quisque hostem ferre--properabat.</foreign> <foreign lang="la">"Student,"</foreign> Cortius interprets by <foreign lang="la">"cupiunt."</foreign></note> to strive, to the utmost of their power,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To the utmost of their power] <quote lang="la">Summ&acirc; ope,</quote> with their utmost ability. "A Sallustian mode of expression. Cicero would have said <foreign lang="la">summ&acirc; oper&acirc;, summo studio, summ&acirc;, contentione.</foreign> Ennius has <foreign lang="la">'Summa nituntur opum vi.'</foreign>" Colerus.</note> not to pass through life in obscurity,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In obscurity] <quote lang="la">Silentio</quote>. So as to have nothing said of them, either during their lives or at their death. So in c. 2: <foreign lang="la">Eorum ego vitam mortemque juxta &aelig;stumo, quoniam de utr&acirc;que siletur.</foreign> When <placeName key="tgn,2071526">Ovid</placeName> says, <foreign lang="la">Bene qui latuit, bene vixit,</foreign> and <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName>, <foreign lang="la">Nec vixit mal&egrave;, qui vivens moriensque fefellit,</foreign> they merely signify that he has some comfort in life, who, in ignoble obscurity, escapes trouble and censure. But men thus undistinguished are, in the estimation of Sallust, little superior to the brute creation. <foreign lang="la">"Optimus quisque,</foreign> says Muretus, quoting <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, <foreign lang="la">"honoris et glori&aelig; studio maxim&egrave; ducitur;"</foreign> the ablest men are most actuated by the desire of honor and glory, and are more solicitous about the character which they will bear among posterity. With reason, therefore, does <placeName key="tgn,2565867">Pallas</placeName>, in the Odyssey, address the following exhortation to Telemachus:
<quote><l>Hast thou not heard how young Orestes, fir'd</l>
<l>With great revenge, immortal praise acquir'd ?</l>
<l>* * * * *</l>
<l>O greatly bless'd with ev'ry blooming grace,</l>
<l>With equal steps the paths of glory trace !</l>
<l>Join to that royal youth's your rival name,</l>
<l>And shine eternal in the sphere of fame.</l></quote></note> like the beasts of the field,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Like the beasts of the field] <quote lang="la">Veluti pecora.</quote> Many translators have rendered <quote lang="la">pecora</quote> "brutes" or "beasts;" <foreign lang="la">pecus,</foreign> however, does not mean brutes in general, but answers to our English word cattle.</note> which nature has formed groveling<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Groveling] <quote lang="la">Prona.</quote> I have adopted groveling from Mair's old translation. <foreign lang="la">Pronus,</foreign> stooping to the earth, is applied to cattle, in opposition to <foreign lang="la">erectus,</foreign> which is applied to man; as in the following lines of <placeName key="tgn,2071526">Ovid</placeName>, Met. i. 76:
<quote lang="la"><l>Pronaque cum spectent animalia c&aelig;tera terram,</l>
<l>Os homini sublime dedit, c&aelig;lumque tueri</l>
<l>Jussit, et erectos ad sidera tollere vultus."</l></quote>
<cit><quote><l>"------ while the mute creation downward bend</l>
<l>Their sight, and to their earthly mother tend,</l>
<l>Man looks aloft, and with erected eyes</l>
<l>Beholds his own hereditary skies.</l></quote>
<bibl>Dryden.</bibl></cit>
Which <placeName key="tgn,7013820">Milton</placeName> (Par. L. vii. 502) has paraphrased:
<quote><l>There wanted yet the master-work, the end</l>
<l>Of all yet done; a creature, who not prone</l>
<l>And brute as other creatures, but endued</l>
<l>With sanctity of reason, might erect</l>
<l>His stature, and upright with front serene</l>
<l>Govern the rest, self-knowing, and-from thence</l>
<l>Magnanimous to correspond with heaven.</l></quote>
So Silius Italicus, xv. 84:
<quote lang="la"><l>Nonne vides hominum ut celsos ad sidera vultus</l>
<l>Sustulerit Deus, et sublimia finxerit ora,</l>
<l>C&ugrave;m pecudes, volucrumque genus, formasque ferarum,</l>
<l>Segnem atque obsc&aelig;nam passim stravisset in alvum.</l></quote>
<quote><l>See'st thou not how the Deity has rais'd</l>
<l>The countenance of man erect to heav'n,</l>
<l>Gazing sublime, while prone to earth he bent</l>
<l>Th' inferior tribes, reptiles, and pasturing herds,</l>
<l>And beasts of prey, to appetite enslav'd?</l></quote>
"When Nature," says <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName>, de <placeName key="tgn,2004195">Legg</placeName>. i. 9, "had made other animals abject, and consigned them to the pastures, she made man alone upright, and raised him to the contemplation of heaven, as of his birthplace and former abode;" a passage which <placeName key="tgn,1014723">Dryden</placeName> seems to have had in his mind when he translated the lines of <placeName key="tgn,2033049">Ovid</placeName> cited above. Let us add Juvenal, xv. 146:
<quote lang="la"><l>Sensum &agrave; c&aelig;lesti demissum traximus arce,</l>
<l>Cujus egent prona et terram spectantia.</l></quote>
<quote><l>To us is reason giv'n, of heav'nly birth,</l>
<l>Denied to beasts, that prone regard the earth.</l></quote></note> and subservient to appetite.
<pb n="3"/></p>
<p>All our power is situate in the mind and in the body.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">All our power is situate in the mind and in the body] <quote lang="la">Sed omnis nostra vis in animo et corpore sita.</quote> All our power is placed, or consists, in our mind and our body. The particle <foreign lang="la">sed,</foreign> which is merely a connective, answering to the Greek <foreign lang="greek">de/,</foreign> and which would be useless in an English translation, I have omitted.</note> Of the mind we rather employ the government;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Of the mind we--employ the government] <quote lang="la">Animi imperio--utimur.</quote> "What the Deity is in the universe, the mind is in man; what matter is to the universe, the body is to us; let the worse, therefore, serve the better."--Sen. Epist. lxv. <foreign lang="la">Dux et imperator vit&aelig; mortalium animus est.</foreign> the mind is the guide and ruler of the life of mortals.--Jug. c. 1. " An animal consists of mind and body, of which the one is formed by nature to rule and the other to obey."--Aristot. Polit. i. 5. Muretus and Graswinckel will supply abundance of similar passages.</note> of the body, the <pb n="4"/>service.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Of the mind we rather employ the government; of the body, the service] <quote lang="la">Animi imperio, corporis servitio magis utimur.</quote> The word <foreign lang="la">magis</foreign> is not to be regarded as useless. " It signifies," says Cortius, " that the mind rules, and the body obeys, in general, and with greater reason." At certain times the body may seem to have the mastery, as when we are under the irresistible influence of hunger or thirst.</note> The one is common to us with the gods; the other with the brutes. It appears to me, therefore, more reasonable<note anchored="yes" place="foot">It appears to me, therefore, more reasonable, etc.] <quote lang="la">Quo mihi rectius videtur,</quote> etc. I have rendered <foreign lang="la">quo</foreign> by therefore. " <foreign lang="la">Quo,</foreign>" observes Cortius, "is <foreign lang="la">propter quod</foreign> with the proper force of the ablative case. So Jug. c. 84: <foreign lang="la">Quo mihi acrius adnitendum est, </foreign>etc; c. 2, <foreign lang="la">Quo magis pravitas eorum admiranda est.</foreign> Some expositors would force us to believe that these ablatives are inseparably connected with the comparative degree, as in <foreign lang="la">quo minus, eo major,</foreign> and similar expressions; whereas common sense shows that they can not be so connected." Kritzius is one of those who interprets in the way to which Cortius alludes, as if the drift of the passage were, <foreign lang="la">Quanto magis animus corpori pr&aelig;tat, tanto rectius ingenii opibus gloriam qu&aelig;rere.</foreign> But most of the commentators and translators rightly follow Cortius. " <foreign lang="la">Quo,</foreign>" says Pappaur, "is for <foreign lang="la">quocirca."</foreign></note> to pursue glory by means of the intellect than of bodily strength, and, since the life which we enjoy is short, to make the remembrance of us as lasting as possible. For the glory of wealth and beauty is fleeting and perishable; that of intellectual power is illustrious and immortal.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">That of intellectual powor is illustrious and immortal] <quote lang="la">Virtus clara &aelig;ternaque habetur.</quote> The only one of our English translators who has given the right sense of <foreign lang="la">virtus</foreign> in this passage, is Sir Henry Steuart, who was guided to it by the Abb&eacute; Thyvon and M. Beauz&eacute;e. " It appears somewhat singular," says Sir Henry, "that none of the numerous translators of Sallust, whether among ourselves or among foreign nations--the Abb&eacute; Thyvon and M. Beauz&eacute;e excepted--have thought of giving to the word <foreign lang="la">virtus,</foreign> in this place, what so obviously is the meaning intended by the historian; namely, 'genius, ability, distinguished talents.' Indeed, the whole tenor of the passage, as well as the scope of the context, leaves no room to doubt the fact. The main objects of comparison, throughout the three first sections of this Pr&aelig;mium, or introductory discourse, are not vice and virtue, but body and mind; a listless indolence, and a vigorous, honorable activity. On this account it is pretty evident, that by <foreign lang="la">virtus</foreign> Sallust could never mean the Greek <foreign lang="greek">a)reth/,</foreign> virtue or moral worth,' but that he had in his eye the well-known interpretation of Varro, who considers it <foreign lang="la">ut viri vis</foreign> (De Ling. Lat. iv.), as denoting the useful energy which ennobles a man, and should chiefly distinguish him among his fellow-creatures. In order to be convinced of the justice of this rendering, we need only turn to another passage of our author, in the second section of the Pr&aelig;mium to the Jugarthine War, where the same train of thought is again pursued, although he gives it somewhat a different turn in the piece last mentioned. The object, notwithstanding, of both these Dissertations is to illustrate, in a striking manner, the pre-eminence of the mind over extrinsic advantages or bodily endowments, and to show that it is by genius alone that we may aspire to a reputation which shall never die. <foreign lang="la">Igitur pr&aelig;clara facies, magn&aelig; diviti&aelig;, adhuc vis corporis, et alia hujusmodi omnia, brevi dilabuntur: at ingenii egregia facinora, sicut anima, immortalia sunt."</foreign>
<pb n="5"/>
<p>Yet it was long a subject of dispute among mankind, whether military efforts were more advanced by strength of body, or by force of intellect. For, in affairs of war, it is necessary to plan before beginning to act,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">It is necessary to plan before beginning to act] <quote lang="la">Priusquam incipias, consulto--opus est.</quote> Most translators have rendered <foreign lang="la">consulto</foreign> " deliberation," or something equivalent; but it is planning or contrivance that is signified. Demosthenes, in his Oration <foreign lang="la">de Pace,</foreign> reproaches the Athenians with acting without any settled plan: <foreign lang="greek">(*oi( me\n ga\r a)/lloi pa/ntes a)/nqrwpoi pro\ tw=n pragma/twn e)iw/qasi xrh=sqai tw=| *bouleuesqai, u(mei=s o)ude\ meta\ ta\ pra/gmata.</foreign></note> and, after planning, to act with promptitude and vigor.'<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To act with promptitude and vigor] <quote lang="la">Matur&egrave; facto opus est.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Matur&egrave; facto"</foreign> seems to include the notions both of promptitude and vigor, of force as well as speed; for what would be the use of acting expeditiously, unless expedition be attended with power and effect ?</note> Thus, each<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Each] <quote lang="la">Utrumque.</quote> The corporeal and mental faculties.</note> being insufficient of itself, the one requires the assistance of the other."<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The one requires the assistance of the other] <quote lang="la">Alterum alterius auxilio eget.</quote> " <foreign lang="la">Eget,</foreign>" says Cortius, "is the reading of all the MSS." <foreign lang="la">Veget,</foreign> which Havercamp and some others have adopted, was the conjecture of Palmerius, on account of <foreign lang="la">indigens</foreign> occurring in the same sentence. But <foreign lang="la">eget</foreign> agrees far better with <quote lang="la">consulto et--matur&egrave; facto opus est,</quote> in the preceding sentence.</note></p></note></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2">
<p>In early times, accordingly, kings (for that was the first title of sovereignty in the world) applied themselves in different ways;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">II. Applied themselves in different ways] <foreign lang="la">Diversi.</foreign> <foreign lang="la">"Modo et instituto diverse, diversa sequentes."</foreign>Cortius.</note> some exercised the mind, others the body. At that period, however,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">At that period, however] <quote lang="la">Et jam tum.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Tunc temporis pr&aelig;cis&egrave;,</foreign> at that time precisely, which is the force of the particle <foreign lang="la">jam,</foreign> as <foreign lang="la">Donatus</foreign> shows. * * * I have therefore written <foreign lang="la">et jam</foreign> separately. * * * Virg. &AElig;n. vii. 737. <foreign lang="la">Late jam tum ditione premebat Sarrastes populos."</foreign> Cortius.</note> the life of man was passed without covetousness <note anchored="yes" place="foot">Without covetousness] <quote lang="la">Sine cupiditate.</quote> " As in the famous golden age. See Tacit. Ann. iii. 26." Cortius. See also <placeName key="tgn,2033049">Ovid</placeName>. Met. i. 89, seq. But "such times were never," as Cowper says.</note> every one was satisfied with his own. But after <placeName key="tgn,2273622">Cyrus</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName><note anchored="yes" place="foot">But after <placeName key="tgn,2074299">Cyrus</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName>, etc.] <quote lang="la">Postea ver&ograve; qu&agrave;m in, Asi&acirc; <placeName key="tgn,2074299">Cyrus</placeName>,</quote> etc. Sallust writes as if he had supposed that kings were more moderate before the time of <placeName key="tgn,2074299">Cyrus</placeName>. But this can hardly have been the case. " The Romans," says De Brosses, whose words I abridge, " though not learned in antiquity, could not have been ignorant that there were great conquerors before Cyrus; as <placeName key="tgn,7017998">Ninus</placeName> and Sesostris. But as their reigns belonged rather to the fabulous ages, Sallust, in entering upon a serious history, wished to confine himself to what was certain, and went no further back than the records of Herodotus and Thucydides." <placeName key="tgn,7017998">Ninus</placeName>, says Justin. i. 1, was the first to change, through inordinate ambition, the <foreign lang="la">veterem et quasi avitum gentibus morem;</foreign> that is, to break through the settled restraints of law and order. Gerlach agrees in opinion with De Brosses.</note> and the Laced&aelig;monians and Athenians in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, began <pb n="6"/>to subjugate cities and nations, to deem the lust of dominion a reason for war, and to imagine the greatest glory to be in the most extensive empire, it was then at length discovered, by proof and experience,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Proof and experience] <quote lang="la">Periculo atque negotiis.</quote> Gronovius rightly interprets <foreign lang="la">periculo</foreign><foreign lang="la"> "experiundo, experimentis,"</foreign> by experiment or trial. Cortius takes <foreign lang="la">periculo atque negotiis</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">periculosis negotiis,</foreign> by hendyadys; but to this figure, as Kritzius remarks, we ought but sparingly to have recourse. It is better, he adds, to take the words in their ordinary signification, understanding by <foreign lang="la">negotia</foreign> <foreign lang="la">"res graviores."</foreign> Bernouf judiciously explains <foreign lang="la">negotiis</foreign> by <foreign lang="la">"ips&acirc; negotiorum tractatione,"</foreign> i.e. by the management of affairs, or by experience in affairs. Dureau Delamalle, the French translator, has <foreign lang="fr">"l'exp&eacute;rience et la pratique."</foreign> Mair has "trial and experience," which, I believe, faithfully expresses Sallust's meaning. Rose gives only "experience" for both words.</note> that mental power has the greatest effect in military operations. And, indeed,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">And, indeed, if the intellectual ability, etc.] <quote lang="la">Quod si--animi virtus,</quote> etc. " Quod si" can not here be rendered but if; it is rather equivalent to <foreign lang="la">quapropter si,</foreign> and might be expressed by wherefore if, if therefore, if then, so that if.</note> if the intellectual ability<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Intellectual ability] <quote lang="la">Animi virtus.</quote> See the remarks on <foreign lang="la">virtus,</foreign> above cited.</note> of kings and magistrates<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Magistrates] <quote lang="la">Imperatorum.</quote> "Understand all who govern states, whether in war or in peace." Bernouf. Sallust calls the consuls <quote lang="la">imperatores,</quote> c. 6.</note> were exerted to the same degree in peace as in war, human affairs would be more orderly and settled, and you would not see governments shifted from hand to hand,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Governments shifted from hand to hand] <quote lang="la">Aliud ali&ograve; ferri.</quote> Evidently alluding to changes in government.</note> and things universally changed and confused. For dominion is easily secured by those qualities by which it was at first obtained. But when sloth has introduced itself in the place of industry, and covetousness and pride in that of moderation and equity, the fortune of a state is altered together with its morals; and thus authority is always transferred from the less to the more deserving.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Less to the more deserving] <quote lang="la">Ad optimum quemque &agrave; minus bono.</quote> " From the less good to the best."</note></p>
<p>Even in agriculture,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Even in agriculture, etc.] <quote lang="la">Qu&aelig; homines arant, navigant, &aelig;dificant, virtuti omnia parent.</quote> Literally, what men plow, sail, etc. Sallust's meaning is, that agriculture, navigation, and architecture, though they may seem to be effected by mere bodily exertion, are as much the result of mental power us the highest of human pursuits.</note> in navigation, and in architecture, whatever man performs owns the dominion of intellect. Yet many human beings, resigned to sensuality and indolence, uninstructed <pb n="7"/>and unimproved, have passed through life like travelers in a strange country;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Like travelers in a strange country] <quote lang="la">Sicuti peregrinantes.</quote> <quote lang="la">Vivere nesciunt; igitur in vit&acirc; quasi hospites sunt;</quote> they know not how to use life, and are therefore, as it were, strangers in it. Dietsch. "<foreign lang="la">Peregrinantes, qui, qu&acirc; transeunt, nullum sui vestigium relinquunt:"</foreign> they are as travelers who do nothing to leave any trace of their course. Pappaur.</note> to whom, certainly, contrary to the intention of nature, the body was a gratification, and the mind a burden. Of these I hold the life and death in equal estimation;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Of these I hold the life and death in equal estimation] <quote lang="la">Eorum ego vit&agrave;m mortemque juxta &aelig;stimo.</quote> I count them of the same value dead as alive, for they are honored in the one state as much as in the other. "Those who, are devoted to the gratification of their appetites," as Sallust says, "let us regard as inferior animals, not as men; and some, indeed, not as living, but as dead animals." <placeName key="tgn,1002882">Seneca</placeName>, Ep. lx.</note> for silence is maintained concerning both. But he only, indeed, seems to me to live, and to enjoy life, who, intent upon some employment, seeks reputation from some ennobling enterprise, or honorable pursuit.</p>
<p>But in the great abundance of occupations, nature points out different paths to different individuals.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3">
<p>To act well for the Commonwealth is noble, and even to speak well for it is not without merit.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">III. Not without merit] <quote lang="la">Haud absurdum.</quote> I have borrowed this expression from Rose, to whom Muretus furnished <foreign lang="la">"su&acirc; laude non caret."</foreign> "The word <foreign lang="la">absurdus</foreign> is often used by the Latins as an epithet for sounds disagreeable to the ear; but at length it came to be applied to any action unbecoming a rational being." Kunhardt.</note> Both in peace and in war it is possible to obtain celebrity; many who have acted, and many who have recorded the actions of others, receive their tribute of praise. And to me, assuredly, though by no means equal glory attends the narrator and the performer of illustrious deeds, it yet seems in the highest degeee difficult to write the history of great transactions; first, because deeds must be adequately represented<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Deeds must be adequately represented, etc.] <quote lang="la">Facta dictis sunt ex&aelig;quanda.</quote> Most translators have regarded these words as signifying that the subject must be equaled by the style. But it is not of mere style that Sallust is speaking." He means that the matter must be so represented by the words, that honorable actions may not be too much praised, and that dishonorable actions may not be too much blamed; and that the reader may at once understand what was done and how it was done." Kunlhardt.</note> by words; and next, because most readers consider that whatever errors you mention with censure, are mentioned through malevolence and envy; while, when you speak of the great virtue and glory of eminent men, every one hears with acquiescence<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Every one hears with acquiescence, etc.] <quote lang="la">Qu&aelig; sibi--&aelig;quo animo accipit,</quote> etc. This is taken from Thucydides, ii. 35. " For praises spoken of other are only endured so far as each one thinks that he is himself also capable of doing any of the things he hears; but that which exceeds their own capacity, men at once envy and disbelieve." Dale's Translation: Bohn's Classical Library.</note> only that which he himself thinks easy to be performed; <pb n="8"/>all beyond his own conception he regards as fictitious and incredible.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Regards as fictitious and incredible] <quote lang="la">Veluti ficta, pro falsis ducit. Ducit pro falsis,</quote> he considers as false or incredible, <quote lang="la">veluti ficta,</quote> as if invented.</note></p>
<p>I myself, however, when a young man,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">When a young man] <quote lang="la">Adolescentulus.</quote> "It is generally admitted that all were called <foreign lang="la">adolescentes</foreign> by the Romans, who were between the fifteenth or seventeenth year of their age and the fortieth. The diminutive is used in the same sense, but with a view to contrast more strongly the ardor and spirit of youth with the moderation, prudence, and experience of age. So C&aelig;sar is called <foreign lang="la">adolescentulus,</foreign> in c. 49, at a time when he was in his thirty-third year." Dietsch. And <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, referring to the time of his consulship, says, <foreign lang="la">Defendi rempublicam adolescens,</foreign> Philipp. ii. 46.</note> was at first led by inclination, like most others, to engage in political affairs;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To engage in political affairs] <quote lang="la">Ad rempublicam.</quote> "In the phrase of Cornelius Nepos, <foreign lang="la">honoribus operam dedi,</foreign> I sought to obtain some share in the management of the Republic. All public matters were comprehended under the term <foreign lang="la">Respublica.</foreign>" Cortius.</note> but in that pursuit many circumstances were unfavorable to me; for, instead of modesty, temperance, and integrity,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Integrity] <quote lang="la">Virtute.</quote> Cortius rightly explains this word as meaning justice, equity, and all other virtues necessary in those who manage the affairs of a state. Observe that it is here opposed to <foreign lang="la">avaritia,</foreign> not, as some critics would have it, to <foreign lang="la">largitio.</foreign></note> there prevailed shamelessness, corruption, and rapacity. And although my mind, inexperienced in dishonest practices, detested these vices, yet, in the midst of so great corruption, my tender age was insnared and infected<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Was ensnared and infected] <quote lang="la">Corrupta tenebatur.</quote> As <foreign lang="la">obsessus tenetur,</foreign> Jug., c. 24.</note> by ambition; and, though I shrunk from the vicious principles of those around me, yet the same eagerness for honors, the same obloquy and jealousy,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The same eagerness for honors, the same obloquy and jealousy, etc.] <quote lang="la">Honoris cupido cadem qu&aelig; c&aelig;teros, fama atque invidia vexabat.</quote> I follow the interpretation of Cortius: <foreign lang="la">"Me vexabat honoris cupido, et vexabat propterea etiam eadem, qu&aelig; c&aelig;teros, fama atque invidia."</foreign> He adds, from a gloss in the Guelferbytan MS., that it is a zeugma. "<foreign lang="la">Fama atque invidia,</foreign>" says Gronovius, "is <foreign lang="greek">e(n dia\ duoi=n,</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">invidiosa et maligna fame.</foreign>" Bernouf, with Zanchius and others, read <foreign lang="la">fam&acirc; atque invidi&acirc;</foreign> in the ablative case; and the Bipont edition has <foreign lang="la">eadem qu&acirc;---fam&acirc;, etc.;</foreign> but the method of Cortius is, to me, by far the most straightforward and satisfactory. Sallust, observes De Brosses, in his note on this passage, wrote the account of Catiline's conspiracy shortly after his expulsion from the Senate, and wishes to make it appear that he suffered from calumny on the occasion; though he took no trouble, in the subsequent part of his life, to put such calumny to silence.</note> which disquieted others, disquieted myself.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="4">
<p> When, therefore, my mind had rest from its numerous <pb n="9"/>troubles and trials, and I had determined to pass the remainder of my days unconnected with public life, it was not my intention to waste my valuable leisure in indolence and inactivity, or, engaging in servile occupations, to spend my time in agriculture or hunting ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">IV. Servile occupations--agriculture or hunting] <quote lang="la">Agrum colendo, aut venando, senvilibus officiis intentum.</quote> By calling agriculture and hunting <foreign lang="la">servilia officia,</foreign> Sallust intends, as is remarked by Graswinckelius, little more than was expressed in the saying of <placeName key="tgn,2089671">Julian</placeName> the emperor, <foreign lang="la">Turpe est sapienti, cum habeat animum, captare laudes ex corpore.</foreign> <foreign lang="la">"Ita ergo,"</foreign> adds the commentator, <foreign lang="la">agricultura et venatio servilia officia sunt, quum in solo consistant corporis usu, animum, ver&ograve; nec meliorem nec prudentiorem reddant. Qui labor in se cert&egrave; est illiberalis, ei pr&aelig;sertim cui facultas sit ad meliora."</foreign> Symmachus (1 v. Ep. 66) and some others, whose remarks the reader may see in Havercamp, think that Sallust might have spoken of hunting and agriculture with more respect, and accuse him of not remembering, with sufficient veneration, the kings and princes that have amused themselves in hunting, and such illustrious plowmen as Curius and <placeName key="tgn,2068518">Cincinnatus</placeName>. Sallust, however, is sufficiently defended from censure by the Abb&eacute; Thyvon, in a dissertation much longer than the subject deserves, and much longer than most readers are willing to peruse.</note> but, returning to those studies<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Returning to those studies, etc.] <quote lang="la">A quo incepto studio me ambitio mala detinuerat, e&ograve;dem regressus.</quote> " The study, namely, of writing history, to which he signifies that he was attached in c. 3." Cortius.</note> from which, at their commencement, a corrupt ambition had allured me, I determined to write, in detatched portions,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In detached portions] <quote lang="la">Carptim.</quote> Plin. Ep. viii., 47: <quote lang="la">Respondebis non posse perinde carptim, ut contexta placere</quote>: et vi. 22: <quote lang="la">Egit carptim et <foreign lang="greek">kata\ kefa/laia</foreign>,</quote> Dietsch.</note> the transactions of the Roman people, as any occurrence should seem worthy of mention; an undertaking to which I was the rather inclined, as my mind was uninfluenced by hope, fear, or political partisanship. I shall accordingly give a brief account, with as much truth as I can, of the Conspiracy of Catiline; for I think it an enterprise eminently deserving of record, from the unusual nature both of its guilt and of its perils. But before I enter upon my narrative, I must give a short description of the character of the man.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="5">
<p> LUCIUS CATILINE was a man of noble birth,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">V. Of noble birth] <quote lang="la">Nobili genere natus.</quote> His three names were Lucius Sergius Catilina, he being of the family of the Sergii, for whose antiquity <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName> is responsible, &AElig;n. v. 121: <foreign lang="la">Sergestusque, domus tenet &agrave; quo Sergia nomen.</foreign> And Juvenal says, Sat. viii. 321: <foreign lang="la">Quid, Catilino, tuis natalibus atque Cethegi Inveniet quisquam sublimius?</foreign> His great grandfather, L. Sergius Silus, had eminently distinguished himself by his services in the second Punic war. See Plin, Hist. Nat. vii, 29, 2 Catiline was born A.U.C. 647, A.C, 107." Dietsch. Ammianus Marcellinus (lib, xxv.) says that he was the last of the Sergii.</note> and of eminent mental and personal endowments; but of a vicious and <pb n="10"/>depraved disposition. His delight, from his youth, had been in civil commotions, bloodshed, robbery, and sedition;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Sedition] <quote lang="la">Discordia civilis.</quote></note> and in such scenes he had spent his early years.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">And in such scenes he had spent his early years] <quote lang="la">Ibique juventutem suam exercuit.</quote> " It is to be observed that the Roman writers often used an adverb, where we, of modern times, should express ourselves more specifically by using a noun." Dietsch on c. 3, <foreign lang="la">ibique multa mihi advorsa fuere. Juventus</foreign> properly signified the time between thirty and forty-five years of age; <foreign lang="la">adolescentia</foreign> that between fifteen and thirty. But this distinction was not always accurately observed. Catiline had taken an active part in supporting Sylla, and in carrying into execution his cruel proscriptions and mandates. <foreign lang="la">"Quis erat hujus (Sull&aelig;) imperii minister? Quis nisi Catilina, jam in omne facinus manus exercens?"</foreign> Sen. de Ir&acirc;, iii. 18.</note> His constitution could endure hunger, want of sleep, and cold, to a degree surpassing belief. His mind was daring, subtle, and versatile, capable of pretending or dissembling whatever he wished.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Capable of pretending or dissembling whatever he wished] <quote lang="la">Cujuslibet rei simulator ac dissimulator.</quote> "Dissimulation is the negative, when a man lets fall signs and arguments, that he is not that he is; simulation is the affirmative, when a man industriously and expressly feigns and pretends to be that he is not." Bacon, Essay vi.</note> He was covetous of other men's property, and prodigal of his own. He had abundance of eloquence,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Abundance of eloquence] <quote lang="la">Satis eloquenti&aelig;.</quote> Cortius reads <foreign lang="la">loquenti&aelig;.</foreign> "<foreign lang="la">Loquentia</foreign> is a certain facility of speech not necessarily attended with sound sense; called by the Greeks <foreign lang="greek">lali/a.</foreign>" Bernouf. "Julius Candidus used excellently to observe that <foreign lang="la">eloquentia</foreign> was one thing, and <foreign lang="la">loquentia</foreign> another; for eloquence is given to few, but what Candidus called <foreign lang="la">loquentia,</foreign> or fluency of speech, is the talent of many, and especially of the most impudent." Plin. Ep. v. 20. But <foreign lang="la">eloquenti&aelig;</foreign> is the reading of most of the MSS., and <foreign lang="la">loquenti&aelig;</foreign> if Aulus Gellius (i. 15) was rightly informed, was a correction of Valerius Probus, the grammarian, who said that Sallust must have written so, as <foreign lang="la">eloquenti&aelig;</foreign> could not agree with <foreign lang="la">sapienti&aelig; parum.</foreign> This opinion of Probus however, may be questioned. May not Sallust have written <foreign lang="la">eloquenti&aelig;,</foreign> with the intention of signifying that Catiline had abundance of eloquence to work on the minds of others, though he wanted prudence to regulate his own conduct? Have there not been other men of whom the same may be said, as Mirabeau, for example? The speeches that Sallust puts into Catiline's mouth (c. 20, 58) are surely to be characterized rather as <foreign lang="la">eloquentia</foreign> than <foreign lang="la">loquentia.</foreign> On the whole, and especially from the concurrence of MSS., I prefer to read <foreign lang="la">eloquenti&aelig;,</foreign> with the more recent editors, <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>, Kritz, and Dietsch.</note> though but little wisdom. His insatiable ambition was always pursuing objects extravagant, romantic, and unattainable.</p>
<p>Since the time of Sylla's dictatorship,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Since the time of Sylla's dictatorship] <quote lang="la">Post dominationem Lucii Syll&aelig;.</quote> " The meaning is not the same as if it were <quote lang="la">finit&acirc; dominatione,</quote> but is the same as <foreign lang="la">ab eo tempore quo dominari c&aelig;perat.</foreign> In French, therefore, <foreign lang="la">post</foreign> should be rendered by <foreign lang="fr">depuis,</foreign> not, as it is commonly translated, <foreign lang="fr">apr&egrave;s.</foreign>" Bernouf. As <foreign lang="la">dictator</foreign> was the title that Sylla assumed, I have translated <foreign lang="la">dominatio,</foreign> "dictatorship." Rose, <placeName key="tgn,2000355">Gordon</placeName>, and others, render it "usurpation."</note> a strong desire of <pb n="11"/>seizing the government possessed him, nor did he at all care, provided that he secured power<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Power] <quote lang="la">Regnum.</quote> Chief authority, rule, dominion.</note> for himself, by what means he might arrive at it. His violent spirit was daily more and more hurried on by the diminution of his patrimony, and by his consciousness of guilt; both which evils he had increased by those practices which I have mentioned above. The corrupt morals of the state, too, which extravagance and selfishness, pernicious and contending vices, rendered thoroughly depraved,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Rendered thoroughly depraved] <quote lang="la">Vexabant.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Corrumpere et pessundare studebant."</foreign> Bernouf. <foreign lang="la">Quos vexabant,</foreign> be it observed, refers to <foreign lang="la">mores,</foreign> as <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName> and Kritz interpret not to <foreign lang="la">cives</foreign> understood in <foreign lang="la">civitatis,</foreign> which is the evidently erroneous method of Cortius.</note> furnished him with additional incentives to action.</p>
<p>Since the occasion has thus brought public morals under my notice, the subject itself seems to call upon me to look back, and briefly to describe the conduct of our ancestors<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Conduct of our ancestors] <quote lang="la">Instituta majorum.</quote> The principles adopted by our ancestors, with regard both to their own conduct, and to the management of the state. That this is the meaning, is evident from the following account.</note> in peace and war; how they managed the state, and how powerful they left it; and how, by gradual alteration, it became, from being the most virtuous, the most vicious and depraved.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="6">
<p> Of the city of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, as I understand,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">VI. As I understand] <quote lang="la">Sicut ego accepi.</quote> "By these words he plainly shows that nothing certain was known about the origin of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>. The reader may consult Livy, lib. i.; <placeName key="tgn,2105285">Justin</placeName>, lib. xliii.; and Dionys. Halicar., lib. i. ; all of whom attribute its rise to the Trojans." Bernouf.</note> the founders and earliest inhabitants were the Trojans, who, under the conduct of &AElig;neas, were wandering about as exiles from their country, without any settled abode; and with these were joined the Aborigines,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Aborigines] <foreign lang="la">Aborigines.</foreign> The original inhabitants of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; the same as <foreign lang="la">indigen&aelig;,</foreign> or the Greek <foreign lang="greek">*)auto/xqones.</foreign></note> a savage race of men, without laws or government, free, and owning no control. How easily these two tribes, though of different origin, dissimilar language, and opposite habits of life, formed a union when they met within the same walls, is almost incredible.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Almost incredible] <quote lang="la">Incredibile memoratu.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Non credi potest, si memoratur; superat omnem fidem."</foreign> Pappaur. Yet that which actually happened, can not be absolutely incredible; and I have, therefore, inserted almost.</note> But when their state, from an accession of population and territory, and an improved condition of morals, showed itself tolerably flourishing and powerful, <pb n="12"/>envy, as is generally the case in human affairs, was the consequence of its prosperity. The neighboring kings and people, accordingly, began to assail them in war, while a few only of their friends came to their support; for the rest, struck with alarm, shrunk from sharing their dangers. But the Romans, active at home and in the field, prepared with alacrity for their defense.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Prepared with alacrity for their defense] <quote lang="la">Festinare, parare.</quote> "Made haste, prepared." " <foreign lang="la">Intenti ut festinanter pararent ea, qu&aelig; defensioni aut bello usui essent."</foreign> Pappaur.</note> They encouraged one another, and hurried to meet the enemy. They protected, with their arms, their liberty, their country, and their homes. And when they had at length repelled danger by valor, they lent assistance to their allies and supporters, and procured friendships rather by bestowing<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Procured friendships rather by bestowing, etc.] <quote lang="la">Magisque dandis, quam accipundis beneficiis amicitias parabant.</quote> Thucyd. ii., 40: <foreign lang="greek">ou) pa/sxontes eu=), a)lla\ drw=ntes, ktw/meqa tou\s fi/lous.</foreign></note> favors than by receiving them.</p>
<p>They had a government regulated by laws. The denomination of their government was monarchy. Chosen men, whose bodies might be enfeebled by years, but whose minds were vigorous in understanding, formed the council of the state; and these, whether from their age, or from the similarity of their duty, were called FATHERS.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">FATHERS] <quote lang="la">PATRES.</quote> "(<placeName key="tgn,2072021">Romulus</placeName>) appointed that the direction of the state should be in the hands of the old men, who, from their authority, were called Fathers from their age, <foreign lang="la">Senatus.</foreign>" Florus, i. 1. <foreign lang="la">Senatus</foreign> from. <foreign lang="la">senex.</foreign> "<foreign lang="la"> Patres ab honore--appellati."</foreign> Livy.</note> But afterward, when the monarchical power, which had been originally established for the protection of liberty, and for the promotion of the public interest, had degenerated into tyranny and oppression, they changed their plan, and appointed two magistrates,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Two magistrates <quote lang="la">Binos imperatores.</quote> The two consuls. They were more properly called <quote lang="la">imperatores</quote> at first, when the law, which settled their power, said <foreign lang="la">"Regio imperio duo sunto"</foreign> (Cic. de <placeName key="tgn,2004195">Legg</placeName>. iii. 4), than afterward, when the people and tribunes had made encroachments on their authority.</note> with power only annual; for they conceived that, by this method, the human mind would be least likely to grow overbearing for want of control.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="7">
<p> At this period every citizen began to seek distinction, and to display his talents with greater freedom; for, with princes, the meritorious are greater objects of suspicion than the undeserving, and to them the worth of others is a source of <pb n="13"/>alarm. But when liberty was secured, it is almost incredible<note anchored="yes" place="foot">VII. Almost incredible] <quote lang="la">Incredibile memoratu.</quote> See above, c. 6.</note> how much the state strengthened itself in a short space of time, so strong a passion for distinction had pervaded it. Now, for the first time, the youth, as soon as they were able to bear the toil of war,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Able to bear the toils of war] <quote lang="la">Laboris ac belli patiens.</quote> As by <foreign lang="la">laboris</foreign> the labor of war is evidently intended, I have thought it better to render the words in this manner. The reading is Cortius'. Havercamp and others have <foreign lang="la">"simul ac belli patiens erat, in castris per laborem usu militiam discebat;"</foreign> but <foreign lang="la">per laborem usu</foreign> is assuredly not the hand of Sallust.</note> acquired military skill by actual service in the camp, and took pleasure rather in splendid arms and military steeds than in the society of mistresses and convivial indulgence. To such men no toil was unusual, no place was difficult or inaccessible, no armed enemy was formidable; their valor had overcome every thing. But among themselves the grand rivalry was for glory; each sought to be first to wound an enemy, to scale a wall, and to be noticed while performing such an exploit. Distinction such as this they regarded as wealth, honor, and true nobility.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Honor and true nobility] <quote lang="la">Bonam famam magnamque nobilitatem.</quote></note> They were covetous of praise, but liberal of money; they desired competent riches but boundless glory. I could mention, but that the account would draw me too far from my subject, places in which the Roman people, with a small body of men, routed vast armies of the enemy; and cities, which, though fortified by nature, they carried by assault.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="8">
<p> But, assuredly, Fortune rules in all things. She makes every thing famous or obscure rather from caprice than in conformity with truth. The exploits of the Athenians, as far as I can judge, were very great and glorious,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">VIII. Very great and glorious] <quote lang="la">Satis ampl&aelig; magnific&aelig;que.</quote> In speaking of this amplification of the Athenian exploits, he alludes, as Colerus observes, to the histories of Thucydides, Xenophon, and perhaps Herodotus; not, as Wasse seems to imagine, to the representations of the poets.</note> something inferior to what fame has represented them. But because writers of great talent flourished there, the actions of the Athenians are celebrated over the world as the most splendid achievements. Thus, the merit of those who have acted is estimated at the highest point to which illustrious intellects could exalt it in their writings.</p>
<p>But among the Romans there was never any such abundance of writers;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">There was never any such abundance of writers] <quote lang="la">Nunquam ea copia fuit.</quote> I follow Kuhnhardt, who thinks <foreign lang="la">copia</foreign> equivalent to <foreign lang="la">multitudo.</foreign> Others render it advantage, or something similar; which seems less applicable to the passage. Compare c. 28: <foreign lang="la">Latrones--quorum--magna copia erat.</foreign></note> for, with them, the most able men were the most
<pb n="14"/>actively employed. No one exercised the mind independently of the body: every man of ability chose to act rather than narrate,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Chose to act rather than narrate] "For," as <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> says, " neither among those who are engaged in establishing a state, nor among those carrying on wars, nor among those who are curbed and restrained under the rule of kings, is the desire of distinction in eloquence wont to arise." Graswinckelius.</note> and was more desirous that his own merits should be celebrated by others, than that he himself should record theirs.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="9">
<p> Good morals, accordingly, were cultivated in the city and in the camp. There was the greatest possible concord, and the least possible avarice. Justice and probity prevailed among the citizens, not more from the influence of the laws than from natural inclination. They displayed animosity, enmity, and resentment only against the enemy. Citizens contended with citizens in nothing but honor. They were magnificent in their religious services, frugal in their families, and steady in their friendships.</p>
<p>By these two virtues, intrepidity in war, and equity in peace, they maintained themselves and their state. Of their exercise of which virtues, I consider these as the greatest proofs; that, in war, punishment was oftener inflicted on those who attacked an enemy contrary to orders, and who, when commanded to retreat, retired too slowly from the contest, than on those who had dared to desert their standards, or, when pressed by the enemy,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">IX. Pressed by the enemy] <quote lang="la">Pulsi.</quote> In the words <foreign lang="la">pulsi loco cedere ausi erant, loco</foreign> is to be joined, as Dietsch observes, with <foreign lang="la">cedere,</foreign> not, as Kritzius puts it, with <foreign lang="la">pulsi.</foreign> "To retreat," adds Dietsch, " is disgraceful only to those <foreign lang="la">qui ab hostibus se pelli patiantur,</foreign> who suffer themselves to be repulsed by the enemy."</note> to abandon their posts; and that, in peace, they governed more by conferring benefits than by exciting terror, and, when they received an injury, chose rather to pardon than to revenge it.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="10">
<p> But when, by perseverance and integrity, the republic had increased its power; when mighty princes had been vanquished in war;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">X. When mighty princes had been vanquished in war] Perses, Antiochus, Mithridates, Tigranes, and others.</note> when barbarous tribes and populous states had been reduced to subjection; when <placeName key="tgn,7016143">Carthage</placeName>, the rival of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>'s dominion, had been utterly destroyed, and sea and land lay <pb n="15"/>every where open to her sway, Fortune then began to exercise her tyranny, and to introduce universal innovation. To those who had easily endured toils, dangers, and doubtful and difficult circumstances, ease and wealth, the objects of desire to others, became a burden and a trouble. At first the love of money, and then that of power, began to prevail, and these became, as it were, the sources of every evil. For avarice subverted honesty, integrity, and other honorable principles, and, in their stead, inculcated pride, inhumanity, contempt of religion, and general venality. Ambition prompted many to become deceitful; to keep one thing concealed in the breast, and another ready on the tongue;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To keep one thing concealed in the breast, and another ready on the tongue] <quote lang="la">Aliud clausum in pectore, aliud in lingu&acirc; promptum, habere.</quote>
<quote><foreign lang="greek">*)exqro\s ga/r moi kei=nos o(mw=s *)ai+/dao pu/lh|sin</foreign><lb/>
<foreign lang="greek">*(\os x) e(/teron me\n keu/qei e)ni\ fresi\n, a)/llo de\ ba/zei.</foreign><lb/>
Il., ix. 313.</quote>
<quote>Who dares think one thing, and another tell,<lb/>
My heart detests him as the gates of hell. <placeName key="tgn,2000523">Pope</placeName>.</quote></note> to estimate friendships and enmities, not by their worth, but according to interest; and to carry rather a specious countenance than an honest heart. These vices at first advanced but slowly, and were sometimes restrained by correction; but afterward, when their infection had spread like a pestilence, the state was entirely changed, and the government, from being the most equitable and praiseworthy, became rapacious and insupportable.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="11">
<p> At first, however, it was ambition, rather than avarice,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XI. At first, however, it was ambition, rather than avarice, etc.] <quote lang="la">Sed prim&ograve; magis ambitio qu&agrave;m avaritia animos hominum exercebat.</quote> Sallust has been accused of having made, in this passage, an assertion at variance with what he had said before (c. 10), <foreign lang="la">Igitur prim&ograve; pecuni&aelig;, deinde imperii cupido, crevit,</foreign> and it will be hard to prove that the accusation is not just. Sir H. Steuart, indeed, endeavors to reconcile the passages by giving them the following "meaning," which, he says, "seems perfectly evident:" "Although avarice was the first to make its appearance at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, yet, after both had had existence, it was ambition that, of the two vices, laid the stronger hold on the minds of men, and more speedily grew to an inordinate height." To me, however, it "seems perfectly evident" that the Latin can be made to yield no such "meaning." How these passages agree," says Rupertus, " I do not understand; unless we suppose that Sallust, by the word <foreign lang="la">prim&ograve;</foreign> does not always signify order."</note> that influenced the minds of men; a vice which approaches nearer to virtue than the other. For of glory, honor, and power, the worthy is as desirous as the worthless; but the <pb n="16"/>one pursues them by just methods; the other, being destitute of honorable qualities, works with fraud and deceit. But avarice has merely money for its object, which no wise man has ever immoderately desired. It is a vice which, as if imbued with deadly poison, enervates whatever is manly in body or mind.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Enervates whatever is manly in body or mind] <quote lang="la">Corpus virilemque animum eff&aelig;minat.</quote> That avarice weakens the mind, is generally admitted. But how does it weaken the body ? The most satisfactory answer to this question is, in the opinion of Aulus Gellius (iii. 1), that that those who are intent on getting riches devote themselves to sedentary pursuits, as those of usurers and money-changers, neglecting all such exercises and employments as strengthen the body. There is, however, another explanation by Valerius Probus, given in the same chapter of Aulus Gellius, which perhaps is the true one; namely, that Sallust, by body and mind, intended merely to signify the whole man.</note> It is always unbounded and insatiable, and is abated neither by abundance nor by want.</p>
<p>But after Lucius Sylla, having recovered the government<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Having recovered the government] <quote lang="la">Recept&acirc; republic&acirc;.</quote> Having wrested it from the hands of Marius and his party.</note> by force of arms, proceeded, after a fair commencement, to a pernicious termination, all became robbers and plunderers;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">All became robbers and plunderers] <quote lang="la">Rapere omnes, trahere.</quote> He means that there was a general indulgence in plunder among Sylla's party, and among all who, in whatever character, could profit by supporting it. Thus he says immediately afterward, "neque modum neque modestiam <foreign lang="la">victores habere."</foreign></note> some set their affections on houses, others on lands; his victorious troops knew neither restraint nor moderation, but inflicted on the citizens disgraceful and inhuman outrages. Their rapacity was increased by the circumstance that Sylla, in order to secure the attachment of the forces which he had commanded in <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Which he had commanded in <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName>] <quote lang="la">Quem in Asi&acirc; ductaverat.</quote> I have here deserted Cortius, who gives <foreign lang="la">in Asiam,</foreign> "into <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName>," but this, as Bernouf justly observes, is incompatible with the frequentative verb <foreign lang="la">ductaverat.</foreign></note> had treated them, contrary to the practice of our ancestors, with extraordinary indulgence, and exemption from discipline; and pleasant and luxurious quarters had easily, during seasons of idleness, enervated the minds of the soldiery. Then the armies of the Roman people first became habituated to licentiousness and intemperance, and began to admire statues, pictures, and sculptured vases; to seize such objects alike in public edifices and private dwellings;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In public edifices and private dwellings] <quote lang="la">Privatim ac public&egrave;</quote> I have translated this according to the notion of Bernouf. Others, as Dietsch and Pappaur, consider <foreign lang="la">privatim</foreign> as signifying each on his own account, and <foreign lang="la">public&egrave;,</foreign> in the name of the Republic.</note> to spoil temples; and to cast off respect for every thing, sacred and profane. Such troops, accordingly, when once <pb n="17"/>they obtained the mastery, left nothing to be vanquished. Success unsettles the principles even of the wise, and scarcely would those of debauched habits use victory with moderation.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="12">
<p> When wealth was once considered an honor, and glory, authority, and power attended on it, virtue lost her influence, poverty was thought a disgrace, and a life of innocence was regarded as a life of ill-nature.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XII. A life of innocence was regarded as a life of ill-nature] <quote lang="la">Innocentia pro malivolenti&acirc; duci c&aelig;pit.</quote> "Whoever continued honest and upright, was considered by the unprincipled around him as their enemy; for a good man among the bad can never be regarded as of their party." Bernouf.</note> From the influence of riches, accordingly, luxury, avarice, and pride prevailed among the youth; they grew at once rapacious and prodigal; they undervalued what was their own, and coveted what was another's; they set at naught modesty and continence; they lost all distinction between sacred and profane, and threw off all consideration and self-restraint.</p>
<p>It furnishes much matter for reflection,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">It furnishes much matter for reflection] <quote lang="la">Oper&aelig; pretium est.</quote></note> after viewing our modern mansions and villas extended to the size of cities, to contemplate the temples which our ancestors, a most devout race of men, erected to the gods. But our forefathers adorned the fanes of the deities with devotion, and their homes with their own glory, and took nothing from those whom they conquered but the power of doing harm; their descendants, on the contrary, the basest of mankind,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Basest of mankind] <quote lang="la">Ignavissumi mortales.</quote> It is opposed to <foreign lang="la">fortissumi viri,</foreign> which follows, <foreign lang="la">"Qui nec fortiter nec bene quidquam fecere."</foreign>Cortius.</note> have even wrested from their allies, with the most flagrant injustice, whatever their brave and victorious ancestors had left to their vanquished enemies; as if the only use of power were to inflict injury.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="13">
<p> For why should I mention those displays of extravagance, which can be believed by none but those who have seen them; as that mountains have been leveled, and seas covered with edifices,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XIII. Seas covered with edifices] <quote lang="la">Maria constructa esse.</quote>
<quote lang="la"><l>Contracta pisces &aelig;quora sentiunt,</l>
<l>Jactis in altum molibus, etc. Hor. Od., iii.</l></quote>
<quote>----The haughty lord, who lays<lb/>
His deep foundations in the seas,<lb/>
And scorns earth's narrow bound;<lb/>
The fish affrighted feel their waves<lb/>
Contracted by his numerous slaves,<lb/>
Even in the vast profound. Francis.</quote></note> by many private citizens; men whom I consider <pb n="18"/>to have made a sport of their wealth,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To have made a sport of their wealth] <quote lang="la">Quibus mihi videntur ludibrio fuisse diviti&aelig;.</quote> "They spent their riches on objects which, in the judgment of men of sense, are ridiculous and contemptible." Cortius.</note> since they were impatient to squander disreputably what they might have enjoyed with honor.</p>
<p>But the love of irregular gratification, open debauchery, and all kinds of luxury,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Luxury] <quote lang="la">Cult&ucirc;s.</quote> "<foreign lang="la">Deliciarum in victu,</foreign> luxuries of the table; for we must be careful not to suppose that apparel is meant." Cortius.</note> had spread abroad with no less force. Men forgot their sex; women threw off all the restraints of modesty. To gratify appetite, they sought for every kind of production by land and by sea; they slept before there was any inclination for sleep; they no longer waited to feel hunger, thirst, cold,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Cold] <quote lang="la">Frigus.</quote> It is mentioned by Cortius that this word is wanting in one MS.; and the English reader may possibly wish that it were away altogether. Cortius refers it to cool places built of stone, sometimes underground, to which the luxurious retired in the hot weather; and he cites <placeName key="tgn,2119609">Pliny</placeName>, Ep., v. 6, who speaks of a <foreign lang="la">crytoporticus,</foreign> a gallery from which the sun was excluded, almost as if it were underground, and which even in summer was cold nearly to freezing. He also refers to Ambros., Epist. xii., and Casaubon. ad Spartian. <placeName key="tgn,2021876">Adrian</placeName>., c. x., p. 87.</note> or fatigue, but anticipated them all by luxurious indulgence. Such propensities drove the youth, when their patrimonies were exhausted, to criminal practices; for their minds, impregnated with evil habits, could not easily abstain from gratifying their passions, and were thus the more inordinately devoted in every way to rapacity and extravagance.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="14">
<p> In so populous and so corrupt a city, Catiline, as it was very easy to do, kept about him, like a body-guard, crowds of the unprincipled and desperate. For all those shameless, libertine, and profligate characters, who had dissipated their patrimonies by gaming,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XIV. Gaming] <quote lang="la">Manu.</quote> <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>, Dietsch, Kritzius, and all the recent editors, agree to interpret <foreign lang="la">manu</foreign> by gaming. </note> luxury, and sensuality; all who had contracted heavy debts, to purchase immunity for their crimes or offenses; all assassins<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Assassins] <quote lang="la">Parricid&aelig;.</quote> "Not only he who had killed his father was called a <foreign lang="la">parricide,</foreign> but he who had killed any man; as is evident from a law of Numa Pompilius: If any one unlawfully and knowingly bring a free man to death, let him be <foreign lang="la">a parricide.</foreign>" <foreign lang="la">Festus sub voce Parrici.</foreign></note> or sacrilegious persons from every quarter, convicted or dreading conviction for their evil deeds; all, besides, whom their tongue or their hand maintained by perjury or civil bloodshed; all, in fine, whom wickedness, poverty, or a guilty conscience disquieted, were the associates <pb n="19"/>and intimate friends of Catiline. And if any one, as yet of unblemished character, fell into his society, he was presently rendered, by daily intercourse and temptation, similar and equal to the rest. But it was the young whose acquaintance he chiefly courted; as their minds, ductile and unsettled from their age, were easily insnared by his stratagems. For as the passions of each, according to his years, appeared excited, he furnished mistresses to some, bought horses and dogs for others, and spared, in a word, neither his purse nor his character, if he could but make them his devoted and trustworthy supporters. There were some, I know, who thought that the youth, who frequented the house of Catiline, were guilty of crimes against nature; but this report arose rather from other causes than from any evidence of the fact.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Than from any evidence of the fact] <quote lang="la">Qu&agrave;m qu&ograve;d cuiquam id compertum foret.</quote></note></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="15">
<p> Catiline, in his youth, had been guilty of many criminal connections, with a virgin of noble birth,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XV. With a virgin of noble birth] <quote lang="la">Cum virgine nobili.</quote> Who this was is not known. The name may have been suppressed from respect to her family. If what is found in a fragment of <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName> be true, Catiline had an illicit connection with some female, and afterward married the daughter who was the fruit of the connection: <foreign lang="la">Ex eodem stupro et uxorem et filiam invenisti;</foreign> Orat. in Tog. Cand. (Oration xvi., Ernesti's edit.) On which words Asconius Pedianus makes this comment: <foreign lang="la">"Dicitur Catilinam adulterium commisisse cum e&acirc; qu&aelig; ei postea socrus fuit, et ex eo stupro duxisse uxorem, c&ugrave;m filia ejus esset. H&aelig;c Lucceius quoque Catilin&aelig; objecit in orationibus, quas in eum scripsit. Nomina harum mulierum nondum inveni."</foreign> Plutarch, too (Life of <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName>, c. 10), says that Catiline was accused of having corrupted his own daughter.</note> with a priestess of <placeName key="tgn,1016295">Vesta</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">With a priestess of <placeName key="tgn,1016295">Vesta</placeName>] <quote lang="la">Cum sacerdote Vest&aelig;.</quote> This priestess of <placeName key="tgn,1016295">Vesta</placeName> was Fabia Terentia, sister to Terentia, <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName>'s wife, whom Sallust, after she was divorced by <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName>, married. Clodius accused her, but she was acquitted, either because she was thought innocent, or because the interest of Catulus and others, who exerted themselves in her favor, procured her acquittal. See Orosius, vi. 3; the Oration of <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName>, quoted in the preceding note; and Asconius's commentary on it.</note> and of many other offenses of this nature, in defiance alike of law and religion. At last, when he was smitten with a passion for Aurelia Orestilla,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Aurelia Orestilla] See c. 35. She was the sister or daughter, as De Brosses thinks, of Cneius Aurelius Orestis, who had been pr&aelig;tor, A.U.C. 677.</note> in whom no good man, at any time of her life, commended any thing but her beauty, it is confidently believed that because she hesitated to marry him, from the dread of having a grown-up step-son,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A grown-up step-son] <quote lang="la">Privignum adult&acirc; &aelig;tate.</quote> A son of Catiline's by a former marriage.</note> he cleared the <pb n="20"/>house for their nuptials by putting his son to death. And this crime appears to me to have been the chief cause of hurrying forward the conspiracy. For his guilty mind, at peace with neither gods nor men, found no comfort either waking or sleeping; so effectually did conscience desolate his tortured spirit.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Desolate his tortured spirit] <quote lang="la">Mentem exciteam vastabat.</quote> "Conscience desolates the mind, when it deprives it of its proper power and tranquillity, and introduces into it perpetual disquietude." Cortius. Many editions have <foreign lang="la">vexabat.</foreign></note> His complexion, in consequence, was pale, his eyes haggard, his walk sometimes quick and sometimes slow, and distraction was plainly apparent in every feature and look.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="16">
<p> The young men, whom, as I said before, he had enticed to join him, he initiated, by various methods, in evil practices. From among them he furnished false witnesses,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XVI. He furnished false witnesses, etc.] <quote lang="la">Testis signatoresque falsos commodare.</quote> "If any one wanted any such character, Catiline was ready to supply him from among his troop." Bernouf.</note> and forgers of signatures; and he taught them all to regard, with equal unconcern, honor, property, and danger. At length, when he had stripped them of all character and shame, he led them to other and greater enormities. If a motive for crime did not readily occur, he incited them, nevertheless, to circumvent and murder inoffensive persons,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Inoffensive persons, etc.] <quote lang="la">Insontes, sicuti sontes.</quote> Most translators have rendered these words " innocent" and " guilty," terms which suggest nothing satisfactory to the English reader. The <foreign lang="la">insontes</foreign> are those who had given Catiline no cause of offense; the <foreign lang="la">sontes</foreign> those who had in some way incurred his displeasure, or become objects of his rapacity.</note> just as if they had injured him; for, lest their hand or heart should grow torpid for want of employment, he chose to be gratuitously wicked and cruel.</p>
<p>Depending on such accomplices and adherents, and knowing that the load of debt was every where great, and that the veterans of Sylla,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Veterans of Sylla, etc.] Elsewhere called the colonists of Sylla; men to whom Sylla had given large tracts of land as rewards for their services, but who, having lived extravagantly, had fallen into such debt and distress, that, as <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName> said, nothing could relieve them but the resurrection of Sylla from the dead. Cic. ii. Orat. in Cat.</note> having spent their money too liberally, and remembering their spoils and former victory, were longing for a civil war, Catiline formed the design of overthrowing the government. There was no army in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; Pompey was fighting in a distant part of the world;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Pompey was fighting in a distant part of the world] <quote lang="la">In extremis terris.</quote> Pompey was then conducting the war against Mithridates and Tigranes, in <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7006651">Armenia</placeName>.</note> he himself had great hopes of <pb n="21"/>obtaining the consulship; the senate was wholly off its guard ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The senate was wholly off its guard] <quote lang="la">Senatus nihil sane intentus.</quote> The senate was regardless, and unsuspicious of any danger.</note> every thing was quiet and tranquil; and all these circumstances were exceedingly favorable for Catiline.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="17">
<p> Accordingly, about the beginning of June, in the consulship of Lucius C&aelig;sar<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XVII. Lucius C&aelig;sar] He was a relation of Julius C&aelig;sar; and his sister was the wife of M. Antonius, the orator, and mother of Mark Antony, the triumvir.</note> and Caius Figulus, he at first addressed each of his accomplices separately, encouraged some, and sounded others, and informed them of his own resources, of the unprepared condition of the state, and of the great prizes to be expected from the conspiracy. When he had ascertained, to his satisfaction, all that he required, he summoned all whose necessities were the most urgent, and whose spirits were the most daring, to a general conference.</p>
<p>At that meeting there were present, of senatorial rank, Publius Lentulus <placeName key="perseus,Sura">Sura</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Publius Lentulus Sura] He was of the same family with Sylla, that of the Cornelii. He had filled the office of consul, but his conduct had been afterward so profligate, that the censors expelled him from the senate. To enable him to resume his seat, he had obtained, as a qualification, the office of pr&aelig;tor, which he held at the time of the conspiracy. He was called Sura, because, when he had squandered the public money in his qu&aelig;storship, and was called to account by Sylla for his dishonesty, he declined to make any defense, but said, " I present you the calf of my leg (<foreign lang="la">sura</foreign>) ;" alluding to a custom among boys playing at ball, of inflicting a certain number of strokes on the leg of an unsuccessful player. Plutarch, Life of <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, c. 17.</note> Publius Autronius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Publius Autronius] He had been a companion of <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> in his boyhood, and his colleague in the qu&aelig;storship. He was banished in the year after the conspiracy, together with Cassius, L&aelig;ca, Vargunteius, Servius Sylla, and Caius Cornelius, under the Plautian law. De Brosses.</note> Lucius Cassius Longinus,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Lucius Cassius Longinus] He had been a competitor with Cicero for the consulship. Ascon. Ped. in Cic. Orat. in Tog. Cand. His corpulence was such that Cassius's fat (<foreign lang="la">Cassii adeps</foreign>) became proverbial. Cic. Orat. in Catil., iii. 7.</note> Caius Cethegus,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Caius Cethegus] He also was one of the Cornelian family. In the civil wars, says De Brosses, he had first taken the side of Marius, and afterward that of Sylla. Both Cicero (Orat. in Catil., ii. 7) and Sallust describe him as fiery and rash.</note> Publius and Servius Sylla<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Publius and Servius Sylla] These were nephews of Sylla the dictator. Publius, though present on this occasion seems not to have joined in the plot, since, when he was afterward accused of having been a conspirator, he was defended by Cicero and acquitted. See Cic. Orat. pro P. Syll&acirc;. He was afterward with C&aelig;sar in the battle of <placeName key="tgn,2578319">Pharsalia</placeName>. C&aelig;s. de B. C., iii. 89.</note> the sons <pb n="22"/>of Servius Sylla, Lucius Vargunteius<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Lucius Vargunteius] " Of him or his family little is known. He had been, before this period, accused of bribery, and defended by Hortensius. Cic. pro P. Syll&acirc;, c. 2." Bernouf.</note> Quintus Annius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Quintus Annius] He is thought by De Brosses to have been the same Annius that cut off the head of M. Antonius the orator, and carried it to Marius. Plutarch, Vit. Marii, c. 44.</note> Marcus Porcius L&aelig;ca,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Marcus Porcius L&aelig;ca] He was one of the same <foreign lang="la">gens</foreign> with the Catones, but of a different family.</note> Lucius Bestia,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Lucius Bestia] Of the Calpurnian <foreign lang="la">gens.</foreign> He escaped death on the discovery of the conspiracy, and was afterward &aelig;dile, and candidate for the pr&aelig;torship, but was driven into exile for bribery. Being recalled by C&aelig;sar, he became candidate for the consulship, but was unsuccessful. De Brosses.</note> Quintus Curius;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Quintus Curius] He was a descendant of M. Curius Dentatus, the opponent of Pyrrhus. He was so notorious as a gamester and a profligate, that he was removed from the senate, A.U.C. 683. See c. 23. As he had been the first to give information of the conspiracy to <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, public honors were decreed him, but he was deprived of them by the influence of C&aelig;sar, whom he had named as one of the conspirators. Sueton. C&aelig;s. 17; Appian. De Bell. Civ., lib. ii.</note> and, of the equestrian order, Marcus Fulvius Nobilior,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">M. Fulvius Nobilior] " He was not put to death, but exiled, A.U.C. 699. Cic. ad Att. iv., 16." Bernouf;</note> Lucius Statilius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Lucius Statilius] of him nothing more is known than is told by Sallust.</note> Publius Gabinius Capito,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Publius Gabinius Capito] <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, instead of <placeName key="tgn,2038075">Capito</placeName>, calls him Cimber. Orat. in Cat., iii. 3. The family was originally from Gabii.</note> Caius Cornelius ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Caius Cornelius) There were two branches of the <foreign lang="la">gens Cornelia,</foreign> one patrician, the other plebeian, from which sprung this conspirator.</note> with many from the colonies and municipal towns,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Municipal towns] <quote lang="la">Municipiis.</quote> The <foreign lang="la">municipia</foreign> were towns of which the inhabitants were admitted to the rights of Roman citizens, but which were allowed to govern themselves by their own laws, and to choose their own magistrates. See Aul. Gell., xvi. 13; <placeName key="tgn,7013368">Beaufort</placeName>, Rep. Rom., vol. v." Bernouf.</note>
 persons of consequence in their own localities. There were many others, too, among the nobility, concerned in the plot, but less openly; men whom the hope of power, rather than poverty or any other exigence, prompted to join in the affair. But most of the young men, and especially the sons of the nobility, favored the schemes of Catiline; they who had abundant means of living at ease, either splendidly or voluptuously, preferred uncertainties to certainties, war to peace. There were some, also, at that time, who believed that Marcus Licinius Crassus<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Marcus Licinius Crassus] The same who, with Pompey and C&aelig;sar, formed the first triumvirate, and who was afterward killed in his expedition against the Parthians. He had, before the time of the conspiracy, held the offices of pr&aelig;tor and consul.</note> was not unacquainted with the conspiracy; because Cneius Pompey, whom he hated, was <pb n="23"/>at the head of a large army, and he was willing that the power of any one whomsoever should raise itself against Pompey's influence; trusting, at the same time, that if the plot should succeed, he would easily place himself at the head of the conspirators.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="18">
<p> But previously<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XVIII. But previously, etc.] Sallust here makes a digression, to give an account of a conspiracy that was formed three years before that of Catiline.</note> to this period, a small number of persons, among whom was Catiline, had formed a design against the state: of which affair I shall here give as accurate account as I am able.</p>
<p>Under the consulship of Lucius Tullus and Marcus Lepidus, Publius Autronius and Publius Sylla,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Publius Autronius and Publius Sylla] The same who are mentioned in the preceding chapter. They were consuls elect, and some editions have the words <foreign lang="la">designati consoles</foreign> immediately following their names.</note> having been tried for bribery under the laws against it,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Having been tried for bribery under the laws against it] <quote lang="la">Legibus ambit&ucirc;s interrogati.</quote> Bribery at their election, is the meaning of the word <foreign lang="la">ambitus,</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">ambire,</foreign> as Cortius observes, is <foreign lang="la">circumeundo favorem et suffragia qu&aelig;rere.</foreign> De Brosses translates the passage thus: <foreign lang="fr">"Autrone et Sylla, convaincus d'avoir obtenu le consulat par corruption des suffrages, avaient &eacute;t&eacute; punis selon la rigueur de la loi."</foreign> There were several very severe Roman laws against bribery. Autronius and Sylla were both excluded from the consulship.</note> had paid the penalty of the offense. Shortly after Catiline, being brought to trial for extortion,<note anchored="yes" place="foot"> For extortion] <quote lang="la">Pecuniarum repetundarum.</quote> Catiline had been pr&aelig;tor in <placeName key="tgn,2078153">Africa</placeName> and, at the expiration of his office, was accused of extortion by Publius Clodius, on the part of the Africans. He escaped by bribing the prosecutor and judges.</note> had been prevented from standing for the consulship, because he had been unable to declare himself a candidate within the legitimate number of days.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To declare himself a candidate within the legitimate number of days] <quote lang="la">Prohibitus erat consulatum petere, qu&ograve;d intra legitimos dies profiteri</quote> (<foreign lang="la">se candidatum,</foreign> says Cortius, citing Suet. Aug. 4) <foreign lang="la">nequiverit.</foreign> A person could not be a candidate for the consulship, unless he could declare himself free from accusation within a certain number of days before the time of holding the <foreign lang="la">comitia centuriata.</foreign> That number of days was <foreign lang="la">trinundinum spatium,</foreign> that is, the time occupied by three market-days, <foreign lang="la">tres nundin&aelig;</foreign> with seven days intervening between the first and second, and between the second and third; or seventeen days. The <foreign lang="la">nundin&aelig;</foreign> (from <foreign lang="la">novem</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">dies</foreign>) were held, as it is commonly expressed, every ninth day; whence Cortius and others considered <foreign lang="la">trinundinum spatium</foreign> to be twenty-seven, or even thirty days; but this way of reckoning was not that of the Romans, who made the last day of <emph>the first ennead</emph> to be also the first day of the second. Concerning the <foreign lang="la">nundin&aelig;</foreign> see Macrob. Sat. i. 16. " M&uuml;ller and Longius most erroneously supposed the <foreign lang="la">trinundinum</foreign> to be about thirty days; for that it embraced only seventeen days has been fully shown by Ernesti, Clav. Cic., sub voce ; by <placeName key="tgn,2030080">Scheller</placeName> in Lex. Ampl., p. 11, 669 ; by Nitschius Antiquitt. Romm. i. p. 623; and by Drachenborch (cited by <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>) ad Liv. iii. 35." Kritzius. </note> There was at that time, <pb n="24"/>too, a young patrician of the most daring spirit, needy and discontented, named Cneius <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Cneius <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName>] Of the Calpurnian <foreign lang="la">gens.</foreign> Suetonius (Vit. C&aelig;s., c. 9) mentions three authors who related that Crassus and C&aelig;sar were both concerned in this plot; and that, if it had succeeded, Crassus was to have assumed the dictatorship, and made C&aelig;sar his master of the horse. The conspiracy, as these writers state, failed through the remorse or irresolution of Crassus.</note> whom poverty and vicious principles instigated to disturb the government. Catiline and Autronius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Catiline and Autronius] After these two names, in Havercamp's and many other editions, follow the words <quote lang="la">circiter nonas Decembres,</quote> i.e., about the fifth of December.</note> having concerted measures with this Piso, prepared to assassinate the consuls, Lucius Cotta and Lucius Torquatus, in the Capitol, on the first of January,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">On the first of January] <quote lang="la">Kalendis Januariis.</quote> On this day the consuls were accustomed to enter on their office. The consuls whom they were going to kill, Cotta and Torquatus, were those who had been chosen in the place of Autronius and Sylla.</note> when they, having seized on the fasces, were to send Piso with an army to take possession of the two <placeName key="tgn,2683006">Spains</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The two <placeName key="tgn,2683006">Spains</placeName>] Hither and Thither Spain. <quote lang="la">Hispania Citerior</quote> and <quote lang="la">Ulterior,</quote> as they were called by the Romans.</note> But their design being discovered, they postponed the assassination to the fifth of February; when they meditated the destruction, not of the consuls only, but of most of the senate. And had not Catiline, who was in front of the senate-house, been too hasty to give the singal to his associates, there would that day have been perpetrated the most atrocious outrage since the city of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> was founded. But as the armed conspirators had not yet assembled in sufficient numbers, the want of force frustrated the design.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="19">
<p> Some time afterward, <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName> was sent as qu&aelig;stor, with Pr&aelig;torian authority, into Hither Spain; Crassus promoting the appointment, because he knew him to be a bitter enemy to Cneius Pompey. Nor were the senate, indeed, unwilling<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XIX. Nor were the senate, indeed, unwilling, etc.] See Dio Cass. xxxvi. 27.</note> to grant him the province; for they wished so infamous a character to be removed from the seat of government; and many worthy men, at the same time, thought that there was some security in him against the power of Pompey, which was then becoming formidable. But this <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName>, on his march toward his province, was murdered by some Spanish cavalry whom he had in his army. These barbarians, as some say, had been unable <pb n="25"/>to endure his unjust, haughty, and cruel orders; but others assert that this body of cavalry, being old and trusty adherents of Pompey, attacked <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName> at his instigation; since the Spaniards, they observed, had never before committed such an outrage, but had patiently submitted to many severe commands. This question we shall leave undecided. Of the first conspiracy enough has been said.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="20">
<p> When Catiline saw those, whom I have just above mentioned,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XX. Just above mentioned] In c. 17.</note> assembled, though he had often discussed many points with them singly, yet thinking it would be to his purpose to address and exhort them in a body, retired with them into a private apartment of his house, where, when all witnesses were withdrawn, he harangued them to the following effect:</p>
<p>" If your courage and fidelity had not been sufficiently proved by me, this favorable opportunity<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Favorable opportunity] <quote lang="la">Opportuna res.</quote> See the latter part of c. 16.</note> would have occurred to no purpose; mighty hopes, absolute power, would in vain be within our grasp; nor should I, depending on irresolution or ficklemindedness, pursue contingencies instead of certainties. But as I have, on many remarkable occasions, experienced your bravery and attachment to me, I have ventured to engage in a most important and glorious enterprise. I am aware, too, that whatever advantages or evils affect you, the same affect me; and to have the same desires and the same aversions, is assuredly a firm bond of friendship.</p>
<p>"What I have been meditating you have already heard separately. But my ardor for action is daily more and more excited, when I consider what our future condition of life must be, unless we ourselves assert our claims to liberty.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Assert our claims to liberty] <quote lang="la">Nosmet ipsi vindicamus in libertatem.</quote> Unless we vindicate ourselves into liberty. See below,<foreign lang="la">"En illa, illa, quam s&aelig;pe opt&acirc;stis, libertas,"</foreign> etc.</note> For since the government has fallen under the power and jurisdiction of a few, kings and princes<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Kings and princes] <quote lang="la">Reges tetrarch&aelig;.</quote> Tetrarchs were properly those who had the government of the fourth part of the country; but at length, the signification of the word being extended, it was applied to any governors of any country who were possessed of supreme authority, and yet were not acknowledged as kings by the Romans. See Hirt. Bell. <placeName key="tgn,2082772">Alex</placeName>. c. 67: Deiotarus, at that time tetrarch of almost all Gallogr&aelig;cia, a supremacy which the other tetrarchs would not allow to be granted him either by the laws or by custom, but indisputably acknowledged as king of Armenia Minor by the senate," etc. Dietsch. "<placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,2578489">Phil</placeName>. II., speaks of Reges Tetrarchas Dynastasque. And Lucan has (vii. 46) Tretrarch&aelig; regesque tenent, magnique tyranni." Wasse. <placeName key="tgn,2032226">Horace</placeName> also says,
<quote lang="la"><l>---- Modo reges atque tetrarchas,</l>
<l>Omnia magna loquens.</l></quote>
I have, with Rose, rendered the word <foreign lang="la">princes,</foreign> as being the most eligible term.
</note> have constantly been their tributaries; <pb n="26"/>nations and states have paid them taxes; but all the rest of us, however brave and worthy, whether noble or plebeian, have been regarded as a mere mob, without interest or authority, and subject to those, to whom, if the state were in a sound condition, we should be a terror. Hence, all influence, power, honor, and wealth, are in their hands, or where they dispose of them; to us they have left only insults,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Insults] <quote lang="la">Repulsas.</quote> Repulses in standing for office.</note> dangers, persecutions, and poverty. To such indignities, O bravest of men, how long will you submit? Is it not better to die in a glorious attempt, than, after having been the sport of other men's insolence, to resign a wretched and degraded existence with ignominy?</p>
<p>"But success (I call gods and men to witness!) is in our own hands. Our years are fresh, our spirit is unbroken; among our oppressors, on the contrary, through age and wealth a general debility has been produced. We have therefore only to make a beginning; the course of events<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The course of events, etc.] <quote lang="la">C&aelig;tera res expediet.</quote>--" Of. Cic. Ep. Div. xiii. 26: <foreign lang="la">explicare et expedire negotia.</foreign>" <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>.</note> will accomplish the rest.</p>
<p>"Who in the world, indeed, that has the feelings of a man, can endure that they should have a superfluity of riches, to squander in building over seas<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Building over seas] See c. 13.</note> and leveling mountains, and that means should be wanting to us even for the necessaries of life; that they should join together two houses or more, and and that we should not have a hearth to call our own ? They, though they purchase pictures, statues, and embossed plate ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Embossed plate] <quote lang="la">Toreumata.</quote> The same as <foreign lang="la">vasa c&aelig;lata,</foreign> sculptured vases, c. 11. Vessels ornamented in bas-relief; from <foreign lang="greek">toreu/ein,</foreign> <foreign lang="la">scuolere;</foreign> see <placeName key="tgn,1013077">Bentley</placeName> ad Hor. A. P., 441. <foreign lang="la">"Perbona toreumata, in his pocula duo,"</foreign> etc. Cic. in Verr. iv. 18.</note> though they pull down new buildings and erect others, and lavish and abuse their wealth in every possible method, yet can not, with the utmost efforts of caprice, exhaust it. But for us there is poverty at home, debts abroad; our present circumstances <pb n="27"/>are bad, our prospects much worse; and what, in a word, have we left, but a miserable existence ?</p>
<p>"Will you not, then, awake to action? Behold that liberty, that liberty for which you have so often wished, with wealth, honor, and glory, are set before your eyes. All these prizes fortune offers to the victorious. Let the enterprise itself, then, let the opportunity, let your poverty, your dangers, and the glorious spoils of war, animate you far more than my words. Use me either as your leader or your fellow-soldier; neither my heart nor my hand shall be wanting to you. These objects I hope to effect, in concert with you, in the character of consul; unless, iudeed, my expectation deceives me, and you prefer to be slaves rather than masters."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="21">
<p> When these men, surrounded with numberless evils, but without any resources or hopes of good, had heard this address, though they thought it much for their advantage to disturb the public tranquillity, yet most of them called on Catiline to state on what terms they were to engage in the contest; what benefits they were to expect from taking up arms; and what support and encouragement they had, and in what quarters.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXI. What support or encouragement they had, and in what quarters] <quote lang="la">Quid ubique opis aut spei haberent;</quote> i.e. <quote lang="la">quid opis aut spei, et ubi, haberent.</quote> So c. 27, init. <foreign lang="la">Quem ubique opportunum credebat,</foreign> i.e., says Cortius, <foreign lang="la">"quem, et ubi illum, opportunum credebat."</foreign></note> Catiline then promised them the abolition of their debts;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Abolition of their debts] <quote lang="la">Tabulas novas.</quote> Debts were registered on tablets; and, when the debts were paid, the score was effaced, and the tablets were ready to be used <emph>as new.</emph> See Ernesti's Clav. in Cic. <foreign lang="la">sub voce.</foreign>
</note> a proscription of the wealthy citizens;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Proscription of the wealthy citizens] <quote lang="la">Proscriptionem locupletium.</quote> The practice of proscription was commenced by Sylla, who posted up, in public places of the city, the names of those whom he doomed to death, offering rewards to such as should bring him their heads. Their money and estates he divided among his adherents, and Catiline excited his adherents with hopes of similar plunder.
</note> offices, sacerdotal dignities, plunder, and all other gratifications which war, and the license of conquerors, can afford. He added that <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName> was in Hither Spain, and Publius Sittius Nucerinus with an army in <placeName key="tgn,1000176">Mauritania</placeName>, both of whom were privy to his plans; that Caius Antonius, whom he hoped to have for a colleague, was canvassing for the consulship, a man with whom he was intimate, and who was involved in all manner of embarrassments; and that, in conjunction with him, he himself, when consul, would commence operations. He, moreover, assailed <pb n="28"/>all the respectable citizens with reproaches, commended each of his associates by name, reminded one of his poverty, another of his ruling passion,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Another of his ruling passion] <quote lang="la">Admonebat--alium cupiditatis sec&aelig;.</quote> Rose renders this passage, " Some he put in mind of their poverty, others of their amours." De Brosses renders it, <foreign lang="fr">"Il remontre &agrave; l'un sa pauvret&eacute;, &agrave; l'autre son ambition."</foreign> Ruling passion, however, seems to be the proper sense of <foreign lang="la">cupiditatis;</foreign> as it is said, in c. 14, " As the passions of each, according to his years, appeared excited, he furnished mistresses to some, bought horses and dogs for others," etc.
</note> several others of their danger or disgrace, and many of the spoils which they had obtained by the victory of Sylla. When he saw their spirits sufficiently elevated, he charged them to attend to his interest at the election of consuls, and dismissed the assembly.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="22">
<p> There were some, at that time, who said that Catiline, having ended his speech, and wishing to bind his accomplices in guilt by an oath, handed round among them, in goblets, the blood of a human body mixed with wine; and that when all, after an imprecation, had tasted of it, as is usual in sacred rites, he disclosed his design; and they asserted<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXII. They asserted] <quote lang="la">Dictitare.</quote> In referring this word to the circulators of the report, I follow Cortius, <placeName key="tgn,2083270">Gerlach</placeName>, Kritzius, and Bernouf. Wasse, with less discrimination, refers it to Catiline. This story of the drinking of human blood is copied by Florus, iv. 1, and by Plutarch in his Life of <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>. Dio Cassius (lib. xxxvii.) says that the conspirators were reported to have killed a child on the occasion.</note> that he did this, in order that they might be the more closely attached to one another, by being mutually conscious of such an atrocity. But so some thought that this report, and many others, were invented by persons who supposed that the odium against <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, which afterward arose, might be lessened by imputing an enormity of guilt to the conspirators who had suffered death. The evidence which I have obtained, in support of this charge, is not at all in proportion to its magnitude.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="23">
<p> Among those present at this meeting was Quintus Curius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXIII. Quintus Curius] The same that is mentioned in c. 17.</note> a man of no mean family, but immersed in vices and crimes, and whom the censors had ignominiously expelled from the senate. In this person there was not less levity than impudence; he could neither keep secret what he heard, nor conceal his own crimes; he was altogether heedless what he said or what he did. He had long had a criminal intercourse with Fulvia, a woman of high birth; but growing less acceptable to her, because, in his reduced circumstances, he had less means <pb n="29"/>of being liberal, he began, on a sudden, to boast, and to promise her seas and mountains;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To promise her seas and mountains] <quote lang="la">Maria montesque polliceri.</quote> A proverbial expression. Ter. Phorm., i. 2, 18: <foreign lang="la">Mod&ograve; non montes auri pollicens.</foreign> Pers., iii. 65: <foreign lang="la">Et quid opus Cratero magnos promittere emontes.</foreign></note> threatening her, at times, with the sword, if she were not submissive to his will; and acting, in his general conduct, with greater arrogance than ever.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">With greater arrogance than ever] <quote lang="la">Feroci&ugrave;s qu&agrave;m solitus erat.</quote></note> Fulvia, having learned the cause of his extravagant behavior, did not keep such danger to the state a secret; but, without naming her informant, communicated to several persons what she had heard and under what circumstances, concerning Catiline's conspiracy. This intelligence it was that incited the feelings of the citizens to give the consulship to Marcus Tullius <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To Marcus Tullius Cicero] Cicero was now in his forty-third year, and had filled the office of qu&aelig;stor, edile, and pr&aelig;tor.</note> For before this period, most of the nobility were moved with jealousy, and thought the consulship in some degree sullied, if a man of no family,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A man of no family] <quote lang="la">Novus homo.</quote> A term applied to such as could not boast of any ancestor that had held any curule magistracy, that is, had been consul, pr&aelig;tor, censor, or chief edile.</note> however meritorious, obtained it. But when danger showed itself, envy and pride were laid aside.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="24">
<p> Accordingly, when the comitia were held, Marcus Tullius and Caius Antonius were declared consuls; an event which gave the first shock to the conspirators. The ardor of Catiline, however, was not at all diminished; he formed every day new schemes; he deposited arms, in convenient places, throughout <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; he sent sums of money borrowed on his own credit, or that of his friends, to a certain <placeName key="tgn,7013995">Manlius</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXIV. <placeName key="tgn,7013995">Manlius</placeName>] He had been an officer in the army of Sylla, and, having been distinguished for his services, had been placed at the head of a colony of veterans settled about F&aelig;sul&aelig;; but he had squandered his property in extravagance. See Plutarch, Vit. Cic., Dio Cassius, and Appian.</note> at F&aelig;sul&aelig;,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">F&aelig;sul&aelig;] A town of Etruria, at the foot of the Appennines, not far from Florence. It is the Fesole of Milton:
<quote>At evening from the top of Fesole,
<lb/>Or in Valdarno to desery new lands, etc. Par. L. i. 289.</quote>
</note> who was subsequently the first to engage in hostilities. At this period, too, he is said to have attached to his cause great numbers of men of all classes, and some women, who had, in their earlier days, supported an expensive life by the price of their beauty, but who, when age had lessened their gains but not their extravagance, had contracted heavy debts. By the influence <pb n="30"/>of these females, Catiline hoped to gain over the slaves in Rome, to get the city set on fire, and either to secure the support of their husbands or take away their lives.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="25">
<p> In the number of those ladies was Sempronia,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXV. Sempronia] Of the same <foreign lang="la">gens</foreign> as the two Gracchi. She was the wife of Decimus Brutus.</note> a woman who had committed many crimes with the spirit of a man. In birth and beauty, in her husband and her children, she was extremely fortunate; she was skilled in Greek and Roman literature; she could sing, play, and dance,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Sing, play, and dance] <quote lang="la">Psallere, saltare.</quote> As <foreign lang="la">psallo</foreign> signifies both to play on a musical instrument, and to sing to it while playing, I have thought it necessary to give both senses in the translation.</note> with greater elegance than became a woman of virtue, and possessed many other accomplishments that tend to excite the passions. But nothing was ever less valued by her than honor or chastity. Whether she was more prodigal of her money or her reputation, it would have been difficult to decide. Her desires were so ardent that she oftener made advances to the other sex than waited for solicitation. She had frequently, before this period, forfeited her word, forsworn debts, been privy to murder, and hurried into the utmost excesses by her extravagance and poverty. But her abilities were by no means despicable;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">By no means despicable] <quote lang="la">Haud absurdum.</quote> Compare, <foreign lang="la">Bene dicere haud absurdum est,</foreign> c. 3.</note> she could compose verses, jest, and join in conversation either modest, tender, or licentious. In a word, she was distinguished<note anchored="yes" place="foot">She was distinguished, etc.] <quote lang="la">Mult&aelig; faceti&aelig;, multusque lepos inerat.</quote> Both <foreign lang="la">faceti&aelig;</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">lepos</foreign> mean "agreeableness, humor, pleasantry;" but <foreign lang="la">lepos</foreign> here seems to refer to diction, as in Cic. Orat. i. 7: <foreign lang="la">Magnus in jocando lepos.</foreign></note> by much refinement of wit, and much grace of expression.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="26">
<p> Catiline, having made these arrangements, still canvassed for the consulship for the following year; hoping that, if he should be elected, he would easily manage Antonius according to his pleasure. Nor did he, in the mean time remain inactive, but devised schemes, in every possible way, against Cicero, who, however, did not want skill or policy to guard against them. For, at the very beginning of his consulship, he had, by making many promises through Fulvia, prevailed on Quintus Curius, whom I have already mentioned, to give him secret information of Catiline's proceedings. He had also persuaded his colleague, Antonius, by an arrangement respecting <pb n="31"/>their provinces,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXVI. By an arrangement respecting their provinces] <quote lang="la">Pactione provinci&aelig;.</quote> This passage has been absurdly misrepresented by most translators, except De Brosses. Even Rose, who was a scholar, translated <foreign lang="la">pactione provinci&aelig;,</foreign> "by promising a province to his colleague." Plutarch, in his Life of Cicero, says that the two provinces, which Cicero and his colleague Antonius shared between them, were Gaul and Macedonia, and that Cicero, in order to retain Antonius in the interest of the senate, exchanged with him Macedonia, which had fallen to himself, for the inferior province of Gaul. See Jug., c. 27.</note> to entertain no sentiment of disaffection toward the state; and he kept around him, though without ostentation, a guard of his friends and dependents.</p>
<p>When the day of the comitia came, and neither Catiline's efforts for the consulship, nor the plots which he had laid for the consuls in the Campus Martius,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Plots which he had laid for the consuls in the Campus Martius] <quote lang="la">Insidi&aelig; quas consuli in campo fecerat.</quote> I have here departed from the text of Cortius, who reads <foreign lang="la">consulibus,</foreign> thinking that Catiline, in his rage, might have extended his plots even to the consuls-elect. But <foreign lang="la">consuli,</foreign> there is little doubt, is the right reading, as it is favored by what is said at the beginning of the chapter, <foreign lang="la">insidias parabat Ciceroni,</foreign> by what follows in the next chapter, <foreign lang="la">consuli insidias tendere,</foreign> and by the words, <foreign lang="la">sperans, si designatus foret, facil&egrave; se ex voluntate Antonio usurum;</foreign> for if Catiline trusted that he should be able to use his pleasure with Antonius, he could hardly think it necessary to form plots against his life. I have De Brosses on my side, who translates the phrase, <foreign lang="fr">les pi&egrave;ges o&ugrave; il comptait faire p&egrave;rir le consul.</foreign> The words <foreign lang="la">in campo,</foreign>  which look extremely like an intruded gloss, I wonder that Cortius should have retained. " <foreign lang="la">Consuli</foreign> ," says Gerlach, "appears the more eligible, not only on account of <foreign lang="la">consuli insidias tendere,</foreign> c. 27, but because nothing but the death of Cicero was necessary to make everything favorable for Catiline." Kritzius, Bernouf, Dietsch, Pappaur, Allen, and all the modern editors, read <foreign lang="la">Consuli.</foreign> See also the end of c. 27: <foreign lang="la">Si pri&ugrave;s Ciceronem oppressisset.</foreign>
</note> were attended with success, he determined to proceed to war, and resort to the utmost extremities, since what he had attempted secretly had ended in confusion and disgrace.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Had ended in confusion and disgrace] <quote lang="la">Aspera f&aelig;daque evenerant.</quote> I have borrowed from Murphy.</note></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="27">
<p> He accordingly dispatched Caius Manlius to F&aelig;sul&aelig;, and the adjacent parts of Etruria; one Septimius, of Camerinum,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXVI. Of Camnerinum] Camertem. "' That is, a native of Camerinum, a town on the confines of Umbria and Picenum. Hence the noun <foreign lang="la">Camers,</foreign> as Cic. Pro. Syll., c. 19, <foreign lang="la">in agro Camerti.</foreign>" Cortius.</note> into the Picenian territory; Caius Julius into Apulia; and others to various places, wherever he thought each would be most serviceable.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Wherever he thought each would be most serviceable] <quote lang="la">Ubi quemque opportunum credebat.</quote> "<foreign lang="la">Propri&egrave; reddas: quem, et ubi ilium, opportunum credebat.</foreign>" Cortius. See c. 23.</note> He himself, in the mean time, was making many simultaneous efforts at Rome; he laid plots for the consul; he arranged schemes for burning the city; he <pb n="32"/>occupied suitable posts with armed men; he went constantly armed himself, and ordered his followers to do the same; he exhorted them to be always on their guard and prepared for action; he was active and vigilant by day and by night, and was exhausted neither by sleeplessness nor by toil. At last, however, when none of his numerous projects succeeded,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">When none of his numerous projects succeeded] <quote lang="la">Ubi multa agitanti nihil procedit.</quote></note> he again, with the aid of Marcus Porcius L&aelig;ca, convoked the leaders of the conspiracy in the dead of night, when, after many complaints of their apathy, he informed them that he had sent forward Manlius to that body of men whom he had prepared to take up arms; and others of the confederates into other eligible places, to make a commencement of hostilities; and that he himself was eager to set out to the army, if he could but first cut off Cicero, who was the chief obstruction to his measures.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="28">
<p> While, therefore, the rest were in alarm and hesitation, Caius Cornelius, a Roman knight, who offered his services, and Lucius Vargunteius, a senator, in company with him, agreed to go with an armed force, on that very night, and with but little delay,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXVIII. On that very night, and with but little delay] <quote lang="la">E&acirc; nocte, paulo post.</quote> They resolved on going soon after the meeting broke up, so that they might reach Cicero's house early in the morning, which was the usual time for waiting on great men. <foreign lang="la">Ingentem foribus domus alta superbis mane salutant&ucirc;m totis vomit &aelig;dibus undam.</foreign> Virg. Georg., ii. 461.</note> to the house of Cicero, under pretense of paying their respects to him, and to kill him unawares, and unprepared for defense, in his own residence. But Curius, when he heard of the imminent danger that threatened the consul, immediately gave him notice, by the agency of Fulvia, of the treachery which was contemplated. The assassins, in consequence, were refused admission, and found that they had undertaken such an attempt only to be disappointed.</p>
<p>In the mean time, Manlius was in Etruria, stirring up the populace, who, both from poverty, and from resentment for their injuries (for, under the tyranny of Sylla, they had lost their lands and other property), were eager for a revolution. He also attached to himself all sorts of marauders, who were numerous in those parts, and some of Sylla's colonists, whose dissipation and extravagance had exhausted their enormous plunder.
<pb n="33"/></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="29">
<p> When these proceedings were reported to Cicero, he, being alarmed at the twofold danger, since he could no longer secure the city against treachery by his private efforts, nor could gain satisfactory intelligence of the magnitude or intentions of . the army of Manlius, laid the matter, which was already a subject of discussion among the people, before the senate. The senate, accordingly, as is usual in any perilous emergency, decreed that THE CONSULS SHOULD MAKE IT THEIR CARE THAT THE COMMONWEALTH SHOULD RECEIVE NO INJURY. This is the greatest power which, according to the practice at Rome, is granted<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXIX. This is the greatest power which--is granted, etc.] <quote lang="la">Ea potestas per senatum, more Romano, magistratui maxima permittitur.</quote> Cortius, <foreign lang="la">mir&acirc; judicii perversitate,</foreign> as Kritzius observes, makes <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign> the ablative case, understanding <foreign lang="la">"decretione," "formula,"</foreign> or some such word; but, happily, no one has followed him.</note> by the senate to the magistrate, and which authorizes him to raise troops; to make war; to assume unlimited control over the allies and the citizens; to take the chief command and jurisdiction at home and in the field; rights which, without an order of the people, the consul is not permitted to exercise.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="30">
<p> A few days afterward, Lucius S&aelig;nius, a senator, read to the senate a letter, which, he said, he had received from F&aelig;sul&aelig;, and in which it was stated that Caius Manlius, with a large force, had taken the field by the 27th of October.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXX. By the 27th of October] <quote lang="la">Ante diem VI. Kalendas Novembres.</quote> He means that they were in arms on or before that day.</note> Others at the same time, as is not uncommon in such a crisis, spread reports of omens and prodigies; others of meetings being held, of arms being transported, and of insurrections of the slaves at Capua and in Apulia. In consequence of these rumors, Quintus Marcius Rex<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Quintus Marcius Rex] He had been proconsul in Cilicia, and was expecting a triumph for his successes.</note> was dispatched, by a decree of the senate, to F&aelig;sul&aelig;, and Quintus Metellus Creticus<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Quintus Metellus Creticus] He had obtained the surname of Creticus from having reduced the island of Crete.</note> into Apulia and the parts adjacent; both which officers, with the title of commanders,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Both which officers, with the title of commanders, etc.] <quote lang="la">Ii utrique ad urbem imperatores erant ; impediti ne triumpharent calumni&acirc; paucorum, quibus omnia, honesta atque inhonesta vendere mos erat.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Imperator"</foreign> was a title given by the army, and confirmed by the senate, to a victorious general, who had slain a certain number of the enemy. What the number was is not known. The general bore this title as an addition to his name, until he obtained (if it were granted him) a triumph, for which be was obliged to wait <foreign lang="la">ad urbem,</foreign> near the city, since he was not allowed to enter the gates as long as he held any military command. These <foreign lang="la">imperatores</foreign> had been debarred from their expected honor by a party who would sell any thing honorable, as a triumph, or any thing dishonorable, as a license to violate the laws.</note> were waiting near the city, having been <pb n="34"/>prevented from entering in triumph, by the malice of a cabal, whose custom it was to ask a price for every thing, whether honorable or infamous. The pr&aelig;tors, too, Quintus Pompeius Rufus, and Quintus Metellus Celer, were sent off, the one to Capua, the other to Picenum, and power was given them to levy a force proportioned to the exigency and the danger. The senate also decreed, that if any one should give information of the conspiracy which had been formed against the state, his reward should be, if a slave, his freedom and a hundred sestertia; if a freeman, a complete pardon and two hundred sestertia<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A hundred sestertia--two hundred sestertia] A hundred sestertia were about 807l. 5s. 10d. of our money.</note>. They further appointed that the schools of gladiators<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Schools of gladiators] <quote lang="la">Gladiatori&aelig; famili&aelig;.</quote> Any number of gladiators under one teacher, or trainer (<foreign lang="la">lanista</foreign>), was called <foreign lang="la">familia.</foreign> They were to be distributed in different parts, and to be strictly watched, that they might not run off to join Catiline. See Graswinckelius, Rupertus, and Gerlach.</note> should be distributed in Capua and other municipal towns, according to the capacity of each; and that, at Rome, watches should be posted throughout the city, of which the inferior magistrates<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The inferior magistrates] The &aelig;diles, tribunes, qa&aelig;stors, and all others below the consuls, censors, and pr&aelig;tors. Aul. Gell., xiii. 15.</note> should have the charge.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="31">
<p> By such proceedings as these the citizens were struck with alarm, and the appearance of the city was changed. In place of that extreme gayety and dissipation,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXI. Dissipation] <quote lang="la">Lascivia.</quote> "Devotion to public amusements and gayety. The word is used in the same sense as in Lucretius, v. 1398:
<quote><l>Tum caput atquc humeros plexis redimire coronis.</l>
<l>Floribus et foliis, lascivia l&aelig;ta monebat.</l></quote>
Then sportive gayety promtped them to deck their heads and shoulders with garlands of flowers and leaves." Bernouf.</note> to which long tranquillity<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Long tranquillity] <quote lang="la">Diuturna quies.</quote> "Since the victory of Sylla to the time of which Sallust is speaking, that is, for about twenty years, there had been a complete cessation from civil discord and disturbance." Bernouf.</note> had given rise, a sudden gloom spread over all classes; they became anxious and agitated; they felt secure neither in any place, nor with any person; they were not at war, yet enjoyed no peace; each measured the public danger by his own fear. The women, also, to whom, from the extent of the empire, the dread of war was new, gave way to lamentation, raised supplicating hands to heaven, mourned over their <pb n="35"/>infants, made constant inquiries, trembled at every thing, and, forgetting their pride and their pleasures, felt nothing but alarm for themselves and their country.</p>
<p>Yet the unrelenting spirit of Catiline persisted in the same purposes, notwithstanding the precautions that were adopted against him, and though he himself was accused by Lucius Paullus under the Plautian law.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The Plautian law] <quote lang="la">Lege Plauti&acirc;.</quote> "This law was that of M. Plautius Silanus, a tribune of the people, which was directed against such as excited a sedition in the state, or formed plots against the life of any individual." <foreign lang="la">Cyprianus Popma.</foreign> See Dr. Smith's Dict. of Gr. and Rom. Antiquities, sub VIS.</note> At last, with a view to dissemble, and under pretense of clearing his character, as if he had been provoked by some attack, he went into the senatehouse. It was then that Marcus Tullius, the consul, whether alarmed at his presence, or fired with indignation against him, delivered that splendid speech, so beneficial to the republic, which he afterward wrote and published.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Which he afterward wrote and published] <quote lang="la">Quam poste&agrave; scriptam edidit.</quote> This was the first of Cicero's four Orations against Catiline. The epithet applied to it by Sallust, which I have rendered "splendid," is <foreign lang="la">luculentam;</foreign> that is, says Gerlach, <foreign lang="la">"luminibus verborum et sententiarum ornatam,"</foreign> distinguished by much brilliancy of words and thoughts. And so say Kritzius, Bernouf, and Dietsch. Cortius, who is followed by Dahl, Langius, and M&uuml;ller, makes the word equivalent merely to lucid, in the supposition that Sallust intended to bestow on the speech, as on other performances of Cicero, only very cool praise. Luculentus, however, seems certainly to mean something more than <foreign lang="la">lucidus.</foreign></note></p>
<p>When Cicero sat down, Catiline, being prepared to pretend ignorance of the whole matter, entreated, with downcast looks and suppliant voice, that "the Conscript Fathers would not too hastily believe any thing against him;" saying "that he was sprung from such a family, and had so ordered his life from his youth, as to have every happiness in prospect; and that they were not to suppose that he, a patrician, whose services to the Roman people, as well as those of his ancestors, had been so numerous, should want to ruin the state, when Marcus Tullius, a mere adopted citizen of Rome,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A mere adopted citizen of Rome] <quote lang="la">Inquilinus civis urbis Rom&aelig;.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Inquilinus"</foreign> means properly a lodger, or tenant in the house of another. Cicero was born at Arpinum, and is therefore called by Catiline a citizen of Rome merely by adoption or by sufferance. Appian, in repeating this account (Bell. Civ., ii. 104), says, <foreign lang="greek">)*igkoui/linon, w(=| r(h/mati kalou=si tou\z e)noikou=ntas e)n a/llotoi/aiz o)iki/aiz.</foreign></note> was eager to preserve it." When he was proceeding to add other invectives, they all raised an outcry against him, and called him an enemy and a <pb n="36"/>traitor.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Traitor] <quote lang="la">Parricidam.</quote> See c. 14. "An oppressor or betrayer of his country is justly called a parricide ; for our country is the common parent of all. Cic. ad Attic." Wasse.</note> Being thus exasperated, " Since I am encompassed by enemies," he exclaimed,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Since I am encompassed by enemies, he exclaimed, etc.] " It was not on this day, nor indeed to Cicero, that this answer was made by Catilina. It was a reply to Cato, uttered a few days before the comitia for electing consuls, which were held on the 22d day of October. See Cic. pro Mur&aelig;ne, c. 25. Cicero's speech was delivered on the 8th of November. Sallust is, therefore, in error on this point, as well as Florus and Valerius Maximus, who have followed him." Bernouf. From other accounts we may infer that no reply was made to Cicero by Catiline on this occasion. Plutarch, in his Life of Cicero, says that Catiline, before Cicero rose, seemed desirous to address the senate in defense of his proceedings, but that the senators refused to listen to him. Of any answer to Cicero's speech, on the part of Catiline, he makes no mention. Cicero himself, in his second Oration against Catiline, says that Catiline could not endure his voice, but, when he was ordered to go into exile, <foreign lang="la">"paruit, quievit,"</foreign> obeyed and submitted in silence. And in his Oration, c. 37, he says, " That most audacious of men, Catiline, when he was accused by me in the senate, was dumb."</note> "and driven to desperation, I will extinguish the flame kindled around me in a general ruin."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="32">
<p> He then hurried from the senate to his own house; and then, after much reflection with himself, thinking that, as his plots against the consul had been unsuccessful, and as he knew the city to be secured from fire by the watch, his best course would be to augment his army, and make provision for the war before the legions could be raised, he set out in the dead of night, and with a few attendants, to the camp of Manlius. But he left in charge to Lentulus and Cethegus, and others of whose prompt determination he was assured, to strengthen the interests of their party in every possible way, to forward the plots against the consul, and to make arrangements for a massacre, for firing the city, and for other destructive operations of war; promising that he himself would shortly advance on the city with a large army.</p>
<p>During the course of these proceedings at Rome, Caius Manlius dispatched some of his followers as deputies to Quintus Marcius Rex, with directions to address him<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXII. With directions to address him, etc.] <quote lang="la">Cum mandatis hujuscemodi.</quote> The communication, as Cortius observes, was not an epistle, but a verbal message.</note> to the following effect:</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="33">
<p> "We call gods and men to witness, general, that we have taken up arms neither to injure our country, nor to occasion peril to any one, but to defend our own persons from harm; who, wretched and in want, have been deprived, <pb n="37"/>most of us, of our homes, and all of us of our character and property, by the oppression and cruelty of usurers; nor has any one of us been allowed, according to the usage of our ancestors, to have the benefit of the law,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXIII. To have the benefit of the law] <quote lang="la">Lege uti.</quote> The law here meant was the Papirian law, by which it was provided, contrary to the old law of the Twelve Tables, that no one should be confined in prison for debt, and that the property of the debtor only, not his person, should be liable for what he owed. Livy (viii. 28) relates the occurrence which gave rise to this law, and says that it ruptured one of the strongest bonds of credit.</note> or, when our property was lost to keep our persons free. Such has been the inhumanity of the usurers and of the pr&aelig;tor.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The pr&aelig;tor] The <quote lang="la">pro&aelig;tor urbanus,</quote> or city pr&aelig;tor, who decided all causes between citizens, and passed sentence on debtors.</note></p>
<p>"Often have your forefathers, taking compassion on the commonalty at Rome, relieved their distress by decrees ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Relieved their distress by decrees] <quote lang="la">Decretis suis inopi&aelig; opitulati sunt.</quote> In allusion to the laws passed at various times for diminishing the rate of interest.</note> and very lately, within our, own memory, silver, by reason of the pressure of debt, and with the consent of all respectable citizens, was paid with brass.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Silver--was paid with brass] <quote lang="la">Agentum &aelig;re solutum est.</quote> Thus a <foreign lang="la">sestertius,</foreign> which was of silver, and was worth four asses, was paid with one as, which was of brass; or the fourth part only of the debt was paid. See Plin. H. N. xxxiii. 3; and Velleius Paterculus, ii. 23 ; who says, <foreign lang="la">quadrantem solvi,</foreign> that a quarter of their debts were paid by the debtors, by a law of Valerius Flaccus, when he became consul on the death of Marius.</note></p>
<p>"Often too, we must own, have the commonalty themselves, driven by desire of power, or by the arrogance of their rulers, seceded<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Often--have the commonalty--seceded, etc.] "This happened three times: 1. To the <foreign lang="la">Mons Sacer,</foreign> on account of debt; Liv. ii. 32. 2. To the Aventine, and thence to the <foreign lang="la">Mons Sacer,</foreign> through the tyranny of Appius Claudius, the decemvir; Liv. iii. 50. 3. To the Janiculum, on account of debt; Liv. Epist. xi." Bernouf.</note> under arms from the patricians. But at power or wealth, for the sake of which wars, and all kinds of strife, arise among mankind, we do not aim; we desire only our liberty, which no honorable man relinquishes but with life. We therefore conjure you and the senate to befriend your unhappy fellow-citizens; to restore us the protection of the law, which the injustice of the pr&aelig;tor has taken from us; and not to lay on us the necessity of considering how we may perish, so as best to avenge our blood."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="34">
<p> To this address Quintus Marcius replied, that, "if they wished to make any petition to the senate, they <pb n="38"/>must lay down their arms, and proceed as suppliants to Rome;" adding, that "such had always been the kindness<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXIV. That such had always been the kindness, etc.] <quote lang="la">E&acirc; mansuetudine atque misericordi&acirc; senatum populumque Romanum semper fuisse.</quote> " That the senate, etc., had always been of such kindness." I have deserted the Latin for the English idiom.</note> and humanity of the Roman senate and people, that none had ever asked help of them in vain."</p>
<p>Catiline, on his march, sent letters to most men of consular dignity, and to all the most respectable citizens, stating that "as he was beset by false accusations, and unable to resist the combination of his enemies, he was submitting to the will of fortune, and going into exile at Marseilles; not that he was guilty of the great wickedness laid to his charge, but that the state might be undisturbed, and that no insurrection might arise from his defense of himself."</p>
<p>Quintus Catulus, however, read in the senate a letter of a very different character, which, he said, was delivered to him in he name of Catiline, and of which the following is a copy:</p>
<p><note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXV. The commencement of this letter is different in different editions. In Havercamp it stands thus: <foreign lang="la">Egregiatua fides, re cognita grata mihi, magnis in meis periculis, fiduciam commendationi me&aelig; tribuit.</foreign> Cortius corrected it as follows: <foreign lang="la">Egregia tua fides, re cognita, gratam in magnis periculis fiduciam commendationi me&aelig; tribuit.</foreign> Cortius's reading has been adopted by Kritzius, Bernouf, and most other editors. Gerlach and Dietsch have recalled the old text. That Cortius's is the better, few will deny; for it can hardly be supposed that Sallust used <foreign lang="la">mihi, meis,</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">me&aelig;</foreign> in such close succession. Some, however, as Rupertus and Gerlach, defend Havercamp's text, by asserting, from the phrase <foreign lang="la">earum exemplam infra scriptum,</foreign> that this is a true copy of the letter, and that the style is, therefore, not Sallust's, but Catiline's. But such an opinion is sufficiently refuted by Cortius, whose remarks I will transcribe: "Rupertus," says he, <foreign lang="la">"quod in promptu erat, Catilin&aelig; culpam tribuit, qui non eo, quo Crispus, stilo scripserit. Sed cur oratio ejus tam apta et composita supr&agrave; c. 20 refertur? At, inquis, hic ipsum litterarum exemplum exhibetur. At vide mihi exemplum litterarum Lentuli, c. 44; et lege Ciceronem, qui idem exhibet, et senties sensum magis quam verba referri. Quare inanis h&aelig;c quidem excusatio."</foreign> Yet it is not to be denied that <foreign lang="la">grata mihi</foreign> is the reading of all the manuscripts.</note>XXXV. "Lucius Catiline to Quintus Catulus, wishing health. Your eminent integrity, known to me by experience,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Known--by experience] <quote lang="la">Re cognita.</quote> " Cognita" be it observed, <foreign lang="la">tironum grati&acirc;,</foreign> is the nominative case. <cit><quote>"Catiline had experienced the friendship of Catulus in his affair with Fabia Terentia; for it was by his means that he escaped when he was brought to trial, as is related by Orosius."</quote> <bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> gives a pleasing confidence, in the midst of great <pb n="39"/>perils, to my present recommendation.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Recommendation] <quote lang="la">Commendationi.</quote> His recommendation of his affairs, and of Orestilla, to the care of Catulus.</note> I have determined, therefore, to make no formal defense<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Formal defense] <quote lang="la">Defensionem.</quote> Opposed to <foreign lang="la">satisfactionem,</foreign> which follows, and which means a private apology or explanation. <foreign lang="la">"Defensio,</foreign> a defense, was properly a statement or speech to be made against an adversary, or before judges; <foreign lang="la">satisfactio</foreign> was rather an excuse or apology made to a friend, or any other person, in a private communication." <bibl>Cortius.</bibl></note> with regard to my new course of conduct; yet I was resolved, though conscious of no guilt,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Though conscious of no guilt] <quote lang="la">Ex null&acirc; conscienti&acirc; de cold&acirc;.</quote> This phrase is explained by Cortius as equivalent to <foreign lang="la">"Propter conscientam de null&acirc; culp&acirc;,"</foreign> or " inasmuch as I am conscious of no fault." " <foreign lang="la">De culp&acirc;,"</foreign> he adds, is the same as <foreign lang="la">culp&aelig;</foreign> ; so in the ii. Epist. to C&aelig;sar, c. 1: <foreign lang="la">Neque de futuro quisquam satix callidus; and c. 9: de illis potissimum jactura fit."</foreign></note> to offer you some explanation,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To make no formal defense--to offer you some explanation] <quote lang="la">Defensionem--parare; satisfactionem--proponere. " Parare,</quote>" says Cortius, "is applied to a defense which might require some study and premeditation; <quote lang="la">proponere</quote> to such a statement as it was easy to make at once."</note> which, on my word of honor,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">On my word of honor] <quote lang="la">Me dius fidus,</quote> sc. juvet. So may the god of faith help me, as I speak truth. But who is the god of faith ? <foreign lang="la">Dius,</foreign> say some, is the same as <foreign lang="la">Deus</foreign> (Plautus has <foreign lang="la">Deus fidius,</foreign> Asin i. 1, 18); and the god here meant is probably Jupiter (<foreign lang="la">sub dio</foreign> being equivalent to <foreign lang="la">sub Jove</foreign>); so that <foreign lang="la">Dius fidius</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">fidius</foreign> being an adjective from <foreign lang="la">fides</foreign>) will be the <foreign lang="greek">*zeuz pi/stioz</foreign> of the Greeks. <foreign lang="la">Me dius fidius</foreign> will therefore be, "May Jupiter help me !" This is the mode of explication adopted by Gerlach, Bernouf, and Dietsch. Others, with Festus (<foreign lang="la">sub voce Medius fidius</foreign>) make <foreign lang="la">fidius</foreign> equivalent to <foreign lang="la">filius,</foreign> because the ancients, according to Festus, often used D for L, and <foreign lang="la">dius fidius</foreign> will then be the same as <foreign lang="greek">*dio\s</foreign> or Jovis filius, or Hercules, and <foreign lang="la">medius fidius</foreign> will be the same as <foreign lang="la">mehercules</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">mehercule.</foreign> Varro de L. L. (v. 10, ed. Sprengel) mentions a certain &AElig;lius who was of this opinion. Against this derivation there is the quantity of <foreign lang="la">fidius,</foreign> of which the first syllable is short: <foreign lang="la">Qu&aelig;rebam Nonas Sanco fidone referrem,</foreign> Ov. Fast. vi. 213. But if we consider <foreign lang="la">dius</foreign> the same as <foreign lang="la">deus,</foreign> we may as well consider <foreign lang="la">dius fidius</foreign> to be the god Hercules as the god Jupiter, and may thus make <foreign lang="la">medius fidius</foreign> identical with <foreign lang="la">mehercules,</foreign> as it probably is. " Tertullian, de Idol. 20, says that <foreign lang="la">medius fidius</foreign> is a form of swearing by Hercules." Schiller's Lex. sub <foreign lang="la">Fidius.</foreign> This point will be made tolerably clear if we consider (with Varro, v. 10, and Ovid, loc. cit.) <foreign lang="la">Dius, Fidius</foreign> to be the same with the Sabine Sancus, or Semo Sancus, and Semo Sancus to be the same with Hercules.</note> you may receive as true.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">You may receive as true] <quote lang="la">Veram licet cognoscas.</quote> Some editions, before that of Cortius, have <quote lang="la">qu&aelig;--licet vera mecum recognoscas;</quote> which was adopted from a quotation of Servius ad &AElig;n. iv. 204. But twenty of the best MSS., according to Certius, have <quote lang="la">veram licet cognoscas.</quote></note> Provoked by injuries and indignities, since, being robbed of the fruit of my labor and exertion,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Robbed of the fruit of my labor and exertion] <quote lang="la">Fructu laboris industri&aelig;que me&aelig; privatus.</quote> "The honors which he sought he elegantly calls the fruit of his labor, because the one is obtained by the other.'" <bibl>Cortius.</bibl></note> I did not obtain the post of honor due to me,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Post of honor due to me] <quote lang="la">Statum dignitatis.</quote> The consulship.</note> I have undertaken, according to my custom, the public cause <pb n="40"/>of the distressed. Not but that I could have paid, out of my own property, the debts contracted on my own security ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">On my own security] <quote lang="la">Meis nominibus.</quote> "He uses the plural," says Herzogius, "because he had not borrowed once only, or from one person, but oftentimes, and from many." No other critic attempts to explain this point. For <foreign lang="la">alienis nominibus,</foreign> which follows, being in the plural, there is very good reason. My translation is in conformity with Bernouf's comment.</note> while the generosity of Orestilla, out of her own fortune and her daughter's, would discharge those incurred on the security of others. But because I saw unworthy men ennobled with honors, and myself proscribed<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Proscribed] <quote lang="la">Alienatum.</quote> <cit><quote>"Repulsed from all hope of the consulship."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> on groundless suspicion, I have for this very reason, adopted a course,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Adopted a course] <quote lang="la">Spes--secutus sum.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Spem sequi</foreign> is a phrase often used when the direction of the mind to any thing, action, or course of conduct, and the subsequent election and adoption of what appears advantageous, is signified." <bibl>Cortius.</bibl></note> amply justifiable in my present circumstances, for preserving what honor is left to me. When I was proceeding to write more, intelligence was brought that violence is preparing against me. I now commend and intrust Orestilla to your protection ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Protection] <quote lang="la">Fidei.</quote></note> intreating you, by your love for your own children, to defend her from injury.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Intreating you, by your love for your own children, to defend her from injury] <quote lang="la">Eam ab injuri&acirc; defendas, per liberos tuos rogatus.</quote> "Defend her from injury, being intreated [to do so] by [or for the sake of] your own children."</note> Farewell."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="36">
<p> Catiline himself, having stayed a few days with Caius Flaminius Flamma in the neighborhood of Arretium,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXVI. In the neighborhood of Arretium] <quote lang="la">In agro Arretino.</quote> Havercamp, and many of the old editions, have <foreign lang="la">Reatino;</foreign> "but," says Cortius, "if Catiline went the direct road to F&aelig;sul&aelig;, as is rendered extremely probable by his pretense that he was going to Marseilles, and by the assertion of Cicero, made the day after his departure, that he was on his way to join Manlius, we must certainly read <foreign lang="la">Arretino.</foreign>" Arretium (now <foreign lang="la">Arezzo</foreign>) lay in his road to F&aelig;sul&aelig;; Reate was many miles out of it.</note> while he was supplying the adjacent parts, already excited to insurrection, with arms, marched with his fasces, and -other ensigns of authority, to join Manlius in his camp.</p>
<p>When this was known at Rome, the senate declared Catiline and Manlius enemies to the state, and fixed a day as to the rest of their force, before which they might lay down their arms with impunity, except such as had been convicted of capital offenses. They also decreed that the consuls should <pb n="41"/>hold a levy; that Antonius, with an army, should hasten in pursuit of Catiline; and that Cicero should protect the city.</p>
<p>At this period the empire of Rome appears to me to have been in an extremely deplorable condition ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In an extremely deplorable condition] <quote lang="la">Multo maxim&egrave; miserabile.</quote> <foreign lang="la">Multo</foreign> is added to superlatives, like <foreign lang="la">long&egrave;.</foreign> So c. 52, <foreign lang="la">multo pulcherrimam eam nos haberemus.</foreign> Cortius gives several other instances.</note> for though every nation, from the rising to the setting of the sun, lay in subjection to her arms, and though peace and prosperity, which mankind think the greatest blessings, were hers in abundance, there yet were found, among her citizens, men who were bent with obstinate determination, to plunge themselves and their country into ruin; for, notwithstanding the two decrees of the senate,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Notwithstanding the two decrees of the senate] <quote lang="la">Duobus senati decretis.</quote> I have translated it "the two decrees," with Rose. One of the two was that respecting the rewards mentioned in c. 30 ; the other was that spoken of in c. 36, allowing the followers of Catiline to lay down their arms before a certain day.</note> not one individual, out of so vast a number, was induced by the offer of reward to give information of the conspiracy; nor was there a single deserter from the camp of Catiline. So strong a spirit of disaffection had, like a pestilence, pervaded the minds of most of the citizens.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="37">
<p> Nor was this disaffected spirit confined to those who were actually concerned in the conspiracy; for the whole of the common people, from a desire of change, favored the projects of Catiline. This they seemed to do in accordance with their general character; for, in every state, they that are poor envy those of a better class, and endeavor to exalt the factious ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXVII. Endeavor to exalt the factious] <quote lang="la">Malos extollunt.</quote> They strive to elevate into office those who resemble themselves.</note> they dislike the established condition of things, and long for something new; they are discontented with their own circumstances, and desire a general alteration; they can support themselves amid tumult and sedition, without anxiety, since poverty does not easily suffer loss.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Poverty does not easily suffer loss] <quote lang="la">Egestas facil&egrave; habetur sine damno</quote> He that has nothing, has nothing to lose. Petron. Sat., c. 119: <foreign lang="la">Inops audacia tuta est.</foreign></note></p>
<p>As for the populace of the city, they had become disaffected<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Had become disaffected] <quote lang="la">Pr&aelig;ceps abierat.</quote> Had grown demoralized, sunk in corruption, and ready to join in any plots against the state. So Sallust says of Sempronia, <foreign lang="la">pr&aelig;ceps abierat,</foreign> c. 25.</note> from various causes. In the first place,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In the first place] <quote lang="la">Primum omnium.</quote> "These words refer, not to <foreign lang="la">item</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">postremo</foreign> in the same sentence, but to <foreign lang="la">deinde</foreign> at the commencement of the next." <bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></note> such as every where <pb n="42"/>took the lead in crime and profligacy, with others who had squandered their fortunes in dissipation, and, in a word, all whom vice and villainy had driven from their homes, had flocked to Rome as a general receptacle of impurity. In the next place, many, who thought of the success of Sylla, when they had seen some raised from common soldiers into senators, and others so enriched as to live in regal luxury and pomp, hoped, each for himself, similar results from victory, if they should once take up arms. In addition to this, the youth, who, in the country, had earned a scanty livelihood by manual labor, tempted by public and private largesses, had preferred idleness in the city to unwelcome toil in the field. To these, and all others of similar character, public disorders would furnish subsistence. It is not at all surprising, therefore, that men in distress, of dissolute principles and extravagant expectations, should have consulted the interest of the state no further than as it was subservient to their own. Besides, those whose parents, by the victory of Sylla, had been proscribed, whose property had been confiscated, and whose civil rights had been curtailed,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Civil rights had been curtailed] <quote lang="la">Jus libertatis imminutum erat.</quote> " Sylla, by one of his laws, had rendered the children of proscribed persons incapable of holding any public office; a law unjust, indeed, but which, having been established and acted upon for more than twenty years, could not be rescinded without inconvenience to the government. Cicero, accordingly, opposed the attempts which were made, in his consulship, to remove this restriction, as he himself states in his Oration against Piso, c. 2." <bibl>Bernouf.</bibl> See Vell. Paterc., ii., 28; Plutarch, Vit. Syll.; Quintil., xi. 1, where a fragment of Cicero's speech, <foreign lang="la">De Proscriptorum Liberis,</foreign> is preserved. This law of Sylla was at length abrogated by Julius C&aelig;sar, Suet. J. C&aelig;s. 41; Plutarch Vit. C&aelig;s.; Dio Cass., xli. 18.</note> looked forward to the event of a war with precisely the same feelings.</p>
<p>All those, too, who were of any party opposed to that of the senate, were desirous rather that the state should be embroiled, than that they themselves should be out of power. This was an evil, which, after many years, had returned upon the community to the extent to which it now prevailed.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">This was an evil--to the extent to which it now prevailed] <quote lang="la">Id ade&ograve; malum multos post annos in civitatem reverterat.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Adeo,"</foreign> says Cortius, "is particular <foreign lang="la">elegantissima.</foreign>" Allen makes it equivalent to <foreign lang="la">e&ograve; usque.</foreign></note></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="38">
<p> For after the powers of the tribunes, in the consulate of Cneius Pompey and Marcus Crassus, had been fully <pb n="43"/>restored,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXVIII. The powers of the tribunes--had been fully restored] <quote lang="la">Tribunicia potestas restituta.</quote> Before the time of Sylla, the power of the tribunes had grown immoderate, but Sylla diminished and almost annihilated it, by taking from them the privileges of holding any other magistracy after the tribunate, of publicly addressing the people, of proposing laws, and of listening to appeals. But in the consulship of Cotta, A.U.C. 679, the first of these privileges had been restored; and in that of Pompey and Crassus, A.U.C. 683, the tribunes were reinstated in all their former powers.</note> certain young men, of an ardent age and temper, having obtained that high office,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Having obtained that high office] <quote lang="la">Summam potestatem nacti.</quote> Cortius thinks these words spurious.</note> began to stir up the populace by inveighing against the senate, and proceeded, in course of time, by means of largesses and promises, to inflame them more and more; by which methods they became popular and powerful. On the other hand, the most of the nobility opposed their proceedings to the utmost; under pretense, indeed, of supporting the senate, but in reality for their own aggrandizement. For, to state the truth in few words, whatever parties, during that period, disturbed the republic under plausible pretexts, some, as if to defend the rights of the people, others, to make the authority of the senate as great as possible, all, though affecting concern for the public good, contended every one for his own interest. In such contests there was neither moderation nor limit; each party made a merciless use of its successes.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="39">
<p> After Pompey, however, was sent to the maritime and Mithridatic wars, the power of the people was diminished, and the influence of the few increased. These few kept all public offices, the administration of the provinces, and every thing else, in their own hands; they themselves lived free from harm,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XXXIX. Free from harm] <quote lang="la">Innoxii.</quote> In a passive sense.</note> in flourishing circumstances, and without apprehension; overawing others, at the same time, with threats of impeachment,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Overawing others -- with threats of impeachment] <quote lang="la">C&aelig;teros judiciis errere.</quote> <cit><quote>"Accusationibus et judiciorum periculis."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> so that, when in office, they might be less inclined to inflame the people. But as soon as a prospect of change, in this dubious state of affairs, had presented itself, the old spirit of contention awakened their passions; and had Catiline, in his first battle, come off victorious, or left the struggle undecided, great distress and calamity must certainly have fallen upon the state, nor would those, who might at last have gained the ascendency, have been allowed to enjoy <pb n="44"/>it long, for some superior power would have wrested dominion and liberty from them when weary and exhausted.</p>
<p>There were some, however, unconnected with the conspiracy, who set out to join Catiline at an early period of his proceedings. Among these was Aulus Fulvius, the son of a senator, whom, being arrested on his journey, his father ordered to be put to death.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">His father ordered to be put to death] <quote lang="la">Parens necari jussit.</quote> "His father put him to death, not by order of the consuls, but by his own private authority; nor was he the only one who, at the same period, exercised similar power." Dion. Cass., lib. xxxvii. The father observed on the occasion that, " he had begotten him, not for Catiline against his country, but for his country against Catiline." Val. Max., v. 8. The Roman laws allowed fathers absolute control over the lives of their children.</note> In Rome, at the same time, Lentulus, in pursuance of Catiline's directions, was endeavoring to gain over, by his own agency or that of others, all whom he thought adapted, either by principles or circumstances, to promote an insurrection; and not citizens only, but every description of men who could be of any service in war.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="40">
<p> He accordingly commissioned one Publius Umbrenus to apply to certain deputies of the Allobroges,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XL. Certain deputies of the Allobroges] <quote lang="la">Legatos Allobrogum.</quote> Plutarch, in his Life of Cicero, says that there were then at Rome two deputies from this Gallic nation, sent to complain of oppression on the part of the Roman governors.</note> and to lead them, if he could, to a participation in the war; supposing that as they were nationally and individually involved in debt, and as the Gauls were naturally warlike, they might easily be drawn into such an enterprise. Umbrenus, as he had traded in Gaul, was known to most of the chief men there, and personally acquainted with them; and consequently, without loss of time, as soon as he noticed the deputies in the Forum, he asked them, after making a few inquiries about the state of their country, and affecting to commiserate its fallen condition, " what termination they expected to such calamities?" When he found that they complained of the rapacity of the magistrates, inveighed against the senate for not affording them relief, and looked to death as the only remedy for their sufferings, "Yet I," said he, "if you will but act as men, will show you a method by which you may escape these pressing difficulties." When he had said this, the Allobroges, animated with the highest hopes, besought Umbrenus to take compassion on them; saying that there was nothing so disagreeable or difficult, <pb n="45"/>which they would not most gladly perform, if it would but free their country from debt. He then conducted them to the house of Decimus Brutus, which was close to the Forum, and, on account of Sempronia, not unsuitable to his purpose, as Brutus was then absent from Rome.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">As Brutus was then absent from Rome] <quote lang="la">Nam tum Brutus ab Rom&acirc; aberat.</quote> From this remark, say Zanchius and Omnibonus, it is evident that Brutus was not privy to the conspiracy.
<cit><quote>"What sort of woman Sempronia was, has been told in c. 25. Some have thought that she was the wife of Decimus Brutus; but since Sallust speaks of her as being in the decay of her beauty at the time of the conspiracy, and since Brutus, as may be seen in C&aelig;sar (B. G. vii., sub fin.), was then very young, it is probable that she had only an illicit connection with him, but had gained such an ascendency over his affections, by her arts of seduction, as to induce him to make her his mistress, and to allow her to reside in his house."</quote><bibl>Beauz&eacute;e.</bibl></cit>
I have, however, followed those who think that Brutus was the husband of Sempronia. Sallust (c. 24), speaking of the woman, of whom Sempronia was one, says that Catiline <foreign lang="la">credebat posse--viros earum vel adjungere sibi, vel interficere.</foreign> The truth, on such a point, is of little importance.</note> In order, too, to give greater weight to his representations, he sent for Gabinius, and, in his presence, explained the objects of the conspiracy, and mentioned the names of the confederates, as well as those of many other persons, of every sort, who were guiltless of it, for the purpose of inspiring the embassadors with greater confidence. At length, when they had promised their assistance, he let them depart.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="41">
<p> Yet the Allobroges were long in suspense what course they should adopt. On the one hand, there was debt, an inclination for war, and great advantages to be expected from victory ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLI. To be expected from victory] <quote lang="la">In spe victori&aelig;.</quote></note> on the other, superior resources, safe plans, and certain rewards<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Certain rewards] <quote lang="la">Certa pr&aelig;mia.</quote> <cit><quote>"Offered by the senate to those who should give information of the conspiracy. See c. 30."</quote><bibl>Kuhnhardt</bibl></cit></note> instead of uncertain expectations. As they were balancing these considerations, the good fortune of the state at length prevailed. They accordingly disclosed the whole affair, just as they had learned it, to Quintus Fabius Sanga,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Quintus Fabius Sanga] <cit><quote>"A descendent of that Fabius who, for having subdued the Allobroges, was surnamed Allobrogicus."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit> Whole states often chose patrons as well as individuals.</note> to whose patronage their state was very greatly indebted. Cicero, being apprized of the matter by Sanga, directed the deputies to pretend a strong desire for the success of the plot, to seek interviews with the rest of the conspirators, to make them fair promises, and to endeavor to lay them open to conviction as much as possible.
<pb n="46"/></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="42">
<p> Much about the same time there were commotions<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLII. There were commotions] <quote lang="la">Motus erat.</quote> <cit><quote><foreign lang="la">"Motus</foreign> is also used by Cicero and Livy in the singular number for <foreign lang="la">seditiones</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">tumultus.</foreign> No change is therefore to be made in the text."</quote><bibl>Gerlach.</bibl></cit> <cit><quote><foreign lang="la">"Motus bellicos intelligit, tumultus; ut Flor., iii. 13."</foreign></quote><bibl>Cortius.</bibl></cit></note> in Hither and Further Gaul, in the Picenian and Bruttian territories, and in Apulia. For those, whom Catiline had previously sent to those parts, had begun, without consideration, and seemingly with madness, to attempt every thing at once; and, by nocturnal meetings, by removing armor and weapons from place to place, and by hurrying and confusing every thing, had created more alarm than danger. Of these, Quintus Metellus Celer, the pr&aelig;tor, having brought several to trial,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Having brought several to trial] <quote lang="la">Complures--causs&acirc; cognit&acirc;.</quote> <cit><quote>"<foreign lang="la">Caussam cognoscere</foreign> is the legal phrase for examining as to the authors and causes of any crime."</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit></note> under the decree of the senate, had thrown them into prison, as had also Caius Mur&aelig;na in Further Gaul,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Caius Mur&aelig;na in Further Gaul] <quote lang="la">In Ulteriore Galli&acirc; C. Mur&aelig;na.</quote> All the editions, previous to that of Cortius, have <foreign lang="la">in citeriore Galli&acirc;.</foreign> " But C. Mur&aelig;na," says the critic, " commanded in Gallia Transalpina, or Ulterior Gaul, as appears from Cic. pro Mur&aelig;na, c. 41. To attribute such an error to a lapse of memory in Sallust, would be absurd. I have, therefore, confidently altered <foreign lang="la">citeriore</foreign> into <foreign lang="la">ulteriore.</foreign>" The praise of having first discovered the error, however, is due, not to Cortius, but to Felicius Durantinus, a friend of Rivius, in whose note on the passage his discovery is recorded.</note> who governed that province in quality of legate.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="43">
<p> But at Rome, in the mean time, Lentulus, with the other leaders of the conspiracy, having secured what they thought a large force, had arranged, that as soon as Catiline should reach the neighborhood of F&aelig;sul&aelig;, Lucius Bestia, a tribune of the people, having called an assembly, should complain of the proceedings of Cicero, and lay the odium of this most oppressive war on the excellent consul ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLIII. The excellent consul] <quote lang="la">Optimo consuli.</quote> With the exception of the slight commendation bestowed on his speech, <foreign lang="la">luculentam</foreign> atque <foreign lang="la">utilem reipublic&aelig;,</foreign> c. 31, this is the only epithet of praise that Sallust bestows on the consul throughout his narrative. That it could be regarded only as frigid eulogy, is apparent from a passage in one of Cicero's letters to Atticus (xii. 21), in which he speaks of the same epithet having been applied to him by Brutus: " Brutus thinks that he pays me a great compliment when he calls me an excellent consul (<foreign lang="la">optimum consulem</foreign>); but what enemy could speak more coldly of me?"</note> and that the rest of the conspirators, taking this as a signal, should, on the following night, proceed to execute their respective parts.</p>
<p>These parts are said to have been thus distributed. Statilius and Gabinius, with a large force, were to set on fire twelve. <pb n="47"/>places of the city, convenient for their purpose,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Twelve places of the city, convenient for their purpose] <quote lang="la">Duodecim--opportuna loca.</quote> Plutarch, in his Life of Cicero, says a hundred places. Few narratives lose by repetition.</note> at the same time; in order that, during the consequent tumult,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In order that, during the consequent tumult] <quote lang="la">Qu&ograve; tumultu.</quote> "It is best," says Dietsch, "to take <foreign lang="la">quo</foreign> as the <foreign lang="la">particula finalis</foreign> (to the end that), and <foreign lang="la">tumultu</foreign> as the ablative of the instrument."</note> an easier access might be obtained to the consul, and to the others whose destruction was intended; Cethegus was to beset the gate of Cicero, and attack him personally with violence; others were to single out other victims; while the sons of certain families, mostly of the nobility, were to kill their fathers; and, when all were in consternation at the massacre and conflagration, they were to sally forth to join Catiline.</p>
<p>While they were thus forming and settling their plans, Cethegus was incessantly complaining of the want of spirit in his associates; observing, that they wasted excellent opportunities through hesitation and delay;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Delay] <quote lang="la">Dies prolatando.</quote> By putting off from day to day.</note> that, in such an enterprise, there was need, not of deliberation, but of action; and that he himself, if a few would support him, would storm the senatehouse while the others remained inactive. Being naturally bold, sanguine, and prompt to act, he thought that success depended on rapidity of execution.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="44">
<p> The Allobroges, according to the directions of Cicero, procured interviews, by means of Gabinius, with the other conspirators; and from Lentulus, Cethegus, Statilius, and Cassius, they demanded an oath, which they might carry under seal to their countrymen, who otherwise would hardly join in so important an affair. To this the others consented without suspicion; but Cassius promised them soon to visit their country,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLIV. Soon to visit their country] <quote lang="la">Semet e&ograve; brevi venturum.</quote> <cit><quote>"It is plain that the adverb relates to what precedes (<foreign lang="la">ad cives</foreign>); and that Cassius expresses an intention to set out for Gaul."</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit></note> and, indeed, left the city a little before the deputies.</p>
<p>In order that the Allobroges, before they reached home, might confirm their agreement with Catiline, by giving and receiving pledges of faith, Lentulus sent with them one Titus Volturcius, a native of Crotona, he himself giving Volturcius a letter for Catiline, of which the following is a copy:</p>
<p>"Who I am, you will learn from the person whom I have <pb n="48"/>sent to you. Reflect seriously in how desperate a situation you are placed, and remember that you are a man.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Remember that you are a man] <quote lang="la">Memineris te virum.</quote> Remember that you are a man, and ought to act as one. Cicero, in repeating this letter from memory (Orat. in Cat., iii. 5), gives the phrase, <foreign lang="la">Cura ut vir sis.</foreign></note> Consider what your views demand, and seek aid from all, even the lowest." In addition, he gave him this verbal message: "Since he was declared an enemy by the senate, for what reason should he reject the assistance of slaves ? That, in the city, every thing which he had directed was arranged; and that he should not delay to make nearer approaches to it."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="45">
<p> Matters having proceeded thus far, and a night being appointed for the departure of the deputies, Cicero, being by them made acquainted with every thing, directed the pr&aelig;tors,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLV. The pr&aelig;tors] <quote lang="la">Pr&aelig;toribus urbanis,</quote> the pr&aelig;tors of the city.</note> Lucius Valerius Flaccus, and Caius Pomtinus, to arrest the retinue of the Allobroges, by laying in wait for them on the Milvian Bridge ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The Milvian Bridge] <quote lang="la">Ponte Mulvio.</quote> <foreign lang="la">Now Ponte Molle.</foreign></note> he gave them a full explanation of the object with which they were sent,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Of the object with which they were sent] <quote lang="la">Rem--cujus grati&acirc; mittebantur.</quote></note> and left them to manage the rest as occasion might require. Being military men, they placed a force, as had been directed, without disturbance, and secretly invested the bridge; when the deputies, with Volturcius, came to the place, and a shout was raised from each side of the bridge,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">From each side of the bridge] <quote lang="la">Utrinque.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Utrinque,"</foreign> observes Cortius <foreign lang="la">"gloss&aelig;</foreign> MSS. <foreign lang="la">exponunt ex utr&acirc;que parte pontis,</foreign>" and there is little doubt that the exposition is correct. No translator, however, before myself, has availed himself of it.</note> the Gauls, at once comprehending the matter, surrendered themselves immediately to the pr&aelig;tors. Volturcius, at first, encouraging his companions, defended himself against numbers with his sword; but afterward, being unsupported by the Allobroges, he began earnestly to beg Pomtinus, to whom he was known, to save his life, and at last, terrified and despairing of safety, he surrendered himself to the pr&aelig;tors as unconditionally as to foreign enemies.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="46">
<p> The affair being thus concluded, a full account of it was immediately transmitted to the consul by messengers. Great anxiety, and great joy, affected him at the same moment. He rejoiced that, by the discovery of the conspiracy, the state was freed from danger; but he was doubtful how he ought to act, when citizens of such eminence were detected in <pb n="49"/>treason so atrocious. He saw that their punishment would be a weight upon himself, and their escape the destruction of the Commonwealth. Having, however, formed his resolution, he ordered Lentulus, Cethegus, Statilius, Gabinius, and one Quintus C&aelig;parius of Terracina, who was preparing to go to Apulia to raise the slaves, to be summoned before him. The others came without delay; but C&aelig;parius, having left his house a little before, and heard of the discovery of the conspiracy, had fled from the city. The consul himself conducted Lentulus, as he was pr&aelig;tor, holding him by the hand, and ordered the others to be brought into the Temple of Concord, under a guard. Here he assembled the senate, and in a very full attendance of that body, introduced Volturcius with the deputies. Hither also he ordered Valerius Flaccus, the pr&aelig;tor, to bring the box with the letters<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLVI. The box with the letters] <quote lang="la">Scrinium cum literis.</quote> <foreign lang="la">Litter&aelig;</foreign> may be rendered either letter or letters. There is no mention made previously of more letters than that of Lentulus to Catiline, c. 44. But as it is not likely that the deputies carried a box to convey only one letter, I have followed other translators by putting the word in the plural. The oath of the conspirators, too, which was a written document, was probably in the box.</note> which he had taken from the deputies.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="47">
<p> Volturcius, being questioned concerning his journey, concerning his letter,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLVII. His letter] <quote lang="la">Litteris.</quote> His own letter to Catiline, c. 44. So <foreign lang="la">pr&aelig;ter litteras</foreign> a little below.</note> and lastly, what object he had had in view,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">What object he had had in view, etc.] <quote lang="la">Quid, aut qu&acirc; de caus&acirc;, consilii habuisset.</quote> What design he had entertained, and from what motive he had entertained it.</note> and from what motives he had acted, at first began to prevaricate,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To prevaricate] <quote lang="la">Fingere alia.</quote> <cit><quote>"To pretend other things than what had reference to the conspiracy."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> and to pretend ignorance of the conspiracy; but at length, when he was told to speak on the security of the public faith,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">On the security of the public faith] <quote lang="la">Fide public&acirc;.</quote> <cit><quote>"Cicero pledged to him the public faith, with the consent of the senate; or engaged, in the name of the republic, that his life should be spared, if he would but speak the truth."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> he disclosed every circumstance as it had really occurred, stating that he had been admitted as an associate, a few days before, by Gabinius and C&aelig;parius; that he knew no more than the deputies, only that he used to hear from Gabinius, that Publius Autronius, Servius Sylla, Lucius Vargunteius, and many others, were engaged in the conspiracy. The Gauls made a similar confession, and charged Lentulus, who began to affect ignorance, not only with the letter to Catiline, but with <pb n="50"/>remarks which he was in the habit of making, "that the sovereignity of Rome, by the Sibylline books, was predestined to three Cornelii; that Cinna and Sylla had ruled already ;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">That Cinna and Sylla had ruled already] <quote lang="la">Cinnam atque Syllam antea.</quote> "Had ruled," or something similar, must be supplied. Cinna had been the means of recalling Marius from Africa, in conjunction with whom he domineered over the city, and made it a scene of bloodshed and desolation.</note> and that he himself was the third, whose fate it would be to govern the city; and that this, too, was the twentieth year since the Capitol was burned; a year which the augurs, from certain omens, had often said would be stained with the blood of civil war."</p>
<p>The letter then being read, the senate, when all had previously acknowledged their seals,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Their seals] <quote lang="la">Signa sua.</quote> <cit><quote lang="fr">"Leurs cachets, leurs sceaux."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit> The Romans tied their letters round with a string, the knot of which they covered with wax, and impressed with a seal. To open the letter it was necessary to cut the string: "<foreign lang="la">nos linum incidimus.</foreign>" Cic. Or. in Cat. iii. 5. See also C. Nep. Paus. 4, and Adam's Roman Antiquities. The seal of Lentulus had on it a likeness of one of his ancestors; see Cicero, loc. cit.</note> decreed that Lentulus, being deprived of his office, should, as well as the rest, be placed in private custody.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In private custody] <quote lang="la">In liberis custodiis.</quote> Literally, in "free custody," but "private custody" conveys a better notion of the arrangement to the mind of the English reader. It was called free because the persons in custody were not confined in prison. Plutarch calls it <foreign lang="greek">u)/desmon fulakh/n,</foreign> as also Dion., cap. lviii. 3. See Tacit. Ann. vi. 3. It was adopted in the case of persons of rank and consideration.</note> Lentulus, accordingly, was given in charge to Publius Lentulus Spinther, who was then &aelig;dile; Cethegus, to Quintus Cornificius; Statilius, to Caius C&aelig;sar; Gabinius, to Marcus Crassus; and C&aelig;parius, who had just before been arrested in his flight, to Cneius Terentius, a senator.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="48">
<p> The common people, meanwhile, who had at first, from a desire of change in the government, been too much inclined to war, having, on the discovery of the plot, altered their sentiments, began to execrate the projects of Catiline, to extol Cicero to the skies; and, as if rescued from slavery, to give proofs of joy and exultation. Other effects of war they expected as a gain rather than a loss; but the burning of the city they thought inhuman, outrageous, and fatal, especially to themselves, whose whole property consisted in their daily necessaries and the clothes which they wore.</p>
<p>On the following day, a certain Lucius Tarquinius was brought before the senate, who was said to have been arrested as he was setting out to join Catiline. This person, having <pb n="51"/>offered to give information of the conspiracy, if the public faith were pledged to him,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLVIII. If the public faith were pledged to him] <quote lang="la">Si fides publica data esset.</quote> See c. 47.</note> and being directed by the consul to state what he knew, gave the senate nearly the same account as Volturcius had given, concerning the intended conflagration, the massacre of respectable citizens, and the approach of the enemy, adding that " he was sent by Marcus Crassus to assure Catiline that the apprehension of Lentulus, Cethegus, and others of the conspirators, ought not to alarm him, but that he should hasten, with so much the more expedition to the city, in order to revive the courage of the rest, and to facilitate the escape of those in custody."<note anchored="yes" place="foot">And to facilitate the escape of those in custody] <quote lang="la">Et illi facilius &egrave; periculo eriperentur.</quote></note> When Tarquinius named Crassus, a man of noble birth, of very great wealth, and of vast influence, some, thinking the statement incredible, others, though they supposed it true, yet, judging that at such a crisis a man of such power<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A man of such power] <quote lang="la">Tanta vis hominis.</quote> So great power of the man.</note> was rather to be soothed than irritated (most of them, too, from personal reasons, being under obligation to Crassus), exclaimed that he was " a false witness," and demanded that the matter should be put to the vote. Cicero, accordingly, taking their opinions, a full senate decreed " that the testimony of Tarquinius appeared false; that he himself should be kept in prison; and that no further liberty of speaking<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Liberty of speaking] <quote lang="la">Potestatem.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"'Potestatem loquendi."</foreign> <foreign lang="la">Cyprianus Popma.</foreign> As it did not appear that he spoke the truth, the pledge which the senate had given him, on condition that he spoke the truth, went for nothing; he was not allowed to continue his evidence, and was sent to prison.</note> should be granted him, unless he should name the person at whose instigation he had fabricated so shameful a calumny."</p>
<p>There were some, at that time, who thought that this affair was contrived by Publius Autronius, in order that the interest of Crassus, if he were accused, might, from participation in the danger, more readily screen the rest. Others said that Tarquinius was suborned by Cicero, that Crassus might not disturb the state, by taking upon him, as was his custom,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">As was his custom] <quote lang="la">More suo.</quote> Plutarch, in his Life of Crassus, relates that frequently when Pompey, C&aelig;sar, and Cicero, had refused to undertake the defense of certain persons, as being unworthy of their support, Crassus would plead in their behalf; and that he thus gained great popularity among the common people.</note> the <pb n="52"/>defense of the criminals. That this attack on his character was made by Cicero, I afterward heard Crassus himself assert.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="49">
<p> Yet, at the same time, neither by interest, nor by solicitation, nor by bribes, could Quintus Catulus, and Caius Piso, prevail upon Cicero to have Caius C&aelig;sar falsely accused, either by means of the Allobroges, or any other evidence. Both of these men were at bitter enmity with C&aelig;sar; Piso, as having been attacked by him, when he was on<note anchored="yes" place="foot">XLIX. Piso, as having been attacked by him, when he was on, etc.] <quote lang="la">Piso, oppugnatus in judicio repetundarum propter cujusdam Transpadani supplicium injustum.</quote> Such is the reading and punctuation of Cortius. Some editions insert <foreign lang="la">pecuniarum</foreign> before <foreign lang="la">repetundarum,</foreign> and some a comma after it. I have interpreted the passage in conformity with the explanation of Kritzius, which seems to me the most judicious that has been offered. <foreign lang="la">Oppugnatus,</foreign> says he, is equivalent to <foreign lang="la">gravitur vexatus,</foreign> or violently assailed and Piso was thus assailed by C&aelig;sar on account of his unjust execution of the Gaul; the words <foreign lang="la">in judicio repetundarum</foreign> merely mark the time when C&aelig;sar's attack was made. While he was on his trial for one thing, he was attacked by C&aelig;sar for another. Gerlach, observing that the words <foreign lang="la">in judicio</foreign> are wanting in one MS., would omit them, and make <foreign lang="la">oppugnatus</foreign> govern <foreign lang="la">pecuniarum repetundarum,</foreign> as if it were <foreign lang="la">accusatus;</foreign> a change which would certainly not improve the passage. The <foreign lang="la">Galli Transpadani</foreign> seem to have been much attached to C&aelig;sar; see Cic. Ep. ad Att., v. 2; ad Fam. xvi. 12.</note> his trial for extortion, on a charge of having illegally put to death a Transpadane Gaul; Catulus, as having hated him ever since he stood for the pontificate, because, at an advanced age, and after filling the highest offices, he had been defeated by C&aelig;sar, who was then comparatively a youth.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Comparatively a youth] <quote lang="la">Adolescentalo.</quote> C&aelig;sar was then in the thirty-third, or, as some say, the thirty-seventh year of his age. See the note on this word, c. 8.</note> The opportunity, too, seemed favorable for such an accusation; for C&aelig;sar, by extraordinary generosity in private, and by magnificent exhibitions in public,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">By magnificent exhibitions in public] <quote lang="la">Public&egrave; maximis muneribus.</quote> Shows of gladiators.</note> had fallen greatly into debt. But when they failed to persuade the consul to such injustice, they themselves, by going from one person to another, and spreading fictions of their own, which they pretended to have heard from Volturcius or the Allobroges, excited such violent odium against him, that certain Roman knights, who were stationed as an armed guard round the Temple of Concord, being prompted, either by the greatness of the danger, or by the impulse of a high spirit, to testify more openly their zeal for the republic, threatened C&aelig;sar with their swords as he went out of the senate-house.
<pb n="53"/></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="50">
<p> While these occurrences were passing in the senate, and while rewards were being voted, an approbation of their evidence, to the Allobrogian deputies and to Titus Volturcius, the freedmen, and some of the other dependents of Lentulus, were urging the artisans and slaves, in various directions throughout the city,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">L. In various directions throughout the city] <quote lang="la">Variis itineribus--in vicis.</quote> Going hither and thither through the streets.</note> to attempt his rescue; some, too, applied to the ringleaders of the mob, who were always ready to disturb the state for pay. Cethegus, at the same time, was soliciting, through his agents, his slaves<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Slaves] <quote lang="la">Familiam.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Servos suos, qui propri&egrave; familia."</foreign> Cortius. <foreign lang="la">Familia</foreign> is a number of <foreign lang="la">famuli.</foreign></note> and freedmen, men trained to deeds of audacity, to collect themselves into an armed body, and force a way into his place of confinement.</p>
<p>The consul, when he heard that these things were in agitation, having distributed armed bodies of men, as the circumstances and occasion demanded, called a meeting of the senate, and desired to know " what they wished to be done concerning those who had been committed to custody." A full senate, however, had but a short time before<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A full senate, however, had but a short time before, etc.] The senate had already decreed that they were enemies to their country; Cicero now calls a meeting to ascertain what sentence should be passed on them.</note> declared them traitors to their country. On this occasion, Decimus Junius Silanus, who, as consul elect, was first asked his opinion, moved<note anchored="yes" place="foot">On this occasion--moved] <quote lang="la">Tunc--decreverat.</quote> The <foreign lang="la">tunc</foreign> (or as most editors have it, <foreign lang="la">tum</foreign>) must be referred to the second meeting of the senate, for it does not appear that any proposal concerning the punishment of the prisoners was made at the first meeting. There would be no doubt on this point, were it not for the pluperfect tense, <foreign lang="la">decreverat.</foreign> I have translated it as the perfect. We must suppose that Sallust had his thoughts on C&aelig;sar's speech, which was to follow, and signifies that all this business had been done before C&aelig;sar addressed the house. Kritzius thinks that the pluperfect was referred by Sallust, not to C&aelig;sar's speech; but to the decree of the senate which was finally made; but this is surely a less satisfactory method of settling the matter. Sallust often uses the pluperfect, where his reader would expect the perfect; see, for instance, <foreign lang="la">concusserat,</foreign> at the beginning of c. 24.</note> that capital punishment should be inflicted, not only on those who were in confinement, but also on Lucius Cassius, Publius Furius, Publius Umbrenus, and Quintus Annius, if they should be apprehended; but afterward, being influenced by the speech of Caius C&aelig;sar, he said that he would go over to the opinion of Tiberius Nero,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">That he would go over to the opinion of Tiberius Nero] <quote lang="la">Pedibus in sententian Tib. Neronis--iturum.</quote> Any question submitted to the senate was decided by the majority of votes, which was ascertained either by <foreign lang="la">numeratio,</foreign> a counting of the votes, or by <foreign lang="la">discessio,</foreign> when those who were of one opinion, at the direction of the presiding magistrate, passed over to one side of the house, and those who were of the contrary opinion, to the other. See Aul. Gell. xiv. 7; Suet. Tib. 31; Adam's Rom. Ant.; Dr. Smith's Dictionary, Art. <foreign lang="la">Senatus.</foreign></note> <pb n="54"/>had proposed that the guards should be increased, and that the senate should deliberate further on the matter. C&aelig;sar, when it came to his turn, being asked his opinion by the consul, spoke to the following effect:</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="51">
<p> "It becomes all men,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LI. It becomes all men, etc.] The beginning of this speech, attributed to C&aelig;sar, is imitated from Demosthenes, <foreign lang="greek">*heri\ tw=n e)n *xersonh/sw| pragma/twn: )/*edei me\n, w)= u)/ndrez *aqhnai=oi, tou\z le/gontaz, u)/pantaz e)n u(mi=n mh/te pro\s e)/xqran poiei=sqai lo/gon mhde/na, mh/te pro\s xa/rin.</foreign> "It should be incumbent on all who speak before you, O Athenians, to advance no sentiment with any view either to enmity or to favor."</note> Conscript Fathers, who deliberate on dubious matters, to be influenced neither by hatred, affection, anger, nor pity. The mind, when such feelings obstruct its view, can not easily see what is right; nor has any human being consulted, at the same moment, his passion and his interest. When the mind is freely exerted, its reasoning is sound; but passion, if it gain possession of it, becomes its tyrant, and reason is powerless.</p>
<p>"I could easily mention, Conscript Fathers, numerous examples of kings and nations, who, swayed by resentment or compassion, have adopted injudicious courses of conduct; but I had rather speak of these instances in which our ancestors, in opposition to the impulse of passion, acted with wisdom and sound policy.</p>
<p>"In the Macedonian war, which we carried on against king Perses, the great and powerful state of Rhodes, which had risen by the aid of the Roman people, was faithless and hostile to us; yet, when the war was ended, and the conduct of the Rhodians was taken into consideration, our forefathers left them unmolested lest any should say that war was made upon them for the sake of seizing their wealth, rather than of punishing their faithlessness. Throughout the Punic war, too, though the Carthaginians, both during peace and in suspension of arms, were guilty of many acts of injustice, yet our ancestors never took occasion to retaliate, but considered rather what was worthy of themselves, than what might be justly inflicted on their enemies.</p>
<p>"Similar caution, Conscript Fathers, is to be observed by <pb n="55"/>yourselves, that the guilt of Lentulus, and the other conspirators, may not have greater weight with you than your own dignity, and that you may not regard your indignation more than your character. If, indeed, a punishment adequate to their crimes be discovered, I consent to extraordinary measures;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">I consent to extraordinary measures] <quote lang="la">Novum consilium adprobo.</quote> <cit><quote>"That is, I consent that you depart from the usage of your ancestors, by which Roman citizens were protected from death."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> but if the enormity of their crime exceeds whatever can be devised,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Whatever can be devised] <quote lang="la">Omnium ingenia.</quote></note> I think that we should inflict only such penalties as the laws have provided.</p>
<p>"Most of those, who have given their opinions before me, have deplored, in studied and impressive language,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Studied and impressive language] <quote lang="la">Composit&egrave;. atque magnific&egrave;.</quote> <foreign lang="la">Composit&egrave;,</foreign> in language nicely put together; elegantly. <foreign lang="la">Magnific&egrave;,</foreign> in striking or imposing terms. <foreign lang="la">Composit&egrave;</foreign> is applied to the speech of C&aelig;sar, by Cato, in the following chapter.</note> the sad fate that threatens the republic; they have recounted the barbarities of war, and the afflictions that would fallon the vanquished; they have told us that maidens would be dishonored, and youths abused; that children would be torn from the embraces of their parents; that matrons would be subjected to the pleasure of the conquerors; that temples and dwelling-houses would be plundered; that massacres and fires would follow; ane that every place would be filled with arms, corpses, blood, and lamentation. But to what end, in the name of the eternal gods! was such eloquence directed? Was it intended to render you indignant at the conspiracy? A speech, no doubt, will inflame him whom so frightful and monstrous a reality has not provoked! Far from it: for to no man does evil, directed against himself, appear a light matter; many, on the contrary, have felt it more seriously than was right.</p>
<p>"But to different persons, Conscript Fathers, different degrees of license are allowed. If those who pass a life sunk in obscurity, commit any error, through excessive angel, few become aware of it, for their fame is as limited as their fortune; but of those who live invested with extensive power, and in an exalted station, the whole world knows the proceedings. Thus in the highest position there is the least liberty of action; and it becomes us to indulge neither partiality nor aversion, but least of all animosity; for what in others is called resentment, is in the powerful termed violence and cruelty.
<pb n="56"/></p>
<p>"I am indeed of opinion, Conscript Fathers, that the utmost degree of torture is inadequate to punish their crime; but the generality of mankind dwell on that which happens last, and, in the case of malefactors, forget their guilt, and talk only of their punishment, should that punishment have been inordinately severe. I feel assured, too, that Decimus Silanus, a man of spirit and resolution, made the suggestions which he offered, from zeal for the state, and that he had no view, in so important a matter, to favor or to enmity; such I know to be his character, and such his discretion.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Such I know to be his character, such his discretion] <quote lang="la">Eos mores, earn modestiam viri cognovi.</quote> I have translated <foreign lang="la">modestiam,</foreign> discretion, which seems to be the proper meaning of the word. Beauz&eacute;e renders it prudence, and adds a note upon it, which may be worth transcription. "I translate <foreign lang="la">modestia,</foreign>" says he, "by prudence, and think myself authorized to do so. <foreign lang="la">Sic definitur &agrave; Stoicis,</foreign> says Cicero (De Off. i. 40), <foreign lang="la">ut modestia sit sicentia earum rerum, qu&aelig; agentur, aut dicentur, loco suo collocandarum;</foreign> and shortly afterward, <foreign lang="la">Sic fit ut modestia scientia sit opportunitatis idoneorum ad agendum temporum.</foreign> And what is understood in French by prudence? It is, according to the Dictionary of the Academy, 'a virtue by which we discern and practice what is proper in the conduct of life.' This is almost a translation of the words of Cicero."</note> Yet his proposal appears to me, I will not say cruel (for what can be cruel that is directed against such characters?), but foreign to our policy. For assuredly, Silanus, either your fears, or their treason, must have induced you, a consul elect, to propose this new kind of punishment. Of fear it is unnecessary to speak, when by the prompt activity of that distinguished man our consul, such numerous forces are under arms; and as to the punishment, we may say, what is indeed the truth, that in trouble and distress, death is a relief from suffering, and not a torment;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">That--death is a relief from suffering, not a torment, etc.] This Epicurean doctrine prevailed very much at Rome in C&aelig;sar's time, and afterward. We may very well suppose C&aelig;sar to have been a sincere convert to it. Cato alludes to this passage in the speech which follows; as also Cicero, in his fourth Oration against Catiline, c. 4. See, for opinions on this point, the first book of Cicero's Tusculan Questions.</note> that it puts an end to all human woes; and that, beyond it, there is no place either for sorrow or joy.</p>
<p>"But why, in the name of the immortal gods, did you not add to your proposal, Silanus, that, before they were put to death, they should be punished with the scourge? Was it because the Porcian law<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The Porcian law] <quote lang="la">Lex Portia.</quote> A law proposed by P. Porcius L&aelig;ca, one of the tribunes, A. U. C. 454, which enacted that no one should bind, scourge, or kill a Roman citizen. See Liv., x. 9; Cic. pro. Rabir., 3, 4; Verr., v. 63; de Rep., ii, 31.</note> forbids it? But other <pb n="57"/>laws<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Other laws] <quote lang="la">Ali&aelig; leges.</quote> So C&aelig;sar says below, <foreign lang="la">"Tum lex Porcia ali&aelig;que parat&aelig;, quibus legibus auxilium damnatis permissum;"</foreign> what other laws these were is uncertain. One of them, however, was the Sempronian law, proposed by Caius Gracchus, which ordained that sentence should not be passed on the life of a Roman citizen without the order of the people. See Cic. pro Rabir. 4. So <foreign lang="la">"O lex Porcia legesque Semproni&aelig;!"</foreign> Cic. in Verr., v. 63.</note> forbid condemned citizens to be deprived of life, and allow them to go into exile. Or was it because scourging is a severer penalty than death? Yet what can be too severe, or too harsh, toward men convicted of such an offense? But if scourging be a milder punishment than death, how is it consistent to observe the law as to the smaller point, when you disregard it as to the greater?</p>
<p>"But who it may be asked, will blame any severity that shall be decreed against these parricides<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Parricides] See c. 14, 32.</note> of their country? I answer that time, the course of events,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The course of events] <quote lang="la">Dies.</quote> <cit><quote><foreign lang="la">"Id est, temporis momentum (<foreign lang="de">der ver&auml;n derte Zeitpunkt</foreign>)."</foreign></quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit> Things change, and that which is approved at one period, is blamed at another. <foreign lang="la">Tempus</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">dies</foreign> are sometimes joined (Liv., xxii. 39, ii. 45), as if not only time in general, but particular periods, as from day to day, were intended.</note> and fortune, whose caprice governs nations, may blame it. Whatever shall fall on the traitors, will fall on them justly; but it is for you, Conscript Fathers, to consider well what you resolve to inflict on others. All precedents productive of evil effects,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">All precedents productive of evil effects] <quote lang="la">Omnia mala exempla.</quote> Examples of severe punishments are meant.</note> have had their origin from what was good; but when a government passes into the hands of the ignorant or unprincipled, any new example of severity,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Any new example of severity, etc.] <quote lang="la">Novum illud exemplum ab dignis et idoneis ad indignos et non idoneos transferetur.</quote> Gerlach, Kritzius, Dietsch, and Bernouf, agree to giving to this passage the sense which is given in the translation. <foreign lang="la">Digni</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">idonei</foreign> are here used in a bad sense, for <foreign lang="la">digni et idonei qui p&aelig;n&acirc; afficiantur,</foreign> deserving and fit objects for punishment.</note> inflicted on deserving and suitable objects, is extended to those that are improper and undeserving of it. The Laced&aelig;monians, when they had conquered the Athenians,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">When they had conquered the Athenians] At the conclusion of the Peloponnesian war.</note> appointed thirty men to govern their state. These thirty began their administration by putting to death, even without a trial, all who were notoriously wicked, or publicly detestable; acts at which the people rejoiced, and extolled their justice. But afterward, when their lawless power gradually increased, they proceeded, at their pleasure, to kill the good and the bad indiscriminately, <pb n="58"/>and to strike terror into all; and thus the state, overpowered and enslaved, paid a heavy penalty for its imprudent exultation.</p>
<p>"Within our own memory, too, when the victorious Sylla ordered Damasippus,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Damasippus] "He, in the consulship of Caius Marius, the younger, and Cneius Carbo, was city pr&aelig;tor, and put to death some of the most eminent senators, a short time before the victory of Sylla. See Veil. Paterc. ii. 26." <bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></note> and others of similar character, who had risen by distressing their country, to be put to death, who did not commend the proceeding? All exclaimed that wicked and factious men, who had troubled the state with their seditious practices, had justly forfeited their lives. Yet this proceeding was the commencement of great bloodshed. For whenever any one coveted the mansion or villa, or even the plate or apparel of another, he exerted his influence to have him numbered among the proscribed. Thus they, to whom the death of Damasippus had been a subject of joy, were soon after dragged to death themselves; nor was there any cessation of slaughter, until Sylla had glutted all his partisans with riches.</p>
<p>"Such excesses, indeed, I do not fear from Marcus Tullius, or in these times. But in a large state there arise many men of various dispositions. At some other period, and under another consul, who, like the present, may have an army at his command, some false accusation may be credited as true; and when, with our example for a precedent, the consul shall have drawn the sword on the authority of the senate, who shall stay its progress, or moderate its fury?</p>
<p>"Our ancestors, Conscript Fathers, were never deficient in conduct or courage; nor did pride prevent them from imitating the customs of other nations, if they appeared deserving of regard. Their armor, and weapons of war, they borrowed from the Samnites; their ensigns of authority,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Ensigns of authority] <quote lang="la">Insignia magistratum.</quote> "The fasces and axes of the twelve lictors, the robe adorned with purple, the curule chair, and the ivory scepter. For the Etrurians, as Dionysius Halicarnassensis relates, having been subdued, in a nine years' war, by Tarquinius Priscus, and having obtained peace on condition of submitting to him as their sovereign, presented him with the <foreign lang="la">insignia</foreign> of their own monarchs. See Strabo, lib. v.; Florus, i. 5." <bibl>Kuhnhardt.</bibl></note> for the most part, from the Etrurians; and, in short, whatever appeared eligible to them, whether among allies or among enemies, they adopted at home with the greatest readiness, being more inclined to <pb n="59"/>emulate merit than to be jealous of it. But at the same time, adopting a practice from Greece, they punished their citizens with the scourge, and inflicted capital punishment on such as were condemned. When the republic, however, became powerful, and faction grew strong from the vast number of citizens, men began to involve the innocent in condemnation, and other like abuses were practiced; and it was then that the Porcian and other laws were provided, by which condemned citizens were allowed to go into exile. This lenity of our ancestors, Conscript Fathers, I regard as a very strong reason why we should not adopt any new measures of severity. For assuredly there was greater merit and wisdom in those, who raised so mighty an empire from humble means, than in us, who can scarcely preserve what they so honorably acquired. Am I of opinion, then, you will ask, that the conspirators should be set free, and that the army of Catiline should thus be increased? Far from it; my recommendation is, that their property be confiscated, and that they themselves be kept in custody in such of the municipal towns as are best able to bear the expense;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Best able to bear the expense] <quote lang="la">Maxim&egrave; opibus valent.</quote> Are possessed of most resources.</note> that no one hereafter bring their case before the senate, or speak on it to the people; and that the senate now give their opinion, that he who shall act contrary to this, will act against the republic and the general safety."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="52">
<p> When C&aelig;sar had ended his speech, the rest briefly expressed their assent,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LII. The rest briefly expressed their assent, etc.] <quote lang="la">C&aelig;teri verbo, alius alii, vari&egrave; assentiebantur. Verbo assentiebantur</quote> signifies that they expressed their assent merely by a word or two, as <foreign lang="la">assentior Silano, assentior Tiberio Neroni, aut C&aelig;sari,</foreign> the three who had already spoken. <foreign lang="la">Vari&egrave;,</foreign> "in support of their different proposals."</note> some to one speaker, and some to another, in support of their different proposals; but Marcius Porcius Cato, being asked his opinion, made a speech to the following purport:</p>
<p>"My feelings, Conscript Fathers, are extremely different,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">My feelings, Conscript Fathers, are extremely different, etc.] <quote lang="la">Long&egrave; mihi alia mens est, P. C.,</quote> etc. The commencement of Cato's speech is evidently copied from the beginning of the third Olynthiac of Demosthenes: <foreign lang="greek">)*ouxi\ tau=ta pari/statai/ moi ginw/skein, w) u)/ndrez )*aqhnai=i, o(/tan te e)is tu\ pru/gmata u)poble/yw kai\ o(/tan pro\z tou\z lo/gouz o(u\z u)kou/w tou\z ue\n ga\r lo/gouz peri\ tou= timwrh/sasqai *fi/lippon o(rw(= gignome/nouz, tu\ de\ pru/gmata e)iz tou=to proh/konta w(/ste o(/pwz mh\ peiso\meqa a)ntoi\ pro/teron kakw=z ske/yasqai de/on.</foreign> <cit><quote>"I am by no means affected in the same manner, Athenians, when I review the state of our affairs, and when I attend to those speakers who have now declared their sentiments. They insist that we should punish Philip, but our affairs, situated as they now appear, warn us to guard against the dangers with which we ourselves are threatened."</quote><bibl>Leland.</bibl></cit></note> <pb n="60"/>when I contemplate our circumstances and dangers, and when I revolve in my mind the sentiments of some who have spoken before me. Those speakers, as it seems to me, have considered only how to punish the traitors who have raised war against their country, their parents, their altars, and their homes;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Their altars and their homes] <quote lang="la">Aris atque focis suis.</quote> "When <foreign lang="la">ar&aelig;</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">foci</foreign> are joined, beware of supposing that they are to be distinguished as referring the one (<foreign lang="la">ar&aelig;</foreign>) to the public temples, and the other (<foreign lang="la">foci</foreign>) to private dwellings. * * * Both are to be understood of private houses, in which the <foreign lang="la">ara</foreign> belonged to the <foreign lang="la">Dii Penates,</foreign> and was placed in the <foreign lang="la">impluvium</foreign> in the inner part of the house; the <foreign lang="la">focus</foreign> was dedicated to the <foreign lang="la">lares,</foreign> and was in the halt." Ernesti, Clav. Cic., sub. v. <foreign lang="la">Ara.</foreign> Of the commentators on Sallust, Kritzius is, I believe, the only one who has concurred in this notion of Ernesti; Langius and Dietsch (with Cortius) adhere to the common opinion that <foreign lang="la">ar&aelig;</foreign> are the public altars. Dietsch refers, for a complete refutation of Ernesti, to G. A. B. Hertzberg <foreign lang="la">de Diis Romanorum Penatibus,</foreign> Hal&aelig;, <date value="1840">1840</date>, p. 64; a book which I have not seen. Certainly, in the observation of Cicero ad Att., vii. 11, <foreign lang="la">"Non est respublica in parietibus, sed in aris et focis,"</foreign> <foreign lang="la">ar&aelig;</foreign> must be considered (as Schiller observes) to denote the public altars and national religion. See Schiller's Lex. v. <foreign lang="la">Ara.</foreign></note> but the state of affairs warns us rather to secure ourselves against them, than to take counsel as to what sentence we should pass upon them. Other crimes you may punish after they have been committed; but as to this, unless you prevent its commission, you will, when it has once taken effect, in vain appeal to justice.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In vain appeal to justice] <quote lang="la">Frusta judicia implores.</quote> <foreign lang="la">Judicia,</foreign> trials, to procure the inflictions of legal penalties.</note> When the city is taken, no power is left to the vanquished.</p>
<p>"But, in the name of the immortal gods, I call upon you, who have always valued your mansions and villas, your statues and pictures, at a higher price than the welfare of your country; if you wish to preserve those possessions, of whatever kind they are, to which you are attached; if you wish to secure quiet for the enjoyment of your pleasures, arouse yourselves, and act in defense of your country. We are not now debating on the revenues, or on injuries done to our allies, but our liberty and our life is at stake.</p>
<p>"Often, Conscript Fathers, have I spoken at great length in this assembly; often have I complained of the luxury and avarice of our citizens, and, by that very means, have incurred the displeasure of many. I, who never excused to myself, or <pb n="61"/>to my own conscience, the commission of any fault, could not easily pardon the misconduct,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Could not easily pardon the misconduct, etc.] <quote lang="la">Hand facile alterius lubidini maleafacta condonabam.</quote> "Could not easily forgive the licentiousness of another its evil deeds."</note> or indulge the licentiousness, of others. But though you little regarded my remonstrances, yet the republic remained secure; its own strength<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Yet the republic remained secure; its own strength, etc.] <quote lang="la">Tamen respublica firma, opulentia neglegentiam tolerabat.</quote> This is Cortius's reading; some editors, as Havercamp, Kritzius, and Dietsch, insert <foreign lang="la">erat</foreign> after <foreign lang="la">firma.</foreign> Whether <foreign lang="la">opulentia</foreign> is the nominative or ablative, is disputed. "<foreign lang="la">Opulentia,"</foreign> says Allen, <foreign lang="la">"casum sextum intellige, et repete respublica (ad tolerabat)."</foreign> "<foreign lang="la">Opulentia,</foreign>" says Kritzius, <foreign lang="la">"melius nominativo capiendum videtur; nam que sequuntur verba novam enunciationem efficient."</foreign> I have preferred to take it as a nominative.</note> was proof against your remissness. The question, however, at present under discussion, is not whether we live in a good or a bad state of morals; nor how great, or how splendid, the empire of the Roman people is; but whether these things around us, of whatever value they are, are to continue our own, or to fall, with ourselves, into the hands of the enemy.</p>
<p>"In such a case, does any one talk to me of gentleness and compassion? For some time past, it is true, we have lost the real name of things;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">We have lost the real names of things, etc.] Imitated from Thuydides, iii. 32: <foreign lang="greek">*kai th\n e)iwqu\ian u)ciwsin tw=n o)noma/twn e)z tu\ e)/rga a)nth/llacan th=( dikaiw/sei. *to/lma me\n ga\r a)lo/gistos, a)nsri/a file/tairos e)nomi/sqh, mellmsiz te promhqh\s, seigia e)upreph\s to\ de\ sw\fron, tou= ana/ndrou pro/sxhma, ka\i to\ pro\s a)/pan suneto\n, e)pi\ pa)n a)rgo/n.</foreign> "The ordinary meaning of words was changed by then as they thought proper. For reckless daring was regarded as courage that was true to its friends; prudent delay, as specious cowardice; moderation, as a cloak for unmanliness; being intelligent in every thing, as being useful for nothing." Dale's translation: Bohn's Classical Library.</note> for to lavish the property of others is called generosity, and audacity in wickedness is called heroism; and hence the state is reduced to the brink of ruin. But let those, who thus misname things; be liberal, since such is the practice, out of the property of our allies; let them be merciful to the robbers of the treasury; but let them not lavish our blood, and, while they spare a few criminals, bring destruction on all the guiltless.</p>
<p>"Caius CA&aelig;sar, a short time ago, spoke in fair and elegant language,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Elegant language] <quote lang="la">Composit&egrave;.</quote> See above, c. 51.</note> before this assembly, on the subject of life and death; considering as false, I suppose, what is told of the dead; that the bad, going a different way from the good, inhabit <pb n="62"/>places gloomy, desolate, dreary, and full of horror. He accordingly proposed that the property of the conspirators should be confiscated, and themselves kept in custody in the municipal towns; fearing, it seems, that, if they remain at Rome, they may be rescued either by their accomplices in the conspiracy, or by a hired mob; as if, forsooth, the mischievous and profligate were to be found only in the city, and not through the whole of Italy, or as if desperate attempts would not be more likely to succeed where there is less power to resist them. His proposal, therefore, if he fears any danger from them, is absurd; but if, amid such universal terror, he alone is free from alarm, it the more concerns me to fear for you and myself.</p>
<p>"Be assured, then, that when you decide on the fate of Lentulus and the other prisoners, you at the same time determine that of the army of Catilihe, and of all the conspirators. The more spirit you display in your decision, the more will their confidence be diminished; but if they shall perceive you in the smallest degree irresolute, they will advance upon you with fury.</p>
<p>"Do not suppose that our ancestors, from so small a commencement, raised the republic to greatness merely by force of arms. If such had been the case, we should enjoy it in a most excellent condition;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">In a most excellent condition] <quote lang="la">Multo pulcherrumam.</quote> See c. 36.</note> for of allies and citizens,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">For of allies and citizens, etc.] Imitated from Demosthenes, Philipp tn. 4.</note> as well as arms and horses, we have a much greater abundance than they had. But there were other things which made them great, but which among us have no existence; such as industry at home, equitable government abroad, and minds impartial in council, uninfluenced by any immoral or improper feeling. Instead of such virtues, we have luxury and avarice; public distress, and private superfluity; we extol wealth, and yield to indolence; no distinction is made between good men and bad; and ambition usurps the honors due to virtue. Nor is this wonderful; since you study each his individual interest, and since at home you are slaves to pleasure, and here to money or favor; and hence it happens that an attack is made on the defenseless state.</p>
<p>"But on these subjects I shall say no more. Certain citizens, <pb n="63"/>of the highest rank, have conspired to ruin their country; they are engaging the Gauls, the bitterest foes of the Roman name, to join in a war against us; the leader of the enemy is ready to make a descent upon us; and do you hesitate, even in such circumstances, how to treat armed incendiaries arrested within your walls? I advise you to have mercy upon them<note anchored="yes" place="foot">I advise you to have mercy upon them] <quote lang="la">Misereamini censeo,</quote> i.e., <foreign lang="la">censeo ut misereamini</foreign>, spoken ironically. Most translators have taken the words in the sense of "You would take pity on them, I suppose," or something similar.</note> they are young men who have been led astray by ambition; send them away, even with arms in their hands. But such mercy, and such clemency, if they turn those arms against you, will end in misery to yourselves. The case is, assuredly, dangerous, but you do not fear it; yes, you fear it greatly, but you hesitate how to act, through weakness and want of spirit, waiting one for another, and trusting to the immortal gods, who have so often preserved your country in the greatest dangers. But the protection of the gods is not obtained by vows and effeminate supplications; it is by vigilance, activity, and prudent measures, that general welfare is secured. When you are once resigned to sloth and indolence, it is in vain that you implore the gods; for they are then indignant and threaten vengeance.</p>
<p>"In the days of our forefathers, Titus Manlius Torquatus, during a war with the Gauls, ordered his own son to be put to death, because he had fought with an enemy contrary to orders. That noble youth suffered for excess of bravery; and do you hesitate what sentence to pass on the most inhuman of traitors? Perhaps their former life is at variance with their present crime. Spare, then, the dignity of Lentulus, if he has ever spared his own honor or character, or had any regard for gods or for men. Pardon the youth of Cethegus, unless this be the second time that he has made war upon his country.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Unless this be the second time that he has made war upon his country] <cit><quote>"Cethegus first made war ou his country in conjunction with Marius."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit> Whether Sallust alludes to this, or intimates (as Gerlach thinks) that he was engaged in the first conspiracy, is doubtful.</note> As to Gabinius, Statilius, C&aelig;parius, why should I make any remark upon them? Had they ever possessed the smallest share of discretion, they would never have engaged in such a plot against their country.</p>
<p>"In conclusion, Conscript Fathers, if there were time to <pb n="64"/>amend an error, I might easily suffer you, since you disregard words, to be corrected by experience of consequences. But we are beset by dangers on all sides; Catiline, with his army, is ready to devour us;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Is ready to devour us] <quote lang="la">Faucibus urget.</quote> Cortius, Kritzius, Gerlach, Burnouf, Allen, and Dietsch, are unanimous in interpreting this as a metaphorical expression, alluding to a wild beast with open jaws ready to spring upon its prey. They support this interpretation by Val. Max., v. 3: <foreign lang="la">"Faucibus apprehensam rempublicam;"</foreign> Cic. pro. Cluent., 31: <foreign lang="la">"Quum faucibus premetur;"</foreign> and Plaut. Casin. v. 3, 4, <foreign lang="la">"Manifesto faucibus teneor."</foreign> Some editors have read <foreign lang="la">in faucibus,</foreign> and understood the words as referring to the jaws or narrow passes of Etruria, where Catilme was with his army.</note> while there are other enemies within the walls, and in the heart of the city; nor can any measures be taken, or any plans arranged, without their knowledge. The more necessary is it, therefore, to act with promptitude. What I advise, then, is this: that since the state, by a treasonable combination of abandoned citizens, has been brought into the greatest peril; and since the conspirators have been convicted on the evidence of Titus Volturcius, and the deputies of the Allobroges, and on their own confession, of having concerted massacres, conflagrations, and other horrible and cruel outrages, against their fellow-citizens and their country, punishment be inflicted, according to the usage of our ancestors, on the prisoners who have confessed their guilt, as on men convicted of capital crimes."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="53">
<p> When Cato had resumed his seat, all the senators of consular dignity, and a great part of the rest,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LIII. All the senators of consular dignity, and a great part of the rest] <quote lang="la">Consulares omnes, itemque senat&uacute;s magna pars.</quote> <cit><quote>"As the consulars were senators, the reader would perhaps expect Sallust to have said <foreign lang="la">reliqui senat&ucirc;s,</foreign> but <foreign lang="la">itemque</foreign> is equivalent to <foreign lang="la">et pr&aelig;ter eos.</foreign>"</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit></note> applauded his opinion, and extolled his firmness of mind to the skies. With mutual reproaches, they accused one another of timidity, while Cato was regarded as the greatest and noblest of men; and a decree of the senate was made as he had advised.</p>
<p>After reading and hearing of the many glorious achievements which the Roman people had performed at home and in the field, by sea as well as by land, I happened to be led to consider what had been the great foundation of such illustrious deeds. I knew that the Romans had frequently, with small bodies of men, encountered vast armies of the enemy; I was aware that they had carried on wars<note anchored="yes" place="foot">That they had carried on wars] <quote lang="la">Bella gesta.</quote> That wars had been carried on by them.</note> with limited forces <pb n="65"/>against powerful sovereigns; that they had often sustained, too, the violence of adverse fortune; yet that, while the Greeks excelled them in eloquence, the Gauls surpassed them in military glory. After much reflection, I felt convinced that the eminent virtue of a few citizens had been the cause of all these successes; and hence it had happened that poverty had triumphed over riches, and a few over a multitude. And even in later times, when the state had become corrupted by luxury and indolence, the republic still supported itself, by its own strength, under the misconduct of its generals and magistrates; when, as if the parent stock were exhausted,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">As if the parent stock were exhausted] <quote lang="la">Sicuti eff&aelig;ta parentum.</quote> This is the reading of Cortius, which he endeavors to explain thus: <foreign lang="la">"Ac sicuti eff&aelig;ta parens, inter parentes, sese habere solet, ut nullos amplius liberas proferat, sic Roma sese habuit, ubi multis tempestatibus nemo virtute magnus fuit."</foreign> <foreign lang="la">"Est,"</foreign> he adds, "or <foreign lang="la">solet esse,</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">sese habere solet,</foreign> may very well be understood from the <foreign lang="la">fuit</foreign> which follows." But all this only serves to show what a critic may find to say in defense of a reading to which he is determined to adhere. All the MSS., indeed, have <foreign lang="la">parentum</foreign>, except one, which has <foreign lang="la">parente.</foreign> Dietsch thinks that some word has been lost between <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;ta</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">parentum,</foreign> and proposes to read <foreign lang="la">sicuti eff&aelig;ta &aelig;tate parentum,</foreign> with the sense, as if the age of the parents were too much exhausted to produce strong children. Kritzius, from a suggestion of Cortius (or rather of his predecessor, Rupertus), reads <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;t&aelig; parentum</foreign> (the <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;t&aelig;</foreign> agreeing with <foreign lang="la">Rom&aelig;</foreign> which follows), considering the sense to be the same as <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;t&aelig; parentis</foreign>--as <foreign lang="la">divina dearum</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">divina dea,</foreign> etc. Gerlach retains the reading of Cortius, and adopts his explanation (4to. ed., 1827), but says that the <foreign lang="la">explicatio</foreign> may seem <foreign lang="la">durior,</foreign> and that it is doubtful whether we ought not to have recourse to the <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;ta parente</foreign> of the old critics. Assuredly if we retain <foreign lang="la">parentum, eff&aelig;t&aelig;</foreign> is the only reading that we can well put with it. We may compare with it <foreign lang="la">loca nuda gignentium,</foreign> (Jug. c. 79), i.e. "places bare of objects producing anything." Gronovius knew not what to do with the passage, called it <foreign lang="la">locus intellectus nemini,</foreign> and at last decided on understanding <foreign lang="la">virtute</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;t&aelig; parentum,</foreign> which, <foreign lang="la">pace tanti viri,</foreign> and although Allen has followed him, is little better than folly. The concurrence of the majority of manuscripts in giving <foreign lang="la">parentum</foreign> makes the scholar unwilling to set it aside. However, as no one has explained it satisfactorily even to himself, I have thought it better, with Dietsch, to regard it a <foreign lang="la">scriptura non ferenda,</foreign> and to acquiesce, with Glareanus, Rivius, Burnouf, and the Bipont edition, in the reading <foreign lang="la">eff&aelig;t&acirc; parente.</foreign></note> there was certainly not produced at Rome, for many years, a single citizen of eminent ability. Within my recollection, however, there arose two men of remarkable powers, though of very different character, Marcus Cato and Caius C&aelig;sar, whom, since the subject has brought them before me, it is not my intention to pass in silence, but to describe, to the best of my ability, the disposition and manners of each.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="54">
<p> Their birth, age, and eloquence, were nearly on an equality; their greatness of mind similar, as was also their reputation, <pb n="66"/>though attained by different means.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LIV. Though attained by different means] <quote lang="la">Sed alia alii.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Alii alia gloria,"</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">altera alteri.</foreign> So Livy, i. 21: <foreign lang="la">Duo reges, alius ali&acirc; via.</foreign></note> C&aelig;sar grew eminent by genesroity and munificence; Cato by the integrity of his life. C&aelig;sar was esteemed for his humanity and benevolence; austereness had given dignity to Cato. C&aelig;sar acquired renown by giving, relieving, and pardoning; Cato by bestowing nothing. In C&aelig;sar, there was a refuge for the unfortunate; in Cato, destruction for the bad. In C&aelig;sar, his easiness of temper was admired; in Cato, his firmness. C&aelig;sar, in fine, had applied himself to a life of energy and activity; intent upon the interest of his friends, he was neglectful of his own; he refused nothing to others that was worthy of acceptance, while for himself he desired great power, the command of an army, and a new war in which his talents might be displayed. But Cato's ambition was that of temperance, discretion, and, above all, of austerity; he did not contend in splendor with the rich, or in faction with the seditious, but with the brave in fortitude, with the modest in simplicity,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Simplicity] <quote lang="la">Pudore.</quote> The word here seems to mean the absence of display and ostentation.</note> with the temperate<note anchored="yes" place="foot">With the temperate] <quote lang="la">Cum innocente.</quote> <cit><quote>"That is <foreign lang="la">cum integro et abstinente.</foreign> For <foreign lang="la">innocentia</foreign> is used for <foreign lang="la">abstinentia,</foreign> and opposed to <foreign lang="la">avaritia.</foreign> See Cic. pro Lege Maml., c. 13."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> in abstinence; he was more desirous to be, than to appear, virtuous; and thus, the less he courted popularity, the more it pursued him.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="55">
<p> When the senate, as I have stated, had gone over to the opinion of Cato, the counsel, thinking it best not to wait till night, which was coring on, lest any new attempts should be made during the interval, ordered the triumvirs<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LV. The triumvirs] <quote lang="la">Triumviros.</quote> The <foreign lang="la">triumviri capitales</foreign> who had the charge of the prison and of the punishment of the condemned. They performed their office by deputy, Val. Max., v. 4, 7.</note> to make such preparations as the execution of the conspirators required. He himself, having posted the necessary guards, conducted Lentulus to the prison; and the same office was performed for the rest by the pr&aelig;tors.</p>
<p>There is a place in the prison, which is called the Tullian dungeon,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The Tullian dungeon] <quote lang="la">Tullianum.</quote> <foreign lang="la">Tullianum</foreign> is an adjective, with which <foreign lang="la">robur</foreign> must be understoood, as it was originally constructed, wholly or partially, with oak. See Festus, <foreign lang="la">sub voce Robum</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">Robur:</foreign> his words are <foreign lang="la">arcis robustis incluaebatur,</foreign> of which the sense is not very clear. The prison at Rome was built by Ancus Marcius, and enlarged by Servius Tullius, from whom this part of it had its name; Varro de L. L., iv. 33. It is now transformed into a subterranean chapel, beneath a small church erected over it, called <foreign lang="it">San Pietro in Carcere.</foreign> De Brosses and Eustace both visited it; See Eustace's Classical Tour, vol. i. p. 260, in the Family Library. See also Wasse's note on this passage.</note> and which, after a slight ascent to the left, is sunk <pb n="67"/>about twelve feet under ground. Walls secure it on every side, and over it is a vaulted roof connected with stone arches;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A vaulted roof connected with stone arches] <quote lang="la">Camera lapideis fornicibus vincta.</quote> <cit><quote>"That <foreign lang="la">camera</foreign> was a roof curved in the form of a <foreign lang="la">testudo,</foreign> is generally admitted; see Vitruv. vii. 3; Varr., R. R. iii. 7, init."</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit> The roof is now arched in the usual way.</note> but its appearance is disgusting and horrible, by reason of the filth, darkness, and stench. When Lentulus had been let down into this place, certain men, to whom orders had been given,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Certain men, to whom orders had been given] <quote lang="la">Quibus pr&aelig;ceptum erat.</quote> The editions of Havercamp, Gerlach, Kritzius, and Dietsch, have <foreign lang="la">vindices rerum capitalium, quibus,</foreign> etc. Cortius ejected the first three words from his text as an intruded gloss. If the words be genuine, we must consider these <foreign lang="la">vindices</foreign> to have been the deputies, or <foreign lang="la">lictors,</foreign> of the <foreign lang="la">triumvirs</foreign> mentioned above.</note> strangled him with a cord. Thus this patrician, who was of the illustrious family of the Cornelli, and who filled the office of consul at Rome, met with an end suited to his character and conduct. On Cethegus, Statilius, Gabinius, and C&aelig;parius, punishment was inflicted in a similar manner.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="56">
<p> During these proceedings at Rome, Catiline, out of the entire force which he himself had brought with him, and that which Manlius had previously collected, formed two legions, filling up the cohorts as far as his number would allow;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LVI. As far as his numbers would allow] <quote lang="la">Pro numero militum.</quote> He formed his men into two bodies, which he called legions, and divided each legion, as was usual, into ten cohorts, putting into each cohort as many men as he could. The cohort of a full legion consisted of three maniples, or six hundred men; the legion would then be six thousand men. But the legions were seldom so large as this; they varied at different periods, from six thousand to three thousand; in the time of Polybius they were usually four thousand two hundred. See Adam's Rom. Ant., and Lipsius de Mil. Rom Dial. iv.</note> and afterward, as any volunteers, or recruits from his confederates,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">From his confederates] <quote lang="la">Ex sociis.</quote> <cit><quote>"Understand, not only the leaders in the conspiracy, but those who, in c. 35, are said to have set out to join Catiline, though not at that time exactly implicated in the plot."</quote><bibl>Kritzius.</bibl></cit> It is necessary to notice this, because Cortius erroneously supposes <foreign lang="la">sociis</foreign> to mean the allies of Rome. Dahl, Longius, Muller, Bernouf, Gerlach, and Dietsch, all interpret in the same manner as Kritzius.</note> arrived in his camp, he distributed them equally throughout the cohorts, and thus filled up his legions, in a short time, with their regular number of men, though at first he had not more than two thousand. But, of his whole army, only about a fourth <pb n="68"/>part had the proper weapons of soldiers; the rest, as chance had equipped them, carried darts, spears, or sharpened stakes.</p>
<p>As Antonius approached with his army, Catiline directed his march over the hills, encamping, at one time, in the direction of Rome, at another in that of Gaul. He gave the enemy no opportunity of fighting, yet hoped himself shortly to find one,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Hoped himself shortly to find one] <quote lang="la">Sperabat propediem sese habiturum.</quote> Other editions, as those of Havercamp, Gerlach, Kritzius, Dietsch, and Bernouf, have the words <foreign lang="la">magnas copias</foreign> before <foreign lang="la">sese.</foreign> Cortius struck them out, observing that <foreign lang="la">copi&aelig;</foreign> occurred too often in this chapter, and that in one MS. they were wanting. One manuscript, however, was insufficient authority for discarding them; and the phrase suits much better with what follows, <foreign lang="la">si Rom&aelig; socii incepta patravissent,</foreign> if they are retained.</note> if his accomplices at Rome should succeed in their objects. Slaves, meanwhile, of whom vast numbers<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Slaves--of whom vast numbers, etc.] <quote lang="la">Servitia--cujus--magn&aelig; copi&aelig;.</quote> <foreign lang="la">"Cujus,</foreign>" says Priscian (xvii. 20, vol. ii., p. 81, ed. Krehl), "is referred <foreign lang="la">ad rem,</foreign> that is <foreign lang="la">cujus rei servitiorum</foreign>." <foreign lang="la">Servorum</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">hominum genus,</foreign> is, perhaps, rather what Sallust had in his mind, as the subject of his relation. Gerlach adduces as an expression most nearly approaching to Sallust's, Thucyd., iii. 92; <foreign lang="greek">*kai\ *dwriei/z, h( mhtro/poliz tw=n &amp;aakedaimoni/wn.</foreign></note> had at first flocked to him, he continued to reject, not only as depending on the strength of the conspiracy, but as thinking it impolitic<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Impolitic] <quote lang="la">Alienum suis rationibus.</quote> Foreign to his views; inconsistent with his policy.</note> to appear to share the cause of citizens with runagates.</p>
<p>LVII When it was reported in his camp, however, that the conspiracy had been discovered at Rome, and that Lentulus, Cethegus, and the rest whom I have named, had been put to death, most of those whom the hope of plunder, or the love of change, had led to join in the war, fell away. The remainder Catiline conducted, over rugged mountains, and by forced marches, into the neighborhood of Pistoria, with a view to escape covertly, by cross roads, into Gaul.</p>
<p>But Quintus Metellus Celer, with a force of three legions, had at that time, his station in Picenum, who suspected that Catiline, from the difficulties of his position, would adopt precisely the course which we have just described. When, therefore, he had learned his route from some deserters, he immediately broke up his camp, and took his post at the very foot of the hills, at the point where Catiline's descent would be, in his hurried march into Gaul.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LVII. In his hurried march into Gaul] <quote lang="la">In Galliam properanti.</quote> These words Cortius inclosed in brackets, pronouncing them as a useless gloss. But all editors have retained them as genuine, except the Bipont and Bernouf; who wholly omitted them.</note> Nor was Antonius far distant, as he was pursuing, <pb n="69"/>though with a large army, yet through plainer ground, and with fewer hinderances, the enemy in retreat.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">As he was pursuing, though with a large army, yet through plainer ground, and with fewer hinderances, the enemy in retreat] <quote lang="la">Utpote qui magno exercitu, locis &aelig;quioribus, expeditus, in fug&acirc; sequeretur.</quote> It would be tedious to notice all that has been written upon this passage of Sallust. All the editions, before that of Cortius, had <foreign lang="la">expeditos, in fugam,</foreign> some joining <foreign lang="la">expeditos</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">locis &aelig;quioribus,</foreign> and some with <foreign lang="la">in fugam. Expeditos in fugam</foreign> was first condemned by Wasse, no negligent observer of phrases, who said that no expression parallel to it could be found in any Latin writer. Cortius, seeing that the expedition, of which Sallust is speaking, is on the part of Antonius, not of Catiline, altered <foreign lang="la">expeditos,</foreign> though found in all the manuscripts, into <foreign lang="la">expeditus;</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">in fugam,</foreign> at the same time, into <foreign lang="la">in fug&acirc;;</foreign> and in both these emendations he has been cordially followed by the subsequent editors, Gerlach, Kritzius, and Dietsch. I have translated <foreign lang="la">magno exercitu,</foreign> "though with a large army," although, according to Dietsch and some others, we need not consider a large army as a cause of slowness, but may rather regard it as a cause of speed; since the more numerous were Metellus's forces, the less he would care how many he might leave behind through fatigue, or to guard the baggage; so that he might be the more <foreign lang="la">expeditus,</foreign> unincumbered. With <foreign lang="la">sequeretur</foreign> we must understand <foreign lang="la">hostes.</foreign> The Bipont, Bernouf's, which often follows it, and Havercamp's, are now the only editions of any note that retain <foreign lang="la">expeditos in fugam.</foreign></note></p>
<p>Catiline, when he saw that he was surrounded by mountains and by hostile forces, that his schemes in the city had been unsuccessful, and that there was no hope either of escape or of succor, thinking it best, in such circumstances, to try the fortune of a battle, resolved upon engaging, as speedily as possible, with Antonius. Having, therefore, assembled his troops, he addressed them in the following manner:</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="58">
<p> "I am well aware, soldiers, that words can not inspire courage; and that a spiritless army can not be rendered active,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LVIII. That a spiritless army can not be rendered active, etc.] <quote lang="la">Neque ex ignavo strenuum, neque fortem ex timido exercitum oratione imperatoris fieri.</quote>  I have departed a little from the literal reading, for the sake of ease.</note> or a timid army valiant, by the speech of its commander. Whatever courage is in the heart of a man, whether from nature or from habit, so much will be shown by him in the field; and on him whom neither glory nor danger can move, exhortation is bestowed in vain; for the terror in his breast stops his ears.</p>
<p>"I have called you together, however, to give you a few instructions, and to explain to you, at the same time, my reasons for the course which I have adopted. You all know, soldiers, how severe a penalty the inactivity and cowardice of Lentulus has brought upon himself and us; and how, while waiting for reinforcements from the city, I was unable to march into Gaul. <pb n="70"/>In what situation our affairs now are, you all understand as well as myself. Two armies of the enemy, one on the side of Rome, and the other on that of Gaul, oppose our progress; while the want of corn, and of other necessaries, prevents us from remaining, however strongly we may desire to remain, in our present position. Whithersoever we would go, we must open a passage with our swords. I conjure you, therefore, to maintain a brave and resolute spirit; and to remember, when you advance to battle, that on your own right hands depend<note anchored="yes" place="foot">That on your own right hands depend, etc.] <quote lang="la">In dextris portare.</quote> "That you carry in your right hands."</note> riches, honor, and glory, with the enjoyment of your liberty and of your country. If we conquer, all will be safe; we shall have provisions in abundance; and the colonies and corporate towns will open their gates to us. But if we lose the victory through want of courage, those same places<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Those same places] <quote lang="la">Eadem illa.</quote> <cit><quote lang="la">"Coloni&aelig; atque municipia portas claudent."</quote><bibl>Bernouf.</bibl></cit></note> will turn against us; for neither place nor friend will protect him whom his arms have not protected. Besides, soldiers, the same exigency does not press upon our adversaries, as presses upon us; we fight for our country, for our liberty, for our life; they contend for what but little concerns them,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">They contend for what but little concerns them] <quote lang="la">Illis supervacaneum est pugnare.</quote> It is but of little concern to the great body of them personally: they may fight, but others will have the advantages of their efforts.</note> the power of a small party. Attack them, therefore, with so much the greater confidence, and call to mind your achievements of old.</p>
<p>"We might,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">We might, etc.] <quote lang="la">Licit nobis.</quote> The editions vary between <foreign lang="la">nobis</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">vobis;</foreign> but most, with Cortius, have <foreign lang="la">nobis.</foreign></note> with the utmost ignominy, have passed the rest of our days in exile. Some of you, after losing your property, might have waited at Rome for assistance from others. But because such a life, to men of spirit, was disgusting and unendurable, you resolved upon your present course. If you wish to quit it, you must exert all your resolution, for none but conquerors have exchanged war for peace. To hope for safety in flight, when you have turned away from the enemy the arms by which the body is defended, is indeed madness. In battle, those who are most afraid are always in most danger; but courage is equivalent to a rampart.</p>
<p>"When I contemplate you, soldiers, and when I consider your past exploits, a strong hope of victory animates me. Your <pb n="71"/>spirit, your age, your valor, give me confidence; to say nothing of necessity, which makes even cowards brave. To prevent the numbers of the enemy from surrounding us, our confined situation is sufficient. But should Fortune be unjust to your valor, take care not to lose your lives unavenged; take care not to be taken and butchered like cattle, rather than, fighting like men, to leave to your enemies a bloody and mournful victory."</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="59">
<p> When he had thus spoken, he ordered, after a short delay, the signal for battle to be sounded, and led down his troops, in regular order, to the level ground. Having then sent away the horses of all the cavalry, in order to increase the men's courage by making their danger equal, he himself, on foot, drew up his troops suitably to their numbers and the nature of the ground. As a plain stretched between the mountains on the left, with a rugged rock on the right, he placed eight cohorts in front, and stationed the lest of his force, in close order, in the rear.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LIX. In the rear] <quote lang="la">In subsidio.</quote> Most translators have rendered this, "as a body of reserve;" but such can not well be the signification. It seems only to mean the part behind the front: Catiline places the eight cohorts in front, and the rest of his force <foreign lang="la">in subsidio,</foreign> to support the front. <foreign lang="la">Subsidia,</foreign> according to Varro (de L. L., iv. 16) and Festus (v. <foreign lang="la">Subsidium</foreign>), was a term applied to the Triarii, because they <foreign lang="la">subsidebant,</foreign> or sunk down on one knee until it was their turn to act. See Sheller's Lex. v. <foreign lang="la">Subsidium.</foreign> <cit><quote><foreign lang="la">"Novissimi ordines its dicuntur."</foreign></quote><bibl>Gerlach.</bibl></cit> <foreign lang="la">In subsidiis,</foreign> which occurs a few lines below, seems to signify in lines in the rear; as in Jug. 49, <foreign lang="la">triplicibus subsidiis aciem intruxit,</foreign> i.e. with three lines behind the front. <cit><quote><foreign lang="la">"Subsidium ea pars aciei vocabatur qu&aelig; reliquis submitti posset; C&aelig;s.</foreign> B. G., ii. 25."</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit></note> From among these he removed all the ablest centurions,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">All the ablest centurions] <quote lang="la">Centuriones omnes lectos.</quote> <cit><quote>"<foreign lang="la">Lectos</foreign> you may consider to be the same as <foreign lang="la">eximios, pr&aelig;stantes, centurionum pr&aelig;stantissimum quemque.</foreign>"</quote><bibl>Kritzius.</bibl></cit> Cortius and others take it for a participle, chosen.</note> the veterans,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Veterans] <quote lang="la">Evocatos.</quote> Some would make this also a participle, because, say they, it can not signify <foreign lang="la">evocati,</foreign> or called-out veterans, since, though there were such soldiers in a regular Roman army, there could be none so called in the tumultuary forces of Catiline. But to this it is answered that Catiline had imitated the regular disposition of a Roman army, and that his veterans might consequently be called <foreign lang="la">evocati,</foreign> just as if they had been in one; and, also that <foreign lang="la">evocatus</foreign> as a participle would be useless; for if Catiline removed (<foreign lang="la">subducit</foreign>) the centurions, it is unnecessary to add that he called them out, <cit><quote>"<foreign lang="la">Evocati erant, qui expletis stipendiis non poterant in delectu scribi, sed precibus imperatoris permoti, aut in gratiam ejus, militiam resumebant, homines longo uso militi&aelig; peritissimi.</foreign> Dio., xlv. p. 276. <foreign lang="greek">)*ek tou/twn de\ tw=n a)ndrw=n kai\ to\ tw=n (*houoka/twn h+\ )*ouoka/twn su/sthma</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">o(u=z )*anaklh/touz u=\n ti\z )*ellhni/saz, o)/ti pepaume/noi th=s strate/ias, e)p) au)th\n a/=uqis a)neklh/qmsan, o)uoma/seien</foreign>) <foreign lang="greek">e)nomi/sqh.</foreign> <foreign lang="la">Intelligit itaque ejusmodi homines veteranos, etsi non propri&egrave; erant tales evocati, sed sponte castra Catilin&aelig; essent secuti."</foreign></quote><bibl>Cortius.</bibl></cit></note> and the stoutest of the <pb n="72"/>common soldiers that were regularly armed, into the foremost ranks.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Into the foremost ranks] <quote lang="la">In primam aciem.</quote> Whether Sallust means that he ranged them with the eight cohorts, or only in the first line of the <foreign lang="la">subsidia,</foreign> is not clear.</note> He ordered Caius Manlius to take the command on the right, and a certain officer of F&aelig;sul&aelig;<note anchored="yes" place="foot">A certain officer of F&aelig;sul&aelig;] <quote lang="la">F&aelig;sulanum quemdam.</quote> <cit><quote>"He is thought to have been that P. Furious, whom Cicero (Cat., iii. 6, 14) mentions as having been one of the colonists that Sylla settled at F&aelig;sul&aelig;, and who was to have been executed, if he had been apprehended, for having been concerned in corrupting the Allobrogian deputies."</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit> Plutarch calls this officer Furius.</note> on the left; while he himself, with his freedmen<note anchored="yes" place="foot">His freedmen] <quote lang="la">Libertis.</quote> <cit><quote>"His own freedmen, whom he probably had about him as a body-guard, deeming them the most attached of his adherents. Among them was, possibly, that Sergius, whom we find from Cic. pro Domo, 5, 6, to have been Catiline's armor-bearer."</quote><bibl>Dietsch.</bibl></cit></note> and the colonists,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">The colonists] <quote lang="la">Colonis.</quote> <cit><quote>"Veterans of Sylla, who had been settled by him as colonists in Etruria, and who had now been induced to join Catiline."</quote><bibl>Gerlach.</bibl></cit> See c. 28.</note> took his station by the eagle,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">By the eagle] <quote lang="la">Propter aquilam.</quote> See Cic. in Cat., i. 9.</note> which Caius Marius was said to have had in his army in the Cimbrian war.</p>
<p>On the other side, Caius Antonius, who, being lame,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Being lame] <quote lang="la">Pedibus &aelig;ger.</quote> It has been common among translators to render <foreign lang="la">pedibus &aelig;ger</foreign> afflicted with the gout, though a Roman might surely be lame without having the gout. As the lameness of Antonius, however, according to Dion Cassius (xxxvii. 39), was only pretended, it may be thought more probable that he counterfeited the gout than any other malady. It was with this belief, I suppose, that the writer of a gloss on one of the manuscripts consulted by Cortius, interpreted the words, <foreign lang="la">ultroneam passus est podogram,</foreign> "he was affected with a voluntary gout." Dion Cassius says that he preferred engaging with Antonius, who had the larger army, rather than with Metellus, who had the smaller, because he hoped that Antonius would designedly act in such a way as to lose the victory.</note> was unable to be present in the engagement, gave the command of the army to Marcus Petreius, his lieutenant-general. Petreius, ranged the cohorts of veterans, which he had raised to meet the present insurrection,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">To meet the present insurrection] <quote lang="la">Tumulti caus&acirc;.</quote> Any sudden war or insurrection in Italy or Gaul was called <foreign lang="la">tumultus.</foreign> See Cic. Philipp. v. 12.</note> in front, and behind them the rest of his force in lines. Then, riding round among his troops, and addressing his men by name, he encouraged them, and bade them remember that they were to fight against unarmed marauders, in defense of their country, their children, their temples, and their homes.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Their temples and their homes] <quote lang="la">Aris atque focis suis.</quote> See c. 52.</note> Being a military man, and having served with great reputation, for more than thirty years, as tribune, pr&aelig;fect, lieutenant, or pr&aelig;tor, he knew most of the soldiers and their <pb n="73"/>honorable actions, and, by calling these to their remembrance, roused the spirits of the men.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="60">
<p> When he had made a complete survey, he gave the signal with the trumpet, and ordered the cohorts to advance slowly. The army of the enemy followed his example; and when they approached so near that the action could be commenced by the light-armed troops, both sides, with a loud shout, rushed together in a furious charge.<note anchored="yes" place="foot">LX. In a furious charge] <quote lang="la">Infestis signis.</quote></note> They threw aside their missiles, and fought only with their swords. The veterans, calling to mind their deeds of old, engaged fiercely in the closest combat. The enemy made an obstinate resistance; and both sides contended with the utmost fury. Catiline, during this time, was exerting himself with his light troops in the front, sustaining such as were pressed, substituting fresh men for the wounded, attending to every exigency, charging in person, wounding many an enemy, and performing at once the duties of a valiant soldier and a skillful general.</p>
<p>When Petreius, contrary to his expectation, found Catiline attacking him with such impetuosity, he led his pr&aelig;torian cohort against the centre of the enemy, among whom, being thus thrown into confusion, and offering but partial resistance,<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Offering but partial resistance] <quote lang="la">Alios alibi resistentes.</quote> Not making a stand in a body, but only some in one place, and some in another.</note> he made great slaughter, and ordered, at the same time, an assault on both flanks. Manlius and the F&aelig;sulan, sword in hand, were among the first<note anchored="yes" place="foot">Among the first, etc.] <quote lang="la">In primis pugnantes cadunt.</quote> Cortius very properly refers <foreign lang="la">in primis</foreign> to <foreign lang="la">cadunt.</foreign></note> that fell; and Catiline, when he saw his army routed, and himself left with but few supporters, remembering his birth and former dignity, rushed into the thickest of the enemy, where he was slain, fighting to the last.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="61">
<p> When the battle was over, it was plainly seen what boldness, and what energy of spirit, had prevailed throughout the army of Catiline; for, almost every where, every soldier, after yielding up his breath, covered with his corpse the spot which he had occupied when alive. A few, indeed, whom the pr&aelig;torian cohort had dispersed, had fallen somewhat differently, but all with wounds in front. Catiline himself was found, far in advance of his men, among the dead bodies <pb n="74"/>of the enemy; he was not quite breathless, and still expressed in his countenance the fierceness of spirit which he had shown during his life. Of his whole army, neither in the battle, nor in flight, was any free-born citizen made prisoner, for they had spared their own lives no more than those of the enemy.</p>
<p>Nor did the army of the Roman people obtain a joyful or bloodless victory; for all their bravest men were either killed in the battle, or left the field severely wounded.</p>
<p>Of many who went from the camp to view the ground, or plunder the slain, some, in turning over the bodies of the enemy, discovered a friend, others an acquaintance, others a relative; some, too, recognized their enemies. Thus, gladness and sorrow, grief and joy, were variously felt throughout the whole army.


<pb n="75"/></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="chronology"><head>CHRONOLOGY OF THE CONSPIRACY OF CATILINE.</head>

<p>EXTRACTED FROM DE BROSSES.

<list type="simple">
<headLabel>A.U.C.</headLabel>
<label>685</label>
<item>Coss. L. C&AElig;CILIUS METELLUS, Q. MARCIUS REX.--Catiline is Pr&aelig;tor.</item>
<label>686.</label>
<item>--C. CALPURNIUS PISO, M. ACILIUS GLABRIO.--Catiline Governor of Africa.</item>
<label>687.</label>
<item>--L. VOLCATIUS TULLUS, M. &AElig;MILIUS LEPIDUS.--Deputies from Africa accuse Catiline of extortion, through the agency of Clodius. He is obliged to desist from standing for the consulship, and forms the project of the first conspiracy. See Sall. Cat., c. 18.</item>
<label>688.</label>
<item>--L. MANLIUS TORQUATUS, L. AURELIUS COTTA.--Jan. 1: Catiline's project of the first conspiracy becomes known, and he defers the execution of it to the 5th of February, when he makes an unsuccessful attempt to execute it. July 17: He is acquitted of extortion, and begins to canvass for the consulship for the year <date value="690">690</date>.</item>
<label>689.</label>
<item>--L. JULIUS C&AElig;SAR, C. MARCIUS FIGULUS THERMUS.--June 1: Catiline convokes the chiefs of the second conspiracy. He is disappointed in his views on the consulship.</item>
<label>690.</label>
<item>--M. TULLIUS CICERO, C. ANTONIUS HYBRIDA.--Oct. 19: Cicero lays the affair of the conspiracy before the senate, who decree plenary powers to the consuls for defending the state. Oct. 21: Silanus and Mur&aelig;na are elected consuls for the next year, Catiline, who was a candidate, being rejected. Oct. 22: Catiline is accused under the Plautian Law de vi. Sall. Cat., c. 31. Oct. 24: Manlius takes up arms in Etruria. Nov. 6: Catiline assembles the chief conspirators, by the agency of Porcius L&aelig;ca. Sall. Cat., c. 27. Nov. 7: Vargunteius and Cornelius undertake to assassinate Cicero. Sall. Cat., c. 28. Nov. 8: Catiline appears in the senate; Cicero delivers his first Oration against him; he threatens to extinguish the flame raised around him in a general destruction, and quits Rome. Sall. Cat., c. 31. Nov. 9: Cicero delivers his second Oration against Catiline, before an assembly of the people, convoked by order of the senate. Nov. 20, or thereabouts: Catiline and Manlius are declared public enemies. Soon after this the conspirators attempt to secure the support of the Allobrogian deputies. Dec. 3: About two o'clock in the morning the Allobroges are apprehended. Toward evening Cicero delivers his third Oration against Catiline, before the people. Dec. 5. Cicero's fourth Oration against Catiline, before the senate. Soon after, the conspirators are condemned to death, and great honors are decreed by the senate to Cicero.</item>
<label>691.</label>
<item>--D. JUNIUS SILANUS, L. LICINIUS MUR&AElig;NA.--Jan. 5: Battle of Pistoria, and death of Catiline.</item>
</list>

<pb n="76"/>
</p>
<p>The narrative of Sallust terminates with the account of the battle of Pistoria. There are a few other particulars connected with the history of the conspiracy, which, for the sake of the English reader, it may not be improper to add.</p>
<p>When the victory was gained, Antonius caused Catiline's head to be cut off, and sent it to Rome by the messengers who carried the news. Antonius himself was honored, by a public decree, with the title of <foreign lang="la">Imperator,</foreign> although he had done little to merit the distinction, and although the number of slain, which was three thousand, was less than that for which the title was generally given. See Dio Cass. xxxvii., 40, 41.</p>
<p>The remains of Catiline's army, after the death of their leader, continued to make efforts to raise another insurrection. In August, eight months after the battle, a party, under the command of Lucius Sergius, perhaps a relative or freedman of Catiline, still offered resistance to the forces of the government in Etruria. <foreign lang="la">Reliqui&aelig; conjuratorum, cum L.</foreign> <pb n="77"/><foreign lang="la">Sergio, tumultuantur in Hetruri&acirc;.</foreign> Fragm. Act. Diurn. The responsibility of watching these marauders was left to the proconsul Metellus Celer. After some petty encounters, in which the insurgents were generally worsted, Sergius, having collected his force at the foot of the Alps, attempted to penetrate into the country of the Allobroges, expecting to find them ready to take up arms; but Metellus, learning his intention, pre-occupied the passes, and then surrounded and destroyed him and his followers.</p>
<p>At Rome, in the mean time, great honors were paid to Cicero. A thanksgiving of thirty days was decreed in his name, an honor which had previously been granted to none but military men, and which was granted to him, to use his own words, because he had delivered the city from fire, the citizens from slaughter, and Italy from war. "If my thanks-giving," he also observes, "be compared with those of others, there will be found this difference, that theirs were granted them for having managed the interests of the republic successfully, but that mine was decreed to me for having preserved the republic from ruin." See Cic. Orat. iii., in Cat., c. 6. Pro, Syll&acirc;, c. 30. In Pison. c. 3. Philipp. xiv., 8. Quintus Catulus, then <foreign lang="la">princeps senat&ucirc;s,</foreign> and Marcus Cato styled him, several times, the father of his country.
<cit><quote lang="la"><l>Roma parentem,</l>
<l>Roma patrem patri&aelig; Ciceronem libera dixit.</l></quote>
<bibl>Juv. Sat., viii. 244,</bibl></cit></p>
<p>Of the inferior conspirators, who did not follow Sergius, and who were apprehended at Rome, or in other parts of Italy, after the death of the leaders in the plot, some were put to death, chiefly on the testimony of Lucius Vettius, one of their number, who turned informer against the rest. But many whom he accused were acquitted; others, supposed to be guilty, were allowed to escape.</p></div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
