<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>

<TEI.2>
<teiHeader status="new" type="text">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Works on <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> (English). Machine readable text</title> 
<author>Xenophon</author>
&responsibility;
&fund.AnnCPB;
</titleStmt>
<extent>about 20Kb</extent> 
&Perseus.publish;
<notesStmt><note anchored="yes">Text entered in Philipines 1990.</note></notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
	<monogr>
		<author>Xenophon</author><title>Xenophon in Seven Volumes, 4</title>
	
		<imprint><publisher>Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA; William Heinemann, Ltd., London.</publisher><date>1979</date></imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="chapter"/>
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>

<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2" n="text=Apol.">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>June, 1992</date><respStmt><name>wpm and das</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>tagged text to conform with prose.e dtd. Entered sections. Scanned and inserted text that had dropped out; sections 22-32.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>8/11/92</date><respStmt><name>das</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>changed chapters to div2's</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>10/29/92</date><respStmt><name>das</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>added HEAD's and REFDECL's; glued minor works together</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><group>
<text n="Apol.">
    <body><head>Apology of Socrates</head>
        <p>
<milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It seems to me fitting to hand down to memory, furthermore, how <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, on being indicted, deliberated on his defence and on his end. It is true that others have written about this, and that all of them have reproduced the loftiness of his words,&mdash;a fact which proves that his utterance really was of the character intimated;&mdash;but they have not shown clearly that he had now come to the conclusion that for him death was more to be desired than life; and hence his lofty utterance appears rather ill-considered.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Hermogenes, the son of Hipponicus, however, was a companion of his and has given us reports of such a nature as to show that the sublimity of his speech was appropriate to the resolve he had made. For he stated that on seeing <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> discussing any and every subject rather than the trial, he had said:
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>&ldquo;<persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, ought you not to be giving some thought to what defence you are going to make?&rdquo; That <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> had at first replied, &ldquo;Why, do I not seem to you to have spent my whole life in preparing to defend myself?&rdquo; Then when he asked, &ldquo;How so?&rdquo; he had said, &ldquo;Because all my life I have been guiltless of wrong-doing; and that I consider the finest preparation for a defence.&rdquo; Then when Hermogenes again asked,
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Do you not observe that the Athenian courts have often been carried away by an eloquent speech and have condemned innocent men to death, and often on the other hand the guilty have been acquitted either because their plea aroused compassion or because their speech was witty?&rdquo; &ldquo;Yes, indeed!&rdquo; he had answered; &ldquo;and I have tried twice already to meditate on my defence, but my divine sign interposes.&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>And when Hermogenes observed, &ldquo;That is a surprising statement,&rdquo; he had replied, &ldquo;Do you think it surprising that even God holds it better for me to die now? Do you not know that I would refuse to concede that any man has lived a better life than I have up to now? For I have realized that my whole life has been spent in righteousness toward God and man,&mdash;a fact that affords the greatest satisfaction; and so I have felt a deep self-respect and have discovered that my associates hold corresponding sentiments toward me.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>But now, if my years are prolonged, I know that the frailties of old age will inevitably be realized,&mdash;that my vision must be less perfect and my hearing less keen, that I shall be slower to learn and more forgetful of what I have learned. If I perceive my decay and take to complaining, how,&rdquo; he had continued, &ldquo;could I any longer take pleasure in life?
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Perhaps,&rdquo; he added, &ldquo;God in his kindness is taking my part and securing me the opportunity of ending my life not only in season but also in the way that is easiest. For if I am condemned now, it will clearly be my privilege to suffer a death that is adjudged by those who have superintended this matter to be not only the easiest but also the least irksome to one's friends and one that implants in them the deepest feeling of loss for the dead. For when a person leaves behind in the hearts of his companions no remembrance to cause a blush or a pang, but dissolution comes while he still possesses a sound body and a spirit capable of showing kindliness, how could such a one fail to be sorely missed?
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>It was with good reason,&rdquo; Socrates had continued, &ldquo;that the gods opposed<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See note on p. 494.</note> my studying up my speech at the time when we held that by fair means or foul we must find some plea that would effect my acquittal. For if I had achieved this end, it is clear that instead of now passing out of life, I should merely have provided for dying in the throes of illness or vexed by old age, the sink into which all distresses flow, unrelieved by any joy.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>As Heaven is my witness, Hermogenes,&rdquo; he had gone on, &ldquo;I shall never court that fate; but if I am going to offend the jury by declaring all the blessings that I feel gods and men have bestowed on me, as well as my personal opinion of myself, I shall prefer death to begging meanly for longer life and thus gaining a life far less worthy in exchange for death.&rdquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hermogenes stated that with this resolve Socrates came before the jury after his adversaries had charged him with not believing in the gods worshipped by the state and with the introduction of new deities in their stead and with corruption of the young, and replied:
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>&ldquo;One thing that I marvel at in Meletus, gentlemen, is what may be the basis of his assertion that I do not believe in the gods worshipped by the state; for all who have happened to be near at the time, as well as Meletus himself,&mdash;if he so desired, &mdash; have seen me sacrificing at the communal festivals and on the public altars.
            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>As for introducing &lsquo;new divinities,&rsquo; how could I be guilty of that merely in asserting that a voice of God is made manifest to me indicating my duty? Surely those who take their omens from the cries of birds and the utterances of men form their judgments on &lsquo;voices.&rsquo; Will any one dispute either that thunder utters its &lsquo;voice,&rsquo; or that it is an omen of the greatest moment? Does not the very priestess who sits on the tripod at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> divulge the god's will through a &lsquo;voice&rsquo;?
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>But more than that, in regard to God's foreknowledge of the future and his forewarning thereof to whomsoever he will, these are the same terms, I assert, that all men use, and this is their belief. The only difference between them and me is that whereas they call the sources of their forewarning &lsquo;birds,&rsquo; &lsquo;utterances,&rsquo; &lsquo;chance meetings,&rsquo; &lsquo;prophets,&rsquo; I call mine a &lsquo;divine&rsquo; thing;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or &ldquo;divine sign.&rdquo; Here, as earlier, the mere adjective is used; but in <persName><surname>Plato</surname></persName>'s <title>Theages</title> (<bibl n="Plat. Theag. 128d">Plat. Theag. 128 D</bibl> ff.) and <title>Apology</title> (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 31d">Plat. Apol. 31 D</bibl>) this admonitory something is described as a voice sent by heavenly dispensation, and is called variously &ldquo;the sign&rdquo; (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 41d">Plat. Apol. 41 D</bibl>), &ldquo;the usual sign&rdquo; (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 40c">Plat. Apol. 40 C</bibl>), &ldquo;the divine sign&rdquo; (<bibl n="Plat. Rep. 496c">Plat. Rep. 496 C</bibl>), &ldquo;the usual divine sign&rdquo; (<bibl n="Plat. Euthyd. 272e">Plat. Euthyd. 272 E</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 242b">Plat. Phaedr. 242 B</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Theag. 129b">Plat. Theag. 129 B</bibl>), &ldquo;the sign from God&rdquo; (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 40b">Plat. Apol. 40 B</bibl>), &ldquo;something God-sent and divine&rdquo; (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 31d">Plat. Apol. 31 D</bibl>). Plato reports <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>' description of this as a voice not directing his actions but serving only as a deterrent when he or his friends were contemplating doing something inadvisable.</note> and I think that in using such a term I am speaking with more truth and deeper religious feeling than do those who ascribe the gods' power to birds. Now that I do not lie against God I have the following proof: I have revealed to many of my friends the counsels which God has given me, and in no instance has the event shown that I was mistaken.&rdquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hermogenes further reported that when the jurors raised a clamour at hearing these words, some of them disbelieving his statements, others showing jealousy at his receiving greater favours even from the gods than they, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> resumed: &ldquo;Hark ye; let me tell you something more, so that those of you who feel so inclined may have still greater disbelief in my being honoured of Heaven. Once on a time when Chaerephon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A very enthusiastic follower of <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.</note> made inquiry at the Delphic oracle concerning me, in the presence of many people Apollo answered that no man was more free than I, or more just, or more prudent.&rdquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When the jurors, naturally enough, made a still greater tumult on hearing this statement, he said that <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> again went on: &ldquo;And yet, gentlemen, the god uttered in oracles greater things of Lycurgus, the Lacedaemonian law-giver, than he did of me. For there is a legend that, as Lycurgus entered the temple, the god thus addressed him: &lsquo;I am pondering whether to call you god or man.&rsquo; Now Apollo did not compare me to a god; he did, however, judge that I far excelled the rest of mankind. However, do not believe the god even in this without due grounds, but examine the god's utterance in detail.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>First, who is there in your knowledge that is less a slave to his bodily appetites than I am? Who in the world more free,&mdash;for I accept neither gifts nor pay from any one? Whom would you with reason regard as more just than the one so reconciled to his present possessions as to want nothing beside that belongs to another? And would not a person with good reason call me a wise man, who from the time when I began to understand spoken words have never left off seeking after and learning every good thing that I could?
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>And that my labour has not been in vain do you not think is attested by this fact, that many of my fellow-citizens who strive for virtue and many from abroad choose to associate with me above all other men? And what shall we say is accountable for this fact, that although everybody knows that it is quite impossible for me to repay with money, many people are eager to make me some gift? Or for this, that no demands are made on me by a single person for the repayment of benefits, while many confess that they owe me a debt of gratitude?
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Or for this, that during the siege,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The blockade of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by the Spartans in the last year of the Peloponnesian War.</note> while others were commiserating their lot, I got along without feeling the pinch of poverty any worse than when the city's prosperity was at its height? Or for this, that while other men get their delicacies in the markets and pay a high price for them, I devise more pleasurable ones from the resources of my soul, with no expenditure of money? And now, if no one can convict me of misstatement in all that I have said of myself, do I not unquestionably merit praise from both gods and men?
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>But in spite of all, Meletus, do you maintain that I corrupt the young by such practices? And yet surely we know what kinds of corruption affect the young; so you tell us whether you know of any one who under my influence has fallen from piety into impiety, or from sober into wanton conduct, or from moderation in living into extravagance, or from temperate drinking into sottishness, or from strenuousness into effeminacy, or has been overcome of any other base pleasure.&rdquo;
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>&ldquo;But, by Heaven!&rdquo; said Meletus: &ldquo;there is one set of men I know,&mdash;those whom you have persuaded to obey you rather than their parents.&rdquo; &ldquo;I admit it,&rdquo; he reports <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> as replying, &ldquo;at least so far as education is concerned; for people know that I have taken an interest in that. But in a question of health, men take the advice of physicians rather than that of their parents; and moreover, in the meetings of the legislative assembly all the people of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, without question, follow the advice of those whose words are wisest rather than that of their own relatives. Do you not also elect for your generals, in preference to fathers and brothers,&mdash;yes, by Heaven! in preference to your very selves,&mdash;those whom you regard as having the greatest wisdom in military affairs?&rdquo; &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; Meletus had said; &ldquo;for that is both expedient and conventional.&rdquo;
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Well, then,&rdquo; <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> had rejoined, &ldquo;does it not seem to you an amazing thing that while in other activities those who excel receive honours not merely on a parity with their fellows but even more marked ones, yet I, because I am adjudged by some people supreme in what is man's greatest blessing,&mdash;education,&mdash;am being prosecuted by you on a capital charge?&rdquo;
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>More than this of course was said both by <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> himself and by the friends who joined in his defence. But I have not made it a point to report the whole trial; rather I am satisfied to make it clear that while <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>' whole concern was to keep free from any act of impiety toward the gods or any appearance of wrong-doing toward man, he did not think it meet to beseech the jury to let him escape death; instead, he believed that the time had now come for him to die.
            <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>This conviction of his became more evident than ever after the adverse issue of the trial. For, first of all, when he was bidden to name his penalty, he refused personally and forbade his friends to name one, but said that naming the penalty in itself implied an acknowledgment of guilt. Then, when his companions wished to remove him clandestinely from prison, he would not accompany them, but seemed actually to banter them, asking them whether they knew of any spot outside of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> that was inaccessible to death.
<milestone n="24" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When the trial was over, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> (according to Hermogenes) remarked: &ldquo;Well, gentlemen, those who instructed the witnesses that they must bear false witness against me, perjuring themselves to do so, and those who were won over to do this must feel in their hearts a guilty consciousness of great impiety and iniquity; but as for me, why should my spirit be any less exalted now than before my condemnation, since I have not been proved guilty of having done any of the acts mentioned in the indictment? For it has not been shown that I have sacrificed to new deities in the stead of Zeus and Hera and the gods of their company, or that I have invoked ill oaths or mentioned other gods.
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/>And how could I be corrupting the young by habituating them to fortitude and frugality?  Now of all the acts for which the laws have prescribed the death-penalty&mdash;temple robbery, burglary, enslavement, treason to the state&mdash;not even my adversaries themselves charge me with having committed any of these.  And so it seems astonishing to me how you could ever have been convinced that I had committed an act meriting death.
<milestone n="26" unit="section"/>But further, my spirit need not be less exalted because l am to be executed unjustly; for the ignominy of that attaches not to me but to those who condemned me.  And I get comfort from the case of Palamedes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">One of the Greek warriors at <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>; put to death on a charge of treason trumped up by Odysseus, or by Odysseus, Diomedes, and Agamemnon.</note> also, who died in circumstances similar to mine; for even yet he affords us far more noble themes for song than does Odysseus, the man who unjustly put him to death.  And I know that time to come as well as time past will attest that I, too, far from ever doing any man a wrong or rendering him more wicked, have rather profited those who conversed with me by teaching them, without reward, every good thing that lay in my power.&rdquo;
<milestone n="27" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>With these words he departed, blithe in glance, in mien, in gait, as comported well indeed with the words he had just uttered. When he noticed that those who accompanied him were in tears, &ldquo;What is this?&rdquo; Hermogenes reports him as asking. &ldquo;Are you just now beginning to weep? Have you not known all along that from the moment of my birth nature had condemned me to death? Verily, if I am being destroyed before my time while blessings are still pouring in upon me, clearly that should bring grief to me and to my well-wishers; but if I am ending my life when only troubles are in view, my own opinion is that you ought all to feel cheered, in the assurance that my state is happy.&rdquo;
<milestone n="28" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A man named Apollodorus, who was there with him, a very ardent disciple of <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, but otherwise simple, exclaimed, &ldquo;But, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, what I find it hardest to bear is that I see you being put to death unjustly!&rdquo; The other, stroking Apollodorus' head, is said to have replied, &ldquo;My beloved Apollodorus, was it your preference to see me put to death justly?&rdquo; and smiled as he asked the question.
<milestone n="29" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It is said also that he remarked as he saw Anytus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">One of the three plaintiffs in <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>' trial.</note> passing by: &ldquo;There goes a man who is filled with pride at the thought that he has accomplished some great and noble end in putting me to death, because, seeing him honored by the state with the highest offices, I said that he ought not to confine his son's education to hides<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The tanning trade had been in the family from at least the time of the boy's grandfather.</note> What a vicious, fellow,&rdquo; he continued, &ldquo;not to know, apparently, that whichever one of us has wrought the more beneficial and noble deeds for all time, he is the real victor.
<milestone n="30" unit="section"/>&ldquo;But,&rdquo; he is reported to have added, &ldquo;Homer has attributed to some of his heroes at the moment of dissolution the power to foresee the future; and so I too wish to utter a prophecy.At one time I had a brief association with the son of Anytus, and I thought him not lacking in firmness of spirit; and so I predict that he will not continue in the servile occupation that his father has provided for him; but through want of a worthy adviser he will fall into some disgraceful propensity and will surely go far in the career of vice.&rdquo;
<milestone n="31" unit="section"/>In saying this he was not mistaken; the young man, delighting in wine, never left off drinking night or day, and at last turned out worth nothing to his city, his friends, or himself. So Anytus, even though dead, still enjoys an evil repute for his son's mischievous education and for his own hard-heartedness.
<milestone n="32" unit="section"/>And as for <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, by exalting himself before the court, he brought ill-will upon himself and made his conviction by the jury more certain. Now to me he seems to have met a fate that the gods love; for he escaped the hardest part of life and met the easiest sort of death.
<milestone n="33" unit="section"/>And he displayed the stalwart nature of his heart; for having once decided that to die was better for him than to live longer, he did not weaken in the presence of death (just as he had never set his face against any other thing, either, that was for his good), but was cheerful not only in the expectation of death but in meeting it.
<milestone n="34" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And so, in contemplating the man's wisdom and nobility of character, I find it beyond my power to forget him or, in remembering him, to refrain from praising him. And if among those who make virtue their aim any one has ever been brought into contact with a person more helpful than <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I count that man worthy to be called most blessed.</p></body></text>

<text n="Ec.">

    <body><head>Economics</head><p>
<milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I once heard him discuss the subject of estate management in the following manner.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Tell me, Critobulus, is estate management the name of a branch of knowledge, like medicine, smithing and carpentry?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I think so,&rdquo; replied Critobulus.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And can we say what the function of estate management is, just as we can say what is the function of each of these arts?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, I suppose that the business of a good estate manager is to manage his own estate well.&rdquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, and in case he were put in charge of another man's estate, could he not, if he chose, manage it as well as he manages his own? Anyone who understands carpentry can do for another exactly the same work as he does for himself; and so, I presume, can a good estate manager.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I think so, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Is it possible, then, for one who understands this art, even if he has no property of his own, to earn money by managing another man's estate, just as he might do by building him a house?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, of course; and he would get a good salary if, after taking over an estate, he continued to pay all outgoings, and to increase the estate by showing a balance.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But what do we mean now by an estate?
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Is it the same thing as a house, or is all property that one possesses outside the house also part of the estate?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, I think that even if the property is situated in different cities, everything a man possesses is part of his estate.&rdquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do not some men possess enemies?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Of course; some in fact possess many.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Shall we include their enemies in their possessions?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;It would be ridiculous, surely, if one actually received a salary for increasing the number of a man's enemies!&rdquo;
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because, you know, we supposed a man's estate to be the same as his property.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;To be sure&mdash;meaning thereby the good things that he possesses. No, of course I don't call any bad thing that he may possess property.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You seem to use the word property of whatever is profitable to its owner.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly; but what is harmful I regard as loss rather than wealth.&rdquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, and consequently if a man buys a horse and doesn't know how to manage it, and so keeps on getting thrown and injuring himself by trying to ride it, the horse is not wealth to him, I presume?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, if we assume that wealth is a good thing.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;It follows that land is not wealth either to a man who works it in such a way that his work results in loss.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;To be sure: even land is not wealth if it makes us starve instead of supporting us.&rdquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And the same will hold good of sheep, will it not? if a man loses through ignorance of sheep farming, his sheep too will not be wealth to him?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I think not.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;It seems, then, that your view is this: what is profitable is wealth, what is harmful is not wealth.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Quite so.&rdquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;That is to say, the same things are wealth and not wealth, according as one understands or does not understand how to use them. A flute, for example, is wealth to one who is competent to play it, but to an incompetent person it is no better than useless stones.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;True&mdash;unless he sells it.&rdquo;
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;We now see that to persons who don't understand its use, a flute is wealth if they sell it, but not wealth if they keep it instead of selling.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and our argument runs consistently, since we have said that what is profitable is wealth. For a flute, if not put up for sale, is not wealth, because it is useless: if put up for sale it becomes wealth.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; commented <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;provided he knows how to sell; but again, in case he sells it for something he doesn't know how to use, even then the sale doesn't convert it into wealth, according to you.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You imply, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that even money isn't wealth to one who doesn't know how to use it.&rdquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And you, I think, agree with me to this extent, that wealth is that from which a man can derive profit. At any rate, if a man uses his money to buy a mistress who makes him worse off in body and soul and estate, how can his money be profitable to him then?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;By no means, unless we are ready to maintain that the weed called nightshade, which drives you mad if you eat it, is wealth.&rdquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then money is to be kept at a distance, Critobulus, if one doesn't know how to use it, and not to be included in wealth. But how about friends? If one knows how to make use of them so as to profit by them, what are they to be called?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Wealth, of course, and much more so than cattle, if it be true that they are more profitable than cattle.&rdquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, and it follows from what you say that enemies too are wealth to anyone who can derive profit from them.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, that is my opinion.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Consequently it is the business of a good estate manager to know how to deal with enemies so as to derive profit from them too.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Most decidedly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In fact, Critobulus, you cannot fail to notice that many private persons have been indebted to war for the increase of their estates, and many princes too.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, so far so good, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. But sometimes we come across persons possessed of knowledge and means whereby they can increase their estates if they work, and we find that they are unwilling to do so; and consequently we see that their knowledge profits them nothing. What are we to make of that? In these cases, surely, neither their knowledge nor their property is wealth?&rdquo;
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Are you trying to raise a discussion about slaves, Critobulus?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Oh no, not at all: I am referring to persons of whom some, at any rate, are considered men of the highest lineage. I observe that there are persons skilled in the arts of war or peace, as the case may be, who are unwilling to practice them, and the reason, I think, is just this, that they have no master over them.&rdquo;
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What, no master over them, when, in spite of their prayers for prosperity and their desire to do what will bring them good, they are thwarted in their intentions by the powers that rule them?&rdquo;
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And who, pray, may these unseen rulers be?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, not unseen, but open and undisguised, surely! And very vicious rulers they are too, as you yourself must see, if at least you regard idleness and moral cowardice and negligence as vice.
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>Aye, and then there is a set of deceitful mistresses that pretend to be pleasures&mdash;such as gambling and consorting with bad companions: even the victims of their deception find as time goes on that these, after all, are really pains concealed beneath a thin veneer of pleasures, and that they are hindering them from all profitable work by their influence over them.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But there are other men, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, whose energy is not hindered by these influences, in fact they have an eager desire to work and to make an income: nevertheless they exhaust their estates and are beset with difficulties.&rdquo;
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, they too are slaves, and hard indeed are their masters: some are in bondage to gluttony, some to lechery, some to drink, and some to foolish and costly ambitions. And so hard is the rule of these passions over every man who falls into their clutches, that so long as they see that he is strong and capable of work, they force him to pay over all the profits of his toil, and to spend it on their own desires; but no sooner do they find that he is too old to work, than they leave him to an old age of misery, and try to fasten the yoke on other shoulders.
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/>Ah, Critobulus, we must fight for our freedom against these tyrants as persistently as if they were armed men trying to enslave us. Indeed, open enemies may be gentlemen, and when they enslave us, may, by chastening, purge us of our faults and cause us to live better lives in future. But such mistresses as these never cease to plague men in body and soul and estate all the time that they have dominion over them.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The word was now with Critobulus, who continued thus:<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, I think you have told me quite enough about such passions as these, and when I examine myself I find, I think, that I have them fairly well under control; and therefore, if you will advise me what I should do to increase my estate, I don't think those mistresses, as you call them, are likely to hinder me. So do not hesitate to give me any good advice you can: unless, indeed, you have made up your mind that we are rich enough already, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and think we have no need of more money?&rdquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Oh, if you mean to include me, I certainly think I have no need of more money and am rich enough. But you seem to me to be quite poor, Critobulus, and at times, I assure you, I feel quite sorry for you.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And how much, pray,&rdquo; asked Critobulus, laughing, &ldquo;would your property fetch at a sale, do you suppose, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and how much would mine?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, if I found a good buyer, I think the whole of my goods and chattels, including the house, might readily sell for five minae.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A little more than 20 pounds.</note> Yours, I feel sure, would fetch more than a hundred times that sum.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And in spite of that estimate, you really think you have no need of money and pity me for my poverty?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, because my property is sufficient to satisfy my wants, but I don't think you would have enough to keep up the style you are living in and to support your reputation, even if your fortune were three times what it is.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How can that be?&rdquo; exclaimed Critobulus.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because, in the first place,&rdquo; explained <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;I notice that you are bound to offer many large sacrifices; else, I fancy, you would get into trouble with gods and men alike. Secondly, it is your duty to entertain many strangers, on a generous scale too. Thirdly, you have to give dinners and play the benefactor to the citizens, or you lose your following.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Moreover, I observe that already the state is exacting heavy contributions from you: you must needs keep horses, pay for choruses and gymnastic competitions, and accept presidencies;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">It is unlikely that <foreign lang="greek">prostatei/as</foreign> is used here for <foreign lang="greek">prostasi/as,</foreign> the charge of resident aliens, since there is no proof that this duty involved expense to the patron.</note> and if war breaks out, I know they will require you to maintain a ship and pay taxes that will nearly crush you. Whenever you seem to fall short of what is expected of you, the Athenians will certainly punish you as though they had caught you robbing them.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Besides all this, I notice that you imagine yourself to be a rich man; you are indifferent to money, and yet go courting minions, as though the cost were nothing to you. And that is why I pity you, and fear that you may come to grief and find yourself reduced to penury.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Now, if I ran short of money, no doubt you know as well as I do that I should not lack helpers who would need to contribute very little to fill my cup to overflowing. But your friends, though far better supplied with means to support their establishment than you, yet look to receive help from you.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I cannot dispute this, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; said Critobulus, &ldquo;but it is time for you to take me in hand, and see that I don't become a real object of pity.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> exclaimed, &ldquo;What, don't you think it strange, Critobulus, that a little while ago, when I said I was rich, you laughed at me, as though I did not even know the meaning of riches, and would not cease until you had proved me wrong and made me own that my possessions were less than one-hundredth part of yours, and yet now you bid me take you in hand and see that you don't become in literal truth a poor man?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I see that you understand one process by which wealth is created&mdash;how to create a balance. So a man who saves on a small income can, I suppose, very easily show a large surplus with a large one.&rdquo;
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then don't you remember saying just now in our conversation, when you wouldn't give me leave to utter a syllable, that if a man doesn't know how to manage horses, his horses are not wealth to him, nor his land, sheep, money or anything else, if he doesn't know how to manage them? Now these are the sources from which income is derived: and how do you suppose that I can possibly know how to manage any of these things, seeing that I never yet possessed any one of them?&rdquo;
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Still we held that, even if a man happens to have no wealth, there is such a thing as a science of household management. Then what reason is there why you should not know it?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Exactly the same reason, of course, that a man would have for not knowing how to play on the flute if he had never possessed one himself and had never borrowed one to learn on.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>That is just my case with regard to estate management; for never having possessed wealth myself, I have not had an opportunity of learning on an instrument of my own, and nobody has ever let me handle his, until you made your offer. Beginners, I fancy, are apt to spoil the lyres they learn on; and if I attempted to learn to manage estates by practising on yours, possibly I might spoil it entirely for you.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Ah, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>!&rdquo; rejoined Critobulus, &ldquo;I see you are eager to avoid giving me any help towards lightening the weight of my troublesome duties.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Not at all, not at all,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;I am all eagerness to tell you all I know.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Suppose that you had come to me for fire, and I, having none by me, had taken you to some place where you could get it; you would not, I think, have found fault with me: or, if you had asked for water, and I, having none myself, had brought you to some other place for it, I feel sure that you would not have found fault with me for that either: or, suppose you wanted to learn music with me and I directed you to persons far more skilled in music than I am, who would be grateful to you for taking lessons with them, what fault could you find with me for doing so?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;None, if I were fair, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well then, Critobulus, I will direct you to others far more skilled than I in the things you now seek to learn from me. I confess that I have made a point of finding out who are the greatest masters of various sciences to be found in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>For observing once that the same pursuits lead in one case to great poverty and in another to great riches, I was filled with amazement, and thought it worth while to consider what this could mean. And on consideration I found that these things happen quite naturally.
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>For I saw that those who follow these pursuits carelessly suffer loss, and I discovered that those who devote themselves earnestly to them accomplish them more quickly, more easily and with more profit. I think that if you would elect to learn from these, you too with God's favour would turn out a clever man of business.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;<persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; exclaimed Critobulus on hearing this, &ldquo;I don't intend to let you go now, until you have proved to my satisfaction what you have promised in the presence of our friends here to prove.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well then,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;what if I prove to your satisfaction, Critobulus, to begin with, that some men spend large sums in building houses that are useless, while others build houses perfect in all respects for much less? Will you think that I am putting before you one of the operations that constitute estate management?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, certainly.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And what if I show you next the companion to this&mdash;that some possess many costly belongings and cannot use them at need, and do not even know whether they are safe and sound, and so are continually worried themselves and worrying their servants, whereas others, though they possess not more, but even less, have whatever they want ready for use?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What is the reason of this, then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Is it not simply this, that the former stow their things away anywhere and the latter have everything neatly arranged in some place?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, of course, arranged carefully in the proper place, not just anywhere.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Your point, I take it, is that this too is an element in estate management.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then what if I show you besides that in some households nearly all the servants are in fetters and yet continually try to run away, whereas in others they are under no restraint and are willing to work and to stay at their posts? Won't you think that here too I am pointing out to you a notable effect of estate management?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, of course; very much so.&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And that when men farm the same kind of land, some are poverty-stricken and declare that they are ruined by farming, and others do well with the farm and have all they want in abundance?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, of course; for maybe some spend money not on necessary purposes only but on what brings harm to the owner and the estate.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Perhaps there are such people.
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>But I am referring rather to those who haven't the money to meet even the necessary expenses, though professing to be farmers.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Now what can be the reason of that, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I will take you to these too; and when you watch them, you will find out, I fancy.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Of course; that is, if I can.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then you must watch, and try by experiment whether you are capable of understanding. At present I observe that when a comedy is to be seen, you get up very early and walk a very long way and press me eagerly to go to the play with you. But you have never yet invited me to see a drama of real life like this.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You think me ridiculous, don't you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You think yourself far more so, I am sure.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>And suppose I show you that some have been brought to penury by keeping horses, while others prosper by doing so, and moreover glory in their gain?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, I too see and know instances of both; I am not one of the gainers for all that.&rdquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;The fact is you watch them just as you watch the actors in tragedy or comedy, not, I suppose, to become a playwright, but for the pleasure of seeing and hearing something. And perhaps there is no harm in that, because you don't want to write plays; but seeing that you are forced to meddle with horses, don't you think that common-sense requires you to see that you are not ignorant of the business, the more so as the self-same horses are both good to use and profitable to sell?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Would you have me break in colts, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Of course not, no more than I would have you buy children to train as agricultural labourers; but horses and human beings alike, I think, on reaching a certain age forthwith become useful and go on improving. I can also show you that husbands differ widely in their treatment of their wives, and some succeed in winning their co-operation and thereby increase their estates, while others bring utter ruin on their houses by their behaviour to them.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And ought one to blame the husband or the wife for that, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;When a sheep is ailing,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;we generally blame the shepherd, and when a horse is vicious, we generally find fault with his rider. In the case of a wife, if she receives instruction in the right way from her husband and yet does badly, perhaps she should bear the blame; but if the husband does not instruct his wife in the right way of doing things, and so finds her ignorant, should he not bear the blame himself?
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>Anyhow, Critobulus, you should tell us the truth, for we are all friends here. Is there anyone to whom you commit more affairs of importance than you commit to your wife?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;There is not.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Is there anyone with whom you talk less?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;There are few or none, I confess.&rdquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And you married her when she was a mere child and had seen and heard almost nothing?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then it would be far more surprising if she understood what she should say or do than if she made mistakes.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But what of the husbands who, as you say, have good wives, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>? Did they train them themselves?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;There's nothing like investigation. I will introduce Aspasia to you, and she will explain the whole matter to you with more knowledge than I possess.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>I think that the wife who is a good partner in the household contributes just as much as her husband to its good; because the incomings for the most part are the result of the husband's exertions, but the outgoings are controlled mostly by the wife's dispensation. If both do their part well, the estate is increased; if they act incompetently, it is diminished.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>If you think you want to know about other branches of knowledge, I fancy I can show you people who acquit themselves creditably in any one of them.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Surely, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, there is no need to go through the whole list. For it is not easy to get workmen who are skilled in all the arts, nor is it possible to become an expert in them. Pray select the branches of knowledge that seem the noblest and would be most suitable for me to cultivate: show me these, and those who practise them; and give me from your own knowledge any help you can towards learning them.&rdquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Very good, Critobulus; for, to be sure, the illiberal arts, as they are called, are spoken against, and are, naturally enough, held in utter disdain in our states. For they spoil the bodies of the workmen and the foremen, forcing them to sit still and live indoors, and in some cases to spend the day at the fire. The softening of the body involves a serious weakening of the mind.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Moreover, these so-called illiberal arts leave no spare time for attention to one's friends and city, so that those who follow them are reputed bad at dealing with friends<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or, less probably, &ldquo;bad for friends to deal with.&rdquo;</note> and bad defenders of their country. In fact, in some of the states, and especially in those reputed warlike, it is not even lawful for any of the citizens to work at illiberal arts.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But what arts, pray, do you advise us to follow, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Need we be ashamed of imitating the king of the Persians? For they say that he pays close attention to husbandry and the art of war, holding that these are two of the noblest and most necessary pursuits.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And do you really believe, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; exclaimed Critobulus on hearing this, &ldquo;that the king of the Persians includes husbandry among his occupations?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Perhaps, Critobulus, the following considerations will enable us to discover whether he does so. We allow that he pays close attention to warfare, because he has given a standing order to every governor of the nations from which he receives tribute, to supply maintenance for a specified number of horsemen and archers and slingers and light infantry, that they may be strong enough to control his subjects and to protect the country in the event of an invasion; and,
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>apart from these, he maintains garrisons in the citadels. Maintenance for these is supplied by the governor charged with this duty, and the king annually reviews the mercenaries and all the other troops ordered to be under arms, assembling all but the men in the citadels at the place of muster, as it is called: he personally inspects the men who are near his residence, and sends trusted agents to review those who live far away.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>The officers, whether commanders of garrisons or of regiments or viceroys, who turn out with a full complement of men and parade them equipped with horses and arms in good condition, he promotes in the scale of honour and enriches with large grants of money; but those officers whom he finds to be neglecting the garrisons or making profit out of them he punishes severely, and appoints others to take their office. These actions, then, seem to us to leave no room for question that he pays attention to warfare.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;As for the country, he personally examines so much of it as he sees in the course of his progress through it; and he receives reports from his trusted agents on the territories that he does not see for himself. To those governors who are able to show him that their country is densely populated and that the land is in cultivation and well stocked with the trees of the district and with the crops, he assigns more territory and gives presents, and rewards them with seats of honour.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Cyropaedia,</title> VIII. i. 39.</note> Those whose territory he finds uncultivated and thinly populated either through harsh administration or through contempt or through carelessness, he punishes, and appoints others to take their office.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>By such action, does he seem to provide less for the cultivation of the land by the inhabitants than for its protection by the garrisons? Moreover, each of these duties is entrusted to a separate class of officers; one class governs the residents and the labourers, and collects tribute from them, the other commands the men under arms and the garrisons.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>If the commander of a garrison affords insufficient protection to the country, the civil governor and controller of agriculture denounces the commander, setting out that the inhabitants are unable to work the farms for want of protection. If, on the other hand, the commander brings peace to the farms, and the governor nevertheless causes the land to be sparsely populated and idle, the commander in turn denounces the governor.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>For, roughly speaking, where cultivation is inefficient, the garrisons are not maintained and the tribute cannot be paid. Wherever a viceroy is appointed, he attends to both these matters.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this point Critobulus said:
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, if the Great King does this, it seems to me that he pays as much attention to husbandry as to warfare.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yet further,&rdquo; continued <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;in all the districts he resides in and visits he takes care that there are &lsquo;paradises,&rsquo; as they call them, full of all the good and beautiful things that the soil will produce, and in this he himself spends most of his time, except when the season precludes it.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then it is of course necessary, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, to take care that these paradises in which the king spends his time shall contain a fine stock of trees and all other beautiful things that the soil produces.&rdquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And some say, Critobulus, that when the king makes gifts, he first invites those who have distinguished themselves in war, because it is useless to have broad acres under tillage unless there are men to defend them; and next to them, those who stock and cultivate the land best, saying that even stout-hearted warriors cannot live without the aid of workers.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>There is a story that <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName>, lately the most illustrious of princes, once said to the company invited to receive his gifts, &lsquo;I myself deserve to receive the gifts awarded in both classes; for I am the best at stocking land and the best at protecting the stock.&rsquo;&rdquo;
        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, if <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName> said that, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, he took as much pride in cultivating and stocking land as in being a warrior.&rdquo;
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, and, upon my word, if <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName> had only lived, it seems that he would have proved an excellent ruler. One of the many proofs that he has given of this is the fact that, when he was on his way to fight his brother for the throne, it is said that not a man deserted from <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName> to the king, whereas tens of thousands deserted from the king to <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName>.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>I think you have one clear proof of a ruler's excellence, when men obey him willingly<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Mem</title> III. iii. 9.</note> and choose to stand by him in moments of danger. Now his friends all fought at his side and fell at his side to a man, fighting round his body, with the one exception of Ariaeus, whose place in the battle was, in point of fact, on the left wing.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Anabasis,</title> I. ix. 31. Ariaeus fled when he saw that <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName> had fallen.</note>
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Further, the story goes that when <persName><surname>Lysander</surname></persName> came to him bringing the gifts form the allies, this <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName> showed him various marks of friendliness, as <persName><surname>Lysander</surname></persName> himself related once to a stranger at <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, adding besides that <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName> personally showed him round his paradise at <placeName key="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName>.
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/>Now <persName><surname>Lysander</surname></persName> admired the beauty of the trees in it, the accuracy of the spacing, the straightness of the rows, the regularity of the angles and the multitude of the sweet scents that clung round them as they walked; and for wonder of these things he cried, &lsquo;<persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName>, I really do admire all these lovely things, but I am far more impressed with your agent's skill in measuring and arranging everything so exactly.&rsquo;
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/>Cyrus was delighted to hear this and said: &lsquo;Well, <persName><surname>Lysander</surname></persName>, the whole of the measurement and arrangement is my own work, and I did some of the planting myself.&rsquo;
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/>&lsquo;What, <persName><surname>Cyrus</surname></persName>?&rsquo; exclaimed Lysander, looking at him, and marking the beauty and perfume of his robes, and the splendour of the necklaces and bangles and other jewels that he was wearing; &lsquo;did you really plant part of this with your own hands?&rsquo;
<milestone n="24" unit="section"/>&lsquo;Does that surprise you, Lysander?&rsquo; asked Cyrus in reply. &lsquo;I swear by the Sun-god that I never yet sat down to dinner when in sound health, without first working hard at some task of war or agriculture, or exerting myself somehow.&rsquo;
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Lysander himself declared, I should add, that on hearing this, he congratulated him in these words: &lsquo;I think you deserve your happiness, Cyrus, for you earn it by your virtues.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Now I tell you this,&rdquo; continued <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;because even the wealthiest cannot hold aloof from husbandry. For the pursuit of it is in some sense a luxury as well as a means of increasing one's estate and of training the body in all that a free man should be able to do.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For, in the first place, the earth yields to cultivators the food by which men live; she yields besides the luxuries they enjoy.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Secondly, she supplies all the things with which they decorate altars and statues and themselves, along with most pleasant sights and scents. Thirdly, she produces or feeds the ingredients of many delicate dishes; for the art of breeding stock is closely linked with husbandry; so that men have victims for propitiating the gods with sacrifice and cattle for their own use.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>And though she supplies good things in abundance, she suffers them not to be won without toil, but accustoms men to endure winter's cold and summer's heat. She gives increased strength through exercise to the men that labour with their own hands, and hardens the overseers of the work by rousing them early and forcing them to move about briskly. For on a farm no less than in a town the most important operations have their fixed times.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Again, if a man wants to serve in the cavalry, farming is his most efficient partner in furnishing keep for his horse; if on foot, it makes his body brisk. And the land helps in some measure to arouse a liking for the toil of hunting, since it affords facilities for keeping hounds and at the same time supplies food for the wild game that preys on the land.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>And if husbandry benefits horses and hounds, they benefit the farm no less, the horses by carrying the overseer early to the scene of his duties and enabling him to leave it late, the hounds by keeping the wild animals from injuring crops and sheep, and by helping to give safety to solitude.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>The land also stimulates armed protection of the country on the part of the husbandmen, by nourishing her crops in the open for the strongest to take.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>And what art produces better runners, throwers and jumpers than husbandry? What art rewards the labourer more generously? What art welcomes her follower more gladly, inviting him to come and take whatever he wants? What art entertains strangers more generously?
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Where is there greater facility for passing the winter comforted by generous fire and warm baths, than on a farm? Where is it pleasanter to spend the summer enjoying the cool waters and breezes and shade, than in the country?
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>What other art yields more seemly first-fruits for the gods, or gives occasion for more crowded festivals? What art is dearer to servants, or pleasanter to a wife, or more delightful to children, or more agreeable to friends?
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>To me indeed it seems strange, if any free man has come by a possession pleasanter than this, or has found out an occupation pleasanter than this or more useful for winning a livelihood.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yet again, the earth willingly<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or <foreign lang="greek">qeo\s ou)=a,</foreign> &ldquo;is a goddess and.&rdquo;</note> teaches righteousness to those who can learn; for the better she is served, the more good things she gives in return.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>And if haply those who are occupied in farming, and are receiving a rigorous and manly teaching, are forced at any time to quit their lands by great armies, they, as men well-found in mind and in body, can enter the country of those who hinder them, and take sufficient for their support. Often in time of war it is safer to go armed in search of food than to gather it with farming implements.
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Moreover, husbandry helps to train men for corporate effort. For men are essential to an expedition against an enemy, and the cultivation of the soil demands the aid of men.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Therefore nobody can be a good farmer unless he makes his labourers both eager and obedient; and the captain who leads men against an enemy must contrive to secure the same results by rewarding those who act as brave men should act and punishing the disobedient.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>And it is no less necessary for a farmer to encourage his labourers often, than for a general to encourage his men. And slaves need the stimulus of good hopes no less, nay, even more than free men, to make them steadfast.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>It has been nobly said that husbandry is the mother and nurse of the other arts. For when husbandry flourishes, all the other arts are in good fettle; but whenever the land is compelled to lie waste, the other arts of landsmen and mariners alike well-nigh perish.&rdquo;
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; replied Critobulus to this, &ldquo;I think you are right so far. But in husbandry a man can rely very little on forecast. For hailstorms and frosts sometimes, and droughts and rains and blight ruin schemes well planned and well carried out; and sometimes well-bred stock is miserably destroyed by an outbreak of disease.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> in reply,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Mem.</title> I. iv. 15; iv. iii. 12. <title>Cyrop.</title> I. vi. 46.</note> &ldquo;I thought you knew, Critobulus, that the operations of husbandry no less than those of war are in the hands of the gods. And you observe, I suppose, that men engaged in war try to propitate the gods before taking action; and with sacrifices and omens seek to know what they ought to do and what they ought not to do;
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>and for the business of husbandry do you think it less necessary to ask the blessing of the gods? Know of a surety that right-minded men offer prayer for fruits and crops and cattle and horses and sheep, aye and for all that they possess.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I think you are right when you bid me try to begin every undertaking with the gods' help, since the gods control the works of peace no less than of war. We will try, then, to do so. But now go back to the point where you broke off in your talk about estate management, and try to expound the subject completely step by step, since after hearing what you have said so far, I seem even now to discern rather more clearly than before what I must do to earn my living.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I suggest then,&rdquo; resumed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;that we should first recapitulate those points of our discussion on which we have already reached agreement, in order that we may try to agree as thoroughly, if possible, when we go through the remaining steps.&rdquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;O yes; when several are jointly interested in money, it is pleasant to have no disagreement in going over the accounts; and it is equally pleasant for us, as the interested parties in a discussion, to agree as we go over the several steps.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well now, we thought that estate management is the name of a branch of knowledge, and this knowledge appeared to be that by which men can increase estates, and an estate appeared to be identical with the total of one's property, and we said that property is that which is useful for supplying a livelihood, and useful things turned out to be all those things that one knows how to use.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Now we thought that it is impossible to learn all the sciences, and we agreed with our states in rejecting the so-called illiberal arts, because they seem to spoil the body and unnerve the mind.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>We said<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing to this effect occurs in c. iv.</note> that the clearest proof of this would be forthcoming, if in the course of a hostile invasion the husbandmen and craftsmen were made to sit apart, and each group were asked whether they voted for defending the country or withdrawing from the open and guarding the fortresses.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>We thought that in these circumstances the men who have to do with the land would give their vote for defending it, the craftsmen for not fighting, but sitting still, as they have been brought up to do, aloof from toil and danger.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>We came to the conclusion that for a gentleman the best occupation and the best science is husbandry, from which men obtain what is necessary to them.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>For this occupation seemed to be the easiest to learn and the pleasantest to work at, to give to the body the greatest measure of strength and beauty, and to leave to the mind the greatest amount of spare time for attending to the interests of one's friends and city.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>Moreover, since the crops grow and the cattle on a farm graze outside the walls, husbandry seemed to us to help in some measure to make the workers valiant. And so this way of making a living appeared to be held in the highest estimation by our states, because it seems to turn out the best citizens and most loyal to the community.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I have already heard enough, I think, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, to convince me that it is in the highest degree honourable, good and pleasant to get a living by husbandry. But you told me that you have discovered the reasons why some farmers are so successful that husbandry yields them all they need in abundance, and others are so inefficient that they find farming unprofitable. I should like to hear the reasons in each case, in order that we may do what is good and avoid what is harmful.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well then, Critobulus, I propose to give you a complete account of an interview I once had with a man whom I took to be really one of those who are justly styled &lsquo;gentlemen.&rsquo;&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I should greatly like to hear it, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, for I long to deserve that title myself.&rdquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then I will tell you how I came to take note of him. For it took me a very little time to visit our good builders, good smiths, good painters, good sculptors, and other people of the kind, and to inspect those of their works that are declared to be beautiful;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/>but I felt a desire to meet one of those who are called by that grand name &lsquo;gentleman,&rsquo; which implies &lsquo;beautiful' as well as &lsquo;good,&rsquo; in order to consider what they did to deserve it.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>And, first, because the epithet &lsquo;beautiful&rsquo; is added to &lsquo;good,&rsquo; I went up to every person I noticed, and tried to discover whether I could anywhere see goodness in combination with beauty.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>But after all, it was not so: I thought I discovered that some who were beautiful to look at were thoroughly depraved in their minds. So I decided to let good looks alone, and to seek out someone known as &lsquo;a gentleman.&rsquo;
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>Accordingly, since I heard the name applied to Ischomachus by men, women, citizens and strangers alike, I decided to meet him, if I could.
<milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;So, happening one day to see him sitting in the cloister of the temple of Zeus Eleutherius apparently at leisure, I approached, and sitting down at his side, said:<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why sitting still, Ischomachus? You are not much in the habit of doing nothing; for generally when I see you in the market-place you are either busy or at least not wholly idle.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;True, and you would not have seen me so now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, had I not made an appointment with some strangers here.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Pray where do you spend your time,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;and what do you do when you are not engaged in some such occupation? For I want very much to learn how you came to be called a gentleman, since you do not pass your time indoors, and your condition does not suggest that you do so.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Smiling at my question,
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>&lsquo;How came you to be called a gentleman?&rsquo;, and apparently well pleased, Ischomachus answered: &lsquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, whether certain persons call me so when they talk to you about me, I know not. Assuredly when they challenge me to an exchange of property in order to escape some public burden, fitting a warship or providing a chorus, nobody looks for the &ldquo;gentleman,&rdquo; but the challenge refers to me as plain &ldquo;Ischomachus,&rdquo; my father's son. Well now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, as you ask the question, I certainly do not pass my time indoors; for, you know, my wife is quite capable of looking after the house by herself.&rsquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Ah, Ischomachus,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;that is just what I want to hear from you. Did you yourself train your wife to be of the right sort, or did she know her household duties when you received her from her parents?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, what knowledge could she have had, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, when I took her for my wife? She was not yet fifteen years old when she came to me, and up to that time she had lived in leading-strings, seeing, hearing and saying as little as possible.
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>If when she came she knew no more than how, when given wool, to turn out a cloak, and had seen only how the spinning is given out to the maids, is not that as much as could be expected? For in control of her appetite, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, she had been excellently trained; and this sort of training is, in my opinion, the most important to man and woman alike.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But in other respects did you train your wife yourself, Ischomachus, so that she should be competent to perform her duties?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh no, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; not until I had first offered sacrifice and prayed that I might really teach, and she learn what was best for us both.&rsquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Did not your wife join with you in these same sacrifices and prayers?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh yes, earnestly promising before heaven to behave as she ought to do; and it was easy to see that she would not neglect the lessons I taught her.&rsquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Pray tell me, Ischomachus, what was the first lesson you taught her, since I would sooner hear this from your lips than an account of the noblest athletic event or horse-race?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, as soon as I found her docile and sufficiently domesticated to carry on conversation, I questioned her to this effect:<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Tell me, dear, have you realised for what reason I took you and your parents gave you to me?
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>For it is obvious to you, I am sure, that we should have had no difficulty in finding someone else to share our beds. But I for myself and your parents for you considered who was the best partner of home and children that we could get. My choice fell on you, and your parents, it appears, chose me as the best they could find.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>Now if God grants us children, we will then think out how we shall best train them. For one of the blessings in which we shall share is the acquisition of the very best of allies and the very best of support in old age; but at present we share in this our home.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>For I am paying into the common stock all that I have, and you have put in all that you brought with you. And we are not to reckon up which of us has actually contributed the greater amount, but we should know of a surety that the one who proves the better partner makes the more valuable contribution.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;My wife's answer was as follows, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>: &ldquo;How can I possibly help you? What power have I? Nay, all depends on you. My duty, as my mother told me, is to be discreet.&rdquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, of course, dear,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;my father said the same to me. But discretion both in a man and a woman, means acting in such a manner that their possessions shall be in the best condition possible, and that as much as possible shall be added to them by fair and honourable means.&rdquo;
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;And what do you see that I can possibly do to help in the improvement of our property?&rdquo; asked my wife.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Why,&rdquo; said I, &ldquo;of course you must try to do as well as possible what the gods made you capable of doing and the law sanctions.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;And pray, what is that?&rdquo; said she.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Things of no small moment, I fancy,&rdquo; replied I, &ldquo;unless, indeed, the tasks over which the queen bee in the hive presides are of small moment.
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>For it seems to me, dear, that the gods with great discernment have coupled together male and female, as they are called, chiefly in order that they may form a perfect partnership in mutual service.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>For, in the first place, that the various species of living creatures may not fail, they are joined in wedlock for the production of children. Secondly, offspring to support them in old age is provided by this union, to human beings, at any rate. Thirdly, human beings live not in the open air, like beasts, but obviously need shelter.
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>Nevertheless, those who mean to win store to fill the covered place, have need of someone to work at the open-air occupations; since ploughing, sowing, planting and grazing are all such open-air employments; and these supply the needful food.
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/>Then again, as soon as this is stored in the covered place, then there is need of someone to keep it and to work at the things that must be done under cover. Cover is needed for the nursing of the infants; cover is needed for the making of the corn into bread, and likewise for the manufacture of clothes from the wool.
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/>And since both the indoor and the outdoor tasks demand labour and attention, God from the first adapted the woman's nature, I think, to the indoor and man's to the outdoor tasks and cares.
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;For he made the man's body and mind more capable of enduring cold and heat, and journeys and campaigns; and therefore imposed on him the outdoor tasks. To the woman, since he has made her body less capable of such endurance, I take it that God has assigned the indoor tasks.
<milestone n="24" unit="section"/>And knowing that he had created in the woman and had imposed on her the nourishment of the infants, he meted out to her a larger portion of affection for new-born babes than to the man.
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/>And since he imposed on the woman the protection of the stores also, knowing that for protection a fearful disposition is no disadvantage, God meted out a larger share of fear to the woman than to the man; and knowing that he who deals with the outdoor tasks will have to be their defender against any wrong-doer, he meted out to him again a larger share of courage.
<milestone n="26" unit="section"/>But because both must give and take, he granted to both impartially memory and attention; and so you could not distinguish whether the male or the female sex has the larger share of these.
<milestone n="27" unit="section"/>And God also gave to both impartially the power to practise due self-control, and gave authority to whichever is the better&mdash;whether it be the man or the woman&mdash;to win a larger portion of the good that comes from it.
<milestone n="28" unit="section"/>And just because both have not the same aptitudes, they have the more need of each other, and each member of the pair is the more useful to the other, the one being competent where the other is deficient.
<milestone n="29" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Now since we know, dear, what duties have been assigned to each of us by God, we must endeavour, each of us, to do the duties allotted to us as well as possible.
<milestone n="30" unit="section"/>The law, moreover, approves of them, for it joins together man and woman. And as God has made them partners in their children, so the law appoints them partners in the home. And besides, the law declares those tasks to be honourable for each of them wherein God has made the one to excel the other. Thus, to be woman it is more honourable to stay indoors than to abide in the fields, but to the man it is unseemly rather to stay indoors than to attend to the work outside.
<milestone n="31" unit="section"/>If a man acts contrary to the nature God has given him, possibly his defiance is detected by the gods and he is punished for neglecting his own work, or meddling with his wife's.
<milestone n="32" unit="section"/>I think that the queen bee is busy about just such other tasks appointed by God.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Cyrop.</title>v. i. 24.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;And pray,&rdquo; said she, &ldquo;how do the queen bee's tasks resemble those that I have to do?&rdquo;
<milestone n="33" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;How? she stays in the hive,&rdquo; I answered, &ldquo;and does not suffer the bees to be idle; but those whose duty it is to work outside she sends forth to their work; and whatever each of them brings in, she knows and receives it, and keeps it till it is wanted. And when the time is come to use it, she portions out the just share to each.
<milestone n="34" unit="section"/>She likewise presides over the weaving of the combs in the hive, that they may be well and quickly woven, and cares for the brood of little ones, that it be duly reared up. And when the young bees have been duly reared and are fit for work, she sends them forth to found a colony, with a leader to guide the young adventurers.&rdquo;
<milestone n="35" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Then shall I too have to do these things?&rdquo; said my wife.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Indeed you will,&rdquo; said I; &ldquo;your duty will be to remain indoors and send out those servants whose work is outside, and superintend those who are to work indoors, and to receive the incomings,
<milestone n="36" unit="section"/>and distribute so much of them as must be spent, and watch over so much as is to be kept in store, and take care that the sum laid by for a year be not spent in a month. And when wool is brought to you, you must see that cloaks are made for those that want them. You must see too that the dry corn is in good condition for making food.
<milestone n="37" unit="section"/>One of the duties that fall to you, however, will perhaps seem rather thankless: you will have to see that any servant who is ill is cared for.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh no,&rdquo; cried my wife, &ldquo;it will be delightful, assuming that those who are well cared for are going to feel grateful and be more loyal than before.&rdquo;
<milestone n="38" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, my dear,&rdquo; cried I, delighted with her answer, &ldquo;what makes the bees so devoted to their leader in the hive, that when she forsakes it, they all follow her, and not one thinks of staying behind? Is it not the result of some such thoughtful acts on her part?&rdquo;
<milestone n="39" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;It would surprise me,&rdquo; answered my wife, &ldquo;if the leader's activities did not concern you more than me. For my care of the goods indoors and my management would look rather ridiculous, I fancy, if you did not see that something is gathered in from outside.&rdquo;
<milestone n="40" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;And my ingathering would look ridiculous,&rdquo; I countered, &ldquo;if there were not someone to keep what is gathered in. Don't you see how they who &lsquo;draw water in a leaky jar,&rsquo; as the saying goes, are pitied, because they seem to labour in vain?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course,&rdquo; she said, &ldquo;for they are indeed in a miserable plight if they do that.&rdquo;
<milestone n="41" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;But I assure you, dear, there are other duties peculiar to you that are pleasant to perform. It is delightful to teach spinning to a maid who had no knowledge of it when you received her, and to double her worth to you: to take in hand a girl who is ignorant of housekeeping and service, and after teaching her and making her trustworthy and serviceable to find her worth any amount: to have the power of rewarding the discreet and useful members of your household, and of punishing anyone who turns out to be a rogue.
<milestone n="42" unit="section"/>But the pleasantest experience of all is to prove yourself better than I am, to make me your servant; and, so far from having cause to fear that as you grow older you may be less honoured in the household, to feel confident that with advancing years, the better partner you prove to me and the better housewife to our children, the greater will be the honour paid to you in our home.
        <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>For it is not through outward comeliness that the sum of things good and beautiful is increased in the world, but by the daily practice of the virtues.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Such was the tenor of my earliest talks with her, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, so far as I can recall them.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And did you find, Ischomachus, that they acted as a stimulus to her diligence?&rsquo; I asked.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, indeed,&rsquo; answered Ischomachus, &lsquo;and I recollect that she was vexed and blushed crimson, because she could not give me something from the stores when I asked for it.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>And seeing that she was annoyed, I said: &ldquo;Don't worry, dear, because you cannot give me what I am asking for. For not to be able to use a thing when you want it is poverty unquestionably; but a failure to get the thing that you seek is less grievous than not to seek it at all because you know that it does not exist. The fact is, you are not to blame for this, but I, because I handed over the things to you without giving directions where they were to be put, so that you might know where to put them and where to find them.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>My dear, there is nothing so convenient or so good for human beings as order. Thus, a chorus is a combination of human beings; but when the members of it do as they choose, it becomes mere confusion, and there is no pleasure in watching it; but when they act and chant in an orderly fashion, then those same men at once seem worth seeing and worth hearing.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Again, my dear, an army in disorder is a confused mass, an easy prey to enemies, a disgusting sight to friends and utterly useless, &mdash;donkey, trooper, carrier, light-armed, horseman, chariot, huddled together.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Cyropoedia,</title> VI. iii. 25; <title>Mem.</title> III. i. 7.</note> For how are they to march in such a plight, when they hamper one another, some walking while others run, some running while others halt, chariot colliding with horseman, donkey with chariot, carrier with trooper?
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>If there is fighting to be done, how can they fight in such a state? For the units that must needs run away when attacked are enough to trample underfoot the heavy infantry.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>But an army in orderly array is a noble sight to friends, and an unwelcome spectacle to the enemy. What friend would not rejoice as he watches a strong body of troopers marching in order, would not admire cavalry riding in squadrons? And what enemy would not fear troopers, horsemen, light-armed, archers, slingers disposed in serried ranks and following their officers in orderly fashion?
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Nay, even on the march where order is kept, though they number tens of thousands, all move steadily forward as one man; for the line behind is continually filling up the gap.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Or, again, why is a man-of-war laden with men terrible to an enemy and a goodly sight to friends, if not for its speed? Why do the men on board not hamper one another? Is it not just because they are seated in order, swing forward and backward in order, embark and disembark in order?
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>If I want a type of disorder, I think of a farmer who has stored barley, wheat and pulse in one bin; and then when he wants a bannock or a loaf or a pudding, must pick out the grain instead of finding it separate and ready for use.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;And so, my dear, if you do not want this confusion, and wish to know exactly how to manage our goods, and to find with ease whatever is wanted, and to satisfy me by giving me anything I ask for, let us choose the place that each portion should occupy; and, having put the things in their place, let us instruct the maid to take them from it and put them back again. Thus we shall know what is safe and sound and what is not; for the place itself will miss whatever is not in it, and a glance will reveal anything that wants attention, and the knowledge where each thing is will quickly bring it to hand, so that we can use it without trouble.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Once I had an opportunity of looking over the great Phoenician merchantman, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and I thought I had never seen tackle so excellently and accurately arranged. For I never saw so many bits of stuff packed away separately in so small a receptacle.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>As you know, a ship needs a great quantity of wooden and corded implements when she comes into port or puts to sea, much rigging, as it is called, when she sails, many contrivances to protect her against enemy vessels; she carries a large supply of arms for the men, and contains a set of household utensils for each mess. In addition to all this, she is laden with cargo which the skipper carries for profit.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>And all the things I mention were contained in a chamber of little more than a hundred square cubits.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><foreign lang="greek">deka/klinos</foreign> is literally &ldquo;having space for ten couches&rdquo;; but it seems that such compounds of <foreign lang="greek">kli/nh</foreign> (&ldquo;a couch&rdquo;) were used to denote a definite measure of size.</note> And I noticed that each kind of thing was so neatly stowed away that there was no confusion, no work for a searcher, nothing out of place, no troublesome untying to cause delay when anything was wanted for immediate use.
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>I found that the steersman's servant, who is called the mate, knows each particular section so exactly, that he can tell even when away where everything is kept and how much there is of it, just as well as a man who knows how to spell can tell how many letters there are in <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> and in what order they come.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Now I saw this man in his spare time inspecting all the stores that are wanted, as a matter of course, in the ship.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or, more probably, &ldquo;during the voyage.&rdquo;</note> I was surprised to see him looking over them, and asked what he was doing. &ldquo;Sir,&rdquo; he answered, &ldquo;I am looking to see how the ship's tackle is stored, in case of accident, or whether anything is missing or mixed up with other stuff.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>For when God sends a storm at sea, there's no time to search about for what you want or to serve it out if it's in a muddle. For God threatens and punishes careless fellows, and you're lucky if he merely refrains from destroying the innocent; and if he saves you when you do your work well, you have much cause to thank heaven.&rdquo;
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Now after seeing the ship's tackle in such perfect order, I told my wife: &ldquo;Considering that folk aboard a merchant vessel, even though it be a little one, find room for things and keep order, though tossed violently to and fro, and find what they want to get, though terror-stricken, it would be downright carelessness on our part if we, who have large storerooms in our house to keep everything separate and whose house rests on solid ground, fail to find a good and handy place for everything. Would it not be sheer stupidity on our part?
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;How good it is to keep one's stock of utensils in order, and how easy to find a suitable place in a house to put each set in, I have already said.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>And what a beautiful sight is afforded by boots of all sorts and conditions ranged in rows! How beautiful it is to see cloaks of all sorts and conditions kept separate, or blankets, or brazen vessels, or table furniture! Yes, no serious man will smile when I claim that there is beauty in the order even of pots and pans set out in neat array, however much it may move the laughter of a wit.
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>There is nothing, in short, that does not gain in beauty when set out in order. For each set looks like a troop of utensils, and the space between the sets is beautiful to see, when each set is kept clear of it, just as a troop of dancers about the altar is a beautiful spectacle in itself, and even the free space looks beautiful and unencumbered.
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;We can test the truth of what I say, dear, without any inconvenience and with very little trouble. Moreover, my dear, there is no ground for any misgiving that it is hard to find someone who will get to know the various places and remember to put each set in its proper place.
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/>For we know, I take it, that the city as a whole has ten thousand times as much of everything as we have; and yet you may order any sort of servant to buy something in the market and to bring it home, and he will be at no loss: every one of them is bound to know where he should go to get each article. Now the only reason for this is that everything is kept in a fixed place.
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/>But when you are searching for a person, you often fail to find him, though he may be searching for you himself. And for this again the one reason is that no place of meeting has been fixed.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Such is the gist of the conversation I think I remember having with her about the arrangement of utensils and their use.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And what was the result?&rsquo; I asked; &lsquo;did you think, Ischomachus, that your wife paid any heed to the lessons you tried so earnestly to teach her?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, she promised to attend to them, and was evidently pleased beyond measure to feel that she had found a solution of her difficulties, and she begged me to lose no time in arranging things as I had suggested.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And how did you arrange things for her, Ischomachus?&rsquo; I asked.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, I decided first to show her the possibilities of our house. For it contains few elaborate decorations, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; but the rooms are designed simply with the object of providing as convenient receptacles as possible for the things that are to fill them, and thus each room invited just what was suited to it.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Thus the store-room by the security of its position called for the most valuable blankets and utensils, the dry covered rooms for the corn, the cool for the wine, the well-lit for those works of art and vessels that need light.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>I showed her decorated living-rooms for the family that are cool in summer and warm in winter.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Mem.</title> III. viii. 9.</note> I showed her that the whole house fronts south, so that it was obvious that it is sunny in winter and shady in summer.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>I showed her the women's quarters too, separated by a bolted door from the men's, so that nothing which ought not to be moved may be taken out, and that the servants may not breed without our leave. For honest servants generally prove more loyal if they have a family; but rogues, if they live in wedlock, become all the more prone to mischief.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And now that we had completed the list, we forthwith set about separating the furniture tribe by tribe. We began by collecting together the vessels we use in sacrificing. After that we put together the women's holiday finery, and the men's holiday and war garb, blankets in the women's, blankets in the men's quarters, women's shoes, men's shoes.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Another tribe consisted of arms, and three others of implements for spinning, for bread-making and for cooking; others, again, of the things required for washing, at the kneading-trough, and for table use. All these we divided into two sets, things in constant use and things reserved for festivities.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>We also put by themselves the things consumed month by month, and set apart the supplies calculated to last for a year. For this plan makes it easier to tell how they will last to the end of the time. When we had divided all the portable property tribe by tribe, we arranged everything in its proper place.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>After that we showed the servants who have to use them where to keep the utensils they require daily, for baking, cooking, spinning and so forth; handed them over to their care and charged them to see that they were safe and sound.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>The things that we use only for festivals or entertainments, or on rare occasions, we handed over to the housekeeper, and after showing her their places and counting and making a written list of all the items, we told her to give them out to the right servants, to remember what she gave to each of them, and when receiving them back to put everything in the place from which she took it.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;In appointing the housekeeper, we chose the woman whom on consideration we judged to be the most temperate in eating and wine drinking and sleeping<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Mem.</title> I. v. 1; <title>Cyropaedia,</title> I. vi. 8.</note> and the most modest with men, the one, too, who seemed to have the best memory, to be most careful not to offend us by neglecting her duties, and to think most how she could earn some reward by obliging us.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>We also taught her to be loyal to us by making her a partner in all our joys and calling on her to share our troubles. Moreover, we trained her to be eager for the improvement of our estate, by making her familiar with it and by allowing her to share in our success.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>And further, we put justice into her, by giving more honour to the just than to the unjust, and by showing her that the just live in greater wealth and freedom than the unjust; and we placed her in that position of superiority.
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;When all this was done, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I told my wife that all these measures were futile, unless she saw to it herself that our arrangement was strictly adhered to in every detail. I explained that in well-ordered cities the citizens are not satisfied with passing good laws; they go further, and choose guardians of the laws, who act as overseers, commending the law-abiding and punishing law-breakers.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>So I charged my wife to consider herself guardian of the laws to our household. And just as the commander of a garrison inspects his guards, so must she inspect the chattels whenever she thought it well to do so; as the Council scrutinises the cavalry and the horses, so she was to make sure that everything was in good condition: like a queen, she must reward the worthy with praise and honour, so far as in her lay, and not spare rebuke and punishment when they were called for.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Moreover, I taught her that she should not be vexed that I assigned heavier duties to her than to the servants in respect of our possessions. Servants, I pointed out, carry, tend and guard their master's property, and only in this sense have a share in it; they have no right to use anything except by the owner's leave; but everything belongs to the master, to use it as he will.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>Therefore, I explained, he who gains most by the preservation of the goods and loses most by their destruction, is the one who is bound to take most care of them.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, now, Ischomachus,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;was your wife inclined to pay heed to your words?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; he cried, &lsquo;she just told me that I was mistaken if I supposed that I was laying a hard task on her in telling her that she must take care of our things. It would have been harder, she said, had I required her to neglect her own possessions, than to have the duty of attending to her own peculiar blessings.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>The fact is,&rsquo; he added, &lsquo;just as it naturally comes easier to a good woman to care for her own children than to neglect them, so, I imagine, a good woman finds it pleasanter to look after her own possessions than to neglect them.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Now when I heard that his wife had given him this answer, I exclaimed; &lsquo;Upon my word, Ischomachus, your wife has a truly masculine mind by your showing!'<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes,&rsquo; said Ischomachus, &lsquo;and I am prepared to give you other examples of high-mindedness on her part, when a word from me was enough to secure her instant obedience.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Tell me what they are,&rsquo; I cried; &lsquo;for if Zeuxis showed me a fair woman's portrait painted by his own hand, it would not give me half the pleasure I derive from the contemplation of a living woman's virtues.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Thereupon Ischomachus took up his parable. &lsquo;Well, one day, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I noticed that her face was made up: she had rubbed in white lead in order to look even whiter than she is, and alkanet juice to heighten the rosy colour of her cheeks; and she was wearing boots with thick soles to increase her height.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>So I said to her, &ldquo;Tell me, my dear, how should I appear more worthy of your love as a partner in our goods, by disclosing to you our belongings just as they are, without boasting of imaginary possessions or concealing any part of what we have, or by trying to trick you with an exaggerated account, showing you bad money and gilt necklaces and describing clothes that will fade as real purple?&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Hush!&rdquo; she broke in immediately, &ldquo;pray don't be like that&mdash;I could not love you with all my heart if you were like that!&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Then, are we not joined together by another bond of union, dear, to be partners in our bodies?&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;The world says so, at any rate.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;How then should I seem more worthy of your love in this partnership of the body&mdash;by striving to have my body hale and strong when I present it to you, and so literally to be of a good countenance in your sight, or by smearing my cheeks with red lead and painting myself under the eyes with rouge before I show myself to you and clasp you in my arms, cheating you and offering to your eyes and hands red lead instead of my real flesh?&rdquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh,&rdquo; she cried, &ldquo;I would sooner touch you than red lead, would sooner see your own colour than rouge, would sooner see your eyes bright than smeared with grease.&rdquo;
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&ldquo;&lsquo;Then please assume, my dear, that I do not prefer white paint and dye of alkanet to your real colour; but just as the gods have made horses to delight in horses, cattle in cattle, sheep in sheep, so human beings find the human body undisguised most delightful.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Tricks like these may serve to gull outsiders, but people who live together are bound to be found out, if they try to deceive one another. For they are found out while they are dressing in the morning; they perspire and are lost; a tear convicts them; the bath reveals them as they are!&rsquo;&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And, pray, what did she say to that?&rsquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>I asked.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Nothing,&rsquo; he said, &lsquo;only she gave up such practices from that day forward, and tried to let me se her undisguised and as she should be. Still, she did ask whether I could advise her on one point: how she might make herself really beautiful, instead of merely seeming to be so.
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>And this was my advice, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>: &ldquo;Don't sit about for ever like a slave, but try, God helping you, to behave as a mistress: stand before the loom and be ready to instruct those who know less than you, and to learn from those who know more: look after the bakingmaid: stand by the housekeeper when she is serving out stores: go round and see whether everything is in its place.&rdquo; For I thought that would give her a walk as well as occupation.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>I also said it was excellent exercise to mix flour and knead dough; and to shake and fold cloaks and bedclothes; such excercise would give her a better appetite, improve her health, and add natural colour to her cheeks.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>Besides, when a wife's looks outshine a maid's and she is fresher and more becomingly dressed, they're a ravishing sight, especially when the wife is also willing to oblige, whereas the girl's services are compulsory.
        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>But wives who sit about like fine ladies, expose themselves to comparison with painted and fraudulent hussies. And now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, you may be sure, my wife's dress and appearance are in accord with my instructions and with my present description.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;At this point I said, &lsquo;Ischomachus, I think your account of your wife's occupations is sufficient for the present&mdash;and very creditable it is to both of you. But now tell me of your own: thus you will have the satisfaction of stating the reasons why you are so highly respected, and I shall be much beholden to you for a complete account of a gentleman's occupations, and if my understanding serves, for a thorough knowledge of them.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; answered Ischomachus, &lsquo;it will be a very great pleasure to me to give you an account of my daily occupations, that you may correct me if you think there is anything amiss in my conduct.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;As to that,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;how could I presume to correct a perfect gentleman, I who am supposed to be a mere chatterer with my head in the air,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><foreign lang="greek">a)dlesxei=n, a)erometrei=n;</foreign> these are taunts commonly levelled at <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; thus, for instance, Aristophanes, <title>Clouds</title>, 225: &ldquo;What are you at, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo; &ldquo;I'm walking the air and pondering on the sun&rdquo;; and <date value="1480">1480</date>: Socr., &ldquo;Excuse my silly chatter.&rdquo;</note> I who am called&mdash;the most senseless of all taunts&mdash;a poor beggar?
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>I do assure you, Ischomachus, this last imputation would have driven me to despair, were it not that a day or two ago I came upon the horse of Nicias the foreigner.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">If the text is right, this person cannot be the well-known Nicias.</note> I saw a crowd walking behind the creature and staring, and heard some of them talking volubly about him. Well, I went up to the groom and asked him if the horse had many possessions.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>The man looked at me as if I must be mad to ask such a question, and asked me how a horse could own property. At that I recovered, for his answer showed that it is possible even for a poor horse to be a good one, if nature has given him a good spirit.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Assume, therefore, that it is possible for me to be a good man, and give me a complete account of your occupations, that, so far as my understanding allows me, I may endeavour to follow your example from to-morrow morning; for that's a good day for entering on a course of virtue.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You're joking, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; said Ischomachus; &lsquo;nevertheless I will tell you what principles I try my best to follow consistently in life.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>For I seem to realise that, while the gods have made it impossible for men to prosper without knowing and attending to the things they ought to do, to some of the wise and careful they grant prosperity, and to some deny it; and therefore I begin by worshipping the gods, and try to conduct myself in such a way that I may have health and strength in answer to my prayers, the respect of my fellow-citizens, the affection of my friends, safety with honour in war, and wealth increased by honest means.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;What, Ischomachus,&rsquo; I asked on hearing that, &lsquo;do you really want to be rich and to have much, along with much trouble to take care of it?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;The answer to your questions,&rsquo; said he, &lsquo;is, Yes, I do indeed. For I would fain honour the gods without counting the cost, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, help friends in need, and look to it that the city lacks no adornment that my means can supply.&rsquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Truly noble aspirations, Ischomachus,&rsquo; I cried, &lsquo;and worthy of a man of means, no doubt! Seeing that there are many who cannot live without help from others, and many are content if they can get enough for their own needs, surely those who can maintain their own estate and yet have enough left to adorn the city and relieve their friends may well be thought high and mighty men.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>However,&rsquo; I added, &lsquo;praise of such men is a commonplace among us. Please return to your first statement, Ischomachus, and tell me how you take care of your health and your strength, how you make it possible to come through war with safety and honour. I shall be content to hear about your money-making afterwards.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; replied Ischomachus, &lsquo;all these things hang together, so far as I can see. For if a man has plenty to eat, and works off the effects<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Cyropaedia</title> I. ii, 10.</note> properly, I take it that he both insures his health and adds to his strength. By training himself in the arts of war he is more qualified to save himself honourably, and by due diligence and avoidance of loose habits, he is more likely to increase his estate.&rsquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;So far, Ischomachus, I follow you,&rsquo; I answered. &lsquo;You mean that by working after meals, by diligence and by training, a man is more apt to obtain the good things of life. But now I should like you to give me details. By what kind of work do you endeavour to keep your health and strength? How do you train yourself in the arts of war? What diligence do you use to have a surplus from which to help friends and strengthen the city?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; replied Ischomachus, &lsquo;I rise from my bed at an hour when, if I want to call on anyone, I am sure to find him still at home. If I have any business to do in town, I make it an opportunity for getting a walk.
        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>If there is nothing pressing to be done in town, my servant leads my horse to the farm, and I make my walk by going to it on foot, with more benefit, perhaps, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, than if I took a turn in the arcade.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>When I reach the farm, I may find planting, clearing, sowing or harvesting in progress. I superintend all the details of the work, and make any improvements in method that I can suggest.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>After this, I usually mount my horse and go through exercises, imitating as closely as I can the exercises needed in warfare. I avoid neither slope nor steep incline, ditch nor watercourse, but I use all possible care not to lame my horse when he takes them.
        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>After I have finished, the servant gives the horse a roll and leads him home, bringing with him from the farm anything we happen to want in the city. I divide the return home between walking and running. Arrived, I clean myself with a strigil, and then I have luncheon, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, eating just enough to get through the day neither empty-bellied nor too full.&rsquo;
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Upon my word, Ischomachus,&rsquo; cried I, &lsquo;I am delighted with your activities. For you have a pack of appliances for securing health and strength, of exercises for war and specifies for getting rich, and you use them all at the same time! That does seem to me admirable!
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>And in fact you afford convincing proofs that your method in pursuing each of these objects is sound. For we see you generally in the enjoyment of health and strength, thanks to the gods, and we know that you are considered one of our best horsemen and wealthiest citizens.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And what comes of these activities, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>? Not, as you perhaps expected to hear, that I am generally dubbed a gentleman, but that I am persistently slandered.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Ah,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;but I was meaning to ask you, Ischomachus, whether you include in your system ability to conduct a prosecution and defence, in case you have to appear in the courts?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; he answered, &lsquo;do you not see<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Mem.</title> IV. viii. 4.</note> that this is just what I am constantly practising&mdash;showing my traducers that I wrong no man and do all the good I can to many? And do you not think that I practise myself in accusing, by taking careful note of certain persons who are doing wrong to many individuals and to the state, and are doing no good to anyone?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="23" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But tell me one thing more, Ischomachus,&rsquo; I said; &lsquo;do you also practise the art of expounding these matters?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; he replied, &lsquo;I assiduously practise the art of speaking. For I get one of the servants to act as prosecutor or defendant, and try to confute him; or I praise or blame someone before his friends; or I act as peace-maker between some of my acquaintances by trying to show them that it is to their interest to be friends rather than enemies.
<milestone n="24" unit="section"/>I assist at a court-martial and censure a soldier, or take turns in defending a man who is unjustly blamed, or in accusing one who is unjustly honoured. We often sit in counsel and speak in support of the course we want to adopt and against the course we want to avoid.
        <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>I have often been singled out before now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and condemned to suffer punishment or pay damages.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;By whom, Ischomachus?&rsquo; I asked; &lsquo;I am in the dark about that!'<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;By my wife,&rsquo; was his answer.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And, pray, how do you plead?&rsquo; said I.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Pretty well, when it is to my interest to speak the truth. But when lying is called for, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I can't make the worse cause appear the better&mdash;oh no, not at all.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Perhaps, Ischomachus,&rsquo; I commented, &lsquo;you can't make the falsehood into the truth!&rsquo;&rdquo;
        <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But perhaps I am keeping you, Ischomachus,&rsquo; I continued, &lsquo;and you want to get away now?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh no, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; he answered; &lsquo;I should not think of going before the market empties.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;To be sure,&rsquo; I continued; &lsquo;you take the utmost care not to forfeit your right to be called a gentleman! For I daresay there are many things claiming your attention now; but, as you have made an appointment with those strangers, you are determined not to break it.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But I assure you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I am not neglecting the matters you refer to, either; for I keep bailiff's on my farms.&rsquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And when you want a bailiff, Ischomachus, do you look out for a man qualified for such a post, and then try to buy him&mdash;when you want a builder, I feel sure you inquire for a qualified man and try to get him&mdash;or do you train your bailiff's yourself?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course I try to train them myself, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. For the man has to be capable of taking charge in my absence; so why need he know anything but what I know myself? For if I am fit to manage the farm, I presume I can teach another man what I know myself.&rsquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then the first requirement will be that he should be loyal to you and yours, if he is to represent you in your absence. For if a steward is not loyal, what is the good of any knowledge he may possess?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;None, of course; but I may tell you, loyalty to me and to mine is the first lesson I try to teach.&rsquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And how, in heaven's name, do you teach your man to be loyal to you and yours?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;By rewarding him, of course, whenever the gods bestow some good thing on us in abundance.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You mean, then, that those who enjoy a share of your good things are loyal to you and want you to prosper?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I find that is the best instrument for producing loyalty.&rsquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But, now, if he is loyal to you, Ischomachus, will that be enough to make him a competent bailiff? Don't you see that though all men, practically, wish themselves well, yet there are many who won't take the trouble to get for themselves the good things they want to have?&rsquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, when I want to make bailiffs of such men, of course I teach them also to be careful.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Pray how do you do that?
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>I was under the impression that carefulness is a virtue that can't possibly be taught.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;True, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, it isn't possible to teach everyone you come across to be careful.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Very well; what sort of men can be taught? Point these out to me, at all events.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;In the first place, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, you can't make careful men of hard drinkers; for drink makes them forget everything they ought to do.&rsquo;
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then are drunkards the only men who will never become careful, or are there others?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course there are&mdash;sluggards must be included; for you can't do your own business when you are asleep, nor make others do theirs.&rsquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, then, will these make up the total of persons incapable of learning this lesson, or are there yet others besides?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;I should add that in my opinion a man who falls desperately in love is incapable of giving more attention to anything than he gives to the object of his passion.
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/>For it isn't easy to find hope or occupation more delightful than devotion to the darling! aye, and when the thing to be done presses, no harder punishment can easily be thought of than the prevention of intercourse with the beloved! Therefore I shrink from attempting to make a manager of that sort of man too.&rsquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And what about the men who have a passion for lucre? Are they also incapable of being trained to take charge of the work of a farm?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Not at all; of course not. In fact, they very easily qualify for the work. It is merely necessary to point out to them that diligence is profitable.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And assuming that the others are free from the faults that you condemn and are covetous of gain in a moderate degree, how do you teach them to be careful in the affairs you want them to superintend?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;By a very simple plan, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. Whenever I notice that they are careful, I commend them and try to show them honour; but when they appear careless, I try to say and do the sort of things that will sting them.&rsquo;
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Turn now, Ischomachus, from the subject of the men in training for the occupation, and tell me about the system: is it possible for anyone to make others careful if he is careless himself?&rsquo;
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course not: an unmusical person could as soon teach music. For it is hard to learn to do a thing well when the teacher prompts you badly; and when a master prompts a servant to be careless, it is difficult for the man to become a good servant.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>To put it shortly, I don't think I have discovered a bad master with good servants: I have, however, come across a good master with bad servants&mdash;but they suffered for it! If you want to make men fit to take charge, you must supervise their work and examine it, and be ready to reward work well carried through, and not shrink from punishing carelessness as it deserves.
        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>I like the answer that is attributed to the Persian. The king, you know, had happened on a good horse, and wanted to fatten him as speedily as possible. So he asked one who was reputed clever with horses what is the quickest way of fattening a horse. &ldquo;The master's eye,&rdquo; replied the man. I think we may apply the answer generally, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and say that the master's eye in the main does the good and worthy work.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;When you have impressed on a man,&rsquo; I resumed, &lsquo;the necessity of careful attention to the duties you assign to him, will he then be competent to act as bailiff, or must he learn something besides, if he is to be efficient?&rsquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course,&rsquo; answered Ischomachus, &lsquo;he has still to understand what he has to do, and when and how to do it. Otherwise how could a bailiff be of more use than a doctor who takes care to visit a patient early and late, but has no notion of the right way to treat his illness?&rsquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, but suppose he has learned how farm-work is to be done, will he want something more yet, or will your man now be a perfect bailiff?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;I think he must learn to rule the labourers.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And do you train your bailiffs to be competent to rule too?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, I try, anyhow.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And pray tell me how you train them to be rulers of men.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;By a childishly easy method, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. I daresay you'll laugh if I tell you.&rsquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh, but it is certainly not a laughing matter, Ischomachus. For anyone who can make men fit to rule others can also teach them to be masters of others; and if he can make them fit to be masters, he can make them fit to be kings. So anyone who can do that seems to me to deserve high praise rather than laughter.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, other creatures learn obedience in two ways&mdash;by being punished when they try to disobey, and by being rewarded when they are eager to serve you.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Colts, for example, learn to obey the horsebreaker by getting something they like when they are obedient, and suffering inconvenience when they are disobedient, until they carry out the horsebreaker's intentions.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Puppies, again, are much inferior to men in intelligence and power of expression; and yet they learn to run in circles and turn somersaults and do many other tricks in the same way; for when they obey they get something that they want, and when they are careless, they are punished.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>And men can be made more obedient by word of mouth merely, by being shown that it is good for them to obey. But in dealing with slaves the training thought suitable for wild animals is also a very effective way of teaching obedience; for you will do much with them by filling their bellies with the food they hanker after. Those of an ambitious disposition are also spurred on by praise, some natures being hungry for praise as others for meat and drink.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>Now these are precisely the things that I do myself with a view to making men more obedient; but they are not the only lessons I give to those whom I want to appoint my bailiffs. I have other ways of helping them on. For the clothes that I must provide for my work-people and the shoes are not all alike. Some are better than others, some worse, in order that I may reward the better servant with the superior articles, and give the inferior things to the less deserving.
        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>For I think it is very disheartening to good servants, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, when they see that they do all the work, and others who are not willing to work hard and run risks when need be, get the same as they.
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>For my part, then, I don't choose to put the deserving on a level with the worthless, and when I know that my bailiffs have distributed the best things to the most deserving, I commend them; and if I see that flattery or any other futile service wins special favour, I don't overlook it, but reprove the bailiff, and try to show him, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that such favouritism is not even in his own interest.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Now, Ischomachus,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;when you find your man so competent to rule that he can make them obedient, do you think him a perfect bailiff, or does he want anything else, even with the qualifications you have mentioned?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; returned Ischomachus, &lsquo;he must be honest and not touch his master's property. For if the man who handles the crops dares to make away with them, and doesn't leave enough to give a profit on the undertaking, what good can come of farming under his management?&rsquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then do you take it on yourself to teach this kind of justice too?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Certainly: I don't find, however, that all readily pay heed to this lesson.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Nevertheless I guide the servants into the path of justice with the aid of maxims drawn from the laws of <persName><surname>Draco</surname></persName> and <persName><surname>Solon</surname></persName>. For it seems to me that these famous men enacted many of their laws with an eye on this particular kind of justice.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>For it is written: &ldquo;thieves shall be fined for their thefts,&rdquo; and &ldquo;anyone guilty of attempt shall be imprisoned if taken in the act, and put to death.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This is neither a clear nor an exact statement of the law attributed to Solon in <bibl n="Dem. 24.113">Dem. 24.113</bibl>; and some suspect a corruption in the text.</note> The object of these enactments was clearly to make covetousness unprofitable to the offender.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>By applying some of these clauses and other enactments found in the Persian king's code, I try to make my servants upright in the matters that pass through their hands.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>For while those laws only penalise the wrongdoer,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Mem</title>. III. iv. 8.</note> the king's code not only punishes the guilty, but also benefits the upright. Thus, seeing that the honest grow richer than the dishonest, many, despite their love of lucre, are careful to remain free from dishonesty.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>And if I find any attempting to persist in dishonesty, although they are well treated, I regard them as incorrigibly greedy, and have nothing more to do with them.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>On the other hand, if I discover that a man is inclined to be honest not only because he gains by his honesty, but also from a desire to win my approbation, I treat him like a free man by making him rich; and not only so, but I honour him as a gentleman.
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>For I think, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that the difference between ambition and greed consists in this, that for the sake of praise and honour the ambitious are willing to work properly, to take risks and refrain from dishonest gain.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, well, I won't go on to ask whether anything more is wanting to your man, after you have implanted in him a desire for your prosperity and have made him also careful to see that you achieve it, and have obtained for him, besides, the knowledge needful to ensure that every piece of work done shall add to the profits, and, further, have made him capable of ruling, and when, besides all this, he takes as much delight in producing heavy crops for you in due season as you would take if you did the work yourself. For it seems to me that a man like that would make a very valuable bailiff. Nevertheless, Ischomachus, don't leave a gap in that part of the subject to which we have given the most cursory attention.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Which is it?&rsquo; asked Ischomachus.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You said, you know, that the greatest lesson to learn is how things ought to be done; and added that, if a man is ignorant what to do and how to do it, no good can come of his management.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Then he said, &lsquo;<persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, are you insisting now that I should teach the whole art and mystery of agriculture?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes,&rsquo; said I; &lsquo;for maybe it is just this that makes rich men of those who understand it, and condemns the ignorant to a life of penury, for all their toil.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, you shall now hear how kindly a thing is this art. Helpful, pleasant, honourable, dear to gods and men in the highest degree, it is also in the highest degree easy to learn. Noble qualities surely! As you know, we call those creatures noble that are beautiful, great and helpful, and yet gentle towards men.&rsquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Ah, but I think, Ischomachus, that I quite understand your account of these matters&mdash;I mean how to teach a bailiff; for I think I follow your statement that you make him loyal to you, and careful and capable of ruling and honest.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>But you said that one who is to be successful in the management of a farm must learn what to do and how and when to do it. That is the subject that we have treated, it seems to me, in a rather cursory fashion,
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>as if you said that anyone who is to be capable of writing from dictation and reading what is written must know the alphabet. For had I been told that, I should have been told, to be sure, that I must know the alphabet, but I don't think that piece of information would help me to know it.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>So too now; I am easily convinced that a man who is to manage a farm successfully must understand farming, but that knowledge doesn't help me to understand how to farm.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Were I to decide this very moment to be a farmer, I think I should be like that doctor who goes round visiting the sick, but has no knowledge of the right way to treat them. Therefore, that I may not be like him, you must teach me the actual operations of farming.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, farming is not troublesome to learn, like other arts, which the pupil must study till he is worn out before he can earn his keep by his work. Some things you can understand by watching men at work, others by just being told, well enough to teach another if you wish. And I believe that you know a good deal about it yourself, without being aware of the fact.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>The truth is that, whereas other artists conceal more or less the most important points in their own art, the farmer who plants best is most pleased when he is being watched, so is he who sows best. Question him about any piece of work well done: and he will tell you exactly how he did it.
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>So farming, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, more than any other calling, seems to produce a generous disposition in its followers.&rsquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;An excellent preamble,&rsquo; I cried, &lsquo;and not of a sort to damp the hearer's curiosity. Come, describe it to me, all the more because it is so simple to learn. For it is no disgrace to you to teach elementary lessons, but far more a disgrace to me not to understand them, especially if they are really useful.&rsquo;&rdquo;
        <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;First then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I want to show you that what is called the most complicated problem in agriculture by the authors who write most accurately on the theory of the subject, but are not practical farmers, is really a simple matter.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For they tell us that to be a successful farmer one must first know the nature of the soil.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, and they are right,&rsquo; I remarked; &lsquo;for if you don't know what the soil is capable of growing, you can't know, I suppose, what to plant or what to sow.&rsquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well then,&rsquo; said Ischomachus, &lsquo;you can tell by looking at the crops and trees on another man's land what the soil can and what it cannot grow. But when you have found out, it is useless to fight against the gods. For you are not likely to get a better yield from the land by sowing and planting what you want instead of the crops and trees that the land prefers.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>If it happens that the land does not declare its own capabilities because the owners are lazy, you can often gather more correct information from a neighbouring plot than from a neighbouring proprietor.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Yes, and even if the land lies waste, it reveals its nature. For if the wild stuff growing on the land is of fine quality, then by good farming the soil is capable of yielding cultivated crops of fine quality. So the nature of the soil can be ascertained even by the novice who has no experience of farming.&rsquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, I think I am now confident, Ischomachus, that I need not avoid farming from fear of not knowing the nature of the soil.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>The fact is, I am reminded that fishermen, though their business is in the sea, and they neither stop the boat to take a look nor slow down, nevertheless, when they see the crops as they scud past the farms, do not hesitate to express an opinion about the land, which is the good and which is the bad sort, now condemning, now praising it. And, what is more, I notice that in their opinion about the good land they generally agree exactly with experienced farmers.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, let me refresh your memory on the subject of agriculture; but where do you wish me to begin? For I am aware that I shall tell you very much that you know already about the right method of farming.&rsquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;First, Ischomachus, I think I should be glad to learn, for this is the philosopher's way, how I am to cultivate the land if I want to get the heaviest crops of wheat and barley out of it.&rsquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, you know, I take it, that fallow must be prepared for sowing?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, I know.&rsquo;
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Suppose, then, we start ploughing in winter?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, the land will be a bog!'<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;How about starting in summer?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;The land will be hard to plough up.&rsquo;
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;It seems that spring is the season for beginning this work.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, the land is likely to be more friable if it is broken up then.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, and the grass turned up is long enough at that season to serve as manure, but, not having shed seed, it will not grow.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>You know also, I presume, that fallow land can't be satisfactory unless it is clear of weeds and thoroughly baked in the sun?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, certainly; that is essential, I think.&rsquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Do you think that there is any better way of securing that than by turning the land over as often as possible in summer?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Nay, I know for certain that if you want the weeds to lie on the surface and wither in the heat, and the land to be baked by the sun, the surest way is to plough it up at midday in midsummer.&rsquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And if men prepare the fallow by digging, is it not obvious that they too must separate the weeds from the soil?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, and they must throw the weeds on the surface to wither, and turn up the ground so that the lower spit<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Literally, the &ldquo;crude land.&rdquo;</note> may be baked.&rsquo;&rdquo;
        <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You see, then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that we agree about the fallow.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;It does seem so, to be sure.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And now as to the time for sowing, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. Is it not your opinion that the time to sow is that which has been invariably found to be the best by past experience, and is universally approved by present practice?
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For as soon as autumn ends, all men, I suppose, look anxiously to God, to see when he will send rain on the earth and make them free to sow.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, Ischomachus, all men have made up their minds, of course, not to sow in dry ground if they can help it, those who sowed without waiting to be bidden by God having had to wrestle with many losses.&rsquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;So far, then,&rsquo; said Ischomachus, &lsquo;all the world is of one mind.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes,&rsquo; said I, &lsquo;where God is our teacher we all come to think alike. For example, all agree that it is better to wear warm clothes in winter, if they can, and all agree on the desirability of having a fire, if they have wood.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But,&rsquo; said Ischomachus, &lsquo;when we come to the question whether sowing is best done early or very late or at the mid-season, we find much difference of opinion, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.&rsquo; by fixed laws; but in one year it may be advantageous to sow early, in another very late, in another at mid-season.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then do you think, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that it is better to select one of these times for sowing, whether you sow much or little, or to begin at the earliest moment and continue sowing to the latest?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;For my part, Ischomachus, I think it is best to sow for succession throughout the season. For in my opinion it is much better to get enough food at all times than too much at one time and not enough at another.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Here again, then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, pupil and teacher are of one opinion; and, moreover, you, the pupil, are first in stating this opinion.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well now, is casting the seed a complicated problem?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;By all means let us take that also into consideration, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. I presume that you know as well as I that the seed must be cast by the hand?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, I have seen it.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Ah,&rsquo; he said, &lsquo;but some men can cast evenly, and some cannot.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then sowers no less than lyre-players need practice, that the hand may be the servant of the will.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Certainly.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>But suppose that some of the land is rather light and some rather heavy?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;What do you mean by that?&rsquo; I interrupted. &lsquo;By &ldquo;light&rdquo; do you mean &ldquo;weak,&rdquo; and by &ldquo;heavy,&rdquo; &ldquo;strong&rdquo;?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, I do; and I ask you whether you would give the same quantity of seed to both kinds, or to which you would give more?&rsquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, my principle is this: the stronger the wine, the more water I add; the stronger the bearer, the heavier the burden I put on his back; and if it is necessary to feed others, I should require the richest men to feed the greatest number. But tell me whether weak land, like draught animals, becomes stronger when you put more corn into it.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Ah, you're joking, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; he said, laughing, &lsquo;but allow me to tell you that, if after putting in the seed you plough it in again as soon as the blade appears when the land is obtaining plenty of nourishment from the sky, it makes food for the soil, and strengthens it like manure. If, on the other hand, you let the seed go on growing on the land until it is bolled, it's hard for weak land to yield much grain in the end. It's hard, you know, for a weak sow to rear a big litter of fine pigs.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Do you mean, Ischomachus, that the weaker the soil the less seed should be put into it?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, of course, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; and you agree when you say that your invariable custom is to make the burden light that is to be borne by the weak.&rsquo;
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But the hoers, now, Ischomachus, why do you put them on the corn?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;I presume you know that in winter there is a heavy rainfall?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Let us assume, then, that part of the corn is waterlogged and covered with mud, and some of the roots are exposed by flooding. And it often happens, you know, that in consequence of rain weeds spring up among the corn and choke it.&rsquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;All these things are likely to happen.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then don't you think that in such circumstances the corn needs prompt succour?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Certainly.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;What should be done, do you think, to succour the part that is under the mud?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;The soil should be lifted.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And the part that has its roots exposed?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;It should be earthed up.&rsquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;What if weeds are springing up, choking the corn and robbing it of its food, much as useless drones rob bees of the food they have laid in store by their industry?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;The weeds must be cut, of course, just as the drones must be removed from the hive.&rsquo;
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Don't you think, then, that we have good reason for putting on men to hoe?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;No doubt; but I am reflecting, Ischomachus, on the advantage of bringing in an apt simile. For you roused my wrath against the weeds by mentioning the drones, much more than when you spoke of mere weeds.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;However,&rsquo; I continued, &lsquo;after this comes reaping, I fancy. So give me any information you can with regard to that too.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes&mdash;unless I find that you know just what I do about that subject too. You know, then, that the corn must be cut.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;I know that, naturally.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Are you for standing with your back to the wind when you cut corn, or facing it?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Not facing it, no! I think it is irritating both to the eyes and to the hands to reap with cornstalks and spikes blowing in your face.&rsquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And would you cut near the top or close to the ground?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;If the stalk is short, I should cut low down, so that the straw may be more useful; but if it is long, I think it would be right to cut in the middle, in order that the threshers and winnowers may not spend needless trouble on what they don't want. I imagine that the stubble may be burnt with advantage to the land, or thrown on the manure heap to increase its bulk.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Do you notice, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that you stand convicted of knowing just what I know about reaping too?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, it seems so; and I want to know besides whether I understand threshing as well.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then you know this much, that draught animals are used in threshing?&rsquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, of course I do; and that the term draught animals includes oxen, mules and horses.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then do you not think that all the beasts know is how to trample on the corn as they are driven?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Why, what more should draught animals know?&rsquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And who sees that they tread out the right corn, and that the threshing is level, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;The threshers, clearly. By continually turning the untrodden corn and throwing it under the animal's feet they will, of course, keep it level on the floor and take least time over the work.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;So far, then, your knowledge is quite as good as mine.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Will not our next task be to clean the corn by winnowing, Ischomachus?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; and tell me, do you know that if you start on the windward side of the floor, you will find the husks carried right across the floor?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;It must be so.&rsquo;
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Is it not likely, then, that some will fall on the grain?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, it is a long way for the husks to be blown, right over the grain to the empty part of the floor.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But what if you start winnowing against the wind?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Clearly the chaff will at once fall in the right place.&rsquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And as soon as you have cleaned the corn over one half of the floor, will you at once go on throwing up the rest of the chaff while the corn lies about just as it is, or will you first sweep the clean corn towards the edge,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The meaning of <foreign lang="greek">po/los</foreign> here is really unknown, I believe.</note> so as to occupy the smallest space?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course I shall first sweep the clean corn up, so that my chaff may be carried across into the empty space, and I may not have to throw up the same chaff twice.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, it seems you are capable of teaching the quickest way of cleaning corn.&rsquo; things; and so I have been thinking for some time whether my knowledge extends to smelting gold, playing the flute, and painting pictures. For I have never been taught these things any more than I have been taught farming; but I have watched men working at these arts, just as I have watched them farming.&rsquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And didn't I tell you just now that farming is the noblest art for this among other reasons, because it is the easiest to learn?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Enough, Ischomachus; I know. I understood about sowing, it seems, but I wasn't aware that I understood.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;However, is the planting of fruit trees another branch of agriculture?&rsquo; I continued.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;It is, indeed,&rsquo; answered Ischomachus.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then how can I understand all about sowing, and yet know nothing of planting?&rsquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;What, don't you understand it?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;How can I, when I don't know what kind of soil to plant in, nor how deep a hole to dig, nor how broad, nor how much of the plant should be buried, nor how it must be set in the ground to grow best?&rsquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Come then, learn whatever you don't know. I am sure you have seen the sort of trenches they dig for plants.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, often enough.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Did you ever see one more than three feet deep?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;No, of course not&mdash;nor more than two and a half.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Well, did you ever see one more than three feet broad?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course not, nor more than two feet.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Come then, answer this question too.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Did you ever see one less than a foot deep?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Never less than a foot and a half, of course. For the plants would come out of the ground when it is stirred about them if they were put in so much too shallow.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then you know this well enough, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that the trenches are never more than two and a half feet deep, nor less than a foot and a half.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;A thing so obvious as that can't escape one's eyes.&rsquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Again, can you distinguish between dry and wet ground by using your eyes?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh, I should think that the land round Lycabettus and any like it is an example of dry ground, and the low-lying land at Phalerum and any like it of wet.&rsquo;
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;In which then would you dig the hole deep for your plant, in the dry or the wet ground?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;In the dry, of course; because if you dug deep in the wet, you would come on water, and water would stop your planting.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;I think you are quite right. Now suppose the holes are dug; have you ever noticed how<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">There must be something wrong with the text here. The MSS. give <foreign lang="greek">o(phni/ka</foreign>, &ldquo;just when,&rdquo; but that has nothing to do with the matter in hand. Is something lost?</note> the plants for each kind of soil should be put in?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh, yes.&rsquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then assuming that you want them to grow as quickly as possible, do you think that if you put some prepared soil under them the cuttings will strike sooner through soft earth into the hard stuff, or through unbroken ground?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Clearly, they will form roots more quickly in prepared soil than in unbroken ground.&rsquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then soil must be placed below the plant?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;No doubt it must.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And if you set the whole cutting upright, pointing to the sky, do you think it would take root better, or would you lay part of it slanting under the soil that has been put below, so that it lies like a gamma upside down?&rsquo;
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course I would; for then there would be more buds underground; and I notice that plants shoot from the buds above ground, so I suppose that the buds under the ground do just the same; and with many shoots forming underground, the plant will make strong and rapid growth, I suppose.&rsquo;
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Then it turns out that on these points too your opinion agrees with mine. But would you merely heap up the earth, or make it firm round the plant?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;I should make it firm, of course; for if it were not firm, I feel sure that the rain would make mud of the loose earth, and the sun would dry it up from top to bottom; so the plants would run the risk of damping off through too much water, or withering from too much heat at the roots.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;About vine<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The mention of the vine comes in so abruptly that one again suspects the loss of something in the text.</note> planting then, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, your views are again exactly the same as mine.&rsquo; too?&rsquo; I asked.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, and to all other fruit trees, I think; for in planting other trees why discard anything that gives good results with the vine?&rsquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But the olive&mdash;how shall we plant that, Ischomachus?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You know quite well, and are only trying to draw me out again. For I am sure you see that a deeper hole is dug for the olive (it is constantly being done on the roadside); you see also that all the growing shoots have stumps adhering to them; and you see that all the heads of the plants are coated with clay, and the part of the plant that is above ground is wrapped up.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Yes, I see all this.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You do! Then what is there in it that you don't understand? Is it that you don't know how to put the crocks on the top of the clay, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course there is nothing in what you have said that I don't know, Ischomachus. But I am again set thinking what can have made me answer &lsquo;No&rsquo; to the question you put to me a while ago, when you asked me briefly, Did I understand planting? For I thought I should have nothing to say about the right method of planting. But now that you have undertaken to question me in particular, my answers, you tell me, agree exactly with the views of a farmer so famous for his skill as yourself!
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Can it be that questioning is a kind of teaching, Ischomachus? The fact is, I have just discovered the plan of your series of questions! You lead me by paths of knowledge familiar to me, point out things like what I know, and bring me to think that I really know things that I thought I had no knowledge of.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Now suppose I questioned you about money,&rsquo; said Ischomachus, &lsquo;whether it is good or bad, could I persuade you that you know how to distinguish good from false by test? And by putting questions about flute-players could I convince you that you understand flute-playing; and by means of questions about painters and other artists&mdash;'<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You might, since you have convinced me that I understand agriculture, though I know that I have never been taught this art.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;No, it isn't so, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>I told you a while ago that agriculture is such a humane, gentle art that you have but to see her and listen to her, and she at once makes you understand her.
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>She herself gives you many lessons in the best way of treating her. For instance, the vine climbs the nearest tree, and so teaches you that she wants support. And when her clusters are yet tender, she spreads her leaves about them, and teaches you to shade the exposed parts from the sun's rays during that period.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>But when it is now time for her grapes to be sweetened by the sun, she sheds her leaves, teaching you to strip her and ripen her fruit. And thanks to her teeming fertility, she shows some mellow clusters while she carries others yet sour, so saying to you: Pluck my grapes as men pluck figs,&mdash;choose the luscious ones as they come.&rsquo;&rdquo;
        <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And now I asked, &lsquo;How is it then, Ischomachus, if the operations of husbandry are so easy to learn and all alike know what must needs be done, that all have not the same fortune? How is it that some farmers live in abundance and have more than they want, while others cannot get the bare necessaries of life, and even run into debt?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Oh, I will tell you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>It is not knowledge nor want of knowledge on the part of farmers that causes one to thrive while another is needy.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>You won't hear a story like this running about: The estate has gone to ruin because the sower sowed unevenly, or because he didn't plant the rows straight, or because someone, not knowing the right soil for vines, planted them in barren ground, or because someone didn't know that it is well to prepare the fallow for sowing, or because someone didn't know that it is well to manure the land.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>No, you are much more likely to hear it said: The man gets no corn from his field because he takes no trouble to see that it is sown or manured. Or, The man has got no wine, for he takes no trouble to plant vines or to make his old stock bear. Or, The man has neither olives nor figs, because he doesn't take the trouble; he does nothing to get them.
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>It is not the farmers reputed to have made some clever discovery in agriculture who differ in fortune from others: it is things of this sort that make all the difference, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>This is true of generals also: there are some branches of strategy in which one is better or worse than another, not because he differs in intelligence, but in point of carefulness, undoubtedly. For the things that all generals know, and most privates, are done by some commanders and left undone by others.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>For example, they all know that when marching through an enemy's country, the right way is to march in the formation in which they will fight best, if need be. Well, knowing this, some observe the rule, others break it.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>All know that it is right to post sentries by day and night before the camp; but this too is a duty that some attend to, while others neglect it.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Again, where will you find the man who does not know that, in marching through a defile, it is better to occupy the points of vantage first? Yet this measure of precaution too is duly taken by some and neglected by others.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>So, too, everyone will say that in agriculture there is nothing so good as manure, and their eyes tell them that nature produces it. All know exactly how it is produced, and it is easy to get any amount of it; and yet, while some take care to have it collected, others care nothing about it.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Yet the rain is sent from heaven, and all the hollows become pools of water, and the earth yields herbage of every kind which must be cleared off the ground by the sower before sowing; and the rubbish he removes has but to be thrown into water, and time of itself will make what the soil likes. For every kind of vegetation, every kind of soil in stagnant water turns into manure.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;And again, all the ways of treating the soil when it is too wet for sowing or too salt for planting are familiar to all men&mdash;how the land is drained by ditches, how the salt is corrected by being mixed with saltless substances, liquid or dry. Yet these matters, again, do not always receive attention.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Suppose a man to be wholly ignorant as to what the land can produce, and to be unable to see crop or tree on it, or to hear from anyone the truth about it, yet is it not far easier for any man to prove a parcel of land than to test a horse or to test a human being? For the land never plays tricks, but reveals frankly and truthfully what she can and what she cannot do.
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/>I think that just because she conceals nothing from our knowledge and understanding, the land is the surest tester of good and bad men. For the slothful cannot plead ignorance, as in other arts: land, as all men know, responds to good treatment.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Husbandry is the clear accuser of the recreant soul. For no one persuades himself that man could live without bread; therefore if a man will not dig and knows no other profit-earning trade, he is clearly minded to live by stealing or robbery or begging&mdash;or he is an utter fool.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Farming,&rsquo; he added, &lsquo;may result in profit or in loss; it makes a great difference to the result, even when many labourers are employed, whether the farmer takes care that the men are working during the working hours or is careless about it. For one man in ten by working all the time may easily make a difference, and another by knocking off before the time;
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>and, of course, if the men are allowed to be slack all the day long, the decrease in the work done may easily amount to one half of the whole.
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Just as two travellers on the road, both young and in good health, will differ so much in pace that one will cover two hundred furlongs to the other's hundred, because the one does what he set out to do, by going ahead, while the other is all for ease, now resting by a fountain or in the shade, now gazing at the view, now wooing the soft breeze;
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>so in farm work there is a vast difference in effectiveness between the men who do the job they are put on to do and those who, instead of doing it, invent excuses for not working and are allowed to be slack.
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>In fact, between good work and dishonest slothfulness there is as wide a difference as between actual work and actual idleness. Suppose the vines are being hoed to clear the ground of weeds: if the hoeing is so badly done that the weeds grow ranker and more abundant, how can you call that anything but idleness?&rsquo;
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;These, then, are the evils that crush estates far more than sheer lack of knowledge. For the outgoing expenses of the estate are not a penny less; but the work done is insufficient to show a profit on the expenditure; after that there's no need to wonder if the expected surplus is converted into a loss.
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/>On the other hand, to a careful man, who works strenuously at agriculture, no business gives quicker returns than farming. My father taught me that and proved it by his own practice. For he never allowed me to buy a piece of land that was well farmed; but pressed me to buy any that was uncultivated and unplanted owing to the owner's neglect or incapacity.
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Well farmed land,&rdquo; he would say, &ldquo;costs a large sum and can't be improved;&rdquo; and he held that where there is no room for improvement there is not much pleasure to be got from the land: landed estate and livestock must be continually coming on to give the fullest measure of satisfaction. Now nothing improves more than a farm that is being transformed from a wilderness into fruitful fields.
        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>I assure you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that we have often added a hundredfold to the value of a farm. There is so much money in this idea, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, and it is so easy to learn, that no sooner have you heard of it from me than you know as much as I do, and can go home and teach it to someone else, if you like.
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/>Moreover, my father did not get his knowledge of it at secondhand, nor did he discover it by much thought; but he would say that, thanks to his love of husbandry and hard work, he had coveted a farm of this sort in order that he might have something to do, and combine profit with pleasure.
        <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>For I assure you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, no Athenian, I believe, had such a strong natural love of agriculture as my father.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Now on hearing this I asked, &lsquo;Did your father keep all the farms that he cultivated, Ischomachus, or did he sell when he could get a good price?&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;He sold, of course,&rsquo; answered Ischomachus, &lsquo;but, you see, owing to his industrious habits, he would promptly buy another that was out of cultivation.&rsquo;
<milestone n="27" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You mean, Ischomachus, that your father really loved agriculture as intensely as merchants love corn. So deep is their love of corn that on receiving reports that it is abundant anywhere, merchants will voyage in quest of it: they will cross the <placeName key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName>, the Euxine, the Sicilian sea;
<milestone n="28" unit="section"/>and when they have got as much as possible, they carry it over the sea, and they actually stow it in the very ship in which they sail themselves. And when they want money, they don't throw the corn away anywhere at haphazard, but they carry it to the place where they hear that corn is most valued and the people prize it most highly, and deliver it to them there. Yes, your father's love of agriculture seems to be something like that.&rsquo;
<milestone n="29" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;You're joking, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rsquo; rejoined Ischomachus; &lsquo;but I hold that a man has a no less genuine love of building who sells his houses as soon as they are finished and proceeds to build others.&rsquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course; and I declare, Ischomachus, on my oath that I believe you, that all men naturally love whatever they think will bring them profit.&rsquo;&rdquo;
<milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;But I am pondering over the skill with which you have presented the whole argument in support of your proposition, Ischomachus. For you stated that husbandry is the easiest of all arts to learn, and after hearing all that you have said, I am quite convinced that this is so.&rsquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;Of course it is,&rsquo; cried Ischomachus; &lsquo;but I grant you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, that in respect of aptitude for command, which is common to all forms of business alike&mdash;agriculture, politics, estate-management, warfare&mdash;in that respect the intelligence shown by different classes of men varies greatly.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For example, on a man-of-war, when the ship is on the high seas and the rowers must toil all day to reach port, some boatswains can say and do the right thing to sharpen the men's spirits and make them work with a will, while others are so unintelligent that it takes them more than twice the time to finish the same voyage. Here they land bathed in sweat, with mutual congratulations, boatswain and seamen. There they arrive with a dry skin; they hate their master and he hates them.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Generals, too, differ from one another in this respect. For some make their men unwilling to work and to take risks, disinclined and unwilling to obey, except under compulsion, and actually proud of defying their commander: aye, and they cause them to have no sense of dishonour when something disgraceful occurs.
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Contrast the genius, the brave and scientific leader: let him take over the command of these same troops, or of others if you like. What effect has he on them? They are ashamed to do a disgraceful act, think it better to obey, and take a pride in obedience, working cheerfully, every man and all together, when it is necessary to work.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Just as a love of work may spring up in the mind of a private soldier here and there, so a whole army under the influence of a good leader is inspired with love of work and ambition to distinguish itself under the commander's eye.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Let this be the feeling of the rank and file for their commander; and I tell you, he is the strong leader, he, and not the sturdiest soldier, not the best with bow and javelin, not the man who rides the best horse and is foremost in facing danger, not the ideal of knight or targeteer, but he who can make his soldiers feel that they are bound to follow him through fire and in any adventure.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Him you may justly call high-minded who has many followers of like mind; and with reason may he be said to march &ldquo;with a strong arm&rdquo; whose will many an arm is ready to serve; and truly great is he who can do great deeds by his will rather than his strength.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;&lsquo;So too in private industries, the man in authority &mdash;bailiff or manager&mdash;who can make the workers keen, industrious and persevering&mdash;he is the man who gives a lift to the business and swells the surplus.
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>But, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, if the appearance of the master in the field, of the man who has the fullest power to punish the bad and reward the strenuous workmen, makes no striking impression on the men at work, I for one cannot envy him. But if at sight of him they bestir themselves, and a spirit of determination and rivalry and eagerness to excel falls on every workman, then I should say: this man has a touch of the kingly nature in him.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>And this, in my judgment, is the greatest thing in every operation that makes any demand on the labour of men, and therefore in agriculture. Mind you, I do not go so far as to say that this can be learnt at sight or at a single hearing. On the contrary, to acquire these powers a man needs education; he must be possessed of great natural gifts; above all, he must be a genius.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>For I reckon this gift is not altogether human, but divine&mdash;this power to win willing obedience: it is manifestly a gift of the gods to the true votaries of prudence. Despotic rule over unwilling subjects they give, I fancy, to those whom they judge worthy to live the life of Tantalus, of whom it is said that in hell he spends eternity, dreading a second death.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p></body></text>

<text n="Sym.">

    <body><head>Symposium</head><p>
<milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To my mind it is worth while to relate not only the serious acts of great and good men but also what they do in their lighter moods. I should like to narrate an experience of mine that gives me this conviction.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It was on the occasion of the horse-races at the greater Panathenaic games; Callias, Hipponicus' son, was enamoured, as it happened, of the boy Autolycus, and in honour of his victory in the pancratium<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The pancratium was a severe athletic contest involving a combination of boxing and wrestling, and requiring on the part of the contestants unusual physique and condition. There were separate events open to men and to boys.</note> had brought him to see the spectacle. When the racing was over, Callias proceeded on his way to his house in the Peiraeus with Autolycus and the boy's father; Niceratus also was in his company.
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>But on catching sight of a group comprising <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, Critobulus, Hermogenes, Antisthenes, and Charmides, Callias bade one of his servants escort Autolycus and the others, and himself going over to <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> and his companions, said,
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>&ldquo;This is an opportune meeting, for I am about to give a dinner in honour of Autolycus and his father; and I think that my entertainment would present a great deal more brilliance if my dining-room were graced with the presence of men like you, whose hearts have undergone philosophy's purification, than it would with generals and cavalry commanders and office-seekers.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You are always quizzing us,&rdquo; replied <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;for you have yourself paid a good deal of money for wisdom to Protagoras, Gorgias, Prodicus, and many others, while you see that we are what you might call amateurs in philosophy; and so you feel supercilious toward us.&rdquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; said Callias, &ldquo;so far, I admit, I have been keeping you ignorant of my ability at profound and lengthy discourse; but now, if you will favour me with your company, I will prove to you that I am a person of some consequence.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now at first <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> and his companions thanked him for the invitation, as might be expected, but would not promise to attend the banquet; when it became clear, however, that he was taking their refusal very much to heart, they went with him. And so his guests arrived, some having first taken their exercise and their rub-down, others with the addition of a bath.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Autolycus took a seat by his father's side; the others, of course, reclined.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Attic reliefs depicting banquet scenes show that it was customary for the men to recline at table, but for the women and children, if present, to sit.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A person who took note of the course of events would have come at once to the conclusion that beauty is in its essence something regal, especially when, as in the present case of Autolycus, its possessor joins with it modesty and sobriety.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>For in the first place, just as the sudden glow of a light at night draws all eyes to itself, so now the beauty of Autolycus compelled every one to look at him. And again, there was not one of the onlookers who did not feel his soul strangely stirred by the boy; some of them grew quieter than before, others even assumed some kind of a pose.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>Now it is true that all who are under the influence of any of the gods seem well worth gazing at; but whereas those who are possessed of the other gods have a tendency to be sterner of countenance, more terrifying of voice, and more vehement, those who are inspired by chaste Love have a more tender look, subdue their voices to more gentle tones, and assume a supremely noble bearing. Such was the demeanour of Callias at this time under the influence of Love; and therefore he was an object well worth the gaze of those initiated into the worship of this god.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The company, then, were feasting in silence, as though some one in authority had commanded them to do so, when Philip the buffoon knocked at the door and told the porter to announce who he was and that he desired to be admitted; he added that with regard to food he had come all prepared, in all varieties&mdash;to dine on some other person's,&mdash;and that his servant was in great distress with the load he carried of&mdash;nothing, and with having an empty stomach. Hearing this, Callias said,
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Well, gentlemen, we cannot decently begrudge him at the least the shelter of our roof; so let him come in.&rdquo; With the words he cast a glance at Autolycus, obviously trying to make out what he had thought of the pleasantry.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>But Philip, standing at the threshold of the men's hall where the banquet was served, announced:<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You all know that I am a jester; and so I have come here with a will, thinking it more of a joke to come to your dinner uninvited than to come by invitation.&rdquo; &ldquo;Well, then,&rdquo; said Callias, &ldquo;take a place; for the guests, though well fed, as you observe, on seriousness, are perhaps rather ill supplied with laughter.&rdquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>No sooner were they engaged in their dinner than Philip attempted a witticism, with a view to rendering the service that secured him all his dinner engagements; but on finding that he did not excite any laughter, he showed himself, for the time, considerably vexed. A little later, however, he must try another jest; but when they would not laugh at him this time either, he stopped while the dinner was in full swing, covered his head with his cloak, and lay down on his couch.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>&ldquo;What does this mean, Philip?&rdquo; Callias inquired. &ldquo;Are you seized with a pain?&rdquo; Philip replied with a groan, &ldquo;Yes, Callias, by Heaven, with a severe one; for since laughter has perished from the world, my business is ruined. For in times past, the reason why I got invitations to dinner was that I might stir up laughter among the guests and make them merry; but now, what will induce any one to invite me? For I could no more turn serious than I could become immortal; and certainly no one will invite me in the hope of a return invitation, as every one knows that there is not a vestige of tradition of bringing dinner into my house.&rdquo; As he said this, he wiped his nose, and to judge by the sound, he was evidently weeping.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>All tried to comfort him with the promise that they would laugh next time, and urged him to eat; and Critobulus actually burst out into a guffaw at his lugubrious moaning. The moment Philip heard the laughter he uncovered his head, and exhorting his spirit to be of good courage, in view of approaching engagements,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Philip puns on the ambiguous <foreign lang="greek">sumbolai/,</foreign> which means either hostile encounters or a banquet to which the viands are contributed by the guests. His exhortation to his spirit is quite Odyssean.</note> he fell to eating again.
<milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When the tables had been removed and the guests had poured a libation and sung a hymn, there entered a man from <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, to give them an evening's merriment. He had with him a fine flute-girl, a dancing-girl&mdash;one of those skilled in acrobatic tricks,&mdash;and a very handsome boy, who was expert at playing the cither and at dancing; the Syracusan made money by exhibiting their performances as a spectacle.
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>They now played for the assemblage, the flute-girl on the flute, the boy on the cither; and it was agreed that both furnished capital amusement. Thereupon <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> remarked: &ldquo;On my word, Callias, you are giving us a perfect dinner; for not only have you set before us a feast that is above criticism, but you are also offering us very delightful sights and sounds.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Suppose we go further,&rdquo; said Callias, &ldquo;and have some one bring us some perfume, so that we may dine in the midst of pleasant odours, also.&rdquo; &ldquo;No, indeed!&rdquo; replied <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;For just as one kind of dress looks well on a woman and another kind on a man, so the odours appropriate to men and to women are diverse. No man, surely, ever uses perfume for a man's sake. And as for the women, particularly if they chance to be young brides, like the wives of Niceratus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the bride of Niceratus, see Introduction, p. 377.</note> here and Critobulus, how can they want any additional perfume? For that is what they are redolent of, themselves.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Perfumes were used at marriage by both bride and groom.</note> The odour of the olive oil, on the other hand, that is used in the gymnasium is more delightful when you have it on your flesh than perfume is to women, and when you lack it, the want of it is more keenly felt.
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Indeed, so far as perfume is concerned, when once a man has anointed himself with it, the scent forthwith is all one whether he be slave or free; but the odours that result from the exertions of freemen demand primarily noble pursuits engaged in for many years if they are to be sweet and suggestive of freedom.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;That may do for young fellows,&rdquo; observed Lycon; &ldquo;but what of us who no longer exercise in the gymnasia? What should be our distinguishing scent?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Nobility of soul, surely!&rdquo; replied <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And where may a person get this ointment?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly not from the perfumers,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But where, then?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Theognis has said:<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Theognis 35 f. (with <foreign lang="greek">maqh/seai</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">dida/ceai</foreign>).</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&lsquo;Good men teach good; society with bad<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Will but corrupt the good mind that you had.&rsquo;&rdquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do you hear that, my son?&rdquo; asked Lycon.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, indeed he does,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;and he puts it into practice, too. At any rate, when he desired to become a prize-winner in the pancratium, &lsqb;he availed himself of your help to discover the champions in that sport and associated with them; and so, if he desires to learn the ways of virtue,&rsqb;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The words in brackets are meant to represent approximately the sense of words that have been lost in the manuscripts.</note> he will again with your help seek out the man who seems to him most proficient in this way of life and will associate with him.&rdquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thereupon there was a chorus of voices. &ldquo;Where will he find an instructor in this subject?&rdquo; said one. Another maintained that it could not be taught at all. A third asserted that this could be learned if anything could.
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>&ldquo;Since this is a debatable matter,&rdquo; suggested <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;let us reserve it for another time; for the present let us finish what we have on hand. For I see that the dancing girl here is standing ready, and that some one is bringing her some hoops.&rdquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At that, the other girl began to accompany the dancer on the flute, and a boy at her elbow handed her up the hoops until he had given her twelve. She took these and as she danced kept throwing them whirling into the air, observing the proper height to throw them so as to catch them in a regular rhythm.
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> looked on he remarked: &ldquo;This girl's feat, gentlemen, is only one of many proofs that woman's nature is really not a whit inferior to man's, except in its lack of judgment and physical strength. So if any one of you has a wife, let him confidently set about teaching her whatever he would like to have her know.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;If that is your view, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; asked Antisthenes, &ldquo;how does it come that you don't practise what you preach by yourself educating Xanthippe, but live with a wife who is the hardest to get along with of all the women there are&mdash;yes, or all that ever were, I suspect, or ever will be?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because,&rdquo; he replied, &ldquo;I observe that men who wish to become expert horsemen do not get the most docile horses but rather those that are high-mettled, believing that if they can manage this kind, they will easily handle any other. My course is similar. Mankind at large is what I wish to deal and associate with; and so I have got her, well assured that if I can endure her, I shall have no difficulty in my relations with all the rest of human kind.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>These words, in the judgment of the guests, did not go wide of the mark.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But now there was brought in a hoop set all around with upright swords; over these the dancer turned somersaults into the hoop and out again, to the dismay of the onlookers, who thought that she might suffer some mishap. She, however, went through this performance fearlessly and safely.
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, drawing Antisthenes' attention, said: &ldquo;Witnesses of this feat, surely, will never again deny, I feel sure, that courage, like other things, admits of being taught, when this girl, in spite of her sex, leaps so boldly in among the swords!&rdquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, then,&rdquo; asked Antisthenes, &ldquo;had this Syracusan not better exhibit his dancer to the city and announce that if the Athenians will pay him for it he will give all the men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> the courage to face the spear?&rdquo;
    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well said!&rdquo; interjected Philip. &ldquo;I certainly should like to see Peisander the politician<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Peisander, a demagogue of some power in the unsettled times of the Peloponnesian War, had a number of weak points, especially his military record, which were exposed by the comic poets Eupolis, Hermippus, Plato, and Aristophanes. Cf. <bibl n="Aristoph. Birds 1553">Aristoph. Birds 1553 ff.</bibl></note> learning to turn somersaults among the knives; for, as it is now, his inability to look spears in the face makes him shrink even from joining the army.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this point the boy performed a dance, eliciting from <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> the remark, &ldquo;Did you notice that, handsome as the boy is, he appears even handsomer in the poses of the dance than when he is at rest?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;It looks to me,&rdquo; said Charmides, &ldquo;as if you were puffing the dancing-master.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Assuredly,&rdquo; replied <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;and I remarked something else, too,&mdash;that no part of his body was idle during the dance, but neck, legs, and hands were all active together. And that is the way a person must dance who intends to increase the suppleness of his body. And for myself,&rdquo; he continued, addressing the Syracusan, &ldquo;I should be delighted to learn the figures from you.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What use will you make of them?&rdquo; the other asked.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I will dance, by Zeus.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This raised a general laugh; but <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, with a perfectly grave expression on his face, said: &ldquo;You are laughing at me, are you? Is it because I want to exercise to better my health? Or because I want to take more pleasure in my food and my sleep? Or is it because I am eager for such exercises as these, not like the long-distance runners, who develop their legs at the expense of their shoulders, nor like the prize-fighters, who develop their shoulders but become thin-legged, but rather with a view to giving my body a symmetrical development by exercising it in every part?
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Or are you laughing because I shall not need to hunt up a partner to exercise with, or to strip, old as I am, in a crowd, but shall find a moderate-sized room<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Literally, <title>a room of seven couches.</title> Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Ec. 8.13">Xen. Ec. 8.13</bibl>.</note> large enough for me (just as but now this room was large enough for the lad here to get up a sweat in), and because in winter I shall exercise under cover, and when it is very hot, in the shade?
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>Or is this what provokes your laughter, that I have an unduly large paunch and wish to reduce it? Don't you know that just the other day Charmides here caught me dancing early in the morning?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Indeed I did,&rdquo; said Charmides; &ldquo;and at first I was dumbfounded and feared that you were going stark mad; but when I heard you say much the same things as you did just now, I myself went home, and although I did not dance, for I had never learned how, I practised shadow-boxing, for I knew how to do that.&rdquo;
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Undoubtedly,&rdquo; said Philip; &ldquo;at any rate, your legs appear so nearly equal in weight to your shoulders that I imagine if you were to go to the market commissioners and put your lower parts in the scale against your upper parts, as if they were loaves of bread,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Since the Athenians were dependent largely on imported grain, they developed an elaborate system of regulations, administered by several sets of officials, to protect the consumers from speculation and extortion. One set of officials controlled the weight and the price of bread.</note> they would let you off without a fine.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;When you are ready to begin your lessons, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; said Callias, &ldquo;pray invite me, so that I may be opposite you in the figures and may learn with you.&rdquo;
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Come,&rdquo; said Philip, &ldquo;let me have some flute music, so that I may dance too.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So he got up and mimicked in detail the dancing of both the boy and the girl.
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/>To begin with, since the company had applauded the way the boy's natural beauty was increased by the grace of the dancing postures, Philip made a burlesque out of the performance by rendering every part of his body that was in motion more grotesque than it naturally was; and whereas the girl had bent backward until she resembled a hoop, he tried to do the same by bending forward. Finally, since they had given the boy applause for putting every part of his body into play in the dance, he told the flute girl to hit up the time faster, and danced away, flinging out legs, hands, and head all at the same time;
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/>and when he was quite exhausted, he exclaimed as he laid himself down: &ldquo;Here is proof, gentlemen, that my style of dancing, also, gives excellent exercise; it has certainly given me a thirst; so let the servant fill me up the big goblet.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly,&rdquo; replied Callias; &ldquo;and the same for us, for we are thirsty with laughing at you.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> again interposed. &ldquo;Well, gentlemen,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;so far as drinking is concerned, you have my hearty approval; for wine does of a truth &lsquo;moisten the soul&rsquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Apparently a reminiscence of Aristophanes' <title>Knights,</title> 96.</note> and lull our griefs to sleep just as the mandragora does with men, at the same time awakening kindly feelings as oil quickens a flame.
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/>However, I suspect that men's bodies fare the same as those of plants that grow in the ground. When God gives the plants water in floods to drink, they cannot stand up straight or let the breezes blow through them; but when they drink only as much as they enjoy, they grow up very straight and tall and come to full and abundant fruitage.
<milestone n="26" unit="section"/>So it is with us. If we pour ourselves immense draughts, it will be no long time before both our bodies and our minds reel, and we shall not be able even to draw breath, much less to speak sensibly; but if the servants frequently &lsquo;besprinkle&rsquo; us&mdash;if I too may use a Gorgian<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Gorgias was a famous contemporary orator and teacher of rhetoric, whose speeches, though dazzling to inexperienced audiences, were over-formal and ornate. Some of his metaphors drew the criticism of Aristotle as being far-fetched. Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Rh. 3.3.4">Aristot. Rhet. 3.3.4</bibl> (1406b 4 ff.).</note> expression&mdash;with small cups, we shall thus not be driven on by the wine to a state of intoxication, but instead shall be brought by its gentle persuasion to a more sportive mood.&rdquo;
<milestone n="27" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This resolution received a unanimous vote, with an amendment added by Philip to the effect that the wine-pourers should emulate skilful charioteers by driving the cups around with ever increasing speed. This the wine-pourers proceeded to do.
        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>After this the boy, attuning his lyre to the flute, played and sang, and won the applause of all; and brought from Charmides the remark, &ldquo;It seems to me, gentlemen, that, as <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> said of the wine, so this blending of the young people's beauty and of the notes of the music lulls one's griefs to sleep and awakens the goddess of Love.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> resumed the conversation. &ldquo;These people, gentlemen,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;show their competence to give us pleasure; and yet we, I am sure, think ourselves considerably superior to them. Will it not be to our shame, therefore, if we do not make even an attempt, while here together, to be of some service or to give some pleasure one to another?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At that many spoke up: &ldquo;You lead the way, then, and tell us what to begin talking about to realize most fully what you have in mind.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;For my part,&rdquo; he answered, &ldquo;I should like to have Callias redeem his promise; for he said, you remember, that if we would take dinner with him, he would give us an exhibition of his profundity.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; rejoined Callias; &ldquo;and I will do so, if the rest of you will also lay before us any serviceable knowledge that you severally possess.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well,&rdquo; answered <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;no one objects to telling what he considers the most valuable knowledge in his possession.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Very well, then,&rdquo; said Callias, &ldquo;I will now tell you what I take greatest pride in. It is that I believe I have the power to make men better.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How?&rdquo; asked Antisthenes. &ldquo;By teaching them some manual trade, or by teaching nobility of character?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;The latter, if righteousness<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The word <foreign lang="greek">dikaiosu/nh,</foreign> translated here by &ldquo;righteousness,&rdquo; is sometimes well represented by <title>justice</title> or <title>honesty.</title> It is the virtue discussed by Plato in the <title>Republic</title> and by Aristotle in the fifth book of his <title>Ethics.</title></note> is the same thing as nobility.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly it is,&rdquo; replied Antisthenes, &ldquo;and the least debatable kind, too; for though courage and wisdom appear at times to work injury both to one's friends and to the state, righteousness and unrighteousness never overlap at a single point.&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, then, when every one of you has named the benefit he can confer, I will not begrudge describing the art that gives me the success that I speak of. And so, Niceratus,&rdquo; he suggested, &ldquo;it is your turn; tell us what kind of knowledge you take pride in.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;My father was anxious to see me develop into a good man,&rdquo; said Niceratus, &ldquo;and as a means to this end he compelled me to memorize all of Homer; and so even now I can repeat the whole <title>Iliad</title> and the <title>Odyssey</title> by heart.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But have you failed to observe,&rdquo; questioned Antisthenes, &ldquo;that the rhapsodes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">These professional reciters of epic poetry are represented as being criticized by <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, in much the same way as here, in <persName><surname>Xenophon</surname></persName>'s <title>Memorabilia,</title> IV. ii. 10 and in <persName><surname>Plato</surname></persName>'s <title>Ion.</title></note> too, all know these poems?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How could I,&rdquo; he replied, &ldquo;when I listen to their recitations nearly every day?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, do you know any tribe of men,&rdquo; went on the other, &ldquo;more stupid than the rhapsodes?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, indeed,&rdquo; answered Niceratus; &ldquo;not I, I am sure.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;and the reason is clear: they do not know the inner meaning of the poems. But you have paid a good deal of money to Stesimbrotus, Anaximander, and many other Homeric critics, so that nothing of their valuable teaching can have escaped your knowledge.
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>But what about you, Critobulus?&rdquo; he continued. &ldquo;What do you take greates pride in?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In beauty,&rdquo; he replied.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What?&rdquo; exclaimed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;Are you too going to be able to maintain that you can make us better, and by means of your beauty?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Why, otherwise, it is clear enough that I shall cut but an indifferent figure.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Critobulus seems to imply that beauty is his only resource.</note>
        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And you, Antisthenes,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;what do you take pride in?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In wealth,&rdquo; he replied.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hermogenes asked him whether he had a large amount of money; he swore that he did not have even a penny.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You own a great deal of land, then?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, perhaps it might prove big enough,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;for Autolycus here to sand himself in.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The reference is to the handful or so of dry sand that an athlete put on after oiling his skin.</note>
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;It looks as if we should have to hear from you, too. And how about you, Charmides?&rdquo; he continued. &ldquo;What do you take pride in?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What pride,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;on the contrary, is in my poverty.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;A charming thing, upon my word!&rdquo; exclaimed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;It seldom causes envy or is a bone of contention; and it is kept safe without the necessity of a guard, and grows sturdier by neglect!&rdquo;
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But what of you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo; said Callias. &ldquo;What are you proud of?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> drew up his face into a very solemn expression, and answered, &ldquo;The trade of procurer.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>After the rest had had a laugh at him, &ldquo;Very well,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;you may laugh, but I know that I could make a lot of money if I cared to follow the trade.&rdquo;
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;As for you,&rdquo; said Lycon, addressing Philip, &ldquo;it is obvious that your pride is in your jesting.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And my pride is better founded, I think,&rdquo; replied Philip, &ldquo;than that of Callippides, the actor,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Callippides was regarded at this time and afterward as perhaps the most illustrious tragic actor of his time.</note> who is consumed with vanity because he can fill the seats with audiences that weep.&rdquo;
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Will you also not tell us, Lycon,&rdquo; said Antisthenes, &ldquo;what it is that you take pride in?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Don't you all know,&rdquo; he answered, &ldquo;that it is in my son here?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And as for him,&rdquo; said one, &ldquo;it is plain that he is proud at having taken a prize.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this Autolycus blushed and said, &ldquo;No, indeed, not that.&rdquo;
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>All looked at him, delighted to hear him speak, and one asked, &ldquo;What is it, then, Autolycus, that you are proud of?&rdquo; and he answered, &ldquo;My father,&rdquo; and with the words nestled close against him.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When Callias saw this, &ldquo;Do you realize, Lycon,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;that you are the richest man in the world?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, indeed,&rdquo; the other replied, &ldquo;I certainly do not know that.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Why, are you blind to the fact that you would not part with your son for the wealth of the Great King?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I am caught,&rdquo; was the answer, &ldquo;red-handed; it does look as if I were the richest man in the world.&rdquo;
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What about you, Hermogenes?&rdquo; said Niceratus. &ldquo;What do you delight in most?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In the goodness and the power of my friends,&rdquo; he answered, &ldquo;and in the fact that with all their excellence they have regard for me.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thereupon all eyes were turned toward him, and many speaking at once asked him whether he would not discover these friends to them; and he answered that he would not be at all loath to do so.
        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this point <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> said: &ldquo;I suspect that it remains now for each one of us to prove that what he engaged himself to champion is of real worth.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;You may hear me first,&rdquo; said Callias. &ldquo;While I listen to your philosophical discussions of what righteousness is, I am all the time actually rendering men more righteous.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How so, my good friend?&rdquo; asked <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Why, by giving them money.&rdquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Antisthenes got up and in a very argumentative fashion interrogated him. &ldquo;Where do you think men harbour their righteousness, Callias, in their souls or in their purses?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In their souls,&rdquo; he replied.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;So you make their souls more righteous by putting money into their purses?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I surely do.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because they know that they have the wherewithal to buy the necessities of life, and so they are reluctant to expose themselves to the hazards of crime.&rdquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And do they repay you,&rdquo; he asked, &ldquo;the money that they get from you?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Heavens, no!&rdquo; he replied.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, do they substitute thanks for money payment?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, indeed, nor that either,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;On the contrary, some of them have an even greater dislike of me than before they got the money.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;It is remarkable,&rdquo; said Antisthenes, looking fixedly at him as though he had him in a corner, &ldquo;that you can make them righteous toward others but not toward yourself.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What is there remarkable about that?&rdquo; asked Callias. &ldquo;Do you not see plenty of carpenters, also, and architects that build houses for many another person but cannot do it for themselves, but live in rented houses? Come now, my captious friend, take your medicine and own that you are beaten.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;By all means,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;let him do so. For even the soothsayers have the reputation, you know, of prophesying the future for others but of not being able to foresee their own fate.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here the discussion of this point ended.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Niceratus remarked: &ldquo;You may now hear me tell wherein you will be improved by associating with me. You know, doubtless, that the sage Homer has written about practically everything pertaining to man. Any one of you, therefore, who wishes to acquire the art of the householder, the political leader, or the general, or to become like Achilles or Ajax or Nestor or Odysseus, should seek my favour, for I understand all these things.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Ha!&rdquo; said Antisthenes; &ldquo;do you understand how to play the king, too, knowing, as you do, that Homer praised Agamemnon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Iliad,</title> iii. 179.</note> for being &lsquo;both goodly king and spearman strong&rsquo;?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, indeed!&rdquo; said he; &ldquo;and I know also that in driving a chariot one must run close to the goalpost at the turn<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <title>Iliad,</title> xxiii. 323, 334.</note> and<cit><quote type="verse"> Himself lean lightly to the left within The polished car, the right-hand trace-horse goad, Urge him with shouts, and let him have the reins.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Hom. Il. 23.335-337</note></quote><bibl>Hom. Il. 23.335-337</bibl></cit>
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>And beside this I know something else, which you may test immediately. For Homer says somewhere: &lsquo;An onion, too, a relish for the drink.&rsquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><title>Iliad,</title> xi. 630.</note> Now if some one will bring an onion, you will receive this benefit, at any rate, without delay; for you will get more pleasure out of your drinking.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Gentlemen,&rdquo; said Charmides, &ldquo;Niceratus is intent on going home smelling of onions to make his wife believe that no one would even have conceived the thought of kissing him.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Undoubtedly,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;But we run the risk of getting a different sort of reputation, one that will bring us ridicule. For though the onion seems to be in the truest sense a relish, since it adds to our enjoyment not only of food, but also of drink, yet if we eat it not only with our dinner but after it as well, take care that some one does not say of us that on our visit to Callias we were merely indulging our appetites.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Heaven forbid, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>!&rdquo; was the reply. &ldquo;I grant that when a man is setting out for battle, it is well for him to nibble an onion, just as some people give their game-cocks a feed of garlic before pitting them together in the ring; as for us, however, our plans perhaps look more to getting a kiss from some one than to fighting.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>That was about the way the discussion of this point ended.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Critobulus said: &ldquo;Shall I take my turn now and tell you my grounds for taking pride in my handsomeness?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do,&rdquo; they said.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, then, if I am not handsome, as I think I am, you could fairly be sued for misrepresentation; for though no one asks you for an oath, you are always swearing that I am handsome. And indeed I believe you; for I consider you to be honourable men.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>But, on the other hand, if I really am handsome and you have the same feelings toward me that I have toward the one who is handsome in my eyes, I swear by all the gods that I would not take the kingdom of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> in exchange for the possession of beauty.
<milestone n="12" unit="section"/>For as it is, I would rather gaze at Cleinias<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A young cousin of the brilliant and dissipated Alcibiades.</note> than at all the other beautiful objects in the world. I would rather be blind to all things else than to Cleinias alone. I chafe at both night and sleep because then I do not see him; I feel the deepest gratitude to day and the sun because they reveal Cleinias to me.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>We handsome people have a right to be proud of this fact, too, that whereas the strong man must get the good things of his desire by toil, and the brave man by adventure, and the wise man by his eloquence, the handsome person can attain all his ends without doing anything.
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/>So far as I, at least, am concerned, although I realize that money is a delightful possession, I should take more delight in giving what I have to Cleinias than in adding to my possessions from another person's; and I should take more delight in being a slave than in being a free man, if Cleinias would deign to be my master. For I should find it easier to toil for him than to rest, and it would be more delightful to risk my life for his sake than to live in safety.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>And so, Callias, if you are proud of your ability to make people more righteous, I have a better &lsquo;right&rsquo; than you to claim that I can influence men toward every sort of virtue. For since we handsome men exert a certain inspiration upon the amorous, we make them more generous in money matters, more strenuous and heroic amid dangers, yes, and more modest and self-controlled also; for they feel abashed about the very things that they want most.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>Madness is in those people, too, who do not elect the handsome men as generals; I certainly would go through fire with Cleinias, and I know that you would, also, with me. Therefore, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, do not puzzle any more over the question whether or not my beauty will be of any benefit to men.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>But more than that, beauty is not to be contemned on this ground, either, that it soon passes its prime; for just as we recognize beauty in a boy, so we do in a youth, a full-grown man, or an old man. Witness the fact that in selecting garlandbearers for Athena they choose beautiful old men, thus intimating that beauty attends every period of life.
        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Furthermore, if it is pleasurable to attain one's desires with the good will of the giver, I know very well that at this very moment, without uttering a word, I could persuade this boy or this girl to give me a kiss sooner than you could, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, no matter how long and profoundly you might argue.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How now?&rdquo; exclaimed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;You boast as though you actually thought yourself a handsomer man than me.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Of course,&rdquo; was Critobulus's reply; &ldquo;otherwise I should be the ugliest of all the Satyrs ever on the stage.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, as fortune would have it, really resembled these creatures.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This is regarded by some as a comment interpolated in the text, though doubtless true enough. Plato (<title>Symp.</title> 215 A, B, E; 216 C, D; 221 D, E; cf. 222 D) represents Alcibiades as likening <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> to the Sileni and particularly to the Satyr Marsyas. Vase paintings and statues give an idea of the Greek conception of their coarse features. They regularly formed the chorus in the Satyr-plays that were given in connection with tragedies.</note>
        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Come, come,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;see that you remember to enter a beauty contest with me when the discussion now under way has gone the rounds. And let our judges be not Alexander, Priam's son,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Usually called <persName>Paris</persName>; the judge of beauty when Hera, Athena, and Aphrodite appealed for a decision.</note> but these very persons whom you consider eager to give you a kiss.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Would you not entrust the arbitrament to Cleinias, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Aren't you ever going to get your mind off Cleinias?&rdquo; was the rejoinder.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;If I refrain from mentioning his name, do you suppose that I shall have him any the less in mind? Do you not know that I have so clear an image of him in my heart that had I ability as a sculptor or a painter I could produce a likeness of him from this image that would be quite as close as if he were sitting for me in person?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Why do you annoy me, then,&rdquo; was <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>' retort, &ldquo;and keep taking me about to places where you can see him in person, if you possess so faithful an image of him?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, the sight of him in person has the power to delight one, whereas the sight of the image does not give pleasure, but implants a craving for him.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="23" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;For my part, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; said Hermogenes, &ldquo;I do not regard it as at all like you to countenance such a mad passion of love in Critobulus.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What? Do you suppose,&rdquo; asked <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;that this condition has arisen since he began associating with me?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;If not, when did it?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do you not notice that the soft down is just beginning to grow down in front of his ears, while that of Cleinias is already creeping up the nape of his neck? Well, then, this hot flame of his was kindled in the days when they used to go to school together.
<milestone n="24" unit="section"/>It was the discovery of this that caused his father to put him into my hands, in the hope that I might do him some good. And without question he is already much improved. For awhile ago he was like those who look at the Gorgons&mdash;he would gaze at Cleinias with a fixed and stony stare and would never leave his presence; but now I have seen him actually close his eyes in a wink.
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/>But to tell you the truth, gentlemen,&rdquo; he continued, &ldquo;by Heaven! it does look to me&mdash;to speak confidentially&mdash;as if he had also kissed Cleinias; and there is nothing more terribly potent than this at kindling the fires of passion. For it is insatiable and holds out seductive hopes.
<milestone n="26" unit="section"/>For this reason I maintain that one who intends to possess the power of self-control must refrain from kissing those in the bloom of beauty.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="27" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But why in the world, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; Charmides now asked, &ldquo;do you flourish your bogeys so to frighten us, your friends, away from the beauties, when, by Apollo! I have seen you yourself,&rdquo; he continued, &ldquo;when the two of you were hunting down something in the same book-roll at the school, sitting head to head, with your nude shoulder pressing against Critobulus's nude shoulder?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="28" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Dear me!&rdquo; exclaimed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;So that is what affected me like the bite of a wild animal! And for over five days my shoulder smarted and I felt as if I had something like a sting in my heart. But now, Critobulus,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;in the presence of all these witnesses I warn you not to lay a finger on me until you get as much hair on your chin as you have on your head.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Such was the mingled raillery and seriousness that these indulged in.
<milestone n="29" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But Callias now remarked, &ldquo;It is your turn, Charmides, to tell us why poverty makes you feel proud.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Very well,&rdquo; said he. &ldquo;So much, at least, every one admits, that assurance is preferable to fear, freedom to slavery, being the recipient of attention to being the giver of it, the confidence of one's country to its distrust.
<milestone n="30" unit="section"/>Now, as for my situation in our commonwealth, when I was rich, I was, to begin with, in dread of some one's digging through the wall of my house and not only getting my money but also doing me a mischief personally; in the next place, I knuckled down to the blackmailers, knowing well enough that my abilities lay more in the direction of suffering injury than of inflicting it on them. Then, too, I was for ever being ordered by the government to undergo some expenditure or other, and I never had the opportunity for foreign travel.
        <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>Now, however, since I am stripped of my property over the border and get no income from the property in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, and my household effects have been sold, I stretch out and enjoy a sound sleep, I have gained the confidence of the state, I am no longer subjected to threats but do the threatening now myself; and I have the free man's privilege of going abroad or staying here at home as I please. People now actually rise from their seats in deference to me, and rich men obsequiously give me the right of way on the street,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Charmides is apparently drawing the picture of the independent voter or member of a jury.</note>
        <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>Now I am like a despot; then I was clearly a slave. Then I paid a revenue to the body politic; now I live on the tribute<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The poor relief.</note> that the state pays to me. Moreover, people used to vilify me, when I was wealthy, for consorting with <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; but now that I have got poor, no one bothers his head about it any longer. Again, when my property was large, either the government or fate was continually making me throw some of it to the winds; but now, far from throwing anything away (for I possess nothing), I am always in expectation of acquiring something.&rdquo;
<milestone n="33" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Your prayers, also,&rdquo; said Callias, &ldquo;are doubtless to the effect that you may never be rich; and if you ever have a fine dream you sacrifice, do you not, to the deities who avert disasters?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Oh, no&rsquo;&rdquo; was the reply; &ldquo;I don't go so far as that; I hazard the danger with great heroism if I have any expectation of getting something from some one.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="34" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Come, now, Antisthenes,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;take your turn and tell us how it is that with such slender means you base your pride on wealth.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because, sirs, I conceive that people's wealth and poverty are to be found not in their real estate but in their hearts.
<milestone n="35" unit="section"/>For I see many persons, not in office, who though possessors of large resources, yet look upon themselves as so poor that they bend their backs to any toil, any risk, if only they may increase their holdings; and again I know of brothers, with equal shares in their inheritance, where one of them has plenty, and more than enough to meet expenses, while the other is in utter want.
<milestone n="36" unit="section"/>Again, I am told of certain despots, also, who have such a greedy appetite for riches that they commit much more dreadful crimes than they who are afflicted with the direst poverty. For it is of course their want that makes some people steal, others commit burglary, others follow the slave trade; but there are some despots who destroy whole families, kill men wholesale, oftentimes enslave even entire cities, for the sake of money.
<milestone n="37" unit="section"/>As for such men, I pity them deeply for their malignant disease; for in my eyes their malady resembles that of a person who possessed abundance but though continually eating could never be satisfied. For my own part, my possessions are so great that I can hardly find them myself; yet I have enough so that I can eat until I reach a point where I no longer feel hungry and drink until I do not feel thirsty and have enough clothing so that when out of doors I do not feel the cold any more than my superlatively wealthy friend Callias here;
<milestone n="38" unit="section"/>and when I get into the house I look on my walls as exceedingly warm tunics and the roofs as exceptionally thick mantles; and the bedding that I own is so satisfactory that it is actually a hard task to get me awake in the morning. If I ever feel a natural desire for converse with women, I am so well satisfied with whatever chance puts in my way that those to whom I make my addresses are more than glad to welcome me because they have no one else who wants to consort with them.
<milestone n="39" unit="section"/>In a word, all these items appeal to me as being so conducive to enjoyment that I could not pray for greater pleasure in performing any one of them, but could pray rather for less&mdash;so much more pleasurable do I regard some of them than is good for one.
<milestone n="40" unit="section"/>But the most valuable parcel of my wealth I reckon to be this, that even though some one were to rob me of what I now possess, I see no occupation so humble that it would not give me adequate fare.
<milestone n="41" unit="section"/>For whenever I feel an inclination to indulge my appetite, I do not buy fancy articles at the market (for they come high), but I draw on the store-house of my soul. And it goes a long way farther toward producing enjoyment when I take food only after awaiting the craving for it than when I partake of one of these fancy dishes, like this fine Thasian wine that fortune has put in my way and I am drinking without the promptings of thirst.
<milestone n="42" unit="section"/>Yes, and it is natural that those whose eyes are set on frugality should be more honest than those whose eyes are fixed on money-making. For those who are most contented with what they have are least likely to covet what belongs to others.
        <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>And it is worth noting that wealth of this kind makes people generous, also. My friend <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> here and I are examples. For <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, from whom I acquired this wealth of mine, did not come to my relief with limitation of number and weight, but made over to me all that I could carry. And as for me, I am now niggardly to no one, but both make an open display of my abundance to all my friends and share my spiritual wealth with any one of them that desires it.
        <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>But&mdash;most exquisite possession of all!&mdash;you observe that I always have leisure, with the result that I can go and see whatever is worth seeing, and hear whatever is worth hearing and&mdash;what I prize highest&mdash;pass the whole day, untroubled by business, in <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>' company. Like me, he does not bestow his admiration on those who count the most gold, but spends his time with those who are congenial to him.&rdquo;
<milestone n="45" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Such was the thesis maintained by Antisthenes. &ldquo;So help me Hera,&rdquo; commented Callias, &ldquo;among the numerous reasons I find for congratulating you on your wealth, one is that the government does not lay its commands on you and treat you as a slave, another is that people do not feel resentful at your not making them a loan.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do not be congratulating him,&rdquo; said Niceratus; &ldquo;because I am about to go and get him to make me a loan&mdash;of his contentment with his lot, schooled as I am by Homer to count<cit><quote type="verse">Seven pots unfired, ten talents' weight of gold, A score of gleaming cauldrons, chargers twelve,</quote><bibl>Hom. Iliad 9.122 f., 264 f.</bibl></cit> weighing and calculating until I am never done with yearning for vast riches; as a result, some people perhaps regard me as just a bit fond of lucre.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A burst of laughter from the whole company greeted this admission; for they considered that he had told nothing more than the truth.
<milestone n="46" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Hermogenes, it devolves on you,&rdquo; some one now remarked, &ldquo;to mention who your friends are and to demonstrate their great power and their solicitude for you, so that your pride in them may appear justified.&rdquo;
<milestone n="47" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Very well; in the first place, it is clear as day that both Greeks and barbarians believe that the gods know everything both present and to come; at any rate, all cities and all races ask the gods, by the diviner's art, for advice as to what to do and what to avoid. Second, it is likewise manifest that we consider them able to work us good or ill; at all events, every one prays the gods to avert evil and grant blessings.
<milestone n="48" unit="section"/>Well, these gods, omniscient and omnipotent, feel so friendly toward me that their watchfulness over me never lets me out of their ken night or day, no matter where I am going or what business I have in view. They know the results also that will follow any act; and so they send me as messengers omens of sounds, dreams, and birds, and thus indicate what I ought to do and what I ought not to do. And when I do their bidding, I never regret it; on the other hand, I have before now disregarded them and have been punished for it.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="49" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;None of these statements,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;is incredible. But what I should like very much to know is how you serve them to keep them so friendly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;A very economical service it is, I declare!&rdquo; responded Hermogenes. &ldquo;I sound their praises,&mdash;which costs nothing; I always restore them part of what they give me; I avoid profanity of speech as far as I can; and I never wittingly lie in matters wherein I have invoked them to be my witnesses.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Truly,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;if it is conduct like this that gives you their friendship, then the gods also, it would seem, take delight in nobility of soul!&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Such was the serious turn given to the discussion of this topic.
<milestone n="50" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When they got around to Philip, they asked him what he saw in the jester's profession to feel proud of it.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Have I not a right to be proud,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;when all know that I am a jester, and so whenever they have a bit of good fortune, give me hearty invitations to come and join them, but when they suffer some reverse, run from me with never a glance behind, in dread that they may be forced to laugh in spite of themselves?&rdquo;
<milestone n="51" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Your pride is abundantly justified,&rdquo; said Niceratus. &ldquo;In my case, on the contrary, those friends who enjoy success keep out of my way, but those that run into some mishap reckon up their kinship to me on the family tree, and I can't get rid of them.&rdquo;
<milestone n="52" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No doubt,&rdquo; said Charmides; and then, turning to the Syracusan, &ldquo;What is it that you are proud of? The boy, I suppose?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Quite the contrary,&rdquo; was the reply; &ldquo;I am instead in extreme apprehension about him. For I understand that there are certain persons plotting his undoing.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="53" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On receiving this information, &ldquo;Good Heavens!&rdquo; exclaimed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;what wrong do they imagine your lad has done them that is grave enough to make them wish to kill him?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;It is not killing him that they desire; oh, no! but to persuade him to sleep with them.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Your belief, then, if I mistake not, is that if this happened, he would be undone?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;Aye, utterly!&rdquo;
<milestone n="54" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Do you not then sleep in his bed yourself?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;Most certainly, all night and every night.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Marry, you are in great luck to be formed of such flesh that you are unique in not corrupting those that sleep with you. And so you have a right to be proud of your flesh if of nothing else.&rdquo;
<milestone n="55" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;And yet that is not the basis of my pride.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;What is, then?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;Fools, in faith. They give me a livelihood by coming to view my marionettes.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; ejaculated Philip; &ldquo;that explains the prayer I heard you uttering the other day, that wherever you were the gods would grant you an abundant harvest of grain but a crop-failure of wits!&rdquo;
        <milestone n="56" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Good!&rdquo; said Callias. &ldquo;And now, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, what can you advance in support of your pride in that disreputable profession that you mentioned?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Let us first,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;come to an understanding on the functions that belong to the procurer. Do not hesitate to answer all the questions I ask you, so that we may know our points of agreement. Is that your pleasure?&rdquo; he asked.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly,&rdquo; was their reply; and when they had once started with &ldquo;certainly,&rdquo; that was the regular answer they all made to his questions thereafter.
<milestone n="57" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Well, then, you consider it the function of a good procurer to render the man or the woman whom he is serving attractive to his or her associates?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>All. &ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Now, one thing that contributes to rendering a person attractive is a comely arrangement of hair and clothing, is it not?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>All. &ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;
<milestone n="58" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;This, also, we know, do we not, that it is in a man's power to use the one pair of eyes to express both friendship and hostility?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And again, it is possible to speak both modestly and boldly with the same voice?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Moreover, are there not words that create ill feeling and others that conduce to friendliness?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;
<milestone n="59" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Now the good procurer would teach only the words that tend to make one attractive, would he not?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Which one would be the better?&rdquo; he continued, &ldquo;the one who could make people attractive to a single person or the one who could make them attractive to many?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This question brought a division; some said, &ldquo;Clearly the one who could make them attractive to a great many&rdquo;; the others merely repeated, &ldquo;Certainly.&rdquo;
<milestone n="60" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Remarking that they were all of one mind on this point as on the others, he went on: &ldquo;If a person could render people attractive to the entire community, would he not satisfy the requirements of the ideal procurer?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Indubitably,&rdquo; they all said.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And so, if one could produce men of this type out of his clients, he would be entitled to feel proud of his profession and to receive a high remuneration, would he not?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="61" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>All agreeing on this point, too, he added, &ldquo;Antisthenes here seems to me to be a man of just that sort.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Antisthenes asked, &ldquo;Are you resigning your profession to me, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Assuredly,&rdquo; was the answer. &ldquo;For I see that you have brought to a high state of perfection the complementary trade.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What is that?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;The profession of go-between,&rdquo; he said.
<milestone n="62" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Antisthenes was much incensed and asked, &ldquo;What knowledge can you possibly have of my being guilty of such a thing as that?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I know several instances,&rdquo; he replied. &ldquo;I know that you acted the part between Callias here and the scholar Prodicus, when you saw that Callias was in love with philosophy and that Prodicus wanted money. I know also that you did the same for Hippias, the Elean, from whom Callias got his memory system; and as a result, Callias has become more amorous than ever, because he finds it impossible to forget any beauty he sees.
        <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>And just recently, you remember, you introduced the stranger from <placeName key="perseus,Heraclea,Thessaly">Heraclea</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Zeuxippus, the painter. Cf. Plato, <title>Protag.</title> 318 B, C.</note> to me, after arousing my keen interest in him by your commendations. For this I am indeed grateful to you; for I look upon him as endowed with a truly noble nature. And did you not laud Aeschylus the Phleiasian<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing further seems to be known of this man.</note> to me and me to him until you brought us to such a pass that in mutual yearning, excited by your words, we went coursing like hounds to find each other?
<milestone n="64" unit="section"/>It is the witnessing of your talent at achieving such a result that makes me judge you an excellent go-between. For the man who can recognize those who are fitted to be mutually helpful and can make them desire one another's acquaintance, that man, in my opinion, could also create friendship between cities and arrange suitable marriages, and would be a very valuable acquisition as friend or ally for both states and individuals. But you got indignant, as if you had received an affront, when I said that you were a good go-between.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But, indeed, that is all over now,&rdquo; he replied; &ldquo;for with this power mine I shall find my soul chock-full of riches.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And so this round of discourse was brought to a close.
        <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Callias now said, &ldquo;Critobulus, are you going to refuse to enter the lists in the beauty contest with <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Undoubtedly!&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;for probably he notices that the procurer stands high in the favour of the judges.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But yet in spite of that,&rdquo; retorted Critobulus, &ldquo;I do not shun the contest. So make your plea, if you can produce any profound reason, and prove that you are more handsome than I. Only,&rdquo; he added, &ldquo;let some one bring the light close to him.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;The first step, then, in my suit,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;is to summon you to the preliminary hearing; be so kind as to answer my questions.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;And you proceed to put them.&rdquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do you hold, then, that beauty is to be found only in man, or is it also in other objects?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Crit. &ldquo;In faith, my opinion is that beauty is to be found quite as well in a horse or an ox or in any number of inanimate things. I know, at any rate, that a shield may be beautiful, or a sword, or a spear.&rdquo;
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;How can it be that all these things are beautiful when they are entirely dissimilar?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Why, they are beautiful and fine,&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Critobulus, of course, gets into trouble by his poor definition of beauty. In the Greek the ensuing discussion is made plausible by the fact that throughout both disputants use only one word, <foreign lang="greek">kalo/s</foreign>, which means not only &ldquo;beautiful&rdquo; or handsome but also &ldquo;glorious, noble, excellent, fine;&rdquo; and though starting with the first meaning it soon shifts to the last. The translator is compelled to use different terms for this in the two parts of the argument.</note> answered Critobulus, &ldquo;if they are well made for the respective functions for which we obtain them, or if they are naturally well constituted to serve our needs.&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Do you know the reason why we need eyes?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Crit. &ldquo;Obviously to see with.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In that case, it would appear without further 9ado that my eyes are finer ones than yours.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How so?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Because, while yours see only straight ahead, mine, by bulging out as they do, see also to the sides.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Crit. &ldquo;Do you mean to say that a crab is better equipped visually than any other creature?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Absolutely; for its eyes are also better set to insure strength.&rdquo;
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Crit. &ldquo;Well, let that pass; but whose nose is finer, yours or mine?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Mine, I consider, granting that Providence made us noses to smell with. For your nostrils look down toward the ground, but mine are wide open and turned outward so that I can catch scents from all about.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But how do you make a snub nose handsomer than a straight one?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;For the reason that it does not put a barricade between the eyes but allows them unobstructed vision of whatever they desire to see; whereas a high nose, as if in despite, has walled the eyes off one from the other.&rdquo;
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;As for the mouth,&rdquo; said Critobulus, &ldquo;I concede that point. For if it is created for the purpose of biting off food, you could bite off a far bigger mouthful than I could. And don't you think that your kiss is also the more tender because you have thick lips?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;According to your argument, it would seem that I have a mouth more ugly even than an ass's. But do you not reckon it a proof of my superior beauty that the River Nymphs, goddesses as they are, bear as their offspring the Seileni, who resemble me more closely than they do you?&rdquo;
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;I cannot argue any longer with you,&rdquo; answered Critobulus; &ldquo;let them distribute the ballots, so that I may know without suspense what fine or punishment I must undergo. Only,&rdquo; he continued, &ldquo;let the balloting be secret, for I am afraid that the &lsquo;wealth' you and Antisthenes possess will overmaster me.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So the maiden and the lad turned in the ballots secretly. While this was going on, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> saw to it that the light should be brought in front of Critobulus, so that the judges might not be misled, and stipulated that the prize given by the judges to crown the victor should be kisses and not ribbons.
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>When the ballots were turned out of the urn and proved to be a unanimous verdict in favour of Critobulus, &ldquo;Faugh!&rdquo; exclaimed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; &ldquo;your money, Critobulus, does not appear to resemble Callias's. For his makes people more honest, while yours is about the most potent to corrupt men, whether members of a jury or judges of a contest.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this some of the company urged Critobulus to take his kisses, the need of victory; others advised him to get the consent of the young people's legal guardian; and others indulged in other badinage. But even then Hermogenes kept silent. And <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, calling him by name, inquired, &ldquo;Hermogenes, could you define &lsquo;convivial unpleasantness' for us?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;If you ask me what it actually is,&rdquo; he answered, &ldquo;I do not know; but I am willing to tell you what I think it is.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Very well, tell us that.&rdquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Herm. &ldquo;My definition of &lsquo;convivial unpleasantness' is the annoying of one's companions at their drink.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Well, do you realize that at the present moment you conform to the definition by annoying us with your taciturnity?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Herm. &ldquo;What! while you are talking?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, but in the intervals.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Why, don't you see that a person could not insert even a hair in the interstices of your talk, much less a word?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Callias,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, appealing to him, &ldquo;could you come to the rescue of a man hard put to it for an answer?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, indeed,&rdquo; said he: &ldquo;we are absolutely quiet every time the flute is played.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hermogenes retorted, &ldquo;Is it your wish that I should converse with you to the accompaniment of a flute, the way the actor Nicostratus used to recite tetrameter verses?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In Heaven's name, do so, Hermogenes,&rdquo; urged <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>. &ldquo;For I believe that precisely as a song is more agreeable when accompanied on the flute, so your discourse would be embellished somewhat by the music, especially if you were to gesticulate and pose, like the flute-girl, to point your words.&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What is the tune to be,&rdquo; asked Callias, &ldquo;when Antisthenes here gets some one at the banquet cornered in an argument?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;For the discomfited disputant,&rdquo; said Antisthenes, &ldquo;I think the appropriate music would be a hissing.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The Syracusan, seeing that with such conversation going on the banqueters were paying no attention to his show, but were enjoying one another's company, said spitefully to <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;<persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, are you the one nick-named the &lsquo;Thinker&rsquo;?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Well, isn't that preferable,&rdquo; he rejoined, &ldquo;to being called the &lsquo;Thoughtless&rsquo;?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, if it were not that you are supposed to be a thinker on celestial subjects.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The Syracusan uses the word applied by the Greeks first to astronomical and then to philosophical (especially ontological) inquiry, a word of reproach for radical thinkers that was used against <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> in Aristophanes' burlesque, the <title>Clouds,</title> and later played a more serious part in <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>' trial.</note>
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Do you know,&rdquo; asked <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;anything more celestial than the gods?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;No; but that is not what people say you are concerned with, but rather with the most unbeneficial things.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soc. &ldquo;Even granting the expression, it would still be the gods that are my concern; for (1) they cause rain under the heavens and so are beneficial, and (2) they produce light, also under the heavens, and are thus again beneficial. If the pun is strained,&rdquo; he added, &ldquo;you have only yourself to blame for it, for annoying me.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Syr. &ldquo;Well, let that pass. But tell me the distance between us in flea's feet; for people say that your geometry includes such measurements as that.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In a famous passage in the <title>Clouds</title> (144 ff., cf. also 830 f.), published two years before this banquet was supposed to have been held, Aristophanes had represented <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> and Chaerephon as measuring a flea's jump in terms of its own feet.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this Antisthenes said to Philip: &ldquo;You are clever at hitting off a person's likeness; wouldn't you say that our friend here resembles one with a penchant for abuse?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Yes, indeed,&rdquo; came the answer; &ldquo;and I see a resemblance in him to many another kind of person, too.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Nevertheless,&rdquo; interposed <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;do not draw the comparison, lest you take on a similar likeness to one stooping to abuse.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But suppose I am likening him to all the upright, the very e/lite; then I should deserve to be compared to a eulogist, rather than to a detractor.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Ah, you resemble the latter right now, for you are asserting that every one is better than he.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">i.e., (if the text is sound), by saying that he resembles the virtuous, thus assuming that he is not actually one of them.</note>
        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Would you have me compare him to those who excel him in villainy?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, not those, either.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;What, to no one?&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No; don't compare him to any one in any particular.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;But if I hold my peace, I do not understand how I am going to render services suitable to such a fine dinner.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;That is easily effected,&rdquo; said <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;if you will be reticent on matters that should not be talked about.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus was quenched this bit of convivial unpleasantness.
        <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then some among the rest of the banqueters kept urging Philip to go on with his comparisons, while others opposed. As the clamour rose to some height, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> once more interposed, saying: &ldquo;Since we all want to talk, would this not be a fine time to join in singing?&rdquo; And with the words he began a song.
        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>When they had finished, a potter's wheel was brought in for the dancing girl on which she intended performing some feats of jugglery.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This prompted <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> to observe to the Syracusan: &ldquo;Sir, it is quite probable that, to use your words, I am indeed a &lsquo;thinker&rsquo;; at any rate, I am now considering how it might be possible for this lad of yours and this maid to exert as little effort as may be, and at the same time give us the greatest possible amount of pleasure in watching them,&mdash;this being your purpose, also, I am sure.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now, turning somersaults in among knives seems to me to be a dangerous exhibition, which is utterly out of place at a banquet. Also, to write or read aloud on a whirling potter's wheel may perhaps be something of a feat; yet I cannot conceive what pleasure even this can afford. Nor is it any more diverting to watch the young and beautiful going through bodily contortions and imitating hoops than to contemplate them in repose.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>For it is of course no rare event to meet with marvels, if that is what one's mind is set on. He may marvel at what he finds immediately at hand,&mdash;for instance, why the lamp gives light owing to its having a bright flame, while a bronze mirror, likewise bright, does not produce light but instead reflects other things that appear in it; or how it comes about that olive oil, though wet, makes the flame higher, while water, because it is wet, puts the fire out.
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>However, these questions also fail to promote the same object that wine does; but if the young people were to have a flute accompaniment and dance figures depicting the Graces, the Horae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or, the Seasons. Or it may be used here in the Homeric sense of the maidens who kept the cloud gate of Heaven.</note> and the Nymphs, I believe that they would be far less wearied themselves and that the charms of the banquet would be greatly enhanced.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Upon my word, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,&rdquo; replied the Syracusan, &ldquo;you are quite right; and I will bring in a spectacle that will delight you.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So the Syracusan withdrew amid applause. <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> now opened up another new topic for discussion. &ldquo;Gentlemen,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;it is to be expected of us, is it not, when in the presence of a mighty deity that is coeval with the eternal gods, yet youngest of them all in appearance, in magnitude encompassing the universe, but enthroned in the heart of man,&mdash;I mean Love,&mdash;that we should not be unmindful of him, particularly in view of the fact that we are all of his following?
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For I cannot name a time when I was not in love with some one, and I know that Charmides here has gained many lovers and has in some instances felt the passion himself; and Critobulus, though even yet the object of love, is already beginning to feel this passion for others.
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Nay, Niceratus too, so I am told, is in love with his wife and finds his love reciprocated. And as for Hermogenes, who of us does not know that he is pining away with love for nobility of character, whatever that may be? Do you not observe how serious his brows are, how calm his gaze, how modest his words, how gentle his voice, how genial his demeanour? That though he enjoys the friendship of the most august gods, yet he does not disdain us mortals? Are you the only person, Antisthenes, in love with no one?&rdquo;
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;No, by Heaven!&rdquo; replied he; &ldquo;I am madly in love&mdash;with you.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, banteringly, pretending to be coquettish, said: &ldquo;Don't pester me just now; I am engaged in other business, as you see.&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;How transparent you are, sir procurer of your own charms,&rdquo; Antisthenes rejoined, &ldquo;in always doing something like this; at one time you refuse me audience on the pretext of your divine sign,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See footnote on page 494 of the <title>Defence.</title></note> at another time because you have some other purpose in mind.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;In Heaven's name, Antisthenes,&rdquo; implored <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, &ldquo;only refrain from beating me; any other manifestation of your bad temper I am wont to endure, and shall continue to do so, in a friendly spirit. But,&rdquo; he went on, &ldquo;let us keep your love a secret, because it is founded not on my spirit but on my physical beauty.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>But as for you, Callias, all the city knows that you are in love with Autolycus, and so, I think, do a great many men from abroad. The reason for this is the fact that you are both sons of distinguished fathers and are yourselves in the public eye.
<milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Now, I have always felt an admiration for your character, but at the present time I feel a much keener one, for I see that you are in love with a person who is not marked by dainty elegance nor wanton effeminacy, but shows to the world physical strength and stamina, virile courage and sobriety. Setting one's heart on such traits gives an insight into the lover's character.
<milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Now, whether there is one Aphrodite or two, &lsquo;Heavenly&rsquo; and &lsquo;Vulgar,&rsquo; I do not know; for even Zeus, though considered one and the same, yet has many by-names. I do know, however, that in the case of Aphrodite there are separate altars and temples for the two, and also rituals, those of the &lsquo;Vulgar&rsquo; Aphrodite excelling in looseness, those of the &lsquo;Heavenly&rsquo; in chastity.
<milestone n="10" unit="section"/>One might conjecture, also, that different types of love come from the different sources, carnal love from the &lsquo;Vulgar' Aphrodite, and from the &lsquo;Heavenly&rsquo; spiritual love, love of friendship and of noble conduct. That is the sort of love, Callias, that seems to have you in its grip.
<milestone n="11" unit="section"/>I infer this from the noble nature of the one you love and because I see that you include his father in your meetings with him. For the virtuous lover does not make any of these matters a secret from the father of his beloved.&rdquo;
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Marry,&rdquo; quoth Hermogenes, &ldquo;you arouse my admiration in numerous ways, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, but now more than ever, because in the very act of flattering Callias you are in fact educating him to conform to the ideal.&rdquo;<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;True,&rdquo; he replied; &ldquo;and to add to his pleasure, I wish to bear testimony to him that spiritual love is far superior to carnal.
<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>For we all know that there is no converse worth the mention that does not comprise affection. Now affection on the part of those who feel admiration for character is commonly termed a pleasant and willing constraint; whereas many of those who have a merely physical concupiscence reprehend and detest the ways of those they love.
<milestone n="14" unit="section"/>But suppose they are satisfied on both scores; yet the bloom of youth soon passes its prime, and as this disappears, affection also inevitably fades away as fast; but the soul becomes more and more lovable the longer it progresses toward wisdom.
<milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Besides, in the enjoyment of physical beauty there is a point of surfeit, so that one cannot help feeling toward his favourite the same effect that he gets toward food by gratification of the appetite. But affection for the soul, being pure, is also less liable to satiety, though it does not follow, as one might suppose, that it is also less rich in the graces of Aphrodite; on the contrary, our prayer that the goddess will bestow her grace on our words and deeds is manifestly answered.
<milestone n="16" unit="section"/>Now, no further argument is necessary to show that a soul verdant with the beauty of freeborn men and with a disposition that is reverent and noble, a soul that from the very first displays its leadership among its own fellows and is kindly withal, feels an admiration and an affection for the object of its love; but I will go on to prove the reasonableness of the position that such a lover will have his affection returned.
<milestone n="17" unit="section"/>First, who could feel dislike for one by whom he knew himself to be regarded as the pattern of nobleness, and, in the next place, saw that he made his favourite's honour of more account than his own pleasure, and beside this felt assured that this affection would not be lessened under any circumstances, no matter whether he suffered some reverse or lost his comeliness through the ravages of illness?
<milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Moreover, must not those who enjoy a mutual affection unavoidably take pleasure in looking into each other's faces, converse in amity, and trust and be trusted, and not only take thought each for the other but also take a common joy in prosperity and feel a common distress if some ill fortune befall, and live in happiness when their society is attended by sound health, but be much more constantly together if one or the other become ill, and be even more solicitous, each for the other, when absent than when present? Are not all these things marked by Aphrodite's grace? It is by conducting themselves thus that men continue mutually to love friendship and enjoy it clear down to old age.
<milestone n="19" unit="section"/>But what is there to induce a favourite to make a return of affection to a lover who bases his feeling solely on the flesh? Would it be the consideration that the lover allots to himself the joys he desires but gives the favourite only what excites the deepest contempt? Or that he conceals, as best he can, from the favourite's relatives the ends that he is bent on attaining?
<milestone n="20" unit="section"/>As for his using entreaty rather than coercion, that is all the stronger reason for detestation. For any one who applies force merely discovers his rascality, but he who uses persuasion corrupts the soul of the one upon whom he prevails.
<milestone n="21" unit="section"/>Once more, how will he who traffics in his beauty feel greater affection toward the buyer than he who puts his produce up for sale and disposes of it in the open market? For assuredly he will not be moved to affection because he is a youthful companion to one who is not youthful, or because he is handsome when the other is no longer so, or because he is untouched by passion when the other is in its sway. For a youth does not share in the pleasure of the intercourse as a woman does, but looks on, sober, at another in love's intoxication.
<milestone n="22" unit="section"/>Consequently, it need not excite any surprise if contempt for the lover is engendered in him. If one looked into the matter, also, he would descry no ill effect when people are loved for their personality, but that many shocking results have come from companionship lost to shame.
<milestone n="23" unit="section"/>I will now go on to show also that the union is servile when one's regard is for the body rather than when it is for the soul. For he who inculcates right speech and conduct would merit the honour given by Achilles to Cheiron and Phoenix;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cheiron, the just Centaur, and Phoenix, an exile who was received into the household of Peleus; both were tutors to the young Achilles.</note> but the man who lusts only after the flesh would with good reason be treated like a mendicant; for he is always dogging the footsteps of his favourite, begging and beseeching the favour of one more kiss or some other caress.
<milestone n="24" unit="section"/>Do not be surprised at my plain speaking; the wine helps to incite me, and the kind of love that ever dwells with me spurs me on to say what I think about its opposite.
<milestone n="25" unit="section"/>For, to my way of thinking, the man whose attention is attracted only by his beloved's appearance is like one who has rented a farm; his aim is not to increase its value but to gain from it as much of a harvest as he can for himself. On the other hand, the man whose goal is friendship is more like one possessing a farm of his own; at any rate he utilizes all sources to enhance his loved one's worth.
<milestone n="26" unit="section"/>Furthermore, the favourite who realizes that he who lavishes physical charms will be the lover's sovereign will in all likelihood be loose in his general conduct; but the one who feels that he cannot keep his lover faithful without nobility of character will more probably give heed to virtue.
<milestone n="27" unit="section"/>But the greatest blessing that befalls the man who yearns to render his favourite a good friend is the necessity of himself making virtue his habitual practice. For one cannot produce goodness in his companion while his own conduct is evil, nor can he himself exhibit shamelessness and incontinence and at the same time render his beloved self-controlled and reverent.
<milestone n="28" unit="section"/>My heart is set on showing you, Callias, on the basis of olden tales, also, that not only humankind but also gods and demi-gods set higher value on the friendship of the spirit than on the enjoyment of the body.
<milestone n="29" unit="section"/>For in all cases where Zeus became enamoured of mortal women for their beauty, though he united with them he suffered them to remain mortal; but all those persons whom he delighted in for their souls' sake he made immortal. Among the latter are Heracles and the Sons of Zeus;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Castor and Pollux.</note> and tradition includes others also.
        <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>And I aver that even in the case of Ganymede, it was not his person but his spiritual character that influenced Zeus to carry him up to <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>. This is confirmed by his very name. Homer, you remember, has the words,<cit><quote type="verse">He joys to hear;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing like the first expression, except the bare occurrence of <foreign lang="greek">ga/nutai</foreign> (&ldquo;he joys&rdquo;), is to be found anywhere in the extant Homeric poems. The second phrase, also, is not in these poems, although several different expressions much resembling it are to be seen in the <title>Iliad,</title> vii. 278, xvii. 325, xviii. 363, xxiv. 88, 282, 674 and the <title>Odyssey,</title> ii. 38, xi. 445, xix. 353, xx. 46. Either Xenophon's memory is faulty or he is quoting from some of the lost epics.</note></quote><bibl>Perhaps Homeric Poems</bibl></cit> that is to say, &lsquo;he rejoices to hear;&rsquo; and in another place,<cit><quote type="verse">&lsquo;harbouring shrewd devices in his heart.&rsquo; </quote><bibl>Perhaps <title>Iliad</title>, 7.278, 17.325, 18.363, 24.88, 282, 674 or <title>Odyssey</title>, 2.38, 11.445, 19.353, 20.46.</bibl></cit> This, again, means &lsquo;harbouring wise counsels in his heart.&rsquo; So the name given Gany-mede, compounded of the two foregoing elements, signifies not physically but mentally attractive;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> takes the name Ganymede to be a compound of the two archaic words <foreign lang="greek">ga/nutai</foreign> &ldquo;he joys,&rdquo; &ldquo;exults&rdquo; and <foreign lang="greek">mh/dea</foreign> &ldquo;devices,&rdquo; &ldquo;thoughts&rdquo;.</note> hence his honour among the gods.
<milestone n="31" unit="section"/>Or again, Niceratus, Homer pictures us Achilles looking upon Patroclus not as the object of his passion but as a comrade, and in this spirit signally avenging his death. So we have songs telling also how Orestes, Pylades, Theseus, Peirithous, and many other illustrious demi-gods wrought glorious deeds of valour side by side, not because they shared a common bed but because of mutual admiration and respect.
<milestone n="32" unit="section"/>Moreover, take the splendid feats of the present day; would not a person discover that they are all done for glory's sake by persons willing to endure hardship and jeopardy, rather than by those who are drifting into the habit of preferring pleasure to a good name? Yet Pausanias, the lover of the poet Agathon, has said in his defence of those who wallow in lasciviousness that the most valiant army, even, would be one recruited of lovers and their favourites!
<milestone n="33" unit="section"/>For these, he said, would in his opinion be most likely to be prevented by shame from deserting one another,&mdash;a strange assertion, indeed, that persons acquiring an habitual indifference to censure and to abandoned conduct toward one another will be most likely to be deterred by shame from any infamous act.
<milestone n="34" unit="section"/>But he went further and adduced as evidence in support of his position both the Thebans and the Eleans, alleging that this was their policy; he stated, in fine, that though sharing common beds they nevertheless assigned to their favourites places alongside themselves in the battle-line. But this is a false analogy; for such practices, though normal among them, with us are banned by the severest reprobation. My own view is that those who assign these posts in battle suggest thereby that they are suspicious that the objects of their love, if left by themselves, will not perform the duties of brave men.
<milestone n="35" unit="section"/>In contrast to this, the Lacedaemonians, who hold that if a person so much as feels a carnal concupiscence he will never come to any good end, cause the objects of their love to be so consummately brave that even when arrayed with foreigners and even when not stationed in the same line with their lovers they just as surely feel ashamed to desert their comrades. For the goddess they worship is not Impudence but Modesty.
<milestone n="36" unit="section"/>We could all come to one mind, I think, on the point I am trying to make, if we were to consider the question in this way: of two lads, the objects of the different types of love, which one would a person prefer to trust with his money, or his children, or to lay under the obligation of a favour? My own belief is that even the person whose love is founded on the loved one's physical beauty would in all these cases rather put his trust in him whose loveliness is of the spirit.
<milestone n="37" unit="section"/>In your case, Callias, I deem it meet that you should thank Heaven for inspiring you with love for Autolycus. For his ardour for glory is manifest, inasmuch as he undergoes many toils and many bodily discomforts to ensure his being proclaimed victor in the pancratium.
<milestone n="38" unit="section"/>Now if he were to believe that he is going not merely to shed lustre on himself and his father but also to acquire through his manly virtue the ability to serve his friends and to exalt his country by setting up trophies of victory over its enemies, and for these reasons draw the admiring glances of all and be famous among both Greeks and barbarians, do you not suppose that he would esteem and honour highly any one whom he looked upon as the best partner in furthering these designs?
<milestone n="39" unit="section"/>If, then, you would be in his good graces, you must try to find out what sort of knowledge it was that made Themistocles able to give <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> liberty; you must try to find out what kind of knowledge it was that gave Pericles the name of being his country's wisest counsellor; you must reflect, further, how it was that Solon by deep meditation established in his city laws of surpassing worth; you must search and find out what kind of practices it is that gives the Lacedaemonians the reputation of being pre-eminent military commanders; for you are their proxenus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In the absence of regular consular representation, any Greek city-state could secure commercial and political agentsin other cities only by getting influential citizens there to consent to use their good offices, as occasion might arise, in its behalf or in behalf of its citizens when abroad. Such a local native representative of another state was called a proxenus.</note> and their foremost citizens are always being entertained at your house.
<milestone n="40" unit="section"/>You may regard it as certain, therefore, that our city would be quick to entrust itself to your hands, if you so desire. For you possess the highest qualifications for such a trust: you are of aristocratic birth, of Erechtheus' line,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Callias's family belonged to the priestly clan of the Ceryces, who traced their lineage back to Ceryx, son of Hermes and Aglaurus. The latter, however, was not a descendant of Erechtheus, but one of his nurses.</note> a priest serving the gods who under the leadership of Iacchus took the field against the barbarian;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Herodotus (VIII, 65) and Plutarch (<title>Life of Themistocles,</title> XV) report the tradition that while the Greek fleet was at anchor near <placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName> just before the critical sea-fight, great elation was caused at sight of a big cloud of dust (or, in the later version, a brilliant light) off toward <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>, and a wonderful sound as of the Eleusinian festival with its cries to Iacchus, followed by a cloud that drifted directly toward the fleet.</note> and in our day you outshine your predecessors in the splendour of your priestly office in the festival;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In addition to being one of the priestly Ceryces, Callias was an hereditary torch-bearer in the Eleusinian festival.</note> and you possess a person more goodly to the eye than any other in the city and one at the same time able to withstand effort and hardship.
<milestone n="41" unit="section"/>If what I say appears to you gentlemen to be too grave and earnest for a drinking party, I beg you again not to be surprised. For during practically all my life I have been at one with the commonwealth in loving men who to a nature already good add a zealous desire for virtue.&rdquo;
<milestone n="42" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The rest of the company now engaged in a discussion of the views propounded by <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>; but Autolycus kept his eyes fixed on Callias. And Callias, addressing <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, but looking beyond him and returning the gaze of Autolycus, said: &ldquo;So you intend acting the procurer, do you, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, to bring me to the attention of the commonwealth, so that I may enter politics, and the state may always look upon me with favour?&rdquo;
<milestone n="43" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>&ldquo;Assuredly,&rdquo; was the reply, &ldquo;that is, if people see that you set your heart on virtue, not in pretence, but in reality. For false reputation is soon exposed when tried by experience, whereas true manly virtue,&mdash;barring the interposition of Providence,&mdash;confers ever more and more brilliant glory when put to the test of actual deeds.&rdquo;
<milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Their conversation ended here. Autolycus got up to go out for a walk (it being now his usual time); and his father Lycon, as he was departing to accompany him, turned back and said: &ldquo;So help me Hera, Socrates, you seem to me to have a truly noble character.&rdquo;
<milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>After he had withdrawn, a chair of state, first of all, was set down in the room, and then the Syracusan came in with the announcement: &ldquo;Gentlemen, Ariadne will now enter the chamber set apart for her and Dionysus; after that, Dionysus, a little flushed with wine drunk at a banquet of the gods, will come to join her; and then they will disport themselves together.&rdquo;
<milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then, to start proceedings, in came Ariadne, apparelled as a bride, and took her seat in the chair. Dionysus being still invisible, there was heard the Bacchic music played on a flute. Then it was that the assemblage was filled with admiration of the dancing master. For as soon as Ariadne heard the strain, her action was such that every one might have perceived her joy at the sound; and although she did not go to meet Dionysus, nor even rise, yet it was clear that she kept her composure with difficulty.
<milestone n="4" unit="section"/>But when Dionysus caught sight of her, he came dancing toward her and in a most loving manner sat himself on her lap, and putting his arms about her gave her a kiss. Her demeanour was all modesty, and yet she returned his embrace with affection. As the banqueters beheld it, they kept clapping and crying &ldquo;encore!&rdquo;
<milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Then when Dionysus arose and gave his hand to Ariadne to rise also, there was presented the impersonation of lovers kissing and caressing each other. The onlookers viewed a Dionysus truly handsome, an Ariadne truly fair, not presenting a burlesque but offering genuine kisses with their lips; and they were all raised to a high pitch of enthusiasm as they looked on.
<milestone n="6" unit="section"/>For they overheard Dionysus asking her if she loved him, and heard her vowing that she did, so earnestly that not only Dionysus but all the bystanders as well would have taken their oaths in confirmation that the youth and the maid surely felt a mutual affection. For theirs was the appearance not of actors who had been taught their poses but of persons now permitted to satisfy their long-cherished desires.
<milestone n="7" unit="section"/>At last, the banqueters, seeing them in each other's embrace and obviously leaving for the bridal couch, those who were unwedded swore that they would take to themselves wives, and those who were already married mounted horse and rode off to their wives that they might enjoy them. As for Socrates and the others who had lingered behind, they went out with Callias to join Lycon and his son in their walk.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So broke up the banquet held that evening.</p></body></text></group></text></TEI.2>
