<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>

<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader status="new" type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title> Economics (English). Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Aristotle</author> &responsibility; &fund.AnnCPB; </titleStmt>
			<extent>About 91Kb</extent> &Perseus.publish; <notesStmt>
				<note anchored="yes">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Aristotle</author>
						<title>Aristotle in 23 Volumes, Vol. 18, translated by G.C. Armstrong.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1935</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="book"/>
				<state unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English </language>
				<language id="greek">Greek </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>June, 1993</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>wpm</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Tagged in conformance with Prose.e dtd.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>7/27, 1993</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>em</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Put Bekker line 1 milestone tags at the beginning of each section so that the
                    incoming list creator would work. Changed RREFDECL.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>5/27/09</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>RS</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>  
        			$Log: aristot.econ_eng.xml,v $
        			Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 19:18:48  rsingh04
        			cleaned up bad place tags in a few texts and cleaned up the document format

        			Revision 1.1  2009/10/09 19:49:17  rsingh04
        			more reorganizing of texts module by collection

        			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:12:41  rsingh04
        			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

        			Revision 1.11  2009/07/15 17:52:35  student
        			edited entity tags CEH

        			Revision 1.10  2009/07/15 17:50:40  student
        			edited entity tags CEH

        			Revision 1.9  2009/05/27 15:55:14  rsingh04
        			added cvs log keyword

        		</item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>

		<body>
			<div1 type="Book" n="1">
				<p>
                    <milestone n="1343a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> Between Housecraft (the art of governing a Household or Home) and Statecraft
                    (the art of governing a Nation) there are differences corresponding to those
                    between the two kinds of community over which they severally preside. There is,
                    however, this further difference: that whereas the government of a nation is in
                    many hands, a household has but a single ruler.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now some arts are divided into two separate branches, one concerned with the
                    making of an object&mdash;for example a lyre or a flute&mdash;and the
                    other with its use when made. Statecraft on the other hand shows us how to build
                    up a nation from its beginning, as well as how to order rightly a nation that
                    already exists; from which we infer that Housecraft also tells us first how to
                    acquire a household and then how to conduct its affairs.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> By a Nation we
                    mean an assemblage of houses, lands, and property sufficient to enable the
                    inhabitants to lead a civilized life. This is proved by the fact that when such
                    a life is no longer possible for them, the tie itself which unites them is
                    dissolved. Moreover, it is with such a life in view that the association is
                    originally formed; and the object for which a thing exists and has come into
                    being is in fact the very essence of that particular thing.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>From this definition of a Nation, it is evident that the art of
                    Housecraft is older than that of Statecraft, since the Household, which it
                    creates, is older; being a component part of the Nation created by
                        Statecraft.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Accordingly we must consider the
                    nature of Housecraft, and what the Household, which it creates, actually
                        is.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> The component parts of a household are (l) human beings, and (2) goods and
                    chattels. And as households are no exception to the rule that the nature of a
                    thing is first studied in its barest and simplest form,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>we will follow Hesiod and begin by postulating
                    "Homestead first, and a woman; a plough-ox hardy to furrow." For the steading
                    takes precedence among our physical necessities, and the woman among our free
                    associates. It is, therefore, one of the tasks of Homecraft to set in order the
                    relation between man and woman; in other words, to see that it is what it ought
                    to be.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of occupations attendant on our goods and chattels, those come first which
                    are natural. Among these precedence is given to the one which cultivates the
                    land; those like mining, which extract wealth from it, take the second place.
                    Agriculture is the most honest of all such occupations; seeing that the wealth
                    it brings is not derived from other men. Herein it is distinguished from trade
                    and the wage-earning employments, which acquire wealth from others by their
                    consent; and from war, which wrings it from them perforce. It is also a natural
                    occupation; since by Nature's appointment all creatures receive sustenance from
                    their mother, <milestone n="1343b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>and mankind like the rest from their common mother the
                        earth.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> And besides all this, agriculture contributes notably to
                    the making of a manly character; because, unlike the mechanical arts, it does
                    not cripple and weaken the bodies of those engaged in it, but inures them to
                    exposure and toil and invigorates them to face the perils of war. For the
                    farmer's possessions, unlike those of other men, lie outside the city's
                        defences.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="3.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> When we turn our attention to the human part of the
                    household, it is the woman who makes the first claim upon it; &lt;for the
                    natural comes first, as we have said,&gt; and nothing is more natural than
                    the tie between female and male. For we have elsewhere laid down the
                    premiss<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 1.1252a.1">Aristot. Pol. 1.1</bibl>.</note> that Nature is intent on multiplying severally her types;
                    and this is true of every animal in particular. Neither the female, however, can
                    effect this without the male, nor the male without the female; whence the union
                    of the sexes has of necessity arisen.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="3.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now among the lower animals, this union is
                    irrational in character; it exists merely for the purpose of procreation, and
                    lasts only so long as the parents are occupied in producing their brood. In tame
                    animals, on the other hand, and those which possess a greater share of
                    intelligence, it has assumed a more complex form; for in their case we see more
                    examples of mutual help, goodwill, and co-operation. <milestone ed="P" n="3.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is, however, in the human species that this complexity
                    is most marked; since the co-operation between woman and man aims not merely at
                    existence, but at a happy <milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>existence.
                    Nor do mankind beget children merely to pay the service they owe to Nature, but
                    also that they may themselves receive a benefit; for the toil they undergo while
                    they are strong and their offspring is still weak is repaid by that offspring
                    when it in turn is grown strong and the parents by reason of age are
                        weak.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="3.4" unit="Loeb chap"/> At the same time Nature, by this cycle of changes,
                    fulfills her purpose of perpetuating existence; preserving the type when she is
                    unable to preserve the individual.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. GA 731b">Aristot. De Gen. An. 731b.</bibl></note> And so
                    with this purpose in view Divine Providence has fashioned the nature of man and
                    of woman for their partnership. For they are distinguished from each other by
                    the possession of faculties not adapted in every case to the same tasks, but in
                    some cases for opposite ones, though contributing to the same end. For
                    Providence made man stronger and woman weaker, <milestone n="1344a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>so that he in
                    virtue of his manly prowess may be more ready to defend the home, and she, by
                    reason of her timid nature, more ready to keep watch over it; and while he
                    brings in fresh supplies from without, she may keep safe what lies within. In
                    handicrafts again, woman was given a sedentary patience, though denied stamina
                    for endurance of exposure; while man, though inferior to her in quiet
                    employments, is endowed with vigor for every active occupation. In the
                    production of children both share alike; but each makes a different contribution
                    to their upbringing. It is the mother who nurtures, and the father who
                        educates.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="4.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> We begin then with the rules that should govern a man's
                    treatment of his wife. And the first of these forbids him to do her wrong; for
                    if he observes this, he is not likely himself to suffer wrong at her hands. As
                    the Pythagoreans declare, even the common rule or custom of mankind thus
                    ordains, forbidding all wrong to a wife as stringently as though she were a
                    suppliant whom one has raised from the hearthstone. And a man does wrong to his
                    wife when he associates with other women.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="4.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> As regards the intercourse of
                    marriage, wives should neither importune their husbands, nor be restless in
                    their absence; but a man should accustom his wife to be content whether he is at
                    home or away. Good also is the advice of Hesiod: <cit>
                        <quote type="verse">
                            <l met="dactylic">Take thee a maiden to wife, and teach her ways of
                                discretion.</l>
                        </quote>
                        <bibl n="Hes. WD 699">Hes. WD 699</bibl>
                    </cit> For differences of ways and habits are little conducive to
                        affection.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="4.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> As regards adornment: it is not well<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>that souls should approach one another in
                    borrowed plumes, nor is it well in the case of bodies. Intercourse which depends
                    &lt;for its charm&gt; upon outward adornment differs in no respect from
                    that of figures on the stage in their conventional attire.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="5.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of property, the
                    first and most indispensable kind is that which is also best and most amenable
                    to Housecraft; and this is the human chattel. Our first step therefore must be
                    to procure good slaves. Of slaves there are two kinds; those in positions of
                    trust, and the laborers. And since it is matter of experience that the character
                    of the young can be moulded by training, when we require to charge slaves with
                    tasks befitting the free, we have not only to procure the slaves, but to bring
                    them up &lt;for the trust&gt;.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="5.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> In our intercourse with slaves we must
                    neither suffer them to be insolent nor treat them with cruelty. A share of honor
                    should be given to those who are doing more of a freeman's work, and abundance
                    of food to those who are laboring with their hands. And whereas the use of wine
                    renders even free men insolent, so that in many countries they too refrain from
                    it&mdash;as, for instance, the Carthaginians do when they are on
                    campaign&mdash;it follows that we must either deny wine to slaves
                    altogether, or reserve it for rare occasions.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="5.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> We may apportion to our
                    slaves (1) work, (2) chastisement, and (3) food. If men are given food, but no
                    chastisement nor any work, they become insolent. <milestone n="1344b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>If they are made
                    to work, and are chastised, but stinted of their food, such treatment is
                    oppressive, and saps their strength. The remaining alternative, therefore, is to
                    give them work, and a sufficiency of food. Unless we pay men, we cannot control
                    them; and food is a slave's pay.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Slaves, again,
                    are no exception to the rule that men become worse when better conduct is not
                    followed by better treatment, but virtue and vice remain alike unrewarded.
                        <milestone ed="P" n="5.4" unit="Loeb chap"/> Accordingly we must keep watch
                    over our workers, suiting our dispensations and indulgences to their desert;
                    whether it be food or clothing, leisure or chastisement that we are
                    apportioning. Both in theory and in practice we must take for our model a
                    physician's freedom in prescribing his medicines; observing at the same time
                    that food differs from medicine in that it requires to be constantly
                        administered.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="5.5" unit="Loeb chap"/> The best laborers will be furnished by those races of
                    mankind which are neither wholly spiritless nor yet overbold. Each extreme has
                    its vice; the spiritless cannot endure hard labor, and the high-spirited will
                    not readily brook control.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="5.6" unit="Loeb chap"/> Every slave should have before his eyes a
                    definite goal or term of his labor. To set the prize of freedom before him is
                    both just and expedient; since having a prize to work for, and a time defined
                    for its attainment, he will put his heart into his labors. We should, moreover,
                    take hostages &lt;for our slaves' fidelity&gt; by allowing them to beget
                    children; and avoid the practice of purchasing many slaves of the same
                    nationality, as men avoid doing in towns. We should also keep festivals and give
                    treats, more on the slaves account than on that of the freemen;<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>since the free have a fuller share in those
                    enjoyments for the sake of which these institutions exist.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> There are four
                    qualities which the head of a household must possess in dealing with his
                    property. Firstly, he must have the faculty of acquiring, and secondly that of
                    preserving what he has acquired; otherwise there is no more benefit in acquiring
                    than in baling with a colander, or in the proverbial wine-jar with a hole in the
                    bottom. Thirdly and fourthly, he must know how to improve his property, and how
                    to make use of it; since these are the ends for which the powers of acquisition
                    and of preservation are sought.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> Everything we possess should be duly classified ;
                    and the amount of our productive property exceed that of the unproductive.
                    Produce should be so employed that we do not risk all our possessions at once.
                    For the safe keeping of our property, we shall do well to adopt the Persian and
                    Laconian systems. Athenian housecraft has, however, some advantages. The
                    Athenian buys immediately with the produce of his sales, and the smaller
                    households keep no idle deposits in store.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> Under the Persian system, the
                    master himself undertook the entire disposition and supervision of the
                    household, following the practice which
                    Dion used to remark in Dionysius. No one, indeed, takes the same
                    care of another's property as of his own; so that, as far as is possible,
                        <milestone n="1345a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>each man ought to attend to his affairs in person. We may
                    commend also a pair of sayings, one attributed to a Persian and the other to a
                    Libyan. The former on being asked what best conditions a horse, replied "His
                    master's eye."<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Ec.                         12">Xen. Ec.
                        12</bibl>.</note> The Libyan, when asked what kind of manure is best,
                    answered "The master's footprints."<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.4" unit="Loeb chap"/> The master and mistress should, therefore,
                    give personal supervision, each to his or her special department of the
                    household work. In small households, an occasional inspection will suffice; in
                    estates managed through stewards, inspections must be frequent. For in
                    stewardship as in other matters there can be no good copy without a good
                    example; and if the master and mistress do not attend diligently to their
                    estate, their deputies will certainly not do so.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.5" unit="Loeb chap"/> Moreover, as such habits are
                    both commendable for moral reasons and also conducive to good management, the
                    master and mistress will do well to rise earlier than their servants and to
                    retire later; to treat their home as a city, and never leave it unguarded; nor
                    ever, by night or by day, to postpone a task which ought to be done. Rising
                    before daylight is also to be commended; it is a healthy habit, and gives more
                    time for the management of the household as well as for liberal
                        studies.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.6" unit="Loeb chap"/> We have remarked that on small holdings the Athenian
                    method of disposing of the produce is advantageous.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>On large estates, after the amount for the year's or the
                    month's outlay has been set apart, it should be handed to the overseers; and so
                    also with implements, whether for daily or for occasional use. In addition, an
                    inspection of implements and stores should be made periodically, so that
                    remainders and deficiencies may alike be noted.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.7" unit="Loeb chap"/> In constructing a homestead,
                    we have to provide for the stock which it is to shelter, and for its health and
                    well-being. Providing for the stock involves questions such as these: What type
                    of building is best for the storage of crops and of clothing? How are we to
                    store the dry crops, and how the moist ones? Of the other stock, how is the
                    living to be housed, and how the dead? and what accommodation are we to make for
                    slaves and free, for women and men, for foreigners and fellow-citizens? For
                    well-being and health, again, the homestead should be airy in summer, and sunny
                    in winter.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="6.8" unit="Loeb chap"/> A homestead possessing these qualities would be longer
                    than it is deep; and its main front would face the south. On large estates,
                    moreover, it seems worth while to instal as porter a man incapable of other
                    work, to keep his eye on what passes in and out. <milestone n="1345b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>That implements
                    may be ready for use, the Laconian practice should be followed. Each should be
                    kept in its own place; thus it will always be to hand, and not require
                seeking.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Book" n="2">
				<p>
                    <milestone n="1345b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="7" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.1" unit="Loeb chap"/>Right administration of a household demands in the first place familiarity
                    with the sphere of one's action<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or, "the
                        localities wherein we work."</note>; in the second Place, good natural
                    endowments; and in the third, an uprights and industrious way of life. For the
                    lack of any one of these qualifications will involve many a failure in the task
                    one takes in hand.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Of such administrations there
                    are four main types, under which all others may be classified. We have the
                    administration of a king; of the governors under him; of a free state; and of a
                    private citizen.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of these, that of a king is the most extensive, yet at
                    the same time the simplest. A governor's office is also very extensive, but
                    divided into a great variety of departments. The administration of a free state
                    is again very varied, but it is the easiest to conduct; while that, of a private
                    individual presents the like variety, but within limits which are narrowest of
                    all. For the most part, all four will of necessity cover the same ground; we
                    will, however, take them in turn, and see what is especially characteristic of
                        each.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Taking first the royal administration,
                    we see that while theoretically its power is unlimited,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>it is in practice concerned with four departments,
                    namely currency, exports, imports, and expenditure.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> Taking these severally, I
                    assign to that of currency the seasonable regulation of prices; to imports and
                    exports, the profitable disposition, at any given time, of the dues received
                    from provincial governors; and to expenditure, the reduction of outgoings as
                    occasion may serve, and the question of meeting expenses by currency or by
                        commodities.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.4" unit="Loeb chap"/> The second kind of administration, that of the governor,
                    is concerned with six different classes of revenue; those, namely, arising from
                    agriculture, from the special products of the country, from markets, from taxes,
                    from cattle, and from other sources.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Taking these
                    in turn, the first and most important of them is revenue from agriculture, which
                    some call tithe and some produce-tax.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Boeckh
                        translates <foreign lang="greek">E)KFO/RION</foreign> "Grundsteuer." But how
                        then does it differ from <foreign lang="greek">TW=N KATA\ GH=N
                        TELW=N</foreign> below?</note> The second is that from special products; in
                    one place gold, in another silver, in another copper, and so on. Third in
                    importance is revenue from markets, <milestone n="1346a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>and fourth that which arises
                    from taxes on land and on sales. In the fifth place we have revenue from cattle,
                    called tithe or first-fruits; and in the sixth, revenue from other sources,
                    which we term poll-tax, or tax on industry.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.5" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of our third kind of
                    administration, that of a free state, the most important revenue is that arising
                    from the special products of the country. Next follows revenue from markets and
                    occupations; and finally that from every-day transactions.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or (understanding <foreign lang="greek">LEITOURGIW=N</foreign>) "regular public services." </note>
                    <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.6" unit="Loeb chap"/>
                    Fourthly and lastly, we must consider the administration of a private citizen.
                    It is difficult to reduce this to rules owing to the necessary variety of its
                    aims; yet it is the most limited of the four, because both revenues and expenses
                    are &lt;comparatively&gt; small. Taking its revenues in turn, the chief
                    are those from agriculture; next in importance, those from other every-day
                    occupations; while third comes interest on money. Apart from all these, there is
                    a matter common to all kinds of administration which is best considered at this
                    particular point, and deserves more than cursory attention. This is the
                    importance of keeping expenditure within the limits of revenue.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.7" unit="Loeb chap"/> Having thus
                    enumerated the divisions of our subject, we must next consider whether the
                    province or the free state with which we are concerned is able to produce all
                    the forms of revenue we have just detailed<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>or at least the chief of them; &lt;and this being
                    known&gt; must make the best use of what we have. Next we must inquire what
                    kinds of revenue, at present wholly lacking, are yet potentially existent; what
                    kinds, though now small, may with care be increased, and how far certain items
                    of present expenditure may without prejudice to the commonwealth be
                        diminished.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="1.8" unit="Loeb chap"/> Having spoken thus of administrations and their various
                    departments, we have further proceeded to collect such instances as we deemed
                    noteworthy of the means adopted by certain statesmen in times past for the
                    replenishment of the treasury, and also of their skill in administration. These
                    anecdotes &lt;which follow&gt;, seemed to us by no means lacking in
                    utility; being capable from time to time of application by others to the
                    business they themselves have in hand.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.1" unit="Loeb chap"/> Cypselus of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> had made a vow that if he became
                    master of the city, he would offer to Zeus the entire property of the
                    Corinthians. Accordingly he commanded them to make a return of their
                    possessions; <milestone n="1346b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>which done, he took from each a tenth part, and told them to
                    employ the remainder in trading. A year later, he repeated the process. And so
                    in ten years' time it came to pass that Cypselus received the entire amount
                    which he had dedicated; while the Corinthians on their part had replaced all
                    that they had paid him.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.2" unit="Loeb chap"/> Lygdamis of <placeName key="perseus,Naxos City">Naxos</placeName>, after driving into exile a party of the inhabitants, found
                    that no one would give him a fair price for their property. He therefore sold it
                    to the exiled owners. The exiles had left behind them a number of works of art
                    destined for temple offerings, which lay in certain workshops in an unfinished
                    condition. These Lygdamis proceeded to sell to the exiles and whoso else would
                    buy them; allowing each purchaser to have his name engraved on the
                        offering.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.3" unit="Loeb chap"/> The people of <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, being in need of funds, sold such dedicated lands as
                    belonged to the State; those under crops, for a term of years, and those
                    uncultivated, in perpetuity. In like manner they sold lands appropriated to
                    religious celebrations or ancestral cults, not excepting those that were on
                    private estates<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See <bibl n="Lys. 7">Lys. 7</bibl>,
                        the seventh Speech of the Athenian orator Lysias.</note>; for the owners of
                    the surrounding land were ready to give a high price for them. To the
                    dispossessed celebrants &lt;they assigned&gt; such other public lands
                    surrounding the gymnasium, the agora, or the harbor,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>as belonged to the State. Moreover they claimed as
                    public property all open spaces where anything was sold, together with the
                    sea-fisheries, the traffic in salt, and the trade of professional conjurors,
                    soothsayers, charm-sellers, and the like; exacting from all these one-third of
                    their gains. The right of changing money they sold to a single bank, whose
                    proprietor was given a monopoly of the sale and purchase of coin, protected
                    under penalty of confiscation.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And whereas
                    previously the rights of citizenship were by law confined to those whose parents
                    were both citizens, lack of funds, induced them to offer citizenship to him who
                    had one citizen parent on payment of the sum of thirty minae.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A mina of silver (1 lb. 5 oz. avoirdupois) was coined into
                        100 drachmae, each being an artisan's ordinary daily wage.</note>
                    <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On another occasion, when food and funds were
                    both scarce, they called home all vessels that were trading in the <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>. On the merchants protesting, they were
                    at length allowed to trade on payment of a tithe of their profits. This tax of
                    10 per cent was also extended to purchases of every kind. <milestone n="1347a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It happened that certain aliens residing in the city had lent
                    money on the security of citizens' property. As these aliens did not possess the
                    right of holding such property, the people offered to recognize the title of
                    anyone who chose to pay into the treasury one third of the amount
                        secured.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.4" unit="Loeb chap"/> Hippias of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> offered for sale upper stories that projected over the
                    public streets,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. Goethe,<title>Warheit und
                            Dichtung</title>, Book I. "In Frankfurt, as in several ancient cities,
                        those who had erected wooden buildings had sought to obtain more room by
                        allowing the first and higher floors to overhang in the street. . . . At
                        last a law was carried that in all entirely new houses the first floor alone
                        should project; above that, the wall should be perpendicular." The poet's
                        father, wishing to rebuild his house without sacrifice of floor-space,
                        underpinned the upper stories and renewed the building piecemeal from below.
                        Cf. also 14.</note> together with flights of steps, railings, and doors that
                    opened outwards. The owners of the buildings bought them, and in this way a
                    large sum of money was collected.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He also called
                        in<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Lit. "rendered invalid." </note> the
                    existing currency, promising to pay the holders at a fixed rate. But when they
                    came to receive the new mintage, he reissued the old coins.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Those who were expecting to equip a war-vessel or preside over
                    a tribe or train a chorus or undertake the expense of some other public service
                    of the kind, he allowed, if they chose, to commute the service for a moderate
                    sum, and to be enrolled on the list of those who had performed it.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Moreover, whenever a citizen died, the priestess of the
                    temple of Athena on the Acropolis<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This was the
                        public treasury, like the Temple of Saturnus at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</note> was to receive one quart
                    measure of barley, one of wheat, and a silver obolus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">1/6 of the drachma. See 3 above.</note> And when a child was
                    born, the father paid the same dues.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.5" unit="Loeb chap"/> The Athenian colonists at <placeName key="perseus,Potidaia">Potidaea</placeName>, being in need of funds for the war,
                    agreed that all should make a return of their property for assessment of
                        tax.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>But instead of each returning
                    the entire amount to his own parish, properties were to be assessed separately,
                    each in its own locality, so that the poor might propose a reduced assessment;
                    while those without any &lt;landed&gt; property were assessed at two
                    minae a head. On these assessments each man paid the State the full amount of
                    the war-tax.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.6" unit="Loeb chap"/> The city of <placeName key="perseus,Antissa">Antissa</placeName> had been accustomed to celebrate the festival of Dionysus
                    with great magnificence. Year by year<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or "All
                        through the year." </note> great provision was made for the occasion, and
                    costly sacrifices were prepared. Now one year the city found itself in need of
                    funds; and shortly before the festival, on the proposal of a citizen named
                    Sosipolis, the people after vowing that they would next year offer to Dionysus a
                    double amount, collected all that had been provided and sold it. In this way
                    they realized a large sum of money to meet their necessity.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.7" unit="Loeb chap"/> On one occasion
                    the people of <placeName key="perseus,Lampsakos">Lampsacus</placeName> were expecting
                    to be attacked by a large fleet of triremes.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">War-ships, each propelled by some 174 rowers ranked in three tiers.</note>
                    The price of barley meal being then four drachmae for a bushel and a half, they
                    instructed the retailers to sell it at six drachmae. Oil, which was at three
                    drachmae for six pints, was to be sold at four drachmae and a half, and wine and
                    other commodities at a proportionate increase. In this way the retailer got the
                    original price, <milestone n="1347b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>while the State took the addition and filled its
                        treasury.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.8" unit="Loeb chap"/> The people of <placeName key="tgn,7018769">Heraclea</placeName>, being about to dispatch a fleet of forty ships against
                    the lords of <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, were at a loss
                    for the necessary funds. They therefore bought up all the merchants' stock of
                    corn and oil and wine and other marketable commodities, agreeing to pay at a
                    future date. The merchants were well satisfied that they had disposed of their
                    cargoes without breaking bulk; and the people, advancing two months' pay to
                    their armament, sent along with it a fleet of merchant-vessels laden with the
                    commodities, every ship being in charge of a public official. When the
                    expedition reached its goal, the men purchased from these officials all they
                    needed. In this way, the money was collected before the leaders again paid their
                    men; so that the same payment sufficed until the expedition returned
                        home.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.9" unit="Loeb chap"/> When the Samians entreated the Lacedaemonians for money
                    to enable them to return to their country, the Lacedaemonians passed a
                    resolution that they and their servants and their beasts of burden should go
                    without food for one day; and that the expense each one thus saved should be
                    given to the Samians.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.10" unit="Loeb chap"/> The people
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcedon">Chalcedon</placeName> had a large number
                    of mercenary troops in their city, to whom they could not pay the wages they
                    owed. Accordingly they made proclamation that anyone, either citizen or alien,
                    who had right of reprisal against any city or individual, and wished to exercise
                    it, should have his name entered on a list. A large number of names was
                    enrolled, and the people thus obtained a specious pretext for exercising
                    reprisal upon ships that were passing on their way to the <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>. They accordingly arrested the ships
                    and fixed a period within which they would consider any claims that might be
                    made in respect of them. Having now a large fund in hand, they paid off the
                    mercenaries, and set up a tribunal to decide the claims; and those whose goods
                    had been unjustly seized were compensated out of the revenues of the
                        state.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.11" unit="Loeb chap"/> At <placeName key="perseus,Cyzicus">Cyzicus</placeName>,
                    civil strife broke out between the democratic and oligarchic parties. The former
                    proved victorious, and the rich citizens were placed under arrest. But as the
                    city owed money to its troops, a resolution was passed that the lives of those
                    under arrest should be spared, and that they should be allowed to depart into
                    exile on paying a sum of money to the state.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.12" unit="Loeb chap"/> At <placeName key="perseus,Chios City">Chios</placeName> there was a law that all debts should be
                    entered on a public register. Being in need of funds, <milestone n="1348a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>the people
                    resolved that debtors should pay their debts into the treasury, and that the
                    state should meet the creditors' interest out of its revenues until its former
                    prosperity returned.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.13" unit="Loeb chap"/> Mausolus lord of <placeName key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName> received from the King of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Probably Artaxerxes II.
                        who reigned <dateRange from="-405" to="-359">405</dateRange>-359
                    B.C.</note> a demand for tribute. Therefore he summoned the wealthiest men in
                    his dominion, and told them that the King was asking for the tribute, and he had
                    not the means of paying it. Men whom he had previously suborned at once came
                    forward and declared what each was ready to contribute. With this example before
                    them, they who were wealthier than these, partly in shame and partly in alarm,
                    promised and paid much larger sums than the others.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Being again in lack of funds, Mausolus summoned a public meeting of the people
                    of Mylassa and told them that the King of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> was preparing to attack him; and that Mylassa his capital
                    city was unfortified. He therefore bade the citizens contribute each as
                    liberally as he could, saying that what they now paid in would afford security
                    to the rest of their possessions. By these means he obtained large
                    contributions. But though he kept the money, he declared that heaven, for the
                    present, forbade the building of the walls.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.14" unit="Loeb chap"/> Condalus, who was a
                    lieutenant-governor under Mausolus, whenever on his progress through the country
                    he was presented with a sheep,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>a pig,
                    or a calf, had a record made of the donor's name and of the date. He then bade
                    the man take the beast home and keep it until he should again pass that way.
                    After what he considered a sufficient interval, he would demand the beast
                    together with such profits as he reckoned it had produced. All trees, too, which
                    projected over the king's highway, or fell thereon, he sold as profits accruing
                    to the State.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When one of his soldiers died, he
                    charged a drachma for the right of passing the body through the gates. This was
                    not only a source of revenue, but a check on the commanders, who were thus
                    prevented from falsifying the date of the man's death.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Noticing that the Lycians were fond of wearing their hair long,
                    Condalus proclaimed that a dispatch had arrived from the King ordering him to
                    send hair to make forelocks for his horses; and that Mausolus had therefore
                    instructed him to shave their heads. However, if they would pay him a fixed sum
                    per head, he would send to <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> for
                    hair. They were glad to comply with his demand, and a large sum was collected,
                    the number of those taxed being great.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.15" unit="Loeb chap"/> Aristoteles of <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Mentioned by Proclus in his commentary on the <title>Timaeus</title> of
                        Plato. A coin of <placeName key="tgn,7018000">Phocaea</placeName> is extant
                        bearing the name.</note> when governor of <placeName key="tgn,7018000">Phocaea</placeName>, found himself in need of funds. Noticing that there
                    were at <placeName key="tgn,7018000">Phocaea</placeName> two opposing parties,
                    he held a secret conference with one of them, <milestone n="1348b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>at which he
                    declared that the other party was offering him money if he would favor their
                    pretensions; that he, however, preferred to receive from those now before him,
                    and to entrust to them the administration of the city. On hearing this, they
                    immediately contributed the money he asked, and gave it him. Thereupon he told
                    the other party what he had received from them; and they in turn promised him at
                    least an equal amount. Having thus taken the money of both factions, he effected
                    a reconciliation between them.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He also observed
                    that there were many law-suits pending between the citizens, and that they had
                    grave and long-standing plaints against one another which had arisen in course
                    of war. He therefore appointed a tribunal, and made proclamation that all who
                    failed to appear before it within a stated period should lose the right to a
                    legal decision of their outstanding claims. Then, by taking into his own hands
                    the court-fees for a number of suits, and also those appeal-cases which involved
                    penalties, and receiving [through others] money from both sides, he obtained
                    altogether a very considerable sum.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.16" unit="Loeb chap"/> The people of Clazomenae, suffering from
                    dearth of grain and scarcity of funds, passed a resolution that any private
                    citizens who had stores of oil should lend it to the State at
                        interest;<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>this being a produce
                    which their land bears in abundance. The loan arranged, they hired vessels and
                    sent them to the depots whence they obtained their grain, &lt;and bought a
                    consignment&gt; on security of the value of the oil.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The same people, owing their mercenaries twenty talents of pay
                    and being unable to find it, were giving the leaders of the troop four talents
                    of interest each year. But failing to reduce the capital debt, and committed to
                    this fruitless drain on their revenue, they struck an iron coinage of twenty
                    talents, bearing the face-value of the silver. This they distributed
                    proportionately among the wealthiest citizens, and received from them silver to
                    the same amount. Through this expedient, the private citizens possessed a
                    currency which was good for their daily needs, and the state was relieved of its
                    debt. Next, they proceeded to pay interest out of revenue to those who had
                    advanced the silver; and little by little distributed repayment among them,
                    recalling at the same time the currency of iron.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><bibl n="Plut. Lyc. 1.1">Plut. Lycurgus</bibl> speaks of an iron
                        currency at <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, and <bibl n="Sen. Ben. 1.1">Seneca De beneficiis</bibl> of a leather one. These,
                        not being exchangeable abroad, threw the nation upon its own resources and
                        prevented the import of luxuries.</note>
                    <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.17" unit="Loeb chap"/> The
                    people of Selybria had a law, passed in time of famine, which forbade the export
                    of grain. On one occasion, however, they were in need of funds; and as they
                    possessed large stores of grain, they passed a resolution that citizens should
                    deliver up their corn to the state at the regular fixed price, <milestone n="1349a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>each
                    retaining for himself a year's supply. They then granted right of export to any
                    who desired it, fixing what they deemed a suitable price.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.18" unit="Loeb chap"/> At <placeName key="perseus,Abydos,Mysia">Abydos</placeName> civil strife had caused the land to
                    remain uncultivated; while the resident aliens, to whom the city was already
                    indebted, refused to make any further advances. A resolution was accordingly
                    passed that anyone who would might lend money to enable the farmers to cultivate
                    their land, on the understanding that the lender had the first claim on its
                    produce; others taking from what was then left.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.19" unit="Loeb chap"/> The people of <placeName key="perseus,Ephesos">Ephesus</placeName>, being in need of funds, passed a law
                    forbidding their women to wear gold, and ordering them to lend the State what
                    gold they had in their possession.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>They also
                    offered to any citizen who was willing to pay a fixed sum the right of having
                    his name inscribed on a certain pillar of their temple<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This temple, dedicated to Artemis, was restored with great
                        magnificence after its destruction by fire in <date value="-356">356</date>
                        B.C. For its fame see <bibl n="Acts 19">Acts 19</bibl>. Portions of the
                        sculptured pillars are to be seen in the British Museum.</note> as the donor
                        thereof.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.20" unit="Loeb chap"/> Dionysius of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, being desirous of collecting funds, called a public
                    assembly, and declared that Demeter had appeared to him, and bade him convey all
                    the women's ornaments into her temple. That he himself had done so with the
                    ornaments of his own household; and the others must now follow his example, and
                    thereby avoid any visitation of the goddess's anger. Anyone who failed to comply
                    would, he declared, be guilty of sacrilege.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>Through fear of the goddess as well as of the despot, all the
                    citizens brought in whatever they had. Then Dionysius, after sacrificing to the
                    goddess, removed the ornaments to his own treasury as a loan which he had
                    borrowed from her. As time went on, the women again appeared with precious
                    ornaments. Dionysius thereupon issued a decree that any woman who desired to
                    wear gold should make an offering of a fixed amount in the temple.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Intending to build a fleet of triremes, Dionysius knew
                    that he should require funds for the purpose. He therefore called an assembly
                    and declared that a certain city was offered to him by traitors, and he needed
                    money to pay them. The citizens therefore must contribute two staters
                        apiece.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The stater was a Persian gold coin
                        worth 20 drachmae. (See 3.) </note> The money was paid; but after two or
                    three days, Dionysius, pretending that the plot had failed, thanked the citizens
                    and returned to each his contribution. In this way he won the confidence of the
                    citizens; so that when he again asked for money, they contributed in the
                    expectation that they would receive it back. But this time he kept it for
                    building the fleet.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On another occasion being in
                    straits for silver he minted a coinage of tin, and summoning a public assembly,
                    spoke at length in its favor. The citizens perforce voted that everyone should
                    regard as silver, and not as tin, whatever he received. <milestone n="1349b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Again being in need of funds, he requested the citizens to
                    contribute. On their declaring that they had not the wherewithal, he brought out
                    the furnishings of his palace and offered them for sale, pretending to be
                    compelled through lack of money. At the sale, he had a list made of the articles
                    and their purchasers; and when they had all paid, he commanded every one to
                    bring back the article he had bought.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Finding that
                    because of his imposts the citizens were ceasing to rear sheep and cattle, he
                    made proclamation that he needed no more money until a certain
                    &lt;date&gt;; so that those who now became possessed of any stock would
                    not be liable to taxation. A large number of citizens lost no time in acquiring
                    a quantity of sheep and cattle, on the understanding that they would be free of
                    impost. But Dionysius, when he thought the fitting time was come, had them all
                    valued and imposed a tax. The citizens were angry at being thus deceived, and
                    proceeded to kill and sell their beasts. On Dionysius's making a decree that
                    only such beasts should be slain as were needed each day, the owners retorted by
                    offering their animals as sacrifices; whereupon the despot forbade the sacrifice
                    of female beasts.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Once more funds were lacking,
                    and Dionysius ordered a list to be made for him of all houses whose heirs were
                    orphan. Having obtained a complete list, he made use of the orphans' property
                    until each should come of age.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>After the capture
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Rhegion">Rhegium</placeName>, he summoned a meeting of
                    the citizens, and told them why he had a good right to sell them as
                        slaves.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>If, however, they would
                    pay him the expenses of the war and three minae<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See 3.</note> a head besides, he would release them. The people of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rhegion">Rhegium</placeName> brought forth all their
                    hoards; the poor borrowed from the wealthier and from the foreigners resident in
                    the city; and so the amount demanded was paid. But though he received this money
                    from them, none the less he sold them all for slaves, having succeeded
                    &lt;by his trick&gt; in bringing to light the hoarded goods which they
                    had previously concealed.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On another occasion he
                    had borrowed money from the citizens, promising to repay it. On their demanding
                    its return, he bade each bring him, under pain of death, whatever silver he
                    possessed. This silver when brought he coined into drachmae each bearing the
                    face value of two: with these he repaid the &lt;previous&gt; debt and
                    also what had just been brought in.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He also made a
                    raid on Tyrrhenia with a hundred ships, and rifled the temple of Leucothea of a
                    large amount of gold and silver, besides a quantity of works of art. But being
                    aware that his sailors too had taken much plunder, <milestone n="1350a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>he made
                    proclamation that each should bring him, under pain of death, one-half of what
                    he had; the remainder of their takings they might keep. On the understanding
                    that if they brought in half their plunder they would retain the rest in
                    security, they obeyed. But when Dionysius had got the treasure into his hands,
                    he commanded them to bring him the other half as well.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.21" unit="Loeb chap"/> The people of
                    Mende used to meet the expenses of administration from harbor and other duties,
                    but refrained from collecting the imposts on land and on houses. They kept,
                    however, a register of the owners, and when the state was in need of funds, they
                    collected the arrears. Meanwhile the owners had the advantage of trafficking
                    with their whole property undiminished by any payment of percentages.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The same city being at war with <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> and needing funds, passed a
                    resolution that all the slaves they possessed, with the exception of one male
                    and one female apiece, should be sold on behalf of the State, which was thus
                    enabled to raise a loan from private citizens.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or: "that citizens should sell to the state what slaves they possessed . .
                        . as the equivalent of a loan from private persons to the city &lt;of
                        the slaves' value&gt;." </note>
                    <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.22" unit="Loeb chap"/>
                    Callistratus, when in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, caused
                    the harbor-dues, which were usually sold for twenty talents, to produce twice as
                    much. For noticing that only the wealthier men were accustomed to buy them
                    because the sureties for the twenty talents were obliged to show talent for
                        talent,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>he issued a proclamation
                    that anyone might buy the dues on furnishing securities for one-third of the
                    amount, or as much more as could be procured in each case.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.23" unit="Loeb chap"/> Timotheus of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> during his campaign
                    against <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> was short of
                    silver, and issued to his men a copper coinage instead. On their complaining, he
                    told them that all the merchants and retailers would accept it in lieu of
                    silver. But the merchants he instructed to buy in turn with the copper they
                    received such produce of the land as was for sale, as well as any booty brought
                    to them; such copper as remained on their hands he would exchange for
                        silver.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>During the campaign of <placeName key="perseus,Corcyra City">Corcyra</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Apparently in <date value="-375">375</date> B.C. See the end of Xenophon's
                            fifth Book of<title>Hellenica</title><bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5">Xen. Hell. 5</bibl>.</note>
                    this same Timotheus was reduced to sore straits. His men demanded their pay;
                    refused to obey his orders; and declared they would desert to the enemy.
                    Accordingly he summoned a meeting and told them that the stormy weather was
                    delaying the arrival of the silver he expected; meanwhile, as he had on hand
                    such abundance of provisions, he would charge them nothing for the three months'
                    ration of grain already advanced. <milestone n="1350b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>The men, unable to believe that
                    Timotheus would have sacrificed so large a sum to them unless he was in truth
                    expecting the money, made no further claim for pay until he had completed his
                        dispositions.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At the siege of <placeName key="perseus,Samos City">Samos</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In
                            <date value="-366">366</date> B.C.</note> Timotheus sold the crops and
                    other country property to the besieged Samians themselves, and thus obtained
                    plenty of money to pay his men. But finding the camp was short of provisions
                    owing to the arrival of reinforcements, he forbade the sale of milled corn, or
                    of any measure less than 1 1/2 bushels of corn or 8 1/2 gallons of wine or oil.
                    Accordingly the officers bought supplies wholesale and issued them to their men;
                    the reinforcements thenceforth brought their own provisions, and sold any
                    surplus on their departure. In this way the needs of the soldiers were
                    satisfactorily met.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.24" unit="Loeb chap"/> Didales the Persian was able to provide for the daily
                    needs of his mercenaries from the enemy's country; but had no coined money to
                    give them. When their pay became due, and they demanded it, he had recourse to
                    the following trick.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>He called a
                    meeting, and told the men that he had plenty of money, but that it was stored in
                    a certain fortress, which he named. He then broke up his encampment and marched
                    in that direction. On reaching the neighborhood of the fortress, he himself went
                    on ahead, and entering the place seized all the silver vessels in the temples.
                    He then loaded his mules in such a way that this plate was exposed, thus
                    suggesting that silver formed the entire load; and so continued his march. The
                    soldiers, beholding the plate and supposing that they convoyed a full load of
                    silver, were cheered by the expectation of their pay. They were informed however
                    by Didales that they would have to take it to <placeName key="tgn,7002339">Amisus</placeName> to be coined&mdash;a journey of many days, and in
                    the winter season. And during all this time, he continued to employ the army
                    without giving it more than its necessary rations.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Moreover, all the craftsmen in the army, and the hucksters who traded with the
                    soldiers by barter, were under his personal control, and enjoyed a complete
                        monopoly.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.25" unit="Loeb chap"/> When <placeName key="perseus,Taos">Taos</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Called Tachos (<foreign lang="greek">*TAXW/S</foreign>) by Xenophon and Plutarch. Perhaps that form should be
                        restored here. (Bonitz and Susemihl.) The name recurs in 37.</note> king of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, needed funds for an
                    expedition he was making, Chabrias of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> advised him to inform the priests that to save expense it
                    was necessary to suppress some of the temples together with the majority of the
                    attendant priests. <milestone n="1351a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>On hearing this, each priesthood, being anxious to retain
                    their own temple, offered him money from their private possessions &lt;as
                    well as from the temple funds&gt;. When the king had thus received money
                    from them all, Chabrias bade him tell the priests to spend on the temple-service
                    and on their own maintenance one-tenth of what they formerly spent, and lend him
                    the remainder until he had made peace with the King &lt;of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>&gt;.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Moreover, each inhabitant was to contribute a stated proportion of his
                    household and personal possessions; and when grain was sold, buyer and seller
                    were each to contribute, apart from the price, one obol per artabe<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The artabe was a Persian measure containing
                        nearly 50 quarts. The obol was 1/6 of a drachma of silver.</note>; while a
                    tax of one tenth was to be imposed on profits arising from ships and workshops
                    and other sources of gain.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Again, when <placeName key="perseus,Taos">Taos</placeName> was on the point of setting out from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, Chabrias advised him to make
                    requisition of all uncoined gold and silver in the possession of the
                    inhabitants; and when most of them complied, he bade the king make use of the
                    bullion, and refer the lenders to the governors of his provinces for
                    compensation out of the taxes.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.26" unit="Loeb chap"/> Iphicrates of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> provided Cotys with money for a force which he had
                    collected in the following manner.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>He
                    bade him order &lt;each&gt; of his subjects to sow for him a piece of
                    land bearing 4 1/2 bushels. A large quantity of grain was thus gathered, from
                    the price of which, when brought to the depots on the coast, the king obtained
                    as much money as he wanted.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.27" unit="Loeb chap"/> Cotys of <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> asked the people of Peirinthus for a loan to enable him to
                    raise an army. On their refusing, he begged them at any rate to let him have
                    some of their citizens to garrison certain fortresses, and release for active
                    service the men who were there on duty. They readily complied, thinking thus to
                    obtain control of the fortresses. But Cotys placed in custody the men they sent,
                    and told the citizens that they might have them back when they had sent him the
                    amount of the loan he desired.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.28" unit="Loeb chap"/> Mentor of <placeName key="tgn,7011265">Rhodes</placeName>, after taking Hermias prisoner and seizing his fortresses,
                    left in their various districts the officials appointed by him. By this means he
                    restored their confidence, so that they all took again to themselves the
                    property they had hidden or had sent secretly out of the country. Then Mentor
                    arrested them and stripped them of all they had. <milestone n="1351b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.29" unit="Loeb chap"/> Memnon of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7011265">Rhodes</placeName>, on making himself master of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Lampsakos">Lampsacus</placeName>, found he was in need of
                    funds. He therefore assessed upon the wealthiest inhabitants a quantity of
                    silver, telling them that they should recover it from the other citizens. But
                    when the other citizens made their contributions, Memnon said they must lend him
                    this money also, fixing a certain date for its repayment.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Again being in need of funds, he asked for a contribution, to
                    be recovered, as he said, from the city revenues. The citizens complied,
                    thinking that they would speedily reimburse themselves. But when the revenue
                    payments came in, he declared that he must have these also, and would repay the
                    lenders subsequently with interest.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>His mercenary
                    troops he requested to forgo six days' pay and rations each year, on the plea
                    that on those days they were neither on garrison duty nor on the march nor did
                    they incur any expense. (He referred to the days omitted from alternate
                        months.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">As the moon's cycle is completed in
                        29 1/2 days, it was customary to alternate "hollow" months of 29 days with
                        the "full" months of 30 days. Memnon paid his men by the month, but deducted
                        a day's pay every "hollow" month.</note>) <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Moreover, being accustomed previously to issue his men's rations of corn on
                    the second day of the month, in the first month he postponed the distribution
                    for three days, and in the second month for five; proceeding in this fashion
                    until at length it took place on the last day of the month.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.30" unit="Loeb chap"/> Charidemus of
                    Oreus, being in occupation of certain fortress-towns in <placeName key="tgn,5004216">Aeolis</placeName>,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>and threatened with an attack by Artabazus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the circumstances, and a (hostile) account of this
                        commander's adventures, see Demosthenes,<title>Against
                            Aristocrates</title><bibl n="Dem. 23">Dem. 23</bibl>.</note> was in need of
                    money to pay his troops. After their first contributions, the inhabitants
                    declared they had no more to give. Charidemus then issued a proclamation to the
                    town he deemed wealthiest, bidding the inhabitants send away to another fortress
                    all the coin and valuables they possessed, under convoy which he would provide.
                    He himself openly set the example with his own goods, and prevailed on them to
                    comply. But when he had conducted them a little way out of the town, he made an
                    inventory of their goods, took all he wanted, and led them home again.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He had also issued a proclamation in the cities he
                    governed forbidding anyone to keep arms in his house, under pain of a stated
                    fine. At first, however, he took no care to enforce it, nor did he make any
                    inquisition; so that the people treated his proclamation as nugatory, and made
                    no attempt to get rid of what arms each possessed. Then Charidemus unexpectedly
                    ordered a search to be made from house to house, and exacted the penalty from
                    those who were found in possession of arms.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.31" unit="Loeb chap"/> A Macedonian named
                    Philoxenus, who was governor of <placeName key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>,
                    being in need of funds proclaimed that he intended to celebrate the festival of
                    Dionysus. <milestone n="1352a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>The wealthiest inhabitants were selected to provide the
                    choruses, and were informed what they were expected to furnish. Noticing their
                    disinclination, Philoxenus sent to them privately and asked what they would give
                    to be relieved of the duty. They told him they were prepared to pay a much
                    larger sum than they expected to spend &lt;on the choruses&gt; in order
                    to avoid the trouble and the interruption of their business. Philoxenus accepted
                    their offers, and proceeded to enrol a second levy. These also paid; and at last
                    he received what he desired from each company.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.32" unit="Loeb chap"/> Euaises the Syrian, when
                    governor of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, received information
                    that the local governors were meditating rebellion. He therefore summoned them
                    to the palace and proceeded to hang them all, sending word to their relations
                    that they were in prison. These accordingly made offers, each on behalf of his
                    own kinsman, seeking by payment to secure their release. Euaises agreed to
                    accept a certain sum for each, and when it had been paid returned to the
                    relations the dead body.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.33" unit="Loeb chap"/> While Cleomenes of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> was governor of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf.
                            <bibl n="Dem. 56">Dem. 56</bibl>: "Cleomenes . . . from the time that he
                        received the government, has done immense mischief to your state, and still
                        more to the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, by
                        buying up corn for resale and keeping it at his own price" (
                            Kennedy's translation).</note> at a time
                    when there was some scarcity in the land, but elsewhere a grievous famine, he
                    forbade the export of grain. On the local governors representing<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>that if there were no export of grain they
                    would be unable to pay in their taxes, he allowed the export, but laid a heavy
                    duty on the corn. By this means he obtained a large amount of duty from a small
                    amount of export, and at the same time deprived the officials of their
                        excuse.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When Cleomenes was making a progress
                    by water through the province where the crocodile is worshipped, one of his
                    servants was carried off. Accordingly, summoning the priests, he told them that
                    he intended to retaliate on the crocodiles for this unprovoked aggression; and
                    gave orders for a battue. The priests, to save the credit of their god,
                    collected all the gold they could, and succeeded in putting an end to the
                        pursuit.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>King Alexander had given Cleomenes
                    command to establish a town near the island of <placeName key="tgn,7015484">Pharus</placeName>, and to transfer thither the market hitherto held at
                        <placeName key="tgn,1001079">Canopus</placeName>. Sailing therefore to
                        <placeName key="tgn,1001079">Canopus</placeName> he informed the priests and
                    the men of property there that he was come to remove them. The priests and
                    residents thereupon contributed money to induce him to leave their market where
                    it was. He took what they offered, and departed; but afterwards returned, when
                    all was ready to build the town, <milestone n="1352b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>and proceeded to demand an excessive sum;
                    which represented, he said, the difference the change of site would make to him.
                    They however declared themselves unable to pay it, and were accordingly
                        removed.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On another occasion he sent an agent
                    to make a certain purchase for him. Learning that the agent had made a good
                    bargain, but intended to charge him a high price, he proceeded to inform the
                    man's associates that he had been told he had purchased the goods at an
                    excessive price, and that therefore he did not intend to recognize the
                    transaction; denouncing at the same time with feigned anger the fellow's
                    stupidity. They on hearing this asked him not to believe what was said against
                    the agent until he himself arrived and rendered his account. On the man's
                    arrival, his associates told him what Cleomenes had said. He, desirous of
                    winning their approval as well as that of Cleomenes, debited the latter with the
                    actual price he had given.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At a time when the
                    price of grain in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> was ten
                    drachmae &lt;a measure&gt; ,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">If the
                        measure intended is the Attic medimnos , it is 1 1/2 bushels. The Persian
                        artabe may however be meant, which was equal to 1 medimnos and 1/16th. In
                        either case the price is very high compared with 3 drachmae per medimnos,
                        the price at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in <date value="-390">390</date> B.C. Yet <bibl n="Plb. 9.44">Polybius
                        9.44</bibl> says that at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>
                        during the war with Hannibal (210) corn was sold for fifteen drachmae per
                        medimnos. As a contrast cf. what the same author says of the fertility of
                        Gallia Cisalpina, where in time of peace this same measure of wheat was sold
                        for four obols, and of barley for two. See note on 25.</note> Cleomenes sent
                    for the growers and asked them at what price they would contract to supply him
                    with their produce. On their quoting a price lower than what they were charging
                    the merchants, he offered them the full price they were accustomed to receive
                    from others; and taking over the entire supply,<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>sold it at a fixed rate of thirty-two drachmae &lt;for the
                    same measure&gt;.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He also sent for the
                    priests, and told them that the expenditure on the temples was very unevenly
                    distributed in the country; and that some of these, together with the majority
                    of the attendant priests, must accordingly be suppressed. The priests, supposing
                    him to be in earnest, and wishing each to secure the continuance of his own
                    temple and office, gave him money individually from their private possessions as
                    well as collectively from the temple funds.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf.
                        25.</note>
                    <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.34" unit="Loeb chap"/>
                    Antimenes of Rhodes, who was appointed by Alexander superintendent of highways
                    in the province of <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, adopted the
                    following means of raising funds. An ancient law of the country imposed a tax of
                    one-tenth on all imports; but this had fallen into total abeyance. Antimenes
                    kept a watch for all governors and soldiers whose arrival was expected, and upon
                    the many ambassadors and craftsmen who were invited to the city, but brought
                    with them others who dwelt there unofficially; and also upon the multitude of
                    presents that were brought &lt;to these persons&gt; , on which he
                    exacted the legal tax of a tenth.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Another
                    expedient was this. He invited the owners of any slaves in the camp to register
                    them at whatever value they desired, undertaking at the same time to pay him
                    eight drachmae a year. If the slave ran away, the owner was to recover the
                    registered value. <milestone n="1353a" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/>Many slaves were thus registered, and a large sum of
                    money was paid &lt;in premiums&gt;. And when a slave ran away, Antimenes
                    instructed the governor of the &lt;province&gt; where the camp lay
                    either to recover the man or to pay his master his value.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.35" unit="Loeb chap"/> Ophellas of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> appointed an officer
                    to superintend the revenues of the Province of <placeName key="tgn,7001308">Athribis</placeName>. The local governors came to him, and told him they
                    were willing to pay a much larger amount in taxes; but asked him to remove the
                    present superintendent. Ophellas inquired if they were really able to pay what
                    they promised; and on their assuring him that they were, left the superintendent
                    in office and instructed him to demand from them the amount of tax which they
                    themselves had assessed. And so, without being chargeable either with
                    discountenancing the officer he had appointed, or with taxing the governors
                    beyond their own estimate, he obtained from the latter many times his previous
                        revenue.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.36" unit="Loeb chap"/> Pythocles the Athenian recommended his fellow-countrymen
                    that the State should take over from private citizens the lead obtained from the
                    mines of <placeName key="perseus,Laurion">Laurium</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">These silver mines were state property; but mining rights
                        therein were let to private citizens. Lead and silver were found in the same
                        ore and had to be separated. The weight of the lead is not specified: it may
                        have been a talent of 80 lbs. See Boeckh, <title>Staatshaushaltung der
                            Athener</title>; and <bibl n="Xen. Ways 1">Xen. Ways</bibl>.</note> at the price
                    of two drachmae &lt;per talent&gt; which they were asking, and should
                    itself sell it at the fixed price of six drachmae.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.37" unit="Loeb chap"/> Chabrias had levied crews
                        for<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/>a hundred and twenty ships to
                    serve King Taos.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See 25.</note> Finding that
                    Taos needed only sixty ships, he gave the crews of the superfluous sixty their
                    choice between providing those who were to serve with two months' rations, and
                    themselves taking their place. Desiring to remain at their business, they gave
                    what he demanded.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.38" unit="Loeb chap"/> Antimenes bade the governors of the provinces replenish,
                    in accordance with the law of the country, the magazines along the royal
                    highways. Whenever an army passed through the country or any other body of men
                    unaccompanied by the king, he sent an officer to sell them the contents of the
                    magazines. <milestone n="1353b" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Bekker" n="1" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.39" unit="Loeb chap"/> Cleomenes, as the beginning of the month approached when
                    his soldiers' allowance became due, deliberately sailed away down the river; and
                    not till the month was advanced did he return and distribute the allowance. For
                    the coming month, he omitted the distribution altogether until the following
                    month began. Thus the men were quieted by the recent distribution, and
                    Cleomenes, passing over a month each year, docked his troops of a month's
                        pay.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><foreign lang="greek">SITARXI/A</foreign> (corn allowance) and <foreign lang="greek">MISQO/S</foreign> (pay) here seem to be identified; possibly because in a
                        land where grain was readily purchasable the former was given in money. Cf.
                        23, 29.</note>
                    <milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.40" unit="Loeb chap"/>
                    Stabelbius, king of the Mysians, lacking pay to give his troops, summoned a
                    meeting of the officers, and declared that he no longer needed the private
                    soldiers, but only the officers. When he required troops, he would entrust a sum
                    of money to each officer and send him to collect mercenaries; but that meanwhile
                    he preferred to give the officers the pay he would otherwise have to give the
                    men. Accordingly he bade each dismiss the men who were on his own muster-roll.
                    The officers, scenting a source of gain for themselves, dismissed their men, as
                    they were bidden. Shortly afterwards, Stabelbius called them together and
                    informed them that a conductor without his chorus and an officer without his men
                    were alike useless; wherefore let them depart from his country.<milestone ed="Bekker" n="20" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone ed="P" n="2.41" unit="Loeb chap"/> When Dionysius was making a tour of the
                    temples, wherever he saw a gold or silver table set, he bade them fill a cup "in
                    honor of the good spirit,"<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Cic. N.D. 3.3.4">Cic. De natura deorum 3.3.4</bibl> and <bibl n="Ath. 15.693">Athenaeus Deipnosophistae 15.693</bibl>.</note> and then
                    had the table carried away. Wherever, again, he saw a precious bowl set before
                    one of the images, he would order its removal, with the words" I accept it." He
                    also stripped the images of their golden raiment and garlands, and declaring he
                    would give them lighter and more fragrant wear, arrayed them in robes of white
                    &lt;linen&gt; and garlands of white socks.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="Book" n="3">
				<p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="Rose" n="1" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A good wife should be the mistress of her
                    home, having under her care all that is within it, according to the rules we
                    have laid down. She should allow none to enter without her husband's knowledge,
                    dreading above all things the gossip of gadding women, which tends to poison the
                    soul. She alone should have knowledge of what happens within, whilst if any harm
                    is wrought by those from without, her husband will bear the blame. She must
                    exercise control of the money spent on such festivities as her husband has
                    approved, keeping, moreover, within the limit set by law upon expenditure,
                    dress, and ornament;<milestone ed="Rose" n="10" unit="line"/>and remembering
                    that beauty depends not on costliness of raiment, nor does abundance of gold so
                    conduce to the praise of a woman as self-control in all that she does, and her
                    inclination towards an honorable and well-ordered life.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="1 Peter 3.3.4">1 Peter 3.3.4</bibl>.</note> For
                    such adornment of the soul as this is in truth ever a thing to be envied, and a
                    far surer warrant for the payment, to the woman herself in her old age and to
                    her children after her, of the due meed of praise.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This, then, is the province over which a woman should be minded to bear an
                    orderly rule; for it seems not fitting that a man should know all that passes
                    within the house. But in all other matters, let it be her aim to obey her
                    husband; giving no heed to public affairs, nor desiring any part in arranging
                    the marriages of her children.<milestone ed="p" n="20" unit="card"/><milestone ed="Rose" n="20" unit="line"/>Rather, when the time shall come to give or
                    receive in marriage sons or daughters, let her even then hearken to her husband
                    in all respects, and agreeing with him obey his behest; considering that it is
                    less unseemly for him to deal with a matter within the house than it is for her
                    to pry into those outside its walls. Nay, it is fitting that a woman of
                    well-ordered life should consider that her husband's uses are as laws appointed
                    for her own life by divine will, along with the marriage state and the fortune
                    she shares. If she endures them with patience and gentleness, she will rule her
                    home with ease; otherwise, not so easily. Wherefore not only when her husband is
                    in prosperity<milestone ed="Rose" n="30" unit="line"/>and good report does it
                    beseem her to be in modest agreement with him, and to render him the service he
                    wills, but also in times of adversity. If, through sickness or fault of
                    judgement, his good fortune fails, then must she show her quality,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or (if manifestam esse represents <foreign lang="greek">DHLONO/TI</foreign>) "then plainly it is her part to
                        encourage . . . and to yield . . ." </note> encouraging him ever with words
                    of cheer and yielding him obedience in all fitting ways; only let her do nothing
                    base or unworthy of herself, or remember any wrong her husband may have done her
                    through distress of mind. Let her refrain from all complaint, nor charge him
                    with the wrong, but rather attribute everything of this kind to sickness or
                    ignorance or accidental errors. For the more sedulous her service herein, the
                    fuller will be his gratitude<milestone ed="p" n="40" unit="card"/><milestone ed="Rose" n="40" unit="line"/>when he is restored, and freed from his
                    trouble; and if she has failed to obey him when he commanded aught that is
                    amiss, the deeper will be his recognition &lt;of her loyalty&gt; when
                    health returns. Wherefore, whilst careful to avoid such &lt;misplaced
                    obedience&gt;, in other respects she will serve him more assiduously than if
                    she had been a bondwoman bought and taken home. For he has indeed bought her
                    with a great price&mdash;with partnership in his life and in the procreation
                    of children; than which things nought could be greater or more divine. And
                    besides all this, the wife who had only lived in company with a fortunate
                    husband would not have had the like opportunity to show her true quality. For
                    though there be no small merit in a right and noble use of prosperity, still the
                    right endurance of adversity justly receives an honor greater by far.<milestone ed="Rose" n="50" unit="line"/>For only a great soul can live in the midst of
                    trouble and wrong without itself committing any base act. And so, while praying
                    that her husband may be spared adversity, if trouble should come it beseems the
                    wife to consider that here a good woman wins her highest praise. Let her bethink
                    herself how Alcestis would never have attained such renown nor Penelope have
                    deserved all the high praises bestowed on her had not their husbands known
                    adversity; whereas the troubles of Admetus and Ulysses have obtained for their
                    wives a reputation that shall never die. For because in time of distress they
                    proved themselves faithful and dutiful to their husbands, the gods have bestowed
                    on them the honor they deserved. To find partners in prosperity is easy
                        enough;<milestone ed="Rose" n="60" unit="line"/>but only the best women are
                    ready to share in adversity. For all these reasons it is fitting that a woman
                    should &lt;in time of adversity&gt; pay her husband an honor greater by
                    far, nor feel shame on his account even when, as Orpheus says,<quote>Holy health
                        of soul, and wealth, the child of a brave spirit, companion him no
                        more.</quote><milestone ed="p" n="65" unit="card"/>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Such then is the
                    pattern of the rules and ways of living which a good wife will observe. And the
                    rules which a good husband will follow in treatment of his wife will be similar;
                    seeing that she has entered his home like a suppliant from without, and is
                    pledged to be the partner of his life and parenthood; and that the offspring she
                    leaves behind her will bear the names of their parents, her name as well as his.
                    And what could be more divine than this, or more desired by a man of sound
                        mind,<milestone ed="Rose" n="70" unit="line"/>than to beget by a noble and
                    honored wife children who shall be the most loyal supporters and discreet
                    guardians of their parents in old age, and the preservers of the whole house?
                    Rightly reared by father and mother, children will grow up virtuous, as those
                    who have treated them piously and righteously deserve that they should; but
                    &lt;parents&gt; who observe not these precepts will be losers thereby.
                    For unless parents have given their children an example how to live, the
                    children in their turn will be able to offer a fair and specious excuse
                    &lt;for undutifulness&gt;. Such parents will risk being rejected by
                    their offspring for their evil lives, and thus bringing destruction upon their
                    own heads.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Wherefore his wife's training should be
                    the object of a man's unstinting care;<milestone ed="Rose" n="80" unit="line"/>that so far as is possible their children may spring from the noblest of
                    stock. For the tiller of the soil spares no pains to sow his seed in the most
                    fertile and best cultivated land, looking thus to obtain the fairest fruits; and
                    to save it from devastation is ready, if such be his lot, to fall in conflict
                    with his foes; a death which men crown with the highest of praise. Seeing, then,
                    that such care is lavished on the body's food, surely every care should be taken
                    on behalf of our own children's mother and nurse, in whom is implanted the seed
                    from which there springs a living soul. For it is only by this means that each
                    mortal, successively produced, participates in immortality; and that petitions
                    and prayers continue to be offered to ancestral gods.<milestone ed="Rose" n="90" unit="line"/>So that he who thinks lightly of this<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">i.e., the procreation of children.</note> would seem also to
                    be slighting the gods. For their sake then, in whose presence he offered
                    sacrifice and led his wife home, promising to honor her far above all others
                    saving his parents, &lt;a man must have care for wife and
                        children&gt;.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now a virtuous wife is best
                    honored when she sees that her husband is faithful to her, and has no preference
                    for another woman; but before all others loves and trusts her and holds her as
                    his own. And so much the more will the woman seek to be what he accounts her. If
                    she perceives that her husband's affection for her is faithful and righteous,
                    she too will be faithful and righteous towards him.<milestone ed="Rose" n="100" unit="line"/>Wherefore a man of sound mind ought not to forget what honors
                    are proper to his parents or what fittingly belong to his wife and children; so
                    that rendering to each and all their own, he may obey the law of men and of
                    gods. For the deprivation we feel most of all is that of the special honor which
                    is our due; nor will abundant gifts of what belongs to others be welcome to him
                    who is dispossessed of his own. Now to a wife nothing is of more value, nothing
                    more rightfully her own, than honored and faithful partnership with her husband.
                    Wherefore it befits not a man of sound mind to bestow his person promiscuously,
                    or have random intercourse with women; for otherwise the base-born will share in
                    the rights of his lawful children,<milestone ed="Rose" n="110" unit="line"/>and
                    his wife will be robbed of her honor due, and shame be attached to his
                        sons.<milestone ed="p" n="111" unit="card"/>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To all these
                    matters, therefore, a man should give heed. And it is fitting that he should
                    approach his wife in honorable wise, full of self-restraint and awe; and in his
                    conversation with her, should use only the words of a right-minded man,
                    suggesting only such acts as are themselves lawful and honorable; treating her
                    with much self-restraint and trust,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or
                        "loyalty." </note> and passing over any trivial or unintentional errors she
                    has committed. And if through ignorance she has done wrong, he should advise her
                    of it without threatening, in a courteous and modest manner. Indifference
                    &lt;to her faults&gt; and harsh reproof &lt;of them&gt;, he must
                    alike avoid. Between a courtesan and her lover, such tempers are allowed their
                        course;<milestone ed="Rose" n="120" unit="line"/>between a free woman and
                    her lawful spouse there should be a reverent and modest mingling of love and
                    fear. For of fear there are two kinds. The fear which virtuous and honorable
                    sons feel towards their fathers, and loyal citizens towards right-minded rulers,
                    has for its companions reverence and modesty; but the other kind, felt by slaves
                    for masters and by subjects for despots who treat them with injustice and wrong,
                    is associated with hostility and hatred.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>By
                    choosing the better of all these alternatives a husband should secure the
                    agreement, loyalty, and devotion of his wife, so that whether he himself is
                    present or not, there may be no difference in her attitude towards him, since
                    she realizes that they are alike guardians of the common interests; and so when
                    he is away she may feel that to her no man is kinder <milestone ed="Rose" n="130" unit="line"/>or more virtuous or more truly hers than her own
                        husband.<milestone ed="p" n="131" unit="card"/>And &lt;a good
                    wife&gt; will make this manifest from the beginning by her unfailing regard
                    for the common welfare, novice though she be in such matters. And if the husband
                    learns first to master himself, he will thereby become his wife's best guide in
                    all the affairs of life, and will teach her to follow his example. For Homer
                    pays no honor either to affection or to fear apart from the shame or modesty
                    that shrinks from evil. Everywhere he bids affection be coupled with
                    self-control and shame; whilst the fear he commends is such as Helen owns when
                    she thus addresses Priam: "Beloved sire of my lord, it is fitting that I fear
                    thee and dread thee and revere"<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><bibl n="Hom.                         Il. 3.172">Hom.
                            Il. 3.172</bibl>:<quote type="verse">
                            <l met="dactylic">
                                <foreign lang="greek">AI)DOI=O/S TE/ MOI/ E)SSI, FI/LE E(KURE/,
                                    DEINO/S TE</foreign>
                            </l>
                        </quote>..</note>; meaning that her love for him is mingled with fear and
                    modest shame. And again, Ulysses speaks to Nausicaa in this manner:<milestone ed="Rose" n="140" unit="line"/> "Thou, lady, dost fill me with wonder and
                    with fear."<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 6.168">Hom. Od. 6.168</bibl>
                        (like the young palm-tree at <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>): <quote type="verse">
                            <l met="dactylic">
                                <foreign lang="greek">W(S SE/, GU/NAI, A)/GAMAI/ TE TE/QHPA/ TE
                                    DEI/DIA/ T' AI)NW=S</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">GOU/NWN A(/YASQAI</foreign>
                            </l>
                        </quote>. . .</note> For Homer believes that this is the feeling of a
                    &lt;good&gt; husband and wife for one another, and that if they so feel,
                    it will be well with them both. For none ever loves or admires or fears in this
                    shamefaced way one of baser character; but such are the feelings towards one
                    another of nobler souls and those by nature good; or of the inferior toward
                    those they know to be their betters. Feeling thus toward Penelope, Ulysses
                    remained faithful to her in his wanderings; whereas Agamemnon did wrong to his
                    wife for the sake of Chryseis, declaring in open assembly that a base captive
                    woman, and of alien race besides, was in no wise inferior to Clytemnestra in
                    womanly excellence.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 1.113">Hom. Il.
                        1.113</bibl>: <quote type="verse">
                            <l met="dactylic">
                                <foreign lang="greek">KAI\ GA/R R(A *KLUTAIMNH/STRHS
                                PROBE/BOULA,</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">KOURIDI/HS A)LO/XOU, E)PEI\ OU)/ E(QE/N E)STI
                                    XEREI/WN,</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">OU) DE/MAS OU)DE\ FUH/N, OU)/T' A)\R FRE/NAS
                                    OU)/TE TI E)/RGA</foreign>
                            </l>
                        </quote>.</note><milestone ed="p" n="150" unit="card"/><milestone ed="Rose" n="150" unit="line"/>This was ill spoken of the mother of his children; nor
                    was his connection with the other a righteous one. How could it be, when he had
                    but recently compelled her to be his concubine, and before he had any experience
                    of her behavior to him? Ulysses on the other hand, when the daughter of
                        Atlas<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Calypso. See <bibl n="Hom. Od. 5.136">Hom. Od.
                            5.136, 203ff.</bibl></note> besought him to share her bed and board, and
                    promised him immortality and everlasting happiness, could not bring himself even
                    for the sake of immortality to betray the kindness and love and loyalty of his
                    wife, deeming immortality purchased by unrighteousness to be the worst of all
                    punishments.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Gorg.                         472">Plat. Gorg.
                            472ff.</bibl></note> For it was only to save his comrades that he
                    yielded his person to Circe; and in answer to her he even declared that in his
                    eyes nothing could be more lovely than his native isle, rugged though it
                        were;<milestone ed="Rose" n="160" unit="line"/>and prayed that he might die,
                    if only he might look upon his mortal wife and son.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Hom. Od. 9.26">Hom. Od. 9.26ff.</bibl>.</note> So firmly did
                    he keep troth with his wife; and received in return from her the like
                        loyalty.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">With this chapter cf. the poem of
                        Simon Dach (<date value="1648">1648</date>) translated by Longfellow as
                        "Annie of Tharaw."</note><milestone ed="p" n="162" unit="card"/>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Once again, in
                    the words addressed by Ulysses to Nausicaa<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><bibl n="P">Hom. Od. 6.180ff.</bibl>: <quote type="verse">
                            <l met="dactylic">
                                <foreign lang="greek">SOI\ DE\ QEOI\ TO/SA DOI=EN O(/SA FRESI\
                                    SH=|SI MENOINA=|S,</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">A)/NDRA TE KAI\ OI)=KON KAI\ O(MOFROSU/NHN
                                    O)PA/SEIAN</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">E)SQLH/N: OU) ME\N GA\R TOU= GE KREI=SSON KAI\
                                    A)/REION,</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">H)\ O(/Q' O(MOFRONE/ONTE NOH/MASIN OI)=KON
                                    E)/XHTON</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">A)NH\R H)DE\ GUNH/: PO/LL' A)/LGEA
                                    DUSMENE/ESSIN,</foreign>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">XA/RMATA D' EU)MENE/TH|SI: MA/LISTA DE/ T'
                                    E)/KLUON AU)TOI/</foreign>
                            </l>
                        </quote>.</note> the poet makes clear the great honor in which he holds the
                    virtuous companionship of man and wife in marriage. There he prays the gods to
                    grant her a husband and a home; and between herself and her husband, precious
                    unity of mind; provided that such unity be for righteous ends. For, says he,
                    there is no greater blessing on earth than when husband and wife rule their home
                    in harmony of mind and will. Moreover it is evident from this that the unity
                    which the poet commends<milestone ed="Rose" n="170" unit="line"/>is no mutual
                    subservience in each other's vices, but one that is rightfully allied with
                    wisdom and understanding; for this is the meaning of the words "rule the house
                    in &lt;harmony of&gt; mind." And he goes on to say that wherever such a
                    love is found between man and wife, it is a cause of sore distress to those who
                    hate them and of delight to those that love them; while the truth of his words
                    is most of all acknowledged by the happy pair.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The Greek, as cited above, is <foreign lang="greek">MA/LISTA DE/ T'
                            E)/KLUON AU)TOI/</foreign>, "and themselves best know their own case."
                    </note> For when wife and husband are agreed about the best things in life, of
                    necessity the friends of each will also be mutually agreed; and the strength
                    which the pair gain from their unity will make them formidable to their enemies
                    and helpful to their own. But when discord reigns between them, their friends
                    too will disagree and become in consequence enfeebled, while the pair themselves
                    will suffer most of all.<milestone ed="p" n="180" unit="card"/><milestone ed="Rose" n="180" unit="line"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In all these
                    precepts it is clear that the poet is teaching husband and wife to dissuade one
                    another from whatever is evil and dishonorable, while unselfishly furthering to
                    the best of their power one another's honorable and righteous aims. In the first
                    place they will strive to perform all duty towards their parents, the husband
                    towards those of his wife no less than towards his own, and she in her turn
                    towards his. Their next duties are towards their children, their friends, their
                    estate, and their entire household which they will treat as a common possession;
                    each vying with the other in the effort to contribute most to the common
                    welfare, and to excel in virtue and righteousness; laying aside arrogance, and
                    ruling with justice in a kindly and unassuming spirit.<milestone ed="Rose" n="190" unit="line"/>And so at length, when they reach old age, and are
                    freed from the duty of providing for others and from preoccupation with the
                    pleasures and desires of youth, they will be able to give answer also to their
                    children, if question arise whether child or parent<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or "which of their parents." </note> has contributed more
                    good things to the common household store; and will be well assured that
                    whatsoever of evil has befallen them is due to fortune, and whatsoever of good,
                    to their own virtue. One who comes victorious through such question wins from
                    heaven, as Pindar says,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A mistranslation of the
                        following words, cited by <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 331a">Plat. Rep. 331a</bibl>: <cit>
                            <quote type="verse">
                                <l met="lyric">
                                    <foreign lang="greek">GLUKEI=A/ OI( KARDI/AN A)TA/LLOISA
                                        GHROTRO/FOS SUNAOREI=</foreign>
                                </l>
                                <l>
                                    <foreign lang="greek">E)LPI/S, A(\ MA/LISTA QNATW=N</foreign>
                                </l>
                                <l>
                                    <foreign lang="greek">POLU/STROFON GNW/MAN KUBERNA=|</foreign>
                                </l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl n="Pind. Fr. 214">Pind. Frag. 214 (Loeb)</bibl>
                        </cit>, "the old age (of a righteous man) is sustained by a pleasant
                        companion that cherishes his heart; even by Hope, who more than aught else
                        guides the wayward mind of mortals." </note> his chiefest reward; for "hope,
                    and a soul filled with fair thoughts are supreme in the manifold mind of
                    mortals" ; and next, from his children the good fortune of being sustained by
                    them in his old age. And therefore it behoves us to preserve throughout our
                    lives a righteous attitude towards all gods and mortal men, to each
                    individually, and to all in common<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Or "both as
                        individuals and as members of a community." </note>;<milestone ed="Rose" n="200" unit="line"/>and not least towards our own wives and children and
                    parents.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
