<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">An vitiositas ad infelicitatem sufficia</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.099">
      <body>
         <head>Whether vice is sufficient to render a man
				unhappy<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Tho' this tract is so defective, both in the beginning and end, that they
					cannot, even to this present, be so much as guess'd at; yet the title and fragment
					we have left sufficiently discover the author's intention. Now as, from the ruins of
					an old regal palace, our imagination does in some sort represent to us, low beautiful it was whilst it stood entire; so tills little remnant suffices to show the greatness
					of our loss. But though the injury of time has depriv'd us of this benefit, and
					many others of like nature; yet this remainder, as imperfect as it is, may be profitable to us, and serve to put us in mind of our duty. Our author having, in the
					beginning, describ'd the misery of a covetous person, and of a courtier, adds, in
					prosecution of his principal design, that Vice is the absolute effector of infelicity,
					having need of no instruments or servants, to render a man miserable; whence he
					collects, that there is no danger or calamity which we ought not rather to choose,
					than to be vicious. He answers the objections made to the contrary, and concludes
					that no adversity can prejudice us, if it be not accompany'd with Vice. (S. W.)</note>
				        <lb/> [<hi rend="italics">The beginning is lost.</hi>]</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.499"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He suffers much, who for a dowry has
				</l>
                     <l>His body sold,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Euripides says; for he gets but small matters by it, and
					those very uncertain. But to him who passes not through
					much ashes, but through a certain regal pile of fire, being
					perpetually short breathed, full of fear, and bathed in
					sweat as if he had crossed the seas to and fro, she gives at
					last a certain Tantalian wealth, which he cannot enjoy by
					reason of the continual turmoil that encumbers him. For
					that Sicyonian horse-courser was well advised, who presented the king of the Achaeans with a swift-footed mare,
					<quote rend="blockquote">That to proud Ilium's siege he might not go,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXIII. 297.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but stay at home and take his pleasure, wallowing in the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.500"/>
					
					depth of his riches, and giving himself up to an unmolested
					ease.</p>
            <p>But those who now seem to be without trouble and men
					of action do, without being called to it, thrust themselves
					headlong into the courts of princes, where they must be
					obliged to tedious attending and watching, that they may
					gain an horse, a chain, or some such blessed favor.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In the mean time the wife, of joy bereft,
					</l>
                     <l>Sits tearing her fair cheeks, the house is left
					</l>
                     <l>Imperfect and half built;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>whilst the husband is drawn and hurried about, wandering
					amongst others, allured by hopes of which he is often
					disappointed, suffering disgrace and same. But if he
					happens to obtain any of those things he so eagerly desires,
					after he has been turned about and made dizzy with being
					Fortune's sport, he seeks a dismission, and declares those to
					be happy who live obscure and safe; whilst they, in the
					mean time, have the same opinion of him whom they see
					mounted so far above them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>So absolutely does Vice dispose of all men, being
				such a self-sufficient worker of infelicity, that it has no need
				either of instruments or servants. Other tyrants, endeavoring to render those men miserable whom they punish,
				maintain executioners and tormentors, devise searing-irons
				and racks, to plague the reasonless soul. But Vice, without any preparation of engines, as soon as it enters into the
				soul, torments and dejects it, filling a man with grief, lamentations, sorrow, and repentance. For a sign that this
				is so, you may observe that many being cut are silent, being
				scourged take it patiently, and being racked and tormented
				by their lords and tyrants send not forth the least shriek,
				since the soul, repressing the voice by reason, restrains and
				keeps it in as with the hand; but you will scarce ever be
				able to quiet anger or to silence sorrow; nor can you persuade one that is in a fright to stand still, or one that is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.501"/>
				
				stung with remorse of conscience to forbear exclaiming,
				tearing his hair, and smiting his thigh. So much is Vice
				more violent than either fire or sword.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Cities, when by fixing up of writings they publish
				their intentions of building temples or erecting colossuses,
				hear the proposals of different artists, contending about the
				undertaking of the work, and bringing in their accounts
				and models; after which, they choose him who will perform it best, quickest, and with the least expense. Now
				imagine, that we also set forth a proclamation of a purpose
				to make a wretched man or a miserable life, and that Fortune and Vice come with differing proposals to offer their
				service for the performance of this design. The one (to
				wit, Fortune) is provided with abundance of various instruments and costly furniture, to render human life miserable
				and unhappy. She draws after her robberies, wars, the
				murders of tyrants, storms from the sea, and lightnings
				from the air. She mixes hemlock, brings in swords, hires
				slanderers, kindles fevers, jingles shackles, and builds up
				prisons round about; although most of these things are
				rather from Vice than Fortune. But let us suppose them
				to be all from Fortune; and let Vice, standing naked and
				wanting no exterior things against man, ask Fortune how
				she will make a man unhappy and faint-hearted.</p>
            <p>Fortune, let her say, dost thou threaten poverty? Metrocles laughs at thee, who sleeping in the winter amongst
					the sheep, and in the summer in the porches of the temples, challenged the kings of the Persians, that wintered in
					Babylon and passed the summer in Media, to vie with him
					for happiness. Dost thou bring on servitude, bonds, and
					the being sold for a slave ? Diogenes contemns thee, who
					being exposed to sale by pirates, cried out, Who will buy a
					master? Dost thou brew a cup of poison? Didst thou
					not offer such a one to Socrates? And yet he mildly and
					meekly, without trembling or changing either color or
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.502"/>
					
					countenance, drank it briskly up; whilst those who survived esteemed him happy, as one that would not be even
					in the other world without a divine portion. Moreover, as
					for thy fire, Decius the Roman general prevented it, when,
					having caused a great fire to be made in the midst between
					two armies, he sacrificed himself to Saturn, according to a
					vow made for the aggrandizing of the Romans' dominion.
					And amongst the Indians, such chaste wives as are true
					lovers of their husbands strive and contend with one another for the fire, and all the rest sing forth the happiness
					of her who, having obtained the victory, is burnt with her
					deceased husband. And of the Sages in those parts, there
					is not one esteemed a holy and most blessed man, if he did
					not, whilst he was yet living and in the perfect enjoyment
					of his health and understanding, separate by fire his soul
					from his body, and purging away what was mortal, depart
					pure out of the flesh.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt reduce one from great wealth, a stately
					house, a well-furnished table, and abundance of all things,
					to a threadbare coat, a wallet, and begging of his daily
					food. These things were to Diogenes the beginnings of
					happiness, and to Crates of liberty and glory. But thou
					wilt, perhaps, fasten one to the cross, or impale him on a
					stake. Now what cares Theodorus, whether it is above
					or under ground that he putrefies ? These were the happy
					sepultures of the Scythians; and amongst the Hyrcanians,
					dogs&mdash;amongst the Bactrians, birds&mdash;do according to the
					laws devour the dead bodies of those who have made a
					blessed end.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Whom then do these things render unhappy? The
				unmanly and irrational, the effeminate and unexercised,
				with such as retain the foolish and frightful opinions they
				received in their infancy. Fortune then does not perfectly
				produce infelicity, unless it has Vice to co-operate with it.
				For as a thread will cut in sunder a bone that has been
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.503"/>
				
				steeped in ashes and vinegar, and as workmen bend and
				fashion ivory as they please, after it has been softened and
				rendered pliable by beer, when it is otherwise inflexible;
				so Fortune, coming upon that which is already ill-affected
				of itself and rendered soft by Vice, pierces into it and hollows it. And as the paroecus,&mdash;though hurtful to no
				other, nor any way prejudicing those who touch it or bear
				it about them,&mdash;if any one who is wounded is but brought
				into the place where it is, immediately kills him, being
				already by his wound predisposed to receive the defluxion;
				so the soul which is to be overthrown by Fortune must
				have in itself some ulcer of its own, and some malady within its flesh, that it may render those accidents which come
				from abroad miserable and lamentable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Is then Vice also such that it should stand in need
				of Fortune's help for the working of infelicity? By no
				means. She does not make the sea swell with storms and
				tempests, she besets not the deserts lying at the feet of the
				mountains with robbers, she pours not down storms of
				hail on the fruitful fields, she raises not up Meletus, Anytus, and Callixenus, to be calumniators, she takes not away
				wealth, she hinders not any from the command of armies,
				that she may make men unhappy; but she renders them
				rich, abounding in wealth, having great inheritances on
				the earth; she bears them company at sea; she sticks
				close to them, pining them with lust, inflaming them with
				wrath, overwhelming them with superstitions, drawing
				them by their eyes. . . .<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The rest is wanting.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>