<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De E apud Delphos</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.090">
      <body>
         <head>Of the word <foreign lang="greek">ei)</foreign> engraven over the gate of
				Apollo's temple at Delphi.
				<lb/> Ammonius, Lamprias, Plutarch, Theon, Eustrophus, Nicander.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.478"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>I HAPPENED not long since, dear Serapion, on certain
				not unelegant verses, which Dicaearchus supposes Euripides to have spoken to King Archelaus:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'm poor, you rich, I'll therefore nothing give;
				</l>
                     <l>Lest me or fool or beggar you believe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For he who out of his little estate makes small presents to
					those that have great possessions does them no pleasure;
					nay, being not believed to give even that little for nothing,
					he incurs the suspicion of being of a sordid and ungenerous
					disposition. But since pecuniary presents are both in
					bounty and beauty far inferior to such as proceed from
					learning and wisdom, it is honorable both to make such
					presents, and at our giving them, to desire suitable returns
					from the receivers. I therefore, sending to you,&mdash;and
					through you to our friends in those parts,&mdash;as a first-fruit
					offering, some discourses concerning the Pythian affairs,
					confess that I do in requital expect others, both more and
					better, from you, as being persons conversant in a great
					city, and enjoying more leisure amongst many books and
					conferences of all sorts. For indeed our good Apollo
					seems to cure and solve such difficulties as occur in the
					ordinary management of our life, by giving his oracles to
					those that resort to him; but as for those which concern
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.479"/>
					
					learning, he leaves and proposes them to that faculty of the
					soul which is naturally addicted to the study of philosophy,
					imprinting in it a desire leading to truth; as is manifest
					both in many other matters. and in the consecration of this
					inscription <hi rend="italics">EI.</hi> For it is not probable. that it was by chance
					or by a lottery (as it were) of letters that this word alone
					was placed in the principal seat in the God's temple, and
					received the dignity of a sacred donary and spectacle; but
					it is highly credible that those who at the beginning philosophized concerning this God gave it that station, either as.
					seeing it in some peculiar and extraordinary power, or
					using it as a symbol to signify some other thing worthy of
					our attention.</p>
            <p>Having therefore often formerly declined and avoided
					this discourse, when proposed in the school, I was lately
					surprised by my own children as I was debating with certain strangers, who were on their departure out of Delphi,
					so that I could not in civility hold them in suspense nor
					yet refuse discoursing with them, since they were exceeding earnest to hear something. Being therefore set down
					by the temple, I began myself to search into some things,
					and to ask them concerning others, being by the place and
					the very talk put in mind of those things we had heretofore, when Nero passed through these parts, heard Ammonius and some others discourse; the same difficulty having
					been then likewise in this very place propounded.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Since therefore this God is no less a philosopher than
				a prophet, Ammonius seemed to all of us rightly to apply
				every one of his names to this purpose, and to teach that
				he is Pythius (or a <hi rend="italics">questionist</hi>) to those who begin to learn
				and enquire; Delius and Phanaeus (or a <hi rend="italics">manifester</hi> and
				<hi rend="italics">prover</hi>) to those to whom somewhat of the truth is already
				manifest and shines forth; Ismenius (or <hi rend="italics">knowing</hi>) to those
				that have acquired knowledge; and Leschenorius (or <hi rend="italics">discoursing</hi>) when they practise and enjoy their science, making
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.480"/>
				
				 use of it to discourse and philosophize with one
				another. Now, forasmuch as to philosophize implies to
				enquire, to wonder, and to doubt, it is probable (he said)
				that many of the things that concern God are not unfitly
				concealed under enigmas, and require that one should ask
				the reason why, and seek to be instructed in the causes,
				&mdash;as, why of all wood fir only is burnt in the eternal fire,
				why the laurel only is used in fumigations, why there are
				erected but two statues of the Fates, they being everywhere else thought to be three, why no woman is permitted to have access to the oracle, what is the reason of
				the tripod, and other such like things, which, being proposed to those who are not altogether irrational and soulless, allure and incite them to consider, hear, and discourse
				something about them. And do but behold how many
				questions these inscriptions, <q direct="unspecified">Know thyself</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Nothing
					too much,</q> have set afoot amongst the philosophers, and
				what a multitude of discourses has sprung up from each of
				them, as from a seed; than neither of which, I think the
				matter now in question to be less fruitful.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Ammonius having spoken thus, Lamprias the Delphian said: The reason indeed which we have heard of
				this is plain and very short; for they say that those Sages,
				who were by some called Sophisters, were but five, Chilo,
				Thales, Solon, Bias, and Pittacus. But after that Cleobulus
				the tyrant of the Lindians, and Periander the Corinthian,
				though wholly destitute of virtue and wisdom, had by
				their power, friends, and courtesy forced a reputation, they
				usurped the name of Sages, and set forth and dispersed
				all over Greece certain sentences and sayings, not unlike
				to those which had been spoken by the five former wise
				men. The five, however, being discontented at this, would
				not reprove their arrogancy, nor openly contest and enter
				into quarrels for glory with men of so great power; but
				assembling here together, and consulting with one another,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.481"/>
				
				they consecrated the letter <hi rend="italics">E,</hi> which is in the order of the
				alphabet the fifth, and signifies five in number, protesting
				of themselves before the God that they were but five, and
				rejecting and abdicating the sixth and seventh as not belonging to them. Now that these things are not spoken
				beside the cushion, any one might understand who should
				have heard those who have care of the temple naming the
				golden <hi rend="italics">EI</hi> the <hi rend="italics">EI</hi> of Livia, the wife of Augustus Caesar;
				and the brazen one the <hi rend="italics">El</hi> of the Athenians; but the first
				and ancientest of all, which is the wooden one, they call
				the <hi rend="italics">EI</hi> of the Sages, as not being of any one, but the
				common dedication of them all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>At this Ammonius gently smiled, supposing Lamprias
				to have delivered an opinion of his own, but to have
				feigned that he had heard the story from others, lest he
				might be obliged to give an account of it. But another
				of those that were present said that this had some affinity
				with what a certain Chaldean stranger had lately babbled,
				to wit, that there are in the alphabet seven letters rendering a perfect sound of themselves, and in the heavens
				seven stars moved by their own proper motion, not bound
				or linked to that of the others; that E is from the beginning the second in order of the vowels, and the sun the
				second of the planets, or next to the moon, and that the
				Greeks do unanimously (so to speak) repute Apollo to be
				the same with the sun. But these things, said he, wholly
				savor of his counting-table and his trifling. But Lamprias,
				it seems, was not sensible of his having stirred up all
				those of the temple against his discourse. For there was
				not a man of the Delphians who knew any thing of what
				he said; but they all alleged the common and current
				opinion, holding that neither the sight nor the sound of
				this writing, but the word alone as it was written, contained some symbol or secret signification.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>For the syllable <hi rend="italics">EI</hi> (<hi rend="italics">if</hi>) is, as the Delphians conceive
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.482"/>
				
				it, and as Nicander the priest (who was then present) also
				said, a conveyance and form of prayer to the God, and
				has the leading place in the questions of those who at
				every turn use it, asking <hi rend="italics">if</hi> they shall overcome, <hi rend="italics">if</hi> they
				shall marry, <hi rend="italics">if</hi> it is convenient to go to sea, <hi rend="italics">if</hi> to till the
				ground, <hi rend="italics">if</hi> to travel. And the wise God, bidding adieu to
				the logicians, who think nothing at all can be made of
				this particle <hi rend="italics">EI</hi> and any clause following it, understands
				and admits all interrogations annexed to it, as real things.
				Now, because it is proper for us to consult him as a prophet,
				and common to pray to him as a God, they suppose that
				this word has no less a precatory than an interrogatory
				power. For every one who prays or wishes says, <foreign lang="greek">ei) ga\r w)/felon</foreign>,
				<hi rend="italics">O if I were,</hi> &amp;c. And Archilochus has also this
				expression:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If I might be so happy as to touch
				</l>
                     <l>My Neobule's hand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And they say that the second syllable in the word <foreign lang="greek">ei)/qe</foreign> is
					redundant like <foreign lang="greek">qh/n</foreign> in this of Sophron, <foreign lang="greek">(\*ama te/knwn qh\n deuome/na</foreign>,
					<hi rend="italics">desiring also children;</hi> and in this of Homer, <foreign lang="greek">(*ws qh\n kai\ so\n e)gw\ lu/sw me/nos</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">as I will also foil thy strength;</hi> but in the
					word <hi rend="italics">EI</hi> there is sufficiently declared an optative power.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Nicander having delivered these words, our friend
				Theon, whom you know, asked Ammonius if he might
				have liberty to plead for logic, which was so highly injured. And Ammonius bidding him speak and defend it,
				he said: Now that this God is a most expert logician many
				of his oracles show; for it is, to wit, the part of the same
				artist to dissolve and frame ambiguities. Moreover, as
				Plato said, when an oracle was given to the Greeks that
				they should double the altar in Delos, which is a work of
				the utmost perfection in geometry, that the God did not
				order the doing of that very thing, but commanded the
				Greeks to apply themselves to geometry; so the same God,
				by giving ambiguous oracles, honors and recommends logic,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.483"/>
				
				as necessary to those who desire to understand him aright.
				Now this conjunction <hi rend="italics">El,</hi> or <hi rend="italics">if,</hi> has a very great efficacy in
				logic, as forming the most rational proposition; for how
				can it be otherwise, since the very brutes have indeed the
				knowledge of the substance of things, but to man only
				has Nature given the consideration and judgment of consequence? For that there is both day and light, wolves and
				dogs and birds are sensible. But that if it is day there
				must be light, no other animal understands but man, who
				only has the conception of antecedent and consequent, of
				the significance and connection of these things with one
				another, and of their habitude and difference, from which
				demonstrations take their principal beginnings. Now since
				philosophy is conversant about truth, since the light of
				truth is demonstration, and the beginning of demonstration
				this connection of propositions; the faculty which contains
				and effects this was by wise men, with good reason, consecrated to the God who most of all loves truth. Now
				the God indeed is a prophet, and the art of prophesying
				is a divination concerning the future from things that are
				present and past. For neither is the original of any thing
				without a cause, nor the foreknowledge of any thing without reason. But since all things that are done follow and
				are connected to those that have been done, and those that
				shall be done to those that are done, according to the progress proceeding from the beginning to the end; he who
				knows how to look into the causes of this together, and
				naturally connect them one with another, knows also and
				divines
				<quote rend="blockquote">What things now are, shall be, or e'er have been.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 70.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Homer indeed excellently well places first things that
					are present, and afterwards what is future and past. For
					by the very nature of the connection the argument is based
					on that which now is. Thus, <q direct="unspecified">if this is, that preceded;</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.484"/>
					
					and again, <q direct="unspecified">if this is, that shall be.</q> For the knowledge of
					the consequence is, as has been said, an artificial and
					rational thing; but sense gives the assumption to reason.
					Whence (though it may seem indecent to say it) I will not
					be afraid to aver this, that the tripod of truth is reason,
					which recognizes the dependence of the consequent on
					the antecedent, and then, assuming the reality of the antecedent, infers the conclusion of the demonstration. If then
					the Pythian Apollo delights in music, and is pleased with
					the singing of swans and the harmony of the lute, what
					wonder is it that, for the sake of logic, he embraces and
					loves this argumentative particle, which he sees the philosophers so much and so frequently to use? Hercules indeed,
					not having yet unbound Prometheus, nor conversed with
					the sophisters that were with Chiron and Atlas, but being
					still a young man and a plain Boeotian, at first abolished
					logic and derided this word <hi rend="italics">EI;</hi> but afterwards he seemed
					by force to have seized on the tripod, and contended with
					our God himself for the pre-eminence in this art; for being
					grown up in age, he appeared to be the most expert both
					in divination and logic.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Theon having ended his speech, I think it was Eustrophus the Athenian who said to us: Do you not see
				how valiantly Theon vindicates logic, having, in a manner,
				got on the lion's skin? So it is not right even for us&mdash;who comprehensively place all the affairs, nature, and principles of things both divine and human in number, and
				make it most especially the author and lord of honest and
				estimable things&mdash;to be at quiet, but we must willingly
				offer the first-fruits of our dear mathematics to the God;
				since we think that this letter E does not of itself differ
				from the other letters either in power, figure, or expression,
				but that it has been preferred as being the sign of that
				great number which has an influence over all things,
				called the Quinary (or Pemptas), from which the Sages
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.485"/>
				
				have expressed the art of numbering by the verb <foreign lang="greek">pempta/zein</foreign>
				(signifying <hi rend="italics">to account by fives</hi>). Now Eustrophus spake
				these things to us, not in jest, but because I did at that
				time studiously apply myself to the mathematics, and perhaps also in every thing to honor that saying, <q direct="unspecified">Nothing
					too much,</q> as having been conversant in the Academy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>I answered therefore that Eustrophus has excellently
				solved the difficulty by number. For (said I) since all
				number is distributed into even and odd, unity is in efficacy
				common to them both,&mdash;for that being added to an even
				number, it makes it odd, and to an odd, it makes it even,
				two constituting the beginning of the even, and three of
				the odd. Now the number of five, composed of these
				two, is deservedly honored, as being the first compound
				made of the first simple numbers, and is called the marriage, for the resemblance of the odd with the male, and
				the even with the female. For in the divisions of the
				numbers into equal parts, the even, being wholly separated,
				leaves a certain capacious beginning and space in itself;
				but in the odd, suffering the same thing, there always
				remains a middle, of generative distribution, by which it is
				more fruitful than the other, and being mixed is always
				master, never mastered. For by the mixture of both,
				even and odd together, there is never produced an even
				number but always an odd. But which is more, either of
				them added to and compounded with itself shows the difference; for no even joined with another even ever produced an odd, or went forth of its proper nature, being
				through weakness unable to generate another and imperfect. But odd numbers mixed with odd do, through their
				being every way fruitful, produce many even ones. Time
				does not now permit us to set down the other powers and
				differences of numbers. Therefore have the Pythagoreans, through a certain resemblance, said that five is the
				marriage of the first male and the first female number. This
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.486"/>
				
				also is it for which it is called Nature, by the multiplication of itself determining again into itself. For as Nature,
				taking a grain of wheat for seed and diffusing it, produces
				many forms and species between, by which she brings her
				work to an end, but at last she shows again a grain of
				wheat, restoring the beginning in the end of all; so, while
				the rest of the numbers, when they are multiplied into
				others, terminate by the increase only those of five and
				six, multiplied by themselves, bring back and preserve
				themselves. For six times six makes thirty-six, and five
				times five makes twenty-five. And again, six does this
				once, and only after one manner, to wit, when it is squared.
				But this indeed befalls five both by multiplication and by
				composition with itself, to which being added, it alternatively makes itself and ten; and this as far as all number
				can extend, this number imitating the beginning or first
				Cause which governs the universe. For as that first Cause,
				preserving the world by itself, does reciprocally perfect
				itself by the world, as Heraclitus says of fire,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Fire turns to all things, and all things to fire;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and as money is changed for gold, and gold for money; so
					the congress of five with itself is framed by Nature to produce nothing imperfect or strange, but has limited changes;
					for it either generates itself or ten, that is, either what is
					proper to itself, or what is perfect.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Now if any one shall say, What is all this to Apollo?
				we will answer, that it concerns not Apollo only, but Bacchus also, who has no less to do with Delphi than Apollo
				himself. For we have heard the divines, partly in verse
				partly in prose, saying and singing, that the God is of his
				own nature incorruptible and eternal, but yet, through a
				certain fatal decree and reason, suffers changes of himself,
				having sometimes his nature kindled into a fire, and making
				all things alike, and otherwhiles becoming various, in different
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.487"/>
				
				 shapes, passions, and powers, like unto the World,
				and is named by this best-known of names. But the wiser,
				concealing from the vulgar the change into fire, call him
				both Apollo from his unity<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Deriving Apollo from <foreign lang="greek">a</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">polu/s</foreign> (or <foreign lang="greek">pollo/s</foreign>), <hi rend="italics">much.</hi> (G.)</note> and Phoebus from his purity
				and unpollutedness. But as for the passion and change of
				his conversion into winds, water, earth, stars, and the various kinds of plants and animals, and its order and disposition, this they obscurely represent as a certain distraction
				and dismembering; and they now call him Dionysus, Zagreus, Nyctelius, and Isodaetes, exhibiting and chanting
				forth certain corruptions, disparitions, deaths, and resurrections, which are all riddles and fables suited to the said
				mutations. To Dionysus or Bacchus they sing dithyrambic
				verses, full of passions and change, joined with a certain
				wandering and agitation backwards and forwards; for, as
				Aeschylus says,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The dithyramb, whose sounds are dissonant,
				</l>
                     <l>'Tis fit should wait on Bacchus.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But to Apollo they sing the well-ordered paean and a
					discreet song. And Apollo both in their sculptures and
					statues they always make to be young and never declining
					to old age; but Dionysus they represent in many shapes
					and forms. Lastly, to the one they attribute equality,
					order, and unmixed gravity; but to the other, a certain
					unequal mixture of sports, petulancy, gravity, and madness,
					surnaming him,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Evius Bacchus, who to rage incites
					</l>
                     <l>Women on tops of mountains, and delights
					</l>
                     <l>In frantic worship.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they not unfitly touch the property of both changes.
					Now because the time of the revolutions in these changes
					is not equal, but that of the one which they call Koros
					(that is, <hi rend="italics">satiety</hi>) is longer, and that of the other named
					Chresmosyne (or <hi rend="italics">want</hi>) shorter; observing in this the proportion,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.488"/>
					
					 they all the rest of the year use in their sacrifices
					the paean; but at the beginning of winter, rousing up the
					dithyramb, and laying the paean to rest, they do for three
					months invocate Bacchus instead of Apollo, esteeming the
					creation of the world to be the same in proportion of
					time to the conflagration of it as three to one.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But these things have perhaps had more than sufficient time spent on them. This, however, is evident, that
				they properly attribute to this God the number of five,
				saying that it sometimes of itself produces itself like fire,
				and other whiles the number of ten, like the world. But
				do we think that this number is not also concerned with
				music, which is of all things most acceptable to this God
				For the chiefest operation of harmony is, as one may say,
				about symphonies. Now that these are five and no more,
				reason convinces even him who will by his senses without
				reasoning make trial either on strings or pipe-holes. For
				all these accords take their original in proportions of number; and the proportion of the symphony diatessaron is
				sesquitertial, of diapente sesquialter, of diapason duple, of
				diapason with diapente triple, and of disdiapason quadruple. But as for that which, transcending all measures, the
				musicians add to these, naming it diapason with diatessaron,
				it is not fit we should receive it, gratifying the unreasonable pleasure of the ear against proportion, which is as the
				law. I may therefore let pass the five positions of the
				tetrachords, and also the five first,&mdash;whether they are to
				be called tones, tropes, or harmonies,&mdash;according to the
				changes of which by rising or falling, either to more or
				less, the rest are bases or trebles. And, whereas there are
				many or rather infinite intervals, are not five of them only
				used in music, to wit, diesis, hemitonion, tons, triemitonion,
				and ditonon? Nor is there in the voice any other space,
				either greater or less, that, being distinguished by base or
				treble, comes into melody.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.489"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Passing by many other such like things, said I, I
				will produce only Plato; who says, that there is but one
				world, but that if this were not alone, so that there were
				others besides it, they would be in all five and no more.
				For indeed, though there is but this one only world, as
				Aristotle is also of opinion, yet this world is in some sort
				composed and assembled of five, of which one indeed is of
				earth, another of water, the third of fire, the fourth of air,
				and the fifth, being heaven, some call light and others the
				sky; and some also name this same the fifth essence,
				which alone of all, bodies is naturally carried about in a
				circle, and not of necessity or otherwise by accident.
				Wherefore Plato, knowing that, of the figures which are
				in Nature, there are five most excellent and perfect,&mdash;to
				wit, the pyramid, the cube, the octahedron, the icosahedron, and the dodecahedron,&mdash;has fitly accommodated
				each of them to each of these worlds or bodies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>There are some also who apply the faculties of the
				senses, being equal in number, to these five first bodies,
				seeing the touch to be firm and earthly, and the taste to
				perceive the qualities of savors by moisture. Now the
				air being struck upon is a voice and sound to the ear; and
				as for the other two,&mdash;the scent, which the smell has obtained for its object, being an exhalation and engendered
				by heat, is fiery; and the sight, which shines by reason of
				its affinity to the sky and light, has from them a temperature and complexion equally mingled of both. Now neither
				has any animal any other sense, nor the world any other
				nature simple and unmixed; but there has been made, as
				appears, a certain wonderful distribution and congruity of
				five to five.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Having here stopped a little, and made a small
				pause between, I said: What a fault, O Eustrophus, were
				we like to have committed, having almost passed by Homer,
				as if he were not the first that distributed the world into
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.490"/>
				
				five parts, who assigned the three which are in the midst
				to three Gods, and left the two extremes, Olympus and
				the Earth&mdash;of which one is the limit of things above,
				the other of things below&mdash;common and undistributed.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. XV. 189.</note>
				But we must, as Euripides says, return to our discourse.
				For those who magnify the quaternary, or number of four,
				teach not amiss, that every solid body had its generation
				by reason of this. For since every solid consists in length
				and breadth, having withal a depth; and since before
				length there is extant a point, answerable to unity, and
				length without breadth is called a line and consists of two;
				and the motion of a line towards breadth exhibits also the
				procreation of a superficies in the number three ; and the
				argumentation of this, when depth is added to it, goes on
				to a solid in the number four; it is manifest to every one,
				that the quaternary, having carried on Nature hitherto,
				and even to the perfecting of a body and the exhibiting it
				tangible, massy, and solid, has yet at last left it wanting
				the greatest accomplishment. For that which is inanimate
				is, to speak sincerely, orphan-like, imperfect, and fit for
				nothing at all, unless there is some soul to use it; but the
				motion or disposition introducing a soul, being a change
				made by the number five, adds the consummation to Nature, and has a reason so much more excellent than the
				quaternary, as an animal differs in dignity from that which
				is inanimate. Moreover, the symmetry and power of this
				number five, having obtained greater force, has not permitted the animate body to proceed to infinite sorts, but
				has exhibited five species of all things that have life. For
				there are Gods, Genii, and heroes, and then after them the
				fourth sort is men, and the fifth and last the irrational and
				brutish animal. Furthermore, if you divide the soul itself
				according to its nature, its first and most obscure part or
				faculty is the vegetative, the second the sensitive, then the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.491"/>
				
				concupiscible, after that the irascible; and having brought
				on and perfected Nature in the faculty of the rational, it
				rests in this fifth, as in the top of all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Now the generation of this number, which has so
				many and so great faculties, is also beautiful,&mdash;not that
				which we have already discoursed of, from two and three,
				but that which the first principle joined with the first
				square has exhibited. For the principle of all number is
				unity, and the first square is the quaternary; now the
				quinary is composed of these, as of form and of matter which
				has attained to perfection. And if it is right, which some
				hold, that unity is also square, as being the power of
				itself and terminating in itself; the quinary, being made
				of the first two squares, could not have a more noble
				original.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>But as for its greatest excellency, I fear, lest being
				spoken it should press our Plato as much as he himself
				said Anaxagoras was pressed by the name of the moon,
				when he made a certain opinion concerning her illuminations, which was very ancient, to be an invention of his
				own. For has he not said this in his dialogue entitled
				Cratylus?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Cratyl. p. 403 A.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yes indeed, answered Eustrophus; but I see not any
					thing that has fallen out like it. And yet you know, that
					in the Sophister<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Sophist. p. 254 D.</note> he demonstrates five principal beginnings, to wit, that which <hi rend="italics">is,</hi> or <hi rend="italics">Ens</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">to\ o)/n</foreign>), the <hi rend="italics">Same,</hi> the
					<hi rend="italics">Different,</hi> adding to these, for a fourth and fifth, <hi rend="italics">Motion,</hi>
					and <hi rend="italics">Rest.</hi> Again, in his dialogue called Philebus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Phileb. p. 23 C-E.</note> using
					another manner of division, he says, that there is one thing
					Infinite, and another the End; and that all generation
					consists of these two mixed together. Then he puts the
					cause by which they are mixed for the fourth kind; and
					has left us to conjecture the fifth, by which the things that
					were mixed have again a division and dissipation. Now I
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.492"/>
					
					am of opinion that these last are delivered as the images
					or representations of those before,&mdash;to wit, the things
					engendered of Ens, the Infinite of Motion, the End of Rest,
					the Mixing Principle of the Same, and the Separating
					Principle of the Different. But if these are different from
					those, yet both that way and this way these principles are
					still distinguished into five kinds and differences. Now
					some one, said he, being persuaded of these things and
					seeing them before Plato, consecrated to the God two E E,
					for a mark and symbol of the number of all things. And
					having perhaps further understood that good also appears
					in five kinds, of which the first is the mean, the second
					the commensurate, the third understanding, the fourth the
					sciences, arts, and true opinions in the soul, and the fifth a
					certain pleasure, pure and unmixed with sorrow; he stops
					there, subjoining that of Orpheus:
					<quote rend="blockquote">In the sixth age stay your desire of singing.</quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>After what I have spoken to you, I said, Yet one
				short word to those about Nicander,
				<quote rend="blockquote">I'll sing to men of skill.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For on the sixth day of the new moon, when you introduce
					the Pythia into the Prytaneum, the first of the three lots
					tends with you towards five, casting neither three, nor two,
					one to another.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">I leave this corrupt passage as I find it in the old translation. The Greek
						cannot be tortured into any sense. (G.)</note> For is not this so?</p>
            <p>It is so, said Nicander; but the cause is not to be told
					to others.</p>
            <p>Well then, said I smiling, till such time as the God admits us, being consecrated, to know the truth, this also
					shall be added to those things that have been spoken concerning the quinary. This end, as I remember, had the
					discourse of the arithmetical and mathematical encomiums
					of E.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.493"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>But Ammonius, who had himself also bestowed not
				the worst part of his time in mathematical philosophy, was
				delighted with what had been spoken, and said: It is not
				meet too eagerly to oppose these young men about these
				things, except by saying that every one of the numbers
				will afford you, if you desire to praise it, no small subject
				of commendations. And what need is there to speak of
				others? For the septener, sacred to Apollo, will take up
				a day's time, before one can in words run through all its
				powers. We shall therefore pronounce, that the Sages do
				at once contest both against common law and a long series
				of time, if, throwing the septenary out of its seat, they
				consecrate the quinary to the God, as being more suitable
				to him. I am therefore of opinion, that this syllable signifies neither number, order, nor connection, nor any other
				of the deficient parts, but is a self-perfect appellation and
				salutation of the God, which brings the speaker to the
				conception of the power of the God at the very moment
				of uttering it. For the God in a manner calls upon every
				one of us who comes hither, with this salutation, Know
				thyself, which is nothing inferior to All hail. And we
				again, answering the God, say to him <foreign lang="greek">*ei)=</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">thou art;</hi> attributing to him the true, unfeigned, and sole appellation of
				being, as agreeing to him alone.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>For we indeed do not at all essentially partake of
				being; but every mortal nature, being in the midst between generation and corruption, exhibits an appearance,
				and an obscure and weak opinion of itself. And if you
				fix your thought, desiring to comprehend it,&mdash;as the hard
				grasping of water, by the pressing and squeezing together
				that which is fluid, loses that which is held,&mdash;so when
				reason pursues too evident a perception of any one of the
				things subject to passion and change, it is deceived and
				led away, partly towards its generation and partly towards
				its corruption, being able to apprehend nothing either remaining
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.494"/>
				
				 or really subsisting. For we cannot, as Heraclitus says, step twice into the same river, or twice find any
				perishable substance in the same state; but by the suddenness and swiftness of the change, it disperses and again
				gathers together, comes and goes. Whence what is generated of it reaches not to the perfection of being, because the
				generation never ceases nor is at an end; but always
				changing, of seed it makes an embryo, next an infant, then
				a child, then a stripling, after that a young man, then a
				full-grown man, an elderly man, and lastly, a decrepit old
				man, corrupting the former generations and statues by the
				latter. But we ridiculously fear one death, having already
				so often died and still dying. For not only, as Heraclitus
				said, is the death of fire the generation of air, and the
				death of air the generation of water; but you may see this
				more plainly in men themselves; for the full-grown man
				perishes when the old man comes, as the youth terminated
				in the full-grown man, the child in the youth, the infant in
				the child. So yesterday died in to-day, and to-day dies in
				to-morrow; so that none remains nor is one, but we are
				generated many, according as matter glides and turns about
				one phantasm and common mould. For how do we, if we
				remain the same, delight now in other things than we delighted in before? How do we love, hate, admire, and
				contemn things contrary to the former? How do we use
				other words and other passions, not having the same form,
				figure, or understanding? For neither is it probable we
				should be thus differently affected without change, neither
				is he who changes the same. And if he is not the same,
				neither is he at all; but changing from the same, he
				changes also his being, being made one from another. But
				the sense is deceived through the ignorance of being, supposing that to be which appears.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>What then is it that has really a being? That
				which is eternal, unbegotten, and incorruptible, to which no
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.495"/>
				
				time brings a change. For time is a certain movable thing
				appearing in connection with fleeting matter, always flowing and unstable, like a leaky vessel full of corruption and
				generation; of which the sayings <q direct="unspecified">after</q> and <q direct="unspecified">before,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">it
					has been</q> and <q direct="unspecified">it shall be,</q> are of themselves a confession
				that it has no being. For to say that what not yet is or what
				has already ceased to be is in being, how foolish and absurd
				is it. And as for that on which we chiefly ground the under
				standing of time,&mdash;saying, the instant, present, and now,&mdash;
				this again reason wholly rejects and overthrows; for it is
				lost between the future and the past, like a flash of light,
				and is separated into two when we will behold it. Now
				if the same thing befalls Nature, which is measured by
				time, as does the time which measures it, there is nothing
				in it permanent or subsistent, but all things are either
				breeding or dying, according to their commixture with
				time. Whence also it is not lawful to say of any thing
				which is, that it was or shall be; for these are inclinations
				and departures and changes of that whose nature is not to
				continue in being.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>But God, we must say, <hi rend="italics">is,</hi> and he is not in any time,
				but in eternity, which is immovable without time, and free
				from inclination, in which there is nothing first, or last, or
				newer; but being one, it has filled its eternal duration with
				one only <q direct="unspecified">now</q>; and that only <hi rend="italics">is</hi> which is really according
				to this, of which it cannot be said, that it either was or
				shall be, or that it begins or shall end. Thus ought those
				who worship to salute and invocate this Eternal Being, or
				else indeed, as some of the ancients have done, with this
				expression <foreign lang="greek">*ei)= e(/n</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">Thou art one.</hi> For the Divinity is not
				many, as every one of us is made of ten thousand differences in affections, being a confused heap, filled with all
				diversities. But that which <hi rend="italics">is</hi> must be one, as one must
				have a being. But diversity, which is esteemed to be different from being, goes forth to the generation of that which
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.496"/>
				
				is not. Whence both the first of his names agrees rightly
				with this God, as do also the second and third. For he is
				called Apollo, as denying plurality and rejecting multitude;
				and Ie&iuml;os, as being only one; and Phoebus was the name
				given by the ancients to every thing that is pure and chaste;
				as the Thessalians even to this day, if I am not mistaken,
				say of their priests, when on vacant days they abstain from
				the temples and keep themselves retired, that they purify
				themselves (<foreign lang="greek">foibonomei=sqai</foreign>). Now that which is one is sincere
				and pure. For pollution is by the mixture of one thing
				with another; as Homer, speaking of a piece of ivory dyed
				red, said it was <q direct="unspecified">polluted</q> by the dye, and dyers say of
				mixed colors that they are corrupted, and call the mixture
				itself corruption. It is therefore always requisite for that
				which is incorruptible and pure to be one and unmixed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Now, as for those who think Apollo and the Sun to
				be the same, they are to be caressed and loved for their
				ingenuity, as placing the notion of God in that which they
				most reverence, of all things that they know and desire.
				And now, as if they were dreaming of God the most glorious
				dream, let us stir up and exhort them to ascend higher, and
				to contemplate his reality and his essence; but to honor
				also this his image (the Sun), and to venerate that generative faculty he has placed in it, since it exhibits in some
				sort by its brightness&mdash;as far as it is possible for a sensible thing to represent an intellectual, and a movable thing
				that which is permanent&mdash;certain manifestations and resemblances of his benignity and blessedness. But as for
				those his sallyings out and changes, when he casts forth
				fire, . . . and when he again draws himself in, afterwards
				extending himself into the earth, sea, winds, animals, and
				strange accidents both of animals and plants, they cannot
				so much as be hearkened to without impiety; or else God
				will be worse than the child in the poet,&mdash;who made
				himself sport with a heap of sand, first raised and then
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.497"/>
				
				again scattered abroad by himself,&mdash;if he shall do the same
				in respect of the universe, first framing the world when it
				was not, and then destroying it when made. On the contrary, whatsoever of him is in any sort infused into the
				world, that binds together its substance, and restrains the
				corporeal weakness which tends to corruption. And it
				seems to me that this word is chiefly opposed to that
				doctrine, and that <foreign lang="greek">*ei)=</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">Thou art,</hi> is spoken to this God, as
				testifying that there is never in him any going forth or
				change. But to do and suffer this agrees to one of the other
				Gods, or rather Daemons, ordained to take care about Nature in generation and corruption; as is immediately manifest from their names, being wholly contrary and of different
				significations. For the one is called Apollo (or <hi rend="italics">not many</hi>),
				the other Pluto (or <hi rend="italics">many</hi>); the one Delius (from <hi rend="italics">clearness</hi>), the other Aidoneus (from <hi rend="italics">obscurity</hi>); the one Phoebus (or <hi rend="italics">shining</hi>), the other Scotius (or <hi rend="italics">dark</hi>); with the one
				are the Muses and Mnemosyne (or <hi rend="italics">song</hi> and <hi rend="italics">memory</hi>)
				with the other Lethe and Siope (or <hi rend="italics">forgetfulness</hi> and
				<hi rend="italics">silence</hi>). The one is (from <hi rend="italics">contemplating</hi> and <hi rend="italics">showing</hi>)
				named Theorius and Phanaeus; the other is
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Prince of dark night and sluggish sleep, whose fate
				</l>
                     <l>Is that men him most of all Gods do hate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Of Apollo also Pindar not unpleasantly sung, that he
					<quote rend="blockquote">The gentlest of all Gods to mortals is declared.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore Euripides rightly also said:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>These mournful songs suit well with men deceased,
					</l>
                     <l>With which gold-haired Apollo's no way pleased.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And before him Stesichorus:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Apollo joys in sports and pleasant tones;
					</l>
                     <l>But Pluto takes delight in griefs and moans.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Sophocles also evidently attributes to either of them his
					proper instruments, in these words:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Neither the lute nor psaltery is fit
					</l>
                     <l>For mournful matters.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.498"/>
            <p>For it is but very lately, and in a manner of yesterday, that
					the pipe has dared to introduce itself into delightful matters; having in former times drawn men to mourning, and
					possessing about these things no very honorable or splendid
					employment. But afterwards all was brought into confusion, which was due especially to those who confounded
					the affairs of the Gods with those of the Genii.</p>
            <p>But the sentence, Know thyself, seems in one respect to
					contradict this word <hi rend="italics">EI,</hi> and in another to agree with it.
					For the one is pronounced with admiration and veneration
					to God, as being eternal; and the other is a remembrance
					to mortal men of their nature and infirmity.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>