<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ad principem ineruditum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold North Fowler</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.10.p.51"/>
         <div1>
            <head>TO AN UNEDUCATED RULER (AD PRINCIPEM INERUDITUM)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>The brief essay To an Uneducated Ruler may have
					formed part of a lecture, or it may, as its traditional
					title suggests, have been composed as a letter to
					some person in authority. There is nothing in it
					to prove either assumption. No striking or unusual precepts or doctrines are here promulgated,
					but the essay is enlivened by a few interesting tales
					and, considering its brevity, by a somewhat unusual
					number of rather elaborate similes. As usual
					Plutarch depends upon earlier writers for most of his
					material. The ending is so abrupt as to warrant the
					belief that the essay, in its present form, is only a
					fragment.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.53"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Plato was asked by the Cyrenaeans<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That Plato in his extensive travels visited Cyrene is attested by Diogenes Laertius, <hi rend="italics">Vit. Phil.</hi> iii. 6.</note> to compose a
					set of laws and leave it for them and to give them a
					well-ordered government; but he refused, saying
					that it was difficult to make laws for the Cyrenaeans
					because they were so prosperous.
					<quote rend="blockquote">For nothing is so haughty</quote>
					harsh, and ungovernable
					<quote rend="blockquote">by nature as a man,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A quotation from some tragic poet; see Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 617.</note>
               </quote>
					when he possesses what he regards as prosperity.
					And that is why it is difficult to give advice to rulers
					in matters of government, for they are afraid to
					accept reason as a ruler over them, lest it curtail the
					advantage of their power by making them slaves to
					duty. For they are not familiar with the saying of
					Theopompus, the King of Sparta who first made the
					Ephors<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The five Ephors at Sparta, representing the five local tribes, were in charge of civil law and public order. Whether they were established by Lycurgus or by Theopompus (about 757 b.c. or later) is uncertain. In the sixth and fifth centuries b.c. they seem to have had more power than the kings.</note> associates of the Kings ; then, when his
					wife reproached him because he would hand down
					to his children a less powerful office than that which
					he had received he said : <q direct="unspecified">Nay, more powerful
						rather, inasmuch as it is more secure.</q> For by
					giving up that which was excessive and absolute in
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.55"/>
					
					
					it he avoided both the envy and the danger. And
					yet Theopompus, by diverting to a different body
					the vast stream of his royal authority, deprived
					himself of as much as he gave to others. But when
					philosophical reason derived from philosophy has
					been established as the ruler's coadjutor and guardian, it removes the hazardous element from his power,
					as a surgeon removes that which threatens a patient's
					health and leaves that which is sound.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But most kings and rulers are so foolish as to
					act like unskilful sculptors, who think their colossal
					figures look large and imposing if they are modelled
					with their feet far apart, their muscles tense, and
					their mouths wide open. For these rulers seem by
					heaviness of voice, harshness of expression, truculence of manner, and unsociability in their way of
					living to be imitating the dignity and majesty of
					the princely station, although in fact they are not
					at all different from colossal statues which have a
					heroic and godlike form on the outside, but inside
					are full of clay, stone, and lead, - except that in the
					case of the statues the weight of those substances
					keeps them permanently upright without leaning,
					whereas uneducated generals and rulers are often
					rocked and capsized by the ignorance within them ;
					for since the foundation upon which they have built
					up their lofty power is not laid straight, they lean
					with it and lose their balance. But just as a rule,
					if it is made rigid and inflexible, makes other
					things straight when they are fitted to it and laid
					alongside it, in like manner the sovereign must first
					gain command of himself, must regulate his own soul
					and establish his own character, then make his subjects
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.57"/>
					
					
					fit his pattern. For one who is falling cannot
					hold others up, nor can one who is ignorant teach,
					nor the uncultivated impart culture, nor the disorderly make order, nor can he rule who is under
					no rule. But most people foolishly believe that the
					first advantage of ruling is freedom from being ruled.
					And indeed the King of the Persians used to think
					that everyone was a slave except his own wife,
					whose master he ought to have been most of all.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Who, then, shall rule the ruler ? The
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Law, the king of all,
					</l>
                  <l>Both mortals and immortals,</l>
               </quote>
					as Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk-Schroeder, p. 458, no. 169 [151]; Sandys, p. 602, no. 169 (L.C.L.). Quoted by Plato, <hi rend="italics">Gorg.</hi> 484 b, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 690 b.</note> says - not law written outside him in books
					or on wooden tablets<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A reference to the original tablets of Solon's laws. See <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 779 b and note <hi rend="italics">b</hi>, p. 46 above.</note> or the like, but reason endowed
					with life within him, always abiding with him and
					watching over him and never leaving his soul without
					its leadership. For example, the King of the Persians
					had one of his chamberlains assigned to the special
					duty of entering his chamber in the morning and saying to him : <q direct="unspecified">Arise, O King, and consider matters
						which the great Oromasdes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Oromasdes is the Greek form of Ormaszd, Auramasda, or Ahura Mazda, the great god of the Persians.</note> wished you to consider.</q> But the educated and wise ruler has within
					him the voice which always thus speaks to him and
					exhorts him. Indeed Polemo said that love was
					<q direct="unspecified">the service of the gods for the care and preservation
						of the young</q> ; one might more truly say that rulers
					serve god for the care and preservation of men, in
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.59"/>
					
					
					order that of the glorious gifts which the gods give
					to men they may distribute some and safeguard
					others.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Dost thou behold this lofty, boundless sky
					</l>
                  <l>Which holds the earth enwrapped in soft embrace?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, unknown drama, Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 663. The following line is <foreign lang="greek">tou=ton no/mize *zh=na, to/nd' h(gou= *qeo/n</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">Believe that this is Zeus, consider this thy God.</q> Cicero translates this line in <hi rend="italics">De Natura Deorum</hi>, ii. 25. 65.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					The sky sends down the beginnings of the appropriate seeds, and the earth causes them to sprout up ;
					some are made to grow by showers and some by
					winds, and some by the warmth of stars and moon ;
					but it is the sun which adorns all things and mingles
					in all things what men call the <q direct="unspecified">love charm</q> which
					is derived from himself. But these gifts and blessings, so excellent and so great, which the gods
					bestow cannot be rightly enjoyed nor used without
					law and justice and a ruler. Now justice is the aim
					and end of law, but law is the work of the ruler, and
					the ruler is the image of God who orders all things.
					Such a ruler needs no Pheidias nor Polycleitus nor
					Myron to model him, but by his virtue he forms himself in the likeness of God and thus creates a statue
					most delightful of all to behold and most worthy
					of divinity. Now just as in the heavens God has
					established as a most beautiful image of himself the
					sun and the moon, so in states a ruler
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>who in God's likeness
					</l>
                  <l>Righteous decisions upholds,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xix. 109 and 111.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					that is to say, one who, possessing god's wisdom,
					establishes, as his likeness and luminary, intelligence
					in place of sceptre or thunderbolt or trident, with
					which attributes some rulers represent themselves
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.61"/>
					
					
					in sculpture and painting, thus causing their folly
					to arouse hostile feelings, because they claim what
					they cannot attain. For God visits his wrath
					upon those who imitate his thunders, lightnings,
					and sunbeams, but with those who emulate his
					virtue and make themselves like unto his goodness
					and mercy he is well pleased and therefore causes
					them to prosper and gives them a share of his own
					equity, justice, truth, and gentleness, than which
					nothing is more divine, - nor fire, nor light, nor the
					course of the sun, nor the risings and settings of the
					stars, nor eternity and immortality. For God enjoys
					felicity, not through the length of his life, but through
					the ruling quality of his virtue; for this is divine; and
					excellent also is that part of virtue which submits to
					rule.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Now it is true that Anaxarchus, trying to console Alexander in his agony of mind over his killing
					of Cleitus, said that the reason why Justice and
					Right are seated by the side<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Just as at Athens the archons had their <hi rend="italics">paredroi</hi> who aided them in the performance of some of their functions, so here Justice and Right are called the <hi rend="italics">paredroi</hi> of Zeus.</note> of Zeus is that men
					may consider every act of a king as righteous and just;
					but neither correct nor helpful were the means he
					took in endeavouring to heal the king's remorse
					for his sin, by encouraging him to further acts of
					the same sort. But if a guess about this matter
					is proper, I should say that Zeus does not have
					Justice to sit beside him, but is himself Justice
					and Right and the oldest and most perfect of laws ;
					but the ancients state it in that way in their
					writings and teachings, to imply that without
					Justice not even Zeus can rule well. <q direct="unspecified">She is a
						virgin,</q> according to Hesiod,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 256-257 <foreign lang="greek">h( de/ te parqe/nos e)sti *di/kh, *dio\s e)kgegaui=a kudrh/ t' ai)doi/h te qew=n, oi(\ *)/olumpon e)/xousin</foreign>. <q direct="unspecified">And there is Virgin Justice, the daughter of Zeus, who is honoured and reverenced among the gods who dwell on Olympus</q> (tr. H. G. Evelyn White in L.C.L.).</note> uncorrupted, dwelling
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.63"/>
					
					
					with reverence, self-restraint, and helpfulness ; and
					therefore kings are called <q direct="unspecified">reverend,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 402.</note> for it is
					fitting that those be most revered who have least to
					fear. But the ruler should have more fear of doing
					than of suffering evil ; for the former is the cause of
					the latter ; and that kind of fear on the part of the
					ruler is humane and not ignoble to be afraid on
					behalf of his subjects lest they may without his
					knowledge suffer harm,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Just as the dogs keep their watch, toiling hard for the
					flocks in the sheepfold,
					</l>
                  <l>When they have heard a ferocious wild beast,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 183-184.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					not for their own sake but for the sake of those whom
					they are guarding. Epameinondas, when all the
					Thebans crowded to a certain festival and gave
					themselves up utterly to drink, went alone and
					patrolled the armouries and the walls, saying that
					he was keeping sober and awake that the others
					might be free to be drunk and asleep. And Cato
					at Utica issued a proclamation to send all the other
					survivors of the defeat to the seashore ; he saw
					them aboard ship, prayed that they might have a
					good voyage, then returned home and killed himself ; thereby teaching us in whose behalf the ruler
					ought to feel fear and what the ruler ought to
					despise. But Clearchus, tyrant of Pontus, used to
					crawl into a chest like a snake and sleep there, and
					Aristodemus of Argos would mount to an upper
					room entered by a trap-door, then put his bed on
					the door and sleep in it with his mistress ; and the
					girl's mother would take the ladder away from below
					and set it up again in the morning. How do you
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.65"/>
					
					
					imagine he must have shuddered at the theatre,
					the city hall, the senate - chamber, the convivial
					feast, he who had made his bedchamber a prison
					cell ? For in reality kings fear for their subjects,
					but tyrants fear their subjects ; and therefore they
					increase their fear as they increase their power,
					for when they have more subjects they have more
					men to fear.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>For it is neither probable nor fitting that god
					is, as some philosophers say, mingled with matter,
					which is altogether passive, and with things, which
					are subject to countless necessities, chances, and
					changes. On the contrary, somewhere up above
					in contact with that nature which, in accordance with
					the same principles, remains always as it is, established, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 254 b.</note> says, upon pedestals of holiness,
					proceeding in accordance with nature in his straight
					course, he reaches his goal.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 716 a.</note> And as the sun, his
					most beautiful image, appears in the heavens as his
					mirrored likeness to those who are able to see him
					in it, just so he has established in states the light
					of justice and of knowledge of himself as an image
					which the blessed and the wise copy with the help
					of philosophy, modelling themselves after the most
					beautiful of all things. But nothing implants this
					disposition in men except the teachings of philosophy, to keep us from having the same experience
					as Alexander, who, seeing Diogenes at Corinth,
					admiring him for his natural gifts, and being astonished by his spirit and greatness, said : <q direct="unspecified">If I
						were not Alexander, I should be Diogenes,</q> by
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.67"/>
					
					
					which he almost said that he was weighed down by
					his good fortune, glory, and power which kept him
					from virtue and left him no leisure, and that he
					envied the cynic's cloak and wallet because Diogenes
					was invincible and secure against capture by means
					of these, not, as he was himself, by means of arms,
					horses, and pikes. So by being a philosopher he was
					able to become Diogenes in disposition and yet to
					remain Alexander in outward fortunes, and to become all the more Diogenes because he was Alexander, since for his great ship of fortune, tossed by
					high winds and surging sea, he needed heavy ballast
					and a great pilot.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>For in weak and lowly private persons folly is
					combined with lack of power and, therefore, results
					in no wrongdoing, just as in bad dreams a feeling of
					distress disturbs the spirit, and it cannot rouse itself
					in accordance with its desires ; but power when
					wickedness is added to it brings increased vigour to
					the passions. For the saying of Dionysius is true;
					he said, namely, that he enjoyed his power most when
					he did quickly what he wished. There is indeed
					great danger that he who can do what he wishes
					may wish what he ought not to do :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Straightway then was the word, and the deed was forthwith accomplished.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xix. 242.</note>
               </quote>
					Wickedness, when by reason of power it possesses
					rapid speed, forces every passion to emerge, making
					of anger murder, of love adultery, of covetousness
					confiscation.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.69"/>
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Straightway then was the word,</quote>
						and the offender is done away with ; suspicion arises,
					the man who is slandered is put to death. But as
					the physicists say that the lightning breaks forth later
					than the thunder, as the flowing of blood is later
					than the wound, but is seen sooner, since the hearing
					waits for the sound, whereas the sight goes to meet
					the light; so in governments punishments come
					before the accusations and convictions are pronounced
					before the proofs are given.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>For now the spirit yields and holds no longer firm,
					</l>
                  <l>As yields the anchor's fluke in sand when waves are high,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From a work of an unknown tragic poet; see Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 911, no. 379; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 446 a.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					unless the weight of reason presses upon power and
					holds it down, and the ruler imitates the sun, which,
					when it mounts up in the northern sky and reaches
					its greatest altitude, has the least motion, thus by
					greater slowness ensuring the safety of its course.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Nor is it possible in positions of power for vices
					to be concealed. Epileptics, if they go up to a high
					place and move about, grow dizzy and reel, which
					makes their disease evident, and just so Fortune by
					such things as riches, reputations, or offices exalts
					uneducated and uncultured men a little and then, as
					soon as they have risen high, gives them a conspicuous
					fall; or, to use a better simile, just as in a number
					of vessels you could not tell which is whole and
					which is defective, but when you pour liquid into
					them the leak appears, just so corrupt souls cannot
					contain power, but leak out in acts of desire, anger,
					imposture, and bad taste. But what is the use of
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.71"/>
					
					
					saying these things, when even the slightest short-comings in men of conspicuous reputation are made
					the subject of calumny ? Too much wine caused
					slander against Cimon, too much sleep against Scipio,
					Lucullus was ill spoken of because his dinners were
					too expensive . . .
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>