<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De capienda ex inimicis utilitate</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.072">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.280"/>
         <head>How a man may receive advantage and profit from his enemies.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Not to mention, Cornelius Pulcher, your gentle as
					well as skilful administration of public affairs, for which
					goodness and humanity you have gotten an interest in mankind, we clearly perceive that in your private conversation
					you have made a quiet and peaceable way of living your
					choice and continual practice. By this means you are
					justly esteemed a useful member of the commonwealth in
					general, and also a friendly affable companion to those who
					familiarly converse with you, as being a person free from
					all sour, rough, and peevish humors. For, as it is said of
					Crete, we may by great chance discover one single region
					of the world that never afforded any dens or coverts for
					wild beasts. But through the long succession of ages,
					even to this time, there scarce ever was a state or kingdom that hath not suffered under envy, hatred, emulation,
					the love of strife, fierce and unruly passions, of all others
					the most productive of enmity and ill-will among men.
					Nay, if nothing else will bring it to pass, familiarity will
					at last breed contempt, and the very friendship of men
					doth frequently draw them into quarrels, that prove sharp
					and sometimes implacable. Which that wise man Chilo
					did well understand, who, when he heard another assert
					that he had no enemy, asked him very pertinently whether
					he had no friend. In my judgment therefore it is absolutely necessary that a man, especially if he sit at the
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.281"/>
					
					helm and be engaged to steer the government, should
					watchfully observe every posture and motion of his enemy,
					and subscribe to Xenophon's opinion in this case; who
					hath set it down as a maxim of the greatest wisdom, that
					a man should make the best advantage he can of him
					that is his adversary.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, having lately determined to write somewhat
						on this argument, I have now gathered together all my
						scattered thoughts and meditations upon it, which I have
						sent to you, digested into as plain a method as I could;
						forbearing all along to mention those observations I have
						heretofore made and written in my Political Precepts,
						because I know you have that treatise at your hand, and
						often under your eye.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Our ancestors were well satisfied and content if they
					could safely guard themselves from the violent incursions
					of wild beasts, and this was the end and object of all their
					contests with these creatures. But their posterity have
					laid down their weapons of defence, and have invented a
					quite contrary use of them, making them serviceable to
					some of the chief ends of human life. For their flesh
					serves for food, and their hair for clothing; medicines and
					antidotes are devised out of their entrails; and their skins
					are converted into armor. So that we may upon good
					grounds fear that, if these supplies should fail, their manner of life would appear savage, destitute of convenient
					food and raiment, barbarous and naked.</p>
            <p>Although we receive these benefits and comforts from
						the very beasts, yet some men suppose themselves happy
						and secure enough, provided they escape all harm from
						enemies, not regarding Xenophon's judgment, whom they
						ought to credit in this matter, that every man endowed
						with common sense and understanding may, if he please,
						make his opposites very useful and profitable to him.</p>
            <p>Because then we cannot live in this world out of the
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.282"/>
						
						neighborhood of such as will continually labor to do us
						injury or oppose us, let us search out some way whereby
						this advantage and profit from enemies may be acquired.</p>
            <p>The best experienced gardener cannot so change the
						nature of every tree, that it shall yield pleasant and well-tasted fruit; neither can the craftiest huntsman tame every
						beast. One therefore makes the best use he can of his
						trees, the other of his beast; although the first perhaps are
						barren and dry, the latter wild and ungovernable. So seawater is unwholesome and not to be drunk; yet it affords
						nourishment to all sorts of fish, and serves as it were for a
						chariot to convey those who visit foreign countries. The
						Satyr would have kissed and embraced the fire the first
						time he saw it; but Prometheus bids him take heed, else he
						might have cause to lament the loss of his beard,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*tra/gos ge/neion a)=ra penqh/seis si/ ge,</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Thou goat, soon thou shalt bewail the loss of</hi>
							           <hi rend="italics">thy beard.</hi> This verse is supposed to belong to the Satyrdrama <hi rend="italics">Prometheus</hi> ofAeschylus, which was exhibited with the trilogy to which the Persians belong. Thewhole tetralogy, according to the <hi rend="italics">didascalia,</hi> consisted of the <hi rend="italics">Phineus, Persians, Glaucus,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Prometheus. (G.)</hi>
               </note> if he
						came too near that which burns all it touches. Yet this
						very fire is a most beneficial thing to mankind; it bestows
						upon us the blessings both of light and heat, and serves
						those who know how to use it for the most excellent instrument of mechanic arts. Directed by these examples, we
						may be able to take right measures of our enemies, considering that by one handle or other we may lay hold
						of them for the use and benefit of our lives; though
						otherwise they may appear very untractable and hurtful
						to us.</p>
            <p>There are many things which, when we have obtained
						them by much labor and sweat, become nauseous, ungrateful, and directly contrary to our inclinations; but
						there are some (you know) who can turn the very indispositions of their bodies into an occasion of rest and freedom
						from business. And hard pains that have fallen upon
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.283"/>
						
						many men have rendered them only the more robust
						through vigorous exercise. There are others who, as
						Diogenes and Crates did, have made banishment from their
						native country and loss of all their goods a means to pass
						out of a troublesome world into the quiet and serene state
						of philosophy and mental contemplation. So the Stoic
						Zeno welcomed the good fortune, when he heard the ship
						was broken wherein his adventures were, because she had
						reduced him to a torn coat, to the safety and innocence
						of a mean and low condition. For as some creatures of
						strong constitutions eat serpents and digest them well,&mdash;
						nay, there are some whose stomachs can by a strange
						powerful heat concoct shells or stones,&mdash;while on the
						contrary, there are the weak and diseased, who loathe
						even bread and wine, the most agreeable and best supports
						of human life; so the foolish and inconsiderate spoil the
						very friendships they are engaged in, but the wise and
						prudent make good use of the hatred and enmity of men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>To those then who are discreet and cautious, the
					most malignant and worst part of enmity becomes advantageous and useful. But what is this you talk of all this
					whileAn enemy is ever diligent and watchful to contrive stratagems and lay snares for us, not omitting any
					opportunity whereby he may carry on his malicious purposes. He lays siege to our whole life, and turns spy into
					the most minute action of it; not as Lynceus is said to
					look into oaks and stones, but by arts of insinuation he
					gets to the knowledge of our secrets, by our bosom friend,
					domestic servant, and intimate acquaintance. As much as
					possibly he can, he enquires what we have done, and labors
					to dive into the most hidden counsels of our minds. Nay,
					our friends do often escape our notice, either when they
					die or are sick, because we are careless and neglect them;
					but we are apt to examine and pry curiously almost into
					the very dreams of our enemies.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.284"/>
            <p>Now our enemy (to gratify his ill-will towards us) doth
						acquaint himself with the infirmities both of our bodies and
						mind, with the debts we have contracted, and with all the
						differences that arise in our families, all which he knows
						as well, if not better, than ourselves. He sticks fast to our
						faults, and chiefly makes his invidious remarks upon them.
						Nay, our most depraved affections, that are the worst distempers of our minds, are always the subjects of his inquiry;
						just as vultures pursue putrid flesh, noisome and corrupted
						carcasses, because they have no perception of those that
						are sound and in health. So our enemies catch at our failings, and then they spread them abroad by uncharitable
						and ill-natured reports.</p>
            <p>Hence we are taught this useful lesson for the direction
						and management of our conversations in the world, that
						we be circumspect and wary in every thing we speak or do,
						as if our enemy always stood at our elbow and overlooked
						every action. Hence we learn to lead blameless and inoffensive lives. This will beget in us vehement desires and
						earnest endeavors of restraining disorderly passions. This
						will fill our minds with good thoughts and meditations, and
						with strong resolutions to proceed in a virtuous and harmless course of life.</p>
            <p>For as those commonwealths and cities know best how
						to value the happiness of having good and wholesome laws,
						and most admire and love the safety of a quiet and peaceable constitution of things, which have been harassed by
						wars with their neighbors or by long expeditions; so those
						persons who have been brought to live soberly by tile fear
						and awe of enemies, who have learned to guard against
						negligence and idleness, and to do every thing with a view
						to some profitable end, are by degrees (they know not how)
						drawn into a habit of living so as to offend nobody, and
						their manners are composed and fixed in their obedience to
						virtue by custom and use, with very little help from the
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.285"/>
						
						reason. For they always carry in their minds that saying
						of Homer, if we act any thing amiss,
						
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Priam will laugh at us, and all his brood;</l>
               </quote>
						
						our enemies will please themselves and scoff at our defects; therefore we will do nothing that is ridiculous, sinful,
						base, or ignoble, lest we become a laughing-stock to such
						as do not love us.</p>
            <p>In the theatre we often see great artists in music and
						singing very supine and remiss, doing nothing as they
						should, whilst they play or sing alone; but whenever they
						challenge one another and contend for mastery, they do
						not only rouse up themselves, but they tune their instruments more carefully, they are more curious in the choice
						of their strings, and they try their notes in frequent and
						more harmonious consorts. Just so a man who hath an
						adversary perpetually to rival him in the well ordering of
						his life and reputation is thereby rendered more prudent
						in what he does, looks after his actions more circumspectly,
						and takes as much care of the accurateness of them as the
						musician does of his lute or organ. For evil hath this
						peculiar quality in it, that it dreads an enemy more than a
						friend. For this cause Nasica, when some thought the
						Roman affairs were established for ever in peace and safety,
						after they had razed Carthage and enslaved Greece, declared that even then they were in the greatest danger of
						all and most likely to be undone, because there were none
						left whom they might still fear and stand in some awe of.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>And here may be inserted that wise and facetious
					answer of Diogenes to one that asked him how he might
					be revenged of his enemy: The only way, says he, to gall
					and fret him effectually is for yourself to appear a good
					and honest man. The common people are generally envious and vexed in their minds, as oft as they see the cattle
					of those they have no kindness for, their dogs, or their
					horses, in a thriving condition; they sigh, fret, set their
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.286"/>
					
					teeth, and show all the tokens of a malicious temper, when
					they behold their fields well tilled, or their gardens adorned
					and beset with flowers. If these things make them so
					restless and uneasy, what dost thou think they would do,
					what a torment would it be to them, if thou shouldst demonstrate thyself in the face of the world to be in all thy
					carriage a man of impartial justice, a sound understanding,
					unblamable integrity, of a ready and eloquent speech, sincere and upright in all your dealings, sober and temperate
					in all that you eat or drink;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>While from the culture of a prudent mind,</l>
						            <l>Harvests of wise and noble thought you reap.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Aeschyl. Septem, 593 See note on page 202. (G.)</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Those that are conquered, saith Pindar, must seal up
						their lips; they dare not open their mouths, no, not even
						to mutter.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Fragment 253</note> But all men in these circumstances are not so
						restrained; but such chiefly as come behind their opposites
						in the practice of diligence, honesty, greatness of mind,
						humanity, and beneficence. These are beautiful and glorious virtues, as Demosthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Fals. Legat. p. 406, 4.</note> says, that are too pure and
						great to be touched by an ill tongue, that stop the mouths
						of backbiters, choke them and command them to be silent.
						Make it thy business therefore to surpass the base; for this
						surely thou canst do. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orest. 251.</note> If we would vex them that hate
						us, we must not reproach our adversary for an effeminate
						and debauched person, or one of a boorish and filthy conversation; but instead of throwing this dirt, we ourselves
						must be remarkable for a steady virtue and a wellgoverned behavior; we must speak the truth, and carry
						ourselves civilly and justly towards all who hold any correspondence or maintain any commerce with us. But if at
						any time a man is so transported by passion as to utter any
						bitter words, he must take heed that he himself be not
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.287"/>
						
						chargeable for those crimes for which he upbraids others;
						he must descend into himself, examine and cleanse his own
						breast, that no putrefaction nor rottenness be lodged there;
						otherwise he will be condemned as the physician is by the
						tragedian:&mdash;
						
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Wilt thou heal others, thou thyself being full of sores?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Eurip. Frag. No. 1071.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>If a man should jeer you and say that you are a dunce
						and illiterate, upon this motive you ought to apply your
						mind to the taking of pains in the study of philosophy and
						all kinds of learning. If he abuses you for a coward, then
						raise up your mind to a courageous manliness and an undaunted boldness of spirit. If he tells you you are lascivious
						and wanton, this scandal may be wiped off by having your
						mind barred up against all impressions of lust, and your
						discourse free from the least obscenity. These are allowable returns, and the most cutting strokes you can give your
						enemy; there being nothing that carries in it more vexation
						and disgrace, than that scandalous censures should fall
						back upon the head of him who was the first author of
						them. For as the beams of the sun reverberated do most
						severely affect and punish weak eyes, so those calumnies
						are most vexatious and intolerable which truth retorts back
						upon their first broachers. For as the north-east wind
						gathers clouds, so does a vicious life gather unto itself opprobrious speeches.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Insomuch that Plato, when he was in company with
					any persons that were guilty of unhandsome actions, was
					wont thus to reflect upon himself and ask this question,
					Am I of the like temper and disposition with these men?
					In like manner, whosoever passes a hard censure upon another man's life should presently make use of selfexamination, and enquire what his own is; by which means he
					will come to know what his failings are, and how to amend
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.288"/>
					
					them. Thus the very censures and backbitings of his
					enemy will redound to his advantage, although in itself this
					censorious humor is a very vain, empty, and useless thing.
					For every one will laugh at and deride that man who is
					humpbacked and baldpated, while at the same time he
					makes sport with the natural deformities of his brethren;
					it being a very ridiculous unaccountable thing to scoff at
					another for those very imperfections for which you yourself
					may be abused. As Leo Byzantinus replied upon the humpbacked man, who in drollery reflected on the weakness of
					his eyes, You mock me for a human infirmity, but you
					bear the marks of divine vengeance on your own back.</p>
            <p>Wherefore no man should arraign another of adultery,
						when he himself is addicted to a more bestial vice. Neither
						may one man justly accuse another of extravagance or looseness, when he himself is stingy and covetous. Alcmaeon
						told Adrastus, that he was near akin to a woman that
						killed her husband; to which Adrastus gave a very pat and
						sharp answer,&mdash;Thou with thy own hands didst murder thy
						mother.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Adrastus of Euripides.</note> After the same sarcastical way of jesting did
						Domitius ask Crassus whether he did not weep for the
						death of the lamprey that was bred in his fish-pond; to
						which Crassus makes this present reply,&mdash;But have I not
						heard that you did not weep when you carried out three
						wives to their burial.</p>
            <p>Whence we may infer that it behooves every man who
						takes upon him to correct or censure another not to be too
						clamorous or merry upon his faults, but to be guilty of no
						such crime as may expose him to the chastisement and
						reproach of others. For the great God seems to have given
						that commandment of <hi rend="italics">Know thyself</hi> to those men more especially who are apt to make remarks upon other men's
						actions and forget themselves. So, as Sophocles hath well
						observed, They often hear that which they would not, because
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.289"/>
						
						 they allow themselves the liberty of talking what
						they please.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>This is the use that may be lawfully made of censuring and judging our enemies; that we may be sure we are
					not culpable for the same misdemeanors which we condemn
					in them. On the contrary, we may reap no less advantage
					from our being judged and censured by our enemies. In
					this case Antisthenes spake incomparably well, that if a man
					would lead a secure and blameless life, it was necessary that
					he should have either very ingenuous and honest friends, or
					very furious enemies, because the first would keep him from
					sinning by their kind admonitions, the latter by their evil
					words and vehement invectives.</p>
            <p>But for as much as in these times friendship is grown
						almost speechless, and hath left off that freedom it did
						once use, since it is loquacious in flattery and dumb in
						admonition, therefore we must expect to hear truth only
						from the mouths of enemies. As Telephus, when he could
						find no physician that he could confide in as his friend,
						thought his adversary's lance would most probably heal his
						wound; so he that hath no friend to give him advice and
						to reprove him in what he acts amiss must bear patiently
						the rebukes of an enemy, and thereby learn to amend the
						errors of his ways; considering seriously the object which
						these severe censures aim at, and not what the person is
						who makes them. For as he who designed the death of
						Prometheus the Thessalian, instead of giving the fatal blow,
						only lanced a swelling that he had, which did really preserve his life and free him from the hazard of approaching
						death; just so may the harsh reprehensions of enemies cure
						some distempers of the mind that were before either unknown or neglected, though these angry speeches do origi
						nally proceed from malice and ill-will. But many, when
						they are accused of a crime, do not consider whether they
						are guilty of the matter alleged against them, but are rather
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.290"/>
						
						solicitous whether the accuser hath nothing that may be
						laid to his charge; like the combatants in a match at wrestling, they take no care to wipe off the dirt that sticks upon
						them, but they go on to besmear one another, and in their
						mutual strugglings they wallow and tumble into more dirt
						and filthiness.</p>
            <p>It is a matter of greater importance and concern to a
						man when he is lashed by the slanders of an enemy, by
						living virtuously to prevent and avert all objections that
						may be made against his life, than it is to scour the spots
						out of his clothes when they are shown him. And even if
						any man with opprobrious language object to you crimes
						you know nothing of, you ought to enquire into the causes
						and reasons of such false accusations, that you may learn
						to take heed for the future and be very wary, lest unwittingly you should commit those offences that are unjustly
						attributed to you, or something that comes near them.
						Lacydes, king of the Argives, was abused as an effeminate person, because he wore his hair long, used to dress
						himself neatly, and his mien was finical. So Pompey,
						though he was very far from any effeminate softness, yet
						was reflected upon and jeered for being used to scratch his
						head with one of his fingers. Crassus also suffered much
						in the like kind, because sometimes he visited a vestal virgin and showed great attention to her, having a design to
						purchase of her a little farm that lay conveniently for him.
						So Postumia was suspected of unchaste actions, and was
						even brought to trial, because she would often be very
						cheerful and discourse freely in men's company. But she
						was found clear of all manner of guilt in that nature.
						Nevertheless at her dismission, Spurius Minucius the Pontifex Maximus gave her this good admonition, that her words
						should be always as pure, chaste, and modest as her life
						was. Themistocles, though he had offended in nothing,
						yet was suspected of treachery with Pausanias, because he
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.291"/>
						
						corresponded familiarly with him, and used every day to
						send him letters and messengers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Whenever then any thing is spoken against you that
					is not true, do not pass it by or despise it because it is false,
					but forthwith examine yourself, and consider what you have
					said or done, what you have ever undertaken, or what converse you have ever had that may have given likelihood to
					the slander; and when this is discovered, decline for the
					future all things that may provoke any reproachful or foul
					language from others.</p>
            <p>For if troubles and difficulties, into which some men fall
						either by chance or through their own inadvertency and
						rashness, may teach others what is fit and safe for them to
						do,&mdash;as Merope says,
						
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Fortune hath taken for her salary</l>
							           <l>My dearest goods, but wisdom she hath given;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>From Euripides.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
						
						why should not we take an enemy for our tutor, who will
						instruct us gratis in those things we knew not before? For
						an enemy sees and understands more in matters relating to
						us than our friends do; because love is blind, as Plato<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Laws, V. p. 731 E</note>
						says, in discerning the imperfections of the thing beloved.
						But spite, malice, ill-will, wrath, and contempt talk much,
						are very inquisitive and quick-sighted. When Hiero was
						upbraided by his enemy for having a stinking breath, he
						returned home and demanded of his wife why she had not
						acquainted him with it. The innocent good woman makes
						this answer: I thought all men's breath had that smell.
						For those things in men that are conspicuous to all are
						sooner understood from the information of enemies than
						from that of friends and acquaintance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Furthermore, an exact government of the tongue is
					a strong evidence of a good mind, and no inconsiderable
					part of virtue. But since every man naturally is desirous
					to propagate his conceits, and without a painful force cannot
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.292"/>
					
					 smother his resentments, it is no easy task to keep
					this unruly member in due subjection, unless such an
					impetuous affection as anger be thoroughly subdued by
					much exercise, care, and study. For such things as <q direct="unspecified">saying let fall against our will,</q> or <q direct="unspecified">a word flying by the
						range of our teeth,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IV. 350.</note> or <q direct="unspecified">a speech escaping us by accident,</q>
					are all likely to happen to those whose ill-exercised minds
					(as it were) fall and waste away, and whose course of life
					is licentious; and we may attribute this to hasty passion
					or to unsettled judgment. For divine Plato tells us that
					for a word, which is the lightest of all things, both Gods
					and men inflict the heaviest penalties.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Laws, XI. p. 935 A.</note> But silence, which
					can never be called to account, doth not only, as Hippocrates hath observed, extinguish thirst, but it bears up
					against all manner of slanders with the constancy of
					Socrates and the courage of Hercules, who was no more
					concerned than a fly at what others said or did. Now it
					is certainly not grander or better than this for a man to
					bear silently and quietly the revilings of an enemy, taking
					care not to provoke him, as if he were swimming by a
					dangerous rock; but the practice is better. For whosoever is thus accustomed to endure patiently the scoffs of an
					enemy will, without any disturbance or trouble, bear with
					the chidings of a wife, the rebukes of a friend, or the
					sharper reproofs of a brother. When a father or mother
					corrects you, you will not be refractory or stubborn under
					the rod. Xanthippe, though she was a woman of a very
					angry and troublesome spirit, could never move Socrates to
					a passion. By being used to bear patiently this heavy
					sufferance at home, he was ever unconcerned, and not
					in the least moved by the most scurrilous and abusive
					tongues he met withal abroad. For it is much better to
					overcome boisterous passions and to bring the mind into a
					calm and even frame of spirit, by contentedly undergoing
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.293"/>
					
					the scoffs, outrages, and affronts of enemies, than to be
					stirred up to choler or revenge by the worst they can say
					or do.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Thus we may show a meek and gentle temper and a
					submissive bearing of evil in our enmities; and even integrity, magnanimity, and goodness of disposition are also
					more conspicuous here than in friendship. For it is not so
					honorable and virtuous to do a friend a kindness, as it is
					unworthy and base to omit this good office when he stands
					in need; but it is an eminent piece of humanity, and a
					manifest token of a nature truly generous, to put up with
					the affronts of an enemy when you have a fair opportunity
					to revenge them. For if any one sympathizes with his
					enemy in his affliction, relieves him in his necessities, and
					is ready to assist his sons and family if they desire it, any
					one that will not love this man for his compassion, and
					highly commend him for his charity, <q direct="unspecified">must have a black
						heart made of adamant or iron,</q> as Pindar says.</p>
            <p>When Caesar made an edict that the statues of Pompey
						which were tumbled down should be rebuilt and restored
						to their former beauty and magnificence, Tully tells him
						that by setting up again Pompey's statues he has erected one
						for himself, an everlasting monument of praise and honor
						to after ages. So that we must give to every one his due,
						to an enemy such respect and honor as he truly deserves.
						Thus a man that praises his enemy for his real deserts
						shall himself obtain the more honor by it; and whenever
						he shall correct or censure him, he will be credited in what
						he does, because every one will believe that he does it out
						of a dislike and just abhorrence of his vice and not of his
						person.</p>
            <p>By this practice we shall be brought at length to perform the most honorable and worthy actions; for he who
						is wont to praise and speak the best things of his enemies
						will never repine at the prosperity or success of his friends
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.294"/>
						
						and acquaintance; he is never troubled, but rather rejoices,
						when they thrive and are happy. And what virtue can
						any man exercise that will be more profitable and delightful to him than this, which takes away from him the
						bitterness of malice, and doth not only break the teeth of
						envy, but, by teaching him to rejoice at another man's
						felicity, doth double his own enjoyment and satisfaction.
						As in war many things, although they are bad and evil in
						themselves, yet have become necessary, and by long custom
						and prescription have obtained the validity of a law, so
						that it is not easy to root them out, even by those who
						thereby suffer much harm; just so doth enmity usher in
						the mind a long train of vices, meagre envy coupled with
						grim hatred, restless jealousy and suspicion, unnatural joy
						at other men's miseries, and a long remembrance of injuries.
						Fraud, deceit, and snares, joined to these forces of wickedness, work infinite mischief in the world, yet they appear
						as no evils at all when they are exerted against an enemy.
						By this means they make a deep entrance into the mind;
						they get fast hold of it, and are hardly shaken off. So
						that, unless we forbear the practice of these ill qualities
						towards our enemies, they will by frequent acts become so
						habitual to us, that we shall be apt to make use of them to
						the manifest wrong and injury of our friends. Wherefore,
						if Pythagoras was highly esteemed for instructing his disciples to avoid all manner of cruelty against beasts themselves,&mdash;so that he himself would redeem them out of
						their captivity in either the fowler's or the fisherman's net,
						and forbade his followers to kill any creature,&mdash;it is surely
						much better and more manly in our differences with men
						to show ourselves generous, just, and detesters of all falsehood, and to moderate and correct all base, unworthy, and
						hurtful passions; that in all our conversation with our
						friends we may be open-hearted, and that we may not
						seek to overreach or deceive others in any of our dealings.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.295"/>
            <p>For Scaurus was a professed enemy and an open accuser
						of Domitius; whereupon a treacherous servant of Domitius comes to Scaurus before the cause was to be heard,
						and tells him that he has a secret to communicate to him
						in relation to the present suit, which he knows not of, and
						which may be very advantageous on his side. Yet Scaurus
						would not permit him to speak a word, but apprehended
						him, and sent him back to his master. And when Cato
						was prosecuting Murena for bribery, and was collecting
						evidence to support his charge, he was accompanied
						(according to custom) by certain persons in the interest
						of the defendant, who watched his transactions. These
						often asked him in the morning, whether he intended on
						that day to collect evidence or make other preparation for
						the trial; and so soon as he told them he should not, they
						put such trust in him that they went their way. This was
						a plain demonstration of the extraordinary deference and
						honor they paid to Cato; but a far greater testimony, and
						one surpassing all the rest, is it to prove that, if we accustom ourselves to deal justly and uprightly with our enemies,
						then we shall not fail to behave ourselves so towards our
						friends.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Simonides was wont to say that there was no lark
					without its crest; so the disposition of men is naturally
					pregnant with strife, suspicion, and envy, which last (as
					Pindar observes) is <q direct="unspecified">the companion of empty-brained
						men.</q> Therefore no man can do any thing that will
					tend more to his own profit and the preservation of his
					peace than utterly to purge out of his mind these corrupt
					affections, and cast them off as the very sink of all iniquity,
					that they may create no more mischief between him and
					his friends. This Onomademus, a judicious and wise man,
					understood well, who, when he was of the prevailing side
					in a civil commotion at Chios, gave this counsel to his
					friends, that they should not quite destroy or drive away
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.296"/>
					
					those of the adverse party, but let some abide there, for
					fear they should begin to fall out among themselves as
					soon as their enemies were all out of the way. Therefore,
					if these uneasy dispositions of the mind be spent and consumed upon enemies, they would never molest or disquiet
					our friends. Neither doth Hesiod approve of one potter
					or one singer's envying another, or that a neighbor or
					relation or brother should resent it ill that another prospers and is successful in the world.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 23.</note> But if there be no
					other way whereby we may be delivered from emulation,
					envy, or contention, we may suffer our minds to vent these
					passions upon the prosperity of our enemies, and whet the
					edge and sharpen the point of our anger upon them. For
					as gardeners that have knowledge and experience in plants
					expect their roses and violets should grow the better by
					being set near leeks and onions,&mdash;because all the sour
					juices of the earth are conveyed into these,&mdash;so an enemy
					by attracting to himself our vicious and peevish qualities,
					may render us less humorsome and more candid and ingenuous to our friends that are in a better or more
					happy state than ourselves.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let us enter the lists with our enemies, and
						contend with them for true glory, lawful empire, and just
						gain. Let us not so much debase ourselves as to be troubled
						and fret at any possessions they enjoy more than we have.
						Let us rather carefully observe those good qualities wherein our enemies excel us, so that by these motives we may
						be excited to outdo them in honest diligence, indefatigable
						industry, prudent caution, and exemplary sobriety; as
						Themistocles complained that the victory Miltiades got at
						Marathon would not let him sleep. But whosoever views
						his adversary exalted far above him in dignities, in pleading of great causes, in administration of state affairs, or in
						favor and friendship with princes, and doth not put forth
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.297"/>
						
						all his strength and power to get before him in these
						things,&mdash;this man commonly pines away, and by degrees
						sinks into the sloth and misery of an envious and inactive
						life. And we may observe, that envy and hatred do raise
						such clouds in the understanding, that a man shall not be
						able to pass a right judgment concerning things which he
						hates; but whosoever with an impartial eye beholds, and
						with a sincere mind judges, the life and manners, discourses, and actions of his enemy, will soon understand
						that many of those things that raise his envy were gotten
						by honest care, a discreet providence, and virtuous deeds.
						Thus the love of honorable and brave actions may be
						kindled and advanced in him, and an idle and lazy course
						of life may be contemned and forsaken.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But if our enemies arrive at high places in the
					courts of princes by flattery or frauds, by bribery or gifts,
					we should not be troubled at it, but should rather be
					pleased in comparing our undisguised and honest way of
					living with theirs which is quite contrary. For Plato, who
					was a competent judge, was of opinion that virtue was a
					more valuable treasure than all the riches above the earth
					or all the mines beneath it. And we ought' evermore to
					have in readiness this saying of Solon:<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Solon, Frag. No. 16.</note> But we will not
					give up our virtue in exchange for their wealth. So will
					we never give up our virtue for the applause of crowded
					theatres, which may be won by a feast, nor for the loftiest
					seats among eunuchs, concubines, and royal satraps. For
					nothing that is worth any one's appetite, nothing that
					is handsome or becoming a man, can proceed from that
					which is in itself evil and base. But, as Plato repeats
					once and again, the lover cannot see the faults of the thing
					or person that he loves, and we apprehend soonest what
					our enemies do amiss; therefore we must let neither our
					joy at their miscarriages nor our sorrow at their successes
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.298"/>
					
					be idle and useless to ourselves, but we are bound to consider in both respects, how we may render ourselves better
					than they are, by avoiding what is faulty and vicious in
					them, and how we may not prove worse than they, if we
					imitate them in what they do excel.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>