<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De capienda ex inimicis utilitate</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1928</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.3"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>HOW TO PROFIT BY ONE'S ENEMIES (DE CAPIENDA EX INIMICIS UTILITATE) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p> The essay on turning even one's enemies to some profitable use was an
						extempore address which was afterwards reduced to writing. It still retains,
						however, some of the marks of its extempore character in an occasional
						asyndeton or anacoluthon, in a few repetitions, and in such little slips as
						reversing the positions of Domitius and Scaurus (91 d). But minor matters of
						this sort cannot obscure the excellence of the essay as a whole, which
						contains much good advice, many wholesome truths, and much common sense. To
						cite but one example, the statement (91 b) that many things which are
						necessary in time of war, but bad under other conditions, acquire the
						sanction of custom and law, and cannot be easily abolished, even though the
						people are being injured by them, will appeal to everybody except the
						confirmed militarist. The essay was written some time after the essay
						entitled Advice to Statesmen, which in turn must be placed shortly after the
						death of Domitian (a.d. 96). </p>
            <p> This is one of the <q direct="unspecified">moral</q> essays of Plutarch which so
						impressed Christians that they were translated into Syriac in the sixth or
						seventh centuries. The translation of this essay is rather an adaptation,
						many details being omitted as unessential, but even so it gives light on the
						Greek text in a few places. The Syriac translation is published in Studia
						Sinaitica, No. IV (London 1894) </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.5"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>I observe, my dear Cornelius Pulcher,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably Cn. Cornelius Pulcher,
							who was procurator in Achaea towards the close of Plutarch's life. He
							also held various other offices. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Corpus Inscr.
								Graec.</hi> i. 1186.</note> that you have chosen the mildest form of
						official administration, in which you are as helpful as possible to the
						public interests while at the same time you show yourself to be very amiable
						in private to those who have audience with you. Now it may be possible to
						find a country, in which, as it is recorded of Crete,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This tradition in
							regard to Crete is found in several ancient writers. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> for example Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi>
							viii. 83.</note> there are no wild animals, but a government which has
						not had to bear with envy or jealous rivalry or
						contention&mdash;emotions most productive of enmity&mdash;has not
						hitherto existed. For our very friendships, if nothing else, involve us in
						enmities. This is what the wise Chilon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same remark is quoted by
							Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 96 A. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Aulus Gellius, i. 3.</note> had in mind, when he
						asked the man who boasted that he had no enemy whether he had no friend
						either. Therefore it seems to me to be the duty of a statesman not only to
						have thoroughly investigated the subject of enemies in general, but also in
						his reading of Xenophon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In <hi rend="italics">Oeconomicus</hi> 1.
							15.</note> to have given more than passing attention to the remark that
						it is a trait of the man of sense <q direct="unspecified">to derive profit even from his
							enemies.</q> Some thoughts, therefore, on this subject, which I
						recently had occasion to express, I have put together in practically the
						same words, and now send them to you, with the omission, so far <pb id="v.2.p.7"/> as possible, of matter contained in my Advice to
							Statesmen,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This work has been preserved; it is to be found in the
								<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 798 A-825 F.</note> since I observe
						that you often have that book close at hand. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Primitive men were quite content if they could escape being injured by
						strange and fierce animals, and this was the aim and end of their struggles
						against the wild beasts ; but their successors, by learning, as they did,
						how to make use of them, now profit by them through using their flesh for
						food, their hair for clothing, their gall and colostrum as medicine, and
						their skins as armour, so that there is good reason to fear that, if the
						supply of wild beasts should fail man, his life would become bestial,
						helpless, and uncivilized.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi> 964
							A.</note> Since, then, it is enough for most people if they can avoid
						suffering ill-treatment at the hands of their enemies, and since Xenophon
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Oeconomicus</hi> 1.15; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, i. 6. 11.</note>
						asserts that men of sense will even derive profit from those who are at
						variance with them, we must not refuse him credence, but rather try to
						discover the system and the art through which this admirable advantage is to
						be gained by those who find it impossible to live without an enemy. </p>
            <p> The farmer cannot domesticate every tree, nor can the huntsman tame every
						beast; and so they have sought to derive profit from these in ways to meet
						their other needs : the farmer from the trees that bear no fruit and the
						huntsman from the Wild animals. The water of the sea is unfit to drink and
						tastes vile ; yet fish thrive in it, and it is a medium for the dispatch and
						conveyance of travellers everywhere. The Satyr, at his first sight of fire,
						wished to kiss and embrace it, but Prometheus said, <pb id="v.2.p.9"/>
						         <quote rend="blockquote">You, goat, will mourn your vanished
								beard,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From <hi rend="italics">Prometheus the Fire-bearer</hi>
								of Aeschylus. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Aeschylus, No. 207.</note>
               </quote> for
						fire burns him who touches it, yet it furnishes light and heat, and is an
						instrument of every craft for those who have learned to use it. So look at
						your enemy, and see whether, in spite of his being in most respects harmful
						and difficult to manage, he does not in some way or other afford you means
						of getting hold of him and of using him as you can use no one else, and so
						can be of profit to you. Many of the circumstances of life are unkindly and
						hateful and repellent to those who have to meet them ; yet you observe that
						some have employed their attacks of bodily illness for quiet resting, and
						trials which have fallen to the lot of many have but strengthened and
						trained them. Some, too, have made banishment and loss of property a means
						of leisure and philosophic study, as did Diogenes<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, vi. 20 ff.</note> and Crates.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vi. 85.</note> And Zeno,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The remark
							of Zeno is again referred to by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 467 D and 603 D: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also
							Diogenes Laertius, vii. 5, and Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De animi
								tranquillitate,</hi> chap. xiii.</note> on learning that the ship
						which bore his venture had been wrecked, exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">A real kindness,
							O Fortune, that thou, too, dost join in driving us to the philosopher's
							cloak !</q> For just as those animals which have the strongest and
						soundest stomachs can eat and digest snakes and scorpions, and there are
						some even that derive nourishment from stones and shells (for they transmute
						such things by reason of the vigour and heat of their spirit), while
						fastidious and sickly persons are nauseated if they partake of bread and
						wine, so fools spoil even their friendships, while wise men are able to make
						a fitting use even of their enmities. 
					</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.11"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>In the first place, then, it seems to me that the most harmful element in
						enmity may be made most profitable to those who give heed. What is this ?
						Your enemy, wide awake, is constantly lying in wait to take advantage of
						your actions, and seeking to gain some hold on you, keeping up a constant
						patrol about your life ; and not only does his sight, like the sight of
						Lynceus, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lynceus was gifted with superhuman powers of vision; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> for example <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>,
							1083 D; Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Nemean Odes</hi>, x. 60; Horace, <hi rend="italics">Epistles</hi>, i. 1. 28, and Pausanias, iv. 2.</note>
						penetrate the oak-tree and stones and tiles, but your enemy, through every
						friend and servant and acquaintance as well, so far as possible, plays the
						detective on your actions and digs his way into your plans and searches them
						through and through. Oftentimes we do not learn, until too late, of the
						illness or the death of our friends, so careless are we and neglectful; but
						our curiosity about our enemies all but prompts us to pry into their dreams
						; sickness, debts, and conjugal disagreements are more likely to be unknown
						to the very persons affected than to their enemy. Especially does he try to
						get hold of their failings and ferret them out. And just as vultures are
						drawn to the smell of decomposed bodies, but have no power to discover those
						that are clean and healthy, so the infirmities, meannesses, and untoward
						experiences of life rouse the energies of the enemy, and it is such things
						as these that the malevolent pounce upon and seize and tear to pieces. Is
						this then profitable ? Assuredly it is, to have to live circumspectly, to
						give heed to one's self, and not to do or say anything carelessly or
						inconsiderately, but always to keep one's life unassailable as though under
						an exact regimen. For the circumspection which thus represses the emotions
						and keeps the reasoning power within bounds gives practice and purpose in
						living a life that <pb id="v.2.p.13"/> is fair and free from reproach. For
						just as states which are chastened by border warfare and continual
						campaigning become well content with good order and a sound government, so
						persons who have been compelled on account of enmities to practise soberness
						of living, to guard against indolence and contemptuousness, and to let some
						good purpose prompt each act, are insensibly led by force of habit to make
						no mistakes, and are made orderly in their behaviour, even if reason
						co-operate but slightly. For when men keep always ready in mind the thought
						that <quote rend="blockquote">Priam and Priam's sons would in truth have
							cause for rejoicing,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 255. The
								words are addressed by Nestor to the Greek leaders, Agamemnon and
								Achilles, who have quarrelled.</note>
               </quote> it causes them to face
						about and turn aside and abandon such things as give their enemies occasion
						for rejoicing and derision. Furthermore, we observe that the Dionysiac
							artists<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Actors and musicians.</note> often play their parts in the
						theatres in a listless, dispirited, and inaccurate way when they are by
						themselves ; but when there is rivalry and competition with another company,
						then they apply not only themselves but their instruments more attentively,
						picking their strings and tuning them and playing their flutes in more exact
						harmony. So the man who knows that his enemy is his competitor in life and
						repute is more heedful of himself, and more circumspect about his actions,
						and brings his life into a more thorough harmony. For it is a peculiar mark
						of vice, that we feel more ashamed of our faults before our enemies than
						before our friends. This is the ground of Nasica's remark, when some
						expressed their belief that the power of the Romans was now secure, inasmuch
						as the Carthaginians had been annihilated and <pb id="v.2.p.15"/> the
						Achaeans reduced to subjection. <q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">now is
							our position really dangerous, since we have left for ourselves none to
							make us either afraid or ashamed.</q>
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Moreover, as a supplement to this take the declaration of
							Diogenes,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 21
							E.</note> which is thoroughly philosophic and statesmanlike: <q direct="unspecified">How
							shall I defend myself against my enemy ?</q>
						         <q direct="unspecified">By proving yourself good and honourable.</q> Men are much
						distressed when they see their enemies' horses winning renown or their dogs
						gaining approval. At the sight of a well-tilled field or a flourishing
						garden they groan. What, think you, would be their state of mind if you were
						to show yourself to be an honest, sensible man and a useful citizen, of high
						repute in speech, clean in actions, orderly in living, <quote rend="blockquote">Reaping the deep-sown furrow of your mind From which
							all goodly counsels spring? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus <hi rend="italics">Seven
									against Thebes</hi>, 593; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 32 D, 186 B, and <hi rend="italics">Life of
									Aristides</hi>, chap. iii. (p. 320 B).</note>
               </quote> Pindar
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 229 (ed. Christ).</note>
						says, <quote rend="blockquote">The vanquished are bound In the fetters of
							silence profound,</quote> not absolutely or universally, however, but
						only those who realize that they are outdone by their enemies in diligence,
						goodness, magnanimity, kindly deeds, and good works. These are the things
						which, as Demosthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, Or. xix. (<hi rend="italics">De
								falsa legatione</hi>) 208 (p. 406).</note> puts it, <q direct="unspecified">retard
							the tongue, stop the mouth, constrict the throat, and leave one with
							nothing to say.</q>
						         <quote rend="blockquote">Be thou unlike the base ; this thou canst do.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Orestes</hi>,
							251.</note>
               </quote> If you wish to distress the man who hates you, do
						not revile him as lewd, effeminate, licentious, vulgar, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar,
							Frag. 229 (ed. Christ). d Demosthenes, Or. xix. (De falsa legatione) 208
							(p. 406). e Euripides, Orestes, 251.</note>
						         <pb id="v.2.p.17"/> or illiberal, but be a man yourself, show self-control,
						be truthful, and treat with kindness and justice those who have to deal with
						you. And if you are led into reviling, remove yourself as far as possible
						from the things for which you revile him. Enter within the portals of your
						own soul, look about to see if there be any rottenness there, lest some vice
						lurking somewhere within whisper to you the words of the tragedian: <quote rend="blockquote">Wouldst thou heal others, full of sores thyself ?
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown play of Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>
								Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,</hi> Euripides, No.
								1086; Plutarch quotes the line also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 1 F, 481 A, and 1110 E.</note>
               </quote> If you call
						your enemy uneducated, strive to intensify in yourself the love of learning
						and industry ; if you call him a coward, rouse even more your selfreliance
						and manliness ; if you call him unchaste and licentious, obliterate from
						your soul whatever trace of devotion to pleasure may be lurking there
						unperceived. For there is nothing more disgraceful or painful than
						evil-speaking that recoils upon its author. So reflected light appears to be
						the more troublesome in cases of weak eyesight, and the same is true of
						censures that by the truth are brought back upon the very persons who are
						responsible for them. For as surely the north-east wind <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Proverbial;
								<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Problem.</hi> 26. 1; Theophrastus, <hi rend="italics">De
								ventis</hi>, p. 410; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi>ii.
							48; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 823 B, and Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Adespota, No. 75.</note>
						brings the clouds, so surely does a bad life bring revilings upon itself.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>As often as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This remark of Plato is cited also in the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 40 D, 129 D, and 463 E.</note> found
						himself in the company of persons whose conduct was unseemly, he was wont to
						say to himself, <q direct="unspecified">Is it possible that I am like them ?</q> But if
						the man who reviles another's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch, Moralia, 823 b, and Nauck,
							Trag. Graec. Frag., Adespota, No. 75. c This remark of Plato is cited
							also in the Moralia, 40 d, 129 d, and 463 e.</note>
						         <pb id="v.2.p.19"/> life will at once carefully inspect his own, and
						readjust it by directing and turning it aside into the opposite course, he
						will have gained something useful from this reviling, which, otherwise, not
						only gives the impression of being useless and inane, but is so in fact. </p>
            <p> Now most people laugh if a man who is bald or hump-backed reviles and jeers
						at others for being in such case ; for it is altogether ridiculous to
						indulge in reviling and jeering at anything that affords to another the
						opportunity for a caustic retort. For example, Leo <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 633 C, for a slightly different version of the
							story.</note> of Byzantium, being reviled by a humpback for the weakness
						of his eyes, said, <q direct="unspecified">You reproach me with that which can happen to any
							man, while you bear on your back the mark of God's wrath!</q> Do
						not therefore ever revile an adulterer when you yourself are given to
						unnatural lust, nor a profligate when you yourself are stingy. <quote rend="blockquote">Own kin are you of her who slew her spouse</quote> are
						the words of Alcmeon to Adrastus. What then does Adrastus say ? He
						reproaches the speaker with a shameful deed which is not another's but all
						his own : <quote rend="blockquote">But you yourself slew her who gave you
								birth.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Alcmaeon</hi> of Euripides;
									<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">T.G.F.,</hi> Adespota, No. 358. Quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 35 D.</note>
               </quote> Domitius
						remarked to Crassus, <q direct="unspecified">Did you not weep at the death of a lamprey
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Crassus's pet eel was famous. Plutarch speaks of it twice
								elsewhere: <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 811 A and 976 A. Of
								other writers, Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De natura animal</hi>.
								viii. 4, contains the most interesting account of it.</note> which
							was being kept for you in a fish-pond ?</q> And the other replied,
							<q direct="unspecified">Did you not bury three wives and not shed a tear ?</q> The
						man who is going to indulge in reviling need not be smart and loud-voiced
						and aggressive, but he must be irreproachable and unimpeachable. For upon
						nobody does the divine power seem so to enjoin <pb id="v.2.p.21"/> the
						precept, <q direct="unspecified">Know thyself,</q> as upon him who purposes to censure
						another, so that such persons may not, by saying what they want to say, have
						to hear what they do not want to hear. For a person of this type, as
						Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Two lines of a longer quotation from an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
								Frag.</hi>, Sophocles, No. 843.</note> puts it, <quote rend="blockquote">By babbling thoughtless talk is wont to hear Against
							his will the words he willing speaks.</quote>
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>There may be, then, so much that is profitable and useful in reviling one's
						enemy; but no less profit lies in the alternative of being reviled oneself
						and ill spoken of by one's enemies. Hence Antisthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diogenes is
							given as the author of this saying twice elsewhere in the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 74 C and 82 A. One MS. gives Diogenes
							here.</note> was quite right in saying that, as a matter of
						self-preservation, men have need of true friends or else of ardent enemies ;
						for the first by admonition, and the second by reviling, turn them from
						error. But since friendship's voice has nowadays become thin and weak when
						it comes to frank speaking, while its flattery is voluble and its admonition
						mute, we have to depend upon our enemies to hear the truth. For as
							Telephus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Among the many references to this story, it is perhaps
							sufficient to cite <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 46 F; Propertius,
							ii. 1. 63; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Tristia</hi>v. 1. 15.</note> unable
						to find a suitable physician, subjected his wound to his enemy's spear, so
						those who are cut off from benevolent admonition must submit with patience
						to the remarks of a malevolent enemy if he exposes and reprehends their
						vice, and they must give consideration to the facts only, and not to what is
						in the mind of the detractor. Another parallel is the case of the man who,
						with intent to kill the Thessalian Prometheus, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apparetly a sort of
							nickname of Jason of Pherae; at any rate this story is told of Jason by
							Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De natura deorum</hi>, iii. 28 (70); Pliny,
								<hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> vii. 51; and Valerius Maximus, i.
							8, ext. 6. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, ii. 3. 36.</note> smote with his sword a tumour
						which Prometheus had, and opened it so that the man's life 
						<pb id="v.2.p.23"/> was saved, and he obtained relief from his tumour
						through its bursting ; so oftentimes reviling launched upon a man by the
						prompting of anger or enmity cures some evil in his soul which either was
						not recognized or was disregarded by him. But most persons on being reviled
						do not stop to think whether the reproach is applicable to themselves, but
						they try to think what other form of reproach is applicable to the reviler,
						and, just as wrestlers do not wipe the dust from off their own bodies, so
						these persons do not wipe off the revilings from themselves, but they
						besmear one another, and in consequence get besmirched and begrimed by each
						other as they grapple together. But it is more imperative that the man who
						is ill spoken of by an enemy should rid himself of the attribute in
						question, than that he should get rid of a stain on his clothes to which his
						attention has been called ; and if anybody mentions things which are not
						really attributes of ours, we should nevertheless seek to learn the cause
						which has given rise to such slanderous assertions, and we must exercise
						vigilance, for fear that we unwittingly commit some error either
						approximating or resembling the one mentioned. For example, an unwarranted
						suspicion of unmanliness was aroused against Lacydes, king of the Argives,
						by a certain arrangement of his hair and a mincing gait, and Pompey
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mention of this habit of Pompey's is found also in the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 800 D, in the <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Pompey</hi>, chap. xlviii. (p. 645 A), and in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Caesar</hi> chap. iv. (p. 709 B).</note>
						suffered in the same way on account of his habit of scratching his head with
						one finger, although he was very far removed from effeminacy and
						licentiousness. Crassus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is told more fully in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Crassus</hi>, chap. i. (p. 543 B).</note>
						incurred the charge of being too intimate with one of the Vestal virgins,
						when he only wanted to buy from her a piece of good land, and for this
						reason had many private <pb id="v.2.p.25"/> interviews with her and paid her
						much attention. Again, Postumia's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A Vestal Virgin; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Livy, iv. 44.</note> ready laughter and overbold talk in
						men's company put her under unjust suspicion, so that she was tried for
						unchastity. She was found innocent of the charge, but in dismissing her the
						Poritifex Maximus, Spurius Minucius, reminded her that the language she used
						should have no less dignity than her life. And again Pausanias inflicted on
						Themistocles, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucydides, i. 135; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also
							Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Themistocles</hi>, chap. xxiii. (p.
							123 c).</note> who was doing nothing wrong, the suspicion of treason by
						treating him as a friend, and by writing and sending messages to him
						continually. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Whenever, then, anything untrue has been said, you must not despise and
						disregard it just because it is false, but rather consider what word or act
						of yours, which of your pursuits or associations, has given colour to the
						calumny, and then be studiously careful to avoid it. For if others by
						becoming involved in undesired situations thereby learn a useful
						lesson&mdash;just as Merope says that <quote rend="blockquote">Inconstant Fortune took from me, To pay her fee, the dearest that I
							had, But she for that hath made me wise&mdash;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Cresphontes</hi> of Euripides; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,</hi> Euripides, No.
								458.</note>
               </quote> what is to hinder a man from taking his enemy as
						his teacher without fee, and profiting thereby, and thus learning, to some
						extent, the things of which he was unaware ? For there are many things which
						an enemy is quicker to perceive than a friend (for Love is blind regarding
						the loved one, as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, p. 731 E.
							The quotation is repeated a few pages farther on (92 E), and also in the
								<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 48 E and 1000 A.</note> says), and
						inherent in hatred, along with curiosity, is the inability to hold one's
						tongue. Hiero <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated in the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 175 B, and elsewhere by other writers. One author
							tells it of Gelon.</note> was reviled by <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated
							in the Moralia, 175 b, and elsewhere by other writers. One author tells
							it of Gelon.</note>
						         <pb id="v.2.p.27"/> one of his enemies for his offensive breath ; so when he
						went home he said to his wife, <q direct="unspecified">What do you mean ? Even you never told
							me of this.</q> But she being virtuous and innocent said, <q direct="unspecified">I
							supposed that all men smelt so.</q> Thus it is that things which are
						perceptible, material, and evident to all the world, may sooner be learned
						from our enemies than from our friends and close associates. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But, quite apart from this, control over the tongue, which is no small part
						of virtue, is something which it is impossible to keep always in subjection
						and obedience to the reasoning faculties, unless a man by training,
						practice, and industry has mastered the worst of his emotions, such as
						anger, for example. For the <q direct="unspecified">voice that slips out
							unintended,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A picturesque experssion several times used by
							Homer, <hi rend="italics">e.g. Il.</hi> iv. 350; xiv. 83; <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> i. 64; xxiii. 70. The source of the other
							two quotations is unknown.</note> and the <quote rend="blockquote">Word
							that has 'scaped the lips' prison,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A picturesque experssion several
								times used by Homer, <hi rend="italics">e.g. Il.</hi> iv. 350; xiv.
								83; <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> i. 64; xxiii. 70. The source of the
								other two quotations is unknown.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Some of the sayings that flit forth of
								themselves,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A picturesque experssion several times used by
								Homer, <hi rend="italics">e.g. Il.</hi> iv. 350; xiv. 83; <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> i. 64; xxiii. 70. The source of the
								other two quotations is unknown.</note>
               </quote> are all incident to
						temperaments that are quite untrained, and are unsteady and fluctuating, so
						to speak, owing to weakness of will, headstrong opinions, and a reckless way
						of living. Just for a word, the lightest thing in the world, is ordained,
						according to the divine Plato,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, pp.
							717 C and 935 A. Plutarch quotes it again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 456 D and 505 C.</note> heaviest punishment, coming
						from both gods and men. But silence cannot under any circumstances be called
						to an accounting (it is more than a preventive of thirst, as Hippocrates
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 515 A.</note> says of
						it), and in the midst of reviling it is <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">e.g. II. iv. 350 ; xiv. 83 ;
							Od. i. 64 ; xxiii. 70. The source of the other two quotations is
							unknown. b Plato, Laws, pp. 717 c and 935 a. Plutarch quotes it again in
							Moralia, 456 d and 505 c. c Cf. Moralia, 515 a.</note>
						         <pb id="v.2.p.29"/> dignified and Socratic, or rather Heraclean, if it be
						true that Heracles <quote rend="blockquote">Not so much as to a fly gave
							heed to words of hatred.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Source unknown; the story in Pausanias, v.
								14, is not to the point.</note>
               </quote> Indeed, there is nothing
						more dignified and noble than to maintain a calm demeanour when an enemy
						reviles one, <quote rend="blockquote">Passing by a man's scoffs Just as
							swimmers swim past a precipitous rock,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The source of the quotation
								is not known.</note>
               </quote> but far more important is the practice.
						If you once acquire the habit of bearing an enemy's abuse in silence, you
						will very easily bear up under a wife's attack when she rails at you, and
						without discomposure will patiently hear the most bitter utterances of a
						friend or a brother; and when you meet with blows or missiles at the hands
						of a father or mother, you will show no sign of passion or wrath. For
						instance, Socrates bore with Xanthippe,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 2. 10.</note> who was irascible and acrimonious,
						for he thought that he should have no difficulty in getting along with other
						people if he accustomed himself to bear patiently with her; but it is much
						better to secure this training from the scurrilous, angry, scoffing, and
						abusive attacks of enemies and outsiders, and thus accustom the temper to be
						unruffled and not even impatient in the midst of reviling. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>In this manner, then, it is possible for us to display the qualities of
						gentleness and forbearance in connexion with our enmities, and also
						straightforwardness, magnanimity, and goodness better than in our
						friendships. For it is not so honourable to do a good turn to a friend as it
						is disgraceful not to do it when he is in need ; but even to forgo taking
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, Symposium, 2. 10.</note>
						         <pb id="v.2.p.31"/> vengeance on an enemy when he offers a good opportunity
						is a handsome thing to do. But in case a man shows compassion for an enemy
						in affliction, and gives a helping hand to him when he has come to be in
						need, and displays some concern and zeal in behalf of his children and his
						household affairs when they come to want, I say that whosoever does not feel
						affection for such a man because of his kindliness, or does not commend his
						goodness, <quote rend="blockquote">Hath a black heart Forged from adamant or
							else from steel.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Part of a longer fragment of Pindar; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi>
								123 (ed. Christ); quoted again by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 558 A.</note>
               </quote> When Caesar gave orders
						that the statues in honour of Pompey, which had been thrown down, should be
						restored, Cicero <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch repeats this story in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 205 D; <hi rend="italics">Life of Caesar</hi>, chap.
							lvii. (p. 734 E), and <hi rend="italics">Life of Cicero</hi>, chap. xl.
							(p. 881 D). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>Suetonius, <hi rend="italics">Caesar</hi>, 75.</note> said to him, <q direct="unspecified">You have restored
							Pompey's statues, but you have made your own secure.</q> Wherefore
						there must be no scanting of commendation or due honour in the case of an
						enemy who has justly gained a fair repute. For such an attitude wins greater
						commendation for those who bestow it, and inspires confidence, when later a
						man makes a complaint that he does so, not because he hates the person, but
						because he disapproves of the action. But best of all, and most
						advantageous, is the fact that a man is farthest removed from envying the
						good fortune of his friends or the success of his relatives, if he has
						acquired the habit of commending his enemies, and feeling no pang and
						cherishing no grudge when they prosper. And yet what other process of
						training produces greater benefit to our souls or a better disposition, than
						does that which takes from us all our jealousy and our proneness to envy ?
						Just as many of the things which are necessary in war, but bad under other
						conditions, when they once acquire the sanction of custom and law, <pb id="v.2.p.33"/> cannot easily be abolished by the people even though the
						people are being injured by them, so enmity introduces envy along with
						hatred, and leaves as a residue jealousy, joy over others' misfortunes, and
						vindictiveness. Moreover, knavery, deceit, and intrigue, which seem not bad
						or unjust when employed against an enemy, if once they find a lodgement,
						acquire a permanent tenure, and are hard to eject. The next thing is that
						men of themselves employ these against their friends through force of habit,
						unless they are on their guard against using them against their enemies. If
						then Pythagoras <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 729 E.</note> was
						right when, in trying to accustom men to refrain from cruelty and rapacity
						in connexion with dumb animals, he used to intercede with fowlers, and buy
						up catches of fish and direct that they be released, and forbid the killing
						of any domesticated animal, it is surely a grander achievement by far, in
						disagreements and contentions with human beings, for a man to be a noble,
						honest, and ingenuous enemy, and to repress and put down his base, ignoble,
						and knavish propensities, so that in his dealings with his friends he may be
						always steadfast and may keep himself from wrongdoing. Scaurus was an enemy
						of Domitius and his accuser before the law. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the facts see Cicero,
								<hi rend="italics">Oration for King Deiotarus</hi>, 11
						(31).</note>Now a servant of Domitius came to Scaurus before the trial,
						claiming to have information on some matters that had escaped Scaurus's
						knowledge, but Scaurus would not let him speak, and caused the man to be
						arrested and taken back to his master. When Cato was prosecuting Murena for
						corrupt political practices and was getting together his evidence, there
						followed him, in accordance with the usage of the <pb id="v.2.p.35"/>
							time,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Explained more fully in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Cato
								Minor</hi>, chap. xxi. (p. 769 B), where the story is
							repeated.</note> men who watched what was being done. Very often they
						would ask him if he was intending that day to gather evidence or to do any
						work on the case, and if he said <q direct="unspecified">No,</q> they believed him and
						went away. In these facts may be found the greatest proof of Cato's repute ;
						but it is a greater thing, and indeed the noblest, that, if we acquire the
						habit of practising honesty in dealing even with our enemies, we shall never
						deal dishonestly and knavishly with our intimate associates and friends.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But since <quote rend="blockquote">On every lark a crest must grow,</quote>
						as Simonides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>
               </note> puts it, and since all human nature bears its crop
						of contention, jealousy, and envy, <quote rend="blockquote">Boon comrade of
							rattle-brained men,</quote> as Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 212 (ed. Christ).</note> says, a man would profit in no
						moderate degree by venting these emotions upon his enemies, and turning the
						course of such discharges,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Memorabilia</hi>, i. 4. 6.</note> so to speak, as far
						away as possible from his associates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.
								Moralia</hi>, 813 A, where the story is repeated almost word for
							word.</note> and relatives. This fact, as it seems, a statesman, Demus
						by name,e apprehended: when he found himself on the winning side in a civic
						strife in Chios, he advised his party associates not to banish all their
						opponents, but to leave some of them behind, <q direct="unspecified">in order,</q> he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">that we may not begin to quarrel <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">of Timoleon, chap.
								xxxvii. (253 e), with much the same application. Cf. Bergk, Poet.
								Lyr. Graec. iii. p. 418, Simonides, No. 68; Diehl, Anthologia
								Lyrica, ii. p. 62 ; Edmonds, Lyra Graeca (in L.C.L.), ii. p. 278,
								all differing in their reading of this one line. c Frag. 212 (ed.
								Christ). d Cf. Xenophon, Memorabilia, i. 4. 6. e Cf. Moralia, 813 a,
								where the story is repeated almost word for word.</note>
							           <pb id="v.2.p.37"/> with our friends, through being completely rid of
							our enemies.</q> So also in our own case, if our emotions of this
						sort are expended upon our enemies, they will cause less annoyance to our
						friends. For <q direct="unspecified">a potter</q> must not <q direct="unspecified">envy potter,</q>
						nor <q direct="unspecified">a minstrel a minstrel,</q> as Hesiod <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The references
							are to the <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 25-26 and 27.</note>
						puts it, nor must there be any feeling of rivalry against a neighbour or
						relative or brother who is <q direct="unspecified">winning his way towards riches</q>
						and meeting with prosperity. But if there is no other way of getting rid of
						strifes, envies, and contentions, accustom yourself to feel the sting of
						resentment when your enemies enjoy health and happiness, and whet your
						contentiousness to a sharp jagged edge on these. For just as skilled
						gardeners believe that they improve their roses and violets by planting
						beside them garlic and onions (since whatever pungency and malod rousness
						there is in what the plants feed on is all drawn off into the vegetables),
						thus also your enemy, by taking up and diverting to himself your malice and
						jealousy, will render you more kindly and less disagreeable to your friends
						in their prosperity. For this reason it is with our enemies that we must
						also engage in rivalry for repute or office or honest money-getting, not
						only feeling the sting of resentment if they get the advantage of us, but
						also watching carefully every means by which they get the advantage, and
						trying to surpass them in painstaking, diligence, selfcontrol, and
						self-criticism: after the manner of Themistocles, who said that Miltiades'
						victory at Marathon would not let him sleep.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Themistocles</hi>,
							chap. iii. (p. 113 B), and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 84 B and 800
							B.</note> For he who thinks that it is by mere good luck that his enemy
						surpasses him in public offices, in pleading cases, in state administration,
						or in his standing with friends <pb id="v.2.p.39"/> and leading men, and who
						from activity and emulation sinks down into a state of utter jealousy and
						discouragement, has abiding with him an envy that is inert and ineffectual.
						If, however, a man is not blind <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note
							on 90 A <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>
               </note> in regard to the object of
						his hatred, but makes himself an honest observer of the other's life,
						character, words, and deeds, he will discover that most of the successes
						which excite the envy of others come to those who have won them as the
						result of painstaking, forethought, and fair conduct, and so, bending all
						his energies in this direction, he will put into practice his own ambitions
						and high aspirations, and will eradicate his listlessness and indolence.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But even if our enemies by flattery, knavery, bribery, or hireling service
						appear to reap their reward in the form of dishonourable and sordid
						influence at court or in the government, they will not be a source of
						annoyance but rather of joy to us when we compare our own freedom, the
						simplicity of our life, and its immunity from scurrilous attack. For <q direct="unspecified">
							all the gold on earth and beneath the earth is not worth so much as
							virtue,</q> as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, p.
							728 A; quoted also by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>1124
							E.</note> says, and we must always keep ready in mind the sentiment of
						Solon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Quoted more fully in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 78 C, and
							as here, 472 E.</note>: <q rend="blockquoted" direct="unspecified">But we will not take
							in exchange All of their wealth for our virtue,</q> nor yet the
						acclamations of spectators who have dined at our expense, nor honours such
						as front seats among eunuchs and concubines, and royal governorships ; for
						nothing enviable or noble ever springs from dishonour. But since <q direct="unspecified">
							love is blind regarding <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Quoted more fully in Moralia, 78 c, and
								as here, 472 e.</note>
							           <pb id="v.2.p.41"/> the loved one,</q> as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A reminiscence
							from Plato; see the note on 90 A <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>
						says, and it is rather our enemies who by their unseemly conduct afford us
						an opportunity to view our own, neither our joy at their failures nor our
						sorrow at their successes ought to go without being employed to some
						purpose, but we should take into account both their failures and successes
						in studying how by guarding against the former we may be better than they,
						and by imitating the latter no worse. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A reminiscence from Plato; see
							the note on 90 a supra.</note>
					       </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>