<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quomodo adulator ab amico internoscatur</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1927</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v1.p.263"/>
         <div1 type="section">
            <head>HOW TO TELL A FLATTERER FROM A FRIEND (QUOMODO ADULATOR AB AMICO INTERNOSCATUR)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>Plutarch's essay on flatterers is addressed to C.
					Julius Antiochus Philopappus, a descendant of the
					kings of Commagene, whose monument still stands
					on the Museum Hill at Athens. He was a patron
					of art and literature, and on friendly terms with
					Plutarch.a</p>
            <p>The essay is not concerned with the impecunious
					and dependent adherents (parasites) of the rich, but
					with the adroit flatterers of a higher standing, who
					worm their way into the confidence of great men, and
					exercise a pernicious influence upon them. That
					Philopappus may have stood in need of such a
					warning may readily be inferred.</p>
            <p>The essay, at the close, digresses into a disquisition on frank speech (<foreign lang="greek">parrhsi/a</foreign>) that might
					easily have been made into a separate treatise,
					but which is developed naturally from the attempt to
					distinguish the genuineness of a friend from the
					affectation of a flatterer. Frank speech was regarded
					in classical times as the birthright of every Athenian
					citizen, but under the political conditions existent in
					Plutarch's day it was probably safer to cultivate it
					as a private virtue.</p>
            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">a Cf. Moralia, 628 b, which gives a brief account of a
					great dinner given by King Philopappus at which both he
					and Plutarch were present.</note>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v1.p.265"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 731 D, E.</note> says, my dear Antiochus Philopappus, that everyone grants forgiveness
					to the man who avows that he dearly loves himself, but he also says that
					along with many other faults which are engendered thereby the most serious
					is that which makes it impossible for such a man to be an honest and
					unbiased judge of himself. <q direct="unspecified">For Love is blind as regards the
						beloved,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi>; cited also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 90 A, 92 E, and 1000 A.</note> unless one, through study, has acquired the habit of
					respecting and pursuing what is honourable rather than what is inbred and
					familiar. This fact affords to the flatterer a very wide field within the
					realm of friendship,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">True friendship is, of course, proof against flattery, but friendship weakened by self-love is a sort of borderland between true friendship and flattery in which the flatterer can work.</note> since in our love of self he has an excellent base of
					operations against us. It is because of this self-love that everybody is
					himself his own foremost and greatest flatterer, and hence finds no
					difficulty in admitting the outsider to witness with him and to confirm his
					own conceits and desires. For the man who is spoken of with opprobrium as a
					lover of flatterers is in high degree a lover of self, and, because of his
					kindly feeling toward himself, he desires and conceives himself to be
					endowed with all manner of good qualities ; but although the desire for
					these is not unnatural, yet the conceit that one possesses them is dangerous
					and must be carefully avoided. Now
					
					<pb id="v1.p.267"/>
					
					if Truth is a thing
					divine, and, as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 730 C.</note> puts it, the origin <q direct="unspecified">of all good for gods and
						all good for men,</q> then the flatterer is in all likelihood an
					enemy to the gods and particularly to the Pythian god. For the flatterer
					always takes a position over against the maxim <q direct="unspecified">Know thyself,</q>
					by creating in every man deception towards himself and ignorance both of
					himself and of the good and evil that concerns himself ; the good he renders
					defective and incomplete, and the evil wholly impossible to amend. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>If the flatterer, then, like most other evils, attacked solely or mostly the
					ignoble and mean, he would not be so formidable or so hard to guard against.
					But the fact is, that as bore-worms make their entrance chiefly into the
					delicate and sweetscented kinds of wood, so it is ambitious, honest, and
					promising characters that receive and nourish the flatterer as he hangs upon
					them. Moreover, just as Simonides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. 393.</note> says, <quote rend="blockquote">The rearing of horses consorts not
						with Zacynthus, But with wheat-bearing acres,</quote> so we observe that flattery
					does not attend upon poor, obscure, or unimportant persons, but makes itself
					a stumbling-block and a pestilence in great houses and great affairs, and
					oftentimes overturns kingdoms and principalities. Wherefore it is no small
					task, nor a matter requiring but slight foresight, to subject it to
					examination, so that, being thoroughly exposed, it may be prevented from
					injuring or discrediting friendship. Vermin depart from dying persons and
					forsake their bodies, as the blood, from which the vermin derive their
					sustenance, loses its vitality ; and so flatterers are never so much 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.269"/>
					
					as to be seen coming near where succulence and warmth
					are lacking, but where renown and power attend, there do they throng and
					thrive; but if a change come, they slink away quickly and are gone. But we
					must not wait until that experience shall befall, which is a thing
					profitless, or rather injurious and not devoid of danger. For it is cruel to
					discover friends that are no friends at a crucial time which calls for
					friends, since there is then no exchanging one that is untrustworthy and
					spurious for the true and trustworthy. But one's friend, like a coin, should
					have been examined and approved before the time of need, not proved by the
					need to be no friend. For we must not wait for injury to open our eyes, but
					to avoid injury we must gain acquaintance with the flatterer and learn how
					to detect him; otherwise we shall be in the same case with those who try to
					learn about deadly drugs by tasting them first, and so ruin and destroy
					themselves in order to reach their decision. We do not, of course, commend
					such persons, nor again those who rate the friend as something noble and
					beneficial, and so imagine that all who are socially agreeable at once stand
					openly convicted of being flatterers. For a friend is not unpleasant or
					absolute, nor is it bitterness and sternness that give dignity to
					friendship, but this very nobility and dignity in it is sweet and desirable.
					<quote rend="blockquote">Close by its side have the Graces and Longing established their dwelling,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 64.</note>
               </quote>
					and not merely for one who is in misfortune <quote rend="blockquote">'Tis sweet to gaze into a kind
						man's eyes,</quote> as Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ion</hi>, 732; again cited in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 69 A.</note> has it, but when friendship attends us,
					
					<pb id="v1.p.271"/>
					
					it brings pleasure and delight to our prosperity no less
					than it takes away the griefs and the feeling of helplessness from
					adversity. As Evenus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Again cited in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 126 D, 697 D, and 1010 C.</note> has remarked that fire is the best of sauce, so God,
					by commingling friendship with our life, has made everything cheerful, sweet
					and agreeable, when friendship is there to share in our enjoyment. Indeed,
					how the flatterer could use pleasures to insinuate himself, if he saw that
					friendship was nowhere ready to welcome what is pleasant, no man can
					explain. But just as false and counterfeit imitations of gold imitate only
					its brilliancy and lustre, so apparently the flatterer, imitating the
					pleasant and attractive characteristics of the friend, always presents
					himself in a cheerful and blithe mood, with never a whit of crossing or
					opposition. But that is no reason why persons who express commendation
					should instantly be suspected of being simply flatterers. For commendation
					at the right time is no less becoming to friendship than is censure, or we
					may express it better by saying that complaining and fault-finding generally
					is unfriendly and unsociable, whereas the kindly feeling that ungrudgingly
					and readily bestows commendation for noble acts inclines us, at some later
					time, cheerfully and without distress to bear admonishment and frankness of
					speech, since we believe, and are content, that the man who is glad to
					commend blames only when he must. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>One might say, then, that it is difficult to distinguish flatterer and
					friend, if neither pleasure nor praise shows the difference ; indeed, in
					services and courtesies we may often observe that friendship is outstripped
					by flattery. How can it be helped, will
					
					<pb id="v1.p.273"/>
					
					
					
					be our answer,
					if we are in quest of the real flatterer, who takes hold of the business
					with adroitness and skill, and if we do not, like most people, regard as
					flatterers merely those self-ministering <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Men too poor to afford a servant, and hence obliged to carry their own bottle of oil to the bath. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Against Conon</hi>, 16 (p. 1262).</note> trencherslaves, so called, whose
					tongue will be wagging, as one man has put it, as soon as the water is
					brought for the hands, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The ceremonial washing of the hands immediately before eating.</note> for whom one dish and one glass of wine is enough to
					show their ill breeding with its display of vulgarity and offensiveness ?
					Surely there was no need to press the case against Melanthius, the parasite
					of Alexander of Pherae, who, in answer to those who asked how Alexander was
					slain, said, <q direct="unspecified">By a stab through his ribs that hit me in my belly
					</q> ; nor those who throng round a rich man's table whom <quote rend="blockquote">Not fire, nor
						steel, Nor bronze can keep From coming each day to dine.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Flatterers</hi> of Eupolis according to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 778 E; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. p. 303.</note>
               </quote> nor the
					flatteresses in Cyprus, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, 256 D.</note> who when they had crossed over into Syria, acquired
					the nickname of <q direct="unspecified">ladderesses,</q> because by prostrating
					themselves they afforded by their bodies a means for the women of the royal
					household to mount their carriages. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Against whom, then, must we be on our guard ? Against the man who does not
					seem to flatter and will not admit that he does so, the man who is never to
					be found hanging round the kitchen, never caught noting the shadow on the
					sun-dial to see if it is getting towards dinner-time, never gets drunk and
					drops down in a heap on the floor ; he is usually sober, he is always busy,
					and must have a hand in everything ; he has a mind to be in all secrets, and
					in general plays the part of friend with the gravity of a tragedian and
					
					<pb id="v1.p.275"/>
					
					
					not like a comedian or a buffoon. For as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 361 A.</note> says,
					<q direct="unspecified">it is the height of dishonesty to seem to be honest when one is
						not,</q> and so the flattery which we must regard as difficult to
					deal with is that which is hidden, not that which is openly avowed, that
					which is serious, not that which is meant as a joke. For such flattery
					infects even true friendship with distrust, unless we give heed, for in many
					respects it coincides with friendship. Now it is true that Gobryas, having
					forced his way into a dark room along with the fleeing Magian, and finding
					himself engaged in a desperate struggle, called upon Darius, who had stopped
					beside them and was in doubt what to do, to strike even though he should
					pierce them both <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, iii. 78.</note> ; but we, if we can by no means approve the sentiment,
					<q direct="unspecified">Down with a foe though a friend go too,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 362.</note> have great
					cause to fear in seeking to detach the flatterer, who through many
					similarities is closely interlocked with the friend, lest in some way we
					either cast out the useful along with the bad, or else, in trying to spare
					what is close to our hearts, we fall upon what is injurious. So, I think,
					when wild seeds which have a shape and size approximating to wheat have got
					mixed with it, the process of cleaning is difficult (for either they do not
					pass out through a finer sieve, or else they do pass out through a coarser,
					and the wheat along with them) ; in like manner, flattery which blends
					itself with every emotion, every movement, need, and habit, is hard to
					separate from friendship. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>For the very reason, however, that friendship is the most pleasant thing in
					the world, and because nothing else gives greater delight, the flatterer
					allures by means of pleasures and concerns himself
					
					<pb id="v1.p.277"/>
					
					
					with
					pleasures. And just because graciousness and usefulness go with friendship
					(which is the reason why they say that a friend is more indispensable than
					fire and water), the flatterer thrusts himself into services for us,
					striving always to appear earnest, unremitting, and diligent. And inasmuch
					as that which most especially cements a friendship begun is a likeness of
					pursuits and characters, and since to take delight in the same things and
					avoid the same things is what generally brings people together in the first
					place, and gets them acquainted through the bond of sympathy, the flatterer
					takes note of this fact, and adjusts and shapes himself, as though he were
					so much inert matter, endeavouring to adapt and mould himself to fit those
					whom he attacks through imitation; and he is so supple in changes and so
					plausible in his copyings that we may exclaim : <quote rend="blockquote">Achilles' self thou art and
						not his son.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 363; quoted by Plutarch also in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Alcibiades</hi>, 203 C.</note>
               </quote> But the most unprincipled trick of all that he has is this :
					perceiving that frankness of speech, by common report and belief, is the
					language of friendship especially (as an animal has its peculiar cry), and,
					on the other hand, that lack of frankness is unfriendly and ignoble, he does
					not allow even this to escape imitation, but, just as clever cooks employ
					bitter extracts and astringent flavourings to remove the cloying effect of
					sweet things, so flatterers apply a frankness which is not genuine or
					beneficial, but which, as it were, winks while it frowns, and does nothing
					but tickle. For these reasons, then, the man is hard to detect, as is the
					case with some animals to which Nature has given the faculty of changing
					their hue, so that they exactly conform to
					<pb id="v1.p.279"/>
					
					
					the colours
					and objects beneath them. And since the flatterer uses resemblances to
					deceive and to wrap about him, it is our task to use the differences in
					order to unwrap him and lay him bare, in the act, as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 239 D.</note> puts it, of
					<q direct="unspecified">adorning himself with alien colours and forms for want of any of
						his own.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Let us, then, consider this matter from the beginning. We have previously
					said that with most people the beginning of friendship is their congenial
					disposition and nature, which welcomes the same habits and traits, as nearly
					as may be, and takes delight in the same pursuits, activities, and
					avocations ; on the subject of this it has also been said: <quote rend="blockquote">An old man hath
						the sweetest tongue for old, And child for child, and woman suits her kind,
						A sick man suits the sick ; misfortune's thrall Hath charms for him who hath
						just met mischance.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 364, and Kock, <hi rend="italics">Comm. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. 606.</note>
               </quote> So then the flatterer, knowing that when people take
					delight in the same things it is only natural that they find enjoyment and
					satisfaction in each other's company, adopts this course in making his first
					attempts to approach each victim and to secure a lodgement near him; he acts
					as though the man were some animal running at large in a pasture, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A reminiscence of Plato's <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 493 A.</note> and by
					affecting the same pursuits, the same avocations, interests and manner of
					life, he gradually gets close to him, and rubs up against him so as to take
					on his colouring, until his victim gives him some hold and becomes docile
					and accustomed to his touch : he is ever disapproving actions and lives and
					persons which he perceives his victim to dislike, while if anything pleases
					the other he commends, not with 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.281"/>
					
					moderation, but so as plainly to outdo him in amazement
					and wonder, and at the same time he stoutly maintains that his affection and
					hatred are the result of judgement rather than of emotion. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>What, then, is the method of exposing him, and by what differences is it
					possible to detect that he is not really like-minded, or even in a fair way
					to become like-minded, but is merely imitating such a character ? In the
					first place, it is necessary to observe the uniformity and permanence of his
					tastes, whether he always takes delight in the same things, and commends
					always the same things, and whether he directs and ordains his own life
					according to one pattern, as becomes a free-born man and a lover of
					congenial friendship and intimacy ; for such is the conduct of a friend. But
					the flatterer, since he has no abiding-place of character to dwell in, and
					since he leads a life not of his own choosing but another's, moulding and
					adapting himself to suit another, is not simple, not one, but variable and
					many in one, and, like water that is poured into one receptacle after
					another, he is constantly on the move from place to place, and changes his
					shape to fit his receiver. The capture of the ape, as it seems, is effected
					while he is trying to imitate man by moving and dancing as the man does :
					but the flatterer himself leads on and entices others, not imitating all
					persons alike, but with one he joins in dancing and singing, and with
					another in wrestling and getting covered with dust; if he gets hold of a
					huntsman fond of the chase, he follows on, all but shouting out the words of
					Phaedra <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus</hi>, 218.</note> : <quote rend="blockquote">Ye gods, but I yearn to encourage the hounds, As I haste on the
						track of the dapple deer.</quote>
					          <pb id="v1.p.283"/>
					
					He does not trouble himself in
					regard to the quarry, but he goes about to net and ensnare the huntsman
					himself. But if he is on the track of a scholarly and studious young man,
					now again he is absorbed in books, his beard grows down to his feet, the
					scholar's gown is the thing now and a stoic indifference, and endless talk
					about Plato's numbers and right-angled triangles. At another time, if some
					easy-tempered man fall in his way, who is a hard drinker and rich, <quote rend="blockquote">Then
						stands forth the wily Odysseus stripped of his tatters;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xxii. 1.</note>
               </quote> off goes the
					scholar's gown, the beard is mowed down like an unprofitable crop ; it's
					wine-coolers and glasses now, bursts of laughter while walking in the
					streets, and frivolous jokes against the devotees of philosophy. Just so at
					Syracuse, it is said, after Plato had arrived, and an insane ardour for
					philosophy laid hold on Dionysius, the king's palace was filled with dust by
					reason of the multitude of men that were drawing their geometrical diagrams
					in it: but when Plato fell out of favour, and Dionysius, shaking himself
					free from philosophy, returned post-haste to wine and women and foolish talk
					and licentiousness, then grossness and forgetfulness and fatuity seized upon
					the whole people as though they had undergone a transformation in Circe's
					house. A further testimony is to be found in the action of the great
					flatterers and the demagogues, of whom the greatest was Alcibiades. At
					Athens he indulged in frivolous jesting, kept a racing-stable, and led a
					life full of urbanity and agreeable enjoyment; in Lacedaemon he kept his
					hair cropped close, he wore the coarsest clothing, he bathed in cold water ;
					in Thrace he was a fighter and a hard drinker : but when he came to
					
					<pb id="v1.p.285"/>
					Tissaphernes, he took to soft living, and luxury, and
					pretentiousness. So by making himself like to all these people and
					conforming his way to theirs he tried to conciliate them and win their
					favour. Not of this type, however, was Epameinondas or Agesilaus, who,
					although they had to do with a very large number of men and cities and modes
					of life, yet maintained everywhere their own proper character in dress,
					conduct, language, and life. So, too, Plato in Syracuse was the same sort of
					man as in the Academy, and to Dionysius he was the same as to Dion. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>The changes of the flatterer, which are like those of a cuttle-fish, may be
					most easily detected if a man pretends that he is very changeable himself
					and disapproves the mode of life which he previously approved, and suddenly
					shows a liking for actions, conduct, or language which used to offend him.
					For he will see that the flatterer is nowhere constant, has no character of
					his own, that it is not because of his own feelings that he loves and hates,
					and rejoices and grieves, but that, like a mirror, he only catches the
					images of alien feelings, lives and movements. For he is the kind of man,
					who, if you chance to blame one of your friends before him, will exclaim,
					<q direct="unspecified">You've been slow in discovering the man's character; for my part
						I took a dislike to him long ago.</q> But if, on the next occasion,
					you change about again and commend the man, then you may be sure the
					flatterer will avow that he shares your pleasure and thanks you for the
					man's sake, and that he believes in him. If you say that you must adopt some
					other sort of life, as, for example, by changing from public life to ease
					and quietness, then he says, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, we 
						
						<pb id="v1.p.287"/>
						ought long
						ago to have secured release from turmoils and jealousies.</q> But
					again if you appear to be bent on public activity and speaking, then he
					chimes in, <q direct="unspecified">Your thoughts are worthy of you; ease is a pleasant
						thing, but it is inglorious and mean.</q> Without more ado we must
					say to such a man : <quote rend="blockquote">Stranger, you seem to me now a different man than
						aforetime.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, xvi. 181.</note>
               </quote> I have no use for a friend that shifts about just as I do and
					nods assent just as I do (for my shadow better performs that function), but
					I want one that tells the truth as I do, and decides for himself as I do.
					This is one method, then, of detecting the flatterer ; </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>but here follows a second point of difference which ought to be observed, in
					his habits of imitation. The true friend is neither an imitator of
					everything nor ready to commend everything, but only the best things ; <quote rend="blockquote">His
						nature 'tis to share not hate but love,</quote> as Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Antigone</hi>, 523.</note> has it, and most
					assuredly to share also in right conduct and in love for the good, not in
					error and evil-doing, unless, as a result of association and close
					acquaintance, an emanation and infection, like that which comes from a
					diseased eye, contaminate him against his will with a touch of baseness or
					error. In a similar way it is said that close acquaintances used to copy <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 26 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>
					Plato's stoop, Aristotle's lisp, and King Alexander's twisted neck as well
					as the harshness of his voice in conversation. In fact, some people
					unconsciously acquire most of their peculiarities from the traits or the
					lives of others. But the flatterer's case is exactly the same as that of the
					chameleon. For the chameleon can make
					
					<pb id="v1.p.289"/>
					himself like to
					every colour except white, and the flatterer, being utterly incapable of
					making himself like to another in any quality that is really worth while,
					leaves no shameful thing unimitated ; but even as bad painters, who by
					reason of incompetence are unable to attain to the beautiful, depend upon
					wrinkles, moles, and scars to bring out their resemblances, so the flatterer
					makes himself an imitator of licentiousness, superstition, passionate anger,
					harshness toward servants, and distrust toward household and kinsmen. For by
					nature he is of himself prone to the worse, and he seems very far removed
					from disapproving what is shameful, since he imitates it. In fact it is
					those who follow a higher ideal and show distress and annoyance at the
					errors of their friends, who fall under suspicion. This is the thing that
					brought Dion into disfavour with Dionysius, Samius with Philip, Cleomenes
					with Ptolemy, and finally brought about their undoing. But the flatterer,
					desiring to be and to seem pleasant and loyal at the same time, affects to
					take greater delight in the worse things, as one who for the great love he
					bears will take no offence even at what is base, but feels with his friend
					and shares his nature in all things. For this reason flatterers will not be
					denied a share even in the chances of life which happen without our will;
					but they flatter the sickly by pretending to be afflicted with the same
					malady, and not to be able to see or hear distinctly if they have to do with
					those who are dim-sighted or hard of hearing, just as the flatterers of
					Dionysius, whose sight was failing, used to bump against one another and
					upset the dishes at dinner. And some seize upon afflictions rather as a
					means to insinuate themselves
					
					<pb id="v1.p.291"/>
					still more, and carry
					their fellow-feeling so far as to include inmost secrets. If they know, for
					example, that one or another is unfortunate in his marriage, or suspicious
					towards his sons or his household, they do not spare themselves, but lament
					over their own children or wife or kinsmen or household, divulging certain
					secret faults of theirs. For such similarity makes fellow-feeling stronger,
					so that the others, conceiving themselves to have received pledges, are more
					inclined to let out some of their own secrets to the flatterers, and having
					so done they take up with them, and are afraid to abandon the confidential
					relation. I personally know of one man who put away his wife after his
					friend had sent his own away; but he was caught visiting her in secret and
					sending messages to her after his friend's wife had got wind of what was
					going on. Quite unacquainted with a flatterer, then, was he who thought that
					these iambic verses <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. 669.</note> applied to a flatterer rather than to a crab : <quote rend="blockquote">His
						body is all belly ; eyes that look All ways ; a beast that travels on its
						teeth.</quote> For such a description is that of a parasite, one of <quote rend="blockquote">The saucepan
							friends and friends postprandial,</quote> as Eupolis <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. 349.</note> puts it. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>However, let us reserve this matter for its proper place in our discussion.
					But let us not omit to note this clever turn which the flatterer has in his
					imitations, that if he does imitate any of the good qualities of the person
					whom he flatters, he gives him always the upper hand. The reason is this :
					between true friends there is neither emulation nor envy, but whether their
					share of success is equal or less, they 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.293"/>
					bear it with moderation and without vexation. But the
					flatterer, mindful always that he is to play the second part, abates from
					his equality in the imitation, admitting that he is beaten and distanced in
					everything save what is bad. In bad things, however, he does not relinquish
					the first place, but, if the other man is malcontent, he calls himself
					choleric ; if the man is superstitious he says of himself that he is
					possessed ; that the man is in love, but that he himself is mad with
					passion. <q direct="unspecified">You laughed inopportunely,</q> he says, <q direct="unspecified">but I
						nearly died of laughing.</q> But in good things it is just the
					reverse. The flatterer says that he himself is a good runner, but the other
					man simply flies ; that he himself is a fairly good horseman, <q direct="unspecified">but
						what is that compared with this Centaur ?</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">I am a natural born poet, and I write verse that is not at all bad,
						yet <quote rend="blockquote">To Zeus belongs the thunder, not to me.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. p. 736.</note>
                  </quote>
               </q> a Thus at the same
					time he thinks to show that the other's tastes are excellent by imitating
					them, and that his prowess is unrivalled by letting himself be outdone.
					Thus, then, in the flatterer's attempts to conform himself to another,
					differences like these are found which distinguish him from a friend. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Since, however, as has been said before, the element of pleasure is common to
					both (for the good man takes no less delight in his friends than the bad man
					in his flatterers), let us now, if you will, draw the distinction between
					them in this respect. The distinction lies in referring the pleasure to its
					end. Look at it in this way: There is a pleasant odour in a perfume, there
					is a pleasant odour in a medicine.
					
					<pb id="v1.p.295"/>
					But the difference is
					that the former has been created for pleasure and for nothing else, while in
					the latter the purgative, stimulative, or tissue-building principle that
					gives it value is only incidentally sweet-smelling. Then again, painters mix
					bright colours and pigments, and there are also some physicians' drugs that
					are bright in appearance, and have a colour that is not repellent. What,
					then, is the difference ? Is it not plain that we shall distinguish them by
					the end for which they are employed ? So, in a similar way, the graciousness
					of friends, in addition to goodness and profit, possesses also the power of
					giving pleasure as a sort of efflorescence, and there are times when friends
					enjoy together jest and food and wine, and indeed even mirth and nonsense,
					as a sort of spice for noble and serious things. To this purport it has been
					said: <quote rend="blockquote">Joy they had in converse, speaking each to the other <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 643.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Else there
						were nothing Which could have parted us twain in the midst of our love and
						enjoyment.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv. 178.</note>
               </quote> But the whole work and final aim of the flatterer is always to
					be serving up some spicy and highlyseasoned jest or prank or story, incited
					by pleasure and to incite pleasure. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Possibly a reminiscence from Plato, <hi rend="italics">Gorgias</hi>, 465 ff.</note> To put it in few words, the flatterer
					thinks he ought to do anything to be agreeable, while the friend, by doing
					always what he ought to do, is oftentimes agreeable and oftentimes
					disagreeable, not from any desire to be disagreeable, and yet not attempting
					to avoid even this if it be better. For he is like a physician, who, if it
					be for the good of the patient, administers saffron or spikenard, and indeed
					oftentimes prescribes a
					
					<pb id="v1.p.297"/>
					grateful bath or generous diet,
					but there are cases where he lets all these go and drops in a dose of
					castor, or else of <quote rend="blockquote">Polium, pungent to smell, whose stench is surely most
						horrid,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nicander, <hi rend="italics">Theriaca</hi>, 64. On the herb <hi rend="italics">polium</hi> see Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, xxi. 7 (21). 44 and xxi. 20 (84), 145.</note>
               </quote> or he compounds some hellebore and makes a man drink it down,
					setting neither in this case the disagreeable nor in the other the agreeable
					as his final aim, but endeavouring through either course to bring his
					patient to one state—that which is for his good. So it is with the friend;
					sometimes by constantly exalting and gladdening another with praise and
					graciousness he leads him on toward that which is honourable, as did he who
					said <quote rend="blockquote">Teucer, dear to my heart, son of Telamon, prince of the people. Aim
						your other shafts like this,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> viii. 281.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">How then, I ask, could I ever forget
							Odysseus the godlike ?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> x. 243, and <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> i. 65.</note>
               </quote> Or again, when there is need of reprehension, he
					assails with stinging words and all the frankness of a guardian: <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Foolish you
						are, Menelaus, cherished by Zeus; nor is needed Any such folly as this.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 109.</note>
               </q>
					There are times, too, when he combines deeds with words, as did Menedemus,
					who chastened the profligate and disorderly son of his friend Asclepiades by
					shutting the door upon him and not speaking to him ; and Arcesilaus forbade
					Baton his lecture-room when the latter had composed a comic line on
					Cleanthes, and it was only when Baton had placated Cleanthes and was
					repentant that Arcesilaus became reconciled with him. For one ought to hurt
					a friend
					
					<pb id="v1.p.299"/>
					
					only to help him ; and ought not by hurting him
					to kill friendship, but to use the stinging word as a medicine which
					restores and preserves health in that to which it is applied. Wherefore a
					friend, like a skilled musician, in effecting a transition to what is noble
					and beneficial, now relaxes and now tightens a string, and so is often
					pleasant and always profitable; but the flatterer, being accustomed to play
					his accompaniment of pleasantness and graciousness in one key only, knows
					nothing either of acts of resistance or of words that hurt, but is guided by
					the other's wish only, and makes every note and utterance to accord with
					him. As Xenophon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xen. <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 11, 5.</note> says of Agesilaus, that he was glad to be commended by
					those who were willing to blame him also, so we must regard that which gives
					delight and joy as true to friendship, if at times it is able also to hurt
					our feelings and to resist our desires ; but we must be suspicious of an
					association that is confined to pleasures, one whose complaisance is unmixed
					and without a sting ; and we ought in fact to keep in mind the saying of the
					Spartan,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Archidamidas, according to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 218 B.</note> who, when Charillus the king was commended, said, <q direct="unspecified">How can
						he be a good man, who is not harsh even with rascals ?</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>They say that the gad-fly finds lodgement with cattle close by the ear, as
					does the tick with dogs ; so also the flatterer takes hold of ambitious
					men's ears with his words of praise, and once settled there, he is hard to
					dislodge. Wherefore in this matter especially it is necessary to keep the
					judgement awake and on the alert, to see whether the praise is for the
					action or for the man. It is for the action if they praise us in absence
					rather than in our presence ; also if they, too, cherish the same desires
					and
					<pb id="v1.p.301"/>
					aspirations themselves and praise not us alone but
					all persons for like conduct; also if they are not found doing and saying
					now this and now the opposite ; but, chief of all, if we ourselves know that
					we feel no regret for those actions for which we are praised, no feeling of
					shame and no wish that we had said or done the opposite. For if our own
					conscience protests and refuses to accept the praise, then it is not
					affected or touched, and is proof against assault by the flatterer. Yet, in
					some way that passes my knowledge, most people have no patience with efforts
					to console them in their misfortunes, but are more influenced by those who
					commiserate and condole with them ; and whenever these same people are
					guilty of mistakes and blunders, the man who by chiding and blaming implants
					the sting of repentance is taken to be an enemy and an accuser, whereas they
					welcome the man who praises and extols what they have done, and regard him
					as kindly and friendly. Now those who unthinkingly praise and join in
					applauding an act or a saying, or anything offered by another, whether he be
					in earnest or in jest, are harmful only for the moment and for the matter at
					hand; but those who with their praises pierce to the man's character, and
					indeed even touch his habit of mind with their flattery, are doing the very
					thing that servants do who steal not from the heap <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The grain, after being winnowed, was heaped on the threshing-floor.</note> but from the seed-corn.
					For, since the disposition and character are the seed from which actions
					spring, such persons are thus perverting the very first principle and
					fountain-head of living, inasmuch as they are investing vice with the names
					that belong to 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.303"/>
					virtue. Amid factions and wars, Thucydides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thuc. iii. 82.</note> says,
					<q direct="unspecified">they changed the commonly accepted meaning of words when applied
						to deeds as they thought proper. Reckless daring came to be regarded as
						devoted courage, watchful waiting as specious cowardice, moderation as a
						craven's pretext, a keen understanding for everything as want of energy
						to undertake anything.</q> And so in attempts at flattery we should
					be observant and on our guard against prodigality being called <q direct="unspecified">
						liberality,</q> cowardice <q direct="unspecified">self-preservation,</q>
					impulsiveness <q direct="unspecified">quickness,</q> stinginess <q direct="unspecified">
						frugality,</q> the amorous man <q direct="unspecified">companionable and
							amiable,</q> the irascible and overbearing <q direct="unspecified">spirited,</q>
					the insignificant and meek <q direct="unspecified">kindly.</q> So Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 474 E; <hi rend="italics">cf. supra</hi> 45 A.</note> somewhere says
					that the lover, being a flatterer of his beloved, calls one with a snub nose
					<q direct="unspecified">fetching,</q> one with a hooked nose <q direct="unspecified">kingly,</q>
					dark persons <q direct="unspecified">manly,</q> and fair persons <q direct="unspecified">children of the
						gods</q> ; while <q direct="unspecified">honey-hued</q> is purely the creation
					of a lover who calls sallowness by this endearing term, and cheerfully puts
					up with it. And yet an ugly man who is made to believe that he is handsome,
					or a short man that he is tall, is not for long a party to the deception,
					and the injury that he suffers is slight and not irremediable. But as for
					the praise which accustoms a man to treat vices as virtues, so that he feels
					not disgusted with them but delighted, which also takes away all shame for
					his errors—this is the sort that brought afflictions upon the people of
					Sicily, by calling the savage cruelty of Dionysius and of Phalaris <q direct="unspecified">
						hatred of wickedness</q> ; this it is that ruined Egypt, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ptolemy Philopator (221-205 B.C.); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Polybius, v. 34.</note> by giving
					to Ptolemy's effeminacy, his religious mania, his hallelujahs, his clashing
					of cymbals, the name of
					
					<pb id="v1.p.305"/>
					          <q direct="unspecified">piety</q> and <q direct="unspecified">devotion to the gods</q> ; this it
					is that all but subverted and destroyed the character of the Romans in those
					days, by trying to extenuate Antony's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Antony</hi>, chap. ix. (920).</note> luxuriousness, his excesses and
					ostentatious displays, as <q direct="unspecified">blithe and kind-hearted actions due to his
						generous treatment at the hands of Power and Fortune.</q> What else
					was it that fastened the mouthpiece and flute upon Ptolemy <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ptolemy Auletes (80-51 B.C.); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Strabo xvii. 11 (p. 796).</note> ? What else set
					a tragic stage for Nero, and invested him with mask and buskins ? Was it not
					the praise of his flatterers ? And is not almost any king called an Apollo
					if he can hum a tune, and a Dionysus if he gets drunk, and a Heracles if he
					can wrestle ? And is he not delighted, and thus led on into all kinds of
					disgrace by the flattery ? </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>For this reason we must be especially on our guard against the flatterer in
					the matter of his praises. But of this he is not unconscious himself, and he
					is adroit at guarding against the breath of suspicion. If, for example, he
					gets hold of some coxcomb, or a rustic wearing a thick coat of skin, he
					indulges his raillery without limit, just as Strouthias, in the play, walks
					all over Bias, and takes a fling at his stupidity by such praise as this :
					<quote rend="blockquote">More you have drunk Than royal Alexander,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Flatterer</hi> of Menander; Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii., <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi>, No. 293.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Ha ! ha ! A good one on the
						Cyprian,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> No. 29.</note>
               </quote> But as for the more clever people, he observes that 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.307"/>
					
					they are particularly on the look-out for him in this
					quarter, that they stand well upon their guard in this place and region ; so
					he does not deploy his praise in a frontal attack, but fetches a wide
					circuit, and <quote rend="blockquote">Approaches noiseless as to catch a beast,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Source unknown.</note>
               </quote> touching and
					handling him. Now he will report other people's praise of him, quoting
					another's words as public speakers do, how he had the pleasure of meeting in
					the market-place with some strangers or elderly men, who recounted many
					handsome things of him and expressed their admiration ; then again, he will
					fabricate and concoct some trivial and false accusation against him, which
					he feigns to have heard from others, and comes up in hot haste to inquire
					when it was he said this or when it was he did that. And if the man denies
					the thing, as he naturally will, then on the instant the flatterer seizes
					him and launches him into a flood of praise : <q direct="unspecified">I wondered if you did
						speak ill of any of your good friends, since it is not your nature to
						speak ill even of your enemies, or if you did make any attempt on
						other's property when you give away so much of your own.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Others, like painters who set off bright and brilliant colours by laying- on
					dark and sombre tints close beside them, covertly praise and foster the
					vices to which their victims are addicted by condemning and abusing, or
					disparaging and ridiculing, the opposite qualities. Among the profligate
					they condemn frugality as <q direct="unspecified">rusticity</q>; and among avaricious
					evil-doers, whose wealth is gained from shameful and unscrupulous deeds,
					they condemn contented independence and honesty as <q direct="unspecified">the want
						
						<pb id="v1.p.309"/>
						of courage and vigour for active life</q> ; but
					when they associate with the easy-going and quiet people who avoid the
					crowded centres of the cities, they are not ashamed to call public life
					<q direct="unspecified">a troublesome meddling with others' affairs,</q> and
					ambition <q direct="unspecified">unprofitable vainglory.</q> Often enough a way to
					flatter a public speaker is to disparage a philosopher, and with lascivious
					women great repute is gained by those who brand faithful and loving wives as
					<q direct="unspecified">cold</q> and <q direct="unspecified">countrified.</q> But here is the
					height of depravity, in that the flatterers do not spare their own selves.
					For as wrestlers put their own bodies into a lowly posture in order to throw
					their opponents, so flatterers, by blaming themselves, pass surreptitiously
					into admiration for their neighbours : <q direct="unspecified">I am a miserable coward on the
						water, I have no stomach for hardships, I go mad with anger when anyone
						speaks ill of me ; but for this man here,</q> he says, <q direct="unspecified">
							nothing has any terrors, nothing any hardship, but he is a singular
							person ; he bears everything with good humour, everything without
							distress.</q> But if there be somebody who imagines himself
					possessed of great sense, and desires to be downright and uncompromising,
					who because he poses as an upright man, forsooth, always uses as a defence
					and shield this line : <quote rend="blockquote">Son of Tydeus, praise me not too much, nor chide me,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 249.</note>
               </quote>
					the accomplished flatterer does not approach him by this road, but there is
					another device to apply to a man of this sort. Accordingly the flatterer
					comes to consult with him about his own affairs, as with one obviously his
					superior in wisdom, and says that while he has other friends more intimate
					yet he
					
					<pb id="v1.p.311"/>
					
					finds it necessary to trouble him. <q direct="unspecified">For
						where can we resort who are in need of counsel, and whom can we trust ?
					</q> Then having heard whatever the other may say, he asserts that he
					has received, not counsel, but the word of authority ; and with that he
					takes his departure. And if he observes that the man lays some claim to
					skill in letters, he gives him some of his own writings, and asks him to
					read and correct them. Mithridates, the king, posed as an amateur physician,
					and some of his companions offered themselves to be operated upon and
					cauterized by him, thus flattering by deeds and not by words ; for he felt
					that their confidence in him was a testimony to his skill. <quote rend="blockquote">In many a guise
						do the gods appear,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From thes tock lines used at the close of the <hi rend="italics">Alcestis</hi>, the <hi rend="italics">Andromache</hi>, the <hi rend="italics">Bacchae</hi>, and the <hi rend="italics">Helena</hi>, of Euripides.</note>
               </quote> and this class of dissimulated praise, which calls for
					a more cunning sort of precaution, is to be brought to light by deliberately
					formulating absurd advice and suggestions, and by making senseless
					corrections. For if he fails to contradict anything, if he assents to
					everything and accepts it, and at each suggestion exclaims <q direct="unspecified">good
					</q> and <q direct="unspecified">excellent,</q> he makes it perfectly plain that he
					<quote rend="blockquote">The password asks, to gain some other end,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 365.</note>
               </quote> his real desire being to praise
					his victim and to puff him up all the more. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Moreover, just as some have defined painting as silent poetry,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A dictum attributed to Simonides by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 346 F, where it is quoted in full. The full form is found also <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 17 F.</note> so there is a
					kind of praise that is silent flattery. For just as men engaged in hunting
					are less noticed by their quarry if they pretend not to be so engaged, but
					to be going along the road or tending flocks or tilling the soil, so
					flatterers gain the best hold with their praise when they pretend
					
					<pb id="v1.p.313"/>
					
					not to be praising, but to be doing something else.
					Take, for example, a man who yields his seat or his place at table to a
					new-comer, or if he is engaged in speaking to the popular assembly or the
					senate and discovers that someone of the wealthy wants to speak, suddenly
					lapses into silence in the midst of his argument, and surrenders the
					platform with his right to speak ; such a man by his silence, far more than
					one who indulges in loud acclaim, makes it plain that he regards the rich
					person as his better and his superior in intelligence. This is the reason
					why such persons are to be seen taking possession of the front seats at
					entertainments and theatres, not because they think they have any right to
					them, but so that they may flatter the rich by giving up their seats. So,
					too, in an assemblage or a formal meeting they may be observed to begin a
					subject of discussion, and later to give ground as though before their
					betters, and to shift over with the utmost readiness to the other side, if
					the man opposing them be a person of power or wealth or repute. Herein lies
					the supreme test by which we must detect such cases of cringing submission
					and giving way, in that deference is paid, not to experience or virtue or
					age, but to wealth and repute. Apelles, the painter, as Megabyzus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 472 A.</note> took a
					seat by his side, eager to discuss line and chiaroscuro, said, <q direct="unspecified">Do
						you see these boys here who are grinding the body for my colours ? They
						were all attention while you kept silent, and admired your purple robe
						and golden ornaments, but now they are laughing at you because you have
						undertaken to speak of matters which you have never learned.</q> And
					Solon, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, i. 30-33; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, xxvii. (93 B).</note> when Croesus inquired about happiness, declared that Tellus, one of
					the
					
					<pb id="v1.p.315"/>
					inconspicuous men at Athens, and Cleobis and Biton,
					were more blest by fate than he. But flatterers proclaim that kings and
					wealthy persons and rulers are not only prosperous and blessed, but that
					they also rank first in understanding, technical skill, and every form of
					virtue. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Again, some people will not even listen to the Stoics, when they call the
					wise man at the same time rich, handsome, well-born, and a king ; but
					flatterers declare of the rich man that he is at the same time an orator and
					a poet, and, if he will, a painter and a musician, and swift of foot and
					strong of body ; and they allow themselves to be thrown in wrestling and
					outdistanced in running, as Crison of Himera was outdistanced in a foot-race
					with Alexander, but Alexander saw through the deception and was indignant. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 471 F.</note>
					Carneades used to say that the sons of the wealthy and sons of kings do
					learn to ride on horseback, but that they learn nothing else well and
					properly ; for in their studies their teacher flatters them with praise, and
					their opponent in wrestling does the same by submitting to be thrown,
					whereas the horse, having no knowledge or concern even as to who is private
					citizen or ruler, or rich or poor, throws headlong those who cannot ride
					him. It was therefore silly and foolish of Bion to say that <q direct="unspecified">if he
						were sure to make his field productive and fruitful by lauding it,
						should he not then seem to be in error if he did not do this rather than
						give himself the trouble to dig it over ? And so, too, a man would not
						be an improper subject for praise, if by virtue of praise alone he
						becomes profitable and abundantly productive of good.</q> But the
					truth is that a field is 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.317"/>
					
					not made any the worse by being praised, whereas a man
					is puffed up and ruined by those who praise him falsely and beyond his
					deserts. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Enough, then, on this topic. Let us, as the next step, look at the subject of
					frankness. As Patroclus, when he equipped himself with the armour of
					Achilles, and drove forth his horses to battle, did not venture to touch the
					Pelian spear, but left that, and that only, behind, so the flatterer, when
					he arrays himself to masquerade in the badges and insignia proper to a
					friend, ought to leave frankness alone as the one thing not to be touched or
					imitated, as though it were a choice piece of equipment, <quote rend="blockquote">Heavy and big and
						solid,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 14.</note>
               </quote> belonging to friendship only. But since they shrink from the
					exposure that awaits them in laughter and wine, and in jest and jollity, and
					their next effort is to raise their business to a serious <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">High-brow</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the note in Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi> in the L.C.L., p. 316.</note> level, by
					putting a stern face on their flattery, and tempering it with a little blame
					and admonition, let us not neglect to examine this point also. My mind is
					this : Just as in Menander's comedy <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The few fragments may be found in Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 148, or in Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi> in the L.C.L., p. 458.</note> the sham Heracles comes on carrying a
					club which is not solid nor strong, but a light and hollow counterfeit, so
					the flatterer's frankness will appear, if we test it, to be soft and without
					weight or firmness, just like women's cushions, which, while they seem to
					support and to offer resistance to their heads, yet rather yield and give
					way to them ; and in the same way this counterfeit frankness, through having
					a hollow, false, and unsound bulk, is inflated and swollen, to the intent
					that later when it contracts and collapses it may 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.319"/>
					take in and drag along with it the man who throws
					himself upon it. For the true frankness such as a friend displays applies
					itself to errors that are being committed ; the pain which it causes is
					salutary and benignant, and, like honey, it causes the sore places to smart
					and cleanses them too, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There are many references in ancient writers to this property of honey. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Phocion</hi>, chap. ii. (p. 742 B). The fact that honey quickly destroys pathogenic germs, like those of typhoid, has recently received scientific demonstration; <hi rend="italics">cf. Bulletin</hi> 252 of the Colorado Agricultural College.</note> but in its other uses it is wholesome and sweet;
					this later shall have a chapter to itself.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Chap. 26, <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
               </note> But the flatterer, in the first
					place, makes a parade of harshness and of being acrimonious and inexorable
					in his bearing towards others. For he is rough with his own servants, and
					very quick to pounce on the errors of his kinsmen and household, refusing to
					admire or extol any outsider but rather despising all such ; he is
					relentless in his efforts to stir up others to anger by his slanders ; his
					aim is to get the name of a hater of iniquity, and to give the impression
					that he would not willingly abate his frankness to please others, nor do or
					say anything at all to curry favour. In the second place, he pretends not to
					know or notice a single real and important misdeed, but he is very quick to
					swoop down upon trifling and immaterial shortcomings, and to indulge in an
					intense and vehement tirade if he sees that a bit of furniture is carelessly
					placed, if he sees that a man is a poor manager, if anyone is careless about
					having his hair cut or about his clothing, or does not give proper care to
					some dog or horse ; but let a man disregard his parents, neglect his
					children, insult his wife, disdain his household, squander his money, all
					this is nothing to him, but in the midst of such matters he is mute and
					craven, like a trainer who allows an athlete to get drunk and live loosely,
					and then is very stern about oilflask 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.321"/>
					and flesh-scraper, or like a schoolmaster who scolds a
					boy about his slate and pencil, and affects not to hear his blunders in
					grammar and diction. For the flatterer is the sort of person who will not
					say a word regarding the actual discourse of a cheap and ridiculous speaker,
					but will find fault with his voice, and accuse him severely because he ruins
					his throat by drinking cold water ; or if he is requested to look over a
					wretched piece of writing, he will find fault with the paper for being
					rough, and call the copyist abominably careless. So it was with the
					flatterers of Ptolemy, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably Ptolemy Euergetes II., also called Physcon (146-117 B.C.); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Athenaeus, xii. 73 (p. 549 D).</note> who posed as a lover of learning; they would contend
					with him about an obscure word or a trifling verse or a point of history,
					and keep it up till midnight; but when he indulged in wanton cruelty and
					violence, played the cymbals and conducted his initiations, not one of all
					these people opposed his course. Just imagine a man using a surgeon's lancet
					to cut the hair and nails of a person suffering from tumours and abscesses !
					Yet this is the sort of thing that flatterers do, who apply their frankness
					to those parts that feel no hurt or pain. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>There is still another class of persons, even more unscrupulous than these,
					who employ this frankness of speech and reprehension of theirs in order to
					give pleasure. For example, Agis, the Argive, on an occasion when Alexander
					gave great gifts to a jester, in his jealousy and chagrin shouted out,
					<q direct="unspecified">Heavens, what gross absurdity !</q> The king turned upon
					him angrily and said, <q direct="unspecified">What's that you say ?</q> Whereupon he
					replied, <q direct="unspecified">I confess that I feel troubled and indignant at seeing that
						all you sons of Zeus alike show favour to flatterers and ridiculous
						persons. For Heracles had pleasure in
							
							<pb id="v1.p.323"/>
							
							certain
							Cercopes, and Dionysus in Sileni, and one can see that such persons are
							in good repute with you.</q> And once, when Tiberius Caesar had come
					into the Senate, one of the flatterers arose and said that they ought, being
					free men, to speak frankly, and not to dissemble or refrain from discussing
					anything that might be for the general good. Having thus aroused general
					attention, in the ensuing silence, as Tiberius gave ear, he said, <q direct="unspecified">
						Listen, Caesar, to the charges which we are all making against you, but
						which no one dares to speak out. You do not take proper care of
						yourself, you are prodigal of your bodily strength, you are continually
						wearing it out in your anxieties and labours in our behalf, you give
						yourself no respite either by day or by night.</q> As he drew out a
					long string of such phrases, they say that the orator Cassius Severus
					remarked, <q direct="unspecified">Such frankness as this will be the death of this man !
					</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>All that is really a minor matter. But we come now to matters that are a
					serious problem, and do great damage to the foolish, when the flatterer's
					accusations are directed against emotions and weaknesses the contrary to
					those that a person really has. For example, Himerius the flatterer used to
					vilify a man, the most illiberal and avaricious of the rich men at Athens,
					as a careless profligate destined to starve miserably together with his
					children. Or again, on the other hand, they will reproach profligate and
					lavish spenders with meanness and sordidness (as Titus Petronius did with
					Nero) ; or they will bid rulers who deal savagely and fiercely with their
					subjects to lay aside their excessive clemency and their inopportune and
					unprofitable pity. Very like to these also is the man who pretends to be on
					his
					
					<pb id="v1.p.325"/>
					
					guard against some simple and stupid fool, and to
					fear him as a clever rascal; and so, too, if a malicious person, and one
					that delights in constant evil-speaking and fault-finding, be induced to
					commend some man of note, a flatterer of this stamp takes him straight in
					hand, and contradicts him, declaring that it is a weakness of his to commend
					even the worthless. <q direct="unspecified">For who is this fellow, or what brilliant thing
						has he said or done ?</q> Especially in regard to love affairs they
					beset their victims and add fuel to their fire. Likewise if they see that
					any are in disagreement with their brothers, or that they contemn their
					parents, or deal scornfully with their wives, they do not admonish or
					arraign them, but try to intensify such feelings. <q direct="unspecified">You have no proper
						appreciation of yourself,</q> they say, and, <q direct="unspecified">You have
							yourself to blame for this, because you always affect such an obsequious
							and humble air.</q> And if, as a result of temper and jealousy, a
					feeling of irritation is engendered toward a mistress or another man's wife
					with whom the man has a love-affair, in comes flattery at once with a
					splendid frankness, adding fire to fire, pleading for justice, accusing the
					lover of many unloving, obdurate, and reprehensible actions : <quote rend="blockquote">O ingrate,
						after crowding kiss on kiss !<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Myrmidons</hi> of Aeschylus. Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Aesch.</hi>, No. 135; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 715 C.</note>
               </quote> So the friends of Antony, who was consumed
					with love of the Egyptian woman,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Antony</hi>, chap. liii. (940 D).</note> tried to make him believe that she was
					enamoured of him, and, upbraiding him, they would call him cold and haughty
					: <q direct="unspecified">For the woman, forsaking so great a kingdom and so many happy
						employments, is wearing her life away, as she follows with you on your
						marches in the guise of a concubine;
						<pb id="v1.p.327"/>
						            <quote rend="blockquote">But the mind in
							your breast is proof against enchantment,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> x. 329.</note>
                  </quote> and you are indifferent to
						her distress.</q> He was pleased at being taken to task for such
					wrongdoing, and taking more pleasure in those who accused him than he did
					even in any who commended him, he failed to see that by this seeming
					admonition he was being perversely drawn towards her. Such frankness is like
					the love bites of lascivious women ; it arouses and tickles the sense of
					pleasure by pretending to cause pain. So undiluted wine is of itself a
					helpful remedy for the hemlock poison, but if they add it to hemlock and mix
					the two together they make the potency of the drug quite beyond remedy,
					since it is rapidly carried to the heart by the heat. In like manner the
					unscrupulous, being well aware that frankness is a great remedy for
					flattery, flatter by means of frankness itself. It is for this reason that
					Bias did not give a good answer to the man who asked him <q direct="unspecified">What is the
						fiercest animal ?</q> when he replied, <q direct="unspecified">Of the wild animals
							the tyrant, and of the domesticated the flatterer.</q> For it were
					nearer the truth to say, that among flatterers those who hover about the
					bath and the table are domesticated, whereas he that extends his meddling
					and slander and malice like tentacles into the bedchamber and the women's
					privacy, is an uncivilized brute and most hard to handle. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>One mode of protection, as it would seem, is to realize and remember always
					that our soul has its two sides : on the one side are truthfulness, love for
					what is honourable, and power to reason, and on the other side
					irrationality, love of falsehood, and the emotional element; the friend is
					always found on the better side as counsel and advocate, trying, after
					
					<pb id="v1.p.329"/>
					
					the manner of a physician, to foster the growth of what
					is sound and to preserve it; but the flatterer takes his place on the side
					of the emotional and irrational, and this he excites and tickles and
					wheedles, and tries to divorce from the reasoning powers by contriving for
					it divers low forms of pleasurable enjoyment. There are some sorts of food,
					for example, that are without affinity for either the blood or the breath,
					which add no vigour to nerves or marrow, but only excite the lower passions,
					arouse the appetite, and make unsound flesh that is morbid within. So the
					flatterer's talk adds nothing to the thinking and reasoning powers, but only
					promotes familiarity with some amorous pleasure, intensifies a foolish fit
					of temper, provokes envy, engenders an offensive and inane bulk of conceit,
					commiserates in distress, or, by a succession of slanders and forebodings,
					causes malice, illiberality and distrust to grow bitter, timorous, and
					suspicious ; and these are all matters that will not escape the observant.
					For the flatterer is always covertly on the watch for some emotion, and
					pampering it, and his presence is like that of a tumour in that he ever
					comes immediately following some morbid or inflamed condition of the soul.
					<q direct="unspecified">Are you angry ? Punish then.</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do you crave a thing ? Then buy it.</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Are you afraid ? Let's run away.</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Have you a suspicion ? Then give it credence.</q> But if it is
					hard to detect the flatterer when he is engaged with these major emotions,
					inasmuch as our power to reason is deranged by their vehemence and
					magnitude, yet with the lesser ones he will better give a vantage, since his
					behaviour here will be the same. For example, if a man is afraid that he may
					
					<pb id="v1.p.331"/>
					have a headache or a digestive upset from drinking
					or eating to excess, and hesitates about bathing and taking food, a friend
					will try to hold him back, and advise him to be careful and cautious, but
					the flatterer drags him off to the baths, and bids him order some novel
					dish, and not to maltreat his body by forced abstinence. And if he sees his
					man to be feebly inclined towards some journey or voyage or undertaking, he
					will say that the occasion is not pressing but that they will accomplish the
					same result by postponement or by sending somebody else. If the man, after
					promising money as a loan or a gift to some personal friend, wants to change
					his mind, but is ashamed to do so, the flatterer throws his weight upon the
					worse inclination, strengthens his opinion touching his purse, and banishes
					his feeling of mortification, bidding him be economical, since he has many
					expenses and many mouths to feed. It follows, therefore, that if we are not
					unaware of our own feelings of covetousness, shamelessness, and cowardice,
					we shall not be unaware of the flatterer. For he always acts as an advocate
					of such emotions, and is frank in discussing the results to which they lead.
					This, then, is enough on this subject. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Let us come without more ado to the topic of services and ministrations ; for
					it is in these that the flatterer brings about a great confusion and
					uncertainty in regard to the difference between himself and the friend,
					because he appears to be brisk and eager in everything and never to make an
					excuse. For the character of a friend, like the <q direct="unspecified">language of
						truth,</q> is, as Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 469, 472.</note> puts it, <q direct="unspecified">simple,</q>
					plain, and unaffected, whereas that of the flatterer, in very truth
					
					<pb id="v1.p.333"/>
					Self-sick, hath need of dextrous remedies, and of a good
					many too, I venture to affirm, and of an uncommon sort. Take the case of one
					person meeting another : a friend sometimes, without the exchange of a word,
					but merely by a glance and a smile, gives and receives through the medium of
					the eyes an intimation of the goodwill and intimacy that is in the heart,
					and passes on. But the flatterer runs, pursues, extends his greeting at a
					distance, and if he be seen and spoken to first, he pleads his defence with
					witnesses and oaths over and over again. It is the same with actions :
					friends omit many of the trifling formalities, not being at all exacting or
					officious in this respect, not putting themselves forward for every kind of
					ministration ; whereas the flatterer is in these matters persistent,
					assiduous, and untiring, giving to no one else place or space for a good
					office, but he is eager for orders, and if he receives none he is nettled,
					or rather he is utterly dispirited and gives way to lamentations. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Now to people of sense these are manifestations, not of a pure nor a chaste
					friendship, but of a friendship that is more ready than it should be to
					solicit and embrace. We need first, however, to consider the difference
					shown by the two men in offering their services. It has been well said by
					writers before our time that a friend's offer takes this form : <quote rend="blockquote">Yes, if I
						have the power, and if it can be accomplished,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiv. 196; xviii. 427; <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> v. 90.</note>
               </quote> while a flatterer's is like
					this : <quote rend="blockquote">Speak what you have in mind.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiv. 195; xviii. 426; <hi rend="italics">Od. v. 89.</hi>
                  </note>
               </quote> In fact the comic poets introduce on
					the stage characters of this sort:
					<pb id="v1.p.335"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Match me, Nicomachus,
						against that brute ; If I don't pulp his carcase with my whip And make his
						visage softer than a sponge.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 432, <hi rend="italics">Adespot.</hi> No. 125.</note>
               </quote> In the second place, no friend enters into
					cooperation unless he has first been taken into consultation, and then only
					after he has examined the undertaking and agreed in setting it down as
					fitting or expedient; but if anyone concedes to the flatterer an opportunity
					to take part in examining and pronouncing upon some matter in hand, inasmuch
					as he not only desires to yield and give gratification, but also fears to
					afford suspicion that he may draw back and avoid the task, he gives way and
					adds his urgency to the other's desires. For it is not easy to find a
					wealthy man or a king who will say : <quote rend="blockquote">Give me a beggar—and if he so will,
						Worse than a beggar—who, through love for me Leaves fear behind, and speaks
						his heart's belief; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Ino</hi> of Euripides; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Eurip.</hi> No. 412.</note>
               </quote> but such people, like the tragedians, want to have a
					chorus of friends singing the same tune or a sympathetic audience to applaud
					them. This is the reason why Merope in the tragedy gives this advice : <quote rend="blockquote">Have
						friends who are not yielding in their speech, But let your house be barred
						against the knaves Who try by pleasing you to win regard.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Part of a much longer fragment from the <hi rend="italics">Erechtheus</hi> of Euripides; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Eurip.</hi> No. 362, xi. 18-20. There is no evidence, save this quotation, for Merope's appearance in the play, and it seems much more probably that the lines were spoken by Praxithea, the wife of Erechtheus.</note>
               </quote> But such people
					generally do just the opposite ; they abominate those who are <q direct="unspecified">not
						yielding in speech,</q> who take a stand against them for their own
					good, while <q direct="unspecified">the knaves who try to win regard,</q> the 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.337"/>
					
					servile impostors, they receive not only within their
					<q direct="unspecified">houses barred,</q> but even within their secret emotions and
					concerns. The more simple-minded of such flatterers does not think it
					necessary or proper that he be taken into consultation regarding matters of
					this sort, but only that he be a ministrant and servant; whereas the more
					unscrupulous will do no more than to join in the deliberation, contracting
					his brows, and looking his assent, but says not a word. However, if the
					other man states his view, then he says, <q direct="unspecified">Gad, but you got a bit
						ahead of me ; I was just going to say that very thing.</q> Now the
					mathematicians tell us that surfaces and lines do not bend or extend or move
					of themselves, being imaginary conceptions without material substance, but
					that they bend and extend and change their position along with the bodies of
					which they are the boundaries : so, too, you shall detect the flatterer by
					his being always in agreement with his victim in words and expressions,
					—yes, in pleasures and in angry passions too—so that in these matters, at
					least, the difference is quite easy to detect. Still more is this evident in
					the manner of his ministrations. For a gracious act on the part of a friend
					is like a living thing : it has its most potent qualities deep within it,
					and there is nothing on the surface to suggest show or display ; but, as a
					physician cures without his patient's knowledge, so oftentimes a friend does
					a good turn by interceding or by settling, while the object of his
					solicitude knows nothing of it. Such a friend was Arcesilaus in all his
					dealings, and this was especially seen of him when he discovered the poverty
					of Apelles of Chios, who was ill; for on his next visit he came with twenty
					shillings, and taking a seat by the bed,
					
					<pb id="v1.p.339"/>
					remarked,
					<q direct="unspecified">There is nothing here but Empedocles' elements, <quote rend="blockquote">Fire and water
						and earth and the gentle heights of ether.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From a much longer quotation; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, I. 230, i. 18.</note>
                  </quote> But you are not even lying
						at ease.</q> And with that he re-arranged his pillow, and,
					unobserved, slipped the money underneath. When the aged servingwoman
					discovered it, and in amazement announced her discovery to Apelles, he said
					with a laugh, <q direct="unspecified">Arcesilaus contrived that fraud !</q> Moreover,
					the saying that <q direct="unspecified">children are born like their parents</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 235.</note>
					holds true in the field of philosophy. At any rate, Lacydes, the associate
					of Arcesilaus, stood by Cephisocrates, as did his other friends, when he was
					impeached ; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The facts are not otherwise known.</note> and when the prosecutor demanded his ring, Cephisocrates
					quietly let it fall beside him, and Lacydes, perceiving this, put his foot
					on it and concealed it; for the tell-tale evidence was in the ring. After
					the verdict, Cephisocrates was shaking hands with the jurors, when one of
					them, who apparently had seen what happened, bade him thank Lacydes, and
					related the whole affair ; but Lacydes had told it to nobody. So, too, I
					imagine the gods confer their benefits, for the most part, without our
					knowledge, since it is their nature to take pleasure in the mere act of
					being gracious and doing good. But the flatterer's activity shows no sign of
					honesty, truth, straightforwardness, or generosity, but only sweating and
					clamour and running to and fro, and a strained look that gives the
					appearance and suggestion of onerous and urgent business. It is like an
					extravagantly wrought picture, which by means of gaudy pigments, irregular
					folds in the garments, 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.341"/>
					
					wrinkles, and sharp angles, strives to produce an
					impression of vividness. He is offensive, too, as he relates how he has had
					to go hither and thither on the business, how he has worried over it, and
					then, as he tells of all the enmity he has incurred, and then of his
					countless troubles and great tribulations ; and, as a result, he gets a
					declaration that it was not worth all that. For any favour that evokes a
					reproach from its recipient is offensive, disfavoured, intolerable; and in
					the flatterer's favours there is this reproach and mortification, which is
					felt, not at some later time, but at the very time when they are performed.
					But if a friend has to tell what he has done, he reports it modestly and
					says nothing about himself. It was in this spirit that the Lacedaemonians
					sent corn to the people of Smyrna in their need, and when these expressed
					their admiration of the gracious action, the Lacedaemonians said, <q direct="unspecified">It
						was nothing of any importance ; we merely voted that we and our cattle
						go without dinner for one day, and collected the amount.</q> Such
					graciousness is not only the mark of a generous spirit, but it is pleasanter
					for the recipients, since they feel that those who assist them suffer no
					great damage. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>It is not therefore by the flatterer's offensiveness in his ministrations, or
					by his facile way of offering his services, that one can best learn to know
					his nature, but a better distinction may be found in the nature of his
					service, whether it is honourable or dishonourable, and whether its purpose
					is to give pleasure or help. For a friend will not, as Gorgias was wont to
					declare, expect his friend to support him in honest projects, and yet
					himself serve the other in many also that are dishonest, for he
					
					<pb id="v1.p.343"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">In virtue joins, and not in viciousness.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Iphigenia at Aulis</hi>, 407.</note>
               </quote> Much rather,
					therefore, will he try to turn his friend aside from what is unbecoming ;
					and if he cannot persuade him, then he may well retort with Phocion's remark
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Again referred to by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 142 B, 188 F; <hi rend="italics">Life of Phocion</hi>, chap. xxx. (755 B); and <hi rend="italics">Life of Agis</hi>, chap. ii. (795 E).</note> to Antipater : <q direct="unspecified">You cannot use me as both friend and
						flatterer,</q> that is as a friend and not a friend. For one should
					assist a friend in doing, not in misdoing, in advising, not in ill-devising,
					in supporting his conclusions, not his delusions, in sharing his mishaps,
					not his misdeeds. No, we would choose not even to have knowledge of our
					friends' dishonourable actions ; how then can we possibly choose to
					cooperate in them and to share in the unseemly conduct ? As the
					Lacedaemonians, defeated in battle by Antipater, in making terms of peace
					bade him prescribe any penalty he would, but nothing dishonourable, so a
					friend, if need befall for his services that involves expense, danger, or
					labour, is foremost in insisting, without excuse or hesitation, that he be
					called upon and that he do his share, but wherever disgrace goes with it, he
					is also foremost in begging to be left alone and spared from participation.
					But flattery, on the contrary, in arduous and dangerous ministrations fails
					you, and if you test it by sounding, it does not ring clear, but has an
					ignoble tone jangling with some excuse; but for any shameful, mean, or
					disreputable service you may use the flatterer as you will, and treat him as
					the dirt beneath your feet; and he thinks it nothing dreadful or insulting.
					You must have noticed the ape. He cannot guard the house like the dog, nor
					carry a load like the horse, 
					
					<pb id="v1.p.345"/>
					
					nor plough the land like oxen ; and so he has to bear
					abuse and scurrility, and endure practical jokes, thus submitting to be made
					an instrument of laughter. So also with the flatterer : unable to help
					another with words or money or to back him in a quarrel, and unequal to
					anything laborious or serious, yet he makes no excuses when it comes to
					underhand actions, he is a faithful helper in a love-affair, he knows
					exactly the price to be paid for a prostitute, he is not careless in
					checking up the charge for a wine supper, nor slow in making arrangements
					for dinners, he tries to be in the good graces of mistresses; but if bidden
					to be impudent toward a wife's relatives or to help in hustling a wife out
					of doors he is relentless and unabashed. As a result the man is not hard to
					detect in this way, either ; for if he is told to do any disreputable and
					dishonourable thing that you will, he is ready to be prodigal of himself in
					trying to gratify the man who tells him to do it. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>The great difference between flatterer and friend may be most clearly
					perceived by his disposition towards one's other friends. For a friend finds
					it most pleasant to love and be loved along with many others, and he is
					always constant in his endeavours that his friend shall have many friends <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch has devoted a separate essay (<hi rend="italics">De amicorum multitudine</hi>) to this subject (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 93 B-79 B).</note>
					and be much honoured ; believing that <q direct="unspecified">friends own everything in
						common</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Orestes</hi>, 735.</note> he thinks that no possession ought to be held so much
					in common as friends. But the flatterer is false, spurious, and debased,
					inasmuch as he fully understands that he is committing a crime against
					friendship, which in his hands becomes a counterfeit coin as it were. While
					he is by nature jealous, yet he employs his jealousy against his own kind,
					striving constantly to outdo them in scurrility
					
					<pb id="v1.p.347"/>
					and idle
					gossip, but he stands in awesome dread of his betters, not indeed because he
					is <quote rend="blockquote">Trudging afoot beside a Lydian chariot,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Pindar, according to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Nicias</hi>, chap. i. (523 B). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> i. 469 (<hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 206).</note>
               </quote> but because, as Simonides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. 417 (<hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 64) has adopted an amended reading.</note> puts
					it, he <quote rend="blockquote">Hath not even lead to show 'Gainst gold refined and unalloyed.</quote>
					Whenever, then, the flatterer, who is but a light and deceptive plated-ware,
					is examined and closely compared with genuine and solid-wrought friendship,
					he does not stand the test, but he is exposed, and so he does the same thing
					as the man who had painted a wretched picture of some cocks. For the painter
					bade his servant scare all real cocks as far away as possible from the
					canvas ; and so the flatterer scares all real friends away, and does not
					allow them to come near ; or if he cannot accomplish this, he openly cringes
					to them, pays them attentions, and makes a great show of respect for them as
					for superiors, but secretly he is suggesting and spreading some sort of
					calumny ; and when secret talk has caused an irritating sore, even though he
					be not entirely successful at the outset, yet he remembers and observes the
					precept of Medius. This Medius was, if I may call him so, leader and skilled
					master of the choir of flatterers that danced attendance on Alexander, and
					were banded together against all good men. Now he urged them not to be
					afraid to assail and sting with their calumnies, pointing out that, even if
					the man who is stung succeeds in healing the wound, the scar of the calumny
					will still remain. In fact it was by such scars, or rather such gangrenes
					
					<pb id="v1.p.349"/>
					and cancers, that Alexander was consumed so that he
					destroyed Callisthenes, Parmenio, and Philotas, and put himself without
					reserve into the hands of men like Hagno, Bagoas, Agesias, and Demetrius, to
					be brought low, by submitting to be worshipped, bedecked and fantastically
					tricked out by them, after the manner of a barbaric idol. So great is the
					power wielded by giving gratification, and it is greatest, apparently, with
					those who seem to be the greatest personages. For self-conceit regarding the
					noblest qualities, coupled with the wish to have them, gives both confidence
					and boldness to the flatterer.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the first chapter of the essay, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 49 A.</note> It is true that lofty places are difficult
					of approach and access for those who propose to capture them, but loftiness
					or conceit, in a mind which lacks sense because of the favours of Fortune or
					Nature, lies at the mercy of the insignificant and mean. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Wherefore I now urge, as I did at the beginning of this treatise, that we
					eradicate from ourselves self-love and conceit. For these, by flattering us
					beforehand, render us less resistant to flatterers from without, since we
					are quite ready to receive them. But if, in obedience to the god, we learn
					that the precept, <q direct="unspecified">Know thyself,</q> is invaluable to each of us,
					and if at the same time we carefully review our own nature and upbringing
					and education, how in countless ways they fall short of true excellence, and
					have inseparably connected with them many a sad and heedless fault of word,
					deed, and feeling, we shall not very readily let the flatterers walk over
					us. Now Alexander <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xxii. (677 B) and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 717 B.</note> said that two things moved him to discredit those who
					proclaimed him a god, his sleeping and his passion for women, evidently
					feeling that
					<pb id="v1.p.351"/>
					in these matters he revealed the more
					ignoble and susceptible side of himself; and so in our own case, if we are
					careful to observe many and many a fault of our own, shameful and grievous,
					both of omission and commission, we shall constantly be detecting our own
					need, not of a friend to commend and extol us, but of a friend to take us to
					task, to be frank with us, and indeed to blame us when our conduct is bad.
					For there are but few among many who have the courage to show frankness
					rather than favour to their friends. And again, among those few you cannot
					easily find men who know how to do this, but rather you shall find those who
					think that if they abuse and find fault they use frankness. Yet frankness,
					like any other medicine, if it be not applied at the proper time, does but
					cause useless suffering and disturbance, and it accomplishes, one may say,
					painfully what flattery accomplishes pleasantly. For people are injured, not
					only by untimely praise, but by untimely blame as well; and it is this
					especially that delivers them over, broadside on, to the flatterers, an easy
					prey, since like water they glide away from the steeps that repel toward the
					valleys that softly invite. Frankness, therefore, should be combined with
					good manners, and there should be reason in it to take away its excess and
					intensity, which may be compared to that of light, so that any who are
					exposed to it shall not, for being disturbed and distressed by those who
					find fault with everything and accuse every one, take refuge in the shadow
					of the flatterer, and turn away towards what does not cause pain. Now every
					form of vice, my dear Philopappus, is to be avoided through virtue, and not
					through the vice that is its antithesis,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethics</hi>, ii. 7, and Horace, <hi rend="italics">Satires</hi>, i. 2. 24.</note> as some people, for
					
					<pb id="v1.p.353"/>
					instance, think to escape bashfulness through
					shamelessness, rusticity through scurrility, and to make their manner to be
					farthest removed from cowardice and softness if they can make themselves
					seem nearest to impudence and boldness. Others again, to prove themselves
					free from superstition, adopt atheism, and play the knave to show that they
					are not fools, and thus distort their character, like a piece of wood, from
					one form of crookedness to its opposite, because they do not know how to
					straighten it. But the most shameful way of disavowing the name of flatterer
					is to cause pain without profit; and it shows an utterly rude and tactless
					disregard of goodwill in one's relations with friends to resort to being
					disagreeable and harsh in order to avoid abasement and servility in
					friendship. Such a person is like a freedman of the comic stage, who thinks
					that abuse is a fair use of equal speech. Since, therefore, it is a shameful
					thing to fall into flattery in aiming to please, and a shameful thing also,
					in trying to avoid flattery, to destroy the friendly thoughtfulness for
					another by immoderate liberty of speech, we ought to keep ourselves from
					both the one and the other extreme, and in frankness, as in anything else,
					achieve the right from the mean. The subject itself requiring, as it does,
					consequent elaboration, seems to determine that this be the final complement
					of our work. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Seeing, therefore, that there are certain fatal faults attending upon
					frankness, let us in the first place divest it of all self-regard by
					exercising all vigilance lest we seem to have some private reason for our
					reproaches, such as a personal wrong or grievance. For people are wont to
					think that anger, not goodwill, is the motive of a man who
					
					<pb id="v1.p.355"/>
					speaks on his own behalf, and that this is not admonition but
					fault-finding. For frankness is friendly and noble, but fault-finding is
					selfish and mean. For this reason those who speak frankly are respected and
					admired, while fault-finders meet with recrimination and contempt.
					Agamemnon, for instance, has no patience with Achilles, who appears to have
					spoken with moderate frankness only, but when Odysseus assails him bitterly
					and says, <quote rend="blockquote">Hopeless and helpless ! Would you had to rule some other Paltry
						band, not this,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiv. 84.</note>
               </quote> he yields and puts up with it, quieted by the friendly
					concern and good sense of the other's words. For Odysseus, who had no ground
					for anger personally, spoke boldly to him in behalf of Greece, while
					Achilles seemed to be incensed chiefly on his own account. And it is true
					that Achilles himself, although he was <q direct="unspecified">not a man of sweet or gentle
						temper,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xx. 467.</note> but a <quote rend="blockquote">Terrible man, who is given to blaming even the
							blameless,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A verse made by combining words contained in Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 653-4 and xiii. 775.</note>
               </quote> submitted himself to Patroclus in silence, although Patroclus
					often launched upon him strictures like this : <quote rend="blockquote">Ruthless man, your sire was
						not the knightly Peleus, Nor was Thetis your mother ; no, the grey-gleaming
						ocean Bore you, and high rugged rocks, you are so hard-hearted.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 33.</note>
               </quote> The orator
					Hypereides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Phocion</hi>, chap. x. (746 D).</note> used to tell the Athenians that it was only right that they
					consider, not merely whether he was bitter, but whether he was so upon no
					cause ; and in the same way, the admonition of 
					<pb id="v1.p.357"/>
					
					a thing to be treated with respect and reverence, not to
					be faced out. And if one also makes it clear that in speaking frankly he is
					leaving out of all account or consideration his friend's lapses toward
					himself, but taking him to task for certain other shortcomings, and that it
					is in the interest of other persons that he visits him with stinging reproof
					so unsparingly, the force of such frankness is irresistible, and the
					generous attitude of the speaker serves only to intensify the bitterness and
					severity of his admonition. Therefore, while it has been well said that when
					we are angry or at variance with friends, we ought then most of all to be
					doing or planning what will be for their advantage or interest, yet it is no
					less material in friendship, when we feel that we ourselves are slighted and
					neglected, to speak frankly in behalf of others who are likewise being
					neglected, and to remind our friends of them. For example, Plato, in the
					midst of suspicions and disagreements with Dionysius, asked him for an
					appointment for an interview, and Dionysius granted it, supposing that Plato
					had some long tale of fault-finding to rehearse on his own account. But
					Plato talked with him somewhat after this fashion : <q direct="unspecified">If you should
						learn, Dionysius, that some ill-disposed man had made the voyage to
						Sicily, cherishing the desire to do you harm, but unable to find an
						opportunity, would you allow him to sail away, and should you let him
						withdraw unscathed ?</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Far from it, Plato,</q> said Dionysius, <q direct="unspecified">for not only the
						acts of enemies but their intentions as well must be detested and
						punished.</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">If now,</q> said Plato, <q direct="unspecified">somebody has come hither out of
						goodwill to you, wishing to be the author of some good to you, but you
						give him no
							
							<pb id="v1.p.359"/>
							
							opportunity, is it proper to let such a
							man go without showing him any gratitude or attention ?</q> When
					Dionysius asked who the man was, <q direct="unspecified">Aeschines,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">
						in character as fair as any one of Socrates' companions, and potent in
						speech to improve those with whom he may associate ; but after sailing
						hither over a vast expanse of the sea in order to discuss philosophy
						with you, he finds himself neglected.</q> These words so moved
					Dionysius, that he straightway embraced Plato affectionately, marvelling at
					his kindliness and high-mindedness, and afterwards he paid to Aeschines
					honourable and distinguished attentions. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>In the second place, then, let us purge away, as it were, and eliminate from
					our frankness all arrogance, ridicule, scoffing, and scurrility, which are
					the unwholesome seasoning of free speech. Just as a certain orderliness and
					neatness should pervade the work of a surgeon when he performs an operation,
					but his hand should forbear all dancing and reckless motions, all flourishes
					and superfluity of gesticulation, so frankness has plenty of room for tact
					and urbanity, if such graciousness does not impair the high office of
					frankness ; but when effrontery and offensiveness and arrogance are coupled
					with it, they spoil and ruin it completely. There was point, therefore, and
					polish in the retort with which the harper <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 179 B, 334 D, and 634 D.</note> stopped Philip's mouth when
					Philip attempted to argue with him about playing upon his instrument.
					<q direct="unspecified">God forbid,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">that your Majesty should
						ever fall so low as to have a better knowledge of these matters than
						I.</q> But Epicharmus was not right in his retort upon Hiero, who
					had made away with some of his intimate friends, and then a few days later
					invited
					<pb id="v1.p.361"/>
					
					Epicharmus to dinner. <q direct="unspecified">But the other
						day,</q> said Epicharmus, <q direct="unspecified">you held a sacrifice without
							invitation, of friends !</q> As badly answered Antiphon, when the
					question was up for discussion in the presence of Dionysius as to <q direct="unspecified">
						what is the best kind of bronze,</q> and he said, <q direct="unspecified">The kind
							from which they fashioned the statues of Harmodius and Aristogeiton <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The traditional <q direct="unspecified">tyrannicides</q> of Athens.</note> at
							Athens.</q> For the offensiveness and bitterness of such retorts
					profits nothing, their scurrility and frivolity gives no pleasure ; but a
					retort of this kind betokens intemperance of the tongue combined with malice
					and arrogance, and not without enmity. By employing it men eventually bring
					about their own destruction, since they are simply <q direct="unspecified">dancing on the
						edge of the pit.</q> For Antiphon was put to death by order of
					Dionysius, and Timagenes lost his place in Caesar's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Caesar Augustus.</note> friendship because,
					while he never indulged in any high-minded utterance, yet in social
					gatherings and in discussions, for no serious purpose at all, but <quote rend="blockquote">Whatsoever
						he thought would move the Argives to laughter,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 215.</note>
               </quote> he would on every possible
					occasion put forward friendship's cause as an artful excuse for railing. It
					is true that the comic poets <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, for example, as in the <hi rend="italics">Frogs</hi> 686 ff.</note> addressed to their audiences many stern
					rebukes of value to the citizens ; but the admixture of drollery and
					scurrility in them, like a vile dressing with food, made their frankness
					ineffective and useless, so that there was nothing left for the authors but
					a name of malice and coarseness, and no profit for the hearers from their
					words. On other occasions jest and laughter may well enough be employed with
					friends, but frankness of speech ought to have seriousness and
					
					<pb id="v1.p.363"/>
					
					character. And if it concern matters of greater moment,
					let feeling be so evident, the countenance so serious, and the voice so
					earnest that the words may claim credence and touch the heart. Failure to
					observe the proper occasion is in any case exceedingly harmful, but
					particularly when frankness is concerned it destroys its profitableness.
					That in the midst of wine and hard drinking we must be on our guard against
					anything of this sort is plain enough. It is like overcasting fair weather
					with a storm-cloud, when in the midst of jesting and merrymaking someone
					starts a discussion that makes others frown and sets the face in rigid
					lines, as though the topic were meant to combat the god of Relaxation who
					<q direct="unspecified">relaxes the bond of troubled cares,</q> as Pindar <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> i. 480 (<hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 248). Lyaeus, an epithet of Bacchus, Plutarch assumes to be derived from <foreign lang="greek">lu/ein</foreign>, to loose.</note> puts it.
					This neglect of occasion contains a great danger also. For men's minds are
					perilously inclined to anger on account of the wine, and oftentimes heavy
					drinking takes control of their frankness and creates enmity. And in
					general, it does not show a noble or stout heart, but unmanliness rather,
					for one who never displays boldness of speech when he is sober to be bold at
					table, as is the way of cowardly curs. There is no need, then, to multiply
					words on this subject. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Now we observe that many people have neither the assurance nor the courage to
					school their friends when these are prospering, but on the contrary feel
					that good fortune is altogether inaccessible and impregnable to admonition,
					whereas, when one of their friends has fallen and come to grief, they assail
					him and trample upon him now he is reduced to a subordinate and humble
					position, letting loose upon him a flood of frank speech, like a stream
					which has been held in unnatural restraint, and they find a welcome
					
					<pb id="v1.p.365"/>
					pleasure in the change because of their friend's former
					disdain and their own weakness ; it would therefore be well to discuss this
					matter also, and to make a reply to Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Orestes</hi>, 667.</note> when he says, <quote rend="blockquote">When Heaven
						grants us luck, what need of friends ?</quote> The reply is, that in good fortune
					men have most need of friends to speak frankly and reduce their excess of
					pride. For there are few persons who in good fortune have still a sober mind
					; most have need of discretion and reason to be put into them from without,
					which shall repress them when they are puffed up and unsettled with the
					favours of fortune. But when the Heavenly power casts them down and strips
					off their importance, there is in these calamities alone admonition enough
					to work repentance. Wherefore at such a time there is no use for a friend's
					frankness or for words charged with grave and stinging reproof; but in such
					reversals truly <quote rend="blockquote">'Tis sweet to gaze into a kind man's eyes,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Ion</hi>, 732.</note>
               </quote> when he offers
					consolation and encouragement. And this was true of Clearchus, the sight of
					whose face, Xenophon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 6. 11.</note> says, so kindly and benevolent in the midst of <q direct="unspecified">
						battles and perils,</q> strengthened the confidence of the men in
					the face of danger. But he who applies frankness of speech and stinging
					reproof to a person in misfortune, might as well apply some stimulant of
					vision to a disordered and inflamed eye ; he effects no cure nor any
					abatement of the pain, but only adds irritation to the painfulness, and
					exasperates the sufferer. Thus no man in good health, for instance, is at
					all harsh or ferocious against a friend who blames him for yielding to women
					and wine, or for being lazy and neglecting to take exercise, or for
					indulging perpetually in baths or
					<pb id="v1.p.367"/>
					
					unseasonable
					gourmandise. But for a man who is sick it is intolerable, nay, an
					aggravation of the sickness, to be told, <q direct="unspecified">See what comes of your
						intemperance, your soft living, your gluttony and wenching.</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Heavens, man, what a time to talk of that! I am writing my will, the
						doctors are preparing for me a dose of castor or scammony, and you
						admonish and lecture me!</q> Under such conditions, then, the very
					circumstances in which the unfortunate find themselves leave no room for
					frank speaking and sententious saws, but they do require gentle usage and
					help. When children fall down, the nurses do not rush up to them to berate
					them, but they take them up, wash them, and straighten their clothes, and,
					after all this is done, they then rebuke and punish them. It is said that
					when Demetrius of Phalerum had been banished from his native land and was
					living in obscurity and humble station near Thebes, he was not well pleased
					to see Crates approaching, anticipating some cynical frankness and harsh
					language. But Crates met him with all gentleness, and conversed with him
					concerning the subject of banishment, how there was nothing bad in it, nor
					any good cause to feel distress, since thus he was set free from a hazardous
					and insecure office ; at the same time he urged him not to be discouraged
					over himself and his present condition. Whereupon Demetrius, becoming more
					cheerful and once more taking heart, said to his friends, <q direct="unspecified">What a
						pity that those activities and occupations of mine have kept me from
						knowing a man like this !</q> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">The kindly words of friends for one
							in grief And admonitions when one plays the fool. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 962. Again cited by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 102 B.</note>
               </quote>
					          <pb id="v1.p.369"/>
					
					This
					is the way of noble friends, but the ignoble and degraded flatterers of the
					fortunate are <q direct="unspecified">like the old fractures and sprains,</q> which, as
					Demosthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">De corona</hi>, 198.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">are stirred afresh whenever the body suffers some
						ill,</q> and so these persons have a clinging fondness for reverses,
					as though they were pleased with them and derived enjoyment from them. For
					if a man really needs a reminder where he has come to grief through
					following his own ill-advised counsel, sufficient are the words : <quote rend="blockquote">Never did
						I approve the act; indeed I often Spoke against it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 108.</note>
               </quote> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>In what circumstances, then, should a friend be severe, and when should he be
					emphatic in using frank speech ? It is when occasions demand of him that he
					check the headlong course of pleasure or of anger or of arrogance, or that
					he abate avarice or curb inconsiderate heedlessness. Such was the frankness
					of Solon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, i. 30-32; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, xx. 94 D.</note> towards Croesus, who was spoiled and pampered by fickle fortune,
					when he bade him look to the end. In such manner Socrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 215 E.</note> tried to keep
					Alcibiades in check, and drew an honest tear from his eyes by exposing his
					faults, and so turned his heart. Of such sort was the conduct of Cyrus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, v. 5. 5 ff.</note>
					towards Cyaxares, and of Plato toward Dion at the time when the latter was
					at the height of his splendour and was drawing the eyes of all mankind upon
					himself through the beauty and magnificence of his works, when Plato
					exhorted him to be on his guard against <q direct="unspecified">arbitrary self-will</q>
					and to fear it, <q direct="unspecified">since it is companion to solitude.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Letters</hi>, iv. 321 C. Again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Dion</hi>, chap. viii. (961 C); chap. liii. (981 B); and <hi rend="italics">Life of Coriolanus</hi>, chap. xv. (220 D); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also 220 D.</note>
					Speusippus also 
					<pb id="v1.p.371"/>
					
					wrote to Dion <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diogenes Laertius, iv. 5, also records that Speusipus wrote letters to Dion.</note> not to feel proud if there was much talk
					of him among children and light-minded women, but to see to it that by
					adorning Sicily with holiness, justice, and the best of laws, he should
					<q direct="unspecified">bring name and fame</q> to the Academy. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 1742.</note> But, on the other
					hand, Euctus and Eulaeus, companions of Perseus, while his good fortune
					lasted always behaved so as to please him, and complied with his humour, and
					like all the rest they followed where he led ; but when, after his
					disastrous encounter with the Romans <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Under Lucius Aemilius Paullus (168 B.C.).</note> at Pydna, he took to flight, these
					men beset him with bitter reproaches, and continually reminded him of his
					errors and omissions, reviling him for everything he had done, until the
					man, smarting with grief and anger, stabbed them with his dagger and made an
					end of both of them. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Let thus much, then, serve to define the proper occasion in general. But the
					friend who is concerned for his friends must not let slip the occasions
					which they themselves often present, but he should turn these to account.
					For sometimes a question, the telling of a story, blame or commendation of
					like things in other people, may serve as an opening for frank speech. For
					example, Demaratus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 179 C, Plutarch records the successful result of Demaratus's frankness with Philip.</note> is said to have come to Macedonia during the time when
					Philip was at odds with his wife and son. Philip, after greeting him,
					inquired how well the Greeks were at harmony together ; and Demaratus, who
					knew him well and wished him well, said, <q direct="unspecified">A glorious thing for you,
						Philip, to be inquiring about the concord of Athenians and
						Peloponnesians, while you let your own household be full of all this
						quarrelling 
						<pb id="v1.p.373"/>
						
						and dissension!</q> Excellent, too, was the
					retort of Diogenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 606 B.</note> on the occasion when he had entered Philip's camp and
					was brought before Philip himself, at the time when Philip was on his way to
					fight the Greeks. Not knowing who Diogenes was, Philip asked him if he were
					a spy. <q direct="unspecified">Yes, indeed, Philip,</q> he replied, <q direct="unspecified">I am here to
						spy upon your ill-advised folly, because of which you, without any
						compelling reason, are on your way to hazard a kingdom and your life on
						the outcome of a single hour.</q> This perhaps was rather severe.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>But another opportunity for admonition arises when people, having been
					reviled by others for their errors, have become submissive and downcast. The
					tactful man will make an adept use of this, by rebuffing and dispersing the
					revilers, and by taking hold of his friend in private and reminding him
					that, if there is no other reason for his being circumspect, he should at
					least try to keep his enemies from being bold. <q direct="unspecified">For where have these
						fellows a chance to open their mouths, or what can they say against you,
						if you put away and cast from you all that which gets you a bad name ?
					</q> In this way he who reviles is charged with hurting, and he who
					admonishes is credited with helping. But some persons manage more cleverly,
					and by finding fault with strangers, turn their own intimate acquaintances
					to repentance ; for they accuse the others of what they know their own
					acquaintances are doing. My professor, Ammonius, at an afternoon lecture
					perceived that some of his students had eaten a luncheon that was anything
					but frugal, and so he ordered his freedman to chastise his own servant,
					remarking by way of explanation that <q direct="unspecified">that boy
						
						<pb id="v1.p.375"/>
						
						can't lunch without his wine !</q> At the same time he glanced
					towards us, so that the rebuke took hold of the guilty. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>One other point: we must be very careful about the use of frank speech toward
					a friend before a large company, bearing in mind the incident in which Plato
					was involved. It so happened that Socrates had handled one of his
					acquaintances rather severely in a conversation which took place close by
					the money-changers', whereupon Plato said, <q direct="unspecified">Were it not better that
						this had been said in private ?</q> Socrates retorted, <q direct="unspecified">
							Should you not have done better if you had addressed your remark to me
							in private ?</q> And again, when Pythagoras once assailed a devoted
					pupil pretty roughly in the presence of several persons, the youth, as the
					story goes, hanged himself, and from that time on Pythagoras never
					admonished anybody when anyone else was present. For error should be treated
					as a foul disease, and all admonition and disclosure should be in secret,
					with nothing of show or display in it to attract a crowd of witnesses and
					spectators. For it is not like friendship, but sophistry, to seek for glory
					in other men's faults, and to make a fair show before the spectators, like
					the physicians who perform operations in the theatres with an eye to
					attracting patients. Quite apart from the affront involved—which ought never
					to be allowed in any corrective treatment— some regard must be paid to the
					contentiousness and self-will that belong to vice ; for it is not enough to
					say, as Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Stheneboea; cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Eurip.</hi> No. 665.</note> has it, that <quote rend="blockquote">Love reproved More urgent grows,</quote> but if
					admonition be offered in public, and unsparingly,
					<pb id="v1.p.377"/>
					
					it
					only confirms each and every morbid emotion in its shamelessness. Hence,
					just as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 729 C. Also cited or referred to by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 14 B, 144 F, 272 C.</note> insists that elderly men who are trying to cultivate a sense
					of respect among the young, must themselves, first of all, show respect for
					the young, so among friends a modest frankness best engenders modesty, and a
					cautious quiet approach and treatment of the erring one saps the foundations
					of his vice and annihilates it, since it gradually becomes imbued with
					consideration for the consideration shown to it. It follows, then, that the
					best way is to <quote rend="blockquote">Hold one's head quite close, that the others may not hear
						it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> i. 157.</note>
               </quote> And least of all is it decent to expose a husband in the hearing of his
					wife, and a father in the sight of his children, and a lover in the presence
					of his beloved, or a teacher in the presence of his students : for such
					persons are driven almost insane with grief and anger at being taken to task
					before those with whom they feel it is necessary to stand well. I imagine
					also that it was not so much the wine that caused Cleitus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is told in detail by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chaps. l., li. (693 C).</note> to be so
					exasperating to Alexander, as that he gave the impression of trying to curb
					him before a large company. And Aristomenes, Ptolemy's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ptolemy V. Epiphanes (205-181 B.C.); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Polybius, xv. 31.</note> tutor, because he
					gave Ptolemy a slap to wake him up, as he was nodding while an embassy was
					present, thereby afforded a hold to the flatterers, who affected to be
					indignant on the king's behalf, and said, <q direct="unspecified">If with all your fatiguing
						duties and great lack of sleep you dropped off, we ought to admonish you
						in private, not to lay hands on you before so many people</q> ; and
					Ptolemy sent a goblet of poison with orders that
					
					<pb id="v1.p.379"/>
					
					
					
					the man should drink it off. So, too, Aristophanes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Acharnians</hi>, 503; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also lines 378 ff. and the scholium on 378.</note>
					says that Cleon accused him because
					<quote rend="blockquote">With strangers present he reviles the State,</quote>
					thus trying to exasperate the Athenians against
					him. This blunder, therefore, along with the others,
					must be guarded against by those who desire, not
					to show off, or to win popularity, but to employ
					frank speaking in a way that is beneficial and
					salutary. In feet, persons that use frank speaking
					ought to be able to say what Thucydides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">i. 70.</note> represents
					the Corinthians as saying about themselves, that
					they <q direct="unspecified">have a good right to reprove others</q>—which
					is not a bad way of putting it. For as Lysander,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. xxii. (445 D). The story is repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 E and 229 C. A similar remark is attributed to Agesilaus in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 212 E.</note>
					we are told, said to the man from Megara, who in
					the council of the allies was making bold to speak
					for Greece, that <q direct="unspecified">his words needed a country to
						back them</q> ; so it may well be that every man's
					frank speaking needs to be backed by character, but
					this is especially true in the case of those who
					admonish others and try to bring them to their
					sober senses. Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 491 F.</note> at any rate used to say that
					he admonished Speusippus by his life, as, to be sure,
					the mere sight of Xenocrates in the lecture-room, and
					a glance from him, converted Polemon and made
					him a changed man. But the speech of a man
					light-minded and mean in character, when it undertakes to deal in frankness, results only in evoking
					the retort:
				
					
					<pb id="v1.p.381"/>
					
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Wouldst thou heal others, full of sores thyself!<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Eurip.</hi> No. 1086; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 88 D, 481 E, 1110 E.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>Since, however, circumstances oftentimes impel
					men that are none too good themselves to use
					admonition when in the company of others who are
					no better than they, the most reasonable method
					would be that which in some way involves and
					includes in the arraignment the speaker himself.
					This is the principle of the reproof <quote rend="blockquote">Son of Tydeus, what has made us forget our swift prowess ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 313; quoted with additional lines, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 30 E.</note>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">We are no match now even for Hector
						Who is only one man.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> viii. 234.</note>
               </quote>
					And in this way Socrates quietly took the young men
					to task, not assuming that he himself was exempted
					from ignorance, but feeling that he had need as well
					as they to study virtue and to search for truth. For
					those win goodwill and confidence who give the impression that, while addicted to the same faults, they
					are correcting their friends precisely as they correct
					themselves. But the man who gives himself airs in
					trying to curb another as though he himself were
					some pure and passionless being, unless he be well
					on in years or possessed of an acknowledged position
					in virtue and repute, only appears annoying and
					tedious, and profits nothing. Therefore it was not
					without a purpose that Phoenix interjected the
					account of his own misfortunes, his attempt in a fit
					of anger to slay his father, and his sudden change of
					heart,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lest I be known among the Greeks as my father's slayer<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ix. 461. See the note on 26 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					This he did because he would not seem to admonish
					
					
					<pb id="v1.p.383"/>
					
					
					
					Achilles as though he were unaffected by anger and
					without fault himself. For such things make a
					deep moral impression, and persons are more wont
					to yield to those who seem to have like emotions but
					no feeling of contempt.
					Since a brilliant light must not be brought near to
					an inflamed eye, and a troubled spirit likewise does
					not put up with frank speaking and plain reproof,
					among the most useful helps is a light admixture of
					praise, as in the following:
					<quote rend="blockquote">Not without honour now can you be remiss in swift prowess,
					You who are all the best in our host. No cause for a quarrel
					Have I 'gainst any man who may be remiss in the fighting,
					If he is craven, but with you I am wroth beyond measure,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiii. 116.</note>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Pandarus, where is now your bow and its winged arrows?
						Where your repute which no man among us can rival?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> v. 171.</note>
               </quote>
					Lines like the following also sound a clear summons
					to come back when men are on the verge of giving
					way:
					<quote rend="blockquote">Where's Oedipus and all those riddles famed?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 1688.</note>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Can much-enduring Heracles speak thus?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hercules Furens</hi>, 1250.</note>
               </quote>
					For not only do they mitigate the harsh and
					peremptory tone of the censure, but they also arouse
					in a man a desire to emulate his better self, since he
					is made to feel ashamed of disgraceful conduct by
					being reminded of his honourable actions, and is
					prompted to look upon himself as an example of
					what is better. But whenever we draw comparisons
					with other people, as, for example, with those of a
					man's own age or his fellow-citizens or his kinsmen,
					then the spirit of contentiousness that belongs
					
					<pb id="v1.p.385"/>
					
					
					
					to vice is made sullen and savage, and it will often
					suggest with some temper, <q direct="unspecified">Then why don't you
						go away to my betters, and not trouble me ?</q> One
					must, therefore, in frank speaking toward one set
					of persons be on his guard against commending
					another set, with the single exception, it is true, of
					parents. For example, Agamemnon can say :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Truly Tydeus' son is not much like his father,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> v. 800.</note>
               </quote>
					and so, too, Odysseus in the Scyrians :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Dost thou, to shame the glory of thy race,
						Card wool, whose father was the noblest Greek ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown poet; Nauck; <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 9; quoted with variant reading, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 34 D.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>Least of all is it becoming to reply to admonition with admonition, and to counter frank
					speaking with frank speaking. For this provokes
					instant heat, and causes estrangement, and such
					altercation, as a rule, bewrays, not the man that
					merely rewards frankness with frankness, but the
					man that cannot tolerate frankness. It is better,
					therefore, to bear patiently with a friend who affects
					to offer admonition ; for if later he errs himself, and
					requires admonition, this very fact, in a certain way,
					gives our frank speaking a chance to speak frankly.
					For if he be gently reminded, without any show of
					resentment, that he himself has not been wont to
					overlook the errors of his friends, but to take his
					friends to task and enlighten them, he will be much
					more inclined to yield and accept the correction, as
					being a way to requite a kindly and gracious feeling,
					and not fault-finding or anger.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>Then again, as Thucydides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">ii. 64.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">Whoever
					incurs unpopularity over matters of the highest
					
					
					<pb id="v1.p.387"/>
					
					
					
					importance, shows a right judgement</q>; so it is
					the duty of a friend to accept the odium that comes
					from giving admonition when matters of importance
					and of great concern are at stake. But if he is for
					ever bickering over everything and about everything, and approaches his acquaintance in the manner
					not of a friend but of a schoolmaster, his admonitions
					will lose their edge and effectiveness in matters of
					the highest importance, since, like a physician who
					should dole out his supply of a pungent or bitter
					but necessary and costly medicine by prescribing
					it in a great number of slight cases where it is not
					necessary, he will have used up his supply of frankness
					without result. He will, therefore, be earnestly
					on his guard against continual censoriousness in
					himself; and if another person is apt to search
					narrowly into everything, and keeps up a continual
					comment of petty accusation, this will give him the
					key, as it were, in opening an attack on faults that
					are more important. The physician Philotimus, on
					an occasion, when a man with an ulcerated liver
					showed him his finger with a whitlow on it, said,
					<q direct="unspecified">My friend, you need not concern yourself about
						a sore finger.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Essentially the same story that is told <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 43 B.</note> And so, too, the right occasion
					gives a friend a chance to say to the man whose
					accusations are based on trifles of no real import,
					<q direct="unspecified">Why dwell on playful sports and conviviality and
						nonsense ? Let this man, my friend, but get rid
						of the woman he keeps, or cease gambling, and there
						we have a man in all else admirable.</q> For the man
					who receives indulgence in small matters is not
					unready to grant to his friend the right to speak
					frankly in regard to the greater. But the inveterate
					nagger, everywhere sour and unpleasant, noticing
					
					<pb id="v1.p.389"/>
					
					
					
					everything and officiously making it his concern, is
					not only intolerable to children and brothers, but is
					unendurable even to slaves.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>But since, to quote Euripides,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 528.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">not everything connected with old age is bad,</q> and the same
					thing holds true also of our friends' fatuity, we
					ought to keep close watch upon our friends not only
					when they go wrong but also when they are right,
					and indeed the first step should be commendation
					cheerfully bestowed. Then later, just as steel is
					made compact by cooling, and takes on a temper
					as the result of having first been relaxed and softened
					by heat, so when our friends have become mollified
					and warmed by our commendations we should give
					them an application of frankness like a tempering
					bath. For the right occasion gives us a chance to
					say, <q direct="unspecified">Is this conduct worthy to compare with that ?
						Do you see what fruits honour yields ? This is
						what we your friends demand ; this befits your own
						character; nature intended you for this.</q> But those
					other promptings must be exorcised—
					<quote rend="blockquote">Off to the mountain or else to the surge of the loud-roaring
						ocean.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 347.</note>
               </quote>
					For as a kind-hearted physician would prefer to
					relieve a sick man's ailment by sleep and diet rather
					than by castor and scammony, so a kindly friend, a
					good father, and a teacher, take pleasure in using
					commendation rather than blame for the correction
					of character. For nothing else makes the frank
					person give so little pain and do so much good by his
					words, as to refrain from all show of temper, and to
					approach the erring good-humouredly and with kindliness. For this reason they should not be sharply
					refuted when they make denial, nor prevented from
					
					<pb id="v1.p.391"/>
					
					
					
					defending themselves; but we should in some way
					or other help them to evolve some presentable
					excuses, and, repudiating the worse motive, provide
					one more tolerable ourselves, such as is found in
					Hector's <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 326.</note> words to his brother :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Strange man ! 'Tis not right to nurse this wrath in
						your bosom,</quote>
					as though his withdrawal from the combat were not
					desertion, or cowardice, but only a display of temper.
					And so Nestor <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ix. 109.</note> to Agamemnon :
					<quote rend="blockquote">But you to your high-minded spirit
						Gave way.</quote>
					For a higher moral tone, I think, is assumed in saying
					<q direct="unspecified">You acted unbecomingly</q> rather than <q direct="unspecified">You did
						wrong,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">You were inadvertent</q> rather than
					<q direct="unspecified">You were ignorant,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Don't be contentious
						with your brother</q> rather than <q direct="unspecified">Don't be jealous of
							your brother,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Keep away from the woman
								who is trying to ruin you</q> rather than <q direct="unspecified">Stop trying
									to ruin the woman.</q> Such is the method which
					frankness seeks to take when it would reclaim a
					wrongdoer ; but to stir a man to action it tries the
					opposite method. For example, whenever it either
					becomes necessary to divert persons that are on the
					point of going wrong, or when we would give an
					earnest impulse to those who are trying to make a
					stand against the onset of a violent adverse impulse,
					or who are quite without energy and spirit for what
					is noble, we should turn round and ascribe their
					action to some unnatural or unbecoming motives.
					Thus Odysseus, as Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Dinner-guests</hi> probably; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Soph.</hi> No. 141. See, however, Jebb-Pearson, <hi rend="italics">The Fragments of Sophocles</hi>, ii. p. 205.</note> represents him, in
					trying to rouse the spirit of Achilles, says that
					Achilles is not angry on account of the dinner, but
					
					<pb id="v1.p.393"/>
					
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Already at the sight of builded Troy
						You are afraid.</quote>
					And again when Achilles is exceedingly indignant
					at this, and says that he is for sailing away, Odysseus
					says
					<quote rend="blockquote">I know what 'tis you flee; not ill repute,
						But Hector's near ; it is not good to stay.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Dinner-guests</hi> probably. See note C, p. 390.</note>
               </quote>
					So by alarming the spirited and manly man with an
					imputation of cowardice, the chaste and orderly with
					an imputation of licentiousness, the liberal and lordly
					with an imputation of pettiness and stinginess, they
					give to such persons an impulse toward what is
					noble, and turn them away from what is disgraceful,
					proving themselves moderate in matters beyond
					remedy, and owning more to sorrow and sympathy
					than to blame in their frank speaking ; but in efforts
					to prevent the commission of error and in any
					wrestling with the emotions they are severe, inexorable, and unremitting. For this is the right time
					for a resolute goodwill and genuine frankness.
					Blame for past deeds is a weapon which we see
					enemies using against each other. Whereby is
					confirmed the saying of Diogenes that as a matter
					of self-preservation, a man needs to be supplied with
					good friends or else with ardent enemies ; for the
					former instruct him, and the latter take him to task.
					But it is better to guard against errors by following
					proffered advice than to repent of errors because of
					men's upbraiding. This is the reason why it is
					necessary to treat frankness as a fine art, inasmuch
					as it is the greatest and most potent medicine in
					friendship, always needing, however, all care to hit
					the right occasion, and a tempering with moderation.
					
					<pb id="v1.p.395"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Since, then, as has been said, frankness, from
					its very nature, is oftentimes painful to the person
					to whom it is applied, there is need to follow the
					example of the physicians ; for they, in a surgical
					operation, do not leave the part that has been operated
					upon in its suffering and pain, but treat it with
					soothing lotions and fomentations ; nor do persons
					that use admonition with skill simply apply its
					bitterness and sting, and then run away ; but by
					further converse and gentle words they mollify and
					assuage, even as stone-cutters smooth and polish the
					portions of statues that have been previously
					hammered and chiselled. But the man who has been
					hard hit and scored by frankness, if he be left rough
					and tumid and uneven, will, owing to the effect of
					anger, not readily respond to an appeal the next
					time, or put up with attempts to soothe him. Therefore those who employ admonition should be particularly on their guard in this respect, and not take
					their leave too soon, nor allow anything painful and
					irritating to their acquaintances to form the final
					topic of conversation at an interview.
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>