<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Apophthegmata Laconica</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text n="tlg-0007.082">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.385"/>
         <head>Laconic Apophthegms; or Remarkable Sayings of the Spartans.</head>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agasicles.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agasicles the Spartan king, when one wondered why,
					since he was a great lover of instruction, he would not
					admit Philophanes the Sophist, freely said, I ought to be
					their scholar whose son I am. And to one enquiring how
					a governor should be secure without guards, he replied,
					If he rules his subjects as fathers do their sons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agesilaus the Great.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agesilaus the Great, being once chosen steward of a
					feast, and asked by the butler how much wine he allowed
					every guest, returned: If you have a great deal provided,
					as much as every one calls for; if but a little, give them
					all an equal share. When he saw a malefactor resolutely
					endure his torments, How great a rascal is this fellow, he
					cried out, that uses patience, bravery, and courage, in such
					an impious and dishonest case! To one commending an
					orator for his skill in amplifying petty matters he said, I
					don't think that shoemaker a good workman that makes a
					great shoe for a little foot. When one in discourse said to
					him, Sir, you have assented to such a thing already, and
					repeated it very often, he replied, Yes, if it is right; but
					if not, I said so indeed but never assented. And the other
					rejoining, But, sir, a king is obliged to perform Whatever
					he hath granted by his nod;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. 527</note> No more, he returned, than
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.386"/>
					
					those that petition him are bound to make none but good
					and just requests, and to consider all circumstances of time
					and what befits a king. When he heard any praise or
					censure, he thought it as necessary to enquire into the
					character of those that spake as of those of whom they
					spake. While he was a boy, at a certain solemnity of
					naked dancing, the person that ordered that affair put him
					in a dishonorable place; and he, though already declared
					king, endured it, saying, I'll show that it is not the places
					that grace men, but men the places. To a physician prescribing him a nice and tedious course of physic, he said,
					By Castor and Pollux, unless I am destined to live at any
					rate, I surely shall not if I take all this. Whilst he stood
					by the altar of Minerva Chalcioecus sacrificing an ox, a
					louse bit him. At this he never blushed, but cracked him
					before the whole company, adding these words, By all the
					Gods, it is pleasant to kill a plotter at the very altar. Another time seeing a boy pull a mouse by the tail out of his
					hole, and the mouse turn and bite the boy's fingers and so
					escape; he bade his companions take notice of it, saying,
					If so little a creature will oppose injurious violence, what
					think ye that men ought to do?</p>
            <p>Being eager for war against the Persians to free the
					Asiatic Greeks, he consulted the oracle of Jupiter at Dodona; and that telling him to go on as he designed, he
					brought the answer to the Ephors, upon which they ordered
					him to go to Delphi and put the same question. He went,
					and put it in this form: Apollo, are you of the same mind
					with your father? And the oracle agreeing, he was chosen
					general and the war began. Now Tissaphernes, at first
					being afraid of Agesilaus, came to articles, and agreed that
					the Greek cities should be free and left to their own laws;
					but afterward procuring a great army from the king, he
					declared war against him unless he should presently leave
					Asia. Glad of this treachery of Tissaphernes, he marched
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.387"/>
					
					as if his design was to make an inroad upon Caria; but
					when Tissaphernes had brought his troops thither, he
					turned upon Phrygia, and took a great many cities and
					abundance of rich spoil, saying to his friend: To break one's
					promise is indeed impious; but to outwit an enemy is not
					only just and glorious, but profitable and sweet. Being
					inferior to the enemy in horse, he retreated to Ephesus, and
					ordered all the wealthy to provide each a man and horse,
					which should excuse them from personal service in his
					wars. By which means, in the room of rich cowards, he
					was soon furnished with stout men and able horses; and
					this he said he did in imitation of Agamemnon, who
					agreed for a serviceable mare to discharge a wealthy coward. When he ordered the captives to be sold naked and
					the chapmen came, a thousand bid money for the clothes,
					but all derided the bodies of the men, which were tender
					and white by reason of their delicate breeding, as useless
					and worth nothing. He said to his soldiers, Look, those
					are the things for which ye fight, and these are the things
					with whom ye fight. Having beaten Tissaphernes in Lydia
					and killed many of his men, he wasted the territories of
					the king; and the king sending money and desiring a
					peace, Agesilaus replied: To grant peace is in the power
					only of the commonwealth. I delight to enrich my soldiers
					rather than myself, and think it agreeable to the honor of
					the Greeks not to receive gifts from their enemies but to
					take spoils.</p>
            <p>Megabytes the son of Spithridates, a very pretty boy,
					who thought himself very well beloved, coming to him to
					offer a kiss and an embrace, he turned away his head. But
					when the boy had not appeared a long time, Agesilaus enquired after him; and his friends replied, that it was his
					own fault, since he derided the kiss of the pretty boy, and
					the youth was afraid to come again. Agesilaus, standing
					silent and musing a pretty while, said: Well, I will use no
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.388"/>
					
					persuasions, for methinks I had rather conquer such desires
					than take the most popular city of my enemies; for it is
					better to preserve our own than rob others of their liberty.
					In all things else he was very exact, and a strict observer
					of the law; but in his friends' concerns he thought that to
					be too scrupulous was a bare pretence to cloak unwillingness to use his interest. And agreeable to this, there is
					extant a small note of his, interceding for a friend to one
					Idrieus a Carian: If Nicias is not guilty, discharge him;
					if he is, discharge him for my sake; but by all means pray
					let him be discharged. This was his usual humor in his
					friends' concerns, yet sometimes profit and convenience was
					preferred; for once breaking up his camp in disorder, and
					leaving one that he loved behind him sick, when he begged
					and beseeched him with tears to have compassion, he turned
					and said, How hard it is to be pitiful and wise at once! His
					diet was the same with that of his attendants; he never
					fed to satisfy, nor drank himself drunk; he used sleep not
					as a master, but as a servant to his affairs; and was so fitted
					to endure heat or cold, that he alone was undisturbed at the
					change of seasons. He lodged amongst his soldiers, and
					his bed was as mean as any; and this he had always in his
					mouth: It befits a governor to excel private men not in
					delicacy and softness, but in bravery and courage. And
					therefore when one asked him what good Lycurgus's laws
					had brought to Sparta, he replied, Contempt of pleasure.
					And to one that wondered at his and the other Lacedaemonians' mean fare and poor attire, he said, From this
					course of life, sir, we reap liberty. And to one advising
					him to indulge more, saying, Chance is uncertain, and you
					may never have the opportunity again, he replied, I accustom myself so that, let whatever change happen, I shall
					need no change. When he was grown old, he continued
					the same course; and to one asking him why at his age in
					very cold weather he would not wear a coat, he replied, that
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.389"/>
					
					the youth may imitate, having the old men and governors
					for example.</p>
            <p>The Thasians, when he marched through their country,
					presented him with corn, geese, sweetmeats, honey-cakes,
					and all sorts of delicacies, both of meat and drink; he accepted the corn, but commanded them to carry back the
					rest, as useless and unprofitable to him. But they importunately pressing him to take all, he ordered them to be
					given to the Helots; and when some asked the reason, he
					replied, They that profess bravery ought not to meddle
					with such delicacies; and whatever takes with slaves cannot be agreeable to the free. Another time the Thasians,
					after considerable benefits received, made him a God and
					dedicated temples to his honor, and sent an embassy to
					compliment him on that occasion. When he had read
					over the honors the ambassadors had brought him, Well,
					said he, and can your country make men Gods? And they
					affirming, Go to, he rejoined, make yourselves all Gods
					first; and when that is done, I'll believe you can make me
					one. The Greeks in Asia decreeing him statues, he wrote
					thus to them: Let there be no representation of me, either
					painted, founded, or engraved. In Asia, seeing a house roofed
					with square beams, he asked the master whether trees in
					their country were grown square. And he replying, No,
					but round; What then, said he, if they grew square, would
					you make them round? Being asked how far Sparta's
					bounds extended, shaking a spear he replied, As far as this
					will reach. And to another enquiring why Sparta was
					without walls, he showed the citizens in arms, saying, Look,
					these are the walls of Sparta. And to another that put
					the same question he replied, Cities should be walled not
					with stones and timber, but with the courage of the inhabitants; and his friends he advised to strive to be rich not
					in money, but in bravery and virtue. When he would have
					his soldiers do any thing quickly, he before them all put the
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.390"/>
					
					first hand to it; he was proud that he wrought as much as
					any, and valued himself more upon ruling his own desires
					than upon being king. When one saw a lame Spartan
					marching to the war, and endeavored to procure a horse
					for him, How, said he, don't you know that war needs those
					that will stay, not those that will fly? Being asked how he
					got this greateatreputation, he replied, By contemning death.
					And another time, one enquiring why the Spartans used
					pipes and music when they fought, he said, When all move
					in measure, it may be known who is brave and who a coward. When he heard one magnifying the king of Persia's
					happiness, who was but young, Yes, said he, Priam himself
					was not unhappy at that age.</p>
            <p>When he had conquered a great part of Asia, he designed to march against the King himself, to break his
					quiet and hinder him from corrupting the popular men
					amongst the Greeks; but being recalled by the Ephors to
					oppose the designs which the other Greek states, bought
					with the King's gold, were forming against Sparta, he said,
					A good ruler should be governed by the laws,&mdash;and sailed
					away from Asia, leaving the Greeks there extremely sorry
					at his departure. And because the stamp of the Persian
					money was an archer, he said, when he broke up his camp,
					that he was driven out of Asia by thirty thousand of the
					King's archers. For so many pieces of gold being carried
					to Thebes and Athens by Timocrates, and distributed
					amongst the popular men, the people were excited to
					war upon the Spartans. And this epistle he sent to the
					Ephors:&mdash;
					
					<text>
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Agesilaus to the Ephors, Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>We have subdued a great part of Asia, driven out the
							barbarians, and furnished Ionia with arms. But since
							you command me back, I follow, nay almost come before
							this epistle; for I am not governor for myself, but for the
							
							<pb id="v.1.p.391"/>
							
							commonwealth. And then a king truly rules according to
							justice, when he is governed by the laws, the Ephors, or
							others that are in authority in the commonwealth.</p>
                  </body>
               </text>
            </p>
            <p>Passing the Hellespont, he marched through Thrace, but
					made no applications to any of the barbarians, only sending to know whether he marched through the country of
					an enemy or a friend. All the others received him as
					friends and guided him in his march; only the Troadians
					(of whom, as story says, even Xerxes bought his passage)
					demanded of Agesilaus a hundred talents of silver and as
					many women. But he scoffingly replied, Why then do not
					you come presently to receive what you demand? And
					leading on his army, he fought them; and having destroyed
					a considerable number, he marched through. To the king
					of Macedon he sent the same question; and he replying
					that he would consider of it, Let him consider, saith he,
					and we will be marching on. Upon which the king, surprised at his daring temper and afraid of his force, admitted him as a friend. The Thessalians having assisted
					his enemies, he wasted their country, and sent Xenocles
					and Scythes to Larissa in order to make a treaty. These
					being seized and detained, all others stomached it extremely, and were of opinion that Agesilaus should besiege and
					storm Larissa. But he replying that he would not give
					either of their lives for all Thessaly, he had them delivered upon articles. Hearing of a battle fought near Corinth, in which very few of the Spartans, but many of the
					Corinthians, Athenians, and their allies were slain, he did
					not appear joyful, or puffed up with his victory, but fetching a deep sigh cried out, Unhappy Greece, that hath destroyed herself men enough to have conquered all the
					barbarians! The Pharsalians pressing upon him and distressing his forces with five hundred horse, he charged
					them, and after the rout raised a trophy at the foot of
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.392"/>
					
					Narthacium. And this victory pleased him more than all
					the others he had won, because with his single cavalry he
					had beaten those that vaunted themselves as the best
					horsemen in the world. Diphridas bringing him commands immediately upon his march to make an inroad into
					Boeotia,&mdash;though he designed the same thing in a short
					time, when he should be better prepared,&mdash;he obeyed,
					and sending for twenty thousand men from the camp at
					Corinth, marched into Boeotia; and at Coronea joining
					battle with the Thebans, Athenians, Argives, Corinthians,
					and Locrians altogether, he won, though desperately
					wounded himself, the greatest battle (as Xenophon affirms) that was fought in his age. And yet when he
					returned, after so much glory and so many victories, he
					made no alteration in his course of life.</p>
            <p>When he saw some of the citizens think themselves
					brave fellows for breeding horses for the race, he persuaded his sister Cunisca to get into a chariot and put in
					for the prize at the Olympian games, intending by that way
					to convince the Greeks that it was no argument of bravery,
					but of wealth and profuse expense. Having Xenophon
					the philosopher at his house, and treating him with great
					consideration, he urged him to send for his children and
					have them brought up in Sparta, where they might learn
					the most excellent of arts, how to govern and how to be
					governed. And at another time being asked by what
					means the Lacedaemonians flourished above others, Because, says he, they are more studious than others how
					to rule and how to obey. When Lysander was dead,
					he found a strong faction, which Lysander upon his return from Asia had associated against him, and was very
					eager to show the people what manner of citizen Lysander was whilst he lived. And finding among Lysander's
					papers an oration composed by Cleon of Halicarnassus,
					about new designs and changing the government, which
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.393"/>
					
					Lysander was to speak to the people, he resolved to publish
					it. But when an old politician, perusing the discourse and
					fearing its effect upon the people, advised him not to dig
					up Lysander but rather bury the speech with him, he
					followed the advice, and made no more of it. Those of
					the contrary faction he did not openly molest, but by cunning contrivance he got some of them into office, and then
					showed them to be rascals when in power. And then
					defending them or getting their pardon when accused, he
					brought them over to his own side, so that he had no enemy
					at last. To one desiring him to write to his acquaintance in
					Asia, that he might have justice done him, he replied, My
					acquaintance will do thee justice, though I do not write.
					One showed him the wall of a city strongly built and well
					fortified, and asked him whether he did not think it a fine
					thing. Yes, by heaven, he replied, for women, but not for
					men to live in. To a Megarian talking great things of his
					city he said, Youth, thy words want an army.</p>
            <p>What he saw others admire he seemed not so much as
					to know; and when Callipides, a man famous among the
					Greeks for acting tragedies and caressed by all, met him
					and saluted him, and then impudently intruding amongst
					his companions showed himself, supposing that Agesilaus
					would take notice of him and begin some familiar discourse, and at last asked, Doth not your majesty know me?
					Have not you heard who I am?&mdash;he looked upon him and
					said, Art not thou Callipides, the Merry Andrew? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">Deikhli/ktas,</foreign>the Spartan word for the more common <foreign lang="greek">u(pokri/ths</foreign>(G.)</note> (For
					that is the name the Lacedaemonians give an actor.) Being once desired to hear a man imitate a nightingale,.he
					refused, saying, I have often heard the bird itself. Menecrates the physician, for his good success in some desperate
					diseases, was called Jupiter; and priding himself in the
					name, he presumed to write to Agesilaus thus: Menecrates
					Jupiter to King Agesilaus wisheth good health. Reading
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.394"/>
					
					no more, he presently wrote back: King Agesilaus to
					Menecrates wisheth a sound mind.</p>
            <p>When Conon and Pharnabazus with the king's navy
					were masters of the sea and wasted the coasts of Laconia,
					and Athens&mdash;Pharnabazus defraying the charges&mdash;was
					surrounded with a wall, the Lacedaemonians made a peace
					with the Persian; and sending Antalcidas, one of their citizens, to Tiribazus, they agreed to deliver into the King's
					hands all the Asiatic Greeks, for whose freedom Agesilaus
					fought. Upon which account Agesilaus was not at all
					blemished by this dishonorable treaty; for Antalcidas was
					his enemy, and clapped up a peace on purpose because the
					war raised Agesilaus and got him glory. When one said,
					The Lacedaemonians are becoming medized, he replied,
					Rather the Medes are becoming laconized. And being
					asked which was the better virtue, courage or justice, he
					said: Courage would be good for nothing, if there were no
					justice; and if all men were just, there would be no need
					of courage. The Asians being wont to style the king of
					Persia The Great; How, said he, is he greater than I am,
					if he is not more just or temperate? And he used to say,
					The Greeks in Asia are mean-spirited freemen, but stout
					slaves. And being asked how one might get the greatest
					reputation amongst men, he replied, By speaking the best
					and doing the bravest things. And he had this saying commonly in his mouth, A commander should be daring against
					his enemy, and kind and good-natured to his own soldiers.
					When one asked him what boys should learn; That, said
					he, which they shall use when men. When he sat judge
					upon a cause, the accuser spake floridly and well; but the
					defendant meanly and ever now and then repeated these
					words, Agesilaus, a king should assist the laws. What, said
					he, dost thou think, if any one dug down thy house or took
					away thy coat, a mason or a weaver would assist thee?</p>
            <p>A letter being brought him from the king of Persia by
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.395"/>
					
					a Persian that came with Callias the Spartan, after the
					peace was concluded, offering him friendship and kind entertainment, he would not receive it, bidding the messenger
					tell the king that there was no need to send private letters
					to him; for if he was a friend to Sparta and meant well to
					Greece, he would do his best to be his friend; but if he
					designed upon their liberty, he might know that, though
					he received a thousand- letters from him, he would be his
					enemy. He was very fond of his children; and it is reported that once toying with them he got astride upon a
					reed as upon a horse, and rode about the room; and being
					seen by one of his friends, he desired him not to speak of
					it till he had children of his own. When he had fought
					often with the Thebans and was wounded in the battle,
					Antalcidas, as it is reported, said to him: Indeed, sir, you
					have received a very fair reward for instructing the Thebans, whom, when ignorant and unwilling, you have forced
					to learn the art of war. For story tells us, the Lacedaemonians at that time by frequent skirmishes had made the
					Thebans better soldiers than themselves. And therefore
					Lycurgus, the old lawgiver, forbade them to fight often
					with the same nation, lest the enemy should learn their
					discipline. When he understood that the allies took it
					very ill, that in their frequent expeditions they, being great
					in number, followed the Spartans that were but few; designing to show their mistake about the number, he ordered
					all the allies to sit down in one body and the Lacedaemonians in another by themselves. Then he made proclamation that all the potters should rise first; and when they
					stood up, the braziers next; then the carpenters, next the
					masons, and so all other traders in order. Now almost all
					the allies stood up and not one of the Spartans, for their
					law forbids them all mechanical employments. Then said
					Agesilaus, with a smile, See now how many soldiers we provide more than you. When at the battle of Leuctra many
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.396"/>
					
					of the Spartans fled and upon that account were obnoxious
					to the laws, the Ephors, seeing the city had but few men
					and stood in great need of soldiers at that time, would free
					them from the infamy and yet still keep the laws in force.
					Upon that account they put the power of making laws into
					the hands of Agesilaus; and he coming into the assembly
					said, I will make no new laws, nor will I add any thing to
					those you already have, nor take therefrom, nor change
					them in any wise; but I will order that the laws you
					already have be in force from to-morrow.</p>
            <p>Epaminondas rushing on with a torrent and tide of force,
					and the Thebans and their allies being puffed up with this
					victory, though he had but an inconsiderable number, Agesilaus repulsed them from the city and forced them to
					retreat. In the battle at Mantinea, he advised the Spartans
					to neglect the others and fight Epaminondas only, saying:
					The wise alone is the stout man, and the cause of victory;
					and therefore if we take him off, we shall quickly have
					the rest; for they are fools and worth nothing. And it
					happened accordingly; for Epaminondas having the better
					of the day and the Spartans being routed, as he turned
					about and encouraged his soldiers to pursue, a Lacedaemonian gave him his death-wound. He falling, the Spartans that fled with Agesilaus rallied and turned the victory;
					the Thebans appearing to have much the worse, and the
					Spartans the better of the day. When Sparta had a great
					many hired soldiers in pay, and wanted money to carry on
					the war, Agesilaus, upon the king of Egypt's desire, went
					to serve him for money. But the meanness of his habit
					brought him into contempt with the people of that country; for they, according to their bad notions of princes, expected that the king of Sparta should appear like the
					Persian, gaudily attired. But in a little time he sufficiently
					convinced them that majesty and glory were to be gotten
					by prudence and courage. When he found his men discouraged
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.397"/>
					
					 at the number of the enemy (for they were
					200,000) and their own fewness, just before the engagement, without any man's privity, he contrived how to encourage them: in the hollow of his left hand he wrote
					VICTORY, and taking the liver from the priest, he put it into
					that hand, and held it a pretty while, pretending he was in
					doubt and perplexity at some appearance, till the characters were imprinted on the flesh; and then he showed it to
					the soldiers, telling them the Gods gave certain signs of
					victory by these characters. Upon which, thinking they
					had sure evidence of good success, they marched resolutely to the battle. When the enemy much exceeded
					them in number and were making an entrenchment round
					his camp, and Nectabius, whom then he assisted, urged
					him to fight; I would not, said he, hinder our enemies
					from making their number as small as ours. And when
					the trench was almost drawn round, ordering his army
					to the space between, and so fighting upon equal terms,
					with those few soldiers he had he routed and killed abundance of the enemy, and sent home a great treasure. Dying
					on his voyage from Egypt, he commanded his attendants
					not to make any figure or representation of his body; For,
					said he, if I have done any brave action, that will preserve
					my memory; if not, neither will a thousand statues, the
					works of base mechanics.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agesipolis the Son of Cleombrotus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agesipolis the son of Cleombrotus, when one told him
					that Philip had razed Olynthus in a few days, said, Well,
					but he is not able to build such another in twice that time.
					To one saying that whilst he was king he himself was an
					hostage with some other youths, and not their wives or
					children, he replied, Very good, for it is fit we ourselves
					should suffer for our own faults. When he designed to
					send for some whelps from home, and one said, Sir, none
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.398"/>
					
					must be carried out of the country, he replied, Nor men
					heretofore, but now they may.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agesipolis the Son of Pausanias.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agesipolis the son of Pausanias, when the Athenians
					appealed to the Megarians as arbitrators of the differences
					between them, said, It is a shame, Athenians, that those
					who were once the lords of all Greece should understand
					what is right and just less than the people of Megara.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agis the Son of Archidamus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agis the son of Archidamus, when the Ephors gave
					orders, Go take the youth, and follow this man into his
					own country, and he shall guide thee to the very citadel,
					said: How can it be prudent to trust so many youths to the
					fidelity of him who betrays his own country? Being asked
					what art was chiefly learned in Sparta, To know, he replied, how to govern and to be governed, he used to say,
					The Spartans do not enquire how many the enemy are, but
					where they are. At Mantinea, being advised not to fight
					the enemy, who exceeded him in number, he said, It is
					necessary for him to fight a great many that would rule a
					great many. To one enquiring how many the Spartans
					were, Enough, he replied, to keep rascals at a distance.
					Marching by the walls of Corinth, and perceiving them to
					be high and strong and stretching out to a great length, he
					said, What women live there? To an orator that said
					speech was the best thing, he rejoined, You then, when
					you are silent, are worth nothing. When the Argives,
					after they had been once beaten, faced him more boldly
					than before; on seeing many of the allies disheartened, he
					said, Courage, sirs! for when we conquerors shake, what
					do you think is the condition of the conquered? To an
					ambassador from the Abderites, after he had ended his
					long speech, enquiring what answer he should carry to his
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.399"/>
					
					city, he replied, This: As long as you talked, so long I quietly heard. Some commending the Eleans for exact justice
					in determining the prizes at the Olympian games, he said,
					What great wonder is it, that in four years they can be just
					one day? To some that told him he was envied by the
					heirs of the other royal family, Well, said he, their own
					misfortunes will torment them, and my own and my friends'
					success besides. When one advised him to give the flying
					enemy room to run, he said, How shall we fight those that
					stand to it and resist, if we dare not engage those whom
					their cowardice makes fly? When one proposed a way to
					free Greece, well contrived indeed but hard to be brought
					about, he said, Friend, thy words want an army and a treasure. To one saying, Philip won't let you set foot upon any
					other part of Greece, he returned, Sir, we have room
					enough in our own country. An ambassador from Perinthus to Lacedaemon, after a long tedious speech, asking
					what answer he should carry back to the Perinthians, he
					said, What but this?&mdash;that thou couldst hardly find an end
					to thy talk, and I kept silent. He went by himself ambassador to Philip; and Philip saying, What! but one? he
					replied, I am an ambassador but to one. An old man, observing that the ancient laws were neglected and that new
					evil customs crept in, said to him, when he was now grown
					old himself, All things here at Sparta are turned topsy-turvy. He replied with a joke: If it is so, it is agreeable
					to reason; for when I was a boy, I heard my father say
					that all things were then topsy-turvy; and he heard his
					father say the same; and it is no wonder if succeeding
					times are worse than the preceding; but it is a wonder if
					they happen to be better, or but just as good. Being
					asked how a man could be always free, he replied, If he
					contemns death.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.400"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agis the Younger.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agis the Younger, when Demades said, The Spartans'
					swords are so short that our jugglers can easily swallow
					them, replied, Yet the Spartans can reach their enemies
					with these swords. A base fellow often asking who was
					the bravest of the Spartans, he said, He that is most unlike thee.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Agis the Last.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Agis, the last king of Lacedaemon, being taken and
					condemned by the Ephors without hearing, as he was led
					to the gallows, saw one of the officers weeping. Do not
					weep for me, he said, who, being so unjustly, so barbarously
					condemned, am in a better condition than my murderers.
					And having spoken thus, he quietly submitted himself to
					the halter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Acrotatus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Acrotatus, when his parents commanded him to join in
					some unjust action, refused for some time; but when they
					grew importunate, he said: When I was under your power
					I had no notion of justice, but now you have delivered me
					to my country and her laws, and to the best of your power
					have taught me loyalty and justice, I shall endeavor to follow these rather than you. And since you would have me
					to do that which is best, and since just actions are best for
					a private man and much more for a governor, I shall do
					what you would have me, and refuse what you command.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Alcamenes the Son of Teleclus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Alcamenes the son of Teleclus, being asked how a ruler
					might best secure his government, replied, By slighting
					gain. And to another enquiring why he refused the presents the Messenians made him he said, Because, if I had
					taken them, I and the laws could never have agreed.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.401"/>
            <p>When one said that though he had wealth enough he lived
					but meanly, he replied, Well, it is a glory for one that hath
					abundance to live as reason not as appetite directs.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Alexandridas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Alexandridas, the son of Leo, said to one that was much
					concerned at his banishment from the city, Good sir, be
					not concerned that you must leave the city, but that you
					have left justice. To one that talked to the Ephors very
					pertinently but a great deal too much he said, Sir, your
					discourse is very good, but ill-timed. And when one asked
					him why they let their Helot slaves cultivate the fields, and
					did not take care of them themselves, he replied, Because
					we acquired our land not caring for it but for ourselves.
					Another saying, Desire of reputation causes abundance of
					mischief, and those are happy that are free from it; Then,
					he subjoined, it follows that villains are happy; for do you
					think that he that commits sacrilege or doth an injury takes
					any care for credit and reputation? Another asking why
					in a battle the Spartans venture so boldly into danger, Because, said he, we train ourselves to have a reverential
					regard for our lives, not, as others do, to tremble for them.
					Another demanding why the judges took so many days to
					pass sentence in a capital cause, and why he that was
					acquitted still remained liable to be brought to trial, he
					replied: They consult so long, because if they make a mistake in judgment and condemn a man to death, they cannot
					correct their judgment; and the accused still remains liable,
					because this provision might enable them to give even a
					better judgment than before.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Anaxander the Son of Eurycrates.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Anaxander, the son of Eurycrates, to one asking him
					why the Spartans laid up no money in the exchequer, replied, that the keepers of it might not be tempted to be
					knaves.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.402"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>Of <hi rend="italics">Anaxilas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Anaxilas, when one wondered for what reason the Ephors
					did not rise up to the king, since the kings made them,
					said, It is for the same reason for which they are appointed
					Ephors (or overseers).</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Androclidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Androclidas a Spartan, being maimed in his leg, enlisted
					in the army; and when some refused him because he was
					maimed, he said, It must not be those that can run away,
					hut those that can stand to it, that must fight the enemy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="14">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Antalcidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Antalcidas, when he was to be initiated in the Samothracian mysteries, and was asked by the priest what great sin
					he had committed in all his life, replied, If I have committed
					any, the Gods know it already. To an Athenian that called
					the Lacedaemonians illiterate he said, True; for we alone
					have learned no ill from you. Another Athenian saying,
					We have often beat you back from the Cephissus, he subjoined, Butwe never repulsed you from the Eurotas. To
					another demanding how one might please most men, he
					replied, By speaking what delights, and doing what profits
					them. A Sophist being about to read him an encomium
					of Hercules, he said, Why, who has blamed him? To
					Agesilaus, when he was wounded in a battle by the Thebans, he said, Sir, you have a fine reward for forcing them
					to learn the art of war; for, by the many skirmishes Agesilaus had with them, they learned discipline and became
					good soldiers. He said, The youth are the walls of Sparta,
					and the points of their spears its bounds. To one enquiring why the Lacedaemonians fought with such short swords,
					he replied, We come up close to our enemies.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.403"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="15">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Antiochus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Antiochus, one of the Ephors, when he heard Philip had
					bestowed some lands on the Messenians, said, Well, but
					hath Philip also given them forces, that they may be able
					to defend his gift</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="16">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Aregeus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Aregeus, when some praised not their own but other
					men's wives, said: Faith, about virtuous women there
					should be no common talk; and what beauty they have
					none but their own husbands should understand. As he
					was walking through Selinus, a city of Sicily, he saw this
					epitaph upon a tomb,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Those that extinguished the tyrannic flame,</l>
						            <l>Surprised by war and hasty fate,</l>
						            <l>Though they are still alive in lasting fame,</l>
						            <l>Lie buried near Selinus' gate;&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
					
					and said: You died deservedly for quenching it wnen
					already in a flame; for you should have hindered it from
					coming to a blaze.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="17">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Ariston.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Ariston, when one commended the saying of Cleomenes,
					&mdash;who, being asked what a good king should do, replied,
					Good turns to his friends, and evil to his enemies,&mdash;said:
					How much better is it, sir, to do good to our friends, and
					make our enemies our friends! Though upon all hands it
					is agreed Socrates spoke this first, yet he hath the credit of
					it too. To one asking how many the Spartans were in
					number he replied, Enough to chase our enemies. An
					Athenian making a funeral oration in praise of those that
					fell by the hand of the Lacedaemonians, he said, What
					brave fellows then were ours, that conquered these!</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Archidamidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Archidamidas said to one commending Charilas for
					being kind to all alike, How can he deserve commendation,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.404"/>
					
					 that is gentle to the wicked and unjust? When one
					was angry with Hecataeus the Sophist because when ad
					mitted to the public entertainment he said nothing, he said,
					Sir, you seem not to understand that he that knows how to
					speak knows also when to speak.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Archidamus the Son of Zeuxidamus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Archidamus the son of Zeuxidamus, when one asked
					him who were governors at Sparta, replied, The laws, and
					the magistrates according to those laws. To one that
					praised a fiddler and admired his skill he said, How must
					you prize brave men, when you can give a fiddler such a
					commendation! When one recommending a musician to
					him said, This man plays well upon the harp, he returned,
					And we have this man who makes broth well;&mdash;as if it
					were no more to raise pleasure and tickle with a sound
					than with meats and broths. To one that promised to make
					his wine sweet he said, To what purpose? for we shall
					spend the more, and ruin our public mess. When he
					besieged Corinth, seeing some hares started under the
					very walls, he said to his soldiers, Our enemies may be
					easily surprised. Two choosing him arbitrator, he brought
					them both into the temple of Minerva of the Brazen House,
					and made them swear to stand to his determination; and
					when they had both sworn, he said, I determine that you
					shall not go out of this temple, till you have ended all the
					differences between you. Dionysius the Sicilian tyrant
					sending his daughters some very rich apparel, he refused
					it, saying, When this is on, I am afraid they will look ugly
					and deformed. When he saw his son rashly engaging the
					Athenians, he said, Pray get more strength or less spirit.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="20">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Archidamus the Son of Agesilaus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Archidamus the son of Agesilaus, when Philip after the
					battle at Chaeronea sent him a haughty letter, returned
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.405"/>
					
					this answer, If you measure your shadow, you will find it
					no greater than before the victory. And being asked how
					much land the Spartans possessed, he said, As much as
					their spears reach. Periander, a physician, being well
					skilled in his profession and of good credit, but writing
					very bad poems, he said to him, Why, Periander, instead
					of a good physician are you eager to be called a bad poet
					In the war with Philip, when some advised him to fight at
					some distance from his own country, he replied, Let us not
					mind that, but whether we shall fight bravely and beat our
					enemies. To some who commended him for routing the
					Arcadians he said, It had been better if we had been too
					hard for them in policy rather than in strength. When he
					invaded Arcadia, understanding that the Eleans were ready
					to oppose him, he wrote thus: Archidamus to the Eleans;
					It is good to be quiet. The allies in the Peloponnesian
					war consulting what treasure would be sufficient to carry
					on the war, and desiring to set the tax, he said, War cannot
					be put on a certain allowance. As soon as ever he saw a
					dart shot out of an engine brought from Sicily, he cried
					out, Good God! true valor is gone for ever. When the
					Greeks refused to obey him orto stand to those conditions
					which he had made with Antigonus and Craterus the
					Macedonians, but would be free, alleging that the
					Spartans would prove more rigorous lords than the Macedonians, he said: A sheep always uses the same voice,
					but a man various and many, till he hath perfected his
					designs.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="21">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Astycratidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Astycratidas, after Agis the king was beaten by Antigonus at Megalopolis, was asked, What will you Spartans
					do? will you serve the Macedonians? He replied, Why
					so, can Antipater hinder us from dying in the defence
					of Sparta?
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.406"/>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="22">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Bias.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Bias being surprised by an ambush that Iphicrates the
					Athenian general had laid, and his soldiers demanding
					what must be done, he replied, You must provide for your
					own safety, and I must fight manfully and die.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="23">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Brasidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Brasidas catching a mouse amongst some dry figs, the
					mouse bit him; upon which he let her go, and said to his
					companions, There is nothing so little but it may preserve
					itself, if it dares resist the invaders. In a battle, being
					shot through the shield into the body, he drew the dart
					out and with it killed the enemy. And one asking how
					his wound came, he replied, By the treachery of my shield.
					As he was leading forth his army, he wrote to the Ephors,
					I will accomplish what I wish in this war, or I will die for
					it. Being killed as he fought to free the Greeks in Thrace,
					the ambassadors that were sent to Sparta to condole his
					loss made a visit to his mother Argileonis. And the first
					question she asked was, whether Brasidas died bravely.
					And the Thracians extolling him and saying there was no
					such man in the world; You mistake, sir, said she, it is
					true, Brasidas was a good man, but Sparta can show many
					who are better.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="24">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Damonidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Damonidas, when the master of the festival set him in
					the lowest place in the choral dance, said, Well, sir, you
					have found a way to make this place, which was infamous
					before, noble and honorable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="25">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Damis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Damis to some letters that were sent to him by Alexander, intimating that he should vote Alexander a God,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.407"/>
					
					returned this answer: We are content that Alexander (if
					he will) be called a God.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="26">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Damindas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Damindas, when Philip invaded Peloponnesus, and one
					said that the Spartans would suffer great mischiefs unless
					they accepted his proposals, said, Thou woman-man, what
					misery can we suffer that despise death?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="27">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Dercyllidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Dercyllidas, being sent ambassador to Pyrrhus,&mdash;who
					was then with his army on the borders of Sparta, and required them either to receive their king Cleonymus, or
					he would make them know they were no better than
					other men,&mdash;replied, If he is a God, we do not fear him,
					for we have committed no fault; if a man, we are as good
					as he.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="28">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Demaratus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Demaratus,&mdash;when Orontes talked very roughly to him,
					and one said, Demaratus, Orontes uses you very roughly,&mdash;
					replied, I have no reason to be angry, for those that speak
					to please do the mischief, not those that talk out of malice.
					To one enquiring why they disgrace those that lose their
					shields in a battle and not those that lose their head-pieces
					or breastplates, he answered, Because these serve for their
					private safety only, but their shield for the common defence and strength of the whole army. Hearing one play
					upon the harp, he said, The man seems to play the fool
					well. In a certain assembly, when he was asked whether
					he held his tongue because he was a fool or for want of
					words, he replied, A fool cannot hold his tongue. When
					one asked him why being king he fled Sparta, he answered,
					Because the laws rule there. A Persian having by many
					presents enticed the boy that he loved from him, and saying,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.408"/>
					
					 Spartan, I have caught your love; No, faith, he answered, but you have bought him. One having revolted
					from the king of Persia, and by Demaratus's persuasion
					returning again to his obedience, and the king designing his death, Demaratus said: It is dishonorable, O king,
					whilst he was an enemy not to be able to punish him for
					his revolt, and to kill him now he is a friend. To a parasite of the king that often jeered him about his exile he
					said: Sir, I will not fight you, for you have lost your
					post in life.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Following Wyttenbach's emendation for <q direct="unspecified">I have lost my post.</q> (G.)</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="29">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Emprepes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Emprepes, one of the Ephors, cut out two of the nine
					strings of Phrynis the musician's harp with a hatchet, saying, Do not abuse music.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="30">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Epaenetus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Epaenetus said that liars were the cause of all villanies
					and injustice in the world.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="31">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Euboidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Euboidas, hearing some commend another man's wife,
					disliked it and said, Strangers who are not of the house
					should never speak of the manner of any woman.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="32">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Eudamidas the Son of Archidamus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Eudamidas, the son of Archidamus and brother of Agis,
					seeing Xenocrates, now grown old, philosophizing in the
					Academy with some of his acquaintance, asked what old
					man that was. And it being answered, He is a wise man,
					and one of those that seek after virtue; he replied, When
					will he use it, if he is seeking of it now? Another time,
					when he heard a philosopher discoursing that none but a
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.409"/>
					
					learned man could be a good general, he said, Indeed the
					discourse is admirable, but he that makes it is of no credit
					in this matter, for he hath never heard a trumpet sound.
					Just as Xenocrates had finished his discourse, Eudamidas
					came into his school, and when one of his companions said,
					As soon as we came he ended; So he ought, he replied, if
					he had spoken all that was needful on the subject. And
					the other saying, Yet it were a pleasant thing to hear him,
					he replied, If we visited one that had supped already,
					should we desire him to sit down again? When one asked
					him why, when all the citizens voted a war with the
					Macedonians, he appeared for peace, he answered, Because
					I have no mind to convince them of their mistake. And
					when another encouraged them to this war, mentioning
					their various victories over the Persians, he said, Sir, you
					appear not to see that this would be as absurd as to set
					upon fifty wolves because you have beaten a thousand
					sheep. A musician playing very well, some asked him
					what manner of man he was in his opinion, and he answered, A great seducer in a small matter. Hearing one
					commending Athens, he said, Who could have reason to
					praise that city which no man ever loved because he had
					been made better in it? An Argive saying that the Spartans being taken from their own customs grew worse by
					travel, he replied, But you, when you come into Sparta, do
					not return worse, but much better. When Alexander
					ordered by public proclamation in the Olympic games,
					that all exiles whatever, except the Thebans, had free
					liberty to return to their own country, Eudamidas said:
					This is a woful proclamation to you Thebans, but yet honorable; for of all the Grecians Alexander fears only you.
					Being asked why before a battle they sacrificed to the
					Muses, he replied, That our brave actions may be worthily
					recorded.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.410"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="33">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Eurycratidas the Son of Anaxandridas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Eurycratidas the son of Anaxandridas, when one asked
					him why the Ephor sat every day to determine causes
					about contracts, replied, That we may learn to keep our
					word even with our enemies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="34">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Zeuxidamus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Zeuxidamus, when one asked him why they did not set
					down all their laws concerning bravery and courage in
					writing and let the young men read them, answered, Because they should be accustomed to mind valiant actions,
					rather than books and writings. An Aetolian saying that
					war was better than peace for those that would be brave
					men, No, faith, said he, but death is better than life.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="35">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Herondas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Herondas, when one at Athens was condemned for idleness, being informed of it desired one to show him the
					man that had been convicted of so gentlemanly an offence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="36">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Thearidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Thearidas whetting his sword, being asked, Is it sharp,
					Thearidas replied, Yes, sharper than a slander.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="37">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Themisteas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Themisteas the prophet foretold to King Leonidas his
					own and his soldiers' destruction at Thermopylae, and being commanded by Leonidas to return to Sparta, under
					pretence of informing the state how affairs stood, but really
					that he might not perish with the rest, he refused, saying,
					I was sent as a soldier, not as a courier to carry news.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="38">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Theopompus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Theopompus, when one asked him how a monarch may be
					safe, replied, If he will give his friends just freedom to speak
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.411"/>
					
					the truth, and to the best of his power not allow his subjects to be oppressed. To a guest of his that said, In my
					own country I am called a lover of the Spartans, he replied,
					It would be more honorable for you to be called a lover of
					your citizens than a lover of the Spartans. An ambassador from Elis saying that his city sent him because he was
					the only man amongst them that admired and followed the
					Spartan way of living, Theopompus asked, And pray, sir,
					which way is best, yours or the other citizens? And the
					ambassador replying, Mine; he subjoined, How then can
					that city stand, in which amongst so many inhabitants
					there is but one good man? When one said that Sparta
					was preserved because the kings knew how to govern; No,
					he replied, but because the citizens know how to be governed. The Pylians voting him greater honors, he wrote to
					them thus, Moderate honors time augments, but it defaces
					the immoderate.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="39">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Thorycion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Thorycion on his return from Delphi, seeing Philip's
					army possessed of the narrow passage at the Isthmus, said,
					Peloponnesus hath very bad porters in you Corinthians.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="40">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Thectamenes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Thectamenes, when the Ephors condemned him to die,
					went away smiling; and one of the company asked him
					whether he despised the judicial proceedings of Sparta.
					No, said he, but I am glad that I am ordered to pay a fine
					which I can pay out of my own stock, without being beholden to any man or taking up money upon interest.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="41">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Hippodamus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Hippodamus, when Agis was joined in command with
					Archidamus, being sent with Agis to Sparta to look after
					affairs there, said, But shall I not die a more glorious death
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.412"/>
					
					fighting valiantly in defence of Sparta? He was above
					fourscore years of age, yet he put on his armor, fought on
					the right hand of the king, and died bravely.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="42">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Hippocratidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Hippocratidas, when the governor of Caria sent him
					word that he had a Spartan in his hands who concealed a
					conspiracy that he was privy to, and asked how he should
					deal with him, returned this answer: If you have done
					him any great kindness, kill him; if not, banish him as a
					base fellow, too mean-spirited to be good. A youth whom
					his lover followed meeting him and blushing at the encounter, he said: You should keep such company that,
					whoever sees you, you will have no reason to change color.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="43">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Callicratidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Callicratidas the admiral, when some of Lysander's
					friends desired him to permit them to kill one of the enemy,
					and offered fifty talents for the favor, though he wanted
					money extremely to buy provision for his soldiers, refused;
					and when Cleander urged him, and said, Sir, I would have
					taken the money if I were you, he replied, So would I,
					were I Cleander. When he came to Sardis to Cyrus the
					Younger, who was then an ally of the Lacedaemonians,
					about a sum of money to equip his navy, on the first day
					he ordered his officers to tell Cyrus that he desired audience; but being told that he was drinking, Well, said he,
					I shall stay till he hath done. But understanding that he
					could not be admitted that day, he presently left the court,
					and thereupon was thought a rude and uncivil fellow. On
					the next day, when he received the same answer and could
					not be admitted, he said, I must not be so eager for money
					as to do any thing unbecoming Sparta. And presently he
					returned to Ephesus, cursing those who had first endured
					the insolence of the barbarians, and had taught them to
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.413"/>
					
					rely upon their wealth and abuse others; and he swore to
					his companions that as soon as ever he came to Sparta, he
					would do all that lay in his power to reconcile the Greek
					states, that they might be more dreadful to the barbarians,
					and not forced to seek assistance from them to ruin one
					another. Being asked what manner of men the Ionians
					were, he replied, Bad freemen, but good slaves. When
					Cyrus sent his soldiers their pay, and some particular presents to himself, he received the pay, but sent back the
					presents, saying that there was no need of any private
					friendship between them, for the common league with the
					Lacedaemonians included him. Designing to engage near
					Arginusae, when Hermon the pilot said, It is advisable to
					tack about, for the Athenians exceed us in number; he exclaimed: What then! it is base and dishonorable to Sparta
					to fly, but to stand to it and die or conquer is brave and
					noble. As he was sacrificing before the battle, when he
					heard the priest presaging that the army would conquer
					but the captain fall, undauntedly he said: Sparta doth not
					depend on one man; my country will receive no great loss
					by my death, but a considerable one by my yielding to the
					enemy. And ordering Cleander to succeed as admiral, he
					readily engaged, and died in the battle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="44">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Cleombrotuts the Son of Pausanias.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Cleombrotus, the son of Pausanias, when a friend of his
					contended with his father which was the best man, said,
					Sir, my father must be better than you, till you get a son
					as well as he.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="45">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Cleomenes the Son of Anaxandridas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Cleomenes, the son of Anaxandridas, was wont to say
					that Homer was the poet of the Lacedaemonjans, Hesiod
					of the Helots; for one taught the art of war, and the other
					husbandry. Having made a truce for seven days with the
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.414"/>
					
					Argives, he watched his opportunity the third night, and
					perceiving them secure and negligent by reason of the
					truce, he fell upon them whilst they were asleep, killed
					some, and took others prisoners. Upon this being upbraided for breach of articles, he said that his oath did not
					extend to night as well as day, and to hurt a man's enemies
					any way, both before God and man, was much better than
					to be just. It happened that he missed taking Argos, in
					hopes of which he broke his oath; for the women taking
					the old arms out of the temples defended the city. And
					afterwards running stark mad, he seized a knife, and ripped
					himself up from the very ankles to the vital parts, and thus
					died grinning and laughing. The priest advising him not
					to march to Argos,&mdash;for he would be forced to a dishonorable retreat,&mdash;when he came near the city and saw the
					gates shut and the women upon the walls, he said: What,
					sir priests, will this be a dishonorable retreat, when, the
					men being all lost, the women have shut the gates? When
					some of the Argives railed at him as an impious and forsworn wretch, he said, Well, it is in your power to rail at
					me, and in mine to mischief you. The Samian ambassadors urging him to make war on the tyrant Polycrates, and
					making long harangues on that account, he said: The beginning of your speech I don't remember, and therefore I
					cannot understand the middle, and the last I don't like. A
					pirate spoiling the country, and when he was taken saying,
					I had no provision for my soldiers, and therefore went to
					those who had store and would not give it willingly, to force
					it from them; Cleomenes said, True villainy goes the
					shortest way to work. A base fellow railing at him, he
					said, Well, I think thou railest at everybody, that being
					employed to defend ourselves, we may have no time to
					speak of thy baseness.</p>
            <p>One of the citizens saying that a good king should be
					always mild and gracious, True, said he, as long as he doth
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.415"/>
					
					not make himself contemptible. Being tormented with a
					long disease, he consulted the priests and expiators, to
					whom he formerly gave no credit; and when a friend of
					his wondered at the action, Why dost thou wonder, said he,
					for I am not the same man I was then; and since I am not
					the same, I do not approve the same things. A Sophist
					discoursing of courage, he laughed exceedingly; and the
					Sophist saying, Why do you laugh, Cleomenes, when you
					hear one treat of courage, especially since you are a king?
					Because, sir, said he, if a swallow should discourse of it, I
					should laugh; but if an eagle, I should hearken attentively.</p>
            <p>When the Argives boasted that they would retrieve their
					defeat by a new battle, he said, I wonder if the addition of
					two syllables<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, changing <foreign lang="greek">ma/xesqai</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">to fight</hi>) into <foreign lang="greek">a)nama/xesqai</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">to retrieve aidefeat</hi>). (G.)</note> has made you braver than you were before.
					When one railed at him, and said, Thou art luxurious,
					Cleomenes; Well, he replied, that is better than to be
					unjust; but thou art covetous, although thou art master of
					abundance of superfluities. A friend willing to recommend a musician to him, besides other large commendations,
					said he was the best musician in all Greece. Cleomenes,
					pointing to one that stood by, said, Faith, sir, that fellow is
					my best cook. Maeander the Samian tyrant, flying to Sparta
					upon the invasion of the Persian, discovering what treasure
					he had brought, and offering Cleomenes as much as he
					would have, Cleomenes refused, and beside took care that
					he should not give any of the citizens a farthing; but going
					to the Ephors, told them that it would be good for Sparta
					to send that Samian guest of his out of Peloponnesus, lest
					he should persuade any of the Lacedaemonians to be a
					knave. And they taking his advice ordered Maeander to
					be gone that very day. One asking why, since they had
					beaten the Argives so often, they did not totally destroy
					them, he replied, That we may have some to exercise our
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.416"/>
					
					youth. One demanding why the Spartans did not dedicate
					the spoils of their enemies to the Gods, Because, said he,
					they are taken from cowards; and such things as are
					betrayed to us by the cowardice of the possessors are fit
					neither for our youth to see, nor to be dedicated to the
					Gods.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="46">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Cleomenes the Son of Cleombrotus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Cleomenes, the son of Cleombrotus, to one that presented
					him some game-cocks, and said, Sir, these will die before
					they run, returned: Pray let me have some of that breed
					which will kill these, for certainly they are the better of
					the two.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="47">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Labotus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Labotus said to one that made a long discourse: Why
					such great preambles to so small a matter? A speech
					should be no bigger than the subject.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="48">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Leotychidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Leotychidas the First, when one said he was very inconstant, replied, My inconstancy proceeds from the variety of
					times, and not as yours from innate baseness. And to another asking him what was the best way to secure his present happiness, he answered, Not to trust all to Fortune.
					And to another enquiring what free-born boys should principally learn, That, said he, which will profit them when
					they are grown men. And to another asking why the
					Spartans drink little, he replied, That we may consult concerning others, and not others concerning us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="49">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Leotychidas the Son of Aristo.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Leotychidas the son of Aristo, when one told him that
					Demaratus's sons spake ill of him, replied, Faith, no
					wonder, for not one of them can speak well. A serpent
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.417"/>
					
					twisting about the key of his inmost door, and the priests
					declaring it a prodigy; I cannot think it so, said he, but it
					had been one if the key had twisted round the serpent.
					To Philip, a priest of Orpheus's mysteries, in extreme poverty, saying that those whom he initiated were very happy
					after death, he said, Why then, you sot, don't you die
					quickly, and bewail your poverty and misery no more?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="50">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Leo the Son of Eucratidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Leo the son of Eucratidas, being asked in what city a
					man might live with the greatest safety, replied, In that
					where the inhabitants have neither too much nor too little;
					where justice is strong and injustice weak. Seeing the
					racers in the Olympian games very solicitous at starting to
					get some advantage of one another, he said, How much
					more careful are these racers to be counted swift than just!
					To one discoursing of some profitable matters out of due
					season he said, Sir, you do a very good thing at a very bad
					time.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="51">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Leonidas the Son of Anaxandridas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Leonidas, the son of Anaxandridas and brother to Cleomenes, when one said to him, Abating that you are king,
					you are no better than we, replied, But unless I had been
					better than you, I had not been king. His wife Gorgo,
					when he went forth to Thermopylae to fight the Persian,
					asked him what command he left with her; and he replied,
					Marry brave men, and bear them brave children. The
					Ephors saying, You lead but few to Thermopylae; They
					are many, said he, considering on what design we go. And
					when they again asked him whether he had any other enterprise in his thought, he replied, I pretend to go to hinder
					the barbarians' passage, but really to die fighting for the
					Greeks. When he was at Thermopylae, he said to his
					soldiers: They report the enemy is at hand, and we lose
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.418"/>
					
					time; for we must either beat the barbarian or die ourselves. And to another saying, What, the flights of the
					Persian arrows will darken the very sun, he said, Therefore
					it will be pleasant for us to fight in the shade. And another saying, What, Leonidas, do you come to fight so great
					a number with so few?&mdash;he returned: If you esteem number, all Greece is not able to match a small part of that
					army; if courage, this number is sufficient. And to another discoursing after the same manner he said, I have
					enough, since they are to be killed. When Xerxes wrote
					to him thus, Sir, you may forbear to fight against the Gods,
					but may follow my interest and be lord of all Greece, he
					answered: If you understood wherein consisted the happiness of life, you would not covet other men's; but know
					that I would rather die for the liberty of Greece than be a
					monarch over my countrymen. And Xerxes writing to him
					again thus, Send me thy arms, he returned, Come and take
					them. When he resolved to fall upon the enemy, and his
					captains of the war told him he must stay till the forces of
					the allies had joined him, he said: Do you think all those
					that intend to fight are not here already? Or do you not
					understand that those only fight who fear and reverence
					their kings? And he ordered his soldiers so to dine, as if
					they were to sup in another world. And being asked why
					the bravest men prefer an honorable death before an inglorious life, he replied, Because they believe one is the gift
					of Nature, while the other is peculiarly their own. Being
					desirous to save the striplings that were with him, and
					knowing very well that if he dealt openly with them none
					would accept his kindness, he gave each of them privately
					letters to carry to the Ephors. He desired likewise to save
					three of those that were grown men; but they having some
					notice of his design refused the letters. And one of them
					said, I came, sir, to be a soldier, and not a courier; and
					the second, I shall be a better man if here than if away;
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.419"/>
					
					and the third, I will not be behind these, but the first in
					the fight.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="52">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Lochagus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Lochagus the father of Polyaenides and Siron, when
					one told him one of his sons was dead, said, I knew long
					ago that he must die.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="53">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Lycurgus the Lawgiver.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Lycurgus the lawgiver, designing to reclaim his citizens
					from their former luxury and bring them to a more sober
					course of life and make them brave men (for they were
					then loose and delicate), bred up two whelps of the same
					litter; one he kept at home, bred him tenderly, and fed
					him well; but the other he taught to hunt, and used him
					to the chase. Both these dogs he brought out into the
					public assembly, and setting down some scraps of meat and
					letting go a hare at the same time, each of the dogs ran
					greedily to what they had been accustomed. And the
					hunter catching the hare, Lycurgus said: See, countrymen,
					how these two, though of the same litter, by my breeding
					them are become very different; and that custom and exercise conduces more than Nature to make things brave and
					excellent. Some say that he did not bring out two whelps
					of the same kind, but one a house dog and the other a
					hunter; the former of which (though the baser kind) he
					had accustomed to the woods, and the other (though more
					noble) kept lazily at home; and when in public, each of
					them pursuing his usual delight, he had given a clear evidence that education is of considerable force in raising bad
					or good inclinations, he said: Therefore, countrymen, our
					honorable extraction, that idol of the crowd, though from
					Hercules himself, profits us little, unless we learn and exercise all our life in such famous exploits as made him
					accounted the most noble and the most glorious in the
					world.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.420"/>
            <p>When he made a division of the land, giving each man
					an equal portion, it is reported that some while after, in
					his return from a journey, as he past through the country
					in harvest time and saw the cocks of wheat all equal and
					lying promiscuously, he was extremely pleased, and with a
					smile said to his companions, All Sparta looks like the possession of many loving brothers who have lately divided
					their estate. Having discharged every man from his debts,
					he endeavored likewise to divide all movables equally
					amongst all, that he might have no inequality in his commonwealth. But seeing that the rich men would hardly
					endure this open and apparent spoil, he cried down all
					gold and silver coin, and ordered nothing but iron to be
					current; and rated every man's estate and defined how
					much it was worth upon exchange for that money. By
					this means all injustice was banished Sparta; for none
					would steal, none take bribes, none cheat or rob any man
					of that which he could not conceal, which none would
					envy, which could not be used without discovery, or carried
					into other countries with advantage. Besides, this contrivance freed them from all superfluous arts; for no merchant,
					Sophist, fortune-teller, or mountebank would live amongst
					them; no carver, no contriver ever troubled Sparta; because he cried down all money that was advantageous to
					them, and permitted none but this iron coin, each piece
					of which was an Aegina pound in weight, and less than a
					penny in value.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">According to Plutarch, the Spartan iron coin weighed an Aeginetan mina
						(about 1 1/2 lbs. avoir.), and was of the value of four chalci (or 3 1/4 farthings, about 1 1/2
						cents). (G.)</note> Designing farther to check all luxury
					and greediness after wealth, he instituted public meals,
					where all the citizens were obliged to eat. And when
					some of his friends demanded what he designed by this
					institution and why he divided the citizens, when in arms,
					into small companies, he replied: That they may more
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.421"/>
					
					easily hear the word of command; and if there are any
					designs against the state, the conspiracy may join but
					few; and besides, that there may be an equality in the
					provision, and that neither in meat nor drink, sets, tables,
					or any furniture, the rich may be better provided than the
					poor. When he had by this contrivance made wealth less
					desirable, it being unfit both for use and show, he said to
					his familiars, What a brave thing is it, my friends, by our
					actions to make Plutus appear (as he is indeed) blind!
					He took care that none should sup at home and afterwards,
					when they were full of other victuals, come to the public
					entertainments; for all the rest reproached him that did
					not feed with them as a glutton and of too delicate a palate for the public provision; and when he was discovered,
					he was severely punished. And therefore Agis the king,
					when after a long absence he returned from the camp (the
					Athenians were beaten in the expedition), willing to sup
					at home with his wife once, sent a servant for his allowance; the officers refused, and the next day the Ephors
					fined him for the fault.</p>
            <p>The wealthy citizens being offended at these constitutions made a mutiny against him, abused, threw stones,
					and designed to kill him, Thus pursued, he ran through
					the market-place towards the temple of Minerva of the
					Brazen House, and reached it before any of the others;
					only Alcander pursuing close struck him as he turned
					about, and beat out one eye. Afterward the commonwealth
					delivered up this Alcander to his mercy; but he neither
					inflicted any punishment nor gave him an ill word, but
					kindly entertained him at his own house, and brought him
					to be his friend, an admirer of his course of life and very
					well affected to all his laws. Yet he built a monument of
					this sad disaster in the temple of Minerva, naming it Optiletis,&mdash;for the Dorians in that country call eyes <hi rend="italics">optiloi.</hi>
					Being asked why he used no written laws, he replied, Because
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.422"/>
					
					 those that are well instructed are able to suit matters
					to the present occasion. And another time, when some
					enquired why he had ordained that the timber which
					roofed the houses should be wrought with the axe only,
					and the doors with no other instrument but the saw, he
					answered: That my citizens might be moderate in every
					thing which they bring into their houses, and possess nothing which others so much prize and value. And hence
					it is reported that King Leotychides the First, supping with
					a friend and seeing the roof curiously arched and richly
					wrought, asked him whether in that country the trees grew
					square. And some demanding why he forbade them to
					war often with the same nation, he replied, Lest being
					often forced to stand on their defence, they should get experience and be masters of our art. And therefore it was a
					great fault in Agesilaus, that by his frequent incursions
					into Boeotia he made the Thebans a match for the Lacedaemonians. And another asking why he exercised the
					virgins' bodies with racing, wrestling, throwing the bar, and
					the like, he answered: That the first rooting of the children
					being strong and firm, their growth might be proportionable; and that the women might have strength to bear and
					more easily undergo the pains of travail, or, if necessity
					should require, be able to fight for themselves, their country, and their children. Some being displeased that the
					virgins went about naked at certain solemnities, and demanding the reason of that custom, he replied: That using
					the same exercises with men, they might equal them in
					strength and health of body and in courage and bravery
					of mind, and be above that mean opinion which the vulgar
					had of them. And hence goes the story of Gorgo, wife
					of Leonidas, that when a stranger, a friend of hers, said,
					You Spartan women alone rule men, she replied, Good
					reason, for we alone bear men. By ordering that no bachelor should be admitted a spectator of these naked solemnities
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.423"/>
					
					and fixing some other disgrace on them, he made them all eager to be married and get children; besides, he deprived them
					of that honor and observance which the young men were
					bound to pay their elders. And upon that account none
					can blame what was said to Dercyllidas, though a brave
					captain'; for as he approached, one of the young men
					refused to rise up and give him place, saying, You have
					not begotten any to give place to me.</p>
            <p>When one asked him why he allowed no dowry to be
					given with a maid, he answered, that none might be slighted
					for their poverty or courted for their wealth, but that every
					one, considering the manners of the maid, might choose
					for the sake of virtue. And for the same reason he forbade all painting of the face and curiousness in dress and
					ornament. To one that asked him why he made a law
					that before such an age neither sex should marry, he answered, that the children might be lusty, being born of
					persons of full age. And to one wondering why he would
					not suffer the husband to lie all night with his wife, but
					commanded them to be most of the day and all the night
					with their fellows, and creep to their wives cautiously and
					by stealth, he said: I do it that they may be strong in
					body, having never been satiated and surfeited with pleasure; that they may be always fresh in love, and their children more strong and lusty. He forbade all perfumes, as
					nothing but good oil corrupted, and the dyer's art, as a
					flatterer and enticer of the sense; and he ejected all skilled
					in ornament and dressing, as those who by their lewd devices corrupt the true arts of decency and living well. At
					that time the women were so chaste and such strangers to
					that lightness to which they were afterwards addicted, that
					adultery was incredible; and there goes a saying of Geradatas, one of the ancient Spartans, who being asked by
					a stranger what punishment the Spartans appointed for
					adulterers (for Lycurgus mentioned none), he said, Sir, we
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.424"/>
					
					have no adulterers amongst us. And he replying, But suppose there should be? Geradatas made the same reply;
					For how (said he) could there be an adulterer in Sparta,
					where wealth, delicacy, and all ornaments are disesteemed,
					and modesty, neatness, and obedience to the governors only
					are in request? When one desired him to establish a democracy in Sparta, he said, Pray, sir, do you first set up that
					form in your own family. And to another demanding why
					he ordered such mean sacrifices he answered, That we may
					always be able to honor the Gods. He permitted the citizens those exercises only in which the hand is not stretched
					out; and one demanding his reason, he replied, That none
					in any labor may be accustomed to be weary. And another enquiring why he ordered that in a war the camp
					should be often changed, he answered, That we may damage
					our enemies the more. Another demanding why he forbade to storm a castle, he said, Lest my brave men should
					be killed by a woman, a boy, or some man of as mean
					courage.</p>
            <p>When the Thebans asked his advice about the sacrifices
					and lamentation which they instituted in honor of Leucothea, he gave them this: If you think her a Goddess, do
					not lament; if a woman, do not sacrifice to her as a Goddess. To some of the citizens enquiring, How shall we
					avoid the invasions of enemies, he replied, If you are
					poor, and one covets no more than another. And to others
					demanding why he did not wall his city he said, That city
					is not unwalled which is encompassed with men and not
					brick. The Spartans are curious in their hair, and tell us
					that Lycurgus said, It makes the handsome more amiable,
					and the ugly more terrible. He ordered that in a war they
					should pursue the routed enemy so far as to secure the
					victory, and then retreat, saying, it was unbecoming the
					Grecian bravery to butcher those that fled; and beside,
					it was useful, for their enemies, knowing that they spared
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.425"/>
					
					all that yielded and cut in pieces the opposers, would
					easily conclude that it was safer to fly than to stand stoutly
					to it and resist. When one asked him why he charged his
					soldiers not to meddle with the spoil of their slain enemies,
					he replied, Lest while they are eager on their prey they
					neglect their fighting, but also that they may keep their
					order and their poverty together.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="54">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Lysander.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Lysander, when Dionysius sent him two gowns, and bade
					him choose which he would to carry to his daughter, said,
					She can choose best; and so took both away with him.
					This Lysander being a very crafty fellow, frequently using
					subtle tricks and notable deceits, placing all justice and
					honesty in profit and advantage, would confess that truth
					indeed was better than a lie, but the worth and dignity of
					either was to be defined by their usefulness to our affairs.
					And to some that were bitter upon him for these deceitful
					practices, as unworthy of Hercules's family, and owing his
					success to little mean tricks and not plain force and open
					dealing, he answered with a smile, When the lion's skin
					cannot prevail, a little of the fox's must be used. And to
					others that upbraided him for breaking his oaths made at
					Miletus he said, Boys must be cheated with cockal-bones,
					and men with oaths. Having surprised the Athenians by
					an ambush near the Goat Rivers and routed them, and afterwards by famine forced the city to surrender, he wrote to
					the Ephors, Athens is taken. When the Argives were in
					a debate with the Lacedaemonians about their confines and
					seemed to have the better reasons on their side, drawing his
					sword, he said, He that hath this is the best pleader about
					confines. Leading his army through Boeotia, and finding
					that state wavering and not fixed on either party, he sent to
					know whether he should march through their country with
					his spears up or down. At an assembly of the states of
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.426"/>
					
					Greece, when a Megarian talked saucily to him, he said, Sir,
					your words want a city. The Corinthians revolting, and he
					approaching to the walls that he saw the Spartans not eager
					to storm, while at the same time hares were skipping over
					the trenches of the town; Are not you ashamed (said he)
					to be afraid of those enemies whose slothfulness suffers
					even hares to sleep upon their walls? At Samothrace, as
					he was consulting the oracle, the priests ordered him to
					confess the greatest crime he had been guilty of in his
					whole life. What, said he, is this your own, or the God's
					command? And the priests replying, The God's; said he,
					Do you withdraw, and I will tell them, if they make any
					such demand. A Persian asking him what polity he liked,
					That, he replied, which assigns stout men and cowards suitable rewards. To one that said, Sir, I always commend
					you and speak in your behalf,&mdash;Well, said he, I have two
					oxen in the field, and though neither says one word, I know
					very well which is the laborious and which the lazy. To
					one that railed at him he said, Speak, sir, let us have it all
					fast, if thou canst empty thy soul of those wicked thoughts
					which thou seemest full of. Some time after his death,
					there happening a difference between the Spartans and
					their allies, Agesilaus went to Lysander's house to inspect
					some papers that lay in his custody relating to that matter;
					and there found an oration composed for Lysander concerning the government, setting forth that it was expedient
					to set aside the families of the Europrotidae and Agidae, to
					admit all to an equal claim, and choose their king out of
					the worthiest men, that the crown might be the reward not
					of those that shared in the blood of Hercules, but of those
					who were like him for virtue and courage, that virtue that
					exalted him into a God. This oration Agesilaus was resolved to publish, to show the Spartans how much they
					were mistaken in Lysander and to discredit his friends;
					but they say, Cratidas the president of the Ephors fearing
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.427"/>
					
					this oration, if published, would prevail upon the people,
					advised Agesilaus to be quiet, telling him that he should
					not dig up Lysander, but rather bury that oration with him,
					being so cunningly contrived, so powerful to persuade.
					Those that courted his daughters, and when at his death
					he appeared to be poor forsook them, the Ephors fined,
					because whilst they thought him rich they caressed him,
					but scorned him when by his poverty they knew him to be
					just and honest.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="55">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Namertes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Namertes being on an embassy, when one of that country
					told him he was a happy man in having so many friends,
					asked him if he knew any certain way to try whether a
					man had many friends or not; and the other being earnest
					to be told, Namertes replied, Adversity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="56">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Nicander.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Nicander, when one told him that the Argives spake
					very ill of him, said, Well, they suffer for speaking ill of
					good men. And to one that enquired why they wore long
					hair and long beards, he answered, Because man's natural
					ornaments are the handsomest and the cheapest. An Athenian saying, Nicander, you Spartans are extremely idle;
					You say true, he answered, but we do not busy ourselves
					like you in every trifle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="57">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Panthoidas.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>When Panthoidas was ambassador in Asia and some
					showed him a strong fortification, Faith, said he, it is a
					fine cloister for women. In the Academy, when the philosophers had made a great many and excellent discourses,
					and asked Panthoidas how he liked them; Indeed, said he,
					I think them very good, but of no profit at all, since you
					yourselves do not use them.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.428"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="58">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Pausanias the Son of Cleombrotus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Pausanias the son of Cleombrotus, when the Delians
					pleaded their title to the island against the Athenians, and
					urged that according to their law no women were ever
					brought to bed or any carcass buried in the isle, said.
					How then can that be your country, in which not one of
					you was born or shall ever lie? The exiles urging him to
					march against the Athenians, and saying that, when he
					was proclaimed victor in the Olympic games, these alone
					hissed; How, says he, since they hissed whilst we did them
					good, what do you think they will do when abused? When
					one asked him why they made Tyrtaeus the poet a citizen,
					he answered, That no foreigner should be our captain. A
					man of a weak and puny body advising to fight the enemy
					both by sea and land; Pray, sir, says he, will you strip and
					show what a man you are who advise to engage? When
					some amongst the spoils of the barbarians admired the
					richness of their clothes; It had been better, he said, that
					they had been men of worth themselves than that they
					should possess things of worth. After the victory over
					the Medes at Plataea, he commanded his officers to set
					before him the Persian banquet that was already dressed;
					which appearing very sumptuous, By heaven, quoth he,
					the Persian is an abominable glutton, who, when he hath
					such delicacies at home, comes to eat our barley-cakes.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="59">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Pausanias the Son of Plistoanax.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Pausanias the son of Plistoanax replied to one that
					asked him why it was not lawful for the Spartans to abrogate any of their old laws, Because men ought to be subject to laws, and not the laws to men. When banished
					and at Tegea, he commended the Lacedaemonians. One
					said to him, Why then did you not stay at Sparta? And
					he returned, Physicians are conversant not amongst the
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.429"/>
					
					healthy, but the diseased. To one asking him how they
					should conquer the Thracians, he replied, If we make the
					best man our captain. A physician, after he had felt his
					pulse and considered his constitution, saying, He ails nothing; It is because, sir, he replied, I use none of your
					physic. When one of his friends blamed him for giving
					a physician an ill character, since he had no experience of
					his skill nor received any injury from him; No, faith, said
					he, for had I tried him, I had not lived to give this character. And when the physician said, Sir, you are an old man;
					That happens, he replied, because you were never my doctor. And he was used to say, that he was the best physician, who did not let his patients rot above ground, but
					quickly buried them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="60">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Paedaretus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Paedaretus, when one told him the enemies were numerous, said, Therefore we shall get the greater reputation, for
					we shall kill the more. Seeing a man soft by nature and
					a coward commended by the citizens for his lenity and good
					disposition, he said, We should not praise men that are like
					women, nor women that are like men, unless some extremity forceth a woman to stand upon her guard. When he
					was not chosen into the three hundred (the chief order in
					the city), he went away laughing and very jocund; and the
					Ephors calling him back and asking why he laughed, Why,
					said he, I congratulate the happiness of the city, that enjoys three hundred citizens better than myself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="61">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Plistarchus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Plistarchus the son of Leonidas, to one asking him why
					they did not take their names from the first kings replied,
					Because the former were rather captains than kings, but
					the later otherwise. A certain advocate using a thousand
					little jests in his pleading; Sir, said he, you do not consider
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.430"/>
					
					 that, as those that often wrestle are wrestlers at last,
					so you by often exciting laughter will become ridiculous
					yourself. When one told him that an notorious railer
					spoke well of him; I'll lay my life, said he, somebody hath
					told him I am dead, for he can speak well of no man
					living.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="62">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Plistoanax.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Plistoanax the son of Pausanias, when an Athenian
					orator called the Lacedaemonians unlearned fellows, said,
					'Tis true, for we alone of all the Greeks have not learned
					any ill from you.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="63">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Polydorus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Polydorus the son of Alcamenes, when one often threatened his enemies, said to him, Do not you perceive, sir,
					that you waste a great part of your revenge? As he
					marched his army against Messene, a friend asked him if
					he would fight against his brothers? No, said he, but I
					put in for an estate to which none, as yet, hath any good
					title. The Argives after the fight of the three hundred
					being totally routed in a set battle, the allies urged him not
					to let the opportunity slip, but storm and take the city of
					the enemy; for it would be very easy, now all the men
					were destroyed and none but women left. He replied: I
					love to vanquish my enemies when I fight on equal terms;
					nor do I think it just in him who was commissioned to
					contest about the confines of the two states, to desire to be
					master of the city; for I came only to recover our own
					territories and not to seize theirs. Being asked once
					why the Spartans ventured so bravely in battle; Because,
					said he, we have learned to reverence and not fear our
					leaders.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.431"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="64">
            <head>Of Polycratidas.</head>
            <p>Polycratidas being joined with others in an embassy to
					the lieutenants of the king, being asked whether they came
					as private or public persons, returned, If we obtain our
					demands, as public; if not, as private.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="65">
            <head>Of Phoebidas.</head>
            <p>Phoebidas, just before the battle at Leuctra, when some
					said, This day will show who is a brave man, replied, 'Tis
					a fine day indeed that can show a brave man alive.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="66">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Soos.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It is reported of Soos that, when his army was shut up
					by the Clitorians in a disadvantageous strait and wanted
					water, he agreed to restore all the places he had taken,
					if all his men should drink of the neighboring fountain.
					Now the enemy had secured the spring and guarded it.
					These articles being sworn to, he convened his soldiers,
					and promised to give him the kingdom who would forbear
					drinking; but none accepting it, he went to the water,
					sprinkled himself, and so departed, whilst the enemies
					looked on; and he therefore refused to restore the places,
					because he himself had not drunk.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="67">
            <head>
               <hi rend="italics">Of Telecrus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Telecrus, to one reporting that his father spake ill of
					him, replied, He would not speak so unless he had reason
					for it. When his brother said, The citizens have not that
					kindness for me they have for you, but use me more coarsely, though born of the same parents, he replied, You do
					not know how to bear an injury, and I do. Being asked
					what was the reason of that custom among the Spartans
					for the younger to rise up in reverence to the elder, Because, said he, by this behavior towards those to whom
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.432"/>
					
					they have no relation, they may learn to reverence their
					parents more. To one enquiring what wealth he had, he
					returned, No more than enough.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="68">
            <head>Of Charillus.</head>
            <p>Charillus being asked why Lycurgus made so few laws;
					Because, he replied, those whose words are few need but
					few laws. Another enquiring why their virgins appear in
					public unveiled, and their wives veiled; Because, said he,
					virgins ought to find husbands, married women keep those
					they have. To a slave saucily opposing him he said, I
					would kill thee if I were not angry. And being asked
					what polity he thought best; That, said he, in which most
					of the citizens without any disturbance contend about virtue. And to a friend enquiring why amongst them all the
					images of the Gods were armed he replied, That those
					reproaches we cast upon men for their cowardice may not
					reflect upon the Gods, and that our youth may not supplicate the Deities unarmed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="69">
            <head>The remarkable speeches of some obscure men amongst the Spartans.</head>
            <p>WHEN the Samian ambassadors had made a long harangue, the Spartans answered, We have forgot the first
					part, and so cannot understand the last. To the Thebans
					violently contesting with them about something they replied,
					Your spirit should be less, or your forces greater. A Lacedaemonian being asked why he kept his beard so long;
					That seeing my gray hairs, he replied, I may do nothing
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.433"/>
					
					but what becomes them. One commending the best warriors, a Spartan that overheard said, At Troy. Another,
					hearing that some forced their guests to drink after supper,
					said, What! not to eat too? Pindar in his poems having
					called Athens the prop of Greece, a Spartan said, Greece
					would soon fall if it leaned on such a prop. When one,
					seeing the Athenians pictured killing the Spartans, said,
					The Athenians are stout fellows; Yes, subjoined a Spartan,
					in a picture. To one that was very attentive to a scandalous accusation a Spartan said, Pray, sir, be not prodigal of
					your ears against me. And to one under correction that
					cried out, I offend against my will, another said, Therefore
					suffer against thy will. One seeing some journeying in a
					chariot said, God forbid that I should sit where I cannot
					rise up to reverence my elders. Some Chian travellers
					vomiting after supper in the consistory, and dunging in the
					very seats of the Ephors, first they made strict inquiry
					whether the offenders were citizens or not; but finding they
					were Chians, they publicly proclaimed that they gave the
					Chians leave to be filthy and uncivil.</p>
            <p>When one saw a merchant sell hard almonds at double
					the price that others were usually sold at, he said, Are
					stones scarce? Another pulling a nightingale, and finding
					but a very small body, said, Thou art voice and nothing
					else. Another Spartan, seeing Diogenes the Cynic in very
					cold weather embrace a brazen statue, asked whether he
					was not very cold; and he replying, No, he rejoined, What
					great matter then is it that you do? A Metapontine, being
					jeered by a Spartan for cowardice, replied, Nay, sir, we are
					masters of some of the territories of other states; Then, said
					the Spartan, you are not only cowards but unjust. A traveller at Sparta, standing long upon one leg, said to a Lacedaemonian, I do not believe you can do as much; True, said
					he, but every goose can. To one valuing himself upon
					his skill in oratory a Spartan said, By heaven, there never
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.434"/>
					
					was and never can be any art without truth. An Argive
					saying, We have the tombs of many Spartans amongst us;
					a Spartan replied, But we cannot show the grave of one
					Argive; meaning that they had often invaded Argos, but
					the Argives never Sparta. A Spartan that was taken captive and to be sold,&mdash;when the crier said, Here's a Spartan
					to be sold,&mdash;stopped his mouth, saying, Cry a captive. One
					of the soldiers of Lysimachus, being asked by him whether
					he was a true Spartanor one of the Helot slaves, replied,
					Do you imagine a Lacedaemonian would serve you for a
					groat a day? The Thebans, having beaten the Lacedaemonians at Leuctra, marched to the river Eurotas itself,
					where one of them boasting said, Where are the Spartans
					now? To whom a captive replied, They are not at hand,
					sir, for if they had been, you had not come so far. The
					Athenians, having surrendered their own city to the Spartans, requested that they might be permitted to enjoy Samos
					only; upon which the Spartans said, When you are not at
					your own disposal, would you be lords of others? And
					hence came that proverb, He that is not master of himself
					begs Samos.</p>
            <p>When the Lacedaemonians had taken a town by storm,
					the Ephors said, The exercise of our youth is lost, for now
					they will have none to contend with them. The Persian
					offering to raze a city that had frequent quarrels and skirmishes with the Spartans, they desired him to forbear and
					not take away the whetstone of their youth. They appointed no masters to instruct their boys in wrestling, that
					they might contend not in sleights of art and little tricks,
					but in strength and courage; and therefore Lysander,
					being asked by what means Charon was too hard for him,
					replied, By sleights and cunning. When Philip, having
					entered their territories, sent to know whether he should
					come as an enemy or a friend, the Spartans returned,
					Neither. Hearing that the ambassador they had sent to
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.435"/>
					
					Antigonus the son of Demetrius had called him king, they
					fined him, though he had obtained of him in a time of
					scarcity a bushel of wheat for every person in the city. A
					vicious person giving excellent good counsel, they received
					it, but took it from him and attributed it to another, a man
					regular and of a good life. When some brothers differed,
					they fined the father for neglecting his sons and suffering
					them to be at strife. They fined likewise a musician that
					came amongst them, for playing the harp with his fingers.
					Two boys fighting, one wounded the other mortally with a
					hook. And when his acquaintance, just as he was dying,
					vowed to revenge his death and have the blood of him that
					killed him; By no means, saith he, it is unjust, for I had
					done the same thing if I had been stout and more speedy
					in my stroke. Another boy, at the time when freemen's
					sons are allowed to steal what they can and it is a disgrace
					to be discovered, when some of his companions had stolen
					a young fox and delivered it to him, and the owners came
					to search, hid it under his gown; and though the angry
					little beast bit through his side to his very guts, he endured it quietly, that he might not be discovered. When
					the searchers were gone and the boys saw what had happened, they chid him roundly, saying, It had been better to
					produce the fox, than thus to conceal him by losing your
					own life; No, no! he replied, it is much better to die in
					torments, than to let my softness betray me and suffer a
					life thai had been scandalous. Some meeting certain
					Spartans upon the road said, Sirs, you have good luck, for
					the robbers are just gone. Faith, they replied, they have
					good luck that they did not meet with us. A Lacedaemonian, being asked what he knew, answered, To be free.
					A Spartan boy, being taken by Antigonus and sold, obeyed
					his master readily in every thing that he thought not below
					a freeman to do; but when he was commanded to bring a
					chamber-pot, unable to contain he said, I will not serve;
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.436"/>
					
					but his master pressing him, he ran to the top of the
					house, and saying, You shall find what you have bought,
					threw himself down headlong and died. Another being to
					be sold, when the chapman asked him, Wilt thou be towardly if I buy thee? Yes, he returned, and if you do not
					buy me. Another captive, when the crier said, Here's a
					slave to be sold, cried out, You villain, why not a captive?
					A Spartan, who had a fly engraven on his shield no bigger
					than Nature hath made that creature, when some jeered
					him as if he did it on purpose that he might not be taken
					notice of, replied: It is that I may be known; for I advance so near my enemies that they can well perceive my
					impress, as little as it is. Another, when at an entertainment a harp was brought in, said, It is not the custom of
					the Spartans to play the fool. A Spartan being asked
					whether the way to Sparta was safe or not, replied: That
					is according as you go down thither; for lions that approach rue their coming, and hares we hunt in their very
					coverts. A Spartan wrestling, when he could not make
					his adversary that had got the upper hand of him loose his
					hold, and was unable to avoid the fall, bit him by the arm;
					and the other saying, Spartan, thou bitest like a woman;
					No, said he, but like a lion. A lame man, marching out
					to war and being laughed at, said, There is no need of
					those that can run away, but of those that can stand to it
					and defend their post. Another being shot through said
					with his last breath: It doth not trouble me that I die, but
					that I should be killed by a woman before I had performed
					some notable exploit. One coming into an inn and giving
					the host a piece of meat to make ready for him,&mdash;when
					the host demanded some cheese and oil besides,&mdash;What!
					says the Spartan, if I had cheese should I want meat?
					When one called Lampis of Aegina happy, because he
					seemed a rich man, having many ships of his own at sea,
					a Spartan said, I do not like that happiness that hangs by
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.437"/>
					
					a cord. One telling a Spartan that he lied, the Spartan
					returned: True, for we are free; but others, unless they
					speak truth, will suffer for it. When one had undertaken
					to make a carcass stand upright, and tried every way to no
					purpose; Faith, said he, there wants something within.
					Tynnichus bore his son Thrasybulus's death very patiently.
					and there is this epigram made upon him:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Stout Thrasybulus on his shield was brought</l>
						            <l>From bloody fields, where he had bravely fought;</l>
						            <l>The Argives beat, and as he stoutly prest,</l>
						            <l>Seven spears, and Death attending, pierced his breast.</l>
						            <l>The father took the corpse, and as he bled,</l>
						            <l>He laid it on the funeral pile, and said:</l>
						            <l>Be cowards mourned, I'll spend no tear nor groan,</l>
						            <l>Whilst thus I burn a Spartan and my son.</l>
               </quote>
					
					The keeper of the bath allowing more water than ordinary
					to Alcibiades the Athenian, a Spartan said, What! is he
					more foul, that he wants more than others? Philip making an inroad upon Sparta, and all the Spartans expecting
					to be cut off, he said to one of them, Now what will you
					Spartans do? And he replied: What, but to die bravely?
					for only we of all the Greeks have learned to be free and
					not endure a yoke. When Agis was beaten and Antipater
					demanded fifty boys for hostages, Eteocles, one of the then
					Ephors, answered: Boys we will not give, lest swerving
					from the customs of their country they prove slothful and
					untoward, and so incapable of the privilege of citizens;
					but of women and old men you shall have twice as many.
					And when upon refusal he threatened some sharp afflictions, he returned: If you lay upon us somewhat worse
					than death, we shall die the more readily. An old man
					in the Olympic games being desirous to see the sport, and
					unprovided of a seat, went about from place to place, was
					laughed and jeered at, but none offered him the civility;
					but when he came to the Spartans' quarter, all the boys
					and some of the men rose from their seats, and made him
					room. At this, all the Greeks clapped and praised their
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.438"/>
					
					behavior; upon which the good old man shaking his hoary
					hairs, with tears in his eyes, said: Good God! how well
					all the Greeks know what is good, and yet only the Lacedaemonians practise it! And some say the same thing was
					done at Athens. For at the great solemnity of the Athenians, the Panathenaic festival, the Attics abused an old
					man, calling him as if they designed to make room for
					him, and when he came putting him off again; and when
					after this manner he had passed through almost all, he
					came to that quarter where the Spartan spectators sat, and
					all of them presently rose up and gave him place; the
					whole multitude, extremely taken with this action, clapped
					and shouted; upon which one of the Spartans said: By
					Heaven, these Athenians know what should be done, but
					are not much for doing it. A beggar asking an alms of a
					Lacedaemonian, he said: Well, should I give thee any
					thing, thou wilt be the greater beggar, for he that first gave
					thee money made thee idle, and is the cause of this base
					and dishonorable way of living. Another Spartan, seeing
					a fellow gathering charity for the Gods' sake, said, I will
					never regard those as Gods that are poorer than myself.
					Another, having taken one in adultery with an ugly whore,
					cried out, Poor man, how great was thy necessity! Another,
					hearing an orator very lofty and swelling in his speech,
					said, Faith, this is a brave man, how excellently he rolls
					his tongue about nothing! A stranger being at Sparta, and
					observing how much the young men reverenced the old,
					said, At Sparta alone it is desirable to be old. A Lacedaemonian, being asked what manner of poet Tyrtaeus was,
					replied, Excellent to whet the courage of our youth.
					Another that had very sore eyes listed himself a soldier;
					when some said to him, Poor man, whither in that condition, and what wilt thou do in a fight? He returned, If
					I can do nothing else, I shall blunt the enemies' sword.
					Buris and Spertis, two Lacedaemonians, going voluntarily
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.439"/>
					
					to Xerxes the Persian to suffer that punishment which the
					oracle had adjudged due to Sparta for killing those ambassadors the King had sent, as soon as they care desired
					Xerxes to put them to death as he pleased, that they
					might make satisfaction for the Spartans. But he, surprised at this gallantry, forgave the men and desired their
					service in his court; to which they replied, How can we
					stay here, and leave our country, our laws, and those men
					for whom we came so far to die? Indarnes the general
					pressing them to make peace, and promising them equal
					honors with the King's greatest favorites, they returned, Sir,
					you seem to be ignorant of the value of liberty, which no
					man in his wits would change for the Persian empire. A
					Spartan in a journey, when a friend of his had purposely
					avoided him the day before, and the next day, having obtained very rich furniture, splendidly received him, trampled
					on his tapestry saying, This was the cause why I had not
					so much as a mat to sleep upon last night. Another coming to Athens, and seeing the Athenians crying salt-fish and
					dainties to sell up and down the streets, others gathering
					taxes, keeping stews, and busied about a thousand such
					dishonest trades, and looking on nothing as base and unbecoming; after his return, when his acquaintance enquired
					how things were at Athens, he replied, All well; intimating by this irony that all things there were esteemed
					good and commendable, and nothing base. Another, being
					questioned about something, denied it; and the enquirer
					rejoining, Thou liest, he replied: And art not thou a fool
					to ask me what you know yourself very well? Some
					Lacedaemonians being sent ambassadors to the tyrant
					Lygdamis, pretending sickness he deferred their audience
					a long time. They said to one of his officers, Pray, sir,
					assure him that we did not come to wrestle but to treat
					with him. A priest initiating a Spartan in holy mysteries
					asked him what was the greatest wickedness he was ever
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.440"/>
					
					guilty of. And he replying, The Gods know very well,
					and the priest pressing him the more and saying he must
					needs discover, the Spartan asked, To whom? to thee or
					the God? And the priest saying, To the God, he rejoined,
					Then do you withdraw. Another at night passing by a
					tomb and imagining he saw a ghost, made towards it with
					his spear, and striking it through cried out, Whither dost
					thou fly, poor twice dead ghost? Another having vowed
					to throw himself headlong from the Leucadian rock, when
					he came to the top and saw the vast precipice, he went
					down again; upon which being jeered by an acquaintance,
					he said, I did not imagine that one vow needed another
					that was greater. Another in a battle had his sword lifted
					up to kill his enemy, but the retreat being sounded, he did
					not let the blow fall; and when one asked him why, when
					his enemy was at his mercy, he did not use the advantage,
					Because, said he, it is better to obey my leader than kill
					my enemy. One saying to a Spartan that was worsted in
					the Olympic games, Spartan, thy adversary was the better
					man; No, he replied, but the better tripper.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>