<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De cupiditate divitiarum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.103">
      <body>
         <head>Of the love of wealth.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.294"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>HIPPOMACHUS, a master of the exercises, when some
				were commending a tall man that had long hands as one
				that promised fair to be good at fisticuffs, replied, A fit man
				indeed, if the victor's laurel were to be hanged up aloft,
				and should be his that could best reach it and take it down.
				We may say the same to those that esteem so extravagantly
				and repute it so great a felicity to possess fair fields, stately
				mansion-houses, and a great deal of money lying by them,
				&mdash;that they were in the right, if happiness were to be
				bought and sold. You may see indeed many-persons that
				choose rather to be rich and at the same time very miserable, than to part with their money and become happy.
				But, alas! indolency and repose of spirit, magnanimity,
				constancy, resolution, and contentment of mind,&mdash;these
				are not a money-purchase. Being wealthy is not despising
				wealth; nor is possessing things superfluous the same as
				not needing things superfluous.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>From what other evils then can riches free us, if they
				deliver us not even from an inordinate desire of them? It
				is true, indeed, that by drinking men allay their thirst after
				drink, and by eating they satisfy their longings after food;
				and he that said,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bestow a coat, of your good will,
				</l>
                     <l>On poor Hipponax cold and chill</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>if more clothes had been heaped on than he needed,
					would have thrown them off, as being ill at ease. But the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.295"/>
					
					love of money is not abated by having silver and gold;
					neither do covetous desires cease by possessing still more.
					But one may say to wealth, as to an insolent quack,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Thy physic's nought, and makes my illness worse.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>When this distemper seizes a man that wants only bread
					and a house to put his head in, ordinary raiment and such
					victuals as come first to hand, it fills him with eager desires
					after gold and silver, ivory and emeralds, hounds and
					horses; thus taking off the appetite, and carrying it from
					things that are necessary after things that are troublesome
					and unusual, hard to come by, and unprofitable when obtained. For no man is poor as to what nature requires
					and what suffices it; no man takes up money on use to
					buy meal or cheese, bread or olives; but you may see one
					man run into debt for the purchase of a sumptuous house,
					another for an adjoining olive-yard, another for corn-fields
					or vineyards, another for Galatian mules, and another by a
					vain expense,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For horses fitly paired, with prancing feet
					</l>
                     <l>To draw the empty chariots through the street,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XV. 453.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>has been plunged over head and ears into contracts and
					use-money, pawns and mortgages. Moreover, as they that
					use to drink after they have quenched their thirst, and
					to eat after their hunger is satisfied, vomit up even what
					they took when they were athirst or hungry; so they
					that covet things useless and superfluous, enjoy not even
					those that are necessary. This is the character of these
					men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>As for those that spend nothing although they possess
				much, and yet are always craving more, they may still more
				increase our wonder at their folly, especially when one calls
				to mind that of Aristippus, who was wont to say, that when
				a man eats and drinks liberally and yet is never the nearer
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.296"/>
				
				being filled, he presently goes to the physician and enquires what is his disease and his indisposition and how
				he may get rid of it; but if one that has five beds desires
				ten, and having ten tables is for purchasing as many more,
				and having land and money in good store is not at all filled,
				but still is bent, even breaking his natural rest, upon getting more, and when he has never so much never has
				enough, this man thinks he has no need of a physician to
				cure him and to show him from what cause his distemper
				arises. Indeed, when a man is athirst that hath not drunk
				at all, we expect that upon his drinking his thirstiness
				should cease; but as for him that drinks and drinks and
				so goes on without giving over, we do not think such a one
				needs further repletion, but evacuation; and we advise him
				by all means to vomit, as knowing that his trouble proceeds not from the want of any thing, but from some sharp
				humor or preternatural heat that is within him.</p>
            <p>Among those persons, therefore, that are for increasing
					their substance and getting more, he that is poor and indigent may perhaps give over his cares when he has got a
					house or found a treasure, or, by a friend's help, has paid
					his debts and his creditors have discharged him. But as
					for him that, having more than enough, yet still desires to
					have, more, it is not gold nor silver, not horses, sheep, or
					oxen, that can cure him of this disease, but he needs evacuation and purgation. For his distemper is not penury
					and want, but an insatiable desire and thirst after riches,
					proceeding from a depraved and inconsiderate judgment of
					things, which if it be not plucked out of men's minds, like
					a thing twisting across and contracting them, they will
					always be in want of superfluities, that is, be craving things
					they have no need of.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>When a physician visits a patient that has thrown
				himself upon his bed and lies there groaning and refusing
				to eat, he feels his pulse and asks him some questions;
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.297"/>
				
				and finding that he is not at all feverish, he tells him it
				is his mind that is distempered, and goes his way. When
				we see therefore a man pining away for more means and
				sighing sadly at any expenses, forbearing no sordid or
				painful course that brings him gain, when yet he hath
				houses and lands, herds and slaves, and clothes enough,
				what shall we call this man's disease but poverty of mind?
				For as for want of money, one friend, as Menander says,
				by being a benefactor to him can cure it; but as to this
				other of the mind, all a man's friends, living or dead, cannot satisfy it. It was therefore a good saying of Solon
				concerning such persons:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Those men that after wealth aspire
				</l>
                     <l>Set no fixed bounds to their desire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>To those indeed that are wise, the riches that Nature
					requires are limited, and confined within the compass of
					their rear needs, as within a circle drawn from a centre
					at a certain distance.</p>
            <p>There is also this particular mischief in the love of
					wealth, that this desire hinders and opposes its own satisfaction, which other desires do procure. For no man
					abstains from a good morsel because he loves dainties,
					nor from wine because he thirsts after wine, as these men
					abstain from using money because they love money. Does
					it not look like madness and a piteous distemper, for a
					man not to make use of a garment because he shakes with
					cold, to refuse to eat bread because he is ready to famish
					with hunger, and not to use wealth because he is greedy
					of getting it? This is the evil case that Thrasonides describes: <q direct="unspecified">I have such a thing within by me, I have it in
						my power, and I will this thing (like those that are madly
						in love), but I do it not. When I have locked and sealed
						up all, or have told out so much to the usurers and tradesmen, I scrape together and hunt after more; I quarrel
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.298"/>
						
						and contend with the servants, the ploughmen and debtors. O Apollo, hast thou ever seen a more wretched man,
						or any lover more miserable?</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Sophocles being asked by one whether he was able
				yet to company with a woman; Heavens defend, said he,
				I have got my liberty, and by means of my old age have
				escaped those mad and furious masters. For it is very fit
				and becoming that, when our pleasures leave us, those
				desires should do so too, which, as Alcaeus says,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Twas never any man's good hap
				</l>
                     <l>Nor woman's wholly to escape.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But it is otherwise in the love of wealth, which, like a
					hard and severe mistress, compels us to get what it forbids us to enjoy, and excites an appetite but denies the
					pleasure of its gratification. Stratonicus wittily abused
					the Rhodians for their profuseness, when he said that they
					builded their houses as if they were immortal, but provided for their tables as if they were to live but a little
					while. So covetous men seem to be profuse by what they
					possess, when they are sordid wretches if you consider
					what they use and enjoy; for they endure labor, but taste
					no pleasure.</p>
            <p>Demades once came to Phocion's house and surprised
					him as he was at dinner; and when he saw his frugal
					and slender diet, I much wonder, Phocion, says he, that
					you should manage state affairs, and can dine as you do.
					For this orator himself pleaded causes and harangued the
					people only for his gut; and looking upon Athens as affording too little a supply for his luxury, he fetched his
					provisions from Macedonia. For which cause Antipater,
					seeing him when he was an old man, compared him to a
					sacrifice when all was over and there remained nothing of
					the beast but only the tongue and the stomach. But who
					would not wonder at thee, O wretched man, who, being
					able to live as thou dost,&mdash;so sordidly, so unlike a man,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.299"/>
					
					bestowing nothing on anybody, being currish to thy
					friends, and without any ambition to serve the public,&mdash;
					yet afflictest thyself and watchest whole nights, hirest out
					thy labors, liest at catch for inheritances, crouchest to
					every one, when thou art so well provided by thy sordid
					parsimony to live at ease?</p>
            <p>It is reported of a certain Byzantine, that, surprising a
					whoremaster with his wife that was very hard-favored, he
					cried out, O wretch, what compelled thee to do this?&mdash;for
					her dowry is my solace. It is necessary for kings, for procurators under them, for those that covet pre-eminence and
					rule over cities, that they should heap up treasure; they
					are forced through ambition, pride, and vain-glory to make
					feasts, to gratify friends, to maintain a retinue, to send
					presents, to feed armies, to purchase gladiators. But thou
					hast so much business lying upon thy hand, tormentest
					thyself, tumblest up and down, and all this while livest
					the life of a snail in thy shell through parsimony, and
					endurest all hardships, receiving no advantage at all; just
					like the bath-keeper's ass, that carries the wood and fuel
					for the fires and is always filled with the smoke and ashes
					of the stove, but itself is neither bathed nor warmed,
					washed nor cleansed there.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>I have said enough of this sort of covetousness, which
				makes a man live the life of an ass or ant. But there is
				another sort of it which is more savage, that calumniates
				and gets inheritance by bad arts, that pries into other
				men's affairs, that is full of thoughtfulness and cares,
				counting how many of their friends are yet alive, and
				after all enjoying nothing of what by all these arts has
				been heaped up.</p>
            <p>As therefore we have a greater aversion and hatred
					against vipers, poisonous flies, and spiders than against
					bears and lions, because they kill and destroy men, but
					serve themselves no farther of their carcasses, which they
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.300"/>
					
					do not feed upon as those other wild beasts do; so they
					that become bad and ill men through sordidness and parsimony deserve more of our abhorrence than those that
					prove such by luxurious living and excess, for they deprive others of what they are neither able nor inclined to
					make use of themselves. Hence it is that the luxurious,
					when they are rich and well provided, give some truce to
					their debaucheries; as Demosthenes said to some that
					were of opinion that Demades ceased to be an ill man.
					Now, says he, you see him full and glutted, like lions,
					that then hunt not after prey. But as for the others,
					who in the management of affairs propose no end to
					themselves either of pleasure or profit, their covetous desires have no truce or cessation, they being always empty
					and standing in need of all things.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>But some perhaps may plead on their behalf, that
				these men keep and hoard up their wealth for their children and heirs,&mdash;to whom they part with nothing whilst
				they are alive; but, like those mice that live in mines and
				pick up and eat the golden sands and ore, you cannot
				come by any of that gold, till you anatomize them to find
				it after they are dead. But to what end, I pray, would
				they leave such a deal of money and a great estate to
				their children and heirs? That they forsooth may preserve it also for others, and those others in like manner
				shall hand it down to their children (just like those
				earthen pipes the potters make for a water-course, which
				retain none of the water themselves, but one pipe only
				conveys it to the next), till some informing false accuser or
				tyrant appears and cuts off, this keeper in trust, and when
				his breath is stopped, derives and diverts the course of
				his wealth into another channel; or, as they say, till some
				one that is the most wicked of the race devours and consumes all that those who went before him had preserved.
				For not only, as Euripides says,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.301"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Children from slaves derived and baser blood
					</l>
                     <l>Prove prodigal and lewd, none come to good;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but it is as true of the children of the parsimonious; as
					Diogenes wittily abused this sort of men, when he said
					that it was better to be a certain Megarian's ram than his
					son. For, under the pretence of training them up and instructing them, they undo and pervert them, implanting in
					them their own love of money and meanness of spirit, and
					erecting as it were a fortress for the securing their inheritance in the minds of their heirs.</p>
            <p>For the instructions and lessons they give them are such
					as these: Gain as much and spend as little as may be;
					value yourself according to what you are worth. But certainly this is not to instruct, but to contract and sew them
					up, just like a purse, the better to conceal and keep what
					is put into it. The purse indeed becomes foul and musty
					after money is put up in it; but the children of the covetous, before they are enriched by their parents, are replenished with covetous desires which they derive from them.
					And indeed they pay them a deserved reward for their
					instructions, not loving them because they shall receive a
					great estate from them, but hating them because they have
					it not so soon as they fain would. For being taught to
					admire nothing but wealth, nor knowing any other end of
					living but to get a great estate, they account the life of
					their parents to be a hindrance to that of their own, and
					fancy so much time is taken from their own age as is added
					to theirs. Wherefore, whilst their parents are yet living,
					they secretly always steal their pleasures; and what they
					bestow upon their friends or spend upon their lusts, and
					even what they give to their teachers, is fetched as it were
					from another's estate, not from their own.</p>
            <p>But when their parents are dead and they are once
					possessed of their keys and seals, then their way of living
					is of another fashion, and they put on another face and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.302"/>
					
					aspect, grave, severe, and morose. You hear no more of
					their former pastimes, nor of exercises with the ball and
					in wrestling, nor of the Academy or the Lyceum: but they
					are wholly taken up in examining the servants, looking
					over writings, in debating matters with those that receive or
					owe them money. Their hurry of business and thoughtfulness will not give them leave to dine, and they are forced
					to make the night their time of bathing; the gymnastic
					schools in which they were educated and the water of Dirce
					are neglected. If any man ask him, Will you not go and
					hear the philosopher? How can I, says he, now that my
					father is dead? I am not at leisure. O miserable wretch!
					What has thy father left thee to be compared with what he
					has taken from thee, thy leisure and thy liberty? And
					yet it is not so much he that hath done it, as the wealth
					that flows round thee and overpowers thee, which, like the
					women Hesiod speaks of,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thee without firebrands burns, and unawares
					</l>
                     <l>Resigns thee up to dotage and gray hairs,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 703.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>bringing on thy soul those cares&mdash;like untimely wrinkles
					and old age&mdash;that spring from covetous desires and multiplicity of business, that shrivel up all thy vigor and
					gayety, all sense of honor, all kindness and humanity
					within thee.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But some will say, Do you not see rich men live
				splendidly and spend high? To whom we answer: Dost
				thou not hear what Aristotle says, that some there are that
				do not use wealth, and some that abuse it? For neither
				sort do what is fit and becoming; but what the one sort
				possess does neither advantage nor adorn them, and what
				the other sort have does both hurt and dishonor them.</p>
            <p>But let us further consider, What is the use of riches,
					for which men so much admire theme? Is it the enjoyment of what suffices nature? Alas! in this respect the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.303"/>
					
					wealthy have no advantage of those that are of a meaner
					fortune; but wealth (as Theophrastus says) is really no
					wealth and need not be coveted, if Callias, the richest man
					of Athens, and Ismenias, the wealthiest of Thebes, made
					use but of the same things that Socrates and Epaminondas
					did. For as Agathon sent away the music from the room
					where he feasted to the women's apartment, contenting
					himself with the discourses of his guests, so you would
					reject and send away the purple beds and the high prized
					tables and all other superfluous things, should you see that
					the rich make use of the same things with the poor.</p>
            <p>I do not mean thou shouldst presently
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hang up the rudder in the smoke at ease,
					</l>
                     <l>And let the mules' and oxen's labor cease;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 45.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but much rather the impertinent labor of goldsmiths, turners, perfumers, and cooks, when thou resolvest wisely and
					soberly to banish all useless things.</p>
            <p>But if the things that suffice nature lie in common
					among those that have and those that want riches,&mdash;if
					rich men pride themselves only in things superfluous, and
					thou art ready to praise Scopas of Thessaly, who, when one
					begged somewhat of him he had in his house, as a superfluous thing he had no use for, made answer, <q direct="unspecified">But we rich
						men count our felicity and happiness to lie in these superfluities, and not in those necessary things,</q>&mdash;if your case
					be thus, have a care you do not seem like one that magnifies and prefers a pomp and public show at a festival
					before life itself.</p>
            <p>Our country's feast of Bacchus was in old time celebrated in a more homely manner, though with great mirth
					and jollity. One carried in procession a vessel of wine and
					a branch of a vine, afterwards followed one leading a goat,
					another followed him bearing a basket of dried figs, and
					after all came a phallus. But all these are now despised
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.304"/>
					
					and out of date, the procession being made with golden
					vessels and costly garments, driving of chariots and persons
					in masquerade. And just thus the things that are necessary and useful in riches are swallowed up by those that
					are unprofitable and superfluous.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>The most of us commit the mistake of Telemachus.
				For he through inexperience, or rather want of good taste,
				when he saw Nestor's house furnished with beds and tables,
				garments and carpets, and well stored with sweet and
				pleasant wine, did not look upon him as so happy a man
				in being thus well provided with things necessary and
				useful; but when he beheld the ivory, gold, and amber
				in Menelaus's house, he cried out in amazement:&mdash;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such, and not nobler, in the realms above,
				</l>
                     <l>My wonder dictates is the dome of Jove.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IV. 74.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas Socrates or Diogenes would have said rather:&mdash;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What vain, vexatious, useless things I've seen,
					</l>
                     <l>And good for nothing but to move one's spleen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thou fool, what is it thou sayest? When thou oughtest to
					have stripped thy wife of her purple and gaudy attire, that
					she might cease to live luxuriously and to run mad after
					strangers and their fashions, instead of this, dost thou
					adorn and beautify thy house, that it may appear like a
					theatre or a stage to all comers?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>The happiness riches pretend to is such that it depends upon spectators and witnesses; else it would signify
				nothing at all. But it is quite otherwise when we consider
				temperance or philosophy, or such knowledge of the Gods
				as is requisite. For these, though unknown to all other
				mortals, communicate a peculiar light and great splendor
				within the soul, and cause a joy that dwells with it as an
				inmate, whilst it enjoys the chiefest good, though neither
				Gods nor men may be privy to it. Such a thing is truth, virtue, or the beauty of geometrical and astrological sciences;
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.305"/>
				
				and do riches, with their bravery and necklaces and all that
				gaudery that pleases girls, deserve to be compared with any
				of these? When nobody observes and looks on, riches are
				truly blind and deprived of light. For if a rich man makes
				a meal with his wife or familiars alone, he makes no stir
				about magnificent tables to eat on or golden cups to drink
				in, but uses those that come next to hand; and his wife,
				without any gold or purple to adorn her, presents herself
				in a plain dress. But when he makes a feast,&mdash;that is,
				when the pomp and theatre is to be fitted and prepared,
				and the scene of riches is to enter,&mdash;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then from the ships, with costly goods full fraught,
				</l>
                     <l>The trevets and the caldrons straight are brought;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See II. XXIII. 259.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>then they provide lamps, and much ado is made about the
					drinking-cups, they put the cup-bearers into a new dress,
					they bring forth whatever is made of gold and silver or set
					with precious stones, thus plainly declaring that they would
					be looked upon by all for rich men. But even though he
					should eat his meal alone, he wants hilarity of mind and
					that contentment which alone makes a feast.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>