<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De musica</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Pseudo-Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0094.002">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.102"/>
         <head>Concerning Music.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <head>Onesicrates, Soterichus, Lysias.</head>
            <p>
					          <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <p>No one will attempt to <hi rend="italics">study</hi> this treatise on music, without some previous
						knowledge of the principles of Greek music, with its various moods, scales, and
						combinations of tetrachords. The whole subject is treated by Boeckh, <hi rend="italics">De Metris
							Pindari</hi> (in Vol. I. 2 of his edition of Pindar); and more at length in Westphal's
						<hi rend="italics">Harmonik und Melop&ouml;ie der Griechen</hi> (in Rossbach and Westphal's <hi rend="italics">Metrik,</hi> Vol. II. 1).</p>
						            <p>An elementary explanation of the ordinary scale and of the names of the notes
							(which are here retained without any attempt at translation) may be of use to the
							reader.</p>
						            <p>The most ancient scale is said to have had only four notes, corresponding to the
							four strings of the tetrachord. But before Terpander's time two forms of the
							heptachord (with seven strings) were already in use. One of these was enlarged to
							an octachord (with eight strings) by adding the octave (called <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign>). This addition
							is ascribed to Terpander by Plutarch (&sect;28); but he is said to have been unwilling
							to increase the number of strings permanently to eight, and to have therefore omitted
							the string called <foreign lang="greek">tri/th,</foreign> thus reducing the octachord again to a heptachord. The notes
							of the full octachord in this form, in the ordinary diatonic scale, are as follows:&mdash;
							
							<table>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">e</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">parupa/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">f</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">lixano/s</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">g</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">me/sh</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">a</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">parame/sh</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">b</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">tri/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">c</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">paranh/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">d</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">8</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">e</hi> (octave)</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
						
						            <p>The note called <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/th</foreign> (hypate, or highest) is the lowest in tone, being named from
							its position. So <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign> or <foreign lang="greek">nea/th</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">lowest</hi>) is the highest in tone.</p>
						            <p>The other of the two heptachords mentioned above contained the octave, but
							omitted the <foreign lang="greek">parame/sh</foreign> and had other changes in the higher notes. The scale is as
							follows:-
							
							<table>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">e</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">parupa/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">f</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">lixano/s</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">g</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">me/sh</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">a</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">tri/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">b</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">paranh/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">c</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                              <hi rend="italics">d</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
							This is not to be confounded with the reduced octachord of Terpander. This
							heptachord includes two tetrachords so united that the lowest note of one is identical
							with the highest note of the other; while the octachord includes two tetracllords
							entirely separated, with each note distinct. The former connection is called
							<foreign lang="greek">kata\ sunafh/n,</foreign> the latter <foreign lang="greek">kata\ dia/zeucin.</foreign> Of the eight notes of the octachord,
							the first four (counting from the lowest), <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/th, parupa/th, lixano/s</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">me/sh,</foreign> are the
							same in the heptachord; <foreign lang="greek">parame/sh</foreign> is omitted in the heptachord; while <foreign lang="greek">tri/th, paranh/th,</foreign>
							and <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign> in the heptachord are designated as <foreign lang="greek">tri/th sunhmme/nwn, paranh/th sunhmme/nwn,</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">nh/th sunhmme/nwn,</foreign> to distinguish them from the notes of the same
							name in the octachord, which sometimes have the designation <foreign lang="greek">diezeugme/nwn,</foreign> but generally are written simply <foreign lang="greek">tri/th,</foreign> &amp;c.</p>
						            <p>These simple scales were enlarged by the addition of higher and lower notes,
							four at the bottom of the scale (i.e. before <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/th</foreign>), called <foreign lang="greek">proslambano/menos, u(pa/th u(patw=n, parupa/th u(patw=n, lixano/s u(patw=n;</foreign> and three at the top (above <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign>), called <foreign lang="greek">nh/th, paranh/th, tri/th,</foreign>
							each with the designation <foreign lang="greek">u(perbolai/wn.</foreign> The lowest three notes
							of the ordinary octachord are here designated by <foreign lang="greek">me/swn,</foreign> when the simple names are
							not used. Thus a scale of fifteen notes was made; and we have one of eighteen by
							including the two classes of <foreign lang="greek">tri/th, paranh/th,</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">nh/th</foreign> designated by <foreign lang="greek">sunhmme/nwn</foreign> and
							<foreign lang="greek">diezeugme/nwn.</foreign>
                  </p>
						            <p>The harmonic intervals, discovered by Pythagoras, are the <hi rend="italics">Octave</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">dia\ pasw=n,</foreign>) with
							its ratio of 2:1; the <hi rend="italics">Fifth</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">dia\ pe/nte</foreign>), with its ratio of 3: 2 (<foreign lang="greek">lo/gos h(mio/lios</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">Sesquialter</hi>); the <hi rend="italics">Fourth</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">dia\ tessa/rwn</foreign>), with its ratio of 4: 3 (<foreign lang="greek">lo/gos e)pi/tritos</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">Sesquilerce</hi>);
							and the <hi rend="italics">Tone</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">to/nos</foreign>), with its ratio of 9: 8 (<foreign lang="greek">lo/gos e)po/gdoos</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">Sesquioctave</hi>). (G.)</p>
					          </note>
					THE wife of Phocion the just was always wont to
					maintain that her chiefest glory consisted in the warlike
					achievements of her husband. For my part, I am of
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.103"/>
					
					opinion that all my glory, not only that peculiar to myself,
					but also what is common to all my familiar friends and relations, flows from the care and diligence of my master that
					taught me learning. For the most renowned performances
					of great commanders tend only to the preservation of some
					few private soldiers or the safety of a single city or nation,
					but make neither the soldiers nor the citizens nor the
					people any thing the better. But true learning, being
					the essence and body of felicity and the source of prudence, we find to be profitable and beneficial, not only to
					one house or city or nation, but to all the race of men.
					Therefore by how much the more the benefit and advantage of learning transcends the profits of military performances, by so much the more is it to be remembered and
					mentioned, as most worthy your study and esteem.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>For this reason, upon the second day of the Saturnalian
				festival, the famous Onesicrates invited certain persons, the
				best skilled in music, to a banquet; by name Soterichus
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.104"/>
				
				of Alexandria, and Lysias, one of those to whom he gave
				a yearly pension. After all had done and the table was
				cleared,&mdash;To dive, said he, most worthy friends, into the
				nature and reason of the human voice is not an argument
				proper for this merry meeting, as being a subject that
				requires a more sober scrutiny. But because our chiefest
				grammarians define the voice to be a percussion of the air
				made sensible to the ear, and for that we were yesterday
				discoursing of Grammar,&mdash;which is an art that can give
				the voice form and shape by means of letters, and store it
				up in the memory as a magazine,&mdash;let us consider what
				is the next science to this which may be said to relate to
				the voice. In my opinion, it must be music. For it is
				one of the chiefest and most religious duties belonging to
				man, to celebrate the praise of the Gods, who gave to him
				alone the most excelling advantage of articulate discourse,
				as Homer has observed in the following verses:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>With sacred hymns and songs that sweetly please,</l>
					             <l>The Grecian youth all day the Gods appease;</l>
					             <l>Their lofty paeans bright Apollo hears,</l>
					             <l>And still the charming sounds delight his ears.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. I. 472.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now then, you that are of the grand musical chorus,
					tell your friends, who was the first that brought music
					into use; what time has added for the advantage of the
					science; who have been the most famous of its professors;
					and lastly, for what and how far it may be beneficial to
					mankind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>This the scholar propounded; to which Lysias made
				reply. Noble Onesicrates, said he, you desire the solution
				of a hard question, that has been by many already proposed. For of the Platonics the most, of the Peripatetic
				philosophers the best, have made it their business to compile several treatises concerning the ancient music and the
				reasons why it came to lose its pristine perfection. Nay,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.105"/>
				
				the very grammarians and musicians themselves who arrived to the height of education have expended much time
				and study upon the same subject, whence has arisen great
				variety of discording opinions among the several writers.
				Heraclides in his Compendium of Music asserts, that
				Amphion, the son of Jupiter and Antiope, was the first
				that invented playing on the harp and lyric poesy, being
				first instructed by his father; which is confirmed by a small
				manuscript, preserved in the city of Sicyon, wherein is set
				down a catalogue of the priests, poets, and musicians of
				Argos. In the same age, he tells us, Linus the Euboean
				composed several elegies; Anthes of Anthedon in Boeotia
				was the first author of hymns, and Pierus of Pieria the first
				that wrote in the praise of the Muses. Philammon also, the
				Delphian, set forth in verse a poem in honor of the nativity
				of Latona, Diana, and Apollo, and was the first that instituted dancing about the temple of Delphi. Thamyras, of
				Thracian extraction, had the best voice and the neatest
				manner of singing of any of his time; so that the poets
				feigned him to be a contender with the Muses. He is said
				to have described in a poem the Titans' war against the
				Gods. There was also Demodocus the Corcyraean, who is
				said to have written the Destruction of Troy, and the Nuptials of Vulcan and Venus; and then Phemius of Ithaca
				composed a poem, entitled The Return of those who came
				back with Agamemnon from Troy. Not that any of these
				stories before cited were compiled in a style like prose
				without metre; they were rather like the poems of Stesichorus and other ancient lyric poets, who composed in
				heroic verse and added a musical accompaniment. The
				same Heraclides writes that Terpander, the first that instituted the lyric <hi rend="italics">nomes,</hi>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">According to K. O. M&uuml;ller (History of Greek Literature, Chap. XII &sect; 4), the
					<hi rend="italics">nomes</hi> were <q direct="unspecified">musical compositions of great simplicity and severity, something resembling the most ancient melodies of our church music.</q> (G.)</note> set verses of Homer as well as his
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.106"/>
				
				own to music according to each of these nomes, and sang
				them at public trials of skill. He also was the first to give
				names to the lyric nomes. In imitation of Terpander, Clonas, an elegiac and epic poet, first instituted nomes for
				flute-music, and also the songs called Prosodia.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*proso/dia</foreign> were songs sung to the music of flutes by processions, as they marched
					to temples or altars; hence, songs of supplication. (G.)</note> And
				Polymnestus the Colophonian in later times used the same
				measure in his compositions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Now the measures appointed by these persons, noble
				Onesicrates, in reference to such songs as are to be sung
				to the flutes or pipes, were distinguished by these names,
				&mdash;Apothetus, Elegiac, Comarchius, Schoenion, Cepion,
				Tenedius, and Trimeles (or of three parts).</p>
            <p>To these succeeding ages added another sort, which were
					called Polymnastia. But the measures set down for those
					that played and sung to the harp, being the invention of
					Terpander, were much more ancient than the former. To
					these he gave the several appellations of Boeotian, Aeolian,
					Trochaean, the Acute, Cepion, Terpandrian, and Tetraoedian.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Rossbach and Westphal, II. 1, p. 84. (G.)</note> And Terpander made preludes to be sung to the
					lyre in heroic verse. Besides, Timotheus testifies how that
					the lyric nomes were anciently appropriated to epic verses.
					For Timotheus merely intermixed the dithyrambic style
					with the ancient nomes in heroic measure, and thus sang
					them, that he might not seem to make too sudden an innovation upon the ancient music. But as for Terpander, he
					seems to have been the most excellent composer to the
					harp of his age, for he is recorded to have been four times
					in succession a victor at the Pythian games. And certainly
					he was one of the most ancient musicians in the world;
					for Glaucus the Italian in his treatise of the ancient poets
					and musicians asserts him to have lived before Archilochus,
					affirming him to be the second next to those that first invented wind-music.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.107"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Alexander in his Collections of Phrygia says, that
				Olympus was the first that brought into Greece the manner of touching the strings with a quill; and next to him
				were the Idaean Dactyli; Hyagnis was the first that sang
				to the pipe; after him his son Marsyas, then Olympus;
				that Terpander imitated Homer in his verses and Orpheus in his musical compositions; but that Orpheus never
				imitated any one, since in his time there were none but
				such as composed to the pipe, which was a manner quite
				different from that of Orpheus. Clonas, a composer of
				nomes for flute-music, and somewhat later than Terpander, as the Arcadians affirm, was born in Tegea or, as the
				Boeotians allege, at Thebes. After Terpander and Clonas
				flourished Archilochus; yet there are some writers who
				affirm, that Ardalus the Troezenian taught the manner of
				composing to wind-music before Clonas. There was also the
				poet Polymnestus, the son of Meles the Colophonian, who
				invented the Polymnestian measures. They farther write
				that Clonas invented the nomes Apothetus and Schoenion.
				Of Polymnestus mention is made by Pindar and Alcman,
				both lyric poets; but of several of the lyric nomes said to
				be instituted by Terpander they make Philammon (the ancient Delphian) author.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Now the music appropriated to the harp, such as it
				was in the time of Terpander, continued in all its simplicity, till Phrynis grew into esteem. For it was not the
				ancient custom to make lyric poems in the present style, or
				to intermix measures and rhythms. For in each nome
				they were careful to observe its own proper pitch; whence
				came the expression <hi rend="italics">nome</hi> (from <foreign lang="greek">no/mos,</foreign> 
               <hi rend="italics">law</hi>), because it was
				unlawful to alter the pitch appointed for each one. At
				length, falling from their devotion to the Gods, they began
				to sing the verses of Homer and other poets. This is
				manifest by the proems of Terpander. Then for the form
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.108"/>
				
				of the harp, it was such as Cepion, one of Terpander's
				scholars, first caused to be made, and it was called the Asian
				harp, because the Lesbian harpers bordering upon Asia
				always made use of it. And it is said that Periclitus, a
				Lesbian by birth, was the last harper who won a prize by
				his skill, which he did at one of the Spartan festivals called
				Carneia; but he being dead, that succession of skilful musicians, which had so long continued among the Lesbians,
				expired. Some there are who erroneously believe that
				Hipponax was contemporary with Terpander, when it is
				plain that Hipponax lived after Periclitus.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Having thus discoursed of the several nomes appropriated to the stringed as well as to the wind instruments,
				we will now speak something in particular concerning
				those peculiar to the wind instruments. First they say,
				that Olympus, a Phrygian player upon the flute, invented
				a certain nome in honor of Apollo, which he called Polycephalus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This seems to be the nome referred to by Pindar, Pyth. XII. 12, as the invention
					of Pallas Athena. The Scholia on the passage of Pindar tell us that the goddess
					represented it in the lamentation of the two surviving Gorgons for their sister Medusa slain by Perseus, and the hissing of the snakes which surrounded their heads,&mdash;
					whence the name <foreign lang="greek">poluke/falos,</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">many-headed.</hi> (G.)</note> or of many heads. This Olympus, they say,
				was descended from the first Olympus, the scholar of Marsyas, who invented several forms of composition in honor
				of the Gods; and he, being a boy beloved of Marsyas, and
				by him taught to play upon the flute, first brought into
				Greece the laws of harmony. Others ascribe the Polycephalus to Crates, the scholar of Olympus; though Pratinas will have Olympus the younger to be the author of it.
				The Harmatian nome is also said to be invented by Olympus,
				the scholar of Marsyas. This Marsyas was by some said
				to be called Masses; which others deny, not allowing him
				any other name but that of Marsyas, the son of that Hyagnis
				who invented the art of playing upon the pipe. But that
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.109"/>
				
				Olympus was the author of the Harmatian nome is plainly
				to be seen in Glaucus's treatise of the ancient poets; and
				that Stesichorus of Himera imitated neither Orpheus nor
				Terpander nor Antilochus nor Thales, but Olympus, and
				that he made use of the Harmatian nome and the dactylic
				dance, which some rather apply to the Orthian mood, while
				others aver it to have been the invention of the Mysians,
				for that some of the ancient pipers were Mysians.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>There was also another mood in use among the ancients, called Cradias, which Hipponax says Mimnermus
				always delighted in. For formerly they that played upon
				the flute sang also elegies at the same time set to notes.
				Which the description of the Panathenaea concerning the
				musical combat makes manifest. Among the rest, Sacadas
				of Argos set several odes and elegies to music, he himself
				being also a good flute-player and thrice a victor at the
				Pythian games. Of him Pindar makes mention. Now
				whereas in the time of Polymnestus and Sacadas there
				existed three musical moods, the Dorian, Phrygian, and
				Lydian, it is said that Sacadas composed a strophe in every
				one of those moods, and then taught the choruses to sing
				the first after the Dorian manner, the second according to
				the Phrygian, and the third after the Lydian manner; and
				this nome was called Trimeres (or threefold) by reason of
				the shifting of the moods, although in the Sicyonian catalogue of the poets Clonas is said to be the inventor of this
				name.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Music then received its first constitution from Terpander at Sparta. Of the second constitution, Thaletas the
				Gortinean, Xenodamus the Cytherean, Xenocritus the Locrian, Polymnestus the Colophonian, and Sacadas the
				Argive were deservedly acknowledged to be the authors.
				For these, having introduced the Gymnopaediae into Lacedaemon, settled the so-called Apodeixeis (or Exhibitions)
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.110"/>
				
				among the Arcadians, and the Endymatia in Argos. Now
				Thaletas, Xenodamus, and Xenocritus, and their scholars,
				were poets that addicted themselves altogether to making
				of paeans; Polymnestus was all for the Orthian or military
				strain, and Sacadas for elegies. Others, and among the
				rest Pratinas, affirm Xenodamus to have been a maker of
				songs for dances (Hyporchemes), and not of paeans; and a
				tune of Xenodamus is preserved, which plainly appears to
				have been composed for a dance. Now that a paean differs
				from a song made for a dance is manifest from the poems
				of Pindar, who made both.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Polymnestus also composed nomes for flute-music;
				but in the Orthian nome he made use of his lyric vein, as
				the students in harmony declare. But in this we cannot
				be positive, because we have nothing of certainty concerning it from antiquity; and whether Thaletas of Crete was
				a composer of hymns is much doubted. For Glaucus,
				asserting Thaletas to be born after Archilochus, says that he
				imitated the odes of Archilochus, only he made them longer,
				and used the Paeonic and Cretic rhythm, which neither
				Archilochus nor Orpheus nor Terpander ever did; for
				Thaletas learned these from Olympus, and became a good
				poet besides. As for Xenocritus the Locrian from Italy,
				it is much questioned whether he was a maker of paeans
				or not, as being one that always took heroic subjects with
				dramatic action for his verses, for which reason some
				there were who called his arguments Dithyrambic. More
				over, Glaucus asserts Thaletas to have preceded him in
				time.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Olympus, by the report of Aristoxenus, is supposed
				by the musicians to have been the inventor of the enharmonic species of music; for before him there was no other
				than the diatonic and chromatic. And it is thought that
				the invention of the enharmonic species was thus brought
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.111"/>
				
				to pass:<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <p>The relations of the enharmonic scale to the ordinary diatonic are thus stated
					by Westphal (pp. 124&ndash;126), <hi rend="italics">b</hi> being here substituted for the German <hi rend="italics">h:</hi>&mdash;
					
					<!--<figure><head>Figure</head></figure>--></p>
					
					             <p>The <foreign lang="greek">d</foreign> inserted between <hi rend="italics">e</hi> and <hi rend="italics">f</hi> and between <hi rend="italics">b</hi> and <hi rend="italics">c</hi> is called <hi rend="italics">diesis,</hi> and represents
						a quarter-tone. The section in Westphal containing this scheme will greatly aid the
						interpretation of &sect; 11 of Plutarch. (G.)</p>
               </note> for that Olympus before altogether composing and
				playing in the diatonic species, and having frequent occasion to shift to the diatonic parhypate, sometimes from the
				paramese and sometimes from the mese, skipping the diatonic lichanos, he found the beauty that appeared in the
				new character; and thus, admiring a conjunction or scheme
				so agreeable to proportion, he made this new species in the
				Doric mood. For now he held no longer to what belonged
				either to the diatonic or to the chromatic, but he was
				already come to the enharmonic. And the first foundations
				of enharmonic music which he laid were these: in enharmonics the first thing that appears is the spondiasmus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is Volkmann's conjecture for <q direct="unspecified">spondee.</q> It is defined by him (according
					to Aristides Quintilianus) as the raising of the tone through three dieses (or quartertones). (G.)</note> to
				which none of the divisions of the tetrachord seems properly to belong, unless any one will take the more intense
				spondiasmus to be diatonic. But he that maintained this
				would maintain a falsehood and an absurdity in harmony;
				a falsehood, because it would be less by a diesis than is
				required by the leading note; an absurdity in harmony,
				because, even if we should place the proper nature of the
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.112"/>
				
				more intense spondiasmus in the simple chromatic, it would
				then come to pass, that two double tones would follow in
				order, the one compounded, the other uncompounded.
				For the thick enharmonic now used in the middle notes
				does not seem to be the invention of the fore-mentioned
				author. But this is more easily understood by hearing any
				musician play in the ancient style; for then you shall find
				the semi-tone in the middle parts to be uncompounded.</p>
            <p>These were the beginnings of enharmonic music; afterwards the semitone was also divided, as well in the Phrygian as Lydian moods. But Olympus seems to have
					advanced music by producing something never known or
					heard of before, and to have gained to himself the honor
					of being the most excellent, not only in the Grecian but in
					all other music.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Let us now proceed to rhythms; for there were
				several varieties of these, as well in musical as in rhythmical composition. And here Terpander, among all those
				novelties with which he adorned music, introduced an
				elegant manner, that gave it much life. After him, beside
				the Terpandrian, which he did not relinquish, Polymnestus
				brought in use another of his own, retaining however the
				former elegant manner, as did also Thaletas and Sacadas.
				Other innovations were also made by Alkman and Stesichorus,
				who nevertheless receded not from the ancient forms. But
				Crexus, Timotheus, and Philoxenus, and those other poets
				of the same age, growing more arrogant and studious of
				novelty, affected those other manners now called Philanthropic and Thematic. For now the fewness of strings and
				the plainness and majesty of the old music are looked upon
				as absolutely out of date.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>And now, having discoursed to the best of my ability
				of the ancient music and the first inventors of it, and how
				succeeding ages brought it to more and more perfection, I
				shall make an end, and give way to my friend Soterichus,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.113"/>
				
				not only greatly skilled in music but in all the rest of the
				sciences. For we have always labored rather on the practical than the contemplative part. Which when Lysias
				had said, he forbare speaking any farther; but then Soterichus thus began.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Most noble Onesicrates, said he, since you have
				engaged us to speak our knowledge concerning the most
				venerable excellencies of music, which is most pleasing to
				the Gods, I cannot but approve the learning of our master
				Lysias, and his great memory in reciting all the inventors
				of the ancient music, and those who have written concerning it. But I must needs say, that he has given us this
				account, trusting only to what he has found recorded. We
				on the other side have not heard of any man that was the
				inventor of the benefits of music, but of the God Apollo,
				adorned with all manner of virtue. The flute was neither
				the invention of Marsyas nor Olympus nor Hyagnis; nor
				was the harp Apollo's invention only, but as a God he was
				the inventor of all the music both of the flute and harp.
				This is manifest from the dances and sacrifices which were
				solemnized to Apollo, as Alcaeus and others in their hymns
				relate. His statue also placed in the Temple of Delos
				holds in his right hand a bow; at his left the Graces stand,
				with every one a musical instrument in her hands, one carrying a harp, another a flute, another with a shepherd's
				pipe set to her lips. And that this is no conceit of mine
				appears from this, that Anticles and Ister have testified the
				same in their commentaries upon these things. And the
				statue is reported to be so ancient, that the artificers were
				said to have lived in the time of Hercules. The youth
				also that carries the Tempic laurel into Delphi is accompanied by one playing upon the flute. And the sacred
				presents of the Hyperboreans were sent of old to Delos,
				attended with flutes, pipes, and harps. Some have thought
				that the God himself played upon the flute, as the best of
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.114"/>
				
				lyrics, Alcman, relates. Corinna also asserts that Apollo
				was by Minerva taught to pipe. Venerable is therefore
				music altogether, as being the invention of the Gods.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>The ancients made use of it for its worth, as they
				did all other beneficial sciences. But our men of art, contemning its ancient majesty, instead of that manly, grave,
				heaven-born music, so acceptable to the Gods, have brought
				into the theatres a sort of effeminate musical tattling, mere
				sound without substance; which Plato utterly rejects in the
				third book of his commonwealth, refusing the Lydian harmony as fit only for lamentations. And they say that this
				was first instituted for doleful songs. Aristoxenus, in his first
				book of music, tells us how that Olympus sang an elegy
				upon the death of Python in the Lydian mood, though
				some will have Menalippides to be the author of that song.
				Pindar, in his paean on the nuptials of Niobe, asserts that
				the Lydian harmony was first used by Anthippus. Others
				affirm, that Torebus was the first that made use of that
				sort of harmony; among the rest, Dionysius the iambic
				writer.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>The mixed Lydian moves the affections, and is fit
				for tragedies. This mood, as Aristoxenus alleges, was
				invented by Sappho, from whom the tragedians learned it
				and joined it with the Doric. The one becomes a majestic,
				lofty style, the other mollifies and stirs to pity; both which
				are the properties of tragedy. The history of music, however, made Pythoclides the flute-player to be the author of
				it; and Lysis reports that Lamprocles the Athenian, finding
				that the diazeuxis (or separation of two tetrachords) was
				not where almost all others thought it had been, but toward
				the treble, made such a scheme as is now from paramese to
				the highest hypate. But for the softer Lydian, being contrary to the mixed Lydian and like the Ionian, they say it
				was invented by Damon the Athenian.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>But as for those sorts of harmony, the one being
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.115"/>
				
				sad and doleful, the other loose and effeminate, Plato deservedly rejected them, and made choice of the Dorian, as
				more proper for sober and warlike men; not being ignorant, however (as Aristoxenus discourses in his second
				book of music), that there might be something advantageous in the rest to a circumspect and wary commonwealth.
				For Plato gave much attention to the art of music, as being
				the hearer of Draco the Athenian and Metellus the Agrigentine; but considering, as we have intimated before, that
				there was much more majesty in the Dorian mood, it was
				that he preferred. He knew moreover that Alcman, Pindar,
				Simonides, and Bacchylides had composed several Parthenia
				in the Doric mood; and that several Prosodia (or supplications to the Gods), several hymns and tragical lamentations, and now and then love verses, were composed to the
				same melody. But he contented himself with such songs
				as were made in honor of Mars or Minerva, or else such
				as were to be sung at solemn offerings, called Spondeia.
				For these he thought sufficient to fortify and raise the mind
				of a sober person; not being at all ignorant in the mean
				time of the Lydian and Ionian, of which he knew the tragedians made use.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Moreover, the ancients well understood all the sorts
				of styles, although they used but few. For it was not their
				ignorance that confined them to such narrow instruments
				and so few strings; nor was it out of ignorance that Olympus and Terpander and those that came after them would
				not admit of larger instruments and more variety of strings.
				This is manifest from the poems of Olympus and Terpander and all those that were their imitators. For, being
				plain and without any more than three strings, these
				so far excelled those that were more numerously strung,
				insomuch that none could imitate Olympus's play; and they
				were all inferior to him when they betook themselves to
				their polychords.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.116"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Then again, that the ancients did not through ignorance abstain from the third string in the spondaic style,
				their use of it in play makes apparent. For had they not
				known the use of it, they would never have struck it in
				harmony with parhypate; but the elegancy and gravity that
				attended the spondaic style by omitting the third string induced them to transfer the music to paranete. The same
				reason may serve for nete; for this in play they struck in
				concord to mese, but in discord to paranete, although in
				song it did not seem to them proper to the slow spondaic
				motion. And not only did they do this, but they did the
				same with nete of the conjunct heptachords; for in play
				they struck it in concord to mese and lichanos, and in discord
				to paranete and parhypate;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Westphal's interpretation of this difficult and probably corrupt passage, II.
					,p.89. (G.)</note> but in singing those touches
				were no way allowable, as being ungrateful to the ear
				and shaming the performer. As certain it is from the
				Phrygians that Olympus and his followers were not ignorant of the third string; for they made use of it not only
				in pulsation, but in their hymns to the Mother of the Gods
				and several other Phrygian songs. Nor is it less apparent,
				with regard to the <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/tai</foreign>, that they never abstained for
				want of skill from that tetrachord in the Dorian mood;
				indeed in other moods they knowingly made use of it, but
				removed it from the Dorian mood to preserve its elegant
				gravity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>The same thing was done also by the tragedians.
				For the tragedians have never to this day used either the
				chromatic or the enharmonic scale; while the lyre, many
				generations older than tragedy, used them from the very
				beginning. Now that the chromatic was more ancient
				than the enharmonic is plain. For we must necessarily
				account it of greater antiquity, according to the custom and
				use of men themselves; otherwise it cannot be said that
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.117"/>
				
				any of the differences and distinctions were ancienter
				the one than the other. Therefore, if any one should
				allege that Aeschylus or Phrynichus abstained from the
				chromatic out of ignorance, would he not be thought to
				maintain a very great absurdity? Such a one might as well
				aver that Pancrates lay under the same blindness, who
				avoided it in most, but made use of it in some things;
				therefore he forebore not out of ignorance, but judgment,
				imitating Pindar and Simonides and that which is at present
				called the ancient manner.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>The same may be said of Tyrtaeus the Mantinean,
				Andreas the Corinthian, Thrasyllus the Phliasian, and
				several others, who, as we well know, abstained by choice
				from the chromatic, from transition, from the increased
				number of strings, and many other common forms of
				rhythms, tunes, diction, composition, and expression. Telephanes of Megara was so great an enemy to the pipe made
				of reed (called syrinx), that he would not suffer the instrument maker to join it to the flute (pipe made of wood or
				horn), and chiefly for that reason forbore to go to the Pythian games. In short, if a man should be thought to be
				ignorant of that which he makes no use of, there would
				be found a great number of ignorant persons in this age.
				For we see that the admirers of the Dorian composition
				make no use of the Antiginedian; the followers of the Antiginedian reject the Dorian; and other musicians refuse
				to imitate Timotheus, being almost all bewitched with the
				trifles and the idle poems of Polyidus. On the other
				side, if we dive into the business of variety and compare
				antiquity with the present times, we shall find there
				was great variety then, and that frequently made use of.
				For then the variation of rhythm was more highly esteemed,
				and the change of their manner of play more frequent. We
				are now lovers of fables, they were then lovers of rhythm.
				Plain it is therefore, that the ancients did not refrain from
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.118"/>
				
				broken measures out of ignorance, but out of judgment.
				And yet what wonder is this, when there are so many other
				things necessary to human life which are not unknown,
				though not made use of by those who have no occasion to
				use them? But they are refused, and the use of them is
				altogether neglected, as not being found proper on many
				occasions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Having already shown that Plato neither for want
				of skill nor for ignorance blamed all the other moods and
				casts of composition, we now proceed to show that he
				really was skilled in harmony. For in his discourse concerning the procreation of the soul, inserted into Timaeus,
				he has made known his great knowledge in all the sciences,
				and of music among the rest, in this manner: <q direct="unspecified">After
					this,</q> saith he, <q direct="unspecified">he filled up the double and treble intervals,
						taking parts from thence, and adding them to the midst
						between them, so that there were in every interval two middle terms.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Timaeus, p. 36 A. See the whole passage in the treatise <hi rend="italics">Of the Procreation of the Soul as discoursed in Timaeus,</hi> Chap. XXIX. (G.)</note> This proem was the effect of his experience
				in music, as we shall presently make out. The means
				from whence every mean is taken are three, arithmetical,
				enharmonical, geometrical. Of these the first exceeds and
				is exceeded in number, the second in proportion, the third
				neither in number nor proportion. Plato therefore, desirous
				to show the harmony of the four elements in the soul, and
				harmonically also to explain the reason of that mutual concord arising from discording and jarring principles, undertakes to make out two middle terms of the soul in every
				interval, according to harmonical proportion. Thus in a
				musical octave there happen to be two middle distances,
				whose proportion we shall explain. As for the octaves,
				they keep a double proportion between their two extremes.
				For example, let the double arithmetical proportion be 6
				and 12, this being the interval between the <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/th me/swn</foreign> and
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.119"/>
				
				the <foreign lang="greek">nh/th diezeugme/nwn;</foreign> 6 therefore and 12 being the two
				extremes, the former note contains the number 6, and the
				latter 12. To these are to be added the intermediate
				numbers, to which the extremes must hold the proportion,
				the one of one and a third, and the other of one and a
				half. These are the numbers 8 and 9. For as 8 contains
				one and a third of 6, so 9 contains one and a half of 6;
				thus you have one extreme. The other is 12, containing 9
				and a third part of 9, and 8 and half 8. These then being
				the numbers between 6 and 12, and the interval of the
				octave consisting of a diatessaron and diapente, it is plain
				that the number 8 belongs to mese, and the number 9 to
				paramese; which being so, it follows that hypate is to
				mese as paramese to nete of the disjunct tetrachords; for it
				is a fourth from the first term to the second of this proportion, and the same interval from the third term to the
				fourth. The same proportion will be also found in the numbers. For as 6 is to 8, so is 8 to 12; and as 6 is to 9, so
				is 8 to 12. For 8 is one and a third part of 6, and 12 of
				9; while 9 is one and a half part of 6, and 12 of 8. What
				has been said may suffice to show how great was Plato's
				zeal and learning in the liberal sciences.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Now that there is something of majesty, something
				great and divine in music, Aristotle, who was Plato's
				scholar, thus labors to convince the world: <q direct="unspecified">Harmony,</q>
				saith he, <q direct="unspecified">descended from heaven, and is of a divine,
					noble, and angelic nature; but being fourfold as to its
					efficacy, it has two means,&mdash;the one arithmetical, the
					other enharmonical. As for its members, its dimensions,
					and its excesses of intervals, they are best discovered by
					number and equality of measure, the whole art being contained in two tetrachords.</q> These are his words. The
				body of it, he saith, consists of discording parts, yet concording one with another; whose means nevertheless
				agree according to arithmetical proportion. For the upper
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.120"/>
				
				string being fitted to the lowest in the ratio of two to one
				produces a perfect diapason. Thus, as we said before,
				nete consisting of twelve units, and hypate of six, the
				paramese accords with hypate according to the sesquialter
				proportion, and has nine units, whilst mese has eight units.
				So that the chiefest intervals through the whole scale are
				the diatessaron (which is the proportion of 4:3), the diapente
				(which is the proportion of 3:2), and the diapason (which
				is the proportion of 2:1); while the proportion of 9:8
				appears in the interval of a tone. With the same inequalities of excess or diminution, all the extremes are
				differenced one from another, and the means from the
				means, either according to the quantity of the numbers
				or the measure of geometry; which Aristotle thus explains,
				observing that nete exceeds mese by a third part of
				itself, and hypate is exceeded by paramese in the same
				proportion, so that the excesses stand in proportion. For
				by the same parts of themselves they exceed and are exceeded; that is, the extremes (nete and hypate) exceed
				and are exceeded by mese and paramese in the same proportions, those of 4: 3 and of 3: 2. Now these excesses are
				in what is called harmonic progression. But the distances
				of nete from mese and of paramese from hypate, expressed
				in numbers, are in the same proportion (12:8 &equals; 9:6); for
				paramese exceeds mese by one-eighth of the latter. Again,
				nete is to hypate as 2:1; paramese to hypate as 3:2; and
				mese to hypate as 4:3. This, according to Aristotle, is the
				natural constitution of harmony, as regards its parts and
				its numbers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>But, according to natural philosophy, both harmony
				and its parts consist of even, odd, and also even-odd.
				Altogether it is even, as consisting of four terms; but its
				parts and proportions are even, odd, and even-odd. So
				nete is even, as consisting of twelve units; paramese is
				odd, of nine; mese even, of eight; and hypate even-odd,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.121"/>
				
				of six (i.e., 2&times;3). Whence it comes to pass, that music
				&mdash;herself and her parts&mdash;being thus constituted as to excesses and proportion, the whole accords with the whole,
				and also with each one of the parts.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>But now as for the senses that are created within
				the body, such as are of celestial and heavenly extraction,
				and which by divine assistance affect the understanding of
				men by means of harmony,&mdash;namely, sight and hearing,&mdash;
				do by the very light and voice express harmony. And others
				which are their attendants, so far as they are senses, likewise exist by harmony; for they perform none of their
				effects without harmony; and although they are inferior
				to the other two, they are not independent of them. Nay,
				those two also, since they enter into human bodies at
				the very same time with God himself, claim by reason a
				vigorous and incomparable nature.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Manifest from hence therefore it is, why the ancient
				Greeks, with more reason than others, were so careful to
				teach their children music. For they deemed it requisite
				by the assistance of music to form and compose the minds of
				youth to what was decent, sober, and virtuous; believing
				the use of music beneficially efficacious to incite to all serious actions, especially to the adventuring upon warlike
				dangers. To which purpose they made use of pipes or
				flutes when they advanced in battle array against their
				enemies; like the Lacedaemonians, who upon the same occasion caused the Castorean melody to be played before
				their battalions. Others inflamed their courage with
				harps, playing the same sort of harmony when they went
				to look danger in the face, as the Cretans did for a long
				time. Others, even to our own times, continue to use the
				trumpet. The Argives made use of flutes at their wrestling matches called Stheneia; which sort of sport was first
				instituted in honor of Danaus, but afterwards consecrated
				to Jupiter Sthenius, or Jupiter the Mighty. And now at
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.122"/>
				
				this day it is the custom to make use of flutes at the games
				called Pentathla, although there is now nothing exquisite
				or antique, nothing like what was customary among men
				of old time, like the song composed by Hierax for this
				very game; still, even though it is sorry stuff and nothing
				exquisite, it is accompanied by flute-music.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>But among the more ancient Greeks, music in
				theatres was never known, for they employed their whole
				musical skill in the worship of the Gods and the education of youth; at which time, there being no theatres
				erected, music was yet confined within the walls of
				their temples, as being that with which they worshipped
				the supreme Deity and sang the praises of virtuous men.
				And it is probable that the word <foreign lang="greek">qe/atron,</foreign> at a later period,
				and <foreign lang="greek">qewrei=n</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">to behold</hi>) much earlier, were derived from <foreign lang="greek">qeo/s</foreign>
				(<hi rend="italics">God</hi>). But in our age is such another face of new inventions, that there is not the least remembrance or care
				of that use of music which related to education; for
				all our musicians make it their business to court the
				theatre Muses, and study nothing but compositions for the
				stage.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>But some will say, Did the ancients invent nothing
				themselves? Yes, say I, they did invent, but their inventions were grave and decent. For they who have written the history of music attribute to Terpander the addition
				of the Dorian nete, which before was not in use. Even
				the whole Mixolydian mood is a new invention. Such were
				also the Orthian manner of melody with Orthian rhythms,
				and also the Trochaeus Semantus.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Rossbach, Griechische Rhythmik, p. 96, &sect; 23. (G.)</note> And if we believe
				Pindar, Terpander was the inventor of the Scolion (or
				roundelay). Archilochus also invented the rhythmic composition of the iambic trimeter, the change to rhythms of
				different character, the melo-dramatic delivery,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">So Rossbach and Westphal interpret <foreign lang="greek">parakatalogh/.</foreign> Metrik, III. pp. 184, 554. (G.)</note> and the
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.123"/>
				
				accompaniment proper to each of these. He is also presumed to be the author of epodes, tetrameters, the Cretic
				and the prosodiac rhythms, and the augmentation of the
				heroic verse. Some make him author also of the elegiac
				measure, as likewise of the extending the iambic to the
				paeon epibatus, the prolonged and heroic to the prosodiac
				and Cretic. And Archilochus is first said to have taught
				how iambics could be partly recited to the stroke of the
				lyre and partly sung; from him the tragedians learned it,
				and from them Crexus took it, and made use of it in
				dithyrambics. It is thought that he invented also playing
				on the lyre at intervals in the song, whereas the ancients
				played only during the singing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Of the Hypolydian mood they make Polymnestus the
				inventor, and the first that taught the lowering and raising
				of the voice (<foreign lang="greek">e)/klusis</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">e)kbolh/</foreign>). To the same Olympus to
				whom they also ascribe the first invention of Grecian and
				well-regulated nomic music they attribute likewise the
				finding out the enharmonic music, the prosodiac measure
				to which is composed the hymn to Mars, and the chorean
				measure which he used in the hymns to the Mother of the
				Gods. Some report him to be the author also of the bacchius. And every one of the ancient songs show that this
				is so. But Lasus of Hermione, transferring the rhythms
				to suit the dithyrambic time, and making use of an instrument with many notes, made an absolute innovation upon
				the ancient music, by the use of more notes, and those
				more widely distributed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>In like manner Menalippides the lyric poet, Philoxenus and Timotheus, all forsook the ancient music. For
				whereas until the time of Terpander the Antissaean the
				harp had only seven strings, he<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is uncertain here to whom the pronoun <hi rend="italics">he</hi> refers. Volkmann transfers the
					whole sentence to the end of Chap. XXIX., referring it to Lasus of Hermione. (G.)</note> added a greater number,
				and gave its notes a wider range. The wind-music also
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.124"/>
				
				exchanged its ancient plainness for a more copious variety.
				For in ancient times, till Menalippides the dithyrambic
				came into request, the wind-music received salaries from
				the poets, poetry holding the first rank and the musicians
				being in the service of the poet. Afterwards that custom
				grew out of date; insomuch that Pherecrates the comedian brings in Music in woman's habit, all bruised and
				battered, and then introduces Justice asking the reason; to
				which Music thus replies:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>' Tis mine to speak, thy part to hear,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Music.</note>
                  </l>
					             <l>And therefore lend a willing ear;</l>
					             <l>Much have I suffered, long opprest</l>
					             <l>By Menalippides, that beast;</l>
					             <l>He haled me from Parnassus' springs,</l>
					             <l>And plagued me with a dozen strings.</l>
					             <l>His rage howe'er sufficed not yet,</l>
					             <l>To make my miseries complete.</l>
					             <l>Cinesias, that cursed Attic,</l>
					             <l>A mere poetical pragmatic,</l>
					             <l>Such horrid strophes in mangled verse</l>
					             <l>Made the unharmonious stage rehearse,</l>
					             <l>That I, tormented with the pains</l>
					             <l>Of cruel dithyrambic strains,</l>
					             <l>Distorted lay, that you would swear</l>
					             <l>The right side now the left side were.</l>
					             <l>Nor did my miseries end here;</l>
					             <l>For Phrynis with his whirlwind brains,</l>
					             <l>Wringing and racking all my veins,</l>
					             <l>Ruined me quite, while nine small wires</l>
					             <l>With harmonies twice six he tires.</l>
					             <l>Yet might not he so much be blamed,</l>
					             <l>From all his errors soon reclaimed;</l>
					             <l>But then Timotheus with his freaks</l>
					             <l>Furrowed my face, and ploughed my cheeks.</l>
					             <l>Say which of them so vile could be?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">JUSTICE.</note>
                  </l>
					             <l>Milesian Pyrrhias, that was he,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Music.</note>
                  </l>
					             <l>Whose fury tortured me much more</l>
					             <l>Than all that I have named before;</l>
					             <l>Where'er I walk the streets alone,</l>
					             <l>If met by him, the angry clown,</l>
					             <l>With his twelve cat-guts strongly bound,</l>
					             <l>He leaves me helpless on the ground.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The original of this fragment of Pllerecrates may be found in Meineke's <hi rend="italics">Poet.
						Comic. Graec. Fraqm.</hi> II. p. 326; and in Didot's edition of the same fragments,
						p. 110. Meineke includes the verses commonly assigned to Aristophanes in the
						extract from Pherecrates. (G.)</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.125"/>
            <p>Aristophanes the comic poet, making mention of Philoxenus, complains of his introducing lyric verses among
					the cyclic choruses, where he brings in Music thus
					speaking:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>He filled me with discordant measures airy,</l>
						            <l>Wicked Hyperbolaei and Niglari;</l>
						            <l>And to uphold the follies of his play,</l>
						            <l>Like a lank radish bowed me every way.</l>
               </quote>
					
					Other comedians have since set forth the absurdity of those
					who have been slicers and manglers of music.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>Now that the right moulding or ruin of ingenuous
				manners and civil conduct lies in a well-grounded musical
				education, Aristoxenus has made apparent. For, of those
				that were contemporary with him, he gives an account of
				Telesias the Theban, who in his youth was bred up in the
				noblest excellences of music, and moreover studied the
				works of the most famous lyrics, Pindar, Dionysius the
				Theban, Lamprus, Pratinas, and all the rest who were accounted most eminent; who played also to perfection upon
				the flute, and was not a little industrious to furnish himself
				with all those other accomplishments of learning; but being past the prime of his age, he was so bewitched with
				the theatre's new fangles and the innovations of multiplied
				notes, that despising those noble precepts and that solid
				practice to which he had been educated, he betook himself to Philoxenus and Timotheus, and among those
				delighted chiefly in such as were most depraved with
				diversity of notes and baneful innovation. And yet, when
				he made it his business to make verses and labor both
				ways as well in that of Pindar as that of Philoxenus, he
				could have no success in the latter. And the reason
				proceeded from the truth and exactness of his first education.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Therefore, if it be the aim of any person to practise
				music with skill and judgment, let him imitate the ancient
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.126"/>
				
				manner; let him also adorn it with those other sciences,
				and make philosophy his tutor, which is sufficient to judge
				what is iii music decent and useful. For music being generally divided into three parts, diatonic, chromatic, and
				enharmonie, it behooves one who comes to learn music
				to understand poetry, which uses these three parts, and to
				know how to express his poetical inventions in proper
				musical form.</p>
            <p>First therefore we are to consider that all musical learning is a sort of habituation, which does not teach the
					reason of her precepts at one and the same time to the
					learner. Moreover, we are to understand that to such an
					education there is not requisite an enumeration of its several divisions, but every one learns by chance what either
					the master or scholar, according to the authority of the
					one and the liberty of the other, has most affection for.
					But the more prudent sort reject this chance-medley way
					of learning, as the Lacedaemonians of old, the Mantineans, and Pallenians, who, making choice either of one
					single method or else but very few styles, used only that
					sort of music which they deemed most proper to regulate the inclinations of youths.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>This will be apparent, if any one shall examine
				every one of the parts, and see what is the subject of their
				several contemplations. For harmony takes cognizance
				of intervals, systems, classes of harmonious sounds, notes,
				tones, and systematical transmutations. Farther than this
				it goes not. And therefore it would be in vain to enquire
				of harmony, whether the poet have rightly and (so to speak)
				musically chosen the Dorian for the beginning, the mixed
				Lydian and Dorian for the end, or the Hypophrygian
				and Phrygian for the middle. For the industry of harmony reaches not to these, and it is defective in many other
				things, as not understanding the force and extent of elegant
				aptness and proper concinnity. Neither did ever the chromatic
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.127"/>
				
				 or enharmonic species arrive to such force of aptitude
				as to discover the nature and genius of the poem; for that is
				the work of the poet. It is as plain, that the sound of the
				system is different from the sound of the descant sung in
				the same system; which, however, does not belong to the
				consideration of harmonical studies. There is the same to
				be said concerning rhythms, for no rhythm can claim to itself the force of perfect aptitude. For we call a thing apt
				and proper when we consider the nature of it. The
				reason of this, we say, is either a certain plain and mixed
				composure, or both; like the enharmonic species of Olympus, by him set in the Phrygian mood and mixed with the
				paeon epibatos, which rendered the beginning of the key
				naturally elegant in what is called the nome of Minerva.
				For having made choice of his key and measure, he only
				changed the paeon epibatos for the trochee, which produced his enharmonic species. However, the enharmonic
				species and Phrygian tone remaining together with the
				whole system, the elegancy of the character was greatly
				altered. For that which was called harmony in the nome
				of Minerva was quite another thing from that in the introduction. He then that has both judgment as well as skill
				is to be accounted the most accurate musician. For he that
				understands the Dorian mood, not being able withal to discern by his judgment what is proper to it and when it is fit
				to be made use of, shall never know what he does; nay, he
				shall quite mistake the nature and custom of the key.
				Indeed it is much questioned among the Dorians themselves, whether the enharmonic composers be competent
				judges of the Dorian songs. The same is to be said concerning the knowledge of rhythm. For he that understands
				a paeon may not understand the proper use of it, though
				he know the measure of which it consists. Because it is
				much doubted among those that make use of paeons,
				whether the bare knowledge make a man capable to determine
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.128"/>
				
				 concerning the proper use of those rhythms; or, as
				others say, whether it aspire to presume so far. Therefore
				it behooves that person to have two sorts of knowledge,
				who will undertake to judge of what is proper and what
				improper; first, of the custom and manner of elegancy for
				which such a composition was intended, and next of those
				things of which the composition consists. And thus, that
				neither the bare knowledge of harmony, nor of rhythm, nor
				of any other things that singly by themselves are but a part
				of the whole body of music, is sufficient to judge and determine either of the one or the other, what has been already
				said may suffice to prove.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>[Now then, there being three species into which all
				harmony is divided, equal in the magnitude of systems or
				intervals and force of notes and tetrachords, we find that
				the ancients never disputed about any more than one; for
				they never troubled themselves with the chromatic or diatonic, but differed only about the enharmonic; and there
				no farther than about the great interval called the diapason.
				The further subdivision indeed caused some little variance,
				but they nearly all agreed that harmony itself is but one.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The passage in brackets is out of place here, and is generally transferred to the
					middle of Chapter XXXVII. (G.)</note> ]
				Therefore he must never think to be a true artist in the understanding and practice of music, who advances no farther
				than the single knowledge of this or that particular: but
				it behooves him to trace through all the particular members
				of it, and so to be master of the whole body, by understanding how to mix and join all the divided members.
				For he that understands only harmony is confined to a
				single manner. Wherefore, in short, it is requisite that
				the sense and understanding concur in judging the parts of
				music; and that they should neither be too hasty, like
				those senses which are rash and forward, nor too slow, like
				those which are dull and heavy; though it may happen
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.129"/>
				
				sometimes, through the inequality of Nature, that the same
				senses may be too slow and too quick at the same time.
				Which things are to be avoided by a sense and judgment
				that would run an equal course.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>For there are three things at least that at the same
				instant strike the ear,&mdash;the note, the time, and the word or
				syllable. By the note we judge of the harmony, by the
				time of the rhythm, and by the word of the matter or subject of the song. As these proceed forth altogether, it is
				requisite the sense should give them entrance at the same
				moment. But this is certain, where the sense is not able to
				separate every one of these and consider the effects of each
				apart, there it can never apprehend what is well or what is
				amiss in any. First therefore let us discourse concerning
				coherence. For it is necessary that coherence accompany
				the discerning faculty. For judgment of good or bad is
				not to be made from notes disjoined, broken time, and
				shattered words, but from coherence. For there is in
				practice a certain commixture of parts which commonly
				are not compounded. So much as to coherence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>We are next to consider whether the masters of
				music are sufficiently capable of being judges of it. Now
				I aver the negative. For it is impossible to be a perfect
				musician and a good judge of music by the knowledge of
				those things that seem to be but parts of the whole body, as
				by excellency of hand upon the instrument, or singing
				readily at first sight, or exquisiteness of the ear, so far as
				this extends to the understanding of harmony and time.
				Neither does the knowledge of time and harmony, pulsation or elocution, or whatever else falls under the same
				consideration, perfect their judgment. Now for the reasons
				why a musician cannot gain a perfect judgment from any
				of these, we must endeavor to make them clear. First then
				it must be granted that, of things about which judgment is
				to be made, some are perfect and others imperfect. Those
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.130"/>
				
				things which are perfect are the compositions in general,
				whether sung or played, and the expression of those, whether
				upon the instruments or by the voice, with the rest of the
				same nature. The imperfect are the things to these appertaining, and for whose sake they are made use of. Such
				are the parts of expression. A second reason may be
				found in poetry, with which the case is the same. For a
				man that hears a consort of voices or instruments can judge
				whether they sing or play in tune, and whether the language
				be plain or not. But every one of these are only parts of
				instrumental and vocal expression; not the end itself, but
				for the sake of the end. For by these and things of the
				same nature shall the elegancy of elocution be judged,
				whether it be proper to the poem which the performer undertakes to sing. The same is to be said of the several
				passions expressed in the poetry.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>The ancients now made principal account of the
				moral impression, and therefore preferred that fashion of
				the antique music which was grave and least affected.
				Therefore the Argives are said to have punished deviation
				from the ancient music, and to have imposed a fine upon
				such as first adventured to play with more than seven strings,
				and to introduce the Mixolydian mood.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note on Chapter XXXIV.</note> Pythagoras, that
				grave philosopher, rejected the judging of music by the
				senses, affirming that the virtue of music could be appreciated only by the intellect. And therefore he did not judge
				of music by the ear, but by the harmonical proportion, and
				thought it sufficient to fix the knowledge of music within
				the compass of the diapason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>But our musicians nowadays have so utterly exploded the most noble of all the moods, which the ancients
				greatly admired for its majesty, that hardly any among them
				make the least account of enharmonic distances. And so
				negligent and lazy are they grown, as to believe the enharmonic
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.131"/>
				
				 diesis to be too contemptible to fall under the apprehension of sense, and they therefore exterminate it out of
				their compositions, deeming those to be triflers that have any
				esteem for it or make use of the mood itself. For proof
				of which they think they bring a most powerful argument,
				which rather appears to be the dulness of their own senses;
				as if whatever fled their apprehensions were to be rejected
				as useless and of no value. And then again they urge that
				its magnitude cannot be perceived through its concord, like
				that of the semitone, tone, and other distances; not understanding, that at the same time they throw out the third,
				fifth, and seventh, of which the one consists of three, the
				other of five, and the last of seven dieses. And on the
				same principle all the intervals that are odd should be rejected as useless, inasmuch as none of them is perceptible
				through concord; and this would include all which by
				means of even the smallest diesis are measured by odd
				numbers. Whence it necessarily follows, that no division
				of the tetrachord would be of use but that which is to be
				measured by all even intervals, as in the syntonic diatonic,
				and in the toniaean chromatic.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>But these opinions are not only contrary to appearance, but repugnant one to another. For they themselves
				chiefly make use of those divisions of tetrachords in which
				most of the intervals are either unequal or irrational. To
				which purpose they always soften both lichanos and paranete, and lower even some of the standing sounds by an
				irrational interval, bringing the trite and paranete to approach them. And especially they applaud the use of
				those systems in which most of the intervals are irrational,
				by relaxing not only those tones which are by nature movable, but also some which are properly fixed; as it is plain
				to those that rightly understand these things.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>Now for the advantages that accrue to men from the
				use of music, the famous Homer has taught it us, introducing
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.132"/>
				
				 Achilles, in the height of his fury toward Agamemnon,
				appeased by the music which he learned from Chiron, a
				person of great wisdom. For thus says he:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Amused at ease, the god-like man they found,</l>
					             <l>Pleased with the solemn harp's harmonious sound.</l>
					             <l>The well-wrought harp from conquered Thebe came;</l>
					             <l>Of polished silver was its costly frame.</l>
					             <l>With this he soothes his angry soul, and sings</l>
					             <l>The immortal deeds of heroes and of kings.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. IX. 186.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				Learn, says Homer, from hence the true use of music.
				For it became Achilles, the son of Peleus the Just, to sing
				the famous acts and achievements of great and valiant men.
				Also, in teaching the most proper time to make use of it, he
				found out a profitable and pleasing pastime for one's leisure
				hours. For Achilles, being both valiant and active, by
				reason of the disgust he had taken against Agamemnon
				withdrew from the war. Homer therefore thought he
				could not do better than by the laudable incitements of music
				and poetry to inflame the hero's courage for those achievements which he afterwards performed. And this he did,
				calling to mind the great actions of former ages. Such
				was then the ancient music, and such the advantages that
				made it profitable. To which end and purpose we read
				that Hercules, Achilles, and many others made use of it;
				whose master, wisest Chiron, is recorded to have taught
				not only music, but morality and physic.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>In brief therefore, a rational person will not blame
				the sciences themselves, if any one make use of them amiss,
				but will adjudge such a failing to be the error of those that
				abuse them. So that whoever he be that shall give his
				mind to the study of music in his youth, if he meet with a
				musical education, proper for the forming and regulating
				his inclinations, he will be sure to applaud and embrace
				that which is noble and generous, and to rebuke and blame
				the contrary, as well in other things as in what belongs to
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.133"/>
				
				music. And by that means he will become clear from all
				reproachful actions, for now having reaped the noblest
				fruit of music, he may be of great use, not only to himself
				but to the commonwealth; while music teaches him to abstain from every thing indecent both in word and deed, and
				to observe decorum, temperance, and regularity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>Now that those cities which were governed by the
				best laws took care always of a generous education in
				music, many testimonies may be produced. But for us it
				shall suffice to have instanced Terpander, who appeased a
				sedition among the Lacedaemonians, and Thaletas the Cretan, of whom Pratinas writes that, being sent for by the
				Lacedaemonians by advice of the oracle, he freed the city
				from a raging pestilence. Homer tells that the Grecians
				stopped the fury of another noisome pestilence by the
				power and charms of the same noble science:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>With sacred hymns and songs that sweetly please,</l>
					             <l>The Grecian youth all day the Gods appease.</l>
					             <l>Their lofty paeans bright Apollo hears,</l>
					             <l>And still the charming sounds delight his ears.</l>
               </quote>
				
				These verses, most excellent master, I thought requisite to
				add as the finishing stone to my musical discourse, which
				were by you cited before<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Section 2.</note> to show the force of harmony.
				For indeed the chiefest and sublimest end of music is the
				graceful return of our thanks to the Gods, and the next is
				to purify and bring our minds to a sober and harmonious
				temper. Thus, said Soterichus, most excellent master, I
				have given you what may be called an encyclic discourse of
				music.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>Nor was Soterichus a little admired for what he had
				spoken, as one that both by his countenance and speech
				had shown his zeal and affection for that noble science.
				After all, said Onesicrates, I must needs applaud this in
				both of you, that you have kept within your own spheres
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.134"/>
				
				and observed your proper limits. For Lysias, not insisting
				any further, undertook only to show us what was necessary
				to the making a good hand, as being an excellent performer himself. But Soterichus has feasted us with a
				discovery of the benefit, the theory, the force, and right
				end of music. But one thing I think they have willingly
				left for me to say; for I cannot think them guilty of so
				much bashfulness that they should be ashamed to bring
				music into banquets, where certainly, if anywhere, it cannot but be very useful, which Homer also confirms to be
				true:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Song and the merry dance, the joy of feasts.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Odyss. I. 152.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				Not that I would have any one believe from these words,
				that Homer thought music useful only for pleasure and
				delight, there being a profounder meaning concealed in the
				verse. For he brought in music to be present at the banquets and revels of the ancients, as believing it then to be
				of greatest use and advantage to repel and mitigate the
				inflaming power of the wine. To which our Aristoxenus
				agrees, who alleges that music was introduced at banquets
				for this reason, that as wine intemperately drunk weakens
				both the body and mind, so music by its harmonious order
				and symmetry assuages and reduces them to their former
				constitution. And therefore it was that Homer reports
				that the ancients made use of music at their solemn festivals.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>But for all this, my most honored friends, methinks
				you have forgot the chiefest thing of all, and that which
				renders music most majestic. For Pythagoras, Archytas,
				Plato, and many others of the ancient philosophers, were
				of opinion, that there could be no motion of the world or
				rolling of the spheres without the assistance of music, since
				the Supreme Deity created all things harmoniously. But
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.135"/>
				
				it would be unseasonable now to enter upon such a discourse, especially at this time, when it would be absurd for
				Music to transgress her highest and most musical office,
				which is to give the laws and limits of time and measure
				to all things. Therefore after he had sung a paean, and
				offered to Saturn and his offspring, with all the other Gods
				and the Muses, he dismissed the company.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>