<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De recta ratione audiendi</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.069">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.441"/>
         <head>Of hearing.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">The Introduction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I HAVE sent, Nicander, the reflections of some spare
					hours concerning Hearing, digested into the following short
					essay, that being out of the hands of governors and come
					to man's estate, you may know how to pay a proper attention to those who would advise you. For that libertinism
					which some wild young fellows, for want of more happy
					education, mistake for liberty, subjects them to harder
					tyrants than their late tutors and masters, even to their
					own vicious inclinations, which, as it were, break loose
					upon them. And as Herodotus observes of women, that
					they put off modesty with their shift,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 8.</note> so some young men
					lay aside with the badges of minority all the sense of
					shame or fear, and divested of the garment of modesty
					which sat so well upon them are covered with insolence.
					But you, who have often heard that to follow God and to
					obey reason are all one, cannot but believe that men of best
					sense in passing from minority to manhood do not throw
					off the government, but simply change their governor. In
					the room of some mercenary pedant, they receive that
					divine guide and governor of human life, reason, under
					whose subjection alone men are properly said to live in
					freedom. For they only live at their own will who have
					learned to will as they ought; and that freedom of will
					which appears in unconstrained appetites and unreasonable
					actions is mean and narrow, and accompanied with much
					repentance.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.442"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>For as newly naturalized citizens who were entire
					strangers and aliens are apt to disrelish many administrations of the government; while those who have previously
					lived in the country, bred up under the constitution and
					acquainted with it, act without difficulty in their several
					stations, well satisfied with their condition; in like manner, a man should for a long time have been bred up
					in philosophy, and accustomed from his earliest years to
					receive his lessons and instruction mingled with philosophic reason, that so he may come at last as a kind and
					familiar friend to philosophy, which alone can array young
					men in the perfect manly robes and ornaments of reason.
					Therefore, I believe, some directions concerning hearing
					will not be ill received by you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Remarks about Hearing in general.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this Theophrastus affirms, that it is the most sensitive
						of all the senses. For the several objects of sight, tasting,
						and feeling do not excite in us so great disturbances and
						alterations as the sudden and frightful noises which assault
						us only at the ears. Yet in reality this sense is more
						rational than sensitive. For there are many organs and
						other parts of the body which serve as avenues and inlets
						to the soul to give admission to vice; there is but one
						passage of virtue into young minds, and that is by the ears,
						provided they be preserved all along free from the corruptions of flattery and untainted with lewd discourses. For
						this reason Xenocrates was of opinion that children ought
						to have a defence fitted to their ears rather than fencers or
						prize-players, because the ears only of the latter suffered
						by the blows, but the morals of the former were hurt and
						maimed by words. Not that he thereby recommended
						deafness, or forbade that they should be suffered to hear at
						all; but he advised only that debauchery might be kept
						out, till better principles, like so many guardians appointed
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.443"/>
						
						by philosophy, had taken charge of that part which is so
						liable to be drawn aside and corrupted by discourse. And
						Bias of old, being ordered by Amasis to send him the best
						and withal the worst part of the sacrifice, sent the tongue;
						because the greatest benefits and disadvantages are derived
						to us thereby. Thus again many diverting themselves with
						children touch their ears, bidding them return the like
						again; by which they seem to intimate to them that such
						best deserve their love and esteem whose obligations enter
						at the ears. This is evident, that he that has lain fallow
						all his days, without tasting instruction, will not only prove
						barren and unfruitful of virtue, but very inclinable to vice;
						for an uncultivated mind, like untilled ground, will soon be
						overrun with weeds. For if that violent propensity of the
						mind to pleasure, and jealousy of all that carries any show
						of pain,&mdash;which proceed not from external causes or received prejudices, but are the natural springs of evil affections and infinite diseases of the mind,&mdash;are suffered to
						take their course, and not restrained, or diverted some other
						way by wholesome instructions, there can be no beast so
						savage that it may not be called tame and civilized in
						respect of such a man.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">More General Rules about Hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then it appears that hearing is of so great use
					and no less danger to young men, I think it a very commendable thing for such a one to reflect continually with
					himself, and consult often with others, how he may hear
					with benefit. And in this particular we may observe many
					to have been mistaken, that they practise speaking before
					they have been used enough to hearing. Speaking they
					think will require some study and attention, but hearing
					cannot be a thing of any difficulty. Those ideed who
					play the game of tennis learn at the same time how to
					throw and how to catch the ball; but in the exercise of
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.444"/>
					
					the tongue, we ought to practise how to talk well before
					we pretend to return, as conception and retention of the
					foetus precede childbirth. When fowls let fall windeggs, it is usually said that they are the rudiments of imperfect fruits which will never quicken and have life; and
					when young men either hear not at all or retain not what
					they hear, their discourse comes from them altogether as
					useless and full of wind,
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>And vain and unregarded turns to air.</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In filling one vessel from another, they take care to incline and turn it so that nothing be spilled, and that it may
						be really filling and not emptying; but they think it not
						worth the heeding to regulate their attention and apply
						themselves with advantage to a speaker, that nothing of
						importance may fall beside or escape them. Yet, what is
						beyond comparison ridiculous, if they happen upon any
						one who has a knack at describing an entertainment or a
						show, or can relate his dream well, or give an handsome
						account of a quarrel between himself and another, such a
						one they hear with the greatest attention, they court him
						to proceed, and importune him for every circumstance.
						Whereas, let another call them about him for any thing
						useful, to exhort to what is decent or reprehend what is
						irregular, or to make up a quarrel, they have not temper
						enough to away with it, but they fight with all their might
						to put him down by argument, if they are able, or if not,
						they haste away to more agreeable fopperies; as if their
						ears, like faulty earthen vessels, might be filled with any
						thing but what is useful or valuable. But as jockeys take
						great care in breeding horses to bring them to rein right
						and endure the bit, so such as have the care of educating
						children should breed them to endure hearing, by allowing
						them to speak little and hear much. And Spintharus,
						speaking in commendation of Epaminondas, says he scarce
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.445"/>
						
						ever met with any man who knew more and spoke less.
						Some again make the observation, that Nature has given
						every man two ears and but one tongue, as a secret intimation that he ought to speak less than he hears.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Directions concerning Attention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, silence is at all times a singular ornament
					of a youth, but especially if he does not interrupt the
					speaker nor carp and except at every thing he says, but
					patiently expects the conclusion, though his discourse be
					none of the best; and when he has done, if he does not
					presently come over him with an objection, but (as
					Aeschines directs) allows time to add, if he please, to
					what has been said, or to alter, or retract. Whereas such
					as turn too suddenly upon a speaker neither hear nor are
					heard themselves, but senselessly chatter to one another,
					and sin against the laws and rules of decorum. But he
					that brings along with him a modest and unwearied attention has this advantage, that whatever is beneficial in the
					discourse he makes his own, and he more readily discovers
					what is false or impertinent, appearing all the while a
					friend to truth rather than to squabbling or rashness.
					Therefore it was not ill said, that such as design to infuse
					goodness into the minds of youth must first exclude thence
					pride and self-conceit more carefully than we squeeze air
					out of bladders which we wish to fill with something useful; because, while they are puffed up with arrogance,
					there is no room to admit any thing else.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Thus again, envy and detraction and prejudice are in
					no case good, but always a great impediment to what is so;
					yet nowhere worse than when they are made the bosom-friends and counsellers of a hearer, because they represent
					the best things to him as unpleasant and impertinent, and
					men in such circumstances are pleased with any thing
					rather than what deserves their applause. Yet he that
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.446"/>
					
					grieves at the wealth, glory, or beauty of any is but simply envious, for he repines only at the good of others; but
					he that is ill-natured to a good speaker is an enemy to his
					own happiness. For discourse to an hearer, like light to
					the eye, is a great benefit, if he will make the best use of
					it. Envy in all other instances carries this pretence with
					it, that it is to be referred to the depraved and ungovernable affections of the mind, but that which is conceived
					against a speaker arises from an unjust presumption and
					vain-glorious affectation of praise.</p>
            <p>In such a case, the man has not leisure to attend to what
						he hears; his soul is in continual hurry and disturbance, at
						one time examining her own habits and endowments, if any
						way inferior to the speaker; anon, watching the behavior
						and inclination of others, if inclined to praise or admire
						his discourse; disordered at the praise and enraged at
						the company, if he meet with any encouragement. She
						easily lets slip and willingly forgets what has been said,
						because the remembrance is a pain and vexation to her;
						she hears what is to come with a great deal of uneasiness
						and concern, and is never so desirous that the speaker
						should hasten to an end, as when he discourses best. After
						all is over, she considers not what was said, but has respect
						only to the common vogue and disposition of the audience;
						she avoids and flies like one distracted such as seem to be
						pleased, and herds among the censorious and perverse. If
						she finds nothing to pervert, then she puts forward other
						speakers, who (as she asserts) have spoken better and with
						greater force of argument on the same subject. Thus, by
						abusing and corrupting what was said, she defeats the use
						and effect of it on herself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>He therefore who comes to hear must for the time
					come to a kind of truce and accommodation with vainglory, and preserve the same evenness and cheerfulness of
					humor he would bring with him if he were invited to a
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.447"/>
					
					festival entertainment or the first-fruits' sacrifice, applauding the orator's power when he speaks to the purpose,
					and where he fails receiving kindly his readiness to communicate what he knows and to persuade others by what
					wrought upon himself. Where he comes off with success,
					he must not impute it to chance or peradventure, but attribute all to study and diligence and art, not only admiring
					but studiously emulating the like; where he has done
					amiss, he must pry curiously into the causes and origin of
					the mistake. For what Xenophon says of discreet house
					keepers, that they make an advantage of their enemies as
					well as their friends, is in some sort true of vigilant and attentive hearers, who reap no less benefit from an ill than a
					good orator. For the meanness and poverty of a thought,
					the emptiness and flatness of an expression, the unseasonableness of a figure, and the impertinence of falling into a
					foolish ecstasy of joy or commendation, and the like, are
					better discovered by a by-stander than by the speaker himself. Therefore his oversight or indiscretion must be brought
					home to ourselves, that we may examine if nothing of the
					same kind has skulked there and imposed on us all the
					while. For there is nothing in the world more easy than
					to discover the faults of others; but it is done to no effect
					if we do not make it useful to ourselves in correcting and
					avoiding the like failures. When therefore you animadvert upon other men's miscarriages, forget not to put that
					question of Plato to yourself, Am not I such anotherWe
					must trace out our own way of writing in the discourses of
					other men, as in another's eyes we see the reflection of our
					own; that we may learn not to be too free in censuring
					others, and may use more circumspection ourselves in
					speaking. To this design the following method of comparison may be very instrumental; if upon our return
					from hearing we take what seemed to us not well or sufficiently handled, and attempt it afresh ourselves, endeavoring
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.448"/>
					
					 to fill out one part or correct another, to vary this or
					model that into a new form from the very beginning. And
					thus Plato examined the oration of Lysias. For it is a
					thing of no great difficulty to raise objections against another man's oration,&mdash;nay, it is a very easy matter,&mdash;but
					to produce a better in its place is a work extremely
					troublesome; as the Spartan, who was told Philip had
					demolished the city Olynthus, made this reply, But he
					cannot raise such another. When then it appears, upon
					handling the same topic, that we do not much excel those
					who undertook it before, this will abate much of our censorious humor, and our pride and self-conceit will be exposed and checked by such comparisons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Caution about Admiration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To contempt is opposed admiration, which indeed
					argues a more candid and better disposition; but even in
					this case no small care is to be observed, and perhaps even
					greater. For although such as are contemptuous and self-conceited receive but little good from what they hear, yet
					the good-natured and such as are given to admire every
					thing take a great deal of harm. And Heraclitus was not
					mistaken when he said that a fool was put in a flutter at
					every thing he heard. We ought indeed to use all the
					candor imaginable in praising the speaker, yet withal as
					great caution in yielding our assent to what he says; to
					look upon his expression and action with a favorable construction, but to inspect the usefulness and truth of his
					doctrine with the nicest and most critical judgment; that
					speakers may cease to be malicious, and that what they say
					may do no mischief. For many false and dangerous principles steal upon us through the authority of the speaker
					and our own credulity. The Spartan Ephors, approving
					the judgment of one of an ill conversation, ordered it to
					be communicated to the people by a person of better life
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.449"/>
					
					and reputation; thereby wisely and politicly using them to
					give more deference to the morals than to the words of such
					as pretend to advise them. But now in philosophy the
					reputation of the speaker must be pulled off, and his words
					examined naked and without a mask; for in hearing as in
					war there are many false alarms. The hoary head of the
					speaker or his gesture, his magisterial look or his assuming
					pride, and above all the noise and clapping of the auditory,
					bear great sway with a raw and inexperienced hearer, who
					is easily carried away with the tide. The very expression,
					if sweet and full and representing things with some pomp
					and greatness, has a secret power to impose upon us. For,
					as many lapses in such as sing to an instrument escape the
					hearers, so luxuriancy and pomp of style dazzle the hearer
					so that he cannot see clearly the argument in hand. And
					Melanthius, as it is said, being asked his opinion concerning a tragedy of Diogenes, made answer that the words
					intercepted his sight of it. But most Sophists in their
					declamations and speeches not only make use of words to
					veil and muffle their design; but with affected tone and
					softness of voice they draw aside and bewitch their followers, for the empty pleasure which they create reaping a
					more empty glory. So that the saying of Dionysius is very
					applicable to them, who, being one day extremely pleased
					with an harper that played excellently well before him,
					promised the fellow a great reward, yet afterwards would
					give him nothing, pretending he had hept his word; For,
					said he, as long as you pleased me by your playing, so long
					were you pleased by hope of the reward. And such also
					is the reward this kind of harangues bring to the authors.
					The hearers admire as long as they are pleased and tickled,
					but the satisfaction on one hand and glory on the other
					conclude with the oration; and the hearers lose their time
					idly, and the speakers their whole life.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.450"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">How to separate the Useful Part of a Discourse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, we must separate the trash and trumpery of an
					oration, that we may come at the more fruitful and useful
					part; not imitating those women who busy themselves in
					gathering nosegays and making garlands, but the more
					useful industry of bees. The former indeed plat and weave
					together the sweetest and gayest flowers, and their skill is
					mighty pretty; but it lasts for one day only, and even then
					is of little or no use; whereas the bees, passing by the
					beds of violets and roses and hyacinth, fix on the prickly
					and biting thyme, and settle upon this <q direct="unspecified">intent on the yellow honey,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Simonides, Frag. No. 47.</note> and taking thence what they need for their
					work, they fly home laden. In like manner, a wellmeaning sincere hearer ought to pass by the flowers of an oration,
					leaving the gaudy show and theatrical part to entertain
					dronish Sophists; and, diving into the very mind of the
					speaker and the sense of his speech, he must draw thence
					what is necessary for his own service; remembering withal
					that he is not come to the theatre or music-meeting, but is
					present at the schools and auditories of philosophy, to learn
					to rectify his way of life by what he hears. In order thereunto, he ought to inspect diligently and try faithfully the
					state and temper of his mind after hearing, if any of his
					affections are more moderate, if any afflictions grow lighter,
					if his constancy and greatness of spirit are confirmed, if he
					feels any divine emotions or inward workings of virtue and
					goodness upon his soul. For it becomes us but ill, when
					we rise from the barber's chair, to be so long in consulting
					the mirror, or to stroke our heads and examine so curiously
					the style in which our hair is trimmed and dressed, and
					then, at our return from hearing in the schools, to think it
					needless to look into ourselves, or examine whether our own
					mind has discharged any turbulent or unprofitable affections
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.451"/>
					
					 and is grown more sedate and serene. For, as Ariston
					was wont to say, The bath and a discourse are of no use
					unless they are purgative.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Let then a young man be pleased and entertained
					with a discourse; but let him not make his pleasure the
					only end of hearing, nor think he may come from the school
					of a philosopher singing and sportive; nor let him call for
					perfumes and essences when he has need of a poultice and
					fomentations. But let him learn to be thankful to him
					that purges away the darkness and stupidity of his mind,
					though (as we clear beehives by smoking) with an offensive or unpalatable discourse. For though it lies upon a
					speaker to take some care that his expression be pleasing
					and plausible, yet a hearer ought not to make that the
					first thing he looks after. Afterward, indeed, when he has
					satisfied his appetite with the substance and has taken
					breath, he may be allowed the curiosity of examining the
					style and expression, whether it has any thing delicate or
					extraordinary; as men quench their thirst before they have
					time to admire the embossing of the bowl. But now such
					a one as is not intent on the subject-matter, but demands
					merely that the style shall be plain and pure Attic, is much
					of his foolish humor who refuses an antidote unless it be
					mixed in Attic porcelain, or who will not put on a coat in
					the winter because the cloth is not made of Attic wool; but
					who can yet sit still, doing nothing and stirring not, under
					such a thin and threadbare cloak as an oration of Lysias.
					That extreme dearth of judgment and good sense, and that
					abundance of subtilty and sophistry which is crept into the
					schools, is all owing to these corruptions of the youngsters; who, observing neither the lives nor public conversation of philosophers, mind nothing but words and jingle,
					and express themselves extravagantly upon what they
					think well said, without ever understanding or enqiring if
					it be useful and necessary, or needless and vain.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.452"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Of asking Questions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, it will be convenient to lay down some
					directions touching asking of questions. For it is true, he
					that comes to a great collation must eat what is set before
					him, not rudely calling for what is not to be had nor finding
					fault with the provision. But he that is invited to partake
					of a discourse, if it be with that proviso, must hear with
					silence; for such disagreeable hearers as occasion digressions by asking impertinent questions and starting foolish
					doubts are an hindrance both to the speaker and the discourse, without benefiting themselves. But when the
					speaker encourages them to propose their objections, he
					must take care that the question be of some consequence
					The suitors in Homer scorned and derided Ulysses.&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To no brave prize aspired the worthless swain,</l>
						            <l>'Twas but for scraps he asked, and asked in vain,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Odyss. XVII. 222.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					
					because they thought it required a great and heroic soul no
					less to ask than to bestow great gifts. But there is much
					better reason to slight and laugh at such a hearer as can
					please himself in asking little trifling questions. Thus
					some young fellows, to proclaim their smattering in logic
					and mathematics, upon all occasions enquire about the divisibility of the infinite, or about motion through a diagonal
					orupon the sides. But we may answer them with Philotimus,
					who, being asked by a consumptive phthisical person for a
					remedy against a whitlow, and perceiving the condition he
					was in by his color and his shortness of breath, replied,
					Sir, you have no reason to be apprehensive of that. So
					we must tell them, You have no reason, young gentlemen,
					to trouble yourselves about these questions; but how to
					shake off your conceit and arrogance, to have done with
					your intrigues and fopperies, and to settle immediately
					upon a modest and well-governed course of life, is the
					question for you.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.453"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Great regard is to be had also to the genius and
					talent of a speaker, that we may enquire about such things
					as are in his way, and not take him out of his knowledge;
					as if one should propose physical or mathematical queries
					to a moral philosophy reader, or apply himself to one who
					prides himself on his knowledge of physics to give his
					opinion on conditional propositions or to resolve a fallacy
					in logic. For, as he that goes about to cleave wood with a
					key or to unlock a door with an axe does not so much misemploy those instruments as deprive himself of the proper
					use of them, so such as are not content with what a speaker
					offers them, but call for such things as he is a stranger to,
					not only are disappointed, but incur the suspicion of malice
					and ill-nature.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Be cautious also how you ask questions yourself, or
					ask too often; for that betrays somewhat of conceit and
					ostentation. But to wait civilly while another proposes his
					scruples argues a studious spiritand willingness that others
					should be informed, unless some sudden perturbation of
					mind require to be repressed or some distemper to be
					assuaged. For perhaps, as Heraclitus says, it is an ill
					thing to conceal even a man's ignorance; it must be
					laid open, that the remedy may be applied. So also if
					anger or superstition or a violent quarrel with your domestics or the mad passion of love,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Which doth the very heart-strings move,</l>
						            <l>That ne'er were stirred before,&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
					
					excite any commotion in your mind, you are not, for fear
					of being galled by reproof, to fly to such as are treating.of
					other arguments: but you must frequent those places
					where your particular case is stating, and after lecture
					address yourself privately to the speaker for better information and fuller satisfaction therein. On the contrary, men
					commonly flatter themselves, and admire the philosopher
					so long as he discourses of indifferent things; but if he
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.454"/>
					
					come home to themselves and deal freely with them about
					their real interests, this they think is beyond all enduring,
					or at best a needless piece of supererogation. For they
					naturally think that they ought to hear philosophy in the
					schools, like actors on the stage, while in matters out of
					the school they believe them to be no better men than
					themselves; and, to confess the truth, they have but reason
					to think so of many Sophists, who, having once left the?
					desk and laid aside their books, in the serious concerns of
					human life are utterly insignificant and even more ignorant
					than the vulgar. But they do not know that even the austerity or raillery of real philosophers, their very nod or
					look, their smile or frown, and especially their admonitions
					directed to particular persons, are of weighty importance
					to such as can brook or attend to them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Directions concerning Praising.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for commendation, some caution and mean is to
					be observed in it; because to be either deficient or excessive in that particular shows a base spirit. He is but a
					morose and rigid hearer whom no part of an oration can
					work upon or move, one who is full of a secret presumptuous opinion of himself, and of an inbred conceit that he
					could do better things himself; one who dares not alter his
					countenance as occasion requires, or let fall the least word
					to testify his good wishes, but with silence and affected
					gravity hunts after the reputation of a sagacious and profound person, and thinks that all the praise is lost to himself which he bestows on others, as if it were money. For
					many wrest that sentence of Pythagoras, who used to say
					that he had learned by philosophy to admire nothing; but
					these men think that to admire nobody and to honor nobody consists in despising everybody, and they aim at seeming grave by being contemptuous. Philosophy indeed removes that foolish admiration and surprise which proceeds
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.455"/>
					
					from doubt or ignorance, by laying open to us the causes
					of things, but endeavors not to destroy all good-nature and
					humanity. And those who are truly good take it, for their
					greatest honor and commendation to be just in paying
					honor and commendation where it is due to others; and
					for a man to adorn another is a most glorious ornament,
					proceeding from a generous abundance of glory and honor
					in himself; while those who are niggardly in praising
					others only betray how poor and bare they are of praises
					at home.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Not to be too prone to commend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet to use no consideration at all, but to stand up and
						make a clamor at every word or syllable, is to offend in the
						other extreme. Such fluttering fellows for the most part
						oblige not the speakers themselves, and are always a plague
						and common grievance to the hearers, exciting them many
						times against their inclination, and forcing them for very
						shame to join in the tumult. In the end, he that raised
						the disturbance receives no benefit by the discourse, but
						goes away with the character of a scoffer or flatterer or
						novice. A judge, it is true, ought to hear and determine
						without favor or ill-will, regarding only what is just and
						equitable; but in philosophical proceedings the case is
						altered, where neither law nor oaths tie us up from being
						favorable to the speaker. And the ancients in their temples were wont to place the statue of Mercury among the
						Graces, intimating that orators ought to find a propitious
						and good-natured audience. For they thought it passed all
						belief, that any man could prove so much a blockhead or
						come so wide of the purpose, that, though he should make
						no remarks of his own and quote none of others worthy
						taking notice of, or though the argument and de sign of his
						discourse might not be commendable, yet at least the order
						and disposition or the style should not deserve some
						applause;&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.456"/>
						
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>As oft amidst the furze and thorny brakes</l>
							           <l>The tender violets more securely peep.</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For if some have undertaken successfully to speak in
						commendation of vomiting or a fever, and have even made
						an encomium on a porridge-pot not without some acceptance, certainly a discourse from one that has the least pre
						tence to philosophy cannot but afford some opportunity,
						though it be a slight one, for commendation to a welldisposed auditory. Plato says that all who are in their
						bloom in some way excite the amorous man;&mdash;the fair are
						the children of the Gods, the black are manly, the hooknosed have a look of majesty, the flat-nose gives a graceful
						air, even the sallow complexion is complimented for looking like honey; in spite of all their defects, he cherishes
						and loves them all.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Republic, V. p. 474 D.</note> Thus love, like ivy, must needs find
						something or other to lay hold on. But much more will a studious hearer and scholar be sure to find some not unworthy
						reason for praising every speaker. For Plato in an oration of Lysias, disliking the invention and utterly condemning the disposition as confused, yet praised the style and
						elocution, because every word was wrought off cleverly
						and cleanly turned. Thus a man may see cause enough
						to disapprove the argument of Archilochus, the verse of
						Parmenides, the poverty of Phocylides, the eternal talk of
						Euripides, and inequality of style in Sophocles; and among
						the orators, one has no manner, another is not moving, a
						third has nothing of ornament; yet every one has his
						peculiar power of moving and exciting, for which he is
						praised. Some again do not require of us to testify our
						acceptance by the voice; a pleasing eye or cheerful look,
						or a behavior without any thing of pain or uneasiness, is
						all that they desire. For the following favors are nowadays bestowed of course upon every oration, though the
						speaker may speak to no purpose at all,&mdash;sitting modestly
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.457"/>
						
						without lolling from one side to the other, looking earnestly
						on the speaker, in the posture of an attentive listener, and
						with a countenance which betrays not only no contempt or illwill but not even a mind otherwise employed. For as the
						beauty and excellence of every thing consists in the concurrence of many different accidents, which contribute to
						the symmetry and harmony of the whole, so that, if but
						one inconsiderable part be away or absurdly added, deformity immediately follows; in like manner, not only a
						supercilious look or forbidding mien or roving eyes or
						waving the body to and fro or indecent crossing of the
						legs, but even a nod, a whisper to another, a scornful
						smile, a sleepy yawn, hanging of the head, or the like,
						are all likewise great indecorums and to be avoided with
						particular care.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Yet some there are who can assign a speaker his
					part, and think no duty incumbent on themselves all the
					while; who will have him prepare and premeditate what
					he has to deliver, and yet throw themselves into an
					auditory without any preparation or consideration, as if
					they were invited to a feast, to revel and take their pleasures at another's cost. Yet it is known that even a guest
					has some things required of him to make him suitable and
					agreeable, and certainly a hearer has much more; because
					he ought to be a sharer in the discourse and an assistant
					to the speaker. Neither will it become him to be severe
					at all turns upon every slight miscarriage or perpetually
					putting the speaker's elocution and action to the test,
					while he himself is guilty of grosser enormities in hearing, without danger or control. But as at tennis he
					that takes the ball turns and winds his body according to
					the motion of the server, so a kind of proportion is to be
					observed between the speaker and the hearer, if both will
					discharge their several duties.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.458"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Care to be observed in Praising Persons of all Qualities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither ought we to use any expressions of praise
					indifferently. For it is an ill thing which Epicurus relates,
					that, upon reading any epistles from his friends, those about
					him broke out into tumultuous applauses; and such as
					daily introduce new forms into our auditories, as Divinely
					saidSuperhuman! Inimitable! (as if those used by
					Plato, Socrates, and Hyperides, Well! Wisely! Truly
					said! were not sufficiently expressive), exceed the bounds of
					decency and modesty, nay indeed, do but affront the
					speaker, as though he were fond of such extravagant
					praises. Nor are they less odious and troublesome who
					confirm approbation with impertinent oaths, as if they were
					giving their testimony for a speaker in a court of judicature. And so likewise is it with such as observe not to
					give just deference to the quality of persons, who to a
					philosopher are apt to cry out, Smartly said! or to a reverend gentleman, Wittily! Floridly! applying to philosophy
					such trifles as are proper to scholastic exercises and declamations, and giving meretricious applause to a sober discourse,&mdash;as if a man should compliment the conqueror
					in the Olympic games with a garland of lilies or roses, instead of laurel or wild olive. Euripides the poet one day
					at a rehearsal instructing the chorus in a part that was set
					to a serious air, one of the company unexpectedly fell out
					a laughing; Sir, said he, unless you were very stupid and
					insensible, you could not laugh while I sing in the grave
					mixolydian mood. In like manner a master of philosophy
					and politics may put a stop tothe unseasonable levity and
					pertness of a youngster, by telling him, You seem to be a
					madman and unacquainted with all manner of civility,
					otherwise you would not hum over your tunes or practise
					your new steps while I am discoursing of Gods, or the laws,
					or the supreme magistrate. For consider seriously what a
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.459"/>
					
					very scandalous thing it is that, while a philosopher is in
					his discourse, the passengers in the street, from the clamor
					and hooting of the hearers, should have reason to make it
					a question whether some piper or harper or morris-dancer
					were got in among them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Of bearing Admonitions and Reproofs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Admonitions and reprimands ought to be taken
					neither altogether insensibly nor yet sheepishly. For such
					as carry off a disgrace from a philosopher carelessly and
					without due concern, so as to grin at his reprehensions or
					scoffingly to praise him for them, as sharping parasites
					applaud the scurrilous reflection of their cullies,&mdash;such, I
					say, are shameless and insolent, and betray only their invincible impudence, which is no good or true argument of
					courage. Yet to bear handsomely without passion an innocent jest in raillery is not unbecoming the breeding of
					a gentleman, but a good accomplishment and altogether
					worthy of a Spartan. But when an exhortation to amendment of manners, like a bitter potion, is made up of harsh
					and unpleasant words, in such a case for a youth&mdash;instead of hearing submissively and running into a sweat or
					being seized with dizziness, when the mind is on fire with
					shame and confusion&mdash;to remain unmoved or sneer or
					dissemble his concernment is the certain sign of a dissolute
					and ill-bred man, one whose soul, like callous flesh, being
					hardened with a course of debauchery, will receive no scar
					or impression. Some young men indeed there are of a
					contrary disposition, who having undergone one rebuke fly
					off without ever looking back, turn renegades, and quite
					desert philosophy. These being naturally very modest have
					a good disposition toward an healthful habit of mind, but
					vitiate it by too much tenderness and effeminacy, which
					disables them for bearing a reproof or manfully submitting
					to a correction, and run after more pleasing harangues,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.460"/>
					
					wherewith some flatterers and Sophists soothe and bewitch
					them, without any benefit or advantage. For as he that
					flies from the surgeon after incision, and will not suffer the
					ligature to be applied, endures that part of his skill only
					which is painful, rejecting what would give him ease; so
					such a one as being lanced and scarified by a sharp oration has not patience till the wound be skinned over, goes
					away from philosophy tortured and harassed, without that
					benefit he might receive thereby. For not only Telephus's
					wound was cured by rusty filings of the spear (as Euripides
					has it), but whatever pain philosophy may occasion to a
					meek disposition will be cured and removed by the same
					discourse that gave the wound. He therefore that is reprehended must endure awhile and away with some pain, not
					presently be discouraged or out of heart. Let him behave
					himself as though he were to be initiated into the mysteries
					of philosophy, still hoping, after the lustrations and more
					troublesome ceremonies are undergone, he shall enjoy some
					considerable effect of his present troubles and inconveniences. Or suppose he be wrongfully chidden, it is but
					handsome to expect the conclusion; after that he may
					make his defence, and desire that such freedom and violence may be reserved to repress some other misdemeanor
					which really deserves it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">The Difficulties in Philosophy vincible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But besides this,&mdash;as in grammar, music, and the
					exercises of activity, there are many things which to young
					beginners appear troublesome, laborious, and obscure,
					which yet a fuller knowledge, like acquaintance among
					men, makes more agreeable, ready, and feasible,&mdash;in like
					manner, though philosophy in its first terms and notions
					may seem uncouth and strange, yet a man must not be so
					far discouraged at the first elements as to throw it up
					altogether, but he must bid at all and ply his business
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.461"/>
					
					hard and patiently expect that acquaintance which will
					make all easy and pleasant; and that will not be long in
					coming, bringing great light into things and exciting ardent
					affections to virtue; without which to endure to live, after
					one has through his own effeminacy fallen from philosophy,
					is an argument of a mean spirit and servile disposition. I
					must confess there is some difficulty in the things themselves which is not easily conquered by raw and unexperienced beginners; yet the greatest part of the difficulty they
					bring upon themselves by their own ignorance and inadvertency, falling into the same error from two contrary
					causes. For some, out of a foolish bashfulness and desire
					to be easy to the speaker, are loath to be inquisitive or have
					the thing made plain to them, and so they nod their assent
					to every thing that is said, as if they fully comprehended it.
					And others out of unseasonable vain-glory, and vying with
					their fellows that they may vaunt their readiness of wit
					and quickness of apprehension, pretend to understand
					things before they do, and never understand them at all.
					Now the consequence in both cases is this; the modest go
					away in a great deal of anxiety and doubt, and are forced in
					the end, with greater disgrace, to interrupt the speaker to be
					informed again; and the vain-glorious are troubled to keep
					close and conceal the ignorance they carry about them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Therefore all such sheepishness and self-conceit
					being set aside, let us learn to lay up in our minds whatever is usefully said, enduring to be laughed at by such as
					set up for wits and railers. This course took Cleanthes
					and Xenocrates, who being somewhat slower than their
					fellows did not therefore give over hearing or despond;
					but prevented the jests of others, by comparing themselves
					to narrow-mouthed vessels and to copper plate; because,
					though they received learning with some difficulty, yet they
					retained it surely. For he that will be a good man must
					not only, as Phocylides says,&mdash;
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.462"/>
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Expect much fraud, and many a time be caught,&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
					
					but be laughed at and disgraced, and endure many scurrilous
					and virulent reflections; he must also encounter ignorance
					and wrestle with it with all the strength of his mind, and
					subdue it too.</p>
            <p>Neither on the other hand must the faults be passed by
						which some troublesome people commit out of mere
						laziness and negligence; such men as will not bestow any
						pains in considering themselves, but asking often the same
						questions are a perpetual vexation to the speaker; like
						callow birds always gaping at the bill of the old one,
						and still reaching after what has been prepared and
						worked over by others. Another sort there are, who,
						affecting the reputation of quickness and attention, confound the speaker with their pragmatical curiosity and
						jargon, always haling in something unnecessary and requiring demonstrations of things foreign to the business
						in hand.
						
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thus a short way is long and tedious made,</l>
               </quote>
						
						as Sophocles<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Antigone, 232.</note> says, and that not only to themselves, but
						others also. For by taking off the speaker with vain and
						unnecessary questions they retard the progress of instruction, like travellers in the road, by impertinent halts and
						stops. Hieronymus compares these men to lazy and
						greedy curs, which within doors bite and tear the skins of
						wild animals and lie tugging at their shaggy hair, but in
						the field dare not fasten upon beasts themselves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">A Concluding Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet one exhortation let me leave with these people, that
						having received the general heads of things they would
						supply the rest by their own industry, making their
						memory a guide to their invention; and that, looking on
						the discourse of others only as a kind of first principle or
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.463"/>
						
						seed, they would take care to cherish and increase it. For
						the mind requires not like an earthen vessel to be filled
						up; convenient fuel and aliment only will inflame it with
						a desire of knowledge and ardent love of truth. Now, as
						it would be with a man who, going to his neighbor's to
						borrow fire and finding there a great and bright fire,
						should sit down to warm himself and forget to go home;
						so is it with the one who comes to another to learn, if he
						does not think himself obliged to kindle his own fire within and inflame his own mind, but continues sitting by his
						master as if he were enchanted, delighted by hearing.
						Such a one, although he may get the name of a philosopher, as we get a bright color by sitting by the fire,
						will never clear away the mould and rust of his mind, and
						dispel the darkness of his understanding by the help of
						philosophy. In fine, if there is any other precept concerning hearing, it is briefly this, to be careful in observing
						the last exhortation,&mdash;that is, to join the exercise of our
						invention to our hearing; that so, while we lay down the
						rule that hearing well is the first step to living well, we
						may not content ourselves with a superficial commonplace
						knowledge, but endeavor after such a philosophical habit
						as shall be deeply imprinted on the mind.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>