<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De sollertia animalium</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.129">
      <body>
         <head>Which are the most crafty, water-animals
				or those creatures that breed upon the
				land?
				<lb/> Autobulus, Soclarus, Optatus, Phaedimus, Aristotimus, Heracleo.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.157"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Autobulus. Leonidas, being asked the question what
				he thought of Tyrtaeus, made answer, that he was a good
				poet to whet minds of young men; as a person who,
				by the vigor and spirit of his poetical raptures, kindled
				that wrathful indignation and ambition of honor, which
				emboldened them in combat to the contempt of death and
				danger. Which makes me afraid, my dearest friends, lest
				the encomium of hunting yesterday recited may have inflamed our young gentlemen beyond the bounds of moderation, so as to deem all other things fruitless and of little
				worth, while they rendezvous from all parts to this exercise. So much the rather, because I myself, when I was
				but very young, even beyond the strength of my age,
				seemed to be more than became me addicted to this sport,
				and to be over desirous with Phaedra in Euripides,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With hounds and horn and merry hollow,
					</l>
                     <l>The spotted hart and hind to follow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>So did that discourse affect me, fortified with many and
					probable arguments.</p>
            <p>SOCLARUS. You say very truly, Autobulus. For that
					same poet seems to me to have awakened the force of
					rhetoric, for a long time lulled asleep, to gratify the inclinations
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.158"/>
					
					 of the youthful gentry, and to make himself their
					spring companion. But I am most pleased with him for
					introducing the example of single combatants, from whence
					he takes occasion to praise the sport of hunting, as being
					that which for the most part draws to itself whatever is
					natural in us, or what we have by use acquired, of that delight which men take in fighting with single weapons one
					against another, thus affording an evident prospect of artifice and daring courage, endued with understanding, encountering brutish force and strength, and applauding that
					of Euripides:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Small is the nerveless strength of feeble man,
						</l>
                     <l>Yet through the cunning of his reaching brain,
						</l>
                     <l>By various slights and sundry stratagems,
						</l>
                     <l>Whatever land or th' Ocean breeds he tames.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 218.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>AUTOBULUS. And hence it was, as they say, my dearest
				Soclarus, that men at first became insensible and inhuman,
				having once tasted of murder, and being all accustomed,
				by hunting and following the chase, not only to behold
				without remorse the wounds and blood of wild beasts, but
				to rejoice at their being killed and slaughtered. Afterwards, as at Athens, some sycophant was by the Thirty
				Tyrants set apart for death, as a proper object of capital
				punishment, then a second, and a third; till, proceeding by
				degrees, they seized upon good men, and at length spared
				not the best and most worthy citizens. In like manner
				the first that slew a bear or a wolf obtained applause,
				then the ox and hog were appointed to be killed, under
				pretence of having tasted the sacred things that lay before
				them. Next to them deer, hares, and goats were made
				use of for food, and in some places the flesh of sheep,
				dogs, and horses grew familiar to human taste. The tame
				goose also and pigeon, man's familiar domestic, according
				to Sophocles,&mdash;not for nourishment or to assuage hunger,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.159"/>
				
				as cats and weasels do, but to indulge voluptuous appetites,
				&mdash;they dressed and mangled to pieces. This gave strength
				and vigor to whatever was in nature bloodthirsty and
				savage, and rendering the disposition of man inflexible
				to pity, had almost erased out of his breast whatever was
				inclinable to humanity and mildness. Whereas, on the other
				side, the Pythagoreans, that they might accustom men to
				the love of humanity and compassion, still inculcated into
				their minds a particular care of being mild and gentle
				towards beasts. For there is nothing more powerful than
				custom to win upon all the affections of man, and to
				draw them from moderation to extremity. But I know not
				how it comes to pass, that being entered into this discourse, we have forgot not only the subject we were yesterday upon, but what we had also this day agreed to
				make the theme of our colloquy. For yesterday, as you
				well know, having thrown out a proposition, that all creatures were in some manner partakers of understanding
				and reason, we gave an occasion to you, young huntsmen,
				for a fair dispute, which of the two excelled in craft and
				cunning, the land animals, or the creatures that breed in
				the sea? Which, if you please, we will determine this
				day, if Aristotimus and Phaedimus will stand to their
				agreement; of which two gentlemen, the one has offered
				himself to his friends to be the patron of the land animals,
				the other reserves the honor of being more crafty to those
				of the sea.</p>
            <p>SOCLARUS. They will be as good as their words, I assure
					you, Autobulus, and will be here presently; for I saw them
					both early this morning preparing for the combat. In the
					mean time, if you please, before they begin, let us resume
					something of what was yesterday not so fully discoursed
					of for want of time, or not so carefully argued in our
					wine, as it ought to have been. For there seemed a dispute to resound in my ears from the Stoics' portico, that,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.160"/>
					
					as immortal is opposite to mortal, incorruptible to corruptible, incorporeal to corporeal, in like manner things void
					of reason ought to be opposed to those beings that are endued with reason, lest among so many pairs of contraries
					this alone should be found maimed and imperfect.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>AUTOBULUS. Good now, friend Soclarus, who was he
				that maintained that, because there are certain beings endued with reason, therefore there is nothing void of reason? For we abound with examples in all things that are
				destitute of a soul; nor do we want any other antithesis to
				irrational, but only to oppose whatever is deprived of a
				soul&mdash;as being void of reason and understanding&mdash;to
				that which is endued with reason and understanding together with a soul. But if any one will assert, that Nature is not defective, and that therefore animated Nature is
				partly rational, partly without reason; another may at the
				same time allege, that animated Nature is partly endued
				with imagination, partly deprived of it; partly sensible,
				partly insensible; to the end that Nature may not want
				these opposite habits and privations, as it were, equally
				balanced in the same kind. For, as it would be absurd to
				expect to find some living creatures sensible and others
				without sense, and equally ridiculous to grant imagination
				to some living creatures and not alllow it to others,&mdash;since
				there is no living creature that comes into the world but
				what is presently endued with sense and imagination,&mdash;
				thus would he be as much out of the way, who should require one living creature to be rational and another void
				of reason, and that too when he is disputing with men
				who hold that nothing whatever can partake of sense
				which does not also partake of understanding, and that
				there is no animal not endued by Nature with opinion and
				ratiocination, as well as with sense and instinct. For Nature, which, as they truly say, made all things for the sake
				of something and to some end, did not make a sensible
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.161"/>
				
				creature to be merely sensible of barely suffering something; but since there are many things familiar and agreeable, and other things as baneful and pernicious, no one of
				them could survive for a moment, did they not learn to
				avoid some things and covet the use and benefit of others.
				Sense it is, therefore, that affords to every creature the
				knowledge both of useful and hurtful; but the discretion
				which accompanies the said sense, choosing and seizing
				upon things profitable, and discerning and avoiding things
				pernicious or troublesome, can never be thought to reside
				in any creature not capable to reason, to judge, remember,
				and consider. Therefore, if you will deprive the creatures
				of expectation, memory, design, preparation, hope, fear,
				desire, and grief, you must at the same time deny them the
				use either of eyes or ears, and indeed of all sense and imagination; which it is better for them to be without, since
				they cannot make use of them, than to labor under grief
				and pain, with no means present of averting them.</p>
            <p>There is an oration of Strato the philosopher, demonstrating that without sense there can be no understanding.
					For many times letters cursorily glanced upon by the eye,
					and speeches little regarded by the ear, escape our knowledge, our minds being intent on other matters. Afterwards by recollection the same things return into our mind,
					for us to run through and pursue them in our thoughts as
					we please. Whence we say proverbially, <q direct="unspecified">The mind sees,
						the mind hears; all other things are deaf and blind,</q> in
					regard there can be no sense in the eyes and ears, if understanding be wanting. Therefore King Cleomenes,
					after great commendations given to a copy of verses recited
					at a banquet where he was present, being asked whether
					it were not an admirable piece, bid them that heard it give
					their judgment, for that his mind was in the Peloponnesus.
					Therefore of necessity, whatever creatures are capable of
					sense must also be capable of understanding, if we can
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.162"/>
					
					no otherwise be sensible than by the force of understanding.</p>
            <p>But suppose we should grant that sense has no need of
					the understanding for the performance of the duty incumbent upon it; nevertheless, when that same sense which
					has shown an animal the difference between what is grateful and what is averse to Nature has departed, where is
					that faculty which retains this difference in the memory,
					&mdash;dreading things that are abominable, and longing after
					things that are useful, and if they are wanting, seeking
					means to compass them,&mdash;which provides animals receptacles and places of refuge, that they may look out after their
					prey, and avoid the snares and gins of the hunters? And
					yet those very authors inculcate these things in their introductions, even to the teasing our ears: defining purpose
					to be an indication that something is to be brought to
					completion; design to be an impulse before an impulse;
					preparation to be an action before an action; memory to
					be the comprehension of some certain past impression,
					which at first was apprehended by sense. In all which
					things there is nothing which may not rightly be said to
					partake of reason, and yet all these things are common to
					all creatures; as indeed are certainly all cogitations;
					which, while they lie concealed in the brain, we call
					thoughts, but when they come to be in motion, we name
					conceptions. In the mean time they acknowledge all
					passions and perturbations of the mind to be false judgments and erroneous opinions; so that it is a wonder to
					me, that the same men should oversee so many operations
					and motions, some of desire, others of fear, nay, by Jupiter, many times of envy and emulation itself. And many
					times they themselves punish their dogs and horses when
					they commit a fault, and this not to no purpose, but to
					chastise them by causing in them through pain that trouble
					of mind which we call repentance. Now the tickling the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.163"/>
					
					ear by pleasing sounds is called enchantment, but the bewitching the eye is called bewitching; both which we
					make use of in the domesticating of wild beasts. Harts
					and horses are allured by the sounds of pipes and flutes.
					And there are a sort of crabs which are charmed out of
					their holes by fifes; and it is reported that the shadfish are
					drawn to show themselves above water by singing and
					clapping of hands. The otus also, which is a bird not
					much unlike a night-raven, is taken by allurement of the
					sight; for that while he stands staring upon the fowlers
					dancing before him in measure and figure, and out of
					affection will be striving to act his part by aping their
					motions with his wings and shoulders, he is frequently surprised and taken.</p>
            <p>But as for those that more foolishly affirm that beasts
					are not affected with joy or anger or fear, that the swallow does not build, that the bee does not remember, that
					the lion is not angry, that the hart is not timorous, but that
					they do all these things only as it were and apparently; I
					would fain know what answer they will make to those who
					say, that beasts neither see nor hear, but as it were see and
					as it were hear; that they neither neigh nor bleat, but as
					it were send forth a certain sound; lastly, that they do not
					absolutely live, but live as it were? For, in my opinion,
					to aver this is as contrary to plain demonstration as the
					rest.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>SOCLARUS. Well then, Autobulus, suppose me to be
				one of those that affirm these things. For it is great
				folly for men to compare the actions of beasts with the
				customs, actions, and manner of living men, and above all,
				to deny that beasts have the least inclination or aim at any
				progress towards virtue, to which we bent our discourse.
				Indeed, I doubt whether Nature gave them a beginning or
				no, since they are so incapable to attain the end.</p>
            <p>AUTOBULUS. Why truly, Soclarus, this is not a thing that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.164"/>
					
					seems so absurd to those men. For that while they assert
					the extreme love of parents towards their children to be
					the principle of society and justice, and find at the same
					time this virtue apparent and surpassing in brute animals,
					yet they will not allow them in the least to partake of justice; like mules, which, though they are furnished with
					genital parts, as wanting neither privities nor wombs, and
					mixing with delight and pleasure, yet cannot attain the end
					of generation. But then again I would have you consider,
					whether they be not ridiculous, that affirm Socrates or
					Plato to be no less vicious than the meanest of slaves,&mdash;
					nay more, that they were fools, intemperate, and unjust,&mdash;
					and then find fault with the nature of beasts, as being
					impure and no way accurately framed for the reception of
					virtue; as if this were proof of utter want of reason, and
					not of depravedness and imbecility of reason. And all
					the while, they acknowledge that there are vices of reason,
					of which all brute beasts are guilty; many of which we
					plainly find to be intemperate, fearful, malicious, and unjust. Therefore he that denies that reason exists by Nature
					in a creature, because it is not framed by Nature to attain
					to the perfection of reason, little differs from one that
					should deny a monkey to partake of deformity by Nature,
					or a tortoise of slowness, as being neither susceptible of
					beauty or swiftness. Nor do they observe the distinction
					that lies before their eyes. For reason is in the creature
					by Nature, but right and perfect reason is attained by industry and education; so that naturally all creatures may
					be said to be rational. But if they look for perfection of
					reason and true wisdom, they will hardly find those perfections in any man whatever. For as there is a difference
					between sight and sight, and between flight and flight,
					&mdash;for hawks and grasshoppers do not see alike, neither do
					eagles and partridges fly with equal swiftness,&mdash;so neither
					in all rational creatures is there to be found the same perfection
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.165"/>
					
					 of cunning and acuteness. For as there are many
					examples to be produced of several brute creatures, excelling in the observance of society; fortitude, and foresight
					as to their particular economy and making provision for
					themselves; so on the other side, there may be found
					among them as many of injustice, cowardice, and folly.
					Which is evident from the present contest wherein these
					young gentlemen have engaged themselves, while the one
					has undertaken to maintain that land-animals, the other
					that creatures bred in the sea, are most inclined to virtue.
					Which is plainly demonstrated by comparing river-horses
					with storks. For the one support and cherish their fathers,
					the others kill them that they may enjoy their dams. So
					likewise, if you compare doves with partridges. For the
					cock partridge will not suffer the hen to sit, but breaks her
					eggs and throws them out of the nest if she refuses to be
					trod. But the cock pigeon takes upon him part of the
					female's duty, in brooding over the eggs and feeding the
					young ones; and if the hen happens to be too long absent,
					he corrects her with his bill, till he forces her to return to
					her nest. So that, while Antipater found fault with sheep
					and asses for their nastiness, I wonder how he came to
					pass by lynxes and swallows, of which the one are so
					cleanly that they always remove and hide their excrements,
					the others teach their young ones to turn their tails out of
					their nest, before they let fall their defilement. And indeed, why may we not say that one tree is more docible
					than another, as dogs are more docible than sheep; or one
					pot-herb more timorous than another, as harts are more
					fearful than lions? Or otherwise, as among things immovable, there is not one thing slower in motion than another;
					nor among things that are mute, one thing more vocal than
					another; so neither, among things to which Nature has
					not afforded a faculty of understanding, is there one thing
					more timorous, more slothful, or more intemperate than
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.166"/>
					
					another. But as to those creatures where that faculty is
					present, the difference is manifest in the degrees of more
					or less.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>SOCLARUS. However, it is a wonderful thing to observe, how much man differs from all other creatures in
				probity of manners, in industry, and in all those things
				that relate to justice and common society.</p>
            <p>AUTOBULUS. Nevertheless, my dear friend, this cannot
					be denied, that there are many brute beasts that surpass
					men both in bulk and swiftness, others that far surpass him
					in strength of sight and exactness of hearing; and yet for
					all this we are not to say that man is blind, without
					strength, or wants ears. For Nature has not deprived us
					either of hands or eyes or strength or bulk, though we
					must not compare with camels or elephants. In like manner we must not say that brute beasts are altogether deprived of reason and understanding, because they are more
					dull of understanding, and not so quick at ratiocination as
					we are, as only enjoying a weak and muddy sort of reason,
					like a dim and clouded eye. And did I not presently expect these young gentlemen, being persons both studious
					and learned, to bring together an infinite number of examples in reference to both land and sea-animals, I could
					produce a thousand examples of docility and a thousand
					more of good nature in beasts, which the famous city of
					Rome has given us an opportunity to fetch from her imperial theatres; but we will leave these things fresh and
					untouched, for them to embellish with their eloquent discourse.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I have something to offer by the by,
					which is this, that I am of opinion that there is a mutilation, disease, and defect peculiar to every part and faculty,
					&mdash;as blindness of the eye, lameness of the leg, and stuttering of the tongue,&mdash;which defects cannot be appropriated to any other members. For that blindness can
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.167"/>
					
					never be attributed to that which was never created to see,
					nor lameness to that which never could go, nor can any
					thing be said to stammer that wants a tongue, or to lisp or
					stutter that has not a vocal utterance. And nothing can
					be said to be a changeling or beside his wits or mad, to
					which Nature never gave the use of thought, reason, and
					understanding; for it is impossible to be so without some
					faculty that can suffer either privation or mutilation or
					some other defect. But you have seen dogs that were
					mad, and I have seen horses under the same predicament;
					and some there are who say that bulls and foxes will be
					mad. But the example of dogs is sufficient, which is unquestionable. This makes it evident, that those creatures
					have a sort of reason and understanding not to be despised,
					which being once confused and troubled, the affection
					arises which is called madness. For we do not find either
					their sight or their hearing diminished. Now, as when a
					man is affected with hypochondriac melancholy, or in a
					delirium, it would be absurd to say that he was not beside
					himself, or that his sense, reason, and memory were not
					disturbed,&mdash;for custom tells that they who are in a raving
					condition are not in their right senses, but are fallen from
					their reason,&mdash;so whoever believes that there is any other
					cause why dogs run mad, but only that their natural senses,
					reason, and memories are disturbed, while they cease to
					know faces the most familiar to them before, and abandon
					their most usual food, and overlook what is just before their
					eyes, such a man, I say, seems to me either to overlook what
					is just before his eyes, or else, seeing the conclusions that
					follow, to fight against the truth itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>SOCLARUS. You seem to me to be very much in the
				right, for the Stoics and Peripatetics are led to affirm the
				contrary upon this supposition, that justice could have no
				certain original, but would be altogether incomprehensible and inexistent if all brute creatures should partake
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.168"/>
				
				of reason. For either of necessity we must do a very
				great piece of injustice when we devour and feed upon
				them; or if we forbear the use of them, it will be impossible for us to live, or rather we shall in some measure
				live the lives of beasts, rejecting the use of brute creatures.
				I pass by those innumerable myriads of nomades and
				Troglodytes that know no other food but flesh. But as
				for us that seem to live lovingly and in friendship together, what necessity would there be of laboring on the
				earth, toiling upon the sea, or mining in the mountains,
				what ornament would there be in our life, if it were so
				that we must be bound to live, as it would then become
				us, not only without injury but rather with all civility and
				humanity toward all the sorts of beasts, as being our fellow
				rational creatures? We have no cure, no remedy for an
				unquestionable necessity that deprives us either of life or
				justice, unless we observe that ancient bound and dispensation which, according to Hesiod, distinguishing natures and
				separating every kind by themselves, commands
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The fish, wild beasts, and all the winged fowl,
					</l>
                     <l>To prey upon their kinds without control,
					</l>
                     <l>For among them no law nor justice reigns;
					</l>
                     <l>Only by justice man from man abstains.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 275.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, as brutes can extend no act of justice to
					us, so neither can we commit any act of injustice against
					them. Which argument they who reject have left us no
					benefit of life, nor any the smallest entrance for justice
					into the world.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>AUTOBULUS. These things, dear friend, you utter,
				as the opinion of those people. But we are not to allow
				philosophers a remedy to procure easy delivery, as they do
				to women that are subject to hard labors, merely that they
				may bring us forth justice without any pain or trouble.
				For the same persons, even in the greatest matters, will
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.169"/>
				
				not allow to Epicurus so small and pitiful a thing as the
				slightest inclination of one only atom, for to make way for
				the stars and living creatures and Fortune to come into the
				world, and that thereby our free will might be saved. For
				we ought either to prove what is doubtful or to assume
				what of itself is manifest; so we ought not to take for
				granted this doctrine touching beasts as regards justice,
				unless it is either confessed or otherwise proved by demonstration. For justice has another way to establish itself,
				neither so steep nor so slippery, nor leading to the subversion of evident truths; but which, according to Plato's instruction, my son and thy friend, Soclarus, has showed to
				such as are not captiously contentious but willing to learn.
				For certain it is, that both Empedocles and Heraclitus held
				it for a truth, that man could not be altogether cleared
				from injustice in dealing with beasts as he now does;
				often bewailing and exclaiming against Nature, as if she
				were nothing else but necessity and war, having neither
				any thing unmixed nor any thing truly pure, but still
				arriving at her end by many, and those unjust and unlawful passions. Whence they affirm that generation itself
				originally proceeded from injustice by the conjunction of
				immortal with mortal, and that the thing engendered is still
				contrary to Nature delighted with the parts of that which
				engenders, dismembered from the whole. But this seems
				to be too luxuriant and severe an accusation of Nature.
				For there is yet a more moderate excuse, which does not
				altogether deprive the beasts of reason, yet justifies the
				necessary and convenient use of them; which when the
				ancients introduced, they detested and utterly discountenanced voracious and voluptuous gluttony. Pythagoras
				also resumed the argument, teaching how we might reap
				the benefit of the creatures without doing injustice. For
				they do no injustice, that chastise and kill such savage
				beasts that are both hurtful to man and never will be
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.170"/>
				
				tame. But taming such as are gentle and loving to men,
				they thereby make them assistant in the several uses to
				which they were ordained,&mdash;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The horse and ass, that backs to load resign,
					</l>
                     <l>And race of bulls,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>which, as Prometheus in Aeschylus<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the lost tragedy, Prometheus Unbound, Frag. 188 (Nauck). (G.)</note> observes,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Kind Heaven vouchsafed to men by toil distrest,
						</l>
                     <l>With servile limbs his labors to assist.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we make use of dogs to guard our goats and
					sheep, while they are milked and shorn. For life does
					not presently forsake a man unless he have his platters
					of fish or livers of geese, or unless he may kill whole oxen
					or kids to supply his banquets, or unless&mdash;that he may
					disport himself in the theatre or take his pleasure in hunting&mdash;he may compel some beasts to be daring and to
					fight against their wills, and kill others whom Nature has
					not armed to defend themselves. For, in my opinion, he
					that is for sport and pastime ought to seek out for such as
					will sport and be merry with him. And as it was the saying of Bion, that, though boys throw stones at frogs in
					sport, yet the frogs do not die in sport but in earnest; so
					in hunting and fishing, the fault is in the men delighting
					in the torments and cruel deaths of beasts, and tearing
					them without compassion from their whelps and their
					young ones. For it is not in the making use of beasts
					that men do them wrong, but in the wastefully and cruelly
					destroying them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>SOCLARUS. Contain yourself, my dearest Autobulus,
				and forbear these accusations; for here are several gentlemen coming, all great huntsmen, whom it will be very difficult to bring over to your opinion; neither is it convenient
				to offend them.</p>
            <p>AUTOBULUS. You give me good advice. However, I
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.171"/>
					
					know Eubiotus very well, and my kinsman Ariston; nor
					am I less acquainted with Aeacides and Aristotimus, the
					sons of Dionysius the Delphian, as also with Nicander the
					son of Euthydamus, all expert in the chase by land, as
					Homer expresses it; and therefore likely to take part with
					Aristotimus. On the other side, yonder comes Phaedimus
					too, bringing along with him the islanders and neighbors
					to the sea, Heracleon of Megara, and Philostratus of
					Euboea,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whose whole delight is all the day
						</l>
                     <l>The toilsome pastime of the sea.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Odyss. XII. 116.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But as for Optatus, our equal in years (like Tydides),&mdash;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which of the sides to range him well,
						</l>
                     <l>So versed in both, we cannot tell.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. V. 85.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For he is one that offers as well the first-fruits of his
					fishery to Dictynna, as of his forest spoils to Diana; so
					that it is apparent he comes among us as one that intends
					not to be partial to one side more than the other; or else
					our conjecture is amiss, dear Optatus, that your design is
					only to be an impartial umpire between these young
					gentlemen.</p>
            <p>OPTATUS. You conjecture very truly, Autobulus. For
					the ancient law of Solon is out of date, that punished
					those who stood neuters and refused to adhere to either
					side.</p>
            <p>AUTOBULUS. Seat yourself then here by us, that if there
					should be any occasion for a testimony, we may not be
					troubled to run to Aristotle's writings, but acquiescing in
					your experience, may give our suffrages according to what
					you aver for truth.</p>
            <p>OPTATUS. Go to then, young gentlemen: are ye agreed
					upon the method and order of the dispute?</p>
            <p>PHAEDIMUS. Truly, worthy Soclarus, that very thing
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.172"/>
					
					occasioned a great debate among us; but at length, according to that of Euripides,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The child of Fortune, Chance, the point agreed,
						</l>
                     <l>And fixed the method how we should proceed,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>by giving the precedence to the land animals to plead their
					cause before marine creatures.</p>
            <p>SOCLARUS. Then, Aristotimus, it is high time for you to
					speak and for us to hear.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>ARISTOTIMUS. The court is open to all concerned in
				the controversy. ... Others there are that kill their young
				ones by leaping the females at the very instant of their
				bringing forth. There are a sort of mullets, called pardiae,
				that feed upon their own slime. But the polypus sits all
				the winter feeding upon itself,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In fireless house, and domicils forlorn;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 525.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so slothful, or so stupid, or so given to his gut he is, or
					else so abandoned to all those vices together. And therefore Plato again and again forbids, or rather makes it his
					wish, in his laws, that young men might not be permitted
					to addict themselves to marine fishery, wherein there is no
					exercise of strength' no cogitation of wisdom, nor any
					thing that contributes to fortitude, swiftness, or agility, in
					combating against pikes, congers, or scates; whereas, in
					the chase of wild beasts, the fiercer sort accustom the
					huntsman to contempt of danger, the more subtle sort exercise and sharpen his wit and cunning, the swifter sort
					exercise his strength, and render him more apt to endure
					labor. These are the advantages that accrue to a man by
					hunting; but in fishing, there is nothing worth his while.
					For never any of the Gods got honor by the surname of
					a conger-killer; as Apollo was surnamed the wolf-slayer;
					never any of the Deities gloried in being a darter of mullets, as Diana is honored with the addition of hart-darting.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.173"/>
					
					And what wonder is it, when it is accounted more noble
					for a man to kill than to buy a wild boar, a hart, a goat,
					or a hare, but more honorable to buy a tunny, a lobster, or
					an amy, than to kill one? And therefore, because there is
					nothing in fishing that is noble, no using of gins and
					slight of cunning, it is accounted a sorry, pitiful exercise,
					not worth a man's labor.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>In general then, since the usual arguments by which
				philosophers demonstrate that beasts partake of reason
				are these following,&mdash;purpose, contrivance, memory, passions, care of their young ones, gratefulness to those from
				whom they receive kindnesses, and the remembrance of
				shrewd turns, to which we may add the search after and
				choice of what is needful and beneficial for them, together
				with apparent shows of virtue, as of fortitude, society,
				continence, and magnanimity,&mdash;if we consider the marine
				creatures, we shall not find that our strictest observation
				can perceive in them any of these excellences, or at best
				they are such obscure and imperfect glimmerings as are
				scarce discernible. But in terrestrial and land animals,
				there is not any man but may behold the most luculent, the
				most evident and uncontrollable demonstrations in the world
				of all that has been said. In the first place, observe the
				designs and preparations of bulls provoked to combat, and
				of wild boars whetting their teeth. Again, elephants&mdash;
				since, by digging up or tearing down the trees which they
				intend to feed upon, they blunt and wear out their tushes
				&mdash;make use of only one for those purposes, but reserve
				the other strong and sharp for their own defence. The
				lion also always walks with his feet inverted, hiding his claws
				withinside his paw, to prevent the hunter from tracing
				him easily by his footing. For the track of a lion's claw
				is not easily to be found, so that the hunters are frequently
				at a loss, and wander after the obscure and scarce discernible footsteps of those beasts. You have heard also, I suppose,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.174"/>
				
				 of the ichneumon, how that he arms himself as completely as a soldier with his breastplate and cuirass prepared for battle; in such a manner does that creature
				surround and wrap himself about with a coat of mail,
				when he attacks the crocodile.</p>
            <p>Admirable are the preparations of swallows before they
					go to lay their eggs, how they place the more solid stubble
					for foundations, and upon that build up the slighter straws;
					and if they perceive that the nest wants mud to serve as
					glue, you may observe how they fly to the next lake or
					sea, and after they have skimmed the superficies of the
					water with their wings,&mdash;so as to make them moist, yet
					not heavy with wet,&mdash;they lick up the dust, and so daub
					and bind together the loose and ill-cohering parts of the
					nest. As for the form of their architecture, it is composed
					neither of angles nor of many sides, but smooth and, as
					much as may be, spherical; for that such a figure is lasting and capacious, and not easily affording entrance to
					creatures that lie in wait for their destruction from without.</p>
            <p>Who is there that does not admire, for more reasons
					than one, the labor of the spiders, which seems as pattern
					for the threads that women spin and the nets that are used
					in hunting? For the extraordinary fineness of the spinning, and the evenness of the thread, not discontinued or
					snapped off like the yarn upon a quill, but having the
					smooth and subtle texture of a thin membrane, and knit
					and spun together with a certain clammy moisture imperceptibly mixed; besides the tincture of it, causing a kind
					of airy and misty color, the better to deceive; but above
					all, the conduct and governing of this little engine, in
					which when any thing happens to be entangled, you see
					how presently, like an expert huntsman, the subtle artist
					contracts her net and binds her prey within it;&mdash;all this,
					being every day obvious to our sight and contemplation,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.175"/>
					
					gives credit to my discourse, which otherwise might be
					accounted no less fabulous than what is reported of certain
					Libyan crows, that, when they are a-thirsty, throw stones
					into the water, by that means to raise it to such a height
					that they may be able to reach it with their bills. Then
					again, when I saw a ship dog, in the absence of the seamen, putting in stones in a half-empty jar of oil, it was to
					me a wonder how that dog should understand that the
					pressure of the heavier weight would make the lighter rise.</p>
            <p>And the same artifices are reported of Cretan bees and
					Cilician geese. For the first of these, being to take their
					flight about some windy promontory, ballast themselves
					with little stones, to prevent their being carried away by
					the stronger blasts. And as for the geese, they being
					afraid of the eagles, every time they cross the mountain
					Taurus, carry great stones in their mouths, to the end that
					by that means (as it were) bridling their gaggling tongues,
					they may cross the mountain in silence, without alarming
					their enemies.</p>
            <p>Extraordinary also is the caution which the cranes observe in their flight. For they fly, when the wind is very
					high and the air very tempestuous, not as in fair weather,
					all afront or in manner of the half-moon; but forming a
					triangular body, with the sharp angle of that figure they
					penetrate the wind that ruffles round about them, and by
					that means preserve their order unbroken. On the other
					side, when they fill upon the ground, those that are upon
					the night-watch stand with the whole weight of their
					bodies upon one leg, holding a stone in the claw of the
					other foot. For the holding of the stone keeps them
					awake for a long time together, and wakes them again
					with the noise of the fall if they happen to drop asleep.
					So that it was no wonder that Hercules laid his quiver
					under his arm-pit, and with his strenuous arm embracing
					his bow,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.176"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Slept all the night, where'er he laid his load,
						</l>
                     <l>With his right-handed weight upon the wood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nor do I so much admire at him who was the first that
					hit upon the way to open an oyster, when I meet with and
					consider the artifices of the herons. For a heron, when
					he has swallowed a closed oyster, endures the trouble
					and vexation of it for so long time, till he perceives it
					soften and relaxed by the heat of his stomach; then casting it up again gaping and divided, he takes out that
					which is fit for food.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But as it is a task of great labor accurately to relate
				the economy and contrivances of the emmets, so it would
				argue too much of negligence to pass them over in silence.
				For there is not in Nature a smaller creature; and yet it is
				a most absolute mirror of the greatest and most noble performances, and (as it were) in a transparent drop the
				appearance of all virtue. There is friendship to be discerned in their mutual society. There is the image of
				fortitude in the patient undergoing of labor. In them are
				to be seen many seeds of continence, many of wisdom and
				justice. Insomuch that Cleanthes, who denied that beasts
				were endued with reason, could not forbear reporting how
				he met with the following accident of a crowd of emmets,
				that came to another ant-hill, bringing along with them a
				dead emmet. Presently other emmets ascending out of
				their ant-hill seemed (as it were) to meet them, and then
				disappeared again; and this was done twice or thrice.
				Till at length the one side brought up from under ground
				a worm, as the price of the dead emmet's redemption,
				which the other party of pismires receiving, delivered the
				dead emmet, and so departed. But that which is apparent to all is their equity to each other when they meet one
				another, while they that carry nothing always give way to
				those that are burdened; nor are their divisions and partitions of things too weighty for single carriage less remarkable,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.177"/>
				
				 to the end the burdens may be divided among
				many. But when they bring forth their little eggs and expose them to the cold, Aratus makes it a sign of rainy
				weather.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When from her hollow cells th' industrious ant
					</l>
                     <l>Her hidden store of eggs brings forth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For in that sense many read <foreign lang="greek">h)/ia</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">provision</hi>) for <foreign lang="greek">w)/ea</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">eggs</hi>),
					referring it to the providence of those little creatures, who,
					when they find their provision in their magazines to begin
					to taint and grow rotten, bring it forth and expose it to
					the open air, to prevent the progress of the putrefaction.
					But that which above all things demonstrates the surpassing excellency of their understanding is their preapprehension of the germinating of wheat. For the wheat does
					not remain dry and void of putrefaction, but grows moist
					and turns into a kind of milky substance, when it changes
					from seed to become an herb. For fear therefore that
					preserving the quality it should become useless for food,
					they eat out the very principal part of the grain, from
					whence the wheat sends forth its blossom. I must confess,
					I do not approve of those who dig up ant-hills on purpose
					to improve their learning (as it were) by anatomy. However, they tell us by virtue of that cruel information, that
					the passage or descent from the top of the hill to the nest
					is not directly straight nor easily penetrated by any other
					creature, but intercepted with several turnings and windings, leading through several underminings and perforations
					into three cavities; of which the one is the common place
					of feeding and converse for the whole community, the next
					is the general magazine of their provision, and the third is
					the apartment where they dispose of their dead.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>I am afraid you may deem me too impertinent in
				joining elephants with pismires, and yet I cannot but
				think it seasonable to show the nature and force of understanding,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.178"/>
				
				 as well in the smallest as in the greatest bodies,
				neither obscured in the one nor deficient in the other.</p>
            <p>Some there are that admire in an elephant his aptness
					to learn and to be taught, and the many various postures
					and alterations of movement which he shows upon the
					theatres, not easily to be equalled by human assiduity, as
					subtle and abounding in memory and retention as man is.
					But for my part, I rather choose to prove his evident understanding from the passions and inclinations of the
					creature, that were never taught him, but only infused by
					Nature, as being altogether unmixed and pure without the
					help of art.</p>
            <p>At Rome, not very long ago, there were many elephants
					that were taught many dangerous postures, many winding
					and turnings and circular screwings of their bulky bodies,
					hard to be expressed; among which there was one, which,
					being duller than the rest, and therefore often rated and
					chastised for his stupidity, was seen in the night-time, by
					moonlight, without being forced to it, to practise over his
					lessons with all the industry imaginable.</p>
            <p>Agno tells a story of an elephant in Syria, that was bred
					up in a certain house, who observed that his keeper took
					away and defrauded him every day of half the measure of
					his barley; only that once, the master being present and
					looking on, the keeper poured out the whole measure;
					which was no sooner done, but the elephant, extending his
					proboscis, separated the barley and divided it into two
					equal parts, thereby ingeniously discovering, as much as in
					him lay, the injustice of his keeper.</p>
            <p>Another in revenge that his keeper mixed stones and
					dirt with his barley, as the keeper's meat was boiling upon
					the fire, took up the ashes and flung them into the pot.</p>
            <p>Another being provoked by the boys in Rome, that
					pricked his proboscis with the sharp ends of their writingsteels, caught one of them in his proboscis, and mounted
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.179"/>
					
					him up into the air, as if he intended to have squashed
					out his guts; but upon the loud outcries of the spectators,
					set him gently down again upon his feet, and so went on,
					believing he had sufficiently punished the boy in scaring
					him. Many other things are reported of the wild elephants
					that feed without control, but nothing more to be admired
					than their passing, of great rivers. For first of all the
					youngest and the least flounces into the stream; whom the
					rest beholding from the shore, if they see that the less
					bulky leader keeps steady footing with his back above
					water, they are then assured and confident that they may
					boldly adventure without any danger.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Having thus far proceeded in our discourse, I cannot
				think it well done to pass by the cunning of the fox, by
				reason of the similitude it has with the former. The
				mythologists tell us that the dove which Deucalion sent
				out of his ark, returning back again, was to him a certain
				sign of the storm not ceased; but of serene and fair
				weather, when she flew quite away. But the Thracians
				to this day, when they design to pass a river that is frozen
				over, make use of a fox to try whether the ice will bear or
				no. For the fox, treading gently, lays his ear to the ice,
				and if he perceive by the noise of the water that the stream
				runs very close underneath, conjecturing from thence that
				the congelation is not deep but thin, and no way steadfastly
				solid, he makes a stop, and if he be suffered, returns back
				again; but if he perceive no noise, he goes on boldly.
				Nor can we say that this is only an exquisiteness of sense
				without reason; but it is a syllogistical deduction from
				sense, concluding that whatever makes a noise is moved;
				whatever is moved, cannot be frozen; what is not frozen,
				is moist; what is moist, gives way. The logicians say
				that a dog, making use of the argument drawn from many
				disjunctive propositions, thus reasons with himself, in places
				where several highways meet: Either the wild beast is
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.180"/>
				
				gone this way, or that, or that way; but not that way, nor
				that way, therefore this way: the force of sense affording
				nothing but the minor premise, but the force of reason
				affording the major proposition, and inferring the conclusion
				of the assumption. But a dog stands in no need of any
				such testimonial; in regard it is both false and adulterate.
				For sense itself shows which way the beast is fled, by his
				tracks and footsteps, bidding farewell to disjunctive and
				copulative propositions. The nature of dogs is palpably
				to be discerned by many other actions, affections, and dutiful service, neither the effects of hearing or seeing, but
				practicable only by reason and understanding. It would
				be ridiculous for me to discourse of the continence, obedience, and industry of dogs in hunting, to you that are so
				well confirmed in the knowledge of those things by daily
				experience and practice.</p>
            <p>There was a Roman named Calvus, slain in the civil
					wars, whose head nobody durst cut off before they killed
					the dog that guarded his body and fought in defence of
					his master. It happened that King Pyrrhus, travelling
					one day, lit upon a dog watching over the carcass of
					a person slain; and hearing that the dog had been there
					three days without meat or drink, yet would not forsake
					his dead master, ordered that the man should be buried,
					but that the dog should be preserved and brought to him.
					A few days after, there was a muster of the soldiers, so
					that they were forced to march all in order by the king,
					with the dog quietly lying by him for a good while. But
					when he saw the murderers of his master pass by him, he
					flew upon them with a more than ordinary fury, barking
					and baying and tearing his throat, and ever and anon turning about to the king; which did not only rouse the king's
					suspicion, but the jealousy of all that stood about him.
					Upon which the men were presently apprehended; and
					though the circumstances were very slight which otherwise
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.181"/>
					
					appeared against them, yet they confessed the fact and
					were executed.</p>
            <p>The same thing is reported to have been done by a dog
					that belonged to Hesiod, surnamed the wise, which discovered the sons of Ganyctor the Naupactian, by whom
					Hesiod was murdered. But that which came to the knowledge of our parents, when they were students at Athens,
					is yet more evident than any thing we have said. For a
					certain person getting into the temple of Aesculapius,
					after he had stolen all the massy offerings of gold and
					silver, made his escape, not believing he was discovered.
					But the dog which belonged to the temple, who was called
					Capparus, when he found that none of the sacristans
					took any notice of his barking, pursued himself the sacrilegious thief; and though at first the fellow pelted him
					with stones, he could not beat him off. So soon as it was
					day, the dog still followed him, though at such a distance
					that he always kept him in his eyes. When the fellow
					threw him meat he refused it; when the thief went to bed,
					the dog watched at his door; and when he rose in the
					morning, the dog still followed him, fawning upon the
					passengers on the road, but still barking and baying at
					the heels of the thief. These things when they who were
					in pursuit of the sacrilegious person heard, and were told
					withal by those they met the color and bigness of the dog,
					they were the more vigorous in the pursuit; and by that
					means overtaking the thief, brought him back from Crommyon, while the dog ran before, leaping and capering and
					full of joy, as it were challenging to himself the praise and
					reward of apprehending the temple-robber. And indeed
					the Athenians were so grateful to him, that they decreed
					him such a quantity of meat to be publicly measured to
					him, and ordered the priests to take care to see it done; in
					imitation of the kindness of the ancient Athenians in rewarding the mule.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.182"/>
            <p>For when Pericles built the temple Hecatompedon (or
					Parthenon) in the tower of Athens, it so fell out that the
					stones were to be fetched every day many furlongs off, and
					a world of carriages were made use of for that purpose.
					Among the rest of the mules that labored hard in this employment, there was one that, though dismissed by reason
					of age, would still go down to the Ceramicus, and meeting
					the carts that brought the stones, would be always in their
					company running by their sides, as it were by the way of
					encouragement and to excite them to work cheerfully. So
					that the people, admiring the zeal of the mule, ordered
					him to be fed at the public charge, as they were wont to
					decree public alms to the superannuated wrestlers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>And therefore they who deny that there is any thing
				of justice due from us towards dumb animals may be said
				to speak true, so far as concerns them that live in the sea
				and haunt the abysses of the deep. For those kind of
				creatures are altogether unsociable, without affection for
				their young ones, void of all softness of disposition; and
				therefore it was well said of Homer, speaking to a person
				whom he looked upon as a mere savage,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But as for thee, so little worth,
					</l>
                     <l>The gleaming sea did bring thee forth;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 34.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>in regard the sea brings forth nothing friendly, nothing
					mansuete or gentle. But he that uses the same discourse
					and arguments against land animals is himself a brute and
					savage creature; unless any man will affirm that there was
					nothing of justice due from Lysimachus to the Hyrcanian
					dog, that would not stir from the body of his deceased
					master, and when he saw his master's carcass burning, ran
					and threw himself into the flames. The same is reported
					to have been done by the dog Astus, that was kept by one
					Pyrrhus, not the king, but a private person of that name.
					For upon the death of his master, he would not stir from
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.183"/>
					
					the body, but when it was carried forth, leaped upon the
					bier, and at length threw himself into the funeral pile, and
					was burnt alive with his master's body.</p>
            <p>The elephant also which carried King Porus, when the
					king was wounded in the battle against Alexander, pulled
					out several darts out of his wounds with his proboscis,
					with no less tenderness and care than the chirurgeon could
					have done; and though the elephant himself was but in a
					very bad condition, yet would he not give over till he perceived the king was ready to reel and sink down by reason
					of the blood which he had lost; and then fearing lest the
					king should fall, he stooped down gently, to ease the king
					in sliding to the ground.</p>
            <p>Such was the humor of Bucephalus, who, before he was
					accoutred, would suffer his groom to back him, but when
					he had all his royal trappings and housings about him,
					would permit nobody but Alexander to bestride him.
					But if any other persons approached him in curiosity to
					try what they could do, he encountered them open-mouthed,
					and neighing out his fury, leaped upon their shoulders,
					bore them down, and trampled then under his feet, unless
					prevented by keeping at a distance or by speedy flight.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Nor am I ignorant but that there is something of
				variety in every one of these examples, which you must
				acknowledge. And indeed it is not easy to find out the
				natural dexterity of any one ingenious and docible animal,
				which is not accompanied with more than one single virtue.
				Thus, where there is affection toward their young ones,
				there is desire of praise. Where there is generosity, there
				is also moderation of anger. Cunning likewise and understanding are rarely parted from daring boldness and fortitude. But as for those that rather choose to divide and
				distinguish every one of these virtues particularly by themselves, they shall find in dogs a fair demonstration of a
				gentle and yet lofty mind at the same time, in turning away
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.184"/>
				
				from such as sit quietly upon the ground; according to that
				of Homer,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With hideous noise the dogs upon him flew;
					</l>
                     <l>But sly Ulysses, who the danger knew,
					</l>
                     <l>Sate husht and still, and from his royal hand
					</l>
                     <l>His sceptre dropt, as useless in command.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIV. 30.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For dogs never bite or worry those that prostrate themselves at their mercy and put on a face of humility. Thus
					they say the bravest of those Indian dogs that fought
					against Alexander never stirred or so much as looked about
					them upon the letting loose of a hart, a boar, and a bear;
					but when they saw a lion, then they began to rouse, to
					shake, and prepare themselves for the combat. By which
					it was plain that they thought only the lion an antagonist
					worthy of their courage, but despised all the rest as below
					their anger.</p>
            <p>Your hounds that usually hunt hares, if they kill the
					hares themselves, take great delight in tearing them to
					pieces and lapping up the blood. But if the hare despairing of her life, as many times it happens, runs herself to
					death, the hounds finding her dead will never touch her, but
					stand wagging their tails, as if they did hunt not so much
					for the love of the food as for victory and triumph's sake.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>There are many examples of cunning and subtlety
				abounding in land creatures; but to omit slights and artifices of foxes, cranes, and jackdaws, of which I shall say
				nothing, because they are things already so well known, I
				shall make use of the testimony of Thales, the ancientest
				of our philosophers, who is reported to have chiefly admired the most excellent in any art or cunning.</p>
            <p>A certain mule that was wont to carry salt, in fording a
					river, by accident happened to stumble, by which means
					the water melting away the salt, when the mule rose again
					he felt himself much lighter; the cause of which the mule
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.185"/>
					
					was very sensible of, and laid it up in his memory, insomuch that every time he forded the same river, he would
					always stoop when he came into the deepest part, and fill
					his vessels with water, crouching down, and leaning sometimes to one side, sometimes to the other. Thales hearing
					this, ordered the vessels to be well filled with wool and
					sponges, and to drive the mule laden after that manner.
					But then the mule, as he was wont, filling his burthens
					with water, reasoned with himself that he had ill consulted
					his own benefit, and ever afterwards, when he forded the
					same river, was so careful and cautious, that he would
					never suffer his burthens so much as to touch the water by
					accident.</p>
            <p>Another piece of cunning, joined with an extraordinary
					affection to their young ones, is to be observed in partridges,
					which instruct their young ones, ere they are able to fly,
					when they are pursued by the fowlers, to lay themselves
					upon their backs, their breasts covered with some clod of
					earth or little heap of dirt, under which they may lie
					concealed. On the other side, the old partridges do deceive the fowlers, and draw them quite a contrary way,
					make short flights from one place to another, thereby enticing the fowlers to follow them; till thus allured from
					their young ones, the fowlers give over all hopes of being
					masters of their game.</p>
            <p>In like manner, hares returning to their forms dispose
					their leverets one to one place, another to another, at the
					distance many times of an acre of ground; so that, upon
					the tracing either of men or hounds, they are sure not to
					be all in danger at one time,&mdash;themselves in the mean
					time not easy to be tracked, by reason of the various
					windings and turnings which they make, until at length,
					by giving a large leap, they discontinue the print of their
					feet, and so betake themselves to their rest.</p>
            <p>A bear, when she perceives her winter sleep coming
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.186"/>
					
					upon her, before she grows stiff and unwieldy, cleanses
					the place where she intends to conceal herself, and in
					her passage thither lifts up her paws as high as she can,
					and treads upon the ground with the top of her toes, and
					at length turning herself upon her back, throws herself
					into her receptacle.</p>
            <p>Your hinds generally calve at a distance from all places
					frequented by flesh-devouring beasts; and stags, when they
					find themselves unwieldy through surplusage of flesh and
					fat, get out of the way and hide themselves, hoping to
					secure themselves by lurking, when they dare not trust to
					their heels.</p>
            <p>The means by which the land hedge-hogs defend and
					guard themselves occasioned the proverb,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Many sly tricks the subtle Reynard knows,
						</l>
                     <l>But one the hedge-hog greater than all those.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the hedge-hog, as Ion the poet says,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Fragment 38.</note> when he spies
					the fox coming,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Round as a pine-nut, or more sphere-like ball,
						</l>
                     <l>Lies with his body palisaded all
						</l>
                     <l>With pointed thorns, which all the fox's slight
						</l>
                     <l>Can find no way to touch, much less to bite.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the provision which the hedge-hogs make for their
					young ones is much more ingenious. For when autumn
					comes, they creep under vines, and shake off the grapes
					with their feet; which done they roll themselves up and
					down, and take them up with their prickles, so that when
					they creep away again, you would think it a walking cluster (and this we have looked on and seen them do); after
					which returning to their holes, they lay themselves down
					for their young ones to feed. Their holes have two openings, one to the south, the other to the north. So that
					when they perceive the alteration of the air, like pilots
					shifting their sails, they stop up that which lies to the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.187"/>
					
					wind and open the other. Which a certain person that
					lived at Cyzicus observing, took upon him from thence
					at any time to tell in what corner the wind would sit.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>As for love and observance of society joined with
				understanding and prudence, Juba produces many examples of it in elephants. For it is the usual practice of the
				elephant-hunters to dig large pits in the elephants' walks,
				and cover them slightly over with dry twigs or other materials; into which if any elephant happens to fall, the
				rest fetch wood and stones to fill up the cavity of the pit,
				that the other may the more easily get out again. And
				some report of the elephants, that they make prayers to
				the Gods by natural instinct, that they perform divine ceremonies to the sea, and worship the rising sun, lifting up
				the proboscis to heaven instead of hands. For which reason they are creatures the most beloved of any by the
				Gods, as Ptolemy Philopator testified. For having vanquished Antiochus, and being desirous to pay a more than
				ordinary honor to the Deity, among many other oblations
				of thanksgivings for his victory, he sacrificed four elephants.
				After which being terrified with a dream, which threatened
				him with the wrath of the Deity for that prodigious sacrifice, he sought out several ways to expiate his offence, and
				among the rest by way of propitiation, he erected four
				elephants of brass to atone for the four elephants he had
				slaughtered.</p>
            <p>Examples not inferior of the observance of society are
					to be found among lions. For the younger carry forth the
					slow and aged, when they hunt abroad for their prey.
					When the old ones are weary and tired, they rest and stay
					for the younger that hunt on; who, when they have seized
					upon any thing, call to the old ones, making a noise like
					the bleating of a calf. They presently hear, and so meeting all together, they feed in common upon the prey.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>In the amours of many animals there is much variety.
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.188"/>
				
				 Some are furious and mad; others observe a kind
				of human decency, and tricking of themselves to set off
				their beauty, not without a courtly kind of conversation.
				Such was the amour of the elephant at Alexandria, that
				rivalled Aristophanes the grammarian. For they were
				both in love with a girl that sold garlands; nor was the
				elephant's courtship less conspicuous than the other's.
				For as he passed through the fruit-market, he always
				brought her apples, and stayed with her for some time, and
				thrusting his proboscis within her waistcoat, instead of
				a hand, took great delight in gently feeling her breasts.</p>
            <p>No less remarkable was the serpent in love with the
					Aetolian woman. He came to her in the night, and getting
					under her garments to her very skin, embraced her naked
					body; and never either willingly or unwillingly did he do
					her any harm, but always about break of day departed;
					which the kindred of the woman observing to be the common custom of the animal, removed her a great way off.
					After that, the serpent came not again for three or four
					days together, being all the while, as it seemed, wandering
					about in search of her. But at length, having with much
					ado found her out, he did not approach her with that mildness as he was wont to do, but after a rougher manner;
					with his folds having first bound her hands to her body,
					with the end of his tail he lashed the calves of her legs;
					expressing thereby a gentle and loving anger, which had
					more in it of indulgent expostulation than punishment.</p>
            <p>I say nothing of a goose in Egypt in love with a boy,
					nor of the ram in love with Glauce who played on the
					harp; for the stories are in all people's mouths. And besides, I am apt to think you are satiated with examples of
					this nature.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>But as for starlings, magpies, and parrots, that learn
				to talk, and afford their teachers such a spirit of voice, so
				well tempered and so adapted for imitation, they seem to
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.189"/>
				
				me to be patrons and advocates in behalf of other creatures, by their talent of learning what they are taught;
				and in some measure to teach us that those creatures also,
				as well as we, partake of vocal expression and articulate
				sound. From whence I conclude it a most ridiculous thing
				in them that would compare these creatures with a sort of
				mute animals, I mean the fish, that have not voice enough
				to howl or make a mournful noise. Whereas, in the natural and untaught notes of these creatures, what music,
				what a charming grace do we observe! To which the
				famous poets and choicest singers among men bear testimony, while they compare their sweetest odes and poems
				to the singing of swans and melody of nightingales. Now
				in regard there is more of reason in teaching than in
				learning, we are to believe Aristotle,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">History of Animals, IV. 9, 19.</note> who assures us that
				terrestrial animals do that likewise, in regard that nightingales have been observed instructing their young ones to
				sing. Of which this may be a sufficient proof, that such
				nightingales are known to sing worse that are taken very
				young from the nest and deprived of the education of the old
				one. For they both learn and are taught from the old one,
				not for hire or to get reputation, but merely out of a delight in mixing their notes together, and because they
				have a greater love for that which is excellent and curious
				in the voice than for what is profitable. Concerning
				which I have a story to tell you, which I heard from several Greeks and Romans, who were eye-witnesses of the
				thing.</p>
            <p>A certain barber in Rome, who had a shop right against
					the temple which is called the Greeks' Market, bred in
					his house a kind of a prodigy of a magpie, whose tongue
					would be always going with the greatest variety imaginable, sometimes imitating human speech, sometimes chattering her wild notes, and sometimes humoring the sounds
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.190"/>
					
					of wind instruments; neither was this by any constraint,
					but as she accustomed herself, with a more than ordinary
					ambition, to leave nothing unspoken, nothing that her imitation should not master.</p>
            <p>It happened a certain person of the wealthier sort, newly
					dead in the neighborhood, was carried forth to be buried
					with a great number of trumpets before him. Now in
					regard it was the custom of the bearers to rest themselves
					before the barber's shop, the trumpeters being excellent in
					their art, and withal commanded so to do, made a long
					stop, sounding all the while.</p>
            <p>After that day the magpie was altogether mute, not so
					much as uttering her usual notes by which she called for
					what she wanted, insomuch that they who before admired
					as they passed to and fro at the chattering and prating of
					the bird now much more wondered at her sudden silence;
					and many suspected her to have been poisoned by some
					that affected peculiar skill in teaching this kind of birds.
					But the greatest number were of opinion, that the noise
					of the trumpets had stupefied her hearing, and that by the
					loss of her hearing the use of her voice was likewise
					extinguished. But her unusual silence proceeded from
					neither of these causes, but from her retiring to privacy, by
					herself to exercise the imitation of what she had heard,
					and to fit and prepare her voice as the instrument to express what she had learned. For soon after she came of
					a sudden to sight again, but had quitted all her former
					customary imitations, and sounded only the music of the
					trumpets, observing all the changes and cadences of the
					harmony, with such exactness of time as was not to be
					imagined; an argument, as I have said before, that the
					aptness in those creatures to learn of themselves is more
					rational than readiness to be taught by others. Nor do I
					think it proper to pass by in silence one wonderful example of the docility of a dog, of which I myself was a
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.191"/>
					
					spectator at Rome. This dog belonged to a certain mimic,
					who at that time had the management of a farce wherein
					there was great variety of parts, which he undertook to
					instruct the actors to perform, with several imitations
					proper for the matters and passions therein represented.
					Among the rest there was one who was to drink a sleepy
					potion, and after he had drunk it, to fall into a deadly
					drowsiness and counterfeit the actions of a dying person.
					The dog, who had studied several of the other gestures
					and postures, more diligently observing this, took a piece
					of bread that was sopped in the potion, and after he had
					ate it, in a short time counterfeited a trembling, then a
					staggering, and afterwards a drowsiness in his .head.
					Then stretching out himself, he lay as if he had been
					dead, and seemed to proffer himself to be dragged out of
					the place and carried to burial, as the plot of the play
					required. Afterwards understanding the time from what
					was said and acted, in the first place he began gently to
					stir, as it were waking out of a profound sleep, and lifting up his head, he gazed about him. Afterwards to the
					amazement of the beholders, he rose up, and went to his
					master to whom he belonged, with all the signs of gladness and fawning kindness, insomuch that all the spectators, and even Caesar himself (for old Vespasian was
					present in Marcellus's theatre) were taken with the sight.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>But perhaps we may seem ridiculous for signalizing
				beasts in this manner because they learn, since we find
				that Democritus affirms us to have been their scholars in
				the greatest matters;&mdash;of the spider, in weaving and
				repairing what we tear or wear out; of the swallow, in
				building houses; and of the mournful swan and nightingale, in singing and imitation. Moreover in others we
				observe a threefold practice of physic, both natural and
				inbred. For tortoises make use of marjoram and weasels
				eat rue, when they have devoured a serpent; and dogs
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.192"/>
				
				purge themselves from abounding gall with a certain sort
				of grass. The dragon quickens the dimness of his sight
				with fennel; and the bear, coming forth of her cave after
				long emaciation, feeds upon the wild arum, for the acrimony of that herb opens and separates her guts when
				clung together. At other times, being overcloyed with
				food, she repairs to the emmet-hills, and thrusting forth
				her tongue all soft and unctuous, by reason of the sweet
				kind of slime that all besmears it, till it be crowded with
				emmets, at length swallows them down her throat, and so
				recovers. And it is reported that the Egyptians observe
				and imitate the bird called ibis, in purging and cleansing
				her bowels with the briny sea-water. For which reason
				the priests, when they hallow themselves, make use of the
				water of which the ibis has drunk; for that those birds
				will not drink the water, if it be medicinal or otherwise
				infected. Some beasts there are that cure themselves by
				abstinence; as wolves and lions, who, when they are
				gorged with flesh, lie still and digest their crudities by the
				warmth of one another's bodies. It is reported also of
				the tiger, that if a kid be thrown to her, she will not eat
				in two days; but growing almost famished the third day,
				if she be not supplied with another, she will tear down
				the cage that holds her, if she have strength enough; yet
				all this while she will not meddle with the first kid, as
				being her companion and fellow-housekeeper.</p>
            <p>More than this, the elephants are said to make use of
					chirurgery; for that being brought to persons wounded,
					they will draw forth the heads of spears and arrows out
					of their bodies with little pain, and without dilacerating
					and mangling the flesh.</p>
            <p>The Cretan goats, which by eating dittany expel the
					arrows shot into their bodies, taught women with child to
					understand the virtue of that herb, so prevalent to expel
					the birth. For those goats being wounded seek no other
					cure, but presently seek out and hunt for dittany.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.193"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>But these things, though wonderful, are not so much
				to be admired as are those beasts that understand the use
				of numbers and have the power of reckoning, like the
				oxen about Susa. For there are oxen in that place that
				water the king's gardens with portable buckets, of which
				the number is fixed. For every ox carries a hundred
				buckets every day, and more you cannot force them to
				take or carry, would you never so fain; insomuch that,
				when constraint has been used for experiment's sake,
				nothing could make them stir after they had carried their
				full number. Such an accurate account do they take, and
				preserve the same in their memory, as Ctesias the Cnidian
				relates it.</p>
            <p>The Libyans deride the Egyptians for the fables which
					they report of the oryx, which, as they say, makes a great
					noise upon the same day, at the very hour, when the Dogstar, which they call Sothes, rises. However, this is certain, that all their goats, when that star rises truly with
					the sun, turn themselves and stand gazing toward the
					east; which is a most unquestionable argument of that
					star's having finished its course, and agrees exactly with
					the astronomer's observations.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>But that my discourse may draw to a conclusion, let
				us (as the saying is) move the stone over the sacred line,
				and add something concerning the divinity and prophetic
				nature with which our terrestrial creatures are endued.
				Which when we consider, we shall find that that part of
				soothsaying which is founded upon the observation of
				birds is not the meanest or most ignoble, but very ancient
				and in great esteem. For the smartness and intelligible
				faculty of birds, together with their capability to receive
				all impressions of fancy, afford the Deity a convenience to
				make use of those faculties as instruments, that he may
				turn them into motion, sounds, chirpings, and forms, now
				to stop and stay, anon to drive forward like the winds; by
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.194"/>
				
				means of some of these stopping short, by the means of
				others directing to their end, the actions and impetuous
				impulses of men. Therefore Euripides in general calls
				birds the criers of the Gods; and particularly Socrates
				styles himself a fellow-servant with the swans. As among
				princes, Pyrrhus was pleased with the surname of Eagle;
				and Antiochus loved to be called Antiochus the Falcon.
				But they who deride men as insipid and void of ingenuity
				call them by the names of fish. And whereas we can
				produce millions of things and accidents which are foretold
				us by land and flying creatures, there is not any one such
				example that the patrons of water-animals call produce in
				their behalf; but being all void of hearing, perfectly sottish, and without any sight, discerning, or providence, they
				are all thrown apart into that same place, unblest and
				hideous, called the sea, as it were into the region of the
				ungodly, where the rational and intellectual part of the
				soul is extinguished; being animated with only some diminutive portion, the lowest that may be imagined, of a
				confused and overwhelmed sense, so that they rather seem
				to palpitate than breathe.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>HERACLEO. Pluck up your brows then, friend Phaedimus; after all this, it is time to rouse thyself in the defence of the islanders, and others that live by the seaside.
				For this has been no frivolous discourse, but a hard fought
				contest, and a continued piece of rhetoric that wanted
				only lattices and a pulpit to give it the honor it deserved.</p>
            <p>PHAEDIMUS. Therefore, you see, it is plain here has been
					foul play and treachery in the case, for a person sober and
					upon premeditation to set upon us when we were stomach-sick and dozed with our last night's compotation. But
					there is no way to avoid the combat; for that, being an
					imitator of Pindar, it shall never be said of me,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Combats refused, when nobly set upon,
						</l>
                     <l>Have virtue into deepest darkness thrown.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.195"/>
            <p>For we have leisure enough, as having not only allowed
					ourselves a vacation from jollity and balls, but our hounds
					and horses a relaxation from their labors, and withal having
					hung up our drag-nets and spears, as having also this day
					granted, for disputation's sake, a general truce to all creatures, as well upon the land as in the sea. However, fear
					not; for I will use it moderately, without producing either
					the opinions of philosophers or the fables of the Egyptians,
					or the relations either of the Indians or Libyans, wanting
					testimony; but such as shall be verified by good witnesses,
					who have made it their business to toil upon the ocean,
					and such as are evident to the eye. For to say truth,
					there is not any one of those examples produced from the
					land which is not apparent and openly manifested to our
					sense. Whereas the sea affords few but such as are difficult to be discerned, as concealing the generation and
					nourishment of most of her creatures, their antipathies,
					and ways of preserving themselves; in reference to which
					many acts of understanding, memory, and community are
					unknown to us, so that we cannot be so copious in our discourse. Then again, land animals, by reason of their
					familiarity and cohabitation, being in some measure accustomed to the conditions of men, become capable of their
					nutriture, education, and imitation; which sweetens and
					allays all their acerbity and moroseness, like the mixture
					of fresh water with sea brine, and awakening that which
					is slow and disordered in them, inflames it with human
					motions. Whereas the living of sea animals being by many
					degrees remote from the converse of men, and having
					nothing adventitious or that may be said to be acquired by
					custom and familiarity, is altogether peculiar, genuine, and
					unmixed with manners strange and foreign to them; which
					proceeds not from Nature, but from the place itself. For
					Nature, receiving and cherishing whatever knowledge
					comes to herself, affords it also to fish, and makes many
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.196"/>
					
					eels tame and familiar to men, which for that reason are
					called sacred, like those in the fountain Arethusa; so that
					in many places there are fish that will hear and obey when
					called by their names, as the story goes of Crassus's mullet,
					upon the death of which he wept. For which when
					Domitius twitted him in these words, Did not you weep
					when your mullet died?&mdash;he retorted upon him again,
					Did you not bury three wives and never weep at all? The
					crocodiles belonging to the priests not only know the voices
					of those that call them, and suffer themselves to be stroked
					and handled, but gaping hold out their teeth to be cleansed
					and wiped by the hands of the priests.</p>
            <p>Lately Philinus, after he had been long travelling in
					Egypt, returning to us, told us how he saw, in the city
					which derives its name from Anteus, an old woman sleeping by the side of a crocodile, upon a low soft bed well
					and decently dressed up.</p>
            <p>In ancient histories we find that when King Ptolemy
					called the sacred crocodile, and when the crocodile neither
					vouchsafed to appear at his call nor would answer to the
					earnest expostulations of the priests, it was looked upon
					as a prognostication of the death of the king, which happened soon after. Which shows that the race of water-animals is neither without a share of that inestimable thing
					called prophetic signification, nor undeserving those honors
					ascribed to land creatures. For that about Sura, which is
					a village in Lycia between Phellus and Myra, I have heard
					it credibly reported, that there are certain persons who
					make it their business to watch the turns, flights, and pursuits of the fish, whence, by a certain art which they have,
					they gather predictions, as others from the observation of
					birds.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>But let these examples suffice to show, that fish are
				not altogether strangers to mankind, nor altogether void
				of human affection. But for a great and common demonstration
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.197"/>
				
				 of their unmixed and natural understanding, we
				find that there is not any fish that swims, unless they be
				such as stick and cling to the rocks, which is so easily
				taken by men, as asses are seized by wolves, bees by bee-eaters, grasshoppers by swallows, serpents by harts. And
				these last are therefore called <foreign lang="greek">e)/lafoi,</foreign> not from their swiftness (<foreign lang="greek">e)lafro/ths</foreign>), but from a faculty which they have of
				drawing serpents to them (<foreign lang="greek">e(/lkein o)/feis</foreign>). So sheep call the
				wolf by the sound of their feet, and the panther allures
				to her paws both apes and other creatures by the fragrant
				smell of her body. But so suspicious is the sense of all
				water animals, and so watchful are they to avoid all baits
				and treacheries against them, by reason of their extraordinary cunning, that fishing thereby becomes no easy or
				single labor, but a toil that requires various instruments
				and many tricks of human cunning and deceit. This is
				apparent from examples near at hand. For no man desires
				an angling-rod too thick, though strong enough to hold
				against the twitches of the fish when taken; but rather
				they require it slender, lest by casting too great a shadow
				upon the water, it should frighten the suspicious creature. In the next place, they never knit too many knots
				in the line, but make it as smooth as may be, for that
				would too much discover the deceit; and then for the hairs
				which are next the hook, they endeavor to get the whitest
				they can meet with; for so, by reason of the likeness of
				color, they lie the more easily concealed in the water.
				Therefore some there are who, wrongly expounding the
				following verses of Homer,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXIV. 80.</note>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>She to the bottom quickly sinks, like lead,
					</l>
                     <l>Which fixt to horn of rustic ox descends,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes"> horn: <foreign lang="greek">ke/ras</foreign>
                     </note>
                     <l>And brings destruction to the greedy fish,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>believe that the ancients made use of ox-hair for their lines
					with which they angled, alleging that <foreign lang="greek">ke/ras</foreign> then signified
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.198"/>
					
					hair,&mdash;from whence <foreign lang="greek">kei/rasqai,</foreign> 
               <hi rend="italics">to be shaved,</hi> and <foreign lang="greek">koura/,</foreign> 
               <hi rend="italics">shaving,</hi>&mdash;and that <foreign lang="greek">keropla/sths</foreign> in Archilochus signified one who
					takes delight in trimming and decking the hair. But this
					is an error. For they made use of horse-hair, more
					especially that of male horses. For mares, by moistening
					their tails with their urine, render the hair weak and
					brittle. Though Aristotle will not allow any thing to be
					said in all this that requires such extraordinary subtlety.
					Only he says, that the lower piece of the line was fortified
					with a little hollow piece of horn, lest the fish should come
					at the line itself and bite it off; moreover, that they made
					use of round hooks to catch mullets and tunnies, in regard
					they had but small mouths, for that they were afraid of a
					straight hook. He also further says, that the mullet many
					times suspecting the round hook, will swim round about it,
					flapping the bait with his tail, and then turning round,
					secures to himself so much as he has broken off. Or if
					he cannot do that, he shuts his mouth close, and with the
					extremities of his lips nibbles off some part of the bait.</p>
            <p>The fish called labrax behaves himself more stoutly
					than the elephant; for when he perceives himself struck
					with the hook, without assistance he sets himself at liberty, widening the wound by flinging his head to and fro,
					and enduring the painful twingings of the hook, till he
					have freed himself from it with the loss of his flesh. The
					sea fox (or the fish called alopex) seldom bites, but avoids
					the deceit; but if he chance to be taken, he presently turns
					the inside of his body outward. For by reason of the
					strength and moisture of his body, he has a peculiar faculty to turn it so that, the inside coming to be outermost,
					the hook falls off. These things demonstrate understanding, and a subtle and extraordinary use of it in the nick
					and juncture of time.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Other examples there are which show not only this
				same understanding and knowledge, but the community
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.199"/>
				
				and mutual affection of fish. Thus, if one scate happen
				to swallow the hook, all the rest of the scates that are in
				the same shoal presently crowd together and bite the line
				in pieces. The same scates, if any of their companions
				fall into the net, give the prisoners their tails to take hold
				of with their teeth, and so draw them forth by main
				force.</p>
            <p>But the fish called anthiae with far more courage assist
					their fellows in distress. For getting under the line with
					their backs, and setting up their fins, with these, as with
					sharp saws, they endeavor to cut it in two.</p>
            <p>Now we know no land animal that will assist and defend his kind in danger; neither the bear, nor the wild
					boar, nor the lion, nor the panther. True it is that, when
					they are in herds together, they will gather into a circle
					and defend each other in common; but no single land
					animal either knows or cares to assist a single companion,
					but flies and shifts for himself as far off as he can from
					the beast that is wounded and lies a dying. For as for
					that old story of elephants filling up the ditches with
					heaps of adjoining materials, whether wood or earth, for
					the unfortunate elephant the more easily to get up again,
					this, my good friend, is extremely uncouth and foreign to
					us, as if we were bound to believe Juba's books by virtue
					of a royal edict. However, if it is true, it does but serve to
					show that many of the marine creatures are nothing inferior in understanding and community to the most intelligent of the land animals. But as for their mutual society,
					we shall discourse apart of that by itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Now the fishermen, observing how that most fish
				avoided the casts of their hooks by cunning or by striving
				with the tackling, betook themselves to force,&mdash;as the
				Persians use to serve their enemies in their wars,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, by joining hands and sweeping across an island. See the description
					in Herod. VI. 31, and <foreign lang="greek">saghneu/w</foreign> in Liddell and Scott. (G.)</note>&mdash;
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.200"/>
				
				making use of nets, that there might be no escape for
				those that were caught either by the help of reason or
				subtlety. Thus mullets and the fish called julides are
				taken with sweep-nets and drag-nets, as are also several
				other sorts of fish called mormuri, sargi, gobii, and labraces; those that are called casting-nets catch the mullet,
				the gilthead, and the scorpion fish; and therefore Homer
				calls this sort of net <foreign lang="greek">pana/gra,</foreign> or the <hi rend="italics">all-sweeper.</hi>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. V. 487.</note> And yet
				there are some fish that are too cunning for these nets.
				Thus the labrax, perceiving the drawing of the sweep-net,
				with the force of his body beats a hollow place in the mud,
				where he lays himself close till the net be gone over him.
				But as for the dolphin, when he finds himself taken and
				in the midst of the net, he remains there without being in
				the least perplexed, but falls to with a great deal of joy,
				and feasts upon the numerous fry within the meshes; but
				so soon as he comes near the shore, he bites his way
				through the net with his teeth and swims away. Or if he
				chance to be taken, the fishermen do him no other harm
				the first time, but only sew a sort of large bulrush to the
				finny crown upon his head, and so let him go. If they
				take him a second time, they punish him with stripes, well
				knowing him again by the prints of the needle. But that
				rarely happens. For having got pardon the first time, for
				the most part of them, they acknowledge the favor, and
				abstain from spoil for the future.</p>
            <p>Moreover, among the many examples that make evident
					the wariness of fish in avoiding the deceits and craft of
					the fishermen, it would not be convenient to pass by that
					of the cuttle-fish. For this fish, carrying near his neck at
					certain black and inky sort of liquor, so soon as he perceives himself discovered, throws that liquor forth, and
					darkens all the water round about him in such a manner
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.201"/>
					
					makes his escape; imitating therein Homer's Deities, who,
					when they had a mind to save any of their heroes, hid
					them in an azure cloud. But of this enough.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Now for the extraordinary subtlety of fish in hunting
				and catching their own prey, we shall meet with several
				examples of it in several fish. Particularly the starfish,
				understanding his own nature to be such that whatever he
				touches dissolves and liquefies, readily offers his body, and
				permits himself to be touched by all that come near him.</p>
            <p>You know yourself the property of the torpedo or cramp
					fish which not only benumbs all those that touch it, but
					also strikes a numbness through the very net into the hands
					of them that go about to take him. And some that have
					had greater experience of this fish report that, if it happen
					to fall alive upon the land, they that pour water upon it
					shall presently perceive a numbness seizing upon their
					hands and stupefying their feeling, through the water
					affected with the quality of the fish. And therefore, having an innate sense of this faculty, it never makes any resistance against any thing, nor ever is it in danger. Only
					swimming circularly about his prey, he shoots forth the
					effluviums of his nature like so many darts, and first infects
					the water, then the fish through the water, which is neither
					able to defend itself nor to escape, being (as it were) held
					in chains and frozen up.</p>
            <p>The fish called the fisherman is well known to many,
					who has his name given him from his manner of catching
					fish; whose art, as Aristotle writes, the cuttle-fish makes
					use of, for he lets down, like a line, a certain curl which
					Nature has given him, so ordered as to let it run out at
					length or draw it to him again, as he sees occasion. This,
					when he sees any of the lesser fish approach, he offers
					them to bite, and then by degrees pulls the curl nearer and
					nearer by virtue of the bait, till he has drawn his prey
					within the reach of his mouth. And as for the polypus's
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.202"/>
					
					changing his color, Pindar has made it famous in these
					words:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In any city may that man expose
						</l>
                     <l>His safety, who well knows
						</l>
                     <l>Like sea-bred polypus to range,
						</l>
                     <l>And vary color upon every change.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner Theognis:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Change manners with thy friends, observing thus
						</l>
                     <l>The many-colored, cunning polypus;
						</l>
                     <l>Who let him stick to whatsoever rock,
						</l>
                     <l>Of the same color does his body look.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theognis, vs. 215.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is true the chameleon changes color, not out of any
					design or to conceal himself, but out of fear, being naturally timorous and trembling at every noise he hears. And
					this is occasioned by the extraordinary abundance of
					breath which he enjoys, as Theophrastus affirms. For the
					whole body of this creature wants but little of being nothing else but lungs; which demonstrates him to be full of
					spirits, and consequently apt to change. But this same
					change of the polypus is no product of any affection of
					the mind, but a kind of action. For he changes on purpose, making use of this artifice to escape what he fears,
					and to get the food which he lives by. For by fraud, those
					things that he will take never avoid him, and those things
					he will escape pass him by without taking any notice of
					him. For that he devours his own claws is an untruth,
					but that he is afraid of the lamprey and conger is certain;
					for by these he is ill treated, not being able to return them
					any injury, by reason of their being so slippery. Though
					on the other side the crawfish, having once got them within
					his claws, holds them with ease. For slenderness affords
					no help against roughness; but when the polypus comes
					to thrust his horns into the body of the crawfish, then also
					the crawfish dies. And this same vicissitude of avoiding
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.203"/>
					
					and pursuing one another has Nature infused into them on
					purpose to exercise their subtlety and understanding.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Then again we have heard Aristotimus relating how
				the land hedge-hog had a perception of the rising of the
				wind, and praising the trigonal flight of cranes. But for
				my part, I produce no particular hedge-hog of Cyzicus or
				Byzantium, but all the sea hedge-hogs in general; who,
				when they perceive a storm coming, ballast themselves with
				little stones, lest they should be overturned by reason of
				their lightness or carried away by the rolling of the waves,
				which they prevent by the weight of their little stones.</p>
            <p>On the other side, the cranes' order in their flight against
					the wind is not of one sort. But this is a general notion
					among all fish, that they always swim against the waves and
					the tide, and always take care lest the wind being in their
					tails should force their fins from their backs, and leave
					their naked bodies exposed to the cold and other inconveniences; and therefore they still oppose the prows of
					their bodies against the waves. For that while they thus
					cleave the waves at the top, the sea keeps their fins close,
					and lightly flowing over the superficies of their bodies, becomes less burdensome, besides that it suffers not their
					scales to rise.</p>
            <p>This, I say, is common to all fish, except that fish which
					is called ellops; which, as they report, always swims with
					the wind and tide, not minding the erection or opening of
					the scales, which do not lie towards the tail, as in other
					fish.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Moreover, the tunny is so sensible of the equinoxes
				and solstices, that he teaches even men themselves without
				the help of any astrological table. For where the winter
				solstice overtakes him, there he remains till the vernal
				equinox.</p>
            <p>As for that same artifice of the cranes, that keep themselves waking by clutching a stone in their claws, how much
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.204"/>
					
					more cunningly done is that of the dolphin, for whom it
					is not lawful to stand still or to be out of motion. For it
					is the nature of the dolphins to be always in motion; so
					that, when they cease to move, they also cease to live.
					And therefore when sleep seizes them, they raise their
					bodies to the superficies of the sea, and so sinking down
					again with their bellies upward, are carried along with the
					tide till they touch again the shore. Wakened in that
					manner, with an impetuous noise they mount upward again,
					designing thus a kind of rest still intermixed with motion.
					And the same thing is reported of the tunnies for the same
					reason.</p>
            <p>Having thus concluded their mathematical foreknowledge of the mutations of the sun, of which Aristotle
					gives testimony, let me now relate their skill in arithmetic;
					but first of all, their knowledge in optics, of which Aeschylus seems not to have been altogether ignorant. For
					these are his words:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Casting a squint-eye like the tunny.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For tunnies seem to be dim-sighted of one eye. And therefore, when they enter the Euxine Sea, they coast along
					the land on the right side, and contrariwise when they
					come forth; prudently committing the care of their bodies
					to the best eye.</p>
            <p>But wanting arithmetic in order to the preservation of
					mutual love and society one with another, they arrive in
					such a manner to the perfection of that science, that, in
					regard they are extremely desirous to enjoy the society of
					each other, they always make up their whole fry into the
					form of a cube, and make a solid of the whole number
					consisting of six equal planes; and then they swim in such
					order as to present an equal front in each direction. So
					then, if the observer of the tunnies does but exactly take
					the number of the side that he sees, he knows the whole
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.205"/>
					
					number of the shoal; well knowing that the depth is equal
					to the breadth and length.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>The fish amiae, which are another sort of tunnies, are
				so called, because they swim in shoals, as also the pelamydes
				or summer whitings. As for the rest that are seen to swim
				in shoals and to observe a mutual society, their number is
				not to be expressed. And therefore let us proceed to those
				that observe a kind of private and particular society one
				with another. Among which is the pinoteras of Chrysippus, upon which he has expended so much ink, that he
				gives it the precedency in all his books, both physical and
				ethical. For Chrysippus never knew the spongotera, for
				he would not have passed it over out of negligence.</p>
            <p>The pinoteras is so called, from watching the fish called
					pina or the nacre, and in shape resembles a crab; and cohabiting with the nacre, he sits like a porter at his shellside, which he lets continually to stand wide open until he
					spies some small fishes gotten within it, such as they are
					wont to take for their food. Then entering the shell, he
					nips the flesh of the nacre, to give him notice to shut his
					shell; which being done, they feed together within the
					fortification upon the common prey.</p>
            <p>The sponge is governed by a certain little creature more
					like a spider than a crab. For the sponge wants neither
					soul nor sense nor blood; but growing to the stones, as
					many other things do, it has a peculiar motion from itself
					and to itself, which nevertheless stands in need as it were
					of a monitor or instructor. For being otherwise of a substance loose and open, and full of holes and hollowness,
					by reason of the sloth and stupidity of it the sponge-watcher assists to give notice when any thing of food enters the
					cavities of it, at which time the sponge contracts itself
					and falls to feeding.</p>
            <p>But if a man approach and touch it, being nipped and
					admonished by the sponge-watcher, it seems to shudder
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.206"/>
					
					and shut up the body of it, closing and condensing it in
					such a manner as makes it no easy thing to cut it from the
					place where it grows.</p>
            <p>The purple shellfish also, called porphyrae, clustering
					together in a kind of mutual society, build up little combs
					for themselves like bees, wherein they are said to generate; and culling out the choicest substance of the moss and
					seaweed that stick to their shells, they seem to be in a circular commons among themselves, feeding the one upon
					the other's nourishment.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>But why should we admire society in these creatures,
				when the most savage and most unsociable of all creatures
				which either lakes, rivers, or the ocean nourishes, the crocodile, shows himself the most sociable and grateful of water
				monsters in the banquets which he bestows upon the
				trochilus? For the trochilus is a bird that haunts marshes
				and rivers, and he guards and watches over the crocodile,
				not as one that feeds at his table, but as one that lives
				upon his scraps and leavings only. For when this bird
				observes the crocodile asleep, and the ichneumon ready to
				assail him, smeared with mud for the conflict like a wrestler covered with dust, he never leaves crying and pecking
				him with his beak, till he rouse the drowsy monster. In
				return of which the crocodile is so tame and gentle towards
				this bird, that he permits him to enter his yawning chaps,
				and is pleased with his pecking out and cleansing away
				with his beak the remainders of the devoured flesh that
				sticks between his teeth. And when the monster has an
				inclination to shut his mouth, he gives the bird notice by
				a gentle lowering of his jaw, nor will he close his chaps
				till he finds that the bird is flown away. The fish which
				the Greeks call hegemon (or the captain or leader) is a
				small fish, in bigness and shape not much unlike a gudgeon, but by reason of the roughness of his scales is said
				to resemble a bird when she shakes her feathers. This
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.207"/>
				
				fish always keeps company with one of the huge whales,
				and swims before him to direct his course, lest he should
				bruise himself upon the shallows, or fall into any marshy
				place or narrow haven whence he could not easily get out
				again. Therefore the whale follows him, as the ship follows the helm, directing his course with confidence. All
				other things whatever, whether skiff, whether beast or
				stone, that chance to light into the gaping gulf of the
				whale's mouth, immediately perish, being swallowed by
				the monster; but acknowledging his conductor, he receives
				him and lodges him, like an anchor, safely in his jaws.
				There he sleeps; and all the while he takes his rest, the
				whale lies still, as if he were at anchor; and when his
				guide comes forth again, the whale proceeds, never forsaking him night or day; or if he wander without his leader,
				the monster shipwrecks, like a vessel cast upon a rock
				without a helm. And this we saw not long ago near Anticyra, where they report that in former times a whale
				being cast and putrefying caused a pestilence.</p>
            <p>Is it worth while then to compare these observations of
					community and association with those sympathies which,
					as Aristotle relates, exist between foxes and serpents because the eagle is an enemy to both? Or with those of the
					horn-owls with horses, whose dung they love to scrape about
					the field? For my part I observe no such care of one
					another in bees and emmets, which, by reason of their multitude, carry on and perfect their work in common, but
					have no particular care or consideration one of another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>We shall observe this difference more evidently, if
				we direct our discourses upon the most ancient and greatest works of common society, which are the works of generation and procreation of offspring. For in the first
				place, those fish that frequent the shores next adjoining to
				vast lakes or great rivers, when they are near their time of
				bringing forth, retire up into those places, seeking the
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.208"/>
				
				fresh waters which are more gentle and void of brine. For
				tranquillity is most convenient for such as bring forth, and
				there is most safety in rivers and lakes for their young
				ones, as being freest from the devouring monsters of the
				sea. Which is the reason that there is the greatest plenty
				of fish about the Euxine Sea, where there are no whales,
				but only small sea-calves or little dolphins. Besides, the
				mixture of rivers, many in number, and those very large,
				that fall into the Pontus, make the temperature more kindly and proper for breeding and bringing forth. And that
				is most wonderful which is reported of the anthias, which
				Homer<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 407.</note> calls the sacred fish, though some interpret sacred
				to signify great in that place, as we call a certain great
				bone <hi rend="italics">os sacrum,</hi> and the epilepsy, being a great disease,
				the <hi rend="italics">sacred disease,</hi> though others interpret that to be sacred which ought not to be touched, as being dedicated to
				holy use. And Eratosthenes seems to take the gilthead,
				so called from the golden hair about his eyes, for the sacred fish; though many believe it to be the ellops,&mdash;a
				fish seldom seen and difficult to be caught, yet many times
				it appears in the rivers of Pamphylia. So they that catch
				them are crowned, and their boats are also adorned with
				garlands, and as they pass along they are received and
				honored with loud shouts and clapping of hands. However it be, most people take the anthias to be a sacred fish,
				because that where the anthias appears, there are no sea-monsters, but the sponge-cutters dive boldly, and the fish
				as fearlessly spawn, as having a pledge for their security.
				And the reason is twofold, either because the sea-monsters
				dread the anthias, as elephants dread a hog, and lions
				a cock; or else it is a sign that there are no sea-monsters
				in those places, which the anthias knows and observes, as
				being an intelligent fish, endued with sense and a good
				memory.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.209"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>Then again, the care of their young is common to
				both sexes. For the males never devour their offspring,
				but remain and abide constantly by the spawn, protecting
				it with a diligent watchfulness, as Aristotle relates; and
				those that accompany the females moisten the spawn with
				a small quantity of milky seed; for that otherwise the
				spawn will not grow, but remains imperfect and never
				arrives at the due proportion. Particularly the fish called
				phycides make themselves nests in the seaweed to preserve
				their spawn from the waves.</p>
            <p>But the love of the galeus toward her young ones is
					beyond the affection and clemency of any the tamest of
					creatures; for they lay an egg, which being hatched, they
					nourish and carry the young about not outwardly, but
					within their own bowels, as if they could not breed their
					young without a second birth.</p>
            <p>When the young ones are somewhat grown, they put
					them forth again, and teach them to swim close by themselves, then resume them again through their mouths into
					their bellies, and afford them nourishment and safe retirement in their bodies, till they are able to shift for themselves.</p>
            <p>No less admirable is the care of the tortoise, as to the
					bringing forth and preserving her young. For she retires
					out of the sea to lay; but not being able to stay long upon
					the land, she hides her eggs in the sand, covering them
					over gently with the lightest of the gravel; and when she
					has thus sufficiently and assuredly concealed them, some
					report that she marks and streaks the place with her feet,
					that she may be able to know it again; others affirm that
					the female, being turned upon her back upon the sand by
					the male, leaves her particular marks and signatures behind
					her. However it be, this is most wonderful, that after
					waiting forty days (for in so many the eggs come to break)
					she returns, and knowing where the treasure lies, as well
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.210"/>
					
					as any man understands where he hides his gold, she opens
					them with great joy and alacrity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>Many observations like to these are made of the
				crocodile. But such is its skill in choosing a place for
				breeding, that no man can explain it by reason or conjecture. Whence it comes that the foreknowledge of this
				creature is imputed more to divinity than reason. For
				neither farther nor nearer, but just so far as the Nile that
				year will increase and cover the land, thither she goes forth
				and lays her eggs; which the countrymen finding, are able
				to tell one another how far the river will overflow that
				year. So truly does that animal measure for herself, that
				though she live in the water, she may lay her eggs dry.
				But the young ones being hatched, whichsoever of them,
				so soon as they are come to life, does not seize whatever
				comes next&mdash;either upon a fly, or a worm, or a straw, or
				a tuft of grass&mdash;with his mouth, the dam presently tears
				him to pieces with her teeth. But those that are fierce
				and active she loves and cherishes, according to the judgment of the wisest men, imparting her affection by the
				rules of judgment, not by the sway of passion.</p>
            <p>The sea-calves also bring forth upon the dry lands; but
					then fetching out their young ones by degrees, they give
					them a taste of the sea-water, and presently lead them out
					again; and this they often do, till custom has made them
					bold, and brought them to love a sea life.</p>
            <p>Frogs when they couple use a certain croaking invitation, which is commonly called ololygon; and when the
					male has thus enticed the female, they abide together all
					night. For in the water they cannot, and in the daytime
					they are afraid to engender upon the land, which in the
					night-time they do without control. At other times they
					croak more shrill and loud; and this is a sign of rain,
					and holds among the most assured prognostics of wet
					weather.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.211"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>But what absurdity, dearest Neptune, would this
				passion of mine lead me into! How ridiculous should I
				appear, if trifling among sea-calves and frogs, I should
				omit one of the marine animals, the wisest and most beloved by the Gods! For what nightingales are to be compared with the halcyon for music? or who will presume to
				prefer the swallow's love of offspring, the dove's love of
				her mate, or the art and curiosity of the bees, to those
				virtues ascribed to the halcyon? One only island, as history tells us, received and entertained Latona when she
				gave birth; which island, floating before, was then made
				firm land. But when the halcyon brings forth, about the
				winter solstice, the whole ocean remains calm and undisturbed without the wrinkle of a wave. So that there is
				not any other creature for which man has so great an
				affection, seeing that for her sake for seven days and seven
				nights together, in the depth of winter, they sail without
				fear of shipwreck, and make their voyages upon the sea
				with greater safety than they travel upon the land.</p>
            <p>But if it be required that we should make a brief recital
					of her particular virtues, she is so great an example of
					conjugal affection, that she does not keep company with
					her mate for a single season, but for the whole year together, and that not for wantonness (for she never couples
					but with her own), but out of affection and friendship, like
					a truly virtuous married wife. And when her mate through
					age becomes infirm and not able to bear her company, she
					takes care of him, and feeds and carries him about in his
					old age, never forsaking nor leaving him alone, but taking
					him upon her shoulders, carries him from place to place,
					never abandoning him till death.</p>
            <p>As to her affection towards her young ones and care of
					their preservation, so soon as she perceives herself near the
					time of her bringing forth, she presently betakes herself
					to the making of her nest. For the building of which,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.212"/>
					
					she neither makes use of mud and dirt nor props it up
					with walls and rafters, like the swallows; nor does she
					use several members of her body to work with, like the
					bees, that employ their whole body to enter the wax and
					open their cells, with their six feet fashioning their six-sided apartments. For the halcyon having but one
					single instrument, one single tool, which is her bill,
					nor any other help to assist her in labor and her care of
					her young ones, what a wonderful master-piece of workmanship does she erect? Insomuch that it is a difficult
					thing for them that have not well considered it to believe
					their eyesight; her workmanship seeming rather the art
					of a shipwright than of a common builder; of all inventions being the only form not to be overwhelmed and
					washed by the waves. To this purpose she gathers together the thorns of the sea-needle -some straight, others
					oblique, like the woof in the loom -and twists and binds
					them where the thread and yarn are interwoven one within
					another, till she has framed a nest round and oblong, resembling the usual fisher-boats. This when she has finished she launches into the sea, where the waves beating
					gently upon it direct to reform what is amiss, by consolidating the loose and ill compacted parts, where the water
					has forced any entrance; insomuch that at length she
					fastens and strengthens what she has put together in such
					a manner, that it is not to be broken or pierced either by
					stones or steel. Nor is the symmetry and form of the inside and cavity of the nest less to be admired. For it is so
					contrived as only to receive herself; the entrance into it
					not being to be found by any other creature, nor can the
					sea itself find a way into it. I am apt to believe that there
					is none of you who never saw this nest. But for my own
					part, that have often seen and handled one of them, I may
					safely say, that I
					In Delos' temple near Apollo's shrine,
					Something like this, a fabric most divine,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.213"/>
					
					have seen. That is to say, the horned altar, celebrated for
					one of the seven wonders of the world, which without the
					help of parget, glue, soder, paste, or any other binding, is
					framed only of horns that grew on the right side of the
					head of the beast.</p>
            <p>Now may the Deity that is somewhat musical and an
					islander be propitious to me, . . . while I deride the
					questions which those scoffers put,&mdash;wherefore Apollo
					may not be called mullet-shooter, when we find that Venus
					is called the mullet-protectrix; for which reason she is
					honored with temples adjoining to the sea, and sacred
					rights; and certain it is, that she is displeased when any
					mullet is killed. Therefore at Leptis the priests of Neptune never eat any thing that breeds in the sea; and you
					know the mullet is in great veneration among the professors of the Eleusinian mysteries; moreover, that the priestess of Juno at Argos abstains from the same fish; and
					the reason is because the mullets kill and destroy the sea-hare, which is pernicious to man, and therefore they spare
					those creatures that are kind and beneficial to him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>Then again, we find among many of the Greeks
				temples and altars frequently dedicated to Diana Dictynna
				(so called from <foreign lang="greek">di/ktuon</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">a net</hi>) and Delphinian Apollo. And
				that same place which Apollo has peculiarly chosen for
				himself was first of all inhabited by Cretans, having a
				dolphin for their leader. For the Deity did not swim before his army in another shape (as the mythologists dream),
				but sending a dolphin to direct them in their course, the
				dolphin brought them to Cirrha. Story also tells us that
				Soteles and Dionysius, who were sent to Sinope by Ptolemy
				Soter to fetch from thence Serapis, were driven by contrary
				winds beyond Cape Malea, having the Peloponnesus upon
				their right hands; while they were thus wandering and
				out of their course, a dolphin appeared before the prow
				of the headmost vessel, and (as it were) kindly inviting
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.214"/>
				
				them, conducted them into safe harbors and roads, till by
				his good guidance and leading them he at length brought
				the whole fleet to Cirrha. There, when they came to offer
				the usual sacrifices for their safe landing, they came to understand that, of two statues which were in the place, they
				were to take that of Pluto and carry it along with them;
				but as for that of Proserpina, they were only to take the
				mould and leave the statue itself behind. Probable it is
				that the Deity had a kindness for the dolphin, considering
				how much he delights in music. For which reason Pindar
				likens himself to the dolphin, and confesses himself to be
				moved in the same manner as that noble creature,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which flutes' beloved sound
					</l>
                     <l>Excites to play,
					</l>
                     <l>Upon the calm and placid sea.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Though it is very probable that his affection to men is
					more pleasing to the Deity, he being the only creature that
					bears an affection to man as man. For as for the land
					animals, some kinds there are that fly him altogether, and
					the tamest and most gentle follow him and are familiar
					with him, only for the benefit and nourishment which they
					receive from him; as the dog, the horse, and elephant.
					The swallows, by necessity constrained, build in houses,
					seeking shade and security, but are no less afraid of men
					than of the wild beasts. Only to the dolphin has Nature
					bequeathed that excellent quality, so much sought for by
					the best of philosophers, to love for no advantage; for
					that having no need at all of man, he is a kind friend to
					all men, and has lent his assistance to many. There is no
					man that is ignorant of the famous story of Arion. And
					you, my dear friend, have seasonably put us in mind of
					Hesiod; but
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou didst not by a legal course
						</l>
                     <l>Rightly conclude thy long discourse.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 56. See above, chap. 13.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.215"/>
            <p>For when you had spoken so much in praise of the dog,
					you should not have passed by the dolphin. For it would
					have been a blind story of the dog that barked and flew
					with violence upon the murderers, had it not been for the
					dolphins, that took the carcass of Hesiod, floating in the
					sea near Nemeum, and readily receiving it from one
					another, landed it at Rhium, whereby the murder came to
					be known.</p>
            <p>Myrtilus the Lesbian writes, that Enalus the Aeolian,
					being in love with the daughter of Phineus, who, by the
					command of the oracle of Amphitrite was cast into the
					sea by the Penthilidae, when he understood it, threw himself also into the sea, but was saved by a dolphin, and
					carried to Lesbos.</p>
            <p>But the gentleness and kindness of the dolphin towards
					the lad of Jasus was so extraordinary that it might be said
					to amount even to amorous love. For he played and swam
					with him in the daytime, and suffered himself to be
					handled and bestrid by him; nor did he swim away with
					him, but joyfully carried him which way soever the lad by
					the motion of his body turned him, while the Iasians
					flocked from all parts to the shore to 'behold the sight.
					At length the lad, being thrown from the dolphin's back
					by a terrible shower of rain and hail, was drowned.
					Which the dolphin perceiving took up the dead youth,
					and threw himself upon the land together with the body,
					from which he never stirred till he died out of his own
					element; deeming it but just to partake of that end of
					which he seemed to have been the occasion to his friend
					and playfellow. Nor can the Iasians forget the accident,
					but keep it still in remembrance by the stamp upon their
					coin, which is a lad upon a dolphin's back.</p>
            <p>And from hence it was that the fabulous stories of
					Coeranus gained credit. He was a Parian by birth, who
					residing at Byzantium, when a draught of dolphins caught
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.216"/>
					
					in a net were exposed to sale and in danger of slaughter,
					bought them up all, and put them into the sea again. It
					happened not long after that Coeranus took a voyage in a
					vessel of fifty oars, carrying, as the story goes, several
					pirates. But between Naxos and the Bay of Paros he
					suffered shipwreck; and when all the rest were drowned,
					he alone was taken up by a dolphin that hastened to his
					succor, and carried to Sicynthus, and set ashore near the
					cave which to this day bears the name of Coeraneum.
					Upon which Archilochus is said to have made these lines:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of fifty men, great Neptune gentle grown
						</l>
                     <l>Left courteous Coeranus alive alone.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Some years after Coeranus dying, his relations burnt his
					body near the seaside; at what time several dolphins appeared near the shore, as if they had come to his funeral;
					nor would they stir till the funeral was over. Moreover
					Stesichorus writes that Ulysses bore a dolphin painted
					upon his shield; and for what reason the Zacynthian
					records tell us, as Critheus testifies. For they say that
					Telemachus, when he was but a boy, falling into the sea,
					was saved by the dolphins that took him up and set him
					ashore. And therefore he made use of a dolphin for the
					impression of his seal and the ornament of his shield.
					But having promised before that I would produce no fabulous stories, and yet being carried, I know not how, to discourse beyond probability of dolphins by this repetition of
					the stories of Coeranus and Ulysses, I will do justice upon
					myself by concluding here.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>ARISTOTIMUS. Now, gentlemen, it lies on your part
				that are judges, to pronounce sentence.</p>
            <p>SOCLARUS. Assuredly then, for our parts, we shall give
					the same judgment in this, as Sophocles did in another
					case:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Discourse upon discording arguments
						</l>
                     <l>Is then determined best, when what was said
						</l>
                     <l>Is duly weighed and stated on both sides.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.217"/>
            <p>For thus comparing what you have both discoursed one
					against another, it will be found that you have acquitted
					yourselves on both sides like true champions against those
					that would deprive brute animals of sense and understanding.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>