<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Quomodo adolescens poetas audire debeat</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.068">
      <body>
         <head>How a young man ought to hear poems.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.42"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>It may be allowed to be a question fit for the determination of those concerning whom Cato said, Their
					palates are more sensitive than their hearts, whether that
					saying of Philoxenus the poet be true or no, The most
					savory flesh is that which is no flesh, and fish that is no fish.
					Yet this to me, Marcus Sedatus, is out of question, that
					those precepts of philosophy which seem not to be delivered with a designed gravity, such as becomes philosophers,
					take most with persons that are very young, and meet
					with a more ready acceptance and compliance from them.
					Whence it is that they do not only read through Esop's
					fables and the fictions of poets and the Abaris of Heraclides and Ariston's Lyco; but they also read such doctrines
					as relate to the souls of men, if something fabulous be
					mixed with them, with an excess of pleasure that borders on
					enthusiasm. Wherefore we are not only to govern their
					appetites in the delights of eating and drinking, but also
					(and much more) to inure them to a like temperance in
					reading and hearing, that, while they make use of pleasure
					as a sauce, they may pursue that which is wholesome and
					profitable in those things which they read. For neither
					can a city be secure if but one gate be left open to receive
					the enemy, though all the rest be shut; nor a young man
					safe, though he be sufficiently fortified against the assaults
					of all other pleasures, whilst he is without any guard against
					those of the ear. Yea, the nearer the commerce is betwixt
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.43"/>
					
					the delights of that sense and those of the mind and reason,
					by so much the more, when he lies open on that side, is he
					apt to be debauched and corrupted thereby. Seeing therefore we cannot (and perhaps would not if we could) debar
					young men of the size of my Soclarus and thy Cleander
					altogether from the reading of poets, yet let us keep the
					stricter guard upon them, as those who need a guide to
					direct them in their reading more than in their walks.
					Upon which consideration, I find myself disposed to send
					thee at present in writing that discourse concerning Poetry
					which I had lately an occasion to deliver by word of mouth;
					that, when thou hast read it over thyself, thou mayst also
					make such use of it, if thou judgest it may be serviceable
					to that purpose, as those which are engaged to drink hard
					do of amethysts (or preservatives against drunkenness),&mdash;
					that is, that thou mayst communicate it to Cleander, to
					prepossess him therewith; seeing he is naturally endowed
					with a brisk, piercing, and daring wit, and therefore more
					prone to be inveigled by that sort of study.</p>
            <p>They say of the fish called polypus that
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>His head in one respect is very good,
						</l>
                     <l>But in another very naughty food;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>because, though it be very luscious to eat, yet it is thought
						to disturb the fancy with frightful and confused dreams.
						And the like observation may be made concerning poetry,
						that it affords sweet and withal wholesome nourishment to
						the minds of young men, but yet it contains likewise no
						less matter of disturbance and emotion to them that want
						a right conduct in the study thereof. For of it also, as well
						as of Egypt, may it be said that (to those who will use it)
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Its over-fertile and luxuriant field
						</l>
                     <l>Medicines and poisons intermixt doth yield;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for therein
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love with soft passions and rich language drest
						</l>
                     <l>Oft steals the heart out of th' ingenuous breast.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IV. 230; Il. XIV. 216.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.44"/>
            <p>And indeed such only are endangered thereby, for the
						charms of that art ordinarily affect not those that are
						downright sots and naturally incapable of learning. Wherefore, when Simonides was asked why of all men he could
						not deceive the Thessalians, his answer was, Because they
						are not so well bred as to be capable of being cajoled by
						me. And Gorgias used to call tragical poems cheats,
						wherein he that did cheat was juster than he that did not
						cheat, and he that was cheated was wiser than he that was
						not cheated.</p>
            <p>It deserves therefore our consideration, whether we shall
						put young men into Epicurus's boat,&mdash;wherein, having
						their ears stopped with wax, as those of the men of Ithaca
						were, they shall be obliged to sail by and not so much as
						touch at poetry,&mdash;or rather keep a guard on them, so as
						to oblige their judgments by principles of right reason to
						use it aright, and preserve them from being seduced to
						their hurt by that which affords them so much delight.
						For neither did Lycurgus, the valiant son of Dryas (as
						Homer<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">I1. VI 130.</note> calls him) act like a man of sound reason in the
						course which he took to reform his people that were much
						inclined to drunkenness, by travelling up and down to destroy all the vines in the country; whereas he should have
						ordered that every vine should have a well of water near it,
						that (as Plato saith) the drunken deity might be reduced to
						temperance by a sober one. For water mixed with wine
						takes away the hurtful spirits, while it leaves the useful
						ones in it. Neither should we cut down or destroy the
						Muses' vine, poetry; but where we perceive it luxuriates
						and grows wild through an ungoverned appetite of applause, there ought we to prune away or keep under the
						fabulous and theatrical branches thereof; and where we
						find any of the Graces linked to any of the Muses,&mdash;that
						is, where the lusciousness and tempting charms of language
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.45"/>
						
						 are not altogether barren and unprofitable,&mdash;there
						let us bring in philosophy to incorporate with it.</p>
            <p>For as, where the mandrake grows near the vine and so
						communicates something of its force thereto, the wine that
						is made of its grapes makes the sleep of those that drink
						it more refreshing; so doth the tempering poetry with the
						principles of philosophy and allaying their roughness with
						its fictions render the study of them more easy and the
						relish of them more grateful to young learners. Wherefore those that would give their minds to philosophical
						studies are not obliged to avoid poetry altogether, but
						rather to prepare themselves for philosophy by poems,
						accustoming themselves to search for and embrace that
						which may profit in that which pleaseth them, and rejecting and discarding that wherein they find nothing of this
						nature. For this discrimination is the first step to learning; and when this is attained, then, according to what
						Sophocles saith,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To have begun well what we do intend
						</l>
                     <l>Gives hope and prospect of as good an end.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Let us therefore in the first place possess those whom
					we initiate in the study of poetry with this notion (as one
					which they ought always to have at hand), that
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis frequently the poet's guise
					</l>
                     <l>To intermingle truth with lies;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>which they do sometimes with and sometimes against
						their wills. They do it with their wills, because they find
						strict truth too rigid to comply with that sweetness and
						gracefulness of expression, which most are taken with, so
						readily as fiction doth. For real truth, though it disgust
						never so much, must be told as it is, without alteration;
						but that which is feigned in a discourse can easily yield
						and shift its garb from the distasteful to that which is more
						pleasing. And indeed, neither the measures nor the tropes
						nor the grandeur of words nor the aptness of metaphors
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.46"/>
						
						nor the harmony of the composition gives such a degree
						of elegance and gracefulness to a poem as a well-ordered
						and artificial fiction doth. But as in pictures the colors
						are more delightful to the eye than the lines, because
						those give them a nearer resemblance to the persons they
						were made for, and render them the more apt to deceive
						the beholder; so in poems we are more apt to be smitten
						and fall in love with a probable fiction than with the greatest accuracy that can be observed in measures and phrases,
						where there is nothing fabulous or fictitious joined with it.
						Wherefore Socrates, being induced by some dreams to attempt something in poetry, and finding himself unapt, by
						reason that he had all his lifetime been the champion of
						severe truth, to hammer out of his own invention a likely
						fiction, made choice of Esop's fables to turn into verse; as
						judging nothing to be true poetry that had in it nothing
						of falsehood. For though we have known some sacrifices
						performed without pipes and dances, yet we own no poetry
						which is utterly destitute of fable and fiction. Whence the
						verses of Empedocles and Parmenides, the Theriaca of
						Nicander, and the sentences of Theognis, are rather to be
						accounted speeches than poems, which, that they might not
						walk contemptibly on foot, have borrowed from poetry the
						chariot of verse, to convey them the more creditably through
						the world. Whensoever therefore any thing is spoken in
						poems by any noted and eminently famous man, concerning
						Gods or Daemons or virtue, that is absurd or harsh, he that
						takes such sayings for truths is thereby misled in his apprehension and corrupted with an erroneous opinion. But
						he that constantly keeps in his mind and maintains as his
						principle that the witchcraft of poetry consists in fiction,
						he that can at all turns accost it in this language,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Riddle of art! like which no sphinx beguiles;
						</l>
                     <l>Whose face on one side frowns while th' other smiles!
						</l>
                     <l>Why cheat'st thou, with pretence to make us wise,
						</l>
                     <l>And bid'st sage precepts in a fool's disguise?&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.47"/>
            <p>such a one, I say, will take no harm. by it, nor admit from
						it any absurd thing into his belief. But when he meets in
						poetry with expressions of Neptune's rending the earth to
						pieces and discovering the infernal regions,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See. Il. XX. 57.</note> he will be
						able to check his fears of the reality of any such accident;
						and he will rebuke himself for his anger against Apollo for
						the chief commander of the Greeks,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whom at a banquet, whiles he sings his praise
						</l>
                     <l>And speaks him fair, yet treacherously he slays.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                           <bibl>From Aeschylus. The whole passage is quoted in Plato's Republic, end of
							Book II. (G.)</bibl>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
						
						Yea, he will repress his tears for Achilles and Agamemnon,
						while they are represented as mourning after their death,
						and stretching forth their limber and feeble hands to express their desire to live again. And if at any time the
						charms of poetry transport him into any disquieting passions, he will quickly say to himself, as Homer very elegantly (considering the propension of women to listen after
						fables) says in his Necyia, or relation of the state of
						the dead,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But from the dark dominions speed thy way,
						</l>
                     <l>And climb the steep ascent to upper day;
						</l>
                     <l>To thy chaste bride the wondrous story tell,
						</l>
                     <l>The woes, the horrors, and the laws of hell.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 223.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Such things as I have touched upon are those which the
						poets willingly feign. But more there are which they do
						not feign, but believing them themselves as their own
						proper judgments, they put fictitious colors upon them to
						ingratiate them to us. As when Homer says of Jupiter,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Jove lifts the golden balances, that show
						</l>
                     <l>The fates of mortal men, and things below.
						</l>
                     <l>Here each contending hero's lot he tries,
						</l>
                     <l>And weighs with equal hand their destinies.
						</l>
                     <l>Low sinks the scale surcharged with Hector's fate;
						</l>
                     <l>Heavy with death it sinks, and hell receives the weight.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXII. 210.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>To this fable Aeschylus hath accommodated a whole tragedy
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.48"/>
						
						 which he calls Psychostasia, wherein he introduceth
						Thetis and Aurora standing by Jupiter's balances, and
						deprecating each of them the death of her son engaged
						in a duel. Now there is no man but sees that this fable is
						a creature of the poet's fancy, designed to delight or scare
						the reader. But this other passage,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great Jove is made the treasurer of wars;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IV. 84.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and this other also,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When a God means a noble house to raze,
						</l>
                     <l>He frames one rather than he'll want a cause:</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Niobe of Aeschylus, Frag. 151.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>these passages, I say, express the judgment and belief of
						poets who thereby discover and suggest to us the ignorant
						or mistaken apprehensions they had of the Deities. Moreover, almost every one knows nowadays, that the portentous fancies and contrivances of stories concerning the state
						of the dead are accommodated to popular apprehensions,
						&mdash;that the spectres and phantasms of burning rivers and
						horrid regions and terrible tortures expressed by frightful
						names are all mixed with fable and fiction, as poison with
						food; and that neither Homer nor Pindar nor Sophocles
						ever believed themselves when they wrote at this rate:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There endless floods of shady darkness stream
						</l>
                     <l>From the vast caves, where mother Night doth teem;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There ghosts o'er the vast ocean's waves did glide,
						</l>
                     <l>By the Leucadian promontory's side;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XXIV. 11.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There from th' unfathomed gulf th' infernal lake
						</l>
                     <l>Through narrow straits recurring tides doth make.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, as many of them as deplore death as a lamentable
						thing, or the want of burial after death as a calamitous
						condition, are wont to break out into expressions of this
						nature:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O pass not by, my friend; nor leave me here
						</l>
                     <l>Without a grave, and on that grave a tear;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 72.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.49"/>
            <p>and,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then to the ghosts the mournful soul did fly,
						</l>
                     <l>Sore grieved in midst of youth and strength to die;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 856.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis sweet to see the light. O spare me then,
						</l>
                     <l>Till I arrive at th' usual age of men:
						</l>
                     <l>Nor force my unfledged soul from hence, to know
						</l>
                     <l>The doleful state of dismal shades below.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Iph. Aul. 1218.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These, I say, are the speeches of men persuaded of these
						things, as being possessed by erroneous opinions; and
						therefore they touch us the more nearly and torment us
						inwardly, because we ourselves are full of the same impotent passion from which they were uttered. To fortify us
						therefore against expressions of this nature, let this principle continually ring in our ears, that poetry is not at all
						solicitous to keep to the strict measure of truth. And
						indeed, as to what that truth in these matters is, even
						those men themselves who make it their only study to
						learn and search it out confess that they can hardly discover any certain footsteps to guide them in that enquiry.
						Let us therefore have these verses of Empedocles, in this
						case, at hand:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No sight of man's so clear, no ear so quick,
						</l>
                     <l>No mind so piercing, that's not here to seek;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as also those of Xenophanes:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The truth about the Gods and world, no man
						</l>
                     <l>E'er was or shall be that determine can;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and lastly, that passage concerning Socrates, in Plato,
						where he by the solemnity of an oath disclaims all knowledge of those things. For those who perceive that the
						searching into such matters makes the heads of philosophers themselves giddy cannot but be the less inclined to
						regard what poets say concerning them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>And we shall fix our young man yet the more if,
					when we enter him in the poets, we first describe poetry
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.50"/>
					
					to him, and tell him that it is an imitating art and doth in
					many respects correspond to painting; not only acquainting
					him with that common saying, that poetry is vocal painting and painting silent poetry, but teaching him, moreover, that when we see a lizard or an ape or the face of
					a Thersites in a picture, we are surprised with pleasure
					and wonder at it, not because of any beauty in the things,
					but for the likeness of the draught. For it is repugnant
					to the nature of that which is itself foul to be at the same
					time fair; and therefore it is the imitation&mdash;be the thing
					imitated beautiful or ugly&mdash;that, in case it do express it
					to the life, is commended; and on the contrary, if the
					imitation make a foul thing to appear fair, it is dispraised
					because it observes not decency and likeness. Now some
					painters there are that paint uncomely actions; as Timotheus drew Medea killing her children; Theon, Orestes
					murdering his mother; and Parrhasius, Ulysses counterfeiting madness; yea, Chaerephanes expressed in picture
					the unchaste converse of women with men. Now in such
					cases a young man is to be familiarly acquainted with this
					notion, that, when men praise such pictures, they praise
					not the actions represented but only the painter's art,
					which doth so lively express what was designed in them.
					Wherefore, in like manner, seeing poetry many times describes by imitation foul actions and unseemly passions
					and manners, the young student must not in such descriptions (although performed never so artificially and commendably) believe all that is said as true or embrace it as
					good, but give its due commendation so far only as it suits
					the subject treated of. For as, when we hear the grunting
					of hogs and the shrieking of pulleys and the rustling of
					wind and the roaring of seas, we are, it may be, disturbed
					and displeased, and yet when we hear any one imitating
					these or the like noises handsomely (as Parmenio did that
					of an hog, and Theodorus that of a pulley), we are well
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.51"/>
					
					pleased; and as we avoid (as an unpleasing spectacle) the
					sight of sick persons and of a lazar full of ulcers, and yet
					are delighted to be spectators of the Philoctetes of Aristophon and the Jocasta of Silanion, wherein such wasting and dying persons are well acted; so must the young
					scholar, when he reads in a poem of Thersites the buffoon or Sisyphus the whoremaster or Batrachus the bawd
					speaking or doing any thing, so praise the artificial managery of the poet, adapting the expressions to the persons,
					as withal to look on the discourses and actions so expressed as odious and abominable. For the goodness of
					things themselves differs much from the goodness of the
					imitation of them; the goodness of the latter consisting
					only in propriety and aptness to represent the former.
					Whence to foul actions foul expressions are most suitable
					and proper. As the shoes of Demonides the cripple
					(which, when he had lost them, he wished might suit the
					feet of him that stole them) were but unhandsome shoes,
					but yet fit for the man they were made for; so we may
					say of such expressions as these:&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis worth the while an unjust act to own,
					</l>
                     <l>When it sets him that does it on a throne;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 524.</note>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Get the repute of Just for a disguise,
						</l>
                     <l>And in it do all things whence gain may rise;</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>A talent dowry ! Could I close my eyes
						</l>
                     <l>In sleep, or live, if thee I should despise ?
						</l>
                     <l>And should I not in hell tormented be,
						</l>
                     <l>Could I be guilty of profaning thee?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Menander.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These, it is true, are wicked as well as false speeches, but
						yet are decent enough in the mouth of an Eteocles, an
						Ixion, and an old griping usurer. If therefore we mind
						our children that the poets write not such things as praising and approving them, but do really account them base
						and vicious and therefore accommodate such speeches to
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.52"/>
						
						base and vicious persons, they will never be damnified by
						them from the esteem they have of the poets in whom they
						meet with them. But, on the contrary, the suspicions insinuated into them of the persons will render the words
						and actions ascribed to them suspected for evil, because
						proceeding from such evil men. And of this nature is
						Homer's representation of Paris, when he describes him
						running out of the battle into Helen's bed. For in that he
						attributes no such indecent act to any other, but only to
						that incontinent and adulterous person, he evidently declares that he intends that relation to import a disgrace
						and reproach to such intemperance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>In such passages therefore we are carefully to observe whether or not the poet himself do anywhere give
					any intimation that he dislikes the things he makes such
					persons say; which, in the prologue to his Thais Menander does, in these words:&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therefore, my Muse, describe me now a whore,
					</l>
                     <l>Fair, bold, and furnished with a nimble tongue;
					</l>
                     <l>One that ne'er scruples to do lovers wrong;
					</l>
                     <l>That always craves, and denied shuts her door;
					</l>
                     <l>That truly loves no man, yet, for her ends,
					</l>
                     <l>Affection true to every man pretends.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But Homer of all the poets does it best. For he doth
						beforehand, as it were, bespeak dislike of the evil things
						and approbation of the good things he utters. Of the
						latter take these instances:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He readily did the occasion take,
						</l>
                     <l>And sweet and comfortable words he spake;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VI. 148.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>By him he stood, and with soft speeches quelled
						</l>
                     <l>The wrath which in his heated bosom swelled.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. II. 189.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And for the former, he so performs it as in a manner
						solemnly to forbid us to use or heed such speeches as
						those he mentions, as being foolish and wicked. For example, being to tell us how uncivilly Agamemnon treated
						the priest, he premises these words of his own,&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.53"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not so Atrides: he with kingly pride
						</l>
                     <l>Repulsed the sacred sire, and thus replied;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 24.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>intimating the insolency and unbecomingness of his answer. And when he attributes this passionate speech to Achilles,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O monster, mix'd of insolence and fear,
						</l>
                     <l>Thou dog in forehead, and in heart a deer!</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 225.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he accompanies it with this censure,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor yet the rage his boiling breast forsook,
						</l>
                     <l>Which thus redoubling on Atrides broke;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 223.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for it was unlikely that speaking in such anger he should
						observe any rules of decency.</p>
            <p>And he passeth like censures on actions. As on
						Achilles's foul usage of Hector's carcass,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gloomy he said, and (horrible to view)
						</l>
                     <l>Before the bier the bleeding Hector threw.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXIII. 24.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in like manner he doth very decently shut up relations of things said or done, by adding some sentence
						wherein he declares his judgment of them. As when he
						personates some of the Gods saying, on the occasion of
						the adultery of Mars and Venus discovered by Vulcan's
						artifice,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>See the swift God o'ertaken by the lame !
						</l>
                     <l>Thus ill acts prosper not, but end in shame.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VIII. 329.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And thus concerning Hecter's insolent boasting he says,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With such big words his mind proud sector eased,
						</l>
                     <l>But venerable Juno lie displeased.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VIII. 198.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And when he speaks of Pandarus's shooting, he adds,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He heard, and madly at the motion pleased,
						</l>
                     <l>His polish'd bow with hasty rashness seized.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IV. 104.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now these verbal intimations of the minds and judgments
						of poets are not difficult to be understood by any one that
						will heedfully observe them. But besides these, they give
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.54"/>
						
						us other hints from actions. As Euripides is reported,
						when some blamed him for bringing such an impious and
						flagitious villain as Ixion upon the stage, to have given
						this answer: But yet I brought him not off till I had fastened him to a torturing wheel. This same way of teaching by mute actions is to be found in Homer also, affording us useful contemplations upon those very fables which
						are usually most disliked in him. These some men offer
						force to, that they may reduce them to allegories (which
						the ancients called <foreign lang="greek">u(po/noiai</foreign>), and tell us that Venus committing adultery with Mars, discovered by the Sun, is to be
						understood thus: that when the star called Venus is in
						conjunction with that which hath the name of Mars, bastardly births are produced, and by the Sun's rising and
						discovering them they are not concealed. So will they
						have Juno's dressing herself so accurately to tempt Jupiter,
						and her making use of the girdle of Venus to inflame his
						love, to be nothing else but the purification of that part of
						the air which draweth nearest to the nature of fire. As
						if we were not told the meaning of those fables far better
						by the poet himself. For he teacheth us in that of Venus,
						if we heed it, that light music and wanton songs and discourses which suggest to men obscene fancies debauch
						their manners, and incline them to an unmanly way of
						living in luxury and wantonness, of continually haunting
						the company of women, and of being
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Given to fashions, that their garb may please,
						</l>
                     <l>Hot baths, and couches where they loll at ease.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore also he brings in Ulysses directing the musician thus,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Leave this, and sing the horse, out of whose womb
						</l>
                     <l>The gallant knights that conquered Troy did come;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VIII. 249 and 492.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>evidently teaching us that poets and musicians ought to
						receive the arguments of their songs from sober and understanding
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.55"/>
						
						 men. And in the other fable of Juno he excellently shows that the conversation of women with men.
						and the favors they receive from them procured by sorcery,
						witchcraft, or other unlawful arts, are not only short, unstable, and soon cloying, but also in the issue easily turned
						to loathing and displeasure, when once the pleasure is
						over. For so Jupiter there threatens Juno, when he tells
						her,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hear this, remember, and our fury dread,
						</l>
                     <l>Nor pull the unwilling vengeance on thy head;
						</l>
                     <l>Lest arts and blandishments successless prove
						</l>
                     <l>Thy soft deceits and well dissembled love.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XV. 32.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the fiction and representation of evil acts, when it
						withal acquaints us with the shame and damage befalling
						the doers, hurts not but rather profits him that reads them.
						For which end philosophers make use of examples for our
						instruction and correction out of historical collections;
						and poets do the very same thing, but with this difference,
						that they invent fabulous examples themselves. There
						was one Melanthius, who (whether in jest or earnest he
						said it, it matters not much) affirmed that the city of
						Athens owed its preservation to the dissensions and factions that were among the orators, giving withal this
						reason for his assertion, that thereby they were kept from
						inclining all of them to one side, so that by means of the
						differences among those statesmen there were always some
						that drew the saw the right way for the defeating of destructive counsels. And thus it is too in the contradictions
						among poets, which, by lessening the credit of what they
						say, render them the less powerful to do mischief; and
						therefore, when comparing one saying with another we
						discover their contrariety, we ought to adhere to the better
						side. As in these instances:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Gods, my son, deceive poor men oft-times.
						</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="italics">Ans.</hi> 'Tis easy, sir, on God to lay our crimes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.56"/>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis comfort to thee to be rich, is't not!
					</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="italics">Ans.</hi> No, sir, 'tis bad to be a wealthy sot.</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Die rather than such toilsome pains to take.
						</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="italics">Ans.</hi> To call God's service toil's a foul mistake.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Such contrarieties as these are easily solved, if (as I said)
						we teach youth to judge aright and to give the better saying preference. But if we chance to meet with any absurd
						passages without any others at their heels to confute them,
						we are then to overthrow them with such others as elsewhere are to be found in the author. Nor must we be
						offended with the poet or grieved at him, but only at the
						speeches themselves, which he utters either according to
						the vulgar manner of speaking or, it may be, but in drollery. So, when thou readest in Homer of Gods thrown
						out of heaven headlong one by another, or Gods wounded
						by men and quarrelling and brawling with each other, thou
						mayest readily, if thou wilt, say to him,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sure thy invention here was sorely out,
						</l>
                     <l>Or thou hadst said far better things, no doubt;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VIII. 358.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>yea, and thou dost so elsewhere, and according as thou
						thinkest, to wit, in these passages of thine:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Gods, removed from all that men doth grieve,
						</l>
                     <l>A quiet and contented life do live.</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Herein the immortal Gods for ever blest
							</l>
                     <l>Feel endless joys and undisturbed rest.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Gods, who have themselves no cause to grieve,
					</l>
                     <l>For wretched man a web of sorrow weave.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VI. 138; Odyss. VI. 46; Il. XXIV. 526.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For these argue sound and true opinions of the Gods; but
						those other were only feigned to raise passions in men.
						Again, when Euripides speaks at this rate,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Gods are better than we men by far,
						</l>
                     <l>And yet by them we oft deceived are,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>we may do well to quote him elsewhere against himself,
						where he says better,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If Gods do wrong, surely no Gods there are.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.57"/>
            <p>So also, when Pindar saith bitterly and keenly,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No law forbids us any thing to do,
						</l>
                     <l>Whereby a mischief may befall a foe,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>tell him: But, Pindar, thou thyself sayest elsewhere,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The pleasure which injurious acts attends
						</l>
                     <l>Always in bitter consequences ends.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And when Sophocles speaks thus,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sweet is the gain, wherein to lie and cheat
						</l>
                     <l>Adds the repute of wit to what we get,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>tell him: But we have heard thee say far otherwise,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When the account's cast up, the gain's but poor
						</l>
                     <l>Which by a lying tongue augments the store.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And as to what he saith of riches, to wit:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wealth, where it minds to go, meets with no stay;
						</l>
                     <l>For where it finds not, it can make a way;
						</l>
                     <l>Many fair offers doth the poor let go,
						</l>
                     <l>And lose his prize because his purse is low;
						</l>
                     <l>The fair tongue makes, where wealth can purchase it,
						</l>
                     <l>The foul face beautiful, the fool a wit:&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>here the reader may set in opposition divers other sayings
						of the same author. For example,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>From honor poverty doth not debar,
						</l>
                     <l>Where poor men virtuous and deserving are.</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Whate'er fools think, a man is ne'er the worse
							</l>
                     <l>If he be wise, though with an empty purse.</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>The comfort which he gets who wealth enjoys,
							</l>
                     <l>The vexing care by which 'tis kept destroys.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Menander also somewhere magnifies a voluptuous
						life, and inflames the minds of vain persons with these
						amorous strains,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The glorious sun no living thing doth see,
						</l>
                     <l>But what's a slave to love as well as we.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But yet elsewhere, on the other side, he fastens on us and
						pulls us back to the love of virtue, and checks the rage
						of lust, when he says thus,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The life that is dishonorably spent,
						</l>
                     <l>Be it ne'er so pleasant, yields no true content.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.58"/>
            <p>For these lines are contrary to the former, as they are also
						better and more profitable; so that by comparing them
						considerately one cannot but either be inclined to the better side, or at least flag in the belief of the worse.</p>
            <p>But now, supposing that any of the poets themselves
						afford no such correcting passages to solve what they have
						said amiss, it will then be advisable to confront them with
						the contrary sayings of other famous men, and therewith to
						sway the scales of our judgment to the better side. As,
						when Alexis tempts to debauchery in these verses,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The wise man knows what of all things is best,
						</l>
                     <l>Whilst choosing pleasure he slights all the rest.
						</l>
                     <l>He thinks life's joys complete in these three sorts,
						</l>
                     <l>To drink and eat, and follow wanton sports;
						</l>
                     <l>And what besides seems to pretend to pleasure,
						</l>
                     <l>If it betide him, counts it over measure,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>we must remember that Socrates said the contrary, to wit:
						Bad men live that they may eat and drink, whereas good
						men eat and drink that they may live. And against the
						man that wrote in this manner,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He that designs to encounter with a knave,
						</l>
                     <l>An equal stock of knavery must have,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>seeing he herein advises us to follow other vicious examples, that of Diogenes may well be returned, who being
						asked by what means a man might revenge himself upon
						his enemy, answered, By becoming himself a good and
						honest man. And the same Diogenes may be quoted also
						against Sophocles, who, writing thus of the sacred mysteries, caused great grief and despair to multitudes of
						men:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Most happy they whose eyes are blest to see
						</l>
                     <l>The mysteries which here contained be,
						</l>
                     <l>Before they die ! For only they have joy
						</l>
                     <l>In th' other world; the rest all ills annoy.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This passage being read to Diogenes, What then! says
						he, shall the condition of Pataecion, the notorious robber,
						after death be better than that of Epaminondas, merely for
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.59"/>
						
						his being initiated in these mysteries? In like manner,
						when one Timotheus on the theatre, in the praise of the
						Goddess Diana, called her furious, raging, possessed,
						mad, Cinesias presently cried out to him aloud, May thy
						daughter, Timotheus, be such a Goddess! And witty
						also was that of Bion to Theognis, who said,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>One can not say nor do, if poor he be;
						</l>
                     <l>His tongue is bound to th' peace, as well as he.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theognis, vss. 177, 178.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>How comes it to pass then, said he, Theognis, that thou
						thyself being so poor pratest and gratest our ears in this
						manner?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Nor are we to omit in our reading those hints which,
					from some other words or phrases bordering on those that
					offend us, may help to rectify our apprehensions. But as
					physicians use cantharides, believing that, though their
					bodies be deadly poison, yet their feet and wings are medicinal and can even kill the poison of the flies themselves,
					so must we deal with poems. If any noun or verb near at
					hand may assist to the correction of any such saying, and
					preserve us from putting a bad construction upon it, we
					should take hold of it and employ it to assist a more favorable interpretation. As some do in reference to those
					verses of Homer,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sorrows and tears most commonly are seen
					</l>
                     <l>To be the Gods' rewards to wretched men :&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>The Gods, who have no cause themselves to grieve,
						</l>
                     <l>For wretched man a web of sorrow weave.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IV. 197; Il. XXIV. 526.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For, they say, he says not of men simply, or of all men,
						that the Gods weave for them the fatal web of a sorrowful
						life; but he affirms it only of foolish and imprudent men,
						whom, because their vices make them such, he therefore
						calls wretched and miserable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Another way whereby those passages which are suspicious in poets may be transferred to a better sense may
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.60"/>
					
					be taken from the common use of words, which a young
					man ought indeed to be more exercised in than in the use
					of strange and obscure terms. For it will be a point of
					philology which it will not be unpleasant to him to understand, that when he meets with <foreign lang="greek">r(igedanh/</foreign> in a poet, that word
					signifies an <hi rend="italics">evil death;</hi> for the Macedonians use the word
					<foreign lang="greek">da/nos</foreign> to signify <hi rend="italics">death.</hi> So the Aeolians call victory gotten
					by patient endurance of hardships <foreign lang="greek">kammoni/h</foreign>; and the Dryopians call daemons <foreign lang="greek">po/poi</foreign>.</p>
            <p>But of all things it is most necessary, and no less profitable if we design to receive profit and not hurt from the
						poets, that we understand how they make use of the names
						of Gods, as also of the terms of Evil and Good; and what
						they mean by Fortune and Fate; and whether these words
						be always taken by them in one and the same sense or
						rather in various senses, as also many other words are.
						For so the word <foreign lang="greek">oi)=kos</foreign> sometimes signifies a <hi rend="italics">material house,</hi>
						as, Into the high-roofed house; and sometimes <hi rend="italics">estate,</hi> as,
						My house is devoured. So the word <foreign lang="greek">bo/otos</foreign> sometimes signifies <hi rend="italics">life,</hi> and sometimes <hi rend="italics">wealth.</hi> And <foreign lang="greek">a)lu/ein</foreign> is sometimes
						taken for being <hi rend="italics">uneasy</hi> and <hi rend="italics">disquieted in mind,</hi> as in
						<quote lang="greek" rend="blockquote">
                  <l>w(s e)/faq' h( d' a)lu/ous' a)pebh/sato, tei/reto d' ai)nw=s,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Il. V. 352.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
						and elsewhere for boasting and rejoicing, as in
						<quote lang="greek" rend="blockquote">
                  <l>)\H a)lu/eis, dti )=Iron e)ne/khsas to\n a)lh/thn.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Odyss. XVIII. 333.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
						In like manner <foreign lang="greek">qoa/zein</foreign> signifies either <hi rend="italics">to move,</hi> as in Euripides when he saith,
						<quote lang="greek" rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Kh=tos qoa/zon e)k )Atlantikh=s a(lo/s,&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>or <hi rend="italics">to sit,</hi> as in Sophocles when he writes thus,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ti/nas po/q' e(/dras ta/sde moi qoa/zete,
						</l>
                     <l>(Ikthri/ois kla/doisin e)cestemme/noi.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Oed. Tyr. 2.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is elegant also when they adapt to the present matter, as grammarians teach, the use of words which are commonly of another signification. As here:&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.61"/>
						
						         <quote lang="greek" rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Nh=' o)li/ghn ai/nei=n, mega/lh| d'ni\ forti/a qe/sqai.</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For here <foreign lang="greek">ai)nei=n</foreign> signifies <hi rend="italics">to praise</hi> (instead of <foreign lang="greek">e)painei=n</foreign>), and <hi rend="italics">to</hi>
						         <hi rend="italics">praise</hi> is used for <hi rend="italics">to refuse.</hi> So in conversation it is common with us to say, <foreign lang="greek">kalw=s e)/xei</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">it is well</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italics">No, I thank</hi>
						         <hi rend="italics">you</hi>), and to bid any thing <hi rend="italics">fare well</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">xai/rein</foreign>); by which forms
						of speech we refuse a thing which we do not want, or receive it not, but still with a civil compliment. So also
						some say that Proserpina is called <foreign lang="greek">e)painh/</foreign> in the notion of
						<foreign lang="greek">paraithth/</foreign>, to be <hi rend="italics">deprecated,</hi> because death is by all men
						shunned.</p>
            <p>And the like distinction of words we ought to observe
						also in things more weighty and serious. To begin with
						the Gods, we should teach our youth that poets, when they
						use the names of Gods, sometimes mean properly the
						Divine Beings so called, but otherwhiles understand by
						those names certain powers of which the Gods are the
						donors and authors, they having first led us into the use of
						them by their own practice. As when Archilochus prays,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>King Vulcan, hear thy suppliant, and grant
						</l>
                     <l>That which thou'rt wont to give and I to want,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>it is plain that he means the God himself whom he invokes. But when elsewhere he bewails the drowning of
						his sister's husband, who had not obtained lawful burial,
						and says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Had Vulcan his fair limbs to ashes turned,
						</l>
                     <l>I for his loss had with less passion mourned,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he gives the name of Vulcan to the fire and not to the
						Deity. Again, Euripides, when he says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No; by great Jove I swear, enthroned on high,
						</l>
                     <l>And bloody Mars,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 1006.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>means the Gods themselves who bare those names. But
						when Sophocles saith,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Blind Mars doth mortal men's affairs confound,
						</l>
                     <l>As the swine's snout doth quite deface the ground,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.62"/>
            <p>we are to understand the word Mars to denote not the God
						so called, but war. And by the same word we are to understand also weapons made of hardened brass, in those verses
						of Homer,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>These are the gallant men whose noble blood
						</l>
                     <l>Keen Mars did shed near swift Scamander's flood.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 329.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, in conformity to the instances given, we must
						conceive and bear in mind that by the names of Jupiter
						also sometimes they mean the God himself, sometimes Fortune, and oftentimes also Fate. For when they say,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great Jupiter, who from the lofty hill
						</l>
                     <l>Of Ida govern'st all the world at will;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. III. 276.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>That wrath which hurled to Pluto's gloomy realm
					</l>
                     <l>The souls of mighty chiefs :&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>Such was the sovereign doom, and such the will of Jove;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 3 and 5.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For who (but who himself too fondly loves)
					</l>
                     <l>Dares lay his wisdom in the scale with Jove's?&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they understand Jupiter himself. But when they ascribe
						the event of all things done to Jupiter as the cause, saying
						of him,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Many brave souls to hell Achilles sent,
						</l>
                     <l>And Jove's design accomplished in th' event,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they mean by Jove no more but Fate. For the poet doth
						not conceive that God contrives mischief against mankind,
						but he soundly declares the mere necessity of the things
						themselves, to wit, that prosperity and victory are destined
						by Fate to cities and armies and commanders who govern
						themselves with sobriety, but if they give way to passions
						and commit errors, thereby dividing and crumbling themselves into factions, as those of whom the poet speaks did,
						they do unhandsome actions, and thereby create great disturbances, such as are attended with sad consequences.
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For to all unadvised acts, in fine,
						</l>
                     <l>The Fates unhappy issues do assign.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But when Hesiod brings in Prometheus thus counselling
						his brother Epimetheus,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.63"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Brother, if Jove to thee a present make,
						</l>
                     <l>Take heed that from his hands thou nothing take,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 86.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he useth the name of Jove to express Fortune; for he calls
						the good things which come by her (such as riches, and
						marriages, and empires, and indeed all external things the
						enjoyment whereof is unprofitable to them who know not
						how to use them well) the gifts of Jove. And therefore he
						adviseth Epimetheus (an ill man, and a fool withal) to stand
						in fear of and to guard himself from prosperity, as that
						which would be hurtful and destructive to him.</p>
            <p>Again, where he saith,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Reproach thou not a man for being poor;
						</l>
                     <l>His poverty's God's gift, as is thy store,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 717.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he calls that which befalls men by Fortune God's gift, and
						intimates that it is an unworthy thing to reproach any man
						for that poverty which he falls into by Fortune, whereas
						poverty is then only a matter of disgrace and reproach
						when it is attendant on sloth and idleness, or wantonness
						and prodigality. For, before the name of Fortune was
						used, they knew there was a powerful cause, which moved
						irregularly and unlimitedly and with such a force that no
						human reason could avoid it; and this cause they called by
						the names of Gods. So we are wont to call divers things
						and qualities and discourses, and even men themselves,
						divine. And thus may we rectify many such sayings concerning Jupiter as would otherwise seem very absurd. As
						these, for instance:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Before Jove's door two fatal hogsheads, filled
						</l>
                     <l>With human fortunes, good and bad luck yield:&mdash;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXIV. 527</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of violated oaths Jove took no care,
					</l>
                     <l>But spitefully both parties crushed by war:&mdash; </l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 69</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To Greeks and Trojans both this was the rise
					</l>
                     <l>Of mischief, suitable to Jove's device.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VIII. 81.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.64"/>
            <p>These passages we are to interpret as spoken concerning
						Fortune or Fate, of the causality of both which no account
						can be given by us, nor do their effects fall under our power.
						But where any thing is said of Jupiter that is suitable,
						rational, and probable, there we are to conceive that the
						names of that God is used properly. As in these instances:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Through others' ranks he conquering did range,
						</l>
                     <l>But shunned with Ajax any blows t' exchange;
						</l>
                     <l>But Jove's displeasure on him he had brought,
						</l>
                     <l>Had he with one so much his better fought.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 540.</note>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>For though great matters are Jove's special care,
							</l>
                     <l>Small things t' inferior daemons trusted are.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And other words there are which the poets remove and
						translate from their proper sense by accommodation to
						various things, which deserve also our serious notice. Such
						a one, for instance, is <foreign lang="greek">a)reth/</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">virtue.</hi> For because virtue
						does not only render men prudent, just, and good, both in
						their words and deeds, but also oftentimes purchaseth to
						them honor and power, therefore they call likewise these
						by that name. So we are wont to call both the olive-tree
						and the fruit <foreign lang="greek">e)lai/a</foreign>, and the oak-tree and its acorn <foreign lang="greek">fhgo/s</foreign>,
						communicating the name of the one to the other. Therefore, when our young man reads in the poets such passages
						as these,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This law th' immortal Gods to us have set,
						</l>
                     <l>That none arrive at virtue but by sweat;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 289.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The adverse troops then did the Grecians stout
					</l>
                     <l>By their mere virtue profligate and rout;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 90.</note>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>If now the Fates determined have our death,
						</l>
                     <l>To virtue we'll consign our parting breath;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>let him presently conceive that these things are spoken of
						that most excellent and divine habit in us which we understand to be no other than right reason, or the highest
						attainment of the reasonable nature, and most agreeable
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.65"/>
						
						to the constitution thereof. And again, when he reads
						this,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of virtue Jupiter to one gives more,
						</l>
                     <l>And lessens, when he lifts, another's store;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and this,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Virtue and honor upon wealth attend;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                           <bibl>Il. XX. 242; Hesiod, Works and Days, 313.</bibl>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
							        </quote>
						
						let him not sit down in an astonishing admiration of rich
						men, as if they were enabled by their wealth to purchase
						virtue, nor let him imagine that it is in the power of Fortune to increase or lessen his own wisdom; but let him
						conceive that the poet by virtue meant either glory or power
						or prosperity or something of like import. For poets use
						the same ambiguity also in the word <foreign lang="greek">kako/ths</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">evil,</hi> which
						sometimes in them properly signifies a wicked and malicious disposition of mind, as in that of Hesiod,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Evil is soon acquired; for everywhere
						</l>
                     <l>There's plenty on't and t'all men's dwellings near;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 287.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and sometimes some evil accident or misfortune, as when
						Homer says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sore evils, when they haunt us in our prime,
						</l>
                     <l>Hasten old age on us before our time.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIX. 360.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>So also in the word <foreign lang="greek">eu)daimoni/a</foreign>, he would be sorely deceived
						who should imagine that, wheresoever he meets with it in
						poets, it means (as it does in philosophy) a perfect habitual
						enjoyment of all good things or the leading a life every
						way agreeable to Nature, and that they do not withal by
						the abuse of such words call rich men happy or blessed,
						and power or glory felicity. For, though Homer rightly
						useth terms of that nature in this passage,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though of such great estates I am possest,
						</l>
                     <l>Yet with true inward joy I am not blest;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IV. 93.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and Menander in this,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>So great's th' estate I am endowed withal:
						</l>
                     <l>All say I'm rich, but none me happy call;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.66"/>
            <p>yet Euripides discourseth more confusedly and perplexedly
						when he writes after this manner,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>May I ne'er live that grievous blessed life;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But tell me, man, why valuest thou so high
					</l>
                     <l>Th' unjust beatitude of tyranny ?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Medea, 598; Phoeniss. 549.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>except, as I said, we allow him the use of these words in a
						metaphorical and abusive sense. But enough hath been
						spoken of these matters.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Nevertheless, this principle is not once only but often
					to be inculcated and pressed on young men, that poetry,
					when it undertakes a fictitious argument by way of imitation, though it make use of such ornament and illustration
					as suit the actions and manners treated of, yet disclaims not
					all likelihood of truth, seeing the force of imitation, in
					order to the persuading of men, lies in probability. Wherefore such imitation as does not altogether shake hands with
					truth carries along with it certain signs of virtue and vice
					mixed together in the actions which it doth represent. And
					of this nature is Homer's poetry, which totally bids adieu
					to Stoicism, the principles whereof will not admit any vice
					to come near where virtue is, nor virtue to have any thing to
					do where any vice lodgeth, but affirms that he that is not
					a wise man can do nothing well, and he that is so can do
					nothing amiss. Thus they determine in the schools. But
					in human actions and the affairs of common life the judgment of Euripides is verified, that
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Virtue and vice ne'er separately exist,
					</l>
                     <l>But in the same acts with each other twist.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Aeolus of Euripides.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Next, it is to be observed that poetry, waiving the truth of
						things, does most labor to beautify its fictions with variety and
						multiplicity of contrivance. For variety bestows upon fable
						all that is pathetical, unusual, and surprising, and thereby
						makes it more taking and graceful; whereas what is void of
						variety is unsuitable to the nature of fable, and so raiseth no
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.67"/>
						
						passions at all. Upon which design of variety it is, that the
						poets never represent the same persons always victorious or
						prosperous or acting with the same constant tenor of virtue ;&mdash;yea, even the Gods themselves, when they engage
						in human actions, are not represented as free from passions
						and errors;&mdash;lest, for the want of some difficulties and
						cross passages, their poems should be destitute of that
						briskness which is requisite to move and astonish the minds
						of men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>These things therefore so standing, we should, when
					we enter a young man into the study of the poets, endeavor to free his mind from that degree of esteem of the
					good and great personages in them described as may incline
					him to think them to be mirrors of wisdom and justice, the
					chief of princes, and the exemplary measures of all virtue
					and goodness. For he will receive much prejudice, if he
					shall approve and admire all that comes from such persons
					as great, if he dislike nothing in them himself, nor will
					endure to hear others blame them, though for such words
					and actions as the following passages import:&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh! would to all the immortal powers above,
					</l>
                     <l>Apollo, Pallas, and almighty Jove!
					</l>
                     <l>That not one Trojan might be left alive,
					</l>
                     <l>And not a Greek of all the race survive.
					</l>
                     <l>Might only we the vast destruction shun,
					</l>
                     <l>And only we destroy the accursed town!</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Her breast all gore, with lamentable cries,
					</l>
                     <l>The bleeding innocent Cassandra dies,
					</l>
                     <l>Murdered by Clytemnestra's faithless hand:</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lie with thy father's whore, my mother said,
					</l>
                     <l>That she th' old man may loathe; and I obeyed:</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of all the Gods, O father Jove, there's none
					</l>
                     <l>Thus given to mischief but thyself alone.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 97; Odyss. XI. 421; Il. IX. 452; Il. III. 365.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Our young man is to be taught not to commend such
						things as these, no, nor to show the nimbleness of his wit
						or subtlety in maintaining an argument by finding out plausible colors and pretences to varnish over a bad matter. But
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.68"/>
						
						we should teach him rather to judge that poetry is an
						imitation of the manners and lives of such men as are not
						perfectly pure and unblamable, but such as are tinctured
						with passions, misled by false opinions, and muffled with
						ignorance; though oftentimes they may, by the help of a
						good natural temper, change them for better qualities.
						For the young man's mind, being thus prepared and disposed, will receive no damage by such passages when he
						meets with them in poems, but will on the one side be
						elevated with rapture at those things which are well said
						or done, and on the other, will not entertain but dislike
						those which are of a contrary character. But he that admires and is transported with every thing, as having his
						judgment enslaved by the esteem he hath for the names of
						heroes, will be unawares wheedled into many evil things,
						and be guilty of the same folly with those who imitate the
						crookedness of Plato or the lisping of Aristotle. Neither
						must he carry himself timorously herein, nor, like a superstitious person in a temple, tremblingly adore all he meets
						with; but use himself to such confidence as may enable
						him openly to pronounce, This was ill or incongruously
						said, and, That was bravely and gallantly spoken. For example, Achilles in Homer, being offended at the spinning
						out that war by delays, wherein he was desirous by feats
						of arms to purchase to himself glory, calls the soldiers together when there was an epidemical disease among them.
						But having himself some smattering skill in physic, and
						perceiving after the ninth day, which useth to be decretory
						in such cases, that the disease was no usual one nor proceeding from ordinary causes, when he stands up to speak,
						he waives applying himself to the soldiers, and addresseth
						himself as a councillor to the general, thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why leave we not the fatal Trojan shore,
						</l>
                     <l>And measure back the seas we cross'd before?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For this and the four following quotations, see Il. I. 59, 90, 220, 349; IX. 458.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.69"/>
            <p>And he spake well, and with due moderation and decorum.
						But when the soothsayer Chalcas had told him that he
						feared the wrath of the most potent among the Grecians,
						after an oath that while he lived no man should lay violent
						hands on him, he adds, but not with like wisdom and
						moderation,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not e'en the chief by whom our hosts are led,
						</l>
                     <l>The king of kings, shall touch that sacred head;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>in which speech he declares his low opinion or rather his
						contempt of his chief commander. And then, being farther
						provoked, he drew his weapon with a design to kill him,
						which attempt was neither good nor expedient. And therefore by and by he repented his rashness,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He said, observant of the blue-eyed maid;
						</l>
                     <l>Then in the sheath returned the shining blade;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>wherein again he did rightly and worthily, in that, though
						he could not altogether quell his passion, yet he restrained
						and reduced it under the command of reason, before it
						brake forth into such an irreparable act of mischief. Again,
						even Agamemnon himself talks in that assembly ridiculously, but carries himself more gravely and more like a
						prince in the matter of Chryseis. For whereas Achilles,
						when his Briseis was taken away from him,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In sullenness withdraws from all his friends,
						</l>
                     <l>And in his tent his time lamenting spends;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Agamemnon himself hands into the ship, delivers to her
						friends, and so sends from him, the woman concerning
						whom a little before he declared that he loved her better
						than his wife; and in that action did nothing unbecoming or savoring of fond affection. Also Phoenix, when
						his father bitterly cursed him for having to do with one
						that was his own harlot, says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Him in my rage I purposed to have killed,
						</l>
                     <l>But that my land some God in kindness held;
						</l>
                     <l>And minded me that Greeks would taunting say,
						</l>
                     <l>Lo, here's the man that did his father slav.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.70"/>
            <p>It is true that Aristarchus was afraid to permit these verses
						to stand in the poet, and therefore censured them to be
						expunged. But they were inserted by Homer very aptly
						to the occasion of Phoenix's instructing Achilles what a
						pernicious thing anger is, and what foul acts men do by its
						instigation, while they are capable neither of making use
						of their own reason nor of hearing the counsel of others.
						To which end he also introduceth Meleager at first highly
						offended with his citizens, and afterwards pacified; justly
						therein reprehending disordered passions, and praising it
						as a good and profitable thing not to yield to them, but to
						resist and overcome them, and to repent when one hath
						been overcome by them.</p>
            <p>Now in these instances the difference is manifest. But
						where a like clear judgment cannot be passed, there we
						are to settle the young man's mind thus, by way of distinction. If Nausicaa, having cast her eyes upon Ulysses,
						a stranger, and feeling the same passion for him as Calypso
						had before, did (as one that was ripe for a husband) out
						of wantonness talk with her maidens at this foolish rate,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Heaven ! in my connubial hour decree
						</l>
                     <l>This man my spouse, or such a spouse as he!</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VI. 251.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>she is blameworthy for her impudence and incontinence.
						But if, perceiving the man's breeding by his discourse, and
						admiring the prudence of his addresses, she rather wisheth
						to have such a one for a husband than a merchant or a
						dancing gallant of her fellow-citizens, she is to be commended. And when Ulysses is represented as rejoicing at
						Penelope's jocular conversation with her wooers, and
						at their presenting her with rich garments and other ornaments,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Because she cunningly the fools cajoled,
						</l>
                     <l>And bartered light words for their heavy gold;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XVIII. 282.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>if that joy were occasioned by greediness and covetous
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.71"/>
						
						ness, he discovers himself to be a more sordid prostituter
						of his own wife than Poliager is wont to be represented on
						the stage to have been, of whom it is said,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Happy man he, whose wife, like Capricorn,
						</l>
                     <l>Stores him with riches from a golden horn !</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But if through foresight he thought thereby to get them
						the more within his power, as being lulled asleep in security for the future by the hopes she gave them at present,
						this rejoicing, joined with confidence in his wife, was rational. Again, when he is brought in numbering the goods
						which the Phaeacians had set on shore together with himself and departed; if indeed, being himself left in such a
						solitude, so ignorant where he was, and having no security there for his own person, he is yet solicitous for his
						goods, lest
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sly Phaeacians, when they stole to sea,
						</l>
                     <l>Had stolen some part of what they brought away;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIII. 216.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>the covetousness of the man deserved in truth to be pitied,
						or rather abhorred. But if, as some say in his defence,
						being doubtful whether or no the place where he was
						landed were Ithaca, he made use of the just tale of his
						goods to infer thence the honesty of the Phaeacians,&mdash;because it was not likely they would expose him in a strange
						place and leave him there with his goods by him untouched,
						so as to get nothing by their dishonesty,&mdash;then he makes
						use of a very fit test for this purpose, and deserves commendation for his wisdom in that action. Some also there
						are who find fault with that passage of the putting him on
						shore when he was asleep, if it really so happened, and
						they tell us that the people of Tuscany have still a traditional story among them concerning Ulysses, that he was
						naturally sleepy, and therefore a man whom many men
						could not freely converse with. But if his sleep was but
						feigned, and he made use of this pretence only of a natural
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.72"/>
						
						infirmity, by counterfeiting a nap, to hide the strait he was
						in at that time in his thoughts, betwixt the shame of sending away the Phaeacians without giving them a friendly
						collation and hospitable gifts, and the fear he had of being
						discovered to his enemies by the treating such a company
						of men together, they then approve it.</p>
            <p>Now, by showing young men these things, we shall preserve them from being carried away to any corruption in
						their manners. and dispose them to the election and imitation of those that are good, as being before instructed
						readily to disapprove those and commend these. But this
						ought with the most care to be done in the reading of
						tragedies wherein probable and subtle speeches are made
						use of in the most foul and wicked actions. For that is
						not always true which Sophocles saith, that
						<quote rend="blockquote">From naughty acts good words can ne'er proceed.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For even he himself is wont to apply pleasant reasonings
						and plausible arguments to those manners and actions
						which are wicked or unbecoming. And in another of
						his fellow-tragedians, we may see even Phaedra herself
						represented as justifying her unlawful affection for Hippolytus by accusing Theseus of ill-carriage towards her. And
						in his Troades, he allows Helen the same liberty of speech
						against Hecuba, whom she judgeth to be more worthy of
						punishment than herself for her adultery, because she was
						the mother of Paris that tempted her thereto. A young
						man therefore must not be accustomed to think any thing
						of that nature handsomely or wittily spoken, nor to be
						pleased with such colorable inventions; but rather more to
						abhor such words as tend to the defence of wanton acts
						than the very acts themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>And lastly, it will be useful likewise to enquire into
					the cause why each thing is said. For so Cato, when he
					was a boy, though he was wont to be very observant of all
					his master's commands, yet withal used to ask the cause
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.73"/>
					
					or reason why he so commanded. But poets are not to be
					obeyed as pedagogues and lawgivers are, except they have
					reason to back what they say. And that they will not
					want, when they speak well; and if they speak ill, what
					they say will appear vain and frivolous. But nowadays
					most young men very briskly demand the reason of such
					trivial speeches as these, and enquire in what sense they
					are spoken:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>It bodes ill luck, when vessels you set up,
					</l>
                     <l>To place the ladle on the mixing-cup.</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Who from his chariot to another's leaps,
						</l>
                     <l>Seldom his seat without a combat keeps.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 744; Il. IV. 306.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But to those of greater moment they give credence without
						examination, as to those that follow:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The boldest men are daunted oftentimes,
						</l>
                     <l>When they're reproached with their parents' crimes:</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 424.</note>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>When any man is crushed by adverse fate,
							</l>
                     <l>His spirit should be low as his estate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet such speeches relate to manners, and disquiet
						men's lives by begetting in them evil opinions and unworthy sentiments, except they have learned to return
						answer to each of them thus: <q direct="unspecified">Wherefore is it necessary
							that a man who is crushed by adverse fate should have a
							dejected spirit? Yea, why rather should he not struggle
							against Fortune, and raise himself above the pressures of
							his low circumstances? Why, if I myself be a good and
							wise son of an evil and foolish father, does it not rather
							become me to bear myself confidently upon the account of
							my own virtue, than to be dejected and dispirited because
							of my father's defects?</q> For he that can encounter such
						speeches and oppose them after this manner, not yielding
						himself up to be overset with the blast of every saying,
						but approving that speech of Heraclitus, that
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.74"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whate'er is said, though void of sense and wit,
						</l>
                     <l>The size of a fool's intellect doth fit,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>will reject many such things as falsely and idly spoken.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>These things therefore may be of use to preserve
					us from the hurt we might get by the study of poems.
					Now, as on a vine the fruit oftentimes lies shadowed and
					hidden under its large leaves and luxuriant branches, so
					in the poet's phrases and fictions that encompass them
					there are also many profitable and useful things concealed
					from the view of young men. This, however, ought not to
					be suffered; nor should we be led away from things themselves thus, but rather adhere to such of them as tend to
					the promoting of virtue and the well forming of our manners. It will not be altogether useless therefore, to treat
					briefly in the next place of passages of that nature.
					Wherein I intend to touch only at some particulars, leaving all longer discourses, and the brimming up and furnishing them with a multitude of instances, to those who write
					more for show and ostentation.</p>
            <p>First, therefore, let our young man be taught to understand good and bad manners and persons, and from thence
						apply his mind to the words and deeds which the poet
						decently assigns to either of them. For example, Achilles,
						though in some wrath, speaks to Agamemnon thus decently:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor, when we take a Trojan town, can I
						</l>
                     <l>With thee in spoils and splendid prizes vie;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For this and the five following quotations, see Il. I. 163; II. 226; I. 128; II
							231; IV. 402 and 404.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>whereas Thersites to the same person speaks reproachfully
						in this manner:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis thine whate'er the warrior's breast inflames,
						</l>
                     <l>The golden spoil, and thine the lovely dances.
						</l>
                     <l>With all the wealth our wars and blood bestow,
						</l>
                     <l>Thy tents are crowded and thy chests o'erflow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.75"/>
            <p>Again, Achilles thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whene'er, by Jove's decree, our conquering powers
						</l>
                     <l>Shall humble to the dust Troy's lofty towers;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but Thersites thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">Whom I or some Greek else as captive bring.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Diomedes, when Agamemnon taking a view of the
						army spoke reproachfully to him,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To his hard words forbore to make reply,
						</l>
                     <l>For the respect he bare to majesty;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>whereas Sthenelus, a man of small note, replies on him
						thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sir, when you know the truth, what need to lie?
						</l>
                     <l>For with our fathers we for valor vie.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now the observation of such difference will teach the
						young man the decency of a modest and moderate temper,
						and the unbecoming nauseousness of the contrary vices of
						boasting and cracking of a man's own worth. And it is
						worth while also to take notice of the demeanor of Agamemnon in the same passage. For he passeth by Sthenelus unspoken to; but perceiving Ulysses to be offended,
						he neglects not him, but applies himself to answer him:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">Struck with his generous wrath, the king replies.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IV. 357. For the four following, see Il. IX. 34 and 70; IV. 431; X. 325.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For to have apologized to every one had been too servile
						and misbecoming the dignity of his person; whereas
						equally to have neglected every one had been an act of
						insolence and imprudence. And very handsome it is that
						Diomedes, though in the heat of the battle he answers the
						king only with silence, yet after the battle was over useth
						more liberty towards him, speaking thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">You called me coward, sir, before the Greeks.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is expedient also to take notice of the different carriage
						of a wise man and of a soothsayer popularly courting the
						multitude. For Chalcas very unseasonably makes no scruple
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.76"/>
						
						 to traduce the king before the people, as having been
						the cause of the pestilence that was befallen them. But
						Nestor, intending to bring in a discourse concerning the
						reconciling Achilles to him, that he might not seem to
						charge Agamemnon before the multitude with the miscarriage his passion had occasioned, only adviseth him
						thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But thou, O king, to council call the old....
						</l>
                     <l>Wise weighty counsels aid a state distress'd,
						</l>
                     <l>And such a monarch as can choose the best;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>which done, accordingly after supper he sends his ambassadors. Now this speech of Nestor tended to the rectifying
						of what he had before done amiss; but that of Chalcas,
						only to accuse and disparage him.</p>
            <p>There is likewise consideration to be had of the different
						manners of nations, such as these. The Trojans enter into
						battle with loud outcries and great fierceness; but in the
						army of the Greeks,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sedate and silent move the numerous bands;
						</l>
                     <l>No sound, no whisper, but the chief's commands;
						</l>
                     <l>Those only heard, with awe the rest obey.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For when soldiers are about to engage an enemy, the awe
						they stand in of their officers is an argument both of courage and obedience. For which purpose Plato teacheth us
						that we ought to inure ourselves to fear blame and disgrace
						more than labor and danger. And Cato was wont to say
						that he liked men that were apt to blush better than those
						that looked pale.</p>
            <p>Moreover, there is a particular character to be noted of
						the men who undertake for any action. For Dolon thus
						promiseth:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'll pass through all their lost in a disguise
						</l>
                     <l>To their flag-ship, where she at anchor lies.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But Diomedes promiseth nothing, but only tells them he
						shall fear the less if they send a companion with him;
						whereby is intimated, that discreet foresight is Grecian and
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.77"/>
						
						civil, but rash confidence is barbarous and evil; and the
						former is therefore to be imitated, and the latter to be
						avoided.</p>
            <p>It is a matter too of no unprofitable consideration, how
						the minds of the Trojans and of Hector too were affected
						when he and Ajax were about to engage in a single combat.
						For Aeschylus, when, upon one of the fighters at fisticuffs
						in the Isthmian games receiving a blow on the face, there
						was made a great outcry among the people, said: <q direct="unspecified">What a
							thing is practice! See how the lookers-on only cry out,
							but the man that received the stroke is silent.</q> But when
						the poet tells us, that the Greeks rejoiced when they saw
						Ajax in his glistering armor, but
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Trojans' knees for very fear did quake,
						</l>
                     <l>And even Hector's heart began to ache;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 215. For the three following, see Il. II. 220; VII. 226 and 231.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>who is there that wonders not at this difference,&mdash;when
						the heart of him that was to run the risk of the combat
						only beats inwardly, as if he were to undertake a mere
						wrestling or running match, but the very bodies of the
						spectators tremble and shake, out of the kindness and fear
						which they had for their king?</p>
            <p>In the same poet also we may observe the difference
						betwixt the humor of a coward and a valiant man. For
						Thersites
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Against Achilles a great malice had,
						</l>
                     <l>And wise Ulysses he did hate as bad;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but Ajax is always represented as friendly to Achilles; and
						particularly he speaks thus to Hector concerning him:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hector! approach my arm, and singly know
						</l>
                     <l>What strength thou last, and what the Grecian foe.
						</l>
                     <l>Achilles shuns the fight; yet some there are
						</l>
                     <l>Not void of soul, and not unskill'd in war:</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>wherein he insinuates the high commendation of that valiant man. And in what follows, he speaks like handsome
						things of his fellow-soldiers in general, thus:&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.78"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whole troops of heroes Greece has yet to boast,
						</l>
                     <l>And sends thee one, a sample of her host;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>wherein he doth not boast himself to be the only or the
						best champion, but one of those, among many others, who
						were fit to undertake that combat.</p>
            <p>What hath been said is sufficient upon the point of dissimilitudes; except we think fit to add this, that many of
						the Trojans came into the enemy's power alive, but none
						of the Grecians; and that many of the Trojans supplicated
						to their enemies,&mdash;as (for instance) Adrastus, the sons of
						Antimachus, Lycaon,&mdash;and even Hector himself entreats
						Achilles for a sepulture; but not one of these doth so, as
						judging it barbarous to supplicate to a foe in the field, and
						more Greek-like either to conquer or die.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But as, in the same plant, the bee feeds on the flower,
					the goat on the bud, the hog on the root, and other living
					creatures on the seed and the fruit; so in reading of poems,
					one man singleth out the historical part, another dwells
					upon the elegancy and fit disposal of words, as Aristophanes
					says of Euripides,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>His gallant language runs so smooth and round,
					</l>
                     <l>That I am ravisht with th' harmonious sound;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristophanes, Frag. 397.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but others, to whom this part of my discourse is directed,
						mind only such things as are useful to the bettering of
						manners. And such we are to put in mind that it is an
						absurd thing, that those who delight in fables should not
						let any thing slip them of the vain and extravagant stories
						they find in poets, and that those who affect language should
						pass by nothing that is elegantly and floridly expressed;
						and that only the lovers of honor and virtue, who apply
						themselves to the study of poems not for delight but for
						instruction's sake, should slightly and negligently observe
						what is spoken in them relating to valor, temperance, or
						justice. Of this nature is the following:&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.79"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And stand we deedless, O eternal shame!
						</l>
                     <l>Till Hector's arm involve the ships in flame?
						</l>
                     <l>Haste, let us join, and combat side by side.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 313. For the four following, see Odyss. III. 52; Il. XXIV. 560 and 584; Odyss. XVI. 274</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For to see a man of the greatest wisdom in danger of being
						totally cut off with all those that take part with him, and
						yet affected less with fear of death than of shame and dishonor, must needs excite in a young man a passionate
						affection for virtue. And this,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Joyed was the Goddess, for she much did prize
						</l>
                     <l>A man that was alike both just and wise,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>teacheth us to infer that the Deity delights not in a rich or
						a proper or a strong man, but in one that is furnished with
						wisdom and justice. Again, when the same Goddess (Minerva) saith that the reason why she did not desert or neglect Ulysses was that he was
						<quote rend="blockquote">Gentle, of ready wit, of prudent mind,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>she therein tells us that, of all things pertaining to us,
						nothing is dear to the Gods and divine but our virtue, seeing like naturally delights in like.</p>
            <p>And seeing, moreover, that it both seemeth and really is
						a great thing to be able to moderate a man's anger, but a
						greater by far to guard a man's self beforehand by prudence, that he fall not into it nor be surprised by it, therefore also such passages as tend that way are not slightly to
						be represented to the readers; for example, that Achilles
						himself&mdash;who was a man of no great forbearance, nor inclined to such meekness&mdash;yet warns Priam to be calm and
						not to provoke him, thus,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Move me no more (Achilles thus replies,
						</l>
                     <l>While kindling anger sparkled in his eyes),
						</l>
                     <l>Nor seek by tears my steady soul to bend:
						</l>
                     <l>To yield thy Hector I myself intend:
						</l>
                     <l>Cease; lest, neglectful of high Jove's command,
						</l>
                     <l>I show thee, king, thou tread'st on hostile land;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.80"/>
            <p>and that he himself first washeth and decently covereth the
						body of Hector and then puts it into a chariot, to prevent
						his father's seeing it so unworthily mangled as it was,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lest the unhappy sire,
						</l>
                     <l>Provoked to passion, once more rouse to ire
						</l>
                     <l>The stern Pelides; and nor sacred age,
						</l>
                     <l>Nor Jove's command, should check the rising rage.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For it is a piece of admirable prudence for a man so prone
						to anger, as being by nature hasty and furious, to understand himself so well as to set a guard upon his own
						inclinations, and by avoiding provocations to keep his passion at due distance by the use of reason, lest he should
						be unawares surprised by it. And after the same manner
						must the man that is apt to be drunken forearm himself
						against that vice; and he that is given to wantonness,
						against lust, as Agesilaus refused to receive a kiss from
						a beautiful person addressing to him, and Cyrus would not
						so much as endure to see Panthea. Whereas, on the contrary, those that are not virtuously bred are wont to gather
						fuel to inflame their passions, and voluntarily to abandon
						themselves to those temptations to which of themselves they
						are endangered. But Ulysses does not only restrain his own
						anger, but (perceiving by the discourse of his son Telemachus, that through indignation conceived against such evil
						men he was greatly provoked) he blunts his passion too
						beforehand, and composeth him to calmness and patience, thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There, if base scorn insult my reverend age,
						</l>
                     <l>Bear it, my son! repress thy rising rage.
						</l>
                     <l>If outraged, cease that outrage to repel;
						</l>
                     <l>Bear it, my son! howe'er thy heart rebel.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For as men are not wont to put bridles on their horses
						when they are running in full speed, but bring them bridled
						beforehand to the race; so do they use to preoccupy and
						predispose the minds of those persons with rational considerations to enable them to encounter passion, whom they
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.81"/>
						
						perceive to be too mettlesome and unmanageable upon the
						sight of provoking objects.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the young man is not altogether to neglect
						names themselves when he meets with them; though he is
						not obliged to give much heed to such idle descants as those
						of Cleanthes, who, while he professeth himself an interpreter, plays the trifler, as in these passages of Homer:
						<foreign lang="greek">*zeu= pa/ter )/*idhqen mede/wn</foreign>, and <foreign lang="greek">*zeu= a)/na *dwdwnai=e</foreign>.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. III. 320; XVI. 233.</note> For he will needs
						read the last two of these words joined into one, and make
						them <foreign lang="greek">a)nadwdwnai=e</foreign>; for that the air evaporated from the earth
						by exhalation (<foreign lang="greek">a)na/dosis</foreign>) is so called. Yea, and Chrysippus too, though he does not so trifle, yet is very jejune,
						while he hunts after improbable etymologies. As when
						he will need force the words <foreign lang="greek">eu)ru/opa *kroni/dhn</foreign> to import Jupiter's excellent faculty in speaking and powerfulness to
						persuade thereby.</p>
            <p>But such things as these are fitter to be left to the examination of grammarians; and we are rather to insist upon
						such passages as are both profitable and persuasive. Such,
						for instance, as these:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>My early youth was bred to martial pains,
						</l>
                     <l>My soul impels me to the embattled plains!</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>How skill'd he was in each obliging art;
							</l>
                     <l>The mildest manners, and the gentlest heart.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VI. 444; XVII. 671.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For while the author tells us that fortitude may be taught,
						and that an obliging and graceful way of conversing with
						others is to be gotten by art and the use of reason, he exhorts us not to neglect the improvement of ourselves, but
						by observing our teachers' instructions to learn a becoming carriage, as knowing that clownishness and cowardice
						argue ill-breeding and ignorance. And very suitable to
						what hath been said is that which is said of Jupiter and
						Neptune:&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.82"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gods of one source, of one ethereal race,
						</l>
                     <l>Alike divine, and heaven their native place;
						</l>
                     <l>But Jove the greater; first born of the skies,
						</l>
                     <l>And more than men or Gods supremely wise.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIII. 354.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the poet therein pronounceth wisdom to be the most
						divine and royal quality of all; as placing therein the
						greatest excellency of Jupiter himself, and judging all
						virtues else to be necessarily consequent thereunto. We
						are also to accustom a young man attentively to hear such
						things as these:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Urge him with truth to frame his fair replies:
						</l>
                     <l>And sure he will, for wisdom never lies:</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>The praise of wisdom, in thy youth obtain'd,
							</l>
                     <l>An act so rash, Antilochus, has stain'd:</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Say, is it just, my friend, that Hector's ear
							</l>
                     <l>From such a warrior such a speech should hear?
							</l>
                     <l>I deemed thee once the wisest of thy kind,
							</l>
                     <l>But ill this insult suits a prudent mind.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. III. 20; Il. XXIII. 570; XVII. 170.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These speeches teach us that it is beneath wise men to lie
						or to deal otherwise than fairly, even in games, or to blame
						other men without just cause. And when the poet attributes Pindarus's violation of the truce to his folly, he
						withal declares his judgment that a wise man will not be
						guilty of an unjust action. The like may we also infer
						concerning continence, taking our ground for it from these
						passages:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For him Antaea burn'd with lawless flame,
						</l>
                     <l>And strove to tempt him from the paths of fame:
						</l>
                     <l>In vain she tempted the relentless youth,
						</l>
                     <l>Endued with wisdom, sacred fear, and truth:</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>At first, with worthy shame and decent pride,
							</l>
                     <l>The royal dame his lawless suit denied !
							</l>
                     <l>For virtue's image yet possessed her mind:</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VI. 160; Odyss. III. 265.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>in which speeches the poet assigns wisdom to be the cause
						of continence. And when in exhortations made to encourage soldiers to fight, he speaks in this manner:&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.83"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What mean you, Lycians? Stand! O stand, for shame !</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Yet each reflect who prizes fame or breath,
							</l>
                     <l>On endless infamy, on instant death;
							</l>
                     <l>For, lo ! the fated time, the appointed shore;
							</l>
                     <l>Hark ! the gates burst, the brazen barriers roar !</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 422; XIII. 121.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he seems to intimate that continent men are valiant men;
						because they fear the shame of base actions, and can
						trample on pleasures and stand their ground in the greatest hazards. Whence Timotheus, in the play called Persae,
						takes occasion handsomely to exhort the Grecians thus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Brave soldiers of just shame in awe should stand;
						</l>
                     <l>For the blushing face oft helps the fighting hand.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Aeschylus also makes it a point of wisdom not to be
						blown up with pride when a man is honored, nor to be
						moved or elevated with the acclamations of a multitude,
						writing thus of Amphiaraus:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>His shield no emblem bears; his generous soul
						</l>
                     <l>Wishes to be, not to appear, the best;
						</l>
                     <l>While the deep furrows of his noble mind
						</l>
                     <l>Harvests of wise and prudent counsel bear.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note on the same passage of Aeschylus (Sept. 591), vol. I. p. 210. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For it is the part of a wise man to value himself upon the
						consciousness of his own true worth and excellency.
						Whereas, therefore, all inward perfections are reducible
						to wisdom, it appears that all sorts of virtue and learning
						are included in it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Again, boys may be instructed, by reading the poets
					as they ought, to draw something that is useful and profitable even from those passages that are most suspected as
					wicked and absurd; as the bee is taught by Nature to
					gather the sweetest and most pleasant honey from the
					harshest flowers and sharpest thorns. It does indeed at
					the first blush cast a shrewd suspicion on Agamemnon of
					taking a bribe, when Homer tells us that he discharged
					that rich man from the wars who presented him with his
					fleet mare Aethe:&mdash;
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.84"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whom rich Echepolus, more rich than brave,
					</l>
                     <l>To 'scape the wars, to Agamemnon gave
					</l>
                     <l>(Aethe her name), at home to end his days;
					</l>
                     <l>Base wealth preferring to eternal praise.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXIII. 297.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, as saith Aristotle, it was well done of him to prefer a
						good beast before such a man. For, the truth is, a dog or
						ass is of more value than a timorous and cowardly man
						that wallows in wealth and luxury. Again, Thetis seems
						to do indecently, when she exhorts her son to follow his
						pleasures and minds him of companying with women. But
						even here, on the other side, the continency of Achilles is
						worthy to be considered; who, though he dearly loved
						Briseis&mdash;newly returned to him too,&mdash;yet, when he
						knew his life to be near its end, does not hasten to the
						fruition of pleasures, nor, when he mourns for his friend
						Patroclus, does he (as most men are wont) shut himself up
						from all business and neglect his duty, but only bars himself from recreations for his sorrow's sake, while yet he
						gives himself up to action and military employments.
						And Archilochus is not praiseworthy either, who, in the
						midst of his mourning for his sister's husband drowned
						in the sea, contrives to dispel his grief by drinking and
						merriment. And yet he gives this plausible reason to
						justify that practice of his,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To drink and dance, rather than mourn, I choose;
						</l>
                     <l>Nor wrong I him, whom mourning can't reduce.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For, if he judged himself to do nothing amiss when he
						followed sports and banquets, sure, we shall not do worse,
						if in whatever circumstances we follow the study of philosophy, or manage public affairs, or go to the market or
						to the Academy, or follow our husbandry. Wherefore
						those corrections also are not to be rejected which
						Cleanthes and Antisthenes have made use of. For Antisthenes, seeing the Athenians all in a tumult in the theatre, and justly, upon the pronunciation of this verse,&mdash;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.85"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">Except what men think base, there's nothing ill,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Aeolus of Euripides, Frag. 19.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>presently subjoined this corrective,
						<quote rend="blockquote">What's base is base,&mdash;believe men what they will.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Cleanthes, hearing this passage concerning wealth:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great is th' advantage that great wealth attends,
						</l>
                     <l>For oft with it we purchase health and friends;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Electra, 428.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>presently altered it thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great disadvantage oft attends on wealth;
						</l>
                     <l>We purchase whores with't and destroy our health.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Zeno corrected that of Sophocles,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The man that in a tyrant's palace dwells
						</l>
                     <l>His liberty for's entertainment sells,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>after this manner:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No: if he came in free, he cannot lose
						</l>
                     <l>His liberty, though in a tyrant's house;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>meaning by a free man one that is undaunted and magnanimous, and one of a spirit too great to stoop beneath
						itself. And why may not we also, by some such acclamations as those, call off young men to the better side, by
						using some things spoken by poets after the same manner?
						For example, it is said,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis all that in this life one can require,
						</l>
                     <l>To hit the mark he aims at in desire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>To which we may reply thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis false; except one level his desire
						</l>
                     <l>At what's expedient, and no more require.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For it is an unhappy thing and not to be wished, for a
						man to obtain and be master of what he desires if it be
						inexpedient. Again this saying,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, Agamemnon, must thyself prepare
						</l>
                     <l>Of joy and grief by turns to take thy share:
						</l>
                     <l>Thy father, Atreus, sure, ne'er thee begat,
						</l>
                     <l>To be an unchanged favorite of Fate:</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Iphig. Aul. 29.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.86"/>
            <p>we may thus invert:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy father, Atreus, never thee begat,
						</l>
                     <l>To be an unchanged favorite of Fate:
						</l>
                     <l>Therefore, if moderate thy fortunes are,
						</l>
                     <l>Thou shouldst rejoice always, and grief forbear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Again it is said,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Alas! this ill comes from the powers divine,
						</l>
                     <l>That oft we see what's good, yet it decline.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Chrysippus of Euripides, Frag. 838.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, rather, say we, it is a brutish and irrational and
						wretched fault of ours, that when we understand better
						things, we are carried away to the pursuit of those which
						are worse, through our intemperance and effeminacy.
						Again, one says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">'Tis not the teacher's speech but practice moves.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Menander.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, rather, say we, both the speech and practice,&mdash;or
						the practice by the means of speech,&mdash;as the horse is
						managed with the bridle, and the ship with the helm.
						For virtue hath no instrument so suitable and agreeable to
						human nature to work on men withal, as that of rational
						discourse. Again, we meet with this character of some
						person:
						<quote rend="blockquote">A. Is he more prone to male or female loves ?
							B. He's flexible both ways, where beauty moves.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>But it had been better said thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">He's flexible to both, where virtue moves.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For it is no commendation of a man's dexterity to be
						tossed up and down as pleasure and beauty move him,
						but an argument rather of a weak and unstable disposition. Once more, this speech,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>religion damps the courage of our minds,
						</l>
                     <l>And ev'n wise men to cowardice inclines,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>is by no means to be allowed; but rather the contrary,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Religion truly fortifies men's minds,
						</l>
                     <l>And a wise man to valiant acts inclines,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.87"/>
            <p>and gives not occasion of fear to any but weak and foolish
						persons and such as are ungrateful to the Deity, who are
						apt to look on that divine power and principle which is
						the cause of all good with suspicion and jealousy, as being
						hurtful unto them. And so much for that which I call
						correction of poets' sayings.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>There is yet another way of improving poems,
					taught us well by Chrysippus; which is, by accommodation of any saying, to transfer that which is useful and
					serviceable in it to divers things of the same kind. For
					whereas Hesiod saith,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If but a cow be lost, the common fame
					</l>
                     <l>Upon the next ill neighbor lays the blame;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 348.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>the same may be applied to a man's dog or ass or any
						other beast of his which is liable to the like mischance.
						Again, Euripides saith,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>How can that man be called a slave, who slights
						</l>
                     <l>Ev'n death itself, which servile spirits frights?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>the like whereof may be said of hard labor or painful
						sickness. For as physicians, finding by experience the
						force of any medicine in the cure of some one disease,
						make use of it by accommodation, proportionably to every
						other disease of affinity thereto, so are we to deal with
						such speeches as are of a common import and apt to communicate their value to other things; we must not confine
						them to that one thing only to which they were at first
						adapted, but transfer them to all other of like nature, and
						accustom young men by many parallel instances to see
						the communicableness of them, and exercise the promptness of their wits in such applications. So that when
						Meander says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Happy is he who wealth and wisdom hath,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>they may be able to judge that the same is fitly applicable
						to glory and authority and eloquence also. And the reproof
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.88"/>
						
						 which Ulysses gives Achilles, when he found him
						sitting in Scyrus in the apartment of the young ladies,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, who from noblest Greeks deriv'st thy race,
						</l>
                     <l>Dost thou with spinning wool thy birth disgrace?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>may be as well given to the prodigal, to him that undertakes any dishonest way of living, yea, to the slothful and
						unlearned person, thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, who from noblest Greeks deriv'st thy race,
						</l>
                     <l>Dost thou with fuddling thy great birth disgrace ?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>or dost thou spend thy time in dicing, or quail-striking,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The word here used (<foreign lang="greek">o)rtugokopei=n</foreign>) denotes a game among
						the Grecians, which Suidas describes to be the setting of quails in a
						round compass or ring, and striking at the heads of them; and he that
						in the ring struck down one had liberty to strike at the rest in
						order, but he that missed was obliged to set up quails for others;
						and this they did by turns.</note> or
						deal in adulterate wares or griping usury, not minding any
						thing that is great and worthy thy noble extraction? So
						when they read,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For Wealth, the God most serve, I little care,
						</l>
                     <l>Since the worst men his favors often wear,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Aeolus of Euripides, Frag. 20.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they may be able to infer, therefore, as little regard is to be
						had to glory and bodily beauty and princely robes and
						priestly garlands, all which also we see to be the enjoyments of very bad men. Again, when they read this passage,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A coward father propagates his vice,
						</l>
                     <l>And gets a son heir to his cowardice,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they may in truth apply the same to intemperance, to
						superstition, to envy, and all other diseases of men's minds.
						Again, whereas it is handsomely said of Homer,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Unhappy Paris, fairest to behold !</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
						<quote rend="blockquote">Hector, of noble form,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. III. 39; XVII. 142.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for herein he shows that a man who hath no greater excellency than that of beauty to commend him deserves to
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.89"/>
						
						have it mentioned with contempt and ignominy,&mdash;such expressions we should make use of in like cases to repress the
						insolence of such as bear themselves high upon the account of such things as are of no real value, and to teach
						young men to look upon such compellations as <q direct="unspecified">O thou
							richest of men,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">O thou that excellest in feasting, in
								multitudes of attendants, in herds of cattle, yea, and in
								eloquent speaking itself,</q> to be (as they are indeed) expressions that import reproach and infamy. For, in truth, a
						man that designs to excel ought to endeavor it in those
						things that are in themselves most excellent, and to become
						chief in the chiefest, and great in the greatest things.
						Whereas glory that ariseth from things in themselves small
						and inconsiderable is inglorious and contemptible. To
						mind us whereof we shall never be at a loss for instances,
						if, in reading Homer especially, we observe how he applieth the expressions that import praise or disgrace;
						wherein we have clear proof that he makes small account
						of the good things either of the body or Fortune. And
						first of all, in meetings and salutations, men do not call
						others fair or rich or strong, but use such terms of commendation as these:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Son of Laertes, from great Jove deriving
						</l>
                     <l>Thy pedigree, and skilled in wise contriving;</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Hector, thou son of Priam, whose advice
							</l>
                     <l>With wisest Jove's men count of equal price;</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Achilles, son of' Peleus, whom all story
							</l>
                     <l>Shall mention as the Grecians' greatest glory;</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Divine Patroclus, for thy worth thou art,
							</l>
                     <l>Of all the friends I have, lodged next my heart.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. II. 173; VII. 47; XIX. 216; XI. 608.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And moreover, when they speak disgracefully of any person, they touch not at bodily defects, but direct all their reproaches to vicious actions; as for instance:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A dogged-looking, drunken beast thou art,
						</l>
                     <l>And in thy bosom hast a deer's faint heart;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.90"/>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ajax, at brawling valiant still,
					</l>
                     <l>Whose tongue is used to speaking ill;</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>A tongue so loose hung, and so vain withal,
						</l>
                     <l>Idomeneus, becomes thee not at all;</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Ajax, thy tongue doth oft offend;
						</l>
                     <l>For of thy boasting there's no end.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 225; XXIII. 483 and 474-479; XIII. 824.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, when Ulysses reproacheth Thersites, he objecteth
						not to him his lameness nor his baldness nor his hunched
						back, but the vicious quality of indiscreet babbling. On
						the other side, when Juno means to express a dalliance or
						motherly fondness to her son Vulcan, she courts him with
						an epithet taken from his halting, thus,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Rouse thee, my limping son!<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXI. 331.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In this instance, Homer does (as it were) deride those
						who are ashamed of their lameness or blindness, as not
						thinking any thing a disgrace that is not in itself disgraceful, nor any person liable to a reproach for that which is
						not imputable to himself but to Fortune. These two great
						advantages may be made by those who frequently study
						poets;&mdash;the learning moderation, to keep them from unseasonable and foolish reproaching others with their misfortunes, when they themselves enjoy a constant current of
						prosperity; and magnanimity, that under variety of accidents they be not dejected nor disturbed, but meekly bear
						the being scoffed at, reproached, and drolled upon. Especially, let them have that saying of Philemon ready at
						hand in such cases:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>That spirit's well in tune, whose sweet repose
						</l>
                     <l>No railer's tongue can ever discompose.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, if one that so rails do himself deserve reprehension, thou mayst take occasion to retort upon him his
						own vices and inordinate passions; as when 'Adrastus in
						the tragedy is assaulted thus by Alcmaeon,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Thy sister's one that did her husband kill,</quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.91"/>
            <p>he returns him this answer,
						<quote rend="blockquote">But thou thyself thy mother's blood did spill.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For as they who scourge a man's garments do not touch
						the body, so those that turn other men's evil fortunes or
						mean births to matter of reproach do only with vanity and
						folly enough lash their external circumstances, but touch
						not their internal part, the soul, nor those things which
						truly need correction and reproof.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Moreover, as we have above taught you to abate and
					lessen the credit of evil and hurtful poems by setting in
					opposition to them the famous speeches and sentences of
					such worthy men as have managed public affairs, so will it
					be useful to us, where we find any things in them of civil
					and profitable import, to improve and strengthen them by
					testimonies and proofs taken from philosophers, withal giving these the credit of being the first inventors of them.
					For this is both just and profitable to be done, seeing by
					this means such sayings receive an additional strength and
					esteem, when it appears that what is spoken on the stage
					or sung to the harp or occurs in a scholar's lesson is
					agreeable to the doctrines of Pythagoras and Plato, and
					that the sentences of Chilo and Bias tend to the same issue
					with those that are found in the authors which children
					read. Therefore must we industriously show them that
					these poetical sentences,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not these, O daughter, are thy proper cares,
					</l>
                     <l>Thee milder arts befit, and softer wars;
					</l>
                     <l>Sweet smiles are thine, and kind endearing charms;
					</l>
                     <l>To Mars and Pallas leave the deeds of arms;</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Jove's angry with thee, when thy unmanaged rage
						</l>
                     <l>With those that overmatch thee doth engage;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. V. 428; XI. 513.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>differ not in substance but bear plainly the same sense
						with that philosophical sentence, Know thyself. And
						these,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.92"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fools, who by wrong seek to augment their store,
						</l>
                     <l>And know not how much half than all is more;</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Of counsel giv'n to mischievous intents,
							</l>
                     <l>The man that gives it most of all repents;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 40 and 266.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>are of near kin to what we find in the determination of
						Plato, in his books entitled Gorgias and Concerning the
						Commonwealth, to wit, that it is worse to do than to
						suffer injury, and that a man more endamageth himself
						when he hurts another, than he would be damnified if he
						were the sufferer. And that of Aeschylus,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Cheer up, friend; sorrows, when they highest climb,
						</l>
                     <l>What they exceed in measure want in time,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>we must inform them, is but the same famous sentence
						which is so much admired in Epicurus, that great griefs
						are but short, and those that are of long continuance are
						but small. The former clause whereof is that which Aeschylus here saith expressly, and the latter but the consequent of that. For if a great and intense sorrow do not
						last, then that which doth last is not great nor hard to be
						borne. And those words of Thespis,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Seest not how Jove,&mdash;because he cannot lie
						</l>
                     <l>Nor vaunt nor laugh at impious drollery,
						</l>
                     <l>And pleasure's charms are things to him unknown,&mdash;
						</l>
                     <l>Among the Gods wears the imperial crown?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>wherein differ they from what Plato says, that the divine
						nature is seated far from both joy and grief? And that
						saying of Bacchylides,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Virtue alone doth lasting honor gain,
						</l>
                     <l>But men of wretched souls oft wealth attain;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and those of Euripides much of the same import,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hence temperance in my esteem excels,
						</l>
                     <l>Because it constantly with good men dwells;</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>How much soe'er to honor thou aspire,
							</l>
                     <l>And strive by riches virtue to acquire,
							</l>
                     <l>Still shall thy lot to good men wretched seem;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.93"/>
            <p>do they not evidently confirm to us what the philosophers
						say of riches and other external good things, that without
						virtue they are fruitless and unprofitable enjoyments?</p>
            <p>Now thus to accommodate and reconcile poetry to the
						doctrines of philosophy strips it of its fabulous and personated parts, and makes those things which it delivers
						usefully to acquire also the reputation of gravity; and over
						and above, it inclines the soul of a young man to receive the
						impressions of philosophical precepts. For he will hereby
						be enabled to come to them not altogether destitute of some
						sort of relish of them, not as to things that he has heard
						nothing of before, nor with an head confusedly full of the
						false notions which he hath sucked in from the daily tattle
						of his mother and nurse,&mdash;yea, sometimes too of his
						father and pedant,&mdash;who have been wont to speak of rich
						men as the happy men and mention them always with
						honor, and to express themselves concerning death and
						pain with horror, and to look on virtue without riches
						and glory as a thing of nought and not to be desired.
						Whence it comes to pass, that when such youths first do
						hear things of a quite contrary nature from philosophers,
						they are surprised with a kind of amazement, trouble, and
						stupid astonishment, which makes them afraid to entertain
						or endure them, except they be dealt with as those who
						come out of very great darkness into the light of the bright
						sun, that is, be first accustomed for a while to behold those
						doctrines in fabulous authors, as in a kind of false light, which
						hath but a moderate brightness and is easy to be looked on
						and borne without disturbance to the weak sight. For
						having before heard or read from poets such things as
						these are,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mourn at one's birth, as th' inlet t' all that grieves;
						</l>
                     <l>But joy at death, as that which man relieves;</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Of worldly things a mortal needs but twain;
							</l>
                     <l>The spring supplies his drink, the earth his grain:</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.94"/>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O tyranny, to barbarous nations dear!</l>
                  </lg>
						            <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>This in all human happiness is chief,
						</l>
                     <l>To know as little as we can of grief;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The first two quotations are from Euripides (the first from his Cresphontes); the other two are from unknown tragic poets. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they are the less disturbed and offended when they hear
						from philosophers that no man ought to be much concerned
						about death; that the riches of nature are defined and
						limited; that the happiness of man's life doth not consist in
						the abundance of wealth or vastness of employments or
						height of authority and power, but in freedom from sorrow,
						in moderation of passions, and in such a temper of mind as
						measures all things by the use of Nature.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, upon all these accounts, as well as for all
						the reasons before mentioned, youth stands in need of good
						government to manage it in the reading of poetry, that being
						free from all prejudicate opinions, and rather instructed
						beforehand in conformity thereunto, it may with more calmness, friendliness, and familiarity pass from thence to the
						study of philosophy.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>