<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De defectu oraculorum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.092">
      <body>
         <head>Why the oracles cease to give answers.
				<lb/> Lamprias, Cleombrotus, Didymus, Philippus, Demetrius,
				Ammonius, Heracleon.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.3"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>THERE is an old story, friend Terentius Priscus, that
				heretofore eagles or swans, flying from the opposite bounds
				of the earth, met together where now stands the temple of
				Apollo Pythius, in the place now called the Navel; and
				that some while after, Epimenides the Phaestian, willing to
				satisfy his curiosity, enquired of the oracle of Apollo with
				regard to this story, but received such an answer as made
				him never a jot the wiser; upon which he said:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No navel is there of the earth or sea:
				</l>
                     <l>'Tis known to Gods alone, if one there be.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus fitly did the God chastise this bold enquirer into ancient traditions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But in our time, not long before the celebration of
				the Pythian games during the magistracy of Callistratus,
				there were two holy men who, coming as it were from
				the two opposite ends of the world, met together at the
				city of Delphi. The one was Demetrius the grammarian,
				who came from England to return to Tarsus in Cilicia,
				where he was born; the other, Cleombrotus the Lacedaemonian, who had been long conversant in Egypt and the
				Troglodytic country, and had made several voyages, as well
				on the Red Sea as other parts,&mdash;not as a merchant, to get
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.4"/>
				
				money, but to improve his knowledge and enrich his mind;
				for he had enough to live upon, and cared for no more
				And he was collecting history, as the material for philosophy, the end whereof (as he called it) is theology. He,
				having been lately at the temple and oracle of Jupiter Ammon, seemed not much to marvel at any thing he there saw;
				yet he mentioned to us one particular (which he said was
				told him by the priest of the temple) touching the lamp
				that is never extinguished and spendeth less every year
				than the former. Whence they conjectured an inequality
				of years, whereby each year was shorter than the preceding.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>This discourse was much wondered at by the company, and Demetrius amongst the rest affirmed it unreasonable to ground the knowledge of such great matters on
				such slight and trivial conjectures; for this was not (as
				Alcacus said) to paint the lion from the measure of his
				claw,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">'*ec o)/nuxos to\n le/onta</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">ex ungue leonem.</hi>
               </note> but to change and disorder the motions of celestial
				bodies for the sake of a lamp or the snuff of a candle, and
				to overthrow at one stroke all the mathematical sciences.
				These men, replied Cleombrotus, will not be moved by
				what you say; for first, they will not yield to mathematicians in point of certainty, seeing they may be more easily
				mistaken in their comprehension of time, it being so
				slippery in its motions and with such distant periods, than
				these men in the measures of their oil, about which they
				are so exact and careful because of the strangeness of the
				thing. Moreover, Demetrius, by denying that small things
				are oft the signs and indications of great, must prejudice
				several arts and sciences, and deprive them of the proofs
				of several conclusions and predictions. And yet you
				grammarians will needs vouch that the Demi-gods and
				princes at the Trojan war shaved with razors, because you
				find in Homer the mention of such an instrument; that
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.5"/>
				
				also usury was then in fashion, because he says in one
				place,
				<quote rend="blockquote">A debt is due me neither new nor small,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <foreign lang="greek">)/*enqa xrei=o/s moi o)fe/lletai, ou)/ ti ne/on ge ou)d' o)li/gon</foreign>. Od. III. 367. The same
					interpretation is found in the Scholia on the Odyssey (G.)</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>where you interpret <foreign lang="greek">o)fe/lletai</foreign> to mean <hi rend="italics">increases.</hi> And
					again, when he calls the night quick and sharp, you will
					needs have him to mean by this word, that the shadow of
					the earth being round groweth sharp at the end like the
					body of a cone. Again, who is he that, denying small
					things to be the signs and proofs of great, will allow what
					physicians tell us, namely, that we may prognosticate a
					pestilent summer when great numbers of spiders are seen,
					and also when the fig leaves in the spring resemble crows'
					feet? And who will permit us to measure the greatness
					of the sun's body by a pint or gallon of water, or will grant
					that a small table like a , making a sharp angle leaning on a plane superficies, can show the just measure of
					the elevation of the pole from the horizon which is ever to
					be seen in our hemisphere? And this is what the priests
					may allege in favor of what they affirm; so that we must
					offer other arguments against them, if we will maintain the
					course of the sun to be fixed and unchangeable, as we here
					hold it to be.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Not only of the sun, cried out aloud the philosopher
				Ammonius, who was there present, but also of the whole
				heaven; for, if the years really decrease, the passage which
				the sun makes from one tropic to another must of necessity
				be shortened, so that it shall not take up so great a part of
				the horizon as the mathematicians do imagine, but become
				less and shorter as the southern part approaches the northern. Whence consequently the summer will fall out to be
				shorter and the temperature of the air colder, by reason of
				the sun's turning more inwardly, and describing greater
				parallels within the signs of the tropics than it now does in
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.6"/>
				
				the longest day in summer and the shortest in winter. It
				would moreover also follow, that the pins of the dials in
				the city of Syene will no longer appear shadowless at the
				summer solstice, and some fixed stars will run under the
				horizon, and others against one another, for want of room.
				And should it be alleged that all the other celestial bodies
				keep their courses and ordinary motions without any change,
				they will never be able to cite any cause which shall hasten
				his motion alone above all the rest; but they will be forced
				to confound and disorder all evident appearances which do
				clearly show themselves to our eyes, and especially those
				of the moon. So that there will be no need of observing
				these measures of oil to know the difference of the years;
				because the eclipses will do this, if there be any, seeing
				the sun does oft meet with the moon, and the moon as oft
				falls within the shadow of the earth; so that we need not
				any longer hold arguing on this matter.</p>
            <p>But, says Cleombrotus, I myself have seen the measure
					of the oil, for they have shown it several years; but that
					of the present is far less than that of ancient times. Unto
					which Ammonius answered: How comes it to pass then
					that other people who have an inextinguishable fire in
					veneration, and have preserved it even time out of mind,
					could never remark this? And granting what you say
					concerning this measure of oil, is it not better to attribute
					the cause of this to some coldness or dampness of air; or,
					on the contrary, to some heat or dryness, by which the fire
					in the lamp being weakened needs not so much nourishment, and could not consume the same quantity? For it
					is well known that fire burns better in winter than in summer, its heat being drawn in and enclosed by the cold;
					whereas in great heats and dry weather it is weakened,
					lying dead and languishing without any strength; and if it
					be kindled in the sunshine, its efficacy is small, for it hardly
					catches hold of the wood, and slowly consumes the fuel.
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.7"/>
					
					But we may with greater probability attribute the circumstance of the oil to the oil itself; for oil formerly was of
					less nutriment, as squeezed out of olives which grew upon
					young trees; but being since better ordered, as coming of
					plants more fully grown, it must needs be more effectual
					to the nourishing and keeping of the fire. And this is the
					best way of saving the credit of the Ammonian priests in
					their supposition, which will not endure the test of reason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Ammonius having finished his discourse, I pray, said
				I, Cleombrotus, give us some account of the oracle; for
				it ever has been in great esteem in those parts till these
				times, wherein its divinity and reputation seem to be decayed. Unto which Cleombrotus making no answer, but
				looking down to the ground, Demetrius took up the discourse, saying: You need not busy yourself in enquiries
				after the oracles in those parts, seeing we find the oracles
				in these parts to fail or (to speak better) to be totally silenced, except two or three; so that it would be more to
				the purpose to search into the cause of this silence. But
				we are more concerned in Boeotia, which, although formerly famous throughout all the world for oracles, is now
				like a fountain dried up, so that at present we find them
				dumb. For at this day there is no place in all Boeotia,
				unless in the town of Lebadea, where one can draw out
				any divination, all other parts being become silent and forsaken. Yet in the time of the war against the Persians,
				the oracle of Apollo Pto&uuml;s was in request, as also that
				of Amphiaraus; for both of them were tried. The priest
				of Apollo Pto&uuml;s, who was always wont to return the oracle's answers in Aeolic Greek, spake to him that was
				sent from the barbarians in their own barbarous language,
				so that none of the assistants understood a word; whereby they were given to understand, that it was not lawful
				for the barbarians to have the use of the Greek tongue to
				serve their pleasure. And as to that of Amphiaraus, the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.8"/>
				
				person that was sent thither, having fallen asleep in the
				sanctuary, dreamed that he heard the minister of that God
				bidding him be gone out of the temple and saying that
				the God forbade him to remain, and that he presently
				shoved him out thence with both his hands ; and seeing he
				still stopped by the way, he took up a great stone and
				struck him with it on the head. And what was this but a
				prediction and denunciation of what was to come to pass?
				For Mardonius was not long after defeated by Pausanias,
				who was no king, but only the king of Lacedaemonia's
				guardian and minister, and the then lieutenant of the
				Grecians' army, and was with a stone flung out of a sling
				felled to the ground, just as the Lydian servant thought he
				was struck in his dream. In the same manner also flourished the oracle near Tegyra, where it is said Apollo himself was born; and in effect, there are two sreams that
				glide near the place, one of which is still called the Palm-tree, and the other the Olive-tree. And at this oracle, in
				the time of the Medes' war, Echecrates being then the
				prophet, the God Apollo answered by his mouth, that the
				honor and profit of this war would fall to the Greeks'
				share. And during the Peloponnesian war, the Delians
				having been driven out of their island, they had word
				brought them from the oracle of Delphi, that they should
				search for the place where Apollo was born, and there
				make some certain sacrifice. At which they marvelling,
				and demanding whether Apollo was born elsewhere than
				in their parts, the prophetess Pythia moreover told them
				that a crow would show them the place. These deputies
				from the Delians, in their return home, passed by chance
				through the city of Chaeronea, where they heard their
				hostess at the inn talking to some travellers about the oracle of Tegyra, to which they were going, and at their parting
				they heard them say to her Adieu, Dame Corone.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*koow/ih</foreign>, that is, <hi rend="italics">Crow.</hi>
               </note> By
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.9"/>
				
				this they comprehended the meaning of Pythia's answer;
				and having offered their sacrifices at Tegyra, they were
				soon after restored and established in their own country.
				Yet there have been given later answers from these oracles
				than those you have mentioned; but now they have wholly
				ceased, so that it will not be besides the matter, seeing we
				are near by Apollo Pythius, to enquire after the cause of
				this change.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Thus discoursing together, we left the temple, and
				were come as far as the Cnidian Hall, where entering in,
				we found our friends which we looked for, being set down
				in expectation of our coming. All the rest were at leisure, by reason of the time of the day, and did nothing
				but anoint their bodies, or gaze on the wrestlers who
				were exercising themselves. Whereupon Demetrius
				laughing said to them: It seems to me that you are not
				discoursing of any matter of great consequence, for I see
				you labor not under deep thoughts. It is true, replied
				Heracleon the Megarean, we are not a disputing, whether
				the verb <foreign lang="greek">*ba/llw</foreign> in his future tense loses one of his <foreign lang="greek">ll</foreign>, nor
				from what positive or primitive are formed or derived these
				two comparatives, <foreign lang="greek">xei=ron</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">be/ltion</foreign>, and these two superlatives, <foreign lang="greek">xei/riston</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">be/ltiston</foreign>; for such questions as these
				make people knit their brows. A man may discourse of
				all other matters, especially of philosophy, without these
				frowning angry looks that put the by-standers into a fright.
				Receive us then, said Demetrius, into your company, and,
				if you please, the question too which has been now agitated amongst us, which does well agree with the place
				where we are, and, relating to the God Apollo, concerns
				therefore all that are here; but, however, let us have no
				knitting of the brows or frowning looks.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Being then all set down close together, and Demetrius having proposed the question we were upon, Didymus
				the Cynic philosopher, surnamed Planetiades, getting upon
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.10"/>
				
				his feet and striking the ground two or three times with
				his stick, cried out: O Jupiter! what a hard question do
				you offer! What a difficult matter do you propose! For
				is it any wonder, the whole world wallowing in wickedness, and Shame and Retributive Justice having departed
				from men (as Hesiod long ago predicted), that the Gods
				should no longer suffer their oracles to be among them,
				as heretofore? For my part, I wonder there is so much
				as one left, and that Hercules or some other of the Gods
				has not long since plucked up and carried away the
				tripod whereon are offered such base and villainous questions to Apollo; some coming to him as a mere paltry
				astrologer, to try his skill and impose on him by subtle
				questions, others asking him about treasures buried under
				ground, others about incestuous marriages. So that Pythagoras is here soon convinced of his mistake, when he affirmed that the time when men are honestest is when they
				present themselves before the Gods; for those filthy passions, which they dare not discover before a grave mortal
				man, they scruple not to utter to Apollo. He had gone
				further, if Heracleon had not pulled him by the sleeve;
				and myself, who was better acquainted than any in the
				company besides, thus spake to him: Cease, friend Planetiades, from angering Apollo against thee, seeing he is
				sharp and choleric and not easily reconciled; although,
				as Pindar says,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Mortals to favor, Heaven has him enjoined.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And whether he be the sun, or the master of the sun and
					father of it, being above all visible natures, it is not to be
					supposed he disdains to hold any further intercourse with
					men at this time, seeing he gives them their birth, nourishment, subsistence, and reason. Neither is it credible
					that the Divine Providence (who, like a kind and indulgent
					mother, produces and conserves all things for our use)
					should show herself malevolent only in the matter of divination,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.11"/>
					
					 or deprive us of it having once given it us; as if,
					when there were more oracles than there are now in the
					world, men were not then as wicked. But let us make a
					Pythian truce (as they say) with vice, which you are always sharply reprehending, and sit down here together to
					try whether we can find out any other cause of the ceasing
					of oracles; and let me only advise you, by the way, to remember that you keep this God propitious and move him
					not to wrath. Planetiades was so moved with these
					speeches, that he went away immediately, without speaking a word.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>The company remaining a while in silence, Ammonius, addressing himself to me, said: Prithee, Lamprias,
				let us take care of what we say, and not be rash in our
				assertions; for we do not well when we make the God to
				be little or no cause of these oracles ceasing; for he that
				attributes the failing of them to any other cause than the
				will and decree of the God gives occasion to suspect him
				of believing that they never were nor are now by his disposition, but by some other means. For there is no other
				more excellent and noble cause and power which can destroy and abolish divination, if it be the work of a God.
				And as for Plantiades's discourse, it does not at all please
				me, as well for the inequality and inconstancy which he attributes to the God, as for other reasons. For he makes
				him sometimes rejecting and detesting vice, and sometimes
				admitting and receiving it, just as a king, or rather a tyrant, who drives wicked people out of one gate, and receives them through another, and negotiates with them.
				But the greatest and most perfect work, that will admit of
				no additions, is that which agrees best with the dignity of
				the Gods. By supposing this, we may in my judgment
				affirm that in this common scarcity of men, occasioned by
				the former wars and seditions over all the world, Greece
				has most suffered; so that she can with much difficulty
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.12"/>
				
				raise three thousand men, which number the single city of
				Megara sent heretofore to Plataea. Wherefore if the
				God now forsakes several oracles which anciently were
				frequented, what is this but a sign that Greece is at this
				time very much dispeopled, in comparison of what it was
				heretofore; and he that will affirm this shall not want for
				arguments. For of what use would the oracle be now,
				which was heretofore at Tegyra or at Ptoum? For scarcely shall you meet, in a whole day's time, with so much as
				a herdsman or shepherd in those parts. We find also in
				writing, that this place of divination where we now are,
				and which is as ancient as any, and as famous and renowned
				as any in all Greece, was for a considerable time deserted
				and inaccessible, by means of a dangerous creature that
				resorted hither, namely a dragon. Yet those that have
				written this did not well comprehend the occasion of the
				oracle's ceasing; for the dragon did not make the place
				solitary, but rather the solitude of the place occasioned
				the dragon to repair hither. Since that time, when Greece
				became populous and full of towns, they had two women
				prophetesses, who went down one after another into the
				cave. Moreover, there was a third chosen, if need were;
				whereas now there is but one, and yet we do not complain
				of it, because she is sufficient. And therefore we do not
				well to repine at Providence, seeing there is no want
				of divinations, where all that come are satisfied in whatever they desire to know. Homer tells us, Agamemnon had nine heralds, and yet with these could he
				hardly keep in order the Greeks, they being so many in
				number; but you will find here that the voice of one man
				is sufficient to be heard all over the theatre. The oracles
				then spake by more organs or voices, because there were
				then a greater number of men. So that we should think
				it strange, if the God should suffer the prophetical divination to be spilt and run to waste like water, or everywhere
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.13"/>
				
				to resound, as in solitary fields we hear the rocks echoing
				the voices of shepherds and bleating cattle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Ammonius having said these words, and I returning
				no answer, Cleombrotus took up the discourse, and addressed himself to me. Hast thou then, said he, confessed
				that it is the God who makes and unmakes oracles? Not
				I, said I; for I maintain that God was never the cause of
				taking away or abolishing any oracle or divination; but,
				on the contrary, whereas he produces and prepares several
				things for our use, so Nature leads them into corruption,
				and not seldom into a privation of their whole being. Or,
				to speak better, matter, which is itself privation or negation, often flies away, and dissolves what a more excellent
				being than herself had wrought. So that I am of opinion,
				there are other causes which obscure and extinguish these
				prophetic spirits. For though God does give to men several good and excellent things, yet he gives to none of
				them the power to exist eternally; for, though the Gods
				never die, yet their gifts do, as Sophocles speaks. It were
				then well becoming philosophers who exercise themselves
				in the study of Nature and the first matter, to enquire into
				the existence, property, and tendency of those things, but
				to leave the origin and first cause to God, as is most reasonable. For it is a very childish and silly thing, to suppose that the God himself does, like the spirits speaking
				in the bowels of ventriloquists (which were anciently
				called Euryclees, and now Pythons), enter into the bodies
				of the prophets, and speak by their mouths and voices, as
				fit instruments for that purpose. For he that thus mixes
				God in human affairs has not that respect and reverence
				which is due to so great a majesty, as being ignorant of
				his power and virtue.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Cleombrotus then answered: You say very well;
				but it is a hard matter to comprehend and define how far
				this providence does extend itself. They seem both alike
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.14"/>
				
				faulty to me, who will have him simply the cause of nothing at all in the world, and who will have him to be
				concerned in all things; for both of these are run into extremes. But as those say well who hold that Plato, having
				invented the element on which spring up the qualities,&mdash;
				which we sometimes call the first matter, and sometimes
				Nature,&mdash;has thereby delivered the philosophers from
				several great difficulties; so it seems to me, that those who
				have ranked the genus of Daemons between that of Gods
				and men have solved greater doubts and difficulties, as
				having found the knot which does, as it were, join and
				hold together our society and communication with them.
				It is uncertain whence this opinion arose, whether from the
				ancient Magi by Zoroaster, or from Thrace by Orpheus, or
				from Egypt, or Phrygia; as may be conjectured from the
				sight of the sacrifices which are made in both countries,
				where amongst their holy and divine ceremonies there is
				seen a mixture of mortality and mourning. And as to the
				Greeks, Homer has indifferently used these two names,
				terming sometimes the Gods Daemons, and other whiles
				Daemons Gods. But Hesiod was the first that did best
				and most distinctly lay down four reasonable natures, the
				Gods, the Daemons (being many in number, and good in
				their kind), heroes, and men; for the Demi-gods are reckoned
				amongst heroes. Others say, there is a transmutation of
				bodies as well as of souls; and that, just as we see of the
				earth is engendered water, of the water the air, and of the
				air fire, the nature of the substance still ascending higher,
				so good spirits always change for the best, being transformed from men into heroes, and from heroes into
				Daemons; and from Daemons, by degrees and in a long
				space of time, a few souls being refined and purified come
				to partake of the nature of the Divinity. But there are
				some that cannot contain themselves, but rove about till
				they be entangled into mortal bodies, where they live
				meanly and obscurely, like smoke.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.15"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>And moreover, Hesiod imagines that the Daemons
				themselves, after certain revolutions of time, do at length
				die. For, introducing a Nymph speaking, he marks the
				time wherein they expire:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nine ages of men in their flower doth live
				</l>
                     <l>The railing crow; four times the stags surmount
				</l>
                     <l>The life of crows; to ravens doth Nature give
				</l>
                     <l>A threefold age of stags, by true account;
				</l>
                     <l>One phoenix lives as long as ravens nine.
				</l>
                     <l>But you, fair Nymphs, as the daughters verily
				</l>
                     <l>Of mighty Jove and of Nature divine,
				</l>
                     <l>The phoenix's years tenfold do multiply.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now those which do not well understand what the poet
					means by this word <foreign lang="greek">genea/</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">age</hi>) do cause this computation
					of time to amount to a great number of years. For the
					word means a year; so that the total sum makes but 9720
					years, which is the space of the age of Daemons. And
					there are several mathematicians who make it shorter than
					this. Pindar himself does not make it longer when he
					says, Destiny has given Nymphs an equal life with trees;
					and therefore they are called Hamadryades, because they
					spring up and die with oaks. He was going on, when
					Demetrius interrupting him thus said: How is it possible,
					Cleombrotus, that you should maintain that a year was
					called by this poet the age of a man, seeing it is not the
					space of his flower and youth, nor of his old age ? For there
					are divers readings of this place, some reading <foreign lang="greek">h(bw/ntwn</foreign>, others
					<foreign lang="greek">ghrw/ntwn</foreign>,&mdash;one signifying <hi rend="italics">flourishing,</hi> the other <hi rend="italics">aged.</hi> Now
					those that understand hereby <q direct="unspecified"> flourishing</q> reckon thirty
					years for the age of man's life, according to the opinion of
					Heraclitus; this being the space of time in which a father
					has begotten a son who then is apt and able to beget
					another. And those that read <q direct="unspecified"> aged</q> allow to the age of
					man a hundred and eight years, saying that fifty-four years
					are just the half part of a man's life, which number consists
					of unity, the first two plane numbers, two squares, and two
					cubes (i. e. 1 + 2 + 3 + 4+ 9 + 8 + 27); which numbers Plato
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.16"/>
					
					himself has appropriated to the procreation of the soul.
					And it seems also that Hesiod by these words intimated the
					consummation of the world by fire; at which time it is likely
					the Nymphs, with the rivers, marshes, and woods where
					they inhabit, shall be consumed,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such as in woods, or grotto's shady cell,
					</l>
                     <l>Near sacred springs and verdant meadows dwell.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XX. 8.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>I have heard, says Cleombrotus, this alleged by
				several, and find that the Stoical conflagration hath intruded
				itself not only upon the works of Heraclitus and Orpheus,
				but also upon Hesiod's, imposing such meanings on their
				words as they never thought of. But I cannot approve of
				the consummation of the world which they maintain, nor
				of the other impossible matters; and especially what they
				say about the crow and the stag would force us to believe in
				the most excessive numbers. Moreover, the year, containing
				in itself the beginning and end of all things which the
				seasons bring and the earth produces, may, in my opinion,
				be not impertinently called the age of man. For you
				yourselves confess that Hesiod does somewhere call the life
				of man <foreign lang="greek">genea/</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">age</hi>). What say you, does he not? Which
				Demetrius confessing, he proceeded in this manner: It is
				also certain that we call the vessels whereby we measure
				things by the names of the things measured in them; as a
				pint, a quart, or a bushel. As we then call a unit a number,
				though it be but the least part and measure and the beginning of a number; so has he called a year the age of man,
				because it is the measure wherewith it is measured. As
				for those numbers which those others describe, they be not
				of such singularity and importance. But the sum of 9920
				is thus composed. The four numbers arising in order
				from one, being added together and multiplied by four,
				amount to forty; this forty being tripled five times makes up
				the total of the forecited number. But as to that it is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.17"/>
				
				not necessary to enter into a debate with Demetrius; for
				whether it be a short or a long time, certain or uncertain,
				wherewith Hesiod limits the soul of a Daemon and the life
				of a Demi-god, either of those will prove, by ancient and
				evident testimonies, that there are natures neuter and
				mean, and as it were in the confines of the Gods and men,
				subject to mortal passions and necessary changes; which
				natures, according to the tradition and example of our
				predecessors, it is fitting we should call Daemons, giving
				them all due honor.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>To which purpose Xenocrates, one of the familiar
				friends of Plato, was wont to allege the example of
				triangles, which agree very well with the subject; for that
				triangle which has equal sides and equal angles he compared unto the divine and immortal nature; and that
				which has all three unequal, to the human and mortal
				nature; and that which has two equal and one unequal,
				to the nature of Daemons, which is endued with the passions and perturbations of the mortal nature, and the force
				and power of the divine. Even Nature has set before us
				sensible figures and resemblance of this; of the Gods, the
				sun and the stars; of mortal men, the comets, flashings in
				the night, and shooting-stars. And this similitude is taken
				up by Euripides, when he saith:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He that but now was fleshy, plump, and gay,
				</l>
                     <l>As a fall'n star his glories melt away;
				</l>
                     <l>Like that extinguished on the ground he lies,
				</l>
                     <l>Breathing his soul into the ambient skies.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And for a mixed body representing the nature of Daemons,
					we have the moon; which some, observing it to be subject
					to increase and decrease and wholly to disappear, have
					thought very agreeable to the mutable condition of Daemons; and for this reason they have termed her a terrestrial
					star, others Olympic earth, and others the inheritance and
					possession of Hecate, both heavenly and earthly. As one
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.18"/>
					
					then that should take from the world the air, and remove
					it from between the moon and the earth, would dissolve the
					continuation and composition of the universe, by leaving
					an empty place in the midst, without any contexture to
					hold the two parts together; so those that do not allow
					Daemons oppose all communication and conference of the
					Gods with men, seeing they destroy that nature (as Plato
					says) which serves as an interpreter and messenger between
					them both; or else they constrain us to perplex and confound all things together, by mixing the divine nature with
					human passions, and plucking it down from heaven, as the
					women of Thessaly are said to do the moon. Even this
					fiction has met with belief in some women, because Aglaonice, the daughter of Hegetor, being skilful in astrology,
					made the vulgar believe, whenever the moon was eclipsed,
					that by means of some charms and enchantments she
					brought it down from heaven. But as to us, let us not
					think there are any oracles or divinations without some
					divinity, or that the Gods are not pleased with sacrifices,
					and our services, and other ceremonies. And, on the other
					hand, let us not think that God is present in them, or employs himself personally about them; but rather believe
					that he does commit them to his officers, the Daemons, who
					are the spies and scouts of the Gods, wandering and
					circuiting about at their commands,&mdash;some beholding and
					ordering the sacred ceremonies and oblations offered to the
					Gods, others being employed to revenge and punish the
					high misdemeanors and enormous injustices of men. There
					are, moreover, others, to whom Hesiod gives a very venerable name, calling them the distributers of riches and
					donors of largesses among mortals; for the Gods have
					allowed them the privilege, and granted them a royal commission to see them duly distributed. He informs us here,
					by the way, that to be beneficent and liberal of favors is
					the proper office of a king. For there is a difference of
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.19"/>
					
					virtue between these Daemons, as much as between men.
					For there are some of them in whom still there are some
					small remains (though weak and scarcely discernible) of the
					sensitive and irrational soul, which, like a small quantity
					of excrements and superfluities, stay still behind. Others
					there are, in whom there abideth a greater measure of
					these gross humors, the marks and traces of which are to
					be seen in many places, in the odd and singular ceremonies
					and sacrifices and the strange fables which prevail.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>As to the mysteries and secret ceremonies, by which
				we may more clearly than by any other means understand
				the nature of Daemons, let me keep a religious silence, as
				Herodotus says. But as to the certain feasts and direful
				sacrifices which are held as unfortunate and mournful
				days, and are celebrated by eating raw flesh and tearing
				the skin with the nails, or days wherein they fast and smite
				their breasts, and in several places utter filthy and dishonest
				words during the sacrifices,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wagging their heads in frantic wise,
				</l>
                     <l>With strange alarms and hideous cries,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>I will never think these done on any of the Gods' account,
					but rather to avert, mollify, and appease the wrath and
					fury of some bad Daemons. For it is not likely there ever
					was a God that expected or required men to be sacrificed
					to him, as has been anciently done, or who received such
					kind of sacrifices with approbation. Neither must we
					imagine it was for nothing, that kings and great men have
					delivered their own children to be sacrificed, or that they
					sacrificed them themselves with their own hands; but
					they intended hereby to avert and appease the malice
					and rancor of some evil spirits, or to satisfy the violent
					and raging lusts of some, who either could not or would
					not enjoy them with their bodies or by their bodies. Even
					as Hercules besieged the city of Oechalia for a wench that
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.20"/>
					
					was therein, so these powerful and tyrannical Daemons,
					requiring some human soul which is still compassed with
					a body, and yet not being able to satisfy their lust by the
					body, do therefore bring the plague and famine into towns,
					raise wars and seditions, till such time as they obtain and
					enjoy that which they love. Others, on the contrary (as I
					remember I observed in Crete, for I was some considerable
					time there) celebrate a feast in which they show the
					figure of a man without a head, calling it Molus, the father
					of Meriones, who, having violently laid hands on the
					Nymph, was afterwards found without a head.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>The rapes committed on boys or girls, the long
				voyages, flights, banishments, and voluntary services of the
				Gods, which are sung by the poets, are passions fitting to
				be attributed not to Gods, but to Daemons, whose fortunes
				were recorded in memorial of their virtue and power.
				Neither is Aeschylus in the right, when he says,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Divine Apollo banished from the sky;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>nor Admetus in Sophocles, saying of a God,
					<quote rend="blockquote">My cock by crowing led him to the mill.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>The divines of Delphi were far from the truth when they
					asserted that there was a combat between Apollo and a
					Dragon about the possession of this oracle. No less are
					they to blame who suffer the poets or orators in the open
					theatres to act or speak of such matters; whereby they
					seem to condemn those things which themselves perform
					in their sacred solemnities. Philippus (for this man was
					an historian, and then present in the company), wondering
					at what was last said, enquired what divine solemnities
					they contradicted and condemned who contended one
					against another in the theatres. Even those, quoth Cleombrotus, which concern the oracle of Delphi, by which
					this city has lately admitted into these ceremonies and sacrifices all the Greeks without Thermopylae, including those
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.21"/>
					
					that dwell as far as the vale of Tempe. For the tabernacle or hut, which is set up every ninth year within the
					court-yard of this temple, is not a representation of the
					Dragon's den, but of some king or tyrant; as likewise
					the assaulting of it in great silence, by the way termed
					Dolonia, in which they lead hither a youth whose father
					and mother are still living, with torches burning; and
					having set this tabernacle on fire and overthrown the
					table, they run away as fast as they are able through the
					doors of the temple, never looking behind them. In fine,
					this boy's wanderings, together with his servile offices, and
					all the expiatory sacrifices about Tempe, seem to declare
					the commission of some horrid crime in this place. For
					it looks silly to affirm that Apollo, for having killed the
					Dragon, was forced to fly to the farthest parts of Greece
					to be cleansed and purified; and that he there made certain offerings and libations, as men do when they design
					the appeasing those vindictive spirits whom we call Alastores and Palamnaei, which is to say, the revengers of
					such crimes as cannot be forgotten but must have punishment. It is true, indeed, that the relation which I have
					heard touching this flight is very strange and wonderful;
					but if there be any truth in it, we must not suppose it
					was an ordinary and common matter which happened
					then about this oracle. Yet lest I should be thought, as
					Empedocles says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Starting new heads, to wander from the text,
					</l>
                     <l>And make the theme we have in hand perplext,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>I entreat you to let me put a fit conclusion to my discourse
					(for now the time requires it), and to say what several have
					said before me, that when the Daemons who are appointed
					for the government and superintendency of oracles do fail,
					the oracles must of necessity fail too; and when they depart elsewhere, the divining powers must likewise cease in
					those places; but when they return again, after a long
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.22"/>
					
					time, the places will begin again to speak, like musical instruments handled by those that know how to use them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Cleombrotus having said thus much, Heracleon took
				up the discourse, saying: We have never an infidel among
				us, but are all agreed in our opinions touching the Gods;
				yet let us have a care, Philippus, lest in the heat and
				multiplicity of our words we unawares broach some
				false doctrine that may tend to impiety. Well! but, saith
				Philippus, I hope Cleombrotus has not said any thing
				which may occasion this caution. His asserting (says
				Heracleon) that they be not the Gods who preside over
				the oracles (because we are to suppose them free from all
				worldly care), but Daemons, or the Gods' officers or
				messengers, does not scandalize me; but to attribute to
				these Daemons all the calamities, vexations, and plagues
				which happen to mortal men,&mdash;snatching these violently
				(we may almost say) from the verses of Empedocles,&mdash;
				and in the end to make them to die like them, this, in my
				mind, savors of bold presumption. Cleombrotus, having
				asked Philippus who this young man was, and being informed of his name and country, proceeded in this manner: I know very well, Heracleon, that the discourse I
				used may bear an absurd construction; but there is no
				speaking of great matters without laying first great foundations for the proof of one's opinion. But, as for your
				part, you are not sensible how you contradict even that
				which you allow; for granting, as you do, that there be
				Demons, but not allowing them to be vicious and mortal,
				you cannot prove there are any at all. For wherein do
				they differ from Gods, supposing they be incorruptible and
				impassible and not liable to error?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Whilst Heracleon was musing, and studying how to
				answer this, Cleombrotus went on, saying: It is not only
				Empedocles who affirms there are bad Daemons, but even
				Plato, Xenocrates, and Chrysippus; yea, and Democritus,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.23"/>
				
				when he prayed he might meet with good spirits, which
				shows that he thought there were bad as well as good
				Daemons. And as to their mortality, I have heard it reported from a person that was neither fool nor knave,
				being Epitherses, the father of Aemilianus the orator,
				whom some of you have heard declaim. This Epitherses
				was my townsman and a school-master, who told me that,
				designing a voyage to Italy, he embarked himself on a
				vessel well laden both with goods and passengers. About
				the evening the vessel was becalmed about the Isles Echinades, whereupon their ship drove with the tide till it was
				carried near the Isles of Paxi; when immediately a voice
				was heard by most of the passengers (who were then
				awake, and taking a cup after supper) calling unto one
				Thamus, and that with so loud a voice as made all the
				company amazed; which Thamus was a mariner of Egypt,
				whose name was scarcely known in the ship. He returned
				no answer to the first calls; but at the third he replied,
				Here ! here! I am the man. Then the voice said aloud to
				him, When you are arrived at Palodes, take care to make
				it known that the great God Pan is dead. Epitherses told
				us, this voice did much astonish all that heard it, and
				caused much arguing whether this voice was to be obeyed
				or slighted. Thamus, for his part, was resolved, if the
				wind permitted, to sail by the place without saying a word;
				but if the wind ceased and there ensued a calm, to speak
				and cry out as loud as he was able what he was enjoined.
				Being come to Palodes, there was no wind stirring, and the
				sea was as smooth as glass. Whereupon Thamus standing
				on the deck, with his face towards the land, uttered with a
				loud voice his message, saying, The great Pan is dead. He
				had no sooner said this, but they heard a dreadful noise,
				not only of one, but of several, who, to their thinking,
				groaned and lamented with a kind of astonishment. And
				there being many persons in the ship, an account of this
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.24"/>
				
				was soon spread over Rome, which made Tiberius the Emperor send for Thamus; and he seemed to give such heed
				to what he told him, that he earnestly enquired who this
				Pan was; and the learned men about him gave in their
				judgments, that it was the son of Mercury by Penelope.
				There were some then in the company who declared they
				had heard old Aemilianus say as much.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Demetrius then related, that about Britain there
				were many small and desolate islands, some of which were
				called the Isles of Daemons and Demi-gods; and that he
				himself, at the command of the Emperor, sailed to the
				nearest of those places for curiosity's sake, where he found
				few inhabitants; but that they were all esteemed by the
				Britains as sacred and divine. Not long after he was
				arrived there, he said, the air and the weather were very
				foul and tempestuous, and there followed a terrible storm
				of wind and thunder; which at length ceasing, he says,
				the inhabitants told him that one of the Daemons or Demigods was deceased. For as a lamp, said he, while it is
				lighted, offends nobody with its scent, but when it is extinguished, it sends out such a scent as is nauseous to everybody; so these great souls, whilst they shine, are mild and
				gracious, without being troublesome to anybody; but
				when they draw to an end, they cause great storms and
				tempests, and not seldom infect the air with contagious
				distempers. They say farther, that Saturn is detained
				prisoner in one of those islands, and guarded by Briareus,
				being in a sound sleep (for that is the device to hold him
				captive), and that he has several of those Daemons for his
				valets and attendants.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Thus then spake Cleombrotus: I could, says he,
				relate several such stories as these; but it is sufficient that
				what has been said as yet does not contradict the opinion
				of any one here. And we all know, the Stoics believe the
				same as we do concerning the Daemons, and that amongst
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.25"/>
				
				the great company of Gods which are commonly believed,
				there is but one who is eternal and immortal; all the rest,
				having been born in time, shall end by death. As to the
				flouts and scoffing of the Epicureans, they are not to be
				regarded, seeing they have the boldness to treat divine
				providence with as little reverence, calling it by no better
				a name than a mere whimsy and old wives' fable.
				Whereas we, on the contrary, assert that their Infinity
				is fabulous and ridiculous, seeing among such endless numbers of worlds there is not one governed by reason or divine
				providence, they having been all made and upheld by
				chance. If we cannot forbear drolling even in matters of
				philosophy, they are most to be ridiculed who bring into
				their disputes of natural questions certain blind, dumb, and
				lifeless images, which appear they know not where nor
				when, which, they say, proceed from bodies, some of which
				are still living, and others long since dead and rotten.
				Now, such people's opinions as these must needs be exploded and derided by all rational men; yet these very
				people shall be offended and angry at a man's saying there
				be Daemons, and that they subsist both by reason and by
				Nature, and continue a long time.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>Here Ammonius began to speak, saying: In my
				opinion, Theophrastus was in the right, and spoke like a
				philosopher and a divine; for whoever shall deny what he
				alleges must also reject many things which may happen,
				though we understand not the reasons why they do so.
				And granting what he offers to be true, it carries with it
				many things called impossible and unreal. But as to what I
				have heard the Epicureans allege against the Daemons which
				Empedocles brings in,&mdash;as, that it is impossible they can
				be happy and long-lived if they be bad and viciously
				affected, because vice in its own nature is blind and naturally precipitates itself into such mischiefs as destroy life,
				&mdash;that, I must tell you, is vain and idle. For if this
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.26"/>
				
				reasoning be good, it will then follow that Epicurus was a
				worse man than Gorgias the sophister, and Metrodorus
				than Alexis the comic actor; for Alexis lived twice as long
				as Metrodorus, and Gorgias a third longer than Epicurus.
				For it is in another regard we say virtue is strong and vice
				weak. not in reference to the continuance or dissolution of
				the body; for we know there are many animals which are
				dull, slow, and heavy, and many disorderly and lustful,
				which live longer than those that are more sagacious and
				quicker of sense. And therefore they are much in the
				wrong in saying the divine nature is immortal because it
				avoideth the things which are ill and mischievous; for they
				should have supposed the divine nature free from all possibility of falling into corruption and alteration. But perhaps it will be thought not fair to dispute against those
				that are absent; I would have therefore Cleombrotus to
				resume his discourse touching the vanishing and transmigration of Daemons from one place to another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>With all my heart, answered Cleombrotus; but I
				shall now say something which will seem more absurd than
				any telling I have heretofore offered, although it seems to
				be grounded on natural reason; and Plato himself has
				touched upon it, not positively affirming it, but offering it
				as a probable opinion, although among other philosophers
				it has been much cried out against. And seeing that we
				are fallen into a free discourse, and that a man cannot light
				into better company and a more favorable auditory to test
				the story, as if it were foreign coin, I shall therefore tell
				you a story which I heard from a stranger, whose acquaintance has cost me no small sum of money in searching after
				him in divers countries, whom at length, after much travel,
				I found near the Red Sea. He would converse with men
				but once a year, all the rest of his time (as he told me) he
				spent among the Nymphs, Nomades, and Daemons. He
				was very free with me, and extremely obliging. I never
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.27"/>
				
				saw a more graceful person in all my life; and that which
				was very strange in him was, that he was never subject to
				any disease; once every month he ate the bitter fruit of a
				certain medicinal herb. He spake several languages perfectly well; his discourse to me was in the Doric dialect;
				his speech was as charming as the sweetest music, and as
				soon as ever he opened his mouth to speak, there issued
				out of it so sweet and fragrant a breath, that all the place
				was filled with it. Now, as to human learning, such as
				history, he retained the knowledge thereof all the year;
				but as to the gift of divination, he was inspired therewith
				only one day in the year, in which he went down to the
				sea-side, and there foretold things to come. And thither
				resorted to him the princes and great men of all the
				country, or else their secretaries, who there attended his
				coming at a prefixed day, and then returned. This person
				attributed divination to the Daemons, and was well pleased
				to hear what we related concerning Delphi. Whatsoever
				we told concerning Bacchus and the sacrifices which are
				offered to him, he knew it all, saying that, as these were
				great accidents which happened to Daemons, so also was
				that which was related of the serpent Python. And he
				affirmed, that he who slew him was not banished for nine
				years, neither did he fly into the Valley of Tempe, but
				was driven out of this world into another, from whence,
				after nine revolutions of the great years, being returned,
				cleansed, and purified, and become a true Phoebus,&mdash;that
				is to say, clear and bright,&mdash;he had at length recovered
				the superintendence of the Delphic oracle, which in the
				mean time had been committed to the charge of Themis
				He said as much concerning what is related of Typhon
				and the Titans. For he affirmed, they were the battles of
				Daemons against Daemons, and the flights and banishments
				of those that had been vanquished, or the punishments
				inflicted by the Gods on those who had committed such
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.28"/>
				
				acts as Typhon is said to have done against Osiris, and
				Saturn against Uranus, whose honors are much obscured,
				or wholly lost, by being translated into another world.
				For I know that the Solymeans, who are borderers to the
				Lycians, did greatly honor Saturn; but since he killed
				their princes, Arsalus, Dryus, and Trosobius, he fled into
				some other country, they knew not where, and he now is
				in a manner forgotten. But they called these three&mdash;
				Arsalus, Dryus, and Trosobius&mdash;the severe Gods, and the
				Lycians do at this day curse people in their names, as well
				in private as in public. Several other such like examples
				may a man find in the records of the Gods. And if we
				call any of the Daemons by the usual and common names
				of the Gods, on whom they do depend, it is no marvel at
				all, said the stranger; for they like to be called by the
				Gods on whom they do depend, and from whom they have
				received their honor and power; even as amongst us men
				one is named Diius, another Athenae, another Apollonius,
				another Dionysius, and still another Hermaeus. And
				there are some who have names imposed on them, as
				it were, by chance, which yet do well agree with their
				tempers; whereas some carry the names of the Gods
				which do not at all suit with their weaknesses.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Here Cleombrotus having paused, his discourse
				seemed strange to all the company, and Heracleon demanded of him, how all this concerned Plato, and how he
				had given occasion to this discourse. Unto which Cleombrotus answered: You do well to put me in mind of it;
				for first, Plato ever rejected the infinity of worlds, yet
				would determine nothing positively touching the precise
				number of them. And granting the probability of their
				opinion who affirmed there were five, one for each element,
				as to his own part, he kept to one, which seems to be his
				genuine opinion; whereas all other philosophers have been
				afraid to receive and admit the multitude of worlds, as if
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.29"/>
				
				those who did not limit matter to one must needs fall
				into troublesome and boundless infinity. But was this
				stranger, said I, of the same opinion with Plato, touching
				the number of the worlds? Or did you not all the while
				ask his opinion in that matter? I was far from failing
				herein, says Cleombrotus, seeing I found him so communicative and affable to me. He told me, that neither was
				the number of the worlds infinite, neither was there but
				only one, nor five; but a hundred and eighty-three, which
				were ranged in a triangular form, every side containing
				sixty worlds; and of the three remaining, every corner
				had one. That they were so ordered, that one always
				touched another in a circle, like those who dance in a
				ring. That the plain within the triangle is, as it were, the
				foundation and common altar to all those worlds, which is
				called the Plain of Truth, in which lie the designs, moulds,
				ideas, and invariable examples of all things which were,
				or ever shall be; and about these is Eternity, whence
				flowed Time, as from a river, into these worlds. Moreover, that the souls of men, if they have lived well in this
				world, do see these ideas once in ten thousand years; and
				that the most holy mystical ceremonies which are performed here are no more than a dream of this sacred
				vision. And further, that all the pains which are taken
				in the study of philosophy are to attain to a sight of those
				beauties; otherwise they were all lost labors. I heard
				him, said he, relate all these things as perfectly, as if they
				had been some religious rites wherein he would have
				instructed me; for he brought me no proof or demonstration to confirm what he said.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Here, turning myself to Demetrius, I asked him
				what were the words which the wooers of Penelope spake
				in Homer, when they saw Ulysses handling his bow. And
				Demetrius having put me in mind of them, I said: It
				came into my thoughts to say as much of this wonderful
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.30"/>
				
				man. He was indeed <q direct="unspecified"> an observer and a cunning thief</q>
				of opinions and discourses, and a person conversant in all
				sorts of learning, being a Greek born, and perfectly well
				skilled in the studies of his country. For this number of
				worlds shows us that he was neither an Indian nor an
				Egyptian; but his father was a Dorian Greek of the country of Sicily, named Petron, born in the city of Himera,
				who wrote a little book on this subject, which I indeed
				never saw, nor can tell whether it be extant. But Hippys,
				a native of Rhegium, mentioned by Phanias the Eresian,
				tells us, it was the doctrine of Petron that there were a
				hundred and eighty-three worlds, tacked to one another in
				their first principle; but he does not explain to us what
				this phrase means, nor does he offer any reason to prove
				this. It is certain, says Demetrius, that Plato himself,
				bringing no argument to evince this point, does hereby
				overthrow this opinion. Yet, says Heracleon, we have
				heard you grammarians say that Homer was the first
				author of this opinion, as having divided the universe
				into five worlds, heaven, water, air, earth, and that which
				he calls Olympus; of which he leaveth two to be common,&mdash;the earth to all beneath, and Olympus to all above,
				&mdash;but the three in the midst between them he attributes
				unto three several Gods. In the, like manner Plato, assigning unto the principal parts of the universe the first
				forms and most excellent figures of the bodies, calls them
				five worlds,&mdash;those of the earth, water, air, and fire, and
				finally, of that which comprehended all the others, which
				he calls Dodecaedron (which is to say, with twelve bases),
				which, amply extending, is of easy motion and capacity,
				its form and figure being very fit and proper for the revolutions and motions of the souls. What need is there then,
				cried Demetrius, of bringing in good old Homer? For
				we have had fables enough already. But Plato is far from
				calling the different elements five worlds; for even where
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.31"/>
				
				he disputes against those who assert an infinite number of
				worlds, he affirms, there is only one created of God and
				satisfying him, consisting of the entire corporeal Nature,
				perfect, endued with self-sufficiency, and wanting nothing; and therefore we may well think it strange that the
				truth which he spake should occasion the extravagancy of
				others. For had he not maintained the world's unity, he
				would in some sort have given a foundation to those who
				affirm an infinite number of worlds; but that he asserted
				precisely five, this is marvellously strange and far from all
				probability, unless you can (says he, turning himself to
				me) clear this point. How! (said I) are you then resolved
				to drop here your first dispute about oracles, and to take
				up another of no less difficulty? Not so, replied Demetrius; yet we must take cognizance of this, which does, as
				it were, hold out its hand to us, though we shall not remain long upon it, but treat of it by the way, and soon
				return to our first discourse.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>First of all then, I say, the reasons which hinder us
				from asserting an infinite number of worlds do not hinder
				us from affirming that there are more than one; for as
				well in many worlds as in one there may be Providence
				and Divination, while Fortune intervenes only in the smallest things; but most part of the grand and principal things
				have and take their beginnings and changes by order,
				which could not be in an infinite number of worlds. And
				it is more conformable to reason to say that God made
				more than one world; for, being perfectly good, he wants
				no virtue, and least of all justice and friendship, for they
				do chiefly become the nature of the Gods. Now God
				hath nothing that is superfluous and useless; and therefore there must be other inferior Gods proceeding from
				him, and other worlds made by him, towards whom he
				must use these social virtues; for he cannot exercise those
				virtues of justice and benignity on himself or any part of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.32"/>
				
				himself, but on others. So that it is not likely this world
				should float and wander about, without either friend,
				neighbor, or any sort of communication, in an infinite
				vacuum. For we see Nature includes all single things in
				genera and species, like as in vessels or in husks of seeds;
				for there is nothing to be found in Nature&mdash;and nothing
				can have a common notion or appellation&mdash;which is not
				qualified both in common and in particular. Now the
				world is not said to be such in common, but in particular,
				for its quality is derived from its being an harmonious
				whole made up of different parts. But yet, there being
				no such thing in Nature as one man alone, one horse,
				one star, one God, one Daemon, why may we not believe that there is not in Nature one only world and no
				more, but several? And if any one shall object against
				me that this world hath likewise but one earth and one
				sea, I can answer him, he is much deceived by not understanding the evidence afforded by like parts. For we
				divide the earth into similar parts of the same denomination; for all the parts of the earth are earth, and so of
				the sea; but no part of the world is still the world, it
				being composed of divers and different natures.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>For as to the inconvenience which some do seem
				to fear, and in respect of which they confine all the matter
				within one world, lest, there remaining any thing without,
				it should disturb the composition of this, by the resistances
				and jars which it would make against it,&mdash;they have no
				need to dread this. For, there being many worlds, and
				each of them in particular having one definite and determinate measure and limit of its substance and matter, no
				part thereof will be without order and good disposition,
				nothing will remain superfluous or be cast out as an excrement. For the reason which belongeth to each world,
				being able to rule and govern the matter that is allotted
				thereto, will not suffer that any thing shall run out of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.33"/>
				
				course and order, and rencounter and jumble another
				world, nor likewise that any thing from another shall
				justle or disturb it, there being nothing in Nature infinite
				and inordinate in quantity, nor in motion without reason
				and order. And if perhaps there be any influence that
				passes from the one to the other, this is a fraternal communication, whereby they mix themselves together, like
				the light of the stars and the influence of their temperatures, and whereby they themselves do rejoice in beholding one another with a benign aspect, and give to the Gods
				(who are good and many in number in every world) an
				opportunity of knowing and caressing one another. For
				there is nothing in all this that is impossible, or fabulous,
				or contrary to reason; though some may think so because
				of the opinion of Aristotle, who saith that all bodies have
				their proper and natural places, by which means the earth
				must on all sides tend to the midst, and the water must
				rest upon it, serving by its weight for a foundation to the
				other lighter elements. Were there then many worlds, the
				earth would be often found above the airy and fiery regions,
				and as often under them; while air and water would be
				sometimes in their natural places, and sometimes in others
				which are their unnatural; which things being impossible,
				as he thinks, it follows then, there are neither two nor
				more worlds, but one only, which is this here, consisting
				of all kinds of elements, disposed according to Nature,
				agreeably to the diversity of bodies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>But in all this there is more probability than truth.
				For consider, friend Demetrius; when he saith that some
				bodies tend towards the midst, which is to say, downwards,
				the others from the midst, that is, upward, and a third
				sort move round about the midst, what does he mean by the
				midst? This cannot be understood in respect of a vacuum,
				there being no such thing in Nature, as he says himself;
				and, moreover, those that do allow it say that it can have
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.34"/>
				
				no middle, no more than beginning and end; for beginning and end are extremities, but that which is infinite,
				everybody knows, is without an end. But supposing we
				should be necessitated to admit a middle in a vacuum, it is
				impossible to comprehend and imagine the difference in
				the motions of bodies towards it, because there is neither
				in this vacuum any power attractive of the body, nor in
				the bodies any inclination or affection to tend on all sides
				to this middle. And it is no less difficult to imagine that
				bodies can move of themselves towards an incorporeal
				place, or receive any motion from it. This middle then
				must be understood not locally, but corporeally. For this
				world being a mass and union consisting of different bodies joined together, this diversity of them must beget different motions from one another; which appears in that each
				of these bodies changing its substance does at the same
				time change its place. For subtilization and rarefaction
				dissipate the matter which springeth from the midst and
				ariseth upwards; whereas, on the contrary, condensation
				and constipation depress and drive it down towards the
				middle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>On these points it is not necessary to discourse any
				longer in this place. For whatever cause a man supposes
				shall produce such passions and changes, that very cause
				will contain each of these worlds in itself; because each
				of them has its sea and land, each its proper middle, and
				each its passions and change of bodies, and the nature
				and power which contain and preserve each in its place
				and being. For that which is without, whether it be
				nothing at all or an infinite vacuum, cannot allow any middle, as we have already said. But there being several
				worlds, each has its proper middle apart; so that in each
				of them there will be motions proper to bodies, some tending down to the midst, others mounting aloft from the
				midst, others moving round about it, according as they
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.35"/>
				
				themselves do distinguish motions. And he who asserts
				there are many middles, and that heavy bodies from all
				sides do tend unto one alone, is like to him who shall affirm that the blood of several men runs from all parts
				into one vein, or that all their brains should be contained
				within one and the same membrane; supposing it absurd,
				that all natural bodies which are solid should not be in one
				place, and the rare in another. He that thus thinketh is
				certainly a mean philosopher; and no better is he who
				will not allow the whole to have all parts in their order,
				rank, and natural situation. What could be more foolish,
				than for a man to call that a world which had a moon
				within it so situated, as if a man should have his brains
				in his heels, and his heart in his forehead? Whereas there
				is no absurdity or inconveniency, if, in supposing several
				distinct worlds separated from one another, a man should
				distinguish and separate their parts. For in each of them
				the earth, sea, and sky will be placed and situated in their
				proper places, and each of these worlds may have its superior, inferior, circular, and middle part, not in respect
				of another world, nor in reference to what is without, but
				to what is within itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>And as to the argument which some do draw from
				a stone supposed to be placed without the world, it
				neither proves rest nor motion; for how could it remain
				suspended, seeing it is by nature heavy, or move towards
				the midst of the world, as other ponderous bodies, seeing
				it is neither part of it nor like it? And as to that earth
				which is fixed and environed by another world, we must
				not wonder, considering its weightiness, if it does not drop
				down, seeing it is upheld by a certain natural force pertaining to it. For if we shall take high and low not within the world but without, we shall find ourselves involved
				in the same difficulties as Epicurus was when he made his
				little indivisible atoms to move and tend to those places
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.36"/>
				
				which are under foot, as if the vacuum had feet, or its infinite space would permit one to talk of high or low. Indeed, a man would marvel what should cause Chrysippus
				to say, that the world was placed and situated directly in
				the midst, and that the matter thereof, from all eternity
				having possessed itself of the midst, yet is so compacted
				together that it remains for ever. For he writes this in
				his Fourth Book of Possible Things, vainly imagining
				there is a middle in that vast emptiness, and still more absurdly attributing unto that middle, which is not, the cause
				of the world's stability and continuance; he having often
				said in other writings of his that the substance is upheld
				and governed, partly by the motions tending to the midst
				of it, and partly by others parting from the midst of it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>As to the other oppositions which the Stoics make,
				who should fear them? As when they demand, how it is
				possible to maintain a fatal destiny and a divide providence, and how it can be otherwise but that we must admit of several Jupiters, when we assert the plurality of
				worlds. Now if there be an inconveniency in admitting
				many Jupiters, their opinions will appear far more absurd;
				for they imagine there are suns, and moons, Apollos, Dianas, and Neptunes innumerable, in innumerable changes
				and revolutions of worlds. But where is the necessity
				which lies upon us to grant that there must be many Jupiters if there be many worlds, seeing that each of them may
				be subject to a sovereign governor of the whole, a God
				endued with a suitable mind and ability, like to him whom
				we name the Lord and Father of all things? Or what
				shall hinder us from asserting that the several worlds must
				be subject to the providence and destiny of Jupiter, and
				that he has an eye to all things, directing all, and administering to them the principles, seeds, and causes of all
				things which are made ? For, while we often see here a
				body composed of several other distinct bodies,&mdash;for example,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.37"/>
				
				 the assembly of a town, an army, or a chorus,&mdash;
				in each of which bodies there is life, prudence, and understanding; so it cannot be impossible that, in the whole
				universe, ten or fifty or a hundred worlds which may be in
				it should all use the same reason, and all correspond with
				the same principle. For this order and disposition is very
				suitable to the Gods; for we must not make them kings
				of a swarm of bees who never stir out of their hives, or
				keep them fast imprisoned in matter, like those who affirm
				the Gods to be certain dispositions of the air, and powers
				of waters and fire, infused and mixed within, which arise
				and spring up together with the world, and in time are to
				be burnt and end with it,&mdash;not affording them the liberty of
				coachmen and pilots, but nailing them down to their bases
				like statues and images. For they enclose the Gods within matter, and that in so strict a manner as makes them
				liable to all the changes, alterations, and decays of it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>It is certainly more agreeable to the nature of the
				Gods to say that they are wholly at liberty, like Castor and
				Pollux, ready to succor such as are overtaken by bad
				weather at sea; for when they appear, the winds cease and
				the waves are calmed. Not that they navigate and are
				partakers of the same peril; but they only appear in the
				sky, and the danger is over. Thus do the Gods visit each
				world, and rule and provide for all things in them. Jupiter in Homer cast not his eyes far from the city of Troy
				into Thrace, and to the nomad Scythians along the river
				Ister; but the true Jupiter has several seemly and agreeable passages for his majesty from one world into another,
				not looking into the infinite vacuum without, nor regarding
				himself and nothing else, as some have imagined, but
				weighing the deeds of Gods and men, and the motions and
				revolutions of the stars. For the Divinity does not hate
				variety and changes, but takes great pleasure in them, as
				one may conjecture by the circuits, conversions, and mutations
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.38"/>
				
				 observable in the heavens. And therefore I conclude
				that the infinite number of worlds is a chimera, which has
				not the least probability of truth, and which cannot by any
				means admit of any God, but must be wholly guided by
				chance and fortune. Whereas the government and providence of a certain definite number of worlds has nothing in
				it that seems more laborious and unworthy than that which
				is employed in the direction of one alone, which is transformed, renewed, and reformed an infinite number of
				times.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>Having said this, I paused. And Philippus immediately cried out: Whether this be certain or not, I will
				not be too positive; but if we carry God beyond one world,
				it would more gratify me to know why we should make
				him the Creator only of five worlds and no more, and what
				proportion this number bears to that of the worlds, than to
				know why the word E I was inscribed upon this temple.
				For this is neither a triangular, a quadrate, a perfect, nor
				a cubic number, neither does it yield any elegancy to such
				as are delighted in this kind of sciences. As to what concerns the argument dawn from the number of elements,
				which Plato seems to have touched upon, it is obscure and
				improbable, and will not afford this consequence,&mdash;that,
				as there are formed from matter five sorts of regular bodies,
				which have equal angles and equal sides, and are environed
				with equal superficies, so there were from the beginning
				five worlds, made and formed of these five bodies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Yet Theodorus the Solian, said I, when he reads
				Plato's mathematics to his scholars, both keeps to the text
				and clearly expounds it, when he saith, the pyramid, octahedron, dodecahedron. icosahedron (which Plato lays
				down as the first bodies) are all beautiful both in their
				proportions and equalities; Nature cannot contrive and
				make better than these, nor perhaps so good. Yet they
				have not all the same constitution and origin; for the least
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.39"/>
				
				and slightest of the five is the pyramid; the greatest, which
				has most parts, is the dodecahedron; and of the other
				two, the icosahedron is greater than the octahedron by
				more than twofold, if you compare their number of triangles. And therefore it is impossible they should be all
				made at once, of one and the same matter; for the smallest and most subtile have been certainly more pliable to the
				hand of the workman who moved and fashioned the matter, and consequently were sooner made and shaped, than
				those which have stronger parts and a greater mass of
				bodies, and whose composition was more laborious and
				difficult, like the dodecahedron. Whence it follows that
				the pyramid was the first body, and not one of the others,
				which were by nature last produced. Now the way also
				to avoid this absurdity is to separate and divide matter into
				five worlds; here the pyramid (for she is the first and most
				simple), there the octahedron, and there the icosahedron;
				and out of that which exists first in every one of these the
				rest draw their original by the concretion of parts, by which
				every thing is changed into every thing, as Plato himself
				shows us by examples throughout. But it will suffice us
				briefly to learn thus much. Air is engendered by the extinction of fire, and the same being subtilized and rarefied
				produceth fire. Now by the seeds of these two we may
				find out the passions and transmutations of all. The seminary or beginning of fire is the pyramid, consisting of
				twenty-four first triangles; and the octahedron is the seminary of the air, consisting of forty-eight triangles of the
				same kind. So that the one element of air stands upon
				two of fire, joined together and condensed. And again,
				one body or element of air is divided into two of fire, which
				again, becoming thick and hard, is changed into water; so
				that, throughout, that which comes first into light gives
				easily birth unto the rest by transmutation. And so it
				comes to pass, that there is not merely one first principle
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.40"/>
				
				of all things; but one thing is so mixed with the origin
				of another, in the several changes and alterations of nature
				by motion, that the same name and denomination belong
				equally to all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>But here Ammonius interrupted him, and said:
				Notwithstanding that those things are so peremptorily and
				so pompously asserted by Theodorus, yet I shall wonder if
				he be not forced to make use of such suppositions as are
				destructive of themselves and one of another. For he will
				have it, that the five worlds he speaks of were not composed all at one time, but that that which was subtilest, and
				which gave least trouble in the making, came out first into
				being. And as if it were a consequent, and not a repugnant thing, he supposes that the matter does not always
				drive out into existence that which is most subtile and simple, but that sometimes the thickest, grossest, and heaviest
				parts do anticipate the more subtile in generation. But
				besides this, supposing that there be five primitive bodies
				or elements, and consequently that there be as many worlds,
				there are but four of those orders which he discourses rationally concerning. For as to the cube, he takes it away
				and removes it, as it were in a game of counters; for it is
				naturally unfit either to turn into any thing besides itself,
				or to yield that any of those other bodies be converted into
				it, inasmuch as the triangles of which they consist be not
				of the same sort. For all the rest consist in common of
				demi-triangles (or halves of equilateral triangles); but the
				proper subject of which the cube is particularly composed
				is the right isosceles triangle, which admits no inclination to a demi-triangle, nor can possibly be united and
				incorporated with it. If there be then five bodies, and consequently five worlds, and in each of these worlds the
				principle of generation be that body which is first produced,
				it must happen that, where the cube is the first in generation, none of the rest can possibly be produced, it being
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.41"/>
				
				contrary to its nature to change into any of them. Not to
				insist here, that Theodorus and those of his mind make
				the element or principle of which the dodecahedron is
				composed to be different from the rest, it not being that
				triangle which is termed scalene, with three unequal sides,
				out of which the pyramid, octahedron, and icosahedron,
				according to Plato, are produced; so that (said Ammonius
				laughing) you must solve these objections, or offer something new concerning the matter in debate.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato's discussion of triangles and the regular solids, Timaeus, pp. 53 C-56 C, with the commentaries See also Grote's Plato, Vol. III. p. 269. (G.)</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>And I answered him, that, for my part, I knew not
				at present how to say any thing which carried more probability. But perhaps (said I) it is better for a man to give
				an account of his own opinion than of another's. Therefore I say that, there being supposed from the beginning
				of things two several natures contrary to each other,&mdash;
				the one sensible, mutable, subject to generation, corruption,
				and change every way, the other spiritual and intelligible,
				and abiding always in the same state,&mdash;it would be very
				strange, my friends, to say that the spiritual nature admitteth of division and hath diversity and difference in it, and
				to be angry if a man will not allow the passible and corporeal nature to be wholly united in itself, without dividing
				it into many parts. For it is most suitable to the permanent and divine natures to be tied and linked to each other,
				and to avoid, as much as is possible, all division and separation; and yet, amongst incorporeal natures the power of
				diversity works greater differences in regard to essential
				forms and reason, than those of distance of place in the
				corporeal world. And therefore Plato, refuting those who
				hold this proposition, that all is one, asserts these five
				grounds and principles of all,&mdash;entity, identity, diversity,
				motion, and rest; which five immaterial principles being
				admitted, it is no marvel if Nature have made every one of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.42"/>
				
				these to be an imitation, though not exact, yet as perfect
				and agreeable as could be drawn, of a correspondent principle in the corporeal mystery, partaking, as much as can
				be, of its power and virtue. For it is very plain that the
				cube is most proper and agreeable to repose and rest, by
				reason of the stability and firmness of those plain surfaces
				of which it consists. And as to the pyramid, everybody
				soon sees and acknowledges the nature of fire in it, by the
				slenderness of its decreasing sides, and the sharpness of its
				angles; and the nature of the dodecahedron, apt to comprehend all the other figures, may seem more properly to
				be the corporeal image of Ens, or Being in the general,
				indifferent to this or that particular form or shape. And
				of the other two which remain, the icosahedron resembleth
				the principle of diversity, and the octahedron principally
				partakes of the identical nature. And thus from one of
				these the air is produced, which partakes of and borders
				upon every substance, under one and the same outward
				form and appearance; and the other has afforded us the
				element of water, which by mixture may put on the greatest diversity of qualities. Therefore if Nature requires a
				certain uniformity and harmony in all things, it must be
				then that there are neither more nor fewer worlds in the
				corporeal nature than there are patterns or samples in
				the incorporeal, to the end that each pattern or sample in
				the invisible nature may have its own primary position and
				power, answering to a secondary or derivative in the different constitution or composition of bodies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>And this may serve for an answer to those that wonder at our dividing Nature, subject to generation and alteration, into so many kinds. But I entreat you all further,
				attentively to consider with yourselves that, of the two first
				and supreme principles of all things,&mdash;that is to say, the
				unity, and the indefinite binary or duality,&mdash;this latter,
				being the element and chief origin of all deformity and disorder,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.43"/>
				
				 is termed infinity, and on the contrary, the nature of
				unity, determining and limiting the void infinity, which has
				no proportion nor termination, reduces it into form, and
				renders it in some manner capable of receiving a denomination which belongs only to sensible and particular things.
				Now these two general principles appear first in number;
				for the multitude is indeed no number, unless a certain
				form of the matter resulting out of indeterminate infinity
				is cut off, and bounded within respective limits, either
				shorter or longer. For then each multitude is made number, when once it is determined and limited by unity;
				whereas, if we take away unity, then the indeterminate
				duality brings all into confusion, and renders it without
				harmony, without number or measure. Now, the form not
				being the destruction of matter, but rather the order and
				the beauty of it, both these principles therefore must be
				within number, from whence ariseth the chief disparity and
				greatest difference. For the infinite and indeterminate
				principle is the cause of the even number; and the other
				better principle, which is the unity, is the father (as it
				were) of the odd number. So that the first even number
				is two, and the first odd number is three; of which is composed five by conjunction, which is by its composition common to both, but of power or nature not even but odd.
				For, since sensible and corporeal nature is divided into several parts, on account of its inborn necessity of diversity, it
				was necessary that the number of these parts should not
				be either the first even number, nor yet the first uneven or
				odd, but a third, consisting of both; to the end that it
				might be procreated out of both principles, viz. of that
				which causeth the even number, and of that which produceth the odd; for the one cannot be parted from the
				other, inasmuch as both have the nature, power, and force
				of a principle. These two principles being then joined
				together, the better one being mightier prevails over the indeterminate
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.44"/>
				
				 infinity or duality, which divideth the corporeal
				nature; and thus the matter being divided, the unity interposing itself between has hindered the universe from being
				divided and parted into two equal portions. But there has
				been a multitude of worlds caused by the diversity and disagreement of the infinite Nature; but this multitude was
				brought into an odd number by the virtue and power of
				identity, or the finite principle; and it was therefore odd,
				because the better principle would not suffer Nature to
				stretch itself further than was fitting. For if there had
				been nothing but pure and simple unity, the matter would
				have known no separation; but being mixed with the
				dividing nature of duality, it has by this means suffered
				separation and division; yet it has stopped here, by the
				odd numbers being the superior and master to the even.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>This is the reason why the ancients were used to
				express numbering or reckoning by <foreign lang="greek">pempa/sasqai</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">to count by
					fives.</hi> And I am of opinion that that word <foreign lang="greek">pa/nta</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">all,</hi> is
				derived from <foreign lang="greek">pe/nte</foreign>, which is to say <hi rend="italics">five,</hi> five being compounded of the first numbers. For all the other numbers
				being afterwards multiplied by others, they produce numbers different from themselves; whereas five, being multiplied by an even number, produceth a perfect ten, and
				multiplied by an odd number, representeth itself again;
				not to insist that it is composed of the two first tetragons
				or quadrate numbers (unity and four), and that, being the
				first number whose square is equivalent to the two squares
				before it, it composeth the fairest of right angled triangles,
				and is the first number which containeth the sesquilateral
				proportion. Perhaps all these reasons are not very pertinent to the discourse of the present dispute, it being better
				to allege that in this number there is a natural virtue of
				dividing, and that nature divideth many things by this
				number. For in ourselves she has placed five senses, and
				five parts of the soul, the vital, the sensitive, the concupiscible,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.45"/>
				
				 the irascible, and the rational; and as many fingers
				on each hand; and the most fruitful seed disperseth itself
				but into five, for we read nowhere of a woman that
				brought forth more than five at a birth. And the Egyptians
				also tell us that the Goddess Rhea was delivered of five
				Gods, giving us to understand in covert terms that of the
				same matter were procreated five worlds. And in the
				universe, the earth is divided into five zones, the heaven
				into five circles,&mdash;two arctics, two tropics, and one equinoctial in the midst. There are five revolutions of planets
				or wandering stars, inasmuch as the Sun, Venus, and
				Mercury make but one and the same revolution. And the
				construction of the world consists of an harmonical measure;
				even as our musical chords consist of the posture of five
				tetrachords, ranged orderly one after another, that is to say,
				those called <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/twn, me/swn, sunhmme/nwn, diezeugme/nwn</foreign>, and <foreign lang="greek">u(perbolai/wn</foreign>.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note prefixed to Plutarch's Treatise on Music. (G.)</note>
				The intervals also which are used in singing are five, diesis,
				semitone, tone, the tone and a half, and the double tone;
				so that Nature seems to delight more in making all things
				according to the number five, than she does in producing
				them in a spherical form, as Aristotle writeth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>But it will perhaps be demanded, why Plato refers
				the number of worlds to the five regular bodies or figures,
				saying that God made use of the number five in the fabric
				of the world, as it were transcribing and copying this; and
				then, having proposed a doubt and question of the number
				of the worlds, whether there be five, or one only, thereby
				clearly shows that his conjecture is grounded on this
				conceit of the five regular bodies. If now we may make
				a probable conjecture as to his opinion, we may believe
				that of necessity, with the diversity of these figures and
				bodies, there must presently ensue a difference and diversity of motions; as he himself teacheth, affirming that
				whatever is subtilized or condensed does, at the same time
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.46"/>
				
				with its alteration of substance, alter and change its place.
				For if from the air there is engendered fire, when the
				octahedron is dissolved and vanished into pyramids, or, on
				the contrary, if the air be produced from the fire pressed
				and squeezed up into the form of the octahedron, it is not
				possible it should remain there where it was before, but it
				flies and runs to another place, forcing and combating
				whatever stands in the way to oppose it. And he shows
				this more clearly and evidently by an example and similitude of fans, and such like things as drive away the chaff
				from the corn; for thus the elements driving the matter,
				and being driven by it, do always bring like to like, some
				taking up this place, others that, before the world was
				digested as now it is. The matter then being in that condition in which it is likely every thing is where God is not
				present, the five first qualities, or first bodies, having each
				their proper and peculiar inclinations and motions, went
				apart, not wholly and altogether, nor throughly divided
				and separated one from another; for when all was huddled
				in confusion, such as were surmounted went continually
				against their nature with the mightier. And therefore,
				some going on one side and others going on the other,
				hence it has happened that there have been as many portions and distinctions as there are divers kinds of first
				bodies; one of fire, not wholly pure, but inclining towards
				the form of fire; another of an ethereal nature, yet not
				wholly so, but inclining thereto; another of earth, not
				simple and mere earth, but inclining to the form of earth.
				But especially there was a communication of water and air;
				for these, as we have already mentioned, went their ways,
				replenished with divers other kinds. For God did not
				separate and distribute the matter, but having found it thus
				carelessly dissipated in itself, and each part being carried
				away in such great disorder and confusion, he ranged and
				ordered it into symmetry and proportion; and setting
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.47"/>
				
				reason over each as a guardian and governor, he made
				as many worlds as there were first bodies. However, in
				respect to Ammonius, let these Platonical notions pass for
				what they are worth. For my part, I will never be overzealous in this precise number of worlds; but this I will
				say, that those who hold there are more than one, yet not
				an infinite number, have as good grounds as others, seeing
				the matter does naturally spread itself and is diffused into
				many parts,&mdash;not resting in one, while yet it is contrary
				to reason that it should be infinitely extended. In short,
				let us here especially be mindful of the wise precepts of
				the Academy, and preserve ourselves upon such slippery
				ground as the controversy concerning the infinity of
				worlds, by refusing a too confident assent.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>And when I had finished this discourse, Demetrius
				said: Lamprias is very much in the right; for the Gods
				deceive us with multiplicities, not of shadows and impostures (as Euripides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Euripides, Frag. 925.</note> expresseth it), but even of realities and
				substances themselves, when we presume to be positive, as
				if we understood them in things of such weight and moment. But we must, as he advises us, return to our first
				question, which we seem to have forgotten. For what
				was said concerning the oracles remaining dumb and useless when the Daemons who presided over them were
				departed, even as we see musical instruments yield no harmony when the musician does not handle them,&mdash;this, I
				say, brings a greater question into debate, namely touching
				the cause and power by which these Daemons use to make
				their prophets and prophetesses to be ravished with enthusiasm and filled with fantastical imaginations. For to say
				the oracles are silent as being forsaken by the Daemons is
				nothing, unless we be first shown how (when they are
				present and govern them) they set them at work and make
				them prophesy.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.48"/>
            <p>Ammonius then taking up the discourse, Do you think,
					said he, that the Daemons are any thing else
					<quote rend="blockquote">Than wandering spirits clothed in finest air,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 125.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Hesiod says? For as to my part, I think the same difference which there is between one man and another,
					when they act in a tragedy or comedy, is also to be found
					in this life in souls that are clothed with bodies. So that
					there is nothing in this which is strange or contrary to
					reason, if souls meeting with other souls do imprint on
					them visions and apprehensions of future things, just as
					we show several things already done and come to pass, and
					prognosticate of those which have not yet happened,
					not only by the help of speech, but also by letters and
					writings, or by a bare touch, or a single look;&mdash;unless
					you, Lamprias, are of another opinion. For we heard but
					very lately, that you discoursed at large upon this subject
					with the strangers that came to Lebadea; but he that
					gave us this information could give us no particular account
					of what passed. No wonder, replied I, for several avocations and businesses intervening, occasioned by the oracle
					and the solemn sacrifice that was then performing, made
					our discourse very broken and interrupted. But now, says
					Ammonius, you have auditors at leisure, that are inquisitive and desirous of instruction, so that you may speak
					freely, and expect all the candor and consideration which
					you can desire.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>And the rest of the company making the like exhortations, having paused a while, I began after this manner: It so happened, Ammonius, that you did, without
				your knowledge, give occasion to the discourse which was
				then held; for if the Daemons be souls and spirits separated from bodies and having no communication with
				them, as you affirm, but according to the divine poet
				Hesiod,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.49"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">Are our kind guardians, walking here their rounds,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 123.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>why do we deprive the spirits and souls which are in
					bodies of the same power by which Daemons may foresee
					and foretell things to come? For it is not likely souls do
					acquire any property and power, when they abandon their
					bodies, wherewith they were not endowed before; but
					rather, we should think that they had always the same
					parts, but in a worse degree, when they were mixed with
					bodies, some of them being inapparent and hid, and others
					weak and obscure, like those who see through a thick mist
					or move in water, heavily and uneasily performing their
					operations, much desiring to be cured and so to recover
					what is their own, and to be discharged and purified of
					that which covers them. For as the sun does not then
					properly become bright when he has escaped out of the
					cloud,&mdash;for he is always so, though to our eyes, being
					clouded, he seems obscure and dark,&mdash;so the soul acquires
					not then the faculty of divining when gotten clear of the
					body, as from a cloud, but having the same before, is
					blinded by the commixture and confusion which she has
					with the mortal body. And this cannot seem strange or
					incredible, if we consider nothing else in the soul but the
					faculty of remembrance, which is, as it were, the reverse
					of divination, and if we reflect upon the miraculous power
					it hath of preserving things past, or, we should rather say,
					things present, for of what is past nothing remains, and
					all things do come into being and perish in the same moment, whether they be actions, or words, or passions; they
					all pass by and vanish as soon as they appear; for time,
					like the course of a river, passeth on, and carries every
					thing along with it. But this retentive faculty of the soul
					seizes upon these in some mysterious way, and gives a
					form and a being to those things which are no longer
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.50"/>
					
					present. For the oracle which was given to those of
					Thessaly, touching Arne, enjoined them to declare
					<quote rend="blockquote">The deaf man's hearing, and the blind man's sight.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>But memory is to us the hearing of things without voice,
					and the sight of things invisible; so that, as I now said,
					no marvel, if retaining the things which are no longer in
					being, the soul anticipates several of those which are still
					to come; for these do more concern her, and she does
					naturally sympathize with them, inclining and tending to
					things which are future; whereas, as to those which are
					past and have an end, she leaves them behind her, only
					retaining the bare remembrance of them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>Our souls then, having this inbred power,&mdash;though
				weak, obscure, and hardly able to express their apprehensions,&mdash;yet sometimes spread forth and recover themselves, either in dreams or in the time of sacrifice or
				religious worship, when the body is well purified and endued
				with a certain temperature proper to this effect or when
				the rational and speculative part, being released and freed
				from the solicitude after present things, joineth with the
				irrational and imaginative part to think of and represent
				what is to come. For it is not, as Euripides saith, that he
				is the best prophet who guesses well; but he is the wisest
				man, not whose guess succeeds well in the event, but who,
				whatever the event be, takes reason and probability for his
				guide. Now the faculty of divining, like blank paper, is
				void of any reason or determination of itself, but is susceptible of fantasies and presentiments; and without any
				ratiocination or discourse of reason, it touches on that which
				is to come, when it has withdrawn itself farthest from the
				present. And from this it withdraws by means of a certain disposition of body, by which that state is produced
				which we call inspiration or enthusiasm. Now the body
				is sometimes endued naturally with this disposition; but
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.51"/>
				
				most times the earth casts forth to men the sources and
				causes of several other powers and faculties, some of which
				carry men beside themselves into ecstasy and phrensy, and
				produce maladies and mortalities; others again are good,
				gentle, and profitable, as appears by those who have had
				the experience of them. But this spring, or wind, or
				spirit of divination is most holy and divine, whether it
				comes by itself through the air, or through the water of
				some spring. For, being infused and mixed with the body,
				it produceth an odd temperature and strange disposition in
				the soul, which a man cannot exactly express, though he
				may resemble or compare it to several things. For by
				heat and dilatation it seems to open certain pores that
				make a discovery of future things; like wine, which, causing fumes to ascend up into the head, puts the spirits into
				many unusual motions, and reveals things that were laid
				up in secret. For drunkenness and phrensy, if we will
				believe Euripides, have a near approach to the nature of
				divination, when the soul, being hot and fiery, banishes
				those fears to which prudence and sobriety are subject,
				and which extinguish and quench the spirit of divination.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>Furthermore, a man may say that dryness, being
				mixed with heat, attenuateth and subtilizeth the spirit, and
				makes it pure and of an ethereal nature and consistence;
				for the soul itself, according to Heraclitus, is of a dry constitution; whereas moisture does not only dim the sight
				and dull the hearing, but when mingled with the air and
				touching the superficies of mirrors, dusketh the brightness
				of the one and takes away the light of the other. Or perhaps, on the contrary, by some refrigeration and condensation of this spirit, like the tincture and hardening of iron,
				this part of the soul which does prognosticate may become
				more intense and get a perfect edge. Just as tin being
				melted with brass (which of itself is rare and spongeous)
				does drive it nearer and make it more massy and solid, and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.52"/>
				
				withal causeth it to look more bright and resplendent; so
				I cannot see any reason, why this prophetical exhalation,
				having some congruence and affinity with souls, may not
				fill up that which is lax and empty, and drive it more close
				together. For there are many things which have a reference and congruity one with another; as the bean is useful in dyeing purple, and soda in dyeing saffron, if they
				be mixed therewith; and as Empedocles says,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Linen is dyed with the bright saffron's flower.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And we have learned of you, Demetrius, that only the
					river Cydnus cleaneth the knife consecrated to Apollo, in
					the city of Tarsus in Cilicia, and that there is no other
					water which can scour and cleanse it. So in the town of
					Olympia, they temper ashes with the water of the river
					Alpheus, with which they make a mortar wherewith they
					plaster the altar there; but if this be attempted to be done
					by the water of any other river, it is all to no purpose.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>It is no wonder then if, the earth sending up many
				exhalations, only those of this sort transport the soul with
				a divine fury, and give it a faculty of foretelling future
				things. And, without a doubt, what is related touching
				the oracle of this place does herewith agree; for it is here
				where this faculty of divining first showed itself, by means
				of a certain shepherd, who chanced to fall down and began to utter enthusiastic speeches concerning future events;
				of which at first the neighbors took no notice; but when
				they saw what he foretold came to pass, they had him in
				admiration; and the most learned among the Delphians,
				speaking of this man, are used to call him by the name of
				Coretas. The soul seems to me to mix and join itself with
				this prophetic exhalation, just as the eye is affected with
				the light. For the eye, which has a natural property and
				faculty of seeing, would be wholly useless without the
				light; so the soul, having this faculty and property of foreseeing
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.53"/>
				
				 future things, as an eye, has need of a proper object which may enlighten and sharpen it. And therefore
				the ancients took the sun and Apollo to be the same God;
				and those who understand the beauty and wisdom of analogy or proportion do tell us, that as the body is to the soul,
				the sight to the mind, and light to truth, so is the sun with
				reference to Apollo; affirming the sun to be the offspring
				proceeding perpetually from Apollo, who is eternal and
				who continually bringeth him forth. For as the sun enlightens and excites the visive powers of the senses, so
				Apollo does excite the prophetic virtue in the soul.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>Those then that imagined that both were one and the
				same God have with good reason dedicated and consecrated
				this oracle to Apollo and to the earth, deeming it to be the
				sun which imprinted this temperature and disposition on
				the earth, from whence arose this predictive exhalation.
				For as Hesiod, with far better reason than other philosophers, calls the earth
				<quote rend="blockquote">The well-fixed seat of all things;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Theogony, 117.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so do we esteem it eternal, immortal, and incorruptible.
					But as to the virtues and faculties which are in it, we believe that some fail in one place, and spring up anew in
					another. It seems also (for so some experiments incline
					us to conjecture) that these transitions, changes, and revolutions in process of time do circulate and return to the
					same place, and begin again where they left off. In some
					countries we see lakes and whole rivers and not a few
					fountains and springs of hot waters have sometimes failed
					and been entirely lost, and at others have fled and absconded themselves, being hidden and concealed under the
					earth; but perhaps some years after do appear again in the
					same place, or else run hard by. And so of metal mines,
					some have been quite exhausted, as the silver ones about
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.54"/>
					
					Attica; and the same has happened to the veins of brass
					ore in Euboea, of which the best blades were made and
					hardened in cold water, as the poet Aeschylus tells us,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Taking his sword, a right Euboean blade.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is not long since the quarry of Carystus has ceased to
					yield a certain soft stone, which was wont to be drawn into a fine thread; for I suppose some here have seen towels,
					net-work, and coifs woven of that thread, which could
					not be burnt; but when they were soiled with using, people flung them into the fire, and took them thence white
					and clean, the fire only purifying them. But all this is vanished; and there is nothing but some few fibres or hairy
					threads, lying up and down scatteringly in the grain of the
					stones, to be seen now in the quarry.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>Aristotle and his followers affirm that all this proceeds from an exhalation within the earth, and when this
				fails or removes to another place, or revives and recovers
				itself again, the phenomena proceeding from them do so
				too. The same must we say of the prophetical exhalations
				which spring from the earth, that their virtue also is not
				immortal, but may wax old and decay; for it is not unlikely that great floods of rain and showers do extinguish
				them, and that the claps of thunder do dissipate them; or
				else (which I look upon to be the principal cause) they
				are sunk lower into the earth or utterly destroyed by the
				shock of earthquakes and the confusion that attends them,
				as here in this place there still remain the tragical monuments of that great earthquake that overthrew the city.
				And in the town of Orchomenus, they say, when the pestilence carried away such multitudes of people, the oracle
				of Tiresias of a sudden ceased, and remains mute to this
				day. And whether the like has not happened to the oracles in Cilicia, as we have heard it hath, no man can better
				inform us than you, Demetrius.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.55"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>I cannot tell, says Demetrius, how things are at
				present in those parts, for you all know I have been long
				absent from thence; but when I was there, both that of
				Mopsus and of Amphilochus flourished and were in great
				esteem. And as to the oracle of Mopsus, I can from my
				own knowledge tell you a strange story about it. The
				Governor of Cicilia was a man inclining to scepticism
				about the Gods,&mdash;through the infirmity of his unbelief, I
				think, for otherwise he was an oppressor and a worthless
				man,&mdash;and he had about him several Epicureans, who are
				wont to mock at the belief of such things as seem contrary to reason, as they themselves say, standing much upon
				their goodly natural philosophy. He sent a freed servant
				of his to the oracle, like a spy into an enemy's camp, with
				a letter sealed, wherein was the question he was to ask
				the oracle, nobody knowing the contents thereof. This
				man then, as the custom of the place is, remaining all
				night in the temple-porch asleep, related the next morning
				the dream which he had; for he thought he saw a very
				handsome man stand before him, who said only this word,
				Black, to him, and nothing else, for he vanished away immediately. This seemed to us very impertinent, though
				we could not tell what to make of it; but the governor
				marvelled at it, and was so nettled with it, that he had the
				oracle in great veneration ever since; for, opening the letter, he showed this question which was therein: Shall I
				sacrifice to thee a white bull or a black? Which dashed
				his Epicureans quite out of countenance, and he offered
				the sacrifice required, and to the day of his death continued a devout admirer of Mopsus.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>When Demetrius had given us this relation, he held
				his peace. And I, being desirous to put an end to this
				conference, cast mine eyes on Philippus and Ammonius,
				who sat together; and they, I thought, looked as if they
				had something to say to me, and therefore I kept silent.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.56"/>
				
				With that Ammonius: Philippus hath something to offer,
				Lamprias, touching what hath been debated; for he thinks,
				as well as other folks, that Apollo and the sun are the
				same God. But the question which I propose is of greater consequence; for just now in our discourse we have
				taken away divination from the Gods, and openly attributed
				it to the Daemons, and now we are for excluding them
				also, and dispossessing them of the oracle and three-footed
				stool, referring the cause, or rather the nature and essence,
				of divination to exhalations, winds, and vapors; for these
				opinions carry us still farther off from the Gods, introducing such a cause of this event as Euripides makes Polyphemus to allege:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The earth by force, whether she will or no
				</l>
                     <l>Does for my cattle make the grass to grow.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Cyclops, 332.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Yet he says that he sacrificed his herds, not to the Gods,
					but to himself and his own belly, <q direct="unspecified">the greatest of all
						Daemons;</q> whereas we offer them sacrifices and prayers
					to obtain an answer from their oracles; but to what purpose, if it be true that souls are naturally endued with the
					faculty of prediction, and that the chief cause that excites
					this faculty and virtue is a certain temperature of air and
					winds? And what signifies then the sacred institutions
					and setting apart these religious prophetesses, for the giving of answers? And why do they return no answer at
					all, unless the sacrifice tremble all over, even from the very
					feet, whilst the wine is poured on its head? For it is not
					enough to wag the head, as other beasts do which are appointed for sacrifices; but this quaking and shivering must
					be universal throughout all parts of the body, and that
					with a trembling noise; for if this be not done, they say
					that the oracle will give no answer, neither is the priestess
					even introduced. For it is very proper and suitable for
					them to do and believe thus who ascribe the impulses of
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.57"/>
					
					prophetical inspiration either to a God or a Daemon, but by
					no means for those that are of your opinion. For the exhalation which springeth out of the ground, whether the
					beast tremble or not, will always, if it be present, cause a
					ravishment and transport of spirit, and dispose the soul
					alike, not only of Pythia, but of any one else that first cometh or is presented. And it must needs seem absurd to
					set apart one certain woman for the delivery of these oracles, and to oblige her to virginity and chastity all her
					days, when the thing is referred to such a cause. For as
					to that Coretas, whom the Delphians will needs have to be
					the first that happened to fall upon this chink or crevice of
					the ground, and gave the first proof of the virtue of the
					place,&mdash;he, I say, seems to me not at all to differ from
					other herdsmen or shepherds, supposing what is reported
					of him to be true, as I believe it is not. And truly, when
					I call to mind of what benefit this oracle has been unto
					the Greeks, not only in their wars and building of cities,
					but also in the stresses of plague and famine, methinks it
					is very unfit to refer its invention and original unto mere
					chance, rather than to God and divine providence. But
					I would willingly have you, Lamprias, says he, to speak on
					this point, and I pray you, Philippus, to have patience a
					while. With all my heart, replied Philippus, and I dare
					undertake the same for all the company.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>And, as to my part, quoth I, O Philippus! I am
				not only much moved, but also ashamed, considering my
				youth, in the presence of so many wise and grave personages, to appear as if I endeavored by sophistry to impose
				upon them, and to destroy and evacuate what sage and
				holy men have determined concerning the divine nature
				and power. But though I am young, yet Plato was old
				and wise as you are, and he shall be my example and advocate in this case. He reprehended Anaxagoras for applying himself too much to natural causes, always following
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.58"/>
				
				and pursuing the necessary and material cause of the passions and affections incident to bodies, and omitting the
				final and efficient, which are much better and more considerable principles than the other. But Plato either first, or
				most of all the philosophers, hath joined both of these
				principles together, attributing to God the causality of all
				things that are according to reason, and yet not depriving
				matter of a necessary or passive concurrence; but acknowledging that the adorning and disposing of all this sensible
				world does not depend on one single and simple cause,
				but took its being from the conjunction and fellowship of
				matter with reason. This may be illustrated by the works
				of art; as, for example, without going any further, the
				foot of the famous cup which is amongst the treasure of
				this temple, which Herodotus calls a Hypocrateridion, that
				has for the material causes fire and iron, and pliableness
				by means of fire, and the tincture in water, without which
				such a piece of work could not be wrought. But the
				principal cause, and that which is most properly so called,
				which wrought by all these, was art and reason. And we
				see the name of the artist set on all such pieces, according to that,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Twas Thasian Polygnotus, Aglaophon's son,
				</l>
                     <l>That drew this draught of conquer'd Ilium.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But yet, without colors mixed and confounded with one
					another, it had been impossible to have done a piece so
					pleasing to the eye. Should one come then and enquire
					into the material cause, searching into and discoursing
					concerning the alterations and mutations which the vermilion receives mixed with ochre, or the ceruse with black,
					would he thereby lessen the credit of the painter Polygnotus? And so he that shall discourse how iron is both
					hardened and mollified, and how, being softened in the
					fire, it becomes obedient to them who by beating it drive
					it out in length and breadth; and afterwards, being plunged
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.59"/>
					
					into fresh water, by the coldness of it becomes hardened
					and condensed after it was softened and rarefied by the
					fire, and acquires a firmness and temper which Homer
					calls the strength of the iron,&mdash;does he, because of this,
					e'er the less attribute the cause of the work to the workman? I do not think he does; for those who examine the
					virtues and properties of medicinal drugs do not thereby
					condemn the art of physic. Just as when Plato says that
					we see because the light of the eye is mixed with the
					clearness of the sun, and that we hear by the percussion
					of the air, yet this does not hinder but that we have the
					faculty of seeing and hearing from Divine Providence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>In a word, generation, as I have said, proceeding
				from two causes, the chiefest and most ancient poets and
				divines have stuck only to the first and most excellent of
				these, having on all occasions these known words in their
				mouths,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Jove, the beginning, middle, source of all;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Orphic Fragments, VI. 10 (Hermann).</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but as to the necessary and natural causes, they concern
					not themselves with them. Whereas their successors, who
					were for that reason called natural philosophers, took a
					different course; for they, forsaking this admirable and
					divine principle, ascribe all matter and the passions of it
					to the motions, mutations, and mixtures of its parts. So
					that both of these are defective in their methods, because
					they omit, through ignorance or design, the one the efficient, the others the material cause. Whereas he that
					first pointed at both causes, and manifestly joined with the
					reason, which freely operateth and moveth, the matter,
					which necessarily is obedient and passive, does defend both
					himself and us from all calumny and censure. For we do
					not deprive divination either of God or of reason; seeing
					we allow it for its subject the soul of man, and for its
					instrument an enthusiastic exhalation. For first, the earth,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.60"/>
					
					out of which exhalations are generated, and then the sun,
					which in and upon the earth works all the infinite possibilities of mixture and alteration, are. in the divinity of our
					forefathers, esteemed Gods. And hereunto if we add the
					Daemons as superintendents and guardians of this temperature, as of a harmony and consort, who in due time
					slacken or stretch the virtue of this exhalation, sometimes
					taking from it the too great activity which it has to torment the soul and transport it beyond itself, and mingling
					with it a virtue of moving, without causing pain to those
					that are possessed with it; in all this it seems to me that
					we do nothing that can look strange or impossible or unagreeable to reason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>And when we offer victims before we come to the
				oracle, and crown them with garlands of flowers and pour
				wine on their heads, I see we do not any thing in all this
				that is absurd or repugnant to this opinion of ours. For
				the priests, who offer the sacrifices, and pour out the holy
				wine thereon, and observe their motions and tremblings,
				do this for no other reason besides that of learning whether
				they can receive an answer from the oracle. For the animal which is offered to the Gods must be pure, entire, and
				sound, both as to soul and body. Now it is not very hard
				to discover the marks of the body; and as to the soul,
				they make an experiment of it in setting meal before the
				bulls and presenting pease to the boars; for if they will
				not taste them, it is a certain sign they be not sound. As
				to goats, cold water is a trial for them; for if the beast
				does not seem to be moved and affected when the water is
				poured upon her, this is an evident sign that her soul is
				not right according to Nature. And supposing it should
				be granted that it is a certain and unquestionable sign that
				God will give an answer when the sacrifice thus drenched
				stirs, and that when it is otherwise he vouchsafes none, I
				do not sec herein any thing that disagrees with the account
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.61"/>
				
				of oracles which I have given. For every natural virtue
				produceth the effect to which it is ordained better or worse,
				according as its season is more or less proper; and it is
				likely God gives us signs whereby we may know whether
				the opportunity be gone or not.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>As for my part, I believe the exhalation itself which
				comes out of the ground is not always of the same kind,
				being at one time slack, and at another strong and vigorous; and the truth of that experiment which I use to
				prove it is attested by several strangers, and by all those
				which serve in the temple. For the room where those do
				wait who come for answers from the oracle is sometimes
				&mdash;though not often and at certain stated times, but as it
				were by chance&mdash;filled with such a flagrant odor and
				scent, that no perfumes in the world can exceed it, and
				this arises, as it were, out of a spring, from the sanctuary
				of the temple. And this proceeds very likely from its
				heat or some other power or faculty which is in it; and if
				peradventure this seems to any body an unlikely thing,
				such a one will, however, allow that the prophetess Pythia
				hath that part of the soul unto which this wind and blast
				of inspiration approacheth moved by variety of passions
				and affections, sometimes after one sort and sometimes another, and that she is not always in the same mood and
				temper, like a fixed and immutable harmony which the
				least alteration or change of such and such proportions
				destroys. For there are several vexations and passions,
				which agitate bodies and slide into the soul, that she perceives, but more that she does not, in which case it would
				be better that she should tarry away and not present herself to this divine inspiration, as not being clean and void
				of perturbations, like an instrument of music exquisitely
				made, but at present in disorder and out of tune. For
				wine does not at all times alike surprise the drunkard,
				neither does the sound of the flute always affect in the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.62"/>
				
				same manner him who dances to it. For the same persons
				are sometimes more and sometimes less transported beyond
				themselves, and more or less inebriated, according to the
				present disposition of their bodies. But especially the
				imaginative part of the soul is subject to change and sympathize together with the body, as is apparent from dreams;
				for sometimes we are mightily troubled with many and confused visions in our dreams, and at other times there is a
				perfect calm, undisturbed by any such images or ideas.
				We all know Cleon, a native of Daulia, who used to say
				to himself that in the many years in which he hath lived
				he never had any dream. And among the ancients, the
				same is related of Thrasymedes of Heraea. The cause
				of this lies in the complexion and constitution of bodies,
				as is seen by melancholy people, who are much subject to
				dreams in the night, and their dreams sometimes prove
				true. Inasmuch as such persons' fancies run sometimes
				on one thing and at other times on another, they must
				thereby of necessity now and then light right, as they that
				shoot often must hit sometimes.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="51">
            <p>When therefore the imaginative part of the soul
				and the prophetic blast or exhalation have a sort of harmony and proportion with each other, so as the one, as it
				were in the nature of a medicament, may operate upon the
				other, then happens that enthusiasm or divine fury which
				is discernible in prophets and inspired persons. And, on
				the contrary, when the proportion is lost, there can be no
				prophetical inspiration, or only such as is as good as none;
				for then it is a forced fury, not a natural one, but violent
				and turbulent, such as we have seen to have happened in
				the prophetess Pythia who is lately deceased. For certain
				pilgrims being come for an answer from the oracle, it is
				said the sacrifice endured the first effusion without stirring
				or moving a jot, which made the priests, out of an excess
				of zeal, to continue to pour on more, till the beast was
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.63"/>
				
				almost drowned with cold water; but what happened hereupon to the prophetess Pythia? She went down into the
				hole against her will; but at the first words which she uttered, she plainly showed by the hoarseness of her voice
				that she was not able to bear up against so strong an inspiration (like a ship under sail, oppressed with too much wind),
				but was possessed with a dumb and evil spirit. Finally,
				being horribly disordered and running with dreadful
				screeches towards the door to get out, she threw herself
				violently on the ground, so that not only the pilgrims fled
				for fear, but also the high priest Nicander and the other
				priests and religious which were there present; who entering within a while took her up, being out of her senses;
				and indeed she lived but few days after. For these reasons
				it is that Pythia is obliged to keep her body pure and clean
				from the company of men, there being no stranger permitted to converse with her. And before she goes to the
				oracle, they are used by certain marks to examine whether
				she be fit or no, believing that the God certainly knows
				when her body is disposed and fit to receive, without endangering her person, this enthusiastical inspiration. For
				the force and virtue of this exhalation does not move
				all sorts of persons, nor the same persons in like manner,
				nor as much at one time as at another; but it only gives
				beginning, and, as it were, kindles those spirits which are
				prepared and fitted to receive its influence. Now this
				exhalation is certainly divine and celestial, but yet not
				incorruptible and immortal, nor proof against the eternity
				of time, which subdues all things below the moon, as
				our doctrine teaches,&mdash;and, as some say, all things
				above it, which, weary and in despair as regards eternity and infinity, are apt to be suddenly renewed and
				changed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="52">
            <p>But these things, said I, I must advise you and
				myself often and seriously to consider of, they being liable
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.64"/>
				
				to many disputes and objections, which our leisure will
				not suffer to particularize; and therefore we must remit
				them, together with the questions which Philippus proposes touching Apollo and the sun, to another opportunity.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>