<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Comparationis Aristophanis et Menandri compendium</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.122">
      <body>
         <head>An abstract of a comparison betwixt Aristophanes and Menander.</head>
         <pb id="v.3.p.11"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>To speak in sum and in general, he prefers Menander by far; and as to particulars, he adds what here
				ensues. Aristophanes, he saith, is importune, theatric, and
				sordid in his expression; but Menander not so at all. For
				the rude and vulgar person is taken with the things the
				former speaketh; but the well-bred man will be quite out
				of humor with them. I mean, his opposed terms, his
				words of one cadence, and his derivatives. For the one
				makes use of these with due observance and but seldom,
				and bestows care upon them; but the other frequently,
				unseasonably, and frigidly. <q direct="unspecified">For he is much commended,</q>
				said he, <q direct="unspecified">for ducking the chamberlains, they being indeed
					not chamberlains (<foreign lang="greek">tami/ai</foreign>) but bugbears (<foreign lang="greek">*lami/ai</foreign>).</q> And
				again,&mdash;<q direct="unspecified">This rascal breathes out nothing but roguery and
					affidavitry;</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Beat him well in his belly with the entrails and the guts;</q> and, <q direct="unspecified">I shall laugh till I go to Laughington (<foreign lang="greek">*ge/lan</foreign>);</q> and, <q direct="unspecified">Thou poor sharded ostracized pot,
						what shall I do with thee?</q> and, <q direct="unspecified">To you women surely he
							is a mad plague, for he grew up himself among these mad
							worts;</q>&mdash;and, <q direct="unspecified">Look here, how the moths have eaten
								away my crest;</q> and, <q direct="unspecified">Bring me hither the gorgon-backed
									circle of my shield;</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Give me the round-backed circle
										of a cheese-cake;</q>&mdash;and much more of such like stuff.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristoph. Knights, 437, 455; Thesm. 455; Acharn. 1109, 1124.</note>
				There is then in the structure of his words something
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.12"/>
				
				tragic and something comic, something blustering and
				something prosaic, an obscurity, a vulgarness, a turgidness, and a strutting, with a nauseous prattling and fooling
				And as his style has so great varieties and dissonances in
				it, so neither doth he give to his persons what is fitting and
				proper to each,&mdash;as state (for instance) to a prince, force
				to an orator, innocence to a woman, meanness of language
				to a poor man, and sauciness to a tradesman,&mdash;but he
				deals out to every person, as it were by lot, such words as
				come next to his hand, and you would scarce discern
				whether he that is talking be a son, a father, a peasant, a
				God, an old woman, or a hero.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But now Menander's phrase is so well turned and
				contempered with itself, and so everywhere conspiring,
				that, while it traverses many passions and humors and is
				accommodated to all sorts of persons, it still shows the
				same, and even retains its semblance in trite, familiar, and
				every-day expressions. And if his master do now and
				then require something of rant and noise, he doth but (like
				a skilful flutist) set open all the holes of his pipe, and then
				presently stop them again with good decorum and restore
				the tune to its natural state. And though there be a great
				number of excellent artists of all professions, yet never did
				any shoemaker make the same sort of shoe, or tireman
				the same sort of visor, or tailor the same sort of garment,
				to fit a man, a woman, a child, an old man, and a slave.
				But Menander hath so addressed his style, as to proportion
				it to every sex, condition, and age; and this, though he
				took the business in hand when he was very young, and
				died in the vigor of his composition and action, when, as
				Aristotle tells us, authors receive most and greatest improvement in their styles. If a man shall then compare
				the middle and last with the first of Menander's plays, he
				will by them easily conceive what others he would have
				added to them, had he had but longer life.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.13"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>He adds further, that of dramatic exhibitors, some
				address themselves to the crowd and populace, and others
				again to a few; but it is a hard matter to say which of
				them all knew what was befitting in both the kinds. But
				Aristophanes is neither grateful to the vulgar, nor tolerable
				to the wise; but it fares with his poesy as it doth with a
				courtesan who, when she finds she is now stricken and past
				her prime, counterfeits a sober matron, and then the vulgar
				cannot endure her affectation, and the better sort abominate
				her lewdness and wicked nature. But Menander hath
				with his charms shown himself every way sufficient for
				satisfaction, being the sole lecture, argument, and dispute
				at theatres, schools, and at tables; hereby rendering his
				poesy the most universal ornament that was ever produced
				by Greece, and showing what and how extraordinary his
				ability in language was, while he passes every way with an
				irresistible persuasion, and wins every man's ear and understanding who has knowledge of the Greek tongue. And
				for what other reason in truth should a man of parts and
				erudition be at the pains to frequent the theatre, but for the
				sake of Menander only? And when are the play-houses
				better filled with men of letters, than when his comic
				mask is exhibited? And at private entertainments among
				friends, for whom doth the table more justly make room or
				Bacchus give place than for Menander? To philosophers
				also and hard students (as painters are wont, when they
				have tired out their eyes at their work, to divert them to
				certain florid and green colors) Menander is a repose from
				their auditors and intense thinkings, and entertains their
				minds with gay shady meadows refreshed with cool and
				gentle breezes.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>He adds, moreover, that though this city breeds at this
				time very many and excellent representers of comedy, Menander's plays participate of a plenteous and divine salt, as
				if they were made of the very sea out of which Venus herself
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.14"/>
				
				 sprang. But that of Aristophanes is harsh and coarse,
				and hath in it an angry and biting sharpness. And for my
				part I cannot tell where his so much boasted ability lies,
				whether in his style or persons. The parts he acts I am
				sure are quite over-acted and depraved. His knave (for
				instance) is not fine, but dirty; his peasant is not assured,
				but stupid; his droll is not jocose, but ridiculous; and his
				lover is not gay, but lewd. So that to me the man seems
				not to have written his poesy for any temperate person, but
				to have intended his smut and obscenity for the debauched
				and lewd, his invective and satire for the malicious and
				ill-humored.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>