<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Praecepta gerendae reipublicae</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.118">
      <body>
         <head>Political precepts.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.97"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>If ever, O Menemachus, that saying of Nestor's in
				Homer,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There is no Greek can contradict or mend
					</l>
                     <l>What you have said, yet to no perfect end
					</l>
                     <l>Is your speech brought,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 55.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>might pertinently be made use of and applied, it is against
					those exhorting, but nothing teaching nor any way instructing, philosophers. For they do (in this respect)
					resemble those who are indeed careful in snuffing the
					lamps, but negligent in supplying them with oil. Seeing therefore that you, being by reason moved to engage
					yourself in the affairs of the state, desire, as becomes the
					nobility of your family,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Both to speak and act heroicly</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 443.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>in the service of your country, and that, not having attained to such maturity of age as to have observed the life
					of a wise and philosophical man openly spent in the transactions of the state and public debates, and to have been
					a spectator of worthy examples represented not in word
					but in deed, you request me to lay you down some political precepts and instructions; I think it no ways becoming
					me to give you a denial, but heartily wish that the work
					may be worthy both of your zeal and my forwardness.
					Now I have, according to your request, made use in this
					my discourse of sundry and various examples.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.98"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>First then for the administration of state affairs, let
				there be laid, as a firm and solid foundation, an intention
				and purpose, having for its principles judgment and
				reason, and not any impulse from vain-glory, emulation,
				or want of other employment. For as those who have
				nothing grateful to them at home frequently spend their
				time in the forum, though they have no occasion that requires it; so some men, because they have no business of
				their own worth employing themselves in, thrust themselves into public affairs, using policy as a divertisement.
				Many also, having been by chance engaged in the negotiations of the commonweal, and being cloyed with them
				cannot yet easily quit them; in which they suffer the same
				with those who, going on board a ship that they may be
				there a little tossed, and being after carried away into the
				deep, send forth many a long look towards the shore, being
				sea-sick and giddy-headed, and yet necessitated to stay and
				accommodate themselves to their present fortune.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Past is the lovely pleasure
					</l>
                     <l>They took, when th' sea was calm and weather bright,
					</l>
                     <l>In walking at their leisure
					</l>
                     <l>On the ship's deck,
					</l>
                     <l>Whilst her sharp beak
					</l>
                     <l>With merry gale,
					</l>
                     <l>And full blown sail,
					</l>
                     <l>Did through the surging billows cut its course aright.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And these do most of all discredit the matter by their
					repenting and being discontented, when either hoping for
					glory they fall into disgrace, or expecting to become formidable to others by their power they are engaged in affairs
					full of dangers and troubles. But he who on a well
					grounded principle of reason undertakes to act in the
					public, as an employ very honorable and most beseeming
					him, is dismayed by none of these things; nor does he
					therefore change his opinion. For we must not come to
					the management of the commonweal on a design of
					gaining and growing rich by it, as Stratocles and Dromo
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.99"/>
					
					slides exhorted one another to the golden harvest,&mdash;so
					in mirth terming the tribunal, or place of making harangues
					to the people,&mdash;nor yet as seized with some sudden fit of
					passion, as did heretofore Caius Gracchus, who having,
					whilst his brothers' misfortunes were hot, withdrawn himself to a retired life most remote from public affairs, did
					afterwards, inflamed by indignation at the injuries and
					affronts put on him by some persons, thrust himself into
					the state, where being soon filled with affairs and glory,
					when he sought to desist and desired change and repose,
					he could not (so great was it grown) find how to lay down
					his authority, but perished with it. And as for those who
					through emulation frame themselves for the public as
					actors for the stage, they must needs repent of their
					design, finding themselves under a necessity of either serving those whom they think themselves worthy to govern,
					or disobliging those whom they desire to please. Now I
					am of opinion, that those who by chance and without foresight stumble upon policy, falling as it were into a pit,
					connot but be troubled and repent; whereas they that go
					leisurely into it, with preparation and a good resolution,
					comfort themselves moderately in all occurrences, as having
					no other end of their actions but the discharging of their
					duty with honor.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Now they that have thus grounded their choice within themselves, and rendered it immovable and difficult to be
				changed, must set themselves to contemplate that disposition of the citizens which, being compounded (as it were)
				of all their natures, appears most prevalent among them.
				For the endeavoring presently to form the manners and
				change the nature of a people is neither easy nor safe, but
				a work requiring much time and great authority. But as
				wine in the beginning is overcome by the nature of the
				drinker, but afterwards, gently warming him and mixing
				itself in his veins, assimilates and changes him who drinks
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.100"/>
				
				it into its own likeness, so must a statesman, till he has by
				his reputation and credit obtained a leading power amongst
				the people, accommodate himself to the dispositions of the
				subjects, knowing how to consider and conjecture those
				things with which the people are naturally delighted and
				by which they are usually drawn. The Athenians, to wit,
				are easily moved to anger, and not difficultly changed to
				mercy, more willing to suspect quickly than to be informed
				by leisure; and as they are readier to help mean and inconsiderable persons, so do they embrace and esteem facetious and merry speeches; they are exceedingly delighted
				with those that praise them, and very little offended with
				such as jeer them; they are terrible even to their governors, and yet courteous to their very enemies. Far other
				is the disposition of the Carthaginians, severe, rigid, obsequious to their rulers, harsh to their subjects, most abject
				in their fear, most cruel in their anger, firm in their resolutions, untractable, and hard to be moved by sportive and
				pleasant discourse. Should Cleon have requested them to
				defer their assembly, because he had sacrificed to the Gods
				and was to feast certain strangers, they would not have
				risen up, laughing and clapping their hands for joy; nor,
				if Alcibiades, as he was making an harangue to them, had
				let slip a quail from under his cloak, would they have
				striven who should catch her and restore her to him again,
				but would rather have killed them both on the place, as
				contemning and deriding them; since they banished Hanno
				for making use of a lion to carry his baggage to the army,
				accusing him of affecting tyranny. Neither do I think,
				that the Thebans, if they had been made masters of their
				enemies' letters, would have foreborne looking into them, as
				did the Athenians, when, having taken the messengers of
				Philip who were carrying a letter superscribed to Olympias, they would not so much as open it, or discover the
				conjugal secrets of an absent husband, written to his wife.
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.101"/>
				
				Nor yet do I believe that the Athenians on the other side
				would have patiently suffered the haughtiness and disdain
				of Epaminondas, when, refusing to answer an accusation
				brought against him, he rose up from the theatre, and
				went away through the midst of the assembly to the place
				of public exercises. And much less am I of opinion that
				the Spartans would have endured the contumely and scurrility of Stratocles, who persuaded the people to offer
				sacrifices of thanksgiving to the Gods, as having obtained
				the victory, and afterwards, when, being truly informed of
				the loss they had received, they were angry with him, asked
				them what injury they had sustained in having through
				his means spent three days merrily.</p>
            <p>Courtly flatterers indeed, like to quail-catchers, by imitating the voices and assimilating themselves to the manners of kings, chiefly insinuate into their favors and entrap
					them by deceit; but it is not convenient for a statesman to
					imitate the people's manners, but to know them, and make
					use of those things toward every person by which he is
					most likely to be taken. For the ignorance of men's
					humors brings no less disorders and obstacles in commonweals than in the friendships of kings.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>When therefore you shall have already gotten power
				and authority amongst the people, then must you endeavor
				to reform their disposition, treating them gently, and by
				little and little drawing them to what is better. For the
				changing of a multitude is a difficult and laborious work.
				But as for your own manners and behavior, so compose
				and adorn them, as knowing that you are henceforth to
				lead your life on an open stage; and if it is no easy task
				for you wholly to extirpate vice out of your soul, at least
				take away and retrench those offences which are most
				notorious and apparent. For you cannot but have heard
				how Themistocles, when he designed to enter upon the
				management of public affairs, withdrew himself from drinking
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.102"/>
				
				 and revelling, and fell to watching, fasting, and studying, saying to his intimate friends, that Miltiades's trophy
				suffered him not to sleep. And Pericles also so changed
				himself, both as to the comportment of his body and his
				manner of living, that he walked gravely, discoursed affably, always showed a staid and settled countenance, continually kept his hand under his robe, and went only that
				way which led to the assembly and the senate. For a
				multitude is not so tractable as that it should be easy for
				every one to take it with safety, but it is a service much to
				be valued, if, being like a suspicious and skittish beast, it
				can be so managed that, without being frighted either by
				sight or voice, it will submit to receive instruction.</p>
            <p>These things therefore are not slightly to be observed;
					nor are we to neglect taking such care of our own life and
					manners that they may be clear from all stain and reprehension. For statesmen are not only liable to give an
					account of what they say or do in public; but there is a
					busy enquiry made into their very meals, beds, marriages,
					and every either sportive or serious action. For what need
					we speak of Alcibiades, who, being of all men the most
					active in public affairs, and withal an invincible commander, perished by his irregularity in living and his
					audaciousness, and who by his luxury and prodigality rendered the state unbenefited by all his other good qualities?
					&mdash;since the Athenians blamed Cimon's wine; the Romans,
					having nothing else to cavil at, found fault with Scipio's
					sleeping; and the enemies of Pompey the Great, having
					observed that he scratched his head with one finger, upbraided him with it. For as a freckle or wart in the face
					is more prejudicial than stains, maims, and scars in the
					rest of the body; so little faults, discerned in the lives of
					princes and statesmen, appear great, through an opinion
					most men have conceived of government and policy, which
					they look on as a great and excellent thing, and such as
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.103"/>
					
					ought to be pure from all absurdity and imperfection.
					Therefore not unjustly is Livius Drusus commended, who,
					when several parts of his house lay open to the view of
					his neighbors, being told by a certain workman that he
					would for the expense only of five talents alter and remedy
					that fault, said: I will give thee indeed ten, to make my
					whole house so transparent that all the city may see how I
					live. For he was a temperate and modest man. And yet
					perhaps he had no need of this perspicuity; for many persons pry into those manners, counsels, actions, and lives of
					statesmen which seem to be most deeply concealed, no less
					loving and admiring one, and hating and despising another,
					for their private than for their public transactions. What
					then! perhaps you may say: Do not cities make use also of
					such men as live dissolutely and effeminately? True; for as
					women with child frequently long for stones and chalk, as
					those that are stomach-sick do for salt-fish and such other
					meats, which a little after they spit out again and reject; so
					also the people sometime through wantonness and petulancy, and sometimes for want of better guides, make use of
					those that come first to hand, though at the same time detesting and contemning them, and after rejoice at such
					things spoken against them as the comedian Plato makes
					the people themselves to say:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quick, take me by the hand, and hold me fast,
						</l>
                     <l>Or I'll Agyrrius captain choose in haste.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And again he brings them in, calling for a basin and feather
					that they may vomit, and saying,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A chamber-pot by my tribunal stands.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And a little after,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>It feeds a stinking pest, foul Cephalus.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And the Roman people, when Carbo promised them something, and (to confirm it) added an oath and execration,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.104"/>
					
					unanimously swore on the contrary that they would not believe him. And in Lacedaemon, when a certain dissolute
					man named Demosthenes had delivered a very convenient
					opinion, the people rejected it; but the Ephori, who approved of his advice, having chosen by lot one of the
					ancient senators, commanded him to repeat the same discourse, pouring it (as it were) out of a filthy vessel into a
					clean one, that it might be acceptable to the multitude.
					Of so great moment either way in political affairs is the
					belief conceived of a person's disposition and manners.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Yet are we not therefore so to lay the whole stress on
				virtue, as utterly to neglect all gracefulness and efficacy
				of speech; but esteeming rhetoric, though not the worker,
				yet a coadjutor and forwarder of persuasion, we should
				correct that saying of Menander,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The speaker's manners, not his speech, persuade.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For both manners and language ought to concur, unless
					any one forsooth shall say that&mdash;as it is the pilot who
					steers the ship, and not the rudder, and the rider that turns
					the horse, and not the bridle&mdash;so political virtue, using
					not eloquence but manners as an helm and bridle, persuades and guides a city, which is (to speak with Plato) an
					animal most easy to be turned, managing and directing
					it (as it were) from the poop. For since those great and
					(as Homer calls them) Jove-begotten kings, setting themselves out with their purple, sceptres, guards, and the very
					oracles of the Gods, and subjecting to them by their majesty the multitude, as if they were of a better nature and
					more excellent mould than other men, desired also to be
					eloquent orators, and neglected neither the gracefulness of
					speech,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor public meeting, that more perfect they
						</l>
                     <l>Might be for feats of war,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 441.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.105"/>
            <p>not only venerating Jupiter the counsellor, Mars the
					slaughterer, and Pallas the warrior, but invocating also
					Calliope,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who still attends on regal Majesty,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Od. VII. 165.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>by her persuasive oratory appeasing and moderating the
					fierceness and violence of the people; how is it possible
					that a private man in a plebeian garb and with a vulgar
					mien, undertaking to conduct a city, should ever be able to
					prevail over and govern the multitude, if he is not endowed
					with alluring and all-persuading eloquence? The captains
					indeed and pilots of ships make use of others to deliver
					their commands; but a statesman ought to have in himself
					not only a spirit of government, but also a commanding
					faculty of speech, that he may not stand in need of another's voice, nor be constrained to say, as did Iphicrates
					when he was run down by the eloquence of Aristophon,
					<q direct="unspecified">My adversaries have the better actors, but mine is the
						more excellent play,</q> nor yet be often obliged to make use
					of these words of Euripides,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O that the race of miserable men
						</l>
                     <l>Were speechless!</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Alas! Why have not men's affairs a tongue,
						</l>
                     <l>That those fine pleaders who of right make wrong
						</l>
                     <l>Might be no longer in request?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Frag. 977 and 442.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For to these evasions perhaps might an Alcamenes, a
					Nesiotes, an Ictinus, and any such mechanical persons as
					get their bread by their hands, be permitted on their oath
					to have recourse. As it sometime happened in Athens,
					where, when two architects were examined about the erecting a certain public work, one of them, who was of a free
					and voluble speech and had his tongue (as we say) well
					hung, making a long and premeditated harangue concerning the method and order of raising such a fabric, greatly
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.106"/>
					
					moved the people; but the other, who was indeed the better workman though the worse speaker, coming forth into
					the midst, only said, <q direct="unspecified">Ye men of Athens, what this man has
						spoken, I will do.</q> For those men venerate only Minerva
					surnamed Ergane (or the Artisan), who, as Sophocles says
					of them,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do on the massy anvil lay
						</l>
                     <l>A lifeless iron bar, where they
						</l>
                     <l>With blows of heavy hammer make
						</l>
                     <l>It pliant to the work they undertake.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the prophet or minister of Minerva Polias (that is, the
					protectress of cities) and of Themis (or Justice) the counsellor,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who both convenes assemblies, and again
						</l>
                     <l>Dissolves them,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Od. II. 69.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>making use of no other instrument but speech, does, by
					forming and fashioning some things and smoothing and
					polishing others that, like certain knots in timber or flaws
					in iron, are averse to his work, embellish and adorn a city.
					By this means the government of Pericles was in name (as
					Thucydides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thuc. II. 65.</note> says) a democracy, but in effect the rule of
					one principal man through the power of his eloquence.
					For there were living at the same time Cimon, and also
					Ephialtes and Thucydides,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The son of Melesias, not the historian. (G.)</note> all good men; now Thucydides, being asked by Archidamus, king of the Spartans,
					whether himself or Pericles were the better wrestler, thus
					answered: <q direct="unspecified">That is not easily known; for when I in
						wrestling overthrow him, he, by his words persuading the
						spectators that he did not fall, gains the victory.</q> And
					this did not only bring glory to himself, but safety also to
					the city; for being persuaded by him, it preserved the
					happiness it had gotten, and abstained from intermeddling
					with foreign affairs. But Nicias, though having the same
					design, yet falling short in the art of persuasion, when he
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.107"/>
					
					endeavored by his speech, as by a gentle curb, to restrain
					and turn the people, could not compass it or prevail with
					them, but was fain to depart, being violently hurried and
					dragged (as it were) by the neck and shoulders into Sicily.
					They say, that a wolf is not to be held by the ears; but a
					people and city are chiefly to be drawn by the ears, and
					not as some do who, being unpractised in eloquence, seek
					other absurd and unartificial ways of taking them, and
					either draw them by the belly, making them feasts and
					banquets, or by the purse, bestowing on them gifts and
					largesses, or by the eye, exhibiting to them masks and
					prizes or public shows of dancers and fencers,&mdash;by which
					they do not so much lead as cunningly catch the people.
					For to lead a people is to persuade them by reason and
					eloquence; but such allurements of the multitude nothing differ from the baits laid for the taking of irrational animals.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Let not yet the speech of a statesman be youthful
				and theatrical, as if he were making an harangue composed, like a garland, of curious and florid words; nor again
				&mdash;as Pytheas said of an oration made by Demosthenes,
				that it smelt of the lamp and sophistical curiosity&mdash;let
				it consist of over-subtle arguments and periods, exactly
				framed by rule and compass. But as musicians require
				that the strings of their instruments should be sweetly and
				gently touched, and not rudely thrummed or beaten; so
				in the speech of a statesman, both when he counsels and
				when he commands, there should not appear either violence or cunning, nor should he think himself worthy of
				commendation for having spoken formally, artificially, and
				with an exact observation of punctualities; but his whole
				discourse ought to be full of ingenuous simplicity, true
				magnanimity, fatherly freedom, and careful providence and
				understanding, joined with goodness and honesty, gracefulness and attraction, proceeding from grave expressions
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.108"/>
				
				and proper and persuasive sentences. Now a political
				oration does much more properly than a juridical one admit of sententious speeches, histories, fables, and metaphors, by which those who moderately and seasonably use
				them exceedingly move their hearers; as he did who said,
				Make not Greece one-eyed; and Demades, when he affirmed of himself, that he was to manage the wreck of
				the state; and Archilochus, when he said
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor let the stone of Tantalus
					</l>
                     <l>Over this isle hang always thus;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and Pericles, when he commanded the eyesore<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">So he called the little island Aegina.</note> of the
					Piraeus to be taken away; and Phocion, when he pronounced of Leosthenes's victory, that the beginning or the
					short course of the war was good, but that he feared the
					long race that was to follow. But in general, majesty and
					greatness more benefit a political discourse, a pattern of
					which may be the Philippics, and (amongst the orations set
					down by Thucydides) that of Sthenelaidas the Ephor, that
					of Archidamus at Plataea, and that of Pericles after
					the plague. But as for those rhetorical flourishes and harangues of Ephorus, Theopompus, and Anaximenes, which
					they made after they had armed and set in order the battalions, it may be said of them,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>None talks thus foolishly so near the sword.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Autolycus, Frag. 284, vs. 22.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Nevertheless, both taunts and raillery may sometimes
				be part of political discourse, so they proceed not to injury
				or scurrility, but are usefully spoken by him who either
				reprehends or scoffs. But these things seem most to be
				allowed in answers and replies. For in that manner to
				begin a discourse as if one had purposely prepared himself
				for it, is the part of a common jester, and carries with it
				an opinion of maliciousness; as was incident to the biting
				jests of Cicero, Cato the Elder, and Euxitheus, an intimate
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.109"/>
				
				acquaintance of Aristotle,&mdash;all of whom frequently began
				first to jeer; but in him, who does it only in revenge, the
				seasonableness of it renders it not only pardonable but
				also graceful. Such was the answer of Demosthenes, when
				one that was suspected of thievery derided him for writing
				by night: I know that the keeping my candle burning all
				night is offensive to you. So when Demades bawled out,
				Demosthenes forsooth would correct me: thus would the
				sow (as the proverb has it) teach Minerva;&mdash;That Minerva,
				replied Demosthenes, was not long since taken in adultery.
				Not ungraceful also was that of Xenaenetus to those citizens who upbraided him with flying when he was general,
				'Twas with you, my dear hearts. But in raillery great
				care is to be taken for the avoiding of excess, and of any
				thing that may either by its unseasonableness offend the
				hearers or show the speaker to be of an ungenerous and
				sordid disposition;&mdash;such as were the sayings of Democrates. For he, going up into the assembly, said that, like
				the city, he had little force but much wind; and after the
				overthrow at Chaeronea, going forth to the people, he
				said: I would not have had the state to be in so ill a condition that you should be contented to hear me also giving
				you counsel. For this showed a mean-spirited person, as
				the other did a madman; but neither of them was becoming a statesman. Now the succinctness of Phocion's
				speech was admired; whence Polyeuctus affirmed, that
				Demosthenes was the greatest orator, but that Phocion
				spake most forcibly, for that his discourse did in very few
				words contain abundance of matter. And Demosthenes,
				who contemned others, was wont, when Phocion stood up,
				to say, The hatchet (or pruning-knife) of my orations
				arises.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Let your chief endeavor therefore be, to use to the
				multitude a premeditated and not empty speech, and that
				with safety, knowing that Pericles himself, before he made
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.110"/>
				
				any discourse to the people, was wont to pray that there
				might not a word pass from him foreign to the business he
				was to treat of. It is requisite also, that you have a voluble tongue, and be exercised in speaking on all occurrences; for occasions are quick, and bring many sudden things
				in political affairs. Wherefore also Demosthenes was, as
				they say, inferior to many, withdrawing and absconding
				himself when sudden occasion offered. And Theophrastus relates that Alcibiades, desirous to speak not only what
				he ought but as he ought, often hesitated and stood still
				in the midst of his speech, seeking and composing expressions fit for his purpose. But he who, as matters and
				occasions present themselves, rises up to speak, most of all
				moves, leads, and disposes of the multitude. Thus Leo
				Byzantius came to make an harangue to the Athenians,
				being then at dissension amongst themselves; by whom
				when he perceived himself to be laughed at for the littleness of his stature, What would you do, said he, if you
				saw my wife, who scarce reaches up to my knees? And
				the laughter thereupon increasing, Yet, went he on, as
				little as we are, when we fall out with one another, the
				city of Byzantium is not big enough to hold us. So Pytheas the orator, who declaimed against the honors decreed
				to Alexander, when one said to him, Dare you, being so
				young, discourse of so great matters? made this answer,
				And yet Alexander, whom you decree to be a God, is
				younger than I am.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>It is requisite also for the champion of the commonweal to bring to this not slight but all-concerning contest
				a firm and solid speech, attended with a strong habit of
				voice and a long lasting breath, lest, being tired and spent
				with speaking, he chance to be overcome by
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some ravening crier, with a roaring voice,
					</l>
                     <l>Loud as Cycloborus.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A brook near Athens, the waters of which fell with an extraordinary noise.
						Aristoph. Eq. 137.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.111"/>
            <p>Cato, when he had no hopes of persuading the people or
					senate, whom he found prepossessed by the courtships and
					endeavors of the contrary party, was wont to rise up and
					hold them a whole day with an oration, by that means depriving his adversaries of their opportunity. And thus
					much concerning the preparation and use of speech may
					be sufficient for him who can of himself find out and add
					What necessarily follows from it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>There are, moreover, two avenues or ways of entering
				into the government of the state; the one short and expeditious to the lustre of glory, but not without danger; the
				other more obscure and slow, but having also greater
				security. For some there are who, beginning with some
				great and illustrious action which requires a courageous
				boldness, do, like to those that from a far extended promontory launch forth into the deep, steer directly into the
				very midst of public affairs, thinking Pindar to have been
				in the right when he said,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If you a stately fabric do design,
					</l>
                     <l>Be sure that your work's front with lustre shine.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pind. Olymp. VI. 4.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the multitude do, through a certain satiety and loathing of those to whom they have been accustomed, more
					readily receive a beginner; as the beholders do a fresh
					combatant, and as those dignities and authorities which
					have a splendid and speedy increase dazzle and astonish
					envy. For neither does that fire, as Ariston says, make a
					smoke, nor that glory breed envy, which suddenly and
					quickly shines forth; but of those who grow up slowly
					and by degrees, some are attacked on this side, others on
					that; whence many have withered away about the tribunal,
					before ever they came to flourish. But when, as they say
					of Ladas,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sound o' th' rope yet rattled in his ear,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <q direct="unspecified">the sound of the rope</q>: from whence they set forth to run.</note>
                     <l>When Ladas having finished his career
						</l>
                     <l>Was crowned,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.112"/>
            <p>any one suddenly and gloriously performs an embassy,
					triumphs, or leads forth an army, neither the envious nor
					the disdainful have like power over him as over others.
					Thus did Aratus ascend to glory, making the overthrow of
					the tyrant Nicocles his first step to the management of the
					commonweal. Thus did Alcibiades, settling the alliance
					with the Mantineans against the Lacedaemonians. Pompey also required a triumph, being not yet admitted into
					the senate; and when Sylla opposed it, he said to him,
					More adore the rising than the setting sun; which when
					Sylla heard, he yielded to him. And the people of Rome
					on a sudden, contrary to the ordinary course of the law,
					declared Cornelius Scipio consul, when he stood candidate
					for the aedileship, not from any vulgar reason, but admiring
					the victory he had got, whilst he was but a youth, in a
					single combat fought in Spain, and his conquests a little
					after, performed at Carthage, when he was a tribune of
					foot: in respect of which Cato the Elder cried out with a
					loud voice,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He only's wise, the rest like shadows fly.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Odyss. X. 495.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now then, since the affairs of the cities have neither wars
					to be managed, tyrannies to be overthrown, nor leagues
					and alliances to be treated, what can any one undertake
					for the beginning of an illustrious and splendid government? There are yet left public causes and embassies to
					the emperor, which require the courage and prudence of
					an acute and cautious person. There are also in the cities
					many good and laudable usages neglected, which may be
					restored, and many ill practices brought in by custom, to
					the disgrace or damage of the city, which may be redressed,
					to gain him the esteem of the people. Moreover, a great
					suit rightly determined, fidelity in defending a poor man's
					cause against a powerful adversary, and freedom of speech
					in behalf of justice to some unjust nobleman, have afforded
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.113"/>
					
					some a glorious entrance into the administration of the
					state. Not a few also have been advanced by enmity and
					quarrels, having set themselves to attack such men whose
					dignity was either envied or terrible. For the power of
					him that is overthrown does with greater glory accrue to
					his overthrower. Indeed, through envy to contend against
					a good man, and one that has by virtue been advanced to
					the chiefest honor,&mdash;as Simmias did against Pericles, Alcmaeon against Themistocles, Clodius against Pompey, and
					Meneclides the orator against Epaminondas,&mdash;is neither
					good for one's reputation nor otherwise advantageous. For
					when the multitude, having outraged some good man, soon
					after (as it frequently happens) repent of their indignation,
					they think that way of excusing this offence the easiest
					which is indeed the justest, to wit, the destroying of him
					who was the persuader and author of it. But the rising
					up to humble and pull down a wicked person, who has by
					his audaciousness and cunning subjected the city to himself (such as heretofore Cleon and Clitophon were in
					Athens), makes a glorious entrance to the management
					of public affairs, as it were to a play. I am not ignorant
					also that some, by opposing&mdash;as Ephialtes did at Athens,
					and Phormio amongst the Eleans&mdash;an imperious and oligarchical senate, have at the same time obtained both
					authority and honor; but in this there is great danger to
					him who is but entering upon the administration of state.
					Wherefore Solon took a better beginning; for the city of
					Athens being divided into three parts, the Diacrians (or
					inhabitants of the hill), the Pedieans (or dwellers on the
					plain), and the Paralians (or those whose abode was by
					the water side), he, joining himself with none of them, but
					acting for the common good of them all, and saying and
					doing all things for to bring them to concord, was chosen
					the lawgiver to take away their differences, and by that
					means settled the state.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.114"/>
            <p>Such then and so many beginnings has the more splendid way of entering upon state affairs.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But many gallant men have chosen the safe and
				slow method, as Aristides. Phocion, Pammenes the Theban,
				Lucullus in Rome, Cato, and Agesilaus the Lacedaemonian. For as ivy, twining about the strongest trees, rises
				up together with them; so every one of these, applying
				himself, whilst he was yet young and inglorious, to some
				elder and illustrious personage, and growing up and increasing by little and little under his authority, grounded
				and rooted himself in the commonweal. For Clisthenes advanced Aristides, Chabrias preferred Phocion, Sylla promoted Lucullus, Maximus raised Cato, Pammenes forwarded
				Epaminondas, and Lysander assisted Agesilaus. But this
				last, injuring his own reputation through an unseasonable ambition and jealousy, soon threw off the director of
				his actions; but the rest honestly, politically, and to the
				end, venerated and magnified the authors of their advancement,&mdash;like bodies which are opposed to the sun,&mdash;by reflecting back the light that shone upon them, augmented
				and rendered more illustrious. Certainly those who
				looked asquint upon Scipio called him the player, and his
				companion Laelius the poet or author of his actions; yet
				was not Laelius puffed up by any of these things, but continued to promote the virtue and glory of Scipio. And
				Afranius, the friend of Pompey, though he was very
				meanly descended, yet being at the very point to be chosen
				consul, when he understood that Pompey favored others,
				gave over his suit, saying that his obtaining the consulship
				would not be so honorable as grievous and troublesome to
				him, if it were against the good-will and without the
				assistance of Pompey. Having therefore delayed but one
				year, he enjoyed the dignity and preserved his friendship.
				Now those who are thus by others led, as it were, by the
				hand to glory do, in gratifying one, at the same time also
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.115"/>
				
				gratify the multitude, and incur less odium, if any inconvenience befalls them. Wherefore also Philip (king of
				Macedon) exhorted his son Alexander, whilst he had
				leisure during the reign of another, to get himself friends,
				winning their love by kind and affable behavior.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Now he that begins to enter upon the administration
				of state affairs should choose himself a guide, who is not
				only a man of credit and authority but is also such for his
				virtue. For as it is not every tree that will admit and bear
				the twining of a vine, there being some which utterly
				choke and spoil its growth; so in states, those who are
				no lovers of virtue and goodness, but only of honor and
				sovereignty, afford not young beginners any opportunities
				of performing worthy actions, but do through envy keep
				them down and let them languish whom they regard as
				depriving them of their glory, which is (as it were) their
				food. Thus Marius, having first in Afric and afterwards
				in Galatia done many gallant exploits by the assistance of
				Sylla, forbare any farther to employ him, and utterly cast
				him off, being really vexed at his growing into repute, but
				making his pretence the device engraven on his seal. For
				Sylla, being paymaster under Marius when he was general
				in Afric, and sent by him to Bocchus, brought with him
				Jugurtha prisoner; but as he was an ambitious young
				man, who had but just tasted the sweetness of glory, he
				received not his good fortune with moderation; but having
				caused the representation of the action to be engraven on
				his seal, wore about him Jugurtha delivered into his hands;
				and this did Marius lay to his charge, when he turned him
				off. But Sylla, passing over to Catulus and Metellus, who
				were good men and at difference with Marius, soon after
				in a civil war drove away and ruined Marius, who wanted
				but little of overthrowing Rome. Sylla indeed, on the
				contrary, advanced Pompey from a very youth, rising up
				to him and uncovering his head as he passed by, and not
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.116"/>
				
				only giving other young men occasions of doing captain-like actions, but even instigating some that were backward
				and unwilling. He filled the armies with emulation and
				desire of honor; and thus he had the superiority over them
				all, desiring not to be alone, but the first and greatest
				amongst many great ones. These therefore are the men
				to whom young statesmen ought to adhere, and with these
				they should be (as it were) incorporated, not stealing from
				them their glory,&mdash;like Aesop's wren, which, being carried up on the eagle's wings, suddenly flew away and got
				before her,&mdash;but receiving it of them with friendship and
				good-will since they can never, as Plato says, be able to
				govern aright, if they have not been first well practised in
				obedience.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>After this follows the judgment that is to be had in
				the choice of friends, in which neither the opinion of
				Themistocles nor that of Cleon is to be approved. For
				Cleon, when he first knew that he was to take on him the
				government, assembling his friends together, brake off
				friendship with them, as that which often disables the
				mind, and withdraws it from its just and upright intention
				in managing the affairs of the state. But he would have
				done better, if he had cast out of his soul avarice and
				contention, and cleansed himself from envy and malice.
				For cities want not men that are friendless and unaccompanied, but such as are good and temperate. Now he
				indeed drove away his friends; but a hundred heads of
				fawning flatterers were, as the comedian speaks, licking
				about him;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristoph. Pac. 756</note> and being harsh and severe to those that
				were civil, he again debased himself to court the favor of
				the multitude, doing all things to humor them in their
				dotage, and taking rewards at every man's hand,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristoph. Eq. 1099.</note> and
				joining himself with the worst and most distempered of
				the people against the best. But Themistocles, on the
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.117"/>
				
				contrary, said to one who told him that he would govern
				well if he exhibited himself alike to all: May I never sit
				on that throne on which my friends shall not have more
				power with me than those who are not my friends. Neither did he well in pinning the state to his friendship, and
				submitting the common and public affairs to his private
				favors and affections. And farther, he said to Simonides,
				when he requested somewhat that was not just: Neither
				is he a good poet or musician, who sings against measure;
				nor he an upright magistrate, who gratifies any one against
				the laws. And it would really be a shameful and miserable thing, that the pilot should choose his mariners, and
				the master of a ship the pilot,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who well can rule the helm, and in good guise
					</l>
                     <l>Hoist up the sails, when winds begin to rise,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and that an architect should make choice of such servants and workmen as will not prejudice his work, but
					take pains in the best manner to forward it; but that a
					statesman&mdash;who, as Pindar has it,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The best of artists and chief workman is
						</l>
                     <l>Of equity and justice&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>should not presently choose himself like-affected friends
					and ministers, and such as might co-inspire into him a love
					of honesty; but that one or other should be always unjustly and violently bending him to other uses. For then
					he would seem to differ in nothing from a carpenter or
					mason who, through ignorance or want of experience,
					uses such squares, rules, and levels as will certainly make
					his work to be awry. Since friends are the living and intelligent instruments of statesmen, who ought to be so far
					from bearing them company in their slips and transgressions, that they must be careful they do not, even unknown
					to them, commit a fault.</p>
            <p>And this it was, that disgraced Solon and brought him
					into disrepute amongst his citizens; for he, having an intention
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.118"/>
					
					 to ease men's debts and to bring in that which
					was called at Athens the Seisachtheia (for that was the
					name given by way of extenuation to the cancelling of
					debts), communicated this design to some of his friends,
					who thereupon did a most unjust act; for having got this
					inkling, they borrowed abundance of money, and the law
					being a little after brought to light, they appeared to have
					purchased stately houses, and great store of land with the
					wealth they had borrowed; and Solon, who was himself
					injured, was accused to have been a partaker of their injustice. Agesilaus also was most feeble and mean-spirited
					in what concerned the suits of his friends, being like the
					horse Pegasus in Euripides,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who, frighted, bowed his back, more than his rider would,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Bellerophon, Frag. 311.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so that, being more ready to help them in their misfortunes
					than was requisite, he seemed to be privy to their injustices.
					For he saved Phoebidas, who was accused for having
					without commission surprised the castle of Thebes, called
					Cadmea, saying that such enterprises were to be attempted
					without expecting any orders. And when Sphodrias was
					brought to trial for an unlawful and heinous act, having
					made an incursion into Attica at such time as the Athenians were allies and confederates of the Spartans, he procured him to be acquitted, being softened by the amorous
					entreaties of his son. There is also recorded a short epistle of his to a certain prince, written in these words: If
					Nicias is innocent, discharge him; if he is guilty, discharge
					him for my sake; but however it is, discharge him. But
					Phocion (on the contrary) would not so much as appear in
					behalf of his son-in-law Charicles, when he was accused
					for having taken money of Harpalus; but having said,
					Only for acts of justice have I made you my son-in-law,&mdash;
					went his way. And Timoleon the Corinthian, when he
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.119"/>
					
					could not by admonitions or requests dissuade his brother
					from being a tyrant, confederated with his destroyers. For
					a magistrate ought not to be a friend even to the altar (or
					till he comes to the point of being forsworn), as Pericles
					sometime said, but no farther than is agreeable to all law,
					justice, and the utility of the state; any of which being
					neglected brings a great and public damage, as did the
					not executing of justice on Sphodrias and Phoebidas, who
					did not a little contribute to the engaging of Sparta in the
					Leuctrian war.</p>
            <p>Otherwise, reason of state is so far from necessitating
					one to show himself severe on every peccadillo of his
					friends, that it even permits him, when he has secured the
					principal affairs of the public, to assist them, stand by
					them, and labor for them. There are, moreover, certain
					favors that may be done without envy, as is the helping a
					friend to obtain an office, or rather the putting into his
					hands some honorable commission or some laudable embassy, such as for the congratulating or honoring some
					prince or the making a league of amity and alliance with
					some state. But if there be some difficult but withal illustrious and great action to be performed, having first taken
					it upon himself, he may afterwards assume a friend to his
					assistance, as did Diomedes, whom Homer makes to speak
					in this manner:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Since a companion you will have me take,
						</l>
                     <l>How can I think a better choice to make,
						</l>
                     <l>Than the divine Ulysses?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. X. 242.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Ulysses again as kindly attributes to him the praise of
					the achievement, saying:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>These stately steeds, whose country you demand,
						</l>
                     <l>Nestor, were hither brought from Thracian land,
						</l>
                     <l>Whose king, with twelve of his best friends, lies dead,
						</l>
                     <l>All slain by th' hand of warlike Diomed.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. X. 558.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.120"/>
            <p>For this sort of concession no less adorns the praiser than
					the praised; but self-conceitedness, as Plato says, dwells
					with solitude. He ought moreover to associate his friends
					in those good and kind offices which are done by him,
					bidding those whom he has benefited to love them and
					give them thanks, as having been the procurers and counsellors of his favors to them. But he must reject the dishonest and unreasonable request of his friends, yet not
					churlishly but mildly, teaching and showing them that they
					are not beseeming their virtue and honor. Never was any
					man better at this than Epaminondas, who, having denied
					to deliver out of prison a certain victualler, when requested
					by Pelopidas, and yet a little after dismissing him at the
					desire of his miss, said to his friend, These, O Pelopidas,
					are favors fit for wenches to receive, and not for generals.
					Cato on the other side acted morosely and insolently, when
					Catulus the censor, his most intimate and familiar friend,
					interceded with him for one of those against whom he, being quaestor, had entered process, saying: It would be a
					shame if you, who ought to reform young men for us,
					should be thrust out by our servants. For he might,
					though in effect refusing the requested favor, have yet forborne that severity and bitterness of speech; so that his
					doing what was displeasing to his friend might have seemed
					not to have proceeded from his own inclination, but to
					have been a necessity imposed upon him by law and justice. There are also in the administration of the state
					methods, not dishonorable, of assisting our poorer friends
					in the making of their fortune. Thus did Themistocles,
					who, seeing after a battle one of those which lay dead in
					the field adorned with chains of gold and jewels, did himself pass by him; but turning back to a friend of his, said,
					Do you take these spoils, for you are not yet come to be
					Themistocles. For even the affairs themselves do frequently afford a statesman such opportunities of benefiting
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.121"/>
					
					his friends; for every man is not a Menemachus. To one
					therefore give the patronage of a cause, both just and
					beneficial; to another recommend some rich man, who
					stands in need of management and protection; and help
					a third to be employed in some public work, or to some
					gainful and profitable farm. Epaminondas bade a friend
					of his go to a certain rich man, and ask him for a talent
					by the command of Epaminondas, and when he to whom
					the message was sent came to enquire the reason of it;
					Because, said Epaminondas, he is a very honest man and
					poor; but you, by converting much of the city's wealth to
					your own use, are become rich. And Xenophon reports,
					that Agesilaus delighted in enriching his friends, himself
					making no account of money.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Now since, as Simonides says, all larks must have a
				crest, and every eminent office in a commonweal brings
				enmities and dissensions, it is not a little convenient for a
				statesman to be forewarned also of his comportment in
				these rencounters. Many therefore commend Themistocles
				and Aristides, who, when they were to go forth on an
				embassy or to command together the army, laid down their
				enmity at the confines of the city, taking it up again after
				their return. Some again are highly pleased with the
				action of Cretinas the Magnesian. He, having for his
				rival in the government one Hermias, a man not powerful and rich, but ambitious and high-spirited, when the
				Mithridatic war came on, seeing the city in danger, desired
				Hermias either to take the government upon himself and
				manage the affairs whilst he retired, or, if he would have
				him take the command of the army, to depart himself immediately, lest they should through their ambitious contention destroy the city. The proposal pleased Hermias,
				who, saying that Cretinas was a better soldier than himself,
				did with his wife and children quit the city. Cretinas then
				escorted him as he went forth, furnishing him out of his
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.122"/>
				
				own estate with all such things as are more useful to those
				that fly from home than to those that are besieged; and
				excellently defending the city, unexpectedly preserved it,
				being at the point to be destroyed. For if it is generous
				and proceeding from a magnanimous spirit to cry out,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I love my children, but my country more,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>why should it not be readier for every one of them to say,
					I hate this man, and desire to do him a diskindness, but
					the love of my country has greater power over me? For
					not to condescend to be reconciled to an enemy for those
					very causes for which we ought to abandon even a friend,
					is even to extremity savage and brutish. But far better
					did Phocion and Cato, who grounded not any enmity at all
					on their political differences, but being fierce and obstinate
					only in their public contests not to recede from any thing
					they judged convenient for the state, did in their private
					affairs use those very persons friendly and courteously from
					whom they differed in the other. For one ought not to
					esteem any citizen an enemy, unless it be one like Aristion,
					Nabis, or Catiline, the disease and plague of the city: but
					as for those that are otherwise at discord, a good magistrate
					should, like a skilful musician, by gently setting them up
					or letting them down, bring them to concord; not falling
					angrily and reproachfully upon those that err, but mildly
					reprehending them in such like terms as these of Homer's,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Good friend, I thought you wiser than the rest;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVII. 171</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>You could have told a better tale than this;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 358.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>nor yet repining at their honors, or sparing to speak freely
					in commendation of their good actions, if they say or do
					any thing advantageous to the public. For thus will our
					reprehension, when it is requisite, be credited, and we shall
					render them averse to vice, increasing their virtue, and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.123"/>
					
					showing, by comparing them, how much the one is more
					worthy and beseeming them than the other.</p>
            <p>But I indeed am also of opinion, that a statesman should
					in just causes give testimony to his enemies, stand by them
					when they are accused by sycophants, and discredit imputations brought against them if they are repugnant to their
					characters; as Nero himself, a little before he put to death
					Thraseas, whom of all men he both most hated and feared,
					when one accused him for giving a wrong and unjust sentence, said: I wish Thraseas was but as great a lover of
					me, as he is a most upright judge. Neither is it amiss for
					the daunting of others who are by Nature more inclined to
					vice, when they offend, to make mention of some enemy
					of theirs who is better behaved, and say, Such a one would
					not have spoken or acted thus. And some again, when
					they transgress, are to be put in mind of their virtuous
					progenitors. Thus Homer says,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tydeus has left a son unlike himself.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. V. 800.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Appius, contending in the Comitia with Scipio Africanus, said, How deeply, O Paulus, wouldst thou sigh
					amongst the infernal shades, wert thou but sensible that
					Philonicus the publican guards thy son, who is going to
					stand for the office of censor. For such manner of speeches
					do both admonish the offender, and become their admonishers. Nestor also in Sophocles, being reproached by
					Ajax, thus politicly answers him:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I blame you not, for you act well, although
						</l>
                     <l>You speak but ill.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Cato, who had opposed Pompey in his joining with
					Caesar to force the city; when they fell to open wars, gave
					his opinion that the conduct of the state should be committed to Pompey, saying, that those who are capable to do
					the greatest mischiefs are fittest to put a stop to them.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.124"/>
					
					For reprehension mixed with praise, and accompanied not
					with opprobriousness but liberty of speech, working not
					animosity but remorse and repentance, appears both kind
					and salutary; but railing expressions do not at all beseem
					statesmen. Do but look into the speeches of Demosthenes
					against Aeschines, and of Aeschines against him; and
					again into what Hyperides has written against Demades,
					and consider whether Solon, Pericles, Lycurgus the Lacedaemonian, or Pittacus the Lesbian would have spoken in
					that manner. And yet Demosthenes used this reproachful
					manner of speaking only in his juridical orations or pleadings; for his Philippics are clean and free from all scoffing
					and scurrility. For such discourses do not only more disgrace the speakers than the hearers, but do moreover
					breed confusion in affairs, and disturb counsels and assemblies. Wherefore Phocion did excellently well, who, having broken off his speech to give way to one that railed
					against him, when the other with much ado held his peace,
					going on again where he had left off, said: You have
					already heard what has been spoken of horsemen and
					heavy armed foot; I am now to treat of such as are light
					armed and targeteers.</p>
            <p>But since many persons can hardly contain themselves
					on such occasions, and since railers have often their mouths
					not impertinently stopped by replies; let the answer be
					short and pithy, not showing any indignation or bitterness
					of anger, but mildness joined with raillery and gracefulness, yet somewhat tart and biting. Now such especially
					are the retortings of what has been spoken before. For as
					darts returning against their caster seem to have been repulsed and beaten back by a certain strength and solidity
					in that against which they were thrown; so what was
					spoken seems by the strength and understanding of the
					reproached to have been turned back upon the reproacher.
					Such was that reply of Epaminondas to Callistratus, who
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.125"/>
					
					upbraided the Thebans with Oedipus, and the Argives with
					Orestes,&mdash;one of which had killed his father and the other
					his mother, -Yet they who did these things, being rejected
					by us, were received by you. Such also was the repartee
					of Antalcidas the Spartan to an Athenian, who said to him,
					We have often driven you back and pursued you from the
					Cephissus; But we (replied Antalcidas) never yet pursued
					you from the Eurotas. Phocion also, when Demades cried
					out, The Athenians if they grow mad, will kill thee; elegantly replied, And thee, if they come again to their wits.
					So, when Domitius said to Crassus the orator, Did not you
					weep for the death of the lamprey you kept in your fishpond?&mdash;Did not you, said Crassus to him again, bury three
					wives without ever shedding a tear? These things therefore have indeed their use also in other parts of a man's
					life.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Moreover, some, like Cato, thrust themselves into
				every part of polity, thinking a good citizen should not
				omit any care or industry for the obtaining authority. And
				these men greatly commend Epaminondas; for that being
				by the Thebans through envy and in contempt appointed
				telearch, he did not reject it, but said, that the office does
				not show the man, but the man also the office. He brought
				the telearchate into great and venerable repute, which was
				before nothing but a certain charge of the carrying the
				dung out of the narrow streets and lanes of the city, and
				turning of watercourses. Nor do I doubt but that I myself afford matter of laughter to many who come into this
				our city, being frequently seen in public employed about
				such matters. But that comes into my assistance which is
				related of Antisthenes; for, when one wondered to see him
				carry a piece of stock-fish through the market, 'Tis for myself, said he. But I, on the contrary, say to those who
				upbraid me for being present at and overseeing the measuring of tiles, or the bringing in and unloading of clay and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.126"/>
				
				stones.: It is not for myself, but for my country, that I perform this service. For though he who in his own person
				manages and does many such things for himself may be
				judged mean-spirited and mechanical, yet if he does them
				for the public and for his country, he is not to be deemed
				sordid; but on the contrary, his diligence and readiness,
				extending even to these small matters, is to be esteemed
				greater and more highly to be valued. But others there
				are, that hold Pericles's manner of acting to have been
				more magnanimous and august; amongst which Critolaus
				the Peripatetic, who is of opinion that, as at Athens the
				Salaminian ship and the Paralus were not launched forth
				for every service, but only on necessary and great occasions, so a statesman ought to employ himself in the chiefest and greatest affairs, like the King of the universe, who,
				as Euripides says,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Reserves great things for his own government,
					</l>
                     <l>But small things leaves to Fortune's management.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For neither do we approve the excessively ambitious and
					contentious spirit of Theagenes, who, having obtained the
					victory not only through the whole course of public games,
					but also in many other contests, and not only in wrestling
					but in buffeting and running of long races, at last, being
					at the anniversary festival supper of a certain hero, after
					every one was served, according to the custom, he started
					up, and fell to wrestling, as if it were necessary that no
					other should conquer when he was present; whence he got
					together twelve hundred coronets, most of which one would
					have taken for rubbish.</p>
            <p>Now nothing do they differ from him, who strip themselves for every public affair, and render themselves reprehensible by many, becoming troublesome, and being, when
					they do well, the subject of envy, and when they do ill, of
					rejoicing. And that industry which was at the beginning
					admired turns afterwards to contempt and laughter. In
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.127"/>
					
					this manner it was said; Metiochus leads forth the army,
					Metiochus oversees the highways, Metiochus bakes the
					bread, Metiochus bolts the meal, Metiochus does all things,
					Metiochus shall suffer for it at last. This Metiochus was
					a follower of Pericles, and made use, it seems, of the power
					he had with him invidiously and disdainfully. For a
					statesman ought to find the people when he comes to them
					(as they say) in love with him, and leave in them a longing
					after him when he is absent; which course Scipio Africanus also took, dwelling a long time in the country, at the
					same time both removing from himself the burthen of envy,
					and giving those leisure to breathe, who seemed to be oppressed by his glory. But Timesias the Clazomenian, who
					was otherwise a good commonwealths-man, was ignorant
					of his being envied and hated for doing all things by himself, till the following accident befell him. It happened
					that, as he passed by where certain boys were striking a
					cockal-bone out of an hole, some of them said, that the
					bone was still left within; but he who had stricken it cried
					out, I wish I had as certainly beaten out Timesias's brains,
					as this bone is out of the hole. Timesias, hearing this,
					and thereby understanding the envy and spite borne him by
					every one, returned home, where he imparted the matter
					to his wife, and having commanded her to pack up, all and
					follow him, immediately left both his house and the city.
					And Themistocles seems to have been in some such condition amongst the Athenians, when he said: How is it, O
					ye blessed ones, that you are tired with the frequent receiving of benefits?</p>
            <p>Now some of those things have indeed been rightly
					spoken, others not so well. For a statesman ought not to
					withdraw his affection and providential care from any public affair whatever, nor reserve himself sacred, like the
					anchor in a ship, for the last necessities and hazards of the
					state. But as the masters of ships do some things with their
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.128"/>
					
					own hands, and perform others, sitting afar off, by other
					instruments, turning and winding them by the hands of
					others, and making use of mariners, boatswains, and mates,
					some of which they often call to the stern, putting the helm
					into their hands; so it is convenient for a statesman sometimes to yield the command to his companions, and to invite them kindly and civilly to the tribunal, not managing
					all the affairs of the commonweal by his own speeches,
					decrees, and actions, but having good and faithful men, to
					employ every one of them in that proper and peculiar
					station which he finds to be most suitable for him. Thus
					Pericles used Menippus for the conduct of the armies, by
					Ephialtes he humbled the council of the Areopagus, by
					Charinus he passed the law against the Megarians, and
					sent Lampon to people the city of Thurii. For not only
					is the greatness of authority less liable to be envied by the
					people, when it seems to be divided amongst many; but
					the business also is more exactly done. For as the division
					of the hand into fingers has not weakened it, but rendered
					it more commodious and instrumental for the uses to which
					it serves; so he who in the administration of a state gives
					part of the affairs to others renders the action more efficacious by communicating it. But he who, through an unsatiable desire of glory or power, lays the whole burthen
					of the state upon his own shoulders, and applies himself
					to that for which he is neither fitted by nature nor exercise,&mdash;as Cleon did to the leading forth of armies, Philopoemen to the commanding of navies, and Hannibal to
					haranguing the people,&mdash;has no excuse for his errors;
					but hears that of Euripides objected against him,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, but a carpenter, concernd'st thyself
						</l>
                     <l>With works not wrought in wood;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>being no good orator, you went on an embassage; being
					of a lazy temper, you thrust yourself into the stewardship;
					being ignorant in keeping accounts, you would be treasurer;
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.129"/>
					
					 or, being old and infirm, you took on you the command of the army. But Pericles divided his authority
					with Cimon, reserving to himself the governing within the
					city, and committing to him the manning of the navy and
					making war upon the barbarians; for the other was naturally fitted for war, and himself for civil affairs. Eubulus
					also the Anaphlystian is much commended, that, having
					credit and authority in matters of the greatest importance,
					he managed none of the Grecian affairs, nor betook himself to the conducting of the army; but employing himself
					about the treasure, he augmented the public revenues,
					and greatly benefited the city by them. But Iphicrates,
					practising to make declamations at his own house in the
					presence of many, rendered himself ridiculous; for though
					he had been no bad orator but an excellently good one, yet
					ought he to have contented himself with the glory got by
					arms, and abstaining from the school, to have left it to the
					sophisters.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>But since it is incident to every populacy to be
				malicious and desirous to find fault with their governors,
				and since they are apt to suspect that many, even useful
				things, if they pass without being opposed or contradicted,
				are done by conspiracy, and since this principally brings
				societies and friendships into obloquy; they must not
				indeed leave any real enmity or dissension against themselves, as did Onomademus, a demagogue of the Chians,
				who, having mastered a sedition, suffered not all his adversaries to be expelled the city; lest, said he, we should
				begin to differ with our friends, when we are wholly freed
				from our enemies; for this would be indeed a folly. But
				when the multitude shall have conceived a suspicion against
				any important beneficial project, they must not, as if it
				were by confederacy, all deliver the same opinion; but
				two or three of them must dissent, and mildly oppose their
				friend, and afterwards, as if they were convinced by reason,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.130"/>
				
				change their sentiments; for by this means they draw along
				with them the people, who think them moved by the beneficialness of the thing. But in small matters, and such as
				are of no great consequence, it is not amiss to suffer his
				friends really to differ, every one following his own private
				reason; that so in the principal and greatest concerns, they
				may not seem to act upon design, when they shall unanimously agree to what is best.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>The politician therefore is by nature always the
				prince of the city, as the king among the bees; and in
				consideration of this, he ought always to have the helm of
				public affairs in his hand. But as for those dignities and
				offices to which persons are nominated and chosen by the
				suffrages of the people, he should neither too eagerly nor
				too often pursue them,&mdash;the seeking after offices being
				neither venerable nor popular,&mdash;nor yet should he reject
				them, when the people legally confer them on him and
				invite him to them, but even though they are below his
				reputation, he should accept them and willingly employ
				himself in them; for it is but just that they who have
				been honored by offices of greater dignity should in return
				grace those of inferior rank. And in those more weighty
				and superior employs, such as are the commanding of the
				armies in Athens, the Prytania in Rhodes, and the Boeotarchy amongst us, he should carry himself with such
				moderation as to remit and abate something of their grandeur, adding somewhat of dignity and venerableness to
				those that are meaner and less esteemed, that he may be
				neither despised for these nor envied for those.</p>
            <p>Now it behooves him that enters upon any office, not
					only to have at hand those arguments of which Pericles
					put himself in mind when he first received the robe of
					state: Bethink thyself, Pericles, thou govern'st freemen,
					thou govern'st Grecians, yea, citizens of Athens; but
					farther also, he ought to say thus with himself: Thou,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.131"/>
					
					being a subject, govern'st a city which is under the obedience of Caesar's proconsul or lieutenant. Here is no
					fight in a fair field, this is not the ancient Sardis, nor is
					this the puissance of the Lydians. Thou must make thy
					robe scantier, look from the pavilion to the tribunal, and
					not place too great confidence in thy crown, since thou
					see'st the Roman's shoes over thy head. But in this the
					stage-players are to be imitated, who add indeed to the
					play their own passionate transports, behavior, and countenance, suitable to the person they represent, but yet give
					ear to the prompter, and transgress not the rhyme and
					measures of the faculty granted them by their masters.
					For an error in government brings not, as in the acting of
					a tragedy, only hissing and derision; but many have by
					this means subjected themselves to that
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Severe chastiser, the neck-cutting axe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>As it befell your countryman Pardalas, when he forgot the
					limits of his power. Another, being banished from home
					and confined to a little island, as Solon has it,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Became at last from an Athenian
						</l>
                     <l>A Pholegandrian or Sicinitan.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For we laugh indeed, when we see little children endeavoring to fasten their father's shoes on their own feet, or
					setting their crowns on their own heads in sport. But the
					governors of cities, foolishly exhorting the people to imitate those works, achievements, and actions of their ancestors which are not suitable to the present times and affairs,
					elevate the multitude, and although they do things that are
					ridiculous, they yet meet with a fate which is not fit to be
					laughed at, unless they are men altogether despised. For
					there are many other facts of the ancient Greeks, the recital of which to those who are now living may serve to
					form and moderate their manners; as would be the relating at Athens, not the warlike exploits of their progenitors,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.132"/>
					
					but (for example) the decree of amnesty after the expulsion of the Thirty Tyrants; the fining of Phrynicus, who
					represented in a tragedy the taking of Miletus; how they
					wore garlands on their heads when Cassander rebuilt
					Thebes; how, having intelligence of the Scytalism (or
					slaughter) at Argos in which the Argives put to death fifteen hundred of their own citizens, they commanded a
					lustration (or expiatory sacrifice) to be carried about in a
					full assembly; and how, when they were searching of
					houses for those that were confederated with Harpalus,
					they passed by only one, which was inhabited by a man
					newly married. For by the imitating of such things as
					these, they may even now resemble their ancestors; but
					the fights at Marathon, Eurymedon, and Plataea, and whatever examples vainly puff up and heighten the multitude,
					should be left to the schools of the sophisters.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Now a statesman ought not only to exhibit himself
				and his country blameless to the prince, but also to have
				always for his friend some one of those that are most
				powerful above, as a firm support of polity; for the Romans are of such a disposition, that they are most ready to
				assist their friends in their political endeavors. It is good
				also, when we have received benefit from friendship with
				princes, to apply it to the advancement of our country;
				as did Polybius and Panaetius, who through the favor of
				Scipio to them greatly advantaged their countries for the
				obtaining felicity. So Caesar Augustus, when he had
				taken Alexandria, made his entry into it, holding Arius
				by the hand, and discoursing with him alone of all his
				familiars; after which he said to the Alexandrians, who
				expecting the utmost severity supplicated his favor, that
				he pardoned them first for the greatness of their city,
				secondly for its builder, Alexander, and thirdly, added he,
				to gratify this my friend. Is it then fit to compare to this
				benefit those exceeding gainful commissions and administrations
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.133"/>
				
				 of provinces, in the pursuit of which many even
				grow old at other men's doors, leaving their own domestic
				affairs in the mean time unregarded? Or should we rather
				correct Euripides, singing and saying that, if one must
				watch and sue at another's court and subject one's self to
				some great man's familiarity, it is most commendable so
				to do for the sake of one's country; but otherwise, we
				should embrace and pursue friendships on equal and just
				conditions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Yet ought not he who renders and exhibits his
				country obsequious to potent princes to contribute to the
				oppressing of it, nor having tied its legs to subject also its
				neck, as some do who, referring all things both great and
				little to these potentates, upbraid it with servitude, or rather
				wholly take away the commonwealth, rendering it astonished, timorous, and without command of any thing. For
				as those who are accustomed neither to sup nor bathe
				without the physician do not make so much use of their
				health as Nature affords them; so they who introduce the
				prince's judgment into every decree, council, favor, and
				administration, necessitate the princes to be more masters
				of them than they desire. Now the cause of this is principally the avarice and ambition of the chief citizens. For
				either, by injuring their inferiors, they compel them to fly
				out of the city; or in such things wherein they differ from
				one another, disdaining to be worsted by their fellow-citizens, they bring in such as are more powerful, whence
				both the council, people, courts of judicature, and whole
				magistracy lose their authority. But he ought to appease
				private citizens by equality, and mightier men by mutual
				submissions, so as to keep peace within the commonweal,
				and coolly to determine their affairs; making for these
				things, as it were for secret diseases, a certain political
				medicine, both being himself rather willing to be vanquished amongst his fellow-citizens, than to get the better
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.134"/>
				
				by the injury and dissolution of his country's rights, and
				requesting the same of every one else, and teaching them
				how great a mischief this obstinacy in contending is. But
				now, rather than they will with honor and benignity mutually yield to their fellow-citizens, kinsmen, neighbors,
				and colleagues in office, they do, with no less prejudice
				than shame, carry forth their dissensions to the doors of
				the pleaders, and put them into the hands of pragmatical
				lawyers.</p>
            <p>Physicians indeed turn and drive forth into the superficies of the body such diseases as they are not able utterly
					to extirpate; but a statesman, though he cannot keep a
					city altogether free from internal troubles, yet should, by
					concealing its disturbance and sedition, endeavor to cure
					and compose it, so that it may least stand in need of physicians and medicines from abroad. For the intention of
					a statesman should be fixed upon the public safety, and
					should shun, as has been said, the tumultuous and furious
					motion of vain-glory; and yet in his disposition there
					should be magnanimity,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And undaunted courage,&mdash;as becomes
						</l>
                     <l>The men, who are for their dear country's right
						</l>
                     <l>Prepared till death 'gainst stoutest foes to fight,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. XVII. 156.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and who are bravely resolved, not only to hazard their
					lives against the assaults of invading enemies, but also to
					struggle with the most difficult affairs, and stem the torrent of the most dangerous and impetuous times. For as
					he must not himself be a creator of storms and tempests,
					so neither must he abandon the ship of the state when
					they come upon it; and as he ought not to raise commotions and drive it into danger, so is he obliged, when it
					is tossed and is in peril, to give it his utmost assistance, putting forth all his boldness of speech, as he would throw out
					a sacred anchor when affairs are at the greatest extremity.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.135"/>
					
					Such were the difficulties that befell the Pergamenians
					under Nero, and the Rhodians lately under Domitian, and
					the Thessalians heretofore in the time of Augustus, when
					they burned Petraeus alive.
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>You shall not in this case demurring see,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. IV. 223</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>or starting back for fear, any one who is truly a statesman;
					neither shall you find him accusing others and withdrawing himself out of harm's way; but you shall have him
					rather going on embassies, sailing to foreign parts, and not
					only saying first,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>We're here, Apollo, who the murther wrought,
						</l>
                     <l>No longer plague our country for our fault,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but also ready to undergo perils and dangers for the multitude, even though he has not been at all partaker of their
					crime. For this indeed is a gallant action; and besides its
					honesty, one only man's virtue and magnanimity has often
					wonderfully mitigated the anger conceived against a whole
					multitude, and dissipated the terror and bitterness with
					which- they were threatened. Such an influence with a
					king of Persia had the deportment of Sperchis and Bulis,
					two noble Spartans; and equally prevalent was the speech
					of Stheno with Pompey, when, being about to punish the
					Mamertines for their defection, he was told by Stheno, that
					he would not act justly if he should for one guilty person
					destroy abundance of innocents; for that he himself had
					caused the revolt of the city, by persuading his friends and
					forcing his enemies to that attempt. This speech did so
					dispose Pompey, that he both pardoned the city and courteously treated Stheno. But Sylla's host, having used the
					like virtue towards an unlike person, generously ended his
					days. For when Sylla, having taken the city of Praeneste, determined to put all the rest of the inhabitants to
					the sword, and to spare only him for the hospitality that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.136"/>
					
					had been between them, he, saying that he would not be
					indebted for his preservation to the destroyer of his country, thrust himself in amongst his fellow-citizens, and was
					massacred with them. We ought therefore indeed to
					deprecate such times as these, and hope for better things.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>Moreover, we should honor, as a great and sacred
				thing, every magistracy and magistrate. Now the mutual
				concord and friendship of magistrates with one another is
				a far greater honor of magistracy than their diadems and
				purple-garded robes. Now those who lay for a foundation
				of friendship their having been fellow-soldiers or having
				spent their youth together, and take their being joint commanders or co-magistrates for a cause of enmity, cannot
				avoid being guilty of one of these three evils. For either,
				regarding their colleagues in government as their equals,
				they brangle with them; or looking on them as their superiors, they envy them; or esteeming them their inferiors,
				they despise them; whereas, indeed, one ought to court
				his superior, advance his inferior, honor his equal, and love
				and embrace all, as having been made friends, not by eating at the same table, drinking in the same cup, or meeting
				at the same solemn feast, but by a common and public
				bond, and having in some sort an hereditary benevolence
				derived from their country. Scipio therefore was ill spoken
				of in Rome, for that, making a feast for his friends at the
				dedication of a temple to Hercules, he invited not to it his
				colleague Mummius; for, though in other things they took
				not one another for friends, yet in such occurrences as
				these they should have mutually honored and caressed
				each other, for the sake of their common magistracy. If
				then the omission of so small a civility brought Scipio,
				who was otherwise an admirable man, under a suspicion
				of arrogancy; how can he who seeks to impair the dignity
				of his colleague, or to obfuscate the lustre of his actions,
				or through insolency to draw and attribute all things to
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.137"/>
				
				himself, taking them wholly from his companion, be esteemed reasonable and moderate? I remember that, when
				I was yet but a young man, being jointly with another sent
				on an embassy to the proconsul, and my companion&mdash;I
				know not on what occasion&mdash;stopping by the way, I went
				on alone and performed the affair. Now when at my return I was to render an account of my charge, my father,
				taking me aside, admonished me not to say <hi rend="italics">I went</hi> but <hi rend="italics">We
					went,</hi> not <hi rend="italics">I spoke</hi> but <hi rend="italics">We spoke,</hi> and so through all the
				rest to make my report by associating my companion, and
				rendering him a sharer in my actions. For this is not only
				decent and courteous, but also takes from glory what is
				offensive, that is, envy. Whence it is that great men generally co-ascribe their most glorious actions to their Daemon
				or Fortune; as did Timoleon, who having destroyed the
				tyrannies in Sicily, consecrated a temple to Chance; and
				Python, when, being admired and honored by the Athenians
				for having slain Cotys, he said, God did this, making use
				of my hand. But Theopompus, king of the Lacedaemonians, when one said that Sparta was preserved because its
				kings were well skilled in governing, replied: 'Tis rather
				because the people are well versed in obeying.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>These two things then are affected by each other;
				yet most men both say and think that the business of political instruction is to render the people pliable to be
				governed. For there are in every city more governed than
				governors, and every one who lives in a democracy rules
				only a short time, but is subject all his life, so that it is the
				most excellent and useful lesson we can learn, to obey
				those who are set over us, though they are less furnished
				with authority and reputation.</p>
            <p>For it is absurd that a Theodorus or a Polus, the principal
					actor in a tragedy, should often obey a hireling who plays
					the third part, and speak humbly to him because he wears
					a diadem and a sceptre; and that in real actions and in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.138"/>
					
					the government of the state, a rich and mighty man should
					undervalue and contemn a magistrate because he is simple
					and poor, thus injuring and degrading the dignity of the
					commonweal by his own; whereas he should rather by his
					own reputation and authority have increased and advanced
					that of the magistrate. As in Sparta the kings rose up
					out of their thrones to the ephors, and whoever else was
					sent for by them did not slowly obey, but running hastily
					and with speed through the forum, gave a pattern of obedience to his fellow-citizens, whilst he gloried in honoring
					the magistrates; not like to some ill-bred and barbarous
					persons, who, priding themselves in the abundance of their
					power, affront the judges of the public combats, revile
					the directors of the dances in the Bacchanals, and deride
					military commanders and those that preside over the exercises of youth, neither knowing nor understanding that to
					honor is sometimes more glorious than to be honored. For
					to a man of great authority in a city, his accompanying
					and attending on the magistrate is a greater grace than if
					he were himself accompanied and attended on by him; or
					rather this indeed would bring trouble and envy, but that
					brings real glory, and such as proceeds from kindness and
					good-will. And such a man, being seen sometimes at the
					magistrate's door, and saluting him first, and giving him
					the middle place in walking, does, without taking any
					thing from himself, add ornament to the city.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>It is also a popular thing and wins greatly on the
				multitude, to bear patiently the reproaches and indignation
				of a magistrate, saying either with Diomedes,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great glory soon will follow this,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IV. 415.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>or this, which was sometime said by Demosthenes,&mdash;that
					he is not now Demosthenes only, but a magistrate, or
					a director of public dances, or a wearer of a diadem.
					Let us therefore lay aside our revenge for a time; for
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.139"/>
					
					either we shall come upon him when he is dismissed
					from his office, or shall by delaying gain a cessation of
					anger.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Indeed one should in diligence, providence, and care
				for the public always strive with every magistrate, advising
				them,&mdash;if they are gracious and well behaved,&mdash;of such
				things as are requisite, warning them, and giving them
				opportunities to make use of such things as have been
				rightly counselled, and helping them to advance the common good; but if there is in them any sloth, delay, or ill-disposedness to action, then ought one to go himself and
				speak to the people, and not to neglect or omit the public
				on pretence that it becomes not one magistrate to be
				curious and play the busybody in another's province. For
				the law always gives the first rank in government to him
				who does what is just and knows what is convenient.
				<q direct="unspecified">There was,</q> says Xenophon,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xen. Anab. III. 1, 4.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">one in the army named
					Xenophon, who was neither general nor inferior commander;</q> but yet this man, by his skill in what was fit and
				boldness in attempting, raising himself to command, preserved the Grecians. Now of all Philopoemen's deeds
				this is the most illustrious, that Agis<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably a mistake for <hi rend="italics">Nabis.</hi> See Plutarch's Life of Philopoemen, &sect; 12. (G.)</note> having surprised
				Messene, and the general of the Achaeans being unwilling
				and fearful to go and rescue it, he with some of the forwardest spirits did without a commission make an assault
				and recover it. Yet are we not to attempt innovations on
				every light or trivial occasion; but only in cases of necessity, as did Philopoemen, or for the performance of some
				honorable actions, as did Epaminondas when he continued
				in the Boeotarchy four months longer than was allowed by
				the law, during which he brake into Laconia and re-edified
				Messene. Whence, if any complaint or accusation shall
				on this occasion happen, we may in our defence against
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.140"/>
				
				such accusation plead necessity, or have the greatness and
				gallantry of the action as a comfort for the danger.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>There is recorded a saying of Jason, monarch of
				the Thessalians, which he always had in his mouth when
				he outraged or molested any, that there is a necessity for
				those to be unjust in small matters who will act justly in
				great ones. Now that speech one may presently discern
				to have been made by a despot. But more political is this
				precept, to gratify the populacy with the passing over
				small things, that we may oppose and hinder them when
				they are like to offend in greater. For he that will be
				exact and earnest in all things, never yielding or conniving,
				but always severe and inexorable, accustoms the people to
				strive obstinately, and behave themselves perversely towards him.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But when the waves beat high, the sheet should be
					</l>
                     <l>A little slackened,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>sometimes by unbending himself and sporting graciously
					with them, as in the celebrating of festival sacrifices,
					assisting at public games, and being a spectator at the
					theatres, and sometimes by seeming neither to see nor
					hear, as we pass by the faults of such children in our
					houses; that the faculty of freely chastising and reprehending, being&mdash;like a medicine&mdash;not antiquated or debilitated by use, but having its full vigor and authority,
					may more forcibly move and operate on the multitude in
					matters of greater importance.</p>
            <p>Alexander, being informed that his sister was too familiarly acquainted with a certain handsome young man, was
					not displeased at it, but said, that she also must be permitted to have some enjoyment of the royalty; acting in
					this concession neither rightly nor as beseemed himself;
					for the dissolution and dishonoring of the state ought not
					to be esteemed an enjoyment. But a statesman will not to
					his power permit the people to injure any private citizens,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.141"/>
					
					to confiscate other men's estates, or to share the public
					stock amongst them; but will by persuading, instructing,
					and threatening oppugn such irregular desires, by the feeding and increasing of which Cleon caused many a stinging
					drone, as Plato says, to breed in the city. But if the multitude, taking occasion from some solemn feast of the
					country or the veneration of some God, shall be inclined
					either to exhibit some show, to make some small distribution, to bestow some courteous gratification, or to perform
					some other magnificence, let them in such matters have an
					enjoyment both of their liberality and abundance. For
					there are many examples of such things in the governments of Pericles and Demetrius; and Cimon adorned the
					market-place by planting rows of plane-trees and making
					of walks. Cato also, seeing the populacy in the time of
					Catiline's conspiracy put in a commotion by Caesar, and
					dangerously inclined to make a change in the government,
					persuaded the senate to decree some distributions of money
					amongst the poor, and this being done appeased the tumult
					and quieted the sedition. For, as a physician, having
					taken from his patient great store of corrupt blood, gives
					him a little innocent nourishment; so a statesman, having
					taken from the people some great thing which was either
					inglorious or prejudicial, does again by some small and
					courteous gratuity still their morose and complaining
					humor.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>It is not amiss also dexterously to turn aside the
				eager desires of the people to other useful things, as
				Demades did when he had the revenues of the city under
				his management. For they being bent to send galleys to
				the assistance of those who were in rebellion against Alexander, and commanding him to furnish out money for that
				purpose, he said to them: You have money ready, for I
				have made provision against the Bacchanals, that every
				one of you may receive half a mina; but if you had rather
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.142"/>
				
				have it employed this way, make use as you please of your
				own. And by this means taking them off from sending
				the fleet, lest they should be deprived of the dividend, he
				kept the people from offending Alexander. For there are
				many prejudicial things to which we cannot directly put a
				stop, but we must for that end make use of turning and
				winding; as did Phocion, when he was required at an unseasonable time to make an incursion into Boeotia. For he
				immediately caused proclamation to be made, that all from
				sixteen years of age to sixty should prepare to follow
				him; and when there arose upon it a mutiny amongst the
				old men, he said: There is no hardship put upon you, for
				I, who am above fourscore years old, shall be your general.
				In this manner also is the sending of embassies to be put
				off, by joining in the commission such as are unprepared;
				and the raising of unprofitable buildings, by bidding them
				contribute to it; and the following of indecent suits, by
				ordering the prosecutors to appear together and go together
				from the court. Now the proposers and inciters of the
				people to such things are first to be drawn and associated
				for the doing them; for so they will either by their shifting
				it off seem to break the matter, or by their accepting of it
				have their share in the trouble.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>But when some great and useful matter, yet such as
				requires much struggling and industry, is to be taken in
				hand, endeavor to choose the most powerful of your friends,
				or rather the mildest of the most powerful; for they will
				least thwart you and most co-operate with you, having
				wisdom without a contentious humor. Nevertheless, thoroughly understanding your own nature, you ought, in that
				for which you are naturally less fit, rather to make choice
				of such as are of suitable abilities, than of such as are
				like yourself; as Diomedes, when he went forth to spy,
				passing by the valiant, took for his companion one that was
				prudent and cautious. For thus are actions better counterpoised,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.143"/>
				
				 and there is no contention bred betwixt them,
				when they desire honor from different virtues and qualities.
				If therefore you are yourself no good speaker, choose for
				your assistant in a suit or your companion in an embassy an eloquent man, as Pelopidas did Epaminondas;
				if you are unfit to persuade and converse with the multitude, being too high-minded for it, as was Callicratidas,
				take one that is gracious and courtly; if you are infirm of
				body and unable to undergo fatigues, make choice of one
				who is robust and a lover of labor, as Nicias did of Lamachus. For thus Geryon would have become admirable,
				having many legs, hands, and eyes, if only they had been
				all governed by one soul. But it is in the power of statesmen&mdash;by conferring together, if they are unanimous, not
				only their bodies and wealth, but also their fortunes, authorities, and virtues, to one common use&mdash;to perform the
				same action with greater glory than any one person; not
				as did the Argonauts, who, having left Hercules, were necessitated to have recourse to female subtleties and be subject to enchantments and sorceries, that they might save
				themselves and steal away the fleece.</p>
            <p>Men indeed entering into some temples leave their gold
					without; but iron, that I may speak my mind in a word,
					they never carry into any. Since then the tribunal is a
					temple common to Jupiter the counsellor and protector of
					cities, to Themis, and to Justice, from the very beginning,
					before thou enterest into it, stripping thy soul of avarice
					and the love of wealth, cast them into the shops of bankers and usurers,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And from them turn thyself,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. V. 350.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>esteeming him who heaps up treasures by the management
					of public affairs to rob the temples, plunder graves, and
					steal from his friends, and enriching himself by treachery
					and bearing of false witness, to be an unfaithful counsellor,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.144"/>
					
					a perjured judge, a bribe-taking magistrate, and in brief,
					free from no injustice. Whence it is not necessary to say
					much concerning this matter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Now ambition, though it is more specious than covetousness, brings yet no less plagues into a state. For it is
				usually more accompanied with boldness, as being bred,
				not in slothful and abject spirits, but chiefly in such as are
				vigorous and active; and the vogue of the people, frequently extolling it and driving it by their praises, renders
				it thereby headstrong and hard to be managed. As therefore Plato advised, that we should even from our infancy
				inculcate into young people, that it is not fit for them to
				wear gold about them abroad nor yet to be possessors of
				it, as having a peculiar treasure of their own, immixed
				with their souls,&mdash;enigmatically, as I conceive, insinuating
				the virtue propagated in their natures from the race or stock
				of which they are descended,&mdash;so let us also moderate our
				ambition by saying, that we have in ourselves uncorrupted
				gold, that is, honor unmixed, and free from envy and reprehension, which is still augmented by the consideration and
				contemplation of our acts and jests in the service of the
				commonweal. Wherefore we stand not in need of honors
				painted, cast, or engraven in brass, in which what is most
				admired frequently belongs to another. For the statue of
				a trumpeter or halberdier is not commended or esteemed
				for the sake of the person whom it is made to represent,
				but for that of the workman by whom it is made. And
				Cato, when Rome was in a manner filled with statues,
				would not suffer his to be erected, saying, I had rather
				men should ask why my statue is not set up, than why it
				is. For such things are subject to envy, and the people
				think themselves obliged to those who have not received
				them; whereas those who have received them are esteemed
				burthensome, as seeking public employs for a reward. For
				as he does no great or glorious act who, having without
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.145"/>
				
				danger sailed along the Syrtis, is afterwards cast away in
				the harbor; so he who, having kept himself safe in passing through the treasury and the management of the
				public revenues, is caught with a presidency or a place in
				the Prytaneum, not only dashes against an high promontory, but is likewise drowned.</p>
            <p>He then is best, who desires none of these things, but
					shuns and refuses them all. But if perhaps it is not easy
					wholly to decline a favor or testimonial of the people's
					amity, when they are fully bent to bestow it, yet for those
					who have in the service of the state contended not for silver or presents, but have fought a fight truly sacred and
					deserving a crown, let an inscription, a tablet, a decree, or
					a branch of laurel or olive suffice, such as Epimenides received out of the castle of Athens for having purified the
					city. So Anaxagoras, putting back the other honors that
					were given him, desired that on the day of his death the
					children might have leave to play and intermit their studies. And to the seven Persians who killed the Magi it was
					granted that they and their posterity should wear their
					turban on the fore part of the head; for this, it seems,
					they had made the signal, when they went about that attempt. The honor also which Pittacus received had something political; for being bid to take what portion he
					would of the land he had gotten for his citizens, he accepted as much as he could reach with the cast of his dart.
					So Codes the Roman took as much as he himself, being
					lame, could plough in a day. For the honor should not be a
					recompense of the action, but an acknowledgment of gratitude, that it may continue also long, as those did which we
					have mentioned. But of the three hundred statues erected
					to Demetrius Phalereus, not one was eaten into by rust or
					covered with filth, they being all pulled down whilst himself was yet alive; and those of Demades were melted
					into chamber-pots. Many other honors also have undergone
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.146"/>
					
					 the like fate, being regarded with an ill eye, not only
					for the wickedness of the receiver, but also for the greatness of the gift. A moderation in the expense is therefore
					the best and surest preservative of honors; for such as
					are great, immense, and ponderous are like to unproportioned statues, soon overthrown.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Now I here call those honors which the people,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whose right it is, so name; with them I speak:</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Empedocles has it; since a wise statesman will not despise true honor and favor, consisting in the good-will and
					friendly disposition of those who gratefully remember his
					services; nor will he contemn glory by shunning to please
					his neighbors, as Democritus would have him. For neither the fawning of dogs nor the affection of horses is to be
					rejected by huntsmen and jockeys; nay, it is both profitable and pleasant to breed in those animals which are
					brought up in our houses and live with us, such a disposition towards one's self as Lysimachus's dog showed to his
					master, and as the poet relates Achilles's horses to have
					had towards Patroclus.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. XIX. 404.</note> And I am of opinion that bees
					would fare better if they would make much of those who
					breed them and look after them, and would admit them to
					come near them, than they do by stinging them and driving them away; for now their keepers punish them by
					smothering them with smoke; so they tame unruly horses
					with short bits; and dogs that are apt to run away, by collaring them and fastening them to clogs. But there is
					nothing which renders one man so obsequious and submissive to another, as the confidence of his good-will, and the
					opinion of his integrity and justice. Wherefore Demosthenes rightly affirmed, that the greatest preservative of
					states against tyrants is distrust. For the part of the soul
					by which we believe is most apt to be caught. As therefore
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.147"/>
					
					 Cassandra's gift of prophecy was of no advantage to
					the citizens of Troy, who would not believe her:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The God (says she) would have me to foretell
						</l>
                     <l>Things unbelieved; for when the people well
						</l>
                     <l>Have smarted, groaning under pressures sad,
						</l>
                     <l>They style me wise, till then they think me mad;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so the confidence the citizens had in Archytas, and their
					good-will towards Battus, were highly advantageous to
					those who would make use of them through the good
					opinion they had of them.</p>
            <p>Now the first greatest benefit which is in the reputation
					of statesmen is the confidence that is had in them, giving
					them an entrance into affairs; and the second is, that the
					good-will of the multitude is an armor to the good against
					those that are envious and wicked; for,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As when the careful mother drives the flies
						</l>
                     <l>From her dear babe, which sweetly sleeping lies,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IV. 130.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>it chases away envy, and renders the plebeian equal in authority to the nobleman, the poor man to the rich, and
					the private man to the magistrates; and in a word, when
					truth and virtue are joined with it, it is a strange and favorable wind, directly carrying men into government. And
					on the other side behold and learn by examples the mischievous effects of the contrary disposition. For those of
					Italy slew the wife and children of Dionysius, having first
					violated and polluted them with their lusts; and afterwards burning their bodies, scattered the ashes out of the
					ship into the sea. But when one Menander, who had
					reigned graciously over the Bactrians, died afterwards in
					the camp, the cities indeed by common consent celebrated
					his funeral; but coming to a contest about his relics, they
					were difficultly at last brought to this agreement, that his
					ashes being distributed, every one of them should carry
					away an equal share, and they should all erect monuments
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.148"/>
					
					to him. Again, the Agrigentines, being got rid of Phalaris, made a decree, that none should wear a blue garment;
					for the tyrant's attendants had blue liveries. But the Persians, because Cyrus was hawk-nosed, do to this day love
					such men and esteem them handsomest.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>That is of all loves the strongest and divinest, which
				is by cities and states borne to any man for his virtue. But
				those false-named honors and false testimonials of amity,
				which have their rise from stage-plays, largesses, and fencings, are not unlike the flatteries of whores; the people
				always with smiles bestowing an unconstant and short-lived
				glory on him that presents them and gratifies them.</p>
            <p>He therefore who said, the people were first overthrown
					by him which first bestowed largesses on them, very well
					understood that the multitude lose their strength, being
					rendered weaker by receiving. But these bestowers must
					also know that they destroy themselves, when, purchasing
					glory at great expenses, they make the multitude haughty
					and arrogant, as having it in their power to give and take
					away some very great matter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Yet are we not therefore to act sordidly in the distribution of honorary presents, when there is plenty enough.
				For the people more hate a rich man who gives nothing
				of his own, than they do a poor man that robs the public
				treasury; attributing the former to pride and a contempt
				of them, but the latter to necessity. First, therefore, let
				these largesses be made gratis, for so they more oblige the
				receivers, and strike them with admiration; then, on some
				occasion that has a handsome and laudable pretence, with
				the honor of some God wholly drawing the people to
				devotion; for so there is at the same time bred in them a
				strong apprehension and opinion that the Deity is great
				and venerable, when they see those whom they honor and
				highly esteem so bountifully and readily expending their
				wealth upon his honor. As therefore Plato forbade
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.149"/>
				
				young men who were to be liberally educated to learn the
				Lydian and Phrygian harmony,&mdash;one of which excites the
				mournful and melancholy part of our soul, whilst the other
				increases its inclination to pleasure and sensual delight,&mdash;
				so do you, as much as possibly you can, drive out of the
				city all such largesses as either foster and cherish brutality
				and savageness, or scurrility and lasciviousness; and if
				that cannot be, at least shun them, and oppose the many
				when they desire such spectacles; always making the subjects of our expenses useful and modest, having for their
				end what is good and necessary, or at least what is pleasant
				and acceptable, without any prejudice or injury.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>But if your estate be but indifferent, and by its
				centre and circumference confined to your necessary use,
				it is neither ungenerous nor base to confess your poverty
				and give place to such as are provided for those honorary
				expenses, and not, by taking up money on usury, to render
				yourself at the same time both miserable and ridiculous by
				such services. For they whose abilities fall short cannot
				well conceal themselves, being compelled either to be
				troublesome to their friends, or to court and flatter usurers,
				so that they get not any honor or power, but rather shame
				and contempt by such expenses. It is therefore always
				useful on such occasions to call to mind Lamachus and
				Phocion. For Phocion, when the Athenians at a solemn
				sacrifice called upon him, and often importuned him to
				give them something, said to them, I should be ashamed
				to give to you, and not pay this Callicles,&mdash;pointing to an
				usurer who was standing by. And as for Lamachus, he
				always put down in his bill of charges, when he was general, the money laid out for his shoes and coat. And to
				Hermon, when he refused the undertaking of an office
				because of his poverty, the Thessalians ordained a puncheon of wine a month, and a bushel and a half of meal
				every four days. It is therefore no shame to confess one's
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.150"/>
				
				poverty; nor are the poor in cities of less authority than
				those who feast and exhibit public shows, if they have
				but gotten freedom of speech and reputation by their
				virtue.</p>
            <p>A statesman ought therefore chiefly to moderate himself
					on such occasions, and neither, being himself on foot, go
					into the field against well-mounted cavaliers, nor, being
					himself poor, vie with those that are rich about race
					matches, theatrical pomps, and magnificent tables and banquets; but he should rather strive to be like those who
					endeavor to manage the city by virtue and prudence, always joined with eloquence; in which there is not only
					honesty and venerableness, but also a gracefulness and
					attractiveness,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Far more to be desired than Croesus' wealth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For a good man is neither insolent nor odious; nor is a discreet person self-conceited,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor with a look severe walks he amongst
						</l>
                     <l>His fellow-citizens;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but he is, on the contrary, courteous, affable, and of easy
					access to all, having his house always open, as a port of
					refuge to those that will make use of him, and showing
					his care and kindness, not only by being assistant in the
					necessities and affairs of those that have recourse to him,
					but also by condoling with those that are in adversity, and
					congratulating and rejoicing with such as have been successful; neither is he troublesome or offensive by the multitude and train of domestics attending him at bath, or by
					taking up of places in the theatres, nor remarkable by
					things invidious for luxury and sumptuousness; but he is
					equal and like to others in his clothes, diet, education of
					his children, and the garb and attendance of his wife, as
					desiring in his comportment and manner of living to be
					like the rest of the people. Then he exhibits himself an
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.151"/>
					
					intelligent counsellor, an unfeed advocate and courteous
					arbitrator between men and their wives, and friends at
					variance amongst themselves; not spending a small part
					of the day for the service of the commonweal at the
					tribunal or in the hall of audience, and employing all the
					lest, and the whole remainder of his life, in drawing to
					himself every sort of negotiations and affairs, as the northeast wind does the clouds; but always employing his cares
					on the public, and reputing polity (or the administration
					of the state) as a busy and active life, and not, as it is
					commonly thought, an easy and idle service; he does by
					all these and such like things turn and draw the many,
					who see that all the flatteries and enticements of others
					are but spurious and deceitful baits, when compared to his
					care and providence. The flatterers indeed of Demetrius
					vouchsafed not to give the other potentates of his time,
					amongst whom Alexander's empire was divided, the title
					of kings, but styled Seleucus master of the elephants,
					Lysimachus treasurer, Ptolemaeus admiral, and Agathocles
					governor of the isles. But the multitude, though they
					may at the beginning reject a good and prudent man, yet
					coning afterwards to understand his veracity and the sincerity of his disposition, esteem him a public-spirited person and a magistrate; and of the others, they think and
					call one a maintainer of choruses, a second a feaster,
					and a third a master of the exercises. Moreover, as at
					the banquets made by Callias or Alcibiades, Socrates only
					is heard, and to Socrates all men's eyes are directed; so in
					sound and healthy states Ismenias bestows largesses, Lichas
					makes suppers, and Niceratus provides choruses; but it is
					Epaminondas, Aristides, and Lysander that govern, manage the state, and lead forth the armies. Which if any
					one considers, he ought not to be dejected or amazed at
					the glory gotten amongst the people from theatres, banqueting-halls, and public buildings; since it lasts but a
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.152"/>
					
					short time, being at an end as soon as the prizes and plays
					are over, and having in them nothing honorable or worthy
					of esteem.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Those that are versed in the keeping and breeding
				of bees look on that hive to be healthiest and in best
				condition, where there is most humming, and which is
				fullest of bustle and noise; but he to whom God has committed the care of the rational and political hive, reputing
				the felicity of the people to consist chiefly in quietness and
				tranquillity, will receive and to his power imitate the rest
				of Solon's ordinances, but will doubt and wonder what it
				was that induced him to decree, that he who, when there
				arises a sedition in the city, adheres to neither party should
				be reputed infamous. For in the body, the beginning of
				its change from sickness to health is not wrought by the
				parts that are infected with the disease, but when the
				temperature of such parts as are sound, growing powerful,
				drives away what is contrary to nature; and in a state,
				where the people are disturbed by a sedition not dangerous
				and mortal, but which will after a while be composed and
				allayed, it is of necessity that there be a mixture of much
				that is uninfected and sound, and that it continue and cohabit in it. For thither flows from the wise what is fit and
				natural, and passes into the part that is diseased. But
				when cities are in an universal commotion, they are in
				danger of being utterly destroyed, unless, being constrained
				by some necessity and chastisement from abroad, they are
				by the force of their miseries reduced to wisdom. Yet
				does it not become you in the time of a sedition to sit as
				if you were neither sensible nor sorry, praising your own
				unconcernedness as a quiet and happy life, and taking delight in the error of others. But on such occasions chiefly
				should you put on the buskin of Theramenes, and conferring with both parties, join yourself to neither. For you will
				not seem a stranger by not being a partaker in injustice,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.153"/>
				
				but a common friend to them all by your assistance; nor
				will you be envied for your not sharing in the calamity,
				when you appear equally to condole with every one of
				them. But the best is, by your providential care to prevent the raising of any sedition; and in this consists the
				greatest and most excellent point, as it were, of the political art. For you are to consider that, the greatest benefits
				a city can enjoy being peace, liberty, plenty, abundance of
				men, and concord, the people have at this time no need of
				statesmen for the procuring of peace; since all war,
				whether with Greeks or barbarians, is wholly taken away
				and banished from us. As for liberty, the people have as
				much as the emperors think fit to grant them, and more
				perhaps would not be expedient. The prudent man therefore will beg the Gods to grant to his fellow-citizens the
				unenvied plenty of the earth, and the kind temper of the
				seasons, and that wives may bear <q direct="unspecified">children like to their
					parents,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 235.</note> and also safety for all that is born and produced.</p>
            <p>There remains therefore to a statesman, of all those
					things that are subject to his charge, this alone, which is
					inferior to none of the other benefits, the keeping of those
					who are co-inhabitants of the same city in perpetual concord and friendship, and the taking away of all contentions,
					animosities, and heart-burnings. In which he shall, as in
					the differences between friends, so converse with the party
					appearing to be most injured, as if he himself seemed also
					a sharer in the injury and equally offended at it, endeavoring afterwards so to appease him, by showing him how
					much those who pass by injuries excel such as strive to
					contend and conquer, not only in good-nature and sweetness of disposition, but also in prudence and magnanimity;
					and how, by remitting a little of their right in small matters, they get the better in the greatest and most important.
					He shall afterwards admonish them both in general and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.154"/>
					
					apart, instructing them in the weakness of the Grecian
					affairs, which it is better for intelligent men to make the
					best of, and to live in peace and concord, than to engage in
					a contest for which fortune has left no reward. For what
					authority, what glory is there remaining for the conquerors? What power is there, which the least decree of a
					proconsul cannot abolish or transfer elsewhere, and which,
					though it should continue, would yet have any thing worth
					our pains? But since, as a conflagration in a town does
					not frequently begin in sacred and public places, but a
					lamp negligently left in a house, or the burning of a little
					trash or rubbish, raises a great fire and works a common
					mischief; so sedition in a state is not always kindled by
					contentions about public affairs, but oftentimes the differences arising from private concerns and jangles, being propagated into the public, have disturbed a whole city. It is
					no less becoming a statesman to remedy and prevent all
					these, so that some of them may never have any being,
					others may quickly be extinguished, and others hindered
					from increasing or taking hold of the public, and confined
					amongst the adversaries themselves. And as himself
					ought to take care for this, so should he advertise others,
					that private disturbances are the occasion of public ones,
					and little of great ones, if they are neglected and suffered
					to proceed without taking care to apply fit remedies to
					them in the beginning.</p>
            <p>In this manner is the greatest and most dangerous disturbance that ever happened in Delphi said to have been
					occasioned by Crates, whose daughter Orgilaus, the son of
					Phalis, being about to marry, it happened that the cup
					they were using in the espousals brake asunder of itself;
					which he taking for an ill omen, left his bride, and went
					away with his father. Crates a little after, charging them
					with taking away a certain golden vessel, used in the sacrifices, caused Orgilaus and his brother, unheard, to be precipitated
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.155"/>
					
					 from the top of a rock to the bottom, and afterwards slew several of their most intimate friends, as they
					were at their devotions in the temple of Providence. After
					many such things were perpetrated, the Delphians, putting
					to death Crates and his companions in the sedition, out of
					their estates which they called excommunicated, built the
					temples in the lower part of the town. In Syracuse also
					there were two young men, betwixt whom there was an
					extraordinary intimacy, one of which, having taken into
					his custody his friend's catamite, vitiated him in his
					absence. The other at his return, by way of retaliation,
					debauched his companion's wife. Then one of the ancient
					senators, coming into the council, proposed the banishing
					of them both before the city was ruined by their filling it
					with enmity. Yet did not he prevail; but a sedition
					arising on this occasion by very great calamities overturned
					a most excellently constituted commonweal. You have
					also a domestical example in the enmity between Pardalus
					and Tyrrhenus, which wanted little of destroying Sardis
					by embroiling it in revolt and war on little and private
					differences. A statesman therefore is not to slight the little
					offences and heart-burnings which, as diseases in a body,
					pass speedily from one to another, but to take them in
					hand, suppress, and cure them. For, as Cato says, by
					attention and carefulness great matters are made little, and
					little ones reduced to nothing. Now there is no better
					artifice of inuring men to this, than the showing one's self
					easily pacified in his own private differences, persisting
					without rancor in matters of the first importance, and
					managing none with obstinacy, contending wrath, or any
					other passion, which may work sharpness or bitterness in
					necessary disputes. For as they bind certain round muffles
					about the hands of those who combat at buffets, that in
					their contests there may not arrive any fatal accident,
					the blows being soft and such as can do no great harm; so
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.156"/>
					
					in such suits and processes with one's fellow-citizens, it is
					best to manage the dispute by making use of pure and
					simple pretences, and not by sharpening and empoisoning
					matters, as if they were weapons, with calumnies, malice,
					and threats, to render them pernicious, great, and public.
					For he who in this manner carries himself with those with
					whom he has affairs will have others also subject to him.
					But contentions about public matters, where private grudges
					are taken away, are soon appeased, and bring no difficult
					or fatal mischiefs.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>