<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Platonicae quaestiones</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.133">
      <body>
         <head>Plutarch's Platonic questions.</head>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>Question I</head>
            <pb id="v.5.p.425"/>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>WHAT IS THE REASON THAT GOD BADE SOCRATES TO ACT THE MIDWIFE'S PART TO OTHERS, BUT CHARGED HIMSELF NOT TO GENERATE; AS HE SAYS IN THEAETETUS?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato, Theaet. p. 149 B.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>FOR he would never have used the name of God in
					such a merry, jesting manner, though Plato in that book
					makes Socrates several times to talk with great boasting
					and arrogance, as he does now. <q direct="unspecified">There are many, dear
						friend, so affected towards me, that they are ready even to
						bite me, when I offer to cure them of the least madness.
						For they will not be persuaded that I do it out of goodwill, because they are ignorant that no God bears ill-will
						to man, and that therefore I wish ill to no man; but I cannot allow myself either to stand in a lie or to stifle the
						truth.</q>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theaet. p. 161 C.</note> Whether therefore did he style his own nature,
					which was of a very strong and pregnant wit, by the name
					of God,&mdash;as Menander says, <q direct="unspecified">For our mind is God,</q> and
					as Heraclitus, <q direct="unspecified">Man's genius is a Deity</q>? Or did some
					divine cause or some Daemon or other impart this way of
					philosophizing to Socrates, whereby always interrogating
					others, he cleared them of pride, error, and ignorance,
					and of being troublesome both to themselves and to
					others? For about that time there happened to be in
					Greece several sophisters; to these some young men paid
					great sums of money, for which they purchased a strong
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.426"/>
					
					opinion of learning and wisdom, and of being stout disputants; but this sort of disputation spent much time in
					trifling squabblings, which were of no credit or profit.
					Now Socrates, using an argumentative discourse by way of
					a purgative remedy, procured belief and authority to what
					he said, because in refuting others he himself affirmed
					nothing; and he the sooner gained upon people, because
					he seemed rather to be inquisitive after the truth as well
					as they, than to maintain his own opinion.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Now, however useful a thing judgment is, it is mightily impeached by the begetting of a man's own fancies.
					For the lover is blinded with the thing loved; and nothing
					of a man's own is so beloved as is the opinion and discourse which he has begotten. And the distribution of
					children, said to be the justest, in respect of discourses is
					the unjustest; for there a man must take his own, but
					here a man must choose the best, though it be another
					man's. Therefore he that has children of his own, is a
					worse judge of other men's; it being true, as the sophister
					said well, <q direct="unspecified">The Eleans would be the most proper judges
						of the Olympic games, were no Eleans gamesters.</q> So he
					that would judge of disputations cannot be just, if he
					either seeks the bays for himself, or is himself antagonist
					to either of the antagonists. For as the Grecian captains,
					when they were to decide by their suffrages who had behaved himself the best, every man of them voted for himself; so there is not a philosopher of them all but would do
					the like, besides those that acknowledge, like Socrates, that
					they can say nothing that is their own; and these only are
					the pure uncorrupt judges of the truth. For as the air in
					the ears, unless it be still and void of noise in itself, with
					out any sound or buzzing, does not exactly take sounds;
					so the philosophical judgment in disputations, if it be disturbed and obstreperous within, is hardly comprehensive
					of what is said without. For our familiar and inbred
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.427"/>
					
					opinion will not admit that which is at variance with itself,
					as the number of sects and parties proves, of which philosophy&mdash;if she deals with them in the best manner&mdash;must hold one to be right, and all the others to be at war
					with the truth in their opinions.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Furthermore, if men can comprehend and know
					nothing, God did justly interdict Socrates the procreation
					of false and unstable discourses, which are like wind-eggs,
					and bid him convince others who were of any other
					opinion. And reasoning, which rids us of the greatest of
					evils, error and vanity of mind, is none of the least benefit
					to us; <q direct="unspecified">For God has not granted this to the Esculapians.</q>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theognis, vs. 482.</note>
					Nor did Socrates give physic to the body; indeed he
					purged the mind of secret corruption. But if there be
					any knowledge of the truth, and if the truth be one, he
					has as much that learns it of him that invented it, as the
					inventor himself. Now he the most easily attains the
					truth, that is persuaded he has it not; and he chooses
					best, just as he that has no children of his own adopts the
					best. Mark this well, that poetry, mathematics, oratory,
					and sophistry, which are the things the Deity forbade Socrates to generate, are of no value; and that of the sole
					wisdom about what is divine and intelligible (which Socrates called amiable and eligible for itself), there is neither
					generation nor invention by man, but reminiscence.
					Wherefore Socrates taught nothing, but suggesting principles of doubt, as birth-pains, to young men, he excited
					and at the same time confirmed the innate notions. This
					he called his Art of Midwifery, which did not (as others
					professed) extrinsically confer intelligence upon his auditors; but demonstrated it to be innate, yet imperfect and
					confused, and in want of a nurse to feed and strengthen it.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.428"/>
					
				           </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>Question II</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>WHY DOES HE CALL THE SUPREME GOD FATHER AND MAKER OF,
						ALL THINGS?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Timaeus, p. 28 C.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Is it because he is (as Homer calls him) of created
					Gods and men the Father, and of brutes and things that
					have no soul the maker? If Chrysippus may be credited,
					he is not properly styled the father of the afterbirth who
					supplied the seed, although it springs from the seed. Or
					has he figuratively called the maker of the world the
					father of it? In his Convivium he calls Phaedrus the
					father of the amatorious discourse which he had introduced; and so in his Phaedrus<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Phaedrus, p. 261 A.</note> he calls him <q direct="unspecified">father of
						noble children,</q> when he had been the occasion of many
					excellent discourses about philosophical matters. Or is
					there any difference between a father and a maker? Or
					between procreation and making? For as what is procreated is also made, but not the contrary; so he that
					procreated did also make, for the procreation of an animal
					is the making of it. Now the work of a maker&mdash;as of
					a builder, a weaver, a musical-instrument maker, or a
					statuary&mdash;is altogether distinct and separate from its
					author; but the principle and power of the procreator is
					implanted in the progeny, and contains his nature, the
					progeny being a piece pulled off the procreator. Since
					therefore the world is neither like a piece of potter's work
					nor joiner's work, but there is a great share of life and
					divinity in it, which God from himself communicated to
					and mixed with matter, God may properly be called Father
					of the world&mdash;since it has life in it&mdash;and also the maker
					of it.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>And since these things come very near to Plato's
					opinion, consider, I pray, whether there may not be some
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.429"/>
					
					probability in them. Whereas the world consists of two
					parts, body and soul, God indeed made not the body; but
					matter being provided, he formed and fitted it, binding up
					and confining what was infinite within proper limits and
					figures. But the soul, partaking of mind, reason, and harmony, was not only the work of God, but part of him;
					not only made by him, but begot by him.
					
				</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>Question III</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>In the Republic,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Republic, VI. pp. 509 D-511 E.</note> he supposes the universe, as one line,
						to be cut into two unequal sections; again he cuts each
						of these sections in two after the same proportion, and
						supposes the two sections first made to constitute the two
						genera of things sensible and things intelligible in the
						universe. The first represents the genus of intelligibles,
						comprehending in the first subdivision the primitive forms
						or ideas, in the second the mathematics. Of sensibles, the
						first subdivision comprehends solid bodies, the second
						comprehends the images and representations of them.
						Moreover, to every one of these four he has assigned its
						proper judicatory faculty;&mdash;to the first, reason; to the
						mathematics, the understanding; to sensibles, belief; to
						images and likenesses, conjecture.</p>
               <p>BUT WHAT DOES HE MEAN BY DIVIDING THE UNIVERSE INTO UN
						EQUAL PARTS? AND WHICH OF THE SECTIONS, THE INTELLIGIBLE OR THE SENSIBLE, IS THE GREATER? FOR IN THIS HE
						HAS NOT EXPLAINED HIMSELF.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>At first sight it will appear that the sensible is the
					greater portion. For the essence of intelligibles being
					indivisible, and in the same respect ever the same, is contracted into a little, and pure; but an essence divisible and
					pervading bodies constitutes the sensible part. Now what
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.430"/>
					
					is immaterial is limited; but body in respect of matter is
					infinite and unlimited, and it becomes sensible only when
					it is defined by partaking of the intelligible. Besides, as
					every sensible has many images, shadows, and representations, and from one and the same original several copies
					may be taken both by nature and art; so the latter must
					needs exceed the former in number, according to Plato,
					who makes things intelligible to be patterns or ideas of
					things sensible, like the originals of images and reflections.
					Further, Plato derives the knowledge of ideas from body
					by abstraction and cutting away, leading us by various
					steps in mathematical discipline from arithmetic to geometry, thence to astronomy, and setting harmony above them
					all. For things become geometrical by the accession of
					magnitude to quantity; solid, by the accession of profundity to magnitude; astronomical, by the accession of motion
					to solidity; harmonical, by the accession of sound to motion. Abstract then sound from moving bodies, motion
					from solids, profundity from superficies, magnitude from
					quantity, we are then come to pure intelligible ideas, which
					have no distinction among themselves in respect of the
					one single intelligible essence. For unity makes no number, unless joined by the infinite binary; then it makes a
					number. And thence we proceed to points, thence to
					lines, from them to superficies, and profundities, and
					bodies, and to the qualities of the bodies so and so qualified. Now the reason is the only judicatory faculty of
					intelligibles; and the understanding is the reason in the
					mathematics, where intelligibles appear as by reflection in
					mirrors. But as to the knowledge of bodies, because of
					their multitude, Nature has given us five powers or distinctions of senses; nor are all bodies discerned by them,
					many escaping sense by reason of their smallness. And
					though every one of us consists of a body and soul, yet
					the hegemonic and intellectual faculty is small, being hid
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.431"/>
					
					in the huge mass of flesh. And the case is the same in
					the universe, as to sensible and intelligible. For intelligibles are the principles of bodily things, but every thing
					is greater than the principle whence it came.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Yet, on the contrary, some will say that, by comparing sensibles with intelligibles, we match things mortal
					with divine, in some measure; for God is in intelligibles.
					Besides, the thing contained is ever less than the containing, and the nature of the universe contains the sensible
					in the intelligible. For God, having placed the soul in
					the middle, hath extended it through all, and hath covered
					it all round with bodies. The soul is invisible, and cannot
					be perceived by any of the senses, as Plato says in his
					Book of Laws; therefore every man must die, but the
					world shall never die. For mortality and dissolution surround every one of our vital faculties. The case is quite
					otherwise in the world; for the corporeal part, contained
					in the middle by the more noble and unalterable principle,
					is ever preserved. And a body is said to be without parts
					and indivisible for its minuteness; but what is incorporeal
					and intelligible is so, as being simple and sincere, and void
					of all firmness and difference. Besides, it were folly to
					think to judge of incorporeal things by corporeal. The
					present, or <hi rend="italics">now,</hi> is said to be without parts and indivisible,
					since it is everywhere and no part of the world is void of
					it. But all affections and actions, and all corruptions and
					generations in the world, are contained by this <hi rend="italics">now.</hi> But
					the mind is judge only of what is intelligible, as the sight
					is of light, by reason of its simplicity and similitude. But
					bodies, having several differences and diversities, are comprehended, some by one judicatory faculty, others by
					another, as by several organs. Yet they do not well who
					despise the intelligible and intelligent faculty in us; for
					being great, it comprehends all sensibles, and attains to
					things divine. The most important thing he himself
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.432"/>
					
					teaches in his Banquet, where he shows us how we
					should use amatorious matters, turning our minds from
					sensible goods to things discernible only by the reason,
					that we ought not to be enslaved by the beauty of any
					body, study, or learning, but laying aside such pusillanimity, should turn to the vast ocean of beauty.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato's Symposium, p. 210 D.</note>
					
				           </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>Question IV</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>WHAT IS THE REASON THAT, THOUGH PLATO ALWAYS SAYS THAT
						THE SOUL IS ANCIENTER THAN THE BODY, AND THAT IT IS THE
						CAUSE AND PRINCIPLE OF ITS RISE, YET HE LIKEWISE SAYS,
						THAT NEITHER COULD THE SOUL EXIST WITHOUT THE BODY, NOR
						THE REASON WITHOUT THE SOUL, BUT THE SOUL IN THE BODY
						AND THE REASON IN THE SOUL? FOR SO THE BODY WILL SEEM
						TO BE AND NOT TO BE, BECAUSE IT BOTH EXISTS WITH THE SOUL,
						AND IS BEGOT BY THE SOUL.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Perhaps what we have often said is true; viz., that the
						soul without reason and the body without form did mutually
						ever coexist, and neither of them had generation or beginning. But after the soul did partake of reason and harmony, and being through consent made wise, it wrought a
						change in matter, and being stronger than the other's motions, it drew and converted these motions to itself. So
						the body of the world drew its original from the soul, and
						became conformable and like to it. For the soul did not
						make the Nature of the body out of itself, or out of nothing; but it wrought an orderly and pliable body out of one
						disorderly and formless. Just as if a man should say that
						the virtue of the seed is with the body, and yet that the
						body of the fig-tree or olive-tree was made of the seed, he
						would not be much out; for the body, its innate motion
						and mutation proceeding from the seed, grew up and became what it is. So, when formless and indefinite matter
						was once formed by the inbeing soul, it received such a
						form and disposition.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>Question V.</head>
            <pb id="v.5.p.433"/>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>WHY, SINCE BODIES AND FIGURES ARE CONTAINED PARTLY BY RECTTLINEARS AND PARTLY BY CIRCLES, DOES HE MAKE ISOSCELES
						TRIANGLES AND TRIANGLES OF UNEQUAL SIDES THE PRINCIPLES
						OF RECTILINEARS; OF WHICH THE ISOSCELES TRIANGLE FORMS
						THE CUBE, THE ELEMENT OF THE EARTH; AND A SCALENE TRIANGLE FORMS THE PYRAMID WHICH IS THE SEED OF FIRE, THE
						OCTAHEDRON WHICH IS THE SEED OF AIR, AND THE ICOSAHEDRON
						WHICH IS THE SEED OF WATER;&mdash;WHILE HE DOES NOT MEDDLE
						WITH CIRCULARS, THOUGH HE DOES MENTION THE GLOBE, WHERE
						HE SAYS THAT EACH OF THE AFORE-RECKONED FIGURES DIVIDES
						A ROUND BODY THAT ENCLOSES IT INTO EQUAL PARTS.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Timaeus, pp. 53-56.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Is their opinion true who think that he ascribed a
					dodecahedron to the globe, when he says that God made
					use of it in delineating the universe? For upon account
					of the multitude of its bases and the obtuseness of its
					angles, avoiding all rectitude, it is flexible, and by circumtension, like globes made of twelve skins, it becomes circular and comprehensive. For it has twenty solid angles,
					each of which is contained by three obtuse planes, and
					each of these contains one and the fifth part of a right
					angle. Now it is made up of twelve equilateral and
					equangular quinquangles (or pentagons), each of which
					consists of thirty of the first scalene triangles. Therefore
					it seems to resemble both the Zodiac and the year, it being
					divided into the same number of parts as these.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Or is a right line in Nature prior to circumference;
					or is circumference but an accident of rectilinear? For a
					right line is said to bend; and a circle is described by a
					centre and distance, which is the place of a right line by
					which a circumference is measured, this being everywhere
					equally distant from the middle. And a cone and a cylinder are made by rectilinears; a cone by keeping one side
					of a triangle fixed and carrying another round with the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.434"/>
					
					base,&mdash;a cylinder, by doing the like with a parallelogram.
					Further, that is nearest to principle which is less; but a
					right is the least of all lines, as it is simple; whereas in a
					circumference one part is convex without, another concave
					within. Besides, numbers are before figures, as unity is
					before a point, which is unity in position. But indeed
					unity is triangular; for every triangular number<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Triangular numbers are those
						of which equilateral triangles can be
						formed in this way:&mdash;
						
						<!--<figure><head>[see figure on page]</head></figure>-->
						
						Such are 3, 6, 10, 15, 21, 28, 36, 45, &amp;c.; that is, numbers formed by adding the
						digits in regular order. (G.)</note> taken
					eight times, by adding unity, becomes quadrate; and this
					happens to unity. Therefore a triangle is before a circle,
					whence a right line is before a circumference. Besides,
					no element is divided into things compounded of itself;
					indeed there is a dissolution of all other things into the
					elements. Now a triangle is divided into no circumference,
					but two diameters cut a circle into four triangles; therefore a rectilinear figure is before a circular, and has more
					of the nature of an element. And Plato himself shows
					that a rectilinear is in the first place, and a circular is only
					consequential and accidental. For when he says the earth
					consists of cubes, each of which is contained with rectilinear superficies, he says the earth is spherical and round.
					Therefore there was no need of making a peculiar element
					for round things, since rectilinears, fitted after a certain
					manner among themselves, do make up this figure.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Besides, a right line, whether great or little, preserves
					the same rectitude; but as to the circumference of a circle,
					the less it is, the crookeder it is; the larger, the straighter.
					Therefore if a convex superficies stands on a plane, it
					sometimes touches the subject plane in a point, sometimes in a line. So that a man may imagine that a circumference is made up of little right lines.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>But observe whether this be not true, that no circle
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.435"/>
					
					or sphere in this world is exact; but since by the tension
					and circumtension of the right lines, or by the minuteness
					of the parts, the difference disappears, the figure seems
					circular and round. Therefore no corruptible body moves
					circularly, but altogether in a right line. To be truly
					spherical is not in a sensible body, but is the element of
					the soul and mind, to which he has given circular motion,
					as being agreeable to their nature.
					
				</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>Question VI</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>HOW COMES IT TO PASS THAT IN PHAEDRUS IT IS SAID, THAT THE
						NATURE OF A WING, BY WHICH ANY THING THAT IS HEAVY IS
						CARRIED UPWARDS, PARTICIPATES MOST OF THE BODY OF GOD?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Phaedrus, p. 246 D.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Is it because the discourse is of love, and love is of
						beauty inherent in a body? Now beauty, by similitude to
						things divine, moves and reminds the soul. Or it may be
						(without too much curiosity) he may be understood in plain
						meaning, to wit, that the several faculties of the soul being
						employed about bodies, the power of reasoning and understanding partakes most about divine and heavenly things;
						which he did not impertinently call a wing, it raising the
						soul from mean and mortal things to things above.
					</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>Question VII</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>IN WHAT SENSE DOES PLATO SAY, THAT THE ANTIPERISTASIS (OR
						REACTION) OF MOTION&mdash;BY REASON THERE IS NO VACUUM&mdash;IS
						THE CAUSE OF THE EFFECTS IN PHYSICIANS' CUPPING-GLASSES, IN
						SWALLOWING, IN THROWING OF WEIGHTS, IN THE RUNNING OF
						WATER, IN THUNDER, IN THE ATTRACTION OF THE LOADSTONE,
						AND IN THE HARMONY OF SOUNDS?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Timaeus, pp. 79-81.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>For it seems unreasonable to ascribe the reason of
					such different effects to the selfsame cause.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>How respiration is made by the reaction of the air,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.436"/>
					
					he has sufficiently shown. But the rest, he says, seem to
					be done miraculously, but really the bodies thrust each
					other aside and change places with one another; while he
					has left for us to determine how each is particularly done.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>As to cupping-glasses, the case is thus: the air next
					to the flesh being comprehended and inflamed by the heat,
					and being made more rare than the pores of the brass, does
					not go into a vacuum (for there is no such thing), but into
					the air that is without the cupping-glass, and has an impulse upon it. This air drives that before it; and each, as
					it gives way, strives to succeed into the place which was
					vacuated by the cession of the first. And so the air approaching the flesh comprehended by the cupping-glass,
					and exciting it, draws the humors into the cupping-glass.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Swallowing takes place in the same way. For the
					cavities about the mouth and stomach are full of air; when
					therefore the meat is squeezed down by the tongue and
					tonsils, the elided air follows what gives way, and also
					forces down the meat.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>Weights also thrown cleave the air and dissipate it,
					as they fall with force; the air recoiling back, according
					to its natural tendency to rush in and fill the vacuity, follows the impulse, and accelerates the motion.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>The fall also of thunderbolts is like to darting any
					thing. For by the blow in the cloud, the fiery matter exploded breaks into the air; and it being broken gives way,
					and again being contracted above, by main force it presses
					the thunderbolt downwards contrary to Nature.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>And neither amber nor the loadstone draws any thing
					to it which is near, nor does any thing spontaneously approach them. But this stone emits strong exhalations, by
					which the adjoining air being impelled forceth that which
					is before it; and this being carried round in the circle, and
					returning into the vacuated place, forcibly draws the iron
					in the same direction. In amber there is a flammeous and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.437"/>
					
					spirituous nature, and this by rubbing on the surface is
					emitted by recluse passages, and does the same that the
					loadstone does. It also draws the lightest and driest of
					adjacent bodies, by reason of their tenuity and weakness;
					for it is not so strong nor so endued with weight and
					strength as to force much air and to act with violence and
					to have power over great bodies, as the magnet has. But
					what is the reason the air never draws a stone, nor wood,
					but iron only, to the loadstone? This is a common question both by them who think the coition of these bodies is
					made by the attraction of the loadstone, and by such as
					think it done by the incitement of the iron. Iron is neither
					so rare as wood, nor altogether so solid as gold or a stone;
					but has certain pores and asperities, which in regard of
					the inequality are proportionable to the air; and the air
					being received in certain seats, and having (as it were) certain stays to cling to, does not slip away; but when it is
					carried up to the stone and strikes against it, it draws the
					iron by force along with it to the stone. Such then may
					be the reason of this.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>But the manner of the waters running over the
					earth is not so evident. But it is observable that the waters
					of lakes and ponds stand immovable, because the air about
					them stagnates immovable and admits of no vacuity. For
					the water on the surface of lakes and seas is troubled and
					fluctuates as the air is moved, it following the motion of
					the air, and moving as it is moved. For the force from
					below causes the hollowness of the wave, and from above
					the swelling thereof; until the air ambient and containing
					the water is still. Therefore the flux of such waters as
					follow the motion of the retreating air, and are impelled
					by that which presses behind, is continued without end.
					And this is the reason that the stream increases with the
					waters, and is slow where the water is weak, the air not
					giving way, and therefore suffering less reaction. So the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.438"/>
					
					water of fountains must needs flow upwards, the extrinsic
					air succeeding into the vacuity and throwing the water
					out. In a close house, that keeps in the air and wind, the
					floor sprinkled with water causes an air or wind, because,
					as the sprinkled water falls, the air gives way. For it is
					so provided by Nature that air and water force one another and give way to one another; because there is no
					vacuity in which one can be settled without feeling the
					change and alteration in the other.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>Concerning symphony, he shows how sounds harmonize. A quick sound is acute, a slow is grave. Therefore acute sounds move the senses the quicker; and these
					dying and grave sounds supervening, what arises from the
					contemperation of one with the other causes pleasure to
					the ear, which we call harmony. And by what has been
					said, it may easily be understood that air is the instrument
					of these things. For sound is the stroke upon the sense
					of the hearer, caused by the air; and the air strikes as it
					is struck by the thing moving,&mdash;if violent, acutely,&mdash;if
					languid, softly. The violent stroke comes quick to the
					ear; then the circumambient air receiving a slower, it affects
					and carries the sense along with it.
					
				</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>Question VIII</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>WHAT MEANS TIMAEUS,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Timaeus, p. 42 D.</note> WHEN HE SAYS THAT SOULS ARE DISPERSED
						IN TO THE EARTH, THE MOON, AND INTO OTHER INSTRUMENTS OF
						TIME?</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Does the earth move like the sun, moon, and five
					planets, which for their motions he calls organs or instruments of time? Or is the earth fixed to the axis of the
					universe; yet not so built as to remain immovable, but to
					turn and wheel about, as Aristarchus and Seleucus have
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.439"/>
					
					shown since; Aristarchus only supposing it, Seleucus positively asserting it? Theophrastus writes how that Plato,
					when he grew old, repented him that he had placed the
					earth in the middle of the universe, which was not its
					place.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Or is this contradictory to Plato's opinion elsewhere,
					and in the Greek instead of <foreign lang="greek">xro/nou</foreign> should it be written <foreign lang="greek">xro/nw|,</foreign>
					taking the dative case instead of the genitive, so that the
					stars will not be said to be instruments, but the bodies of
					animals So Aristotle has defined the soul to be <q direct="unspecified">the
						actual being of a natural organic body, having the power
						of life.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristotle on the Soul, II. 1, with Trendelenburg's note. (G.)</note> The sense then must be this, that souls are
					dispersed into meet organical bodies in time. But this is
					far besides his opinion. For it is not once, but several
					times, that he calls the stars instruments of time; as when
					he says, the sun was made, as well as other planets, for
					the distinction and conservation of the numbers of time.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>It is therefore most proper to understand the earth to
					be here an instrument of time; not that the earth is moved,
					as the stars are; but that, they being carried about it, it
					standing still makes sunset and sunrising, by which the
					first measures of time, nights and days, are circumscribed.
					Wherefore he called it the infallible guard and artificer of
					night and day. For the gnomons of dials are instruments
					and measures of time, not in being moved with the shadows, but in standing still; they being like the earth in
					intercepting the light of the sun when it is down,&mdash;as
					Empedocles says that the earth makes night by intercepting light. This therefore may be Plato's meaning.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>And so much the rather might we consider whether
					the sun is not absurdly and without probability said to
					be made for the distinction of time, with the moon and the
					rest of the planets. For as in other respects the dignity
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.440"/>
					
					of the sun is great; so by Plato in his Republic<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Republic, VI. pp. 508, 509.</note> the sun
					is called the king and lord of the whole sensible nature,
					as the Chief Good is of the intelligible. For it is said to
					be the offspring of Good, it giving both generation and
					appearance to things visible; as it is from Good that things
					intelligible both are and are understood. But that this
					God, having such a nature and so great power, should be
					only an instrument of time, and a sure measure of the difference that happens among the eight orbs, as they are
					slow or swift in motion, seems neither decent nor highly
					rational. It must therefore be said to such as are startled
					at these things, that it is their ignorance to think that time
					is the measure of motion in respect of sooner or later, as
					Aristotle calls it; or quantity in motion, as Speusippus;
					or an interval of motion and nothing more, as some of the
					Stoics define it, by an accident, not comprehending its
					essence and power, which Pindar has not ineptly expressed
					in these words: Time, who surpasses all in the seats of the
					blest. Pythagoras also, when he was asked what time was,
					answered, it was the soul of this world. For time is no
					affection or accident of motion, but the cause, power, and
					principle of that symmetry and order that confines all created beings, by which the animated nature of the universe
					is moved. Or rather, this order and symmetry itself&mdash;so
					far as it is motion&mdash;is called time. For this,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Walking by still and silent ways,
						</l>
                        <l>Mortal affairs with justice guides.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Troad. 887.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>According to the ancients, the essence of the soul is a
						number moving itself. Therefore Plato says that time and
						heaven were coexistent, but that motion was before heaven
						had being. But time was not. For then there neither was
						order, nor measure, nor determination; but indefinite motion, as it were, the formless and rude matter of time.
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.441"/>
						
						. . . But when matter was informed with figures, and
						motion with circuitions, from that came the world, from
						this time. Both are representations of God; the world,
						of his essence; time, of his eternity in the form of motion, as the world is God in creation. Therefore they say
						heaven and motion, being bred together, will perish together, if ever they do perish. For nothing is generated
						without time, nor is any thing intelligible without eternity;
						if this is to endure for ever, and that never to die when
						once bred. Time therefore, having a necessary connection
						and affinity with heaven, cannot be called simple motion,
						but (as it were) motion in order having terms and periods;
						whereof since the sun is prefect and overseer, to determine, moderate, produce, and observe changes and seasons,
						which (according to Heraclitus) produce all things, he is
						coadjutor to the governing and chief God, not in trivial
						things, but in the greatest and most momentous affairs.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>Question IX</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>Since Plato in his Commonwealth, discoursing of the
						faculties of the soul, has very well compared the symphony
						of reason and of the irascible and the concupiscent faculties to the harmony of the middle, lowest, and highest
						chord,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Republic, IV. p. 443 D.</note> some men may properly ask this question:&mdash;</p>
               <p>DID PLATO PLACE THE RATIONAL OR THE IRASCIBLE FACULTY IN
						THE MIDDLE? FOR HE IS NOT CLEAR IN THE POINT.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Indeed, according to the natural order of the parts,
					the place of the irascible faculty must be in the middle,
					and of the rational in the highest, which the Greeks call
					hypate. For they of old called the chief and supreme
					<foreign lang="greek">u(/patos.</foreign> So Xenocrates calls Jove, in respect of immutable
					things, <foreign lang="greek">u(/patos</foreign> (or <hi rend="italics">highest</hi>), in respect of sublunary things
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.442"/>
					
					             <foreign lang="greek">ne:/atos</foreign> (or <hi rend="italics">lowest.</hi>) And long before him, Homer calls the
					chief God <foreign lang="greek">u(/patos kreio/ntwn,</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Highest of Rulers.</hi> And Nature has of due given the highest place to what is most
					excellent, having placed reason as a steersman in the head,
					and the concupiscent faculty at a distance, last of all and
					lowest. And the lowest place they call <foreign lang="greek">nea/th,</foreign> as the names
					of the dead, <foreign lang="greek">ne/rteroi</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">e)/neroi,</foreign> do show. And some say, that
					the south wind, inasmuch as it blows from a low and obscure place, is called <foreign lang="greek">no/tos.</foreign> Now since the concupiscent
					faculty stands in the same opposition to reason in which
					the lowest stands to the highest and the last to the first,
					it is not possible for the reason to be uppermost and first,
					and yet for any other part to be the one called <foreign lang="greek">u(/patos</foreign> (or
					<hi rend="italics">highest</hi>). For they that ascribe the power of the middle
					to it, as the ruling power, are ignorant how they deprive
					it of a higher power, namely, of the highest, which is
					competible neither to the irascible nor to the concupiscent
					faculty; since it is the nature of them both to be governed
					by and obsequious to reason, and the nature of neither of
					them to govern and lead it. And the most natural place
					of the irascible faculty seems to be in the middle of the
					other two. For it is the nature of reason to govern, and
					of the irascible faculty both to govern and be governed,
					since it is obsequious to reason, and commands the concupiscent faculty when this is disobedient to reason. And as
					in letters the semi-vowels are middling between mutes and
					vowels, having something more than those and less than
					these; so in the soul of man, the irascible faculty is not
					purely passive, but hath often an imagination of good
					mixed with the irrational appetite of revenge. Plato himself, after he had compared the soul to a pair of horses
					and a charioteer, likened (as every one knows) the rational
					faculty to the charioteer, and the concupiscent to one of
					the horses, which was resty and unmanageable altogether,
					bristly about the ears, deaf and disobedient both to whip
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.443"/>
					
					and spur; and the irascible he makes for the most part
					very obsequious to the bridle of reason, and assistant to it.
					As therefore in a chariot, the middling one in virtue and
					power is not the charioteer, but that one of the horses which
					is worse than his guider and yet better than his fellow;
					so in the soul, Plato gives the middle place not to the
					principal part, but to that faculty which has less of reason
					than the principal part and more than the third. This
					order also observes the analogy of the symphonies, i.e. the
					relation of the irascible to the rational (which is placed
					as hypate) forming the diatessaron (or fourth), that of the
					irascible to the concupiscent (or nete) forming the diapente (or fifth), and that of the rational to the concupiscent (as hypate to nete) forming an octave or diapason.
					But should you place the rational in the middle, you would
					make the irascible farther from the concupiscent; though
					some of the philosophers have taken the irascible and
					the concupiscent faculty for the selfsame, by reason of
					their likeness.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>But it may be ridiculous to describe the first, middle,
					and last by their place; since we see hypate highest in
					the harp, lowest in the pipe; and wheresoever you place
					the mese in the harp, provided it is tunable, it sounds more
					acute than hypate, and more grave than nete. Nor does
					the eye possess the same place in all animals; but whereever it is placed, it is natural for it to see. So a pedagogue,
					though he goes not foremost but follows behind, is said to
					lead (<foreign lang="greek">a)/gein</foreign>), as the general of the Trojan army,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now in the front, now in the rear was seen,
						</l>
                        <l>And kept command;</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 64.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>but wherever he was, he was first and chief in power.
						So the faculties of the soul are not to be ranged by mere
						force in order of place or name, but according to their
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.444"/>
						
						power and analogy. For that in the body of man reason
						is in the highest place, is accidental. But it holds the
						chief and highest power, as mese to hypate, in respect of
						the concupiscent; as mese to nete, in respect of the irascible; insomuch as it depresses and heightens,&mdash;and in
						fine makes a harmony,&mdash;by abating what is too much and
						by not suffering them to flatten and grow dull. For what
						is moderate and symmetrous is defined by mediocrity. Still
						more is it the object of the rational faculty to reduce the
						passions to moderation, which is called sacred, as effecting
						a harmony of the extremes with reason, and through reason with each other. For in chariots the best of the beasts
						is not in the middle; nor is the skill of driving to be placed
						as an extreme, but it is a mediocrity between the inequality of the swiftness and the slowness of the horses.
						So the force of reason takes up the passions irrationally
						moved, and reducing them to measure, constitutes a mediocrity betwixt too much and too little.
						
					</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>Question X</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="0">
               <p>WHY SAID PLATO, THAT SPEECH WAS COMPOSED OF NOUNS AND
						VERBS?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato's Sophist, p. 262 A.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>For he seems to make no other parts of speech but
					them. But Homer in a sportive humor has comprehended
					them all in one verse:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
                     <l>Au)to\s i)w\n klisi/hnde to\ so\n ge/ras, o)/fr' eu)= ei)dh=|s</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 185.</note>
                  </quote>
					
					For in it there is pronoun, participle, noun, preposition,
					article, conjunction, adverb, and verb, the particle <foreign lang="greek">-de</foreign> being
					put instead of the preposition <foreign lang="greek">ei)s;</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">klisi/hnde,</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">to the tent,</hi> is
					said in the same sense as <foreign lang="greek">)*aqhna/ze</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">to Athens.</hi> What then
					shall we say for Plato?</p>
               <pb id="v.5.p.445"/>
               <p>Is it that at first the ancients called that <foreign lang="greek">lo/gos,</foreign> or speech,
						which once was called protasis and now is called axiom or
						proposition,&mdash;which as soon as a man speaks, he speaks
						either true or false? This consists of a noun and verb,
						which logicians call the subject and predicate. For when
						we hear this said, <q direct="unspecified">Socrates philosophizeth</q> or <q direct="unspecified">Socrates
							is changed,</q> requiring nothing more, we say the one is
						true, the other false. For very likely in the beginning
						men wanted speech and articulate voice, to enable them to
						express clearly at once the passions and the patients, the
						actions and the agents. Now, since actions and affections
						are sufficiently expressed by verbs, and they that act and
						are affected by nouns, as he says, these seem to signify.
						And one may say, the rest signify not. For instance, the
						groans and shrieks of stage-players, and even their smiles
						and reticence, make their discourse more emphatic. But
						they have no necessary power to signify any thing, as a
						noun and verb have, but only an ascititious power to vary
						speech; just as they vary letters who mark spirits and
						quantities upon letters, these being the accidents and differences of letters. This the ancients have made manifest, whom sixteen letters sufficed to speak and write any
						thing.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Besides, we must not neglect to observe, that Plato
					says that speech is composed <hi rend="italics">of</hi> these, not <hi rend="italics">by</hi> these; nor
					must we blame Plato for leaving out conjunctions, prepositions, and the like, any more than we should cavil at a
					man who should say such a medicine is composed of wax
					and galbanum, because fire and utensils are omitted, without which it cannot be made. For speech is not composed
					of these; yet by their means, and not without them, speech
					must be composed. As, if a man pronounce <hi rend="italics">beats</hi> or <hi rend="italics">is</hi>
					             <hi rend="italics">beaten,</hi> and put Socrates and Pythagoras to the same, he
					offers us something to conceive and understand. But if
					a man pronounce <hi rend="italics">indeed</hi> or <hi rend="italics">for</hi> or <hi rend="italics">about,</hi> and no more,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.446"/>
					
					none can conceive any notion of a body or matter; and
					unless such words as these be uttered with verbs and
					nouns, they are but empty noise and chattering. For
					neither alone nor joined one with another do they signify
					any thing. And join and confound together conjunctions,
					articles, and prepositions, supposing you would make
					something of them; yet you will be taken to babble, and
					not to speak sense. But when there is a verb in construction with a noun, the result is speech and sense. Therefore some do with good reason make only these two parts
					of speech; and perhaps Homer is willing to declare himself of this mind, when he says so often,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
						               <l>)Epos t' e)/fat' e)/k t' o)no/mazen.</l>
                  </quote>
					
					For by <foreign lang="greek">e)/pos</foreign> he usually means a verb, as in these verses.
					
					<quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">)=Wgu/nai, h)\ ma/la tou=to e)/pos qumalge\s e)/eipes,</quote>
					
					and,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
						               <l>Xai=re, pa/ter, w)= cei=ne, e)/pos d' ei)/per ti le/lektai
						</l>
                     <l>Deino\n, a)/far to\ fe/roien a)narpa/casai a)/ellai.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XXIII. 183; VIII. 408.</note>
                  </quote>
					
					For neither conjunction, article, nor preposition could
					be called <foreign lang="greek">deino/n</foreign> (terrible) or <foreign lang="greek">qumalge/s</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">soul-grieving</hi>), but
					only a verb expressing a base action or a foolish passion
					of the mind. Therefore, when we would praise or dispraise poets or writers, we are wont to say, such a man
					uses Attic nouns and good verbs, or else common nouns
					and verbs; but none can say that Thucydides or Euripides
					used Attic or good or common articles.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>What then? may some say, do the rest of the parts
					conduce nothing to speech? I answer, They conduce, as
					salt does to victuals, or water to barley cakes. And Euenus calls fire the best sauce. Though sometimes there is
					neither occasion for fire to boil, nor for salt to season our
					food, which we have always occasion for. Nor has
					speech always occasion for articles. I think I may say
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.447"/>
					
					this of the Latin tongue, which is now the universal language; for it has taken away all prepositions, saving a
					few, nor does it use any articles, but leaves its nouns (as
					it were) without skirts and borders. Nor is it any wonder,
					since Homer, who in fineness of epic surpasses all men,
					has put articles only to a few nouns, like handles to cans,
					or crests to helmets. Therefore these verses are remarkable wherein the articles are expressed:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ai)/anti de\ ma/lista dai/+froni qumo\n o)/rine
					</l>
                        <l>Tw=| Telamwnia/dh|:</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIV. 459.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>and,
						
						<quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Poi/eon o)/fra to\ kh=tos u(pekprofugw\n a)le/aito</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XX. 147.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>and some few besides. But in a thousand others, the
						omission of the articles hinders neither perspicuity nor
						elegance of phrase.
						4. Now neither an animal nor an instrument nor arms nor
						any thing else is more fine, efficacious, or graceful, for the
						loss of a part. Yet speech, by taking away conjunctions,
						often becomes more persuasive, as here:
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <lg>
                        <l>One rear'd a dagger at a captive's breast;
							</l>
                        <l>One held a living foe, that freshly bled
							</l>
                        <l>With new-made wounds; another dragg'd a dead.</l>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVIII. 536.</note>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>And this of Demosthenes:</p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">A bully in an assault may do much which his victim
						cannot even describe to another person,&mdash;by his mien,
						his look, his voice,&mdash;when he stings by insult, when he
						attacks as an avowed enemy, when he smites with his fist,
						when he gives a blow on the face. These rouse a man;
						these make a man beside himself who is unused to such
						foul abuse.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And again:</p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">Not so with Midias; but from the very day, he talks,
						he abuses, he shouts. Is there an election of magistrates?
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.448"/>
						
						Midias the Anagyrrasian is nominated. He is the advocate
						of Plutarchus; he knows state secrets; the city cannot
						contain him.</q>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes against Midias, p. 537, 25, and p. 578, 29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the figure asyndeton, whereby conjunctions
						are omitted, is highly commended by writers of rhetoric.
						But such as keep overstrict to the law, and (according to
						custom) omit not a conjunction, rhetoricians blame for
						using a dull, flat, tedious style, without any variety in it.
						And inasmuch as logicians mightily want conjunctions for
						the joining together their axioms, as much as charioteers
						want yokes, and Ulysses wanted withs to tie Cyclop's
						sheep; this shows they are not parts of speech, but a
						conjunctive instrument thereof, as the word conjunction imports. Nor do conjunctions join all, but only such as are
						not spoken simply; unless you will make a cord part of
						the burthen, glue a part of a book, or distribution of money
						part of the government. For Demades says, that money
						which is given to the people out of the exchequer for
						public shows is the glue of a democracy. Now what
						conjunction does so of several propositions make one,
						by knitting and joining them together, as marble joins iron
						that is melted with it in the fire Yet the marble neither
						is nor is said to be part of the iron; although in this case
						the substances enter into the mixture and are melted together, so as to form a common substance from many and
						to be mutually affected. But there be some who think
						that conjunctions do not make any thing one, but that this
						kind of discourse is merely an enumeration, as when
						magistrates or days are reckoned in order.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>Moreover, as to the other parts of speech, a pronoun
					is manifestly a sort of noun; not only because it has cases
					like the noun, but because some pronouns, when they are
					applied to objects heretofore defined, by their mere utterance give the most distinct and proper designation of them.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.449"/>
					
					Nor do I know whether he that says <hi rend="italics">Socrates</hi> or he that
					says <hi rend="italics">this one</hi> does more by name declare the person.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>The thing we call a participle, being a mixture of a
					verb and noun, is nothing of itself, as are not the common names of male and female qualities (i.e. adjectives),
					but in construction it is put with others, in regard of tenses
					belonging to verbs, in regard of cases to nouns. Logicians call them <foreign lang="greek">a)na/kl istoi,</foreign>(i.e. <hi rend="italics">reflected</hi>),&mdash;as <foreign lang="greek">fronw=n</foreign> comes
					from <foreign lang="greek">fro/nimos</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">swfronw=n</foreign> from <foreign lang="greek">sw/fronos,</foreign>&mdash;having the force
					both of nouns and appellatives.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>And prepositions are like to the crests of a helmet,
					or footstools and pedestals, which (one may rather say) do
					belong to words than are words themselves. See whether
					they rather be not pieces and scraps of words, as they that
					are in haste write but dashes and pricks for letters. For
					it is plain that <foreign lang="greek">e)mbh=nai</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">e)kbh=nai</foreign> are abbreviations of the
					whole words <foreign lang="greek">e)nto\s bh=nai</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">e)kto\s bh=nai, progene/sqai</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">pro/teron</foreign>
					             <foreign lang="greek">gene/sqai,</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">kaqi/zein</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">ka/tw i(/zein.</foreign> As undoubtedly for haste
					and brevity's sake, instead of <foreign lang="greek">li/qous ba/llein</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">toi/xous o)ru/ttein</foreign>
					men first said <foreign lang="greek">liqobolei=n</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">toixwruxei=n.</foreign>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>Therefore every one of these is of some use in
					speech; but nothing is a part or element of speech (as
					has been said) except a noun and a verb, which make the
					first juncture admitting of truth or falsehood, which some
					call a proposition or protasis, others an axiom, and which
					Plato called speech.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>