<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De Iside et Osiride</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.089">
      <body>
         <head>of Isis and Osiris, or of the ancient religion
				and philosophy of Egypt.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.65"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>IT becomes wise men, dame Clea,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This Clea was priestess to Isis and to Apollo Delphicus.</note> to go to the Gods
				for all the good things they would enjoy. Much more
				ought we, when we would aim at that knowledge of them
				which our nature can arrive at, to pray that they themselves would bestow it upon us; truth being the greatest
				good that man can receive, and the goodliest blessing that
				God can give. Other good things he bestows on men as
				they want them, they being not his own peculiars nor of
				any use to himself. For the blessedness of the Deity consists not in silver and gold, nor yet his power in lightnings
				and thunders, but in knowledge and wisdom. And it was
				the best thing Homer ever said of Gods, when he pronounced thus:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Both of one line, both of one country boast,
				</l>
                     <l>But royal Jove's the eldest and knows most;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIII. 354.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>where he declares Jupiter's prerogative in wisdom and
					science to be the more honorable, by terming it the elder.
					I, for my own part, do believe that the felicity of eternal
					living which the Gods enjoy lies mainly in this, that nothing
					escapes their cognizance that passes in the sphere of generation, and that, should we set aside wisdom and the
					knowledge of true beings,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, <foreign lang="greek">ta\ o)/nta</foreign> in the Platonic sense, as opposed to <foreign lang="greek">ta\ gigno/mena</foreign>. (G.)</note> immortality itself would not
					be life, but merely a long time.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.66"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>And therefore the desire of truth, especially in what
				relates to the Gods, is a sort of grasping after divinity, it
				using learning and enquiry for a kind of resumption of
				things sacred, a work doubtless of more religion than any
				ritual purgation or charge of temples whatever, and especially most acceptable to the Goddess you serve, since she
				is more eminently wise and speculative, and since knowledge and science (as her very name<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch derives Isis, in the usual uncritical way of ancient etymology, from
					the Greek root <foreign lang="greek">i)s</foreign>&mdash;, found in <foreign lang="greek">i)/ste</foreign> from <foreign lang="greek">oi(=da</foreign>. (G.)</note> seems to import)
				appertain more peculiarly to her than any other thing.
				For the name of Isis is Greek, and so is that of her adversary Typhon, who, being puffed up<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, <foreign lang="greek">tetufwme/nos</foreign>. (G.)</note> through ignorance
				and mistake, pulls in pieces and destroys that holy doctrine, which she on the contrary collects, compiles, and
				delivers down to such as are regularly advanced unto the
				deified state; which, by constancy of sober diet, and abstaining from sundry meats and the use of women, both
				restrains the intemperate and voluptuous part, and habituates them to austere and hard services in the temples, the
				end of which is the knowledge of the original, supreme,
				and mental being, which the Goddess would have them
				enquire for, as near to herself and as dwelling with her.
				Besides, the very name of her temple most apparently
				promises the knowledge and acquaintance of true being
				(<foreign lang="greek">to\ o)/n</foreign>), for they call it Iseion (<foreign lang="greek">)/*iseion</foreign>), as who should say, We
				shall know true being, if with reason and sanctimony we
				approach the sacred temples of this Goddess.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Moreover, many have reported her the daughter of
				Hermes, and many of Prometheus; the latter of which
				they esteem as the author of wit and forecast, and the
				former of letters and music. For the same reason also
				they call the former of the Muses at Hermopolis at the
				same time Isis and Justice, Isis being (as we before said)
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.67"/>
				
				no other than wisdom, and revealing things divine to such
				as are truly and justly styled the sacred bearers, and keepers of the sacred robes; and these are such as have in
				their minds, as in an ark, the sacred doctrine about the
				Gods, cleansed from superstitious frights and vain curiosities, keeping out of sight all dark and shady colors, and
				exposing to sight the light and gay ones, to insinuate
				something of the like kind in our persuasion about the
				Gods as we have represented to us in the sacred vestments.
				Wherefore, in that the priests of Isis are dressed up in
				these when they are dead, it is a token to us that this doctrine goes with them to the other life, and that nothing
				else can accompany them thither. For as neither the
				nourishing of beards nor the wearing of mantles can ren
				der men philosophers, so neither will linen garments or
				shaved heads make priests to Isis; but he is a true priest
				of Isis, who, after he hath received from the laws the representations and actions that refer to the Gods, doth next
				apply his reason to the enquiry and speculation of the
				truth contained in them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>For the greater part of men are ignorant even of this
				most common and ordinary thing, for what reason priests
				lay aside their hair and go in linen garments. Some are
				not at all solicitous to be informed about such questions;
				and others say their veneration for sheep is the cause why
				they abstain from their wool as well as their flesh, and that
				they shave their heads in token of mourning, and that
				they wear linen because of the bloomy color which the
				flax sendeth forth, in imitation of that ethereal clarity that
				environs the world. But indeed the true reason of them
				all is one and the same. For it is not lawful (as Plato
				saith) for a clean thing to be touched by an unclean; but
				now no superfluity of food or excrementitious substance
				can be pure or clean; but wool, down, hair, and nails
				come up and grow from superfluous excrements. It would
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.68"/>
				
				be therefore an absurdity for them to lay aside their own
				hair in purgations, by shaving themselves and by making
				their bodies all over smooth, and yet in the mean time to
				wear and carry about them the hairs of brutes. For we
				ought to think that the poet Hesiod, when he saith,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not at a feast of Gods from five-branched tree
				</l>
                     <l>With sharp-edged steel to part the green from dry,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hes. Works and Days, 740. That is, <hi rend="italics">Do not cut your nails at a banquet of the Gods.</hi>
					The briefer precept of Pythagoras was, <foreign lang="greek">*paoa\ qusi/an mh\ o)nuxi/zou</foreign>. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>would teach us to keep the feast when we are already
					cleansed from such things as these, and not in the solemnities themselves to use purgation or removal of excrementitious superfluities. But now flax springs up from an
					immortal being, the earth, and bears an eatable fruit, and
					affords a simple and cleanly clothing, not burdensome to
					him that is covered with it, and convenient for every season
					of the year, and which besides (as they tell us) is the least
					subject to engender vermin; but of this to discourse in
					this place would not be pertinent.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But now the priests do so abhor all kinds of superfluous excrements, that they not only decline most sorts of
				pulse, and of flesh that of sheep and swine, which produce much superfluity, but also in the time of their purgations they exclude salt from their meals. For which, as
				they have several other good reasons, so more especially
				this, that it whets the appetite and renders men over-eager
				after meat and drink. For that the reason why salt is
				not accounted clean should be (as Aristagoras tells us) because that, when it is hardened together, many little animals
				are catched in it and there die, is fond and ridiculous.
				They are also said to water the Apis from a well of his
				own, and to restrain him altogether from the river Nile,&mdash;
				not because they hold the water for polluted by reason of
				the crocodile, as some suppose, for there is nothing in the
				world in more esteem with the Egyptians than the Nile,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.69"/>
				
				but because the water of the Nile being drunk is observed
				to be very feeding, and above all others to conduce to the
				increase of flesh. But they would not have the Apis nor
				themselves neither to be over fat; but that their bodies
				should sit light and easy about their souls, and not press
				and squeeze them down by a mortal part overpowering and
				weighing down the divine.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>They also that at Heliopolis (<hi rend="italics">Sun-town</hi>) wait upon
				the sun never bring wine into his temple, they looking
				upon it as a thing indecent and unfitting to drink by daylight, while their lord and king looks on. The rest of
				them do indeed use it, but very sparingly. They have
				likewise many purgations, wherein they prohibit the use
				of wine, in which they study philosophy, and pass their
				time in learning and teaching things divine. Moreover
				their kings, being priests also themselves, were wont to
				drink it by a certain measure prescribed them in the sacred
				books, as Hecataeus informs us. And they began first to
				drink it in the reign of Psammetichus; but before that
				time they were not used to drink wine at all, no, nor to
				pour it forth in sacrifice as a thing they thought any way
				grateful to the Gods, but as the blood of those who in
				ancient times waged war against the Gods, from whom, falling down from heaven and mixing with the earth, they
				conceived vines to have first sprung; which is the reason
				(say they) that drunkenness renders men besides themselves and mad; they being, as it were, gorged with the
				blood of their ancestors. These things (as Eudoxus tells
				us in the second book of his Travels) are thus related by
				the priests.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>As to sea-fish, they do not all of them abstain from
				all, but some from one sort, and some from another. As
				for example, the Oxyrynchites abstain from such as are
				catched with the angle and hook; for, having the fish
				called oxyrynchus (the pike) in great veneration, they are
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.70"/>
				
				afraid lest the hook should chance to catch hold of it
				and by that means become polluted. They of Syene also
				abstain from the phagrus (or sea-bream) because it is
				observed to appear with the approaching overflow of the
				Nile, and to present itself a voluntary messenger of the
				joyful news of its increase. But the priests abstain from
				all in general. But on the ninth day of the first month,
				when every other Egyptian eats a fried fish before the
				outer door of his house, the priests do not eat any fish,
				but only burn them before their doors. For which they
				have two reasons; the one whereof, being sacred and very
				curious, I shall resume by and by (it agreeing with the
				pious reasonings we shall make upon Osiris and Typhon);
				the other is a very manifest and obvious one, which, by
				declaring fish to be not a necessary but a superfluous
				and curious sort of food, greatly confirms Homer, who
				never makes either the dainty Phaeacians or the Ithacans
				(though both islanders) to make use of fish; no, nor the
				companions of Ulysses either in so long a voyage at sea,
				until they came to the last extremity of want. In short,
				they reckon the sea itself to be made of fire and to lie out
				of Nature's confines, and not to be a part of the world or
				an element, but a preternatural, corrupt, and morbid excrement.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>For nothing hath been ranked among their sacred
				and religious rites that savored of folly, romance, or superstition, as some do suppose; but some of them were
				such as contained some signification of morality and utility,
				and others such as were not without a fineness either in
				history or natural philosophy. As, for instance, in what
				refers to the onions; for that Dictys, the foster-father of
				Isis, as he was reaching at a handful of onions, fell into
				the river and was there drowned, is extremely improbable.
				But the true reason why the priests abhor, detest, and
				avoid the onion is because it is the only plant whose nature
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.71"/>
				
				 it is to grow and spread forth in the wane of the
				moon. Besides, it is no proper food, either for such as
				would practise abstinence and use purgations, or for such
				as would observe the festivals; for the former, because it
				causeth thirst, and for the latter, because it forceth tears
				from those that eat it. They likewise esteem the swine as
				an unhallowed animal, because it is observed to be most
				apt to engender in the wane of the moon, and because
				that such as drink its milk have a leprosy and scabbed
				roughness in their bodies. But the story which they that
				sacrifice a swine at every full moon are wont to subjoin
				after their eating of it,&mdash;how that Typhon, being once
				about the full of the moon in pursuit of a certain swine,
				found by chance the wooden chest wherein lay the body
				of Osiris, and scattered it,&mdash;is not received by all, but
				looked upon as a misrepresented story, as a great many
				more such are. They tell us moreover, that the ancients
				did so much despise delicacy, sumptuousness, and a soft
				and effeminate way of living, that they erected a pillar in
				the temple at Thebes, having engraven upon it several
				grievous curses against King Meinis, who (as they tell us)
				was the first that brought off the Egyptians from a mean,
				wealthless, and simple way of living. There goes also
				another story, how that Technatis, father to Bocchoris,
				commanding an army against the Arabians, and his baggage and provisions not coming in as soon as was expected,
				heartily fed upon such things as he could next light on,
				and afterwards had a sound sleep upon a pallet, whereupon he fell greatly in love with a poor and mean life;
				and for this reason he cursed Meinis, and that with the
				consent of all the priests, and carved that curse upon a
				pillar.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>But their kings (you must know) were always chosen
				either out of the priesthood or soldiery, the latter having
				the right of succession by reason of their military valor,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.72"/>
				
				and the former by reason of their wisdom. But he that
				was chosen out of the soldiery was obliged immediately to
				turn priest, and was thereupon admitted to the participation of their philosophy, whose genius it was to conceal
				the greater part in tales and romantic relations, containing
				dark hints and resemblances of truth; which it is plain
				that even themselves would insinuate to us, while they are
				so kind as to set up Sphinxes before their temples, to intimate that their theology contained in it an enigmatical
				sort of learning. Moreover, the temple of Minerva which
				is at Sais (whom they look upon as the same with Isis)
				had upon it this inscription: I am whatever was, or is, or
				will be; and my veil no mortal ever took up. Besides,
				we find the greater part to be of opinion that the proper
				name of Jupiter in the Egyptian tongue is Amun (from
				which we have derived our word Ammon). But now
				Manetho the Sebennite thinks this word signifies hidden
				and hiding; but Hecataeus of Abdera saith, the Egyptians
				use this word when they call anybody; for that it is
				a term of calling. Therefore they must be of the opinion
				that the first God is the same with the universe; and
				therefore, while they invoke him who is unmanifest and
				hidden, and pray him to make himself manifest and known
				to them, they cry Amun. So great therefore was the piety
				of the Egyptians' philosophy about things divine.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>This is also confirmed by the most learned of the
				Greeks (such as Solon, Thales, Plato, Eudoxus, Pythagoras, and as some say, even Lycurgus) going to Egypt and
				conversing with the priests; of whom they say Eudoxus
				was a hearer of Chonuphis of Memphis, Solon of Sonchis of Sais, and Pythagoras of Oenuphis of Heliopolis.
				Whereof the last named, being (as is probable) more than
				ordinarily admired by the men, and they also by him,
				imitated their symbolical and mysterious way of talking,
				obscuring his sentiments with dark riddles. For the greatest
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.73"/>
				
				 part of the Pythagoric precepts fall nothing short of
				those sacred writings they call hieroglyphical, such as, Do
				not eat in a chariot; Do not sit on a choenix (or measure);
				Plant not a palm-tree; Stir not fire with a knife within the
				house. And I verily believe, that their terming the unit
				Apollo, the number two Diana, the number seven Minerva,
				and the first cube Neptune, refers to the columns set up in
				their temples, and to things there acted, aye, and painted
				too. For they represent their king and lord Osiris by an
				eye and a sceptre. There are some also that interpret his
				name by many-eyed, as if <hi rend="italics">os</hi> in the Egyptian tongue signified many, and <hi rend="italics">iri</hi> an eye. And the heaven, because by
				reason of its eternity it never grows old, they represent by
				a heart with a censer under it. There were also statues
				of judges erected at Thebes, having no hands; and the
				chief of them had also his eyes closed up, hereby signifying
				that among them justice was not to be solicited with either
				bribery or address. Moreover, the men of the sword had
				a beetle carved upon their signets, because there is no
				such thing as a female beetle; for they are all males, and
				they generate their young in certain round pellets formed
				of dirt, being herein as well providers of the place in
				which they are to be engendered, as of the matter of their
				nutrition.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>When therefore you hear the tales which the
				Egyptians relate about the Gods, such as their wanderings,
				discerptions, and such like disasters that befell them, you
				are still to remember that none of these things have been
				really so acted and done as they are told. For they do not
				call the dog Hermes properly, but only attribute the warding, vigilancy, and philosophic acuteness of that animal,
				which by knowing or not knowing distinguishes between
				its friend and its foe (as Plato speaks), to the most knowing
				and ingenious of the Gods. Nor do they believe that the
				sun springs up a little boy from the top of the lotus, but
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.74"/>
				
				they thus set forth his rising to insinuate the kindling of
				his rays by means of humids. Besides, that most savage
				and horrible king of the Persians named Ochus, who,
				when he had massacred abundance of people, afterwards
				slaughtered the Apis, and feasted upon him, both himself
				and his retinue, they called the Sword; and they call him
				so to this very day in their table of kings, hereby not
				denoting properly his person, but resembling by this instrument of murder the severity and mischievousness of his
				disposition. When therefore you thus hear the stories of
				the Gods from such as interpret them with consistency to
				piety and philosophy, and observe and practise those rites
				that are by law established, and are persuaded in your
				mind that you cannot possibly either offer or perform a
				more agreeable thing to the Gods than the entertaining of
				a right notion of them, you will then avoid superstition as a
				no less evil than atheism itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>The story is thus told after the most concise manner,
				the most useless and unnecessary parts being cut off. They
				tell us how that once on a time, Rhea having accompanied
				with Saturn by stealth, the Sun found them out, and pronounced a solemn curse against her, containing that she
				should not be delivered in any month or year; but that
				Hermes, afterwards making his court to the goddess, obtained her favor, in requital of which he went and played
				at dice with the Moon, and won of her the seventieth part
				from each day, and out of all these made five new days,
				which he added to the three hundred and sixty other days
				of the year; and these the Egyptians therefore to this day
				call the Epagomenae (or the superadded days), and they
				observe them as the birthdays of their Gods. Upon the
				first of these, as they say, Osiris was born, and a voice
				came into the world with him, saying, The Lord of all
				things is now born. There are others that affirm that one
				Pamyles, as he was fetching water at Thebes, heard a voice
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.75"/>
				
				out of the temple of Jupiter, bidding him to publish with
				a loud voice that Osiris, the great and good king, was now
				born; and that he thereupon got to be foster-father to
				Osiris, Saturn entrusting him with the charge of him, and
				that the feast called Pamylia (resembling the Priapeian
				procession which the Greeks call Phallephoria) was instituted in honor of him. Upon the second day Arueris was
				born, whom some call Apollo, and others the elder Horus.
				Upon the third Typhon was born, who came not into the
				world either in due time or by the right way, but broke a
				hole in his mother's side, and leaped out at the wound.
				Upon the fourth Isis was born in Panygra. And upon the
				fifth Nephthys, whom they sometimes call the end, and
				sometimes Venus, and sometimes also Victory. Of these
				they say Osiris and Arueris were begot by the Sun, Isis
				by Hermes, and Typhon and Nephthys by Saturn. For
				which reason their kings, looking upon the third of the
				Epagomenae as an inauspicious day, did no business upon
				it, nor took any care of their bodies until the evening.
				They say also that Nephthys was married unto Typhon,
				and that Isis and Osiris were in love with one another before they were born, and enjoyed each other in the dark
				before they came into the world. Some add also that
				Arueris was thus begotten, and that he was called by the
				Egyptians the elder Horus, and by the Greeks Apollo.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>And they say that Osiris, when he was king of
				Egypt, drew them off from a beggarly and bestial way of
				living, by showing them the use of grain, and by making
				them laws, and teaching them to honor the Gods; and that
				afterwards he travelled all the world over, and made it
				civil, having but little need of arms, for he drew the most
				to him, alluring them by persuasion and oratory, intermixed
				with all sorts of poetry and music; whence it is that the
				Greeks look upon him as the very same with Bacchus.
				They further add that Typhon, while he was from home,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.76"/>
				
				attempted nothing against him; for Isis was very watchful,
				and guarded him closely from harm. But when he came
				home, he formed a plot against him, taking seventy-two
				men for accomplices of his conspiracy, and being also
				abetted by a certain Queen of Ethiopia, whose name they
				say was Aso. Having therefore privately taken the measure of Osiris's body, and framed a curious ark, very finely
				beautified and just of the size of his body, he brought it
				to a certain banquet. And as all were wonderfully delighted with so rare a sight and admired it greatly, Typhon in
				a sporting manner promised that whichsoever of the company should by lying in it find it to be of the size of his
				body, should have it for a present. And as every one of
				them was forward to try, and none fitted it, Osiris at last got
				into it himself, and lay along in it; whereupon they that
				were there present immediately ran to it, and clapped down
				the cover upon it, and when they had fastened it down
				with nails, and soldered it with melted lead, they carried it
				forth to the river side, and let it swim into the sea at the
				Tanaitic mouth, which the Egyptians therefore to this day
				detest, and abominate the very naming of it. These things
				happened (as they say) upon the seventeenth of the month
				Athyr, when the sun enters into the Scorpion, and that
				was upon the eight and twentieth year of the reign of
				Osiris. But there are some that say that was the time of
				his life, and not of his reign.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>And because the Pans and Satyrs that inhabited the
				region about Chemmis were the first that knew of this
				disaster and raised the report of it among the people, all
				sudden frights and discomposures among the people have
				been ever since called panics. But when Isis heard of it,
				she cut off in that very place a lock of her hair, and put
				on a mourning weed, where there is a town at this day
				named Kopto; others think that name signifies bereaving,
				for that some use the word for depriving. And as she
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.77"/>
				
				wandered up and down in all places, being deeply perplexed in her thoughts, and left no one she met withal
				unspoken to, she met at last with certain little children, of
				whom also she enquired about the ark. Now these had
				chanced to see all that had passed, and they named to her
				the very mouth of the Nile by which Typhon's accomplices
				had sent the vessel into the sea; for which reason the
				Egyptians account little children to have a faculty of divination, and use more especially to lay hold on their omens
				when they play in sacred places or chance to say an) thing
				there, whatever it be. And finding afterwards that Osiris
				had made his court to her sister, and through mistake enjoyed her instead of herself, for token of which she had
				found the melilot garland which he had left hard by
				Nephthys, she went to seek for the child; for her sister
				had immediately exposed it as soon as she was delivered
				of it, for fear of her husband Typhon. And when with
				great difficulty and labor she had found it, by means of
				certain dogs which conducted her to it, she brought it up;
				and he afterwards became her guardsman and follower,
				being named Anubis, and reported to guard the Gods as
				dogs do men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Of him she had tidings of the ark, how it had been
				thrown out by the sea upon the coasts of Byblos, and the
				flood had gently entangled it in a certain thicket of heath.
				And this heath had in a very small time run up into a
				most beauteous and large tree, and had wrought itself
				about it, clung to it, and quite enclosed it within its trunk.
				Upon which the king of that place, much admiring at the
				unusual bigness of the plant, and cropping off the bushy
				part that encompassed the now invisible chest, made of it
				a post to support the roof of his house. These things (as
				they tell us) Isis being informed of by the divine breath of
				rumor, went herself to Byblos; where when she was come,
				she sate her down hard by a well, very pensive and full of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.78"/>
				
				tears, insomuch that she refused to speak to any person,
				save only to the queen's women, whom she complimented
				and caressed at an extraordinary rate, and would often
				stroke back their hair with her hands, and withal transmit
				a most wonderful fragrant smell out of her body into theirs.
				The queen, perceiving that her women's bodies and hair
				thus breathed of ambrosia, greatly longed to become acquainted with this new stranger. Upon this she being
				sent for, and becoming very intimate with the queen, was
				at last made nurse to her child. Now the name of this
				king (they tell us) was Malcander; and the queen, some
				say, was called Astarte, and some Saosis, and others Nemanun (which in Greek is as much as to say Athena&iuml;s).</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Isis nursed the child by putting her finger into his
				mouth instead of the breast; and in the night-time she
				would by a kind of lambent fire singe away what was
				mortal about him. In the mean while, herself would be
				turned to a swallow, and in that form would fly round
				about the post, bemoaning her misfortune and sad fate;
				until at last, the queen, who stood watching hard by,
				cried out aloud as she saw her child all on a light flame,
				and so robbed him of immortality. Upon which the Goddess discovered herself, and begged the post that held up
				the roof; which when she had obtained and taken down,
				she very quickly cropped off the bushy heath from about it
				and wrapping the trunk in fine linen and pouring perfumed
				oil upon it, she put it into the hands of their kings; and
				therefore the Byblians to this very day worship that piece
				of wood, laying it up in the temple of Isis. Then she
				threw herself down upon the chest, and her lamentations
				were so loud, that the younger of the king's two sons died
				for very fear; but she, having the elder in her own possession, took both him and the ark, and carried them on
				shipboard, and so took sail. But the river Phaedrus
				sending forth a very keen and chill air, it being the dawning
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.79"/>
				
				 of the morn, she grew incensed at it, and dried up its
				current.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>And in the first place where she could take rest,
				and found herself to be now at liberty and alone, she
				opened the ark, and laid her cheeks upon the cheeks of
				Osiris, and embraced him and wept bitterly. The little
				boy seeing her came silently behind her, and peeping saw
				what it was; which she perceiving cast a terrible look
				upon him in the height of her passion; the fright whereof
				the child could not endure, and immediately died. But
				there are some that say it was not so, but that in the forementioned manner he dropped into the sea, and was there
				drowned. And he hath divine honors given him to this
				very day upon the Goddess's account; for they assure us
				that Maneros, whom the Egyptians so often mention in
				their carols at their banquets, is the very same. But others
				say that the boy was named Palaestinus or Pelusius, and
				that the city of that name was so called from him, it
				having been built by the Goddess. They also relate that
				this Maneros, so often spoken of in their songs, was the
				first that invented music. But some there are that would
				make us believe that Maneros was not the name of any
				person, but a certain form of speech, made use of to
				people in drinking and entertaining themselves at feasts,
				by way of wishing that all things might prove auspicious
				and agreeable to them; for that is the thing which the
				Egyptians would express by the word Maneros, when they
				so often roar it forth. In like manner they affirm that the
				likeness of a dead man, which is carried about in a little
				box and shown at feasts, is not to commemorate the disaster of Osiris, as some suppose, but was designed to encourage men to make use of and to enjoy the present
				things whilst they have them, since all men must quickly
				become such as they there see; for which reason they
				bring it into their revels and feasts.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.80"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>But when Isis came to her son Horus, who was then
				at nurse at Buto, and had laid the chest out of the way,
				Typhon, as he was hunting by moonshine, by chance
				lighted upon it, and knowing the body again, tore it into
				fourteen parts, and threw them all about. Which when
				Isis had heard, she went to look for them again in a certain barge made of papyrus, in which she sailed over all
				the fens. Whence (they tell us) it comes to pass, that
				such as go in boats made of this rush are never injured by
				the crocodiles, they having either a fear or else a veneration for it upon the account of the goddess Isis. And this
				(they say) hath occasioned the report that there are many
				sepulchres of Osiris in Egypt, because she made a particular funeral for each member as she found them. There
				are others that tell us it was not so, but that she made several effigies of him and sent them to every city, taking on
				her as if she had sent them his body; so that the greater
				number of people might pay divine honors to him, and
				withal, if it should chance that Typhon should get the better of Horus, and thereupon search for the body of Osiris,
				many bodies being discoursed of and shown him, he might
				despair of ever finding the right one. But of all Osiris's
				members, Isis could never find out his private part, for it
				had been presently flung into the river Nile, and the lepidotus, sea-bream, and pike eating of it, these were for that
				reason more scrupulously avoided by the Egyptians than
				any other fish. But Isis, in lieu of it, made its effigies,
				and so consecrated the phallus for which the Egyptians to
				this day observe a festival.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>After this, Osiris coming out of hell to assist his
				son Horus, first labored and trained him up in the discipline of war, and then questioned him what he thought to
				be the gallantest thing a man could do; to which he soon
				replied, to avenge one's father's and mother's quarrel when
				they suffer injury. He asked him a second time, what animal
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.81"/>
				
				 he esteemed most useful to such as would go to battle.
				Horus told him, a horse; to which he said that he wondered much at his answer, and could not imagine why he
				did not rather name a lion than a horse. Horus replied,
				that a lion might indeed be very serviceable to one that
				needed help, but a horse would serve best to cut off and
				disperse a flying enemy. Which when Osiris heard, he
				was very much pleased with him, looking upon him now
				as sufficiently instructed for a soldier. It is reported likewise that, as a great many went over daily unto Horus,
				Typhon's own concubine Thueris deserted also; but that
				a certain serpent, pursuing her close at the heels, was cut
				in pieces by Horus's men, and that for that reason they
				still fling a certain cord into the midst of the room and
				then chop it to pieces. The battle therefore continued for
				several days, and Horus at last prevailed; but Isis, although
				she had Typhon delivered up to her fast bound, yet would
				not put him to death, but contrariwise loosed him and let
				him go. Which when Horus perceived, he could not
				brook it with any patience, but laid violent hands upon his
				mother, and plucked the royal diadem from off her head.
				But Hermes presently stepped in, and clapped a cow's
				head upon her instead of a helmet. Likewise, when Typhon impeached Horus for being a bastard, Hermes became his advocate, and Horus was judged legitimate by
				all the Gods. After this, they say that Typhon was worsted in two several battles. Isis had also by Osiris, who
				accompanied with her after his decease, Harpocrates, who
				came into the world before his time and was lame in his
				lower parts.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>These then are most of the heads of this fabular
				narration, the more harsh and coarse parts (such as the
				description of Horus and the beheading of Isis) being
				taken out. If therefore they say and believe such things
				as these of the blessed and incorruptible nature (which is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.82"/>
				
				the best conception we can have of divinity) as really thus
				done and happening to it, I need not tell you that you
				ought to spit and to make clean your mouth (as Aeschylus
				speaks) at the mentioning of them. For you are sufficiently averse of yourself to such as entertain such wicked
				and barbarous sentiments concerning the Gods. And yet
				that these relations are nothing akin to those foppish tales
				and vain fictions which poets and story-tellers are wont,
				like spiders, to spin out of their own bowels, without any
				substantial ground or foundation for them, and then weave
				and wire-draw them out at their own pleasures, but contain in them certain abstruse questions and rehearsals of
				events, you yourself are, I suppose, convinced. And as
				mathematicians do assert the rainbow to be an appearance
				of the sun so variegated by reflection of its rays in a cloud,
				so likewise the fable here related is the appearance of some
				doctrine whose meaning is transferred by reflection to
				some other matter; as is plainly suggested to us as well by
				the sacrifices themselves, in which there appears something
				lamentable and very sad, as by the forms and makes of
				their temples, which sometimes run out themselves into
				wings, and into open and airy circs, and at other times
				again have under ground certain private cells, resembling
				vaults and tombs. And this is most plainly hinted to us
				by the opinion received about those of Osiris, because his
				body is said to be interred in so many different places.
				Though it may be they will tell you that some one town,
				such as Abydos or Memphis, is named for the place where
				his true body lies; and that the most powerful and wealthy among the Egyptians are most ambitious to be buried
				at Abydos, that so they may be near the body of their God
				Osiris; and that the Apis is fed at Memphis, because he
				is the image of Osiris's soul, where also they will have it
				that his body is interred. Some also interpret the name
				of this city to signify the haven of good things, and others,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.83"/>
				
				the tomb of Osiris. They add, that the little island at
				Philae is at other times inaccessible and not to be approached to by any man, and that the very birds dare not
				venture to fly over it nor the fish to touch upon its banks;
				yet upon a certain set time the priests go over into it, and
				there perform the accustomed rites for the dead, and crown
				his tomb, which stands there shaded over by a tree called
				methida, exceeding any olive in bigness.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>But Eudoxus saith that, though there be in Egypt
				many tombs reported to be his, yet his true body lies at
				Busiris, for that was the place of his birth; neither can
				there be any room for dispute about Taphosiris, for that its
				very name bespeaks it, Osiris's tomb. I pass by their
				cleaving of wood, their peeling of flax, and the wine libations then made by them, because many of their secret
				mysteries are therein contained. And it is not of this
				God only, but of all others also that are not ungotten and
				incorruptible, that the priests pretend that their bodies lie
				buried with them and are by them served, but their souls
				are stars shining in heaven; and they say that the soul of
				Isis is by the Greeks called the Dog, but by the Egyptians,
				Sothis; and that of Horus, Orion; and that of Typhon, the
				Bear. They also tell us, that towards the support of the
				animals honored by them all others pay the proportion assigned them by the laws, but that those that inhabit the
				country of Thebais are the only men that refuse to contribute any thing, because they believe in no mortal God, but
				in him only whom they call Cneph, who is ungotten and
				immortal.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>They therefore who suppose that, because many
				things of this sort are both related and shown unto travellers, they are but so many commemorations of the actions
				and disasters of mighty kings and tyrants who, by reason
				of their eminent valor or puissance, wrote the title of divinity upon their fame, and afterwards fell into great
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.84"/>
				
				calamities and misfortunes,&mdash;these, I say, make use of the
				most ready way of eluding the story, and plausibly enough
				remove things of harsh and uncouth sound from Gods to
				men. Nay, I will add this farther, that the arguments they
				use are fairly enough deduced from the things themselves
				related. For the Egyptians recount, that Mercury was, in
				regard to the make of his body, with one arm longer than
				the other, and that Typhon was by complexion red, Horus
				white, and Osiris black, as if they had been indeed nothing
				else but men. They moreover style Osiris a commander,
				and Canopus a pilot, from whom they say the star of that
				name was denominated. Also the ship which the Greeks
				call Argo&mdash;being the image of Osiris's ark, and therefore,
				in honor of it, made a constellation&mdash;they make to ride
				not far from Orion and the Dog; whereof the one they
				believe to be sacred to Horus, and the other to Isis.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But I fear this would be to stir things that are not
				to be stirred, and to declare war not only (as Simonides
				speaks) against length of time, but also against many nations and families of mankind, whom a religious reverence
				towards these Gods holds fast bound like men astonished
				and amazed. And this would be no other than going about
				to remove so great and venerable names from heaven to
				earth, thereby shaking and dissolving that worship and
				persuasion that hath entered into almost all men's constitutions from their very birth, and opening vast doors to the
				Atheists' faction, who convert all divine matters into human,
				giving also a large license to the impostures of Euhemerus
				the Messenian, who out of his own brain contrived certain
				memoirs of a most incredible and imaginary mythology,
				and thereby spread all manner of Atheism throughout the
				world. This he did by describing all the received Gods
				under the style of generals, sea-captains, and kings, whom
				he makes to have lived in the more remote and ancient
				times, and to be recorded in golden characters in a certain
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.85"/>
				
				country called Panchon, with which notwithstanding never
				any man, either Barbarian or Grecian, had the good fortune to meet, except Euhemerus alone, who (it seems)
				sailed to the land of the Panchoans and Triphyllians, that
				neither have nor ever had a being.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>And although the actions of Semiramis are sung
				among the Assyrians as very great, and likewise those of
				Sesostris in Egypt, and the Phrygians to this very day style
				all illustrious and strange actions <hi rend="italics">manic,</hi> because Manis,
				one of their ancient kings (whom some call Masdes) was a
				brave and mighty person; and although Cyrus enlarged the
				empire of the Persians, and Alexander that of the Macedonians, within a little matter of the world's end; yet have they
				still retained the names and memorials of gallant princes.
				And if some, puffed up with excessive vain-glory (as Plato
				speaks), having their minds enflamed at once with both
				youthful blood and folly, have with an unruly extravagancy
				taken upon them the style of Gods and had temples erected
				in their honor, yet this opinion of them flourished but for
				a short season, and they afterwards underwent the blame
				of great vanity and arrogancy, conjoined with the highest
				impiety and wickedness; and so,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Like smoke they flew away with swift-paced Fate;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Empedocles.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and being dragged away from the altars like fugitive slaves,
					they have now nothing left them but their tombs and graves.
					Which made Antigonus the Elder, when one Hermodotus
					had in his poems declared him to be son to the Sun and a
					God, to say to him: Friend, he that empties my close-stoolpan knows no such matter of me. And Lysippus the
					carver had good reason to quarrel with the painter Apelles
					for drawing Alexander's picture with a thunder-bolt in
					his hand, whereas himself had made him but with a
					spear, which (he said) was natural and proper for him,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.86"/>
					
					and a weapon the glory of which no time would rob
					him of.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Therefore they maintain the wiser opinion, who hold
				that the things here storied of Typhon, Osiris, and Isis
				were not the events of Gods, nor yet of men, but of certain grand Daemons, whom Plato, Pythagoras, Xenocrates,
				and Chrysippus (following herein the opinion of the most
				ancient theologists) affirm to be of greater strength than
				men, and to transcend our nature by much in power, but
				not to have a divine part pure and unmixed, but such as
				participates of both the soul's nature and the body's sensation, capable of receiving both pleasure and pain, and all
				the passions that attend these mutations, which disorder
				some of them more and others of them less. For there
				are divers degrees both of virtue and vice, as among men,
				so also among Daemons. For what they sing about among
				the Greeks, concerning the Giants and the Titans, and of
				certain horrible actions of Saturn, as also of Python's combats with Apollo, of the flights of Bacchus, and the ramblings of Ceres, come nothing short of the relations about
				Osiris and Typhon and others such, which everybody may
				lawfully and freely hear as they are told in the mythology.
				The like may be also said of those things that, being veiled
				over in the mystic rites and sacred ceremonies of initiation,
				are therefore kept private from the sight and hearing of
				the common sort.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>We also hear Homer often calling such as are extraordinary good <q direct="unspecified">Godlike,</q> and <q direct="unspecified"> God's compeers,</q> and <q direct="unspecified"> gifted
				with wisdom by the Gods.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Odyss. VI. 12; Il. XIII. 810; V. 438; IV. 31.</note> But the epithet derived from
				Daemons we find him to bestow upon the good and bad
				indifferently, as,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  &amp;ldquo;Daemon-like sir, make haste, why do you fear the Argives thus?&amp;rdquo;
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And then on the contrary,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  &amp;ldquo;When the fourth time he rushed on like a Daemon;&amp;rdquo;
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.87"/>
            <p>and again where Jupiter speaks thus to Juno:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Daemonial dame, what hath poor Priam done
					</l>
                     <l>To anger you so much, or what his sons,
					</l>
                     <l>That you resolve fair Ilium's overthrow,
					</l>
                     <l>And your revengeful purpose won't forego?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>where he seems to make Daemons to be of a mixed and
					unequal temper and inclination. Whence it is that Plato
					assigns to the Olympic Gods dexter things and odd numbers, and the opposite to these to Daemons. And Xenocrates also is of opinion, that such days as are commonly
					accounted unlucky, and those holy days in which are used
					scourgings, beatings of breasts, fastings, uncouth words, or
					obscene speeches, do not appertain to the honor of Gods
					or of good Daemons; but he thinks there are in the air,
					that environs us about, certain great and mighty natures,
					but withal morose and tetrical ones, that take pleasure in
					such things as these, and if they have them, they do no
					farther mischief. On the other side, the beneficent ones
					are styled by Hesiod <q direct="unspecified">Holy Daemons,</q> and <q direct="unspecified"> Guardians
						of Mankind,</q> and,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Givers of wealth, this royal gift they have.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 126.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Plato calls this sort the interpreting and ministering
					kind, and saith, they are in a middle place betwixt the
					Gods and men, and that they carry up men's prayers and
					addresses thither, and bring from thence hither prophetic
					answers and distributions of good things. Empedocles
					saith also that Daemons undergo severe punishments for
					their evil deeds and misdemeanors:&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The force of air them to the sea pursues;
					</l>
                     <l>The sea again upon the land them spews;
					</l>
                     <l>From land to th' sun's unwearied beams they're hurled,
					</l>
                     <l>Thence far into the realm of aether whirled,
					</l>
                     <l>Received by each in turn, by all abhorred;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>until, being thus chastened and purified, they are again
					admitted to that region and order that suits their nature.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.88"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Now such things and such like things as these they
				tell us are here meant concerning Typhon; how he, moved
				with envy and spite, perpetrated most wicked and horrible
				things, and putting all things into confusion, filled both
				land and sea with infinite calamities and evils, and afterwards suffered for it condign punishment. But now the
				avenger of Osiris, who was both his sister and wife, having
				extinguished and put an end to the rage and madness of
				Typhon, did not forget the many contests and difficulties
				she had encountered withal, nor her wanderings and travels
				to and fro, so far as to commit her many acts both of wisdom and courage to utter oblivion and silence; but she
				mixed them with their most sacred rites of initiation, and
				together consecrated them as resemblances, dark hints,
				and imitations of her former sufferings, both as an example
				and an encouragement of piety for all men and women that
				should hereafter fall under the like hard circumstances and
				distresses. And now both herself and Osiris being for
				their virtue changed from good Daemons into Gods, as
				were Hercules and Bacchus after them, they have (and not
				without just grounds) the honors of both Gods and Daemons joined together, their power being indeed everywhere
				great, but yet more especial and eminent in things upon
				and under the earth. For Serapis they say is no other
				than Pluto, and Isis the same with Proserpine; as Archemachus of Euboea informs us, as also Heraclides of
				Pontus, who delivers it as his opinion that the oracle at
				Canopus appertains to Pluto.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Besides, Ptolemaeus Soter saw in a dream the colossus
				of Pluto that stood at Sinope (although he knew it not, nor
				had ever seen what shape it was of) calling upon him, and
				bidding him to convey it speedily away to Alexandria.
				And as he was ignorant and at a great loss where it should
				be found, and was telling his dream to his familiars, there
				was found by chance a certain fellow that had been a
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.89"/>
				
				general rambler in all parts (his name was Sosibius), who
				affirmed he had seen at Sinope such a colossus as the king
				had dreamt of. He therefore sent Soteles and Bacchus
				thither, who in a long time and with much difficulty, and
				not without the special help of a Divine Providence, stole
				it away and brought it to Alexandria. When therefore it
				was conveyed thither and viewed, Timothy the expositor
				and Manetho the Sebennite, concluding from the Cerberus
				and serpent that stood by it that it must be the statue of
				Pluto, persuaded Ptolemy it could appertain to no other God
				but Serapis; for he had not this name when he came from
				thence, but after he was removed to Alexandria, he acquired the name of Serapis, which is the Egyptian for
				Pluto. And when Heraclitus the physiologist saith, Pluto
				and Bacchus are one and the same, in whose honor men
				are mad and rave, we are thus led to the same doctrine.
				For those that will needs have Pluto to be the body, the
				soul being as it were distracted and drunken in it, do in
				my opinion make use of an over fine and subtle allegory.
				It is therefore better to make Osiris to be the same with
				Bacchus, and Serapis again with Osiris, he obtaining that
				appellation since the change of his nature. For which
				reason Serapis is a common God to all, as they who participate of divine matters best understand.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>For there is no reason we should attend to the writings of the Phrygians, which say that one Charopos was
				daughter to Hercules, and that Typhon was son to Isaeacus, son of Hercules; no more than we have not to contemn Phylarchus, when he writes that Bacchus first brought
				two bullocks out of India into Egypt, and that the name
				of the one was Apis, and the other Osiris; but that Serapis
				is the name of him who orders the universe, from <foreign lang="greek">sai/rein</foreign>,
				which some use for <hi rend="italics">beautifying</hi> and <hi rend="italics">setting forth.</hi> For
				these sentiments of Phylarchus's are very foolish and absurd; but theirs are much more so who affirm Serapis to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.90"/>
				
				be no God at all, but only the name of the chest in which
				Apis lies; and that there are at Memphis certain great
				gates of copper, called the gates of oblivion and lamentation, which, being opened when they bury the Apis, make
				a doleful and hideous noise; which (say they) is the reason
				that, when we hear any sort of copper instrument sounding, we are presently startled and seized with fear. But
				they judge more discreetly who suppose his name to be
				derived from <foreign lang="greek">seu/esqai</foreign> or <foreign lang="greek">sou=sqai</foreign> (which signifies <hi rend="italics">to be borne
					along</hi>) and so make it to mean, that the motion of the
				universe is hurried and borne along violently. But the
				greatest part of the priests do say that Osiris and Apis are
				both of them but one complex being, while they tell us in
				their sacred commentaries and sermons that we are to look
				upon the Apis as the beautiful image of the soul of Osiris.
				I, for my part, do believe that, if the name of Serapis be
				Egyptian, it may not improperly denote joy and merriment, because I find the Egyptians term the festival which
				we call merry-making in their language <hi rend="italics">sairei.</hi> Besides, I
				find Plato to be of opinion, that Pluto is called Hades
				because he is the son of <foreign lang="greek">*ai)dw/</foreign> (which is <hi rend="italics">Modesty</hi>) and because he is a gentle God to such as are conversant with
				him. And as among the Egyptians there are a great many
				other names that are also definitions of the things they
				express, so they call that place whither they believe men's
				souls to go after death, Amenthes, which signifies in their
				language the receiver and the giver. But whether this be
				one of those names that have been anciently brought over
				and transplanted out of Greece into Egypt, we shall consider some other time; but at present we must hasten to
				despatch the remaining parts of the opinion here handled.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Osiris therefore and Isis passed from the number of
				good Daemons into that of Gods; but the power of Typhon
				being much obscured and weakened, and himself besides in great dejection of mind and in agony and, as it were, at
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.91"/>
				
				the last gasp, they therefore one while use certain sacrifices to comfort and appease his mind, and another while
				again have certain solemnities wherein they abase and
				affront him, both by mishandling and abusing such men as
				they find to have red hair, and by breaking the neck of an
				ass down a precipice (as do the Coptites), because Typhon
				was red-haired and of the ass's complexion. Moreover,
				those of Busiris and Lycopolis never make any use of
				trumpets, because they give a sound like that of asses.
				And they altogether esteem the ass as an animal not clean
				but daemoniac, because of its resemblance to Typhon;
				and when they make cakes at their sacrifices upon the
				months of Payni and Phaophi, they impress upon them an
				ass bound. Also, when they do their sacrifices to the Sun,
				they enjoin such as perform worship to that God neither
				to wear gold nor to give fodder to an ass. It is also most
				apparent that the Pythagoreans look upon Typhon as a
				daemoniac power; for they say he was produced in an
				even proportion of numbers, to wit, in that of fifty-six.
				And again, they say that the property of the triangle
				appertains to Pluto, Bacchus, and Mars; of the quadrangle
				to Rhea, Venus, Ceres, Vesta, and Juno; of the figure of
				twelve angles to Jupiter; and of the figure of fifty-six
				angles to Typhon;&mdash;as Eudoxus relates.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>And because the Egyptians are of opinion that
				Typhon was born of a red complexion, they are therefore
				used to devote to him such of the neat kind as they find
				to be of a red color; and their observation herein is so
				very nice and strict that, if they perceive the beast to have
				but one hair about it that is either black or white, they
				account it unfit for sacrifice. For they hold that what is
				fit to be made a sacrifice must not be of a thing agreeable
				to the Gods, but contrariwise, such things as contain the
				souls of ungodly and wicked men transformed into their
				shapes. Wherefore in the more ancient times they were
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.92"/>
				
				wont, after they had pronounced a solemn curse upon the
				head of the sacrifice, and had cut it off, to fling it into the
				river Nile; but now they distribute it among strangers.
				Those also among the priests that were termed Sphragistae
				or Sealers were wont to seal the beast that was to be offered; and the engraving of their seal was (as Castor tells
				us) a man upon his knees with his hands tied behind him,
				and a knife set under his throat. They believe, moreover,
				that the ass suffers for being like him (as hath been already spoken of), as much for the stupidity and sensualness
				of his disposition as for the redness of his color. Wherefore, because of all the Persian monarchs they had the
				greatest aversion for Ochus, as looking upon him as a
				villanous and abominable person, they gave him the nickname of the ass; upon which he replied: But this ass
				shall dine upon your ox. And so he slaughtered the Apis,
				as Dinon relates to us in his history. As for those that
				tell us that Typhon was seven days flying from the battle
				upon the back of an ass, and having narrowly escaped
				with his life, afterwards begat two sons called Hierosolymus and Judaeus, they are manifestly attempting, as is
				shown by the very matter, to wrest into this fable the
				relations of the Jews.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>And so much for the allegories and secret meanings
				which this head affords us. And now we begin at another
				head, which is the account of those who seem to offer at
				something more philosophical; and of these we will first
				consider the more simple and plain sort. And they are
				those that tell us that, as the Greeks are used to allegorize
				Kronos (or Saturn) into chronos (<hi rend="italics">time</hi>), and Hera (or Juno)
				into aer (<hi rend="italics">air</hi>) and also to resolve the generation of Vulcan
				into the change of air into fire, so also among the Egyptians, Osiris is the river Nile, who accompanies with Isis,
				which is the earth; and Typhon is the sea, into which the
				Nile falling is thereby destroyed and scattered, excepting
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.93"/>
				
				only that part of it which the earth receives and drinks
				up, by means whereof she becomes prolific. There is also
				a kind of a sacred lamentation used to Saturn, wherein
				they bemoan him <q direct="unspecified"> who was born in the left side of the
					world, and died in the right.</q> For the Egyptians believe
				the eastern part to be the world's face, and the northern
				its right hand, and the southern its left. And therefore
				the river Nile, holding its course from the southern parts
				towards the northern, may justly be said to have its birth
				in the left side and its death in the right; for which
				reason, the priests account the sea abominable, and call
				salt Typhon's foam. And it is one of the things they look
				upon as unlawful and prohibited to them, to use salt at
				their tables. And they use not to salute any pilots, because they have to do with the sea. And this is not the
				least reason of their so great aversedness to fish. They
				also make the picture of a fish to denote hatred. And
				therefore at the temple of Minerva at Sais there was carved
				in the porch an infant and an old man, and after them a
				hawk, and then a fish, and after all a hippopotamus, which,
				in a symbolical manner, contained this sentence: O! ye
				that are born and that die, God hateth impudence. From
				whence it is plain, that by a child and an old man they
				express our being born and our dying; by a hawk, God;
				by a fish, hatred (by reason of the sea, as hath been before
				spoken); and by a river-horse, impudence, because (as
				they say) he killeth his sire and forceth his dam. That
				also which the Pythagoreans are used to say, that the sea
				is the tear of Saturn, may seem to hint out to us that it is
				not pure nor congenial with our race.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>These then are the things that may be uttered without doors and in public, they containing nothing but matters of common cognizance. But now the most learned
				and reserved of the priests do not term the Nile only Osiris, and the sea Typhon; but in general, the whole principle
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.94"/>
				
				 and faculty of rendering moist they call Osiris, as
				believing it to be the cause of generation and the very
				substance of the seminal moisture. And on the other hand,
				whatever is a-dust, fiery, or any way drying and repugnant
				to wet, they call Typhon. And therefore, because they believe he was of a red and sallow color when he was born,
				they do not greatly care to meet with men of such looks
				nor willingly converse with them. On the other side again
				they report that Osiris, when he was born, was of a black
				complexion, because that all water renders earth, clothes,
				and clouds black, when mixed with them; and the moisture also that is in young persons makes their hair black;
				but grayness, like a sort of paleness, comes up through
				over much draught upon such as are now past their vigor
				and begin to decline in years. In like manner, the spring
				time is gay, fecund, and very agreeable; but the autumn,
				through defect of moisture, is both destructive to plants
				and sickly to men. Moreover the ox called Mnevis, which
				is kept at Heliopolis (and is sacred to Osiris, and judged
				by some to be the sire of Apis), is of a coal-black color,
				and is honored in the second place after Apis. To which
				we may add, that they call Egypt (which is one of the
				blackest soils in the world) as they do the black part of
				the eye, Chemia. They also liken it to the heart, by reason of its great warmth and moisture, and because it is
				mostly enclosed by and removed towards the left (that is,
				the southern) part of the earth, as the heart is with respect
				to a man's body.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>They believe also that the sun and moon do not go
				in chariots, but sail about the world perpetually in certain
				boats; hinting hereby at their feeding upon and springing
				first out of moisture. They are likewise of the opinion
				that Homer (as well as Thales) had been instructed by
				the Egyptians, which made him affirm water to be the
				spring and first original of all things; for that Oceanus
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.95"/>
				
				is the same with Osiris, and Tethys with Isis, so named
				from <foreign lang="greek">ti/tqh</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">a nurse,</hi> because she is the mother and nurse
				of all things. For the Grecians call the emission of the
				genital humor <foreign lang="greek">a)pousi/a</foreign>, and carnal knowledge <foreign lang="greek">sunousi/a</foreign>: they
				also call a son <foreign lang="greek">ui(o/s</foreign>, from <foreign lang="greek">u(/dwr</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">water,</hi> and <foreign lang="greek">u(=sai</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">to wet;</hi> and
				likewise Bacchus <foreign lang="greek">u(/hs</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">the wetter,</hi> they looking upon him as
				the lord of the humid nature, he being no other than
				Osiris. For Hellanicus hath set him down Hysiris, affirming that he heard him so pronounced by the priests; for so
				he hath written the name of this God all along in his history, and that, in my opinion, not without good reason,
				derived as well from his nature as his invention.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>And that therefore he is one and the same with
				Bacchus, who should better know than yourself, Dame
				Clea, who are not only president of the Delphic prophetesses, but have been also, in right of both your parents, devoted to the Osiriac rites? And if, for the sake of
				others, we shall think ourselves obliged to lay down testimonies for the proof of our present assertion, we shall
				notwithstanding remit those secrets that must not be revealed to their proper place. But now the things which
				the priests do publicly at the interment of the Apis,
				when they carry his body on a raft to be buried, do nothing differ from the procession of Bacchus. For they hang
				about them the skins of hinds, and carry branches in their
				hands, and use the same kind of shoutings and gesticulations that the ecstatics do at the inspired dances of Bacchus. For which reason also many of the Greeks make
				statues of Dionysos Tauromorphos (or Bacchus in the form
				of a bull). And the Elean women, in their ordinary form
				of prayer, beseech the God to come to them with his ox's
				foot. The Argives also have a Bacchus named Bougenes
				(or <hi rend="italics">ox-gotten</hi>); and they call him up out of the waters by
				sounding of trumpets, flinging a young lamb into the
				abyss for him that keeps the door there; and these trumpets
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.96"/>
				
				 they hide within their thyrsi (or green boughs), as
				Socrates, in his Treatise of Rituals, relates. Likewise the
				tales about the Titans, and what they call the Mystic
				Night, have a strange agreement with what they tell us of
				the discerptions, resurrections, and regenerations of Osiris;
				as also what relates to their sepulchres. For not only the
				Egyptians (as hath been already spoken) do show in many
				several places the chests in which Osiris lies; but the Delphians also believe that the relics of Bacchus are laid up
				with them just by the oracle-place; and the Hosii (or holy
				men) perform a secret sacrifice within the temple of Apollo,
				when the Thyiades rouse the God of the fan (as they call
				him). Now that the Greeks do not esteem Bacchus as the
				lord and president of wine only, but also of the whole
				humid nature, Pindar alone is a sufficient witness, when
				he saith,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>May joyous Bacchus send increase of fruit,
				</l>
                     <l>The chaste autumnal light, to all my trees.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For which cause it is forbidden to such as worship Osiris,
					either to destroy a fruit-tree or to stop up a well.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>And they call not only the Nile, but in general
				every humid, the efflux of Osiris. And a pitcher of
				water goes always first in their sacred processions, in
				honor of the God. And they make the figure of a fig-leaf both for the king and the southern climate, which fig-leaf is interpreted to mean the watering and fructifying of
				the universe, for it seems to bear some resemblance in its
				make to the virilities of a man. Moreover, when they
				keep the feast of the Pamylia, which is a Phallic or Priapeian one (as was said before), they expose to view and
				carry about a certain image of a man with a threefold
				privity; for this God is a first origin, and every first origin
				doth by its fecundity multiply what proceeds from it. And
				we are commonly used instead of <q direct="unspecified">many times</q> to say
				<q direct="unspecified">thrice,</q> as <q direct="unspecified">thrice happy,</q> and,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.97"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">As many bonds thrice told, and infinite.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VIII. 340.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Unless (by Jove) we are to understand the word treble as
					spoken by the ancients in a proper sense. For the humid
					nature, being in the beginning the chief source and origin of
					the universe, must of consequence produce the three first
					bodies,&mdash;the earth, air, and fire. For the story which is
					here told by way of surplusage to the tale&mdash;how that Typhon threw the privity of Osiris into the river, and that
					Isis could not find it, and therefore fashioned and prepared
					the resemblance and effigies of it, and appointed it to be
					worshipped and carried about in their processions, like as
					in the Grecian Phallephoria&mdash;amounts but to this, to instruct and teach us that the prolific and generative property of this God had moisture for its first matter, and that by
					means of moisture it came to immix itself with things
					capable of generation. We have also another story told
					us by the Egyptians,&mdash;how that once Apopis, brother to
					the Sun, fell at variance with Jupiter and made war upon
					him; but Jupiter, entering into an alliance with Osiris
					and by his means overthrowing his enemy in a pitched
					battle, afterwards adopted him for his son and gave him
					the name of Dionysus. It is easy to show that this fabular relation borders also upon the verity of physical science. For the Egyptians call the wind Jupiter, with which
					the parching and fiery property makes war; and though
					this be not the sun, yet hath it some cognation with the
					sun. But now moisture, extinguishing the excessiveness
					of drought, increases and strengthens the exhalations of
					wet, which give food and vigor to the air.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Moreover, the ivy, which the Greeks use to consecrate to Bacchus, is called by the Egyptians <hi rend="italics">chenosiris,</hi>
				which word (as they tell us) signifies in their language
				Osiris's tree. Ariston therefore, who wrote of the colony
				of the Athenians, lighted upon a certain epistle of Alexarchus,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.98"/>
				
				 in which it is related that Bacchus, the son of Jupiter and Isis, is not called Osiris by the Egyptians, but
				Arsaphes, which denotes valiant. This is hinted at by Hermaeus also, in his first book about the Egyptians; for he
				saith, the name of Osiris is to be interpreted stout. I shall
				now pass by Mnaseas, who joins Bacchus, Osiris, and Serapis together, and makes them the same with Epaphus.
				I shall also omit Anticlides, who saith that Isis was the
				daughter of Prometheus, and that she was married to Bacchus. For the fore-mentioned proprieties of their festivals
				and sacrifices afford us a much more clear evidence than
				the authorities of writers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>They believe likewise that of all the stars, the Sirius (or Dog) is proper to Isis, because it bringeth on the
				flowing of the Nile. They also pay divine honor to the
				lion, and adorn the gates of their temples with the yawning mouths of lions, because the Nile then overflows its
				banks,
				<quote rend="blockquote">When first the mounting sun the Lion meets.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Aratus.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And as they term the Nile the efflux of Osiris, so they
					hold and esteem the earth for the body of Isis; and not all
					of it either, but that part only which the Nile, as it were,
					leaps over, and thereby impregnates and mixes with it.
					And by this amorous congress they produce Horus. Now
					this Horus is that Hora, or sweet season and just temperament of the ambient air, which nourisheth and preserveth
					all things; and they report him to have been nursed by
					Latona in the marshy grounds about Buto, because moist
					and watery land best feeds those exhaled vapors which
					quench and relax drought and parching heat. But those
					parts of the country which are outmost and upon the confines and sea-coast they call Nephthys; and therefore they
					give her the name of Teleutaea (or the outmost) and report
					her to be married to Typhon. When therefore the Nile
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.99"/>
					
					is excessive great, and so far passes its ordinary bounds
					that it approaches to those that inhabit the outmost quarters, they call this Osiris's accompanying with Nephthys,
					found out by the springing up of plants thereupon, whereof
					the melilot is one; which (as the story tells us), being
					dropped behind and left there, gave Typhon to understand
					the wrong that had been done to his bed. Which made
					them say that Isis had a lawful son called Horus, and
					Nephthys a bastard called Anubis. And indeed they record in the successions of their kings, that Nephthys being
					married to Typhon was at first barren. Now if they do
					not mean this of a woman but of a Goddess, they must
					needs hint that the earth, by reason of its solidity, is in its
					own nature unfruitful and barren.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>And the conspiracy and usurpation of Typhon will
				be the power of the drought, which then prevails and dissipates that generative moisture which both begets the Nile
				and increases it. And the queen of Ethiopia, that abetted
				his quarrel, will denote the southern winds that come from
				Ethiopia. For when these come to overpower the Etesian
				(or anniversary) winds which drive the clouds towards
				Ethiopia, and by that means prevent those showers of rain
				which should augment the Nile from discharging themselves down, Typhon then being rampant scorcheth all,
				and being wholly master of the Nile, which now through
				weakness and debility draws in its head and takes a contrary course, he next thrusts him hollow and sunk as he is
				into the sea. For the story that is told us of the closing
				up of Osiris in a chest seems to me to be nothing else but
				an imitation of the withdrawing and disappearing of the
				water. For which reason they tell us that Osiris was missing upon the month of Athyr; at which time the Etesian
				winds being wholly ceased, the Nile returns to his channel,
				and the country looks bare; the night also growing longer,
				the darkness increases, and so the power of light fades
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.100"/>
				
				away and is overcome. And as the priests act several
				other melancholy things upon this occasion, so they cover
				a gilded cow with a black linen pall, and thus expose her
				to public view at the mourning of the Goddess, for four
				days together, beginning at the seventeenth of the month.
				For the things they mourn for are also four; the first
				whereof is the falling and recess of the river Nile: the
				second, because the northern winds are then quite suppressed by the southern overpowering them; the third,
				because the day is grown shorter than the night; and the
				last and chiefest of all, the barrenness of the earth, together with the nakedness of the trees, which then cast
				their leaves. And on the nineteenth day at night they go
				down to the sea-side, and the priest and sacred livery bring
				forth the chest, having within it a little golden ark into
				which they pour fresh and potable water, and all that are
				there present give a great shout for joy that Osiris is now
				found. Then they take fertile mould, and stir it about in
				that water, and when they have mixed with it several very
				costly odors and spices, they form it into a little image, in
				fashion like a crescent, and then dress it up in fine clothes
				and adorn it, intimating hereby that they believe these
				Gods to be the substance of earth and water.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>But Isis again recovering Osiris, and rearing up
				Horus, made strong by exhalations, mists, and clouds,
				Typhon was indeed reduced, but not executed; for the
				Goddess who is sovereign over the earth would not suffer
				the opposite nature to wet to be utterly extinguished, but
				loosed it and let it go, being desirous the mixture should
				continue. For it would be impossible for the world to be
				complete and perfect, if the property of fire should fail
				and be wanting. And as these things are not spoken by
				them without a considerable show of reason, so neither
				have we reason wholly to contemn this other account which
				they give us; which is, that Typhon in the more ancient
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.101"/>
				
				times was master of Osiris's portion. For (say they) Egypt
				was once all sea. For which reason it is found at this day
				to have abundance of fish-shells, both in its mines and on
				its mountains. And besides that, all the springs and wells
				(which in that country are extreme numerous) have in
				them a salt and brackish water, as if some remainder of
				the ancient sea had run thither, to be laid up in store. But
				in process of time, Horus got the upper hand of Typhon;
				that is, there happened such an opportunity of sudden and
				tempestuous showers of rain, that the Nile pushed the sea
				out, and discovered the champaign land, and afterwards
				filled it up with continual profusions of mud; all which
				hath the testimony of sense to confirm it. For we see at
				this day that, as the river drives down fresh mud and lays
				new earth unto the old, the sea by degrees gives back and
				the salt water runs off, as the parts in the bottom gain
				height by new accessions of mud. We see, moreover, that
				the Pharos, which Homer observed in his time to be a
				whole day's sail from Egypt, is now a part of it; not because it changed its place or came nearer the shore than
				before, but because, the river still adding to and increasing
				the main land, the intermediate sea was obliged to retire.</p>
            <p>To speak the truth, these things are not far unlike the
					explications which the Stoics used to give of the Gods.
					For they also say that the generative and nutritive
					property of the air is called Bacchus; the striking and
					dividing property, Hercules; the receptive property, Ammon; that which passes through the earth and fruits,
					Ceres and Proserpine; and that which passes through the
					sea, Neptune.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>But those who join with these physiological accounts certain mathematical matters relating to astronomy
				suppose Typhon to mean the world of the sun, and Osiris
				that of the moon; for that the moon, being endued with a
				prolific and moistening light, is very favorable both to the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.102"/>
				
				breeding of animals and the springing up of plants; but
				the sun, having in it an immoderate and excessive fire,
				burns and dries up such things as grow up and look green,
				and by its scorching heat renders a great part of the world
				wholly uninhabitable, and very often gets the better of the
				moon. For which reason the Egyptians always call Typhon
				Seth, which in their language signifies a domineering and
				compelling power. And they tell us in their mythology,
				that Hercules is placed in the sun and rides about the
				world in it, and that Hermes doth the like in the moon.
				For the operations of the moon seem to resemble reason
				and to proceed from wisdom, but those of the sun to be
				like unto strokes effected by violence and mere strength.
				But the Stoics affirm the sun to be kindled and fed by the
				sea, and the moon by the waters of springs and pools,
				which send up a sweet and soft exhalation to it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>It is fabled by the Egyptians that Osiris's death
				happened upon the seventeenth day of the month, at which
				time it is evident that the moon is at the fullest. For
				which reason the Pythagoreans call that day Antiphraxis
				(or <hi rend="italics">disjunction</hi>) and utterly abominate the very number.
				For the middle number seventeen, falling in betwixt the
				square number sixteen and the oblong parallelogram
				eighteen (which are the only plane numbers that have
				their peripheries equal with their areas), disjoins and
				separates them from each other; and being divided into
				unequal portions, it makes the sesquioctave proportion
				(9:8). Moreover, there are some that affirm Osiris to have
				lived eight and twenty years; and others again, that he
				only reigned so long, for that is the just number of the
				moon's degrees of light and of the days wherein she performs her circuit. And after they have cleft the tree, at
				the solemnity they call Osiris's Burial, they next form it
				into an ark in fashion like a crescent, because the moon,
				when it joins the sun, becomes first of that figure and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.103"/>
				
				then vanishes away. Likewise the division of Osiris into
				fourteen parts sets forth unto us symbolically the number
				of days in which that luminary is decreasing, from the full
				to the change. Moreover, the day upon which she first
				appears, after she hath now escaped the solar rays and
				passed by the sun, they term <q direct="unspecified">imperfect good;</q> for Osiris
				is beneficent, and as this name hath many other significations, so what they call <q direct="unspecified">effectuating and beneficent force</q>
				is none of the least. Hermaeus also tells us, that his other
				name of Omphis, when interpreted, denotes a benefactor.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>They moreover believe that the several risings of
				the river Nile bear a certain proportion to the variations of
				light in the moon. For they say that its highest rise,
				which is at Elephantine, is eight and twenty cubits high,
				which is the number of its several lights and the measures
				of its monthly course; and that at Mendes and Xois,
				which is the lowest of all, it is six cubits high, which
				answers the half-moon; but that the middlemost rise,
				which is at Memphis, is (when it is at its just height) fourteen cubits high, which answers the full moon. They also
				say that the Apis is the living image of Osiris, and that he
				is begotten when a prolific light darts down from the moon
				and touches the cow when she is disposed for procreation;
				for which reason many things in the Apis bear resemblance
				to the shapes of the moon, it having light colors intermixed
				with shady ones. Moreover, upon the kalends of the
				month Phamenoth they keep a certain holiday, by them
				called Osiris's ascent into the moon, and they account it the
				beginning of their spring. Thus they place the power of
				Osiris in the moon, and affirm him to be there married with
				Isis, which is generation. For which cause they style the
				moon the mother of the world, and believe her to have the
				nature both of male and female, because she is first filled
				and impregnated by the sun, and then herself sends forth
				generative principles into the air, and from thence scatters
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.104"/>
				
				them down upon the earth. For that Typhonian destruction doth not always prevail; but it is very often subdued
				by generation and fast bound like a prisoner, but afterwards gets up again and makes war upon Horus. Now
				this Horus is the terrestrial world, which is not wholly
				exempted from either generation or destruction.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>But there are some that will have this tale to be a
				figurative representation of the eclipses. For the moon is
				under an eclipse at the fill, when the sun is in opposition
				to her, because she then falls into the shadow of the
				earth, as they say Osiris did into his chest. But she hides
				and obscures the sun at the new moon, upon the thirtieth
				day of the month, but doth not extinguish the sun quite,
				any more than Isis did Typhon. And when Nephthys was
				delivered of Anubis, Isis owned the child. For Nephthys
				is that part of the world which is below the earth, and
				invisible to us; and Isis that which is above the earth, and
				visible. But that which touches upon both these, and is
				called the horizon (or bounding circle) and is common to
				them both, is called Anubis, and resembles in shape the
				dog, because the dog makes use of his sight by night as
				well as by day. And therefore Anubis seems to me to
				have a power among the Egyptians much like to that of
				Hecate among the Grecians, he being as well terrestrial as
				Olympic. Some again think Anubis to be Saturn; wherefore, they say, because he produces all things out of himself and breeds them in himself, he had the name of Kyon
				(which signifies in Greek both a dog and a breeder).
				Moreover, those that worship the dog have a certain secret
				meaning that must not be here revealed. And in the more
				remote and ancient times, the dog had the highest honor
				paid him in Egypt; but after that Cambyses had slain the
				Apis and thrown him away contemptuously like a carrion,
				no animal came near to him except the dog only; upon
				this he lost his first honor and the right he had of being
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.105"/>
				
				worshipped above other creatures. There are also some
				that will have the shadow of the earth, into which they
				believe the moon to fall when eclipsed, to be called
				Typhon.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>Wherefore it seems to me not to be unconsonant to
				reason to hold that each of them apart is not in the right,
				but all together are. For it is not drought, nor wind, nor
				sea, nor darkness, but every part of Nature that is hurtful
				or destructive, that belongs to Typhon. For we are not to
				place the first origins of the universe in inanimate bodies,
				as do Democritus and Epicurus; nor to make one reason,
				and one forecast overruling and containing all things, the
				creator of matter without attribute, as the Stoics do; for it
				is alike impossible for any thing bad to exist where God is
				the cause of all things, and for any thing good to exist
				where he is the cause of nothing. For the harmony of
				the world is (according to Heraclitus) like that of a bow
				or a harp, alternately tightened and relaxed; and according
				to Euripides,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor good nor bad here's to be found apart;
				</l>
                     <l>But both immixed in one, for greater art.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Aeolus of Euripides, Frag. 21.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore this most ancient opinion hath been handed
					down from the theologists and law-givers to the poets and
					philosophers, it having an original fathered upon none, but
					having gained a persuasion both strong and indelible, and
					being everywhere professed and received by barbarians as
					well as Grecians,&mdash;and that not only in vulgar discourses
					and public fame, but also in their secret mysteries and
					open sacrifices,&mdash;that the world is neither hurried about
					by wild chance without intelligence, discourse, and direction, nor yet that there is but one reason, which as it were
					with a rudder or with gentle and easy reins directs it and
					holds it in; but that on the contrary, there are in it several
					differing things, and those made up of bad as well as good;
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.106"/>
					
					or rather (to speak more plainly) that Nature produces
					nothing here but what is mixed and tempered. Not that
					there is as it were one store-keeper, who out of two different casks dispenses to us human affairs adulterated and
					mixed together,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">He alludes to Homer, who feigns Jupiter to have in his house two differing jars, the one filled with good things, and the other with bad. See Il. XXIV. 527.</note> as a host doth his liquors; but by
					reason of two contrary origins and opposite powers&mdash;whereof the one leads to the right hand and in a direct
					line, and the other turns to the contrary hand and goes
					athwart&mdash;both human life is mixed, and the world (if not
					all, yet that part which is about the earth and below the
					moon) is become very unequal and various, and liable to
					all manner of changes. For if nothing can come without
					a cause, and if a good thing cannot afford a cause of evil,
					Nature then must certainly have a peculiar source and
					origin of evil as well as of good.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>And this is the opinion of the greatest and wisest
				part of mankind. For some believe that there are two
				Gods, as it were two rival workmen, the one whereof they
				make to be the maker of good things, and the other of
				bad. And some call the better of these God, and the other
				Daemon; as doth Zoroaster the Magian whom they report
				to be five thousand years elder than the Trojan times.
				This Zoroaster now called the one of these Horomazes,
				and the other Arimanius; and affirmed, moreover, that the
				one of them did, of any thing sensible, the most resemble
				light, and the other darkness and ignorance; but that
				Mithras was in the middle betwixt them. For which cause
				the Persians call Mithras the Mediator. And they tell us,
				that he first taught mankind to make vows and offerings of
				thanksgiving to the one, and to offer averting and feral
				sacrifice to the other. For they beat a certain plant called
				<hi rend="italics">omomi</hi> in a mortar, and call upon Pluto and the dark; and
				then mix it with the blood of a sacrificed wolf, and convey
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.107"/>
				
				it to a certain place where the sun never shines, and there
				cast it away. For of plants they believe that some appertain to the good God, and others again to the evil Daemon;
				and likewise they think that such animals as dogs, fowls,
				and urchins belong to the good, but water animals to the
				bad, for which reason they account him happy that kills
				most of these.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>These men moreover tell us a great many romantic
				things about these Gods, whereof these are some. They
				say that, Horomazes springing from purest light, and Arimanius on the other hand from pitchy darkness, these two
				are therefore at war with one another; and that Horomazes made six Gods, whereof the first was the author of
				benevolence, the second of truth, the third of law and
				order; and the rest, one of wisdom, another of wealth,
				and a third of that pleasure which accrues from good
				actions; and that Arimanius likewise made the like number of contrary Gods to confront them. After this, Horomazes, having first trebled his own magnitude, mounted
				up aloft, as far above the sun as the sun itself above the
				earth, and so bespangled the heavens with stars. But one
				star (called Sirius, or the Dog) he set as a kind of sentinel
				or scout before all the rest. And after he had made four
				and twenty Gods more, he placed them all in an egg-shell.
				But those that were made by Arimanius (being themselves
				also of the like number) breaking a hole in this beauteous
				and glazed egg-shell, bad things came by this means to be
				intermixed with good. But the fatal time is now approaching, in which Arimanius, who by means of this brings
				plagues and famines upon the earth, must of necessity be
				himself utterly extinguished and destroyed; at which time,
				the earth being made plain and level, there will be one
				life and one society of mankind, made all happy and of
				one speech. But Theopompus saith, that, according to
				the opinion of the Magi, each of these Gods subdues and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.108"/>
				
				is subdued by turns for the space of three thousand years
				apiece, and that for three thousand years more they quarrel
				and fight, and destroy each other's works; but that at last
				Pluto shall fail, and mankind shall be happy, and neither
				need food nor yield a shadow. And that the God who has
				projected these things shall then for some time take his
				repose and rest; but yet this time is not so much to him,
				although it seem so to man, whose sleep is but short.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>Such then is the mythology of the Magi. But the
				Chaldaeans say, there are Gods of the planets also, two
				whereof they style benefics, and two malefics; the other
				three they pronounce to be common and indifferent. As
				for the Grecians, their opinions are obvious and well
				known to every one; to wit, that they make the good
				part of the world to appertain to Jupiter Olympius, and the
				hateful part to Pluto; and likewise, that they fable Harmonia to have been begotten by Venus and Mars, the one
				whereof is rough and quarrelsome, and the other sweet
				and generative. In the next place consider we the great
				agreement of the philosophers with these people. For
				Heraclitus doth in plain and naked terms call war the
				father, the king, and the lord of all things; and saith that
				Homer, when he first prayed,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">Discord be damned from Gods and human race,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVIII. 107.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>little thought he was then cursing the origination of all
					things, they owing their rise to aversation and quarrel.
					He also saith, that the sun will never exceed his proper
					bounds; and if he should, that
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Tongues, aids of justice, soon will find him out.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Empedocles also calls the benefic principle love and friendship, and very often sweet-looked harmony; and the evil
					principle
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Pernicious enmity and bloody hate.</quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.109"/>
            <p>The Pythagoreans use a great number of terms as attributes of these two principles; of the good, they use the
					unit, the terminate, the permanent, the straight, the odd,
					the square, the equal, the dexter, and the lucid; and
					again of the bad, the two, the interminate, the fluent, the
					crooked, the even, the oblong, the unequal, the sinister,
					and the dark; insomuch that all these are looked upon as
					principles of generation. But Anaxagoras made but two,
					the intelligence and the interminate; and Aristotle called
					the first of these form, and the latter privation. But Plato
					in many places, as it were shading and veiling over his
					opinion, names the first of these opposite principles the
					Same, and the second the Other. But in his book of Laws,
					when he was now grown old, he affirmed, not in riddles
					and emblems but in plain and proper words, that the
					world is not moved by one soul, but perhaps by a great
					many, but not by fewer than two; the one of which is
					beneficent, and the other contrary to it and the author of
					things contrary. He also leaves a certain third nature in
					the midst between, which is neither without soul nor without reason, nor void of a self-moving power (as some suppose), but rests upon both of the preceding principles, but
					yet so as still to affect, desire, and pursue the better of
					them; as I shall make out in the ensuing part of this discourse, in which I design to reconcile the theology of the
					Egyptians principally with this sort of philosophy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>For the frame and constitution of this world is made
				up of contrary powers, but yet such as are not of such
				equal strength but that the better is still predominant.
				But it is impossible for the ill one to be quite extinguished,
				because much of it is interwoven with the body and much
				with the soul of the universe, and it always maintains a
				fierce combat with the better part. And therefore in the
				soul, intellect and reason, which is the prince and master
				of all the best things, is Osiris; and in the earth, in the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.110"/>
				
				winds, in the waters, in the heaven, and in the stars, what
				is ranged, fixed, and in a sound constitution (as orderly
				seasons, due temperament of air, and the revolutions of
				the stars) is the efflux and appearing image of Osiris.
				Again, the passionate, Titanic, irrational, and brutal part
				of the soul is Typhon; and what in the corporeal nature
				is adventitious, morbid, and tumultuous (as irregular seasons, distemperatures of air, eclipses of the sun, and disappearings of the moon) is, as it were, the incursions and
				devastations of Typhon. And the name of Seth, by which
				they call Typhon, declares as much; for it denotes a
				domineering and compelling power, and also very often
				an overturning, and again a leaping over. There are also
				some that say that Bebon was one of Typhon's companions;
				but Manetho saith, Typhon himself was called Bebon.
				Now that name signifies restraining and hindering; as
				who should say, <q direct="unspecified">while all things march along in a regular course and move steadily toward their natural end,
					the power of Typhon stands in their way and stops them.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>For which reason they assign him the ass, the most
				brutal and sottish of all the tame beasts, and the crocodile
				and river-horse, the most savage and fierce of all the wild
				beasts. Of the ass we have spoken already. They show
				us at Hermopolis the statue of Typhon, which is a river-horse with a hawk on his back fighting with a serpent;
				where they set out Typhon by the river-horse, and by the
				hawk that power and principle which Typhon possesses
				himself of by violence, and thereupon ceases not to disturb
				others and to be disturbed himself by his malice. For
				which reason also, when they are to offer sacrifice upon
				the seventh day of the month Tybi, at the festival which
				they call the Arrival of Isis out of Phoenicia, they print
				the river-horse bound upon their sacred cakes. Besides
				this, there is a constant custom at the town of Apollo, for
				every one to eat some part of a crocodile; and having
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.111"/>
				
				upon a certain set day hunted down as many of them at
				they are able, they kill them, and throw down their carcasses before the temple. And they tell us that Typhon
				made his escape from Horus in the form of a crocodile
				for they make all bad and noxious things&mdash;whether animals, plants or passions&mdash;to be the works, the members
				and the motions of Typhon.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="51">
            <p>On the other hand, they represent Osiris by an eye
				and a sceptre, the one whereof expresses forecast, and the
				other power. In like manner Homer, when he called the
				governor and monarch of all the world
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">Supremest Jove, and mighty Counsellor,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VIII. 22.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>seems to me to denote his imperial power by supremest,
					and his well-advisedness and discretion by Counsellor.
					They also oftentimes describe this God by a hawk, because
					he exceeds in quickness of sight and velocity in flying, and
					sustains himself with very little food. He is also said to
					fly over the bodies of dead men that lie unburied, and
					to drop down earth upon their eyes. Likewise, when he
					alights down upon the bank of any river to assuage his
					thirst, he sets his feathers up on end, and after he hath
					done drinking, he lets them fall again. Which he plainly
					doth because he is now safe and escaped from the danger
					of the crocodile; but if he chances to be catched, his
					feathers then continue stiff as before. They also show us
					everywhere Osiris's statue in the shape of a man, with his
					private part erect, to betoken unto us his faculty of generation and nutrition; and they dress up his images in a
					flame-colored robe, esteeming the sun as the body of the
					power of good, and as the visible image of intelligible
					substance. Wherefore we have good reason to reject
					those that ascribe the sun's globe unto Typhon, to whom
					appertaineth nothing of a lucid or salutary nature, nor
					order, nor generation, nor motion attended with measure
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.112"/>
					
					and proportion, but the clean contrary to them. Neither
					is that parching drought, which destroys many animals
					and plants, to be accounted as an effect of the sun, but
					of those winds and waters which in the earth and air are
					not tempered according to the season, at which time the
					principle of the unordered and interminate nature acts at
					random, and so stifles and suppresses those exhalations
					that should ascend.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="52">
            <p>Moreover, in the sacred hymns of Osiris they call
				him up <q direct="unspecified">who lies hidden in the arms of the sun.</q> And
				upon the thirtieth day of the month Epiphi they keep a
				certain festival called the Birthday of the eyes of Horus,
				when the sun and the moon are in one direct line; as esteeming not only the moon but also the sun to be the eye
				and light of Horus. Likewise the three and twentieth
				day of the month Phaophi they make to be the nativity
				of the staves of the sun, which they observe after the
				autumnal equinox, intimating hereby that he now wants,
				as it were, a prop and a stay, as suffering a great diminution
				both of heat and light by his declining and moving obliquely from us. Besides this, they lead the sacred cow
				seven times about her temple at the time of the winter
				solstice. And this going round is called the seeking of
				Osiris, the Goddess being in great distress for water in
				winter time. And the reason of her going round so many
				times is because the sun finishes his passage from the winter to the summer tropic in the seventh month. It is reported also that Horus, the son of Isis, was the first that
				ever sacrificed to the sun upon the fourth day of the month,
				as we find it written in a book called the Birthdays of
				Horus. Moreover, they offer incense to the sun three
				times every day; resin at his rising, myrrh when it is in
				the mid-heaven, and that they call Kyphi about the time
				of his setting. (What each of these means, I shall after
				wards explain.) Now they are of opinion that the sun is
				atoned and pacified by all these.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.113"/>
            <p>But to what purpose should I heap together many things
					of this nature? For there are some that scruple not to say
					plainly that Osiris is the sun, and that he is called Sirius
					by the Greeks, although the Egyptians, adding the article
					to his name, have obscured and brought its sense into
					question. They also declare Isis to be no other than the
					moon, and say that such statues of her as are horned
					were made in imitation of the crescent; and that the black
					habit in which she so passionately pursues the sun, sets
					forth her disappearings and eclipses. For which reason
					they used to invoke the moon in love-concerns; and Eudoxus also saith that Isis presides over love-matters. Now
					these things have in them a show and semblance of reason;
					whereas they that would make Typhon to be the sun deserve not to be heard.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="53">
            <p>But we must again resume our proper discourse.
				Isis is indeed that property of Nature which is feminine
				and receptive of all production; in which sense she was
				called the nurse and the all-receiver by Plato, and the Goddess with ten thousand names by the common sort, because being transmuted by reason she receives all manner
				of shapes and guises. But she hath a natural love to the
				prime and principal of all beings (which is the good principle), and eagerly affects it and pursues after it; and she
				shuns and repels her part of the evil one. And although
				she be indeed both the receptacle and matter of either
				nature, yet she always of herself inclines to the better of
				them, and readily gives way to it to generate upon her and
				to sow its effluxes and resemblances into her; and she rejoices and is very glad when she is impregnated and filled
				with productions. For generation is the production of an
				image of the real substance upon matter, and what is generated is an imitation of what is in truth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="54">
            <p>And therefore not without great consonancy do they
				fable that the soul of Osiris is eternal and incorruptible,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.114"/>
				
				but that his body is often torn in pieces and destroyed by
				Typhon, and that Isis wanders to and fro to look him out,
				and when she hath found him, puts him together again.
				For the permanent being, the mental nature, and the good,
				is itself above corruption and change; but the sensitive
				and corporeal part takes off certain images from it, and
				receives certain proportions, shapes, and resemblances,
				which, like impressions upon wax, do not continue always,
				but are swallowed up by the disorderly and tumultuous
				part, which is chased hither from the upper region and
				makes war with Horus, who is born of Isis, being the sensible image of the mental world. For which reason he is
				said to be prosecuted for bastardy by Typhon, as not being
				pure and sincere,&mdash;like his father, the pure absolute reason,
				unmixed and impassible,&mdash;but embased with matter by
				corporeity. But he gets the better of him, and carries the
				cause, Hermes (that is, reason) witnessing and proving
				that Nature produces the world by becoming herself of
				like form with the mental property. Moreover, the generation of Apollo by Isis and Osiris, while the Gods were
				yet in Rhea's womb, hints out unto us that, before this
				world became visible and was completed by reason, matter,
				being convinced by Nature that she was imperfect alone,
				brought forth the first production. For which reason they
				also say, this deity was born a cripple in the dark, and
				they call him the elder Horus; for he was not the world,
				but a kind of a picture and phantom of the world to be
				afterwards.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="55">
            <p>This Horus is terminate and complete of himself,
				yet hath he not quite destroyed Typhon, but only taken off
				his over great activity and brutal force. Whence it is they
				tell us that at Copto the statue of Horus holds fast in
				hand the privities of Typhon; and they fable that Mercury
				took out Typhon's sinews and used them for harp-strings,
				to denote unto us that, when reason composed the universe,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.115"/>
				
				it made one concord out of many discords, and did not
				abolish but accomplish<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">If we adopt Bentley's emendation <foreign lang="greek">a)neph/rwse</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">a)neplh/rwse</foreign>, we must translate, <q direct="unspecified">did not abolish, but merely maimed, the corruptible faculty.</q> (G.)</note> the corruptible faculty. Whence
				it comes that this power, being weak and feeble in the
				present state of things, blends and mixes with passible and
				mutable parts of the world, and so becomes in the earth
				the causer of concussions and shakings, and in the air of
				parching droughts and tempestuous winds, as also of hurricanes and thunders. It likewise infects both waters and
				winds with pestilential diseases, and runs up and insolently
				rages as high as the very moon, suppressing many times
				and blackening the lucid part, as the Egyptians believe.
				They relate that Typhon one while smote Horus's eye, and
				another while plucked it out and swallowed it up, and
				afterwards gave it back to the sun; intimating by the blow
				the monthly diminution of the moon, and by the blinding
				of him its eclipse, which the sun cures again by shining
				presently upon it as soon as it hath escaped from the
				shadow of the earth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="56">
            <p>Now the better and more divine nature consists of
				three; or of the intelligible part, of matter, and of that
				which is made up of both, which the Greeks call Cosmos
				(that is <hi rend="italics">trimness</hi>) and we the world. Plato therefore uses
				to name the intelligible part the form, the sample, and the
				father; and matter the mother, the nurse, and the seat and
				receptacle of generation; and that again which is made
				up of both, the offspring and the production. And one
				would conjecture that the Egyptians called it the most perfect of triangles, because they likened the nature of the
				universe principally to that; which Plato also in his Commonwealth seems to have made use of to the same purpose,
				when he forms his nuptial diagram. Now in that triangle
				the perpendicular consists of three parts, the base of four,
				and the subtense of five, its square being equal in value
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.116"/>
				
				with the squares of the two that contain it. We are
				therefore to take the perpendicular to represent the male
				property, the base the female, and the subtense that which
				is produced by them both. We are likewise to look upon
				Osiris as the first cause, Isis as the faculty of reception,
				and Horus as the effect. For the number three is the first
				odd and perfect number, and the number four is a square,
				having for its side the even number two. The number
				five also in some respects resembles the father and in some
				again the mother, being made up of three and two; besides, <foreign lang="greek">pa/nta</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">all things</hi>) seems to be derived from <foreign lang="greek">pe/nte</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">five</hi>)
				and they use <foreign lang="greek">pempa/sasqai</foreign> (which is <hi rend="italics">telling five</hi>) for
				counting.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the preceding essay, &sect; 86.</note> Moreover, the number five makes a square equal to
				the number of letters used among the Egyptians, as also
				to the number of years which Apis lived. They are also
				used to call Horus Min, which signifieth as much as <hi rend="italics">seen;</hi>
				for the world is perceptible to sense and visible. And Isis
				they sometimes call Muth, and sometimes again Athyri,
				and sometimes Methyer. And by the first of these names
				they mean mother, by the second Horus's mundane house
				(as Plato calls it, the place and receptacle of generation);
				but the third is compounded of two words, the one whereof signifies full, and the other the cause; for the matter
				of the world is full, and it is closely joined with the good
				and pure and well ordered principle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="57">
            <p>And it may be, Hesiod also, when he makes the first
				things of all to be chaos, earth, hell, and love, may be
				thought to take up no other principles than these, if we
				apply these names as we have already disposed them, to
				wit, that of earth to Isis, that of love to Osiris, and that
				of hell to Typhon; for he seems to lay the chaos under
				all, as a kind of room or place for the world to lie in.
				And the subject we are now upon seems in a manner to
				call for Plato's tale, which Socrates tells us in the Symposium
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.117"/>
				
				 about the production of Eros (or Love), where he saith,
				that once on a time Poverty, having a mighty desire of
				children, laid her down by Plenty's side as he was asleep,
				and that she thereupon conceiving by him brought forth
				Eros, who was of a nature both mixed and various, as
				coming of a father that was good and wise and had
				sufficiency of all things, but of a mother that was very
				needy and poor; and that by reason of her indigence she
				still hankered after another, and was eagerly importunate
				for another. For this same Plenty is no other than the
				first amiable, desirable, complete, and sufficient being; and
				matter is that which he called Poverty, she being of herself alone destitute of the property of good, but when she
				is impregnated by it, she still desires and craves for more.
				Moreover, the world (or Horus) that is produced out of
				these two, being not eternal, nor impassible, nor incorruptible, but ever a making, does therefore machinate, partly
				by shifting of accidents and partly by circular motions, to
				remain still young and never to die.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="58">
            <p>But we must remember that we are not to make use
				of fables as if they were doctrinal throughout, but only to
				take that in each of them which we shall judge to make a
				pertinent resemblance. And therefore, when we treat of
				matter, we need not (with respect to the sentiments of some
				philosophers) to conceit in our minds a certain body void
				of soul and of all quality, and of itself wholly idle and
				unactive. For we use to call oil the matter of an unguent,
				and gold the matter of a statue, though they are not destitute of all quality. And we render the very soul and mind
				of a man as matter to reason, to be dressed up and composed into science and virtue. There have been some also
				that have made the mind to be a receptacle of forms and a
				kind of imprimary for things intelligible; and some are of
				opinion again that the genital humidity in the female sex
				is no active property nor efficient principle, but only the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.118"/>
				
				matter and nutriment of the production. Which when we
				retain in our memories, we ought to conceive likewise that
				this Goddess, which always participates of the first God
				and is ever taken up with the love of those excellencies
				and charms that are about him, is not by nature opposite
				to him; but that, as we are used to say of a good natured woman, that, though she be married to a man and
				constantly enjoys his embraces, yet she hath a fond kind
				of longing after him, so hath she always a strong inclination to the God, though she be present and round about
				him, and though she be impregnated with his most prime
				and pure particles.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="59">
            <p>But where Typhon falls in and touches upon her
				extreme parts, it is there she appears melancholy, and is
				said to mourn, and to look for certain relics and pieces of
				Osiris, and to array them with all diligence; she receiving
				all things that die and laying them up within herself, as
				she again brings forth and sends up out of herself all such
				things as are produced. And those proportions, forms,
				and effluxes of the God that are in the heaven and stars
				do indeed continue always the same; but those that are
				sown abroad into mutable things, as into land, sea, plants,
				and animals, are resolved, destroyed, and buried, and afterwards show themselves again very often, and come up anew
				in several different productions. For which reason the
				fable makes Typhon to be married to Nephthys, and Osiris
				to have accompanied with her by stealth. For the utmost
				and most extreme parts of matter, which they call Nephthys and the end, is mostly under the power of the destructive faculty; but the fecund and salutary power dispenses
				but a feeble and languid seed into those parts, which is all
				destroyed by Typhon, except only what Isis taking up doth
				preserve, cherish, and improve.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="60">
            <p>And in general, Typhon is the prevailing power, as
				both Plato and Aristotle insinuate. Moreover, the generative
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.119"/>
				
				 and salutary part of nature hath its motion towards
				him, in order to procure being; but the destroying and
				corruptive part hath its motion from him, in order to procure not-being. For which reason they call the former
				part Isis, from going (<foreign lang="greek">i)/esqai</foreign>) and being borne-along with
				knowledge, she being a kind of a living and prudent motion. For her name is not of a barbarous original; but,
				as all the Gods have one name (<foreign lang="greek">qeo/s</foreign>) in common, and that
				is derived from the two words, <foreign lang="greek">qe/wn</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">running</hi>) and <foreign lang="greek">qeato/s</foreign>
				(<hi rend="italics">visible</hi>); so also this very Goddess is both from motion
				and science at once called Isis by us and Isis also by the
				Egyptians. So likewise Plato tells us, that the ancients
				called <foreign lang="greek">ou)si/a</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">being</hi>) <foreign lang="greek">i)si/a</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">knowledge</hi>), as also that <foreign lang="greek">no/hsis</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">intelligence</hi>) and <foreign lang="greek">fro/nhsis</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">prudence</hi>) had their names given them
				for being a <foreign lang="greek">fora/</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">agitation</hi>) and motion of <foreign lang="greek">nou=s</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">mind</hi>), which
				was then, as it were, <foreign lang="greek">i(e/menos</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">fero/menos</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">set in motion</hi> and
				<hi rend="italics">borne-along</hi>); and the like he affirmeth of <foreign lang="greek">sunie/nai</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">to understand</hi>), that it was as much as to say <q direct="unspecified">to be in commotion.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Most of the absurd etymologies proposed in this chapter are actually to be found in Plato's Cratylus, from p. 401 C to p. 415 E. (G.)</note>
				Nay he saith, moreover, that they attribute the very names
				of <foreign lang="greek">a)gaqo/n</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">good</hi>) and <foreign lang="greek">a)reth/</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">virtue</hi>) to the ideas of <hi rend="italics">running</hi>
				(<foreign lang="greek">qe/w</foreign>) and of <hi rend="italics">ever-flowing</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">a)ei\ r(e/w</foreign>)<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The usual emendation for <foreign lang="greek">eu(rou=si</foreign> (which the MSS. give) is <foreign lang="greek">eu)roou=si</foreign>. But Plato (Crat. 415 D) derives <foreign lang="greek">a)reth/</foreign> from <foreign lang="greek">to\ a)sxe/tws kai\ to\ a)kwlu/tws a)ei\ r(e/on</foreign>, from which he supposes a form <foreign lang="greek">a)eire/th</foreign> to come, afterwards contracted into <foreign lang="greek">a)reth/</foreign>. I have therefore adopted the reading <foreign lang="greek">a)ei\ r(e/ousi</foreign>, and translated accordingly. (G.)</note> which they imply; as likewise, on the other hand again, they used terms opposite to
				motion by way of reproach; for they called what clogged,
				tied up, locked up, and confined nature from agitation and
				motion <foreign lang="greek">kaki/a</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">baseness</hi> or <hi rend="italics">ill motion</hi>), <foreign lang="greek">a)pori/a</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">difficulty</hi> or <hi rend="italics">difficult motion</hi>), <foreign lang="greek">deili/a</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">fearfulness</hi> or <hi rend="italics">fearful motion</hi>) and <foreign lang="greek">a)ni/a</foreign>
				(<hi rend="italics">sorrow</hi> or <hi rend="italics">want of motion</hi>).</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="61">
            <p>But Osiris had his name from <foreign lang="greek">o(/sios</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">i(ero/s</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">pious</hi>
				and <hi rend="italics">sacred</hi>) compounded; for he is the common idea of
				things in heaven and things in the lower world, the former
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.120"/>
				
				of which the ancients thought fit to style <foreign lang="greek">i(era/</foreign>, and the latter
				<foreign lang="greek">o(/sia</foreign>. But the principle which discloses things heavenly,
				and which appertains to things whose motion tends upwards (<foreign lang="greek">a)/nw</foreign>), is called Anubis, and sometimes he is also named
				Hermanubis, the former name referring to things above,
				and the latter to things beneath. For which reason they
				also sacrifice to him two cocks, the one whereof is white
				and the other of a saffron color, as esteeming the things
				above to be entire and clear, and the things beneath to be
				mixed and various. Nor need any one to wonder at the
				formation of these words from the Grecian tongue; for
				there are many thousand more of this kind, which, accompanying those who at several times removed out of Greece,
				do to this very day sojourn and remain among foreigners;
				some whereof when poetry would bring back into use, it
				hath been falsely accused of barbarism by those men, who
				love to call such words strange and outlandish. They say,
				moreover, that in the so-called books of Hermes there is
				an account given of the sacred names; and that power
				which presides over the circulation of the sun is called
				Horus, and by the Greeks Apollo; and that which is over
				the winds is by some called Osiris, and by others Serapis,
				and by others again in the Egyptian tongue Sothi. Now
				the word Sothi signifies in Greek <hi rend="italics">to breed</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">ku/ein</foreign>) and <hi rend="italics">breeding;</hi> and therefore, by an obliquation of the word <foreign lang="greek">ku/ein</foreign>, the
				star which they account proper to the Goddess Isis is called
				in Greek <foreign lang="greek">ku/wn</foreign>, which is as well <hi rend="italics">dog</hi> as <hi rend="italics">breeder.</hi> And although it be but a fond thing to be over contentious about
				words, yet I had rather yield to the Egyptians the name of
				Serapis than that of Osiris, since I account the former to
				be foreign, and the latter to be Greekish, but believe both
				to appertain to one God and to one power.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="62">
            <p>And the Egyptian theology seems to favor this opinion. For they oftentimes call Isis by the name of Minerva, which in their language expresseth this sentence, <q direct="unspecified">I
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.121"/>
				
				came from myself,</q> and is significative of a motion proceeding from herself. But Typhon is called (as hath been said
				before) Seth, Bebon, and Smu, which names would insinuate a kind of a forcible restraint, and an opposition or
				subversion. Moreover, they call the loadstone Horus's
				bone, and iron Typhon's bone, as Manetho relates. For as
				iron is oftentimes like a thing that is drawn to and follows
				the loadstone, and oftentimes again flies off and recoils to
				the opposite part; so the salutary, good, and intelligent
				motion of the universe doth, as by a gentle persuasion, invert, reduce, and make softer the rugged and Typhonian
				one; and when again it is restrained and forced back, it
				returns into itself, and sinks into its former interminateness. Eudoxus also saith that the Egyptian fable of Jupiter is this, that being once unable to go because his legs
				grew together, he for very shame spent all his time in the
				wilderness; but that Isis dividing and separating these
				parts of his body, he came to have the right use of his
				feet. This fable also hints to us by these words, that the
				intelligence and reason of the God, which walked before in
				the unseen and inconspicuous state, came into generation
				by means of motion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="63">
            <p>The sistrum likewise (or <hi rend="italics">rattle</hi>) doth intimate unto
				us, that all things ought to be agitated and shook (<foreign lang="greek">sei/esqai</foreign>),
				and not to be suffered to rest from their motion, but be as it
				were roused up and awakened when they begin to grow
				drowsy and to droop. For they tell us that the sistrum
				averts and frights away Typhon, insinuating hereby that,
				as corruption locks up and fixes Nature's course, so generation again resolves and excites it by means of motion.
				Moreover, as the sistrum hath its upper part convex, so its
				circumference contains the four things that are shaken;
				for that part of the world also which is liable to generation and corruption is contained by the sphere of the moon,
				but all things are moved and changed in it by means of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.122"/>
				
				the four elements, fire, earth, water, and air. And upon
				the upper part of the circumference of the sistrum, on the
				outside, they set the effigies of a cat carved with a human
				face; and again, on the under part, below the four jingling
				things, they set on one side the face of Isis, and on the
				other the face of Nephthys; symbolically representing
				by these two faces generation and death (for these are
				changes and alterations of the elements), and by the cat
				representing the moon, because of the different colors, the
				night-motion and the great fecundity of this animal. For
				they say that she brings forth first one, then two, and
				three, and four, and five, and so adds one until she comes
				to seven; so that she brings eight and twenty in all, which
				are as many as there are days in each moon; but this
				looks more like a romance. This is certain, that the pupils of her eyes are observed to fill up and grow large upon
				the full of the moon, and again, to grow less upon its de
				crease. And the human face of the cat shows how the
				changes of the moon are governed by mind and reason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="64">
            <p>To sum up all then in one word, it is not reasonable
				to believe that either the water or the sun or the earth or
				the heaven is Osiris or Isis; nor, again, that the fire or the
				drought or the sea is Typhon; but if we simply ascribe to
				Typhon whatever in all these is through excesses or defects
				intemperate or disorderly, and if on the other hand we reverence and honor what in them all is orderly, good, and
				beneficial, esteeming them the operations of Isis, and as
				the image, imitation, and discourse of Osiris, we shall not
				err. And we shall besides take off the incredulity of
				Eudoxus, who makes a great question how it comes to
				pass that neither Ceres hath any part in the care of love
				affairs (but only Isis), nor Bacchus any power either to
				increase the Nile or to preside over the dead. For we
				hold that these Gods are set over the whole share of good
				in common, and that whatever is either good or amiable
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.123"/>
				
				in Nature is all owing to these, the one yielding the principles, and the other receiving and dispensing them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="65">
            <p>By this means we shall be able to deal with the
				vulgar and more importunate sort also, whether their fancy
				be to accommodate the things that refer to these Gods to
				those changes which happen to the ambient air at the several seasons of the year, or to production of fruit and to
				the times of sowing and earing, affirming that Osiris is
				then buried when the sown corn is covered over by the
				earth, and that he revives again and re-appears when it begins to sprout. Which they say is the reason that Isis is
				reported, upon her finding herself to be with child, to have
				hung a certain amulet or charm about her upon the sixth
				day of the month Phaophi, and to have been delivered of
				Harpocrates about the winter solstice, he being in the
				first shootings and sprouts very imperfect and tender. And
				this is the reason (say they) that, when the lentils begin to
				spring up, they offer him their tops for first-fruits. They
				also observe the festival of her child-birth after the vernal
				equinox. For they that hear these things are much taken
				with them and readily give assent to them, and presently
				infer their credibility from the obviousness and familiarness
				of the matter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="66">
            <p>Nor would this be any great harm either, would
				they save us these Gods in common, and not make them
				to be peculiar to the Egyptians, nor confine these names to
				the river Nile, and only to that one piece of ground which
				the river Nile waters; nor affirm their fens and their lotuses to be the subject of this mythology, and so deprive
				the rest of mankind of great and mighty Gods, who have
				neither a Nile nor a Buto nor a Memphis. As for Isis, all
				mankind have her, and are well acquainted with her and
				the other Gods about her; and although they had not anciently learned to call some of them by their Egyptian
				names, yet they from the very first both knew and honored
				the power which belongs to every one of them. In the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.124"/>
				
				second place, what is yet of greater consequence is, that
				they take a mighty care and fear lest, before they are
				aware, they change and dissolve the divine beings into blasts
				of winds, streams of water, sowings of corn, earings of
				land, accidents of the earth, and changes of seasons; as
				those who make Bacchus to be wine and Vulcan to be
				flame. Cleanthes also somewhere saith that Proserpine (or
				Persephone) is the breath of air which is carried (<foreign lang="greek">fero/menon</foreign>)
				through the corn and then dies (<foreign lang="greek">foneu/omenon</foreign>); and again, a
				certain poet saith of reapers,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">Then when the youth the legs of Ceres cut.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For these men seem to me to be nothing wiser than such
					as would take the sails, the cables, and the anchor of a
					ship for the pilot; the yarn and the web for the weaver;
					and the bowl or the mead or the ptisan for the doctor.
					And they over and above produce in men most dangerous
					and atheistical opinions, while they give the names of Gods
					to those natures and things that have in them neither soul
					nor sense, and that are necessarily destroyed by men who
					need them and use them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="67">
            <p>No man can imagine these things can be Gods in
				themselves. And therefore nothing can be a God to men
				that is either without soul or under their power. But yet
				by means of these things we come to think them Gods that
				use them themselves and bestow them upon us, and that
				render them perpetual and continual. And those are not
				some in one country and others in another, nor some Grecians and others barbarians, nor some southern and others
				northern; but as the sun, moon, land, and sea are common
				to all men, but yet have different names in different nations,
				so that one discourse that orders these things, and that one
				forecast that administers them, and those subordinate
				powers that are set over every nation in particular, have
				assigned them by the laws of several countries several
				kinds of honors and appellations. And those that have
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.125"/>
				
				been consecrated to their service make use, some of them
				of darker, and others again of clearer symbols, thereby
				guiding the understanding to the knowledge of things divine, not without much danger and hazard. For some not
				being able to reach their true meaning, have slid into downright superstition; and others again, while they would fly
				the quagmire of superstition, have fallen unwittingly upon
				the precipice of atheism.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="68">
            <p>And for this reason we should here make most use
				of the reasonings from philosophy, which introduce us
				into the knowledge of things sacred, that so we may think
				piously of whatever is said or acted in religion; lest&mdash;as
				Theodorus once said that, as he reached forth his discourses
				in his right hand, some of his auditors received them in
				their left&mdash;so what things the laws have wisely constituted
				about the sacrifices and festivals we should take otherwise
				than as they are meant, and thereby fall into most dangerous errors and mistakes. That therefore we are to construe all these things by reference to reason, we may easily
				perceive by the Egyptians themselves. For upon the nineteenth day of the first month they keep a solemn festival
				to Hermes, wherein they eat honey and figs, and withal
				say these words, <q direct="unspecified">Truth is a sweet thing.</q> And that amulet or charm which they fable Isis to hang about her is,
				when interpreted into our language, <q direct="unspecified">A true voice.</q> Nor
				are we to understand Harpocrates to be either some imperfect or infant God, or a God of pulse (as some will have
				him), but to be the governor and reducer of the tender,
				imperfect, and inarticulate discourse which men have about
				the Gods. For which reason, he hath always his finger
				upon his mouth, as a symbol of talking little and keeping
				silence. Likewise, upon the month of Mesore, they present him with certain pulse, and pronounce these words:
				<q direct="unspecified">The tongue is Fortune, the tongue is God.</q> And of all
				the plants that Egypt produces, they say the Persea is the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.126"/>
				
				most sacred to the Goddess, because its fruit resembles
				the heart, and its leaf the tongue. For there is nothing
				that man possesses that is either more divine, or that hath
				a greater tendency upon happiness, than discourse, and
				especially that which relates to the Gods. For which reason they lay a strict charge upon such as go down to the
				oracle there, to have pious thoughts in their hearts and
				words of good omen in their mouths. But the greater
				part act ludicrous things in their processions and festivals,
				first proclaiming good expressions, and then both speaking and thinking words of most wicked and lewd meaning, and that even of the Gods themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="69">
            <p>How then must we manage ourselves at these tetrical, morose, and mournful sacrifices, if we are neither to
				omit what the laws prescribe us, nor yet to confound and
				distract our thoughts about the Gods with vain and uncouth surmises? There are among the Greeks also many
				things done that are like to those which the Egyptians do
				at their solemnities, and much about the same time too.
				For at the Thesmophoria at Athens the women fast sitting
				upon the bare ground. The Boeotians also remove the
				shrines of Achaea (or Ceres), terming that day the afflictive holiday, because Ceres was then in great affliction for
				her daughter's descent into hell. Now upon this month,
				about the rising of the Pleiades, is the sowing time; and
				the Egyptians call it Athyr, the Athenians Pyanepsion;
				and the Boeotians Damatrios (or the <hi rend="italics">month of Ceres</hi>).
				Moreover Theopompus relates, that those that live towards the sun-setting (or the Hesperii) believe the winter to
				be Saturn, the summer Venus, and the spring time Proserpine; and that they call them by those names, and maintain all to be produced by Saturn and Venus. But the
				Phrygians, being of opinion that the Deity sleeps in the
				winter and wakes in the summer, do, in the manner of
				ecstatics, in the winter time sing lullabies in honor of his
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.127"/>
				
				sleeping, and in the summer time certain rousing carols
				in honor of his waking. In like manner the Paphlagonians say, he is bound and imprisoned in the winter, and
				walks abroad again in the spring and is at liberty.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="70">
            <p>And the nature of the season gives us suspicion
				that this tetrical sort of service was occasioned by the
				absenting of the several sorts of fruits at that time of the
				year; which yet the ancients did not believe to be Gods,
				but such gifts of the Gods as were both great and necessary in order to preserve them from a savage and bestial
				life. And at what time they saw both the fruits that came
				from trees wholly to disappear and fail, and those also
				which themselves had sown to be yet but starved and poor,
				they taking up fresh mould in their hands and laying it
				about their roots, and committing them a second time to
				the ground with uncertain hopes of their ever coming to
				perfection or arriving to maturity, did herein many things
				that might well resemble people at funerals and mourning
				for the dead. Moreover, as we use to say of one that hath
				bought the books of Plato, that he hath bought Plato, and
				of one that hath taken upon him to act the compositions
				of Menander, that he hath acted Menander; in like manner they did not stick to call the gifts and creatures of the
				Gods by the names of the Gods themselves, paying this
				honor and veneration to them for their necessary use.
				But those of after times receiving this practice unskilfully
				and ignorantly, applying the accidents of fruits, and the
				accesses and recesses of things necessary to human life,
				unto the Gods, did not only call them the generations and
				deaths of the Gods, but also believed them such, and so
				filled themselves with abundance of absurd, wicked, and
				distempered notions; and this, although they had the absurdity of such a monstrous opinion before their very eyes.
				And therefore Xenophanes the Colophonian might not
				only put the Egyptians in mind, if they believed those
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.128"/>
				
				they worshipped to be Gods, not to lament for them, and
				if they lamented for them, not to believe them to be Gods;
				but also that it would be extremely ridiculous at one and
				the same time to lament for the fruits of the earth, and to
				pray them to appear again and make themselves ripe,
				that so they may be over again consumed and lamented
				for.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="71">
            <p>But now this in its true intention is no such thing.
				But they make their lamentation for the fruits; and their
				prayers to the Gods, who are the authors and bestowers
				of those fruits, that they would be pleased to produce and
				bring up again other new ones in the place of them that
				are gone. Wherefore it is an excellent saying among
				philosophers, that they that have not learned the true
				sense of words will mistake also in the things; as we see
				those among the Greeks who have not learned nor accustomed themselves to call the brazen and stone statues and
				the painted representations of the Gods their images or
				their honors, but the Gods themselves, are so adventurous
				as to say that Lachares stripped Minerva, that Dionysius
				cropped off Apollo's golden locks, and that Jupiter Capitolinus was burned and destroyed in the civil wars of
				Rome. They therefore, before they are aware, suck in
				and receive bad opinions with these improper words. And
				the Egyptians are not the least guilty herein, with respect
				to the animals which they worship. For the Grecians
				both speak and think aright in these matters, when they
				tell us that the pigeon is sacred to Venus, the serpent to
				Minerva, the raven to Apollo, and the dog to Diana, as
				Euripides somewhere speaks:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Into a bitch transformed you shall be,
				</l>
                     <l>And be the image of bright Hecate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the greater part of the Egyptians worshipping the
					very animals themselves, and courting them as Gods, have
					not only filled their religious worship with matter of scorn
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.129"/>
					
					and derision (for that would be the least harm that could
					come of their blockish ignorance); but a dire conception
					also arises therefrom, which blows up the feeble and simple
					minded into an extravagance of superstition, and when it
					lights upon the more subtle and daring tempers, outrages
					them into atheistical and brutish cogitations. Wherefore
					it seems not inconsonant here to recount what is probable
					upon this subject.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="72">
            <p>For that the Gods, being afraid of Typhon, changed
				themselves into these animals, and did as it were hide
				themselves in the bodies of ibises, dogs, and hawks, is a
				foolery beyond all prodigiousness and legend. And that
				such souls of men departed this life as remain undissolved
				after death have leave to be reborn into this life by these
				bodies only, is equally incredible. And of those who
				would assign some political reason for these things, there
				are some that affirm that Osiris in his great army, dividing
				his forces into many parts (which we in Greek call <foreign lang="greek">lo/xoi</foreign>
				and <foreign lang="greek">ta/ceis</foreign>), at the same time gave every of them certain
				ensigns or colors with the shapes of several animals upon
				them, which in process of time came to be looked upon as
				sacred, and to be worshipped by the several kindred and
				clans in that distribution. Others say again, that the kings
				of after times did, for the greater terror of their enemies,
				wear about them in their battles the golden and silver
				heads and upper parts of fierce animals. But there are
				others that relate that one of these subtle and crafty
				princes, observing the Egyptians to be of a light and vain
				disposition and very inclinable to change and innovation,
				and withal, when sober and unanimous, of an inexpugnable and irrestrainable strength by reason of their mighty
				numbers, therefore taught them, in their several quarters,
				a perpetual kind of superstition, to be the ground of endless quarrels and disputes among them. For the various
				animals which he commanded different cities to observe
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.130"/>
				
				and reverence being at enmity and war with one another,
				and desiring one another for food, each party among them
				being upon the perpetual defence of their proper animals,
				and highly resenting the wrongs that were offered them,
				it happened that, being thus drawn into the quarrels of
				their beasts, they were, before they were aware, engaged
				in hostilities with one another. For at this very day, the
				Lycopolitans (or Wolf-town-men) are the only people among
				the Egyptians that eat the sheep, because the wolf, which
				they esteem to be a God, doth so too. And in our own
				times, the Oxyrynchites (or those of Pike-town), because
				the Cynopolitans (or those of Dog-town) did eat a pike,
				catched the dogs and slew them, and ate of them as they
				would do of a sacrifice; and there arising a civil war upon
				it, in which they did much mischief to one another, they
				were all at last chastised by the Romans.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="73">
            <p>And whereas there are many that say that the soul
				of Typhon himself took its flight into these animals, this
				tale may be looked upon to signify that every irrational and
				brutal nature appertains to the share of the evil Daemon.
				And therefore, when they would pacify him and speak him
				fair, they make their court and addresses to these animals.
				But if there chance to happen a great and excessive
				drought which, above what is ordinary at other times,
				brings along with it either wasting diseases or other
				monstrous and prodigious calamities, the priests then conduct into a dark place, with great silence and stillness,
				some of the animals which are honored by them; and they
				first of all menace and terrify them, and if the mischief
				still continues, they then consecrate and offer them up,
				looking upon this as a way of punishing the evil God, or
				at least as some grand purgation in time of greatest disasters. For, as Manetho relateth, they were used in ancient
				times to burn live men in the city of Ilithyia, entitling them
				Typhonian; and then they made wind, and dispersed and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.131"/>
				
				scattered their ashes into the air. And this was done
				publicly, and at one only season of the year, which was
				the dog-days. But those consecrations of the animals
				worshipped by them which are made in secret, and at
				irregular and uncertain times of the year as occasions require, are wholly unknown to the vulgar sort, except only
				at the time of their burials, at which they produce certain
				other animals, and in the presence of all spectators throw
				them into the grave with them, thinking by this means to
				vex Typhon and to abate the satisfaction he received by
				their deaths. For it is the Apis, with a few more, that is
				thought sacred to Osiris; but the far greater part are assigned to Typhon. And if this account of theirs be true,
				I believe it explains the subject of our enquiry as to such
				animals as are universally received and have their honors
				in common amongst them all; and of this kind is the ibis,
				the hawk, the cynocephalos, and the Apis himself;...
				for so they call the goat which is kept at Mendes.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="74">
            <p>It remains yet behind, that I treat of their beneficialness to man, and of their symbolical use; and some
				of them participate of some one of these, and others of
				both. It is most manifest therefore that they worship the
				ox, the sheep, and the ichneumon for their benefit and
				use; as the Lemniotes did the lark, for finding out the
				locusts' eggs and breaking them, and the Thessalians the
				storks, because that, as their soil bred abundance of serpents, they at their appearance destroyed them all, for
				which reason they enacted a law that whoever killed a
				stork should be banished the country. Moreover the
				Egyptians honored the asp, the weasel, and the beetle,
				observing in them certain dark resemblances of the power
				of the Gods, like those of the sun in drops of water. For
				there are many that to this day believe that the weasel
				engenders by the ear, and brings forth by the mouth, and
				is therein a resemblance of the production of speech; and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.132"/>
				
				that the beetle kind also hath no female, but that the males
				cast out their sperm into a round pellet of earth, which
				they roll about by thrusting it backwards with their hinder
				feet,&mdash;and this in imitation of the sun, which, while itself
				moves from west to east, turns the heaven the contrary
				way. They also compared the asp to a star, for being
				always young, and for performing its motions with great
				ease and glibness, and that without the help of organs.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="75">
            <p>Nor had the crocodile his honor given him without
				a show of probable reason for it; but it is reported to
				have been produced by a representation of God, it being
				the only animal that is without tongue. For the divine
				discourse hath no need of voice, but <q direct="unspecified">marching by still
					and silent ways, it guides mortal affairs by equal justice.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Troad. 887.</note>
				Besides, they say he is the only animal that lives in water
				that hath his eye-sight covered over with a thin and transparent film, descending down from his forehead, so that he
				sees without being seen himself by others, in which he
				agrees with the first God. Moreover, in what place soever
				in the country the female crocodile lays her eggs, that may
				be certainly concluded to be the utmost extent of the rise
				of the river Nile for that year. For not being able to lay
				in the water, and being afraid to lay far from it, they have
				so exact a knowledge of futurity, that though they enjoy
				the benefit of the approaching stream at their laying and
				hatching, they yet preserve their eggs dry and untouched
				by the water. And they lay sixty in all, and are just as
				many days a hatching them, and the longest lived of them
				live as many years; that being the first measure which
				those that are employed about the heavens make use of.
				But of those animals that were honored for both reasons,
				we have already treated of the dog; but now the ibis,
				besides that he killeth all deadly and poisonous vermin,
				was also the first that taught men the evacuation of the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.133"/>
				
				belly by clysters, she being observed to be after this manner washed and purged by herself. Those also of the
				priests that are the strictest observers of their sacred rites,
				when they consecrate water for lustration, use to fetch it
				from some place where the ibis has been drinking; for she
				will neither taste nor come near any unwholesome or infectious water. Besides, with her two legs standing at
				large and her bill, she maketh an equilateral triangle; and
				the speckledness and mixture of her feathers, where there
				are black ones about the white, signify the gibbousness of
				the moon on either side.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="76">
            <p>Nor ought we to think it strange that the Egyptians
				should affect such poor and slender comparisons, when we
				find the Grecians themselves, both in their pictures and
				statues, make use of many such resemblances of the Gods
				as these are. For example, there was in Crete an image
				of Jupiter having no ears, for he that is commander and
				chief over all should hear no one. Phidias also set a serpent by the image of Minerva, and a tortoise by that of
				Venus at Elis, to show that maids needed a guard upon
				them, and that silence and keeping at home became married women. In like manner the trident of Neptune is a
				symbol of the third region of the world, which the sea
				possesses, situated below that of the heaven and air. For
				which reason they also gave their names to Amphitrite and
				the Tritons. The Pythagoreans also honored numbers and
				geometric figures with the names of Gods. For they called
				an equilateral triangle Minerva Coryphagenes (or <hi rend="italics">crown-born</hi>) and Tritogeneia, because it is equally divided by perpendiculars drawn from the three angles. They likewise
				called the unit Apollo; the number two, contention and also
				audaciousness; and the number three, justice; for, wronging
				and being wronged being two extremes caused by deficiency and excess, justice came by equality in the middle.
				But that which is called the sacred quaternion, being the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.134"/>
				
				number thirty-six, was (according to common fame) the
				greatest oath among them, and was called by them the world,
				because it is made up of the first four even numbers and
				the first four odd numbers summed up together.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="77">
            <p>If therefore the most approved of the philosophers
				did not think meet to pass over or disesteem any significant symbol of the Divinity which they observed even in
				things that had neither soul nor body, I believe they regarded yet more those properties of government and conduct which they saw in such natures as had sense, and
				were endued with soul, with passion, and with moral temper. We are not therefore to content ourselves with worshipping these things, but we must worship God through
				them,&mdash;as being the more clear mirrors of him, and produced by Nature,&mdash;so as ever worthily to conceive of them
				as the instruments or artifices of that God which orders
				all things. And it is reasonable to believe that no inanimate being can be more excellent than an animate one, nor
				an insensible than a sensible; no, though one should heap
				together all the gold and emeralds in the universe. For
				the property of the Divinity consists not in fine colors,
				shapes, and slicknesses; but, on the contrary, those natures
				are of a rank below the very dead, that neither did nor
				ever can partake of life. But now that Nature which hath
				life and sees, and which hath the source of her motion
				from her own self, as also the knowledge of things proper
				and alien to her, hath certainly derived an efflux and a
				portion of that prudence which (as Heraclitus speaks)
				considers how the whole universe is governed. Therefore
				the Deity is no worse represented in these animals, than in
				the workmanships of copper and stone, which suffer corruptions and decays as well as they, and are besides naturally void of sense and perception. This then is what I
				esteem the best account that is given of their adoration of
				animals.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.135"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="78">
            <p>As to the sacred vestments, that of Isis is party-colored and of different hues; for her power is about matter, which becomes every thing and receives every thing,
				as light and darkness, day and night, fire and water, life
				and death, beginning and ending. But that of Osiris has
				no shade, no variety of colors, but one only simple one,
				resembling light. For the first principle is untempered,
				and that which is first and of an intelligible nature is
				unmixed; which is the reason why, after they have once
				made use of this garment, they lay it up and keep it close,
				invisible and not to be touched. But those of Isis are
				used often. For sensible things, when they are of daily
				use and familiar to us, afford us many opportunities to display them and to see them in their various mutations; but
				the apprehension of what is intelligible, sincere, and holy,
				darting through the soul like a flash of lightning, attends
				but to some one single glance or glimpse of its object.
				For which reason both Plato and Aristotle call this part
				of philosophy by the name of the epoptic or mysterious
				part, intimating that those who by help of reason have got
				beyond these fanciful, mixed, and various things mount up
				to that first, simple, and immaterial being; and when they
				have certainly reached the pure truth about it, they believe
				they have at last attained to complete philosophy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="79">
            <p>And that which the present priests do darkly hint
				out and insinuate to us, though with much obscurity, great
				shyness, and precaution,&mdash;that this God is the governor
				and prince of those that are dead, and that he is no other
				than he who is called by the Greeks Hades and Pluto,&mdash;
				being not taken in its true sense, disturbs the minds of the
				greater part, while they suspect that the truly holy and
				good God Osiris lives within and beneath the earth, where
				the bodies of those who are supposed to have an end lie
				hid and buried. But he himself is at the remotest distance
				from the earth imaginable, being unstained and unpolluted,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.136"/>
				
				and clean from every substance that is liable to corruption
				and death. But men's souls encompassed here with bodies and passions, have no communication with God, except what they can reach to in conception only, by means
				of philosophy, as by a kind of an obscure dream. But
				when they are loosed from the body, and removed into the
				unseen, invisible, impassible, and pure region, this God is
				then their leader and king; they there as it were hanging
				on him wholly, and beholding without weariness and passionately affecting that beauty which cannot be expressed
				or uttered by men. This the Goddess Isis is always caressing, affecting, and enjoying, according to the old tales,
				and by that means she fills this lower world with all those
				goodly and excellent things which partake of generation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="80">
            <p>This then is that account of these things which
				best suits the nature of the Gods. And if I now must,
				according to my promise, say something concerning those
				things they daily offer by way of incense, you are in the
				first place to understand this, that these people make the
				greatest account imaginable of all endeavors that relate to
				health; and more especially in their sacrifices, purgations,
				and diets, health is no less respected than devotion. For
				they think it would be an unseemly thing to wait upon
				that nature that is pure and every way unblemished and
				untouched, with crazy and diseased minds or bodies.
				Whereas, therefore, the air that we most use and live in
				hath not always the same disposition and temperament,
				but in the night-time grows condense, compresses the body,
				and contracts the mind into a kind of melancholy and
				thoughtful habit, it becoming then as it were foggy and
				dozed, they therefore, as soon as they are up in the morning, burn rosin about them, refreshing and clearing the air
				by its scattered particles, and fanning up the native spirit
				of the body, which is now grown languid and dull; this
				sort of scent having something in it that is very impetuous
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.137"/>
				
				and striking. And perceiving again at noon-time that the
				sun hath drawn up by violence a copious and gross exhalation out of the earth, they by censing mix myrrh also
				with the air; for heat dissolves and dissipates that puddled
				and slimy vapor which at that time gathers together in
				the ambient air. And physicians are also found to help
				pestilential diseases by making great blazes to rarefy the
				air; but it would be much better rarefied, if they would
				burn sweet-scented woods, such as cypress, juniper, and
				pine. And therefore Acron the physician is said to have
				gained a mighty reputation at Athens, in the time of the
				great plague, by ordering people to make fires near to the
				sick; for not a few were benefited by it. Aristotle likewise saith that the odoriferous exhalations of perfumes,
				flowers, and sweet meadows are no less conducing to health
				than to pleasure; for that their warmth and delicacy of
				motion gently relax the brain, which is of its own nature
				cold and clammy. And if it be true that the Egyptians in
				their language call myrrh bal, and that the most proper
				signification of that word is <hi rend="italics">scattering away idle talk,</hi> this
				also adds some testimony to our account of the reason why
				they burn it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="81">
            <p>Moreover, that they call Kyphi is a kind of a composition made up of sixteen ingredients, that is, of honey,
				wine, raisins, cyperus, rosin, myrrh, aspalathus, seseli, mastich, bitumen, nightshade, and dock; to which they add
				the berries of both the junipers (the one whereof they
				call the greater, and the other the lesser sort), as also calamus and cardamom. Neither do they put them together
				slightly or at a random rate; but the sacred books are
				read to the perfumers all the while they are compounding
				them. As for the number of the ingredients (sixteen),
				&mdash;although it may appear important, being the square of
				a square, and making the only square surface which has a
				periphery equal to its area,&mdash;yet I must needs say that
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.138"/>
				
				this contributes but very little here. But it is the contained species (most of which are of aromatic properties)
				that send up a sweet fume and an agreeable exhalation, by
				which the air is changed; and the body, being moved by
				the breath, sinks into a calm and gentle sleep, and retains
				a temperament conducive to sleep; and without the disorders of drunkenness, as it were, it loosens and unties,
				like a sort of knots, the doziness and intenseness of the
				thoughts by day-time; and the fantastic part and that
				which is receptive of dreams it wipes like a mirror and
				renders clearer, with no less efficacy than those strokes of
				the harp which the Pythagoreans made use of before they
				went to sleep, to charm and allay the distempered and
				irrational part of the soul. For we find that strong scents
				many times call back the failing sense, but sometimes dull
				and obstruct it, their wasted parts diffusing themselves by
				their great fineness and subtilty through the whole body;
				like as some physicians tell us that sleep is produced when
				the fumes of meat, by creeping gently about the inwards,
				and as it were groping every part, cause a certain soft
				titillation.</p>
            <p>They also use this Kyphi both for a drink and for a
					medicinal potion; for when drunk it is found to cleanse
					the inwards, it being a loosener of the belly. Besides all
					this, rosin is the creature of the sun, and they gather
					myrrh as the trees weep it out by moonlight; but now of
					those ingredients that make up Kyphi, there are some that
					delight more in the night, as those whose nature it is to be
					nourished by cool blasts, shades, dews, and humidities.
					For the light of day is one thing and simple; and Pindar
					saith, the sun is then seen
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Through solitary air.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Olymp. I. 10.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the air of night is a kind of composition; for it is
					made up of many lights and powers, which, like so many
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.139"/>
					
					several seeds, flow down from every star into one place.
					They therefore very pertinently cense the former things by
					daytime, as being simples and deriving their original from
					the sun; and the latter at the entrance of the night, they
					being mixed and of many and different qualities.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>