<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Quaestiones Naturales</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.125">
      <body>
         <head>Plutarch's Natural Questions.</head>
         <pb id="v.3.p.495"/>
         <p/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>I. 
					<lb/> WHAT IS THE REASON THAT SEA-WATER NOURISHES NOT TREES?</head>
            <p>Is it not for the same reason that it nourishes not earthly
					animals? For Plato, Anaxagoras, and Democritus think
					plants are earthly animals. Nor, though sea-water be aliment to marine plants, as it is to fishes, will it therefore
					nourish earthly plants, since it can neither penetrate the
					roots, because of its grossness, nor ascend, by reason of
					its weight; for this, among many other things, shows seawater to be heavy and terrene, because it more easily
					bears up ships and swimmers. Or is it because drought
					is a great enemy to trees? For sea-water is of a drying
					faculty; upon which account salt resists putrefaction, and
					the bodies of such as wash in the sea are presently dry
					and rough. Or is it because oil is destructive to earthly
					plants, and kills things anointed with it? But sea-water
					participates of much fatness; for it burns together with it.
					Wherefore, when men would quench fire, we forbid them
					to throw on sea-water. Or is it because sea-water is not
					fit to drink and bitter (as Aristotle says) through a mixture
					of burnt earth? For a lye is made by the falling of ashes
					into sweet water, and the dissolution ejects and corrupts
					what was good and potable, as in us men fevers convert
					the humors into bile. As for what woods and plants men
					talk of growing in the Red Sea, they bear no fruit, but
					are nourished by rivers casting up much mud; therefore
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.496"/>
					
					they grow not at any great distance from land, but very
					near to it.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>II.
					<lb/> WHY DO TREES AND SEEDS THRIVE BETTER WITH RAIN THAN WITH WATERING?</head>
            <p>WHETHER is it because (as Laitus thinks) showers, parting the earth by the violence of their fall, make passages,
					whereby the water may more easily penetrate to the root?
					Or cannot this be true; and did Laitus never consider that
					marsh-plants (as cat's-tail, pond-weeds, and rushes) neither
					thrive nor sprout when the rains fall not in their season;
					but it is true, as Aristotle said, rain-water is new and fresh,
					that of lakes old and stale? And what if this be rather
					probable than true? For the waters of fountains and
					rivers are ever fresh, new always arriving; therefore
					Heraclitus said well, that no man could go twice into the
					same river. And yet these very waters nourish worse than
					rain-water. But water from the heavens is light and aerial,
					and, being mixed with spirit, is the quicker passed and
					elevated into the plant, by reason of its tenuity. And for
					this very reason it makes bubbles when mixed with the
					air. Or does that nourish most which is soonest altered
					and overcome by the thing nourished?&mdash;for this very thing
					is concoction. On the contrary, inconcoction is when the
					aliment is too strong to be affected by the thing nourished.
					Now thin, simple, and insipid things are the most easily
					altered, of which number is rain-water, which is bred in
					the air and wind, and falls pure and sincere. But fountain-water, being assimilated to the earth and places through
					which it passes, is filled with many qualities which render
					it less nutritive and slower in alteration to the thing
					nourished. Moreover, that rain-water is easily alterable is
					an argument; because it sooner putrefies than either spring
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.497"/>
					
					or river-water. For concoction seems to be putrefaction,
					as Empedocles says,&mdash;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When in vine wood the water putrefies,
					</l>
                     <l>It turns to wine, while under bark it lies.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Or, which may most readily be assigned for a reason, is
					it because rain is sweet and mild, when it is presently sent
					by the wind? For this reason cattle drink it most greedily,
					and frogs in expectation of it raise their voice, as if they
					were calling for rain to sweeten the marsh and to be sauce
					to the water in the pools. For Aratus makes this a sign of
					approaching rain,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When father frogs, to watery snakes sweet food,
					</l>
                     <l>Do croak and sing in mud, a wretched brood.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>III.
					<lb/> WHY DO HERDSMEN SET SALT BEFORE CATTLE?</head>
            <p>WHETHER (as many think) to nourish them the more, and
					fatten them the better? For salt by its acrimony sharpens
					the appetite, and by opening the passages brings meat
					more easily to digestion. Therefore Apollonius, Herophilus's scholar, would not have lean persons, and such as
					did not thrive, be fed with sweet things and gruel, but
					ordered them to use pickles and salt things for their food,
					whose tenuity, serving instead of frication or sifting, might
					apply the aliment through the passages of the body. Or
					is it for health's sake that men give sheep salt to lick, to
					cut off the redundance of nutriment? For when they
					are over fat, they grow sick; but salt wastes and melts the
					fat. And this they observe so well, that they can more
					easily flay them; for the fat, which agglutinates and fastens
					the skin, is made thin and weak by the acrimony. The
					blood also of things that lick salt is attenuated; nor
					do things within the body stick together when salts are
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.498"/>
					
					mixed with them. Moreover, consider this, whether the
					cattle grow more fruitful and more inclined to coition; for
					bitches do sooner conceive when they are fed with salt
					victuals, and ships which carry salt are more pestered with
					mice, by reason of their frequent coition.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>IV.
					<lb/> WHY IS THE WATER OF SHOWERS WHICH FALLS IN THUNDER AND
					LIGHTNING FITTER TO WATER SEEDS? AND THEY ARE THEREFORE CALLED THUNDER-SHOWERS.</head>
            <p>Is it because they contain much spirit, by reason of their
					confusion and mixture with the air? And the spirit moving the humor sends it more upwards. Or is it because
					heat fighting against cold causes thunder and lightning?
					Whence it is that it thunders very little in winter, but in
					spring and autumn very much, because of the inequality
					of temper; and the heat, concocting the humor, renders it
					friendly and commodious for plants. Or does it thunder
					and lighten most in the spring for the aforesaid cause, and
					do the seeds have greater occasion for the vernal rains
					before summer? Therefore that country which is best
					watered with rain in spring, as Sicily is, produces abundance of good fruit.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>V.
					<lb/> HOW COMES IT TO PASS, THAT SINCE THERE BE EIGHT KINDS OF TASTES, WE FIND THE SALT IN NO FRUIT WHATEVER?</head>
            <p>INDEED, at first the olive is bitter, and the grape acid;
					one whereof afterward turns fat, and the other vinous.
					But the harshness in dates and the austere in pomegranates
					turn sweet. Some pomegranates and apples have only a
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.499"/>
					
					simple acid taste. The pungent taste is frequent in roots
					and seeds.</p>
            <p>Is it because a salt taste is never natural, but arises
					when the rest are corrupt? Therefore such plants and
					seeds as are nourished receive no nourishment from salt;
					it serves indeed some instead of sauce, by preventing a
					surfeit of other nourishment. Or, as men take away saltness and bitingness from the sea-water by distilling, is
					saltness so abolished in hot things by heat? Or indeed
					does the taste (as Plato says) arise from water percolated
					through a plant, and does even sea-water percolated lose
					its saltness, being terrene and of gross parts? Therefore
					people that dig near the sea happen upon wells fit to drink.
					Several also that draw the sea-water into waxen buckets
					receive it sweet and potable, the salt and earthy matter
					being strained out. And straining through clay renders
					sea-water potable, since the clay retains the earthy parts
					and does not let them pass through. And since things are
					so, it is very probable either that plants receive no saltness
					extrinsically, or, if they do, they put it not forth into fruit;
					for things terrene and consisting of gross parts cannot
					pass, by reason of the straitness of the passages. Or may
					saltness be reckoned a sort of bitterness? For so Homer
					says:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Out of his mouth the bitter brine did flow,
					</l>
                     <l>And down his body from his head did go.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. V. 322.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Plato also says that both these tastes have an abstersive
					and colliquative faculty; but the salt does it less, nor is it
					rough. And the bitter seems to differ from the salt in
					abundance of heat, since the salt has also a drying quality.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.500"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>VI.
					<lb/> WHAT IS THE REASON THAT, IF A MAN FREQUENTLY PASS ALONG
					DEWY TREES, THOSE LIMBS THAT TOUCH THE WOOD ARE SEIZED WITH A LEPROSY?</head>
            <p>WHETHER (as Laitus said) that by the tenuity of the dew
					the moisture of the skin is fretted away? Or, as smut and
					mildew fall upon moistened seeds, so, when the green and
					tender parts on the superficies are fretted and dissolved by
					the dew, is a certain noxious taint carried and imparted to
					the most bloodless parts of the body, as the legs and feet,
					which there eats and frets the superficies? For that by
					Nature there is a corrosive faculty in dew sufficiently appears, in that it makes fat people lean; and gross women
					gather it, either with wool or on their clothes, to take down
					their flesh.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>VII.
					<lb/> WHY IN WINTER DO SHIPS SAIL SLOWER IN RIVERS, BUT DO NOT SO IN THE SEA?</head>
            <p>WHETHER, because the river-air, which is at all times
					heavy and slow, being in winter more condensed by the
					cold, does more resist sailing? Or is it long of the water
					rather than the air? For the piercing cold makes the
					water heavy and thick, as one may perceive in a water-clock; for the water passes more slowly in winter than in
					summer. Theophrastus talks of a well about Pangaeum in
					Thrace, how that a vessel filled with the water of it weighs
					twice as much in winter as it does in summer. Besides,
					hence it is apparent that the grossness of the water makes
					ships sail slower, because in winter river-vessels carry
					greater burthens. For the water, being made more dense
					and heavy, makes the more renitency; but the heat hinders the sea from being condensed or frozen.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.501"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>VIII.
					<lb/> WHY, SINCE ALL OTHER LIQUORS UPON MOVING AND STIRRING
					ABOUT GROW COLD, DOES THE SEA BY BEING TOSSED IN WAVES GROW HOT?</head>
            <p>WHETHER that motion expels and dissipates the heat of
					other liquors as a thing adscititious, and the winds do rather
					excite and increase the innate heat of the sea? Its transparentness is an argument of heat; and so is its not being
					frozen, though it is terrene and heavy.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>IX.
					<lb/> WHY IN WINTER IS THE SEA LEAST SALT AND BITTER TO THE
					TASTE? FOR THEY SAY THAT DIONYSIUS THE HYDRAGOGUE REPORTED THIS.</head>
            <p>Is it that the bitterness of the sea is not devoid of all
					sweetness, as receiving so many rivers into it; but, since
					the sun exhales the sweet and potable water thereof,
					arising to the top by reason of its levity, and since this is
					done in summer more than in winter, when it affects the
					sea more weakly by reason of the debility of its heat, that
					so in winter a great deal of sweetness is left, which tempers and mitigates its excessive poisonous bitterness? And
					the same thing befalls potable waters; for in summer they
					are worse, the sun wasting the lightest and sweetest part
					of them. And a fresh sweetness returns in winter, of
					which the sea must needs participate, since it moves, and
					is carried with the rivers into the sea.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.502"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>X.
					<lb/> WHY DO MEN POUR SEA-WATER UPON WINE, AND SAY THE FISHERMEN HAD AN ORACLE GIVEN THEM, WHEREBY THEY WERE BID TO
					DIP BACCHUS INTO THE SEA? AND WHY DO THEY THAT LIVE FAR FROM THE SEA CAST IN SOME ZACYNTHIAN EARTH TOASTED?</head>
            <p>WHETHER that heat is good against cold? Or that it
					quenches heat, by diluting the wine and destroying its
					strength? Or that the aqueous and aerial part of wine
					(which is therefore prone to mutation) is stayed by the
					throwing in of terrene parts, whose nature it is to constipate and condense? Moreover, salts with the sea-water,
					attenuating and colliquating whatever is foreign and superfluous, suffer no fetidness or putrefaction to breed. Besides,
					the gross and terrene parts, being entangled with the heavy
					and sinking together, make a sediment or lees, and so
					make the wine fine.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>XI.
					<lb/> WHY ARE THEY SICKER THAT SAIL ON THE SEA THAN THEY THAT SAIL IN FRESH RIVERS, EVEN IN CALM WEATHER?</head>
            <p>OF all the senses, smelling causes nauseousness the
					most, and of all the passions of the mind, fear. For men
					tremble and shake and bewray themselves upon apprehension of great danger. They that sail in a river are
					troubled with neither of these. And the smell of sweet
					and potable water is familiar to all, and the voyage is without danger. On the sea an unusual smell is troublesome;
					and men are afraid, not knowing what the issue may be.
					Therefore tranquillity abroad avails not, while an estuating
					and disturbed mind disorders the body.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.503"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>XII.
					<lb/> WHY DOES POURING OIL ON THE SEA MAKE IT CLEAR AND CALM?</head>
            <p>Is it for that the winds, slipping the smooth oil, have
					no force, nor cause any waves? This may be probably
					said in respect of things external; but they say that divers
					take oil in their mouths, and when they spout it out they
					have light at the bottom, and it makes the water transparent; so that the slipping of the winds will not hold good
					here for an argument. Therefore it is to be considered,
					whether the sea, which is terrene and uneven, is not compacted and made smooth by the dense oil; and so the sea,
					being compact in itself, leaves passes, and a pellucidity
					penetrable by the sight. Or whether that the air, which
					is naturally mixed with the sea, is lucid, but by being
					troubled grows unequal and shady; and so by the oil's
					density, smoothing its inequality, the sea recovers its evenness and pellucidity.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>XIII.
					<lb/> WHY DO FISHERMEN'S NETS ROOT MORE IN WINTER THAN IN SUMMER, SINCE OTHER THINGS ROT MORE IN SUMMER?</head>
            <p>Is not that the cause which Theophrastus assigns,&mdash;that
					heat (to wit) shuns the cold, and is constrained by it on
					every side? Hence the waters are hottest in the bottom
					of the sea. And so it is on land; for springs are hotter
					in winter, and then lakes and rivers send up most vapors,
					because the heat is compelled to the bottom by the prevailing cold. Or it may be, nets do not rot at that time
					more than at another; but being frozen and dried in the
					cold, since they are therefore the more easily broken by
					the waves, they are liable to something like putrefaction
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.504"/>
					
					and rottenness. And they suffer most in the cold (as
					strained cords are aptest to break in such a season), because then there be most frequent storms at sea. Therefore fishermen guard their nets with certain tinctures, for
					fear they should break. Otherwise a net, neither tinged
					nor daubed with any thing, might more easily deceive the
					fish; since line is of an air color, and is not easily discerned in the sea.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="14">
            <head>XIV.
					<lb/> WHY DO THE DORIANS PRAY FOR BAD MAKING OF THEIR HAY?</head>
            <p>Is it because hay rained upon is never well made? For
					the grass is cut down green and not dry, wherefore it putrefies when wet with rain water. But when before harvest it rains upon corn, this is a help to it against the hot
					south winds; which otherwise would not let the grain fill
					in the ear, but by their heat would hinder and destroy all
					coalition, unless by watering the earth there came a moisture to cool and moisten the ear.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="15">
            <head>XV.
					<lb/> WHY IS A FAT AND DEEP SOIL FRUITFUL OF WHEAT, AND A LEAN SOIL OF BARLEY?</head>
            <p>Is it because a stronger grain needs more nourishment,
					and a weaker a light and thin one? Now barley is weaker
					and laxer than wheat, therefore it affords but little nourishment. And, as a farther testimony to this reason, wheat,
					that is ripe in three months, grows in dryer ground; because it is juiceless, and stands in need of less nourishment, and therefore is more easily brought to perfection.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.505"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="16">
            <head>XVI.
					<lb/> WHY DO MEN SAY, SOW WHEAT IN CLAY AND BARLEY IN DUST?</head>
            <p>Is the reason (as we said) because wheat takes up more
					nourishment; and barley cannot bear so much, but is
					choked with it? Or does wheat, because it is hard and
					ligneous, thrive better when it is softened and loosened in
					a moist soil; and barley at the first in a dry soil, because
					of its rarity? Or is the one temperament congruous and
					harmless to wheat, because it is hot; and the other to barley, because it is cold? Or are men afraid to sow wheat
					in a dry soil, because of the ants, which presently lie in
					wait for it; but they cannot so easily deal with barley nor
					carry it away, because it is a larger grain?
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="17">
            <head>XVII.
					<lb/> WHY DO MEN USE THE HAIR OF HORSES RATHER THAN OF MARES FOR FISHING-LINES?</head>
            <p>Is it that the males are stronger in those parts, as well
					as in others, than the females? Or is it that the females
					spoil the hair of their tails by their staling?
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>XVIII.
					<lb/> WHY IS THE SIGHT OF A CUTTLE-FISH A SIGN OF A GREAT STORM?</head>
            <p>Is it because all fishes of the soft kind cannot endure
					cold, by reason of their nakedness and tenderness? For
					they are covered neither with shell, skin, or scale, though
					within they have hard and bony parts. Hence the Greeks
					call them soft fish. Therefore they easily perceive a storm
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.506"/>
					
					coming, since they are so soon affected by the cold. When
					the polypus gets to shore and embraces the rocks, it is a
					sign the wind is rising; but the cuttle-fish jumps up, to
					shun the cold and the trouble of the bottom of the sea;
					for, of all soft fishes, she is the tenderest and soonest hurt.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>XIX.
					<lb/> WHY DOES THE POLYPUS CHANGE COLOR?</head>
            <p>WHETHER, as Theophrastus writes, because it is an animal by nature timorous; and therefore, being disturbed,
					it changes color with its spirit, as some men do, of whom
					it is said, an ill man ever changes color? But though this
					may serve as a reason for changing its color, it will not for
					the imitation of colors. For the polypus does so change
					its color, that it is of the color of every stone it comes
					nigh. Hence that of Pindar, Mind the color of the marine beast, and so converse cunningly in all cities; and
					that of Theognis:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Put on a mind like th' polyp fish,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>And learn so to dissemble,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>Which of the rock whereto it sticks
					</l>
                     <l>The color doth resemble.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theognis, vs. 215.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And they say, that such as are excellent at craftiness and
					juggling have this in their eye,&mdash;that they may the better
					cheat them they have to deal withal,&mdash;ever to imitate the
					polypus. Some think the polypus can use her skin as a
					garment, and can put it on or off at pleasure. But if
					fear occasions this change in the polypus, is not something
					else more properly the cause? Let us consider what Empedocles says, that effluvia proceed from all things whatever. For not only animals, plants, the earth and sea, but
					stones, and even brass and iron, do continually send out
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.507"/>
					
					many effluvia. For all things corrupt and smell, because
					there runneth always something from them, and they wear
					continually; insomuch that it is thought that by these
					effluvia come all attractions and insultations, some supposing embraces, others blows, some impulses, others circuitions. But especially about the sea rocks, when they are
					wet and cool by the waves (as is most likely), constantly
					some small particles are washed off, which do not incorporate with other bodies, but either pass by the smaller
					passages, or pass through the larger. Now the flesh of
					the polypus, as one may judge by the eye, is hollow, full
					of pores, and capable of effluvia. When therefore she
					is afraid, as her spirit changes she changes herself, and by
					straitening and contracting her body, she encloses the
					neighboring effluvia. And, as a good token of this argument, the polypus cannot imitate the color of every thing
					he comes near, nor the chameleon of any thing that is
					white; but each of these creatures is assimilated only to
					those things to whose effluvia it has pores proportionable.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="20">
            <head>XX.
					<lb/> WHAT IS THE REASON, THAT THE TEARS OF WILD BOARS ARE SWEET, AND THE TEARS OF THE HART SALT AND HURTFUL?</head>
            <p>THE reason seems to be the heat and cold of these animals. For the hart is cold, and the boar is very hot and
					fiery; therefore the one flies from, the other defends himself
					against, his pursuers. Now when great store of heat comes
					to the eyes (as Homer says, with horrid bristles, and eyes
					darting fire), tears are sweet. Some are of Empedocles's
					opinion, who thought that tears proceed from the disturbance of the blood, as whey does from the churning of
					milk; since therefore boar's blood is harsh and black, and
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.508"/>
					
					hart's blood thin and watery, it is consentaneous that
					the tears, which the one sheds when excited to anger, and
					the other when dejected with fear, should be of the same
					nature.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="21">
            <head>XXI.
					<lb/> WHY DO TAME SOWS FARROW OFTEN, SOME AT, ONE TIME AND OTHERS
					AT ANOTHER; AND THE WILD BUT ONCE A YEAR, AND ALL OF THEM
					ABOUT THE SAME TIME AT THE BEGINNING OF SUMMER, WHENCE IT IS SAID,&mdash;</head>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">The wild sow farrowing, that night falls no rain?</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Is it because of plentiful feeding, as in very truth fulness
					doth produce wantonness? For abundance of nourishment breeds abundance of seed both in animals and plants.
					Now wild sows live by their own toil, and that with fear;
					the tame have always food enough, either by nature or
					given them. Or may it not be ascribed to their rest and
					exercise? For the tame do rest and go not far from their
					keepers; the wild get to the mountains, and run about, by
					which means they waste the nutriment, and consume it
					upon the whole body. Therefore either through continual
					converse, or abundance of seed, or because the females
					feed in herds with the males, the tame sows call to mind
					coition and stir up lust, as Empedocles talks of men.
					But in wild sows, which feed apart, desire is cold and dull
					for want of love and conversation. Or is it true, what
					Aristotle says, that Homer called the wild boar <foreign lang="greek">xlou/nhs</foreign>, because he had but one stone? For most boars spoil their
					stones (he says) by rubbing them against stumps of trees.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.509"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="22">
            <head>XXII.
					<lb/> WHY ARE THE PAWS OF BEARS THE SWEETEST AND PLEASANTEST FOOD?</head>
            <p>BECAUSE the flesh of those parts of the body which concoct aliment the best is sweetest; and that concocts best
					which transpires most by motion and exercise. But the
					bear uses the fore-feet most in going and running, and in
					managing of things, as it were with hands.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="23">
            <head>XXIII.
					<lb/> WHY ARE THE STEPS OF WILD BEASTS MOST DIFFICULTLY TRACED IN SPRING-TIME?</head>
            <p>WHETHER the dogs, as Empedocles says, <q direct="unspecified"> with noses find
					the steps of all wild beasts,</q> and draw in those effluvia
					which the beasts leave in the ground; but the various
					smells of plants and flowers lying over the footsteps do
					in spring-time obscure and confound them, and put the
					dogs to a loss at winding them? Therefore about Etna in
					Sicily no man keeps any hunting dogs, because abundance
					of wild marjoram flourishes and grows there the year round,
					and the perpetual flagrancy of the place destroys the scent
					of the wild beasts. There is also a tale, how Proserpine,
					as she was gathering flowers thereabout, was ravished by
					Pluto; therefore people, revering that place as an asylum,
					do not catch any creature that feeds thereabout.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="24">
            <head>XXIV.
					<lb/> WHY ARE THE TRACKS OF WILD BEASTS WORSE SCENTED ABOUT THE FULL MOON?</head>
            <p>WHETHER for the foresaid cause? For the full moons
					bring down the dews; and therefore Alcman calls dew the
					daughter of Jove and Luna in a verse of his,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.510"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Fed by the dew, bred by the Moon and Jove.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For dew is a weak and languid rain, and there is but little
					heat in the moon; which draws water from the earth, as the
					sun does; but because it cannot raise it on high, it soon
					lets it fall.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="25">
            <head>XXV.
					<lb/> WHY DOES FROST MAKE HUNTING DIFFICULT?</head>
            <p>WHETHER is it because the wild beasts leave off going
					far abroad by reason of the cold, and so leave but few signs
					of themselves? Therefore some say, beasts spare the neighboring places, that they may not be sore put to it by going
					far abroad in winter, but may always have food ready at
					hand. Or is it because that for hunting the track alone is
					not sufficient, but there must be scent also? And things
					gently dissolved and loosened by heat afford a smell, but
					too violent cold binds up the scent, and will not let it
					reach the sense. Therefore they say that unguents and
					wine smell least in winter and cold weather; for the then
					concrete air keeps the scent in, and suffers it not to
					disperse.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="26">
            <head>XXVI.
					<lb/> WHAT IS THE REASON THAT BRUTES, WHEN THEY AIL ANY THING,
					SEEK AND PURSUE REMEDIES, AND ARE OFTEN CURED BY THE USE OF THEM?</head>
            <p>DOGS eat grass, to make them vomit bile. Swine seek
					craw-fish, because the eating of them cures the headache.
					The tortoise, when he has eaten a viper, feeds on wild
					marjoram. They say, when a bear has surfeited himself
					and his stomach grows nauseous, he licks up ants, and by
					devouring them is cured. These creatures know such
					things neither by experience nor by chance.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.511"/>
            <p>Whether, as wax draws the bee, and carcasses the vulture afar off by the scent, do craw-fish so draw swine, wild
					marjoram the tortoise, and ants the bear, by smells and
					effluvia accommodated to their nature, they being prompted
					altogether by sense, without any assistance from reason?
					Or do not the temperaments of the body create appetites in
					animals, while diseases create these, producing divers
					acrimonies, sweetnesses, and other unusual and absurd qualities, the humors being altered; as is plain in women
					with child, who eat stones and earth? Therefore skilful
					physicians take their prognostic of recovery or death from
					the appetites of the sick. For Mnesitheus the physician
					says that, in the beginning of a disease of the lungs, he
					that craves onions recovers, and he that craves figs dies;
					because appetites follow the temperament, and the temperament follows diseases. It is therefore probable that
					beasts, if they fall not into mortal diseases, have such a
					disposition and temper, that by following their temper they
					light on their remedies.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="27">
            <head>XXVII.
					<lb/> WHY DOES MUST, IF THE VESSEL STAND IN THE COLD, CONTINUE LONG SWEET?</head>
            <p>Is it because the changing of the sweet must into wine
					is concoction, but cold hinders concoction, because this is
					caused by heat? Or, on the contrary, is the proper taste
					of the grape sweet, and is it then said to be ripe, when
					the sweetness is equally diffused all over it; but does cold,
					not suffering the heat of the grape to exhale, and keeping
					it in, conserve the sweetness of the grape? And this is
					the reason that, in a rainy vintage, must ferments but little;
					for fermentation proceeds from heat, which the cold does
					check.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.512"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="28">
            <head>XXVIII.
					<lb/> WHY, OF ALL WILD BEASTS, DOES NOT THE BOAR BITE THE TOIL, ALTHOUGH BOTH WOLVES AND FOXES DO THIS?</head>
            <p>Is it because his teeth stand so far within his head, that
					he cannot well come at the thread? For his lips, by
					reason of their thickness and largeness, meet close before.
					Or does he rather rely on his paws and mouth, and with
					those rend the toil, and with this defend himself against
					the hunters? His chief refuge is rolling and wallowing;
					therefore, rather than stand gnawing the toil, he rolls often
					about, and so clears himself, having no occasion for his
					teeth.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="29">
            <head>XXIX.
					<lb/> WHAT IS THE REASON THAT WE ADMIRE HOT WATERS (<hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> BATHS)
					AND NOT COLD; SINCE IT IS PLAIN THAT COLD IS AS MUCH THE
					CAUSE OF ONE SORT AS HEAT IS OF THE OTHER?</head>
            <p>IT is not (as some are of opinion) that heat is a quality,
					and cold only a privation of that quality, and so that an
					entity is even less a cause than a non-entity. But we do it
					because Nature has attributed admiration to what is rare,
					and she puts men upon enquiry how any thing comes to
					pass that seldom happens. As Euripides saith,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Behold the boundless Heaven on high,
					</l>
                     <l>Bearing the earth in his moist arms,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>what wonders he brings out by night, and what beauty he
					shows forth by day! . . . The rainbow and the varied
					beauty of the clouds by day, and the lights which burst
					forth by night . . .
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.513"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="30">
            <head>XXX.
					<lb/> WHY ARE VINES WHICH ARE RANK OF LEAVES, BUT OTHERWISE FRUIT- LESS, SAID <foreign lang="greek">traga=n</foreign>?</head>
            <p>Is it because very fat goats (<foreign lang="greek">tra/goi</foreign>) are less able to procreate, nay, scarce able to use coition, by reason of their
					fatness Seed is the superfluity of the aliment which is
					allotted to the body: now, when either an animal or a
					plant is of a very strong constitution and grows fat, it is a
					sign that all the nourishment is spent within, and that
					there is little and base excrement, or none at all.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="31">
            <head>XXXI.
					<lb/> WHY DOES THE VINE IRRIGATED WITH WINE DIE, ESPECIALLY THE VERY WINE MADE FROM ITS OWN GRAPES?</head>
            <p>Is it as baldness happens to great wine-bibbers, the heat
					of the wine evaporating the moisture? Or, as Empedocles saith, <q direct="unspecified">the putrefied water in the wood becomes wine
						beneath the bark,</q> . . . thus, when the vine is outwardly
					irrigated with wine, it is as fire to the vine, and destroys
					the nutritive faculty. Or, because wine is obstructive, it
					gets into the roots, stops the passages, and so hinders
					any moisture from coming to the plant to make it grow
					and thrive. Or, it may seem contrary to Nature that that
					should return into the vine which came out of it; for whatsover moisture comes from plants can neither nourish nor
					be again a part of the plant.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.514"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="32">
            <head>XXXII.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Questions which follow (XXXII-XXXIX) are not found in the Greek,
					but are restored from the Latin translation, said to have been made in the 16th century from a Greek manuscript now lost. The version here given is based upon
					that of Holland. (G.)</note>
					          <lb/> WHY DOTH THE PALM ALONE OF ALL TREES BEND UPWARD WHEN A WEIGHT IS LAID THEREUPON?</head>
            <p>Is it that the fiery and spiritual power which it hath,
					being once provoked and (as it were) angered, putteth
					forth itself so much the more, and mounteth upward? Or
					is it because the weight, forcing the boughs suddenly,
					oppresseth and keepeth down the airy substance which
					they have, and driveth all of it inward; but the same
					afterwards, having resumed strength again, maketh head
					afresh, and more eagerly withstandeth the weight? Or,
					lastly, is it that the softer and more tender branches, not
					able to sustain the violence at first, so soon as the burden
					resteth quiet, by little and little lift up themselves, and
					make a show as if they rose up against it?
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="33">
            <head>XXXIII.
					<lb/> WHAT IS THE REASON THAT PIT-WATER IS LESS NUTRITIVE THAN
					EITHER THAT WHICH ARISETH OUT OF SPRINGS OR THAT WHICH FALLETH DOWN FROM HEAVEN?</head>
            <p>Is it because it is more cold, and withal hath less air in
					it? Or because it containeth much salt from the earth
					mingled therewith?&mdash;now it is well known that salt above
					all other things causeth leanness. Or because standing
					still, and not exercised with running and stirring, it getteth
					a certain malignant quality, which is hurtful to both plants
					and animals, and is the cause that it is neither well concocted nor able to feed and nourish any thing? Hence it
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.515"/>
					
					is that all dead waters of pools are unwholesome, for that
					they cannot digest and despatch those harmful qualities
					which they borrow of the evil property of the air or of
					the earth.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="34">
            <head>XXXIV.
					<lb/> WHY IS THE WEST WIND HELD COMMONLY TO BE THE SWIFTEST, ACCORDING TO THIS VERSE OF HOMER:</head>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let us likewise bestir our feet,
				</l>
                     <l>As fast as Western winds do fleet.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIX. 415.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not because this wind is wont to blow when the
					sky is very well cleansed, and the air is exceeding clear
					and without all clouds?&mdash;for the thickness and impurity
					of the air doth not a little impeach and interrupt the
					course of the winds. Or is it rather because the sun,
					striking through a cold wind with his beams, is the cause
					that it passeth the faster away?&mdash;for whatsoever of cold
					is drawn in by the force of the winds, when the same
					is overcome by heat, as it were its enemy, we must
					think, is driven and set forward further and with greater
					celerity.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="35">
            <head>XXXV.
					<lb/> WHY CANNOT BEES ABIDE SMOKE?</head>
            <p>WHETHER is it because the passages of their vital spirits
					are exceeding strait, and, if it chance that smoke be gotten
					into them and there kept in and intercepted, it is enough
					to stop the poor bees' breath,&mdash;yea, and to strangle them
					quite? Or is not the acrimony and bitterness (think you)
					of the smoke in cause&mdash;for bees are delighted with
					sweet things, and in very truth they have no other nourishment; and therefore no marvel if they detest and abhor
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.516"/>
					
					smoke, as a thing for the bitterness most adverse and contrary unto them. Therefore honey-masters, when they
					make a smoke for to drive away bees, are wont to burn
					bitter herbs, as hemlock, centaury, &amp;c.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="36">
            <head>XXXVI.
					<lb/> WHY WILL BEES SOONER STING THOSE WHO NEWLY BEFORE HAVE COMMITTED WHOREDOM?</head>
            <p>Is it not because it is a creature that wonderfully delighteth in purity, cleanliness, and elegancy, and withal
					hath a marvellous quick sense of smelling? Because
					therefore such unclean dealings between man and woman
					are wont to leave behind much filthiness and impurity,
					the bees both sooner find them out and also conceive
					the greater hatred against them. Hereupon it is that
					in Theocritus the shepherd pleasantly sendeth Venus
					away unto Anchises to be well stung with bees for her
					adultery:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now to mount Ida, to Anchises go,
					</l>
                     <l>Where mighty oaks and cypresses do grow;
					</l>
                     <l>Where hives and trees with honey sweet abound,
					</l>
                     <l>And both with humming noise of bees resound.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theoc. I. 105.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Pindar saith: <q direct="unspecified">Thou little creature, who honey-combs
					dost frame, and with thy sting hast pricked false impure
					Rhoecus for his lewd villanies.</q>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="37">
            <head>XXXVII.
					<lb/> WHY DO DOGS FOLLOW AFTER A STONE THAT IS THROWN AT THEM AND BITE IT, LETTING THE MAN ALONE WHO FLUNG IT?</head>
            <p>Is it because he can comprehend nothing by imagination
					nor call a thing to mind, which are gifts and virtues proper
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.517"/>
					
					to man alone; and therefore, seeing he cannot discern the
					party that offered him injury, he supposeth that to be his
					enemy which seemeth in his eye to threaten him, and of
					it he goes about to be revenged? Or is it that he thinks
					the stone, while it runs along the ground, to be some wild
					beast, and according to his nature he intendeth to catch it
					first; but afterwards, when he seeth himself deceived and
					put besides his reckoning, he setteth upon the man? Or
					rather, doth he not hate the man and the stone both alike,
					but pursueth that only which is next unto him?
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="38">
            <head>XXXVIII.
					<lb/> WHY AT A CERTAIN TIME OF THE YEAR DO ALL SHE-WOLVES WHELP WITHIN THE COMPASS OF TWELVE DAYS?</head>
            <p>ANTIPATER in his History of Animals affirms, that shewolves exclude forth their young ones about the time that
					mast trees shed their blossoms, for upon the taste thereof
					their wombs open; but if there be none of such blooms
					to be had, then their young die within the body and never
					come to light. Moreover, he saith, those countries which
					bring not forth oaks and mast are never troubled nor
					spoiled with wolves. Some attribute all this to a tale
					that goes of Latona; who being with child, and finding
					no abiding place of rest and safety by reason of Juno for
					the space of twelve days, went to Delos, and, being transmuted by Jupiter into a wolf, obtained at his hands that
					all wolves for ever after might within that time be delivered
					of their young.
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.518"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="39">
            <head>XXXIX.
					<lb/> HOW COMETH IT THAT WATER, SEEMING WHITE ALOFT, SHOWETH TO BE BLACK IN THE BOTTOM?</head>
            <p>Is it because depth is the mother of darkness, so that it
					doth dim and mar the sunbeams before they can descend
					so low as it? As for the uppermost superficies of the
					water, because it is immediately affected by the sun, it
					must needs receive the white brightness of the light; the
					which Empedocles verily approveth in these verses:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A river in the bottom seems
					</l>
                     <l>By shade of color black;
					</l>
                     <l>The like is seen in caves and holes,
					</l>
                     <l>By depth, where light they lack.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Or, since the bottom of the sea and of great rivers is
					often full of mud, doth it by reflection of the sunbeams
					represent the like color that the said mud hath? Or is it
					more probable that the water toward the bottom is not
					pure and sincere, but corrupted with an earthy quality,&mdash;
					as continually carrying with it somewhat of that by which
					it runneth and wherewith it is stirred,&mdash;and the same
					settling once to the bottom causeth it to be more troubled
					and less transparent?</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>