<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De esu carnium I</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.131">
      <pb id="v.5.p.3"/>
      <body>
         <head>Of eating of flesh: Tract I.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>You ask of me then for what reason it was that Pythagoras abstained from eating of flesh. I for my part do
				much admire in what humor, with what soul or reason,
				the first man with his mouth touched slaughter, and reached
				to his lips the flesh of a dead animal, and having set before people courses of ghastly corpses and ghosts, could
				give those parts the names of meat and victuals, that but
				a little before lowed, cried, moved, and saw; how his sight
				could endure the blood of slaughtered, flayed, and mangled bodies; how his smell could bear their scent; and
				how the very nastiness happened not to offend the taste,
				while it chewed the sores of others, and participated of
				the saps and juices of deadly wounds.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Crept the raw hides, and with a bellowing sound
					</l>
                     <l>Roared the dead limbs; the burning entrails groaned.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XII. 895.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed is but a fiction and fancy; but the fare itself
					is truly monstrous and prodigious,&mdash;that a man should
					have a stomach to creatures while they yet bellow, and that
					he should be giving directions which of things yet alive
					and speaking is fittest to make food of, and ordering the
					several manners of the seasoning and dressing them and
					serving them up to tables. You ought rather, in my opinion, to have enquired who first began this practice, than
					who of late times left it off.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.4"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>And truly, as for those people who first ventured
				upon eating of flesh, it is very probable that the whole
				reason of their so doing was scarcity and want of other
				food; for it is not likely that their living together in lawless and extravagant lusts, or their growing wanton and
				capricious through the excessive variety of provisions then
				among them, brought them to such unsociable pleasures as these, against Nature. Yea, had they at this
				instant but their sense and voice restored to them, I am
				persuaded they would express themselves to this purpose:</p>
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Oh! happy you, and highly favored of the Gods, who
					now live! Into what an age of the world are you fallen,
					who share and enjoy among you a plentiful portion of
					good things! What abundance of things spring up for
					your use! What fruitful vineyards you enjoy! What
					wealth you gather from the fields! What delicacies from
					trees and plants, which you may gather! You may glut
					and fill yourselves without being polluted. As for us, we
					fell upon the most dismal and affrighting part of time, in
					which we were exposed by our first production to manifold and inextricable wants and necessities. As yet the
					thickened air concealed the heaven from our view, and the
					stars were as yet confused with a disorderly huddle of fire
					and moisture and violent fluxions of winds. As yet the
					sun was not fixed to an unwandering and certain course,
					so as to distinguish morning and evening, nor did he bring
					back the seasons in order crowned with wreaths from the
					fruitful harvest. The land was also spoiled by the inundations of disorderly rivers; and a great part of it was deformed with sloughs, and utterly wild by reason of deep
					quagmires, unfertile forests, and woods. There was then
					no production of tame fruits, nor any instruments of art
					or invention of wit. And hunger gave no time, nor did
					seed-time then stay for the yearly season. What wonder
					is it if we made use of the flesh of beasts contrary to Nature,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.5"/>
					
					 when mud was eaten and the bark of wood, and
					when it was thought a happy thing to find either a sprouting grass or a root of any plant! But when they had by
					chance tasted of or eaten an acorn, they danced for very
					joy about some oak or esculus, calling it by the names of
					life-giver, mother, and nourisher. And this was the only
					festival that those times were acquainted with; upon all
					other occasions, all things were full of anguish and dismal
					sadness. But whence is it that a certain ravenousness and
					frenzy drives you in these happy days to pollute yourselves
					with blood, since you have such an abundance of things
					necessary for your subsistence? Why do you belie the
					earth as unable to maintain you? Why do you profane
					the lawgiver Ceres, and shame the mild and gentle Bacchus, as not furnishing you with sufficiency? Are you not
					ashamed to mix tame fruits with blood and slaughter?
					You are indeed wont to call serpents, leopards, and lions
					savage creatures; but yet yourselves are defiled with blood,
					and come nothing behind them in cruelty. What they kill
					is their ordinary nourishment, but what you kill is your
					better fare.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>For we eat not lions and wolves by way of revenge;
				but we let those go, and catch the harmless and tame sort,
				and such as have neither stings nor teeth to bite with, and
				slay them; which, so may Jove help us, Nature seems to
				us to have produced for their beauty and comeliness only.
				<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">I see not how this that is included within these marks []agreeth with
					this place, or matter in hand: I suppose therefore it is inserted heere without judgement, and taken out of some other booke.</q> &mdash;HOLLAND.</note>[Just as if one seeing the river Nilus overflowing its
				banks, and thereby filling the whole country with genial
				and fertile moisture, should not at all admire that secret
				power in it that produces plants and plenteousness of most
				sweet and useful fruits, but beholding somewhere a crocodile swimming in it, or an asp crawling along, or mice
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.6"/>
				
				(savage and filthy creatures), should presently affirm these
				to be the occasion of all that is amiss, or of any want or
				defect that may happen. Or as if indeed one contemplating this land or ground, how full it is of tame fruits, and
				how heavy with ears of corn, should afterwards espy somewhere in these same cornfields an ear of darnel or a wild
				vetch, and thereupon neglect to reap and gather in the
				corn, and fall a complaining of these. Such another thing
				it would be, if one&mdash;hearing the harangue of some advocate at some bar or pleading, swelling and enlarging and
				hastening towards the relief of some impending danger,
				or else, by Jupiter, in the impeaching and charging of
				certain audacious villanies or indictments, flowing and rolling along, and that not in a simple and poor strain, but
				with many sorts of passions all at once, or rather indeed
				with all sorts, in one and the same manner, into the many
				and various and differing minds of either hearers or judges
				that he is either to turn and change, or else, by Jupiter,
				to soften, appease, and quiet&mdash;should overlook all this
				business, and never consider or reckon upon the labor or
				struggle he had undergone, but pick up certain loose expressions, which the rapid motion of the discourse had
				carried along with it, as by the current of its stream, and
				so had slipped and escaped the rest of the oration, and
				hereupon undervalue the orator.]</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>But we are nothing put out of countenance, either
				by the beauteous gayety of the colors, or by the charmingness of the musical voices, or by the rare sagacity of the
				intellects, or by the cleanliness and neatness of diet, or by
				the rare discretion and prudence of these poor unfortunate
				animals; but for the sake of some little mouthful of flesh,
				we deprive a soul of the sun and light, and of that proportion of life and time it had been born into the world to
				enjoy. And then we fancy that the voices it utters and
				screams forth to us are nothing else but certain inarticulate
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.7"/>
				
				sounds and noises, and not the several deprecations, entreaties, and pleadings of each of them, as it were saying
				thus to us: <q direct="unspecified">I deprecate not thy necessity (if such there
					be), but thy wantonness. Kill me for thy feeding, but do
					not take me off for thy better feeding.</q> O horrible cruelty!
				It is truly an affecting sight to see the very table of rich
				people laid before them, who keep them cooks and caterers
				to furnish them with dead corpses for their daily fare; but
				it is yet more affecting to see it taken away, for the mammocks left are more than that which was eaten. These
				therefore were slain to no purpose. Others there are, who
				are so sparing of what is set before them that they will
				not suffer it to be cut or sliced; thus abstaining from them
				when dead, -while they would not spare them when alive.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Well then, we understand that that sort of men are
				used to say, that in eating of flesh they follow the conduct
				and direction of Nature. But that it is not natural to
				mankind to feed on flesh, we first of all demonstrate from
				the very shape and figure of the body. For a human body
				no ways resembles those that were born for ravenousness;
				it hath no hawk's bill, no sharp talon, no roughness of
				teeth, no such strength of stomach or heat of digestion, as
				can be sufficient to convert or alter such heavy and fleshy
				fare. But even from hence, that is, from the smoothness
				of the tongue; and the slowness of the stomach to digest,
				Nature seems to disclaim all pretence to fleshy victuals.
				But if you will contend that yourself was born to an inclination to such food as you have now a mind to eat, do you
				then yourself kill what you would eat. But do it yourself,
				without the help of a chopping-knife, mallet or axe,&mdash;as
				wolves, bears, and lions do, who kill and eat at once.
				Rend an ox with thy teeth, worry a hog with thy mouth,
				tear a lamb or a hare in pieces, and fall on and eat it alive
				as they do. But if thou hadst rather stay until what thou
				eatest is become dead, and if thou art loath to force a soul
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.8"/>
				
				out of its body, why then dost thou against Nature eat an
				animate thing? Nay, there is nobody that is willing to
				eat even a lifeless and a dead thing as it is; but they boil
				it, and roast it, and alter it by fire and medicines, as it
				were, changing and quenching the slaughtered gore with
				thousands of sweet sauces, that the palate being thereby
				deceived may admit of such uncouth fare. It was indeed
				a witty expression of a Lacedaemonian, who, having purchased a small fish in a certain inn, delivered it to his
				landlord to be dressed; and as he demanded cheese, and
				vinegar, and oil to make sauce, he replied, if I had had
				those, I would not have bought the fish. But we are grown
				so wanton in our bloody luxury, that we have bestowed
				upon flesh the name of meat (<foreign lang="greek">o)/yon</foreign>), and then require
				another seasoning (<foreign lang="greek">o)/yon</foreign>), to this same flesh, mixing oil,
				wine, honey, pickle, and vinegar, with Syrian and Arabian
				spices, as though we really meant to embalm it after its
				disease. Indeed when things are dissolved and made thus
				tender and soft, and are as it were turned into a sort of
				a carrionly corruption, it must needs be a great difficulty
				for concoction to master them, and when it hath mastered
				them, they must needs cause grievous oppressions and
				qualmy indigestions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Diogenes ventured once to eat a raw pourcontrel, that
				he might disuse himself from meat dressed by fire; and
				as several priests and other people stood round him, he
				wrapped his head in his cassock, and so putting the fish
				to his mouth, he thus said unto them: It is for your sake,
				sirs, that I undergo this danger, and run this risk. A
				noble and gallant risk, by Jupiter! For far otherwise
				than as Pelopidas ventured his life for the liberty of the
				Thebans, and Harmodius and Aristogiton for that of the
				Athenians, did this philosopher encounter with a raw pourcontrel, to the end he might make human life more brutish.
				Moreover, these same flesh-eatings not only are preternatural
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.9"/>
				
				 to men's bodies, but also by clogging and cloying
				them, they render their very minds and intellects gross.
				For it is well known to most, that wine and much flesh-eating make the body indeed strong and lusty, but the
				mind weak and feeble. And that I may not offend the
				wrestlers, I will make use of examples out of my own
				country. The Athenians are wont to call us Boeotians
				gross, senseless, and stupid fellows, for no other reason
				but our over-much eating; and Pindar calls us also hogs, for
				the same reason. Menander the comedian calls us <q direct="unspecified">fellows with long jaws.</q> It is observed also that, according
				to the saying of Heraclitus, <q direct="unspecified">the wisest soul is like a
					dry light.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Mullach, Fragm. Philos. p. 325 (No. 73).</note> Earthen jars, if you strike them, will sound;
				but if they be full, they perceive not the strokes that are
				given them. Copper vessels also that are thin communicate the sound round about them, unless some one stop
				and dull the ambient stroke with his fingers. Moreover,
				the eye, when seized with an over-great plenitude of humors, grows dim and feeble for its ordinary work. When
				we behold the sun through a humid air and a great quantity of gross and indigested vapors, we see it not clear and
				bright, but obscure and cloudy, and with glimmering
				beams. Just so in a muddy and clogged body, that is
				swagged down with heavy and unnatural nourishments; it
				must needs happen that the gayety and splendor of the
				mind be confused and dulled, and that it ramble and roll
				after little and scarce discernible objects, since it wants
				clearness and vigor for higher things.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>But to pass by these considerations, is not accustoming one's self to mildness and a human temper of mind an
				admirable thing? For who could wrong or injure a man
				that is so sweetly and humanly disposed with respect to
				the ills of strangers that are not of his kind? I remember
				that three days ago, as I was discoursing, I made mention
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.10"/>
				
				of a saying of Xenocrates, and how the Athenians gave
				judgment upon a certain person who had flayed a living
				ram. For my part I cannot think him a worse criminal
				that torments a poor creature while living, than a man
				that shall take away its life and murder it. But (as it
				seems) we are more sensible of what is done against custom than against Nature. There, however, I discoursed
				on these matters in a more popular style. But as for that
				grand and mysterious principle which (as Plato speaks) is
				incredible to base minds and to such as affect only mortal
				things, I as little care to move it in this discourse as a
				pilot doth a ship in a storm, or a comedian his machine
				while the scenes are moving; but perhaps it would not be
				amiss, by way of introduction and preface, to proclaim certain verses of Empedocles. ... For in these, by way of
				allegory, he hints at men's souls, as that they are tied to
				mortal bodies, to be punished for murders, eating of flesh
				and of one another, although this doctrine seems much
				ancienter than his time. For the fables that are storied
				and related about the discerption of Bacchus, and the attempts of the Titans upon him, and of their tasting of his
				slain body, and of their several punishments and fulminations afterwards, are but a representation of the regeneration. For what in us is unreasonable, disorderly, and
				boisterous, being not divine but demoniac, the ancients
				termed Titans, that is <hi rend="italics">tormented</hi> and <hi rend="italics">punished</hi> (from
				<foreign lang="greek">ti/nw</foreign>)....</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>