<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Maxime cum principbus philosopho esse diserendum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold North Fowler</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.10.p.27"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>THAT A PHILOSOPHER OUGHT TO CONVERSE ESPECIALLY WITH MEN IN POWER (MAXIME CUM PRINCIPIBUS PHILOSOPHO ESSE DISSERENDUM)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>This brief essay was written in support of the contention that the philosopher should exert himself to
					influence the thought and conduct of men in power
					and should not shut himself away from the world.
					This view is consistent with Plutarch's own life. The
					essay is less carefully written than some of the others,
					and the text is somewhat uncertain in a few places,
					among which may be mentioned the very first sentence. In this the first word, Sorcanus, appears to be
					a proper name, but the name does not occur elsewhere, and therefore numerous emendations have
					been proposed. If the reading is correct, Sorcanus
					was some important personage and must have been
					well known to the person, whoever he was, to whom
					the essay is addressed ; for although not written
					exactly in the form of a letter, the essay seems to be
					intended primarily for some one person's edification
					or entertainment.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.29"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>In clasping Sorcanus to your bosom, in prizing,
					pursuing, welcoming, and cultivating his friendship
					- a friendship which will prove useful and fruitful to
					many in private and to many in public life - you are
					acting like a man who loves what is noble, who is
					public-spirited and is a friend of mankind, not, as some
					people say, like one who is merely ambitious for himself. No, on the contrary, the man who is ambitious
					for himself and afraid of every whisper is just the one
					who avoids and fears being called a persistent and
					servile attendant on those in power. For what does
					a man say who is an attendant upon philosophy and
					stands in need of it ? <q direct="unspecified">Let me change from Pericles
						or Cato and become Simo the cobbler or Dionysius
						the schoolmaster, in order that the philosopher may
						converse with me and sit beside me as Socrates did
						with Pericles.</q> And while it is true that Ariston of
						Chios, when the sophists spoke ill of him for talking
						with all who wished it, said, <q direct="unspecified">I wish even the beasts
						could understand words which incite to virtue,</q> yet
					as for us, shall we avoid becoming intimate with
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.31"/>
					
					
					powerful men and rulers, as if they were wild and
					savage ?
				</p>
            <p>
					The teaching of philosophy is not, if I may use
					the words of Pindar,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Nem.</hi> v. 1 <foreign lang="greek">ou)k a)ndriantopoio/s ei)m', w(/st' e)linu/sonta e)rga/zesqai a)ga/lmat' e)p' au)ta=s baqmi/dos</foreign>, loosely quoted. The translation is adapted from that of Sir John Sandys (in L.C.L.).</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">a sculptor to carve statues
						doomed to stand idly on their pedestals and no
						more</q>; no, it strives to make everything that it
					touches active and efficient and alive, it inspires men
					with impulses which urge to action, with judgements
					that lead them towards what is useful, with preferences for things that are honourable, with wisdom
					and greatness of mind joined to gentleness and conservatism, and because they possess these qualities,
					men of public spirit are more eager to converse with
					the prominent and powerful. Certainly if a physician
					is a man of high ideals, he will be better pleased to
					cure the eye which sees for many and watches over
					many, and a philosopher will be more eager to attend
					upon a soul which he sees is solicitous for many and
					is under obligation to be wise and self-restrained
					and just in behalf of many. For surely, if he were
					skilled in discovering and collecting water, as they
					say Heracles and many of the ancients were, he
					would not delight in digging the swineherd's fount
					of Arethusa<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xiii. 404-410. The allusion is to the feeding-place of the swine tended by Eumaeus.</note> in a most distant spot <q direct="unspecified">by the Crow's
						Rock,</q> but in uncovering the unfailing sources of
					some river for cities and camps and the plantations
					of kings and sacred groves. So we hear Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xix. 179.</note>
					calling Minos <q direct="unspecified">the great god's <hi rend="italics">oaristes</hi>,</q> which
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.33"/>
					
					
					means, according to Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Minos</hi>, 319 d. Generally regarded as spurious.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">familiar friend and
						pupil.</q> For they did not think that pupils of the
					gods should be plain citizens or stay-at-homes or
					idlers, but kings, from whose good counsel, justice,
					goodness, and high-mindedness, if those qualities
					were implanted in them, all who had to do with
					them would receive benefit and profit. Of the
					plant <hi rend="italics">eryngium</hi> they say that if one goat take it in
					its mouth, first that goat itself and then the entire
					herd stands still until the herdsman comes and takes
					the plant out, such pungency, like a fire which spreads
					over everything near it and scatters itself abroad, is
					possessed by the emanations of its potency. Certainly the teachings of the philosopher, if they take
					hold of one person in private station who enjoys
					abstention from affairs and circumscribes himself by
					his bodily comforts, as by a circle drawn with geometrical compasses, do not spread out to others, but
					merely create calmness and quiet in that one man,
					then dry up and disappear. But if these teachings
					take possession of a ruler, a statesman, and a man
					of action and fill him with love of honour, through
					one he benefits many, as Anaxagoras did by associating with Pericles, Plato with Dion, and Pythagoras
					with the chief men of the Italiote Greeks. Cato
					himself sailed from his army to visit Athenodorus ;
					and Scipio sent for Panaetius when he himself was
					sent out by the senate
					<quote rend="blockquote">to view the violence and lawfulness of men,</quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.35"/>
					
					
					as Poseidonius says.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xvii. 487.</note> Now what should Panaetius
					have said ? <q direct="unspecified">If you were Bato or Polydeuces or
						some other person in private station who wished
						to run away from the midst of cities and quietly in
						some comer solve or quibble<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <foreign lang="greek">perie/lkein</foreign>, literally <q direct="unspecified">pull about.</q> Plato (<hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 539 b) says that the young, when new to argument, find pleasure <foreign lang="greek">w(/sper skula/kia tw=| e(/lkein te kai\ spara/ttein tw=| lo/gw| tou\s plhsi/on a)ei/</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">like little dogs, in pulling and tearing apart by argument those who happen to be near them.</q>
                  </note> over the syllogisms of
						philosophers, I would gladly welcome you and consort
						with you ; but since you are the son of Aemilius
						Paulus, who was twice consul, and the grandson of
						Scipio Africanus who overcame Hannibal the Carthaginian, shall I, therefore, not converse with you ?</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But the statement that there are two kinds of
					speech, one residing in the mind, the gift of Hermes
					the Leader, and the other residing in the utterance,
					merely an attendant and instrument, is threadbare ;
					we will let it come under the heading
					<quote rend="blockquote">Yes, this I knew before Theognis' birth.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">By an unknown comic poet; Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 495. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 395 e, Aulus Gellius, i. 3. 19, Marx on Lucilius 952.</note>
               </quote>
					But that would not disturb us, because the aim
					and end of both the speech in the mind and the
					speech in the utterance is friendship, towards oneself
					and towards one's neighbour respectively ; for the
					former, ending through philosophy in virtue, makes a
					man harmonious with himself, free from blame from
					himself, and full of peace and friendliness towards
					himself.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.37"/>
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Faction is not, nor is ill-starred strife, to be found in his
					members,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A verse of an unknown poet. Ascribed to Empedocles by Bergk.</note>
               </quote>
					there is no passion disobedient to reason, no strife
					of impulse with impulse, no opposition of argument to
					argument, there is no rough tumult and pleasure on
					the border-line, as it were, between desire and repentance, but everything is gentle and friendly and
					makes each man gain the greatest number of benefits and be pleased with himself. But Pindar says<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Isthm.</hi> ii. 10.</note>
					that the Muse of oral utterance was <q direct="unspecified">not greedy of
						gain, nor toilsome</q> formerly, and I believe she is
					not so now either, but because of lack of education
					and of good taste the <q direct="unspecified">common Hermes</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*koino\s *(ermh=s</foreign> is a proverbial expression meaning <q direct="unspecified">good luck should be shared</q> (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Menander, <hi rend="italics">Arbitrants</hi>, 67; Lucian, <hi rend="italics">Navigium</hi>, 12, p. 256; Theophrastus, <hi rend="italics">Characters</hi>, 30. 7; Aristotle, 1201 a 20). But Hermes was god, not only of gain and luck, but also of eloquence, and here the meaning is that eloquence, which should be for the common good of all, has to be bought.</note> has become venal and ready for hire. For it cannot be
					that, whereas Aphrodit&ecirc; was angry with the daughters
					of Propoetus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Metam.</hi> x. 221 ff., especially 238 ff.</note> because
					<quote rend="blockquote">First they were to devise for young men a shower of
					abominations,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown poet.</note>
               </quote>
					yet Urania, Calliop&ecirc;, and Clio are pleased with those
					who pollute speech for money. No, I think the
					works and gifts of the Muses are more conducive to
					friendship than are those of Aphrodit&ecirc;. For approbation, which some consider the end and purpose
					of speech, is admired as the beginning and seed of
					friendship ; but most people rather bestow reputation altogether by goodwill, believing that we praise
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.39"/>
					
					
					those only whom we love. But just as Ixion slipped
					into the cloud when he was pursuing Hera, so these
					people seize upon a deceptive, showy, and shifting
					appearance in lieu of friendship. But the man of
					sense, if he is engaged in active political life, will ask
					for so much reputation as will inspire confidence and
					thereby give him power for affairs ; for it is neither
					pleasant nor easy to benefit people if they are unwilling, and confidence makes them willing. For
					just as light is more a blessing to those who see than
					to those who are seen, so reputation is more a blessing to those who are aware of it than to those who
					are not overlooked. But he who has withdrawn
					from public affairs, who communes with himself
					and thinks happiness is in quiet and uninterrupted
					leisure, he, <q direct="unspecified">being chaste, worships afar off</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hipp.</hi> 102.</note>
					the reputation which is popular and widespread in
					crowds and theatres, even as Hippolytus worshipped
					Aphrodit&ecirc;, but even he does not despise reputation
					among the right-minded and estimable ; but wealth,
					reputation as a leader, or power in his friendships he
					does not pursue, however neither does he avoid these
					qualities if they are associated with a temperate
					character ; nor, for that matter, does he pursue
					those among the youths who are fine-looking and
					handsome, but those who are teachable and orderly
					and fond of learning ; nor does the beauty of those
					whom he sees endowed with freshness, charm, and
					the flower of youth frighten the philosopher or scare
					him off and drive him away from those who are
					worthy of his attention. So, then, if the dignity
					that befits leadership and power are associated with
					a man of moderation and culture, the philosopher
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.41"/>
					
					
					will not hold aloof from making him a friend and
					cherishing him, nor will he be afraid of being called
					a courtier and a toady.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>For those of men who too much Cypris shun
					</l>
                  <l>Are mad as those who follow her too much;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hipp.</hi> 115, and Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Flor.</hi> 63. 3; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 493.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					and so are those who take that attitude towards
					friendship with famous men and leaders. Hence,
					while the philosopher who abstains from public
					affairs will not avoid such men, yet one who is interested in public life will even go to them with
					open arms ; he will not annoy them against their
					will, nor will he pitch his camp in their ears with
					inopportune sophistical disquisitions, but when they
					wish it, he will be glad to converse and spend his
					leisure with them and eager to associate with them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The field I sow is twelve days' journey round ;
					</l>
                  <l>Berecynthian land;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aesch. <hi rend="italics">Niobe</hi>, Frag. 153, Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 52. The speaker is Tantalus. The Berecynthian land is near Mount Berecynthus in Phrygia.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					if this speaker was not merely a lover of agriculture
					but also a lover of his fellow men, he would find more
					pleasure in sowing the field which could feed so many
					men than in sowing that little plot of Antisthenes'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Xen. <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 3. 8, where Antisthenes says that his land is hardly enough to furnish sand to sprinkle Autolycus with before wrestling.</note>
					which would hardly have been big enough for
					Autolycus to wrestle in ; but if [he meant] : <q direct="unspecified">I sow
						all this in order that I may subjugate the whole
						inhabited world,</q> I deprecate the sentiment.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text is very corrupt, but the general course of the argument based upon the lines supposed to have been spoken by Tantalus may very well have been what is given in the translation. If the rich and powerful use their advantages for the common good of men, they are worthy of the philosopher's attention, but not so if they use their resources for purely selfish ends. See critical note, p. 42.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.43"/>
					
					
					And yet Epicurus, who places happiness in the
					deepest quiet, as in a sheltered and landlocked
					harbour, says that it is not only nobler, but also
					pleasanter, to confer than to receive benefits.
					<quote rend="blockquote">For chiefest joy doth gracious kindness give.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably an iambic trimeter. See Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 495.</note>
               </quote>
					Surely he was wise who gave the Graces the names
					Agla&iuml;a (Splendour), Euphrosyn&ecirc; (Gladness), and
					Thalia (Good-cheer) ; for the delight and joy are
					greater and purer for him who does the gracious
					act. And therefore people are often ashamed to
					receive benefits, but are always delighted to confer
					them ; and they who make those men good upon
					whom many depend confer benefits upon many ;
					and, on the contrary, the slanderers, backbiters,
					and flatterers who constantly corrupt rulers or kings
					or tyrants, are driven away and punished by everyone, as if they were putting deadly poison, not into
					a single cup, but into the public fountain which,
					as they see, everyone uses. Therefore, just as
					people laugh when the flatterers of Callias are ridiculed in comedy, those flatterers of whom Eupolis
					says<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Flatterers</hi>, by Eupolis; Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. p. 303.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>No fire, no, and no weapon,
					</l>
                  <l>Be it of bronze or of iron,
					</l>
                  <l>Keeps them from flocking to dinner,</l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.45"/>
					
					
					but the friends and intimates of the tyrant Apollodorus, of Phalaris, and of Dionysius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cruel tyrants of Cassandreia, Acragas, and Syracuse respectively.</note> they bastinadoed, tortured, and burned, and made them
					for ever polluted and accursed, since the former had
					done harm to one man, but the latter through one,
					the ruler, to many. So the philosophers who associate with persons in private station make those
					individuals inoffensive, harmless, and gentle towards
					themselves, but he who removes evil from the character of a ruler, or directs his mind towards what is
					right, philosophizes, as it were, in the public interest
					and corrects the general power by which all are
					governed. States pay reverence and honour to their
					priests because they ask blessings from the gods, not
					for themselves, their friends, and their families alone,
					but for all the citizens in common; and yet the
					priests do not make the gods givers of blessings, for
					they are such by nature ; the priests merely invoke
					them. But philosophers who associate with rulers
					do make them more just, more moderate, and more
					eager to do good, so that it is very likely that they
					are also happier.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>And I think a lyre-maker would be more willing
					and eager to make a lyre if he knew that the future
					owner of that lyre was to build the walls of the city
					of Thebes, as Amphion did,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">According to the legend, when Amphion played on his lyre, the stones of their own accord formed the walls of Thebes.</note> or, like Thales,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nothing is known of a musician or poet Thales. The musician Thaletas is said to have taught the lawgiver Lycurgus, but we do not hear of his putting an end to faction at Sparta.</note> was to
					put an end to faction among the Lacedaemonians by
					the music of his charms and his exhortations ; and a
					carpenter likewise in making a tiller would be more
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.47"/>
					
					
					pleased if he knew that it would steer the flagship
					of Themistocles fighting in defence of Hellas, or that
					of Pompey when he overcame the pirates. WTiat,
					then, do you imagine the philosopher thinks about
					his teaching, when he reflects that the statesman
					or ruler who accepts it will be a public blessing
					by dispensing justice, making laws, punishing the
					wicked, and making the orderly and the good to
					prosper ? And I imagine that a clever shipbuilder,
					too, would take greater pleasure in making a tiller
					if he knew that it was to steer the Argo, <q direct="unspecified">the concern
						of all,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xii. 70.</note> and a carpenter would not be so eager to
					make a plough or a wagon as the <hi rend="italics">axones</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In his <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, xxv., Plutarch says that Solon's laws were originally inscribed on revolving wooden tablets (<hi rend="italics">axones</hi>) in wooden framers. The <hi rend="italics">axones</hi> were set up in the Royal Stoa. Toward the end of the fifth century, the wooden text having disintegrated and the laws having been modified, a new edition of Solon's laws was inscribed on both sides of a marble wall built in the Royal Stoa and of this a fragment has recently come to light in the Athenian Agora. See J. H. Oliver, <hi rend="italics">Hesperia</hi>, iv. 5 ff., whose views are represented in the above statement.</note> on which
					the laws of Solon were to be engraved. And surely
					the teachings of philosophers, if they are firmly
					engraved in the souls of rulers and statesmen and
					control them, acquire the force of laws ; and that is
					why Plato sailed to Sicily, in the hope that his
					teachings would produce laws and actions in the
					government of Dionysius ; but he found Dionysius,
					like a book which is erased and written over, already
					befouled with stains and incapable of losing the dye
					of his tyranny, since by length of time it had become
					deeply fixed and hard to wash out. No, it is while
					men are still at their best that they should accept
					the worthy teachings.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>