<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De sera numinis vindicta</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.107">
      <body>
         <head>Concerning such whom god is slow to punish.
				<lb/> Patrocleas, Plutarch, Timon, Olympicus.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.140"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>THESE and such like things, O Quintus! when Epicurus had spoken, before any person could return an
				answer, while we were busy at the farther end of the portico,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The scene of the dialogue is laid in the temple of Delphi. (G.)</note> he flung away in great haste. However, we could
				not but in some measure admire at the odd behavior of the
				man, though without taking any farther notice of it in
				words; and therefore, after we had gazed a while one upon
				another, we returned to walk as we were singled out in company before. At this time Patrocleas first breaking silence,
				How say ye, gentlemen? said he: if you think fitting, why
				may not we discuss this question of the last proposer as
				well in his absence as if he were present? To whom
				Timon replying, Surely, said he, it would but ill become
				us, if at us he aimed upon his departure, to neglect the
				arrow sticking in our sides. For Brasidas, as history reports, drawing forth the javelin out of his own body, with
				the same javelin not only wounded him that threw it, but
				slew him outright. But as for ourselves, we surely have no
				need to revenge ourselves on them that pelt us with absurd
				and fallacious reasonings; but it will be sufficient that we
				shake them off before our opinion has taken hold of them.
				Then, said I, which of his sayings is it that has given you
				the greatest cause to be moved? For the man dragged
				into his discourse many things confusedly, and nothing in
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.141"/>
				
				order; but gleaning up and down from this and the other
				place, as it were in the transports of his wrath and scurrility, he then poured the whole in one torrent of abuse
				upon the providence of God.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>To which Patrocleas: The slowness of the Supreme
				Deity and his procrastination in reference to the punishment of the wicked have long perplexed my thoughts; but
				now, puzzled by these arguments which he produces, I
				find myself as it were a stranger to the opinion, and newly
				beginning again to learn. For a long time I could not with
				patience hear that expression of Euripides,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Does he delay and slowly move;
				</l>
                     <l>'Tis but the nature of the Gods above.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orestes, 420.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For indeed it becomes not the Supreme Deity to be remiss
					in any thing, but more especially in the prosecution of the
					wicked, since they themselves are no way negligent or
					dilatory in doing mischief, but are always driven on by the
					most rapid impetuosities of their passions to acts of injustice. For certainly, according to the saying of Thucydides,
					that revenge which follows injury closest at the heels presently puts a stop to the progress of such as make advantage
					of successful wickedness.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the speech of Cleon, Thuc. III. 38.</note> Therefore there is no debt
					with so much prejudice put off, as that of justice. For it
					weakens the hopes of the person wronged and renders him
					comfortless and pensive, but heightens the boldness and
					daring insolence of the oppressor; whereas, on the other
					side, those punishments and chastisements that immediately
					withstand presuming violence not only restrain the committing of future outrages, but more especially bring along
					with them a particular comfort and satisfaction to the sufferers. Which makes me no less troubled at the saying
					of Bias, which frequently comes into my mind. For thus
					he spake once to a notorious reprobate: It is not that I
					doubt thou wilt suffer the just reward of thy wickedness,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.142"/>
					
					but I fear that I myself shall not live to see it. For what
					did the punishment of Aristocrates avail the Messenians
					who were killed before it came to pass? He, having betrayed them at the battle of Taphrus yet remained undetected for above twenty years together, and all that while
					reigned king of the Arcadians, till at length, discovered and
					apprehended, he received the merited recompense of his
					treachery. But alas! they whom he had betrayed were all
					dead at the same time. Or when the Orchomenians had
					lost their children, their friends, and familiar acquaintance
					through the treachery of Lyciscus, what consolation was it
					to them, that many years after a foul distemper seized the
					traitor, and fed upon his body till it had consumed his
					putrefied flesh?&mdash;who, as often as he dipped and bathed
					his feet in the river, with horrid oaths and execrations
					prayed that his members might rot if he had been guilty
					of treachery or any other villany. Nor was it possible
					even for the children's children of the Athenians who had
					been murdered long before, to behold the bodies of those
					sacrilegious caitiffs torn out of their graves and transported
					beyond the confines of their native soil. Whence, in my
					opinion, Euripides absurdly makes use of these expressions, to divert a man from wickedness:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thou fear'st heav'n, thou fearest it in vain;
					</l>
                     <l>Justice is not so hasty, foolish man,
					</l>
                     <l>To pierce thy heart, or with contagious wound
					</l>
                     <l>Or thee or weaker mortals to confound;
					</l>
                     <l>But with slow pace and silent feet his doom
					</l>
                     <l>O'ertakes the sinner, when his time is come.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And I am apt to persuade myself that upon these and no
					other considerations it is, that wicked men encourage and
					give themselves the liberty to attempt and commit all manner of impieties, seeing that the fruit which injustice yields
					is soon ripe, and offers itself early to the gatherer's hand,
					whereas punishment comes late, and lagging long behind
					the pleasure of enjoyment.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.143"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>After Patrocleas had thus discoursed, Olympicus
				taking him up, There is this farther, said he, O Patrocleas!
				which thou shouldst have taken notice of; for how great
				an inconveniency and absurdity arises besides from these
				delays and procrastinations of divine justice! For the
				slowness of its execution takes away the belief of providence; and the wicked, perceiving that calamity does not
				presently follow at the heels of every enormous crime, but
				a long time after, look upon their calamity as a misfortune,
				and calling it chance, not punishment, are nothing at all
				thereby reformed; troubled indeed they well may be at the
				dire accident befallen them, but they never repent of the
				villanies they have committed. For as, in the case of
				horse, the lashing and spurring that immediately pursue
				the transgression correct and reduce him to his duty, but
				all the tugging at the bit and shouting which are late and
				out of time seem to be inflicted for some other reason than
				to teach or instruct, the animal being thereby put to pain
				without understanding his error; in like manner, were the
				impieties of enormous transgressors and heinous offenders
				singly scourged and repressed by immediate severity, it
				would be most likely<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">I follow Wyttenbach's emendation <foreign lang="greek">ma/list' a)/n</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">mo/lis a)/n</foreign>. (G.)</note> to bring them to a sense of their
				folly, humble them, and strike them with an awe of the
				Divine Being, whom they find with a watchful eye beholding the actions and passions of men, and feel to be no
				dilatory but a speedy avenger of iniquity; whereas that
				remiss and slow-paced justice (as Euripides describes it)
				that falls upon the wicked by accident, by reason of its
				uncertainty, ill-timed delay, and disorderly motion, seems
				rather to resemble chance than providence. So that I
				cannot conceive what benefit there is in these millstones
				of the Gods which are said to grind so late,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Referring to the verse, <foreign lang="greek">)*oye\ qew=n a)le/ousi mu/loi, a)le/ousi de\ lepta/</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">the mills of the Gods grind late, but they grind fine.</hi> (G.)</note> as thereby
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.144"/>
				
				celestial punishment is obscured, and the awe of evil doing
				rendered vain and despicable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>These things thus uttered, while I was in a deep
				meditation of what he had said, Timon interposed. Is it
				your pleasure. said he, that I shall give the finishing stroke
				to the difficulties of this knotty question, or shall I first
				permit him to argue in opposition to what has been propounded already? Nay then, said I, to what purpose is it
				to let in a third wave to drown the argument, if one be
				not able to repel or avoid the objections already made
				to begin therefore, as from the Vestal hearth, from that
				ancient circumspection and reverence which our ancestors,
				being Academic philosophers also, bare to the Supreme
				Godhead, we shall utterly decline to speak of that mysterious Being as if we could presume to utter positively any
				thing concerning it. For though it may be borne withal,
				for men unskilled in music to talk at random of notes and
				harmony, or for such as never experienced warfare to discourse of arms and military affairs; yet it would be a bold
				and daring arrogance in us, that are but mortal men, to
				dive too far into the incomprehensible mysteries of Deities
				and Daemons,&mdash;just as if persons void of knowledge
				should undertake to judge of the methods and reason of
				cunning artists by slight opinions and probable conjectures
				of their own. And while one that understands nothing of
				science finds it hard to give a reason why the physician did
				not let blood before but afterwards, or why he did not bathe
				his patient yesterday but to-day; it cannot be that it is safe
				or easy for a mortal to speak otherwise of the Supreme
				Deity than only this, that he alone it is who knows the
				most convenient time to apply most proper corrosives for
				the cure of sin and impiety, and to administer punishments
				as medicaments to every transgressor, yet being not confined to an equal quality and measure common to all distempers, nor to one and the same time. Now that the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.145"/>
				
				medicine of the soul which is called justice is the most
				transcendent of all sciences, besides ten thousand other
				witnesses, even Pindar himself testifies, where he gives to
				God, the ruler and lord of all things, the title of the most
				perfect artificer, as being the grand author and distributer
				of Justice, to whom it properly belongs to determine at
				what time, in what manner, and to what degree to punish
				every particular offender. And Plato asserts that Minos,
				being the son of Jupiter, was the disciple of his father to
				learn this science; intimating thereby that it is impossible
				for any other than a scholar, bred up in the school of equity, rightly to behave himself in the administration of justice,
				or to make a true judgment of another whether he does
				well or no. For the laws which are constituted by men do
				not always prescribe that which is unquestionable and simply decent, or of which the reason is altogether without
				exception perspicuous, in regard that some of their ordinances seem to be on purpose ridiculously contrived; particularly those which in Lacedaemon the Ephori ordain at
				their first entering into the magistracy, that no man suffer
				the hair of his upper lip to grow, and that they shall be
				obedient to the laws to the end they may not seem grievous
				to them. So the Romans, when they asserted the freedom
				of any one, cast a slender rod upon his body; and when
				they make their last wills and testaments, some they leave
				to be their heirs, while to others they sell their estates;
				which seems to be altogether contrary to reason. But that
				of Solon is most absurd, who, when a city is up in arms
				and all in sedition, brands with infamy the person who
				stands neuter and adheres to neither party. And thus a
				man that apprehends not the reason of the lawgiver, or the
				cause why such and such things are so prescribed, might
				number up several absurdities of many laws. What wonder then, since the actions of men are so difficult to be understood, if it be no less difficult to determine concerning
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.146"/>
				
				the Gods, wherefore they inflict their punishments upon
				sinners, sometimes later, sometimes sooner.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Nor do I allege these things as a pretence to avoid
				the dispute, but to secure the pardon which I beg, to the
				end that our discourse, having a regard (as it were) to some
				port or refuge, may proceed the more boldly in producing
				probable circumstances to clear the doubt. But first consider this; that God, according to Plato, when he set himself before the eyes of the whole world as the exemplar of
				all that was good and holy, granted human virtue, by which
				man is in some measure rendered like himself, unto those
				that are able to follow the Deity by imitation. For universal Nature, being at first void of order, received its first
				impulse to change and to be formed into a world, by being
				made to resemble and (as it were) partake of that idea and
				virtue which is in God. And the self-same Plato asserts,
				that Nature first kindled the sense of seeing within us, to
				the end that the soul, by the sight and admiration of the
				heavenly bodies, being accustomed to love and embrace
				decency and order, might be induced to hate the disorderly
				motions of wild and raving passions, and avoid levity and
				rashness and dependence upon chance, as the original of
				all improbity and vice. For there is no greater benefit that
				men can enjoy from God, than, by the imitation and pursuit
				of those perfections and that sanctity which is in him, to
				be excited to the study of virtue. Therefore God, with
				forbearance and at leisure, inflicts his punishment upon the
				wicked; not that he is afraid of committing an error or of
				repenting should he accelerate his indignation; but to
				eradicate that brutish and eager desire of revenge that
				reigns in human breasts, and to teach us that we are not
				in the heat of fury, or when our anger heaving and palpitating boils up above our understanding, to fall upon. those
				who have done us an injury, like those who seek to gratify
				a vehement thirst or craving appetite, but that we should,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.147"/>
				
				in imitation of this mildness and forbearance, wait with
				due composure of mind before we proceed to chastisement
				or correction, till such sufficient time for consideration is
				taken as shall allow the least possible room for repentance.
				For, as Socrates observed, it is far the lesser mischief for a
				man distempered with ebriety and gluttony to drink puddle-water, than, when the mind is disturbed and over-charged
				with anger and fury, before it be settled and become limpid
				again, for a man to seek the satiating his revenge upon
				the body of his friend or kinsman. For it is not the revenge which is the nearest to injury, as Thucydides says,
				but rather that which is the most remote from it, that observes the most convenient opportunity. For as anger,
				according to that of Melanthius,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quite from the brain transplants the wit,
				</l>
                     <l>Vile acts designing to commit;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so reason does that which is just and moderate, laying passion and fury aside. Whence it comes to pass that men,
					giving ear to human examples, become more mansuete and
					gentle; as when they hear how Plato, holding his cudgel
					over his page's shoulders, as himself relates, paused a good
					while, correcting his own anger; and how in like manner
					Archytas, observing the sloth and wilful negligence of his
					servants in the field, and perceiving his passion to rise at a
					more than usual rate, did nothing at all; but as he went
					away, It is your good fortune, said he, that ye have angered
					me. If then the savings of men when called to mind, and
					their actions being told, have such a power to mitigate the
					roughness and vehemency of wrath, much more becomes it
					us, beholding God, with whom there is neither dread nor
					repentance of any thing, deferring nevertheless his punishments to future time and admitting delay, to be cautious
					and circumspect in these matters, and to deem as a divine
					part of virtue that mildness and long-suffering of which
					God affords us an example, while by punishing he reforms
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.148"/>
					
					some few, but by slowly punishing he helpeth and admonisheth many.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>In the second place, therefore, let us consider this,
				that human punishments of injuries regard no more than
				that the party suffer in his turn, and are satisfied when
				the offender has suffered according to his merit; and
				farther they never proceed. Which is the reason that
				they run after provocations, like dogs that bark in their
				fury, and immediately pursue the injury as soon as committed. But probable it is that God, whatever distempered soul it be which he prosecutes with his divine justice,
				observes the motions and inclinations of it, whether they
				be such as tend to repentance, and allows time for the
				reformation of those whose wickedness is neither invincible nor incorrigible. For, since he well knows what a
				proportion of virtue souls carry along with them from himself when they come into the world, and how strong and
				vigorous their innate and primitive good yet continues,&mdash;while wickedness buds forth only preternaturally upon the
				corruption of bad diet and evil conversation, and even
				then some souls recover again to perfect cure or an indifferent habitude,&mdash;therefore he doth not make haste to
				inflict his punishments alike upon all. But those that are
				incurable he presently lops off and deprives of life, deeming it altogether hurtful to others, but most baneful to
				themselves, to be always wallowing in wickedness. But
				as for those who may probably be thought to transgress
				rather out of ignorance of what is virtuous and good, than
				through choice of what is foul and vicious, he grants them
				time to turn; but if they remain obdurate, then likewise
				he inflicts his punishments upon them; for he has no fear
				lest they should escape.</p>
            <p>Now let us consider how oft the characters and lives of
					men are changed; for which reason, the character is called
					<foreign lang="greek">tro/pos</foreign>, as being the <hi rend="italics">changeable</hi> part, and also <foreign lang="greek">h)=qos</foreign>, since <hi rend="italics">cus-</hi>
					
					          <pb id="v.4.p.149"/>
					
					          <hi rend="italics">tom</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">e)/qos</foreign>) chiefly prevails in it and rules with the greatest
					power when it has seized upon it. Therefore I am of
					opinion, that the ancients reported Cecrops to have had
					two bodies, not, as some believe, because of a good king
					he became a merciless and dragon-like tyrant, but rather,
					on the contrary, for that being at first both cruel and
					formidable, afterwards he became a most mild and gentle
					prince. However, if this be uncertain, yet we know both
					Gelo and Hiero the Sicilians, and Pisistratus the son of
					Hippocrates, who, having obtained the sovereignty by violence and wickedness, made a virtuous use of their power,
					and coming unjustly to the throne, became moderate rulers
					and beneficial to the public. For, by recommending wholesome laws and the exercise of useful tillage to their subjects, they reduced them from idle scoffers and talkative
					romancers to be modest citizens and industrious good husbands. And as for Gelo, after he had been successful in
					his war and vanquished the Carthaginians, he refused to
					grant them the peace which they sued for, unless they
					would consent to have it inserted in their articles that they
					would surcease from sacrificing their children to Saturn.</p>
            <p>Over Megalopolis Lydiadas was tyrant; but then, even
					in the time of his tyranny, changing his manners and
					maxims of government and growing into a hatred of injustice, he restored to the citizens their laws, and fighting
					for his country against his own and his subjects' enemies,
					fell an illustrious victim for his country's welfare. Now if
					any one, bearing an antipathy to Miltiades or Cimon, had
					slain the one tyrannizing in the Chersonese or the other
					committing incest with his own sister, or had expelled
					Themistocles out of Athens at what time he lay rioting
					and revelling in the market-place and affronting all that
					came near him, according to the sentence afterwards pronounced against Alcibiades, had we not lost Marathon, the
					Eurymedon, and lovely Artemisium,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.150"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where the Athenian youth
					</l>
                     <l>The famed foundations of their freedom laid?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Pindar.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For great and lofty geniuses produce nothing that is mean
					and little; the innate smartness of their parts will not
					endure the vigor and activity of their spirits to grow lazy;
					but they are tossed to and again, as with the waves, by the
					rolling motions of their own inordinate desire, till at length
					they arrive to a stable and settled constitution of manners.
					Therefore, as a person that is unskilful in husbandry
					would by no means make choice of a piece of ground
					quite overrun with brakes and weeds, abounding with wild
					beasts, running streams, and mud; while, to him who hath
					learnt to understand the nature of the earth, these are certain symptoms of the softness and fertility of the soil; thus
					great geniuses many times produce many absurd and vile
					enormities, of which we not enduring the rugged and
					uneasy vexation, are presently for pruning and lopping off
					the lawless transgressors. But the more prudent judge,
					who discerns the abounding goodness and generosity
					covertly residing in those transcendent geniuses, waits the
					co-operating age and season for reason and virtue to exert
					themselves, and gathers the ripe fruit when Nature has
					matured it. And thus much as to those particulars.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Now to come to another part of our discourse, do you
				not believe that some of the Greeks did very prudently to
				register that law in Egypt among their own, whereby it is
				enacted that, if a woman with child be sentenced to die,
				she shall be reprieved till she be delivered? All the reason
				in the world, you will say. Then, say I, though a man
				cannot bring forth children, yet if he be able, by the assistance of Time, to reveal any hidden action or conspiracy,
				or to discover some concealed mischief, or to be author of
				some wholesome piece of advice,&mdash;or suppose that in time
				he may produce some necessary and useful invention,&mdash;is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.151"/>
				
				it not better to delay the punishment and expect the benefit,
				than hastily to rid him out of the world? It seems so to me,
				said I. And truly you are in the right, replied Patrocleas;
				for let us consider, had Dionysius at the beginning of his
				tyranny suffered according to his merits, never would any
				of the Greeks have re-inhabited Sicily, laid waste by the
				Carthaginians. Nor would the Greeks have repossessed
				Apollonia, nor Anactorium, nor the peninsula of the
				Leucadians, had not Periander's execution been delayed
				for a long time. And if I mistake not, it was to the delay
				of Cassander's punishment that the city of Thebes was
				beholden for her recovery from desolation. But the most
				of those barbarians who assisted at the sacrilegious plunder of
				this temple,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, in the Sacred or Phocian war, 357-346 B.C. (G.)</note> following Timoleon into Sicily, after
				they had vanquished the Carthaginians and dissolved the
				tyrannical government of that island, wicked as they were,
				came all to a wicked end. So the Deity makes use of
				some wicked persons as common executioners to punish
				the wickedness of others, and then destroys those instruments of his wrath,&mdash;which I believe to be true of most
				tyrants. For as the gall of a hyena and the rennet of
				a sea-calf&mdash;both filthy monsters&mdash;contain something in
				them for the cure of diseases; so when some people deserve a sharp and biting punishment, God, subjecting them
				to the implacable severity of some certain tyrant or the
				cruel oppression of some ruler, does not remove either
				the torment or the trouble, till he has cured and purified
				the distempered nation. Such a sort of physic was Phalaris to the Agrigentines, and Marius to the Romans. And
				God expressly foretold the Sicyonians how much their city
				stood in need of most severe chastisement, when, after
				they had violently ravished out of the hands of the Cleonaeans Teletias, a young lad who had been crowned at the
				Pythian games, they tore him limb from limb, as their own
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.152"/>
				
				fellow-citizen. Therefore Orthagoras the tyrant, and after
				him Myro and Clisthenes, put an end to the luxury and
				lasciviousness of the Sicyonians; but the Cleonaeans, not
				having the good fortune to meet with the same cure, went
				all to wreck. To this purpose, hear what Homer says:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>From parent vile by far the better son
				</l>
                     <l>Did spring, whom various virtues did renown</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XV. 641.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet we do not find that ever the son of Copreus performed any famous or memorable achievement; but the
					offspring of Sisyphus, Autolycus, and Phlegyas flourished
					among the number of the most famous and virtuous princes.
					Pericles at Athens descended from an accursed family; and
					Pompey the Great at Rome was the son of Strabo, whose
					dead body the Roman people, in the height of their hatred
					conceived against him when alive, cast forth into the street
					and trampled in the dirt. Where is the absurdity then,&mdash;
					as the husbandman never cuts away the thorn till it injures
					the asparagus, or as the Libyans never burn the stalks till
					they have gathered all the ladanum,&mdash;if God never extirpates the evil and thorny root of a renowned and royal
					race before he has gathered from it the mature and proper
					fruit? For it would have been far better for the Phocians
					to have lost ten thousand of Iphitus's horses and oxen, or
					a far greater sum in gold and silver from the temple of
					Delphi, than that Ulysses and Aesculapius should not have
					been born, and those many others who, of wicked and
					vicious men, became highly virtuous and beneficial to their
					country.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>And should we not think it better to inflict deserved
				punishments in due season and by convenient means,
				than hastily and rashly when a man is in the heat and
				hurry of passion? Witness the example of Callippus,
				who, having stabbed Dio under the pretence of being his
				friend, was himself soon after slain by Dio's intimates with
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.153"/>
				
				the same dagger. Thus again, when Mitius of Argos was
				slain in a city tumult, the brazen statue which stood in the
				market-place, soon after, at the time of the public shows,
				fell down upon the murderer's head and killed him. What
				befell Bessus the Paeonian, and Aristo the Oetaean, chief
				commander of the foreign soldiers, I suppose you understood full well, Patrocleas. Not I, by Jove, said he, but I
				desire to know. Well then, I say, this Aristo, having with
				permission of the tyrants carried away the jewels and
				ornaments belonging to Eriphyle, which lay deposited in
				this temple, made a present of them to his wife. The
				punishment of this was that the son, being highly incensed
				against his mother, for what reason it matters not, set fire
				to his father's house, and burned it to the ground, with all
				the family that were in it.</p>
            <p>As for Bessus, it seems he killed his own father, and
					the murder lay concealed a long time. At length being
					invited to supper among strangers, after he had so loosened
					a swallow's nest with his spear that it fell down, he killed
					all the young ones. Upon which, being asked by the
					guests that were present, what injury the swallows had
					done him that he should commit such an irregular act;
					Did you not hear, said he, these cursed swallows, how they
					clamored and made a noise, false witnesses as they were,
					that I had long ago killed my father? This answer struck
					the rest of the guests with so much wonder, that, after a
					due pondering upon his words, they made known the
					whole story to the king. Upon which, the matter being
					dived into, Bessus was brought to condign punishment.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>These things I have alleged, as it was but reason,
				upon a supposition that there is a forbearance of inflicting punishment upon the wicked. As for what remains,
				it behooves us to listen to Hesiod, where he asserts,&mdash;not
				like Plato, that punishment is a suffering which accompanies injustice,&mdash;but that it is of the same age with it,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.154"/>
				
				and arises from the same place and root. For, says he,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bad counsel, so the Gods ordain,
				</l>
                     <l>Is most of all the adviser's bane.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in another place,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He that his neighbor's harm contrives, his art
					</l>
                     <l>Contrives the mischief 'gainst his own false heart.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 265.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is reported that the cantharis fly, by a certain kind
					of contrariety, carries within itself the cure of the wound
					which it inflicts. On the other side wickedness, at the
					same time it is committed, engendering its own vexation
					and torment, not at last, but at the very instant of the injury offered, suffers the reward of the injustice it has done.
					And as every malefactor who suffers in his body bears his
					own cross to the place of his execution, so are all the
					various torments of various wicked actions prepared by
					wickedness herself. Such a diligent architectress of a
					miserable and wretched life is wickedness, wherein shame
					is still accompanied with a thousand terrors and commotions of the mind, incessant repentance, and never-ceasing
					tumults of the spirits. However, there are some people
					that differ little or nothing from children, who, many times
					beholding malefactors upon the stage, in their gilded vestments and short purple cloaks, dancing with crowns upon
					their heads, admire and look upon them as the most happy
					persons in the world, till they see them gored and lashed,
					and flames of fire curling from underneath their sumptuous
					and gaudy garments. Thus there are many wicked men,
					surrounded with numerous families, splendid in the pomp
					of magistracy, and illustrious for the greatness of their
					power, whose punishments never display themselves till
					those glorious persons come to be the public spectacles of
					the people, either slain and lying weltering in their blood,
					or else standing on the top of the rock, ready to be tumbled headlong down the precipice; which indeed cannot
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.155"/>
					
					so well be said to be a punishment, as the consummation
					and perfection of punishment.</p>
            <p>Moreover, as Herodicus the Selymbrian, falling into a
					consumption, the most incurable of all diseases, was the
					first who intermixed the gymnastic art with the science of
					physic (as Plato relates), and in so doing did spin out
					in length a tedious time of dying, as well for himself as
					for others laboring under the same distemper; in like
					manner some wicked men who flatter themselves to have
					escaped the present punishment, not after a longer time, but
					for a longer time, endure a more lasting, not a slower
					punishment; not punished with old age, but growing old
					under the tribulation of tormenting affliction. When I
					speak of a long time I speak in reference to ourselves.
					For as to the Gods, every distance and distinction of human life is nothing; and to say <q direct="unspecified">now, and not thirty years
						ago</q> is the same thing as to say that such a malefactor
					should be tormented or hanged in the afternoon and not in
					the morning;&mdash;more especially since a man is but shut up
					in this life, like a close prisoner in a gaol, from whence it
					is impossible to make an escape, while yet we feast and
					banquet, are full of business, receive rewards and honors
					and sport. Though certainly these are but like the sports
					of those that play at dice or draughts in the gaol, while the
					rope all the while hangs over their heads.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>So that what should hinder me from asserting, that
				they who are condemned to die and shut up in prison are
				not truly punished till the executioner has chopped off
				their heads, or that he who has drunk hemlock, and then
				walks about and stays till a heaviness seizes his limbs, has
				suffered no punishment before the extinction of his natural
				heat and the coagulation of his blood deprive him of his
				senses,&mdash;that is to say, if we deem the last moment of the
				punishment only to be the punishment, and omit the commotions, terrors, apprehensions, and embitterments of repentance,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.156"/>
				
				 with which every malefactor and all wicked men
				are teased upon the committing of any heinous crime?
				But this is to deny the fish to be taken that has swallowed the hook, before we see it boiled and cut into pieces
				by the cook; for every offender is within the gripes of the
				law, so soon as he has committed the crime and has swallowed the sweet bait of injustice, while his conscience
				within, tearing and gnawing upon his vitals, allows him no
				rest:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Like the swift tunny, frighted from his prey,
				</l>
                     <l>Rolling and plunging in the angered sea.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the daring rashness and precipitate boldness of iniquity
					continue violent and active till the fact be perpetrated;
					but then the passion, like a surceasing tempest, growing
					slack and weak, surrenders itself to superstitious fears and
					terrors. So that Stesichorus may seem to have composed
					the dream of Clytemnestra, to set forth the event and truth
					of things:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then seemed a dragon to draw near,
					</l>
                     <l>With mattery blood all on his head besmeared;
					</l>
                     <l>Therefrom the king Plisthenides appeared.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For visions in dreams, noon-day apparitions, oracles, descents into hell, and whatever objects else which may be
					thought to be transmitted from heaven, raise continual
					tempests and horrors in the very souls of the guilty. Thus
					it is reported that Apollodorus in a dream beheld himself
					flayed by the Scythians and then boiled, and that his heart,
					speaking to him out of the kettle, uttered these words, I
					am the cause thou sufferest all this. And another time,
					that he saw his daughters run about him, their bodies
					burning and all in a flame. Hipparchus also, the son of
					Pisistratus, had a dream, that the Goddess Venus out of a
					certain phial flung blood in his face. The favorites of
					Ptolemy, surnamed the Thunderer, dreamed that they saw
					their master cited to the judgment-seat by Seleucus, where
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.157"/>
					
					wolves and vultures were his judges, and then distributing
					great quantities of flesh among his enemies. Pausanias,
					in the heat of his lust, sent for Cleonice, a free-born virgin
					of Byzantium, with an intention to have enjoyed her all
					night; but when she came, out of a strange sort of jealousy and perturbation for which he could give no reason,
					he stabbed her. This murder was attended with frightful
					visions; insomuch that his repose in the night was not
					only interrupted with the appearance of her shape, but
					still he thought he heard her uttering these lines:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To judgment-seat approach thou near, I say;
					</l>
                     <l>Wrong dealing is to men most hurtful aye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>After this the apparition still haunting him, he sailed to
					the oracle of the dead in Heraclea, and by propitiations,
					charms, and dirges, called up the ghost of the damsel;
					which, appearing before him, told him in few words, that
					he should be free from all his affrights and molestations
					upon his return to Lacedaemon; where he was no sooner
					arrived, but he died.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Therefore, if nothing befalls the soul after the expiration of this life, but death is the end of all reward and
				punishment, I might infer from thence rather that the Deity is remiss and indulgent in swiftly punishing the wicked
				and depriving them of life. For if a man shall assert
				that in the space of this life the wicked are no otherwise
				affected than by the convincement that crime is a fruitless
				and barren thing, that produces nothing of good, nothing
				worthy of esteem, from the many great and terrible combats and agonies of the mind, the consideration of these
				things altogether subverts the soul. As it is related that
				Lysimachus, being under the violent constraint of a parching thirst, surrendered up his person and his dominions to
				the Getae for a little drink; but after he had quenched his
				draught and found himself a captive, Shame of this wickedness of mine, cried he, that for so small a pleasure have
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.158"/>
				
				lost so great a kingdom. But it is a difficult thing for a
				man to resist the natural necessity of mortal passions.
				Yet when a man, either out of avarice, or ambition of
				civil honor and power, or to gratify his venereal desires,
				commits any enormous and heinous crime, after which, the
				thirst and rage of his passion being allayed, he comes to
				set before his eyes the ignominious and horrible passions
				tending to injustice still remaining, but sees nothing useful,
				nothing necessary, nothing conducible to make his life happy; may it not be probably conjectured that such a person
				is frequently solicited by these reflections to consider how
				rashly, either prompted by vain-glory, or for the sake of a
				lawless and barren pleasure, he has overthrown the noblest
				and greatest maxims of justice among men, and overflowed
				his life with shame and trouble? As Simonides jesting was
				wont to say, that the chest which he kept for money he
				found always full, but that which he kept for gratitude he
				found always empty; thus wicked men, contemplating
				their own wickedness, find it always void altogether and
				destitute of hope (since pleasure gives but a short and empty
				delight), but ever weighed down with fears and sorrows,
				ungrateful remembrances, suspicions of futurity, and distrusts of present accidents. Thus we hear Ino complaining upon the theatre, after her repentance of what she
				had done:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dear women, tell me, with what face
				</l>
                     <l>Shall I return to dwell with Athamas,
				</l>
                     <l>As if it ne'er had been my luckless fate
				</l>
                     <l>The worst of foul misdeeds to perpetrate?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Ino of Euripides, Frag. 403.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is it not reason to believe, that the soul of every wicked
					man revolves and reasons within itself, how by burying in
					oblivion former transgressions, and casting from itself the
					consciousness and the guilt of hitherto committed crimes,
					to fit frail mortality under her conduct for a new course of
					life? For there is nothing for a man to confide in, nothing
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.159"/>
					
					 but what vanishes like smoke, nothing durable or constant in whatever impiety proposes to itself,&mdash;unless, by
					Jove, we will allow the unjust and vicious to be sage philosophers,&mdash;but wherever eager avarice and voluptuousness, inexorable hatred, enmity, and improbity associate
					together, there you shall also be sure to find superstition
					nestling and herding with effeminacy and terror of death,
					a swift change of the most violent passions, and an arrogant ambition after undeserved honor. Such men as
					these stand in continual dread of their contemners and
					backbiters, they fear their applauders, believing themselves
					injured by their flatteries; and more especially, they are
					at enmity with bad men, because they are so free to extol
					those that seem good. However, that which hardens men
					to mischief soon cankers, grows brittle, and shivers in
					pieces like bad iron. So that in process of time, coming
					to understand themselves better and to be more sensible of
					their miscarriages, they disdain, abhor, and utterly disclaim
					their former course of life. And when we see how a
					wicked man who restores a trust or becomes security for
					his friend, or ambitious of honor contributes more largely
					to the benefits of his country, is immediately in a condition
					of repentance and sorry for what he has just done, by
					reason of the natural inclination of his mind to ramble
					and change; and how some men, being clapped and
					hummed upon the theatre, presently fall a weeping, their
					desire of glory relapsing into covetousness; we surely
					cannot believe that those which sacrificed the lives of men
					to the success of their tyrannies and conspiracies, as Apollodorus, or plundered their friends of their treasure and
					deprived them of their estates, as Glaucus the son of
					Epicydes, did not repent and abhor themselves, or that they
					were not sorry for the perpetration of such foul enormities. For my part, if it may be lawful for me to deliver
					my opinion, I believe there is no occasion either for the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.160"/>
					
					Gods or men to inflict their punishment upon the most
					wicked and sacrilegious offenders; seeing that the course
					of their own lives is sufficient to chastise their crimes,
					while they remain under the consternations and torments
					attending their impiety.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And now consider whether my discourse have not
				enlarged itself too far. To which Timon: Perhaps (said
				he) it may seem to have been too long, if we consider
				what remains behind, and the length of time required for
				the discussion of our other doubts. For now I am going
				about to put forward the last question, like a new champion, since we have contended already long enough upon
				the former. Now, as to what we have further to say, we
				find that Euripides delivers his mind freely, and censures
				the Gods for imputing the transgressions of forefathers
				unto their offspring. And I am apt to believe that even
				they who are most silent among us do the like. For if
				the offenders themselves have already received their reward, then there is no reason why the innocent should be
				punished, since it is not equal to punish even criminals
				twice for the same fact. But if remiss and careless, the
				Gods, omitting opportunely to inflict their penalties upon
				the wicked, send down their tardy rigor on the blameless,
				they do not well to repair their defective slowness by injustice. As it is reported of Aesop, that he came upon a
				time to Delphi, having brought along with him a great
				quantity of gold which Croesus had bestowed upon him,
				on purpose to offer a most magnificent oblation to the
				Gods, and with a design moreover to distribute among the
				priests and the people of Delphi four minas apiece. But
				there happening some disgust and difference between him
				and the Delphians, he performed his solemnity, but sent
				back his money to Sardis, not deeming those ungrateful
				people worthy of his bounty. Upon which the Delphians,
				laying their heads together, accused him of sacrilege, and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.161"/>
				
				then threw him down headlong from a steep and prodigious precipice, which is there, called Hyampia. Upon
				which it is reported that the Deity, being highly incensed
				against them for so horrid a murder, brought a famine
				upon the land, and infested the people with noisome diseases of all sorts; insomuch that they were constrained to
				make it their business to travel to all the general assemblies and places of public concourse in Greece, making
				public proclamation wherever they came, that, whoever
				they were that would demand justice for the death of
				Aesop, they were prepared to give him satisfaction and
				to undergo whatever penalty he should require. Three
				generations afterwards came one Idmon, a Samian, no way
				of kin or otherwise related to Aesop, but only descended
				from those who had purchased Aesop in Samos; to whom
				the Delphians paid those forfeitures which he demanded,
				and were delivered from all their pressing calamities. And
				from hence (by report) it was, that the punishment of sacrilegious persons was transferred from the rock Hyampia to
				that other cliff which bears the name of Nauplia.</p>
            <p>Neither is Alexander applauded by those who have the
					greatest esteem for his memory (of which number are we
					ourselves), who utterly laid waste the city of Branchidae,
					putting men, women, and children to the sword, for that
					their ancestors had long before delivered up the temple of
					Miletus. In like manner Agathocles, tyrant of Syracuse,
					when the Corcyraeans requested to know the reason of
					him, why he depopulated their island, deriding and scoffing
					at their demand, replied: For no other reason, by Jove,
					but because your forefathers entertained Ulysses. And
					when the islanders of Ithaca expostulated with him, asking why his soldiers carried away their sheep; because,
					said he, when your king came to our island, he put out
					the eyes of the shepherd himself. And therefore do you
					not think Apollo more extravagant than all these, for punishing
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.162"/>
					
					 so severely the Pheneatae by stopping up that profound and spacious receptacle of all those floods that now
					cover their country, upon a bare report that Hercules a
					thousand years ago took away the prophetic tripod and
					carried it to Pheneus?&mdash;or when he foretold to the Sybarites, that all their calamities should cease, upon condition
					they appeased the wrath of Leucadian Juno by enduring
					three ruinous calamities upon their country? Nor is it so
					long since, that the Locrians surceased to send their virgins
					to Troy;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who like the meanest slaves, exposed to scorn,
					</l>
                     <l>Barefoot, with limbs unclad, at earliest morn
					</l>
                     <l>Minerva's temple sweep; yet all the while,
					</l>
                     <l>No privilege has age from weary toil.
					</l>
                     <l>Nor, when with years decrepit, can they claim
					</l>
                     <l>The thinnest veil to hide their aged shame;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and all this to punish the lasciviousness of Ajax.</p>
            <p>Now where is the reason or justice of all this? Nor is
					the custom of the Thracians to be approved, who to this
					day abuse their wives in revenge of their cruelty to Orpheus. And with as little reason are the Barbarians about
					the river Po to be extolled, who once a year put themselves
					into mourning for the misfortune of Phaethon. And still
					more ridiculous than all this it would certainly be, when
					all those people that lived at the time took no notice of
					Phaethon's mischance, that they, who happened to be born
					five or ten generations after, should be so idle as to take
					up the custom of going into black and bewailing his downfall. However, in all these things there is nothing to be
					observed but mere folly; nothing pernicious, nor any thing
					dangerous. But as for the anger of the Gods, what reason
					can be given why their wrath should stop and conceal
					itself upon a sudden, like some certain rivers, and when
					all things seem to be forgot, should break forth upon
					others with so much fury, as not to be atoned but with
					some remarkable calamities?</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.163"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Upon that, so soon as he had done speaking, not a
				little afraid lest, if he should begin again, he would run
				himself into many more and greater absurdities, I asked:
				Do you believe, sir, all that you have said to be true?
				Then he: Though all that I have alleged may not be true,
				yet if only some part may be allowed for truth, do not you
				think there is the same difficulty still remaining in the
				question? It may be so, said I. And thus it is with those
				who labor under a vehement burning fever; for, whether
				covered with one blanket or many, the heat is still the
				same or very little different; yet for refreshment's sake it
				may be convenient sometimes to lighten the weight of the
				clothes; and if the patient refuse your courtesy, to let him
				alone. Yet I must tell you, the greatest part of these
				examples look like fables and fiction. Call to mind therefore the feast called Theoxenia lately celebrated, and that
				most noble portion which the public criers proclaim to be
				received as their due by the offspring of Pindar; and recollect with yourself, how majestic and grateful a mark of
				grandeur you look upon that to be. Truly, said he, I
				judge there is no man living who would not be sensible of
				the curiosity and elegancy of such an honor, displaying
				antiquity void of tincture and false glitter, after the Greek
				manner, unless he were such a brute that I may use the
				words of Pindar himself:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whose coal-black heart, from natural dross unpurged,
				</l>
                     <l>Had only by cold flames at first been forged.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I forbear, said I, to mention that proclamation
					not much unlike to this, usually made in Sparta,&mdash;<q direct="unspecified">After
						the Lesbian singer,</q>&mdash;in honor and memory of the ancient Terpander. But you, on the other side, deem yourself worthy to be preferred above all the rest of the
					Boeotians, as being of the noble race of the Opheltiadae;
					and among the Phocians you claim undoubted pre-eminence,
					for the sake of your ancestor Daiphantus. And, for my
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.164"/>
					
					part, I must acknowledge that you were one of the first
					who assisted me, as my second, against the Lycormaeans
					and Satilaeans, claiming the privilege of wearing crowns
					and the honor due by the laws of Greece to the descendants
					from Hercules; at what time I affirmed, that those honors
					and guerdons ought more especially to be preserved inviolable to the immediate progeny of Hercules, in regard
					that, though he were so great a benefactor to the Greeks,
					yet in his lifetime he was not thought worthy of any
					reward or return of gratitude. You recall to my remembrance, said he, a most noble contest, and worthy the
					debate of philosophy itself. Dismiss therefore, said I,
					that vehement humor of yours that excites you to accuse
					the Gods, nor take it ill, if many times celestial punishment discharges itself upon the offspring of the wicked
					and vicious; or else be not too much overjoyed or too forward to applaud those honors which are due to nobility of
					birth. For it becomes us, if we believe that the reward
					of virtue ought to be extended to posterity, by the same
					reason to take it for granted that punishment for impieties
					committed ought not to be stayed and cease any sooner,
					but that it should run forward at equal pace with the
					reward, which will in turn requite every man with what is
					his due. And therefore they that with pleasure behold
					the race of Cimon highly honored in Athens, but on the
					other side, fret and fume at the exilement of the posterity
					of Lachares or Ariston, are too remiss and oscitant, or
					rather too morose and over quarrelsome with the Deity
					itself, one while accusing the Divinity if the posterity of
					an unjust and wicked person seem to prosper in the world,
					another time no less moody and finding fault if it fall cut
					that the race of the wicked come to be utterly destroyed
					and extirpated from the earth. And thus, whether the
					children of the wicked or the children of the just fall
					under affliction, the case is all one to them; the Gods
					must suffer alike in their bad opinions.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.165"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>These, said I, are the preliminaries, which I would
				have you make use of against those choleric accusers and
				testy snarlers of whom I have given you warning. But
				now to take in hand once more, as it were, the first end of
				the bottom of thread, in this same dark discourse of the
				Gods, wherein there are so many windings and turnings
				and gloomy labyrinths, let us by degrees and with caution
				direct our steps to what is most likely and probable. For,
				even in those things which fall under our daily practice
				and management, we are many times at a loss to determine
				the undoubted and unquestioned truth. For example,
				what certain reason can be given for that custom amongst
				us, of ordering the children of parents that die of a consumption or a dropsy to sit with both their feet soaking in
				the water till the dead body be burnt? For people believe,
				that thereby the disease is prevented from becoming hereditary, and also that it is a charm to secure those children
				from it as long as they live. Again, what should be the
				reason, that if a goat take a piece of sea-holly in her
				mouth, the whole herd will stand still till the goat-herd
				come and take it out? Other hidden properties there are,
				which, by virtue of certain touches and transitions, pass
				from some bodies into others with incredible swiftness and
				often to incredible distances. But we are more apt to
				wonder at distances of time than those of space. And yet
				there is more reason to wonder, that Athens should be
				infected with an epidemic contagion taking its rise in
				Ethiopia, that Pericles should die and Thucydides be smitten with the infection, than that, upon the impiety of the
				Delphians and Sybarites, delayed vengeance should at
				length overtake their posterity. For these hidden powers
				and properties have their sacred connections and correspondences between their utmost endings and their first
				beginnings; of which although the causes be concealed
				from us, yet silently they bring to pass their proper effects.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.166"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Not but that there is a reason ready at hand for the
				public punishments showered down from heaven upon
				particular cities. For a city is a kind of entire thing and
				continued body, a certain sort of creature, never subject to
				the changes and alterations of age, nor varying through
				process of time from one thing to another, but always
				sympathizing and in unity with itself, and receiving the
				punishment or reward of whatever it does or has ever
				acted in common, so long as the community, which makes
				it a body and binds it together with the mutual bands of
				human benefit, preserves its unity. For he that goes about
				of one city to make many, and perhaps an infinite number,
				by distinguishing the intervals of time, seems to be like a
				person who would make several of one single man, because
				he is now grown elderly who before was a young man, and
				before that a mere stripling. Or rather, it resembles the
				method of disputing amongst the Epicharmians, the first
				authors of that manner of arguing called the increaser.
				For example: he that formerly ran in debt, although he
				never paid it, owes nothing now, as being become another
				man; and he that was invited yesterday to supper comes
				the next night an unbidden guest, for that he is quite
				another person. And indeed the distinctions of ages cause
				greater alterations in every one of us than commonly they
				do in cities. For he that has seen Athens may know it
				again thirty years after; the present manners, motions,
				pastimes, serious studies, their familiarities and marks of
				their displeasure, little or nothing differing from what formerly they were. But after a long absence there is many
				a man who, meeting his own familiar friend, hardly knows
				him again, by reason of the great alteration of his countenance and the change of his manners, which are so easily
				subject to the alterations of language, labor, and employment, all manner of accidents, and mutation of laws, that
				even they who are most usually conversant with him admire
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.167"/>
				
				 to see the strangeness and novelty of the change; and
				yet the man is reputed still to be the same from his birth
				to his decease. In the same manner does a city still remain the same; and for that reason we think it but justice,
				that a city should as well be obnoxious to the blame and
				reproach of its ancient inhabitants, as participate the glory
				of their former puissance and renown; else we shall throw
				every thing before we know it into the river of Heraclitus,
				into which (he says) no one can step twice,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Referring to the doctrine of Heraclitus, that all Nature is moving onward, and nothing is the same two successive moments. <q direct="unspecified">You cannot step twice into the same river,</q> he says. See Plat. Cratyl. p. 402 A. (G.)</note> since Nature
				by her changes is ever altering and transforming all things.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Now then, if a city be one entire and continued
				body, the same opinion is to be conceived of a race of
				men, depending upon one and the same beginning, and
				carrying along with it a certain power and communion of
				qualities; in regard that what is begotten cannot be thought
				to be severed from that which begets it, like a piece of
				workmanship from the artificer; the one being begotten
				of the person, the other framed by him. So that what is
				engendered is a part of the original from whence it sprung,
				whether meriting honor or deserving punishment. So that,
				were it not that I might be thought to be too sportive in a
				serious discourse, I would affirm, that the Athenians were
				more unjust to the statue of Cassander when they caused
				it to be melted down and defaced, and that the Syracusans
				were more rigorous to the dead carcass of Dionysius when
				they cast it forth of their own confines, than if they had
				punished their posterity; for that the statue did no way
				partake of the substance of Cassander, and the soul of
				Dionysius was absolutely departed from the body deceased.
				Whereas Nisaeus, Apollocrates, Antipater, Philip, and
				several others descended from wicked parents, still retained
				the most principal part of those who begot them, not lazily
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.168"/>
				
				and sluggishly dormant, but that very part by which they
				live, are nourished, act and move, and become rational and
				sensible creatures. Neither is there any thing of absurdity,
				if, being the offspring of such parents, they should retain
				many of their bad qualities. In short, therefore, I affirm
				that, as it is in the practice of physic, that whatever is
				wholesome and profitable is likewise just, and as he would
				be accounted ridiculous that should aver it to be an act of
				injustice to cauterize the thumb for the cure of the sciatica,
				or when the liver is imposthumated, to scarify the belly, or
				when the hoofs of laboring oxen are over tender, to anoint
				the tips of their horns; in the same manner is he to be
				laughed at who seeks for any other justice in the punishment of vice than the cure and reformation of the offender,
				and who is angry when medicine is applied to some parts
				for the cure of others, as when a chirurgeon opens a vein
				to give his patient ease upon an inflammation of the eyes.
				For such a one seems to look no farther than what he
				reaches by his senses, forgetting that a schoolmaster, by
				chastising one, admonishes all the rest of his scholars, and
				that a general, condemning only one in ten, reduces all the
				rest to obedience. And thus there is not only a cure and
				amendment of one part of the body by another; but many
				times the very soul itself is inclined to vice or reformation,
				by the lewdness or virtue of another, and indeed much
				more readily than one body is affected by another. For, in
				the case of the body, as it seems natural, the same affections and the same changes must always occur; while the
				soul, being agitated by fancy and imagination, becomes
				better or worse, as it is either daring and confident or
				timorous and mistrustful.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>While I was yet speaking, Olympicus interrupting
				me said: You seem by this discourse of yours to infer as
				if the soul were immortal, which is a supposition of great
				consequence. It is very true, said I, nor is it any more
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.169"/>
				
				than what yourselves have granted already; in regard the
				whole dispute has tended from the beginning to this, that
				the supreme Deity overlooks us, and deals to every one of
				us according to our deserts. To which the other: Do you
				then believe (said he) it follows of necessity that, because
				the Deity observes our actions and distributes to every one
				of us according to our merits, therefore our souls should
				exist and be altogether incorruptible, or else for a certain
				time survive the body after death? Not so fast, good sir,
				said I. But can we think that God so little considers his
				own actions, or is such a waster of his time in trifles, that,
				if we had nothing of divine within us, nothing that in the
				least resembled his perfection, nothing permanent and stable, but were only poor creatures, that (according to Homer's expression) faded and dropped like withered leaves,
				and in a short time too, yet he should make so great account of us&mdash;like women that bestow their pains in making little gardens, no less delightful to them than the
				gardens of Adonis, in earthen pans and pots&mdash;as to create
				us souls to blossom and flourish only for a day, in a soft
				and tender body of flesh, without any firm and solid root
				of life, and then to be blasted and extinguished in a moment upon every slight occasion? And therefore, if you
				please, not concerning ourselves with other Deities, let us
				go no farther than the God Apollo, whom here we call
				our own; see whether it is likely that he, knowing that
				the souls of the deceased vanish away like clouds and
				smoke, exhaling from our bodies like a vapor, requires
				that so many propitiations and such great honors be paid
				to the dead, and such veneration be given to the deceased, merely to delude and cozen his believers. And
				therefore, for my part, I will never deny the immortality of
				the soul, till somebody or other, as they say Hercules did
				of old, shall be so daring as to come and take away the
				prophetical tripod, and so quite ruin and destroy the oracle
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.170"/>
				
				For as long as many oracles are uttered even in these our
				days by the Delphic soothsayer, the same in substance
				which was formerly given to Corax the Naxian, it is impious to declare that the human soul can die.</p>
            <p>Then Patrocleas: What oracle was this? Who was
					that same Corax? For both the answer itself and the
					person whom you mention are strangers to my remembrance. Certainly, said I, that cannot be; only it was my
					error which occasioned your ignorance, in making use of
					the addition to the name instead of the name itself. For
					it was Calondas, who slew Archilochus in fight, and who
					was surnamed Corax. He was thereupon ejected by the
					Pythian priestess, as one who had slain a person devoted
					to the Muses; but afterwards, humbling himself in prayers
					and supplications, intermixed with undeniable excuses of
					the fact, was enjoined by the oracle to repair to the habitation of Tettix, there to expiate his crime by appeasing the
					ghost of Archilochus. That place was called Taenarus;
					for there it was, as the report goes, that Tettix the Cretan,
					coming with a navy, landed, built a city not far from the
					Psychopompaeum (or place where ghosts are conjured up),
					and stored it with inhabitants. In like manner, when the
					Spartans were commanded by the oracle to atone the ghost
					of Pausanias, they sent for several exorcisers and conjurers out of Italy, who by virtue of their sacrifices chased
					the apparition out of the temple.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Therefore, said I, there is one and the same reason
				to confirm the providence of God and the immortality of
				the soul; neither is it possible to admit the one, if you
				deny the other. Now then, the soul surviving after the
				decease of the body, the inference is the stronger that it
				partakes of punishment and reward. For during this mortal life the soul is in continual combat like a wrestler; but
				after all those conflicts are at an end, she then receives according to her merits. But what the punishments and what
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.171"/>
				
				the rewards of past transgressions or just and laudable actions are to be while the soul is thus alone by itself, is
				nothing at all to us that are alive; for either they are altogether concealed from our knowledge, or else we give
				but little credit to them. But those punishments that
				reach succeeding posterity, being conspicuous to all that
				are living at the same time, restrain and curb the inclinations of many wicked persons. Now I have a story that I
				lately heard, which I might relate to show that there is no
				punishment more grievous or that touches more to the quick,
				than for a man to behold his children born of his body suffering for his crimes; and that, if the soul of a wicked
				and lawless criminal were to look back to earth and behold, not his statues overturned and his dignities reversed,
				but his own children, his friends, or his nearest kindred
				ruined and overwhelmed with calamity, such a person,
				were he to return to life again, would rather choose the refusal of all Jupiter's honors than abandon himself a second time to his wonted injustice and extravagant desires.
				This story, I say, I could relate, but that I fear lest you should
				censure it for a fable. And therefore I deem it much the
				better way to keep close to what is probable and consentaneous to reason. By no means, replied Olympicus; but
				proceed, and gratify us with your story also, since it was
				so kindly offered. Thereupon, when the rest of the company likewise made me the same request, Permit me, said
				I, in the first place, to pursue the rational part of my discourse, and then, according as it shall seem proper and
				convenient, if it be a fable, you shall have it as cheap as I
				heard it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Bion was of opinion that God, in punishing the
				children of the wicked for the sins of their fathers, seems
				more irregular than a physician that should administer
				physic to a son or a grandchild, to cure the distemper of
				a father or a grandfather. But this comparison does not
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.172"/>
				
				run cleverly; since the amplification of the similitude
				agrees only in some things, but in others is altogether defective. For if one man be cured of a disease by physic,
				the same medicine will not cure another; nor was it ever
				known that any person troubled with sore eyes or laboring
				under a fever was ever restored to perfect health by seeing
				another in the same condition anointed or plastered. But
				the punishments or executions of malefactors are done
				publicly in the face of the world, to the end that, justice
				appearing to be the effect of prudence and reason, some
				may be restrained by the correction inflicted upon others.
				So that Bion never rightly apprehended where the comparison answered to our question. For oftentimes it happens, that a man comes to be haunted with a troublesome
				though not incurable disease, and through sloth and in
				temperance increases his distemper, and weakens his body
				to that degree that he occasions his own death. After
				this, it is true, the son does not fall sick; only he has received from his father's seed such a habit of body as makes
				him liable to the same disease; which a good physician or
				a tender friend or a skilful apothecary or a careful master
				observing confines him to a strict and spare diet, restrains
				him from all manner of superfluity, keeps him from all
				the temptations of delicious fare, wine, and women, and
				making use of wholesome and proper physic, together with
				convenient exercise, dissipates and extirpates the original
				cause of a distemper at the beginning, before it grows to
				a head and gets a masterless dominion over the body.
				And is it not our usual practice thus to admonish those
				that are born of diseased parents, to take timely care of
				themselves, and not to neglect the malady, but to expel
				the original nourishment of the inbred evil, as being then
				easily movable and apt for expulsion? It is very true, cried
				they. Therefore, said I, we cannot be said to do an absurd thing, but what is absolutely necessary,&mdash;nor that
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.173"/>
				
				which is ridiculous, but what is altogether useful,&mdash;while
				we prescribe to the children of the epileptic, the hypochondriacal, and those that are subject to the gout, such
				exercises, diet, and remedies as are proper, not so much
				because they are at that time troubled with the distemper,
				as to prevent the malady. For a man begotten by an unsound body does not therefore deserve punishment, but
				rather the preservation of proper physic and good regimen; which if any one call the punishment of fear or
				effeminacy, because the person is debarred his pleasures
				and put to some sort of pain by cupping and blistering,
				we mind not what he says. If then it be of such importance to preserve, by physic and other proper means, the
				vitiated offspring of another body, foul and corrupted;
				ought we to suffer the hereditary resemblances of a wicked nature to sprout up and bud in the youthful character,
				and to wait till they are diffused into all the affections of
				the mind, and bring forth and ripen the malignant fruit
				of a mischievous disposition? For such is the expression
				of Pindar.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>Or can you believe but that in this particular God
				is wiser than Hesiod, admonishing and exhorting us in
				this manner:<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 735.</note>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor mind the pleasures of the genial bed,
				</l>
                     <l>Returning from th' interment of the dead;
				</l>
                     <l>But propagate the race, when heavenly food
				</l>
                     <l>And feasting with the Gods have warmed the blood;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>intimating thereby, that a man was never to attempt the
					work of generation but in the height of a jocund and
					merry humor, and when he found himself as it were dissolved into jollity; as if from procreation proceeded the
					impressions not only of vice or virtue, but of sorrow and
					joy, and of all other qualities and affections whatever.
					However, it is not the work of human wisdom (as Hesiod
					supposes) but of divine providence, to foresee the sympathies
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.174"/>
					
					 and differences of men's natures, before the malignant infection of their unruly passions come to exert
					itself, by hurrying their unadvised youth into a thousand
					villanous miscarriages. For though the cubs of bears and
					whelps of wolves and apes immediately discover their
					several inbred qualities and natural conditions without any
					disguise or artificial concealment, man is nevertheless a
					creature more refined, who, many times curbed by the
					shame of transgressing common customs, universal opinion,
					or the law, conceals the evil that is within him, and imitates only what is laudable and honest. So that he may
					be thought to have altogether cleansed and rinsed away
					the stains and imperfections of his vicious disposition, and
					so cunningly for a long time to have kept his natural corruption wrapped up under the covering of craft and dissimulation, that we are scarce sensible of the fallacy till we
					feel the stripes or sting of his injustice; believing men to
					be only then unjust, when they offer wrong to ourselves;
					lascivious, when we see them abandoning themselves to
					their lusts; and cowards, when we see them turning their
					backs upon the enemy; just as if any man should be so
					idle as to believe a scorpion had no sting until he felt it,
					or that a viper had no venom until it bit him,&mdash;which is
					a silly conceit. For there is no man that only then becomes wicked when he appears to be so; but, having the
					seeds and principles of iniquity within him long before,
					the thief steals when he meets with a fit opportunity, and
					the tyrant violates the law when he finds himself surrounded with sufficient power. But neither is the nature
					and disposition of any man concealed from God, as taking
					upon him with more exactness to scrutinize the soul than
					the body; nor does he tarry till actual violence or lewdness
					be committed, to punish the hands of the wrong-doer, the
					tongue of the profane, or the transgressing members of
					the lascivious and obscene. For he does not exercise his
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.175"/>
					
					vengeance on the unjust for any wrong that he has received
					by his injustice, nor is he angry with the highway robber
					for any violence done to himself, nor does he abominate
					the adulterer for defiling his bed; but many times, by way
					of cure and reformation, he chastises the adulterer, the
					covetous miser, and the wronger of his neighbors, as physicians endeavor to subdue an epilepsy by preventing the
					coming of the fits.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>What shall I say? But even a little before we
				were offended at the Gods protracting and delaying the
				punishments of the wicked, and now we are as much displeased that they do not curb and chastise the depravities
				of an evil disposition before the fact committed; not considering that many times a mischief contrived for future
				execution may prove more dreadful than a fact already
				committed, and that dormant villany may be more dangerous than open and apparent iniquity; not being able
				to apprehend the reason wherefore it is better to bear with
				the unjust actions of some men, and to prevent the meditating and contrivance of mischief in others. As, in truth,
				we do not rightly comprehend why some remedies and
				physical drugs are no way convenient for those that labor
				under a real disease, yet wholesome and profitable for
				those that are seemingly in health, but yet perhaps in a
				worse condition than they who are sick. Whence it comes
				to pass, that the Gods do not always turn the transgressions of parents upon their children; but if a virtuous son
				happen to be the offspring of a wicked father,&mdash;as often
				it falls out that a sane child is born of one that is unsound
				and crazy,&mdash;such a one is exempted from the punishment
				which threatens the whole descent, as having been adopted
				into a virtuous family. But for a young man that treads
				in the footsteps of a criminal race, it is but just that he
				should succeed to the punishment of his ancestor's iniquity, as one of the debts attached to his inheritance.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.176"/>
				
				For neither was Antigonus punished for the crimes of
				Demetrius; nor (among the ancient heroes) Phyleus for
				the transgressions of Augeas, nor Nestor for the impiety of
				Neleus; in regard that, though their parents were wicked,
				yet they were virtuous themselves. But as for those whose
				nature has embraced and espoused the vices of their parentage, them holy vengeance prosecutes, pursuing the likeness and resemblance of sin. For as the warts and moles
				and freckles of parents, not seen upon the children of
				their own begetting, many times afterwards appear again
				upon the children of their sons and daughters; and as the
				Grecian woman that brought forth a blackamore infant,
				for which she was accused of adultery, proved herself,
				upon diligent inquiry, to be the offspring of an Ethiopian
				after four generations; and as among the children of
				Pytho the Nisibian,&mdash;said to be descended from the
				Sparti, that were the progeny of those men that sprung
				from the teeth of Cadmus's dragon,&mdash;the youngest of his
				sons, who lately died, was born with the print of a spear
				upon his body, the usual mark of that ancient line, which,
				not having been seen for many revolutions of years before,
				started up again, as it were, out of the deep, and showed
				itself the renewed testimonial of the infant's race; so
				many times it happens that the first descents and eldest
				races hide and drown the passions and affections of the
				mind peculiar to the family, which afterward bud forth
				again, and display the natural propensity of the succeeding
				progeny to vice or virtue.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Having thus concluded, I held my peace; when
				Olympicus smiling said: We forbear as yet to give you
				our approbation, that we may not seem to have forgot the
				fable; not but that we believe your discourse to have been
				sufficiently made out by demonstration, only we reserve
				our opinion till we shall have heard the relation of that
				likewise. Upon which, I began again after this manner:
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.177"/>
				
				There was one Thespesius of Soli, the friend and familiar
				acquaintance of that Protogenes who for some time conversed among us. This gentleman, in his youth leading a
				debauched and intemperate life, in a short time spent his
				patrimony, and then for some years became very wicked;
				but afterwards repenting of his former follies and extravagancies, and pursuing the recovery of his lost estate by all
				manner of tricks and shifts, did as is usual with dissolute
				and lascivious youth, who when they have wives of their
				own never mind them at all, but when they have dismissed
				them, and find them married to others that watch them
				with a more vigilant affection, endeavor to corrupt and
				vitiate them by all the unjust and wicked provocations
				imaginable. In this humor, abstaining from nothing that
				was lewd and illegal, so it tended to his gain and profit, he
				got no great matter of wealth, but procured to himself a
				world of infamy by his unjust and knavish dealing with all
				sorts of people. Yet nothing made him more the talk of
				the country, than the answer which was brought him back
				from the oracle of Amphilochus. For thither it seems he
				sent, to inquire of the Deity whether he should live any
				better the remaining part of his life. To which the oracle
				returned, that it would be better with him after he was
				dead. And indeed, not long after, in some measure it so
				fell out; for he happened to fall from a certain precipice
				upon his neck, and though he received no wound nor
				broke any limb, yet the force of the fall beat the breath
				out of his body. Three days after, being carried forth to
				be buried, as they were just ready to let him down into
				the grave, of a sudden he came to himself, and recovering
				his strength, so altered the whole course of his life, that it
				was almost incredible to all that knew him. For by the
				report of the Cilicians, there never was in that age a juster
				person in common dealings between man and man, more
				devout and religious as to divine worship, more an enemy
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.178"/>
				
				to the wicked, nor more constant and faithful to his friends;
				which was the reason that they who were more conversant
				with him were desirous to hear from himself the cause of
				so great an alteration, not believing that so great a reformation could proceed from bare chance; though it was
				true that it did so, as he himself related to Protogenes and
				others of his choicest friends.</p>
            <p>For when his sense first left his body, it seemed to him
					as if he had been some pilot flung from the helm by the
					force of a storm into the midst of the sea. Afterwards,
					rising up again above water by degrees, so soon as he
					thought he had fully recovered his breath, he looked about
					him every way, as if one eye of his soul had been open.
					But he beheld nothing of those things which he was wont
					formerly to see, only he saw stars of a vast magnitude, at
					an immense distance one from the other, and sending forth
					a light most wonderful for the brightness of its color, which
					shot itself out in length with an incredible force; on which
					the soul riding, as it were in a chariot, was most swiftly,
					yet as gently and smoothly, dandled from one place to
					another. But omitting the greatest part of the sights
					which he beheld, he saw, as he said, the souls of such as
					were newly departed, as they mounted from below, resembling little fiery bubbles, to which the air gave way.
					Which bubbles afterwards breaking insensibly and by degrees, the soul came forth in the shapes of men and women,
					light and nimble, as being discharged of all their earthly
					substance. However, they differed in their motion; for
					some of them leaped forth with a wonderful swiftness, and
					mounted up in a direct line; others like so many spindles
					of spinning-wheels turned round and round, sometimes
					whisking upwards, sometimes darting downwards, with a
					confused and mixed agitation, that could hardly be stopped
					in a very long time.</p>
            <p>Of these souls he knew not who the most part were;
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.179"/>
					
					only perceiving two or three of his acquaintance, he endeavored to approach and discourse them. But they
					neither heard him speak, neither indeed did they seem to
					be in their right mind, fluttering and out of their senses,
					avoiding either to be seen or felt; they frisked up and
					down at first, alone and apart by themselves, till meeting
					at length with others in the same condition, they clung together; but still their motions were with the same giddiness
					and uncertainty as before, without steerage or purpose;
					and they sent forth inarticulate sounds, like the cries of
					soldiers in combat, intermixed with the doleful yells of fear
					and lamentation. Others there were that towered aloft in
					the upper region of the air, and these looked gay and
					pleasant, and frequently accosted each other with kindness
					and respect; but they shunned those troubled souls, and
					seemed to show discontent by crowding together, and joy
					and pleasure by expanding and separating from each other.
					One of these, said he, being the soul of a certain kinsman,&mdash;which, because the person died when he was but very
					young, he did not very well know,&mdash;drew near him, and
					saluted him by the name of Thespesius; at which being
					in a kind of amazement, and saying his name was not
					Thespesius but Aridaeus, the spirit replied, 'twas true that
					formerly he was so called, but that from thenceforth he
					must be Thespesius, that is to say <q direct="unspecified">divine.</q> For thou art
					not in the number of the dead as yet, it said, but by a certain destiny and permission of the Gods, thou art come
					hither only with thy intellectual faculty, having left the
					rest of thy soul, like an anchor, in thy body. And that
					thou mayst be assured of this, observe it for a certain rule,
					both now and hereafter, that the souls of the deceased
					neither cast any shadow, neither do they open and shut
					their eyelids. Thespesius having heard this discourse, was
					so much the more encouraged to make use of his own reason; and therefore looking round about to prove the truth
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.180"/>
					
					of what had been told him, he could perceive that there
					followed him a kind of obscure and shadowlike line,
					whereas those other souls shone like a round body of perfect light, and were transparent within. And yet there
					was a very great difference between them too; for that
					some yielded a smooth, even, and contiguous lustre, all of
					one color, like the full-moon in her brightest splendor;
					others were marked with long scales or slender streaks;
					others were all over spotted and very ugly to look upon,
					as being covered with black speckles like the skins of
					vipers; and others were marked by faint scratches.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this kinsman of Thespesius (for nothing hinders but that we may call the souls by the names of the
					persons which they enlivened), proceeding to give a relation of several other things, informed his friend how that
					Adrastea, the daughter of Jupiter and Necessity, was seated
					in the highest place of all, to punish all manner of crimes
					and enormities; and that in the whole number of the
					wicked and ungodly, there never was any one, whether
					great or little, high or low, rich or poor, that ever could
					by force or cunning escape the severe lashes of her rigor.
					But as there are three sorts of punishments, so there are
					three several Furies, or female ministers of justice; and to
					every one of these belongs a peculiar office and degree of
					punishment. The first of these was called Speedy Punishment, who takes in charge those that are presently to receive bodily punishment in this life, which she manages
					after a more gentle manner, omitting the correction of
					many offences which need expiation. But if the cure of
					impiety require a greater labor, the Deity delivers them
					after death to Justice. But when Justice has given them
					over as altogether incurable, then the third and most severe
					of all Adrastea's ministers, Erinnys (the Fury), takes them
					in hand; and after she has chased and coursed them from
					one place to another, flying, yet not knowing where to
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.181"/>
					
					fly, for shelter or relief, plagued and tormented with a
					thousand miseries, she plunges them headlong into an
					invisible abyss, the hideousness of which no tongue car
					express.</p>
            <p>Now, of all these three sorts, that which is inflicted by
					punishment in this life resembles the practice among the
					barbarians. For, as among the Persians, they take off the
					garments and turbans of those that are to be punished, and
					tear and whip them before the offender's faces, while the
					criminals, with tears and lamentations, beseech the executioners to give over; so corporal punishments, and penalties by mulcts and fines, have no sharpness or severity, nor
					do they take hold upon the vice itself, but are inflicted for
					the most part only with regard to appearance and to the
					outward sense. But if any one comes hither that has
					escaped punishment while he lived upon earth and before
					he was well purged from his crimes, Justice takes him to
					task, naked as he is, with his soul displayed, as having
					nothing to conceal or veil his impiety; but on all sides and
					to all men's eyes and every way exposed, she shows him
					first to his honest parents, if he had any such, to let them
					see how degenerate he was and unworthy of his progenitors. But if they were wicked likewise, then are
					their sufferings rendered yet more terrible by the mutual
					sight of each other's miseries, and those for a long time
					inflicted, till each individual crime has been quite effaced
					with pains and torments as far surmounting in sharpness
					and severity all punishments and tortures of the flesh, as
					what is real and evident surpasses an idle dream. But the
					weals and stripes that remain after punishment appear
					more signal in some, in others are less evident.</p>
            <p>View there, said he, those various colors of souls. That
					same black and sordid hue is the tincture of avarice and
					fraud. That bloody and flame-like dye betokens cruelty,
					and an imbittered desire of revenge. Where you perceive
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.182"/>
					
					a bluish color, it is a sign that soul will hardly be cleansed
					from the impurities of lascivious pleasure and voluptuousness. Lastly, that same dark, violet, and venomous color,
					resembling the sordid ink which the cuttle fish spews up,
					proceeds from envy. For as during life the wickedness of
					the soul, being governed by human passions and itself
					governing the body, occasions this variety of colors; so
					here it is the end of expiation and punishment, when these
					are cleansed away, and the soul recovers her native lustre
					and becomes clear and spotless. But so long as these remain, there will be some certain returns of the passions,
					accompanied with little pantings and beatings, as it were
					of the pulse, in some remiss and languid and quickly extinguished, in others more quick and vehement. Some of
					these souls, being again and again chastised, recover a due
					habit and disposition; while others, by the force of ignorance and the enticing show of pleasure, are carried into
					the bodies of brute beasts. For while some, through the
					feebleness of their ratiocinating, while their slothfulness
					will not permit them to contemplate, are impelled by their
					active principle to seek a new generation; others again,
					wanting the instrument of intemperance, yet desirous to
					gratify their desires with the full swing of enjoyment, endeavor to promote their designs by means of the body.
					But alas! here is nothing but an imperfect shadow and
					dream of pleasure, that never attains to ability of performance.</p>
            <p>Having thus said, the spirit quickly carried Thespesius
					to a certain place, as it appeared to him, prodigiously
					spacious; yet so gently and without the least deviation,
					that he seemed to be borne upon the rays of the light as
					upon wings. Thus at length he came to a certain gaping
					chasm, that was fathomless downward, where he found
					himself deserted by that extraordinary force which brought
					him thither, and perceived other souls also to be there in
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.183"/>
					
					the same condition. For hovering upon the wing in flocks
					together like birds, they kept flying round and round the
					yawning rift, but durst not enter into it. Now this same
					cleft withinside resembled the dens of Bacchus, fringed
					about with the pleasing verdure of various herbs and
					plants, that yielded a more delightful prospect still of all
					sorts of flowers, enamelling the green so with a wonderful
					diversity of colors, and breathing forth at the same time a
					soft and gentle breeze, which perfumed all the ambient air
					with odors most surprising, as grateful to the smell as the
					sweet flavor of wine to those that love it. Insomuch that
					the souls banqueting upon these fragrancies were almost
					all dissolved in raptures of mirth and caresses one among
					another, there being nothing to be heard for some fair
					distance round about the place, but jollity and laughter,
					and all the cheerful sounds of joy and harmony, which are
					usual among people that pass their time in sport and merriment.</p>
            <p>The spirit said, moreover, that Bacchus ascended through
					this overture to heaven, and afterwards returning fetched
					up Semele the same way; and that it was called the place
					of oblivion. Wherefore his kinsman would not suffer
					Thespesius to tarry there any longer, though very unwilling to depart, but took him away by force; informing and
					instructing him withal, how strangely and how suddenly the
					mind was subject to be softened and melted by pleasure;
					that the irrational and corporeal part, being watered and
					incarnated thereby, revives the memory of the body,
					and that from this remembrance proceed concupiscence
					and desire, exciting an appetite for a new generation and
					entrance into a body&mdash;which is named <foreign lang="greek">ge/nesis</foreign> as being an
					<hi rend="italics">inclination towards the earth</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">e)pi\ gh=n neu=sis</foreign>)&mdash;when the soul
					is weighed down with overmuch moisture.</p>
            <p>At length, after he had been carried as far another way
					as when he was transported to the yawning overture, he
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.184"/>
					
					thought he beheld a prodigious standing goblet, into which
					several rivers discharged themselves; among which there
					was one whiter than snow or the foam of the sea, another
					resembled the purple color of the rainbow. The tinctures
					of the rest were various; besides that, they had their several lustres at a distance. But when he drew nearer, the
					ambient air became more subtile and rarefied, and the colors
					vanished, so the goblet retained no more of its flourishing
					beauty except the white. At the same time he saw three
					Daemons sitting together in a triangular aspect, and blending and mixing the rivers together with certain measures.
					Thus far, said the guide of Thespesius's soul, did Orpheus
					come, when he sought after the soul of his wife; and not
					well remembering what he had seen, upon his return he
					raised a false report in the world, that the oracle at Delphi
					was in common to Night and Apollo, whereas Apollo never
					had any thing in common with Night. But, said the spirit,
					this oracle is in common to Night and to the Moon, no way
					included within earthly bounds, nor having any fixed or
					certain seat, but always wandering among men in dreams
					and visions. For from hence it is that all dreams are dispersed, compounded as they are of truth jumbled with
					falsehood, and sincerity with the various mixtures of craft
					and delusion. But as for the oracle of Apollo, said the
					spirit, you neither do see it, neither can you behold it; for
					the earthly part of the soul is not capable to release or let
					itself loose, nor is it permitted to reach sublimity, but it
					swags downward, as being fastened to the body.</p>
            <p>And with that, leading Thespesius nearer, the spirit endeavored to show him the light of the Tripod, which, as he
					said, shooting through the bosom of Themis, fell upon
					Parnassus; which Thespesius was desirous to see, but
					could not, in regard the extraordinary brightness of the
					light dazzled his eyes; only passing by, he heard the shrill
					voice of a woman speaking in verse and measure, and
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.185"/>
					
					among other things, as he thought, foretelling the time of
					his death. This the genius told him was the voice of a
					Sibyl who, being orbicularly whirled about in the face of
					the moon, continually sang of future events. Thereupon
					being desirous to hear more, he was tossed the quite contrary way by the violent motion of the moon, as by the
					force of rolling waves; so that he could hear but very little,
					and that very concisely too. Among other things, he heard
					what was prophesied concerning the mountain Vesuvius,
					and the future destruction of Dicaearchia by fire; together
					with a piece of a verse concerning a certain emperor<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Emperor Vespasian.</note> or
					great famous chieftain of that age,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who, though so just that no man could accuse,
					</l>
                     <l>Howe'er his empire should by sickness lose.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>After this, they passed on to behold the torments of those
					that were punished. And indeed at first they met with
					none but lamentable and dismal sights. For Thespesius,
					when he least suspected any such thing, and before he was
					aware, was got among his kindred, his acquaintance, and
					companions, who, groaning under the horrid pains of their
					cruel and ignominious punishments, with mournful cries
					and lamentations called him by his name. At length he
					saw his father ascending out of a certain abyss, all full of
					stripes, gashes, and scars; who stretching forth his hands&mdash;not permitted to keep silence, but constrained to confess
					by his tormentors&mdash;acknowledged that he had most impiously poisoned several of his guests for the sake of their
					gold; of which not being detected while he lived upon
					earth, but being convicted after his decease, he had endured
					part of his torments already, and now they were haling
					him where he should suffer more. However, he durst not
					either entreat or intercede for his father, such was his fear
					and consternation; and therefore being desirous to retire
					and be gone, he looked about for his kind and courteous
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.186"/>
					
					guide; but he had quite left him, so that he saw him no
					more.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, being pushed forward by other deformed
					and grim-looked goblins, as if there had been some necessity for him to pass forward, he saw how that the shadows
					of such as had been notorious malefactors, and had been
					punished in this world, were not tormented so grievously
					nor alike to the others, in regard that only the imperfect
					and irrational part of the soul, which was consequently
					most subject to passions, was that which made them so
					industrious in vice. Whereas those who had shrouded a
					vicious and impious life under the outward profession and
					a gained opinion of virtue, their tormentors constrained to
					turn their insides outward with great difficulty and dreadful pain, and to writhe and screw themselves contrary to
					the course of nature, like the sea scolopenders, which,
					having swallowed the hook, throw forth their bowels and
					lick it out again. Others they flayed and scarified, to
					display their occult hypocrisies and latent impieties, which
					had possessed and corrupted the principal part of their
					souls. Other souls, as he said, he also saw, which being
					twisted two and two, three and three, or more together
					gnawed and devoured each other, either upon the score of
					old grudges and former malice they had borne one another,
					or else in revenge of the injuries and losses they had sustained upon earth.</p>
            <p>Moreover, he said, there were certain lakes that lay
					parallel and equidistant one from the other, the one of
					boiling gold, another of lead, exceeding cold, and the
					third of iron, which was very scaly and rugged. By the
					sides of these lakes stood certain Daemons, that with their
					instruments, like smiths or founders, put in or drew out
					the souls of such as had transgressed either through avarice or an eager desire of other men's goods. For the flame
					of the golden furnace having rendered these souls of a fiery
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.187"/>
					
					and transparent color, they plunged them into that of lead;
					where after they were congealed and hardened into a substance like hail, they were then thrown into the lake of
					iron, where they became black and deformed, and being
					broken and crumbled by the roughness of the iron, changed
					their form; and being thus transformed, they were again
					thrown into the lake of gold; in all these transmutations
					enduring most dreadful and horrid torments. But they
					that suffered the most dire and dismal torture of all were
					those who, thinking that divine vengeance had no more to
					say to them, were again seized and dragged to repeated
					execution; and these were those for whose transgression
					their children or posterity had suffered. For when any of
					the souls of those children come hither and meet with any
					of their parents or ancestors, they fall into a passion, exclaim against them, and show them the marks of what they
					have endured. On the other side, the souls of the parents
					endeavor to sneak out of sight and hide themselves; but
					the others follow them so close at the heels, and load them
					in such a manner with bitter taunts and reproaches, that
					not being able to escape, their tormentors presently lay
					hold of them, and hale them to new tortures, howling and
					yelling at the very thought of what they have suffered
					already. And some of these souls of suffering posterity,
					he said, there were, that swarmed and clung together like
					bees or bats, and in that posture murmured forth their angry complaints of the miseries and calamities which they
					had endured for their sakes.</p>
            <p>The last things that he saw were the souls of such as
					were designed for a second life. These were bowed, bent,
					and transformed into all sorts of creatures by the force of
					tools and anvils and the strength of workmen appointed
					for that purpose, that laid on without mercy, bruising the
					whole limbs of some, breaking others, disjointing others,
					and pounding some to powder and annihilation, on purpose
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.188"/>
					
					to render them fit for other lives and manners. Among
					the rest, he saw the soul of Nero many ways most grievously tortured, but more especially transfixed with iron
					nails. This soul the workmen took in hand; but when
					they had forged it into the form of one of Pindar's vipers,
					which eats its way to life through the bowels of the female,
					of a sudden a conspicuous light shone out, and a voice
					was heard out of the light, which gave order for the transfiguring it again into the shape of some more mild and
					gentle creature; and so they made it to resemble one of
					those creatures that usually sing and croak about the sides
					of ponds and marshes. For indeed he had in some measure been punished for the crimes he had committed; besides, there was some compassion due to him from the
					Gods, for that he had restored the Grecians to their liberty,
					a nation the most noble and best beloved of the Gods
					among all his subjects. And now being about to return,
					such a terrible dread surprised Thespesius as had almost frighted him out of his wits. For a certain woman,
					admirable for her form and stature, laying hold of his arm,
					said to him: Come hither, that thou mayst the better be
					enabled to retain the remembrance of what thou hast seen.
					With that she was about to strike him with a small fiery
					wand, not much unlike to those that painters use; but
					another woman prevented her. After this, as he thought
					himself, he was whirled or hurried away with a strong and
					violent wind, forced as it were through a pipe; and so
					lighting again into his own body, he awoke and found
					himself on the brink of his own grave.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>