<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Regum et imperatorum apophthegmata</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.081">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.185"/>
         <head>The apophthegms or remarkable sayings of kings and great commanders.</head>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>ARTAXERXES</head>
            <p>ARTAXERXES, King of Persia, O Caesar Trajan, greatest
					of princes, esteemed it no less royal and bountiful kindly
					and cheerfully to accept small, than to make great presents;
					and when he was in a progress, and a common country
					laborer, having nothing else, took up water with both his
					hands out of the river and presented it to him, he smiled
					and received it pleasantly, measuring the kindness not by
					the value of the gift, but by the affection of the giver.
					And Lycurgus ordained in Sparta very cheap sacrifices,
					that they might always worship the Gods readily and
					easily with such things as were at hand. Upon the same
					account, when I bring a mean and slender present of the
					common first-fruits of philosophy, accept also (I beseech
					you) with my good affection these short memorials, if they
					may contribute any thing to the knowledge of the manners
					and dispositions of great men, which are more apparent in
					their words than in their actions. My former treatise contains the lives of the most eminent princes, lawgivers, and
					generals, both Romans and Grecians; but most of their
					actions admit a mixture of fortune, whereas such speeches
					and answers as happened amidst their employments, passions, and events afford us (as in a looking-glass) a clear
					discovery of each particular temper and disposition. Accordingly Siramnes the Persian, to such as wondered that
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.186"/>
					
					he usually spoke like a wise man and yet was unsuccessful
					in his designs, replied: I myself am master of my words,
					but the king and fortune have power over my actions.
					In the former treatise speeches and actions are mingled
					together, and require a reader that is at leisure; but in this
					the speeches, being as it were the seeds and the illustrations
					of those lives, are placed by themselves, and will not (I
					think) be tedious to you, since they will give you in a few
					words a review of many memorable persons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>CYRUS</head>
            <p>CYRUS. The Persians affect such as are hawk-nosed
					and think them most beautiful, because Cyrus, the most
					beloved of their kings, had a nose of that shape. Cyrus
					said that those that would not do good for themselves
					ought to be compelled to do good for others; and that nobody ought to govern, unless he was better than those he
					governed. When the Persians were desirous to exchange
					their hills and rocks for a plain and soft country, he would
					not suffer them, saying that both the seeds of plants and the
					lives of men resemble the soil they inhabit.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>DARIUS</head>
            <p>DARIUS. Darius the father of Xerxes used to praise
					himself, saying that he became even wiser in battles and
					dangers. When he laid a tax upon his subjects, he summoned his lieutenants, and asked them whether the tax
					was burthensome or not? When they told him it was
					moderate, he commanded them to pay half as much as was
					at first demanded. As he was opening a pomegranate,
					one asked him what it was of which he would wish for
					a number equal to the seeds thereof. He said, Of men
					like Zopyrus,&mdash;who was a loyal person and his friend.
					This Zopyrus, after he had maimed himself by cutting off
					his nose and ears, beguiled the Babylonians; and being
					trusted by them, he betrayed the city to Darius, who often
					said that he would not have had Zopyrus maimed to gain
					a hundred Babylons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>SEMIRAMIS</head>
            <p>SEMIRAMIS. Semiramis built a monument for herself, with
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.187"/>
					
					this inscription: Whatever king wants treasure, if he open
					this tomb, he may be satisfied. Darius therefore opening it
					found no treasure, but another inscription of this import:
					If thou wert not a wicked person and of insatiable covetousness, thou wouldst not disturb the mansions of the dead.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>XERXES</head>
            <p>XERXES. Arimenes came out of Bactria as a rival for
					the kingdom with his brother Xerxes, the son of Darius.
					Xerxes sent presents to him, commanding those that
					brought them to say: With these your brother Xerxes now
					honors you; and if he chance to be proclaimed king, you
					shall be the next person to himself in the kingdom. When
					Xerxes was declared king, Arimenes immediately did him
					homage and placed the crown upon his head; and Xerxes
					gave him the next place to himself. Being offended with
					the Babylonians, who rebelled, and having overcome
					them, he forbade them weapons, but commanded they
					should practise singing and playing on the flute, keep
					brothel-houses and taverns, and wear loose coats. He
					refused to eat Attic figs that were brought to be sold, until
					he had conquered the country that produced them. When
					he caught some Grecian scouts in his camp, he did them
					no harm, but having allowed them to view his army as
					much as they pleased, he let them go.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>ARTAXERXES</head>
            <p>ARTAXERXES. Artaxerxes, the son of Xerxes, surnamed
					Longimanus (or <hi rend="italics">Long-hand</hi>) because he had one hand
					longer than the other, said, it was more princely to add
					than to take away. He first gave leave to those that
					hunted with him, if they would and saw occasion, to throw
					their darts before him. He also first ordained that punishment for his nobles who had offended, that they should be
					stripped and their garments scourged instead of their bodies;
					and whereas their hair should have been plucked out, that
					the same should be done to their turbans. When Satibarzanes, his chamberlain, petitioned him in an unjust matter,
					and he understood he did it to gain thirty thousand pieces
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.188"/>
					
					of money, he ordered his treasurer to bring the said sum,
					and gave them to him, saying: O Satibarzanes! take it;
					for when I have given you this, I shall not be poorer, but I
					had been more unjust if I had granted your petition.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>CYRUS THE YOUNGER</head>
            <p>CYRUS THE YOUNGER. Cyrus the Younger, when he was
					exhorting the Lacedaemonians to side with him in the war,
					said that he had a stronger heart than his brother, and
					could drink more wine unmixed than he, and bear it better;
					that his brother, when he hunted, could scarce sit his
					horse, or when ill news arrived, his throne. He exhorted
					them to send him men, promising he would give horses
					to footmen, chariots to horsemen, villages to those that
					had farms, and those that possessed villages he would make
					lords of cities; and that he would give them gold and
					silver, not by tale but by weight.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>ARTAXERXES MNEMON</head>
            <p>ARTAXERXES MNEMON. Artaxerxes, the brother of Cyrus
					the Younger, called Mnemon, did not only give very free
					and patient access to any that would speak with him, but
					commanded the queen his wife to draw the curtains of her
					chariot, that petitioners might have the same access to her
					also. When a poor man presented him with a very fair
					and great apple, By the Sun, said he, 'tis my opinion, if this
					person were entrusted with a small city, he would make it
					great. In his flight, when his carriages were plundered,
					and he was forced to eat dry figs and barley-bread, Of how
					great pleasure, said he, have I hitherto lived ignorant!</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>PARYSATIS</head>
            <p>PARYSATIS. Parysatis, the mother of Cyrus and Artaxerxes, advised him that would discourse freely with the
					king, to use words of fine linen.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>ORONTES</head>
            <p>ORONTES. Orontes, the son-in-law of King Artaxerxes,
					falling into disgrace and being condemned, said: As arithmeticians count sometimes myriads on their fingers, sometimes units only; in like manner the favorites of kings
					sometimes can do every thing with them, sometimes little
					or nothing.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.189"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>MEMNON</head>
            <p>MEMNON. Memnon, one of King Darius's generals against
					Alexander, when a mercenary soldier excessively and impudently reviled Alexander, struck him with his spear,
					adding, I pay you to fight against Alexander, not to reproach him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>EGYPTIAN KINGS</head>
            <p>EGYPTIAN KINGS. The Egyptian kings, according unto
					their law, used to swear their judges that they should not
					obey the king when he commanded them to give an unjust
					sentence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>POLTYS</head>
            <p>POLTYS. Poltys king of Thrace, in the Trojan war,
					being solicited both by the Trojan and Grecian ambassadors, advised Alexander to' restore Helen, promising to give
					him two beautiful women for her.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="14">
            <head>TERES</head>
            <p>TERES. Teres, the father of Sitalces, said, when he was
					out of the army and had nothing to do, he thought there
					was no difference between him and his grooms.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="15">
            <head>COTYS</head>
            <p>COTYS. Cotys, when one gave him a leopard, gave him
					a lion for it. He was naturally prone to anger, and severely punished the miscarriages of his servants. When a
					stranger brought him some earthen vessels, thin and brittle,
					but delicately shaped and admirably adorned with sculptures, he requited the stranger for them, and then brake
					them all in pieces, Lest (said he) my passion should provoke me to punish excessively those that brake them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="16">
            <head>IDATHYRSUS</head>
            <p>IDATHYRSUS. Idathyrsus, King of Scythia, when Darius
					invaded him, solicited the Ionian tyrants that they would
					assert their liberty by breaking down the bridge that was
					made over the Danube: which they refusing to do because
					they had sworn fealty to Darius, he called them good,
					honest, lazy slaves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="17">
            <head>ATEAS</head>
            <p>ATEAS. Ateas wrote to Philip: You reign over the Macedonians, men that have learned fighting; and I over the
					Scythians, which can fight with hunger and thirst. As he
					was rubbing his horse, turning to the ambassadors of Philip,
					he asked whether Philip did so or not. He tool prisoner
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.190"/>
					
					Ismenias, an excellent piper, and commanded him to play;
					and when others admired him, he swore it was more pleasant to hear a horse neigh.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>SCILURUS</head>
            <p>SCILURUS. Scilurus on his death-bed, being about to
					leave fourscore sons surviving, offered a bundle of darts to
					each of them, and bade them break them. When all refused,
					drawing out one by one, he easily broke them; thus teaching them that, if they held together, they would continue
					strong, but if they fell out and were divided, they would
					become weak.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>GELO</head>
            <p>GELO. Gelo the tyrant, after he had overcome the Carthaginians at Himera, made peace with them, and among
					other articles compelled them to subscribe this,&mdash;that they
					should no more sacrifice their children to Saturn. He
					often marched the Syracusans out to plant their fields, as
					if it had been to war, that the country might be improved
					by husbandry, and they might not be corrupted by idleness.
					When he demanded a sum of money of the citizens, and
					thereupon a tumult was raised, he told them he would but
					borrow it; and after the war was ended, he restored it to
					them again. At a feast, when a harp was offered, and
					others one after another tuned it and played upon it, he
					sent for his horse, and with an easy agility leaped upon
					him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="20">
            <head>HIERO</head>
            <p>HIERO. Hiero, who succeeded Gelo in the tyranny, said
					he was not disturbed by any that freely spoke against him.
					He judged that those that revealed a secret did an injury
					to those to whom they revealed it; for we hate not only
					those who tell, but them also that hear what we would not
					have disclosed. One upbraided him with his stinking
					breath, and he blamed his wife that never told him of it;
					but she said, I thought all men smelt so. To Xenophanes
					the Colophonian, who said he had much ado to maintain
					two servants, he replied: But Homer, whom you disparage,
					maintains above ten thousand, although he is dead. He
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.191"/>
					
					fined Epicharmus the comedian, for speaking unseemly
					when his wife was by.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="21">
            <head>DIONYSIUS</head>
            <p>DIONYSIUS. Dionysius the Elder, when the public orators cast lots to know in what order they should speak,
					drew as his lot the letter M. And when one said to him,
					<foreign lang="greek">*mwrologei=s,</foreign> You will make a foolish speech, O Dionysius,
					You are mistaken, said he, <foreign lang="greek">*monarxh/sw,</foreign> I shall be a monarch.
					And as soon as his speech was ended, the Syracusans chose
					him general. In the beginning of his tyranny, the citizens
					rebelled and besieged him; and his friends advised him to
					resign the government, rather than to be taken and slain
					by them. But he, seeing a cook butcher an ox and the ox
					immediately fall down dead, said to his friends: Is it not
					a hateful thing, that for fear of so short a death we should
					resign so great a government? When his son, whom he
					intended to make his successor in the government, had
					been detected in debauching a freeman's wife, he asked
					him in anger, When did you ever know me guilty of such
					a crime? But you, sir, replied the son, had not a tyrant
					for your father. Nor will you, said he, have a tyrant for
					your son, unless you mend your manners. And another
					time, going into his son's house and seeing there abundance
					of silver and gold plate, he cried out: Thou art not capable of being a tyrant, who hast made never a friend with
					all the plate I have given thee. When he exacted money
					of the Syracusans, and they lamenting and beseeching him
					pretended they had none, he still exacted more, twice or
					thrice renewing his demands, until he heard them laugh
					and jeer at him as they went to and fro in the market-place,
					and then he gave over. Now, said he, since they contemn
					me, it is a sign they have nothing left. When his mother,
					being ancient, requested him to find a husband for her, I
					can, said he, overpower the laws of the city, but I cannot
					force the laws of Nature. Although he punished other
					malefactors severely, he favored such as stole clothes, that
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.192"/>
					
					the Syracusans might forbear feasting and drunken clubs.
					A certain person told him privately, he could show him a
					way how he might know beforehand such as conspired
					against him. Let us know, said he, going aside. Give
					me, said the person, a talent, that everybody may believe
					that I have taught you the signs and tokens of plotters;
					and he gave it him, pretending he had learned them, much
					admiring the subtilty of the man. Being asked whether
					he was at leisure, he replied: God forbid that it should
					ever befall me. Hearing that two young men very much
					reviled him and his tyranny in their cups, he invited both
					of them to supper; and perceiving that one of them prattled freely and foolishly, but the other drank warily and
					sparing, he dismissed the first as a drunken fellow whose
					treason lay no deeper than his wine, and put the other to
					death as a disaffected and resolved traitor. Some blaming
					him for rewarding and preferring a wicked man, and one
					hated by the citizens; I would have, said he, somebody
					hated more than myself. When he gave presents to the
					ambassadors of Corinth, and they refused them because
					their law forbade them to receive gifts from a prince to
					whom they were sent in embassy, he said they did very ill
					to destroy the only advantage of tyranny, and to declare
					that it was dangerous to receive a kindness from a tyrant.
					Hearing that a citizen had buried a quantity of gold in his
					house, he sent for it; and when the party removed to another city, and bought a farm with part of his treasure
					which he had concealed, Dionysius sent for him and bade
					him take back the rest, since he had now begun to use his
					money, and was no longer making a useful thing useless.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="22">
            <head>DIONYSIUS THE YOUNGER</head>
            <p>DIONYSIUS THE YOUNGER said that he maintained many
					Sophists; not that he admired them, but that he might be
					admired for their sake. When Polyxenus the logician told
					him he had baffled him; Yes, said he, in words, but I have
					caught you in deeds; for you, leaving your own fortune,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.193"/>
					
					attend me and mine. When he was deposed from his government, and one asked him what he got by Plato and
					philosophy, he answered, That I may bear so great a
					change of fortune patiently. Being asked how it came to
					pass that his father, a private and poor man, obtained the
					government of Syracuse, and he already possessed of it,
					and the son of a tyrant, lost it,&mdash;My father, said he, entered upon affairs when the democracy was hated, but I,
					when tyranny was become odious. To another that asked
					him the same question, he replied: My father bequeathed
					to me his government, but not his fortune.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="23">
            <head>AGATHOCLES</head>
            <p>AGATHOCLES was the son of a potter. When he became
					lord and was proclaimed king of Sicily, he was wont to
					place earthen and golden vessels together, and show them
					to young men, telling them, Those I made first, but now
					I make these by my valor and industry. As he was besieging a city, some from the walls reviling him, saying, Do
					you hear, potter, where will you have money to pay your
					soldiers&mdash;he gently answered, I'll tell you, if I take this
					city. And having taken it by storm, he sold the prisoners,
					telling them, If you reproach me again, I will complain to
					your masters. Some inhabitants of Ithaca complained of
					his mariners, that making a descent on the island they had
					taken away some cattle; But your king, said he, came to
					Sicily, and did not only take away sheep, but put out the
					shepherd's eyes, and went his way.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="24">
            <head>DION</head>
            <p>DION. Dion, that deposed Dionysius from the tyranny,
					when he heard Callippus, whom of all his friends and
					attendants he trusted most, conspired against him, refused
					to question him for it, saying: It is better for him to die
					than to live, who must be weary not only of his enemies,
					but of his friends too.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="25">
            <head>ARCHELAUS</head>
            <p>ARCHELAUS. Archelaus, when one of his companions
					(and none of the best) begged a golden cup of him, bade
					the boy give it Euripides; and when the man wondered
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.194"/>
					
					at him, You, said he, are worthy to ask, but he is worthy
					to receive it without asking. A prating barber asked him
					how he would be trimmed. He answered, In silence.
					When Euripides at a banquet embraced fair Agatho and
					kissed him, although he was no longer beardless, he said,
					turning to his friends: Do not wonder at it, for the beauty
					of such as are handsome lasts after autumn.</p>
            <p>Timotheus the harper, receiving of him a reward less
					than his expectation, twitted him for it not obscurely; and
					once singing the short verse of the chorus, You commend
					earth-born silver, directed it to him. And Archelaus
					answered him again singing, But you beg it. When one
					sprinkled water upon him, and his friends would have had
					him punish the man, You are mistaken, said he, he did not
					sprinkle me, but some other person whom he took me
					to be.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="26">
            <head>PHILIP</head>
            <p>PHILIP. Theophrastus tells us that Philip, the father of
					Alexander, was not only greater in his port and success,
					but also freer from luxury than other kings of his time.
					He said the Athenians were happy, if they could find every
					year ten fit to be chosen generals, since in many years he
					could find but one fit to be a general, and that was
					Parmenio. When he had news brought him of divers and
					eminent successes in one day, O Fortune, said he, for all
					these so great kindnesses do me some small mischief.
					After he had conquered Greece, some advised him to place
					garrisons in the cities. No, said he, I had rather be called
					merciful a great while, than lord a little while. His friends
					advised him to banish a railer his court. I will not do it,
					said he, lest he should go about and rail in many places.
					Smicythus accused Nicanor for one that commonly spoke
					evil of King Philip; and his friends advised him to send for
					him and punish him. Truly, said he, Nicanor is not the
					worst of the Macedonians; we ought therefore to consider
					whether we have given him any cause or not. When he
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.195"/>
					
					understood therefore that Nicanor, being slighted by the
					king, was much afflicted with poverty, he ordered a boon
					should be given him. And when Smicythus reported that
					Nicanor was continually abounding in the king's praises,
					You see then, said he, that whether we will be well or ill
					spoken of is in our own power. He said he was beholden
					to the Athenian orators, who by reproaching him made him
					better both in speech and behavior; for I will endeavor,
					said he, both by my words and actions to prove them liars.
					Such Athenians as he took prisoners in the fight at Chaeronea he dismissed without ransom. When they also demanded their garments and quilts, and on that account
					accused the Macedonians, Philip laughed and said, Do ye
					not think these Athenians imagine we beat them at cockal?
					In a fight he broke his collar-bone, and the surgeon that
					had him in cure requested him daily for his reward. Take
					what you will, said he, for you have the key.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greek <foreign lang="greek">klei/s</foreign> (clavis), <hi rend="italics">a key,</hi> signifies also the <hi rend="italics">collar-bone,</hi> (G.)</note> There
					were two brothers called Both and Either; perceiving
					Either was a good understanding busy fellow and Both a
					silly fellow and good for little, he said: Either is Both, and
					Both is Neither. To some that advised him to deal severely
					with the Athenians he said: You talk absurdly, who would
					persuade a man that suffers all things for the sake of glory,
					to overthrow the theatre of glory. Being arbitrator betwixt
					two wicked persons, he commanded one to fly out of Macedonia and the other to pursue him. Being about to pitch
					his camp in a likely place, and hearing there was no hay
					to be had for the cattle, What a life, said he, is ours, since
					we must live according to the convenience of asses! Designing to take a strong fort, which the scouts told him was
					exceeding difficult and impregnable, he asked whether it
					was so difficult that an ass could not come at it laden with
					gold. Lasthenes the Olynthian and his friends being
					aggrieved, and complaining that some of Philip's retinue
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.196"/>
					
					called them traitors, These Macedonians, said he, are a rude
					and clownish people, that call a spade a spade. He exhorted his son to behave himself courteously toward the
					Macedonians, and to acquire influence with the people,
					while he could be affable and gracious during the reign of
					another. He advised him also to make friends of men
					of interest in the cities, both good and bad, that afterwards
					he might make use of these, and suppress those. To Philo
					the Theban, who had been his host and given him entertainment while he remained an hostage at Thebes, and afterwards refused to accept any present from him, he said: Do
					not take from me the title of invincible, by making me inferior
					to you in kindness and bounty. Having taken many prisoners, he was selling them, sitting in an unseemly posture, with
					his tunic tucked up; when one of the captives to be sold
					cried out, Spare me, Philip, for our fathers were friends.
					When Philip asked him, Prithee, how or from whence?
					Let me come nearer, said he, and I'll tell you. When he
					was come up to him, he said: Let down your cloak a little
					lower, for you sit indecently. Whereupon said Philip: Let
					him go, in truth he wisheth me well and is my friend, though
					I did not know him. Being invited to supper, he carried
					many he took up by the way along with him; and perceiving his host troubled (for his provision was not sufficient),
					he sent to each of his friends, and bade them reserve a place
					for the cake. They, believing and expecting it, ate little,
					and so the supper was enough for all. It appeared he
					grieved much at the death of Hipparchus the Euboean.
					For when somebody said it was time for him to die,&mdash;For
					himself, said he, but he died too soon for me, preventing
					me by his death from returning him the kindness his friendship deserved. Hearing that Alexander blamed him for
					having children by several women, Therefore, saith he to
					him, since you have many rivals with you for the kingdom,
					be just and honorable, that you may not receive the kingdom
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.197"/>
					
					 as my gift, but by your own merit. He charged him
					to be observant of Aristotle, and study philosophy, That
					you may not, said he, do many things which I now repent
					of doing. He made one of Antipater's recommendation a
					judge; and perceiving afterwards that his hair and beard
					were colored, he removed him, saying, I could not think
					one that was faithless in his hair could be trusty in his deeds.
					As he sate judge in the cause of one Machaetas, he fell
					asleep, and for want of minding his arguments, gave judgment against him. And when being enraged he cried out,
					I appeal; To whom, said he, wilt thou appeal? To you
					yourself, O king, said he, when you are awake to hear me
					with attention. Then Philip rousing and coming to himself, and perceiving Machaetas was injured, although he
					did not reverse the sentence, he paid the fine himself.
					When Harpalus, in behalf of Crates his kinsman and
					intimate friend, who was charged with disgraceful crimes,
					begged that Crates might pay the fine and so cause the action
					to be withdrawn and avoid public disgrace;&mdash;It is better,
					said he, that he should be reproached upon his own account,
					than we for him. His friends being enraged because the
					Peloponnesians, to whom he had shown favor, hissed at
					him in the Olympic games, What then, said he, would they
					do if we should abuse them? Awaking after he had
					overslept himself in the army; I slept, said he, securely,
					for Antipater watched. Another time, being asleep in the
					day-time, while the Grecians fretting with impatience
					thronged at the gates; Do not wonder, said Parmenio to
					them, if Philip be now asleep, for while you slept he was
					awake. When he corrected a musician at a banquet, and
					discoursed with him concerning notes and instruments, the
					musician replied: Far be that dishonor from your majesty,
					that you should understand these things better than I do.
					While he was at variance with his wife Olympia and his son,
					Demaratus the Corinthian came to him, and Philip asked
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.198"/>
					
					him how the Grecians held together. Demaratus replied:
					You had need to enquire how the Grecians agree, who
					agree so well with your nearest relations. Whereupon he
					let fall his anger, and was reconciled to them. A poor old
					woman petitioned and dunned him often to hear her cause;
					and he answered, I am not at leisure; the old woman
					bawled out, Do not reign then. He admired the speech,
					and immediately heard her and others.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="27">
            <head>ALEXANDER</head>
            <p>ALEXANDER. While Alexander was a boy, Philip had
					great success in his affairs, at which he did not rejoice, but
					told the children that were brought up with him, My father
					will leave me nothing to do. The children answered, Your
					father gets all this for you. But what good, saith he, will
					it do me, if I possess much and do nothing? Being nimble and light-footed, his father encouraged him to run in
					the Olympic race; Yes, said he, if there were any kings
					there to run with me. A wench being brought to lie with
					him late in the evening, he asked why she tarried so long.
					She answered, I staid until my husband was abed; and he
					sharply reproved his pages, because through their carelessness he had almost committed adultery. As he was sacrificing to the Gods liberally, and often offered frankincense,
					Leonidas his tutor standing by said, O son, thus generously
					will you sacrifice, when you have conquered the country
					that bears frankincense. And when he had conquered it,
					he sent him this letter: I have sent you an hundred talents
					of frankincense and cassia, that hereafter you may not be
					niggardly towards the Gods, when you understand I have
					conquered the country in which perfumes grow. The
					night before he fought at the river Granicus, he exhorted
					the Macedonians to sup plentifully and to bring out all
					they had, as they were to sup the next day at the charge
					of their enemies. Perillus, one of his friends, begged of
					him portions for his daughters; and he ordered him to
					receive fifty talents. And when he said, Ten were enough,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.199"/>
					
					Alexander replied: Enough for you to receive, but not for
					me to give. He commanded his steward to give Anaxarchus the philosopher as much as he should ask for. He
					asketh, said the steward, for an hundred talents. He doth
					well, said he, knowing he hath a friend that both can and
					will bestow so much on him. Seeing at Miletus many
					statues of wrestlers that had overcome in the Olympic
					and Pythian games, And where, said he, were these lusty
					fellows when the barbarians assaulted your city? When
					Ada queen of Caria was ambitious often to send him
					sauces and sweetmeats delicately prepared by the best
					cooks and artists, he said, I have better confectioners of
					my own, viz., my night-travelling for my breakfast, and my
					spare breakfast for my dinner. All things being prepared
					for a fight, his captains asked him whether he had any thing
					else to command them. Nothing, said he, but that the
					Macedonians should shave their beards. Parmenio wondering at it, Do you not know, said he, there is no better
					hold in a fight than the beard? When Darius offered him
					ten thousand talents, and to divide Asia equally with him:
					I would accept it, said Parmenio, were I Alexander. And
					so truly would I, said Alexander, if I were Parmenio.
					But he answered Darius, that the earth could not bear
					two suns, nor Asia two kings. When he was going to
					fight for the world at Arbela, against ten hundred thousand
					enemies set in array against him, some of his friends came
					to him, and told him the discourse of the soldiers in their
					tents, who had agreed that nothing of the spoils should be
					brought into the treasury, but they would have all themselves. You tell me good news, said he, for I hear the
					discourse of men that intend to fight, and not to run away.
					Several of his soldiers cameto him and said: O King! be
					of good courage, and fear not the multitude of your enemies, for they will not be able to endure the very stink of
					our sweat. The army being marshalled, he saw a soldier
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.200"/>
					
					fitting his thong to his javelin, and dismissed him as a useless fellow, for fitting his weapons when he should use
					them. As he was reading a letter from his mother, containing secrets and accusations of Antipater, Hephaestion
					also (as he was wont) read it along with him. Alexander
					did not hinder him; but when the letter was read, he took
					his ring off his finger, and laid the seal of it upon Hephaestion's mouth. Being saluted as the son of Jupiter in
					the temple of Ammon by the chief priest; It is no wonder, said he, for Jupiter is by nature the father of all, and
					calls the best men his sons. When he was wounded with
					an arrow in the ankle, and many ran to him that were
					wont to call him a God, he said smiling: That is blood, as
					you see, and not, as Homer saith,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Such humor as distils from blessed Gods.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. V. 340.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					To some that commended the frugality of Antipater, whose
					diet was sober and without luxury; Outwardly, said he,
					Antipater wears white clothes, but within he is all purple.
					In a cold winter day one of his friends invited him to a
					banquet, and there being a little fire on a small hearth, he
					bid him fetch either wood or frankincense. Antipatridas
					brought a beautiful singing woman to supper with him;
					Alexander, being taken with her visage, asked Antipatridas
					whether she was his miss or not. And when he confessed
					she was; O villain, said he, turn her immediately out
					from the banquet. Again, when Cassander forced a kiss
					from Pytho, a boy beloved by Evius the piper, and Alexander perceived that Evius was concerned at it, he was extremely enraged at Cassander, and said with a loud voice,
					It seems nobody must be loved if you can help it. When
					he sent such of the Macedonians as were sick and maimed to
					the sea, they showed him one that was in health and yet
					subscribed his name among the sick; being brought into
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.201"/>
					##
					the presence and examined, he confessed he used that pretence for the love of Telesippa, who was going to the sea.
					Alexander asked, of whom he could make inquiries about
					this Telesippa, and hearing she was a free woman, he said.
					Therefore, my Antigenes, let us persuade her to stay with
					us, for to force her to do so when she is a free woman is
					not according to my custom. Of the mercenary Grecians
					that fought against him he took many prisoners. He commanded the Athenians should be kept in chains, because
					they served for wages when they were allowed a public
					maintenance; and the Thessalians, because when they had
					a fruitful country they did not till it; but he set the Thebans free, saying, To them only I have left neither city nor
					country. He took captive an excellent Indian archer that
					said he could shoot an arrow through a ring, and commanded him to show his skill; and when the man refused
					to do this, he commanded him in a rage to be put to death.
					The man told them that led him to execution that, not
					having practised for many days, he was afraid he should
					miss. Alexander, hearing this, wondered at him and dismissed him with rewards, because he chose rather to die
					than show himself unworthy of his reputation. Taxiles,
					one of the Indian kings, met Alexander, and advised him
					not to make war nor fight with him, but if he were a
					meaner person than himself, to receive kindness from him,
					or if he were a better man, to show kindness to him. He
					answered, that was the very thing they must fight for, who
					should exceed the other in bounty. When he heard the
					rock called Aornus in India was by its situation impregnable, but the commander of it was a coward; Then, said
					he, the place is easy to be taken. Another, commanding
					a rock thought to be invincible, surrendered himself and
					the rock to Alexander, who committed the said rock and
					the adjacent country to his government, saying: I take this
					for a wise man, who chose rather to commit himself to a
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.202"/>
					
					good man than to a strong place. When the rock was
					taken, his friends said that it exceeded the deeds of Hercules. But I, said he, do not think my actions and all my
					empire to be compared with one word of Hercules. He
					fined some of his friends whom he caught playing at dice
					in earnest. Of his chief and most powerful friends, he
					seemed most to respect Craterus, and to love Hephaestion.
					Craterus, said he, is the friend of the king; but Hephaestion is the friend of Alexander. He sent fifty talents to
					Xenocrates the philosopher, who would not receive them,
					saying he was not in want. And he asked whether Xenocrates had no friend either; For as to myself, said he, the
					treasure of Darius is hardly sufficient for me to bestow
					among my friends. He demanded of Porus, after the fight,
					how he should treat him. Royally, said he, like a king.
					And being again asked, what farther he had to request;
					All things, said he, are in that word <hi rend="italics">royally.</hi> Admiring
					his wisdom and valor, he gave him a greater government
					than he had before. Being told a certain person reviled
					him, To do good, said he, and to be evil spoken of is
					kingly. As he was dying, looking upon his friends, I see,
					said he, my funeral tournament will be great. When he
					was dead, Demades the rhetorician likened the Macedonian
					army without a general to Polyphemus the Cyclops when
					his eye was put out.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="28">
            <head>PTOLEMY</head>
            <p>PTOLEMY. Ptolemy, the son of Lagus, frequently supped
					with his friends and lay at their houses; and if at any
					time he invited them to supper, he made use of their furniture, sending for vessels, carpets, and tables; for he himself had only things that were of constant use about him,
					saying it was more becoming a king to make others rich
					than to be rich himself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="29">
            <head>ANTIGONUS</head>
            <p>ANTIGONUS. Antigonus exacted money severely. When
					one told him that Alexander did not do so, It may be so,
					said he; Alexander reaped Asia, and I but glean after him.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.203"/>
            <p>Seeing some soldiers playing at ball in head-pieces and
					breast-plates, he was pleased, and sent for their officers,
					intending to commend them; but when he heard the officers were drinking, he bestowed their commands on the
					soldiers. When all men wondered that in his old age his
					government was mild and easy; Formerly, said he, I sought
					for power, but now for glory and good-will. To Philip his
					son, who asked him in the presence of many when the
					army would march, What, said he, are you afraid that you
					only should not hear the trumpet? The same young man
					being desirous to quarter at a widow's house that had three
					handsome daughters, Antigonus called the quartermaster to
					him: Prithee, said he, help my son out of these straits.
					Recovering from a slight disease, he said: No harm; this
					distemper puts me in mind not to aim at great things, since
					we are mortal. Hermodotus in his poems called him Son
					of the Sun. He that attends my close-stool, said he, sings
					me no such song. When one said, All things in kings are
					just and honorable,&mdash;Indeed, said he, for barbarian kings;
					but for us only honorable things are honorable, and only
					just things are just. Marsyas his brother had a cause depending, and requested him it might be examined at his
					house. Nay, said he, it shall be heard in the judgment-hall, that all may hear whether we do exact justice or not.
					In the winter being forced to pitch his camp where necessaries were scarce, some of his soldiers reproached him,
					not knowing he was near. He opened the tent with his
					cane, saying: Woe be to you, unless you get you farther off
					when you revile me. Aristodemus, one of his friends,
					supposed to be a cook's son, advised him to moderate his gifts
					and expenses. Thy words, said he, Aristodemus, smell of
					the apron. The Athenians, out of a respect to him, gave
					one of his servants the freedom of their city. And I would
					not, said he, have any Athenian whipped by my command. A youth, scholar to Anaximenes the rhetorician,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.204"/>
					
					spoke in his presence a prepared and studied speech;
					and he asking something which he desired to learn, the
					youth was silent. What do you say, said he, is all that
					you have said written in your table-book? When he heard
					another rhetorician say, The snow-spread season makes
					the country fodder spent; Will you not stop, said he,
					prating to me as you do to the rabble? Thrasyllus the
					Cynic begged a drachm of him. That, said he, is too little
					for a king to give. Why then, said the other, give me a
					talent. And that, said he, is too much for a Cynic (or
					for a <hi rend="italics">dog</hi>) to receive. Sending his son Demetrius with
					ships and land-forces to make Greece free; Glory, said
					he, from Greece, as from a watch-tower, will shine throughout the world. Antagoras the poet was boiling a conger,
					and Antigonus, coming behind him as he was stirring his
					skillet, said: Do you think, Antagoras, that Homer boiled
					congers, when he wrote the deeds of Agamemnon? Antagoras replied: Do you think, O King, that Agamemnon,
					when he did such exploits, was a peeping in his army to
					see who boiled congers? After he had seen in a dream
					Mithridates mowing a golden harvest, he designed to kill
					him, and acquainted Demetrius his son with his design,
					making him swear to conceal it. But Demetrius, taking
					Mithridates aside and walking with him by the seaside,
					with the pick of his spear wrote on the shore, <q direct="unspecified">Fly,
						Mithridates;</q> which he understanding, fled into Pontus,
					and there reigned until his death.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="30">
            <head>DEMETRIUS</head>
            <p>DEMETRIUS. Demetrius, while he was besieging Rhodes,
					found in one of the suburbs the picture of Ialysus made
					by Protogenes the painter. The Rhodians sent a herald to
					him, beseeching him not to deface the picture. I will
					sooner, said he, deface my father's statues, than such a
					picture. When he made a league with the Rhodians, he
					left behind him an engine, called the City Taker, that it
					might be a memorial of his magnificence and of their courage.
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.205"/>
					
					 When the Athenians rebelled, and he took the city,
					which had been distressed for want of provision, he called
					an assembly and gave them corn. And while he made a
					speech to them concerning that affair, he spoke improperly; and when one that sat by told him how the word
					ought to be spoken, he said: For this correction I bestow
					upon you five thousand bushels more.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="31">
            <head>ANTIGONUS THE SECOND</head>
            <p>ANTIGONUS THE SECOND. Antigonus the Second&mdash;when
					his father was a prisoner, and sent one of his friends to
					admonish him to pay no regard to any thing that he might
					write at the constraint of Seleucus, and to enter into no
					obligation to surrender up the cities&mdash;wrote to Seleucus
					that he would give up his whole kingdom, and himself for
					an hostage, that his father might be set free. Being about
					to fight by sea with the lieutenants of Ptolemy, and the
					pilot telling him the enemy outnumbered him in ships, he
					said: But how many ships do you reckon my presence to
					be worth? Once when he gave ground, his enemies pressing upon him, he denied that he fled; but he betook himself (as he said) to an advantage that lay behind him. To
					a youth, son of a valiant father, but himself no very great
					soldier, petitioning he might receive his father's pay; Young
					man, said he, I pay and reward men for their own, not for
					their fathers' valor. When Zeno of Citium, whom he
					admired beyond all philosophers, died, he said, The theatre
					of my actions is fallen.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="32">
            <head>LYSIMACHUS</head>
            <p>LYSIMACHUS. Lysimachus, when he was overcome by
					Dromichaetas in Thrace and constrained by thirst, surrendered himself and his army. When he was a prisoner,
					and had drunk; O Gods, said he, for how small a satisfaction have I made myself a slave from a king! To Philippides the comedian, his friend and companion, he said:
					What have I that I may impart to you? He answered,
					What you please, except your secrets.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="33">
            <head>ANTIPATER</head>
            <p>ANTIPATER. Antipater, hearing that Parmenio was slain
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.206"/>
					
					by Alexander, said: If Parmenio conspired against Alexander, whom may we trust? but if he did not, what is to
					be done? Of Demades the rhetorician, now grown old, be
					said: As of sacrifices when finished, so there is nothing left
					of him but his belly and tongue.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="34">
            <head>ANTIOCHUS THE THIRD</head>
            <p>ANTIOCHUS THE THIRD. Antiochus the Third wrote to
					the cities, that if he should at any time write for any thing
					to be done contrary to the law, they should not obey, but
					suppose it to be done out of ignorance. When he saw
					the Priestess of Diana, that she was exceeding beautiful,
					he presently removed from Ephesus, lest he should be
					swayed, contrary to his judgment, to commit some unholy
					act.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="35">
            <head>ANTIOCHUS HIERAX</head>
            <p>ANTIOCHUS HIERAX. Antiochus, surnamed the Hawk,
					warred with his brother Seleucus for the kingdom. After
					Seleucus was overcome by the Galatians, and was not to be
					heard of, but supposed to be slain in the fight, he laid aside
					his purple and went into mourning. A while after, hearing
					his brother was safe, he sacrificed to the Gods for the good
					news, and caused the cities under his dominion to put on
					garlands.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="36">
            <head>EUMENES</head>
            <p>EUMENES. Eumenes was thought to be slain by a conspiracy of Perseus. That report being brought to Pergamus, Attalus his brother put on the crown, married his
					wife, and took upon him the kingdom. Hearing afterwards his brother was alive and upon the way, he met him,
					as he used to do, with his life-guard, and a spear in his
					hand. Eumenes embraced him kindly, and whispered in
					his ear:&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>If a widow you will wed,</l>
						            <l>Wait till you're sure her husband's dead.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>
                        <foreign lang="greek">*mh\ spou=de gh=mai, pri\n teleuth/sant' i)/dh|s.</foreign> From Sophocles's Tyro, Frag. 596.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					But he never afterwards did or spake any thing that showed
					any suspicion all his lifetime; but when he died, be bequeathed to him his queen and kingdom. In requital of
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.207"/>
					
					which, his brother bred up none of his own children,
					although he had many; but when the son of Eumenes
					was grown up, he bestowed the kingdom on him in his
					own lifetime.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="37">
            <head>PYRRHUS THE EPIROT</head>
            <p>PYRRHUS THE EPIROT. Pyrrhus was asked by his sons,
					when they were boys, to whom he would leave the kingdom. To him of you, saith he, that hath the sharpest
					sword. Being asked whether Pytho or Caphisius was the
					better piper, Polysperchon, said he, is the best general.
					He joined in battle with the Romans, and twice overcame
					them, but with the loss of many friends and captains. If
					I should overcome the Romans, said he, in another fight,
					I were undone. Not being able to keep Sicily (as he said)
					from them, turning to his friends he said: What a fine
					wrestling ring do we leave to the Romans and Carthaginians! His soldiers called him Eagle; And I may deserve
					the title, said he, while I am borne upon the wings of your
					arms. Hearing some young men had spoken many re
					proachful words of him in their drink, he summoned them
					all to appear before him next day; when they appeared,
					ne asked the foremost whether they spake such things of
					him or not. The young man answered: Such words were
					spoken, O King, and more we had spoken, if we had had
					more wine.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="38">
            <head>ANTIOCHUS</head>
            <p>ANTIOCHUS. Antiochus, who twice made an inroad into
					Parthia, as he was once a hunting, lost his friends and servants in the pursuit, and went into a cottage of poor people
					who did not know him. As they were at supper, he threw
					out discourse concerning the king; they said for the most
					part he was a good prince, but overlooked many things he
					left to the management of debauched courtiers, and out of
					love of hunting often neglected his necessary affairs; and
					there they stopped. At break of day the guard arrived at
					the cottage, and the king was recognized when the crown
					and purple robes were brought. From the day, said he,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.208"/>
					
					on which I first received these, I never heard truth concerning myself till yesterday. When he besieged Jerusalem, the Jews, in respect of their great festival, begged
					of him seven days' truce; which he not only granted, but
					preparing oxen with gilded horns, with a great quantity of
					incense and perfumes, he went before them to the very
					gates, and having delivered them as a sacrifice to their
					priests, he returned back to his army. The Jews wondered at him, and as soon as their festival was finished,
					surrendered themselves to him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="39">
            <head>THEMISTOCLES</head>
            <p>THEMISTOCLES. Themistocles in his youth was much
					given to wine and women. But after Miltiades the general overcame the Persian at Marathon, Themistocles
					utterly forsook his former disorders; and to such as wondered at the change, he said, The trophy of Miltiades will
					neither suffer me to sleep nor to be idle. Being asked
					whether he would rather be Achilles or Homer,&mdash;And
					pray, said he, which would you rather be, a conqueror in
					the Olympic games, or the crier that proclaims who are
					conquerors? When Xerxes with that great navy made a
					descent upon Greece, he fearing, if Epicydes (a popular,
					but a covetous, corrupt, and cowardly person) were made
					general, the city might be lost, bribed him with a sum of
					money to desist from that pretence. Adimantus was
					afraid to hazard a sea-fight, whereunto Themistocles persuaded and encouraged the Grecians. O Themistocles,
					said he, those that start before their time in the Olympic
					games are always scourged. Aye; but, Adimantus, said
					the other, they that are left behind are not crowned.
					Eurybiades lifted up his cane at him, as if he would strike
					him. Strike, said he, but hear me. When he could not
					persuade Eurybiades to fight in the straits of the sea, he
					sent privately to Xerxes, advising him that he need not
					fear the Grecians, for they were running away. Xerxes
					upon this persuasion, fighting in a place advantageous for
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.209"/>
					
					the Grecians, was worsted; and then he sent him another
					message, and bade him fly with all speed over the Hellespont, for the Grecians designed to break down his bridge;
					that under pretence of saving him he might secure the
					Grecians. A man from the little island Seriphus told
					him, he was famous not upon his own account but through
					the city where he lived. You say true, said he, for if I
					had been a Seriphian, I had not been famous; nor would
					you, if you had been an Athenian. To Antiphatus, a beautiful person that avoided and despised Themistocles when
					he formerly loved him, but came to him and flattered him
					when he was in great power and esteem; Hark you, lad,
					said he, though late, yet both of us are wise at last. To
					Simonides desiring him to give an unjust sentence, You
					would not be a good poet, said he, if you should sing out
					of tune; nor I a good governor, if I should give judgment
					contrary to law. When his son was a little saucy towards
					his mother, he said that this boy had more power than all
					the Grecians, for the Athenians governed Greece, he the
					Athenians, his wife him, and his son his wife. He preferred an honest man that wooed his daughter, before a rich
					man. I would rather, said he, have a man that wants
					money, than money that wants a man. Having a farm to
					sell, he bid the crier proclaim also that it had a good
					neighbor. When the Athenians reviled him; Why do you
					complain, said he, that the same persons so often befriend
					you? And he compared himself to a row of plane-trees,
					under which in a storm passengers run for shelter, but in
					fair weather they pluck the leaves off and abuse them.
					Scoffing at the Eretrians, he said, Like the sword-fish, they
					have a sword indeed, but no heart. Being banished first
					out of Athens and afterwards out of Greece, he betook
					himself to the king of Persia, who bade him speak his
					mind. Speech, he said, was like to tapestry; and like
					it, when it was spread, it showed its figures, but when
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.210"/>
					
					it was folded up, hid and spoiled them. And therefore he
					requested time until he might learn the Persian tongue,
					and could explain himself without an interpreter. Having
					there received great presents, and being enriched of a sudden; O lads, said he to his sons, we had been undone if
					we had not been undone.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="40">
            <head>MYRONIDES</head>
            <p>MYRONIDES. Myronides summoned the Athenians to
					fight against the Boeotians. When the time was almost
					come, and the captains told him they were not near all
					come out; They are come, said he, all that intend to fight.
					And marching while their spirits were up, he overcame
					his enemies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="41">
            <head>ARISTIDES</head>
            <p>ARISTIDES. Aristides the Just always managed his offices
					himself, and avoided all political clubs, because power gotten by the assistance of friends was an encouragement to
					the unjust. When the Athenians were fully bent to banish
					him by an ostracism, an illiterate country fellow came to
					him with his shell, and asked him to write in it the name
					of Aristides. Friend, said he, do you know Aristides
					Not I, said the fellow, but I do not like his surname of
					Just. He said no more, but wrote his name in the shell
					and gave it him. He was at variance with Themistocles,
					who was sent on an embassy with him. Are you content,
					said he, Themistocles, to leave our enmity at the borders?
					and if you please we will take it up again at our return.
					When he levied an assessment upon the Greeks, he returned poorer by so much as he spent in the journey.</p>
            <p>Aeschylus wrote these verses on Amphiaraus&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>His shield no emblem bears; his generous soul</l>
						            <l>Wishes to be, not to appear, the best;</l>
						            <l>While the deep furrows of his noble mind</l>
						            <l>Harvests of wise and prudent counsel bear.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <p>
                           <cit>
                              <quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
							                          <l>Sh=ma d' ou)k e)ph=n ku/klw|</l>
							                          <l>Ou) ga\r dokei=n a)/ristos a)ll' ei\nai qe/lei,</l>
							                          <l>Baqei=an a)/loka dia\freno\s karpou/menos,</l>
							                          <l>)Ec h(=s ta\ kedna\ blasta/nei bouleu/mata.</l>
                              </quote>
                              <bibl>Aesch. Sept. 591.</bibl>
                           </cit>
                        </p>
							                 <p>Thus the passage stands in all MSS, of Aeschylus; but it is quoted by Plutarch in his Life of Aristides, &sect; 3, with <foreign lang="greek">di/kaios</foreign> in the second verse in
								the place of <foreign lang="greek">a)/ristos.</foreign> It has been plausibly conjectured, that the actor who spoke the
								part intentionally substituted the word <foreign lang="greek">di/kaios</foreign> as a compliment to Aristides, on seeing
								him in a conspicuous place among the spectators. See Hermann's note on the passage
								in his edition of Aeschylus. (G.)</p>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.211"/>
            <p>And when they were pronounced in the theatre, all turned
					their eyes upon Aristides.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="42">
            <head>PERICLES</head>
            <p>PERICLES. Whenever he entered on his command as general, while he was putting on his war-cloak, he used thus
					to bespeak himself: Remember, Pericles, you govern freemen, Grecians, Athenians. He advised the Athenians to
					demolish Aegina, as a dangerous eyesore to the haven of
					Piraeus. To a friend that wanted him to bear false witness and to bind the same with an oath, he said: I am a
					friend only as far as the altar. When he lay on his deathbed, he blessed himself that no Athenian ever went into
					mourning upon his account.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="43">
            <head>ALCIBIADES</head>
            <p>ALCIBIADES. Alcibiades while he was a boy, wrestling
					in a ring, seeing he could not break his adversary's hold,
					bit him by the hand; who cried out, You bite like a
					woman. Not so, said he, but like a lion. He had a very
					handsome dog, that cost him seven thousand drachmas;
					and he cut off his tail, that, said he, the Athenians may
					have this story to tell of me, and may concern themselves
					no farther with me. Coming into a school, he called for
					Homer's Iliads; and when the master told him he had
					none of Homer's works, he gave him a box on the ear, and
					went his way. He came to Pericles's gate, and being told
					he was busy a preparing his accounts to be given to the
					people of Athens, Had he not better, said he, contrive
					how he might give no account at all? Being summoned by
					the Athenians out of Sicily to plead for his life, he absconded, saying, that criminal was a fool who studied a
					defence when he might fly for it. But, said one, will you
					not trust your country with your cause? No, said he, nor
					my mother either, lest she mistake and cast a black pebble
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.212"/>
					
					instead of a white one. When he heard death was decreed to him and his associates, Let us convince them, said
					he, that we are alive. And passing over to Lacedaemon,
					he stirred up the Decelean war against the Athenians.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="44">
            <head>LAMACHUS</head>
            <p>LAMACHUS. Lamachus chid a captain for a fault; and
					when he had said he would do so no more, Sir, said he, in
					war there is no room for a second miscarriage.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="45">
            <head>IPHICRATES</head>
            <p>IPHICRATES. Iphicrates was despised because he was
					thought to be a shoemaker's son. The exploit that first
					brought him into repute was this: when he was wounded
					himself, he caught up one of the enemies and carried him
					alive and in his armor to his own ship. He once pitched
					his camp in a country belonging to his allies and confederates, and yet he fortified it exactly with a trench and
					bulwark. Said one to him, What are ye afraid of? Of all
					speeches, said he, none is so dishonorable for a general, as
					I should not have thought it. As he marshalled his army
					to fight with barbarians, I am afraid, said he, they do not
					know Iphicrates, for his very name used to strike terror
					into other enemies. Being accused of a capital crime, he
					said to the informer: O fellow! what art thou doing, who,
					when war is at hand, dost advise the city to consult concerning me, and not with me? To Harmodius, descended
					from the ancient Harmodius, when he reviled him for his
					mean birth, My nobility, said he, begins in me, but yours
					ends in you. A rhetorician asked him in an assembly,
					who he was that he took so much upon him,&mdash;horseman,
					or footman, or archer, or shield-bearer. Neither of them,
					said he, but one that understands how to command all
					those.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="46">
            <head>TIMOTHEUS</head>
            <p>TIMOTHEUS. Timotheus was reputed a successful general, and some that envied him painted cities falling under
					his net of their own accord, while he was asleep. Said
					Timotheus, If I take such cities when I am asleep, what
					do you think I shall do when I am awake? A confident
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.213"/>
					
					commander showed the Athenians a wound he had received. But I, said he, when I was your general in
					Samos, was ashamed that a dart from an engine fell near
					me. The orators set up Chares as one they thought fit to
					be general of the Athenians. Not to be general, said
					Timotheus, but to carry the general's baggage.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="47">
            <head>CHABRTAS</head>
            <p>CHABRTAS. Chabrias said, they were the best commanders
					who best understood the affairs of their enemies. He was
					once indicted for treason with Iphicrates, who blamed him
					for exposing himself to danger, by going to the place of
					exercise, and dining at his usual hour. If the Athenians,
					said he, deal severely with us, you will die all foul and
					gut-foundered; I'll die clean and anointed, with my dinner
					in my belly. He was wont to say, that an army of stags,
					with a lion for their commander, was more formidable than
					an army of lions led by a stag.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="48">
            <head>HEGESIPPUS</head>
            <p>HEGESIPPUS. When Hegesippus, surnamed Crobylus
					(i.e. <hi rend="italics">Top-knot</hi>), instigated the Athenians against Philip,
					one of the assembly cried out, You would not persuade us
					to a war? Yes, indeed, would I, said he, and to mourning
					clothes and to public funerals and to funeral speeches,
					if we intend to live free and not submit to the pleasure
					of the Macedonians.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="49">
            <head>PYTHEAS</head>
            <p>PYTHEAS. Pytheas, when he was a young man, stood
					forth to oppose the decrees made concerning Alexander.
					One said: Have you, young man, the confidence to speak
					in such weighty affairs? And why not? said he: Alexander,
					whom you voted a God, is younger than I am.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="50">
            <head>PHOCION</head>
            <p>PHOCION. Phocion the Athenian was never seen to
					laugh or cry. In an assembly one told him, You seem to
					be thoughtful, Phocion. You guess right, said he, for I
					am contriving how to contract what I have to say to the
					people of Athens. The Oracle told the Athenians, there
					was one man in the city of a contrary judgment to all the
					rest; and the Athenians in a hubbub ordered search to be
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.214"/>
					
					made, who this should be. I, said Phocion, am the man;
					I alone am pleased with nothing the common people say
					or do. Once when he had delivered an opinion which
					pleased the people, and perceived it was entertained by a
					general consent, he turned to his friend, and said: Have I
					not unawares spoken some mischievous thing or other?
					The Athenians gathered a benevolence for a certain sacrifice; and when others contributed to it, he being often
					spoken to said: I should be ashamed to give to you, and
					not to pay this man,&mdash;pointing to one of his creditors.
					Demosthenes the orator told him, If the Athenians should
					be mad, they would kill you. Like enough, said he, me
					if they were mad, but you if they were wise. Aristogiton the informer, being condemned and ready to be
					executed in prison, entreated that Phocion would come to
					him. And when his friends would not suffer him to go to
					so vile a person; And where, said he, would you discourse
					with Aristogiton more pleasantly? The Athenians were
					offended with the Byzantines, for refusing to receive Chares
					into their city, who was sent with forces to assist them
					against Philip. Said Phocion, You ought not to be displeased with the distrust of your confederates, but with
					your commanders that are not to be trusted. Whereupon
					he was chosen general, and being trusted by the Byzantines,
					he forced Philip to return without his errand. King
					Alexander sent him a present of a hundred talents; and
					he asked those that brought it, what it should mean that,
					of all the Athenians, Alexander should be thus kind to
					him. They answered, because he esteemed him alone to
					be a worthy and upright person. Pray therefore, said he,
					let him suffer me to seem as well as to be so. Alexander
					sent to them for some ships, and the people calling for
					Phocion by name, bade him speak his opinion. He stood
					up and told them: I advise you either to conquer yourselves, or else to side with the conqueror. An uncertain
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.215"/>
					
					rumor happened, that Alexander was dead. Immediately
					the orators leaped into the pulpit, and advised them to
					make war without delay; but Phocion entreated them to
					tarry awhile and know the certainty: For, said he, if he
					is dead to-day, he will be dead to-morrow, and so forwards.
					Leosthenes hurried the city into a war, with fond hopes
					conceited at the name of liberty and command. Phocion
					compared his speechesto cypress-trees; They are tall, said
					he, and comely, but bear no fruit. However, the first
					attempts were successful; and when the city was sacrificing for the good news, he was asked whether he did not
					wish he had done this himself. I would, said he, have
					done what has been done, but have advised what I did.
					When the Macedonians invaded Attica and plundered the
					seacoasts, he drew out the youth. When many came to
					him and generally persuaded him by all means to possess
					himself of such an ascent, and thereon to marshal his
					army, O Hercules! said he, how many commanders do I
					see, and how few soldiers? Yet he fought and overcame,
					and slew Nicion, the commander of the Macedonians.
					But in a short time the Athenians were overcome, and
					admitted a garrison sent by Antipater. Menyllus, the
					governor of that garrison, offered money to Phocion, who
					was enraged thereby and said: This man is no better than
					Alexander; and what I refused then I can with less honor
					receive now. Antipater said, of the two friends he had
					at Athens, he could never persuade Phocion to accept a
					present, nor could he ever satisfy Demades with presents.
					When Antipater requested him to do some indirect thing
					or other, Antipater, said he, you cannot have Phocion for
					your friend and flatterer too. After the death of Antipater,
					democracy was established in Athens, and the assembly
					decreed the death of Phocion and his friends. The rest
					were led weeping to execution; but as Phocion passed
					silently, one of his enemies met him and spat in his face.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.216"/>
            <p>But he turned himself to the magistrates, and said, Will
					nobody restrain this insolent fellow? One of those that
					were to suffer with him lamented and took on: Why,
					Euippus, said he, are you not pleased that you die with
					Phocion? When the cup of hemlock was brought to him,
					being asked whether he had any thing to say to his son; I
					command you, said he, and entreat you not to think of
					any revenge upon the Athenians.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="51">
            <head>PISISTRATUS</head>
            <p>PISISTRATUS. Pisistratus, tyrant of Athens, when some
					of his party revolted from him and possessed themselves
					of Phyle, came to them bearing his baggage on his back.
					They asked him what he meant by it. Either, said he, to
					persuade you to return with me, or if I cannot persuade
					you, to tarry with you; and therefore I come prepared
					accordingly. An accusation was brought to him against
					his mother, that she was in love and used secret familiarity
					with a young man, who out of fear for the most part refused her. This young man he invited to supper, and as
					they were at supper asked him how he liked his entertainment. He answered, Very well. Thus, said he, you shall
					be treated daily, if you please my mother. Thrasybulus
					was in love with his daughter, and as he met her, kissed
					her; whereupon his wife would have incensed him against
					Thrasybulus. If, said he, we hate those that love us,
					what shall we do to them that hate us?&mdash;and he gave
					the maid in marriage to Thrasybulus. Some lascivious
					drunken persons by chance met his wife, and used unseemly speech and behavior to her; but the next day they
					begged his pardon with tears. As for you, said he, learn
					to be sober for the future; but as for my wife, yesterday
					she was not abroad at all. He designed to marry another
					wife, and his children asked him whether he could blame
					them for any thing. By no means, said he, but I commend you, and desire to have more such children as you
					are.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="52">
            <head>DEMETRIUS PHALEREUS</head>
            <pb id="v.1.p.217"/>
            <p>DEMETRIUS PHALEREUS. Demetrius Phalereus persuaded
					King Ptolemy to get and study such books as treated of
					government and conduct; for those things are written in
					books which the friends of kings dare not advise.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="53">
            <head>LYCURGUS</head>
            <p>LYCURGUS. Lycurgus the Lacedaemonian brought long
					hair into fashion among his countrymen, saying that it
					rendered those that were handsome more beautiful, and
					those that were deformed more terrible. To one that advised him to set up a democracy in Sparta, Pray, said he,
					do you first set up a democracy in your own house. He
					ordained that houses should be built with saws and axes
					only, thinking they would be ashamed to bring plate,
					tapestry, and costly tables into such pitiful houses. He
					forbade them to contend at boxing or in the double contest
					of boxing and wrestling, that they might not accustom
					themselves to be conquered, no, not so much as in jest.
					He forbade them also to war often against the same
					people, lest they should make them the more warlike.
					Accordingly, many years after, when Agesilaus was wounded, Antalcidas told him the Thebans had rewarded him
					worthily for teaching and accustoming them to war, whether
					they would or no.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="54">
            <head>CHARILLUS</head>
            <p>CHARILLUS. King Charillus, being asked why Lycurgus
					made so few laws, answered, They who use few words do
					not need many laws. When one of the Helots behaved
					rather too insolently towards him, By Castor and Pollux,
					said he, I would kill you, were I not angry. To one that
					asked him why the Spartans wore long hair, Because, said
					he, of all ornaments that is the cheapest.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="55">
            <head>TELECLUS</head>
            <p>TELECLUS. King Teleclus, when his brother inveighed
					against the citizens for not giving him that respect which
					they did to the king, said to him, No wonder, you do not
					know how to bear injury.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="56">
            <head>THEOPOMPUS</head>
            <p>THEOPOMPUS. Theopompus, to one that showed him the
					walls of a city, and asked him if they were not high and
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.218"/>
					
					beautiful, answered, No, not even if they are built for
					womenn.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="57">
            <head>ARCHIDAMUS</head>
            <p>ARCHIDAMUS. Archidamus, in the Peloponnesian war,
					when his allies requested him to appoint them their quota
					of tributes, replied, War has a very irregular appetite.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="58">
            <head>BRASIDAS</head>
            <p>BRASIDAS. Brasidas caught a mouse among his dried
					figs, which bit him, and he let it go. Whereupon, turning
					to the company, Nothing, said he, is so small which may
					not save itself, if it have the valor to defend itself
					against its aggressors. In a fight he was shot through his
					shield, and plucking the spear out of his wound, with the
					same he slew his adversary. When he was asked how he
					came to be wounded, My shield, said he, betrayed me.
					It was his fortune to be slain in battle, as he endeavored to
					liberate the Grecians that were in Thrace. These sent an
					embassy to Lacedaemon, which made a visit to his mother,
					who first asked them whether Brasidas died honorably.
					When the Thracians praised him, and affirmed that there
					would never be such another man, My friends, said she,
					you are mistaken; Brasidas indeed was a valiant man, but
					Lacedaemon hath many more valiant men than he.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="59">
            <head>AGIS</head>
            <p>AGIS. King Agis said, The Lacedaemonians are not wont
					to ask how many, but where the enemy are. At Mantinea
					he was advised not to fight the enemy that exceeded him
					in number. It is necessary, said he, for him to fight with
					many, who would rule over many. The Eleans were commended for managing the Olympic games honorably. What
					wonder, said he, do they do, if one day in four years they
					do justice? When the same persons enlarged in their
					commendation, What wonder is it, said he, if they use
					justice honorably, which is an honorable thing? To a
					lewd person, that often asked who was the best man among
					the Spartans, he answered. He that is most unlike you.
					When another asked what was the number of the Lacedaemonians,&mdash;Sufficient, said he, to defend themselves from
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.219"/>
					
					wicked men. To another that asked him the same question, If you should see them fight, said he, you would
					think them to be many.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="60">
            <head>LYSANDER</head>
            <p>LYSANDER. Dionysius the Tyrant presented Lysander's
					daughters with rich garments, which he refused to accept,
					saying he feared they would seem more deformed in them.
					To such as blamed him for managing much of his affairs
					by stratagems, which was unworthy of Hercules from
					whom he was descended, he answered, Where the lion's
					skin will not reach, it must be pieced with the fox's. When
					the citizens of Argos seemed to make out a better title than
					the Lacedaemonians to a country that was in dispute between them, drawing his sword, He that is master of this,
					said he, can best dispute about bounds of countries. When
					the Lacedaemonians delayed to assault the walls of Corinth,
					and he saw a hare leap out of the trench; Do you fear, said
					he, such enemies as these, whose laziness suffers hares to
					sleep on their walls? To an inhabitant of Megara, that in
					a parley spoke confidently unto him, Your words, said he,
					want the breeding of the city.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="61">
            <head>AGESILAUS</head>
            <p>AGESILAUS. Agesilaus said that the inhabitants of Asia
					were bad freemen and good servants. When they were wont
					to call the king of Persia the Great King, Wherein, said he,
					is he greater than I, if he is not more just and wise than I am?
					Being asked which was better, valor or justice, he answered,
					We should have no need of valor, if we were all just.
					When he broke up his camp suddenly by night in the enemy's country, and saw a lad he loved left behind by reason
					of sickness, and weeping, It is a hard thing, said he, to be
					pitiful and wise at the same time. Menecrates the physician, surnamed Jupiter, inscribed a letter to him thus:
					Menecrates Jupiter to King Agesilaus wisheth joy. And
					he returned in answer: King Agesilaus to Menecrates
					wisheth his wits. When the Lacedaemonians overcame
					the Athenians and their confederates at Corinth, and he
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.220"/>
					
					heard the number of the enemies that were slain; Alas,
					said he, for Greece, who hath destroyed so many of her men
					as were enough to have conquered all the barbarians together. He had received an answer from the Oracle of
					Jupiter in Olympia, which was to his satisfaction. Afterwards the Ephori bade him consult Apollo in the same
					case; and to Delphi he went, and asked that God whether
					he was of the same mind with his father. He interceded
					for one of his friends with Idrieus of Caria, and wrote to
					him thus: If Nicias has not offended, set him free; but
					if he is guilty, set him free for my sake; by all means
					set him free. Being exhorted to hear one that imitated
					the voice of a nightingale, I have often, said he, heard
					nightingales themselves. The law ordained that such as
					ran away should be disgraced. After the fight at Leuctra,
					the Ephori, seeing the city void of men, were willing
					to dispense with that disgrace, and empowered Agesilaus
					to make a law to that purpose. But he standing in the
					midst commanded that after the next day the laws should
					remain in force as before. He was sent to assist the king
					of Egypt, with whom he was besieged by enemies that
					outnumbered his own forces; and when they had entrenched their camp, the king commanded him to go out
					and fight them. Since, said he, they intend to make themselves equal to us, I will not hinder them. When the
					trench was almost finished, he drew up his men in the void
					space, and so fighting with equal advantage he overcame
					them. When he was dying, he charged his friends that
					no fiction or counterfeit (so he called statues) should be
					made for him; For if, said he, I have done any honorable
					exploit, that is my monument; but if I have done none, all
					your statues will signify nothing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="62">
            <head>ARCHIDAMUS</head>
            <p>ARCHIDAMUS. When Archidamus, the son of Agesilaus,
					beheld a dart to be shot from an engine newly brought out
					of Sicily, he cried out, O Hercules! the valor of man is
					at an end.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="63">
            <head>AGIS THE YOUNGER</head>
            <pb id="v.1.p.221"/>
            <p>AGIS THE YOUNGER. Demades said, the Laconians'
					swords were so small, that jugglers might swallow them.
					That may be, said Agis, but the Lacedaemonians can reach
					their enemies very well with them. The Ephori ordered
					him to deliver his soldiers to a traitor. I will not, said
					he, entrust him with strangers, who betrayed his own
					men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="64">
            <head>CLEOMENES</head>
            <p>CLEOMENES. To one that promised to give him hardy
					cocks, that would die fighting, Prithee, said he, give me
					cocks that will kill fighting.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="65">
            <head>PAEDARETUS</head>
            <p>PAEDARETUS. Paedaretus, when he was not chosen
					among the Three Hundred (which was the highest office
					and honor in the city), went away cheerfully and smiling,
					saying, he was glad if the city had three hundred better
					citizens than himself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="66">
            <head>DAMONIDAS</head>
            <p>DAMONIDAS. Damonidas, being placed by him that ordered the chorus in the last rank of it, said: Well done,
					you have found a way to make this place also honorable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="67">
            <head>NICOSTRATUS</head>
            <p>NICOSTRATUS. Archidamus, general of the Argives, enticed Nicostratus to betray a fort, by promises of a great
					sum, and the marriage of what Lacedaemonian lady he
					pleased except the king's daughters. He answered, that
					Archidamus was none of the offspring of Hercules, for he
					went about to punish wicked men, but Archidamus to corrupt honest men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="68">
            <head>EUDAEMONIDAS</head>
            <p>EUDAEMONIDAS. Eudaemonidas beholding Xenocrates,
					when he was old, in the Academy reading philosophy to
					his scholars, and being told he was in quest of virtue,
					asked: And when does he intend to practise it? Another
					time, when he heard a philosopher arguing that only the
					wise man can be a good general, This is a wonderful
					speech, said he, but he that saith it never heard the sound
					of trumpets.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="69">
            <head>ANTIOCHUS</head>
            <p>ANTIOCHUS. Antiochus being Ephor, when he heard
					Philip had given the Messenians a country, asked whether
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.222"/>
					
					he had granted them that they should be victorious when
					they fought for that country.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="70">
            <head>ANTALCIDAS</head>
            <p>ANTALCIDAS. To an Athenian that called the Lacedaemonians unlearned, Therefore we alone, said Antalcidas,
					have learned no mischief of you. To another Athenian
					that told him, Indeed, we have often driven you from the
					Cephissus, he replied, But we never drove you from
					the Eurotas. When a Sophist was beginning to recite
					the praise of Hercules; And who, said he, ever spoke
					against him?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="71">
            <head>EPAMINONDAS</head>
            <p>EPAMINONDAS. No panic fear ever surprised the army
					of the Thebans while Epaminondas was their general.
					He said, to die in war was the most honorable death,
					and the bodies of armed men ought to be exercised,
					not as wrestlers, but in a warlike manner. Wherefore he hated fat men, and dismissed one of them, saying, that three or four shields would scarce serve to secure
					his belly, which would not suffer him to see his members.
					He was so frugal in his diet that, being invited by a
					neighbor to supper, and finding there dishes, ointments, and junkets in abundance, he departed immediately, saying: I thought you were sacrificing, and not
					displaying your luxury. When his cook gave an account
					to his colleagues of the charges for several days, he was
					offended only at the quantity of oil; and when his colleagues wondered at him, I am not, said he, troubled at
					the charge, but that so much oil should be received into
					my body. When the city kept a festival, and all gave
					themselves to banquets and drinking, he was met by one
					of his acquaintance unadorned and in a thoughtful posture.
					He wondering asked him why he of all men should walk
					about in that manner. That all of you, said he, may be
					drunk and revel securely. An ill man, that had committed
					no great fault, he refused to discharge at the request of
					Pelopidas; when his miss entreated for him, he dismissed
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.223"/>
					
					him, saying: Whores are fitting to receive such presents,
					and not generals. The Lacedaemonians invaded the
					Thebans, and oracles were brought to Thebes, some that
					promised victory, others that foretold an overthrow. He
					ordered those to be placed on the right hand of the judgment seat, and these on the left. When they were placed
					accordingly, he rose up and said: If you will obey your
					commanders and unanimously resist your enemies, these
					are your oracles,&mdash;pointing to the better; but if you
					play the cowards, those,&mdash;pointing to the worser. Another time, as he drew nigh to the enemy, it thundered,
					and some that were about him asked him what he thought
					the Gods would signify by it. They signify, said he, that
					the enemy is thunderstruck and demented, since he pitches
					his camp in a bad place, when he was nigh to a better.
					Of all the happy and prosperous events that befell him,
					he said that in this he took most satisfaction, that he overcame the Lacedaemonians at Leuctra while his father and
					mother, that begot him, were living. Whereas he was
					wont to appear with his body anointed and a cheerful
					countenance, the day after that fight he came abroad meanly
					habited and dejected; and when his friends asked him
					whether any misfortune had befallen him, No, said he, but
					yesterday I was pleased more than became a wise man, and
					therefore to-day I chastise that immoderate joy. Perceiving the Spartans concealed their disasters, and desiring to
					discover the greatness of their loss, he did not give them
					leave to take away their dead altogether, but allowed each
					city to bury its own; whereby it appeared that above a
					thousand Lacedaemonians were slain. Jason, monarch of
					Thessaly, was at Thebes as their confederate, and sent two
					thousand pieces of gold to Epaminondas, then in great
					want; but he refused the gold, and when he saw Jason, he
					said: You are the first to commit violence. And borrowing fifty drachms of a citizen, with that money to supply
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.224"/>
					
					his army he invaded Peloponnesus. Another time, when
					the Persian king sent him thirty thousand darics, he chid
					Diomedon severely, asking him whether he sailed so far to
					bribe Epaminondas; and bade him tell the king, as long
					as he wished the prosperity of the Thebans, Epaminondas
					would be his friend gratis, but when he was otherwise
					minded, his enemy. When the Argives were confederates
					with the Thebans, the Athenian ambassadors then in
					Arcadia complained of both, and Callistratus the orator
					reproached the cities with Orestes and Oedipus. But
					Epaminondas stood up and said: We confess there hath
					been one amongst us that killed his father, and among the
					Argives one that killed his mother; but we banished those
					that did such things, and the Athenians entertained them.
					To some Spartans that accused the Thebans of many and
					great crimes, These indeed, said he, are they that have put
					an end to your short dialect. The Athenians made friendship and alliance with Alexander the tyrant of Pherae, who
					was an enemy to the Thebans, and who had promised to
					furnish them with flesh at half an obol a pound. And we,
					said Epaminondas, will supply them with wood to that flesh
					gratis; for if they grow meddlesome, we will make bold
					to cut all the wood in their country for them. Being desirous to keep the Boeotians, that were grown rusty by
					idleness, always in arms, when he was chosen their chief
					magistrate, he used to exhort them, saying: Yet consider
					what you do, my friends; for if I am your general, you
					must be my soldiers. He called their country, which was
					plain and open, the stage of war, which they could keep
					no longer than their hands were upon their shields. Chabrias, having slain a few Thebans near Corinth, that engaged too hotly near the walls, erected a trophy, which
					Epaminondas laughed at, saying, it was not a trophy, but
					a statue of Trivia, which they usually placed in the highway before the gates. One told him that the Athenians
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.225"/>
					
					had sent an army into Peloponnesus adorned with new
					armor. What then? said he, doth Antigenidas sigh because
					Telles hath got new pipes? (Now Antigenidas was an
					excellent piper, but Telles a vile one.) Understanding his
					shield-bearer had taken a great deal of money from a prisoner, Come, said he, give me the shield, and buy you a
					victualling-house to live in; for now you are grown rich
					and wealthy, you will not hazard your life as you did formerly. Being asked whether he thought himself or Chabrias or Iphicrates the better general, It is hard, said he,
					to judge while we live. After he returned out of Laconia,
					he was tried for his life, with his fellow-commanders, for
					continuing Boeotarch four months longer than the law
					allowed. He bade the other commanders lay the blame
					upon him, as if he had forced them, and for himself, he
					said, his actions were his best speech; but if any thing at
					all were to be answered to the judges, he entreated them,
					if they put him todeath, to write his fault upon his monument, that the Grecians might know that Epaminondas
					compelled the Thebans against their will to plunder and fire
					Laconia,&mdash;which in five hundred years before had never
					suffered the like,&mdash;to build Messene two hundred and
					thirty years after it was sacked, to unite the Arcadians,
					and to restore liberty to Greece; for those things were
					done in that expedition. Whereupon the judges arose
					with great laughter, and refused even to receive the votes
					against him. In his last fight, being wounded and carried
					into his tent, he called for Diaphantes and after him fcr
					Iollidas; and when he heard they were slain, he advised
					the Thebans to make their peace with the enemy, since
					they had never a general left them; as by the event proved
					true.. So well did he understand his countrymen.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="72">
            <head>PELOPIDAS</head>
            <p>PELOPIDAS. Pelopidas, Epaminondas's colleague, when
					his friends told him that he neglected a necessary business,
					that was the gathering of money, replied: In good deed
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.226"/>
					
					money is necessary for this Nicomedas, pointing to a lame
					man that could not go. As he was going out to fight, his
					wife beseeched him to have a care of himself. To others
					you may give this advice, said he; but a commander and
					general you must advise that he should save his countrymen. A soldier told him, We are fallen among the enemies. Said he, How are we fallen among them, more than
					they among us? When Alexander, the tyrant of Pherae,
					broke his faith and cast him into prison, he reviled him;
					and when the other told him he did but hasten his death,
					That is my design, said he, that the Thebans may be exasperated against you, and be revenged on you the sooner.
					Thebe, the wife of the tyrant, came to him, and told him
					she wondered to see him so merry in chains. He answered,
					he wondered more at her, that she could endure Alexander without being chained. When Epaminondas caused
					him to be released, he said: I thank Alexander, for I have
					now found by trial that I have not only courage to fight,
					but to die.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="73">
            <head>Roman Apophthegms. M.' CURIUS</head>
            <p>M.' CURIUS. When some blamed M.' Curius for distributing but a small part of a country he took from the enemy,
					and preserving the greater part for the commonwealth, he
					prayed there might be no Roman who would think that
					estate little which was enough to maintain him. The
					Samnites after an overthrow came to him to offer him
					gold, and found him boiling rape-roots. He answered the
					Samnites that he that could sup so wanted no gold, and
					that he had rather rule over those who had gold than have
					it himself.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.227"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="74">
            <head>C. FABRICIUS</head>
            <p>C. FABRICIUS. C. Fabricius, hearing Pyrrhus had overthrown the Romans, told Labienus, it was Pyrrhus, not
					the Epirots, that beat the Romans. He went to treat
					about exchange of prisoners with Pyrrhus, who offered
					him a great sum of gold, which he refused. The next day
					Pyrrhus commanded a very large elephant should secretly
					be placed behind Fabricius, and discover himself by roaring; whereupon Fabricius turned and smiled, saying, I was
					not astonished either at your gold yesterday or at your beast
					to-day. Pyrrhus invited him to tarry with him, and to
					accept of the next command under him: That, said he,
					will be inconvenient for you; for, when the Epirots know
					us both, they will rather have me for their king than you.
					When Fabricius was consul, Pyrrhus's physician sent him
					a letter, wherein he promised him that, if he commanded
					him, he would poison Pyrrhus. Fabricius sent the letter
					to Pyrrhus, and bade him conclude that he was a very bad
					judge both of friends and enemies. The plot was discovered; Pyrrhus hanged his physician, and sent the Roman
					prisoners he had taken without ransom as a present to Fabricius. He, however, refused to accept them, but returned
					the like number, lest he might seem to receive a reward.
					Neither did he disclose the conspiracy out of kindness to
					Pyrrhus, but that the Romans might not seem to kill him
					by treachery, as if they despaired to conquer him in open
					war.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="75">
            <head>FABIUS MAXIMUS</head>
            <p>FABIUS MAXIMUS. Fabius Maximus would not fight,
					but chose to spin away the time with Hannibal,&mdash;who
					wanted both money and provision for his army,&mdash;by
					pursuing and facing him in rocky and mountainous places.
					When many laughed at him and called him Hannibal's
					schoolmaster, he took little notice of them, but pursued
					his own design, and told his friends: He that is afraid of
					scoffs and reproaches is more a coward than he that
					flies from the enemy. When Minucius, his fellow-consul,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.228"/>
					
					upon routing a party of the enemy, was highly extolled as
					a man worthy of Rome; I am more afraid, said he, of
					Minucius's success than of his misfortune. And not long
					after he fell into an ambush, and was in danger of perishing with his forces, until Fabius succored him, slew many
					of the enemy, and brought him off. Whereupon Hannibal
					told his friends: Did I not often presage that cloud on the
					hills would some time or other break upon us? After the
					city received the great overthrow at Cannae, he was chosen
					consul with Marcellus, a daring person and much desirous
					to fight Hannibal, whose forces, if nobody fought him, he
					hoped would shortly disperse and be dissolved. Therefore
					Hannibal said, he feared fighting Marcellus less than
					Fabius who would not fight. He was informed of a
					Lucanian soldier that frequently wandered out of the
					camp by night after a woman he loved, but otherwise an
					admirable soldier; he caused his mistress to be seized
					privately and brought to him. When she came, he sent
					for the soldier and told him: It is known you lie out
					a nights, contrary to the law; but your former good behavior is not forgotten, therefore your faults are forgiven
					to your merits. Henceforwards you shall tarry with me,
					for I have your surety. And he brought out the woman
					to him. Hannibal kept Tarentum with a garrison, all
					but the castle; and Fabius drew the enemy far from it,
					and by a stratagem took the town and plundered it.
					When his secretary asked what was his pleasure as to
					the holy images, Let us leave, said he, the Tarentines
					their offended Gods. When M. Livius, who kept a
					garrison in the castle, said he took Tarentum by his
					assistance, others laughed at him; but said Fabius, You
					say true, for if you had not lost the city, I had not retook it. When he was ancient, his son was consul, and
					as he was discharging his office publicly with many
					attendants, he met him on horseback. The young man
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.229"/>
					
					sent a sergeant to command him to alight; when others
					were at a stand, Fabius presently alighted, and running
					faster than for his age might be expected, embraced his
					son. Well done, son, said he, I see you are wise, and
					know whom you govern, and the grandeur of the office
					you have undertaken.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="76">
            <head>SCIPIO THE ELDER</head>
            <p>SCIPIO THE ELDER. Scipio the Elder spent on his
					studies what leisure the campaign and government would
					allow him, saying, that he did most when he was idle.
					When he took Carthage by storm, some soldiers took
					prisoner a very beautiful virgin, and came and presented
					her to him. I would receive her, said he, with all
					my heart, if I were a private man and not a governor.
					While he was besieging the city of Badia, wherein
					appeared above all a temple of Venus, he ordered
					appearances to be given for actions to be tried before
					him within three days in that temple of Venus; and he
					took the city, and was as good as his word. One asked
					him in Sicily, on what confidence he presumed to pass
					with his navy against Carthage. He showed him three
					hundred disciplined men in armor, and pointed to a
					high tower on the shore; There is not one of these,
					said he, that would not at my command go to the top
					of that tower, and cast himself down headlong. Over
					he went, landed, and burnt the enemy's camp, and the
					Carthaginians sent to him, and covenanted to surrender
					their elephants, ships, and a sum of money. But when
					Hannibal was sailed back from Italy, their reliance on
					him made them repent of those conditions. This coming
					to Scipio's ear, Nor will I, said he, stand to the agreement
					if they will, unless they pay me five thousand talents more
					for sending for Hannibal. The Carthaginians, when they
					were utterly overthrown, sent ambassadors to make peace
					and league with him; he bade those that came return immediately, as refusing to hear them before they brought
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.230"/>
					
					L. Terentius with them, a good man, whom the Carthaginians had taken prisoner. When they brought him, he
					placed him in the council next himself, on the judgment-seat, and then he transacted with the Carthaginians and
					put an end to the war. And Terentius followed him when
					he triumphed, wearing the cap of one that was made free;
					and when he died, Scipio gave wine mingled with honey to
					those that were at the funeral, and performed other funeral
					rites in his honor. But these things were done afterwards.
					King Antiochus, after the Romans invaded him, sent to
					Scipio in Asia for peace; That should have been done
					before, said he, not now when you have received a bridle
					and a rider. The senate decreed him a sum of money out
					of the treasury, but the treasurers refused to open it on
					that day. Then, said he, I will open it myself, for the
					moneys with which I filled it caused it to be shut.
					When Paetilius and Quintus accused him of many crimes
					before the people,&mdash;On this very day, said he, I conquered
					Hannibal and Carthage; I for my part am going with
					my crown on to the Capitol to sacrifice; and let him that
					pleaseth stay and pass his vote upon me. Having thus
					said, he went his way; and the people followed him, leaving his accusers declaiming to themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="77">
            <head>T. QUINCTIUS</head>
            <p>T. QUINCTIUS. T. Quinctius was eminent so early, that
					before he had been tribune, praetor, or aedile, he was
					chosen consul. Being sent as general against Philip, he
					was persuaded to come to a conference with him. And
					when Philip demanded hostages of him, because he was
					accompanied with many Romans while the Macedonians
					had none but himself; You, said Quinctius, have created
					this solitude for yourself, by killing your friends and kindred. Having overcome Philip in battle, he proclaimed
					in the Isthmian games that the Grecians were free and
					to be governed by their own laws. And the Grecians
					redeemed all the Roman prisoners that in Hannibal's days
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.231"/>
					
					were sold for slaves in Greece, each of them with two
					hundred drachms, and made him a present of them; and
					they followed him in Rome in his triumph, wearing caps
					on their heads such as they use to wear who are made free.
					He advised the Achaeans, who designed to make war
					upon the Island Zacynthus, to take heed lest, like a tortoise,
					they should endanger their head by thrusting it out of
					Peloponnesus. When King Antiochus was coming upon
					Greece with great forces, and all men trembled at the
					report of his numbers and equipage, he told the Achaeans
					this story: Once I dined with a friend at Chalcis, and
					when I wondered at the variety of dishes, said my host,
					<q direct="unspecified">All these are pork, only in dressing and sauces they differ.</q> And therefore be not you amazed at the king's
					forces, when you hear talk of spearmen and men-at-arms
					and choice footmen and horse-archers, for all these are but
					Syrians, with some little difference in their weapons. Philopoemen, general of the Achaeans, had good store of
					horses and men-at-arms, but could not tell what to do for
					money; and Quinctius played upon him, saying, Philopoemen had arms and legs, but no belly; and it happened
					his body was much after that shape.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="78">
            <head>CNEUS DOMITIUS</head>
            <p>CNEUS DOMITIUS. Cneus Domitius,&mdash;whom Scipio the
					Great sent in his stead to attend his brother Lucius in the
					war against Antiochus,&mdash;when he had viewed the enemy's army, and the commanders that were with him advised him to set upon them presently, said to them: We
					shall scarce have time enough now to kill so many thousands, plunder their baggage, return to our camp, and
					refresh ourselves too; but we shall have time enough to
					do all this to-morrow. The next day he engaged them,
					and slew fifty thousand of the enemy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="79">
            <head>PUBLIUS LICINIUS</head>
            <p>PUBLIUS LICINIUS. Publius Licinius, consul and general,
					being worsted in a horse engagement by Perseus king of
					Macedon, with what were slain and what were took prisoners,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.232"/>
					
					 lost two thousand eight hundred men. Presently
					after the fight, Perseus sent ambassadors to make peace
					and league with him; and although he was overcome, yet
					he advised the conqueror to submit himself and his affairs
					to the pleasure of the Romans.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="80">
            <head>PAULUS AEMILIUS</head>
            <p>PAULUS AEMILIUS. Paulus Aemilius, when he stood for
					his second consulship, was rejected. Afterwards, the war
					with Perseus and the Macedonians being prolonged by the.
					ignorance and effeminacy of the commanders, they chose
					him consul. I thank, said he, the people for nothing;
					they choose me general, not because I want the office, but
					because they want an officer. As he returned from the
					hall to his own house, and found his little daughter Tertia
					weeping, he asked her what she cried for? Perseus,
					said she (so her little dog was called), is dead. Luckily
					hast thou spoken, girl, said he, and I accept the omen.
					When he found in the camp much confident prating among
					the soldiers, who pretended to advise him and busy themselves as if they had been all officers, he bade them be quiet
					and only whet their swords, and leave other things to his
					care.</p>
            <p>He ordered night-guards should be kept without swords
					or spears, that they might resist sleep, when they had
					nothing wherewith to resist the enemy. He invaded Macedonia by the way of the mountains; and seeing the enemy
					drawn up, when Nasica advised him to set upon them presently, he replied: So I should, if I were of your age; but
					long experience forbids me, after a march, to fight an army
					marshalled regularly. Having overcome Perseus, he feasted
					his friends for joy of the victory, saying, it required the
					same skill to make an army very terrible to the enemy, and
					a banquet very acceptable to our friends. When Perseus
					was taken prisoner, he told Paulus that he would not be
					led in triumph. That, said he, is as you please,&mdash;meaning he might kill himself. He found an infinite quantity
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.233"/>
					
					of money, but kept none for himself; only to his son-in-law Tubero he gave a silver bowl that weighed five pounds,
					as a reward of his valor; and that, they say, was the first
					piece of plate that belonged to the Aemilian family. Of
					the four sons he had, he parted with two that were adopted
					into other families; and of the two that lived with him,
					one of them died at the age of fourteen years, but five
					days before his triumph; and five days after the triumph,
					at the age of twelve years died the other. When the
					people that met him bemoaned and compassionated his
					calamities, Now, said he, my fears and jealousies for my
					country are over, since Fortune hath discharged her revenge
					for our success on my house, and I have paid for all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="81">
            <head>CATO THE ELDER</head>
            <p>CATO THE ELDER. Cato the Elder, in a speech to the
					people, inveighed against luxury and intemperance. How
					hard, said he, is it to persuade the belly, that hath no
					ears? And he wondered how that city was preserved
					wherein a fish was sold for more than an ox! Once he
					scoffed at the prevailing imperiousness of women: All
					other men, said he, govern their wives; but we command
					all other men, and our wives us. He said he had rather
					not be rewarded for his good deeds than not punished for
					his evil deeds; and at any time he could pardon all other
					offenders besides himself. He instigated the magistrates
					to punish all offenders, saying, that they that did not prevent crimes when they might encouraged them. Of young
					men, he liked them that blushed better than those who
					looked pale; and hated a soldier that moved his hands as
					he walked and his feet as he fought, and whose sneeze
					was louder than his outcry when he charged. He said, he
					was the worst governor who could not govern himself. It
					was his opinion that every one ought especially to reverence himself; for every one was always in his own presence. When he saw many had their statues set up, I had
					rather, says he, men should ask why Cato had no statue,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.234"/>
					
					than why he had one. He exhorted those in power to be
					sparing of exercising their power, that they might continue
					in power. They that separate honor from virtue, said he,
					separate virtue from youth. A governor, said he, or judge
					ought to do justice without entreaty, not injustice upon entreaty. He said, that injustice, if it did not endanger the
					authors, endangered all besides. He requested old men
					not to add the disgrace of wickedness to old age, which
					was accompanied with many other evils. He thought an
					angry man differed from a madman only in the shorter
					time which his passion endured. He thought that they
					who enjoyed their fortunes decently and moderately, were
					far from being envied; For men do not envy us, said he,
					but our estates. He said, they that were serious in ridiculous matters would be ridiculous in serious affairs. Honorable actions ought to succeed honorable sayings; Lest,
					said he, they lose their reputation. He blamed the people
					for always choosing the same men officers; For either you
					think, said he, the government little worth, or very few fit
					to govern. He pretended to wonder at one that sold an
					estate by the seaside, as if he were more powerful than
					the sea; for he had drunk up that which the sea could
					hardly drown. When he stood for the consulship, and saw
					others begging and flattering the people for votes, he
					cried out aloud: The people have need of a sharp physician and a great purge; therefore not the mildest but
					the most inexorable person is to be chosen. For which
					word he was chosen before all others. Encouraging young
					men to fight boldly, he oftentimes said, The speech and
					voice terrify and put to flight the enemy more than the
					hand and sword. As he warred against Baetica, he was
					outnumbered by the enemy, and in danger. The Celtiberians offered for two hundred talents to send him a supply,
					and the Romans would not suffer him to engage to pay wages to barbarians. You are out, said he; for if we overcome,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.235"/>
					
					not we but the enemy must pay them; if we are routed,
					there will be nobody to demand nor to pay either. Having taken more cities, as he saith, than he stayed days in
					the enemies' country, he reserved no more of the prey for
					himself than what he ate or drank. He distributed to
					every soldier a round of silver, saying, It was better many
					should return out of the campaign with silver than a few
					with gold; for governors ought to gain nothing by their
					governments but honor. Five servants waited on him in
					the army, whereof one had bought three prisoners; and
					understanding Cato knew it, before he came into his presence he hanged himself. Being requested by Scipio Africanus to befriend the banished Achaeans, that they might
					return to their own country, he made as if he would not be
					concerned in that business; but when the matter was disputed in the senate, rising up, he said: We sit here, as
					if we had nothing else to do but to argue about a few old
					Grecians, whether they shall be carried to their graves by
					our bearers or by those of their own country. Posthumus Albinus wrote a history in Greek, and in it begs the
					pardon of his readers. Said Cato, jeering him, If the Amphictyonic Council commanded him to write it, he ought to
					be pardoned.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="82">
            <head>SCIPIO JUNIOR</head>
            <p>SCIPIO JUNIOR. It is reported that Scipio Junior never
					bought nor sold nor built any thing for the space of fifty-four years, and so long as he lived; and that of so great
					an estate, he left but thirty-three pounds of silver, and two
					of gold behind him, although he was lord of Carthage,
					and enriched his soldiers more than other generals. He
					observed the precept of Polybius, and endeavored never to
					return from the forum, until by some means or other he
					had engaged some one he lighted on to be his friend or companion. While he was yet young, he had such a repute
					for valor and knowledge, that Cato the Elder, being asked
					his opinion of the commanders in Africa, of whom Scipio
					was one, answered in that Greek verse,&mdash;
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.236"/>
					
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Others like shadows fly;</l>
						            <l>He only is wise.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>See Odyss. X. 495.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>When he came from the army to Rome, the people preferred him, not to gratify him, but because they hoped by
					his assistance to conquer Carthage with more ease and
					speed. After he was entered the walls, the Carthaginians
					defended themselves in the castle, separated by the sea,
					not very deep. Polybius advised him to scatter caltrops
					in the water, or planks with iron spikes, that the enemy
					might not pass over to assault their bulwark. He answered, that it was ridiculous for those who had taken
					the walls and were within the city to contrive how they
					might not fight with the enemy. He found the city full of
					Greek statues and presents brought thither from Sicily, and
					made proclamation that such as were present from those
					cities might claim and carry away what belonged to them.
					When others plundered and carried away the spoil, he
					would not suffer any that belonged to him, either slave
					or freeman, to take, nor so much as to buy any of it. He
					assisted C. Laelius, his most beloved friend, when he stood
					to be consul, and asked Pompey (who was thought to be a
					piper's son) whether he stood or not. He replied, No;
					and besides promised to join with them in going about and
					procuring votes, which they believed and expected, but
					were deceived; for news was brought that Pompey was
					in the forum, fawning on and soliciting the citizens for
					himself; whereat others being enraged, Scipio laughed.
					We may thank our own folly for this, said he, that, as if we
					were not to request men but the Gods, we lose our time
					in waiting for a piper. When he stood to be censor, Appius Claudius, his rival, told him that he could salute all
					the Romans by their names, whereas Scipio scarce knew any
					of them. You say true, said he, for it hath been my care
					not to know many, but that all might know me. He advised
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.237"/>
					
					 the city, which then had an army in Celtiberia, to
					send them both to the army, either as tribunes or lieutenants, that thus the soldiers might be witnesses and judges
					of the valor of each of them. When he was made censor,
					he took away his horse from a young man, who, in the
					time while Carthage was besieged, made a costly supper,
					in which was a honey-cake, made after the shape of that
					city, which he named Carthage and set before his guests
					to be plundered by them; and when the young man asked
					the reason why he took his horse from him, he said, Because you plundered Carthage before me. As he saw C.
					Licinius coming towards him, I know, said he, that man is
					perjured; but since nobody accuses him, I cannot be his
					accuser and judge too. The senate sent him thrice, as
					Clitomachus saith, to take cognizance of men, cities, and
					manners, as an overseer of cities, kings, and countries.
					As he came to Alexandria and landed, he went with his
					head covered, and the Alexandrians running about him entreated he would gratify them by uncovering and showing
					them his desirable face. When he uncovered his head,
					they clapped their hands with a loud acclamation. The
					king, by reason of his laziness and corpulency, making a
					hard shift to keep pace with them, Scipio whispered softly
					to Panaetius: The Alexandrians have already received
					some benefit of our visit, for upon our account they have
					seen their king walk. There travelled with him one
					friend, Panaetius the philosopher, and five servants, whereof
					one dying in the journey, he would not buy another, but
					sent for one to Rome. The Numantines seemed invincible, and having overcome several generals, the people the
					second time chose Scipio general in that war. When
					great numbers strived to list them in his army, even that
					the senate forbade, as if Italy thereby would be left destitute. Nor did they allow him money that was in bank, but
					ordered him to receive the revenues of tributes that were
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.238"/>
					
					not yet payable. As to money, Scipio said he wanted none,
					for of his own and by his friends he could be supplied;
					but of the decree concerning the soldiers he complained,
					for the war (he said) was a hard and difficult one, whether
					their defeat had been caused by the valor of the enemy or
					by the cowardice of their own men. When he came to
					the army, he found there much disorder, intemperance,
					superstition, and luxury. Immediately he drove away the
					soothsayers, priests, and panders. He ordered them to
					send away their household stuff, all except kettles, a spit,
					and an earthen cup. He allowed a silver cup, weighing
					not more than two pounds, to such as desired it. He forbade them to bathe; and those that anointed themselves
					were to rub themselves too; for horses wanted another to
					rub them, he said, only because they had no hand of their
					own. He ordered them to eat their dinner standing, and
					to have only such food as was dressed without fire; but
					they might sit down at supper, to bread, plain porridge, and
					flesh boiled or roasted. He himself walked about clothed
					in a black cassock, saying, he mourned for the disgrace
					of the army. He met by chance with the pack-horses of
					Memmius, a tribune that carried wine-coolers set with
					precious stones, and the best Corinthian vessels. Since
					you are such a one, said he, you have made yourself useless to me and to your country for thirty days, but to yourself all your life long. Another showed him a shield well
					adorned. The shield, said he, young man, is a fine one,
					but it becomes a Roman to have his confidence placed
					rather in his right hand than in his left. To one that was
					building the rampart, saying his burthen was very heavy,
					And deservedly, said he, for you trust more to this wood
					than to your sword. When he saw the rash confidence of
					the enemy, he said that he bought security with time; for
					a good general, like a good physician, useth iron as his last
					remedy. And yet he fought when he saw it convenient,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.239"/>
					
					and routed the enemy. When they were worsted, the elder
					men chid them, and asked why they fled from those they
					had pursued so often. It is said a Numantine answered,
					The sheep are the same still, but they have another shepherd. After he had taken Numantia and triumphed a
					second time, he had a controversy with C. Gracchus concerning the senate and the allies; and the abusive people
					made a tumult about him as he spake from the pulpit;
					The outcry of the army, said he, when they charge, never
					disturbed me, much less the clamor of a rabble of newcomers, to whom Italy is a step-mother (I am well assured)
					and not a mother. And when they of Gracchus's party
					cried out, Kill the Tyrant,&mdash;No wonder, said he, that they
					who make war upon their country would kill me first; for
					Rome cannot fall while Scipio stands, nor can Scipio live
					when Rome is fallen.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="83">
            <head>CAECILIUS METELLUS</head>
            <p>CAECILIUS METELLUS. Caecilius Metellus designing to
					reduce a strong fort, a captain told him he would undertake to take it with the loss only of ten men; and he
					asked him, whether he himself would be one of those ten.
					A young colonel asked him what design he had in the
					wheel. If I thought my shirt knew, said he, I would
					pluck it off and burn it. He was at variance with Scipio
					in his lifetime, but he lamented at his death, and commanded
					his sons to assist at the hearse; and said, he gave the Gods
					thanks in the behalf of Rome, that Scipio was born in no
					other country.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="84">
            <head>C. MARIUS</head>
            <p>C. MARIUS. C. Marius was of obscure parentage, pursuing offices by his valor. He pretended to the chief
					aedileship, and perceiving he could not reach it, the same
					day he stood for the lesser, and missing of that also, yet
					for all that he did not despair of being consul. Having a
					wen on each leg, he suffered one to be cut, and endured
					the surgeon without binding, not so much as sighing or
					once contracting his eyebrows; but when the surgeon
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.240"/>
					
					would cut the other, he did not suffer him, saying the cure
					was not worth the pain. In his second consulship, Lucius
					his sister's son offered unchaste force to Trebonius, a soldier, who slew him; when many pleaded against him, he
					did not deny but confessed he killed the colonel, and told
					the reason why. Hereupon Marius called for a crown, the
					reward of extraordinary valor, and put it upon Trebonius's
					head. He had pitched his camp, when he fought against
					the Teutons, in a place where water was wanting; when
					the soldiers told him they were thirsty, he showed them a
					river running by the enemy's trench. Look you, said he,
					there is water for you, to be bought for blood; and they
					desired him to conduct them to fight, while their blood was
					fluent and not all dried up with thirst. In the Cimbrian
					war, he gave a thousand valiant Camertines the freedom of
					Rome, which no law did allow; and to such as blamed
					him for it he said, I could not hear the laws for the clash
					of arrows. In the civil war, he lay patiently entrenched
					and besieged, waiting for a fit opportunity; when Popedius
					Silon called to him,Marius, if you are so great a general come
					down and fight. And do you, said he, if you are so great
					a commander, force me to fight against my will, if you can.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="85">
            <head>LUTATIUS CATULUS</head>
            <p>LUTATIUS CATULUS. Lutatius Catulus in the Cimbrian
					war lay encamped by the side of the river Athesis, and his
					soldiers, seeing the barbarians attempting to pass the river,
					gave back; when he could not make them stand, he
					hastened to the front of them that fled, that they might
					not seem to fly from their enemies but to follow their commander.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="86">
            <head>SYLLA</head>
            <p>SYLLA. Sylla, surnamed the Fortunate, reckoned these
					two things as the chiefest of his felicities,&mdash;the friendship of Metellus Pius, and that he had spared and not
					destroyed the city of Athens.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="87">
            <head>C. POPILIUS</head>
            <p>C. POPILIUS. C. Popilius was sent to Antiochus with a
					letter from the senate, commanding him to withdraw his
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.241"/>
					
					army out of Egypt, and to renounce the protection of that
					kingdom during the minority of Ptolemy's children. When
					he came towards him in his camp, Antiochus kindly saluted
					him at a distance, but without returning his salutation he
					delivered his letter; which being read, the king answered,
					that he would consider, and give his answer. Whereupon
					Popilius with his wand made a circle round him, saying, Consider and answer before you go out of this place; and when
					Antiochus answered that he would give the Romans satisfaction, then at length Popilius saluted and embraced him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="88">
            <head>LUCULLUS</head>
            <p>LUCULLUS. Lucullus in Armenia, with ten thousand foot in
					armor and a thousand horse, was to fight Tigranes and his
					army of a hundred and fifty thousand, the day before the
					nones of October, the same day on which formerly Scipio's
					army was destroyed by the Cimbrians. When one told
					him, The Romans dread and abominate that day; Therefore,
					said he, let us fight to-day valiantly, that we may change
					this day from a black and unlucky one to a joyful and
					festival day for the Romans. His soldiers were most afraid
					of their men-at-arms; but he bade them be of good courage,
					for it was more labor to strip than to overcome them. He
					first came up to their counterscarp, and perceiving the
					confusion of the barbarians, cried out, Fellow-soldiers, the
					day's our own! And when nobody stood him, he pursued,
					and, with the loss of five Romans, slew above a hundred
					thousand of them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="89">
            <head>CN. POMPEIUS</head>
            <p>CN. POMPEIUS. Cn. Pompeius was as much beloved by
					the Romans as his father was hated. When he was young,
					he wholly sided with Sylla, and before he had borne many
					offices or was chosen into the senate, he enlisted many
					soldiers in Italy. When Sylla sent for him, he returned
					answer, that he would not muster his forces in the presence
					of his general, unfleshed and without spoils; nor did he
					come before that in several fights he had overcome the
					captains of the enemy. He was sent by Sylla lieutenant-general
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.242"/>
					
					 into Sicily, and being told that the soldiers turned
					out of the way and forced and plundered the country, he
					sealed the swords of such as he sent abroad, and punished
					all other stragglers and wanderers. He had resolved to
					put the Mamertines, that were of the other side, all to the
					sword; but Sthenius the orator told him, He would do injustice if he should punish many that were innocent for
					the sake of one that was guilty; and that he himself
					was the person that persuaded his friends and forced his
					enemies to side with Marius. Pompey admired the man,
					and said, he could not blame the Mamertines for being
					inveigled by a person who preferred his country beyond
					his own life; and forgave both the city and Sthenius
					too. When he passed into Africa against Domitius and
					overcame him in a great battle, the soldiers saluted him
					Imperator. He answered, he could not receive that
					honor, so long as the fortification of the enemy's camp
					stood undemolished; upon this, although it rained hard,
					they rushed on and plundered the camp. At his return, among other courtesies and honors wherewith Sylla
					entertained him, he styled him The Great; yet when he
					was desirous to triumph, Sylla would not consent, because
					he was not yet chosen into the senate. But when Pompey
					said to those that were about him, Sylla doth not know
					that more worship the rising than the setting sun, Sylla
					cried aloud, Let him triumph. Hereat Servilius, one of
					the nobles, was displeased; the soldiers also withstood his
					triumph, until he had bestowed a largess among them.
					But when Pompey replied, I would rather forego my
					triumph than flatter them,&mdash;Now, said Servilius, I see
					Pompey is truly great and worthy of a triumph. It was a
					custom in Rome, that knights who had served in the wars
					the time appointed by the laws should bring their horse
					into the forum before the censors, and there give an
					account of their warfare and the commanders under whom
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.243"/>
					
					they had served. Pompey, then consul, brought also his
					horse before the censors, Gellius and Lentulus; and when
					they asked him, as the manner is, whether he had served
					all his campaigns, All, said he, and under myself as
					general. Having gotten into his hands the writings of
					Sertorius in Spain, among which were letters from
					several leading men in Rome, inviting Sertorius to Rome
					to innovate and change the government, he burnt them
					all, by that means giving opportunity to ill-affected persons to repent and mend their manners. Phraates, king
					of Parthia, sent to him requesting that the river Euphrates
					might be his bounds. He answered, the Romans had
					rather the right should be their bounds towards Parthia.
					L. Lucullus, after he left the army, gave himself up to
					pleasure and luxury, jeering at Pompey for busying himself
					in affairs unsuitable to his age. He answered, that government became old age better than luxury. In a fit of sickness, his physician prescribed him to eat a thrush; but
					when none could be gotten, because they were out of
					season, one said, that Lucullus had some, for he kept them
					all the year. It seems then, said he, Pompey must not live,
					unless Lucullus play the glutton; and dismissing the physician, he ate such things as were easy to be gotten. In a
					great dearth at Rome, he was chosen by title overseer of
					the market, but in reality lord of sea and land, and sailed
					to Africa, Sardinia, and Sicily. Having procured great
					quantities of wheat, he hastened back to Rome; and when
					by reason of a great tempest the pilots were loath to hoist
					sail, he went first aboard himself, and commanding the
					anchor to be weighed, cried out aloud, There is a necessity
					of sailing, but there is no necessity of living. When the
					difference betwixt him and Caesar broke out, and Marcellinus, one of those whom he had preferred, revolted to
					Caesar and inveighed much against Pompey in the senate;
					Art thou not ashamed, said he, Marcellinus, to reproach
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.244"/>
					
					me, who taught you to speak when you were dumb, and
					fed you full even to vomiting when you were starved? To
					Cato, who severely blamed him because, when he had
					often informed him of the growing power of Caesar, such
					as was dangerous to a democracy, he took little notice of
					it, he answered, Your counsels were more presaging, but
					mine more friendly. Concerning himself he freely professed, that he entered all his offices sooner than he expected, and resigned them sooner than was expected by
					others. After the fight at Pharsalia, in his flight towards
					Egypt, as he was going out of the ship into the fisher-boat
					the king sent to attend him, turning to his wife and son, he
					said nothing to them beside those two verses of Sophocles:
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Whoever comes within a tyrant's door</l>
						            <l>Becomes his slave, though he were free before.</l>
               </quote>
					
					As he came out of the boat, when he was struck with a
					sword, he said nothing; but gave one groan, and covering
					his head submitted to the murderers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="90">
            <head>CICERO</head>
            <p>CICERO. Cicero the orator, when his name was played
					upon and his friends advised him to change it, answered,
					that he would make the name of Cicero more honorable
					than the name of the Catos, the Catuli, or the Scauri. He
					dedicated to the Gods a silver cup with a cover, with the
					first letters of his other names, and instead of Cicero a
					chick-pea (<hi rend="italics">cicer</hi>) engraven. Loud bawling orators, he
					said, were driven by their weakness to noise, as lame men
					to take horse. Verres had a son that in his youth had not
					well secured his chastity; yet he reviled Cicero for his
					effeminacy, and called him catamite. Do you not know,
					said he, that children are to be rebuked at home within
					doors? Metellus Nepos told him he had slain more by his
					testimony than he had saved by his pleadings. You say
					true, said he, my honesty exceeds my eloquence. When
					Metellus asked him who his father was, Your mother, said
					he, hath made that question a harder one for you to answer
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.245"/>
					
					than for me. For she was unchaste, while Metellus himself was a light, inconstant, and passionate man. The
					same Metellus, when Diodotus his master in rhetoric died,
					caused a marble crow to be placed on his monument; and
					Cicero said, he returned his master a very suitable gratuity, who had taught him to fly but not to declaim. Hearing
					that Vatinius, his enemy and otherwise a lewd person, was
					dead, and the next day that he was alive, A mischief on
					him, said he, for lying. To one that seemed to be an
					African, who said he could not hear him when he pleaded,
					And yet, said he, your ears are of full bore. He had summoned Popilius Cotta, an ignorant blockhead that pretended
					to the law, as a witness in a cause; and when he told the
					court he knew nothing of the business, On my conscience,
					I'll warrant you, said Cicero, he thinks you ask him a
					question in the law. Verres sent a golden sphinx as a
					present to Hortensius the orator, who told Cicero, when
					he spoke obscurely, that he was not skilled in riddles.
					That's strange, said he, since you have a sphinx in your
					house. Meeting Voconius with his three daughters that
					were hard favored, he told his friends softly that verse,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Children he hath got,</l>
						            <l>Though Apollo favored not.</l>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>When Faustus the son of Sylla, being very much in
					debt, set up a writing that he would sell his goods by auction, he said, I like this proscription better than his father's.
					When Pompey and Caesar fell out, he said, I know whom
					to fly from, but I know not whom to fly to. He blamed
					Pompey for leaving the city, and for imitating Themistocles
					rather than Pericles, when his affairs did not resemble the
					former's but the latter's. He changed his mind and went
					over to Pompey, who asked him where he left his soninlaw Piso. He answered, With your father-in-law Caesar.
					To one that went over from Caesar to Pompey, saying that
					in his haste and eagerness he had left his horse behind him,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.246"/>
					
					he said, You have taken better care of your horse than of
					yourself. To one that brought news that the friends of
					Caesar looked sourly, You do as good as call them, said
					he, Caesar's enemies. After the battle in Pharsalia, when
					Pompey was fled, one Nonius said they had seven eagles
					left still, and advised to try what they would do. Your
					advice, said he, were good, if we were to fight with jackdaws. Caesar, now conqueror, honorably restored the
					statues of Pompey that were thrown down; whereupon
					Cicero said, that Caesar by erecting Pompey's statues had
					secured his own. He set so high a value on oratory, and
					did so lay out himself especially that way, that having a
					cause to plead before the centumviri, when the day approached and his slave Eros brought him word it was
					deferred until the day following, he presently made him
					free.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="91">
            <head>C. CAESAR</head>
            <p>C. CAESAR. Caius Caesar, when he was a young man,
					fled from Sylla, and fell into the hands of pirates, who first
					demanded of him a sum of money; and he laughed at the
					rogues for not understanding his quality, and promised
					them twice as much as they asked him. Afterwards, when
					he was put into custody until he raised the money, he
					commanded them to be quiet and silent while he slept.
					While he was in prison, he made speeches and verses
					which he read to them, and when they commended them
					but coldly, he called them barbarians and blockheads, and
					threatened them in jest that he would hang them. But
					after a while he was as good as his word; for when the money
					for his ransom was brought and he discharged, he gathered
					men and ships out of Asia, seized the pirates and crucified
					them. At Rome he stood to be chief priest against Catulus, a
					man of great interest among the Romans. To his mother,
					who brought him to the gate, he said, To-day, mother, you
					will have your son high priest or banished. He divorced
					his wife Pompeia, because she was reported to be over
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.247"/>
					
					familiar with Clodius; yet when Clodius was brought to
					trial upon that account, and he was cited as a witness, he
					spake no evil against his wife; and when the accuser asked
					him, Why then did you divorce her?&mdash;Because, said he,
					Caesar's wife ought to be free even from suspicion. As
					he was reading the exploits of Alexander, he wept and
					told his friends, He was of my age when he conquered
					Darius, and I hitherto have done nothing. He passed by
					a little inconsiderable town in the Alps, and his friends
					said, they wondered whether there were any contentions
					and tumults for offices in that place. He stood, and after
					a little pause answered, I had rather be the first in this
					town than second in Rome. He said, great and surprising
					enterprises were not to be consulted upon, but done. And
					coming against Pompey out of his province of Gaul, he
					passed the river Rubicon, saying, Let every die be thrown.
					After Pompey fled to sea from Rome, he went to take
					money out of the treasury: when Metellus, who had the
					charge of it, forbade him and shut it against him, he
					threatened to kill him; whereupon Metellus being astonished, he said to him, This, young man, is harder for me to
					say than to do. When his soldiers were having a tedious
					passage from Brundisium to Dyrrachium, unknown to all
					he went aboard a small vessel, and attempted to pass the
					sea; and when the vessel was in danger of being overset,
					he discovers himself to the pilot, crying out, Trust Fortune,
					and know that you carry Caesar. But the tempest being
					vehement, his soldiers coming about him and expostulating
					passionately with him, asking whether he distrusted them
					and was looking for another army, would not suffer him to
					pass at that time. They fought, and Pompey had the better of it; but instead of following his blow he retreated to
					his camp. To-day, said Caesar, the enemy had the victory,
					but none of them know how to conquer. Pompey commanded his army to stand in array at Pharsalia in their
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.248"/>
					
					place, and to receive the charge from the enemy. In this
					Caesar said he was out, thereby suffering the eagerness of
					his soldiers' spirits, when they were up and inspired with
					rage and success, in the midst of their career to languish
					and expire. After he routed Pharnaces Ponticus at the
					first assault, he wrote thus to his friends, I came, I saw, I
					conquered.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">)=*hlqon, ei)=don, e)ni/khsa,</foreign> veni, vidi, vici.</note> After Scipio was worsted in Africa and fled,
					and Cato had killed himself, he said: I envy thee thy death,
					O Cato! since thou didst envy me the honor of saving thee.
					Antonius and Dolabella were suspected by his friends, who
					advised him to secure them; he answered, I fear none of
					those fat and lazy fellows, but those pale and lean ones,&mdash;
					meaning Brutus and Cassius. As he was at supper, the
					discourse was of death, which sort was the best. That,
					said he, which is unexpected.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="92">
            <head>CAESAR AUGUSTUS</head>
            <p>CAESAR AUGUSTUS. Caesar, who was the first surnamed
					Augustus, being yet young, demanded of Antony the twenty-five millions of money<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is doubtful what amount is here intended by Plutarch. If sesterces are understood, the amount is much less than it is commonly stated; and even if we understand drachmas (or denarii), we shall still fall below the amount commonly given,
						which is 700,000,000 sesterces (or about $28,000,000). See, for example, Veil
						Paterc. II. 60, 4: Sestertium septiens miliens. (G.)</note> which he had taken out of the
					house of Julius Caesar when he was slain, that he might
					pay the Romans the legacies he had left them, every man
					seventy-five drachms. But when Antony detained the
					money, and bade him, if he were wise, let fall his demand,
					he sent the crier to offer his own paternal estate for sale,
					and therewith discharged the legacies; by which means
					he procured a general respect to himself, and to Antony
					the hatred of the Romans. Rymetalces, king of Thrace,
					forsook Antony and went over to Caesar; but bragging
					immoderately in his drink, and nauseously reproaching his
					new confederates, Caesar drank to one of the other
					kings, and told him, I love treason but do not commend
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.249"/>
					
					traitors. The Alexandrians, when he had taken their city,
					expected great severity from him; but when he came upon
					the judgment-seat, he placed Arius the Alexandrian by
					him and told them: I spare this city, first because it is
					great and beautiful, secondly for the sake of its founder,
					Alexander, and thirdly for the sake of Arius my friend.
					When it was told him that Eros, his steward in Egypt,
					having bought a quail that beat all he came near and was
					never worsted by any, had roasted and eaten it, he sent for
					him; and when upon examination he confessed the fact,
					he ordered him to be nailed on the mast of the ship. He
					removed Theodorus, and in his stead made Arius his factor in Sicily, whereupon a petition was presented to him,
					in which was written, Theodorus of Tarsus is either a baldpate or a thief, what is your opinion? Caesar read it, and
					subscribed, I think so. Mecaenas, his intimate companion,
					presented him yearly on his birthday with a piece of plate.
					Athenodorus the philosopher, by reason of his old age,
					begged leave that he might retire from court, which Caesar
					granted; and as Athenodorus was taking his leave of him,
					Remember, said he, Caesar, whenever you are angry, to
					say or do nothing before you have repeated the four-and-twenty letters to yourself. Whereupon Caesar caught him
					by the hand and said, I have need of your presence still;
					and he kept him a year longer, saying, The reward of
					silence is a secure reward. He heard Alexander at the
					age of thirty-two years had subdued the greatest part of
					the world and was at a loss what he should do with the
					rest of his time. But he wondered Alexander should not
					think it a lesser labor to gain a great empire than to set in
					order what he had gotten. He made a law concerning
					adulterers, wherein was determined how the accused were
					to be tried and how the guilty were to be punished. Afterwards, meeting with a young man that was reported to
					have been familiar with his daughter Julia, being enraged
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.250"/>
					
					he struck him with his hands; but when the young man
					cried out, O Caesar! you have made a law, he was so
					troubled at it that he refrained from supper that day.
					When he sent Caius his daughter's son into Armenia, he
					begged of the Gods that the favor of Pompey, the valor
					of Alexander, and his own fortune might attend him.
					He told the Romans he would leave them one to succeed
					him in the government that never consulted twice in the
					same affair, meaning Tiberius. He endeavored to pacify
					some young men that were imperious in their offices; and
					when they gave little heed to him, but still kept a stir,
					Young men, said he, hear an old man to whom old men
					hearkened when he was young. Once, when the Athenians
					had offended him, he wrote to them from Aegina: I suppose
					you know I am angry with you, otherwise I had not wintered at Aegina. Besides this, he neither said nor did any
					thing to them. One of the accusers of Eurycles prated
					lavishly and unreasonably, proceeding so far as to say, If
					these crimes, O Caesar, do not seem great to you, command
					him to repeat to me the seventh book of Thucydides;
					wherefore Caesar being enraged commanded him to prison.
					But afterwards, when he heard he was descended from
					Brasidas, he sent for him again, and dismissed him with a
					moderate rebuke. When Piso built his house from top to
					bottom with great exactness, You cheer my heart, said he,
					who build as if Rome would be eternal.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>