<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De esu carnium II</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1957</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <head>ON THE EATING OF FLESH (DE ESU CARNIUM) II <lb/> INTRODUCTION</head>
            <pb id="v.12.p.563"/>
            <p>Reason urges us with fresh ideas and fresh zeal
					to attack again our yesterday's discourse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's introduction to the second essay on the <hi rend="italics">Fortune of Alexander</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 333 d).</note> on the
					eating of flesh. It is indeed difficult, as Cato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 131 d, 198 d; <hi rend="italics">Life of Cato Major</hi>, 8 (340 a).</note> remarked, to talk to bellies which have no ears. And
					the potion of familiarity has been drunk, like that of
					Circe<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, x. 236.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Commingling pains and pangs, tricks and tears<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps a verse of Empedocles: Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 372, frag. 154 a; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Wilamowitz, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xl, p. 165. (Andrews prefers to adopt the reading <foreign lang="greek">kukew/n</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">potion,</q> assuming a verbal form, <q direct="unspecified">dulls</q> or <q direct="unspecified">blunts,</q> in the preceding or following line.)</note>;</quote>
					nor is it easy to extract the hook of flesh-eating, entangled as it is and embedded in the love of pleasure.
					And, like the Egyptians e who extract the viscera of
					the dead and cut them open in view of the sun, then
					throw them away as being the cause of every single
					sin that the man had committed, it would be well
					for us to excise our own gluttony and lust to kill and
					become pure for the remainder of our lives, since it
					is not so much our belly that drives us to the pollution
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.565"/>
					
					of slaughter ; it is itself polluted by our incontinence.
					Yet if, for heaven's sake, it is really impossible for us
					to be free from error because we are on such terms
					of familiarity with it, let us at least be ashamed of
					our ill doing and resort to it only in reason. We shall
					eat flesh, but from hunger, not as a luxury. We shall
					kill an animal, but in pity and sorrow, not degrading
					or torturing it - which is the current practice in many
					cases, some thrusting red-hot spits into the throats
					of swine so that by the plunging in of the iron the
					blood may be emulsified and, as it circulates through
					the body, may make the flesh tender and delicate.
					Others jump upon the udders of sows<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 210-211 is not quite so gruesome.</note> about to give
					birth and kick them so that, when they have blended
					together blood and milk and gore (Zeus the Purifier I)
					and the unborn young have at the same time been
					destroyed at the moment of birth, they may eat the
					most inflamed part of the creature. Still others sew
					up the eyes of cranes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 60.</note> and swans,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wyttenbach reasonably suggested <q direct="unspecified">geese,</q> but see Athenaeus, 131 f; 393 c-d.</note> shut them up in
					darkness and fatten them, making the flesh appetizing
					with strange compounds and spicy mixtures.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>From these practices it is perfectly evident that
					it is not for nourishment or need or necessity, but
					out of satiety and insolence and luxury that they
					have turned this lawless custom into a pleasure.
					Then, just as with women who are insatiable in
					seeking pleasure, their lust tries everything, goes
					astray, and explores the gamut of profligacy until at
					last it ends in unspeakable practices ; so intemperance in eating passes beyond the necessary ends of
					nature and resorts to cruelty and lawlessness to give
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.567"/>
					
					variety to appetite. For it is in their own company
					that organs of sense are infected and won over and
					become licentious when they do not keep to natural
					standards. Just so the art of hearing has fallen sick,
					corrupting musical taste. From this our luxury and
					debauchery conceives a desire for shameful caresses
					and effeminate titillations. These taught the sight
					not to take pleasure in warlike exercises<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 816 b.</note> or gesticulations or refined dances or statues and paintings, but
					to regard the slaughter and death of men, their
					wounds and combats, as the most precious sort of
					spectacle.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Referring to the gladiatorial combats which came to be substituted for the more refined exhibitions of an earlier age. Plutarch urges the expulsion of such practices from the State in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 822 c; for further examples of this kind of opposition to Roman policy see H. Fuchs, <hi rend="italics">Der geistige Widerstand gegen Rom</hi>, p. 49, n. 60.</note> Just so intemperate intercourse follows
					a lawless meal, inharmonious music follows a shameful debauch, barbarous spectacles follow shameless
					songs and sounds, insensitivity and cruelty toward
					human kind follow savage exhibitions in the theatre.
					It was for this reason that the godlike Lycurgus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, xiii. 5-6 (47 b-c); <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 189 e, 227 c, 285 c; <hi rend="italics">Comment. on Hesiod</hi>, 42 (Bernardakis, vii, p. 72).</note>
					gave directions in certain <hi rend="italics">rhetrae</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or <q direct="unspecified">unwritten laws</q>; the mss. here say <q direct="unspecified">in the three <hi rend="italics">rhetrae</hi>.</q>
               </note> that the doors and
					roofs of houses should be fashioned by saw and axe
					alone and no other tool should be used-not of course
					because he had a quarrel with gimlets and adzes and
					other instruments for delicate work. It was because
					he knew that through such rough-hewn work you
					will not be introducing a gilded couch, nor will you
					be so rash as to bring silver tables and purple rugs
					and precious stones into a simple house. The corollary
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.569"/>
					
					of such a house and couch and table and cup is
					a dinner which is unpretentious and a lunch which
					is truly democratic ; but all manner of luxury and
					extravagance follow the lead of an evil way of life
					<quote rend="blockquote">As new-weaned foal beside his mother runs.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Semonides, frag. 5; see <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 446 e and the note.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>For what sort of dinner is not costly for which
					a living creature loses its life ? Do we hold a life
					cheap ? I do not yet go so far as to say that it may
					well be the life<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, <q direct="unspecified">the reincarnated life.</q>
               </note> of your mother or father or some
					friend or child, as Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As in frag. B 137 (Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 275).</note> declared. Yet it does,
					at least, possess some perception, hearing, seeing,
					imagination, intelligence, which last every creature
					receives from Nature to enable it to acquire what is
					proper for it and to evade what is not. Do but consider which are the philosophers who serve the better
					to humanize us: those<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> iii, p. 186.</note> who bid us eat our children
					and friends and fathers and wives after their death,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, they tell us to eat meat without compunction, because human beings are only mortal, and their souls are not reincarnated in animals.</note>
					or Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 993 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>. The argument is somewhat weakened by the fact (certainly well known to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">e.g. Mor.</hi> 286 d-e) that Pythagoras placed an even more stringent taboo on beans than he did on meat.</note> and Empedocles who try to accustom
					us to act justly toward other creatures also ? You
					ridicule a man who abstains from eating mutton.
					But are we, they<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pythagoras and Empedocles.</note> will say, to refrain from laughter
					when we see you slicing off portions from a dead
					father or mother and sending them to absent friends
					and inviting those who are at hand, heaping their
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.571"/>
					
					
					plates with flesh ? But as it is, perhaps we commit
					a sin when we touch these books of theirs without
					cleansing our hands and faces, our feet and ears - 
					unless, by Heaven, it is a purification of those members to speak on such a subject as this, <q direct="unspecified">washing,</q>
					as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 243 d; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 627 f, 706 e, 711 d.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">the brine from one's ears with the
						fresh water of discourse.</q> If one should compare
					these two sets of books and doctrines,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, of the two schools of philosophy mentioned above in 997 e.</note> the former
					may serve as philosophy for the Scyths and Sogdians
					and the Black Cloaks, whose story as told by Herodotus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch seems to have confused the Black Cloaks (Herodotus, iv. 20, but <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> iv. 107) with the Issedones (iv. 26); and perhaps the Sogdians (iii. 93) with the Padaei (iii. 99); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also i. 216 and iii. 38.</note> gains no credit<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But this clause looks like a semi-learned addition.</note>; but the precepts of
					Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 964 e-f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and Empedocles were the laws for the
					ancient Greeks, along with their diet of wheat. . . .<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There seems to be a lacuna here followed by an interpolation from chapter 6 or 7.</note>
					[Because there is no question of justice between us
					and the irrational animals.]
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Who, then, were they who later decreed this ?
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The first to forge the highway's murderous sword,
					</l>
                  <l>And first to eat the flesh of ploughing ox.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aratus, <hi rend="italics">Phaenomena</hi>, 131 f.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Lucilius' parody in the <hi rend="italics">Palatine Anthology</hi>, xi. 136.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					This is the way, you may be sure, in which tyrants
					begin their course of bloody slaughters. Just as, for
					instance, at Athens<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 959 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> and the note.</note> they put to death initially the
					worst of the sycophants, and likewise in the second
					and third instances; but next, having become accustomed to bloodshed they allowed Niceratus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, ii. 3. 39.</note> the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.573"/>
					
					son of Nicias, to be killed and the general Theramenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, ii. 3. 56.</note> and the philosopher Polemarchus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The son of Cephalus and brother of Lysias; a prominent character in Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, i. For the circumstances of his death see Lysias' oration <hi rend="italics">Against Eratosthenes</hi>. It is, however, somewhat unlikely that Plutarch should call Polemarchus <q direct="unspecified">the philosopher</q> even though he appeared in the <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi> and his philosophic bent was mentioned in the <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi> (257 b); so that, once again, we may be faced with interpolation.</note> Just so,
					at the beginning it was some wild and harmful
					animal that was eaten, then a bird or fish that had
					its flesh torn. And so when our murderous instincts
					had tasted blood and grew practised on wild animals,
					they advanced to the labouring ox and the well-behaved sheep and the house-warding cock ; thus,
					little by little giving a hard edge to our insatiable
					appetite, we have advanced to wars and the slaughter
					and murder of human beings. Yet if someone once
					demonstrates that souls in their rebirths make use of
					common bodies and that what is now rational reverts
					to the irrational, and again what is now wild becomes
					tame, and that Nature changes everything and
					assigns new dwellings
					<quote rend="blockquote">Clothing souls with unfamiliar coat of flesh<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 362; Empedocles, frag. 126.</note>;</quote>
					will not this deter the unruly element in those who
					have adopted the doctrine from implanting disease
					and indigestion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 128 b-e.</note> in our bodies and perverting our
					souls to an ever more cruel lawlessness, as soon as
					we are broken of the habit of not entertaining a
					guest or celebrating a marriage or consorting with
					our friends without bloodshed and murder?
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.575"/>
					
					
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Yet even if the argument of the migration of
					souls from body to body is not demonstrated to the
					point of complete belief, there is enough doubt to
					make us quite cautious and fearful. It is as though
					in a clash of armies by night<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Matthew Arnold, <hi rend="italics">Dover Beach</hi>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l>And we are here as on a darkling plain </l>
                        <l>Swept with confused alarms of struggle and flight, </l>
                        <l>Where ignorant armies clash by night.</l>
                     </quote>
                  </quote>
               </note> you had drawn your
					sword and were rushing at a man whose fallen body
					was hidden by his armour and should hear someone
					remarking that he wasn't quite sure, but that he
					thought and believed that the prostrate figure was
					that of your son or brother or father or tent-mate - 
					which would be the better course : to approve a
					false suspicion and spare your enemy as a friend, or
					to disregard an uncertain authority and kill your
					friend as a foe ? The latter course you will declare
					to be shocking. Consider also Merope<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 500, frag. 456 from the <hi rend="italics">Cresphontes</hi>. Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Poetics</hi>, xiv. 19 (1454 a 5) tells us that all turns out well: Merope recognizes her son before she can kill him; but it was a close thing, as Plutarch implies.</note> in the play
					raising her axe against her son himself because she
					believes him to be that son's murderer and saying
					<quote rend="blockquote">This blow I give you is more costly yet -</quote>
					what a stir she rouses in the theatre as she brings
					them to their feet in terror lest she wound the youth
					before the old man can stop her! Now suppose one
					old man stood beside her saying, <q direct="unspecified">Hit him ! He's
						your enemy,</q> and another who said, <q direct="unspecified">Don't strike!
							He is your son</q> : which would be the greater misdeed, to omit the punishment of an enemy because
					of the son, or to slay a child under the impulse of
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.577"/>
					
					anger against an enemy? In a ease, then, where it
					is not hate or anger or self-defence or fear for ourselves that induces us to murder, but the motive of
					pleasure, and the victim stands there under our power
					with its head bent back and one of our philosophers
					says, <q direct="unspecified">Kill it! It's only a brute beast</q> ; but the
					other says, <q direct="unspecified">Stop! What if the soul of some relative
						or friend has found its way into this body?</q> - Good
					God! Of course the risk is equal or much the same
					in the two cases - if I refuse to eat flesh, or if I,
					disbelieving, kill my child or some other relative!
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>There remains yet another contention with the
					Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> iii, pp. 91, 374.</note> about flesh-eating, and this is not <q direct="unspecified">equal,</q>
					either. For what is this great <q direct="unspecified">tension</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A technical term of Stoic philosophy.</note> on the
					belly and the kitchen ? Why, when they count
					pleasure effeminate and denounce it as being neither
					a good nor an <q direct="unspecified">advanced principle</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Further Stoic technical terms.</note> nor <q direct="unspecified">commensurate with Nature,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Further Stoic technical terms.</note> are they so concerned with
					these pleasures? It would certainly be consistent for
					them, since they banish perfume and cakes from their
					banquets, to be more squeamish about blood and flesh.
					But as it is, confining as it were their philosophy to
					their ledgers, they economize on their dinners in
					trivial and needless details while they do not deprecate this inhuman and murderous item of expense.
					<q direct="unspecified">Of course,</q> they say, <q direct="unspecified">we human beings have no
						compact of justice with irrational animals.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 970 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> Nor,
					one might reply, have you with perfume or exotic
					sweetmeats either. Refrain from animals also, if you
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.579"/>
					
					
					are expelling the useless and unnecessary element in
					pleasure from all its lurking-places.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Let us, however, now examine the point
					whether we really have no compact of justice with
					animals ; and let us do so in no artificial or sophistical
					manner, but fixing our attention on our own emotions
					and conversing like human beings with ourselves and
					weighing . . .<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The rest is lacking.</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>