<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mulierum virtutes</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1931</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.3.p.473"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="intro">
            <head>BRAVERY OF WOMEN (MULIERUM VIRTUTES)
						<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>Plutarch's well-chosen selection of stories about the
						bravery of women was composed for his friend Clea,
						who held high office among the priestesses at Delphi,
						and to whom he dedicated also his treatise on Isis
						and Osiris. He speaks of it as a supplement to a
						conversation on the equality of the sexes, which he
						had with Clea on the occasion of the death of Leontis,
						of blessed memory, suggested no doubt by the noble
						character of the departed. It is not impossible that
						some of the topics discussed in that conversation are
						included here also, so as to make the book a complete
						and finished whole.</p>
            <p>The treatise stands as No. 126 in Lamprias's list of
						Plutarch's works.</p>
            <p>Polyaenus drew freely from this book to embellish
						his <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, as a glance at the notes on the
						following pages will show.</p>
            <p>Novelists who still write of virtuous women and
						heartless villains may find some material in this work
						of Plutarch's. They need not be ashamed to glean
						where a great poet has reaped.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.3.p.475"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="0">
            <head>BRAVERY OF WOMEN</head>
            <p>Regarding the virtues of women, Clea, I do not hold
						the same opinion as Thucydides.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucydides, ii. 45.</note> For he declares
						that the best woman is she about whom there is the
						least talk among persons outside regarding either
						censure or commendation, feeling that the name of
						the good woman, like her person, ought to be shut up
						indoors and never go out.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 217 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> But to my mind Gorgias
						appears to display better taste in advising that not
						the form but the fame of a woman should be known to
						many. Best of all seems the Roman custom,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Camillus</hi>, chap. viii. (133 b), Livy, v. 50; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De oratore</hi>, ii. 11 (44).</note> which
						publicly renders to women, as to men, a fitting commemoration after the end of their life. So when
						Leontis, that most excellent woman, died, I forthwith
						had then a long conversation with you, which was not
						without some share of consolation drawn from
						philosophy, and now, as you desired, I have also
						written out for you the remainder of what I would
						have said on the topic that man's virtues and woman's
						virtues are one and the same. This includes a good
						deal of historical exposition, and it is not composed
						to give pleasure in its perusal. Yet, if in a convincing
						argument delectation is to be found also by reason of
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.477"/>
						
						the very nature of the illustration, then the discussion
						is not devoid of an agreeableness which helps in the
						exposition, nor does it hesitate
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To join
						</l>
                  <l>The Graces with the Muses,
						A consorting most fair,</l>
               </quote>
						as Euripides says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Hercules Furens</hi>, 673. Plutarch probably quoted from memory, as he made one transposition and on substitution. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the critical note.</note> and to pin its faith mostly to the
						love of beauty inherent to the soul.</p>
            <p>If, conceivably, we asserted that painting on the
						part of men and women is the same, and exhibited
						paintings, done by women, of the sort that Apelles,
						or Zeuxis, or Nicomachus has left to us, would anybody reprehend us on the ground that we were aiming
						at giving gratification and allurement rather than at
						persuasion ? I do not think so.</p>
            <p>Or again, if we should declare that the poetic or
						the prophetic art is not one art when practised by
						men and another when practised by women, but the
						same, and if we should put the poems of Sappho side
						by side with those of Anacreon, or the oracles of the
						Sibyl with those of Bacis, will anybody have the power
						justly to impugn the demonstration because these
						lead on the hearer, joyous and delighted,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Horace, <hi rend="italics">Ars Poetica</hi>, 426.</note> to have
						belief in it ? No, you could not say that either ?</p>
            <p>And actually it is not possible to learn better the
						similarity and the difference between the virtues of
						men and of women from any other source than by
						putting lives beside lives and actions beside actions,
						like great works of art, and considering whether the
						magnificence of Semiramis has the same character
						and pattern as that of Sesostris, or the intelligence of
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.479"/>
						
						Tanaquil the same as that of Servius the king, or
						the high spirit of Porcia the sanie as that of Brutus,
						or that of Pelopidas the same as Timocleia's, when
						compared with due regard to the most important
						points of identity and influence. For the fact is that
						the virtues acquire certain other diversities, their own
						colouring as it were, due to varying natures, and they
						take on the likeness of the customs on which they are
						founded, and of the temperament of persons and their
						nurture and mode of living.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Hippocrates, <hi rend="italics">Airs, Waters</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Places</hi>, chap. xxiii. (Hippocrates in the L.C.L., i. p. 132); Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 33 (80); Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 8; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, vii. 127, for the statement of the contrary view.</note> For example, Achilles
						was brave in one way and Ajax in another; and the
						wisdom of Odysseus was not like that of Nestor, nor
						was Cato a just man in exactly the same way as
						Agesilaus, nor Eirene fond of her husband in the
						manner of Alcestis, nor Cornelia high-minded in the
						manner of Olympias. But, with all this, let us not
						postulate many different kinds of bravery, wisdom,
						and justice - if only the individual dissimilarities
						exclude no one of these from receiving its appropriate
						rating.</p>
            <p>Those incidents which are so often recited,
						and those of which I assume that you, having kept
						company with books, have assuredly record and
						knowledge, I will pass over for the present; but with
						this exception : if any tales worthy of perusal have
						escaped the attention of those who, before our time,
						have recorded the commonly published stories.
						Since, however, many deeds worthy of mention have
						been done by women both in association with other
						women and by themselves alone, it may not be a
						bad idea to set down first a brief account of those
						commonly known.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.3.p.481"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>I. THE TROJAN WOMEN<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 265 b; Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Romulus</hi>, chap. i. (17 f); Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 25. 2. The story differs in some details from Virgil's account, as was noted by Dionysius of Halicarnassus in his <hi rend="italics">Roman Antiquities</hi>, i. 72-73.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Most of those that escaped from Troy at the time
						of its capture had to weather a storm, and, because
						of their inexperience in navigation and ignorance of
						the sea, were driven upon the shores of Italy, and,
						in the neighbourhood of the river Tiber, they
						barely escaped by running in, under compulsion,
						where there were anchorages and havens. While the
						men were wandering about the country, in search of
						information, it suddenly occurred to the women to
						reflect that for a happy and successful people any
						sort of a settled habitation on land is better than all
						wandering and voyaging, and that the Trojans must
						create a fatherland, since they were not able to recover that which they had lost. Thereupon, becoming of one mind, they burned the ships, one
						woman, Roma, taking the lead. Having accomplished this, they went to meet the men who were
						hurrying to the sea to save the ships, and, fearful of
						their anger, some embraced their husbands and
						some their relatives, and kissed them coaxingly, and
						mollified them by this manner of blandishment. This
						is the origin of the custom, which still persists among
						the Roman women, of greeting their kinsfolk with a
						kiss.
					</p>
            <p>
						The Trojans, apparently realizing the inevitable
						necessity, and after having also some experience
						with the native inhabitants, who received them
						kindly and humanely, came to be content with what
						had been done by the women, and took up their
						abode there with the Latins.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.483"/>
						
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>II. THE WOMEN OF PHOCIS<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 65; Pausanias, x. 1. 3-11.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						The deed of the women of Phocis has not found
						any writer of high repute to describe it, yet it is not
						inferior in point of bravery to anything ever done by
						women, as is attested by imposing sacred rites which
						the Phocians perform even to this day in the neighbourhood of Hyampolis, and by ancient decrees. Of
						these events a detailed account of the achievements<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, viii. 27-28.</note>
						is given in the Life of Da&iuml;phantus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One of Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi> which has not been preserved. It is No. 38 in the catalogue of Lamprias.</note> and the women's
						part was as follows.
					</p>
            <p>
						The Thessalians were engaged in a war without
						quarter against the Phocians. For the Phocians had
						slain on one day all the Thessalian governors and
						despots in their cities. Whereupon the Thessalians
						massacred two hundred and fifty Phocian hostages<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschines, <hi rend="italics">De falsa legatione</hi>, 140.</note>;
						then with all their forces they made an invasion
						through Locris, having previously passed a resolution to spare no grown man, and to make slaves of
						the children and women. Accordingly Da&iuml;phantus,
						Bathyllius's son, one of the three governors of Phocis,
						persuaded the men to meet the Thessalians in battle,
						and to bring together into some one place the women
						with their children from all Phocis, and to heap about
						them a mass of faggots, and to post guards, giving
						them instructions that, if they learned the men
						were being vanquished, they should with all haste
						set fire to the mass and reduce the living bodies to
						ashes. Nearly all voted approval of the plan, but
						one man arose in the council and said it was only
						right that the women approve this also; otherwise
						they must reject it, and use no compulsion. When
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.485"/>
						
						report of this speech reached the women, they held
						a meeting by themselves and passed the same vote,
						and they exalted Da&iuml;phantus for having conceived
						the best plan for Phocis. It is said that the children
						also held an assembly on their own account and passed
						their vote too.
					</p>
            <p>
						After this had been done, the Phocians engaged
						the enemy near Cleonae of Hyampolis, and gained
						the victory. To this vote of the Phocians the Greeks
						gave the name of<q direct="unspecified">Desperation</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Phocian Desperation,</q> according to Pausanias, x. 1. 7.</note>; and the greatest
						festival of all. the Elaphebolia in honour of Artemis,
						they celebrate in Hyamoolis even to this day in
						commemoration of that victory.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>III. THE WOMEN OF CHIOS<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 66.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						The reason which led the Chians to appropriate
						Leuconia as a settlement was as follows : One of the
						men who appear to have been prominent in Chios was
						getting married, and, as the bride was being conducted
						to his home in a chariot, the king, Hippoclus, a close
						friend of the bridegroom, being there with the rest
						amid the drinking and merry-making, jumped up
						into the chariot, not with intent to do anything
						insulting, but merely following the common custom
						and indulging in facetiousness. Whereupon the friends
						of the bridegroom killed him.
					</p>
            <p>
						Signs of divine anger were soon disclosed to the
						Chians, and the god of the oracle bade them slay the
						slayers of Hippoclus, but they said that they all had
						slain Hippoclus. So the god bade them all leave the
						city, if they were all involved in the crime. And thus
						the guilty, both those who had taken a hand in the
						murder and those who had in any way assented to it,
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.487"/>
						
						being not few in number nor without strength, the
						Chians sent away to settle in Leuconia, which they
						had earlier wrested from the Coroneans and taken
						possession of with the co-operation of the Erythraeans.
					</p>
            <p>
						Later, however, they became involved in war with
						the Erythraeans,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, i. 18; Frontinus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, ii. 5. 15.</note> the most powerful of the lonians;
						and when these marched against Leuconia, they
						were not able to hold out, and agreed to evacuate
						the town under truce, each man to have one cloak
						and one inner garment and nothing else. The
						women, however, called them cowards if they purposed to lay down their arms and go forth naked
						through the midst of the enemy. But when the men
						said that they had given their oath, the women
						bade them not to leave their arms behind, but to say,
						by way of answer to the enemy, that the spear serves
						as a cloak, and the shield as a shirt, to a man of
						spirit. The Chians took this advice, and when they
						used bold words towards the Erythraeans and displayed their weapons, the Erythraeans were frightened at their boldness, and no one approached them
						nor hindered them, but all were well pleased at their
						departure. So the Chians, having been taught
						courage by their women, were saved in this way.
					</p>
            <p>
						A deed which does not in the least fall short of this
						one in bravery was performed by the women of
						Chios many years later at the time when Philip,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Philip V.; the date is probably 201 b.c.</note>
						son of Demetrius, was besieging their city, and had
						made a barbarous and insolent proclamation bidding
						the slaves to desert to him, their reward to be freedom and marriage with their owners, meaning
						thereby that he was intending to unite them with
						the wives of their masters. But the women, suddenly
						possessed of fierce and savage spirit, in company with
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.489"/>
						
						their slaves, who were themselves equally indignant
						and supported the women by their presence, hastened to mount the walls, both bringing stones and
						missiles, and exhorting and importuning the fighting men until, finally, by their vigorous defence and
						the wounds inflicted on the enemy by their missiles,
						they repulsed Philip. And not a single slave deserted
						to him.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>IV. THE WOMEN OF ARGOS<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 223 b; Herodotus, vi. 76 ff; Pausanias, ii. 20. 8.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Of all the deeds performed by women for the
						community none is more famous than the struggle
						against Cleomenes for Argos, which the women
						carried out at the instigation of Telesilla the poetess.
						She, as they say, was the daughter of a famous house
						but sickly in body, and so she sent to the god to ask
						about health; and when an oracle was given her to
						cultivate the Muses, she followed the god's advice,
						and by devoting herself to poetry and music she
						was quickly relieved of her trouble, and was greatly
						admired by the women for her poetic art.
					</p>
            <p>
						But when Cleomenes king of the Spartans, having slain many Argives (but not by any means
						seven thousand, seven hundred and seventy-seven,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Six thousand according to Herodotus, vii. 148. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also vi. 77-82. The date is put about 494 b.c. or possibly earlier.</note>
						as some fabulous narratives have it) proceeded
						against the city, an impulsive daring, divinely
						inspired, came to the younger women to try, for
						their country's sake, to hold off the enemy. Under
						the lead of Telesilla they took up arms,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Found in the temples according to <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 223 b.</note> and,
						taking their stand by the battlements, manned the
						walls all round, so that the enemy were amazed.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.491"/>
						
						The result was that Cleomenes they repulsed with
						great loss, and the other king, Demaratus, who
						managed to get inside, as Socrates says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Histor. Graec.</hi> iv. p. 497.</note> and gained
						possession of the Pamphyliacum, they drove out.
						In this way the city was saved. The women who
						fell in the battle they buried close by the Argive
						Road, and to the survivors they granted the privilege
						of erecting a statute of Ares as a memorial of their
						surpassing valour. Some say that the battle took
						place on the seventh day of the month which is now
						known as the Fourth Month, but anciently was
						called Hermaeus among the Argives; others say
						that it was on the first day of that month, on the
						anniversary of which they celebrate even to this day
						the &lsquo;Festival of Impudence,&rsquo; at which they clothe
						the women in men's shirts and cloaks, and the men
						in women's robes and veils.
					</p>
            <p>
						To repair the scarcity of men they did not unite
						the women with slaves, as Herodotus records,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, vi. 83, does not say quite this. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Politics</hi>, v. 3. 7.</note>
						but with the best of their neighbouring subjects,
						whom they made Argive citizens. It was reputed
						that the women showed disrespect and an intentional indifference to those husbands in their married
						relations from a feeling that they were underlings.
						Wherefore the Argives enacted a law,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Approval by indirection!</note> the one which
						says that married women having a beard must
						occupy the same bed with their husbands!
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>V. THE PERSIAN WOMEN<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, vii. 45. 2; Justin, <hi rend="italics">Historiae Philippicae</hi>, i. 6.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						At the time when Cyrus induced the Persians to
						revolt from king Astyages and the Medes he was
						defeated in battle. As the Persians were fleeing
						to the city, with the enemy not far from forcing their
						way in along with the Persians, the women ran out
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.493"/>
						
						to meet them before the city, and, lifting up their
						garments, said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 241 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Whither are you rushing so fast,
						you biggest cowards in the whole world ? Surely
						you cannot, in your flight, slink in here whence you
						came forth.</q> The Persians, mortified at the sight
						and the words, chiding themselves for cowards,
						rallied and, engaging the enemy afresh, put them to
						rout. As a result of this it became an established
						custom that, whenever the king rode into the city,
						each woman should receive a gold coin; the author
						of the law was Cyrus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, viii. 5. 21.</note> But Ochus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxix. (703 a).</note> they say, being a
						mean man and the most avaricious of the kings, would
						always make a detour round the city and not pass
						within, but would deprive the women of their largess.
						Alexander,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lxix. (703 a).</note> however, entered the city twice, and
						gave all the women who were with child a double
						amount.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>VI. THE CELTIC WOMEN<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, vii. 50.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Before the Celts crossed over the Alps and settled
						in that part of Italy which is now their home, a dire
						and persistent factional discord broke out among them
						which went on and on to the point of civil war. The
						women, however, put themselves between the armed
						forces, and, taking up the controversies, arbitrated
						and decided them with such irreproachable fairness
						that a wondrous friendship of all towards all was
						brought about between both States and families.
						As the result of this they continued to consult with
						the women in regard to war and peace, and to decide
						through them any disputed matters in their relations
						with their allies. At all events, in their treaty with
						Hannibal they wrote the provision that, if the Celts
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.495"/>
						
						complained against the Carthaginians, the governors
						and generals of the Carthaginians in Spain should
						be the judges; and if the Carthaginians complained
						against the Celts, the judges should be the Celtic
						women.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>VII. THE WOMEN OF MELOS<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 64.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						The Melians, being in need of wide acres, put in
						charge of the colony to be sent forth Nymphaeus,
						a young man and unusually handsome. The god
						bade them sail, and wherever they should lose their
						transports to settle in that place. It came about,
						as they put in at Caria and went ashore, that their
						ships were destroyed by a storm. The Carian
						inhabitants of Cryassus, whether pitying their sorry
						plight or fearing their boldness, bade them live near
						themselves, and gave them a portion of their land.
						Later, seeing their great expansion in a short time,
						they plotted to make away with them, after preparing
						a sumptuous banquet for the purpose. It happened that a Carian maiden was in love with Nymphaeus, but nobody else was aware of this. Her
						name was Caphene. As the plan was being put
						into operation, she could not suffer Nymphaeus to
						be put to death, and so she disclosed to him
						the intention of her fellow-citizens. So, when the
						Cryassians came to invite them, Nymphaeus said
						that it was not the custom for the Greeks to go to
						dinner without women. When the Carians heard
						this, they told them to bring the women too. On
						this understanding Nymphaeus informed the Melians
						of what had been done, and told the men to go to the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.497"/>
						
						place unarmed in conventional attire, but that each
						of the women should carry a sword in the fold of her
						garment and sit beside her husband or male relative.
						When, about the middle of the meal, the predetermined signal was given to the Carians, and the Greeks
						realized that the time had come, all the women at
						the same instant threw open the fold of their garments and the men, seizing the swords, attacked
						the barbarians and slew them all together. Then,
						taking possession of the land and razing that city,
						they built another, to which they gave the name of
						New Cryassus. Caphene married Nymphaeus and
						received the honour and gratitude merited by her
						valuable services. It is right and proper to admire
						both the silence and the courage of the women, and
						that not a single one of them among so many was
						led by timidity to turn coward even involuntarily.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="V8">
            <head>VIII. THE ETRUSCAN WOMEN<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 296 b; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, vii. 49; Herodotus, iv. 145-148 and vi. 138 (who says that the men were descendants of the Argonauts); Valerius Maximus, iv. 6, ext. 3; Conon, <hi rend="italics">Narrationes</hi>, 36 and 47.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						When the Etruscans had gained possession of
						Lemnos and Imbros, they carried away forcibly from
						Brauron Athenian women, and children were born
						to them. These the Athenians expelled from the
						islands on the ground that they were in part barbarian, and they put in at Taenarum and made themselves useful to the Spartans in the war with the
						Helots. For this they received citizenship and the
						right of intermarriage, but were not deemed worthy
						to hold office or to be members of the Senate, and
						this gave colour to the idea that some radical design
						underlay their coming together, and that they 
						purposed to disturb the established institutions.
						Accordingly the Spartans took them into custody
						and, shutting them up in prison, placed a strong guard
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.499"/>
						
						over them, seeking to convict them by clear and
						certain proofs. The wives of the prisoners, coming
						to the prison, by dint of many prayers and intreaties,
						were permitted by the guards to pass within just to
						greet and to speak to their husbands.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Who, according to other accounts, were to be put to death that night.</note> When they
						had gone inside they bade their husbands to change
						their clothing quickly, leaving their own for their
						wives, and then, putting on their wives' garments,
						to depart with their faces covered. This done, the
						women waited there, prepared to face all terrors, but
						the guards were deceived and allowed the men to
						pass, supposing, of course, that they were women.
					</p>
            <p>
						Following this, they seized the strongholds on Mount
						Ta&yuml;getus, incited the body of Helots to revolt, and
						gladly received them as an addition to their forces.
						The Spartans were thrown into a great state of fear
						and, sending heralds, made peace with them, the
						conditions being that they should get back their
						wives, should receive money and ships, and sail
						away and, having found land and a city elsewhere, be
						considered as colonists and kindred of the Spartans.
						This the Pelasgians did, taking as leaders Pollis and
						Delphus and Crata&iuml;das, all Spartans. A part of them
						settled in Melos,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, v. 84.</note> but Pollis and his associates, with
						the great majority, sailed to Crete, testing the truth
						of the oracles. For an oracle had been given them
						that whenever they should lose their goddess and
						their anchor they should cease from their wanderings
						and found a city in that place. So, when they had
						come to anchor off that part of Crete which is called
						the Chersonese, panic confusion fell upon them by
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.501"/>
						
						night, by which they were so excited that they leaped
						aboard in utter disorder, leaving behind on land an
						ancient statue of Artemis which had been handed
						down to them from their ancestors, having been
						originally brought to Lemnos from Brauron, and from
						Lemnos had been carried about with them in all their
						journeyings. But when at sea, as the confusion subsided, they missed this, and at the same time Pollis
						discovered that the fluke was gone from the anchor
						(for apparently it had been broken off as the anchor
						dragged in some rocky places, without anybody's
						noticing its loss), he declared that the god-given
						predictions were now fulfilled, and gave the signal to
						return. He took possession of the country, prevailed
						in many battles over those who ranged themselves
						against him, settled Lyctus, and took other cities
						under his control. Because of all this people regard
						them as related to the Athenians by descent on
						account of their mothers, and as colonists of the
						Spartans also.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Politics</hi>, ii. 10. 2.</note>
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>IX. THE LYCIAN WOMEN</head>
            <p>
						That which is said to have happened in Lycia sounds
						like a myth, yet it has some supporting testimony
						in the tales that are told.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 152 ff. and the scholia on <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 328; Hyginus, <hi rend="italics">Fabulae</hi>, no. 57; Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi>, ii. 3. Is Chimarrhus a Chimaera?</note> Amisodarus, as they say,
						whom the Lycians call Isaras, arrived from the Lycian
						colony in the vicinity of Zeleia, bringing with him
						pirate ships, in command of which was Chimarrhus, a
						warlike man, bloodthirsty and brutal. He sailed in
						a vessel which had a lion as its figurehead at the
						prow, and a serpent at the stern. He did much evil
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.503"/>
						
						to the Lycians, and it was not possible to sail the sea
						or even to live in the cities near the sea.
					</p>
            <p>
						This man Bellerophon slew, pursuing him with
						Pegasus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bellerophon's winged horse (which may be found represented on the coins of Corinth).</note> as he was trying to escape. Bellerophon
						also drove out the Amazons, but met with no just
						treatment; in fact, lobates was most unjust with him.
						Because of this, Bellerophon waded into the sea, and
						prayed to Poseidon that, as a requital against lobates,
						the land might become sterile and unprofitable.
						Thereupon he went back after his prayer, and a wave
						arose and inundated the land. It was a fearful sight
						as the sea, following him, rose high in air and covered
						up the plain. The men besought Bellerophon to
						check it, but when they could not prevail on him,
						the women, pulling up their garments, came to meet
						him; and when he, for shame, retreated towards
						the sea again,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 162.</note> the wave also, it is said, went back
						with him.
					</p>
            <p>
						Some, attempting to explain away the mythical
						element in this account, assert that he did not get
						the sea to move by imprecations, but that the most
						fertile part of the plain lies below the sea-level, and
						Bellerophon broke through the ridge extending along
						the shore, which kept the sea out; then, as the ocean
						rushed in violently and covered up the plain, the men
						accomplished nothing by beseeching him, but the
						women, flocking about him in a crowd, met with
						respect, and caused his anger to subside.
					</p>
            <p>
						Still others assert that the Chimaera, as it was
						called, was nothing but a mountain facing the sun,
						and that it caused reflexions of sunlight, fierce and
						fiery in the summer time, and by these, striking all over
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.505"/>
						
						the plain, the crops were dried up; and that Bellerophon, sensing this, cut away the smoothest part of
						the precipice which mostly sent back the reflexions.
						When, however, he met with no gratitude, in anger
						he turned to avenge himself upon the Lycians, but
						was prevailed upon by the women.
					</p>
            <p>
						But the reason which Nymphis gives<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Histor. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 14 (Frag. 13).</note> in the fourth
						book of his treatise about Heracleia is least mythical
						of all; for he says that Bellerophon killed a wild
						boar which was making havoc of the stock and crops
						in the land of the Xanthians, but obtained no fitting
						reward; whereupon he addressed to Poseidon imprecations against the Xanthians, and the whole plain
						suddenly became glittering with a salt deposit and was
						completely ruined, since the soil had become saline.
						This lasted until Bellerophon, out of respect for the
						women who besought him, prayed to Poseidon to
						give up his anger. For this reason it was the custom
						for the Xanthians to bear names derived not from
						their fathers but from their mothers.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, i. 173, and the note in A. H. Sayce's edition (London, 1883), where many of the numerous parallels are cited.</note>
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>X. THE WOMEN OF SALMANTICA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, vii. 48.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						When Hannibal, the son of Barea, before<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably about 220 b.c. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polybius, iii. 14 and Livy, xxi. 5.</note> making
						his campaign against the Romans, attacked a great
						city in Spain, Salmantica, at first the besieged were
						terrified, and agreed to do what was ordered by giving
						him six thousand pounds and three hundred hostages.
						But when he raised the siege, they changed their
						minds and did nothing of what they had agreed to do.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.507"/>
						
						So he returned and ordered his soldiers, with the
						promise of plunder, to attack the city. At this the
						barbarians were panic-stricken, and carne to terms,
						agreeing that the free inhabitants should depart clad
						in one civilian garment, and should leave behind
						weapons, property, slaves, and their city. The
						women, thinking that the enemy would search each
						man as he came out, but would not touch the women,
						took swords, and, hiding them, hastened out with the
						men. When all had come out, Hannibal set over
						them a guard of Masaesylian soldiers in a place near
						the city, and kept them there under constraint. The
						rest of the soldiers rushed into the city in disorder
						and set to plundering. As much booty was being
						carried off, the Masaesylians could not bear to be
						merely spectators, nor did they keep their mind on
						their watching, but were much aggrieved and started
						to move away as if to have their share of the spoils.
						At this juncture the women, calling upon the men,
						handed them the swords, and some of the women
						of themselves attacked their guards. One of them
						snatched away the spear of Banon the interpreter,
						and smote the man himself; but he happened to have
						on his breast-plate. Of the others, the men struck
						down some, routed the rest, and forced a way out in a
						body, accompanied by the women. Hannibal, learning of this, sent in pursuit of them, and caught those
						who could not keep up. The others gained the
						mountains, and, for the time, escaped. Afterwards,
						however, they sent a petition to him, and were
						restored to their city, and received immunity and
						humane treatment.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.509"/>
						
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>XI. THE WOMEN OF MILETUS<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 63. Aulus Gellius, xv. 10, translates the story from a lost work of Plutarch's (<hi rend="italics">De anima</hi>), in which it was doubtless repeated. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bernardakis's ed. of the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, vii. p. 21.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Once upon a time a dire and strange trouble
						took possession of the young women in Miletus for
						some unknown cause. The most popular conjecture
						was that the air had acquired a distracting and infectious constitution, and that this operated to
						produce in them an alteration and derangement of
						mind. At any rate, a yearning for death and an
						insane impulse toward hanging suddenly fell upon
						all of them, and many managed to steal away and
						hang themselves. Arguments and tears of parents
						and comforting words of friends availed nothing, but
						they circumvented every device and cunning effort
						of their watchers in making away with themselves.
						The malady seemed to be of divine origin and beyond
						human help, until, on the advice of a man of sense,
						an ordinance was proposed that the women who
						hanged themselves should be carried naked through
						the market-place to their burial. And when this
						ordinance was passed it not only checked, but stopped
						completely, the young women from killing themselves. Plainly a high testimony to natural goodness
						and to virtue is the desire to guard against ill repute,
						and the fact that the women who had no deterrent
						sense of shame when facing the most terrible of all
						things in the world, death and pain, yet could not
						abide nor bear the thought of disgrace which would
						come after death.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>XII. THE WOMEN OF CEOS</head>
            <p>
						It was a custom for the maidens of Ceos to go in
						a company to the public shrines and spend the day
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.511"/>
						
						together, and their suitors watched their sports and
						dances. At evening they went by turns to each one's
						home and waited upon one another's parents and
						brothers even to washing their feet. Very often
						more than one youth would be in love with one maid,
						but their love was so orderly and so controlled by
						custom, that when the girl became engaged to one,
						the others ceased their attentions at once. The net
						result of this orderly behaviour on the part of the
						women was that there was no memory of a case of
						adultery or seduction in that country for the space
						of seven hundred years.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>XIII. THE WOMEN OF PHOCIS<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A story about the women of Phocis has been told already (<hi rend="italics">supra</hi> 244 a). A better title for this story would be &lsquo;The Women of Amphissa.&rsquo;</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						When the despots in Phocis had seized Delphi,
						and the Thebans were waging war against them in
						what has been called the Sacred War, the women
						devotees of Dionysus, to whom they give the name
						of Thy ads, in Bacchic frenzy wandering at night unwittingly arrived at Amphissa. As they were tired
						out, and sober reason had not yet returned to them,
						they flung themselves down in the market-place, and
						were lying asleep, some here, some there. The
						wives of the men of Amphissa, fearing, because their
						city had become allied with the Phocians, and
						numerous soldiers of the despots were present there,
						that the Thyads might be treated with indignity, all
						ran out into the market-place, and, taking their
						stand round about in silence, did not go up to them
						while they were sleeping, but when they arose from
						their slumber, one devoted herself to one of the
						strangers and another to another, bestowing attentions on them and offering them food. Finally, the
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.513"/>
						
						women of Amphissa, after winning the consent of
						their husbands, accompanied the strangers, who were
						safely escorted as far as the frontier.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="14">
            <head>XIV. VALERIA AND CLOELIA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is told (with interruptions) by Plutarch in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Publicola</hi>, chaps. xvii-xix. (106-107) as well as by many other writers. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example, Livy, ii. 13; Dionysius of Halicarnassus, <hi rend="italics">Roman Antiquities</hi>, v. 32-34; Seneca, <hi rend="italics">Consolatio ad Marciam</hi>, 16. 2; Valerius Maximus, iii. 2. 2; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 31.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						The two things that brought about the expulsion
						of Tarquinius Superbus, seventh king of Rome from
						Romulus, were arrogance and the virtue of Lucretia,
						a woman married to a distinguished man of royal
						lineage. For she was outraged by one of Tarquini sons
						who had been welcomed as a guest at her home. She
						told her friends and family what had been done to her,
						and immediately slew herself. Deposed from power,
						Tarquin waged various wars in his endeavours to regain his sovereignty. Finally he persuaded Porsena,
						ruler of the Etruscans, to march against Rome with
						a great force.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Livy, ii. 9.</note> At the same time with the war
						famine also attacked<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 11.</note> the Romans, and they, learning that Porsena was not merely a great soldier but
						a just and fair man as well, wished to make him
						judge in their case against Tarquin. But Tarquin
						was stubborn, saying that Porsena, if he did not remain faithful as an ally, would not be a just judge
						either; and so Porsena renounced him and made it
						his endeavour that when he went away he should be
						a friend of the Romans, and should get back such
						part of the land as they had cut off from the Etruscans, and also the prisoners of war. To confirm these
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.515"/>
						
						terms hostages were given to him, ten youths and
						ten maidens, among whom was Valeria, the daughter
						of Publicola the consul, whereupon Porsena at once
						remitted all his preparation for the war, although the
						agreement was not yet consummated.
					</p>
            <p>
						The maidens went down to the river as if to bathe,
						a short distance away from the camp. At the instigation of one of them, Cloelia, they fastened their
						clothes to their heads, and took the risk of breasting
						a swift current and deep-whirling eddies, and by
						swimming close together they reached the other
						side by dint of a hard struggle, and with many a
						chance of failure. There are those who say that
						Cloelia procured a horse and, mounting it, swam it
						across slowly, acting as guide for the others, and
						encouraging and helping them as they were swimming. The argument with which they support this
						I will mention in a moment.
					</p>
            <p>
						When the Romans saw them safe and sound, they
						admired the maidens' bravery and daring, yet did
						not like their coming back, nor could endure to prove
						themselves less honourable than one man in keeping
						faith. Accordingly they commanded the girls to go
						back again, and sent men with them to see that they
						got there. Tarquin set an ambush for these when
						they had crossed the river,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">His purpose, according to other accounts, was to prevent the return of the hostages, and so to make it appear that the Romans had not kept faith.</note> and came very near
						getting the maidens in his power. But Valeria,
						daughter of the consul, Publicola, with three servants
						succeeded in escaping to the camp of Porsena, and
						the others Porsena's son, Aruns, rescued from the
						enemy by hastening with all speed to their assistance.
						
					</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.517"/>
            <p>
						When they were brought to the camp, Porsena,
						with a look at them, bade them say which one of them
						was the instigator and leader in the plan. The others,
						for fear regarding Cloelia, said not a word; but
						Cloelia of her own accord said that it was herself,
						and Porsena, in admiration of her, ordered a horse to
						be brought, fittingly caparisoned, and presented it to
						her, and then sent them all back kindly and humanely.
						Many make of this an indication that Cloelia rode
						across the river on a horse. Others, however, say
						this is not so, but that Porsena, because he admired
						her strength and daring as above that of a woman,
						deemed her worthy of a gift fitting for a warrior.
						At all events, there stood an equestrian statue of a
						woman<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Publicola</hi>, chap. xix. (107 c); Livy, ii. 13, who gives a slightly different explanation of the <q direct="unspecified">
                     <foreign lang="la">virgo insidens equo</foreign>
                  </q> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, xxxiv. 13 (28-29).</note> close beside the Sacred Way, as it is called,
						and some say that this is the statue of Cloelia, others
						of Valeria.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="15">
            <head>XV. MICCA AND MEGISTO<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch seems to be our only authority for the details of this narrative, although the atrocities and death of Aristotimus are recorded briefly by Pausanias, v. 5. 1 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> vi. 14. 11), and by Justin, <hi rend="italics">Historiae Philippicae</hi>, xxvi. 1. Aristotimus's name is found on coins of Elis (Head, <hi rend="italics">Historia Numorum</hi>, p. 356).</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Aristotimus, having succeeded in becoming despot
						over the people of Elis, was able to prevail through
						the support of Antigonus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Antigonus Gonatas, king of Macedonia, 283-239 b.c.</note> the king, but he used his
						power for no seemly or moderate purpose. He was
						himself brutal by nature, and he was led by fear to
						be subservient to a band of mixed barbarians who
						kept guard over his person and his sovereignty, and
						he overlooked many arrogant and cruel deeds done
						to the citizens by them. An example is what happened to Philodemus. This man had a beautiful
						daughter named Micca, and this girl one of the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.519"/>
						
						officers of the despot's mercenaries named Lucius,
						to show his arrogance, rather than for love of her,
						undertook to make his paramour, and sent a summons
						for her. Her parents, seeing the necessity, advised
						her to go, but the girl, being noble and high-minded,
						begged her father, embracing and beseeching him,
						that he would rather bear to see her dead than
						robbed of her maidenhood in such a shameful and
						lawless way. There was some delay, and Lucius
						himself, lustful and drunk, started forth in the midst
						of his drinking in a passion. Finding Micca with her
						head on her father's knees, he commanded her to
						follow with him. But, as she was not willing, he tore
						off her clothes and whipped her naked body, while
						she bravely bore the painful blows in silence. Her
						father and mother, effecting nothing by their intreaties and tears, resorted to calling upon gods and
						men to witness their frightful and lawless treatment.
						But the barbarian, utterly crazed by rage and drink,
						killed the maiden, as she lay with her face in her
						father's bosom.
					</p>
            <p>
						The despot, however, was not moved even by
						things like this, but he made away with many, and
						forced even more into exile. At any rate, it is said
						that eight hundred men fled for safety to the Aetolians, asking for rescue of their wives and youngest
						children from the despot. A little later he himself
						caused proclamation to be made that the women
						who wished might go away to their husbands, taking
						along as much as they wished of their feminine possessions. When he learned that they all received
						the proclamation with gladness (and their number
						was over six hundred), he issued orders that all
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.521"/>
						
						should proceed in a company on a specified day, as
						if purposing himself to assure their safety. When
						the day arrived, the women gathered at the gates
						with their possessions which they had packed up, and
						some of their children they carried in their arms, and
						others they had in wagons, and they were waiting
						there for one another. Suddenly many of the despot's
						men bore down upon them, calling out to them,
						while still a long way off, to wait. And when these
						came near, they ordered the women to move back,
						and then turned the teams about and rode them at
						the women, driving them through their midst mercilessly, and giving the women no chance either to
						follow or to stay or to come to the help of their little
						ones who were being killed, some of whom perished
						by being thrown from the wagons, others by falling
						under foot. The mercenaries urged them on like a
						flock of sheep, with shouts and whips, while the
						women tripped over one another, until the soldiers
						had cast them all into prison. Their possessions
						were carried off to Aristotimus.
					</p>
            <p>
						The people of Elis being highly indignant over this
						affair, the holy women devoted to Dionysus, whom
						they call the Sixteen, taking suppliant branches and
						fillets from those sacred to the god, went to meet
						Aristotimus close by the market-place. His bodyguard made way out of respect, and the priestesses
						silently halted, first of all reverently holding out
						their suppliant branches. But when it became clear
						that they were petitioning in behalf of the women,
						and trying by intreaty to mollify his anger, he, greatly
						exasperated with his guards, screamed out that they
						had permitted the priestesses to come into his
						presence, and he made them drive these from the
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.523"/>
						
						market-place by pushing or striking one or another,
						and he fined each woman four hundred pounds.
					</p>
            <p>
						After these events, Hellanicus started a concerted
						activity against the despot. He was a man who,
						owing to his advanced years and the death of two
						sons, was not thought of by the despot as likely
						to be active in any way. The exiles crossed over from
						Aetolia and occupied Amymone, a stronghold in
						Elis, well adapted to serve as a base for warlike
						operations, and there they received a great addition
						to their numbers from the citizens who managed to
						escape from Elis. Aristotimus, alarmed at this,
						went to see the imprisoned women, and, thinking
						that he should accomplish his purpose better by fear
						than by favour, he gave orders to them to write and
						send letters to their husbands so that the men should
						leave the country; and if they would not write, he
						threatened to put them all to death after torturing
						them and making away with their children first.
						As he stood there a long time and urged them to say
						whether they would carry out any part of this programme, most of the women made no answer to him,
						but looked at one another in silence, and showed by
						nods that all their minds were made up not to be
						frightened or perturbed at the threat. Megisto,
						the wife of Timoleon, who, on account of her husband
						and her own virtues as well, held the position of leader,
						did not think it meet to rise, nor would she allow
						the other women to do so; but, keeping her seat, she
						made answer to him : <q direct="unspecified">If you were a sensible man,
						you would not be talking to women about husbands,
						but you would send to them, as to those having
						authority over us, finding better words to say to them
						than those by which you tricked us. But if you despair
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.525"/>
						
						of persuading them yourself, and are attempting
						to use us to mislead them, do not expect to deceive
						us again, and I pray that they may never entertain
						such a base thought that, to spare their wives and
						little children, they should forsake the cause of their
						country's freedom. In truth, it is not so bad a thing
						for them to lose us, whom they have not at present,
						as it is a good thing to rescue the citizens from your
						cruelty and overbearing insolence.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						As Megisto spoke thus, Aristotimus could not
						brook her words, and ordered her young child to be
						brought, as if intending to kill him in her sight. As
						the servants sought for him mingled among the other
						children playing and wrestling, his mother, calling
						him by name, said, <q direct="unspecified">Come here, child, and before
						you can realize and think, be delivered from this
						bitter despotism; since for me it is more grievous
						to look upon your undeserved slavery than upon
						your death.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						At this, Aristotimus drew his sword upon the
						mother herself, but as he was rushing at her in a rage,
						one of his intimate associates, Cylon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the inscription in honour of Cylon found at Delphi, Dittenberger, <hi rend="italics">Sylloge Inscript. Graec.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">3</hi> no. 423 (no. 920 in the second edition).</note> by name,
						who was thought to be loyal to him, but really hated
						him, and was in the consipracy with Hellanicus and
						the rest, intervened and turned him from his purpose
						by intreating him and saying that such action was
						ignoble and womanish, not that of a manly ruler who
						had learned to meet any situation. The result was
						that Aristotimus, with difficulty regaining his senses,
						came away.
					</p>
            <p>
						An ominous thing, however, happened to him.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.527"/>
						
						It was midday, and he was resting, and his wife was
						with him. While preparations for dinner were
						going on, an eagle was seen high in air circling over
						the house; then, as if with intent and design, it let
						fall a good-sized stone on that part of the roof under
						which was the room where Aristotimus happened to
						be lying. At the same moment there was a great
						crash above and shouting outside by those who saw
						the bird. Aristotimus was seized with consternation,
						and when he learned what had happened, he sent for
						a seer whom he constantly consulted in the marketplace, and, much perturbed, questioned him about
						the ominous happening. The seer encouraged him
						to believe that Zeus was rousing him and aiding him,
						but, on the other hand, told those citizens in whom he
						trusted that judgement was hovering over the despot's
						head, and was all but ready to fall on him. Wherefore it seemed best to Hellanicus and his friends not
						to delay but to make their attack on the next day.
					</p>
            <p>
						That night Hellanicus in his sleep dreamed
						that one of his dead sons stood beside him and said,
						<q direct="unspecified">What has happened to you, father, that you are
						asleep? To-morrow you must be commander of
						the city.</q> So he, having gained good courage
						because of the vision, urged on his associates,
						while on the other hand, Aristotimus also having
						learned that Craterus was coming to his aid with a
						numerous force and was encamped at Olympia,
						became so extremely bold that without his bodyguard he went forth into the market-place in the
						company of Cylon. When, therefore, Hellanicus
						realized the opportunity, he did not give the signal
						which had been agreed upon between himself and
						those who were to make the attempt, but with clear
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.529"/>
						
						voice, stretching out both arms at the words, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Why delay, brave men ? Fair is this place
						on the soil of your own native land to stage your
						contest!</q> So then Cylon first, drawing his sword,
						smote one of the men following with Aristotimus,
						but, as Thrasybulus and Lampis rushed at him
						from the opposite side, Aristotimus forestalled the
						conspirators by taking refuge in the temple of Zeus.
						There they slew him, and, exposing his corpse in
						the market-place, they sounded for the citizens the
						call to freedom. As a matter of fact, they were not
						much ahead of the women, for these at once ran
						forth with joyful acclamations and, surrounding the
						men, adorned them with ribbons and garlands.
						Then the crowd surged towards the house of the despot,
						but his wife, bolting the doors of her chamber,
						hanged herself. He had two daughters, still unwedded, most beautiful to look upon, of marriageable age. These they seized and dragged out,
						having resolved to do away with them, but to torture
						and insult them first. But Megisto, with the rest
						of the women, meeting them, cried out that they
						were committing a frightful crime if they who deemed
						themselves worthy to be a democratic people were,
						in this matter, showing recklessness and wanton
						violence like despots. As many had respect for the
						high worth of the woman who spoke so boldly amid
						her tears, they decided to omit the violence, and
						permit the daughters to die by their own hand.
					</p>
            <p>
						When, therefore, they had returned the maidens
						to the house and ordered their death immediately,
						the elder, Myro, loosing her girdle and making a
						noose of it, bade farewell to her sister and urged
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.531"/>
						
						her to take note and do exactly what she saw her
						do, <q direct="unspecified">so that,</q> she said, <q direct="unspecified">we may not end our lives
						in any humiliating way, unworthy of ourselves.</q>
						But when the younger sister wanted the other to
						concede to her the privilege of dying first, and seized
						hold of the girdle, the elder said, <q direct="unspecified">I have never
						denied you anything else that you wanted; and so
						you may receive this favour also, and I will patiently
						endure and bear what is more grievous than death,
						and that is, dearest, to see you die first.</q> Thereupon she instructed her sister how to put the noose
						around her neck, and when she saw that she was
						dead she took her down and covered her. She herself begged Megisto to take care of her and not to
						suffer her to be laid in any ignominious way when she
						should be dead. In consequence no one there was
						so bitter or such a hater of despots as not to shed
						tears and commiserate the nobility of the maidens.
					</p>
            <p>
						Of the deeds, countless in number, done by women
						acting together these may suffice as examples. But
						cases of individual bravery I will put down as they
						come to me, not in any order, because I think that
						the record of the present subject does not at all
						require a chronological arrangement.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="16">
            <head>XVI. PIERIA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 35; Aristaenetus, <hi rend="italics">Letters</hi>, i. 15.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Some of the lonians who came to Miletus, owing
						to lively disagreements with the sons of Neileus, went
						away to Myus and settled there, suffering many ills at
						the hands of the Milesians; for these made war upon
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.533"/>
						
						them because of their defection. However, the war
						was not without truce or intercourse, but at certain
						festivals the women commonly went to Miletus from
						My us. There was among the people of Myus a
						prominent man named Pythes, who had a wife named
						Iapygia and a daughter Pieria. As there was a
						festival in honour of Artemis, and a sacrifice, which
						they call Neleis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Lexikon der griech. und r&ouml;m. Mythologie</hi>, i. p. 572, line 63.</note> he sent his wife, and daughter, who
						had asked that they might participate in the festival.
						The most influential of Neileus's sons, Phrygius by
						name, fell in love with Pieria, and tried to think
						what could be done on his part that would be most
						pleasing to her. And when she said, <q direct="unspecified">If only you
						could make it possible for me to come here often and
						many with me,</q> Phrygius was quick to understand
						that she wanted friendship and peace for the citizens,
						and stopped the war. There was, consequently, in
						both cities repute and honour for Pieria, so that the
						women of Miletus pray even to this day that their
						husbands may love them as Phrygius loved Pieria.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="17">
            <head>XVII. POLYCRITE<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 36; Parthenius, <hi rend="italics">Love Stories</hi>, nos. 9 and 18.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						A war arose between the Naxians and Milesians
						on account of Neaera the wife of Hypsicreon of
						Miletus. It was because she fell in love with
						Promedon of Naxos and sailed away with him. He
						was a friend and guest of Hypsicreon, but yielded to
						Neaera's ardent advances, and then, as she was in
						fear of her husband, he took her away to Naxos, and
						placed her as a suppliant at the shrine of Hestia.
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.535"/>
						
						When the Naxians, as a favour to Promedon, refused
						to give her up, though they advanced another
						excuse, her position as suppliant, the war arose.
						Besides the many others who fought on the side of
						the Milesians the Erythraeans were the most zealous
						among the lonians; and the war dragged on and on,
						and brought great calamities. Then it came to an
						end through a woman's bravery, as it had arisen
						through a woman's badness.
					</p>
            <p>
						Diognetus, the general of the Erythraeans, entrusted with the command of a stronghold, its natural
						advantages reinforced by fortification to menace the
						city of the Naxians, gathered much spoil from the
						Naxians, and captured some free women and maidens;
						with one of these, Polycrite, he fell in love and kept
						her, not as a captive, but in the status of a wedded
						wife. Now when a festival which the Milesians
						celebrate came due in the army, and all turned to
						drinking and social gatherings, Polycrite asked
						Diognetus if there were any reason why she should
						not send some bits of pastry to her brothers. And
						when he not only gave her permission but urged her
						to do so, she slipped into a cake a note written on a
						sheet of lead, and bade the bearer tell her brothers
						that they themselves and no others should consume
						what she had sent. The brothers came upon the
						piece of lead and read the words of Polycrite, advising them to attack the enemy that night, as they
						were all in a state of carelessness from drink on account of the festival. Her brothers took this message
						to their generals and strongly urged them to set
						forth with themselves. When the place had been
						taken and many slain, Polycrite begged for the life of
						Diognetus from her citizens, and saved him. When
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.537"/>
						
						she herself arrived at the gates, and found herself
						confronting the citizens who came to meet her,
						welcoming her with joy and garlands and giving
						expression to their admiration for her, she could not
						bear the immensity of her joy, but fell down dead
						beside the gate; and there she is buried, and her
						tomb is called the Tomb of Envy, as though by some
						envious fortune Polycrite was begrudged the enjoyment of her honours.
					</p>
            <p>
						This is the story which the Naxian writers record.
						Aristotle,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 559 (ed. Rose) = Aulus Gellius, iii. 15.</note> however, says that Polycrite was not taken
						captive, but that Diognetus, in some other way, saw
						her and fell in love with her, and stood ready to give
						or to do anything; and she agreed to come to him,
						if she might obtain just one thing, for which, as the
						philosopher asserts, she required an oath of Diognetus. And when he had given the required oath,
						she demanded in fulfilment that Delium be given to
						her (the place was called by this name), otherwise
						she would have nothing to do with him. He, because
						of his love and his oath, was carried quite away, and
						handed over the spot to Polycrite, and she in turn to
						the citizens. Following this, the Naxians were again
						put on an equal footing, and effected a reconciliation
						with the Milesians on such terms as they desired.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>XVIII. LAMPSACE<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 37.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						There came from Phocaea twin brothers Phobus
						and Blepsus of the family of the Codridae, of whom
						Phobus was the first to throw himself into the sea
						from the Leucadian Rocks,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As a remedy for love, at least in later times.</note> as Charon of Lampsacus
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.539"/>
						
						has recorded.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Histor. Graec.</hi> i. p. 33.</note> Phobus, having influence and princely
						rank, sailed to Parium on some business of his own,
						and having become the friend and guest of Mandron,
						who was king of the Bebrycians who are called the
						Pityoessenians, he aided them by fighting on their
						side when they were being harassed by their neighbours. When Phobus took his departure Mandron
						expressed the utmost regard for him, and, in particular, promised to give him a part of their land and
						city if Phobus wished to come to Pityoessa with
						Phocaean colonists. So Phobus prevailed on his
						citizens and sent out his brother with the colonists.
						And what Mandron had promised was at their disposal, as they expected.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xiii. (589), and Stephanus of Byzantium under Lampsacus.</note> But they, inasmuch as
						they made great gains for themselves through the
						spoils and booty which they took from the neighbouring barbarians, were first an object of envy, and later
						an object of fear also, to the Bebrycians, who, desiring
						to be rid of them, could not prevail on Mandron, who
						was a fair and just man in his treatment of the Greeks;
						but when he had gone away on a journey, they prepared to destroy the Phocians by treachery. But
						the daughter of Mandron, Lampsace, a young girl,
						learned of the plot beforehand, and tried first to
						dissuade her friends and relatives and to point out
						to them that they were undertaking to carry out a
						frightful and wicked deed in murdering men who
						were their benefactors and allies and now also their
						fellow-citizens. But when she could not prevail on
						them, she secretly told the Greeks what was afoot,
						and warned them to be on their guard. And they,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.541"/>
						
						having made ready a sacrifice and banquet, invited
						the Pityoessenians to come to it just outside the city;
						then, dividing themselves into two parties, with the
						one they took possession of the walls, and with the
						other made away with the men. Having gained
						control of the city in this manner, they sent for
						Mandron, and bade him be king jointly with one or
						another of their own number. Lampsace died as the
						result of an illness, and they buried her within the
						city most magnificently, and called the city Lampsacus after her name.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xiii. (589), and Stephanus of Byzantium under Lampsacus.</note> When Mandron, endeavouring to avoid any suspicion of treachery, asked to be
						released from dwelling with them, but asked as his
						right to take away with him the children and wives
						of the slain, they sent them forth, doing them no
						wrong. They rendered heroic honours to Lampsace
						at first; later they voted to offer sacrifice to her as to
						a goddess, and so they continue to do.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>XIX. ARETAPHILA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 38.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Aretaphila, of Cyrene, was not born long years
						ago, but in the crucial times of Mithradates; she
						displayed, however, a bravery and an achievement
						which may well rival the counsel of the heroines of
						olden time. She was the daughter of Aeglator and
						the wife of Phaedimus, both men of note. She had
						beautiful features, and was reputed to be unusually
						sensible and not deficient in political wisdom, but the
						common misfortunes of her country brought her into
						prominence.
					</p>
            <p>
						Nicocrates, having made himself despot over the
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.543"/>
						
						people of Cyrene, not only ordered the murder of
						many persons, but killed with his own hand Melanippus the priest of Apollo, and took the priesthood
						himself. He also killed Phaedimus the husband of
						Aretaphila, and made Aretaphila his unwilling wife.
						In addition to his other unnumbered acts of lawlessness, he stationed guards at the gates, who maltreated
						the dead that were being borne to the grave, prodding them with daggers, and applying red-hot irons
						to them, so that none of the citizens should be secretly
						carried out in the guise of a corpse.
					</p>
            <p>
						Even for Aretaphila her own troubles were hard
						enough to bear, although the despot, because of his
						love for her, granted her the fullest enjoyment
						of his power, for he was quite vanquished by her,
						and with her alone did he conduct himself civilly,
						being relentless and brutal in all else. But even so,
						the piteous and undeserved suffering of her country
						distressed her the more; for one citizen after another
						was slaughtered, and there was no hope of vengeance
						from any quarter; for the exiles, altogether weak
						and timid, were scattered here and there and everywhere. So Aretaphila, risking herself as the sole
						remaining hope for the common weal, and emulating
						the glorious and far-famed daring of Thebe<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Who killed her husband Alexander. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 856 a; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, vi. 4. 35-37; Diodorus, xvi. 14; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De divinatione</hi>, i. 25 (53), <hi rend="italics">De inventione</hi>, ii. 49 (144) and <hi rend="italics">De officiis</hi>, ii. 7 (25); Valerius Maximus, ix. 13, ext. 4. Theopompus wrote an account of this (as Plutarch says, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1093 c).</note> of
						Pherae, but being destitute of faithful supporters
						in the household, such as the circumstances provided for Thebe, undertook to dispatch her husband
						by poison. In preparing, procuring, and testing
						many potent mediums she did not go unnoticed,
						but was betrayed. And when proofs were presented,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.545"/>
						
						Calbia, Nicocrates's mother, who was by nature
						bloodthirsty and inexorable, felt that she ought
						to make away with Aretaphila after torturing her.
						But Nicocrates' love had the effect of tempering his
						anger with procrastination and weakness, and the fact
						that Aretaphila vigorously met the accusations and
						defended herself against them provided some excuse
						for his attitude. But when she was apprehended
						by the proofs, and saw that her preparations for the
						poisoning admitted no denial, she confessed, but said
						that she had prepared no fatal poisoning. <q direct="unspecified">No, my
						dear,</q> said she, <q direct="unspecified">my striving is for very important
						things, your affection for me, and the repute and
						influence which I enjoy because of you, and so am an
						object of envy to bad women. It was fear of their
						potions and devices that led me to invent some
						devices to counteract them. It was foolish and
						feminine perhaps, but not deserving of death,
						unless you as judge decide to put to death because
						of love-potions and charms a woman who yearns for
						more love than you are willing to grant her.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						In spite of this defence of Aretaphila's, Nicocrates
						decided to have her put to the torture, and, with
						Calbia standing by, relentless and inexorable, he
						tested her in this way. She sustained herself with
						indomitable courage under the torments until even
						Calbia unwillingly gave over; and Nicocrates was
						convinced, and acquitted her, and was sorry that he
						had caused her to be tortured; and after no long
						time he came back again, impelled towards her by
						his passion for her, and resumed the old relations,
						and tried through honours and acts of kindness to
						regain her goodwill. But she, who had been triumphant
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.547"/>
						
						over tortures and pain, had no intention of
						being vanquished by a show of favour, and, with
						eagerness for victory added to her eagerness for the
						honourable and good, she resorted to another device.
					</p>
            <p>
						She was fortunate in having a daughter of marriageable age, rather good-looking. Her she dangled as
						a bait before the despot's brother, who was a young
						man and an easy prey to pleasures. There is much
						talk to the effect that Aretaphila, by using charms
						and love-potions on the girl, got the youth in hand and
						upset his reasoning powers. His name was Leander.
						When he had been captivated, and, by importuning
						his brother, had gained his consent to the marriage,
						the girl, on the one hand, instructed by her mother,
						tried to influence him and to induce him to set the
						city free, arguing that not even he himself was living
						as a free man under the despotism, and had not even
						warrant to contract a marriage or to keep to it;
						and, on the other hand, his friends, thinking to do a
						favour to Aretaphila, suggested to his mind certain
						prej udices and suspicions against his brother. When he
						discovered that Aretaphila was planning and working
						to the same end, he undertook the deed, and by
						urging on Daphnis a servant, through him he slew
						Nicocrates. For the rest, he no longer paid any
						attention to Aretaphila, but straightway showed
						by his deeds that he had made away with his brother,
						but not with the despot; for he ruled in a crazy
						and foolish way. Nevertheless there remained with
						him some respect for Aretaphila and some influence
						on her part, as she was not hateful to him and not
						directly hostile, but carried on her activities in his
						affairs unknown to him. First she secretly stirred up
						a war with the Africans for him by persuading a
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.549"/>
						
						certain potentate Anabus to overrun the country
						and lead his army against the city; then she falsely
						accused to Leander his friends and generals, intimating that they were not zealous in carrying on the war,
						but wanted rather peace and quiet, which his circumstances and despotism required, as he wished to
						hold secure his power over the citizens. She said
						that she herself would effect the reconciliation, and
						would get Anabus to come to a conference with him,
						if he would but give the word, before the war should
						have wrought some irremediable ill. When Leander
						gave the word, she herself had a talk with the African
						beforehand, in which she desired him, on the promise
						of many presents and much money, to seize the
						despot when he should come to the conference with
						him. When the African had been won over, Leander
						was hesitant, but, abashed before Aretaphila, who
						said that she would be present herself, he went forth
						unarmed and unattended. When he came near
						and saw Anabus, he again felt uneasy, and wanted
						to wait for his bodyguard. But Aretaphila, who was
						there, at one moment encouraged him, and the next
						called him a coward. Finally, as a delay ensued,
						she, quite impulsively and boldly dragging him by
						the hand, brought him up to the barbarian and
						handed him over. Instantly he was seized and
						made a prisoner, and, after having been put in
						bonds, was kept under watch by the Africans, until
						Aretaphila's friends, who were bringing the money
						for her, arrived, accompanied by the rest of the
						citizens. For almost all of them, on hearing the
						news, ran out at the call. When they saw Aretaphila, they came near forgetting their anger against
						the despot, and considered vengeance upon him a
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.551"/>
						
						secondary concern. Their first concern in the enjoyment of their freedom was to greet her with joy
						and tears, prostrating themselves before her as
						before the statue of a god. As the people surged
						on, one close upon another, it was with difficulty that
						by evening they took over Leander and returned to
						the city. When they had had their fill of honours
						and praises for Aretaphila, they then turned their
						attention to the despots. Calbia they burned alive,
						and Leander they sewed up in a leathern sack and
						sank in the depths of the sea. They asked that
						Aretaphila, as her proper due, should share with the
						best citizens in the control and management of the
						government. But she, as one who had played through
						a drama of varying sort and of many roles up to the
						winning of the prize, when she saw the city free,
						withdrew at once to her own quarters among the
						women, and, rejecting any sort of meddling in affairs,
						spent the rest of her life quietly at the loom in the
						company of her friends and family.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="20">
            <head>XX. CAMMA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">The Cup</hi>, a drama by Alefred Lord Tennyson, follows closely Plutarch's story of Camma, which inspired it. The play (published in 1884) may be found in Tennyson's collected works. It was presented at the Lyceum Theatre in 1881 by Henry Irving and ran for over one hundred and thirty nights. Certainly the account of Camma's death does not lack dramatic quality.<p/>Plutarch repeats the story in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 768 b, and Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 39, also gives his version.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						There were in Galatia two of the most powerful
						of the tetrarchs, distantly related to each other,
						Sinatus and Sinorix. One of these, Sinatus, had
						married a maiden, Camma by name, conspicuous for
						her form and beauty, but even more admired for her
						virtues. Not only was she modest and fond of her
						husband, but she was also quick-witted and high-minded,
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.553"/>
						
						and unusually dear to her inferiors by reason
						of her kindness and benevolence. A thing that
						brought her into greater prominence was the fact
						that she was the priestess of Artemis, whom the
						Galatians especially reverence, and was seen magnificently attired always in connexion with the processions and sacrifices.
					</p>
            <p>
						So Sinorix fell in love with her, and not being
						able to prevail upon her either by persuasion or
						force as long as her husband lived, he committed
						a horrible deed, and treacherously killed Sinatus.
						Then, without allowing much time to elapse, he
						commenced to woo Camma, who was spending time in
						the temple and bearing Sinorix's lawless transgression in no pitiful nor abject manner, but with a
						spirit that showed sense and bided its time. He was
						persistent in his suit, and seemed not to be at all at
						a loss for arguments that had some plausibility, to
						the effect that in all other respects he had shown
						himself a better man than Sinatus, and had made
						away with him for love of Camma and not because
						of any other nefarious intent. The woman's denials
						at the first were not too peremptory, and later, little
						by little, she appeared to be softened; for her relatives and friends also brought pressure to bear upon
						her by way of service and favour to Sinorix, who held
						such very great power, and they tried to persuade
						and coerce her. Finally she yielded, and sent for
						him to come to her, on the ground that the consenting
						and pledging should take place in the presence of
						the goddess. When he had come, she received him
						kindly and, having led him to the altar, poured a
						libation from a bowl, then drank a portion herself
						and bade him drink the rest; it was poisoned mixture
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.555"/>
						
						of milk and honey. When she saw that he had
						drunk, she uttered a clear cry of joy, and, prostrating
						herself before the goddess, said, <q direct="unspecified">I call you to
						witness, goddess most revered, that for the sake of
						this day I have lived on after the murder of Sinatus,
						and during all that time I have derived no comfort
						from life save only the hope of justice; and now
						that justice is mine, I go down to my husband. But
						as for you, wickedest of all men, let your relatives
						make ready a tomb instead of a bridal chamber
						and a wedding.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						When the Galatian heard these words, and felt the
						poison already working and creating a disturbance
						in his body, he mounted a chariot as if to try shaking
						and jolting as a relief, but he got out almost immediately and changed over into a litter, and in the
						evening he died. Camma endured through the
						night, and when she learned that he had come to his
						end, she died cheerful and happy.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="21">
            <head>XXI. STRATONICE</head>
            <p>
						Galatia produced also Stratonice the wife of Deiotarus and Chiomara the wife of Ortiagon, women
						that deserve to be remembered.
					</p>
            <p>
						Stratonice, well knowing that her husband desired
						children from her to succeed to the kingdom, but
						having no child herself, prevailed upon him to have
						a child by anotheF woman, and to connive at its
						being passed off as her own. Deiotarus thought
						highly of the idea, and did everything in dependence
						upon her judgement, and she procured a comely
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.557"/>
						
						maiden from among the prisoners, Electra by name,
						and sealed her to Deiotarus. The children that were
						born she brought up with loving care and in royal
						state as if they had been her own.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="22">
            <head>XXII. CHIOMARA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is printed as one of the fragments of Polybius, xxi. 38 (xxii. 21), from whom it is possible that Plutarch copied the story. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Livy, xxxviii. 24; Valerius Maximus, vi. 1, ext. 2; Florus, <hi rend="italics">Epitome of Roman History</hi>, i. 27. 6 (ii. 11. 6).</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						It came to pass that Chiomara, the wife of Ortiagon,
						was made a prisoner of war along with the rest of the
						women at the time when the Romans under Gnaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Gnaeus Manlius Vulso: the battle took place in 189 b.c.</note>
						overcame in battle the Galatians in Asia. The
						officer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A centurion, according to the Roman account.</note> who obtained possession of her used his good
						fortune as soldiers do, and dishonoured her. He was,
						naturally, an ignorant man with no self-control when
						it came to either pleasure or money. He fell a 
						victim, however, to his love of money, and when a
						very large sum in gold had been mutually agreed
						upon as the price for the woman, he brought her to
						exchange for the ransom to a place where a river,
						flowing between, formed a boundary. When the 
						Galatians had crossed and given him the money and
						received Chiomara, she, by a nod, indicated to one
						man that he should smite the Roman as he was 
						affectionately taking leave of her. And when the
						man obediently struck off the Roman's head, she
						picked it up and, wrapping it in the folds of her
						garment, departed. When she came to her husband
						and threw the head down before him, he said in
						amazement, <q direct="unspecified">A noble thing, dear wife, is fidelity.</q>
						         <q direct="unspecified">Yes.</q> said she, <q direct="unspecified">but it is a nobler thing that only
						one man be alive who has been intimate with me.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">
                     <foreign lang="la">Tempora mutantur, nos et mutamur in illis</foreign>.</q>
               </note>
						
					       </p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.559"/>
            <p>
						Polybius says that be had a conversation with this
						woman in Sardis, and that he admired her good
						sense and intelligence.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="23">
            <head>XXIII. A WOMAN OF PERGAMUM</head>
            <p>
						When Mithradates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Appian, <hi rend="italics">The Mithridatic Wars</hi>, vii. 46.</note> after sending for sixty of the
						noblest of Galatians to come to Pergamum as friends,
						seemed to comport himself arrogantly and despotically toward them, and all were indignant, Poredorix,
						a man of great bodily strength and of unusual spirit,
						tetrarch of the Tosiopians, undertook, when Mithradates should be hearing cases on the tribunal in a
						gymnasium, to seize hold of it suddenly and precipitate him, tribunal and all, down into the ravine. But
						by some chance Mithradates did not go up to the
						gymnasium on that day, but sent for the Galatians
						to come to his house, whereupon Poredorix urged
						them to keep up their courage and, when they all
						should be met together there, to rend Mithradates
						limb from limb, and kill him, by falling upon him from
						all sides at once. Knowledge of this came to Mithradates through the agency of some informer, and he
						delivered over the Galatians one by one to be executed. A little later, happening to remember a
						young man who, in comeliness and beauty, far surpassed those of his age, he felt sorry for him and
						changed his mind. It was plain that he was much
						distressed, since the youth had probably been put to
						death among the first; yet he sent orders that, if
						the youth should be found alive, they should let him
						go. The young man's name was Bepolitanus, and a
						marvellous piece of luck befell him in this wise :
						when he was arrested he was wearing very beautiful
						and costly clothing, which the executioner wished to
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.561"/>
						
						keep, unstained by blood and unsullied, for himself,
						and he was stripping this off in a leisurely way, when
						he saw the messengers from the king running towards
						him and shouting the youth's name. So in the case
						of Bepolitanus, avarice, which has been the undoing
						of many a man, unexpectedly saved his life.
					</p>
            <p>
						Poredorix was executed and his body cast forth
						unburied, and not one of his friends dared to go near
						him; but a woman of Pergamum, who for her loveliness had been known to the Galatian while he was
						living, took the risk of burying and covering up his
						body. The guards, noticing her, arrested her and
						took her before the king. It is said that Mithradates' emotions were stirred at the sight of her, as the
						girl appeared altogether young and innocent. A still
						stronger influence very likely came from his having
						learned that love was the reason behind it all; at any
						rate, he relented and granted her permission to remove
						and bury the corpse, and to take for it clothing and
						adornment from what belonged to him.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="24">
            <head>XXIV. TIMOCLEIA<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch tells of Timocleia more briefly in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. xii. (671 a). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 40; Hieronymus, <hi rend="italics">Adversus Iovinianum</hi>, 35; Zonaras, iv. 9 (185 b).</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Theagenes of Thebes, who had come to entertain
						the same aspirations for his city as Epameinondas and
						Pelopidas and the noblest of the Thebans, came to
						grief, involved in the general fortunes of Greece at
						Chaeroneia, when he was already overpowering and
						pursuing the opposing lines. He is the one who, in
						answer to a man who cried out, <q direct="unspecified">How far is your
						pursuit to go ?</q> said, <q direct="unspecified">As far as Macedonia!</q>
						      </p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.563"/>
            <p>
						A sister survived him to bear witness that by reason
						of the virtues of the family and his own natural
						endowment he was a great and splendid man. However, she had the advantage of getting some benefit
						from her virtues, so that she could bear more lightly
						so much of the general misfortunes as came upon
						her.
					</p>
            <p>
						For when Alexander had overpowered the Thebans,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 335 b.c.</note>
						and some of his men were going to this part of the
						city, and others to that, and plundering, it happened
						that a man took possession of Timocleia's house who
						was not reasonable or civil but arrogant and foolish.
						He was commander of a certain Thracian troop,
						and bore the same name as the king, but was in
						no way like him; for, without showing the least
						respect for the ancestry or the estate of the woman,
						after he had guzzled his fill of wine, he summoned her
						after dinner to spend the night with him. And this
						was not the end; he asked for gold and silver, if
						any had been hidden away by her, at one time
						threatening to kill her, at another promising to keep
						her for all time in the position of a wife. She, seizing
						upon the hold he offered, said, <q direct="unspecified">Would God I had
						been dead before this night rather than to be alive,
						so that I might at least, when all else is being ravaged,
						have preserved my honour. But, since what has
						been done is done, if I must look upon you as my
						protector, lord, and husband, by God's will, I will
						not deprive you of your own; for I see that I myself
						have become whatever your will shall decide. I did
						possess personal ornaments and silver fashioned into
						drinking-cups, and there was also some gold and
						money. When the city was being captured, I told
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.565"/>
						
						my maid-servants to get this all together, and I
						threw it i or rather deposited it, into a dry well.
						Nor do many know of it; for there is a cover over
						the well, and a shady wood growing all around it.
						I hope you may be fortunate in obtaining it, and for
						me it will serve as proofs and tokens to you of the
						happy and splendid state of my house.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						When the Macedonian heard this, he could not
						wait for daylight, but went straight to the place under
						the guidance of Timocleia, and, after ordering the
						garden to be shut close, so that nobody should find
						out what was going on, he climbed down into the
						well in his shirt only. An odious Fate led him on,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The poetic expression probably comes from some lyric or dramatic poet. It can hardly have been made up by Plutarch from Hesiod's <hi rend="italics">Shield of Heracles</hi>, 258.</note>
						destined to work vengeance upon him at the hands
						of Timocleia standing over him at the top of the well.
						When she could tell by his voice that he had reached
						the bottom, she herself brought many of the stones,
						while her maid-servants rolled in many big ones on
						top until they had beaten him down and completely
						buried him. When the Macedonians came to know
						of this and recovered the corpse, inasmuch as proclamation had been made before this to kill none of
						the Thebans, they arrested Timocleia and brought
						her to the king, and told of her daring deed. But
						he, seeing in the composure of her countenance
						and her unhurried step an indication of high
						rank and noble blood, first questioned her as to
						who she was among the women. She quite undauntedly and courageously said, <q direct="unspecified">I had the good
						fortune to have a brother Theagenes, who was a
						general at Chaeroneia and fell there, fighting against
						you Macedonians for the freedom of Greece, that
						we might not have any such experience as we have
						had. But since we have had an experience undeserved
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.567"/>
						
						by our family, we have no wish to escape
						death; for it were better, perhaps, not to live to
						experience another such night, unless you put a
						stop to this thing.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						At this the most sympathetic of those present
						began to weep, but it did not occur to Alexander
						to pity the woman, for he felt that she was too great
						for that, but he marvelled at her bravery and her
						words, which touched him greatly, and he issued
						orders to his officers that they should take good
						and be on the watch that no such insult should again
						be offered to a noted house. Timocleia he allowed
						to go free, both herself and all others who were
						found to be related to her.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="25">
            <head>XXV. ERYXO<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, iv. 160; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 41; M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Histor. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 387, Nicolaus Damasc. Frag. 52.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						Arcesilaus, the son of Battus who was nicknamed
						&lsquo;The Happy,&rsquo; was not at all like his father in his
						ways. In fact, while his father was still living, he
						surrounded his house with a rampart, and was fined
						two hundred pounds by his father; and when his
						father had come to his end, for one thing Arcesilaus,
						being harsh by nature (and this gave him his nickname),<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">He was nicknamed &lsquo;The Harsh.&rsquo;</note> and for another consorting with a vicious
						friend Laarchus, instead of being a king became a
						despot. Laarchus, secretly scheming to become
						despot, banished or murdered the noblest among
						the men of Cyrene, and diverted all the blame for
						this from himself to Arcesilaus; and finally he
						brought Arcesilaus into a wasting and grievous
						illness by a drink containing sea-hare,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A kind of fish (<hi rend="italics">Lepus marinus</hi>); Plutarch (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 983 f) says that it is fatal to human beings.</note> and thus
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.569"/>
						
						accomplished his death; then he took over the
						sovereign rule himself on the pretext that he was
						keeping it for Arcesilaus's son Battus. The boy,
						by reason of his lameness and his youth as well,
						was looked down upon, but to his mother many gave
						heed, for she was discreet and humane, and had many
						influential relatives. Wherefore Laarchus lavished
						attentions upon her, trying to win her as his wife,
						saying that it was only right and proper to make
						Battus his own son by marrying her, and to proclaim him colleague in the sovereignty. Eryxo
						(for that was the woman's name), after taking counsel
						with her brothers, bade Laarchus to have an interview with them, as if she herself looked with favour
						on the marriage. But when Laarchus interviewed
						them, and they purposely misled him and put him
						off, Eryxo sent a maid-servant to him to tell him
						from her that at present her brothers declared themselves opposed, but if the union should be consummated, they would cease their dissent and give
						over; he must, therefore, come to her by night if he
						were willing; for if the beginning were once made,
						all the rest would be well.
					</p>
            <p>
						This was joyful news to Laarchus, and, all excitement in view of the woman's compliant mood, he
						agreed to come whenever she should give the word.
						Eryxo carried out all this in consultation with
						Polyarchus the eldest of her brothers. When a
						time had been determined upon for the coming
						together, Polyarchus was secretly introduced into
						his sister's room, having with him two young men
						with sword in hand who were intent on avenging
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.571"/>
						
						the murder of their father, whom Laarchus, a short
						time before, had put to death.
					</p>
            <p>
						When Eryxo sent for Laarchus, he came in unattended, and, the young men falling upon him, he
						was run through by their swords and killed. His
						body they threw over the wall and, bringing forward
						Battus, they proclaimed him king in succession to
						his father's rights, and Polyarchus restored to the
						people of Cyrene their original form of government.
					</p>
            <p>
						It happened that there were in the city numerous
						soldiers of Amasis, king of the Egyptians. These
						Laarchus had employed as trusty retainers, and they
						were not the least of his instruments through which
						he terrorized the citizens. These soldiers sent men
						to Amasis to accuse Polyarchus and Eryxo, He
						was much incensed and had thoughts of making
						war on the people of Cyrene, but just then it happened
						that his mother died, and it was during the days in
						which he was holding her funeral that messengers
						returned from Amasis with the tidings. So Polyarchus thought it best to go there to make his defence.
						When Eryxo would not be left behind, but expressed
						her wish to go with him and share the danger, their
						mother Critola, although well on in years, would not
						be left behind either. Her standing was of the
						highest, since she was the sister of Battus the Happy.
						When they came to Egypt, the people expressed
						wondrous approval of their exploit, and Amasis
						expressed extraordinary approval of the self-control
						and courage of the woman; and after honouring
						both Polyarchus and the women with presents and
						royal attentions he sent them back to Cyrene.
						
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.573"/>
						
					       </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="26">
            <head>XXVI. XENOCRITE</head>
            <p>
						No less admiration might be expressed for Xenocrite of Cumae for her behaviour towards Aristodemus
						the despot,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Dionysius of Halicarnassus, <hi rend="italics">Roman Antiquities</hi>, v. 4-12; Diodorus, vii. 10.</note> who, some think, had the nickname of
						&lsquo;Mild&rsquo; given to him, but they do not know the truth.
						The fact is that by the barbarians he was called
						&lsquo;Mild,&rsquo; which, in their tongue, means &lsquo;childlike,&rsquo;
						because, when he was a mere youth with others of
						his age who were still wearing their hair long (whom
						they called &lsquo;harassers,&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Strollers who went about singing begging songs. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, 359 d-360 b. <q direct="unspecified">Harassers</q> as a corruption of <q direct="unspecified">Hair-raisers</q> is no more weird than Plutarch's Greek etymology!</note> from their long hair presumably), in the wars against the barbarians he was
						conspicuous and brilliant, not merely by daring and
						the work of his hands, but showing himself to be
						above others in quickness of mind and forethought.
						Wherefore he advanced to the highest offices, being
						admired by his fellow-citizens, and he was sent to
						bring aid to the Romans when they were besieged
						by the Etruscans who would restore Tarquinius
						Superbus to his kingdom. In this campaign, which
						lasted a long time, he gave in altogether to the
						citizens who were in the military service, and, by
						playing the part of a demagogue rather than that
						of a general, he persuaded them to join him in attacking the Senate and in driving into exile the noblest
						and most influential. Following upon this, he made
						himself despot, and in the ways in which he misconducted himself towards women and free-born youth
						he surpassed his former record for viciousness. In
						fact it is recorded in history that he imposed on the
						boys the custom of wearing long hair and golden
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.575"/>
						
						ornaments, and the girls he compelled to bob their
						Iuli r and to wear boys' clothes and the short undergarment. However, he was singularly enamoured
						of Xenocrite, whom he kept, the daughter of an
						exiled father, without restoring her father to his
						country or winning his consent, but believing that
						somehow the girl was contented to be with him,
						inasmuch as she was envied and deemed happy by
						the citizens. But all this did not make any great
						impression on her. She was distressed at being
						partner to a union in which there had been no giving
						in marriage nor plighting of troth, and she longed for
						her country's freedom no less than did those who were
						the object of the despot's hatred.
					</p>
            <p>
						It happened at that juncture that Aristodemus
						was extending a moat all the way round the country,
						a work neither necessary nor useful, but the real
						reason was that he wished to wear out the citizens
						and waste their strength with toils and labours;
						for it was prescribed for each one to carry out a certain
						number of measures of earth. One woman, when
						she saw Aristodemus approaching, stepped well out
						of his way and covered her face with her garment.
						When he had gone, the young men made fun of her
						and asked her, in joke, why her modesty led her to
						avoid Aristodemus only, when she had no such
						feeling towards the rest of the men. She with a very
						serious purpose replied, <q direct="unspecified">Because among all the
						people of Cumae Aristodemus is the only man!</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						These few words thus spoken laid hold upon them
						all, and also incited the noble-minded, for very shame,
						to struggle for their liberty. It is said that when
						Xenocrite heard of it she said that she herself would
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.577"/>
						
						rather carry earth for her father, if he were only in
						his own land, than be associated with Aristodemus
						in all his luxury and power. These things gave
						added strength to those who were banding together
						against Aristodemus, at the head of whom was
						Thymoteles. And when Xenocrite provided them
						with a safe way to get in and assurance that Aristodemus was unarmed and unattended, they forced
						their way in without much difficulty, and dispatched
						him. Thus the city of Cumae was made free by the
						bravery of two women, the one who put into their
						minds the thought and impulse for the deed, and
						the other who co-operated with them to bring about
						its conclusion.
					</p>
            <p>
						Honours and great gifts were tendered to Xenocrite, but she would have none of them; one request
						only she made, to bury the body of Aristodemus,
						and this they granted her, and chose her to be priestess of Demeter, feeling that the honour would be no
						less pleasing to the goddess than appropriate for
						Xenocrite.
					</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="27">
            <head>XXVII. THE WIFE OF PYTHES<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, viii. 42; Herodotus, vii. 27-29 and 38-39, where the name is given as Pythius.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
						It is said the wife of Pythes, contemporary with
						Xerxes, was wise and good. Pythes himself, as
						it appears, came by chance upon some gold mines,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the source of the gold of Pythes see T. Leslie Shear in the <hi rend="italics">Classical Weekly</hi>, xvii. p. 186.</note>
						and, delighting in the wealth from them not with
						moderation, but insatiably and beyond measure,
						he himself spent all his time over them, and put the
						citizens down there also, and compelled all alike
						to dig or carry or wash out the gold, performing no
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.579"/>
						
						other work and carrying on no other activity. Many
						perished and all were completely exhausted, when
						the women, coming to the door of the wife of Pythes,
						made supplication. She bade them depart and not
						lose heart; then she summoned the goldsmiths
						whom she trusted most, secluded them, and ordered
						them to make golden loaves of bread, cakes of all
						sorts, fruit, and whatever else in the way of dainties
						and food she knew Pythes liked best. When these
						had all been made, Pythes arrived home from
						abroad; for he had been travelling. And when he
						called for dinner, his wife caused a golden table to be
						set before him which contained nothing edible, but
						everything of gold. At first Pythes was delighted
						with the mimic food, but when he had gazed his fill,
						he called for something to eat; and she served to him
						a golden replica of whatever he chanced to express
						a desire for. By this time he was in a high dudgeon
						and shouted out that he was hungry, whereupon she
						said, <q direct="unspecified">But it is you who have created for us a plentiful supply of these things, and of nothing else;
						for all skill in the trades has disappeared from among
						us; no one tills the soil, but we have forsaken the
						sowing and planting of crops in the soil and the sustaining food that comes from it, and we dig and delve
						for useless things, wasting our own strength and that
						of our people.</q>
					       </p>
            <p>
						These things moved Pythes, and he did away with
						much of his activities at the mines, but not all,
						ordering a fifth of the citizens to work the mines in
						turn, and the remainder he transferred to agriculture
						and the trades.
					</p>
            <p>
						When Xerxes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus tells the story of Pythes' (Pythius's) relations with Xerxes at length in vii. 27-39.</note> was on his way to invade Greece,
						Pythes, who had been most splendid in his entertainments
						
						<pb id="v.3.p.581"/>
						
						and gifts, asked as a favour from the king
						that, as he had several sons, the king should exempt
						one from military duty, and leave him at home to be
						a comfort to Pythes in his old age. Xerxes, in his
						rage,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De ira</hi>, iii. 16; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, xxxiii. 10 (47).</note> ordered that this one son for whom the father
						made his request should be killed and cut in two,
						and that the army should march between the two
						halves; the others he took with him, and all perished
						in the battles.
					</p>
            <p>
						Because of this Pythes lost all spirit, and went
						through an experience similar to that of many bad
						and foolish men; for he was afraid of death and
						burdened with life. He wished not to live, and yet
						could not let go of life. As there was a great mound
						in the city, and also a river flowing through it, which
						they called the Pythopolites, he made ready a
						mausoleum in the mound, and then turned the course
						of the stream so that the river was carried through
						the mound with its waters touching the tomb.
						Upon the completion of all this he went down into
						the mausoleum, committing the government and care
						of the whole city to his wife, and ordered her not to
						come near him, but to send his dinner for him every
						day, by placing it in a boat, until the time when the
						boat should pass by the tomb with the dinner untouched; then she should cease sending, taking it
						for granted that he was dead. He passed the remainder of his life in this way, and his wife administered the government excellently, and gave the
						citizens relief from their miseries.
						
					</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>