<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De E apud Delphos</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.5.p.194"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>THE E AT DELPHI
					(DE E APUD DELPHOS)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					Plutarch, in this essay on the E at Delphi, tells us
					that beside the well-known inscriptions at Delphi
					there was also a representation of the letter E, the
					fifth letter of the Greek alphabet. The Greek name
					for this letter was EI, and this diphthong, in addition
					to being used in Plutarch's time as the name of E
					(which denotes the number five), is the Greek word
					for <q direct="unspecified">if,</q> and also the word for the second person
					singular of the verb <q direct="unspecified">to be</q> (thou art).
				</p>
            <p>
					In searching for an explanation of the unexplainable it is only natural that the three meanings of EI
					(<q direct="unspecified">five,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">if,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">thou art</q>) should be examined to see if
					any hypothesis based on any one of them might
					possibly yield a rational explanation ; and these
					hypotheses constitute the skeleton about which is
					built the body of Plutarch's essay. From it we gain
					some interesting delineations of character and an
					engaging portrayal of the way in which a philosopher
					acts, or reacts, when forced unwillingly to face the
					unknowable.
				</p>
            <p>
					Plutarch puts forward seven possible explanations
					of the letter :
				</p>
            <p>
					(1) It was dedicated by the Wise Men, as a protest
					against interlopers, to show that their number was
					actually five and not seven (EI = E, five).
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.195"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					(2)	EI is the second vowel, the Sun is the second
					planet, and Apollo is identified with the sun (EI = E,
					the vowel).
				</p>
            <p>
					(3)	EI means <q direct="unspecified">if</q>: people ask the oracle IF
					they shall succeed, or IF they shall do this or that
					(EI=<q direct="unspecified">if</q>).
				</p>
            <p>
					(4)	EI is used in wishes or prayers to the god,
					often in the combination <foreign lang="greek">ei)/qe</foreign> or <foreign lang="greek">ei) ga/r</foreign> (EI = <q direct="unspecified">if</q> or
					<q direct="unspecified">if only</q>).
				</p>
            <p>
					(5)	EI, <q direct="unspecified">if,</q> is an indispensable word in logic for
					the construction of a syllogism (EI = <q direct="unspecified">if</q>).
				</p>
            <p>
					(6)	Five is a most important number in mathematics, physiology, philosophy, and music (EI = E,
					<q direct="unspecified">five</q>).
				</p>
            <p>
					(7)	EI means <q direct="unspecified">thou art</q> and is the address of the
					consultant to Apollo, to indicate that the god has
					eternal being (EI = <q direct="unspecified">thou art</q>).<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This explanation is accepted by Poulsen (<hi rend="italics">Delphi</hi>, p. 149), but is open to very serious objections.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Attempts to explain the letter have been also made
					in modern times by G&ouml;ttling, <hi rend="italics">Berickte der Sacks</hi>.
					<hi rend="italics">Gesell. der Wiss.</hi> I. (1846-47) pp. 311 if., and by
					Schultz in <hi rend="italics">Philologus</hi> (1866), pp. 214 if. Roscher, in
					<hi rend="italics">Philologus</hi> (1900), pp. 21 if.; (1901), pp. 81 if.; (1902),
					pp. 513 if.; <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi> (1901), pp. 470 ff. (comment also by
					C. Robert in the same volume, p. 490), and the <hi rend="italics">Philologische Wochenschrift</hi> (1922), col. 1211, maintains that
					EI is an imperative from <foreign lang="greek">ei)=mi</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">go,</q> addressed to the
					person who carne to consult the oracle, and that it
					means <q direct="unspecified">go on,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">continue</q> into the temple. The
					value of this explanation is somewhat doubtful,
					since EI in this word (<foreign lang="greek">ei)=mi</foreign>) is a true diphthong,
					and so is not generally spelled with simple E
					except in the Corinthian alphabet. Although
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.196"/>
					
					Roscher cites a few examples from inscriptions in
					other dialects where the true diphthongal EI seems
					to be represented by simple E, his evidence is not
					convincing.
				</p>
            <p>
					O. Lagercrantz, in <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxxvi. (1901) pp. 411 if.,
					interprets the E as meaning <foreign lang="greek">h)=</foreign> 
               <q direct="unspecified">he said.</q> To this, of
					course, Roscher objects and suggests that Lagercrantz
					might have thought also of <foreign lang="greek">h)=</foreign> 
               <q direct="unspecified">verily.</q> Thus all the
					various possibilities of interpretation have in turn
					been suggested, and rejected by others.
				</p>
            <p>
					W. N. Bates, in the <hi rend="italics">American Journal of Archaeology</hi>,
					xxix. (1925) pp. 239-246, tries to show that the E
					had its origin in a Minoan character E associated
					with <foreign>(\e</foreign> (as is shown by the evidence of a Cretan gem
					in the Metropolitan Museum of New York) and later
					transferred to Delphi. Since the character was not
					understood, it, like other things at Delphi, came to
					be associated with Apollo. This character has been
					found on the old omphalos discovered in 1913 at
					Delphi in the temple of Apollo.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It might also be recorded that J. E. Harrison, in <hi rend="italics">Comptes Rendus du Congres International d'Archeologie</hi> (Athens, 1905), thinks that the E was <q direct="unspecified">originally three betyl stones or pillars placed on a basis and representing the three Charites</q>! Moreover, C. Fries, in <hi rend="italics">Rheinisches Museum f&uuml;r Philologie</hi>, lxxix. (1930) 343-344, offers as <q direct="unspecified">nodi explicatio</q> the fact that in Sumerian inscriptions E means house or temple, and so may be connected with Babylonian ritual (note the Chaldean in chap. iv.)!</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Interesting are the two coins reproduced in Imhoof-Blumer and P. Gardner, <hi rend="italics">A Numismatic Commentary on
					Pausanias</hi>, plate x. nos. xxii. and xxiii. (text, p. 119),
					which show the E suspended between the middle
					columns of the temple. Learned scholars should
					note that the letter represented is E, not EI : therefore
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.197"/>
					
					such explanations as are based on the true
					diphthong are presumably wrong.
				</p>
            <p>
					The title of the essay is included in the catalogue of
					Lamprias, where it appears as No. 117. It is not
					infrequently quoted or referred to by later writers.
					It has been separately edited by Bernardakis in the
					volume of essays in honour of Ernst Curtius, Leipzig,
					1894. Of interest is also <hi rend="italics">The Delphic Maxims in
					Literature</hi>, by Eliza Gregory Wilkins, Chicago, 1929.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.5.p.199"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="0">
            <p>
					(The persons who take part in the conversation are:
					Ammonius, Lamprias, Plutarch, Theon, Eustrophus, Nicander, and others whose names are not given.)
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Not long ago, my dear Sarapion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A poet living at Athens in Plutarch's day; see <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 396 d ff. and 628 a.</note> I carne upon
					some lines, not badly done, which Dicaearchus thinks
					Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, no. 969.</note> addressed to Archela&uuml;s :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>I will not give poor gifts to one so rich,
					</l>
                  <l>Lest you should take me for a fool, or I
					</l>
                  <l>Should seem by giving to invite a gift.</l>
               </quote>
					For he does no favour who gives small gifts from
					scanty means to wealthy men; and since it is not
					credible that his giving is for nothing, he acquires
					in addition a reputation for disingenuousness and
					servility. Observe also how, as far as independence
					and honour are concerned, material gifts fall far
					below those bestowed by literary discourse and
					wisdom ; and these gifts it is both honourable to
					give and, at the same time, to ask a return of like
					gifts from the recipients. I, at any rate, as I send
					to you, and by means of you for our friends there,
					some of our Pythian discourses, an offering of our
					first-fruits, as it were, confess that I am expecting
					other discourses, both more numerous and of better
					quality, from you and your friends, inasmuch as
					you have not only all the advantages of a great
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.201"/>
					
					city,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At this time Athens had been for several centuries a university city.</note> but you have also more abundant leisure amid
					many books and all manner of discussions.
				</p>
            <p>
					It seems that our beloved Apollo finds a remedy
					and a solution for the problems connected with our
					life by the oracular responses which he gives to those
					who consult him ; but the problems connected with
					our power to reason it seems that he himself launches
					and propounds to him who is by nature inclined to the
					love of knowledge, thus creating in the soul a craving<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 673 b.</note>
					that leads onward to the truth, as is clear in many other
					ways, but particularly in the dedication of the E.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 426 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					For the likelihood is that it was not by chance nor, as
					it were, by lot that this was the only letter that carne
					to occupy first place with the god and attained the
					rank of a sacred offering and something worth seeing;
					but it is likely that those who, in the beginning, sought
					after knowledge of the god either discovered some
					peculiar and unusual potency in it or else used it as a
					token with reference to some other of the matters of
					the highest concern, and thus adopted it.
				</p>
            <p>
					On many other occasions when the subject had
					been brought up in the school I had quietly turned
					aside from it and passed it over, but recently I was
					unexpectedly discovered by my sons in an animated
					discussion with some strangers, whom, since they
					purposed to leave Delphi immediately, it was not
					seemly to try to divert from the subject, nor was it
					seemly for me to ask to be excused from the discussion, for they were altogether eager to hear something about it. I found them seats, therefore, near
					the temple, and I began to seek some answer myself
					and to put questions to them ; influenced as I was by
					the place and the conversation itself, I remembered
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.203"/>
					
					what, when Nero was here some years ago, I had
					heard Ammonius and others discussing, when the
					same question obtruded itself in a similar way.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>That the god is no less a philosopher than a
					prophet Ammonius seemed to all to postulate and prove
					correctly, with reference to this or to that one of his
					several titles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 393 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Cornutus, chap. xxxii.; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, i. 543 (p. 123); and <q direct="unspecified">Apollo</q> in the Index thereto.</note>; that he is the <q direct="unspecified">Pythian</q> (<hi rend="italics">Inquirer</hi>)
					for those that are beginning to learn and inquire ;
					the <q direct="unspecified">Delian</q> (<hi rend="italics">Clear</hi>) and the &lsquo;Phanaean&rsquo; (<hi rend="italics">Disclosing</hi>) for those to whom some part of the truth is
					becoming clear and is being disclosed; the &lsquo;Ismenian&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch's attempt to connect Ismenian with <foreign lang="greek">i)d</foreign>- (<foreign lang="greek">oi(=da</foreign>) can hardly be right.</note>
					(<hi rend="italics">Knowing</hi>) for those who have knowledge ; and the
					<q direct="unspecified">Leschenorian</q> (<hi rend="italics">Conversationalist</hi>) when people have
					active enjoyment of conversation and philosophic
					intercourse with one another. <q direct="unspecified">Since,</q> he wrent on
					to say, <q direct="unspecified">inquiry is the beginning of philosophy, and
						wonder and uncertainty the beginning of inquiry,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Theaetetus</hi>, 155 d.</note> it
						seems only natural that the greater part of what
						concerns the god should be concealed in riddles, and
						should call for some account of the wherefore and an
						explanation of its cause. For example, in the case of
						the undying fire, that pine is the only wood burned
						here, while laurel is used for offering incense ; that
						two Fates have statues here,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, x. 24. 4.</note> whereas three is everywhere the customary number; that no woman<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Ion</hi>, 222.</note>
						is allowed to approach the prophetic shrine ; the
						matter of the tripod ; and the other questions of
						this nature, when they are suggested to persons who
						are not altogether without mind and reason, act as a
						Iure and an invitation to investigate, to read, and to
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.205"/>
						
						talk about them. Note also these inscriptions<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 164 b, 408 e, 511 a.</note> here,
						&lsquo;Know thyself&rsquo; and &lsquo;Avoid extremes,&rsquo; how many
						philosophic inquiries have they set on foot, and what
						a horde of discourses has sprung up from each, as
						from a seed ! And no less productive of discourse
						than any one of them, as I think, is the present subject
						of inquiry.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>When Ammonius had said this, Lamprias, my
					brother, said, <q direct="unspecified">As a matter of fact, the account that
						we have heard is simple and quite brief. For they
						say that those wise men who by some are called
						the &lsquo;Sophists&rsquo; were actually five in number : Chilon,
						Thales, Solon, Bias, and Pittacus. But when Cleobulus, the despot of the Lindians, and later Periander
						of Corinth, who had no part or portion in virtue or
						wisdom, but forcibly acquired their repute through
						power and friends and favours, invaded this name of
						the Wise Men, and sent out and circulated throughout
						Greece certain sentiments and sayings very similar
						to those famous utterances of the Wise Men, these,
						naturally, did not like this at all, but were loath to
						expose the imposture or to arouse open hatred over
						a question of repute, or to carry through a contest
						against such powerful men ; they met here by themselves and, after conferring together, dedicated that
						one of the letters which is fifth in alphabetical order
						and which stands for the number five, thus testifying
						for themselves before the god that they were five,
						and renouncing and rejecting the seventh and the
						sixth as having no connexion with themselves. That
						this account is not beside the mark anyone may
						realize who has heard those connected with the shrine
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.207"/>
						
						naming the golden E the E of Livia, Caesar's wife,
						and the bronze E the E of the Athenians, while the
						first and oldest one, made of wood, they still call to
						this day the E of the Wise Men, as though it were an
						offering, not of one man, but of all the Wise Men in
						common.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Ammonius smiled quietly, suspecting privately
					that Lamprias had been indulging in a mere opinion
					of his own and was fabricating history and tradition
					regarding a matter in which he could not be held
					to account. Someone else among those present said
					that all this was similar to the nonsense which the
					Chaldean visitor had uttered a short time before :
					that there are seven vowels in the alphabet and seven
					stars that have an independent and unconstrained
					motion ; that E is the second in order of the vowels
					from the beginning, and the sun the second planet after
					the moon, and that practically all the Greeks identify
					Apollo with the Sun.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1130 a or 381 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, or 393 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">But all this,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">has
						its source in slate and prate<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An expression as obscure in the Greek as in the English. It means, apparently, <q direct="unspecified">idle talk.</q> 
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> S. A. Naber, <hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi>, xxviii. (1900) p. 134.</note> and in nothing else.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Apparently Lamprias had unwittingly stirred up
					the persons connected with the temple against his
					remarks. For what he had said no one of the Delphians knew anything about; but they were used to
					bring forward the commonly accepted opinion which
					the guides give, holding it to be right that neither the
					appearance nor the sound of the letter has any cryptic
					meaning, but only its name. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">For it is, as the
					Delphians assume,</q> - and on this occasion Nicander,
					the priest, spoke for them and said, <q direct="unspecified">the figure and
						form of the consultation of the god, and it holds the
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.209"/>
						
						first place in every question of those who consult the
						oracle and inquire if they shall be victorious, if they
						shall marry, if it is to their advantage to sail the sea,
						if to take to farming, if to go abroad.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the long list of questions thus introduced in Hunt and Edgar, <hi rend="italics">Select Papyri</hi> (in the L.C.L.), i. pp. 436-438 (nos. 193-195).</note> But the god in
						his wisdom bade a long farewell to the logicians who
						think that nothing real comes out of the particle &lsquo;if&rsquo;
						combined with what the consultant thinks proper to
						undertake, for the god conceives of all the inquiries
						subjoined to this as real things and welcomes them as
						such. And since to inquire from him as from a prophet is our individual prerogative, but to pray to him
						as to a god is common to all, they think that the
						particle contains an optative force no less than an
						interrogative. &lsquo;If only I could,&rsquo; is the regular
						expression of a wish, and Archilochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 402, Archilochus, no. 71; or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi> (L.C.L.), ii. p. 134.</note> says,
						<quote rend="blockquote">If to me it might be granted Neobul&ecirc;'s hand to touch.</quote>
						And in using &lsquo;if only&rsquo; they assert that the second
						word is added unnecessarily, like Sophron's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kaibel, <hi rend="italics">Comic. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 160, Sophron, no. 36.</note>
						&lsquo;surely&rsquo;:
						<quote rend="blockquote">Surely in want of children as well.</quote>
						This is found also in Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvii. 29.</note>
						            <quote rend="blockquote">Since I surely shall break your might</quote>
						but, as they assert, the optative force is adequately
						indicated by the &lsquo;if.&rsquo;</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>When Nicander had expounded all this, my
					friend Theon, whom I presume you know, asked
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.211"/>
					
					Ammonius if Logical Reason had any rights in free
					speech, after being spoken of in such a very insulting
					manner. And when Ammonius urged him to speak
					and come to her assistance, he said, &ldquo;That the god
					is a most logical reasoner the great majority of his
					oracles show clearly ; for surely it is the function of
					the same person both to solve and to invent ambiguities. Moreover, as Plato said, when an oracle was
					given that they should double the size of the altar at
					Delos<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 579 b-d; and on the doubling of the cube, T. L. Heath, <hi rend="italics">A Manual of Greek Mathematics</hi> (Oxford, 1931), pp. 154-170.</note> (a task requiring the highest skill in geometry), it was not this that the god was enjoining,
					but he was urging the Greeks to study geometry.
					And so, in the same way, when the god gives out
					ambiguous oracles, he is promoting and organizing
					logical reasoning as indispensable for those who are
					to apprehend his meaning aright. Certainly in logic
					this copulative conjunction has the greatest force,
					inasmuch as it clearly gives us our most logical form,
					the syllogism. Must not the character of the hypothetical syllogism be of this sort: granted that even
					wild animals have apperception of the existence of
					things, yet to man alone has Nature given the power
					to observe and judge the consequences ? That &lsquo;it is
					day&rsquo; and that &lsquo;it is light&rsquo; assuredly wolves and dogs
					and birds perceive by their senses ; but &lsquo;if it is day,
					then it is light,&rsquo; no creature other than man apprehends,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 216 (p. 70) and 239 (p. 78).</note> for he alone has a concept of antecedent and
					consequent, of apparent implication and connexion of
					these things one with another, and their relations and
					differences, from which our demonstrations derive
					their most authoritative inception. Since, then, philosophy is concerned with truth, and the illumination
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.213"/>
					
					of truth is demonstration, and the inception of
					demonstration is the hypothetical syllogism, then with
					good reason the potent element that effects the connexion and produces this was consecrated by wise
					men to the god who is, above all, a lover of the truth.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;The god, moreover, is a prophet, and the prophetic
					art concerns the future that is to result from things
					present and past. For there is nothing of which
					either the origin is without cause or the foreknowledge thereof without reason ; but since all present
					events follow in close conjunction with past events,
					and all future events follow in close conjunction with
					present events, in accordance with a regular procedure which brings them to fulfilment from beginning to end, he who understands, in consonance
					with Nature, how to fathom the connexions and
					interrelations of the causes one with another knows
					and can declare
					<quote rend="blockquote">What now is, and in future shall be, and has been of aforetime.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 70.</note>
               </quote>
					Very excellently did Homer place first in order the
					present, then the future and the past, for the syllogism
					based on hypothesis has its source in what is ; for
					example, &lsquo;if this is, then that has preceded,&rsquo; and
					again, &lsquo;if this is, then that shall be.&rsquo; The technical
					and rational element here, as has been stated, is the
					knowledge of consequences ; but the senses provide
					the argument with its premise. Therefore, even if
					it be a poor thing to say, I shall not be turned aside
					from saying it, that this is the tripod of truth, namely,
					argument, which lays down the consequent relation
					of the conclusion to the antecedent, and then, premising the existent condition, induces the completion
					of the demonstration. Therefore, if the Pythian god
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.215"/>
					
					plainly finds pleasure in music and the songs of swans
					and the sound of lyres, what wonder is it that, because
					of his fondness for logical reasoning, he should welcome and love that portion of discourse of which he
					observes philosophers making the most particular and
					the most constant use ?
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Heracles, before he had released Prometheus or
						had conversed with the sophists that were associated
						with Cheiron and Atlas, when he was young and a
						thorough Boeotian,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greek equivalent of <q direct="unspecified">Philistine.</q>
                  </note> would do away with logical
						reasoning ;. he ridiculed the &lsquo;if the first, then the
						second,&rsquo; and resolved to carry off the tripod by force<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 413 a, 557 c, 560 d; Pausanias, x. 13. 4; Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi>, ii. 6. 2 (with Frazer's note in L.C.L. edition); Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Lexikon der gr. und r&ouml;m. Mythologie</hi>, i. p. 2213; Baumeister, <hi rend="italics">Denkm&auml;ler des klassischen Altertums</hi>, i. p. 463 ff. The attempt of Heracles to carry off the tripod is represented on the treasury of the Siphnians in the Museum at Delphi.</note>
						and fight it out with the god over his art; since, at
						any rate, as he advanced in years, he also appears to
						have become most skilled in prophecy and in logic.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>When Theon ceased, Eustrophus the Athenian,
					I think it was, said to us in answer, <q direct="unspecified">Do you see
						how zealously Theon defends logic, all but arraying
						himself in the lion's skin ? Under such conditions,
						we who repose in the Theory of Numbers all affairs
						together, natures and principles of things divine and
						human alike, and make this theory far above all else
						our guide and authority in all that is beautiful and
						valuable, should not be likely to hold our peace, but
						to offer to the god the first-fruits of our beloved
						mathematics, believing, as we do, that, taken by
						itself, E is not unlike the other letters either in power
						or in form or as a spoken word, but that it has come
						to be held in honour as the symbol of a great and
						sovereign number, the <hi rend="italics">pempad</hi>, from which the wise
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.217"/>
						
						gave the name &lsquo;<hi rend="italics">pempazein</hi>&rsquo; to counting which is
						done by fives.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, by counting on the fingers: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 374 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 429 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					These words Eustrophus addressed to us not in jest,
					but for the reason that at this time I was devoting
					myself to mathematics with the greatest enthusiasm,
					although I was destined soon to pay all honour to the
					maxim &lsquo;Avoid extremes,&rsquo; when I had once become a
					member of the Academy.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 431 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>I said, therefore, that Eustrophus solved the
					difficulty most excellently with his number. <q direct="unspecified">For
						since,</q> I continued, &ldquo;every number may be classified
					as even or odd, and unity, by virtue of its potentiality,
					is common to both, for the reason that its addition
					makes the odd number even and the even number
					odd,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 429 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and since twTo makes the first of the even numbers and three the first of the odd, and five is produced
					by the union of these numbers, very naturally five has
					come to be honoured as being the first number created
					out of the first numbers ; and it has received the
					name of &lsquo;marriage&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 263 f, 1012 e, 1018 c, and Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, v. chap. xiv. 93. 4 (p. 702 Potter).</note> because of the resemblance of
					the even number to the female and of the odd number
					to the male.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 288 c-e.</note> For in the division of numbers into two
					equal factors, the even number separates completely
					and leaves a certain receptive opening and, as it were,
					a space within itself; but in the odd, when it undergoes this process, there is always left over from the
					division a generative middle part. Wherefore it is
					more generative than the other, and in combination
					it is always dominant and is never dominated.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life and Poetry of Homer</hi>, 145 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 416).</note> For
					in no combination of these two numbers (even and
					odd) is there produced from the two an even number,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.219"/>
					
					but in all combinations an odd. Moreover, each when
					applied to itself and made composite with itself
					shows the difference. For no even number united
					with even gives an odd number, nor does it ever show
					any departure from its own distinctive nature, being
					impotent through its weakness to produce the other
					number, and having no power of accomplishment;
					but odd numbers combined with odd produce a
					numerous progeny of even numbers because of their
					omnipresent generative function. It would not be
					timely at this moment to enumerate the other
					potent properties and divergences of numbers ; let
					it suffice to say that the Pythagoreans called Five
					a &lsquo;Marriage&rsquo; on the ground that it was produced by
					the association of the first male number and the first
					female number.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;There is also a sense in which it has been called
					&lsquo;Nature,&rsquo; since by being multiplied into itself it ends
					in itself again. For even as Nature receives wheat in
					the form of seed and puts it to its use, and creates in
					the interim many shapes and forms through which
					she carries out the process of growth to its end, but,
					to crown all, displays wheat again, and thus presents
					as her result the beginning at the end of the whole,
					so in like manner, while the other numbers when
					raised to a power end in different numbers as the
					result of the increase, only the numbers five and six,
					when multiplied by themselves, repeat themselves
					and preserve their identity. Thus six times six is
					thirty-six, and five times five is twenty-five ; and
					furthermore, the number six does this but once, and
					the single instance is when it is squared ; but with
					five this result is obtained in raising it to any power,
					and it has a unique characteristic, when added to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.221"/>
					
					itself, of producing either itself or ten alternately<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, a number ending in 5 or 0. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 429 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					as the addition progresses, and of doing this to infinity,
					since this number takes its pattern from the primal
					principle which orders the whole. For as that principle by changes creates a complete universe out of
					itself, and then in turn out of the universe creates
					itself again, as Heracleitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 95, Heracleitus, no. b 90.</note> says, &lsquo;and exchanges
					fire for all and all for fire, as gold for goods and goods
					for gold,&rsquo; so, in like manner, the conjunction of five
					with itself is determined by Nature's law to produce
					nothing incomplete or foreign, but it has strictly
					limited changes ; it produces either itself or ten, that
					is to say, either its own characteristic or the perfect
					whole.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>&ldquo;If, then, anyone ask, &lsquo;What has this to do with
					Apollo ?&rsquo;, we shall say that it concerns not only him,
					but also Dionysus, whose share in Delphi is no less
					than that of Apollo.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 365 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and Lucan, v. 73-74; and for the proverb <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 280 d and the note.</note> Now we hear the theologians
					affirming and reciting, sometimes in verse and sometimes in prose, that the god is deathless and eternal
					in his nature,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, v. 14 (p. 711 Potter).</note> but, owing forsooth to some predestined
					design and reason, he undergoes transformations of
					his person, and at one time enkindles his nature
					into fire and makes it altogether like all else, and
					at another time he undergoes all sorts of changes
					in his form, his emotions and his powers, even as the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.223"/>
					
					universe does to-day ; but he is called by the best
					known of his names.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Eclogae Phys. et Ethic.</hi> i. 21. 5 (i. p. 184. 11 ed. Wachsmuth).</note> The more enlightened, however, concealing from the masses the transformation
					into fire, call him Apollo because of his solitary state,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 354 b, 381 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 393 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					and Phoebus because of his purity and stainlessness.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 393 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					And as for his turning into winds and water, earth
					and stars, and into the generations of plants and
					animals, and his adoption of such guises, they speak
					in a deceptive way of what he undergoes in his
					transformation as a tearing apart, as it were, and
					a dismemberment. They give him the names of
					Dionysus, Zagreus, Nyctelius, and Isodaetes ; they
					construct destructions and disappearances, followed
					by returns to life and regenerations — riddles and
					fabulous tales quite in keeping with the aforesaid
					transformations. To this god they also sing the
					dithyrambic strains laden with emotion and with a
					transformation that includes a certain wandering and
					dispersion. Aeschylus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Aeschylus, no. 355.</note> in fact, says
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Fitting it is that the dithyramb
					</l>
                  <l>With its fitful notes should attend
					</l>
                  <l>Dionysus in revel rout.</l>
               </quote>
					But to Apollo they sing the paean, music regulated
					and chaste.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;Apollo the artists represent in paintings and sculpture as ever ageless and young, but Dionysus they
					depict in many guises and forms ; and they attribute
					to Apollo in general a uniformity, orderliness, and
					unadulterated seriousness, but to Dionysus a certain
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.225"/>
					
					variability combined with playfulness, wantonness,
					seriousness, and frenzy. They call upon him<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 730, Adespota, no. 131; quoted by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 607 c and 671 c also.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Euoe Bacchus who incites
					</l>
                  <l>Womankind, Dionysus who delights
					</l>
                  <l>'Mid his honours fraught with frenzy,</l>
               </quote>
					not inappositely apprehending the peculiar character
					of each transformation.
					&ldquo;But since the time of the cycles in these transformations is not equal, but that of the one which they
					call &lsquo;Satiety,&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 616 (p. 186); Philo, <hi rend="italics">De Spec. Leg.</hi> i. 208.</note> is longer, and that of &lsquo;Dearth&rsquo; shorter,
					they observe the ratio, and use the paean at their
					sacrifices for a large part of the year ; but at the
					beginning of winter they awake the dithyramb and,
					laying to rest the paean, they use the dithyramb
					instead of it in their invocations of the god ; for they
					believe that, as three is to one, so is the relation of the
					creation to the conflagration.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>&ldquo;But these remarks have been extended somewhat beyond what the occasion requires. However,
					it is clear that men make Five an attribute of the god,
					which at one time of itself creates itself, like fire, and
					at another time out of itself creates ten, like the
					universe. And in music, which is especially pleasing
					to him, do we imagine that this number plays no
					part ? For the main application of harmony, so far as
					it can be put into words, is concerned with chords.
					That these are five, and no more, reason convinces
					anyone who wishes, by perception alone without
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.227"/>
					
					employing reason, to pursue these matters on the
					strings and stops<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 530 d - 531 c.</note>; for they all have their origin in
					numerical ratios. The ratio of the fourth is four to
					three,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1018 e.</note> that of the fifth is three to two, and that
					of the octave two to one ; that of the octave plus the
					fifth is three to one,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 429 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and that of the double octave
					four to one. The extra chord which the writers on
					harmony introduce, naming it the octave and the
					fourth <hi rend="italics">extra metrum</hi>, does not deserve acceptance,
					since we should be favouring the unreasoning element
					in our sense of hearing contrary to reason, which is as
					much as to say, contrary to law. Now if I may omit
					any discussion of the five stops of the tetrachord,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 430 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1021 e and 1029 a.</note>
					and the first five &lsquo;tones&rsquo; or &lsquo;tropes&rsquo; or &lsquo;harmonies,&rsquo;
					whatever be their right name, from the changes in
					which, through a greater or a less tension, the remaining lower and higher notes are derived, I must
					ask whether, although the intervals are numerous, or
					rather of infinite number, yet the elements of melody
					are not five only,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 430 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> quarter tone, half tone, tone, a tone
					plus a half tone, and double tone ; and there is, in the
					range of notes, no additional space, either smaller or
					greater within the limits set by the high and the low,
					which can yield melody.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">There are many other examples of this sort
					of thing,</q> said I, &ldquo;which I shall pass over. I shall
					merely adduce Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 31 a.</note> who, in speaking about a single
					world, says that if there are others besides ours, and
					ours is not the only one, then there are five altogether
					and no more.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 421 f, 422 f, 430 b, and 887 b.</note> Nevertheless, even if this world of ours
					is the only one ever created, as Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">De Caelo</hi>, i. 8-9 (276 a 18).</note> also thinks,
					even ours, he says, is in a way put together through
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.229"/>
					
					the union of five worlds, of which one is of earth,
					another of water, a third of fire, a fourth of air ; and
					the fifth, the heavens, others call light, and others
					aether, and others call this very thing a fifth substance
					(Quintessence), which alone of the bodies has by
					nature a circular motion that is not the result of any
					compelling powrer or any other incidental cause.
					Wherefore also Plato, apparently noting the five
					most beautiful and complete forms among those found
					in Nature, pyramid, cube, octahedron, icosahedron,
					and dodecahedron, appropriately assigned each to
					each.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">There are some who associate the senses also,
					since they are of the same number, with those primal
					elements, observing that touch functions against
					something resistant, and is earthly, and that taste,
					through moisture in the things tasted, absorbs their
					qualities. Air, when it is struck, becomes voice or
					sound in the hearing of it. Of the two remaining
					senses, odour, which the sense of smell has received
					as its portion, since it is an exhalation and is engendered by heat, bears a resemblance to fire ; and
					in sight, which flashes to its goal owing to its kinship
					with aether and light, there occurs a combination and
					coalescence of the two, which behaves as they do. The
					living being possesses no other sense, nor has the
					world any other nature single and uncombined ; but
					a marvellous distribution and apportionment each to
					each has, as it seems, been made of the five to the
					five.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Therewith I checked myself and, after waiting
					a moment, said, &ldquo;What ails us, Eustrophus, that we
					all but passed over Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xv. 187.</note> as if he were not the first
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.231"/>
					
					to divide the world into five parts ? For he duly
					assigned the three in the middle to the three gods,
					and the two extremes, the heaven and the earth, of
					which the one is the boundary of things below and
					the other of things above, he left to all in common,
					undistributed.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;&lsquo;But the discussion must be carried further back,&rsquo;
					as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, no. 970; repeated in 431 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> remarks. For those who exalt Four
					teach us a lesson that is not without value, that by
					reason of this number all solids have come into being.
					For since every such solid body exists through the
					acquisition of depth by length and breadth, and for
					length must be presupposed a single point assigned
					to unity, and length without breadth, which is called
					a line, is also duality, and the movement of the line
					breadthwise generates a plane in the third instance,
					and when depth is added, through the four factors the
					increase progresses to a solid — it is clear to everyone
					that four, when it has carried Nature forward to the
					point of completing a solid body and producing a
					volume that may be felt and that is resistant, has
					then left Nature lacking in the most important thing
					of all. For the inanimate thing is, to put it simply,
					orphaned, incomplete, and good for nothing, unless
					there be an animating soul to make use of it. The
					impulse or dispensation that creates the soul therein,
					a transformation brought about through five factors
					in all, gives to Nature its due completeness, and is
					as much more potent than four as the living being
					differs in worth from the inanimate thing.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;Moreover, the symmetry and power of five,
					rather than that of any other number, has prevailed
					and has not permitted the animate to progress to
					unlimited classes of beings, but has produced five forms
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.233"/>
					
					of all living things. For there are, as we know, gods,
					demigods, and heroes, and after these the fourth
					class, man<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 415 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; and fifth and last the class of unreasoning animals.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;If you should, moreover, make divisions of the soul
					itself to accord with Nature, the first and least clear
					part of it is the nutritive, second the perceptive, then
					the appetitive, and, next after this, the spirited ; but
					when it had reached the power to reason, and had
					completed its nature, it came to rest there at the
					fifth element as at the highest point.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 429 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>&ldquo;Of this number, which has so many and such
					great powers, the origin also is fair and lovely ; not
					that which we have expounded, that it is composed
					of two and three, but that which the beginning
					combined with the first square produces. For the
					beginning of all number is one, and the first square
					is four<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 429 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; and from these, as though from perfected
					form and matter, comes five. And if certain authorities are right, who, as we know, posit one as the first
					square, since it is a power of itself and its product is
					itself, then five, the offspring of the first two squares,
					does not lack a surpassing nobility of lineage.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> said I, <q direct="unspecified">the most important matter I
					fear may embarrass our Plato when it is stated, just
					as he said that Anaxagoras was embarrassed by the
					name of the Moon, since he tried to claim as his own
					some very ancient opinion in regard to its illumination. Has not Plato said this in the <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi> ?</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 409 a.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Certainly,</q> said Eustrophus, <q direct="unspecified">but what similarity
						there is I do not see.</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.235"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;Well, you know, of course, that in the <hi rend="italics">Sophist</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Sophist</hi>, 256 c.</note>
					he demonstrates that the supreme first principles are
					five : Being, Identity, Divergence, and fourth and
					fifth besides these, Motion and Rest.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 428 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> But in the
					<hi rend="italics">Philebus</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Philebus</hi>, 23 c.</note> he employs another method of division
					and affirms that the Infinite is one and the Definite
					a second, and from the combination of these all
					generation arises. The cause which makes them
					combine he posits as a fourth class ; the fifth he has
					left for us to surmise, by which the things combined
					attain once more dissociation and disengagement.
					I infer that these are intended to be figurative expressions corresponding to those just mentioned,
					generation corresponding to being, the infinite to
					motion, the definite to rest, the combining principle
					to identity, and the dissociating principle to divergence. But if these last are not the same as the
					others, even so, considered either in that way or in
					this, his division into five different classes would still
					hold good.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;Evidently someone anticipated Plato in comprehending this before he did, and for that reason
					dedicated to the god an E as a demonstration and
					symbol of the number of all the elements.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;Furthermore, observing that the Good displays
					itself under five categories,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. ibid.</hi> 66 a-c.</note> of which the first is
					moderation, the second due proportion, the third the
					mind, the fourth the sciences and arts and the true
					opinions that have to do with the soul, and the fifth
					any pleasure that is pure and unalloyed with pain, at
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.237"/>
					
					this point he leaves off, thus suggesting the Orphic
					verse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Orphic Fragments, no. 14.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Bring to an end the current of song in the sixth generation.</quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Following upon all this that has been said to
					you,</q> I continued, <q direct="unspecified">&lsquo;I shall sing one short verse&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> no. 334; quoted again by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 636 d.</note>
						for Nicander and his friends, &lsquo;men of sagacity.&rsquo; On
						the sixth day of the new month, namely, when the
						prophetic priestess is conducted down to the Prytaneum, the first of your three sortitions is for five, she
						casting three and you casting two, each with reference
						to the other.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greek text is at this point somewhat uncertain.</note> Is not this actually so ?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> said Nicander, <q direct="unspecified">but the reason must not
						be told to others.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said I, smiling, <q direct="unspecified">until such time as we
						become holy men, and God grants us to know the
						truth, this also shall be added to what may be said on
						behalf of the Five.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Thus, as I remember, the tale of arithmetical and
					of mathematical laudations of E came to an end.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Ammonius, inasmuch as he plainly held that in
					mathematics was contained not the least important
					part of philosophy, was pleased with these remarks,
					and said, &ldquo;It is not worth while to argue too precisely
					over these matters with the young, except to say that
					every one of the numbers will provide not a little for
					them that wish to sing its praises. What need to
					speak of the others ? Why, the sacred Seven of
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.239"/>
					
					Apollo will consume the whole day before the
					narration of all its powers is finished. Then again, we
					shall be branding the wise men as &lsquo;warring with&rsquo;
					common custom, as well as with &lsquo;the long years of
					time,&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> i. p. 522, Simonides, no. 193, and Edmonds in <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, ii. p. 340, in L.C.L.; Plutarch refers to this also in 359 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Theseus</hi>, chap. x. (p. 4 f).</note> if they are to oust Seven from its place of
					honour and make Five sacred to the god, on the ground
					that it is in some way more closely related to him. I
					am therefore of the opinion that the significance of
					the letter is neither a numeral nor a place in a series
					nor a conjunction nor any of the subordinate parts of
					speech. No, it is an address and salutation to the god,
					complete in itself, which, by being spoken, brings him
					who utters it to thoughts of the god's power. For the
					god addresses each one of us as we approach him here
					with the words &lsquo;Know Thyself,&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Charmides</hi>, 164 d-e.</note> as a form of welcome, which certainly is in no wise of less import
					than &lsquo;Hail&rsquo;; and we in turn reply to him &lsquo;Thou art,&rsquo;
					as rendering unto him a form of address which is
					truthful, free from deception, and the only one befitting him only, the assertion of Being.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>&ldquo;The fact is that we really have no part nor
					parcel in Being,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Philo, <hi rend="italics">De Iosepho</hi>, 125 (chap. xxii.).</note> but everything of a mortal nature is
					at some stage between coming into existence and
					passing away,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. 15, Anaximander, no. 9; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 95 e; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 594 (p. 183).</note> and presents only a dim and uncertain
					semblance and appearance of itself; and if you apply
					the whole force of your mind in your desire to
					apprehend it, it is like unto the violent grasping of
					water, which, by squeezing and compression, loses the
					handful enclosed, as it spurts through the fingers<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1082 a.</note>;
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.241"/>
					
					even so Reason, pursuing the exceedingly clear appearance of every one of those things that are susceptible
					to modification and change, is baffled by the one
					aspect of its coming into being, and by the other of
					its passing away ; and thus it is unable to apprehend
					a single thing that is abiding or really existent.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;&lsquo;It is impossible to step twice in the same river&rsquo;
					are the words of Heracleitus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 96, Heracleitus, no. 91. Plutarch refers to this dictum also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 559 c.</note> nor is it possible to lay
					hold twice of any mortal substance in a permanent
					state ; by the suddenness and swiftness of the change
					in it there &lsquo;comes dispersion and, at another time,
					a gathering together&rsquo;; or, rather, not at another time
					nor later, but at the same instant it both settles into
					its place and forsakes its place ; &lsquo;it is coming and
					going.&rsquo;
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;Wherefore that which is born of it never attains
					unto being because of the unceasing and unstaying
					process of generation, which, ever bringing change,
					produces from the seed an embryo, then a babe, then a
					child, and in due course a boy, a young man, a mature
					man, an elderly man, an old man, causing the first
					generations and ages to pass away by those which
					succeed them. But we have a ridiculous fear of one
					death, we who have already died so many deaths, and
					still are dying! For not only is it true, as Heracleitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 93, Heracleitus, no. 76.</note>
					used to say, that the death of heat is birth for steam,
					and the death of steam is birth for water, but the case
					is even more clearly to be seen in our own selves: the
					man in his prime passes away when the old man comes
					into existence, the young man passes away into the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.243"/>
					
					man in his prime, the child into the young man, and the
					babe into the child. Dead is the man of yesterday, for
					he is passed into the man of to-day ; and the man of
					to-day is dying as he passes into the man of to-morrow.
					Nobody remains one person, nor is one person; but
					we become many persons, even as matter is drawn
					about some one semblance and common mould<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 50 c.</note> with
					imperceptible movement. Else how is it that, if we
					remain the same persons, we take delight in some
					things now, whereas earlier we took delight in different
					things ; that we love or hate opposite things, and so
					too with our admirations and our disapprovals, and
					that we use other words and feel other emotions and
					have no longer the same personal appearance, the
					same external form, or the same purposes in mind ?
					For without change it is not reasonable that a person
					should have different experiences and emotions ; and
					if he changes, he is not the same person ; and if he is
					not the same person, he has no permanent being, but
					changes his very nature as one personality in him
					succeeds to another. Our senses, through ignorance
					of reality, falsely tell us that what appears to be is.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>&ldquo;What, then, really is Being? It is that which is
					eternal, without beginning and without end, to which
					no length of time brings change. For time is something that is in motion, appearing in connexion with
					moving matter, ever flowing, retaining nothing, a
					receptacle, as it were, of birth and decay, whose
					familiar &lsquo;afterwards&rsquo; and &lsquo;before,&rsquo; &lsquo;shall be&rsquo; and
					&lsquo;has been,&rsquo; when they are uttered, are of themselves
					a confession of Not Being. For to speak of that which
					has not yet occurred in terms of Being, or to say of
					what has already ceased to be, that it is, is silly and
					absurd. And as for that on which we most rely to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.245"/>
					
					support our conception of time, as we utter the words,
					&lsquo;it is here,&rsquo; &lsquo;it is at hand,&rsquo; and &lsquo;now&rsquo; — all this again
					reason, entering in, demolishes utterly. For &lsquo;now&rsquo; is
					crowded out into the future and the past, when we
					would look upon it as a culmination ; for of necessity it
					suffers division. And if Nature, when it is measured,
					is subject to the same processes as is the agent that
					measures it, then there is nothing in Nature that has
					permanence or even existence, but all things are in the
					process of creation or destruction according to their
					relative distribution with respect to time. Wherefore
					it is irreverent in the case of that which is to say even
					that it was or shall be; for these are certain deviations, transitions, and alterations, belonging to that
					which by its nature has no permanence in Being.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>&ldquo;But God is (if there be need to say so), and He
					exists for no fixed time, but for the everlasting ages
					which are immovable, timeless, and undeviating, in
					which there is no earlier nor later, no future nor past,
					no older nor younger; but He, being One, has with
					only one &lsquo;Now&rsquo; completely filled &lsquo;For ever&rsquo;; and only
					when Being is after His pattern is it in reality Being,
					not having been nor about to be, nor has it had a
					beginning nor is it destined to come to an end.
					Under these conditions, therefore, we ought, as we
					pay Him reverence, to greet Him and to address
					Him with the words, &lsquo;Thou art&rsquo;; or even, I vow, as
					did some of the men of old, &lsquo;Thou art One.&rsquo;
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.247"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;In fact the Deity is not Many, like each of us
					who is compounded of hundreds of different factors
					which arise in the course of our experience, a heterogenous collection combined in a haphazard way. But
					Being must have Unity, even as Unity must have
					Being. Now divergence from Unity, because of its
					differing from Being, deviates into the creation of that
					which has no Being. Wherefore the first of the god's
					names is excellently adapted to him, and so are the
					second and third as well. He is Apollo, that is to say,
					denying the Many<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 354 b, 381 f, and 388 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and abjuring multiplicity ; he is
					Ieius, as being One and One alone<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ieius is doubtless derived from <foreign lang="greek">i)h/</foreign>, a cry used in invoking Apollo, but Plutarch would derive it from <foreign lang="greek">i)/a, i)/hs</foreign>, an epic word meaning <q direct="unspecified">one.</q>
               </note>; and Phoebus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 388 f and 421 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> as
					is well known, is a name that the men of old used to
					give to everything pure and undefiled ; even as the
					Thessalians, to this day, I believe, when their priests,
					on the prohibited days, are spending their time alone
					by themselves outside the temples, say that the priests
					&lsquo;are keeping Phoebus.&rsquo;
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo; Unity is simple and pure. For it is by the admixture of one thing with another that contamination
					arises, even as Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 141.</note> somewhere says that some
					ivory which is being dyed red is being &lsquo;contaminated,&rsquo;
					and dyers speak of colours that are mixed as being
					&lsquo;spoiled&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 436 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 270 f.</note>; and they call the mixing &lsquo;spoiling.&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 725 c.</note>
					Therefore it is characteristic of the imperishable and
					pure to be one and uncombined.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>&ldquo;Those who hold that Apollo and the sun are
					the same,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 1130 a, and 386 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> it is right and proper that Ave welcome and
					love for their goodness of heart in placing their concept of the god in that thing which they honour most
					of all the things that they know and yearn for. But,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.249"/>
					
					as though they were now having a sleepy vision of the
					god amid the loveliest of dreams, let us wake them
					and urge them to proceed to loftier heights and to
					contemplate the waking vision of him, and what he
					truly is, but to pay honour also to this imagery of him
					in the sun and to revere the creative power associated
					with it, in so far as it is possible by what is perceived
					through the senses to gain an image of what is conceived in the mind, and by that which is ever in
					motion an image of that which moves not, an image
					that in some way or other transmits some gleams
					reflecting and mirroring his kindliness and blessedness. And as for his vagaries and transformations
					when he sends forth fire that sweeps his own self
					along with it, as they say,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 389 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and again when he forces
					it down here and directs it upon the earth and sea and
					winds and living creatures, and, besides, the terrible
					things done both to living creatures and to growing
					vegetation — to such tales it is irreverent even to listen;
					else will the god be more futile than the Poet's
					fancied child<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xv. 362.</note> playing a game amid the sand that is
					heaped together and then scattered again by him, if
					the god indulges in this game with the universe
					constantly, fashioning the world that does not exist,
					and destroying it again when it has been created.
					For, on the contrary, so far as he is in some way
					present in the world, by this his presence does he bind
					together its substance and prevail over its corporeal
					weakness, which tends toward dissolution. And it
					seems to me right to address to the god the words
					&lsquo;Thou art,&rsquo; which are most opposed to this account,
					and testify against it, believing that never does any
					vagary or transformation take place near him, but
					that such acts and experiences are related to some
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.251"/>
					
					other god, or rather to some demigod, whose office
					is concerned with Nature in dissolution and generation ; and this is clear at once from the names which
					are, as it were, correspondingly antithetic. For the
					one is spoken of as Apollo (<hi rend="italics">not many</hi>), the other as
					Pluto (<hi rend="italics">abounding</hi>) ; the one Delian (<hi rend="italics">clear</hi>), the other
					A&iuml;doneus (<hi rend="italics">unseen</hi>) ; the one Phoebus (<hi rend="italics">bright</hi>), the
					other Scotios (<hi rend="italics">dark</hi>)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 385 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; with the one are associated
					the Muses and Memory, with the other Oblivion
					and Silence ; the one is Theorian (<hi rend="italics">observing</hi>) and
					Phanaean (<hi rend="italics">disclosing</hi>), and the other
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lord of the darkling Night and idling Sleep<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1130 a; Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 719, Adespota, no. 92; or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi> (in L.C.L.), iii. p. 452.</note>;</quote>
					and he is also
					<quote rend="blockquote">Of all the gods most hateful to mortals.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 159.</note>
               </quote>
					Whereas concerning the other Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Frag. 149 (ed. Christ), quoted also in 413 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1102 e.</note> has said not
					unpleasingly
					<quote rend="blockquote">And towards mortal men he hath been judged the most
					gentle.</quote>
					It was fitting therefore for Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Suppliants</hi>, 975.</note> to say,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Drink-offerings for the dead who are gone
					</l>
                  <l>And the strains that the god of the golden hair,
					</l>
                  <l>Apollo, will never accept as his own.</l>
               </quote>
					And even before him Stesichorus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 224, Stesichorus, no. 50; or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi> (in L.C.L.), ii. p. 58.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.253"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The harp and sport and song
					</l>
                  <l>Most doth Apollo love ;
					</l>
                  <l>Sorrows and groans are Hades' share.</l>
               </quote>
					And it is evident that Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Sophocles, no. 765.</note> assigns each of the
					instruments to each god in these words :
					<quote rend="blockquote">No harp, no lyre is welcome for laments.</quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;As a matter of fact it was only after a long lapse of
					time and only recently that the flute ventured to utter
					a sound &lsquo;over things of delight,&rsquo; but during all the early
					time it used to be fetched in for times of mourning,
					and it had the task of rendering service on these
					occasions, not a very honourable or cheerful one.
					Later it carne to be generally associated with everything. Especially did those who confounded the
					attributes of the gods with the attributes of demigods get themselves into confusion.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">But this much may be said : it appears that as a
						sort of antithesis to &lsquo;Thou art&rsquo; stands the admonition &lsquo;Know thyself,&rsquo; and then again it seems, in a
						manner, to be in accord therewith, for the one is an
						utterance addressed in awe and reverence to the god
						as existent through all eternity, the other is a reminder to mortal man of his own nature and the
						weaknesses that beset him.</q>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>