<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De tuenda sanitate praecepta</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.077">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.251"/>
         <head>Plutarch's rules for the preservation of health: a dialogue. Moschio, Zeuxippus.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>MOSCHIO. And you, Zeuxippus, diverted Glaucus the
				physician from entering into a philosophical discourse with
				you yesterday.</p>
            <p>ZEUXIPPUS. I did not hinder him in the least, friend
					Moschio, it was he that would not discourse in philosophy.
					But I feared and avoided giving so contentious a man any
					opportunity of discourse; for though in physic the man
					has (as Homer<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XL 514.</note> expresses it) an excellency before most of
					his profession, yet in philosophy he is not altogether so
					candid, but indeed so rude in all his disputations, that he
					is hardly to be borne with, flying (as it were) at us open
					mouthed. So that it is neither an easy nor indeed a just
					thing, that we should bear those confusions in terms he
					makes, when we are disputing about a wholesome diet.
					Besides, he maintains that the bounds of philosophy and
					medicine are as distinct as those of the Mysians and Phrygians. And taking hold of some of those things we were
					discoursing of, perhaps not with all exactness, yet not
					without some profit, he made scurrilous reflections on
					them.</p>
            <p>MOSCHIO. But I am ready, Zeuxippus, to hear those
					and the other things you shall discourse of, with a great
					deal of pleasure.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.252"/>
            <p>ZEUXIPPUS. You have naturally a philosophical genius,
					Moschio, and are troubled to see a philosopher have no
					kindness for the study of medicine. You are uneasy that
					he should think it concerns him more to study geometry,
					logic, and music, than to be desirous to understand
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>What in his house is well or ill-designed,</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Odyss. IV. 392.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					his house being his own body. You shall see manyspectators at that play where their charges are defrayed out of
					the public stock, as they do at Athens. Now among all
					the liberal arts, medicine not only contains so neat and
					large a field of pleasure as to give place to none, but she
					pays plentifully the charges of those who delight in the
					study of her by giving them health and safety; so that it
					ought not to be called transgressing the bounds of a philosopher to dispute about those things which relate to health,
					but rather, all bounds being laid aside, we ought to pursue
					our studies in the same common field, and so enjoy both
					the pleasure and the profit of them.</p>
            <p>MOSCHIO. But to pass by Glaucus, who with his pretended gravity would be thought to be so perfect as not to
					stand in need of philosophy,&mdash;do you, if you please, run
					through the whole discourse, and first, those things which
					you say were not so exactly handled and which Glaucus
					carped at.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>ZEUXIPPUS. A friend of ours then heard one alleging
				that to keep one's hands always warm and never suffer
				them to be cold did not a little conduce to health; and, on
				the contrary, keeping the extreme parts of the body cold
				drives the heat inward, so that you are always in a fever
				or the fear of one. But those things which force the heat
				outwards do distribute and draw the matter to all parts,
				with advantage to our health. If in any work we employ
				our hands, we are able to keep in them that heat which is
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.253"/>
				
				induced by their motion. But when we do not work with
				our hands, we should take all care to keep our extreme
				parts from cold.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>This was one of those things he ridiculed. The second, as I remember, was touching the food allowed the
				sick, which he advises us sometimes both to touch and
				taste when we are in good health, that so we may be used
				to it, and not be shy of it, like little children, or hate such
				a diet, but by degrees make it natural and familiar to our
				appetite; that in our sickness we may not nauseate wholesome diet, as if it were physic, nor be uneasy when we are
				prescribed any insipid thing, that lacks both the smell and
				taste of a kitchen. Wherefore we need not squeamishly
				refuse to eat before we wash, or to drink water when we
				may have wine, or to take warm drink in summer when
				there is snow at hand. We must, however, lay aside all
				foppish ostentation and sophistry as well as vain-glory in
				this abstinence, and quietly by ourselves accustom our appetite to obey reason with willingness, that thus we may
				wean our minds long beforehand from that dainty contempt
				of such food which we feel in time of sickness, and that
				we may not then effeminately bewail our condition, as if we
				were fallen from great and beloved pleasures into a low
				and sordid diet. It was well said, Choose out the best condition you can, and custom will make it pleasant to you.
				And this will be beneficial in most things we undertake,
				but more especially as to diet; if, in the height of our
				health, we introduce a custom whereby those things may
				be rendered easy, familiar, and, as it were, domestics of
				our bodies, remembering what some suffer and do in sickness, who fret, and are not able to endure warm water or
				gruel or bread when it is brought to them, calling them
				dirty and unseemly things, and the persons who would
				urge them to them base and troublesome. The bath hath
				destroyed many whose distemper at the beginning was not
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.254"/>
				
				very bad, only because they could not endure to eat before
				they washed; among whom Titus the emperor was one,
				as his physicians affirm.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>This also was said, that a thin diet is the healthfulest
				to the body. But we ought chiefly to avoid all excess in
				meat or drink or pleasure, when there is any feast or entertainment at hand, or when we expect any royal or
				princely banquet, or solemnity which we cannot possibly
				avoid; then ought the body to be light and in readiness to
				receive the winds and waves it is to meet with. It is a
				hard matter for a man at a feast or collation to keep that
				mediocrity or bounds he has been used to, so as not to
				seem rude, precise, or troublesome to the rest of the company. Lest we should add fire to fire, as the proverb is,
				or one debauch or excess to another, we should take care
				to imitate that ingenious droll of Philip, which was this.
				He was invited to supper by a countryman, who supposed
				he would bring but few friends with him; but when he
				saw him bring a great many, there not being much provided, he was much concerned at it: which when Philip
				perceived, he sent privately to every one of his friends, that
				they should leave a corner for cake; they believing this
				and still expecting, ate so sparingly that there was supper
				enough for them all. So we ought beforehand to prepare
				ourselves against all unavoidable invitations, that there may
				be room left in our body, not only for the meal and the
				dessert, but for drunkenness itself, by bringing in a fresh
				and a willing appetite along with us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But if such a necessity should surprise you when you
				are already loaded or indisposed, in the presence either of
				persons of quality or of strangers that come in upon you
				unawares, and you cannot for shame but go and drink with
				them that are ready for that purpose, then you ought to
				arm yourself against that modesty and prejudicial shamefacedness with that of Creon in the tragedy, who says,&mdash;
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.255"/>
				
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>'Tis better, sirs, I should you now displease,</l>
					             <l>Than by complying next day lose my ease.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>See Eurip. Medea, 290.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				He who throws himself into a pleurisy or frenzy, to
				avoid being censured as an uncivil person, is certainly no
				well-bred man, nor has he sense of understanding enough
				to converse with men, unless in a tavern or a cook-shop.
				Whereas an excuse ingeniously and dexterously made is
				no less acceptable than compliance. He that makes a
				feast, though he be as unwilling to taste of it himself as if
				it was a sacrifice, yet if he be merry and jocund over his
				glass at table, jesting and drolling upon himself, seems
				better company than they who are drunk and gluttonized
				together. Among the ancients, he made mention of Alexander, who after hard drinking was ashamed to resist
				the importunity of Medius, who invited him afresh to the
				drinking of wine, of which he died; and of our time, of
				Regulus the wrestler, who, being called by break of day
				by Titus Caesar to the bath, went and washed with him,
				and drinking but once (as they say) was seized with an
				apoplexy, and died immediately. These things Glaucus
				in laughter objected to as pedantic. He was not over-fond
				of hearing farther, nor indeed were we of discoursing
				more. But do you give heed to every thing that was
				said.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>First, Socrates advises us to beware of such meats
				as persuade a man to eat them though he be not hungry,
				and of those drinks that would prevail with a man to drink
				them when he is not thirsty. Not that he absolutely forbade us the use of them; but he taught that we might use
				them where there was occasion for it, suiting the pleasure
				of them to our necessity, as cities converted the money
				which was designed for the festivals into a supply for war.
				For that which is agreeable by nature, so long as it is a
				part of our nourishment, is proper for us. He that is
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.256"/>
				
				hungry should eat necessary food and find it pleasant; but
				when he is freed from his common appetite, he ought not
				to raise up a fresh one. For, as dancing was no unpleasant
				exercise to Socrates himself, so he that can make his meal
				of sweetmeats or a second course receives the less damage.
				But he that has taken already what may sufficiently satisfy
				his nature ought by all means to avoid them. And concerning these things, indecorum and ambition are no less
				to be avoided than the love of pleasure or gluttony. For
				these often persuade men to eat without hunger or drink
				without thirst, possessing them with base and troublesome fancies, as if it were indecent not to taste of every
				thing which is either a rarity or of great price, as udder,
				Italian mushrooms, Samian cakes, or snow in Egypt.
				Again, these often incite men to eat things rare and much
				talked of, they being led to it, as it were, by the scent of
				vain-glory, and making their bodies to partake of them
				without any necessity of it, that they may have something
				to tell others, who shall admire their having eaten such
				rare and superfluous things. And thus it is with them in
				relation to fine women; when they are in bed with their
				own wives, however beautiful and loving they may be, they
				are no way concerned; but on Phryne or Lais they bestow
				their money, inciting an infirm and unfit body, and provoking it to intemperate pleasures, and all this out of a
				vain-glorious humor. Phryne herself said in her old age,
				that she sold her lees and dregs the dearer because she
				had been in such repute when she was young.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>It is indeed a great and miraculous thing that, if we
				allow the body all the pleasures which nature needs and
				can bear,&mdash;or rather, if we struggle against its appetites
				on most occasions and put it off, and are at last brought
				with difficulty to yield to its necessities, or (as Plato saith)
				give way when it bites and strains itself,&mdash;after all we
				should come off without harm. But, on the other hand,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.257"/>
				
				those desires which descend from the mind into the
				body, and urge and force it to obey and accompany them
				in all their motions and affections, must of necessity leave
				behind them the greatest and severest ills, as the effects of
				such infirm and dark delights. The desire of our mind
				ought no ways to incite our bodies to any pleasure, for the
				beginning of this is against nature. And as the tickling
				of one's armpits forces a laughter, which is neither moderate nor merry, nor indeed properly a laughter, but rather
				troublesome and like convulsions; so those pleasures
				which the molested and disturbed body receives from the
				mind are furious, troublesome, and wholly strangers to
				nature. Therefore when any rare or noble dish is before
				you, you will get more honor by refraining from it than
				partaking of it. Remember what Simonides said, that he
				never repented that he had held his tongue, but often that
				he had spoken; so we shall not repent that we have
				refused a good dish or drunk water instead of Falernian,
				but the contrary. We are not only to commit no violence
				on Nature; but when any of those things are offered to
				her, even if she has a desire for them, we ought oftentimes
				to direct the appetite to a more innocent and accustomed
				diet, that she may be used to it and acquainted with it;
				for as the Theban said (though not over honestly), If the
				law must be violated, it looks best when it is done for an
				empire.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eteocles the Theban, in Eurip. Phoeniss. 524.</note> But we say better, if we are to take pride in any
				such thing, it is best when it is in that moderation which
				conduces to our health. But a narrowness of soul and a
				stingy humor compel some men to keep under and defraud
				their genius at home, who, when they enjoy the costly fare
				of another man's table, do cram themselves as eagerly as
				if it were all plunder; then they are taken ill, go home,
				and the next day find the crudity of their stomachs the
				reward of their unsatiableness. Wherefore Crates, supposing
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.258"/>
				
				 that luxury and prodigality were the chief cause
				of seditions and insurrections in a city, in a droll advises
				that we should never go beyond a lentil in our meals, lest
				we bring ourselves into sedition. But let every one exhort
				himself not to increase his meal beyond a lentil, and not to
				pass by cresses and olives and fall upon pudding and fish,
				that he may not by his over-eating bring his body into
				tumults, disturbances, and diarrhoeas; for a mean diet
				keeps the appetite within its natural bounds, but the arts
				of cooks and confectioners, with their elaborate dishes and
				aromatic sauces, do (according to the comedian) push forward and enlarge the bounds of pleasure, and entrench
				upon those of our profit. I know not how it comes to
				pass that we should abominate and hate those women that
				either bewitch or give philters to their husbands, and yet
				give our meat and drink to our slaves and hirelings, to all
				but corrupt and poison them. For though that may seem
				too severe which was said by Arcesilaus against lascivious
				and adulterous persons, that it signifies little which way
				one goes about such beastly work;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*mhde\n diafe/rein o)/pisqe/n tina h)\ e)/mprosqen ei)=nai ki/naidon.</foreign>
               </note> yet it is not much
				from our purpose. For what difference is there (to speak
				ingenuously) whether satyrion moves and whets my lust,
				or my taste is irritated by the scent of the meat or the
				sauce, so that, like a part infected with itch, it shall always
				need scratching and tickling?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But we shall perhaps discourse against pleasures in
				another place, and show the beauty and dignity that temperance has within itself; but our present discourse is in
				praise of many and great pleasures. For diseases do not
				either rob or spoil us of so much business, hope, journeys,
				or exercise, as they do of pleasure; so that it is no way
				convenient for those who would follow their pleasure to
				neglect their health. There are diseases which will permit
				a man to study philosophy and to exercise any military
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.259"/>
				
				office, nay, to act the kingly part. But the pleasures and
				enjoyments of the body are such as cannot be born alive
				in the midst of a distemperor if they are, the pleasures
				they afford are not only short and impure, but mixed with
				much alloy, and they bear the marks of that storm and
				tempest out of which they rise. Venus herself delights
				not in a gorged, but in a calm and serene body; and
				pleasure is the end of that, as well as it is of meat and
				drink. Health is to pleasure as still weather to the halcyon, giving it a safe and commodious birth and nest.
				Prodicus seems elegantly enough to have said, that of all
				sauces fire was the best; but most true it is to say, that
				health gives things the most divine and grateful relish. For
				meat, whether it be boiled, roasted, or stewed, has no
				pleasure or gusto in it to a sick, surfeited, or nauseous
				stomach. But a clean and undebauched appetite renders
				every thing sweet and delightful to a sound body, and (as
				Homer expresses it) devourable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>As Demades told the Athenians, who unseasonably
				made war, that they never treated of peace but in mourning, so we never think of a moderate and slender diet but
				when we are in a fever or under a course of physic. But
				when we are in these extremities, we diligently conceal our
				enormities, though we remember them well enough; yet as
				many do, we lay the blame of our illness now upon the air,
				now upon the unhealthfulness of the place or the length
				of a journey, to take it off from that intemperance and
				luxury which was the cause of it. As Lysimachus, when
				he was among the Scythians and constrained by his thirst,
				delivered up himself and his army into captivity, but afterwards, drinking cold water, cried out, O ye Gods! for how
				short a pleasure have I thrown away a great felicity!&mdash;so
				in our sickness, we ought to consider with ourselves that,
				for the sake of a draught of cold water, an unseasonable
				bath, or good company, we spoil many of our delights as
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.260"/>
				
				well as our honorable business, and lose many pleasant
				diversions. The remorse that arises from these considerations wounds the conscience, and sticks to us in our health
				like a scar, to make us more cautious as to our diet. For
				a healthful body does not breed any enormous appetite, or
				such as we cannot prevail with or overcome. But we
				ought to put on resolution against our extravagant desires
				or efforts towards enjoyment, esteeming it a low and childish thing to give ear to their complaints and murmurings;
				for they cease as soon as the cloth is taken away, and will
				neither accuse you of injustice, nor think you have done
				them wrong; but on the contrary, you will find them the
				next day pure and brisk, no way clogged or nauseating. As
				Timotheus said, when he had had a light philosophic dinner
				the other day with Plato in the Academy, They who dine
				with Plato never complain the next morning. It is reported that Alexander said, when he had turned off his
				usual cooks, that he carried always better with him; for
				his journeys by night recommended his dinner to him, and
				the slenderness of his dinner recommended his supper.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>I am not ignorant that fevers seize men upon a
				fatigue or excess of heat or cold. But as the scent of flowers, which in itself is but faint, if mixed with oil is more
				strong and fragrant; so an inward fulness gives, as it were,
				a body and substance to external causes and beginnings of
				sickness. For without this they could do no hurt, but
				would vanish and fade away if there were lowness of
				blood and pureness of spirit to receive the motion, which
				in fulness and superabundance, as in disturbed mud, makes
				all things polluted, troublesome, and hardly recoverable.
				We ought not to imitate the good mariner who out of covetousness loads his ship hard and afterwards labors hard
				to throw out the salt water, by first clogging and overcharging our bodies and endeavoring afterwards to clear
				them by purges and clysters; but we ought to keep our
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.261"/>
				
				bodies in right order, that if at any time they should be
				oppressed, their lightness may keep them up like a cork.
			</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>We ought chiefly to be careful in all predispositions
				and forewarnings of sickness. For all distempers do not
				invade us, as Hesiod expresses it,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>In silence,&mdash;for the Gods have struck them dumb;</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Hesiod, Works and Days, 102.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				but the most of them have ill digestion and a kind of a
				laziness, which are the forerunners and harbingers that
				give us warning. Sudden heaviness and weariness tell us
				a distemper is not far off, as Hippocrates affirms, by reason
				(it seems) of that fulness which doth oppress and load the
				spirit in the nerves. Some men, when their bodies all but
				contradict them and invite them to a couch and repose,
				through gluttony and love of pleasure throw themselves
				into a bath or make haste to some drinking meeting, as if
				they were laying in for a siege; being mightily in fear lest
				the fever should seize them before they have dined. Those
				who pretend to more elegance are not caught in this manner, but foolishly enough; for, being ashamed to own their
				qualms and debauch or to keep house all day, when others
				call them to go with them to the gymnasium, they arise
				and pull off their clothes with them, doing the same things
				which they do that are in health. Intemperance and effeminacy make many fly for patronage to the proverb,
				Wine is best after wine, and one debauch is the way to
				drive out another. This excites their hopes, and persuades
				and urges them to rise from their beds and rashly to fall
				to their wonted excesses. Against which hope he ought
				to set that prudent advice of Cato, when he says that great
				things ought to be made less, and the lesser to be quite
				left off; and that it is better to abstain to no purpose and
				be at quiet, than to run ourselves into hazard by forcing
				ourselves either to bath or dinner. For if there be any ill
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.262"/>
				
				in it, it is an injury to us that we did not watch over ourselves and refrain; but if there be none, it is no inconvenience to your body to have abstained and be made more
				pure by it. He is but a child who is afraid lest his friends
				and servants should perceive that he is sick either of a
				surfeit or a debauch. He that is ashamed to confess the
				crudity of his stomach to-day will to-morrow with shame
				confess that he has either a diarrhoea, a fever, or the
				griping in the guts. You think it is a disgrace to want,
				but it is a greater disgrace to bear the crudity, heaviness, and
				fulness of your body, when it has to be carried into the
				bath, like a rotten and leaky boat into the sea. As some
				seamen are ashamed to live on shore when there is a storm
				at sea, yet when they are at sea lie shamefully crying and
				retching to vomit; so in any suspicion or tendency of the
				body to any disease, they think it an indecorum to keep
				their bed one day and not to have their table spread, yet
				most shamefully for many days together are forced to be
				purged and plastered, flattering and obeying their physicians, asking for wine or cold water, being forced to do
				and say many unseasonable and absurd things, by reason
				of the pain and fear they are in. Those therefore who
				cannot govern themselves on account of pleasures, but
				yield to their lusts and are carried away by them, may
				opportunely be taught and put in mind that they receive
				the greatest share of their pleasures from their bodies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And as the Spartans gave the cook vinegar and salt,
				and bade him look for the rest in the victim, so in our
				bodies, the best sauce to whatsoever is brought before us is
				that our bodies are pure and in health. For any thing that
				is sweet or costly is so in its own nature and apart from
				any thing else; but it becomes sweet to the taste only when
				it is in a body which is delighted with it and which is disposed as nature doth require. But in those bodies which
				are foul, surfeited, and not pleased with it, it loses its beauty
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.263"/>
				
				and convenience. Wherefore we need not be concerned
				whether fish be fresh or bread fine, or whether the bath be
				warm or your she-friend a beauty; but whether you are
				not squeamish and foul, whether you are not disturbed and
				do not feel the dregs of yesterday's debauch. Otherwise
				it will be as when some drunken revellers break into a
				house where they are mourning, bringing neither mirth nor
				pleasure with them, but increasing the lamentation. So
				Venus, meats, baths, and wines, in a body that is crazy and
				out of order, mingled with what is vitiated and corrupted,
				stir up phlegm and choler, and create great trouble; neither
				do they bring any pleasure that is answerable to their expectations, or worth either enjoying or speaking of.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>A diet which is very exact and precisely according
				to rule puts one's body both in fear and danger; it hinders
				the gallantry of our soul itself, makes it suspicious of every
				thing or of having to do with any thing, no less in pleasures
				than in labors; so that it dares not undertake any thing
				boldly and courageously. We ought to do by our body as
				by the sail of a ship in fair and clear weather:&mdash;we must
				not contract it and draw it in too much, nor be too remiss
				or negligent about it when we have any suspicion upon us,
				but give it some allowance and make it pliable (as we have
				said), and not wait for crudities and diarrhoeas, or heat or
				drowsiness, by which some, as by messengers and apparitors, are frighted and moderate themselves when a fever is
				at hand; but we must long beforehand guard against the
				storm, as if the north wind blew at sea.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>It is absurd, as Democritus says, by the croaking of
				ravens, the crowing of a cock, or the wallowing of a sow
				in the mire, carefully to observe the signs of windy or rainy
				weather, and not to prevent and guard ourselves against
				the motions and fluctuations of our bodies or the indication of a distemper, nor to understand the signs of a storm
				which is just ready to break forth within ourselves. So
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.264"/>
				
				that we are not only to observe our bodies as to meat and
				exercise, whether they use them more sluggishly or unwillingly than they were wont; or whether we be more thirsty
				and hungry than we use to be; but we are also to take care
				as to our sleep, whether it be continued and easy, or
				whether it be irregular and convulsive. For absurd dreams
				and irregular and unusual fantasies show either abundance or thickness of humors, or else a disturbance of the
				spirits within. For the motions of the soul show that the
				body is nigh a distemper. For there are despondencies of
				mind and fears that are without reason or any apparent
				cause, which extinguish our hopes on a sudden. Some
				there are that are sharp and prone to anger, whom a little
				thing makes sad; and these cry and are in great trouble
				when ill vapors and fumes meet together and (as Plato says)
				are intermingled in the ways and passages of the soul.
				Wherefore those to whom such things happen must consider and remember, that even if there be nothing spiritual,
				there is some bodily cause which needs to be brought away
				and purged.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Besides, it is profitable for him who visits his friends
				in their sickness to enquire after the causes of it. Let us not
				sophistically or impertinently discourse about lodgements,
				irruptions of blood, and commonplaces, merely to show
				our skill in the terms of art which are used in medicine.
				But when we have with diligence heard such trivial and
				common things discoursed of as fulness or emptiness,
				weariness, lack of sleep, and (above all) the diet which the
				patient kept before he fell sick, then,&mdash;as Plato used to
				ask himself, after the miscarriage of other men he had
				been with, Am not I also such a one?&mdash;so ought we to
				take care by our neighbor's misfortunes, and diligently to
				beware that we do not fall into them, and afterwards cry
				out upon our sick-bed, How precious above all other things
				is health! When another is in sickness, let it teach us
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.265"/>
				
				how valuable a treasure health is, which we ought to keep
				and preserve with all possible care. Neither will it be
				amiss for every man to look into his own diet. If therefore
				we have been eating, drinking, laboring, or doing any thing
				to excess, and our bodies give us no suspicion or hint of a
				distemper, yet ought we nevertheless to stand upon our
				guard and take care of ourselves,&mdash;if it be after venery
				and labor, by giving of ourselves rest and quiet; if after
				drinking of wine and feasting, by drinking of water; but
				especially, after we have fed on flesh or solid meats or eaten
				divers things, by abstinence, that we may leave no superfluity in our bodies; for these very things, as they are the
				cause of many diseases, likewise administer matter and
				force to other causes. Wherefore it was very well said,
				that to eat&mdash;but not to satiety, to labor&mdash;but not to weariness, and to keep in nature, are of all things the most
				healthful. For intemperance in venery takes away that
				by which vigor our nourishment is elaborated, and causes
				more superfluity and redundance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>But we shall begin and treat of each of these, and
				first we shall discourse of those exercises which are proper
				for a scholar. And as he that said he should prescribe
				nothing for the teeth to them that dwelt by the seaside
				taught them the benefit of the sea-water, so one would
				think that there was no need of writing to scholars concerning exercise. For it is wonderful what an exercise the
				daily use of speech is, not only as to health but even to
				strength. I mean not fleshly and athletic health, or such
				as makes one's external parts firm, like the outside of a
				house, but such as gives a right tone and inward vigor to
				the vital and noble parts. And that the vital spirit increases strength is made plain by them who anointed the
				wrestlers, who commanded them, when their limbs were
				rubbed, to withstand such frictions in some sort, in holding
				their wind, observing carefully those parts of the body
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.266"/>
				
				which were smeared and rubbed.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text of this passage is uncertain, and probably corrupt. I have given Holland's version of the doubtful expressions. (G.)</note> Now the voice, being
				a motion of the spirit, not superficially but firmly seated
				in the bowels, as it were in a fountain, increases the heat,
				thins the blood, purges every vein, opens all the arteries,
				neither does it permit the coagulation or condensation of
				any superfluous humor, which would settle like dregs in
				those vessels which receive and work our nourishment.
				Wherefore we ought by much speaking to accustom ourselves to this exercise, and make it familiar to us; and if
				we suspect that our bodies are weaker or more tired than
				ordinary, by reading or reciting. For what riding in a
				coach is compared with bodily exercise, that is reading
				compared with disputing, if you carry your voice softly and
				low, as it were in the chariot of another man's words.
				For disputes bring with them a vehemence and contention,
				adding the labor of the mind to that of the body. All
				passionate noise, and such as would force our lungs, ought
				to be avoided; for irregular and violent strains of our voice
				may break something within us, or bring us into convulsions. But when a student has either read or disputed,
				before he walks abroad, he ought to make use of a gentle
				and tepid friction, to open the pores of his body, as much as
				is possible, even to his very bowels, that so his spirits may
				gently and quietly diffuse themselves to the extreme parts
				of his body. The bounds that this friction ought not to
				exceed are, that it be done no longer than it is pleasant to
				our sense and without pain. For he that so allays the disturbance which is within himself and the agitation of his
				spirits will not be troubled by that superfluity which remains in him; and if it be unseasonable for to walk, or if
				his business hinder him, it is no great matter; for nature
				has already received satisfaction. Whether one be at sea
				or in a public inn, it is not necessary that he should be
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.267"/>
				
				silent, though all the company laugh at him. For where
				it is no shame to eat, it is certainly no shame to exercise
				yourself; but it is worse to stand in awe of and be troubled
				with seamen, carriers, and innkeepers, that laugh at you
				not because you play at ball or fight a shadow, but because
				in your discourse you exercise yourself by teaching others,
				or by enquiring and learning something yourself, or else by
				calling to mind something. For Socrates said, he that
				uses the exercise of dancing had need have a room big
				enough to hold seven beds; but he that makes either singing or discourse his exercise may do it either standing or
				lying in any place. But this one thing we must observe,
				that when we are conscious to ourselves that we are too
				full, or have been concerned with Venus, or labored hard,
				we do not too much strain our voice, as so many rhetoricians and readers in philosophy do, some of whom out of
				glory and ambition, some for reward or private contentions,
				have forced themselves beyond what has been convenient.
				Our Niger, when he was teaching philosophy in Galatia,
				by chance swallowed the bone of a fish; but a stranger
				coming to teach in his place, Niger, fearing he might run
				away with his repute, continued to read his lectures, though
				the bone still stuck in his throat; from whence a great and
				hard inflammation arising, he, being unable to undergo the
				pain, permitted a deep incision to be made, by which wound
				the bone was taken out; but the wound growing worse,
				and rheum falling upon it, it killed him. But this may be
				mentioned hereafter in its proper place.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>After exercise to use a cold bath is boyish, and has
				more ostentation in it than health; for though it may seem
				to harden our bodies and make them not so subject to outward accidents, yet it does more prejudice to the inward
				parts, by hindering transpiration, fixing the rumors, and
				condensing those vapors which love freedom and transpiration. Besides, necessity will force those who use cold
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.268"/>
				
				baths into that exact and accurate way of diet they would
				so much avoid, and make them take care they be not in the
				least extravagant, for every such error is sure to receive
				a bitter reproof. But a warm bath is much more pardonable, for it does not so much destroy our natural vigor and
				strength as it does conduce to our health, laying a soft and
				easy foundation for concoction, preparing those things for
				digestion which are not easily digested without any pain
				(if they be not very crude and deep lodged), and fleeing
				us from all inward weariness. But when we do sensibly
				perceive our bodies to be indifferent well, or as they ought
				to be, we should omit bathing, and anoint ourselves by the
				fire; which is better if the body stand in need of heat, for
				it dispenses a warmth throughout. But we should make
				use of the sun more or less, as the temper of the air permits. So much may suffice to have been said concerning
				exercises.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>As for what has been said of diet before, if any part
				of it be profitable in instructing us how we should allay
				and bring down our appetites, there yet remains one thing
				more to be advised: that if it be troublesome to treat one's
				belly like one broke loose, and to contend with it though
				it has no ears (as Cato said), then ought we to take care
				that the quality of what we eat may make the quantity
				more light; and we should eat cautiously of such food as
				is solid and most nourishing (for it is hard always to refuse it), such as flesh, cheese, dried figs, and boiled eggs;
				but more freely of those things which are thin and light,
				such as moist herbs, fowl, and fish if it be not too fat; for
				he that eats such things as these may gratify his appetite,
				and yet not oppress his body. But ill digestion is chiefly
				to be feared after flesh, for it presently very much clogs us
				and leaves ill relics behind it. It would be best to accustom one's self to eat no flesh at all, for the earth affords
				plenty enough of things fit not only for nourishment, but
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.269"/>
				
				for delight and enjoyment; some of which you may eat
				without much preparation, and others you may make
				pleasant by adding divers other things to them. But since
				custom is almost a second nature, we may eat flesh, but
				not to the cloying of our appetites, like wolves or lions,
				but only to lay as it were a foundation and bulwark for our
				nourishment,&mdash;and then come to other meats and sauces
				which are more agreeable to the nature of our bodies and
				do less dull our rational soul, which seems to be enlivened
				by a light and brisk diet.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>As for liquids, we should never make milk our drink,
				but rather take it as food, it yielding much solid nourishment. As for wine, we must say to it what Euripides
				said to Venus:&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thy joys with moderation I would have,</l>
					             <l>And that I ne'er may want them humbly crave.</l>
               </quote>
				
				For wine is the most beneficial of all drinks, the pleasantest medicine in the world, and of all dainties the least
				cloying to the appetite, provided more regard be given to
				the opportunity of the time of drinking it than even to its
				being properly mixed with water. Water, not only when
				it is mixed with wine, but also if it be drunk by itself
				between mixed wine and water, makes the mingled wine
				the less hurtful. We should accustom ourselves therefore
				in our daily diet to drink two or three glasses of water,
				which will allay the strength of the wine, and make drinking of water familiar to our body, that so in a case of
				necessity it may not be looked on as a stranger, and we be
				offended at it. It so falls out, that some have then the
				greatest inclination for wine when there is most need they
				should drink water; for such men, when they have been
				exposed to great heat of the sun, or have fallen into a
				chill, or have been speaking vehemently, or have been
				more than ordinarily thoughtful about any thing, or after
				any fatigue or labor, are of the opinion that they ought to
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.270"/>
				
				drink wine, as if nature required some repose for the body
				and some diversion after its labors. But nature requires
				no such repose (if you will call pleasure repose), but desires only such an alteration as shall be between pleasure
				and pain; in which case we ought to abate of our diet,
				and either wholly abstain from wine, or drink it allayed
				with very much mixture of water. For wine, being sharp
				and fiery, increases the disturbances of the body, exasperates them, and wounds the parts affected; which stand
				more in need of being comforted and smoothed, which
				water does the best of any thing. If, when we are not
				thirsty, we drink warm water after labor, exercise, or heat,
				we find our inward parts loosened and smoothed by it; for
				the moisture of water is gentle and not violent, but that of
				wine carries a great force in it, which is no ways agreeable in the fore-mentioned cases. And if any one should
				be afraid that abstinence would bring upon the bodythat
				acrimony and bitterness which some say it will, he is like
				those children who think themselves much wronged because
				they may not eat just before the fit of a fever. The best
				mean between both these is drinking of water. We oftentimes sacrifice to Bacchus himself without wine, doing very
				well in accustoming ourselves not to be always desirous
				of wine. Minos made the pipe and the crown be laid aside
				at the sacrifice when there was mourning. And yet we
				know an afflicted mind is not at all affected by either the
				pipe or crown; but there is no body so strong, to which, in
				commotion or a fever, wine does not do a great deal of
				injury.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>The Lydians are reported in a famine to have spent
				one day in eating, and the next in sports and drollery. But
				a lover of learning and a friend to the Muses, when at any
				time he is forced to sup later than ordinary, will not be so
				much a slave to his belly as to lay aside a geographical
				scheme when it is before him, or his book, or his lyre; but
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.271"/>
				
				strenuously turning himself, and taking his mind off from
				eating, he will in the Muses' name drive away all such desires, as so many Harpies, from his table. Will not the
				Scythian in the midst 'of his cups oftentimes handle his
				bow and twang the string, thereby rousing up himself from
				that drunkenness in which he was immersed? Will a
				Greek be afraid, because he is laughed at, by books and
				letters gently to loosen and unbend any blind and obstinate
				desire? The young men in Menander, when they were
				drinking, were trepanned by a bawd, which brought in to
				them a company of handsome and richly attired women;
				but every one, as he said,
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Cast down his eyes and fell to junketing,&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
				
				not one daring to look upon them. Lovers of learning
				have many fair and pleasant diversions, if they can no
				other way keep in their canine and brutish appetites
				when they see the table spread. The bawling of such fellows as anoint wrestlers, and the opinion of pedagogues
				that it hinders our nourishment and dulls one's head to
				discourse of learning at table, are indeed of some force
				then, when we are called upon to solve a fallacy like the
				<hi rend="italics">Indus</hi> or to dispute about the <hi rend="italics">Kyrieuon</hi> at a feast. For
				though the pith of the palm-tree is very sweet, yet they
				say it will cause the headache. To discourse of logic at
				meals is not indeed a very delicious banquet, is rather
				troublesome, and pains one's head; but if there be any
				who will not give us leave to discourse philosophically or
				ask any question or read any thing at table, though it be
				of those things which are not only decent and profitable
				but also pleasantly merry, we will desire them not to
				trouble us, but to talk in this style to the athletes in the
				Xvstum and the Palaestra, who have laid aside their books
				and are wont to spend their whole time in jeers and scurrilous jests, being, as Aristo wittily expresses it, smooth
				and hard, like the pillars in the gymnasium. But we must
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.272"/>
				
				obey our physicians, who advise us to keep some interval
				between supper and sleep, and not to heap up together a
				great deal of victuals in our stomachs and so shorten our
				breath (lest we presently by crude and fermenting aliment
				overcharge our digestion), but rather to take some space
				and breathing-time before we sleep. As those who have
				a mind to exercise themselves after supper do not do it by
				running or wrestling, but rather by gentle exercise, such
				as walking or dancing; so when we intend to exercise our
				minds after supper, we are not to do it with any thing of
				business or care, or with those sophistical disputes which
				bring us into a vain-glorious and violent contention. But
				there are many questions in natural philosophy which are
				easy to discuss and to decide; there are many disquisitions
				which relate to manners, which please the mind (as Homer
				expresses it) and do no way discompose it. Questions in
				history and poetry have been by some ingeniously called
				a second course to a learned man and a scholar. There
				are discourses which are no way troublesome; and, besides,
				fables may be told. Nay, it is easier to discourse of the
				pipe and lyre, or hear them discoursed of, than it is to
				hear either of them played on. The quantity of time
				allowed for this exercise is till our meat be gently settled
				within us, so that our digestion may have power enough
				to master it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Aristotle is of opinion that to walk after supper stirs
				up our natural heat; but to sleep, if it be soon after, chokes
				it. Others again say that rest aids digestion, and that motion disturbs it. Hence some walk immediately after supper;
				others choose rather to keep themselves still. But that
				man seems to obtain the design of both, who cherishes and
				keeps his body quiet, not immediately suffering his mind
				to become heavy and idle, but (as has been said) gently
				distributing and lightening his spirits by either hearing or
				speaking some pleasant thing, such as will neither molest
				nor oppress him.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.273"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Medicinal vomits and purges, which are the bitter
				reliefs of gluttony, are not to be attempted without great
				necessity. The manner of many is to fill themselves because they are empty, and again, because they are full, to
				empty themselves contrary to nature, being no less tormented with being full than being empty; or rather, they
				are troubled at their fulness, as being a hindrance of their
				appetite, and are always emptying themselves, that they
				may make room for new enjoyment. The damage in these
				cases is evident; for the body is disordered and torn by
				both these. It is an inconvenience that always attends
				a vomit, that it increases and gives nourishment to this
				insatiable humor. For it engenders hunger, as violent and
				turbulent as a roaring torrent, which continually annoys a
				man, and forces him to his meat, not like a natural appetite that calls for food, but rather like inflammation that
				calls for plasters and physic. Wherefore his pleasures are
				short and imperfect, and in the enjoyment are very furious
				and unquiet; upon which there come distentions, and
				affections of the pores, and retentions of the spirits, which
				will not wait for the natural evacuations, but run over the
				surface of the body, so that it is like an overloaded ship,
				where it is more necessary to throw something overboard
				than to take any thing more in. Those disturbances in our
				bellies which are caused by physic corrupt and consume
				our inward parts, and do rather increase our superfluous
				humors than bring them away; which is as if one that was
				troubled at the number of Greeks that inhabited the city,
				should call in the Arabians and Scythians.</p>
            <p>Some are so much mistaken that, in order that they may
					void their customary and natural superfluities, they take
					Cnidian-berries or scammony, or some other harsh and incongruous physic, which is more fit to be carried away by
					purge than it is able to purge us. It is best therefore by a
					moderate and regular diet to keep our body in order, so
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.274"/>
					
					that it may command itself as to fulness or emptiness. If
					at any time there be a necessity, we may take a vomit, but
					without physic or much tampering, and such a one as will
					not cause any great disturbance, only enough to save us
					from indigestion by casting up gently what is superfluous.
					For as linen cloths, when they are washed with soap and
					nitre, are more worn out than when they are washed with
					water only, so physical vomits corrupt and destroy the
					body. If at any time we are costive, there is no medicine
					better than some sort of food which will purge you gently
					and with ease, the trial of which is familiar to all, and the
					use without any pain. But if it will not yield to those, we
					may drink water for some days, or fast, or take a clyster,
					rather than take any troublesome purging physic; which
					most men are inclined to do, like that sort of women
					which take things on purpose to miscarry, that they may
					be empty and begin afresh.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But to be done with these, there are some on the
				other side who are too exact in enjoining themselves to
				periodical and set fasts, doing amiss in teaching nature to
				want coercion when there is no occasion for it, and making that abstinence necessary which is not so, and all this
				at times when nature requires her accustomed way of living. It is better to use those injunctions we lay upon our
				bodies with more freedom, even when we have no ill symptom or suspicion upon us; and so to order our diet (as has
				been said), that our bodies may be always obedient to any
				change, and not be enslaved or tied up to one manner of
				living, nor so exact in regarding the times, numbers, and
				periods of our actions. For it is a life neither safe, easy,
				politic, nor like a man, but more like the life of an oyster
				or the trunk of a tree, to live so without any variety, and
				in restraint as to our meat, abstinence, motion, and rest;
				casting ourselves into a gloomy, idle, solitary, unsociable,
				and inglorious way of living, far remote from the administration
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.275"/>
				
				 of the state,&mdash;at least (I may say) in my
				opinion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>For health is not to be purchased by sloth and idleness, for those are chief inconveniences of sickness; and
				there is no difference between him who thinks to enjoy his
				health by idleness and quiet, and him who thinks to preserve his eyes by not using them, and his voice by not
				speaking. For such a man's health will not be any advantage to him in the performance of many things he is
				obliged to do as a man. Idleness can never be said to conduce to health, for it destroys the very end of it. Nor is
				it true that they are the most healthful that do least. For
				Xenocrates was not more healthful than Phocion, or Theophrastus than Demetrius. It signified nothing to Epicurus
				or his followers, as to that so much talked of good habit
				of body, that they declined all business, though it were
				never so honorable. We ought to preserve the natural
				constitution of our bodies by other means, knowing every
				part of our life is capable of sickness and health.</p>
            <p>The contrary advice to that which Plato gave his scholars is to be given to those who are concerned in public
					business. For he was wont to say, whenever he left his
					school; Go to, my boys, see that you employ your leisure
					in some honest sport and pastime. Now to those that are
					in public office our advice is, that they bestow their labor
					on honest and necessary things, not tiring their bodies with
					small or inconsiderable things. For most men upon accident torment themselves with watchings, journeyings, and
					running up and down, for no advantage and with no good
					design, but only that they may do others an injury, or because they envy them or are competitors with them, or
					because they hunt after unprofitable and empty glory. To
					such as these I think Democritus chiefly spoke when he
					said, that if the body should summon the soul before a
					court on an action for ill-treatment, the soul would lose the
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.276"/>
					
					case. And perhaps on the other hand Theophrastus spoke
					well, when he said metaphorically, that the soul pays a
					dear house-rent to its landlord the body. But still the
					body is very much more inconvenienced by the soul, when
					it is used beyond reason and there is not care enough taken
					of it. For when it is in passion, action, or any concern,
					it does not at all consider the body. Jason, being somewhat out of humor, said, that in little things we ought not
					to stand upon justice, so that in greater things we may be
					sure to do it. We, and that in reason, advise any public
					man to trifle and play with little things, and in such cases
					to indulge himself, so that in worthy and great concerns
					he may not bring a dull, tired, and weary body, but one
					that is the better for having lain still, like a ship in the
					dock, that when the soul has occasion again to call it into
					business, <q direct="unspecified">it may run with her, like a sucking colt with
						the mare.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Upon which account, when business gives us leave,
				we ought to refresh our bodies, grudging them neither
				sleep nor dinner nor that ease which is the medium between pain and pleasure; not taking that course which
				most men do, who thereby wear out their bodies by the
				many changes they expose them to, making them like hot
				iron thrown into cold water, by softening and troubling
				them with pleasures, after they have been very much
				strained and oppressed with labor. And on the other
				side, after they have opened their bodies and made them
				tender either by wine or venery, they exercise them either
				at the bar or at court, or enter upon some other business
				which requires earnest and vigorous action. Heraclitus,
				when he was in a dropsy, desired his physician to bring a
				drought upon his body, for it had a glut of rain. Most
				men are very much in the wrong who, after being tired or
				having labored or fasted, moisten (as it were) and dissolve
				their bodies in pleasure, and again force and distend them
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.277"/>
				
				after those pleasures. Nature does not require that we
				should make the body amends at that rate. But an intemperate and slavish mind, so soon as it is free from labor,
				like a sailor, runs insolently into pleasures and delights,
				and again falls upon business, so that nature can have no
				rest or leave to enjoy that temper and calmness which
				it does desire, but is troubled and tormented by all this
				irregularity. Those that have any discretion never so much
				as offer pleasure to the body when it is laboring,&mdash;for at
				such times they do not require it at all,&mdash;nor do they so
				much as think of it, their minds being intent upon that
				employ they are in, either the delight or diligence of the
				soul getting the mastery over all other desires. Epaminondas is reported wittily to have said of a good man that
				died about the time of the battle of Leuctra, How came
				he to have so much leisure as to die, when there was so
				much business stirring? It may truly be asked concerning
				a man that is either of public employ or a scholar, What
				time can such a man spare, either to debauch his stomach
				or be drunk or lascivious? For such men, after they have
				done their business, allow quiet and repose to their bodies,
				reckoning not only unprofitable pains but unnecessary
				pleasures to be enemies to nature, and avoiding them as
				such.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>I have heard that Tiberius Caesar was wont to say,
				that he was a ridiculous man that held forth his hand to
				a physician after sixty. But it seems to me to be a little
				too severely said. But this is certain, that every man
				ought to have skill in his own pulse, for it is very different
				in every man; neither ought he to be ignorant of the temper of his own body, as to heat and cold, or what things
				do him good, and what hurt. For he has no sense, and is
				both a blind and lame inhabitant of his body, that must
				learn these things from another, and must ask his physicians whether it is better with him in winter or summer;
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.278"/>
				
				or whether moist or dry things agree best with him,
				or whether his pulse be frequent or slow. For it is necessary and easy to know such things by custom and experience. It is convenient to understand more what meats
				and drinks are wholesome than what are pleasant, and to
				have more skill in what is good for the stomach than in
				what seems good to the mouth, and in those things that
				are easy of digestion than in those that gratify our palate.
				For it is no less scandalous to ask a physician what is easy
				and what is hard of digestion, and what will agree with
				your stomach and what not, than it is to ask what is sweet,
				and what bitter, and what sour. They nowadays correct
				their cooks, being able well enough to tell what is too
				sweet, too salt, or too sour, but themselves do not know
				what will be light or easy of digestion, and agreeable to
				them. Therefore in the seasoning of broth they seldom
				err, but they do so scurvily pickle themselves every day as to
				afford work enough for the physician. For that pottage
				is not accounted best that is the sweetest, but they mingle
				bitter and sweet together. But they force the body to partake of many, and those cloying pleasures, either not knowing, or not remembering, that to things that are good and
				wholesome nature adds a pleasure unmingled with any
				regret or repentance afterward. We ought also to know
				what things are cognate and convenient to our bodies, and
				be able to direct a proper diet to any one upon any change
				of weather or other circumstance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>As for those inconveniences which sordidness and
				poverty bring upon many, as gathering of fruit, continual
				labor, and running about, and want of rest, which fall
				heavy upon the weaker parts of the body and such as are
				inwardly infirm, we need not fear that any man of employ
				or scholar&mdash;to whom our present discourse belongs&mdash;should
				be troubled with them. But there is a severe sort of sordidness as to their studies, which they ought to avoid, by which
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.279"/>
				
				they are forced many times to neglect their body, oftentimes
				denying it a supply when it has (lone its work, making the
				mortal part of us do its share in work as well as the immortal, and the earthly part as much as the heavenly. But,
				as the ox said to his fellow-servant the camel, when he
				refused to ease him of his burthen, It won't be long before
				you carry my burthen and me too: which fell out to be
				true, when the ox died. So it happens to the mind, when
				it refuses that little relaxation and comfort which it needs
				in its labor; for a little while after a fever or vertigo seizes
				us, and then reading, discoursing, and disputing must be
				laid aside, and it is forced to partake of the body's distemper. Plato therefore rightly exhorts us not to employ
				the mind without the body, nor the body without the mind,
				but to drive them equally like a pair of horses; and when
				at any time the body toils and labors with the mind, then
				to be the more careful of it, and thus to gain its wellbeloved health, believing that it obliges us with the best
				of things when it is no impediment to our knowledge
				and enjoyment of virtue, either in business or discourse.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>