<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Apophthegmata Laconica</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1931</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.3.p.240"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Plutarch was an admirer of the old Spartan virtues, and it seems altogether
						probable that the collection of sayings of Spartans was made by him as
						literary material for use in his writing, as he tells us was his custom
						(Moralia, 457 d and 464 f), and many of the sayings are actually found
						incorporated in his other works. That he did not use all the material which
						he had accumulated is no more than is to be expected from a discriminating
						author.</p>
               <p>The title (Sayings of Spartans) stands as No. 169 in Lamprias's list of
						Plutarch's works.</p>
               <p>A selection from the sayings of the more famous Spartans is incorporated in
						the Sayings of Kings and Commanders, which covers a broader field, including
						both Greeks and Romans, and so does not contain the entire collection of
						Spartan sayings. For example, in the Spartan Sayings, under the name of
						Agesilaus are found seventy-nine different sayings, but only twelve of these
						are selected for inclusion in the Sayings of Kings and Commanders, so that
						the Emperor Trajan (if the collection was made for him) should not. be
						overburdened in his reading !</p>
               <p>The ms. tradition of these Spartan sayings is in sad confusion. The Spartans
						spoke in the Doric dialect, yet according to the ms. tradition of Plutarch
						they spoke sometimes Doric, more often Attic, and <pb id="v.3.p.241"/>
						occasionally used Aeolie forms i It is not likely, for example, that the
						mother of Brasidas spoke Doric (190 c) and Attic (219 d) in making the same
						remark, or that Brasidas spoke sometimes Doric and sometimes Attic (219
						c-d), or that Charillus said the same thing in both Doric (189 f) and Attic
						(232 c). The explanation probably is that Plutarch copied these anecdotes as
						he found them in the books from which he made his excerpts. Xenophon, for
						example, or Thucydides seldom uses Doric, but represents the Spartans as
						speaking Attic, as frankly as Herodotus or Aeschylus represents the Persians
						as spealdng Greek. So on the stage in England or America, or in novels,
						French or German characters speak English, or vice versa-a convention which
						is universally accepted. Hence it should not disturb us to find Plutarch
						recording remarks of Spartans in the Attic dialect, nor should we hastily
						conclude that the mss. are all wrong.</p>
               <p>It would be possible, with our present knowledge, to translate all these
						Spartan sayings into the Doric dialect, but to do so would be a useless tour
						deforce. It would be as if the editor of a newspaper were to insist that
						every story about a Scotchman or a Yankee should be edited to conform to the
						correct Scotch or Yankee dialect-a rather futile proceeding. Hence no
						radical changes have been made in the ms. tradition. Only when the mss. show
						a distinct attempt to quote in Doric has an effort been made to make the
						Doric consistent in itself.</p>
               <p>It will not escape the attentive reader that the names of the Spartans whose
						sayings are quoted are arranged in alphabetical order, for the purpose,
						without doubt, of facilitating reference to them.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.3.p.243"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>AGASICLES <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One of the early kings of Sparta.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When someone expressed surprise to Agasicles, king of the Spartans, because,
						although he was very fond of reading and lectures, yet he would not admit to
						his presence Philophanes, a learned man, he said, <q direct="unspecified">I want to be a
							pupil of those whose son I should like to be as we!!.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In answer to a man who raised the question how anyone could possibly rule in
						safety without the protection of a bodyguard, he said, <q direct="unspecified">If one rules
							his subjects as fathers rule their sons.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> ii.
							47.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>AGESILAUS THE GREAT
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi> Many anecdotes about Agesilaus may be found
						in Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, ii. 1.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Agesilaus the Great was once chosen by lot to be master of ceremonies at an
						evening party, and, when he was asked by the slave who poured the wine how
						much wine he should serve to each man, Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">If much wine
							has been provided, as much as each one asks for; but if only a little,
							then give to all equally.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When a malefactor endured tortures without flinching, Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">
							What an out-and-out <pb id="v.3.p.245"/> villain the man is, devoting
							his endurance and fortitude to such base and shameful purposes !
						</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone praised an orator for his ability in making much of small
						matters, Agesilaus said that a shoemaker is not a good craftsman who puts
						big shoes on a small foot. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 224 C,
								<hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De
								oratore</hi>, i. 54 (231).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone said to him, <q direct="unspecified">You have agreed,</q> and kept repeating
						the same thing, Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, of course, if it is right; but
							if not, then I said so, but I did not agree.</q> And when the other
						added, <q direct="unspecified">But surely kings ought to carry out ‘ whatsoe'er they confirm
							by the royal assent,'</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 527.</note>
						Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">No more than those who approach kings ought to ask
							for what is right and say what is right, trying to hit upon the right
							occasion and a request fitting for kings to grant.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>Whenever he heard people blaming or praising, he thought it was no less
						necessary to inform himself about the ways of those who spoke than of those
						about whom they spoke. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In almost the same words, but with a diffrent
							turn of the thought, in Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 11.
							4.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When he was still a boy, at a celebration of the festival of the naked boys
						the director of the dance assigned him to an inconspicuous place; and he
						obeyed, although he was already destined to be king, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch in his
								<hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chaps. i. and ii. (596 A
							and 597 B), says that Agesilaus was brought up as a private citizen and
							di not become king until after the death of Agis.</note> saying, <q direct="unspecified">
							Good ! I shall show that it is not the places that make men to be held
							in honour, but the men the places.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 149 A. In 219, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> the remark is attributed to Damonidas, and Diogenes
							Laertius, ii. 73, assigns it to Aristippus.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>When a physician prescribed for him an overelaborate <pb id="v.3.p.247"/>
						course of treatment, not at all simple, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Egad, it is not
							ordained that I must live at all hazards, and I refuse to submit to
							everything.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar attitude of Pompey, 204 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>As he was standing at the altar of Athena of the Brazen House sacrificing a
						heifer, a louse bit him; but he did not turn a hair, and, picking it off, he
						cracked it openly before the eyes of all, saying, <q direct="unspecified">By Heaven, it is a
							pleasure to kill the plotter even at the altar.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>At another time he saw a mouse being dragged from a hole by a boy who had
						hold of him, and the mouse turned and bit the hand that held him and
						escaped; whereupon Agesilaus called the attention of the bystanders to this,
						and said, <q direct="unspecified">When the smallest animal thus defends itself against those
							who do it wrong, consider what it becomes men to do.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar story about Brasidas in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 79 E, 190 B, and 219 C.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>Desiring to bring about the war against the Persian for the sake of setting
						free the Greeks living in Asia, he consulted the oracle of Zeus at Dodona,
						and when the god bade him to go on, he reported the answer to the Ephors.
						And they bade him go to Delphi and ask the same question. Accordingly he
						proceeded to the prophetic shrine and put his question in this form :
							<q direct="unspecified">Apollo, are you of the same opinion as your father ?</q>
						And Apollo concurring, Agesilaus was chosen, and began the campaign.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 191 B, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>Tissaphernes, at the outset, in fear of Agesilaus, made a treaty, agreeing
						that the king should leave him the Greek cities free and independent, but,
						after sending for a great army from the king, he <pb id="v.3.p.249"/>
						declared war on Agesilaus unless he should depart from Asia. Agesilaus
						gladly welcomed the transgression, and set forth as if he were intending to
						advance into Cari a; and when Tissaphernes had concentrated his forces
						there, Agesilaus, by a rapid movement thence, invaded Phrygia; and having
						taken very many cities and a wealth of spoil, he said to his friends,
							<q direct="unspecified">To do wrong after making a treaty is impious, but to outwit the
							enemy is not only right and reputable, but also pleasant and
							profitable.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. ix. (600 C): Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iii. 4. 5 ff., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>,
							1. 10; Diodorus, xiv. 79; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, ii. 1. 8-9; Cornelius Nepos, xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi> 2 and 3; Frontinus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, i. 8. 12. </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>Finding himself inferior in horsemen, he retreated to Ephesus, and there made
						proclamation to the men of means that they should each provide a horse and a
						man, and thus gain their own release from service. As a result there were
						collected, in a very short time, both horses and capable men in place of
						wealthy cowards.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. ix. (600 D); Xenophon,
								<hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iii. 4. 15, and <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 1. 24.</note> Agesilaus said he was
						emulating Agamemnon; for Agamemnon accepted a good mare and released from
						service a base man of wealth. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 32
							F. The reference is to Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiii. 296
							ff.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>When, in obedience to his orders that the prisoners of war be sold naked,
						those charged with selling the spoils so offered them, there were many
						buyers for the clothing, but as for the prisoners' bodies, altogether white
						and soft because of their indoor life, the buyers derided them as useless
						and worthless. And Agesilaus, stepping up, said, <q direct="unspecified">These are the
							things for which you fight, and these are the men whom you
							fight.</q>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. ix. (600 E); Xenophon,
								<hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iii. 4. 19. <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 1. 28: Polyaenus ii. 1. 5; Athenaeus, 550 E.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.251"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>Having routed Tissaphernes in the Lydia n country and slain a great many of
						his men, he proceeded to overrun the king's country. The king sent money to
						him, and in return asked for a cessation of hostilities, but Agesilaus said
						that the State alone had the power to make peace, and that it gave him more
						pleasure to enrich his soldiers than to be rich himself, and that he thought
						it a grand thing that the Greeks did not accept gifts from the enemy, but
						took spoils instead. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. x. (601 A-B), where the
							remark is made to Tithraustes, who was sent by the king to supplant
							Tissaphernes. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iii. 4. 25, and <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi> 4.6.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>When Megabates, Spithridates' son, who was most fair of form, came near to
						him as if to greet him with a kiss because the boy felt that he was held in
						aiFection by Agesilaus, Agesilaus drew back. And when the boy stopped coming
						to see him, Agesilaus asked for him; whereupon his friends said that he had
						only himself to blame, because he shrank from coming within kissing distance
						of the fair one, and if he would not act the coward, the boy would come
						again. Agesilaus, reflecting by himself for no brief time in uninterrupted
						silence, finally said, <q direct="unspecified">There is no need of our trying to persuade
							him; for I feel that I had rather be above such things than to take by
							storm the most populous city of our opponents, since it is better to
							preserve one's own liberty than to deprive others of theirs.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xi. (602 A); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>,
							31 C (81 A); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 5, 4-5.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="16">
               <p>In almost all matters he was exact in observing the law, but in anything
						affecting his friends he thought that too rigid justice in dealings with
						them <pb id="v.3.p.253"/> was but a poor excuse. At any rate, there is a
						note of his in circulation addressed to Hidrieus the Carian, in which he
						asks for the release of one of his friends in these words : <q direct="unspecified">If Nicias
							is not guilty, let him go; but if he is guilty, let him go for my sake;
							but let him go anyway.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xiii. (603 B); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="17">
               <p>Such, then, was Agesilaus in his friends' behalf in most matters; but there
						are instances when, in meeting a critical situation, he showed more regard
						for the general weal. At any rate, on a time when camp was being broken in
						some disorder, and Agesilaus was leaving behind his loved one who was ill,
						and the loved one implored him and called him back with tears, Agesilaus,
						turning round, exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">How hard it is to be merciful and sensible
							at the same time !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xiii. (603 C); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="18">
               <p>The mode of living which he followed personally was in no wise better than
						that of his associates. He refrained always from overeating and from heavy
						drinking. Sleep he treated, not as a master, but as governed at all times by
						what he had to do; and such was his attitude towards heat and cold that he
						alone was able to make good use of the different seasons; and in his tent,
						which was in the midst of his soldiers, he had no better bed than anybody
						else. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xiv. (603); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 5. 2-3, and 9. 5; Cornelius Nepos, xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 5. 2.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="19">
               <p>He was continually saying that the commander ought rightly to be superior to
						the privates not in soft living and luxury, but in endurance and courage.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 5. 2.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="20">
               <p>At any rate, when someone inquired what advantage the laws of Lycurgus had
						brought to Sparta, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Contempt for pleasures.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.255"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="21">
               <p>In answer to the man who expressed surprise at the plainness of the clothes
						and the fare both of himself and of the other Spartans, he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							From this mode of life, my friend, we reap a harvest of liberty.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="22">
               <p>When someone else urged him to relax, and said that, because of the
						uncertainty of fortune, the opportunity for this might never come to him, he
						replied, <q direct="unspecified">I accustom myself by training to seek to find a change in
							no change.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="23">
               <p>Even when he had grown old, he followed the same course; and in answer to
						someone who asked him the reason why, at his age, he went about with no
						undergarment in such very cold weather, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that the young
							men may imitate, having the oldest men and the officials as an
							example.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia
								Historia</hi>, vii. 13.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="24">
               <p>The Thasians, as he was marching through their country with his army, sent to
						him flour, geese, sweetmeats, honey-cakes, and other costly foods and drinks
						of all kinds. The flour alone he accepted, but the rest of the things he
						bade those who had brought them to carry back because these were of no use
						to the Spartans. But when the Thasians importuned him and begged him by all
						means to take all, he gave orders to distribute them among the Helots. And
						when the Thasians inquired the reason, he said, <q direct="unspecified">It is not in keeping
							that those who practise manly virtues should indulge in such
							gormandizing, for things that allure the servile crowd are alien to free
							men.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxxvi. (616 F), where the scene is laid in
							Egypt, as also in Cornelius Nepos, xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 8. 3-4. The story is found also in Athenaeus, 657 B
							and in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 20, where it
							is told of Lysander.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.257"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="25">
               <p>At another time the Thasians, because of a feeling that they had been greatly
						befriended by him, honoured him with temples and deifications, and also sent
						an embassy to inform him of their action. When he had read the honours which
						the ambassadors proffered to him, he asked if their country had the power to
						deify men; and when they answered in the affirmative, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Go
							to; make gods of yourselves first, and if you can accomplish this, then
							will I believe that you will be able to make a god of me also.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="26">
               <p>When the Greek peoples of Asia voted to erect statues of him in their most
						prominent cities, he wrote to them : <q direct="unspecified">Let there be no image of me
							painted or sculptured or constructed.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 191 D, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note. By <q direct="unspecified">constructed</q> he probably refers to
							the gold and ivory statues which were common among the Greeks.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="27">
               <p>Seeing in Asia a house roofed with square beams, he asked the owner if timber
						in that country grew square. And when the man said, <q direct="unspecified">No, but
							round,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Well, then, if they were square, would
							you finish them round ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 227 C, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
							Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xii. (47 C).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="28">
               <p>Being asked once how far the bounds of Sparta extended, he said, with a
						flourish of his spear, <q direct="unspecified">As far as this can reach.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 190 E (3), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 217 E (7), 218 F (2), 229 C (6), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and 267 C.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="29">
               <p>When someone else wished to know why Sparta was without walls, he pointed to
						the citizens in full armour and said, <q direct="unspecified">These are the Spartans'
							walls.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 217 E, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> (Antalcidas); Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xix. (52 B); Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 778 D; Epictetus, in Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, v. iii.; Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi> xviii. (<hi rend="italics">De corona</hi>), 299 (325);
							Claudius Claudianus, (viii.), <hi rend="italics">Panegyr. de quarto
								consulatu Honorii</hi>, 508. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 228 E (28) <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.259"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="30">
               <p>When another person put the same question, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Cities ought not
							to be fortified with stones and timbers, but with the strong virtues of
							their inhabitants.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note <hi rend="italics">d</hi> on previous page.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="31">
               <p>He advised his friends to endeavour to be rich, not in money, but in bravery
						and virtue. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="32">
               <p>Whenever he wished a task to be quickly performed by his soldiers, he himself
						took hold first in the sight of all. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
							Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 5. 3. Plutarch tells the
							same sort of thing about C. Marius in his <hi rend="italics">Life</hi>,
							chap. vii. (409 B).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="33">
               <p>He found more cause for pride in his working quite as hard as anybody, and in
						his mastery over himself, rather than in his being king. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 198 E (8), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="34">
               <p>When he saw a lame Spartan going forth to war and asking where he could get a
						horse, Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">Don't you realize that war has need, not of
							those who run away, but of those who stand their ground ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 217 C, 234 E, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>: Valerius Maximus, iii. 7, ext. 8.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="35">
               <p>Being asked how he had fostered his great repute, he said, <q direct="unspecified">By showing
							contempt for death.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 216 C (18), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="36">
               <p>When someone desired to know why Spartans do battle amidst the sound of
						fifes, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that, as all keep step to the music, the cowardly
							and the brave may be plainly seen.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, v. 70; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 13. 8; Lucian, <hi rend="italics">On Dancing</hi>, 10; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, ii. 16 (37); Valerius Maximus, ii. 6.
							2.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="37">
               <p>When someone dwelt upon the great good fortune of the king of Persia, who was
						a very young man, Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">But even Priam at that time of
							life had not met with misfortune.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 113 E.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="38">
               <p>When he had brought a great part of Asia <pb id="v.3.p.261"/> under his
						control, he decided to march against the king himself, so that he might put
						an end to the king's spending his time in leisure and corrupting the popular
						leaders among the Greeks. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xv. (603 E): Xenophon,
								<hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iii. 5. 1, and iv. 1. 41, and <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 1. 7.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="39">
               <p>When he was summoned home by the Ephors because of the war declared against
						Sparta by the surrounding Greek states, influenced by the money which had
						been sent to them by the Persian, he said that the good commander ought to
						be subject to the command of the laws, and sailed away from Asia, leaving
						behind a great yearning for him among the Greeks there. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xv. (p. 603 E): Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 2. 1-3, and <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>,
							1. 36: Cornelius Nepos, xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus, 4.
								1-4.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="40">
               <p>Inasmuch as the Persian coinage was stamped with the figure of a bowman, he
						said, as he was breaking camp, that he was being driven out of Asia by the
						king with thirty thousand bowmen; for such was the number of gold pieces
						brought to Athens and Thebes through Timocrates and distributed among the
						popular leaders; and thus the people were stirred to hostilities against the
						Spartans. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xv. (604 C); <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Artaxerxes</hi>, chap. xx. (1021 D); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iii. 5. 1. Xenophon (<hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi>)
							says that the Persian gold went to Thebes, Corinth, and Argos, and the
							Athenians were eager for the war (naturally, as it was a war of revenge)
							without being bribed.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="41">
               <p>He wrote a letter in reply to the Ephors as follows : <q direct="unspecified">Agesilaus to
							the Ephors greeting. &ldquo; We hae conquered the maist pairt of
							Asia, and made the barbarians rin, an' in Ionia we hae built mony an
							armed camp. But gin ye bid me come back as ye hae set the limit, I'll
							come after the letter, or I'll mebbe get there afore it; for I rule, no
							for masel', but for the State and oor allies. <pb id="v.3.p.263"/> An a
							mori truly rules richt whan he gangs wi' the laws an the Ephors or
							whatever ither rulers there may be in the State.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The letter contains a suspicious number of words for a Laconic
							letter!</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="42">
               <p>When he had crossed the Hellespont and was marching through Thrace he made no
						request of any of the barbarian peoples, but sent to each to inquire
						whether, as he passed through their country, he should find it friendly or
						hostile. Nearly all received him in a friendly manner, and helped him on;
						but the people called Trallians, to whom as it is said even Xerxes gave
						gifts, demanded of Agesilaus, as the price for passing through their land,
						an hundred talents of silver and an equal number of women. And he, making
						fun of them, asked why they did not come at once to get all this, and,
						leading on his forces to where the Trallians were drawn up for battle, he
						engaged them, and, having routed them with great slaughter, he marched
						through. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nos. 42, 43, and 44 are to be found consecutively in nearly
							the same words in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>,
							chap. xvi. (604 D-E).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="43">
               <p>To the king of the Macedonians he sent to propound the same question; and
						when the king said that he would consider it, Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">Let
							him consider it, then, but we will be marching on.</q> Amazed at his
						boldness, and fearful, the king accordingly bade him advance as a friend.b
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="44">
               <p>Since the Thessalians were in alliance with his enemies, he ravaged their
						country. To Larissa, however, he sent Xenocles and Scythes to suggest an
						amicable agreement. But when these were seized and detained, the rest of his
						men bore it very ill, and thought that he ought to encamp about Larissa and
							<pb id="v.3.p.265"/> lay siege to it. But he declared that he would not
						lose either one of those men for the whole of Thessaly, and got them back by
						coming to terms with the enemy. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note <hi rend="italics">b</hi> on
							previous page.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="45">
               <p>When he learned that a battle had been fought in the vicinity of Corinth,
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 304 B.C. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 2. 18 ff.</note> and that only a
						very few of the Spartans had fallen, but a vast number of the Corinthians
						and Athenians and the others on their side, he was not observed to be
						overjoyful or elated at the victory, but with a very deep sigh said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Hech, sirs, for Greece, wha her ane sel' has killed sae mony men—as mony
							as micht pit doon a' the barbarians.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xv. (604 ); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>,
							191 A (6), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 3. 1, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 7.4; Diodorus, xiv. 86; Cornelius Nepos, xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 5. 2.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="46">
               <p>When the Pharsalians beset him and harassed his army, he routed them with
						five hundred horsemen, and set up a trophy at the foot of Mount Narthacium.
						And he was better satisfied with this victory than with all others, because
						he himself by his own efforts had built up this company of cavalry,
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 209 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> and with this
						alone he had overcome those who took the greatest pride in horsemanship.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xvi. (605 A); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 3. 3-9, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 2.
							2-5.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="47">
               <p>Diphridas <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One of the Ephors.</note> brought word to him from home that
						he should at once, as he passed by, invade Boeotia. It had been his purpose
						to do this later after making more adequate preparation, but he did not
						disobey those in authority, and, after sending for two divisions of the army
						in the field at Corinth, he entered Boeotia. At Coroneia he engaged <pb id="v.3.p.267"/> in battle Thebans, Athenians, Argives, Corinthians, and
						the two Locrian peoples, and, although he was in desperate straits by reason
						of the many wounds in his body, he was victorious in the greatest battle, as
						Xenophon says, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 3. 16, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 2. 9. Xenophon took part in the
							battle (<hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, v. 3. 6).</note> of those
						fought in his day. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chaps. xvii. and xviii. (605
							A-F); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 3. 15-20, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 2. 9-16.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="48">
               <p>After he returned home he made no change in anything touching his life and
						his manner of living on account of so many successes and victories.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xix. (606 B-C).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="49">
               <p>Seeing that some of the citizens thought themselves to be somebody and gave
						themselves great airs because they kept a racing stud, he persuaded his
						sister Cynisca to enter a chariot in the races at Olympia, for he wished to
						demonstrate to the Greeks that this sort of thing was no sign of excellence,
						but only of having money and being willing to spend it. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xx. (606 D); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 9. 6; Pausanias, iii. 8. 1-2; iii. 15. 1; v. 12. 5;
							vi. 1. 6; and the epigram in the <hi rend="italics">Greek
							Anthology</hi>, xiii. 16 (L.C.L. v. p. 10), which records Cynisca's
							victory. Fragments of the original inscription, which was cut on the
							pedestal on which the statue of Cynisca stood, were found in the
							excavations at Olympia. See J.G. Frazer, <hi rend="italics">Pausanias</hi>, iv. p. 3; or Pausanias, ed. Hitzig and Blumner, ii.
							p. 532.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="50">
               <p>He had with him Xenophon the philosopher, who was treated with marked
						consideration, and he urged Xenophon to send for his sons, and bring them up
						in Sparta, where they would be taught the fairest of all lessons-to rule and
						to be ruled. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xx. (606 D), and Diogenes Laertius,
							ii. 51 and 54.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="51">
               <p>On one other occasion he was asked what was the especial reason why the
						Spartans were fortunate above all other peoples, and he replied, <q direct="unspecified">
							Because they, above all others, make it their practice to rule and to be
							ruled.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 215 C, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>,
							chap. xxx. (58 C), and <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap.
							i. (596 D); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 2. 16.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.269"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="52">
               <p>After Lysander's death he found a huge association banded together, which
						Lysander, immediately after his return from Asia, had organized against him,
						and he set out to show up Lysander by pointing out what kind of a citizen he
						had been when he was alive. So, after reading a speech which had been left
						among Lysander's papers, the author of which was Cleon of Halicarnassus, and
						which Lysander had been intending to appropriate and deliver before the
						people on the subject of revolution and changing the form of government,
						Agesilaus wished to make it public. But when one of the aged men read the
						speech, and was frightened at its cleverness, and advised him not to
						disinter the dead Lysander, but rather to inter the speech along with him,
						he took the advice and did nothing. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.
								Moralia</hi>, 229 F, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. xxiv. (447 D), and chap.
							xxx. (450 E); <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xx. (606
							E).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="53">
               <p>Those who covertly opposed him he did not openly put to confusion, but
						managed to have some of them always sent out as generals and officers, and
						then he would proceed to demonstrate that they had proved themselves
						unprincipled and greedy in exercising their authority. Then later, when they
						were brought to trial, his role this time would be to help them and defend
						them at their trial; and thus he won their allegiance, and brought them over
						to his own side, so that there was nobody who opposed him. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xx. (606 F).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="54">
               <p>Somebody wanted him to write to his friends in Asia so that the petitioner
						might meet with right treatment there. <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> said Agesilaus,
							<q direct="unspecified">my friends of themselves do what is right, even if I do not
							write to them.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="55">
               <p>Somebody in a foreign land pointed out to Agesilaus the city wall, high
						towering and exceedingly massive in its construction, and asked Agesilaus
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes"> </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.271"/> if it looked grand to him. <q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> said
						Agesilaus, <q direct="unspecified">grand indeed, not for men though, but for women to live
							in.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 190 A, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 215 D, 230 C, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and
							Valerius Maximus, iii. 7, ext. 8.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="56">
               <p>When a man from Megara boasted greatly about his city, Agesilaus said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Young man, your words need a great power to back them.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The remark is usually attributed to Lysander; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap.
							xxii. (445 D); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 71 E, 190 E, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 229 C, <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
							Themistius, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi> xxvii. 334 C. The idea was
							originally expressed by Adeimantus to Themistocles in Herodotus, viii.
							61.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="57">
               <p>Things which he saw other people admiring he seemed not even to notice. For
						example, once upon a time Callippides, the tragic actor, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Famous for
							his impressive acting. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 3. 11; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Poetics</hi>, chap. 26; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>,
							348 E; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, vi. 10.</note>
						who had a name and repute among the Greeks, and was received everywhere with
						the most flattering attention, first of all put himself in front of
						Agesilaus and addressed him, and then pompously thrust himself into the
						company that was walking with him, thus making it plain that he expected the
						king to begin some friendly conversation, and finally he said, <q direct="unspecified">Your
							Majesty, do you not recognize me, and have you not heard who I am ?
						</q> At that Agesilaus looked towards him and said, <q direct="unspecified">Are ye no
							Callippidas the shawman ?</q> That is what the Spartans call the
						strolling players. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxi. (607 D).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="58">
               <p>When he was invited to hear the man who imitated the nightingale's voice, he
						begged to be excused, saying, <q direct="unspecified">I hae heard the bird itsel' mony a
							time.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxi. (607 E); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 B; <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xx. (52 E). A similar remark is attributed to
							Pleistarchus, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 231 C, <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="59">
               <p>Menecrates the physician, who, because of his success in curing certain
						persons who had been given up to die, had come to be called Zeus, used to
						drag <pb id="v.3.p.273"/> in this title on all occasions, and even went so
						far in his effrontery as to write to Agesilaus in this fashion : <q direct="unspecified">
							Menecrates Zeus to King Agesilaus, health and happiness.</q>
						Agesilaus did not read any further, but wrote in reply, </p>
               <p>
						            <q direct="unspecified">King Agesilaus to Menecrates, health andsanity!</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 191 A (5), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxi. (607 E). Ascribed to Philip of Macedon by
							Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xii. 51, and Athenaeus,
							289 B.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="60">
               <p>When Conon and Pharnabazus with the Great Kings fleet were masters of the sea
						and blockaded the Spartans' coast, and the walls of Athens had been rebuilt
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 393 B.C. (Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 8.
							10).</note> with the money provided by Pharnabazus, the Spartans made
						peace with the king. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The peace of Antalcidas, 387 B.C. (Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica,</hi> v. 1. 29; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Artaxerxes</hi>, chap. xxi. (1022 A)).</note>
						They sent one of their citizens, Antalcidas, to Tiribazus, and surrendered
						into the king's power those Greeks in Asia Minor for whose freedom Agesilaus
						had fought. It follows, therefore, that Agesilaus could not have had the
						slightest thing to do with this disreputable business; for Antalcidas was at
						enmity with him, and employed every resource in working for the peace,
						because he felt that the war made Agesilaus great and enhanced his repute
						and importance. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxiii. (608 C).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="61">
               <p>Yet, in answer to a man who said that the Spartans were becoming pro-Persian,
						Agesilaus said that rather the Persians were becoming pro-Spartan !
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 608 D; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
							Artaxerxes</hi>, chap. xxi. (1022 C).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="62">
               <p>Being asked once which was better of the virtues, bravery or justice, he said
						that there is no use for bravery unless justice is also in evidence, and <pb id="v.3.p.275"/> if all men should become just they would have no need
						of bravery. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 190 F (3), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxiii. (608 F).</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="63">
               <p>The inhabitants of Asia were accustomed to give to the king of Persia the
						title of The Great,' but Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">In what, pray, is he
							greater than I. unless he is more just and more self-controlled ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 F (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="64">
               <p>He used to say that the inhabitants of Asia were poor freemen, but good
						slaves. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> 190 F (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="65">
               <p>Being asked how one might most surely have a good name among men, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">If one say what is best and do what is most honourable.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="66">
               <p>He used to say that a general ought to be possessed of boldness towards the
						enemy and kind ness towards the men under him. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, liv. 49, adds, <q direct="unspecified">and reasoning power
							to meet crises.</q>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="67">
               <p>When someone desired to know what boys ought to learn, he said, <q direct="unspecified">That
							which they will use when they become men.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Leotychidas (224 D, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>) and Aristippus
							(diogenes Laertius, ii. 80) expressed the same opinion, which has been
							repeated <hi rend="italics">ad nauseam</hi> by professors of
							paedagogy.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="68">
               <p>Once when he was sitting as judge the accuser spoke well and the defendant
						poorly, merely repeating in answer to each point, <q direct="unspecified">Agesilaus, a king
							must uphold the laws;</q> whereat Agesilaus said, <q direct="unspecified">And if
							somebody had broken into your house, and if somebody had robbed you of
							your coat, should you expect that the builder of the house or the maker
							of the coat would come to your assistance ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="69">
               <p>After the peace was made, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The peace of Antalcidas, 387 B.C. See <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 213 A-B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> a letter from the king of Persia was brought to him,
						of which the <pb id="v.3.p.277"/> Persian with Gallias the Spartan was the
						bearer, in regard to hospitality and friendship; but Agesilaus would not
						receive it, bidding the man to take back word to the king that there was no
						need to send letters to him personally; that if the king showed himself to
						be a friend to Sparta and well disposed towards Greece, he himself, to the
						very best of his power, would be a friend to the king. But if the king
						should be caught plotting against Greece, he went on to say, <q direct="unspecified">even if
							I receive many letters, let him not believe that he shall have me for a
							friend.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap.xxiii. (608 F); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 8. 3 (in almost the same words as here); Aelian,
								<hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, x. 20.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="70">
               <p>He was unusually fond of children, and it is said that at home he used to
						mount astride a stick as a hobby-horse and play with his children when they
						were little. But when he was seen thus by one of his friends, he begged the
						man to tell nobody before he had children of his own. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxv. 610 C): Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia
								Historia</hi>, xii. 15. Diogenes Laertius and Valerius Maximus
							(viii. 8, ext. 1), tell this story of Socrates.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="71">
               <p>He made war continually upon the Thebans, and when he was wounded in the
						battle, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the invasion of Boeotia in 378 B.C.</note> they say that
						Antalcidas exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">This is a fine reward which you are receiving
							from the Thebans for giving them lessons in fighting when they had no
							desire to fight, and no knowledge even of fighting !</q> For, as a
						fact, they say that the Thebans at that time were more warlike than they had
						ever been before, owing to the many campaigns of the Spartans against them.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxvi. (610 D); <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Pelopidas</hi>, cap. xv. (285 D); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>,
							227 C, <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note> It was for this reason that
						Lycurgus of old, in his so-called ' Decrees,' forbade campaigning frequently
						against the same peoples, so that these should not learn to make war.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiii. (47 D), <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 F, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, i. 16. 2.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.279"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="72">
               <p>When he heard once that the allies had come to be disaffected because of the
						continual campaigning (for they in great numbers followed the Spartans who
						were but few), wishing to bring their numbers to the proof, he gave orders
						that the allies all sit down together indiscriminately and the Spartans
						separately by themselves; and then, through the herald, he commanded the
						potters to stand up first; and when these had done so, he commanded the
						smiths to stand up next, and then the carpenters in turn, and the builders,
						and each of the other trades. As a result, pretty nearly all of the allies
						stood up, but of the Spartans not a single one; for there was a prohibition
						against their practising or learning any menial calling. And so Agesilaus,
						with a laugh, said, <q direct="unspecified">You see, men, how many more soldiers we send out
							than you do.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxvi. (610 E); Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, ii. 1. 7.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="73">
               <p>In the battle of Leuctra many Spartans ran away to escape the enemy, and
						these were liable to disgrace as provided by the law. The Ephors, seeing the
						State bereft of men when it was in great need of soldiers, wished to do away
						with the disgrace, and also to observe the laws. Accordingly they chose
						Agesilaus as lawgiver; and he, coming into the public meeting, said, <q direct="unspecified">
							I would not become a lawgiver to enact another set of laws, for in the
							present laws I would make no addition, subtraction, or revision. It is
							good that our present laws be in full force, beginning with the
							morrow.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxx. (612 F): and the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 C (10), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="74">
               <p>Although Epameinondas came on with such <pb id="v.3.p.281"/> an overwhelming
						tide, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The expression is that of Theopompus, as Plutarch tells us in
							his <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxi. (613
							B).</note>and the Thebans and their allies were boasting mightily over
						the victory, nevertheless Agesilaus kept him out of the city and made him
						turn back, although the number of persons in the city was very small.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, vii. 5. 10; Diodorus, xv. 83; Cornelius Nepos,
							xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 6. 1-3.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="75">
               <p>In the battle of Mantineia he urged the Spartans to pay no attention to any
						of the others, but to fight against Epameinondas, for he said that only men
						of intelligence are valiant and may be counted upon to bring victory; if,
						therefore, they could make away with that one man, they would very easily
						reduce the others to subjection; for these were unintelligent and worthless.
						And so it came to pass. For while the victory rested with Epameinondas, and
						the rout of the enemy was complete, as he turned and was cheering on his
						men, one of the Spartans struck him a fatal blow; and when he had fallen,
						Agesilaus's men, rallying from their flight, made the victory hang in the
						balance, and the Thebans showed themselves far inferior, and the Spartans
						far superior. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="76">
               <p>When Sparta was in need of money for war, and was supporting a mercenary
						force, Agesilaus set out for Egypt, having been summoned by the king of the
						Egyptians for a goodly remuneration. But because of the simplicity of his
						clothes he came into contempt among the people there; for they had been
						expecting that they should see the king of Sparta, like the king of Persia,
						with his person magnificently apparelled-a sorry opinion for them to hold
						regarding kings. At any rate, he showed them, before they <pb id="v.3.p.283"/> were done with him, that the proper way to acquire greatness and
						distinction is by understanding and manly virtues. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>,
							chap. xxxvi. (616 B); Cornelius Nepos, xvii., <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, 7. 2.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="77">
               <p>When he saw that his men were on the point of capitulating, for fear of the
						oncoming danger because of the vast number of the enemy (two hundred
						thousand) and the small number with him, he determined, before drawing up
						the battle-line, to forestall this by a plan unknown to the others. And upon
						his hand he wrote the word victory with the letters turned towards the left.
						Then, as he received the liver from the priest, he placed it on the hand
						which had the writing upon it. Holding it for rather a long time, he showed
						perplexity, and kept up a pretence of not knowing what to do, until the
						marks of the letters had been taken up by the liver and imprinted upon it.
						Then he exhibited it to those who with him were to engage in the struggle,
						saying that the gods through the letters had revealed victory. So his men,
						feeling that they had a sure sign that they were to overcome the enemy,
						became bold for the battle. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar trick of Alexander's is told by
							Frontinus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, i. 11. 14.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="78">
               <p>While the enemy were digging a ditch to surround his position (as they could
						do by reason of their vast numbers), and Nectanabis, with whom he was
						allied, was insistent upon a sortie and a decisive battle, Agesilaus said
						that he would not hinder the enemy in their desire to put themselves on
						equal terms with the defenders. And when the trench lacked but little of
						completion, he drew up his men in the open space between the ends, and,
						fighting with equal numbers against equal numbers, <pb id="v.3.p.285"/> he
						routed the enemy with great slaughter by means of few soldiers with him, and
						sent home much money for the State. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
							Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxxix. (618
							A), <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 C (11), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="79">
               <p>On his way home from Egypt death came to him, and in his last hours he gave
						directions to those with him that they should not cause to be made any
						sculptured or painted or imitative representation of his person. <q direct="unspecified">For
							if I have done any goodly deed, that shall be my memorial; but if not,
							then not all the statues in the world, the works of menial and worthless
							men, will avail.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 191 D (12), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>AGESIPOLIS, SON OF CLEOMBROTUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Agesipolis II., king of Sparta, 371-270
						B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Agesipolis, son of Cleombrotus, when somebody said that Philip in a few days
						had razed Olynthus to the ground, said, <q direct="unspecified">By Heaven, he will not build
							another like it in many years !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 40 E and 458 B.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When someone else remarked that he while king had been made hostage with
						those in the prime of life, and not their children or their women, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">That is but just, for it is good that we ourselves should bear
							the consequences of our own mistakes.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When he wished to send for some dogs from home, and someone said, <q direct="unspecified">
							There is no such export permitted from there,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Nor was there of men before this; but now it has been done !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>AGESIPOLIS, SON OF PAUSANIAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, 394-380 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Agesipolis, the son of Pausanias, when the Athenians <pb id="v.3.p.287"/>
						offered to accept the city of Megara as arbitrator regarding some complaints
						which they had each against the other, said, <q direct="unspecified">It is a shame, men of
							Athens, that those who have held the hegemony of the Greeks should know
							less about justice than the Megarians.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>AGIS, SON OF ARCHIDAMUS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Agis II., king of Sparta, 427-401 B.C. Some of
						the sayings attributed to him here should doubtless be assigned to the
						younger Agis (Agis III.).</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Once upon a time the Ephors said to Agis the son of Archidamus, <q direct="unspecified">Take
							the young men and march against the country of this man here. He will
							himself guide you to its citadel.</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">And how, sirs,</q> said Agis, <q direct="unspecified">is it right to entrust so
							many youths to a man who is betraying his own country ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 E (2), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, where the saying is attributed to the
							younger Agis.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Being asked what form of instruction was most in vogue in Sparta, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Knowledge of how to rule and to be ruled.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 212 C (51), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>He said that the Spartans did not ask c how many are the enemy,' but ' where
						are they ? ' <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 C (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When, at Mantineia, he was not permitted to risk a decisive battle with the
						enemy, who outnumbered his men, he said, <q direct="unspecified">He who would rule over many
							must fight with many.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 C (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When someone inquired how many Spartans there were, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Enough
							to keep all bad men away.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 D (5), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>As he was going about among the walls of the Corinthians and observed that
						they were high and <pb id="v.3.p.289"/> towering and vast in extent, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">What women live in that place ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>When a lecturer said, <q direct="unspecified">Speech is the most important thing of
							all,</q> he retorted, <q direct="unspecified">Then if you are silent, you are of no
							worth at all !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>When the Argives, after their defeat, met him again with greater boldness,
						and he saw that his allies were greatly perturbed, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Do not
							be afraid, men; for when we who are victorious are frightened, what do
							you think those vanquished by us are doing ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>In answer to the ambassador from Abdera, who, after winding up a long
						discourse, asked him what report he should make to his people at home, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Report that during all the time you wanted to speak I listened
							in silence.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 232 E (2), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>When some commended the people of Elis because they were very just in
						conducting the Olympic games, he said, <q direct="unspecified">What great or marvellous
							accomplishment is it if they practise justice on one day only in four
							years ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 C (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>In answer to those who said that some members of the other royal house
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Spartans had wo kings and consequently two royal
							families.</note> were jealous of him he said, <q direct="unspecified">So then, their own
							ill fortune will make them miserable and, besides that, the good fortune
							of myself and of my friends.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>When someone proffered the advice that they ought to give a passage-way to
						those of the enemy who were fleeing, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This was a part of the tactics of
							Agesilaus according to Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>,
							ii. 1. 4. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 2. 22 and iv. 3. 19.</note> he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							And how, if we do not <pb id="v.3.p.291"/> fight those who because of
							cowardice are fleeing, shall we fight those who because of bravery stand
							their ground ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>When someone brought forward a plan, for the freedom of the Greeks, which,
						while not lacking idealism, was difficult to put into practice, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Your words, my friend, need the backing of power and money.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same idea which is expressed in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>,
							212 E (56), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>When someone said that Philip would make Greece forbidden ground to them, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">It is quite enough, my friend, for us to go and come within
							the confines of our own land.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This remark must have been made by the younger Agis (Agis III.)</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>An ambassador who had come from Perinthus to Sparta made a long harangue; and
						when he had stopped speaking and asked Agis what report he should make to
						the people of Perinthus, Agis said, <q direct="unspecified">What else except that it was
							hard for you to stop speaking, and that I said nothing ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 232 E (2), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="16">
               <p>He came alone on an embassy to Philip, and when Philip exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">
							What is this ? Have you come all alone ?</q>, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes,
							for I came to only one man.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This remark also must be assigned to the younger Agis, <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 233 (29), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and 511 A, where an unnamed Spartan makes this retort
							to Demetrius.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="17">
               <p>When one of the elderly men said to him in his old age, inasmuch as he saw
						the good old customs falling into desuetude, and other mischievous prae
						tices creeping in, that for this reason everything was getting to be
						topsy-turvy in Sparta, Agis said humorously, <q direct="unspecified">Things are then but
							following a logical course if that is what is happening; for when I was
							a boy, I used to hear from my father that everything was topsy-turvy
							among them; and my father said that, <pb id="v.3.p.293"/> when he was a
							boy, his father had said this to him; so nobody ought to be surprised if
							conditions later are worse than those earlier, but rather to wonder if
							they grow better or remain approximately the same.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The latter part of this has been suspected on account of the length.
							For the sentiment <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> 276-277; Horace, <hi rend="italics">Odes</hi>, iii. 6. 46;
							Aratus, <hi rend="italics">Phaenomena</hi>, 123-127.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="18">
               <p>Being asked how one could be a free man all his life, he said, <q direct="unspecified">By
							feeling contempt for death.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 210 F (35), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>THE YOUNGER AGIS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Agis III., king of Sparta, <hi rend="italics">338-331
							B.C.</hi>
               </note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>The younger Agis, when Demades said that the jugglers who swallow swords use
						the Spartan swords because of their shortness, retorted, <q direct="unspecified">But all the
							same the Spartans reach their enemies with their swords.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 191 E (1).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In answer to a base man who asked repeatedly who was the best Spartan, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">The one most unlike you.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 D (4).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>THE LAST AGIS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Agis IV., king of Sparta, 245-241 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Agis, the last of the kings of Sparta, was arrested as the result of
						treachery and condemned by the Ephors without a trial. As he was being led
						away to the halter he saw one of the officers weeping, and said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Stop your weeping for me, man. For in spite of my being put to death in
							such defiance of law and justice, I am superior to those who are taking
							my life.</q> With these words he willingly offered his neck for the
						noose. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Agis</hi>, chaps. xix.-xx. (p. 803 C).</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.295"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>ACROTATUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Son of Cleomenes II. He died before his father, and so never
						became king.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Acrotatus, when his parents claimed it was his duty to co-operate with them
						in some unjust action, spoke in opposition up to a certain limit. But when
						they insisted, he said, <q direct="unspecified">While I was with you, I had not the
							slightest idea of justice; but since you have surrendered me to our
							country and its laws, and, besides, have had me instructed in justice
							and honourable conduct so far as lay in your power, I shall try to
							follow these rather than you. And since your wish is for me to do what
							is best, and since what is just is best both for a private citizen, and
							much more so for a ruler, I will do what you wish; but as for what you
							propose I shall beg to be excused.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> a similar remark of Agesilaus, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 534 D.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>ALCAMENES, SON OF TELECLUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, 779-742 B.C. (the date is
						uncertain).</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Alcamenes, the son of Teleclus, when somebody inquired how a man could best
						keep a kingdom secure, said, <q direct="unspecified">If he should not hold his own advantage
							too high.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When another person sought to know the reason why he did not accept gifts
						from the Messenians, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because if I took the gifts, it would
							be impossible to maintain peace with impartial regard for the
							laws.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone said that he lived a straitened life while possessed of plenty
						of property, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, for it is a noble thing for one who
							possesses much to live according to reason and not according to his
							desires.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.297"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>ANAXANDRIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 560-520
						B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Anaxandridas, the son of Leo. in answer to a man who took much to heart the
						sentence imposed upon him of exile from the country, said, <q direct="unspecified">My good
							sir, be not downcast at being an exile from your country but at being an
							exile from justice.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>To a man who told the Ephors of things that were needful, but spoke at
						greater length than would have sufficed, he said, <q direct="unspecified">My friend, in
							needless time you dwell upon the need !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to Leo, the father of Anaxandridas, in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 224 F (3), and to Leonidas, the son of Anaxandridas,
							in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xx. (52
							B).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone inquired why they put their fields in the hands of the Helots,
						and did not take care of them themselves, he said, <q direct="unspecified">It was by not
							taking care of the fields, but of ourselves, that we acquired those
							fields.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone else said that high repute works injury to men and that he who
						is freed from this will be happy, he retorted, <q direct="unspecified">Then those who commit
							crimes would, according to your reasoning, be happy. For how could any
							man, in committing sacrilege or any other crime, be concerned over high
							repute ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When another person asked why the Spartans, in their wars, ventured boldly
						into danger, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because we train ourselves to have regard for
							life and not, like others, to be timid about it.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When someone asked him why the elders continue the trials of capital cases
						over several days, and why, even if the defendant is acquitted, he is none
						the less still under indictment, he said, <q direct="unspecified">They take many days to
							decide, because, if they make an error in a capital case, there can be
							no reversal of <pb id="v.3.p.299"/> the judgement; and the accused
							continues, perforce, to be under indictment of the law, because, under
							this law, it may be possible, by deliberation, to arrive at a better
							decision.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the fact <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, chap. xxvii. (37 A); Thucydides, i. 132.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>ANAXANDER, SON OF EURYCRATES <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta in the earlier part of the
						seventh century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Anaxander, the son of Eurycrates, when someone inquired why the Spartans did
						not amass money in the public treasury, said, <q direct="unspecified">So that those made the
							guardians of it may not become corrupt.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>ANAXILAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Son of Archidamus, perhaps one of the arbiters between Athens
						and Megara over Salamis, seventh century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Anaxilas, in answer to the man who wondered why the Ephors did not rise and
						offer their places to the kings,d and this, too, although they were
						appointed to their position by the kings, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
							Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 15. 6; and
							Nicolaus quoted by Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, xliv.
							41 <hi rend="italics">ad fin.</hi>
                  </note>said, <q direct="unspecified">For the very same
							reason that they hold the office of Ephor.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>ANDROCLEIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Possibly the opponent of Lysander, mentioned in Plutarch's
							<hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. viii. (437
					C).</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Androcleidas the Spartan, who had a crippled leg, enrolled himself among the
						fighting-men. And when some persons were insistent that he be not accepted
						because he was crippled, he said, <q direct="unspecified">But I do not have to run away, but
							to stay where I am when I fight the opposing foe.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 210 F (34), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="14">
            <head>ANTALCIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When Antalcidas was being initiated into the mysteries at Samothrace, he was
						asked by the priest <pb id="v.3.p.301"/> what especially dreadful thing he
						had done during his life, and he replied, <q direct="unspecified">If any such deed has been
							committed by me, the gods themselves will know it.</q>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same
							sotry is told of Lysander in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 229 D
							(10), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and of an unknown Spartan in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 236 D (68), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In answer to the Athenian who called the Spartans unlearned, he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							At any rate we are the only people who have learned no evil from
							you.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192 B (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When another Athenian said to him, <q direct="unspecified">You must admit that we have many a
							time put you to rout from the Cephisus,</q> he retorted, <q direct="unspecified">But
							we have never put you to rout from the Eur o t as.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192 C (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Being asked how anybody could best make himself agreeable to people, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">If his conversation with them is most pleasant and his
							suggestions most profitable.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 213 C (65), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When a lecturer was about to read a laudatory essay on Heracles, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Why, who says anything against him ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192 C (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When Agesilaus was wounded in battle by the Thebans, Antalcidas said to his
						face, <q direct="unspecified">You have your just reward for the lessons in fighting you have
							given to that people who had no desire to fight and no knowledge even of
							fighting.</q> For it appeared that they had been made warlike by the
						continual campaigns of Agesilaus against them. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 F (5),
								<hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>He used to say that the young men were the walls of Sparta, and the points of
						their spears its boundaries. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on
								<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 210 E (28, 29, 30), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>In answer to the man who sought to know why the Spartans use short daggers in
						war, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because we fight close to the enemy.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 E, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.303"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="15">
            <head>ANTIOCHUS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Antiochus, when he was Ephor, hearing that Philip had given the Messenians
						their land, asked if he had also provided them with the power to prevail in
						fighting to keep it. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192
							B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="16">
            <head>AREUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Areus I., king of Sparta, 309-265 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Areus, when some men commended, not their own wives, but certain wives of
						other men, said, <q direct="unspecified">By Heaven, there ought to be no random talk about
							fair and noble women, and their characters ought to be totally unknown
							save only to their consorts.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 220 D and 242 E, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Thucydides, ii. 45.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Once upon a time, when he was passing through Selinus in Sicily, he saw
						inscribed upon a monument this elegiac couplet: Here at Selinus these men,
						who tyrc.nny strove to extinguish, Brazen-clad Ares laid low; nigh to our
						gates were they slain. Whereupon he said, <q direct="unspecified">You certainly deserved to
							die for trying to extinguish tyranny when it was ablaze; rather you
							ought to have let it burn itself out completely.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xx. (52 E).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="17">
            <head>ARISTON <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, <hi rend="italics">circa</hi>, 560-510
						B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When someone commended the maxim of Cleomenes, who, on being asked what a
						good king ought to do, said, <q direct="unspecified">To do good to his friends and evil to
							his enemies,</q> Ariston said, <q direct="unspecified">How much better, <pb id="v.3.p.305"/> my good sir, to do good to our friends, and to make
							friends of our enemies ?</q> This, which is universally conceded to
						be one of Socrates' maxims, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But not quite in these words; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, i.
							chap. ix. (335 B ff.), <hi rend="italics">Crito</hi>, chap. x. (49 A
							ff.), <hi rend="italics">Gorgias</hi>, 469 A-B and 475 B-D.</note> is
						also referred to Ariston. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar remark is attributed to Cleobulus
							by Diogenes Laertius, i. 91.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When someone inquired how many Spartans there were in all, he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Enough to keep away our enemies.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 D (5), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When one of the Athenians read a memorial oration in praise of those who fell
						at the hands of the Spartans, he said, <q direct="unspecified">What kind of men, then, do
							you think ours must be who vanquished these ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps the remark of another man named Ariston who lived
							later.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>ARCHIDAMIDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Archidamidas, in answer to a man who commended Charillus because he was
						gentle towards all alike, said, <q direct="unspecified">And how could any man be justly
							commended if he be gentle towards the wicked ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 55 E and 537 D.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When somebody found fault with Hecataeus the sophist because, when he was
						received as a member at the common table, he spoke not a word, Archidamidas
						said, <q direct="unspecified">You do not seem to realize that he who knows how to speak
							knows also the right time for speaking.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xx. (52 C).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>ARCHIDAMUS, SON OF ZEUXIDAMUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Archidamus II., king of Sparta, 469-427
						B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Archidamus, the son of Zeuxidamus, when someone inquired of him who were at
						the head of Sparta, said, <q direct="unspecified">The laws and the magistrates in accordance
							with the laws.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.307"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In answer to a man who praised a harper and expressed amazement at his
						ability, he said, <q direct="unspecified">My good sir, what honours shall you be able to
							offer to good men when you have such praise for a harper ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone, in introducing a musician to him, remarked, <q direct="unspecified">This man is
							a good musician,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">And in this country of ours
							that man there rates as a good soup-maker,</q> thus implying that
						there was no distinction between giving pleasure through the sound of
						instruments and giving it through the preparation of appetizing foods and
						soup. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 223 F, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> (15), where the saying is attributed to
							Cleomenes.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When somebody promised him to make the wine pleasant to the taste, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">What for ? For more of it will be used, and it will make the
							men's eating together less beneficial.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 240 D (2), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, which makes the meaning of this passage quite
							clear.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>As he was establishing his camp hard by the city of Corinth, he saw hares
						start up from a spot near the wall. He said therefore to his fellowsoldiers,
							<q direct="unspecified">The enemy are ours.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar remark is attributed to Lysander in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 E, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 229 D, <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When two persons accepted him as arbiter, he took them to the sacred precinct
						of Athena of the Brazen House, and made them swear to abide by his decision;
						and when they had given their oaths, he said, <q direct="unspecified">My decision, then, is
							that you are not to leave this sacred precinct before you compose your
							differences.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>When Dionysius, the despot of Sicily, sent costly raiment to Archidamus's
						daughters, he would not accept it, saying, <q direct="unspecified">I am afraid that, if the
							girls should put it on, they would appear ugly to me.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 D (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.309"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>Observing that his son was fighting impetuously against the Athenians, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Either add to your strength, or subtract from your
							courage.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="20">
            <head>ARCHID AM US, SON OF AGESILAUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Archidamus III., king of Sparta, 361-338
						B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Archidamus, the son of Agesilaus, when Philip after the battle of Chaeroneia,
						wrote him a somewhat haughty letter, wrote in reply, <q direct="unspecified">If you should
							measure your own shadow, you would not find that it has become any
							greater than before you were victorious.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Being asked how much land the Spartans controlled, he said, <q direct="unspecified">As much
							as they can reach with the spear.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 210 E (28), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Periander, the physician, was distinguished in his profession and commended
						very very highly, but was a writer of wretched verses. <q direct="unspecified">Why in the
							world, Periander,</q> said Archidamus, <q direct="unspecified">do you yearn to be
							called a bad poet instead of a skilful physician?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>In the war against Philip, when some proffered the advice that they ought to
						engage him in battle at a good distance from their own land, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The
							policy of Demosthenes (<hi rend="italics">e.g. Olynthiac</hi> i. <hi rend="italics">ad fin</hi>.).</note> Archidamus said, <q direct="unspecified">No,
							that is not what we ought to look to, but where, in fighting, we shall
							be superior to the enemy.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>In answer to those who commended him when he had been victorious in battle
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <q direct="unspecified">tearless battle</q> in 368 B.C. described by Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, vii. 1. 28-32. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
							Agesilaus</hi>
                  </note> against the Arcadians, he said, <q direct="unspecified">It would
							have been better if we had vanquished them by intelligence rather than
							by strength.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.311"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When he invaded Arcadia, he learned that the Eleans were supporting the
						Arcadians, and so he sent this letter to them : <q direct="unspecified">Archidamus to the
							Eleans. Quiet is a good thing.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The saying is attributed to Periander by Diogenes Laertius, i.
							97.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>In the Peloponnesian war, when his allies sought to know how much money would
						be sufficient, and said it was only fair that he set a limit to their
						contributions, he said, <q direct="unspecified">War does not feed on fixed rations.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 A, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>. The saying
							plainly belongs to Archidamus II. (218 C, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>), who lived at the time of the Peloponnesian war. See
							Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Cleomenes</hi>, chap. xxvii. (817
							E).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>When he saw the missile shot by a catapult, which had been brought then for
						the first time from Sicily, he exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">Great Heavens ! man's
							valour is no more !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 191 D, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>When the Greeks were not willing to take his advice and break their
						agreements with Antipater <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Either Antipater (Wyttenbach's certain
							emendation) or Antigonus (MSS.) is too late for Archidamus III., who
							died in 338 B.C.</note> and Craterus the Macedonian, and be free,
						because of a feeling that the Spartans would be harsher than the
						Macedonians, he said, <q direct="unspecified">A sheep or a goat bleats always in the same
							way, but a man talks in a great variety of ways until he accomplishes
							what he has set his mind upon.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="21">
            <head>ASTYCRATIDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> When someone said to Astycratidas, after the defeat of Agis their king in
						the battle against Antipater in the vicinity of Megalopolis, <q direct="unspecified">What
							will you do, men of Sparta ? Will you be subject to the Macedonians ?
						</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">What! Is there any way in which Antipater can
							forbid us to die fighting for Sparta ?</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.313"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="22">
            <head>BIAS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It seems almost certain that this anecdote is the same as that told
						of Anaxibius by Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, iv. 8. 32-39,
						but if so, the name is out of alphabetical order, and the mistake must be
						ancient. </note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Bias, caught in an ambush by Iphicrates the Athenian general, and asked by
						his soldiers what was to be done, said, <q direct="unspecified">What else except for you to
							save your lives and for me to die fighting ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="23">
            <head>BRASIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Brasidas caught a mouse among some figs, and, when he got bitten, let it go.
						Then, turning to those who were present, he said, <q direct="unspecified">There is nothing
							so small that it does not save its life if it has the courage to defend
							itself against those who would lay hand on it.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> (1).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In a battle he was wounded by a spear which pierced his shield, and, pulling
						the weapon out of the wound, with this very spear he slew his foe. Asked how
						he got his wound, he said, <q direct="unspecified">'Twas when my shield turned
							traitor.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> (2).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>As he was going forth to war he wrote to the Ephors, <q direct="unspecified">What I wull to
							dae I'll dae as regairds the war or be a deid mon.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When it came to pass that he fell in trying to win independence for the
						Greeks who were living in the region of Thrace, the committee which was sent
						to Sparta waited upon his mother Argileonis. Her first question was whether
						Brasidas had come to his end honourably; and when the Thracians spoke of him
						in the highest terms, and said that there was no other like him, she said,
							<q direct="unspecified">You have no knowledge of that, sirs, being from abroad; for
							Brasidas was <pb id="v.3.p.315"/> indeed a good man, but Sparta has many
							better than he was.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 B (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="24">
            <head>DAMONIDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Damonidas, being assigned to the last place in the chorus by the director,
						exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">Good ! You have discovered, sir, how this place which is
							without honour may be made a place of honour.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="25">
            <head>DAMIS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Damis, with reference to the instructions sent from Alexander that they
						should pass a formal vote deifying him, said, <q direct="unspecified">We concede to
							Alexander that, if he so wishes, he may be called a god.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia
								Historia</hi>, ii. 19.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="26">
            <head>DAMINDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> When Philip invaded the Peloponnesus, and someone said, <q direct="unspecified">There is
							danger that the Spartans may meet a dire fate if they do not make terms
							with the invader,</q> Damindas exclaimed,<q direct="unspecified">You poor womanish
							thing! What dire fate could be ours if we have no fear of death ?
						</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="27">
            <head>DERCYLIDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Dercylidas, when Pyrrhus had his army near Sparta,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 272 B.C.</note>
						was sent to him as ambassador; and when Pyrrhus stated that they must
						receive their king Cleonymus, or they would find out that they were no
						braver than any of the rest, Dercylidas interrupted to say, <q direct="unspecified">If this
							man is a god, we do not fear him, for we are guilty of no wrong; but if
							he is a man, he is surely not superior to us.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.317"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="28">
            <head>DEMARATUS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 510 until 491
						B.C., when he was deposed and went to Persia. In 490 B.C. he accompanied
						Xerxes in his invasion of Greece.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Demaratus, when Orontes had talked to him rather haughtily and someone
						remarked, <q direct="unspecified">Orontes has treated you haughtily, Demaratus,</q>
						said, <q direct="unspecified">He has committed no fault against me; for it is those who talk
							to please that do harm, not those who talk with hatred at heart.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When someone asked why they visited disgrace upon those among them who lost
						their shields, but did not do the same thing to those who lost their helmets
						or their breastplates, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because these they put on for their
							own sake, but the shield for the common good of the whole line.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>As he was listening to a musician, he said, <q direct="unspecified">He seems to do his silly
							task fairly well.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar remarks in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 220 F (6) and 234 D (42), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>In a council meeting he was asked whether it was due to foolishness or lack
						of words that he said nothing. <q direct="unspecified">But a fool,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">
							would not be able to hold his tongue.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar remark of Bias in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 503 F, and of Solon in Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, xxxiv. 15.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When someone inquired why he was an exile from Sparta, being a king, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Because her laws are more powerful than I am.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When one of the Persians, by unremitting bribery, had got away from him his
						beloved youth, and said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Ho, Spartan, I have captivated your
							beloved,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Not you, I swear, but you have bought
							and paid for him !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>When one of the Persians deserted from the king and was persuaded by
						Demaratus to change <pb id="v.3.p.319"/> his mind and return, and the king
						was going to have him put to death, Demaratus said, <q direct="unspecified">For shame, your
							Majesty ! To think that when this man was your enemy you could not
							punish him for his desertion but now that he has become your friend, you
							would put him to death !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>In answer to a man who was a parasite of the king and often jeered at him
						over his exile, he said, <q direct="unspecified">I have no quarrel with you, my friend; for
							I have squandered my position in life.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="29">
            <head>ECPREPES</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Ecprepes, an Ephor, cut out with an adze two of the nine strings of Phrynis
						the musician, saying, <q direct="unspecified">Do not murder music.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is repeated in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Agis</hi>, chap. x. (799 F), and with variaions in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 84 A, 238 C (<hi rend="italics">infra</hi>); Athenaeus 636 E; Boethius, <hi rend="italics">De
								Musica</hi>, i. 1.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="30">
            <head>EPAENETUS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Epaenetus said that liars are to blame for all sins and crimes. </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="31">
            <head>EUBOEDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Euboedas, on hearing some men praising the wife of another man, could not
						stomach it, saying, <q direct="unspecified">In regard to a woman's endowments there should
							be absolutely no talk among those outside the family.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 217 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="32">
            <head>EUDAMIDAS, SON OF ARCHIDAMUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eudamidas I., king of Sparta, 330-300 (?)
						B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Eudamidas, the son of Archidamus and the brother of Agis, seeing Xenocrates
						in the Academy, <pb id="v.3.p.321"/> already well oil in years, discussing
						philosophy with his acquaintances, inquired who the old man was. Somebody
						said that he was a wise man and one of the seekers after virtue. <q direct="unspecified">And
							when will he use it,</q> said Eudamidas, <q direct="unspecified">if he is only now
							seeking for it?</q> a </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Hearing a philosopher discoursing to the effect that the wise man is the only
						good general, he said, <q direct="unspecified">The speech is admirable, but the speaker is
							not to be trusted; for he has never been amid the blare of
							trumpets.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Xenocrates had been expounding his theme, and had just reached the
						stopping-point when Eudamidas arrived. One of the persons with him remarked,
							<q direct="unspecified">Just when we arrive he comes to the stopping-point.</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">Quite properly so,</q> said Eudamidas, <q direct="unspecified">if he has already
							said all he wanted to say.</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">It would have been nice to hear him,</q> said the other. <q direct="unspecified">
							Indeed,</q> said Eudamidas, <q direct="unspecified">and if we came to a man who had
							just dined, should we insist that he eat another dinner ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Someone inquired why, when the citizens professed to be all for war against
						the Macedonians, he himself decided in favour of keeping the peace. He
						replied, <q direct="unspecified">Because I do not need to prove that they are lying.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When another man brought up their brave successes against the Persians, and
						was urgent for the war, Eudamidas said, <q direct="unspecified">You do not seem to realize
							that your proposition is the same as fighting fifty wolves after
							overcoming a thousand sheep !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When a certain musician made a great hit, they asked Eudamidas what he
						thought of the man, and he replied, <q direct="unspecified">He has great power to charm in a
							trifling matter.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes"> </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.323"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>When someone praised Athens, he said <q direct="unspecified">And who could praise that city
							deservedly, towards which nobody has ever felt any affection for having
							been made a better man by it ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>When a man from Argos said that the Spartans became more unscrupulous on
						going abroad and being out of the control of their long-established laws,
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">Lions at home, but foxes abroad</q> was proverbial. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Comparison of
								Lysander and Sulla</hi>, chap. iii. (476 E).</note> he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							But you, when you come to Sparta, do not become worse, but
							better.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>When Alexander caused proclamation to be made at Olympia that all exiles
						might return to their own land, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 323 B.C. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, xviii. 8.</note> save only the Thebans,
						Eudamidas said, <q direct="unspecified">The proclamation for you, men of Thebes, is
							unfortunate, but very complimentary; for it is you only that Alexander
							fears.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>Being asked for what purpose they offered sacrifice to the Muses before
						hazardous ventures, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that our deeds may find good
							words.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 238 B, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>,
							chap. xxi. (53 D).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="33">
            <head>EURYCRATIDAS, SON OF ANAXANDRIDAS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably Eurycratidas, son of
						Anaxander, mentioned by Herodotus, vii. 204, in the genealogy of Leonidas.
						He was king of Sparta in the first half of the sixth century
					B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Eurycratidas, the son of Anaxandridas, when someone inquired why the Ephors
						try cases involving contracts <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle,
								<hi rend="italics">Politics</hi>, iii. 1, 10 (1275 b).</note> each
						day, said, <q direct="unspecified">So that also amid our enemies we may trust one
							another.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="34">
            <head>ZEUXIDAMUS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably the son of Leotychidas II., king of Sparta (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 224 E). He died before his father, and so
						never became king.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When someone inquired why they kept the laws in regard to bravery unwritten,
						and did not have <pb id="v.3.p.325"/> them written down and thus give them
						to the young men to read, Zeuxidamus said, <q direct="unspecified">Because the young ought
							to accustom themselves to deeds of manly valour, a better thing than to
							apply their mind to writings.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When a certain Aetolian asserted that, for those who are able to play the
						part of real men, war is better than peace, Zeuxidamus said, <q direct="unspecified">By
							Heaven, no; but for such men death is better than life.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="35">
            <head>HERONDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Herondas was at Athens when a man there was found guilty on a charge of not
						having any occupation, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the subject see Busolt, <hi rend="italics">Griechische Staatskunde</hi> (Munich, 1926), p. 815.</note> and,
						when he heard of this, he bade them point out to him the man who had been
						convicted of the freeman's crime ! <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
							Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xxiv. (54 E).
							The free population of Sparta did no labour.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="36">
            <head>THEARIDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Thearidas, as he was whetting his sword, was asked if it was sharp, and he
						replied, <q direct="unspecified">Sharper than slander.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="37">
            <head>THE M ISTE AS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Themisteas foretold to Leonidas, the king, the coming destruction both of
						himself and of his fellowsoldiers at Thermopylae, for he was a prophet. He
						was sent away by Leonidas to Sparta, on the pretext of announcing there what
						would come to pass, but in reality so that he should not suffer death with
						the rest. He, however, would not brook this, but said, <q direct="unspecified">I was sent
							out to fight, not to carry messages.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A somewhat different version is to be found in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 866 C. The original is in Herodotus, vii. 221, where
							the seer's name is given as Megistias.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.327"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="38">
            <head>THEOPOMPUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta at the time of the first Messenian war, eighth
						(?) century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Theopompus, in answer to a man who asked how anyone could keep a kingdom most
						securely, said, <q direct="unspecified">If he concede to his friends their just share of
							frank speech, and, so far as lies in his power, do not suffer any of his
							subjects to be wronged.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In answer to a man from abroad who said that among his own citizens he was
						called a lover of Sparta, he said, <q direct="unspecified">It would be better to be called a
							lover of your own country than a lover of Sparta.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When the ambassador from Elis said that his citizens had sent him for the
						especial reason that he alone emulated the Spartan way of living, Theopompus
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Is your way of living or that of the other citizens better ?
						</q> And when the man said that his own was, Theopompus said, <q direct="unspecified">
							How, then, can that State be saved in which, among many citizens, only
							one is a good man ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone said that Sparta was saved through its kings, because they were
						competent to rule, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Not so, but through its citizens,
							because they are obedient to the rulers.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 816 E, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xxx. (58 D).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When the people of Pylos voted him some unusually high honours, he wrote in
						reply that time increases modest honours, but obliterates those that are
						extravagant. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When someone pointed out to him a wall, and inquired if it was strong and
						high, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Is it not a place where women live ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 190 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi> This paragraph is not found in some MSS.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.329"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="39">
            <head>THORYCION</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Thorycion, arriving from Delphi and seeing in the Isthmus the forces of
						Philip, who had already gained possession of the narrow entrance, said,
							<q direct="unspecified">The Peloponnesus has poor gate-keepers in you, men of Corinth !
						</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="40">
            <head>THECTAMENES</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Thectamenes, when the Ephors condemned him to death, went away smiling.
						Someone among the bystanders asked him if he felt such contempt for the laws
						of Sparta. <q direct="unspecified">No,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">but I rejoice to think that
							I must pay this penalty myself without begging or borrowing anything
							from anybody.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan
								Disputations</hi>, i. 42 (100).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="41">
            <head>HIPPODAMUS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The attempt has been made to identify Hippodamus with the
						Hippodamus mentioned in Athenaeus, 452 A and in Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, ii. 15, and, by emendation, to
						reconcile this passage with the time of Agis IV.; but both Agis II. and Agis
						III. had fathers named Archidamus, and it is quite possible that the
						incident of sending away from danger the old man and the young heir to the
						throne took place as here narrated.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Hippodamus, when Agis was taking his place on the field of battle beside
						Archidamus, was sent with Agis to Sparta to render his services there.
							<q direct="unspecified">But look you,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">I shall meet no more
							honourable death than in playing the part of a brave man for Sparta's
							sake.</q> (He was over eighty years old.) And thereupon, seizing his
						arms and taking his stand at the king's right hand, he fell fighting. </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="42">
            <head>HIPPOCRATIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The name occurs in Herodotus, viii. 131, as one of the
						earlier kings of Sparta.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>This is the answer of Hippocratidas to the governor of Caria who wrote a
						letter to him because <pb id="v.3.p.331"/> a man from Sparta had been privy
						to the plot of certain conspirators, and had said nothing about it; and the
						governor added a line, asking how he should deal with him. Hippocratidas
						wrote in reply : <q direct="unspecified">If you have done him any great favour, put him to
							death; but if not, expel him from your country, for he is a poltroon so
							far as any virtue is concerned.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When a youth with a lover in attendance met him one day, and turned colour,
						he said, <q direct="unspecified">You ought to walk with persons such that when you are seen
							with them you shall keep the same complexion.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="43">
            <head>CALLICRATIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Upright and straightforward Spartan who commanded the
						Spartan fleet at the battle of Arginusae in 406 B.C. He was killed in the
						battle.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Callicratidas, an admiral, when Lysander's friends made him a fair offer that
						he permit them to make away with one of their enemies and receive ten
						thousand pounds, although he was in sore need of money for rations for his
						sailors, would not consent. Cleander, who was a member of his council, said,
							<q direct="unspecified">But I would take it, if I were you.</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">And so would I,</q> said Callicratidas, <q direct="unspecified">if I were you !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the reply of Alexander, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 180 C (11).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When he came to Cyrus the Younger at Sardis (who was allied with the
						Spartans) to get money for his fleet, on the first day he bade them send in
						word that he wished to have an audience with Cyrus. But when he was told
						that Cyrus was busy drinking, he said, <q direct="unspecified">I will wait till he has
							finished drinking.</q> And at that time he withdrew, when he
						realized that it was not possible to meet Cyrus on that day, thus creating
						the impression that he was somewhat lacking in manners. On the succeeding
						day, when he was again told that Cyrus was drinking and would not come
						forth, he said, <q direct="unspecified">We must not be so eager to <pb id="v.3.p.333"/> get
							money as to do anything unworthy of Sparta,</q> and withdrew to
						Ephesus, invoking many evil curses on those who were first wantonly treated
						by the barbarians and had taught the barbarians to be arrogant because of
						wealth. And he swore to the persons present that, just so soon as he should
						arrive at Sparta, he would do everything to bring about a reconciliation
						among the Greeks, that they might become more formidable to the barbarians,
						and cease begging them for their resources to use against one another.
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life
								of Lysander</hi>, chap. vi. (436 C); Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, i. 6. 6-7.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Being asked what kind of men the lonians were, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Poor freemen,
							but good slaves.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 F (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When Cyrus sent on money to pay the soldiers, and special presents for
						himself as a token of friendship, he took the money only and sent back the
						presents, saying that there was no need of any private friendship between
						him and Cyrus, but the general friendship which had been contracted with all
						the Spartans would serve also for him. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.
								Moralia</hi>, 213 D (69), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>As he was about to engage in the naval battle at Arginusae, Hermon the pilot
						said that it would be well to sail away, for the ships of the Athenians were
						many more in number; but Callicratidas said, <q direct="unspecified">And what of that ? To
							flee is a disgrace and an injury to Sparta. No; to stay here, be it
							death or be it victory, is best.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, i. 6. 32; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De
								officiis</hi>, i. 24 (84).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>As he offered sacrifice before the battle, and heard from the seer that the
						indications of the omens were victory for the army, but death for its
						commander, he said, not at all disconcerted, <q direct="unspecified">Sparta's <pb id="v.3.p.335"/> fate rests not with one man. For, if I am killed,
							my country will not be impaired in any way; but if I yield to the enemy,
							it will be.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Pelopidas</hi>, chap. ii. (177 D).</note> And so, after appointing
						Cleander to take his place as commander, he put forth without delay for the
						naval engagement, and met his death in the battle. </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="44">
            <head>CLEOMBROTUS, SON OF PAUSANIAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, 380-371 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Cleombrotus, the son of Pausanias, when a man from abroad was disputing with
						Cleombrotus's father about excellence, said, <q direct="unspecified">My father is a better
							man than you&mdash;until you too have become a father.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 227 F (14), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
							Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xv. (48 C).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="45">
            <head>CLEOMENES, SON OF ANAXANDRIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, <hi rend="italics">circa</hi>, 517-488 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Cleomenes, the son of Anaxandridas, said that Homer was the poet of the
						Spartans, and Hesiod of the Helots; for Homer had given the necessary
						directions for fighting, and Hesiod for farming. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xiii.
							19.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Having made an armistice of seven days with the Argives, he kept a watch on
						them, and on the third night, when they were sleeping because of their
						reliance on the truce, he attacked them, and slew some and took the others
						prisoners. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De
								officiis</hi>, i. 10 (33). Herodotus, vi. 78-79 (followed by other
							writers), relates that Cleomenes defeated the Argives by a
							different.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When he was reproached for his violation of his oath, he said that he had not
						included the nights as well as the days in his plighted word; and anyway,
						whatever ill one can do to one's enemies is regarded, among both gods and
						men, as something vastly higher than justice. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the phrase <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Electra</hi>,
							584; and Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides,
							no. 758.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.337"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>It was his fortune to be repulsed from Argos, to gain which he had violated
						the truce, owing to the women's taking down the weapons in the shrines and
						defending themselves against him with these. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.
								Moralia</hi>, 245 D, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Pausanias, ii.
							20. 8; Polyaenus, viii. 33.</note> Later he went out of his mind, and,
						getting hold of a small dagger, he slashed himself, beginning with his
						ankles until he reached the vital parts, and thus departed this life
						laughing and grinning. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, vi. 75
							and 84; Athenaeus, 427 C; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia
							Historia</hi>, ii. 41. His madness was traditionally ascribed to
							over-indulgence in strong drink.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>The seer tried to dissuade him from leading his army against the city of the
						Argives, for the return, he said, would be made in disgrace. But when
						Cleomenes had advanced near the city, and saw the gates closed and the women
						upon the walls, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Does it seem to you that the return from
							here can be made in disgrace, where, since the men are dead, the women
							have barred the gates ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>In answer to those of the Argives who upbraided him as an impious perjurer,
						he said, <q direct="unspecified">You have the power to speak ill of me, but I have the power
							to do ill to you.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>To the ambassadors from Samos who urged him to make war upon the despot Poly
						crates, and for this reason spoke at great length, he said, <q direct="unspecified">What you
							said at the beginning I do not remember; for that reason I do not
							comprehend the middle part; and the conclusion I do not approve.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, iii. 46, and the note on 216 A
							(15), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi> The traditional date of the mission
							from Samos (525 B.C.) seems to early to fall within Cleomenes's reign,
							but the chronology is uncertain.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>A certain pirate overran the country, and, when he was captured, said,
							<q direct="unspecified">I had not the means to provide subsistence for my soldiers;
							therefore, to <pb id="v.3.p.339"/> those who had it, but would not
							willingly give it, I came with the purpose of taking it by
							force.</q> To this Cleomenes said, <q direct="unspecified">Villainy is curt.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>When a certain low fellow spoke ill of him, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So it is for
							this reason, is it, that you speak ill of everyone, that we, busied in
							defending ourselves, may not have time to speak of your baseness ?
						</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>When one of the citizens said that the good king ought to be mild at all
						times and in every way, he remarked, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, but not to the extent of
							being despised.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>When he was afflicted with a lingering illness, and began to give attention
						to mind-healers and seers, to whom formerly he had given no attention,
						someone expressed surprise. <q direct="unspecified">Why are you surprised ?</q> said
						he; <q direct="unspecified">for I am not now the same man that I was, and, not being the
							same man, I do not approve the same things.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For a similar change in the attitude of Pericles and of Bion <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of
								Pericles</hi>, chap. xxxviii. (173 A) and Diogenes Laertius, iv.
							54.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>When a public lecturer spoke at considerable length about bravery, he burst
						out laughing; and when the man said, <q direct="unspecified">Why do you laugh, Cleomenes, at
							hearing a man speak about bravery, and that, too, when you are a king ?</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">Because, my friend,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">if it had been a
							swallow speaking about it, T should have done the same thing, but if it
							had been an eagle, I should have kept very quiet.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>When the people of Argos asserted that they would wipe out their former
						defeat <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably in the battle over Thyrea in 546 B.C. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, i. 82, and the reference in
							Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 89 C.</note> by fighting again,
						he said, <q direct="unspecified">I wonder if by the addition of a word of two syllables
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The word <q direct="unspecified">again.</q> They had lost in the previous
								fighting.</note> you have now become more powerful than you were
							before !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>When someone upbraided him, saying, <q direct="unspecified">You are inclined to luxury,
							Cleomenes,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Well, <pb id="v.3.p.341"/> that is
							better than being unjust. And you are avaricious although you possess
							property enough.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>When someone, wishing to introduce a musician to him, said, in addition to
						other commendations, that the man was the best musician among the Greeks,
						Cleomenes pointed to one of the persons near, and said, <q direct="unspecified">Yonder man,
							I swear, ranks with me as the best soup-maker.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 218 C (3) <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, where the saying is attributed to Archidamus II.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="16">
               <p>Maeandrius, the despot of Samos, because of the inroad of the Persians, fled
						to Sparta, and exhibited all the gold and silver vessels which he had
						brought with him, and offered to favour Cleomenes with as many as he wished;
						but he would have none, and, taking good care that the man should not
						distribute any among the rest of the citizens, he went to the Ephors and
						said that it was better for Sparta that his own friend and guest from Samos
						should withdraw from the Peloponnesus, so that he should not persuade anyone
						of the Spartans to become a bad man. And they listened to his advice and
						proclaimed the expulsion of Maeandrius that very day. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is
							taken from Herodotus, iii. 148, in part word for word.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="17">
               <p>When someone said, <q direct="unspecified">Why have you not killed off the people of Argos
							who wage war against you so often ?</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Oh, we
							would not kill them off, for we want to have some trainers for our young
							men.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="18">
               <p>When somebody inquired of him why Spartans do not dedicate to the gods the
						spoils from their enemies, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because they are taken from
							cowards.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 224 F (4), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.343"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="46">
            <head>CLEOMENES, SON OF CLEOMBROTUS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Cleomenes, the son of Cleombrotus, when someone offered him fighting cocks
						and said that they would die fighting for victory, said, <q direct="unspecified">Well then,
							give me some of those that kill them, for those are better than
							these.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="47">
            <head>LABOTAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An early king of Sparta.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Labotas, when someone spoke at very great length, said, <q direct="unspecified">Why, pray,
							such a big introduction to a small subject ? For proportionate to the
							topic should be the words you use.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 208 C (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="48">
            <head>LEOTYCHIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta in the seventh century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Leotychidas the First, when somebody remarked to him that he was very
						changeable, said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, because of varying occasion; not like all you
							because of your baseness.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>In answer to the man who asked how any man could best preserve his present
						state of good fortune, he said, <q direct="unspecified">By not trusting everything to
							chance.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Being asked what freeborn boys had best learn, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Those things
							which may help them when they become men.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 213 D (67), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone inquired for what reason the Spartans drank so little, he
							said,<q direct="unspecified">So that others may not deliberate over us, but we over
							others.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.345"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="49">
            <head>LEOTYCHIDAS, SON OF ARISTON <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Doubtless the son of Menares, Leotychidas
						II., king of Sparta, <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 491-469
					B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Leotychidas, the son of Ariston, in answer to a man who said that the sons of
						Demaratus were speaking ill of him, remarked, <q direct="unspecified">Egad, I don't wonder;
							for not one of them could ever speak a good word.</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same story is found in Diogenes Laertius, ii. 35 (of Socrates),
							and in Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, xix. 5 (of
							Plato).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When at the adjacent gate a snake had coiled around the key, and the
						soothsayers declared this to be a prodigy, he said, <q direct="unspecified">It doesn't seem
							so to me, but if the key had coiled around the snake, that would be a
							prodigy !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The saying is attributed to the others also; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromata</hi>,
							viii. 843 ed. Potter; or iii. 18, ed. Stahlin; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De divinatione</hi>, ii. 28 (62).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>This is his retort to Philip, the priest of the Orphic mysteries, who was in
						the direst straits of poverty, but used to assert that those who were
						initiated under his rites were happy after the conclusion of this life; to
						him Leotychidas said, <q direct="unspecified">You idiot! Why then don't you die as speedily
							as possible so that you may with that cease from bewailing your
							unhappiness and poverty ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, vi. 4, where the remark
							is attributed to Antisthenes.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone inquired why they did not dedicate to the gods the arms taken
						from the enemy, he said that property wrested from its owners owing to
						cowardice it is not good either for the young men to see, or to dedicate to
						the gods. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 224 B (18), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="50">
            <head>LEO, SON OF EURYCRATIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta in the first half of the seventh
						century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When Leo, the son of Eurycratidas, was asked what kind of a city one could
						live in so as to live most safely, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Where the inhabitants
							shall possess neither too much nor too little, and where right shall be
							strong and wrong shall be weak.</q>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.347"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Seeing that the runners at Olympia were eager to gain some advantage in
						starting, he said, <q direct="unspecified">How much more eager are the runners for a quick
							start than for fair play !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone, at an inappropriate time, discoursed about some matters which
						were not unprofitable, he said, <q direct="unspecified">My friend, in needless time you
							dwell upon the need !</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 216 F (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="51">
            <head>LEONIDAS, SON OF ANAXANDRIDAS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The hero of Thermopylae. These sayings were doubtless incorporated, or meant to be incorporated, in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Leonidas</hi>, according to what he says in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 866 B; and some of them may be found in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 854 E-874 D (<hi rend="italics">De Herodoti malignitate).</hi>
               </note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Leonidas, the son of Anaxandridas and the brother of Cleomenes, in answer to
						a man who remarked, <q direct="unspecified">Except for your being king, you are no different
							from the rest of us,</q> said, <q direct="unspecified">But if I were no better than
							you others, I should not be king.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>His wife Gorgo inquired, at the time when he was setting forth to Thermopylae
						to fight the Persian, if he had any instructions to give her, and he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">To marry good men and bear good children.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 240 E (6), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and 866 B.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When the Ephors said that he was taking but few men to Thermopylae, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Too many for the enterprise on which we are going.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid. Cf.</hi> also 225 B (8 and 9), <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and 866 B.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>And when again they said, <q direct="unspecified">Hae ye decided to dae aught else save to
							keep the barbarians from gettin' by?</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">Nominally that,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">but actually expecting to
							die for the Greeks.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When he had arrived at Thermopylae, he said to his comrades in arms, <q direct="unspecified">
							They say that the barbarian 
							<pb id="v.3.p.349"/> has come near and is comin' on while we are wastin'
							time. Truth, soon we shall either kill the barbarians, or else we are
							bound to be killed oursel's.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When someone said, <q direct="unspecified">Because of the arrows of the barbarians it is
							impossible to see the sun,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Won't it be nice,
							then, if we shall have shade in which to fight them ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The remark is attributed to Dieneces by Herodotus, vii. 226. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, vii. 46; Valerius Maximus, iii. 7, ext. 8; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 42 (101).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>When someone else said, <q direct="unspecified">They are near to us,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Then we also are near to them.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 194 D, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 234 B.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>When someone said, <q direct="unspecified">Leonidas, are you here to take such a hazardous
							risk with so few men against so many ?</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">If you
							men think that I rely on numbers, then all Greece is not sufficient, for
							it is but a small fraction of their numbers; but if on men's valour,
							then this number will do.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>When another man remarked the same thing he said, <q direct="unspecified">In truth I am
							taking many if they are all to be slain.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 225 A (3), <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 866 B.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>Xerxes wrote to him, <q direct="unspecified">It is possible for you, by not fighting against
							God but by ranging yourself on my side, to be the sole ruler of
							Greece.</q> But he wrote in reply, <q direct="unspecified">If you had any knowledge
							of the noble things of life, you would refrain from coveting others'
							possessions; but for me to die for Greece is better than to be the sole
							ruler over the people of my race.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>When Xerxes wrote again, <q direct="unspecified">Hand over your arms,</q> he wrote in
						reply, <q direct="unspecified">Come and take them.</q>

						            <pb id="v.3.p.351"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>He wished to engage the enemy at once, but the other commanders, in answer to
						his proposal, said that he must wait for the rest of the allies. <q direct="unspecified">
							Why,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">are not all present who intend to fight ?
							<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 185 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                     </note> Or do you not realize that the only men who fight against the enemy
							are those who respect and revere their kings ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>He bade his soldiers eat their breakfast as if they were to eat their dinner
						in the other world. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 42 (101); Valerius Maximus, iii. 2, ext. 3.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>Being asked why the best of men prefer a glorious death to an inglorious
						life, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because they believe the one to be Nature's gift but
							the other to be within their own control.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>Wishing to save the lives of the young men, and knowing full well that they
						would not submit to such treatment, he gave to each of them a secret
						dispatch, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The reference is to a well-known form of cipher message in use among the Spartans. A narrow leather thong was wrapped around a cylinder, and on the surface thus formed the message was written. When the thong was received it was applied to a duplicate cylinder kept by the recipient, and so the message was read.</note> and sent them to the Ephors. He conceived the desire to save also
						three of the grown men, but they fathomed his design, and would not submit
						to accepting the dispatches. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi> 866 B; and Herodotus, vii. 221, 229, 230.</note> One of them said,<q direct="unspecified">I carne with the
							army, not to carry messages, but to fight;</q> and the second,
							<q direct="unspecified">I should be a better man if I stayed here</q>; and the
						third, <q direct="unspecified">I will not be behind these, but first in the fight.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="52">
            <head>LOCHAGUS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Lochagus, the father of Polyaenides and Seiron, when word was brought to him
						that one of his sons was dead, said, <q direct="unspecified">I have known this long while
							that he was fated to die.</q>

						            <pb id="v.3.p.353"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="53">
            <head>LYCURGUS
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The reputed founder of the Spartan constitution. A brief account of his laws may be found also in Porphry, <hi rend="italics">De abstinentia</hi>, iv. 3 ff.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Lycurgus, the lawgiver, wishing to recall the citizens from the mode of
						living then existent, and to lead them to a more sober and temperate order
						of life, and to render them good and honourable men (for they were living a
						soft life), reared two puppies of the same litter; and one he accustomed to
						dainty food, and allowed it to stay in the house; the other he took afield
						and trained in hunting. Later he brought them into the public assembly and
						put down some bones and dainty food and let loose a hare. Each of the dogs
						made for that to which it was accustomed, and, when the one of them had
						overpowered the hare, he said, <q direct="unspecified">You see, fellow-citizens, that these
							dogs belong to the same stock, but by virtue of the discipline to which
							they have been subjected they have turned out utterly different from
							each other, and you also see that training is more effective than Nature
							for good.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 3 A.</note> 
               </p>
               <p> But some say that he did not bring in dogs which were of the same stock, but
						that one was of the breed of house dogs and the other of hunting dogs; then
						he trained the one of inferior stock for hunting, and the one of better
						stock he accustomed to dainty food. And afterwards, as each made for that to
						which it had become accustomed, he made it clear how much instruction
						contributes for better or worse, saying, <q direct="unspecified">So also in our case,
							fellow-citizens, noble birth, so admired of the multitude, and our being
							descended from Heracles does not bestow any advantage, unless we do the
							sort of things for which he was manifestly the most glorious and most
							noble of all mankind, and 
							<pb id="v.3.p.355"/> unless we practise and learn what is good our whole
							life long.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>He made a redistribution of the land, and assigned an equal share to all the
						citizens; and it is said that a while later, on returning from abroad, as he
						passed through the country, where the harvesting had just been finished, and
						saw the cocks of grain standing near together in even lines, he was much
						pleased, and said with a smile to those who were with him that it looked as
						if all the Spartan land belonged to many brothers who had recently divided
						it. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Related with more detail by Plutarch in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. viii. (44 A).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Having introduced the abolition of debts, he next undertook to divide equally
						all household furnishings, so as to do away completely with all inequality
						and disparity. But when he saw that the people were likely to demur about
						assenting to this outright spoliation, he decreed that gold and silver coin
						should in future have no value, and ordained that the people should use iron
						money only. He also limited the time within which it was lawful to exchange
						their present holdings for this money. When this had been done, all
						wrongdoing was banished from Sparta. For nobody was able to steal or to
						accept a bribe or to defraud or rob any more, when the result was something
						of which concealment was not possible, nor was its acquisition envied, nor
						its use without risk, nor its exportation or importation safe. As an added
						measure, he brought about the banishment from Sparta of everything not
						absolutely necessary. And, by reason of this, no merchant, no public
						lecturer, no soothsayer or mendicant priest, no maker of fancy articles ever
						made his way into 
						<pb id="v.3.p.357"/> Sparta. The reason was that he permitted no handy
						coinage to circulate among them, but instituted the iron coinage
						exclusively, which in weight was over a pound and a quarter, and in value
						not quite a penny. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch tells all this, at somewhat greater length, in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. ix. (440). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 7. 5 and 6; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Eryxias</hi>, 400 B; Pollux, <hi rend="italics">Onomasticon</hi>, vii. 105, and ix. 79; Justin, <hi rend="italics">Historiae Philippicae</hi>, iii. 2. 11-12.</note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Having determined to make an attack upon the prevailing luxury, and to do
						away with the rivalry for riches, he instituted the common meals. And in
						answer to those who sought to know why he had established these, and had
						divided the citizens, when under arms, into small companies, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">So that they may get their orders promptly, and, in case they
							cherish any radical designs, the offence may be confined to a small
							number; also that there may be for all an equal portion of food and
							drink, and so that not only in drink or food, but in bedding or
							furniture or anything else whatsoever, the rich man may have no
							advantage at all over the poor man.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch amplifies this account in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. x. (45 B). </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>Having made wealth unenviable, since nobody could make any use or show of it,
						he said to his intimate friends, <q direct="unspecified">What a good thing it is, my
							friends, to show in actual practice the true characteristic of wealth,
							that it is blind !</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> (45 C).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>He took good care that none should be allowed to dine at home and then come
						to the common meal stuffed with other kinds of food and drink. The rest of
						the company used to berate the man who did not drink or eat with them,
						because they felt that he was lacking in self-control, and was too soft for
						the common way of living. 
						<pb id="v.3.p.359"/> war, wished to dine at home with his wife on this one
						day, and sent for his allowance of food; but the military commanders would
						not send it; and the following day, when the matter was disclosed to the
						Ephors, he was fined by them. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xii. (46 C).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>The well-to-do citizens resented legislation of this type, and, banding
						together, they denounced him and pelted him, wishing to stone him to death.
						As he was being pursued, he rushed through the market-place; and he
						out-distanced almost all his pursuers, and gained refuge in the shrine of
						Athena of the Brazen House; only, as he turned around, Alcander, who was
						pursuing him, put out one of his eyes by a stroke of his staff. But when,
						later, Lycurgus received Alcander, who was handed over to him for punishment
						by vote of the people, he did not treat him ill nor blame him, but, by
						compelling him to live under the same roof with him, he brought it to pass
						that Alcander had only commendation for Lycurgus and for the manner of
						living which he had found there, and was altogether enamoured of this
						discipline. Lycurgus dedicated a memorial of his unhappy experience in the
						shrine of Athena of the Brazen House, and gave to her the added epithet of
						Optilletis; for the Dorians in this part of the world call the eyes ' optics
						(optilloi).' <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch tells the story more fully in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xi. (45 D-46 A); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xiii. 23, and Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, xix. 13.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>Being asked why he had not made any use of written laws, he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Because those who are trained and disciplined in the proper discipline
							can determine what will best serve the occasion.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiii. (47 A).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>At another time when some sought to know why he had ordained that the people
						should use only an axe in putting a roof on their houses, and make a 
						<pb id="v.3.p.361"/> door with a saw only and none of the other tools, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">So that the citizens may be moderate in regard to all the
							things which they bring into the house, and may possess none of the
							things which are the cause of rivalry among other peoples.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiii. (47 C), and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 E (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>It was because of this custom also that their first king Leotychidas, dining
						at somebody's house <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In Corinth, according to Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiii. (47 C); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 E, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note> and observing the construction of the ceiling, which
						was expensive and embellished with panels, asked his host if timbers grew
						square in their country ! </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>Being asked why he had prohibited frequent campaigns against the same foes,
						he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that they may not, by becoming accustomed to defending
							themselves frequently, become skilled in war.</q> It was for this
						reason also that there appeared to be no slight ground for complaint against
						Agesilaus, who by his almost continual inroads and campaigns into Boeotia
						had rendered the Thebans a match for the Spartans. At any rate Antalcidas,
						when he saw him wounded, exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">You have got a handsome reward
							as you deserve for your fostering care in teaching them to fight when
							they did not wish to fight and did not even know how.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiii. (47 D), and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 D, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>When someone else desired to know why he instituted strenuous exercise for
						the bodies of the maidens in races and wrestling and throwing the discus and
						javelin, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that the implanted stock of their offspring, by
							getting a strong start in strong bodies, may attain a noble growth, and
							that they themselves may with vigour abide the birth of their children
							and readily and nobly resist the pains 
							<pb id="v.3.p.363"/> of travail; and moreover, if the need arise, that
							they may be able to fight for themselves, their children, and their
							country.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiv. (47 F); Suidas, <hi rend="italics">Lexicon</hi>, under Lycurgus.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>When some persons expressed disapproval of the nudity of the maidens in the
						processions, and sought to know the reason for it, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that
							they, by following the same practices as the men, may not be inferior to
							them either in bodily strength and health or in mental aspirations and
							qualities, and that they may despise the opinion of the crowd.</q>
						Wherefore is recorded also in regard to Gorgo, the wife of Leonidas, a
						saying to this effect: when some woman, a foreigner presumably, remarked to
						her, <q direct="unspecified">You Spartan women are the only women that lord it over
							your'men,</q> she replied, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, for we are the only women
							that are mothers of men !</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 240 E (5) <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xiv. (47 E-48 B).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>By excluding the unmarried from looking on at the festival of the naked
						youth, and by laying upon them other additional disgrace, he created much
						concern about having children. He also deprived them of the honour and
						attention which the young bestowed on their elders. And nobody said a word
						against the remark which was made to Dercylidas, although he was a general
						and in high repute; for one of the younger men, as Dercylidas approached,
						did not rise to offer his seat, saying, <q direct="unspecified">No, for you are not the
							father of any son who will rise and offer his seat to me.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> chap. xv. (48 C); and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 223 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>When someone inquired why he had made a law that girls should be given in
						marriage without any dowry, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that some of them shall not
							be left unwedded because of lack of means, and some shall not be eagerly
							sought because of abundant wealth, but that each man, with an eye to the
							ways <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes"> </note>
							              <pb id="v.3.p.365"/> of the maid, shall make virtue the basis of his
							choice.</q> For this reason he also banished from the State all
						artificial enhancement of beauty. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, vi. 6.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="16">
               <p>He set limits to the time of marriage for both men and women, and, in answer
						to the man who inquired about this, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that the offspring
							may be sturdy by being sprung from mature parents.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xv. (48 D), and Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 1. 6.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="17">
               <p>In answer to a man who expressed surprise because he debarred the husband
						from spending the nights with his wife, but ordained that he should be with
						his comrades most of the day and pass the whole night in their company, and
						visit his bride secretly and with great circumspection, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So
							that they may be strong of body and never become sated, and that they
							may be ever fresh in affection, and that the children which they bring
							into the world may be more sturdy.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xv. (48 E), and Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 1. 5.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="18">
               <p>He banished perfume on the ground that it spoiled and ruined the olive oil, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">Quaestiones Naturales</hi>, iv. 13. 9. Perfumes in ancient times were made with a base of oil; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 127 B.</note>
						and also the dyer's art on the ground that it was a flattery of the senses.
					</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="19">
               <p>To all whose business was the enhancement of personal beauty he made Sparta
						forbidden ground, for the reason that they outraged the arts through the
						vileness of their art. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. ix. (p. 44 F).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="20">
               <p>So strict in those times was the virtue of the women, and so far removed from
						the laxity of morals which later affected them, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Athenaeus, 142 F, quotes Phylarchus at some length regarding the degeneration of the Spartans.</note> that in the earlier days
						the idea of adultery among them was an incredible 
						<pb id="v.3.p.367"/> thing. There is still recalled a saying of a certain
						Geradatas, a Spartan of the very early times, who, on being asked by a
						foreigner what was done to adulterers in their country, since he saw that
						there had been no legislation by Lycurgus on that subject, said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Sir, there is never an adulterer in our country.</q> But when the
						other retorted with, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, but if there should be ?</q>
						Geradatas said, <q direct="unspecified">His penalty is to provide an enormous bull which by
							stretching his neck over Mount Taygetus can drink from the river
							Eurotas.</q> And when the other in amazement said, <q direct="unspecified">But how
							could there ever be a bull of that size ?</q> Geradatas laughed and
						said, <q direct="unspecified">But how could there ever be an adulterer in Sparta, in which
							wealth and luxury and adventitious aids to beauty are held in disesteem,
							and respect and good order and obedience to authority are given the
							highest place ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In part this is in close agreement with Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xv. (49 C), but the main point, which is lacking in the MSS., is usually inserted here by the editors from the <hi rend="italics">Life</hi>, See the critical note 2.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="21">
               <p>In answer to the man who was insistent that he establish a democracy in the
						State Lycurgus said, <q direct="unspecified">Do you first create a democracy in your own
							house.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 E (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="22">
               <p>When someone inquired why he ordained such small and inexpensive sacrifices
						to the gods, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that we may honour the Divine powers
							without ceasing.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 172 B, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="23">
               <p>As he permitted the citizens to engage only in that kind of athletic contests
						in which the arm is not held up, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As a sign of defeat; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> E. Norman Gardiner, <hi rend="italics">Greek Athletic Sports and Festivals</hi>, (London, 1910), p. 415.</note> somebody inquired what was the reason.
							
						<pb id="v.3.p.369"/> He replied, <q direct="unspecified">So that no one of the citizens
							shall get the habit of crying quits in the midst of a hard
							struggle.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 189 E (4), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="24">
               <p>When someone asked why he ordered a frequent change of camping-place, he
							said,<q direct="unspecified">So that we may inflict greater injury upon our
							enemies.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 12. 5.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="25">
               <p>When someone sought to know why he forbade assaults on walled places, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">So that valiant men may not suffer death at the hands of a
							woman or a child or some such person.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Comparison of Lysander and Sulla</hi>, 477 D. As a matter of fact, the Spartans were quite without ability to attack a walled town, as is clear from Herodotus, ix. 70, and Thucydides, i. 102.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="26">
               <p>When some of the Thebans advised with him in regard to the sacrifice and the
						lamentation which they perform in honour of Leucothea, he advised them that
						if they regarded her as a goddess they should not bewail her, but if they
						looked upon her as a woman they should not offer sacrifice to her as to a
						goddess. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This saying of Xenophanes seems to have been attributed by someone to Lycurgus. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 171 E, 379 B, and 763 C; also Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, ii. 23. 27.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="27">
               <p>In answer to some of the citizens who desired to know, <q direct="unspecified">How can we
							keep off any invasion by enemies,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">If you remain
							poor, and no one of you desires to be more important than
							another.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xix. (52 B).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="28">
               <p>And at another time, when they raised a question about fortifications, he
						said that a city is not unfortified whose crowning glory is men and not
						bricks and stones. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 210 E (29), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="29">
               <p>The Spartans gave particular attention to their hair, recalling a saying of
						Lycurgus in reference to it, 
						<pb id="v.3.p.371"/> that it made the handsome more comely and the ugly more
						frightful. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 E (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="30">
               <p>He gave instructions that in war, when they had put the enemy to flight and
						had gained a victory, they should continue the pursuit only far enough to
						make their success assured, and then return immediately; for he said that it
						was neither a noble trait nor a Greek trait to slay those who had yielded,
						and this policy was not only honourable and magnanimous, but useful as well;
						for the opposing army, knowing that they customarily spared those who
						surrendered, but made away with those who resisted, would regard it as more
						profitable to flee than to stay. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xxii. (54 A); Thucydides, v. 73; Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, i. 16. 3.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="31">
               <p>When somebody inquired why he forbade spoiling the enemy's dead, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">So that the soldiers may not, by looking about covertly for
							spoil, neglect their fighting, but also that they may keep to their
							poverty as well as to their post.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 224 B (16), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="54">
            <head>LYSANDER</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When Dionysius, the despot of Sicily, sent costly garments for Lysander's
						daughters, he would not accept them, saying that he was afraid that because
						of them his daughters would appear ugly rather than beautiful. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 E (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> But a little
						later, when he was sent as ambassador to the same despot from the same
						State, Dionysius sent to him two robes and bade him choose whichever one of
						them he would, and take it to his daughter; but Lysander said that 
						<pb id="v.3.p.373"/> she herself would make a better choice, and, taking
						them both, he departed. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Lysander, who was a clever quibbler, and given to employing cunning
						deceptions to further most of his designs, counted justice as mere
						expediency, and honour as that which is advantageous. He said that the truth
						is better than falsehood, but that the worth and value of either is
						determined by the use to which it is put. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. vii. (437 A).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>In answer to those who blamed him because of his carrying out most of his
						designs through deception, which they said was unworthy of Heracles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The legendary ancestor of both lines of Spartan kings; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Herodotus, vii. 204 and viii. 131.</note> and
						gaining his successes by wile in no straightforward way, he said laughing
						that where he could not get on with the lion's skin it must be pieced out
						with the skin of the fox. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 E (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When others censured him for his violation of his oaths which he had made in
						Miletus he said that one must trick children with knuckle-bones, but men
						with oaths, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 330 F, where it is attributed to Dionysius; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 741 C; Diodorus, x. 9. 1; Dio Chysostom, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi>, lxxiv. (399 R., 640 M.); Polyaenus, <hi rend="italics">Strategemata</hi>, i. 45. 3; and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, vii. 12, who says that some attribute it to Lysander, and others to Philip of Macedon.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>He conquered the Athenians by a ruse at Aegospotami, and by pressing them
						hard through famine he forced them to surrender their city, whereupon he
						wrote to the Ephors, <q direct="unspecified">Athens is taken.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">According to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. xiv. (441 B), the Ephors objected to the verbosity of the dispatch!</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>In answer to the Argives, who were disputing with the Spartans in regard to
						the boundaries of their land and said that they had the better of the case,
			
						<pb id="v.3.p.375"/> he drew his sword and said, <q direct="unspecified">He who is master of
							this talks best about boundaries of land.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 E (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>Seeing that the Boeotians were wavering at the time when he was about to pass
						through their country he sent to them to inquire whether he should march
						through their land with spears at rest or ready for action. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. xxii. (445 D).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>When a Megarian in the common council used plain words to him, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">My friend, your words need a city to back them.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 F (5), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>When the Corinthians had revolted and he was going through their country
						along by the walls and saw that the Spartans were reluctant to attack, a
						hare was seen leaping across the ditch, whereupon he said, <q direct="unspecified">Are you
							not ashamed, men of Sparta, to be afraid of such enemies as these, who
							are so slack that hares sleep in the walls of their city ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 E (4), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>As he was consulting the oracle in Samothrace, the priest bade him tell what
						was the most lawless deed that had ever been committed by him in his
						lifetime. Lysander asked, <q direct="unspecified">Must I do this at your command or at the
							command of the gods ?</q> When the priest said, <q direct="unspecified">At the
							command of the gods,</q> Lysander said, <q direct="unspecified">Then do you take
							yourself out of my way, and I will tell them in case they
							inquire.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 217 C (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>When a Persian asked what kind of a government he commended most highly, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">The government which duly awards what is fitting to both the
							brave and the cowardly.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>In answer to a man who said that he commended him and was very fond of him,
						he said <q direct="unspecified">I have two oxen in a field, and although they 
							<pb id="v.3.p.377"/> both may utter no sound, I know perfectly well
							which one is lazy and which one is the worker.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>When someone was reviling him, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Talk right on, you miserable
							foreigner, talk, and don't leave out anything if thus you may be able to
							empty your soul of the vicious notions with which you seem to be
							filled.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>Some time after his death, when a dispute arose regarding a certain alliance,
						Agesilaus came to Lysander's house to examine the documents in regard to
						this, for Lysander had kept these at his own house. Agesilaus found also a
						book written by Lysander in regard to the government, to this effect: that
						the citizens should take away the kingship from the Eurypontids and the
						Agiads <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 231 C (1), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note> and put it up for election, and make their choice from the best
						men, so that this high honour should belong not to those who were descended
						from Heracles, but to men like Heracles, who should be selected for their
						excellence; for it was because of such excellence that Heracles was exalted
						to divine honours. This document Agesilaus was bent upon publishing to the
						citizens, and demonstrating what kind of a citizen Lysander had been in
						secret, and with the purpose also of discrediting the friends of Lysander.
						But they say that Cratidas, who at that time was at the head of the Ephors,
						anxious lest, if the speech should be read, it might convert the people to
						this way of thinking, restrained Agesilaus and said that he ought not to
						disinter Lysander, but to inter the speech along with him, since it was
						composed with a vicious purpose and in a plausible vein. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 212 C (52), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.379"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>The suitors of his daughters, when after his death he was found to be a poor
						man, renounced their obligations; but the Ephors punished them because when
						they thought he was rich they courted his favour, but when they found from
						his poverty that he was just and honest they disdained him. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lysander</hi>, chap. xxx. (451 A), and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, vi. 4, and x. 15.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="55">
            <head>NAMERTES</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Namertes was sent as an ambassador, and when one of the people in that
						country congratulated him because he had many friends, he asked if this man
						had any sure means of testing the man of many friends; and when the other
						desired to learn, Namertes said, <q direct="unspecified">By means of misfortune.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> John Heywood, <hi rend="italics">Proverbs</hi>, part. i. chap. 11: <q direct="unspecified">But indeede a friend is never known till a man have neede.</q>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="56">
            <head>NICANDER
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An early Spartan king, perhaps <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 809-770 B.C. He was the son of Charillus (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>).</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Nicander, when someone said that the Argives were speaking ill of him, said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Well then, they are paying the penalty for speaking ill of the
							good !</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">He was invading Argolis and laying waste the country; see Pausanias, iii. 7. 4.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When someone inquired why the Spartans wore their hair long and cultivated
						beards, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because for a man his own adornment is the very
							best and cheapest.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 F (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When one of the Athenians said, <q direct="unspecified">Nicander, you Spartans insist too
							much on your principle of doing no work,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Quite
							true; we do not make work of this thing or that thing in your haphazard
							fashion.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 348 F and 710 F; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 803 C-D. See also the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 221 C, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>

						            <pb id="v.3.p.381"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="57">
            <head>PANTHOEDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A Spartan harmost who fell at Tanagra, 377 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Panthoedas went on embassy to Asia and when they pointed out to him a very
						strong wall he said, <q direct="unspecified">By Heaven, strangers, fine quarters for women !
						</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When the philosophers in the Academy were conversing long and seriously, and
						afterwards some people asked Panthoidas how their conversation impressed
						him, he said, <q direct="unspecified">What else than serious ? But there is no good in it
							unless you put it to use.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 192 B, 220 D, and 1033 B-E.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="58">
            <head>PAUSANIAS,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Regent of Sparta from 479 B.C.; commander at Plataea.</note> THE SON OF CLEOMBROTUS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Pausanias, son of Cleombrotus, at the time when the people of Delos were
						asserting their rightful claims to the island against the Athenians, and
						said that according to the law <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The law seems to have been put into effect (426-425 B.C.) some years after the death of this Pausanias (468 B.C.).</note> which prevailed among them there were no
						births and no burials in the island, said, <q direct="unspecified">How can this be your
							native land in which no one of you has ever been born nor shall ever be
							hereafter ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, iii. 104.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When the exiles were inciting him to lead his army against the Athenians, and
						saying that, when his name was proclaimed at Olympia, they were the only
						people who hissed him, he said, <q direct="unspecified">What do you think that those who
							hissed when they were being well treated will do if they are treated ill
							?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar remark is attributed to Philip of Macedon in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 143 F, 179 A, and 457 F.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone inquired why the Spartans had 
						<pb id="v.3.p.383"/> made Tyrtaeus the poet a citizen, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So
							that a stranger shall never appear as our leader.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Tyrtaeus, according to tradition, was a native of Athens.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>In answer to the man who was weak in body, but was urging that they risk a
						battle against the enemy by both land and sea, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Are you
							willing to strip yourself and show what kind of a man you are&mdash;you who
							advise us to fight ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When some people were amazed at the costliness of the raiment found among the
						spoils of the barbarians, he said that it would have been better for them to
						be themselves men of worth than to possess things of worth. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 870 B; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Paradoxa Stoicorum, vi. 1-3 (42-52).</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>After the victory at Plataea over the Persians he ordered that the dinner
						which had been prepared for the Persians should be served to himself and his
						officers. As this had a wondrous sumptuousness, he said, <q direct="unspecified">By Heaven,
							the Persian was a greedy fellow who, when he had all this, came after
							our barley-cake.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ix. 82.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="59">
            <head>PAUSANIAS, THE SON OF PLEISTOANAX <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, 408-394 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Pausanias, the son of Pleistoanax, in answer to the question why it was not
						permitted to change any of the ancient laws in their country, said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Because the laws ought to have authority over the men, and not the men
							over the laws.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When, in Tegea, after he had been exiled, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 394 B.C.</note> he commended the Spartans, someone
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Why did you not stay in Sparta instead of going into exile ?
						</q> And he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because physicians, too, are wont to spend
							their time, not among the healthy, but where the sick are.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar saying which is attributed to Aristippus in Diogenes Laertius, ii. 70.</note>
						
						            <pb id="v.3.p.385"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When someone inquired of him how they could become able to conquer the
						Thracians, he said, <q direct="unspecified">If we should make the best man our
							general.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When a physician paid him a visit and said, <q direct="unspecified">You have nothing wrong
							with you,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">No, for I do not employ you as my
							physician.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When one of his friends blamed him because he spoke ill of a certain
						physician, although he had never had anything to do with him, and had not
						suffered any harm at his hands, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because if I had ever had
							anything to do with him I should not now be alive.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When the physician said to him, <q direct="unspecified">You have lived to be an old
							man,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">That is because I never employed you as my
							physician.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>He said that the best physician was the man who did not allow his patients to
						rot, but buried them quickly. </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="60">
            <head>PAEDARETUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Paedaretus, when someone said that the enemy were many in number,
							remarked,<q direct="unspecified">Then we shall be the more famous, for we shall kill
							more men.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>Seeing a certain man who was effeminate by nature, but was commended by the
						citizens for his moderation, he said, <q direct="unspecified">People should not praise men
							who are like to women nor women who are like to men, unless some
							necessity overtake the woman.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When he was not chosen as one of the three hundred, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, viii. 124; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 4. 3.</note> which was rated as the
						highest honour in the State, he went away cheerful and smiling; but when the
						Ephors called him back, and asked why he was laughing, he said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Because I congratulate 
							<pb id="v.3.p.387"/> the State for having three hundred citizens better
							than myself.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 191 F, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="61">
            <head>PLEISTARCHUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, 480-458 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Pleistarchus the son of Leonidas, in answer to one who asked him for what
						reason they did not take their titles from the names of the first kings,
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Because the first kings needed to be absolute monarchs, but
							those who followed them had no such need.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One of the two lines of the kings of Sparta was called <q direct="unspecified">Agids</q> (or <q direct="unspecified">Agiads</q>) from Agis, the second of that line, and the other <q direct="unspecified">Eurypontids</q> from Eurypon, the third of that line. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. ii. (40 D); Strabo, viii. 366; Pausanias, iii. 7. 1. Presumably Plutarch means that the later Spartan kings did not wish to perpetuate the memory of any harshness, which would have been suggested by the names of the earlier absolute monarchs.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When a certain advocate kept making jests, he said, <q direct="unspecified">You had better be
							on your guard, my friend, against jesting all the time, lest you become
							a jest yourself, just as those who wrestle all the time become
							wrestlers.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>In retort to the man who imitated a nightingale, he said, <q direct="unspecified">My friend,
							I have had more pleasure in hearing the nightingale itself.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 212 F (58), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone said that a certain evil-speaker was commending him, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">I wonder whether possibly someone may not have told him that I
							was dead; for the man can never say a good word of anybody who is
							alive.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 224 D (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="62">
            <head>PLEISTOANAX <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta, 458-408 B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Pleistoanax, the son of Pausanias, when an Attic orator called the Spartans
						unlearned, said, <q direct="unspecified">You are 
							<pb id="v.3.p.389"/> quite right, for we alone of the Greeks have
							learned no evil from you.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 192 B (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="63">
            <head>POLYDORUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">King of Sparta in the second part of the eighth century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Polydorus, the son of Alcamenes, when a certain man was continually making
						threats against his enemies, said, <q direct="unspecified">Don't you see that you are using
							up the best part of your vengeance ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>As he was leading out his army to Messene, someone asked him if he was going
						to fight against his brothers. He said that he was not, but was merely
						proceeding to the unassigned portion of the land. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>The Argives, after the battle of the three hundred, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, i. 82.</note> were again overcome,
						with all their forces, in a set battle, and the allies urged Polydorus not
						to let slip the opportunity, but to make a descent upon the enemy's wall and
						capture their city; for this, they said, would be very easy, since the men
						had been destroyed and the women only were left. He said in answer to them,
							<q direct="unspecified">To my mind it is honourable, when fighting on even terms, to
							conquer our opponents, but, after having fought to settle the boundaries
							of the country, to desire to capture the city I do not regard as just;
							for I came to recapture territory and not to capture a city.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>Being asked why the Spartans risked their lives so bravely in war, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Because they have learned to respect their commanders and not to
							fear them.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 217 A (5), and 227 D (12).</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.391"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="64">
            <head>POLYCRATIDAS</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Polycratidas was sent, along with others, as ambassador to the king's
						generals, and when these asked whether they were there as private citizens
						or had been sent as public representatives, he said, <q direct="unspecified">If we succeed,
							public; if not, private.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xxv. (55 C).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="65">
            <head>PHOEBIDAS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Spartan general, fourth century B.C.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> Phoebidas, before the hazardous engagement at Leuctra, when some remarked
						that this day would show the brave man, said that the day was worth much if
						it had the power to show the brave man. </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="66">
            <head>SOUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Third king of Sparta, second of the Eurypontid line according to tradition.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p> The story is told that Soils, being besieged by the Cleitorians in a rugged
						and waterless stronghold, agreed to give up to them the land which he had
						captured by the spear if all the men with him should drink from the
						neighbouring spring. This spring the enemy were guarding. When the oaths had
						been exchanged, he got together his men and offered the kingdom to the man
						who would not drink; however no one had the strength to resist, but they all
						drank; whereupon he came down after all the rest, and sprinkled himself, the
						enemy still being present, and went back and took possession of the land on
						the ground that he had not drunk. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. ii. (40 C).</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.393"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="67">
            <head>TELECLUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 190 A.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Teleclus, in answer to the man who said that Teleclus's father was speaking
						ill of him, said, <q direct="unspecified">If he had had no cause to speak, he would not have
							spoken.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When his brother said to him that the citizens did not comport themselves
						toward himself as they did toward the king (although he was of the same
						family), but with much less consideration, he said, <q direct="unspecified">The reason is,
							you do not know how to submit to injustice, and I do.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 190 A, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>Being asked why it was the custom among them for the younger men to rise up
						and give place to the elder, he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that, having this attitude
							regarding honour toward those who are not related to them, they may pay
							greater honour to their parents.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 237 D, <hi rend="italics">infra; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Sparta</hi>, 6, 1-3.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone inquired how much property he possessed, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Not
							more than enough.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="68">
            <head>CHARILLUS <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An early king of Sparta; traditionally a contemporary of Lycurgus. Another spelling is Charilaus.</note>
            </head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>Charillus, being asked why Lycurgus made so few laws, said, <q direct="unspecified">Because
							those who use few words have need of but few laws.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 189 F (1), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When someone inquired why they took their girls into public places unveiled,
						but their married women veiled, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Because the girls have to
							find husbands, and the married women have to keep to those who have them
							!</q>
					
						            <pb id="v.3.p.395"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>When one of the Helots conducted himself rather boldly toward him, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">If I were not angry, I would kill you.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 189 F (2), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>When someone asked him what he thought to be the best form of government, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">That in which the greatest number of citizens are willing,
							without civil strife, to vie with one another in virtue.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 154 E.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>When someone inquired why all the statues of the gods erected among them were
						equipped with weapons,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example Head, <hi rend="italics">Historia Numorum</hi> (Oxford, 911), p. 434.</note> he said, <q direct="unspecified">So that we may not put upon the
							gods the reproaches which are spoken against men because of their
							cowardice, and so that the young men may not pray to the gods
							unarmed.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>In answer to the man who inquired why they wore their hair long, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Because this is the natural and inexpensive form of
								ornament.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 189 F (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="69">
            <head>VARIOUS SAYINGS OF SPARTANS TO FAME UNKNOWN</head>
            <div2 type="section" n="1">
               <p>When the ambassadors of the Samians spoke at great length, the Spartans said
						to them, <q direct="unspecified">We hae forgot the first part, and the later part we did na
							ken because we hae forgot the first.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 216 A (15) <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="2">
               <p>When a speaker extended his remarks to a great length, and then asked for
						answers to report to his citizens, they said, <q direct="unspecified">Report that you found
							it hard to stop speaking and we to listen.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 216 A (15), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.397"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="3">
               <p>In answer to the Thebans who were disputing with them over some matters, they
						said, <q direct="unspecified">You should have less pride or more power.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 218 E (8), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="4">
               <p>A Spartan, being asked why he wore his beard so very long, said, <q direct="unspecified">So
							that I may see my grey hairs and do nothing unworthy of them.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="5">
               <p>Another, in answer to the inquiry, <q direct="unspecified">Why do you use short swords ?
						</q> said, <q direct="unspecified">So that we may get close to the enemy.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="6">
               <p>When someone was praising the Argive warriors, a Spartan said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes,
							at Troy ! <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A thousand years before.</note>
                  </q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="7">
               <p>Another, being told that some people after dining are forced to drink, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps because the reference is to the expression <foreign lang="greek">pro\s bi/an pi/nein</foreign> found in Alcaeus (No. 20 in Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 156), Sophocles (<hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 669 Nauck) and Aristophanes (<hi rend="italics">Acharnians</hi>, 73). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Menander, <hi rend="italics">The Arbitrants</hi>, lines 4-5 (in L.C.L. p. 18) where the same words are used.</note> said,
							<q direct="unspecified">What, and are they forced to eat also ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="8">
               <p>When Pindar wrote, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> No. 76 (ed. Christ).</note> 
                  <quote rend="blockquote">Athens the mainstay of Greece,</quote> a Spartan said that Greece
						was like to fall if it rested on any such mainstay as that! </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="9">
               <p>Someone on seeing a painting in which Spartans were depicted being slain by
						Athenians, kept repeating, <q direct="unspecified">Brave, brave Athenians.</q> A Spartan
						cut in with, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, in the picture !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="10">
               <p>To a man who was listening avidly to some spitefully slanderous remarks a
						Spartan said, <q direct="unspecified">Stop being so generous with your ears against me !
						</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar remark of Simonides quoted in Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, ii. 42.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="11">
               <p>To a man who was being punished, and kept saying, <q direct="unspecified">I did wrong
							unwillingly,</q> someone retorted, <q direct="unspecified">Then take your punishment
							unwillingly.</q>
					
						            <pb id="v.3.p.399"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="12">
               <p>Someone, seeing men seated on stools <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not in Sparta, of course.</note> in a privy, said, <q direct="unspecified">God forbid
							that I should ever sit where it is not possible to rise and yield my
							place to an older man.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xx. (52 F).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="13">
               <p>When some Chians, on a visit to Sparta, vomited after dinner in the hall of
						the Ephors, and befouled with ordure the very chairs in which the Ephors
						were wont to sit, the Spartans, first of all, instituted a vigorous
						investigation, lest possibly these might be citizens; but when they learned
						that they were, in fact, Chians, they caused public proclamation to be made
						that ' The Spartans grant permission to the Chians to be filthy.' <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar story is told of Clazomenians by Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, ii. 15.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="14">
               <p>When someone saw almonds of the hard sort <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example, Athenaeus, 53 A.</note> selling at double the price of
						others, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Are stones so scarce ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="15">
               <p>A man plucked a nightingale and finding almost no meat, said, <q direct="unspecified">It's
							all voice ye are, and nought else.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">Vox et praeterea nihil.</q>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="16">
               <p>One of the Spartans saw Diogenes the Cynic holding his arms around a bronze
						statue in very cold weather, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A part ofh is self-imposed training to inure himself to cold, as in the summer he used to roll in the hot sand to inure himself to heat, according to Diogenes Laertius, vi. 23.</note> and asked Diogenes if he were cold; and when
						Diogenes said <q direct="unspecified">No,</q> the other said,<q direct="unspecified">What great thing are
							you doing then ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="17">
               <p>One of the people of Metapontum, being reproached for cowardice by a
						Spartan, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Possibly Cleonymus (Diodorus, xx. 104).</note> said,<q direct="unspecified">But as a matter of fact we have not a little of the
							country of other states</q>; whereupon the Spartan replied, <q direct="unspecified">
							Then you are not only cowardly, but also unjust.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="18">
               <p>A man who was visiting Sparta stood for a long time upon one foot, and said
						to a Spartan, <q direct="unspecified">I do 
							<pb id="v.3.p.401"/> not think that you, sir, could stand upon one foot
							as long as that</q>; and the other interrupting said, <q direct="unspecified">No,
							but there is not a single goose that could not do it.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="19">
               <p>When a man boasted greatly of his art in speaking, a Spartan said, <q direct="unspecified">By
							Heaven, there is no art nor can there be an art without a firm hold on
							truth.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In almost the same words in Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 260 E.</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="20">
               <p>When an Argive said once upon a time, <q direct="unspecified">There are many tombs of
							Spartans in our country,</q> a Spartan said, <q direct="unspecified">But there is
							not a single tomb of an Argive in our country,</q> indicating by
						this that the Spartans had often set foot in Argos, but the Argives had
						never set foot in Sparta. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Agesilaus</hi>, chap. xxxi. (613 D).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="21">
               <p>A Spartan having been taken prisoner in war and put up for sale, when the
						crier said, <q direct="unspecified">I offer a Spartan for sale,</q> stopped his mouth,
						saying, <q direct="unspecified">Cry a prisoner of war.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 234 C (40), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="22">
               <p>One of the men serving in the army of Lysimachus, being asked by him whether
						he were not one of the Helots, said, <q direct="unspecified">Do you suppose that any Spartan
							would come to get the sixpence which you pay ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="23">
               <p>At the time when Thebans had conquered the Spartans at Leuctra and advanced
						to the river Eurotas itself, one of them, boasting, said, <q direct="unspecified">Where are
							the Spartans now ?</q> A Spartan who had been captured by them
						said, <q direct="unspecified">They are not here; otherwise you would not have come thus
							far.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="24">
               <p>At the time when the Athenians had surrendered their city, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At the close of the Peloponnesian war, 404 B.C. Samos had been the naval base for the Athenians during the preceding years.</note> they declared it
						was only right that Samos should be left to them, but the Spartans 
						<pb id="v.3.p.403"/> said, <q direct="unspecified">Do you, at a time when you do not even
							own yourselves, seek to possess others ?</q> From this incident
						arose the proverb : <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Dio Chrysostom, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi>, lxxiv. (637 M., 395 R.); Leutsch and Schneidewin, <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi Graeci</hi>, i. p. 292 (Diogenianus, vii. 34), and ii. p. 571 (Apostol. xiii. 5).</note> 
                  <quote rend="blockquote">Who does not own himself would Samos own.</quote> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="25">
               <p>When the Spartans had taken by storm a certain city, the Ephors said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Gone is the wrestlingschool of our young men; they no longer will have
							competitors.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The last clause looks like an explanatory comment. Pantazides would omit it.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="26">
               <p>When their king promised to wipe out completely another city which, as it
						happened, had given much trouble to the Spartans, they would not allow it,
						saying, <q direct="unspecified">You must not abolish nor remove the whetstone of our
							youth.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="27">
               <p>They appointed no trainers to instruct in wrestling so that the rivalry might
						be not in skill, but in courage. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 639 F, and Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Pelopidas</hi>, chap. vii. (281 B).</note> This is the reason why Lysanoridas, when
						he was asked how Charon had conquered him, said, <q direct="unspecified">By his great
							resourcefulness.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="28">
               <p>Philip wrote at the time when he entered their country, asking whether they
						wished that he should come as a friend or as a foe; and they made answer,
							<q direct="unspecified">Neither.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="29">
               <p>They sent an ambassador to Antigonus, son of Demetrius, and, upon learning
						that the ambassador had addressed Antigonus as King, they fined him,
						although he had brought for each one of them a bushel and a half of wheat at
						a time when there was great scarcity of food. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="30">
               <p>When Demetrius complained that they had 
						<pb id="v.3.p.405"/> sent only one ambassador to him, they replied, <q direct="unspecified">
							Is it not enough&mdash;one to one ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 216 B (16), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="31">
               <p>When a bad man brought in a very good idea, they accepted it; but they took
						it away from him and bestowed the right of proposing it upon another man who
						had lived a virtuous life. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 41 B, and 801 B; Aeschines, <hi rend="italics">Against Timarchus</hi>, 180-181; Philo Judaeus, <hi rend="italics">The Worse Plotting against the Better</hi>, 195 B; Aulus Gellius, xviii. 3.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="32">
               <p>When two brothers quarrelled with each other, the Spartans fined the father
						because he permitted his sons to quarrel. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="33">
               <p>They fined a visiting harp-player because he played the harp with his
						fingers. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thus making the music pleasanter to hear than if he had used the plectrum. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 802 F.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="34">
               <p>Two boys were fighting, and one of them wounded the other mortally with the
						stroke of a sickle. The friends of the wounded boy, as they were about to
						separate, promised to avenge him and make away with the one who had struck
						him, but the boy said, <q direct="unspecified">In Heaven's name do not, for it is not right;
							the fact is, I should have done that myself if I had been quick enough
							and brave enough.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="35">
               <p>In the case of another boy, when the time had arrived during which it was the
						custom for the free boys to steal whatever they could, and it was a disgrace
						not to escape being found out, when the boys with him had stolen a young fox
						alive, and given it to him to keep, and those who had lost the fox came in
						search for it, the boy happened to have slipped the fox under his garment.
						The beast, however, became savage and ate through his side to the vitals;
						but the boy did not move or cry out, so as to avoid being exposed, and
						later, when they had departed, the boys saw what had happened, and blamed
						him, saying that 
						<pb id="v.3.p.407"/> it would have been better to let the fox be seen than
						to hide it even unto death; but the boy said, <q direct="unspecified">Not so, but better to
							die without yielding to the pain than through being detected because of
							weakness of spirit to gain a life to be lived in disgrace.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is told more briefly in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Lycurgus</hi>, chap. xviii. (51 B).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="36">
               <p>Some people, encountering Spartans on the road, said, <q direct="unspecified">You are in
							luck, for robbers have just left this place,</q> but they said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Egad, no, but it is they who are in luck for not encountering
							us.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 194 D (3), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="37">
               <p>A Spartan being asked what he knew, said, <q direct="unspecified">How to be free.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="38">
               <p>A Spartan boy, being taken captive by Antigonus the king and sold, was
						obedient in all else to the one who had bought him, that is, in everything
						which he thought fitting for a free person to do, but when his owner bade
						him bring a chamber-pot, he would not brook such treatment, saying, <q direct="unspecified">
							I will not be a slave</q>; and when the other was insistent, he
						went up upon the roof, and saying, <q direct="unspecified">You will gain much by your
							bargain,</q> he threw himself down and ended his life. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 242 D (30), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi> This story is repeated by Philo Judaeus, <hi rend="italics">Every Virtuous Man is Free</hi>, chap. xvii. (882 C); Seneca, <hi rend="italics">Epistulae Moral</hi>. no. 77 (x. 1. 14), and is referred to by Epictetus, i. 2.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="39">
               <p>Another one being sold, when someone said, <q direct="unspecified">If I buy you, will you be
							good and helpful ?</q> said, <q direct="unspecified">Yes, and if you do not buy
							me.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 242 C (29), <hi rend="italics">infra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="40">
               <p>Another captive being put up for sale, when the crier announced that he was
						offering a slave for sale, said, <q direct="unspecified">You damnable wretch, won't you say
							a captive ' ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 233 C (21), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="41">
               <p>A Spartan had as an emblem on his shield a 
						<pb id="v.3.p.409"/> fly, and that, too, no bigger than life-size. When some
						mockingly said that he had done this to escape being noticed, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">Rather that I may be noticeable; for I come so close to the
							enemy that my emblem is seen by them in its true size.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="42">
               <p>Another, when a lyre was brought in at an evening party, said, <q direct="unspecified">It is
							not Spartan to indulge in nonsense.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 220 A (3). For the expression of similar sentiments see Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Themistocles</hi>, chap. ii. (112 C); Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, i. 2 (4).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="43">
               <p>A Spartan, being asked if the road into Sparta were safe, said, <q direct="unspecified">That
							depends on what kind of a mon ye are; for the lions gang about where
							they wull, but the hares we hunt over that land.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="44">
               <p>In a clinch one wrestler, who had the other by the neck, overpowered him with
						little effort, and pulled him to the ground. Since the one who was down was
						at a disadvantage in using his body, he bit the arm that held him. His
						opponent said, <q direct="unspecified">Spartan, you bite like a woman.</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">No, indeed,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">but like a lion.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same story is told of Alcibiades in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 186 D (1), and in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alcibiades</hi>, chap. i. (192 C).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="45">
               <p>A lame man was going forth to war, and some persons followed after him
						laughing. He turned around and said, <q direct="unspecified">You vile noddles ! A man does
							not need to run away when he fights the enemy, but to stay where he is
							and hold his ground.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 210 F (34), and 217 C; Valerius Maximus, iii. 7, ext. 8.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="46">
               <p>Another, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Callicrates at the battle of Plataea (Herodotus, ix. 72).</note> mortally wounded by an arrow, said, as his life was ebbing away,
							<q direct="unspecified">I am not troubled because I must die, but because my death comes
							at the hands of a womanish archer, and before I have accomplished
							anything.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Aristeides</hi>, chap. xvii. (329 C).</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.411"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="47">
               <p>A man stopped at an inn and gave the innkeeper a piece of meat to prepare;
						and when the innkeeper asked for cheese and oil besides, the other said,
							<q direct="unspecified">If I had cheese, what need should I have of meat too ?</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 995 B, where the meat is fish. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, 787 A; Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi> xxiii. 211 (691).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="48">
               <p>In answer to the man who called Lampis <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lampis was famous for his ships and his wealth. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 787 A; Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi> xxiii. 211 (691).</note> of Aegina happy, because he seemed
						very rich in having many cargoes on the sea in ships, a Spartan said,
							<q direct="unspecified">I do not pay much attention to happiness that hangs by ropes !
						</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 14 (40).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="49">
               <p>When somebody told a Spartan that he was lying, the Spartan replied, <q direct="unspecified">
							Yea, we are free men; but ithers, if they dinna teli the truth, will rue
							it.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 229 A (2).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="50">
               <p>When someone set himself to make a corpse stand upright, and, for all his
						efforts, was unable to do this, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Egad, there is need of
							something inside.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="51">
               <p>Tynnichus, when his son Thrasybulus was slain, bore it sturdily; and this
						epigram <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to Dioscorides in the <hi rend="italics">Palatine Anthology</hi>, vii. 229 (<hi rend="italics">The Greek Anthology</hi> in the L.C.L., ii. p. 130).</note> was written on him : <quote rend="blockquote">Lifeless to Pitane came, on his shield
						upborne, Thrasybulus; Seven the wounds he received, pierced by the Argive
						spears; All in the front did he show them; and him with his blood-stained
						body Tynnichus placed on the pyre, saying these words in his eld : &amp;ldquo;
							Let the poor cowards be mourned, but with never a tear shall I bury You,
							my son, who are mine, yea, and are Sparta's as well.&amp;rdquo;
                  </quote>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="52">
               <p>When the keeper of a bath was pouring in a
						<pb id="v.3.p.413"/> great quantity of water for Alcibiades, a Spartan <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Spartans were not enthusiastic bathers (<hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi> 237 B).</note>
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Why all this for him as if he were not clean ? The fellow is
							pouring in extra water as if for a very dirty man.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="53">
               <p>When Philip of Macedon sent some orders to the Spartans by letter, they wrote
						in reply, <q direct="unspecified">What you wrote about, ' No.'</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story is told with slightly more detail in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 513 A.</note> 
               </p>
               <p> When he invaded the Spartans' country, and all thought that they should be
						destroyed, he said to one of the Spartans, <q direct="unspecified">What shall you do now,
							men of Sparta ?</q> And the other said, <q direct="unspecified">What else than die
							like men ? For we alone of all the Greeks have learned to be free, and
							not to be subject to others.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 14 (42).</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="54">
               <p>After the defeat of Agis, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Agis III., in 331 B.C.</note> Antipater demanded fifty boys as hostages, but
						Eteocles, who was Ephor, said they would not give boys, lest the boys should
						turn out to be uneducated through missing the traditional discipline; and
						they would not be fitted for citizenship either. But the Spartans would
						give, if he so desired, either old men or women to double the number. And
						when Antipater made dire threats if he should not get the boys, the Spartans
						made answer with one consent, <q direct="unspecified">If the orders you lay upon us are
							harsher than death, we shall find it easier to die.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A different version of the Spartans' reply is given in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 64 D.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="55">
               <p>While the games were being held at Olympia, an old man was desirous of seeing
						them, but could find no seat. As he went to place after place, he met with
						insults and jeers, and nobody made room for him. But when he came opposite
						the Spartans, all the boys and many of the men arose and yielded 
						<pb id="v.3.p.415"/> their places. Whereupon the assembled multitude of
						Greeks expressed their approbation of the custom by applause, and commended
						the action beyond measure; but the old man, shaking <quote rend="blockquote">His head grey-haired and
							grey-bearded,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxii. 74, and xxiv. 516.</note>
                  </quote>  and with tears in his eyes, said, <q direct="unspecified">Alas for the evil
							days ! Because all the Greeks know what is right and fair, but the
							Spartans alone practise it.</q>
					          </p>
               <p> Some say that the same thing happened at Athens also. It was at the time of
						the Panathenaic festival, and the people of Attica were teasing an old man
						in an unseemly manner, calling him to them as if they were intending to make
						room for him, and not making room if he came to them. When he had passed
						through almost all the spectators and came opposite the delegates of the
						Spartans, they all arose from where they were sitting and gave him place.
						The crowd, delighted, applauded the action with great approval, and one of
						the Spartans said, <q direct="unspecified">Egad, the Athenians know what is right and fair,
							but do not do it.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De senectute</hi>, 18 (63-64); Valerius Maximus, iv. 5, ext. 2.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="56">
               <p>A beggar asked alms of a Spartan, who said, <q direct="unspecified">If I should give to you,
							you will be the more a beggar; and for this unseemly conduct of yours he
							who first gave to you is responsible, for he thus made you lazy.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="57">
               <p>A Spartan, seeing a man taking up a collection for the gods, said that he did
						not think much of gods who were poorer than himself. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="58">
               <p>A man who caught another in adultery with an ugly woman said, <q direct="unspecified">Puir
							soul! what was yer muckle need ?</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 525 D, the same saying is attributed to a man of Byzantium.</note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.417"/>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="59">
               <p>Another, listening to an orator rolling off long sentences, said, <q direct="unspecified">
							Egad, but the man has courage; he twists his tongue well about no
							subject at all.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="60">
               <p>One man who came to Sparta, and observed the honour which the young render to
						the old, said, <q direct="unspecified">Only in Sparta does it pay to grow old.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar sentiment is attributed to Lysander by Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De senectute</hi>, 18 (63).</note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="61">
               <p>A Spartan, being asked what kind of a man Tyrtaeus the poet was, said,
							<q direct="unspecified">A good man to sharpen the spirit of youth.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="62">
               <p>Another who had sore trouble with his eyes was going forth to war; and when
						some said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Where are you going in that state, or what do you
							purpose to do ?</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Even if I accomplish nothing
							else, I may at least blunt an enemy's sword.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="63">
               <p>Bulis and Sperchis of Sparta went as volunteers to Xerxes king of the
						Persians, to render satisfaction which Sparta owed according to an oracle,
						because the people had killed the heralds sent to them by the Persian. These
						men came before Xerxes and bade him make away with them in any manner he
						desired, as representing the Spartans. But when he, filled with admiration,
						let them go free, and was insistent that they remain with him, they said,
							<q direct="unspecified">And how should we be able to live here, abandoning our country
							and laws and those men in whose behalf we made such a long journey to
							die ?</q> And when Indarnes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hydarnes in Herodotus, vii. 135.</note> the general besought them at greater
						length, and said that they would receive equal honour with the friends of
						the king who stood highest in 
						<pb id="v.3.p.419"/> advancement, they said, <q direct="unspecified">You seem to us not to
							know what is the meed of liberty, which no man of sense would exchange
							for the kingdom of the Persians.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 815 E; Dio Chrysostom, <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi> lxxvi. <hi rend="italics">ad fin.</hi>; Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, vii. 70, and xxix. 27 (quoting Serenus). The ultimate source is probably Herodotus, vii. 134-136.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="64">
               <p>Because a friend with whom a Spartan was intending to stay dodged him on the
						first day, and on the next day, having borrowed bedding, received him
						sumptuously, the Spartan jumped on the bedding and trod it under foot,
						remarking that it was because of this that yesterday he had not had even
						straw to sleep on. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="65">
               <p>Another, on going to Athens, saw that the Athenians were hawking salt fish
						and dainties, collecting taxes, keeping public brothels, and following other
						unseemly pursuits, and holding none of them to be shameful. When he returned
						to his own country, his fellow-citizens asked how things were in Athens, and
						he said, <q direct="unspecified">Everything fair and lovely,</q> speaking sarcastically
						and conveying the idea that .among the Athenians everything is considered
						fair and lovely, and nothing shameful. </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="66">
               <p>Another, being asked a question, answered <q direct="unspecified">No.</q> And when the
						questioner said, <q direct="unspecified">You lie,</q> the other said, <q direct="unspecified">You see,
							then, that it is silly of you to ask questions to which you know the
							answer !</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="67">
               <p>Once upon a time, ambassadors from Sparta arrived at the court of Lygdamis
						the despot. But as he tried to put them off and repeatedly postponed the
						interview, and, to crown all, it was asserted that he was in a delicate
						condition, the Spartans said, <q direct="unspecified">Tell him, in God's name, that we have
							not come to wrestle with him, but to have a talk with him.</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="68">
               <p>When someone, initiating a Spartan into the Mysteries, asked him what his
						conscience told him <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes"> </note>
						            <pb id="v.3.p.421"/> was the most unholy deed he had ever done, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">The gods know.</q> And when the other became even more
						insistent, and said, <q direct="unspecified">It is absolutely necessary that you
							tell,</q> the Spartan asked in turn, <q direct="unspecified">To whom must I teli it
							? To you or to the god ?</q> And when the other said, <q direct="unspecified">To
							the god,</q> the Spartan said, <q direct="unspecified">You go away then.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A similar story is told of Antalcidas, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 217 C (1), and of Lysander, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 229 D (10), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="69">
               <p>Another, passing by a tomb at night, and imagining that he saw a ghost, ran
						at it with uplifted spear, and, as he thrust at it, he exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">
							Where are you fleeing from me, you soul that shall die twice ?</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="70">
               <p>Another, having vowed to throw himself from the Leucadian cliff, went up and
						came down again after seeing the height. Being jeered at for this, he said,
							<q direct="unspecified">I did na think my vow needed anither greater vow to dae it!
						</q>
					          </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="71">
               <p>Another, in the thick of the fight, was about to bring down his sword on an
						enemy when the recall sounded, and he checked the blow. When someone
						inquired why, when he had his enemy in his power, he did not kill him, he
						said, <q direct="unspecified">Because it is better to obey one's commander than to slay an
							enemy.</q> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 273 F; Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Comparison of Pelopidas and Marcellus</hi>, chap. iii. (317 D); Epictetus, ii. 6. The source is doubtless Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, iv. 1. 3, and Chrysantas is the man's name.</note> 
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" n="72">
               <p>Someone said to a Spartan who was defeated at Olympia, <q direct="unspecified">Spartan, your
							opponent proved himself the better man.</q>
						            <q direct="unspecified">No,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">not that, but more upsetting !</q>
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For a similar sentiment, see <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 233 E (27), <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
					          </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>