<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De unius in republica dominatione</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.119">
      <body>
         <head>Of the three sorts of government, monarchy,
				democracy, and oligarchy.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.395"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>As I was considering with myself to bring forth and
				propose to the judgment of this worthy company the discourse I held yesterday in your presence, methought I
				heard political virtue&mdash;not in the illusion of a dream, but
				in a true and real vision&mdash;say thus to me:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A golden ground is laid for sacred songs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>We have already laid the foundation of the discourse by
					persuading and exhorting persons to concern themselves
					in managing the affairs of the commonweal, and now we
					proceed to build upon it the doctrine which is due after
					such an exhortation. For after a man has received an
					admonition and exhortation to deal in the affairs of the
					state, there ought consequently to be given him the precepts of government, following and observing which, he
					may, as much as it is possible for a man to do, profit the
					public, and in the mean time honestly prosecute his own
					affairs with such safety and honor as shall be meet for
					him.</p>
            <p>There is first then one point to be discoursed, which, as
					it is precedent to what we have hereafter to say, so depends
					on what we have said before. Now this is, what sort of
					policy and government is best? For as there are many
					sorts of lives in particular men, so also are there in people
					and states; and the life of a people or state is its policy
					and government. It is therefore necessary to declare which
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.396"/>
					
					is the best, that a statesman may choose it from among the
					rest, or, if that is not possible for him to do, he may at
					least take that which has the nearest resemblance to the
					best.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Now there is one signification of this word policy
				(<foreign lang="greek">politei/a</foreign>) which imports as much as <hi rend="italics">burgess-ship,</hi> that is,
				a participation in the rights and privileges belonging to a
				town, city, or borough; as when we say that the Megarians, by an edict of their city, presented Alexander the
				Great with their <hi rend="italics">policy,</hi> that is, their <hi rend="italics">burgess-ship,</hi> and that,
				Alexander laughing at the offer they made him of it, they
				answered him, that they had never decreed that honor to
				any but Hercules and now to himself. This he wondering
				to hear accepted their present, thinking it honorable inasmuch as it was rare. The life also of a political person,
				who is concerned in the government of the commonweal,
				is called policy, as when we praise the policy of Pericles
				or Bias, that is, the manner of their government, and on
				the contrary, blame that of Hyperbolus and Cleon. Some
				moreover there are, who call a great and memorable action
				performed in the administration of a commonweal a policy,
				such as is the distribution of money, the suppressing of a
				war, the introduction of some notable decree worthy to be
				kept in perpetual memory. In which signification it is a
				common manner of speaking to say, This man to-day has
				done a policy, if he has peradventure effected some remarkable matter in the government of the state.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Besides all these significations there is yet another,
				that is, the order and state by which a commonweal is
				governed, and by which affairs are managed and administered. According to which we say that there are three
				sorts of policy or public government,&mdash;to wit, Monarchy,
				which is regality or kingship, Oligarchy, which is the government by peers and nobles, and Democracy, which is a
				popular or (as we term it) a free state. Now all these are
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.397"/>
				
				mentioned by Herodotus in his Third Book,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. III. 82.</note> where he
				compares them one with another. And these seem to be
				the most general of all; for all other sorts are, as it were,
				the depravation and corruption of these, either by defect
				or excess; as it is in the first consonances of music, when
				the strings are either too straight or too slack.</p>
            <p>Now these three sorts of government have been distributed amongst the nations that have had the mightiest and
					the greatest empire. Thus the Persians enjoyed regality
					or kingship, because their king had full absolute power in
					all things, without being liable to render an account to any
					one. The Spartans had a council consisting of a small
					number, and those the best and most considerable persons
					in the city, who despatched all affairs. The Athenians
					maintained popular government free and exempt from any
					other mixture. In which administration when there are
					any faults, their transgressions and exorbitances are styled
					tyrannies, oppressions of the stronger, unbridled licentiousness of the multitude. That is, when the prince who has
					the royalty permits himself to outrage whomever he
					pleases, and will not suffer any remonstrance to be made
					him concerning it, he becomes a tyrant; when a few lords
					or senators in whose hands the government is arrive at
					that arrogance as to contemn all others, they turn oppressors; and when a popular state breaks forth into disobedience and levelling, it runs into anarchy and unmeasurable
					liberty: and in a word, all of them together will be rashness and folly.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Even then as a skilful musician will make use of all
				sorts of instruments, and play on every one of them, accommodating himself in such manner as its quality can
				bear and as shall be fit to make it yield the sweetest sound,
				but yet, if he will follow Plato's counsel, will lay aside
				fiddles, many-stringed virginals, psalteries, and harps, preferring
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.398"/>
				
				 before all other the lute and bandore; in like
				manner, an able statesman will dexterously manage the
				Laconic and Lycurgian seignory or oligarchy, fitting and
				accommodating his companions who are of equal authority
				with him, and by little and little drawing and reducing
				them to be managed by himself. He will also carry himself discreetly in a popular state, as if he had to deal with
				an instrument of many and differently sounding strings,
				one while letting down and remitting some things, and
				again extending others, as he shall see his opportunity and
				find it most convenient for the government, to which he
				will vigorously apply himself, well knowing when and how
				he ought to resist and contradict; but yet, if he might be
				permitted to make his choice from amongst all sorts of
				government, as from so many musical instruments, he
				would not, if Plato's advice might be taken, choose any
				other but monarchy or regal authority, as being that which
				is indeed alone able to support that most perfect and most
				lofty note of virtue, without suffering him either by force
				or by grace and favor, to frame himself for advantage and
				gain. For all other sorts of governments do in a manner
				as much rule a statesman as he does them, no less carrying
				him than they are carried by him; forasmuch as he has
				no certain power over those from whom he has his authority, but is very often constrained to cry out in these words
				of the poet Aeschylus, which King Demetrius, surnamed
				the Town-taker, often alleged against Fortune, after he had
				lost his kingdom:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou mad'st me first, and now undoest me quite.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>