<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Quaestiones Romanae</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.084">
      <body>
         <head>Roman Questions.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.204"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 1. Wherefore do the Romans require a new-married woman to touch fire and water?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not for one of these reasons; amongst
					elements and principles, one is masculine and the other
					feminine;&mdash; one (fire) hath in it the principles of motion,
					the other (water) hath the faculty of a subject and matter?
					Or is it because fire refines and water cleanseth, and a
					married wife ought to continue pure and chaste? Or is it
					because fire without moisture doth not nourish, but is
					adust, and water destitute of heat is barren and sluggish;
					so both the male and female apart are of no force, but
					a conjunction of both in marriage completes society? Or
					is the meaning that they must never forsake each other,
					but must communicate in every fortune, and although
					there be no goods, yet they may participate with each
					other in fire and water?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 2. Why do they light at nuptials five torches,
				neither more nor less, which they call waxen tapers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Whether it be (as Varro saith) that the
					Praetors use three, but more are permitted to the Aediles,
					and married persons do light the fire at the Aediles'
					torches? Or is it that, having use of many numbers, the
					odd number was reckoned better and perfecter upon other
					accounts, and therefore more adapted to matrimony? For
					the even number admits of division, and the equal parts
					of opposition and repugnancy, whenas the odd cannot be
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.205"/>
					
					divided, but being divided into parts leaves always an
					inequality. The number five is most matrimonial of
					odd numbers, for three is the first odd and two is the first
					even, of which five is compounded, as of male and
					female.</p>
            <p>Or rather, because light is a sign of generation, and it
					is natural to a woman, for the most part, to bring forth so
					far as five successively, and therefore they use five torches?
					Or is it because they suppose that married persons have
					occasion for five Gods, Nuptial Jupiter, Nuptial Juno,
					Venus, Suada, and above all the rest Diana, whom women
					invocate in their travail and child-bed sickness?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 3. What is the reason that, seeing there are
				so many of Diana's temples in Rome, the men refrain going
				into that only which stands in Patrician Street?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it upon the account of the fabulous story,
					that a certain man, ravishing a woman that was there
					worshipping the Goddess, was torn in pieces by dogs;
					and hence this superstitious practice arose, that men enter
					not in?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 4. Why do they in all other temples of
				Diana ordinarily nail up stags' horns against the wall,
				whenas in that of the Aventine they nail up the horns of
				cattle?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it to put them in mind of an old casualty? For it is said, that among the Sabines one Antro
					Coratius had a very comely cow, far excelling all others in
					handsomeness and largeness, and was told by a certain
					diviner that whoever should offer up that cow in sacrifice
					to Diana on the Aventine, his city was determined by fate
					to be the greatest in the world and have dominion over all
					Italy. This man came to Rome, with an intention to sacrifice his cow there; but a servant acquainted King Servius privately with this privacy, and the king making it
					known to Cornelius the priest, Cornelius strictly commands
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.206"/>
					
					Antro to wash in Tiber before he sacrificed, for the law
					requires men so to do who would sacrifice acceptably.
					Wherefore, whilst Antro went to wash, Servius took the
					opportunity to sacrifice the cow to the Goddess, and nailed
					up the horns to the wall in the temple. These things
					are storied by Juba and Varro, only Varro hath not
					described Antro by that name, neither doth he say that
					the Sabine was choused by Cornelius the priest, but by the
					sexton.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 5. Wherefore is it that those that are falsely
				reported to be dead in foreign countries, when they return,
				they receive not by the doors, but getting up to the roof
				of the house, they let them in that way?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Verily the account which Varro gives of this
					matter is altogether fabulous. For he saith, in the Sicilian
					war, when there was a great naval fight, and a very false
					report was rumored concerning many as if they were
					slain, all of them returning home in a little time died.
					But as one of them was going to enter in at his doors,
					they shut together against him of their own accord, neither
					could they be opened by any that attempted it. This man,
					falling in a sleep before the doors, saw an apparition in
					his sleep advising him to let himself down from the roof
					into the house, and doing so, he lived happily and became
					an old man; and hence the custom was confirmed to after
					ages. But consider if these things be not conformable to
					some usages of the Greeks. For they do not esteem those
					pure nor keep them company nor suffer them to approach
					their sacrifices, for whom any funeral was carried forth or
					sepulchre made as if they were dead; and they say that
					Aristinus, being one that was become an object of this sort
					of superstition, sent to Delphi to beg and beseech of the
					God a resolution of the anxieties and troubles which he
					had by reason of the custom then in force. Pythia answered thus:&mdash;
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.207"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sacred rites t' which child-bed folks conform,
					</l>
                     <l>See that thou do to blessed Gods perform.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Aristinus, well understanding the meaning of the oracle,
					puts himself into the women's hands, to be washed and
					wrapped in swaddling clouts, and sucks the breasts, in the
					same manner as when he was newly born; and thus all
					others do, and such are called Hysteropotmi (i.e. those for
					whom a funeral was made while living). But some say
					that these ceremonies were before Aristinus, and that the
					custom was ancient. Wherefore it is not to be wondered
					at, if the Romans, when once they suppose a man buried
					and to have his lot among the dead, do not think it lawful
					for him to go in at the door whereat they that are about
					to sacrifice do go out or those that have sacrificed do enter
					in, but bid them ascend aloft into the air, and thence descend into the open court of the house. For they constantly offer their sacrifices of purification in this open
					court.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 6. Wherefore do women salute their relations
				with their mouth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it should be (as many suppose) that
					women were forbid to drink wine; therefore that those
					that drank it might not be undiscovered, but convicted
					when they met with their acquaintance, kissing became
					a custom? Or is it for the reason which Aristotle the philosopher hath told us? Even that thing which was commonly reported and said to be done in many places, it
					seems, was enterprised by the Trojan women in the confines of Italy. For after the men arrived and went ashore,
					the women set the ships on fire, earnestly longing to be
					discharged of their roving and seafaring condition; but
					dreading their husbands' displeasure, they fell on saluting
					their kindred and acquaintance that met them, by kissing
					and embracing; whereupon the husbands' anger being
					appeased and they reconciled, they used for the future this
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.208"/>
					
					kind of compliment towards them. Or rather might this
					usage be granted to women as a thing that gained them
					reputation and interest, if they appeared hereby to have
					many and good kindred and acquaintance? Or was it that,
					it being unlawful to marry kinswomen, a courteous behavior
					might proceed so far as a kiss, and this was retained only
					as a significant sign of kindred and a note of a familiar
					converse among them? For in former time they did not
					marry women nigh by blood,&mdash; as now they marry not
					aunts or sisters,&mdash;but of late they allowed the marrying
					of cousins for the following reason. A certain man, mean
					in estate, but on the other hand an honest and a popular
					man among the citizens, designed to marry his cousin
					being an heiress, and to get an estate by her. Upon this
					account he was accused; but the people took little notice
					of the accusation, and absolved him of the fault, enacting
					by vote that it might be lawful for any man to marry so far
					as cousins, but prohibited it to all higher degrees of consanguinity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 7. Why is a husband forbid to receive a gift
				from his wife, and a wife from her husband?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if the reason be as Solon writes it,&mdash;describing gifts to be peculiar to dying persons, unless a
					man being entangled by necessity or wheedled by a woman
					be enslaved to force which constrains him, or to pleasure
					which persuades him,&mdash;that thus the gifts of husbands
					and wives became suspected? Or is it that they reputed
					a gift the basest sign of benevolence (for strangers and
					they that have no love for us do give us presents), and so
					took away such a piece of flattery from marriage, that to
					love and be beloved should be devoid of mercenariness,
					should be spontaneous and for its own sake, and not for
					any thing else? Or because women, being corrupted by
					receiving gifts, are thereby especially brought to admit
					strangers, did it seem to be a weighty thing to require
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.209"/>
					
					them to love their own husbands that give them nothing?
					Or was it because all things ought to be common between
					them, the husbands' goods being the wives', and the wives'
					goods the husbands'? For he that accepts that which is
					given learns thereby to esteem that which is not given the
					property of another; so that, by giving but a little to each
					other, they strip each other of all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 8. Why were they prohibited from taking a
				gift of a son-in-law or of a father-in-law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not of a son-in-law, that a man may not
					seem to convey a gift to his wife by his father's hands? and
					of a father-in-law, because it seems just that he that doth
					not give should not receive?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 9. Wherefore is it that they that have wives
				at home, if they be returning out of the country or from any
				remote parts, do send a messenger before, to acquaint them
				that they be at hand?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is not this an argument that a man believes
					his wife to be no idle gossip, whereas to come upon her
					suddenly and unexpectedly has a show as though he came
					hastily to catch her and observe her behavior? Or do they
					send the good tidings of their coming beforehand, as to
					them that are desirous of them and expect them? Or rather
					is it that they desire to enquire concerning their wives
					whether they are in health, and that they may find them at
					home looking for them? Or because, when the husbands
					are wanting, the women have more family concerns and
					business upon their hands, and there are more dissensions
					and hurly-burly among those that are within doors; therefore, that the wife may free herself from these things and
					give a calm and pleasant reception to her husband, she hath
					forewarning of his coming?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 10. Wherefore do men in divine service cover
				their heads; but if they meet any honorable personages
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.210"/>
				
				when they have their cloaks on their heads, they are uncovered?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> The latter part of the question seems to augment the difficulty of the former. If now the story told of
					Aeneas be true, that whilst Diomedes was passing by he
					offered a sacrifice with his head covered, it is rational and
					consequent that, while we cover our heads before our enemies, when we meet our friends and good men we should
					be uncovered. This behavior before the Gods therefore is
					not their peculiar right, but accidental, continuing to be
					observed since that example of Aeneas.</p>
            <p>If there is any thing further to be said, consider whether
					we ought not to enquire only after the reason why men in
					divine service are covered, the other being the consequence
					of it. For they that are uncovered before men of greater
					power do not thereby ascribe honor unto them, but rather
					remove envy from them, that they might not seem to demand or to endure the same kind of reverence which the
					Gods have, or to rejoice that they are served in the same
					manner as they. But they worship the Gods in this manner, either showing their unworthiness in all humility by
					the covering of the head, or rather fearing that some unlucky and ominous voice should come to them from abroad
					whilst they are praying; therefore they pluck up their
					cloaks about their ears. That they strictly observed these
					things is manifest in this, that when they went to consult
					the oracle, they made a great din all about by the tinkling
					of brass kettles. Or is it as Castor saith, that the Roman
					usages were conformable to the Pythagoric notion that the
					daemon within us stands in need of the Gods without us,
					and we make supplication to them with a covered head,
					intimating the body's hiding and absconding of the soul?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 11. Why do they sacrifice to Saturn with an
				uncovered head?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that, whereas Aeneas hath
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.211"/>
					
					instituted the covering of the head in divine service, Saturn's sacrifice was much more ancient? Or is it that they
					are covered before celestial Gods, but reckon Saturn an
					infernal and terrestrial God? Or is it that nothing of the
					truth ought to be obscure and darkened, and the Romans
					repute Saturn to be the father of truth?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 12. Why do they esteem Saturn the father of
				truth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not the reason that some philosophers
					believe that <foreign lang="greek">*kro/nos</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">Saturn</hi>) is the same with <foreign lang="greek">*xro/nos</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">time</hi>),
					and time finds out truth? Or is it for that which was fabled
					of Saturn's age, that it was most just and most likely to
					participate of truth?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 13. Why do they sacrifice to Honor (a God
				so-called) with a bare head?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because glory is splendid, illustrious, and
					unveiled, for which cause men are uncovered before good
					and honorable persons; and for this reason they thus worship the God that bears the name of honor?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 14. Why do sons carry forth their parents at
				funerals with covered heads, but the daughters with uncovered and dishevelled hair?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason because fathers ought to be
					honored by their sons as Gods, but be lamented by their
					daughters as dead, and so the law hath distributed to both
					their proper part? Or is it that what is not the fashion is
					fit for mourning? For it is more customary for women to
					appear publicly with covered heads, and for men with uncovered. Yea, among the Greeks, when any sad calamity
					befalls them, the women are polled close but the men wear
					their hair long, because the usual fashion for men is to be
					polled and for women to wear their hair long. Or was it
					enacted that sons should be covered, for the reason we have
					above mentioned (for verily, saith Varro, they surround their
					fathers' sepulchres at funerals, reverencing them as the temples
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.212"/>
					
					 of the Gods; and having burnt their parents, when
					they first meet with a bone, they say the deceased person
					is deified), but for women was it not lawful to cover their
					heads at funerals? History now tells us that the first that
					put away his wife was Spurius Carbilius, by reason of barrenness; the second was Sulpicius Gallus, seeing her pluck
					up her garments to cover her head; the third was Publius
					Sempronius, because she looked upon the funeral games.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 15. What is the reason that, esteeming Terminus a God (to whom they offer their Terminalia), they
				sacrifice no living creature to him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that Romulus set no bounds to the
					country, that it might be lawful for a man to make excursions, to rob, and to reckon every part of the country his
					own (as the Spartan said) wherever he should pitch his
					spear; but Numa Pompilius, being a just man and a good
					commonwealthsman and a philosopher, set the boundaries
					towards the neighboring countries, and dedicated those
					boundaries to Terminus as the bishop and protector both
					of friendship and of peace, and it was his opinion that it
					ought to be preserved pure and undefiled from blood and
					slaughter?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 16. Why is it that the temple of Matuta is
				not to be gone into by maid-servants; but the ladies bring
				in one only, and her they box and cuff?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> If to baste this maid be a sign that they ought
					not to enter, then they prohibit others according to the
					fable. For Ino, being jealous of her husband's loving the
					servant-maid, is reported to have fell outrageously upon
					her son. The Grecians say the maid was of an Aetolian
					family, and was called Antiphera. Therefore with us also
					in Chaeronea the sexton, standing before the temple of
					Leucothea (Matuta) holding a wand in his hand, makes
					proclamation that no man-servant nor maid-servant, neither
					man nor woman Aetolian, should enter in.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.213"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 17. Why do they not supplicate this Goddess
				for good things for their own children, but for their brethren's and sisters' children?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because Ino was a lover of her sister
					and nursed up her children, but had hard fortune in her
					own children? Or otherwise, in that it is a moral and good
					custom, and makes provision of much benevolence towards
					relations?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 18. Why do many of the richer sort pay tithe
				of their estates to Hercules?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that Hercules sacrificed the
					tenth part of Geryon's oxen at Rome? Or that he freed
					the Romans from the decimation under the Etrurians? Or
					that these things have no sufficient ground of credit from
					history, but that they sacrificed bountifully to Hercules, as
					to a certain monstrous glutton and gormandizer of good
					cheer? Or did they rather do it, restraining extravagant
					riches as a nuisance to the commonwealth, as it were to
					diminish something of that thriving constitution that grows
					up to the highest pitch of corpulency; being of opinion
					that Hercules was most of all honored with and rejoiced in
					these frugalities and contractions of abundance, and that he
					himself was frugal, content with a little, and every way
					sparing in his way of living?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 19. Why do they take the month of January
				for the beginning of the new year?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Anciently March was reckoned the first, as
					is plain by many other marks and especially by this, that
					the fifth month from March was called Quintilis, and the
					sixth Sextilis, and so forward to the last. December was
					so called, being reckoned the tenth from March; hence it
					came to pass that some are of opinion and do affirm that
					the Romans formerly did not complete the year with twelve
					months, but with ten only, allotting to some of the months
					above thirty days. But others give us an account that, as
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.214"/>
					
					December is the tenth from March, January is the eleventh
					and February the twelfth; in which month they use purifications, and perform funeral rites for the deceased upon the
					finishing of the year; but this order of the months being
					changed, they now make January the first, because on the
					first day of this month (which day they call the Kalends of
					January) the first consuls were constituted, the kings being
					deposed. But some speak with a greater probability, which
					say that Romulus, being a warlike and martial man and reputing himself the son of Mars, set March in the front of
					all the months, and named it from Mars; but Numa again,
					being a peaceable prince and ambitious to bring off the citizens from warlike achievements, set them upon husbandry,
					gave the pre-eminence to January, and brought Janus into
					a great reputation, as he was more addicted to civil government and husbandry than to warlike affairs. Now consider whether Numa hath not pitched upon a beginning of
					the year most suitable to our natural disposition. For there
					is nothing at all in the whole circumvolution of things naturally first or last, but by law or custom some appoint one
					beginning of time, some another; but they do best who
					take this beginning from after the winter solstice, when the
					sun, ceasing to make any further progress, returns and converts his course again to us. For there is then a kind of
					tropic in nature itself, which verily increaseth the time of
					light to us and shortens the time of darkness, and makes
					the Lord and Ruler of the. whole current of nature to
					approach nearer to us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 20. When the women beautify the temple of
				the Goddess appropriate to women, which they call Bona,
				why do they bring no myrtle into the house, although they
				be zealous of using all budding and flowering vegetables?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is not the reason (as the fabulous write the
					story) this, that the wife of Faulius a diviner, having drunk
					wine secretly and being discovered, was whipped by her
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.215"/>
					
					husband with myrtle rods; hence the women bring in no
					myrtle, but offer to her a drink-offering of wine, which they
					call milk? Or is it this, that, as they abstain from many
					things, so especially they reserve themselves chaste from all
					things that appertain to venery when they perform that
					divine service; for they do not only turn their husbands
					out of doors but banish from the house every male kind,
					when they exercise this canonical obedience to their Goddess. They therefore reject myrtle as an abomination, it
					being consecrated to Venus; and the Venus whom at this
					day they call Murcia they anciently called Myrtia, as it
					would seem.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 21. Why do the Latins worship a woodpecker, and all of them abstain strictly front this bird?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because one Picus by the enchantments
					of his wife transformed himself, and becoming a woodpecker uttered oracles, and gave oraculous answers to them
					that enquired? Or, if this be altogether incredible and monstrous, there is another of the romantic stories more probable, about Romulus and Remus, when they were exposed
					in the open field, that not only a she-wolf gave them suck,
					but a certain woodpecker flying to them fed them; for even
					now it is very usual that in meads and groves where a
					woodpecker is found there is also a wolf, as Nigidius writes.
					Or rather, as they deem other birds sacred to various Gods,
					so do they deem this sacred to Mars? For it is a daring and
					fierce bird, and hath so strong a beak as to drill an oak to
					the heart by pecking, and cause it to fall.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 22. Why are they of opinion that Janus was
				double-faced, and do describe and paint him so?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because he was a native Greek of
					Perrhaebia (as they story it), and going down into Italy
					and cohabiting with the barbarians of the country, changed
					his language and way of living? Or rather because he persuaded those people of Italy that were savage and lawless
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.216"/>
					
					to a civil life, in that he converted them to husbandry and
					formed them into commonwealths?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 23. Why do they sell things which pertain
				to funerals in the temple of Libitina, seeing they are of
				opinion that Libitina is Venus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that this was one of the wise institutions of King Numa, that they might learn not to esteem
					these things irksome nor fly from them as a defilement?
					Or rather is it to put us in mind that whatever is born must
					die, there being one Goddess that presides over them that
					are born and those that die? And at Delphi there is the
					statue of Venus Epitymbia (on a tomb), to which at their
					drink-offerings they call forth the ghosts of the deceased.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 24. Why have they three beginnings and appointed periods in the months which have not the same
				interval of days between?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it be this (as Juba writes), that on
					the Kalends the magistrates called (<foreign lang="greek">kalei=n</foreign>) the people, and
					proclaimed the Nones for the fifth, while the Ides they esteemed an holy day? Or rather that they who define time
					by the variations of the moon have observed that the moon
					comes under three greatest variations monthly; the first is
					when it is obscured, making a conjunction with the sun;
					the second is when it gets out of the rays of the sun and
					makes her first appearance after the sun is down; the
					third is at her fulness, when it is full moon. They call
					her disappearance and obscurity the Kalends, for every
					thing hid and privy they call <hi rend="italics">clam,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">celare</hi> is to hide.
					The first appearance they call the Nones, by a most fit notation of names, it being the new moon (novilunium); for
					they call it new moon as we do. Ides are so called either
					by reason of the fairness and clear form (<foreign lang="greek">ei)=dos</foreign>) of the moon
					standing forth in her complete splendor, or from the name
					of Jupiter (<foreign lang="greek">*dio/s</foreign>). But in this matter we are not to search
					for the exact number of days, nor to abuse this approximate
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.217"/>
					
					mode of reckoning; seeing that even at this day, when the
					science of astronomy has made so great increase, the inequality of the motion and course of the moon surpasseth
					all experience of mathematicians and cannot be reduced to
					any certain rule of reason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 25. Why do they determine that the days
				after the Kalends, Nones, and Ides are unfit to travel or go
				a long journey in?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it (as most men think, and Livy tells us)
					because on the next day after the Ides of Quintilis (which
					they now call July), the tribunes of the soldiery marching
					forth, the army was conquered by the Gauls in a battle
					about the river Allia and lost the city, whereupon this day
					was reckoned unlucky; and superstition (as it loves to do)
					extended this observation further, and subjected the next
					days after the Nones and Kalends to the same scrupulosity?
					Or what if this notion meet with much contradiction? For
					it was on another day they were defeated in battle, which
					they call Alliensis (from the river) and greatly abominate
					as unsuccessful; and whereas there be many unlucky days,
					they do not observe them in all the months alike, but every
					one in the month it happens in, and it is most improbable
					that all the next days after the Nones and Kalends simply
					considered should contract this superstition. Consider now
					whether&mdash;as they consecrated the first of the months to
					the Olympic Gods, and the second to the infernals, wherein
					they solemnize some purifications and funeral rites to the
					ghosts of the deceased&mdash; they have so constituted the
					three which have been spoken of, as it were, the chief and
					principal days for festival and holy days, designating the next
					following these to daemons and deceased persons, which
					days they esteemed unfortunate and unfit for action. And
					also the Grecians, worshipping their Gods at the new of the
					moon, dedicated the next day to heroes and daemons, and
					the second of the cups was mingled on the behalf of the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.218"/>
					
					male and female heroes. Moreover, time is altogether a
					number; and unity, which is the foundation of a number, is
					of a divine nature. The number next is two, opposite to
					the first, and is the first of even numbers. But an even
					number is defective, imperfect, and indefinite; as again an
					odd number is determinate, definite, and complete. Therefore the Nones succeed the Kalends on the fifth day, the Ides
					follow the Nones on the ninth, for odd numbers do determine the beginnings. But those even numbers which are
					next after the beginnings have not that pre-eminence nor
					influence; hence on such days they take not any actions
					or journey in hand. Wherefore that of Themistocles hath
					reason in it. <q direct="unspecified">The Day after the feast contended with the
						Feast-day, saying that the Feast-day had much labor and
						toil, but she (the Day after the feast) afforded the fruition
						of the provision made for the Feast-day, with much leisure
						and quietness. The Feast-day answered after this wise:
						Thou speakest truth; but if I had not been, neither hadst
						thou been.</q> These things spake Themistocles to the Athenian officers of the army, who succeeded him, signifying
					that they could never have made any figure in the world
					had not he saved the city.</p>
            <p>Since therefore every action and journey worth our diligent management requires necessary provision and preparation, but the Romans of old made no family provision
					on feast-days, nor were careful for any thing but that they
					might attend divine service,&mdash;and this they did with all
					their might, as even now the priests enjoin them in their
					proclamations when they proceed to the sacrifices,&mdash;
					in like manner they did not rush presently after their
					festival solemnities upon a journey or any enterprise (because they were unprovided), but finished that day in
					contriving domestic affairs and fitting themselves for the
					intended occasion abroad. And as even at this day, after
					they have said their prayers and finished their devotion,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.219"/>
					
					they are wont to stay and sit still in the temples, so they
					did not join working days immediately to holy days, but
					made some interval and distance between them, secular
					affairs bringing many troubles and distractions along with
					them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 26. Why do women wear for mourning white
				mantles and white kerchiefs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if they do this in conformity to the
					Magi, who, as they say, standing in defiance of death and
					darkness, do fortify themselves with bright and splendid
					robes? Or, as the dead corpse is wrapped in white, so do
					they judge it meet that the relations should be conformable
					thereto? For they beautify the body so, since they cannot
					the soul; wherefore they wish to follow it as having gone
					before, pure and white, being dismissed after it hath
					fought a great and various warfare. Or is it that what is
					very mean and plain is most becoming in these things?
					For garments dyed of a color argue either luxury or vanity.
					Neither may we say less of black than of sea-green or
					purple, <q direct="unspecified">Verily garments are deceitful, and so are colors.</q>
					And a thing that is naturally black is not dyed by art but
					by nature, and is blended with an intermixed shade. It is
					white only therefore that is sincere, unmixed, free from the
					impurity of a dye, and inimitable; therefore most proper
					to those that are buried. For one that is dead is become
					simple, unmixed, and pure, freed from the body no otherwise than from a tingeing poison. In Argos they wear
					white in mourning, as Socrates saith, vestments rinsed in
					water.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 27. Why do they repute every wall immaculate and sacred, but the gates not so?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it (as Varro hath wrote) that the wall is to
					be accounted sacred, that they might defend it cheerfully
					and even lay down their lives for it? Upon this very
					account it appears that Romulus slew his brother, because
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.220"/>
					
					he attempted to leap over a sacred and inaccessible place,
					and to render it transcendible and profane; but it could
					not possibly be that the gates should be kept sacred,
					through which they carried many things that necessity
					required, even dead corpses. When they built a city from
					the foundation, they marked out with a plough the place
					on which they intended to build it, yoking a bull and a
					cow together; but when they did set out the bounds of
					the walls, measuring the space of the gates, they lifted
					up the ploughshare and carried the plough over it, believing that all the ploughed part should be sacred and
					inviolable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 28. Why do they prohibit the children to
				swear by Hercules within doors, but command them to go
				out of doors to do it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason (as some say) that they are of
					opinion that Hercules was not delighted in a domestic life,
					but chose rather to live abroad in the fields? Or rather
					because he was none of their native country Gods, but a
					foreigner? For neither do they swear by Bacchus within
					doors, he being a foreigner, if it be he whom the Greeks
					call Dionysus. Or what if these things are uttered in
					sport to amuse children; and is this, on the contrary, for
					a restraint of a frivolous and rash oath, as Favorinus
					saith? For that which is done, as it were, with preparation causes delay and deliberation. If a man judges as
					Favorinus doth of the things recorded about Hercules, it
					would seem that this was not common to other Gods, but
					peculiar to him; for history tells us that he had such a
					religious veneration for an oath, that he swore but once
					only to Phyleus, son of Augeas. Wherefore the Pythia
					upbraids the Lacedaemonians with such swearing, as though
					it would be more laudable and better to pay their vows
					than to swear.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 29. Why do they not permit the new married
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.221"/>
				
				woman herself to step over the threshold of the house,
				but the bridemen lift her over?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if the reason be that they, taking their
					first wives by force, brought them thus into their houses,
					when they went not in of their own accord? Or is it that
					they will have them seem to enter into that place as by
					force, not willingly, where they are about to lose their
					virginity? Or is it a significant ceremony to show that
					she is not to go out or leave her dwelling-place till she is
					forced, even as she goes in by force? For with us also in
					Boeotia they burn the axletree of a cart before the doors,
					intimating that the spouse is bound to remain there, the
					instrument of carriage being destroyed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 30. Why do the bridemen that bring in the
				bride require her to say, <q direct="unspecified">Where thou Caius art, there am
					I Caia</q>?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if the reason be that by mutual agreement she enters presently upon participation of all things,
					even to share in the government, and that this is the
					meaning of it, Where thou art lord and master of the
					family, there am I also dame and mistress of the family;
					while these common names they use promiscuously, as the
					lawyers do Caius, Seius, Lucius, Titius, and the philosophers use the names of Dion and Theon? Or is it
					from Caia Secilia, an honest and good woman, married to
					one of Tarquinius's sons, who had her statue of brass
					erected in the temple of Sancus? On this statue were
					anciently hanged sandals and spindles, as significant memorials of her housewifery and industry.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 31. Why is that so much celebrated name
				Thalassius sung at nuptials?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not from wool-spinning? For the Ro
					mans call the Greek <foreign lang="greek">ta/laros</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">wool-basket</hi>) <hi rend="italics">talasus</hi>. Moreover, when they have introduced the bride, they spread a
					fleece under her; and she, having brought in with her a
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.222"/>
					
					distaff and a spindle, all behangs her husband's door with
					woollen yarn? Or it may be true, as historians report, that
					there was a certain young man famous in military achievements, and also an honest man, whose name was Thalassius; now when the Romans seized by force on the Sabine
					daughters coming to see the theatric shows, a comely
					virgin for beauty was brought to Thalassius by some of
					the common sort of people and retainers to him, crying
					out aloud (that they might go the more securely, and that
					none might stop them or take the wench from them) that
					she was carried as a wife to Thalassius; upon which the
					rest of the rabble, greatly honoring Thalassius, followed
					on and accompanied them with their loud acclamations,
					praying for and praising Thalassius; that proving a fortunate match, it became a custom to others at nuptials to
					call over Thalassius, as the Greeks do Hymenaeus.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Livy, I. 9, 12.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 32. Why do they that throw the effigies of
				men from a wooden bridge into the river, in the month
				of May, about the full moon, call those images Argives?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that the barbarians that of old inhabited about that place did in this manner destroy the
					Grecians which they took? Or did their so much admired Hercules reform their practice of killing strangers,
					and teach them this custom of representing their devilish practice by casting in of images? The ancients have
					usually called all Grecians Argives. Or else it may be
					that, since the Arcadians esteemed the Argives open enemies by reason of neighborhood, they that belonged to
					Evander, flying from Greece and taking up their situation
					in Italy, kept up that malignity and enmity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 33. Why would they not in ancient times sup
				abroad without their sons, whilst they were in nonage?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was not this custom brought in by Lycurgus,
					when he introduced the boys to the public mess, that they
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.223"/>
					
					might be inured to use of pleasures modestly, not savagely
					and rudely, having their superiors by them as overseers
					and observers? Verily it is of no small concernment that
					parents should carry themselves with all gravity and sobriety in the presence of their children. For when old
					men are debauched, it will necessarily follow (as Plato
					saith) that young men will be most debauched.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 34. What is the reason that, when the other
				Romans did offer their offerings and libations to the dead
				in the month of February, Decimus Brutus (as Cicero
				saith) did it in December? He verily was the first who,
				entering upon Lusitania, passed from thence with his
				army over the river Lethe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> May it not be that, as many were wont to
					perform funeral rites in the latter part of the day and end
					of the month, it is rational to believe that at the return
					of the year and end of the month also he would honor
					the dead? For December is the last month. Or were
					those adorations paid to the infernal Gods, and was it the
					season of the year to honor them when all sorts of fruits
					had attained ripeness? Or is it because they move the
					earth at the beginning of seed-time, and it is most meet
					then to remember the ghosts below? Or is it that this
					month is by the Romans consecrated to Saturn, whom
					they reckon to be one of the infernal Gods and not of the
					supernal? Or that whilst the great feast of Saturnals did
					last, thought to be attended with the greatest feasting and
					voluptuous enjoyments, it was judged meet to crop off
					some first-fruits of these for the dead? Or what if it be
					a mere lie that only Brutus did sacrifice to the dead in
					this month, since they solemnize funeral rites for Laurentia and offer drink-offerings at her tomb in the month
					of December?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 35. Why do they adore Laurentia so much,
				seeing she was a strumpet?</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.224"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> They say that Acca Laurentia, the nurse of
					Romulus, was diverse from this, and her they ascribe
					honor to in the month of April. But this other Laurentia, they say, was surnamed Fabula, and she became
					noted on this occasion. A certain sexton that belonged
					to Hercules, as it seems, leading an idle life, used to spend
					most of his days at draughts and dice; and on a certain
					time, when it happened that none of those that were
					wont to play with him and partake of his sport were
					present, being very uneasy in himself, he challenged the
					God to play a game at dice with him for this wager, that
					if he got the game he should receive some boon from the
					God, if he lost it he would provide a supper for the God
					and a pretty wench for him to lie with. Whereupon choosing two dice, one for himself and the other for the God,
					and throwing them, he lost the game; upon which, abiding by his challenge, he prepared a very splendid table
					for the God, and picking up Laurentia, a notorious harlot,
					he set her down to the good cheer; and when he had made
					a bed for her in the temple, he departed and shut the doors
					after him. The report went that Hercules came, but had
					not to do with her after the usual manner of men, and
					commanded her to go forth early in the morning into the
					market-place, and whomsoever she first happened to meet
					with, him she should especially set her heart upon and
					procure him to be her copemate. Laurentia accordingly
					arising and going forth happened to meet with a certain
					rich man, a stale bachelor, whose name was Taruntius.
					He lying with her made her whilst he lived the governess
					of his house, and his heiress when he died; some time
					after, she died and left her estate to the city, and therefore
					they have her in so great a reputation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 36. Why do they call one gate at Rome the
				Window, just by which is the bed-chamber of Fortune,
				so called?</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.225"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because Servius, who became the
					most successful king, was believed to have conversed with
					Fortune, who came in to him at a window? Or may this
					be but a fable; and was it that Tarquinius Priscus the
					king dying, his wife Tanaquil, being a discreet and royal
					woman, putting her head out at a window, propounded
					Servius to the citizens, and persuaded them to proclaim
					him king; and that this place had the name of it?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 37. Why is it that, of the things dedicated to
				the Gods, the law permits only the spoils taken in war to
				be neglected and by time to fall into decay, and permits
				them not to have any veneration nor reparation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that men may be of
					opinion that the renown of ancestors fades away, and may
					always be seeking after some fresh monument of fortitude?
					Or rather because time wears out the marks of contention
					with our enemies, and to restore and renew them were
					invidious and malicious? Neither among the Greeks are
					those men renowned who were the first erectors of stone
					or brass trophies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 38. Why did Q. Metellus, being a high priest
				and otherwise reputed a wise man and a statesman, prohibit the use of divination from birds after the Sextile
				month, now called August?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not that&mdash;as we make such observations about noon or early in the day, and also in the beginning or middle of the month (when the moon is new
					or increasing), but beware of the times of the days or
					month's decline as unlucky&mdash;so he also was of opinion
					that the time of year after eight months was, as it were,
					the evening of the year, when it declined and hastened
					towards an end? Or is it because they must use thriving
					and full-grown birds? For such are in summer; but
					towards autumn some are moulting and sickly, others
					chickens and unfledged, others altogether vanished and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.226"/>
					
					fled out of the country by reason of the season of the
					year.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 39. Why is it unlawful for such as are not
				mustered (although they be otherwise conversant in the
				army) to slay an enemy or wound him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> This thing Cato Senior hath made clear in a
					certain epistle, writing to his son and commanding him, if
					he be discharged of the army having fulfilled his time
					there, to return; but if he stay, to take commission from
					the general to march forth in order to wounding and
					slaying the enemy. Is it the reason, that necessity alone
					can give warrant for the killing of a man, while he that
					doth this illegally and without commission is a murderer?
					Therefore Cyrus commended Chrysantas that, when he
					was about to slay an enemy and had lifted up his scimitar
					to take his blow, hearing a retreat sounded, he let the
					man alone and smote him not, as being prohibited. Or is
					it that, if a man conflicts and fights with his enemies and
					falls under a consternation, he ought to be liable to answer
					for it, and not escape punishment? For verily he doth
					not advantage his side so much by smiting and wounding
					him, as he doth mischief by turning his back and flying.
					Therefore he that is disbanded is freed from martial laws;
					but when he doth petition to perform the office of a soldier, he doth again subject himself to military discipline
					and put himself under the command of his general.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 40. Wherefore was it unlawful for a priest
				of Jupiter to be anointed abroad in the air?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it not because it was neither honest nor
					decent to strip the sons naked whilst the father looked on,
					nor the son-in-law whilst the father-in-law looked on?
					Neither in ancient times did they wash together. Verily
					Jupiter is the father, and that which is abroad in the open
					air may be especially said to be as it were in the sight of
					Jupiter. Or is it thus? As it is a profane thing for him
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.227"/>
					
					to strip himself naked in the temple or holy place, so did
					they reverence the open air and firmament, as being full
					of Gods and Daemons? Wherefore we do many necessary
					things within doors, hiding and covering ourselves in our
					houses from the sight of the Gods. Or is it that some
					things are enjoined to the priest only, other things to all
					by a law delivered by the priest? With us (in Boeotia)
					to wear a crown, to wear long hair, to carry iron arms,
					and not to enter the Phocian borders are peculiar, proper
					pieces of the magistrate's service; but not to taste autumnal fruits before the autumnal equinox, and not to
					cut a vine before the spring equinox, are things required
					of all by the magistrate. For each of these has its season. After the same manner (as it appears) among the
					Romans it is peculiar to the priest neither to make use of
					a horse, nor to be absent from home in a journey more
					than three nights, nor to put off his cap, on which account
					he is called Flamen.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Varro, Ling. Lat. V. 84: Quod in Latio capite velato erant semper, ac
						caput cinctum habebant <hi rend="italics">filo, flamines</hi> dicti. Festus, s. v. Flamen Dialis: Flamen, quasi <hi rend="italics">filamen.</hi> (G.)</note> Many other things are enjoined to
					all sorts of men by the priest; of which one is not to be
					anointed abroad in the open air. For the Romans have
					a great prejudice against dry unction; and they are of
					opinion that nothing hath been so great a cause to the
					Grecians of slavery and effeminacy as their fencing and
					wrestling schools, insinuating so much debauchery and
					idleness into the citizens, yea, vicious sloth and buggery;
					yea, that they destroyed the very bodies of youths with
					sleeping, perambulations, dancing, and delicious feeding,
					whereby they insensibly fell from the use of arms, and
					instead of being good soldiers and horsemen, loved to be
					called nimble, good wrestlers, and pretty men. It is
					hard for them to avoid these mischiefs who are unclothed
					in the open air; but they that are anointed within doors
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.228"/>
					
					and cure themselves at home do commit none of these
					vices.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 41. Why had the ancient coin on one side the
				image of double-faced Janus stamped, and on the other
				side the stern or stem of a ship?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it be (as they commonly say) in
					honor of Saturn, that sailed over into Italy in a ship? Or,
					if this be no more than what may be said of many others
					besides (for Janus, Evander, and Aeneas all came by sea
					into Italy), a man may take this to be more probable:
					whereas some things serve for the beauty of a city, some
					things for necessary accommodation, the greatest part of
					the things that beautify a city is a good constitution of government, and the greatest part for necessary accommodation is good trading; whereas now Janus had erected a
					good frame of government among them, reducing them to
					a sober manner of life, and the river being navigable afforded plenty of all necessary commodities, bringing them
					in partly from the sea and partly from the out-borders of
					the country, their coin had a significant stamp, on one side
					the double-faced head of the legislator (as hath been said)
					by reason of the change made by him in their affairs, and
					on the other a small ship because of the river. They used
					also another sort of coin, having engraven on it an ox, a
					sheep, and a sow, to show that they traded most in such
					cattle, and got their riches from these; hence were many
					of the names among the ancients derived, as Suillii, Bubulci, and Porcii, as Fenestella tells us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 42. Why do they use the temple of Saturn
				for a chamber of public treasury, as also an office of record
				for contracts?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is not this the reason, because this saying
					hath obtained credit, that there was no avarice or injustice
					among men while Saturn ruled, but faith and righteousness? Or was it that this God presided over the fruits
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.229"/>
					
					of the field and husbandry? For the sickle signified as
					much, and not, as Antimachus was persuaded and wrote
					with Hesiod,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With crooked falk Saturn 'gainst heavens fought,
					</l>
                     <l>off his father's privities, foul bout.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Money is produced from plenty of fruit and the vent
					of them, therefore they make Saturn the author and preserver of their felicity. That which confirms this is that
					the conventions assembled every ninth day in the marketplace (which they call Nundinae) they reckon sacred to
					Saturn, because the abundance of fruit gave the first occasion of buying and selling. Or are these things farfetched, and was the first that contrived this Saturnine
					chamber of bank Valerius Publicola, upon the suppression
					of the kings, being persuaded it was a strong place, conspicuous, and not easily undermined by treachery?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 43. Wherefore did ambassadors, from whencesoever they came to Rome, go to Saturn's temple, and
				there have their names recorded before the treasurers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was this the cause, that Saturn was a foreigner, and therefore much rejoiced in strangers? Or is
					this better resolved by history? Anciently (as it seems)
					the quaestors sent entertainment to the ambassadors (they
					called the present <hi rend="italics">lautia</hi>), they took care also of the sick,
					and buried their dead out of their public stock; but now
					of late, because of the multitude of ambassadors that come,
					that expense is left off; yet it remains still in use to bring
					the ambassadors unto the treasurers, that their names may
					be recorded.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 44. Why is it not lawful for Jupiter's priests
				to swear?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not the reason, that an oath is a kind of
					test imposed on a free people, but the body and mind of a
					priest ought to be free from imposition? Or is it not unlikely that he will be disbelieved in smaller matters, who is
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.230"/>
					
					entrusted with divine and greater? Or is it that every
					oath concludes with an execration of perjury? And an
					execration is a fearful and a grievous thing. Hence neither
					is it thought fit that priests should curse others. Wherefore the priestess at Athens was commended for refusing
					to curse Alcibiades, when the people required her to do it;
					for she said, I am a praying not a cursing priestess. Or is
					it that the danger of perjury is of a public nature, if a perjured and impious person presides in offering up prayers and
					sacrifices on the behalf of the city?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 45. Why is it that in the solemn feast called
				Veneralia they let wine run so freely out of the temple of
				Venus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason (as some say), that Mezentius the Etrurian general sent to make a league with
					Aeneas, upon the condition that he might have a yearly
					tribute of wine; Aeneas refusing, Mezentius engaged to
					the Etrurians that he would take the wine by force of
					arms and give it to them; Aeneas, hearing of his promise,
					devoted his wine to the Gods, and after the victory he
					gathered in the vintage, and poured it forth before the
					temple of Venus? Or is this a teaching ceremony, that
					we should feast with sobriety and not excess, as if the
					Gods were better pleased with the spillers of wine than
					with the drinkers of it?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 46. Wherefore would the ancients have the
				temple of Horta to stand always open?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason (as Antistius Labeo hath
					told us), that <hi rend="italics">hortari</hi> signifies <hi rend="italics">to quicken one to an action,</hi>
					that Horta is such a Goddess as exhorts and excites to
					good things, and that they suppose therefore that she
					ought always to be in business, never procrastinate, therefore not to be shut up or locked? Or is it rather that Hora,
					as now they call her (the first syllable pronounced long), being a kind of an active and busy Goddess, very circumspect
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.231"/>
					
					and careful, they were of opinion that she was never lazy
					nor neglectful of human affairs? Or is it that this is a
					Greek name, as many others of them are, and signifies a
					Goddess that always oversees and inspects affairs; and
					that therefore she has her temple always open, as one that
					never slumbers nor sleeps? But if Labeo deduceth <hi rend="italics">Hora</hi>
					aright from <hi rend="italics">hortari,</hi> consider whether <hi rend="italics">orator</hi> may not
					rather be said to be derived from thence,&mdash;since the orator, being an exhorting and exciting person, is a counsellor
					or leader of the people,&mdash;and not from imprecation and
					prayer (<hi rend="italics">orando</hi>), as some say.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 47. Why did Romulus build the temple of
				Vulcan without the city?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it were by reason of that fabled
					grudge which Vulcan had against Mars for the sake of
					Venus, that Romulus, being reputed the son of Mars, would
					not make Vulcan a cohabitant of the same house or city
					with him? Or may this be a silly reason; and was that
					temple at first built by Romulus for a senate house and a
					privy council, for him to consult on state affairs together
					with Tatius, where they might be retired with the senators,
					and sit in consultation about matters quietly without interruption from the multitude? Or was it that Rome was
					formerly in danger of being burnt from heaven; and he
					thought good to adore that God, but to place his habitation
					without the city?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 48. Wherefore did they, in the feasts called
				Consualia, put garlands on the horses and asses, and take
				these beasts off from all work?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it not because they celebrated that feast
					to Neptune the cavalier, who was called Consus, and the
					ass takes part and share with the horse in his rest from
					labor? Or was it that, after navigation came in and traffic
					by sea, there succeeded a kind of ease and leisure to the
					cattle in some kind or other?</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.232"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 49. Wherefore was it a custom among the
				candidates for magistracy to present themselves in their
				togas without tunics, as Cato tells us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it not that they should not carry money
					in their bosoms to buy votes with? Or is it that they preferred no man as fit for the magistracy for the sake of his
					birth, riches, or honors, but for his wounds and scars; and
					that these might be visible to them that came about them,
					they came without tunics to the elections? Or, as by courteous behavior, supplication, and submission, so by humbling themselves in nakedness did they gain on the affections
					of the common people?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 50. Why did the Flamen Dialis (Jupiter's
				priest), when his wife died, lay down his priestly dignity,
				as Ateius tells us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not for this reason, because he that marries a wife and loses her after marriage is more unfortunate
					than he that never took a wife; for the family of a married
					man is completed, but the family of him that is married
					and loseth his wife is not only incomplete but mutilated?
					Or is it because his wife joins with the husband in consecration (as there are many sacred rites that ought not to be
					performed unless the wife be present), but to marry another
					immediately after he hath lost the former wife is not perhaps easy to do, and besides is not convenient? Hence it
					was not lawful formerly to put away a wife, nor is it at this
					present lawful; except that Domitian in our remembrance,
					being petitioned, granted it. The priests were present at
					this dissolution of marriage, doing many terrible, strange,
					and uncouth actions. But thou wilt wonder less, if thou
					art informed by history that, when one of the censors died,
					his partner was required to lay down his place. When
					Livius Drusus died, Aemilius Scaurus his colleague would
					not abandon his government before one of the tribunes of
					the people committed him to prison.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.233"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="51">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 51. Why is a dog set before the Lares, whom
				they properly call Praestites, while the Lares themselves
				are covered with dogs' skins?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it that Praestites are they that preside, and
					it is fit that presidents should be keepers, and should be
					frightful to strangers (as dogs are) but mild and gentle to
					those of the family? Or is it rather what some Romans
					assert, that&mdash;as some philosophers who follow Chrysippus
					are of the opinion that evil spirits wander up and down,
					which the Gods do use as public executioners of unholy
					and wicked men&mdash;so the Lares are a certain sort of furious
					and revengeful daemons, that are observers of men's lives
					and families, and are here clothed with dogs' skins and
					have a dog sitting by them, as being sagacious to hunt upon
					the foot and to prosecute wicked men?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="52">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 52. Why do they sacrifice a dog to Mana
				Geneta, and pray that no home-born should become
				good?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason that Geneta is a deity that is
					employed about the generation and purgation of corruptible
					things? For this word signifies a certain flux (i.e. <hi rend="italics">Mana</hi>
					from <hi rend="italics">manare</hi>) and generation, or a flowing generation ; for
					as the Greeks do sacrifice a dog to Hecate, so do the Romans to Geneta on the behalf of the natives of the house.
					Moreover, Socrates saith that the Argives do sacrifice a dog
					to Eilioneia (Lucina) to procure a facility of delivery. But
					what if the prayer be not made for men, but for dogs puppied at home, that none of them should be good; for
					dogs ought to be currish and fierce? Or is it that they
					that are deceased are pleasantly called good; and hence,
					speaking mystically in their prayer, they signify their desire
					that no home-born should die? Neither ought this to seem
					strange; for Aristotle says that it is written in the treaty of
					the Arcadians with the Lacedaemonians that none of the
					Tegeates should be <q direct="unspecified">made good</q> on account of aid rendered
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.234"/>
					
					 to the party of the Lacedaemonians, i.e. that none
					should be slain.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="53">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 53. Why is it that to this very day, while they
				hold the games at the Capitol, they set Sardians to sale by a
				crier, and a certain old man goes before in way of derision,
				carrying a child's bauble about his neck, which they call
				bulla?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because a people of the Tuscans called
					Veientes maintained a fight a long time with Romulus, and
					he took this city last of all, and exposed them and their
					king to sale by an outcry, upbraiding him with his madness
					and folly? And since the Tuscans were Lydians at first,
					and Sardis was the metropolis of the Lydians, so they set
					the Veientes to sale under the name of Sardians, and to
					this day they keep up the custom in a way of pastime.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="54">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 54. Why do they call the flesh-market Macellum?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it not by corrupting the word <foreign lang="greek">ma/geiros, </foreign>a
					<hi rend="italics">cook,</hi> as with many other words, that the custom hath prevailed? For <hi rend="italics">c</hi> and <hi rend="italics">g</hi> are nigh akin to one another, and
					<hi rend="italics">g</hi> came more lately into use, being inserted among the
					other letters by Sp. Carbilius; and now by lispers and
					stammerers <hi rend="italics">l</hi> is pronounced instead of <hi rend="italics">r.</hi> Or this matter
					may be made clear by a story. It is reported, that at Rome
					there was a stout man, a robber, who had robbed many,
					and being taken with much difficulty, was brought to condign punishment: his name was Macellus, out of whose
					riches a public meat-market was built, which bare his
					name.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="55">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 55. Why are the minstrels allowed to go
				about the city on the Ides of January, wearing women's
				apparel?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it for the reason here rehearsed? This
					sort of men (as it seems) had great privileges accruing to
					them from the grant of King Numa, by reason of his
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.235"/>
					
					godly devotion; which things afterward being taken from
					them when the Decemviri managed the government, they
					forsook the city. Whereupon there was a search made
					for them, and one of the priests, offering sacrifice without
					music, made a superstitious scruple of so doing. And
					when they returned not upon invitation, but led their lives
					in Tibur, a certain freedman told the magistrates privately
					that he would undertake to bring them. And providing a
					plentiful feast, as if he had sacrificed to the Gods, he invited the minstrels; women-kind was present also, with
					whom they revelled all night, sporting and dancing. There
					on a sudden the man began a speech, and being surprised
					with a fright, as if his patron had come in upon him, persuaded the pipers to ascend the caravans that were covered
					all over with skins, saying he would carry them back to
					Tibur. But this whole business was but a trepan; for he
					wheeling about the caravan, and they perceiving nothing
					by reason of wine and darkness, he very cunningly brought
					them all into Rome by the morning. Most of them, by
					reason of the night-revel and the drink that they were in,
					happened to be clothed in flowered women's robes; whereupon, being prevailed upon by the magistrates and reconciled, it was decreed that they should go up and down the
					city on that day, habited after this manner.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="56">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 56. Why are they of opinion that matrons
				first built the temple of Carmenta, and at this day do they
				worship her most?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> There is a certain tradition that, when the
					women were prohibited by the senate from the use of chariots drawn by a pair of horses, they conspired together not
					to be got with child and breed children, and in this manner
					to be revenged on their husbands until they revoked the
					decree and gratified them; which being done, children
					were begot, and the women, becoming good breeders and
					very fruitful, built the temple of Carmenta. Some say
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.236"/>
					
					that Carmenta was Evander's mother, and going into Italy
					was called Themis, but as some say, Nicostrata; who, when
					she sang forth oracles in verse, was called Carmenta by the
					Latins; for they call verses <hi rend="italics">carmina.</hi> There are some of
					opinion that Carmenta was a Destiny, therefore the matrons
					sacrifice to her. But the etymology of the word is from
					<hi rend="italics">cares mente</hi> (<hi rend="italics">beside herself</hi>), by reason of divine raptures.
					Hence Carmenta had not her name from carmina; but contrariwise, her verses were called carmina from her, because
					being inspired she sang her oracles in verse.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="57">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 57. What is the reason that, when the women
				do sacrifice to Rumina, they pour forth milk plentifully on
				the sacrifices, but offer no wine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because the Latins call a breast <hi rend="italics">ruma,</hi>
					and that tree (as they say) is called <hi rend="italics">ruminalis</hi> under which
					the she-wolf drew forth her breast to Romulus? And as
					we call those women that bring up children with milk
					from the breast breast-women, so did Rumina&mdash;who was a
					wet nurse, a dry nurse, and a rearer of children&mdash;not
					permit wine, as being hurtful to the infants.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="58">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 58. Why do they call some senators Patres
				Conscripti, and others only Patres?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is not this the reason, that those that were
					first constituted by Romulus they called Patres and Patricians, as being gentlemen who could show their pedigree;
					but those that were elected afterwards from among the
					commonalty they called Patres Conscripti?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="59">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 59. Why was one altar common to Hercules
				and the Muses?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because Hercules taught letters first to
					Evander's people, as Juba tells us? And it was esteemed an
					honorable action of those that taught their friends and relations; for it was but of late that they began to teach for hire.
					The first that opened a grammar school was Spurius Carbilius, a freeman of Carbilius, the first that divorced his wife.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.237"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="60">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 60. What is the reason that, of Hercules's
				two altars, the women do not partake or taste of the things
				offered on the greater?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not because Carmenta's women came too
					late for the sacrifices? The same thing happened also to
					the Pinarii; whence they were excluded from the sacrificial feast, and fasting while others were feasting, they were
					called Pinarii (from <foreign lang="greek">peina/w</foreign>). Or is it upon the account of
					that fabulous story of the coat and Dejaneira?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="61">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 61. What is the reason that it's forbidden to
				mention, enquire after, or name the chief tutelary and
				guardian God of Rome, whether male or female?&mdash;which
				prohibition they confirm with a superstitious tradition,
				reporting that Valerius Soranus perished miserably for
				uttering that name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason (as some Roman histories
					tell us), that there are certain kinds of evocations and
					enchantments, with which they are wont to entice away
					the Gods of their enemies, and to cause theirs to come and
					dwell with them; and they feared lest this mischief should
					befall them from others? As the Tyrians are said to bind
					fast their images with cords, but others, when they will
					send any of them to washing or purifying, require sureties
					for their return; so did the Romans reckon they had their
					God in most safe and secure custody, he being unexpressible and unknown? Or, as Homer hath versified,
					<quote rend="blockquote">The earth all Gods in common have?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XV. 193.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>that men might worship and reverence all Gods that have
					the earth in common, so did the ancient Romans obscure the
					Lord of their Salvation, requiring that not only this but
					all Gods should be reverenced by the citizens?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="62">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 62. Why among them that were called Feciales (in Greek, peace-makers) was he that was named
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.238"/>
				
				Pater Patratus accounted the chiefest? But this must be
				one who hath his father living, and children of his own;
				and he hath even at this time a certain privilege and trust,
				for the Praetors commit to those men's trust the persons of
				those who, by reason of comeliness and beauty, stand in
				need of an exact and chaste guardianship.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that they must be such
					whose children reverence them, and who reverence their
					parents? Or doth the name itself suggest a reason? For
					<hi rend="italics">patratum</hi> will have a thing to be complete and finished;
					for he whose lot it is to be a father whilst his father liveth
					is (as it were) perfecter than others. Or is it that he
					ought to be overseer of oaths and peace, and (according to
					Homer) to see before and behind? He is such a one
					especially, who hath a son for whom he consults, and a
					father with whom he consults.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="63">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 63. Why is he that is called Rex Sacrorum
				(who is king of priests) forbid either to take upon him a
				civil office or to make an oration to the people?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that of old the kings did perform the
					most and greatest sacred rites and offered sacrifices together with the priests; but when they kept not within
					the bounds of moderation and became proud and insolent,
					most of the Grecians, depriving them of their authority,
					left to them only this part of their office, to sacrifice to the
					Gods; but the Romans, casting out kings altogether, gave
					the charge of the sacrifice to another, enjoining him
					neither to meddle with public affairs nor to hold office,
					so that they might seem to be subject to royalty only in
					their sacrifices, and to endure the name of king only with
					respect to the Gods? Hence there is a certain sacrifice
					kept by tradition in the market-place near the Comitia,
					which as soon as the king (i.e. the chief priest) hath
					offered, he immediately withdraws himself by flight out of
					the market-place.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.239"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="64">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 64. Why do they not suffer the table to be
				quite voided when it's taken away, but will have something
				always to remain upon it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it be that they would intimate that
					something of our present enjoyments should be left for
					the future, and that to-day we should be mindful of tomorrow? Or that they reckon it a piece of manners to
					repress and restrain the appetite in our present fruitions?
					For they less desire absent things, who are accustomed to
					abstain from those that are present. Or was it a custom
					of courtesy towards household servants? For they do not
					love so much to take as to partake, deeming that they hold
					a kind of communion with their masters at the table. Or
					is it that no sacred thing ought to be suffered to be empty?
					And the table is a sacred thing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="65">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 65. Why doth not a man lie at first with a
				bride in the light, but when it is dark?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not for modesty's sake, for at the first
					congress he looks upon her as a stranger to him? Or is
					it that he may be inured to go into his own wife with
					modesty? Or, as Solon hath written, <q direct="unspecified">Let the bride go
						into the bed-chamber gnawing a quince, that the first salutation be not harsh and ungrateful.</q> So did the Roman
					lawgiver command that, if there should be any thing
					absurd and unpleasant in her body, she should hide it?
					Or was it intended to cast infamy upon the unlawful use
					of venery by causing that the lawful should have certain
					signs of modesty attending it?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="66">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 66. Why was one of the horse-race rounds
				called Flaminia?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because, when Flaminius, one of the
					ancients, bestowed a field on the city, they employed its
					revenue on the horse-races, and with the overplus money
					built the way which they call Flaminia?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="67">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 67. Why do they call the rod-bearers lictors?</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.240"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, because these men were
					wont to bind desperate bullies, and they followed Romulus
					carrying thongs in their bosoms? The vulgar Romans
					say <hi rend="italics">alligare, to bind,</hi> when the more refined in speech say
					<hi rend="italics">ligare.</hi> Or is now c inserted, when formerly they called
					them <hi rend="italics">litores,</hi> being <hi rend="italics">liturgi,</hi> ministers for public service;
					for <foreign lang="greek">lh=|ton</foreign> until this day is writ for <hi rend="italics">public</hi> in many of the
					Grecian laws, which scarce any is ignorant of.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="68">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 68. Why do the Luperci sacrifice a dog?
				The Luperci are they that run up and down naked (saving
				only their girdles) in the Lupercal plays, and slash all that
				they meet with a whip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution:</hi> Is it not because these feats are done for the
					purification of the city? For they call the month February,
					and indeed the very day Februatus, and the habit of whip
					ping with thongs they call <hi rend="italics">februare,</hi> the word signifying <hi rend="italics">to</hi>
					          <hi rend="italics">cleanse.</hi> And to speak the truth, all the Grecians have
					used, and some do use to this very day, a slain dog for an
					expiatory sacrifice; and among other sacrifices of purification, they offer whelps to Hecate, and sprinkle those that
					need cleansing with the puppy's blood, calling this kind of
					purifying puppification. Or is it that <hi rend="italics">lupus</hi> is <foreign lang="greek">lu/kos</foreign>, a
					<hi rend="italics">wolf,</hi> and Lupercalia are Lycaea; but a dog is at enmity
					with a wolf, therefore is sacrificed on the Lycaean festivals?
					Or is it because the dogs do bark at and perplex the
					Luperci as they scout about the city? Or is it that this
					sacrifice is offered to Pan, and Pan loves dogs because of
					his herds of goats.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="69">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 69. Why, upon the festival called Septimontium, did they observe to abstain from the use of chariots
				drawn by a pair of horses; and even until now, do they
				that regard antiquity still abstain? They do observe the
				Septimontium feast in honor of the addition of the seventh
				hill to the city, upon which it became Septicollis, seven-hilled Rome.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.241"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it be (as some of the Romans conjecture) because the parts of the city are not as yet everywhere connected? Or if this conceit be nothing to the purpose, what if it be that, when the great work of building
					the city was finished and they determined to cease the increasing of the city any further, they rested themselves
					and rested the cattle that bore a share in the labor with
					them, and provided accordingly that they might participate
					of the holiday by rest from labor? Or was it that they
					would have all the citizens always present for the solemnity
					and return of a festival, especially that which was observed
					in remembrance of the compact uniting the parts of the
					city; and that none should desert the city for whose sake
					the feast is kept, they were not allowed to use their yoke
					chariots that day?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="70">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 70. Why do they call those Furciferi which
				are convict of thefts or any other of those slavish crimes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it this (which was an argument of the
					severity of the ancients), that whenever any convicted his
					servant of any villany, he enjoined him to carry the forked
					piece of timber that is under the cart (the tongue of the
					cart), and to go with it through the next villages and neighborhood, to be seen of all, that they might distrust him and
					be aware of him for the future? This piece of wood we
					call a prop, the Romans call it <hi rend="italics">furca, a fork;</hi> hence he
					that carries it about is called <hi rend="italics">furcifer, a fork-bearer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="71">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 71. Why do they bind hay about the horns of
				oxen that are wont to push, that they may be shunned by
				him that meets them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> It is that by reason of gormandizing and stuffing their guts oxen, asses, horses, and men become mischievous, as Sophocles somewhere saith,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>full-fed colt thou kickest up heels,
					</l>
                     <l>From stuffed paunch, cheeks, and full meals?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Romans say that M. Crassus had hay about
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.242"/>
					
					his horns, for they that were turbulent men in the commonwealth were wont to stand in awe of him as a revengeful
					man and one scarce to be meddled with; although afterwards it was said again, that Caesar had taken away Crassus's hay, being the first man of the republic that withstood
					and affronted him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="72">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 72. Why would they have the lanthorns of
				the soothsaying priests (which formerly they called Auspices, and now Augures) to be always open at top, and no
				cover to be put upon them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it as the Pythagoreans do, who make little
					things symbols of great matters,&mdash;as forbidding to sit down
					upon a bushel and to stir up the fire with a sword,&mdash;so
					that the ancients used many enigmatical ceremonies, especially about their priests, and such was this of the lanthorn?
					For the lanthorn is like the body encompassing the soul,
					the soul being the light withinside, and the understanding
					and judgment ought to be always open and quick-sighted,
					and never to be shut up or blown out. And when the
					winds blow, the birds are unsettled and do not afford sound
					prognostics, by reason of their wandering and irregularity
					in flying; by this usage therefore they teach that their
					soothsayers must not prognosticate when there are high
					winds, but in still and calm weather, when they can use
					their open lanthorns.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="73">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 73. Why were priests that had sores about
				them forbid to use divination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is not this a significant sign that, whilst
					they are employed about divine matters, they ought not to
					be in any pain, nor have any sore or passion in their minds,
					but to be cheerful, sincere, and without distraction? Or it
					is but rational, if no man may offer a victim that hath a
					sore, nor use such birds for soothsaying, that much more
					they should themselves be free from these blemishes, and
					be clean, sincere, and sound, when they go about to inspect
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.243"/>
					
					divine prodigies; for an ulcer seems to be a mutilation and
					defilement of the body.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="74">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 74. Why did Servius Tullius build a temple
				of Small Fortune, whom they call Brevis?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because he was of a mean original
					and in a low condition, being born of a captive woman, and
					by fortune came to be king of Rome? Or did not that
					change of his condition manifest the greatness rather than
					the smallness of his fortune? But Servius most of all
					of them seems to ascribe divine influence to Fortune, giving
					thereby a reputation to all his enterprises. For he did
					not only build temples of Hopeful Fortune, of Fortune that
					averteth evil, of Mild, Primogenial, and Masculine Fortune;
					but there is a temple also of Private Fortune, another of
					Regardful Fortune, another of Hopeful Fortune, and the
					fourth of Virgin Fortune. But why should any one mention any more names, seeing there is a temple also of
					Ensnaring Fortune, which they name Viscata, as it were
					ensnaring us when we are as yet afar off, and enforcing us
					upon business.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For an account of the various titles of Fortune at Rome, see Preller, R&ouml;mische
						Mythologie, X. &sect;1; and Plutarch on the Fortune of the Romans, &sect;&sect;5, 10. (G.)</note> Consider this now, whether it be that
					Servius found that great matters are effected by a small
					piece of Fortune, and that it often falls out that great things
					are effected by some or do come to nought by a small thing
					being done or not done. He built therefore a temple of
					Small Fortune, teaching us to take care of our business,
					and not contemn things that happen by reason of their
					smallness.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="75">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 75. Why did they not extinguish a candle,
				but suffer it to burn out of its own accord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that they adored it as being related and akin to unquenchable and eternal fire? Or
					is it a significant ceremony, teaching us that we are not to
					kill and destroy any animated creature that is harmless, fire
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.244"/>
					
					being as it were an animal? For it both needs nourishment and moves itself, and when it is extinguished it
					makes a noise as if it were then slain? Or doth this usage
					instruct us that we ought not to make waste of fire or
					water, or any other necessary thing that we have a superabundance of, but suffer those that have need to use them,
					leaving them to others when we ourselves have no further
					use for them?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="76">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 76. Why do they that would be preferred before others in gentility wear little moons on their shoes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason (as Castor saith), that this
					is a symbol of the place of habitation that is said to be in
					the moon, signifying that after death souls should have the
					moon under their feet again? Or was this a fashion of
					renown among families of greatest antiquity, as were the
					Arcadians of Evander's posterity, that were called men
					born before the moon (<foreign lang="greek">prose/lhnoi</foreign>)? Or is this, like many
					other customs, to put men who are lofty and high-minded
					in mind of the mutability of human affairs to either side,
					setting the moon before them as an example,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When first she comes from dark to light,
					</l>
                     <l>Trimming, her face becomes fair bright,
					</l>
                     <l>Increasing, till she's full in sight;
					</l>
                     <l>Declining then, leaves nought but night?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Sophocles, Frag. 786.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Or was this for a doctrine of obedience to authority,&mdash;
					that they would have us not discontented under it; but, as
					the moon doth willingly obey her superior and conform
					unto him, always vamping after the rays of the sun (as
					Parmenides hath it), so they that are subjects to any prince
					should be contented with their lower station, in the enjoyment of power and dignity derived from him?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="77">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 77. Why are they of an opinion that the year
				is Jupiter's, but the months Juno's?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because Jupiter and Juno reign over the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.245"/>
					
					invisible Gods, who are no otherwise seen but by the eyes
					of our understanding, but the Sun and Moon over the
					visible? And the Sun verily causeth the year, and the
					Moon the months. Neither ought we to think that they
					are bare images of them, but the Sun is Jupiter himself
					materially, and the Moon Juno herself materially. Therefore they name her Juno (a <hi rend="italics">juvenescendo,</hi> the name signifying a thing that is new or grows young) from the nature
					of the Moon; and they call her Lucina (as it were <hi rend="italics">bright</hi>
					or <hi rend="italics">shining),</hi> and they are of opinion that she helps women
					in their travail-pains. Whence is that of the poets:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>By azure leaven beset with stars,
					</l>
                     <l>By th' moon that hastens births;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for they suppose that women have the easiest travail at the
					full of the moon.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="78">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 78. What is the reason that a bird called <hi rend="italics">sinister</hi> in soothsaying is fortunate?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if this be not true, but the dialect deludes so many? For they render <foreign lang="greek">a)ristero/n</foreign> 
               <hi rend="italics">sinistrum;</hi> but
					to permit a thing is <hi rend="italics">sinere,</hi> and they say <hi rend="italics">sine</hi> when they
					desire a thing to be permitted; therefore a prognostic permitting an action (being <hi rend="italics">sinisterium</hi>) the vulgar do understand and call amiss <hi rend="italics">sinistrum.</hi> Or is it as Dionysius saith,
					that when Ascanius, the son of Aeneas, had pitched battle
					against Mezentius, a flash of lightning portending victory
					(as they prognosticated) came on his left hand, and for the
					future they observed it so; or, as some others say, that this
					happened to Aeneas? Moreover, the Thebans routing and
					conquering their enemies by the left wing of the army at
					Leuctra, they continued in all battles to give the left wing
					the pre-eminence. Or is it rather as Juba thinks, that to
					those that look toward the east the north is on the left
					hand, which verily some make the right hand and superior
					part of the world? Consider whether the soothsayers do
					not, as it were, corroborate left-hand things, as the weaker
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.246"/>
					
					by nature, and do intimate as if they introduced a supply
					of that defect of power that is in them. Or is it that they
					think that things terrestrial and mortal stand directly over
					against heavenly and divine things, and do conjecture that
					the things which to us are on the left hand the Gods send
					down from their right hand?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="79">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 79. Why was it lawful to bring the bones of
				one that had triumphed (after he was dead and burnt) into
				the city and lay them there, as Pyrrho the Liparaean hath
				told us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it for the honor they had for the deceased? For they granted that not only generals and other
					eminent persons, but also their offspring, should be buried
					in the market-place, for example, Valerius and Fabricius.
					And they say, when the posterity of these persons died,
					they were brought into the market-place, and a burning firebrand was put under them and immediately
					taken away; and thus all that might have caused envy
					was avoided, and the right to the honor was fully confirmed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="80">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 80. Why did they that publicly feasted the
				triumphers humbly request the consuls, and by messengers
				sent beseech them, not to come to their supper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that it was necessary to give the supreme place and most honorable entertainment to the triumpher, and wait upon him home after supper; whereas,
					the consuls being present, they might do such things to
					none other but them?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="81">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 81. Why did not the tribune of the people
				wear a purple garment, whenas each of the other magistrates wore one?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if the tribune is not a magistrate at
					all? For he neither hath lictors, nor sitting in tribunal
					doth he determine causes; neither do the tribunes, as the
					rest, enter upon their office at the beginning of the year,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.247"/>
					
					nor do they cease when a dictator is chosen; but as if
					they translated all magistratic power to themselves, they
					continue still, being (as it were) no magistrates, but holding another kind of rank. And as some rhetoricians will
					not have a prohibition to be judicial proceeding, seeing it
					doth something contrary to judicial proceeding,&mdash;for the
					one brings in an action at law and gives judgment upon
					it, but the other nonsuits it and dismisseth the cause,&mdash;
					after the like manner they are of opinion that tribuneship
					is rather a curb to magistracy, and that it is an order
					standing in opposition to government rather than a piece
					of government itself; for the tribune's office and authority
					is to withstand the magistrate's authority, even to curtail
					his extravagant power. Perhaps these and similar reasons may be mere ingenious devices; but in truth, since
					tribuneship takes its original from the people, popularity
					is its stronghold, and it is a great thing not to carry it
					above the rest of the people, but to be like the citizens
					they have to do with in gesture, habit, and diet. State
					indeed becomes a consul and a praetor; but as for a tribune (as Caius Curio saith), he must be one that even is
					trampled upon, not grave in countenance, nor difficult of
					access, nor harsh to the rabble, but more tractable to them
					than to others. Hence it was decreed that the tribune's
					doors should not be shut, but be open night and day as
					a haven and place of refuge for distressed people. And
					the more condescending his outward deportment is, by so
					much the more doth he increase in his power; for they
					dignify him as one of public use, and to be resorted to of
					all sorts even as an altar; therefore by the reverence they
					give him, he is sacred, holy, and inviolable; and when he
					makes a public progress, it is a law that every one should
					cleanse and purify the body as defiled.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="82">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 82. Why before the chief officers are rods
				carried bound together, with the axes fastened to them?</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.248"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it be a significant ceremony, to show
					that a magistrate's anger ought not to be rash and ungrounded? Or is it that, while the rods are leisurely unloosing, they make deliberation and delay in their anger,
					so that oftentimes they change their sentence as to the
					punishment? Now, whereas some sort of crimes are
					curable, some incurable, rods correct the corrigible, but
					the axes are to cut off the incorrigible.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="83">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 83. What is the reason that the Romans,
				when they were informed that the barbarians called Bletonesians had sacrificed a man to the Gods, sent for their
				magistrates to punish them; but when they made it appear that they did it in obedience to a certain law, they
				dismissed them, but prohibited the like action for the
				future; whenas they themselves, not many years preceding, buried two men and two women alive in the Forum
				Boarium, two of whom were Greeks and two Gauls? For
				it seems absurd to do this themselves, and yet to reprimand the barbarians as if they were committing profaneness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if this be the reason, that they reckoned it profane to sacrifice a man to the Gods, but necessary to do so to the Daemons? Or were they of opinion
					that they sinned that did such things by custom or law;
					but as for themselves, they did it being enjoined to it by
					the Sibylline books? For it is reported that one Elvia, a
					virgin, riding on horseback was struck with lightning and
					cast from her horse, and the horse was found lying uncovered and she naked, as if on set purpose; her clothes had
					been turned up from her secret parts, also her shoes, rings,
					and head-gear all lay scattered up and down, here and
					there; her tongue also was hanging out of her mouth.
					And when the diviners declared that it was an intolerable
					disgrace to the holy virgins that it should be published,
					and that some part of the abuse did touch the cavaliers, a
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.249"/>
					
					servant of a certain barbarian cavalier informed, that three
					vestal virgins, Aemilia, Licinia, and Martia, about the same
					time had been deflowered, and for a long time played the
					whores with some men, among whom was Butetius, the
					said informer's master. The virgins being convict were punished; and the fact appearing heinous, it was thought meet
					that the priest should consult the Sibylline books, where
					there were oracles found foretelling these things would
					come to pass for mischief to the republic, and enjoining
					them&mdash;in order to avert the impending calamity&mdash;to provide two Grecians and two Gauls, and bury them alive in
					that place, in order to the appeasing some alien and foreign
					Daemons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="84">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 84. Why do they take the beginning of the
				day from the midnight?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason that the commonweal had a
					military constitution at the first? For many matters of
					concern on military expeditions are managed by night. Or
					did they make sunrising the beginning of business, and
					the night the preparation for it? For men ought to come
					prepared to action, and not to be in preparation when they
					should be doing,&mdash;as Myso is reported to have said to
					Chilo the Wise, when he was making a fan in winter. Or
					as the noontide to many is the time for finishing public
					and weighty affairs, so did it seem meet to make midnight
					the beginning? This hath this confirmation, that a Roman
					governor would make no league or confederation in the
					afternoon. Or is it impossible to take the beginning and
					end of the day from sunrising to sunsetting? For, as the
					vulgar measure the beginning of the day by sense to be
					the first appearance of the sun, and take the first beginning
					of the night to be the complete withdrawment of the sun
					from sight, we shall thus have no equinoctial day; but the
					night which we suppose comes nearest in equality to the
					day will be manifestly shorter than the day by the diameter
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.250"/>
					
					of the sun. Which absurdity the mathematicians, going
					about to solve, have determined that, where the centre
					of the sun toucheth the horizon, there is the true parting
					point between day and night. But this contradicts sense;
					for it must follow that whilst there is much light above the
					earth, yea, the sun illuminating us, we will not for all this
					confess it to be day, but must say that it is still night.
					Whereas then it is hard to take the beginning of the day
					from the rising and setting of the sun, by reason of the
					forementioned absurdities, it remains to take the zenith and
					the nadir for the beginning. The last is best, for the sun's
					course from noon is by way of declination from us; but
					from midnight he takes his course towards us, as sunrising
					comes on.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="85">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 85. Wherefore did they not in ancient times
				suffer women to grind or play the cook?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Haply, because they remembered the covenant
					that they made with the Sabines; for after they had robbed
					them of their daughters, and fighting many battles became
					reconciled, among other articles of agreement this was recorded, that a wife was not to grind nor play the cook for
					a Roman husband.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="86">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 86. Why do they not marry wives in the
				month of May?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that because May is between
					April and June,&mdash;concerning which months they have an
					opinion that that is sacred to Venus, this to Juno, both of
					them being nuptial Gods,&mdash;they either take an opportunity
					a little before May, or tarry till it be over? Or is it that
					in this month they offer the greatest expiatory sacrifice,
					now casting the images of men from a bridge into the
					river, and formerly men themselves? Moreover, it is by
					law required that the Flaminica, the reputed priestess of
					Juno, should be most sourly sullen during the time, and
					neither wash nor trim up herself. Or is it because many
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.251"/>
					
					of the Latins in this month offer oblations unto the dead?
					And therefore perhaps they worship Mercury in this
					month, which from Maia derives its name? Or, as some
					say, is May derived from elder age (maior) and Juno from
					younger (iunior)? For youth is more suitable to matrimony, as Euripides hath said,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>age the Cyprian queen must ever shun,
					</l>
                     <l>And Venus from old men in scorn doth run.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore they marry not in May, but tarry till June, which
					is presently after May.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="87">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 87. Why do they part the hair of women
				when they are married with the point of a spear?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if it be a significant ceremony, showing
					that they took their first wives in marriage by force of arms
					and war? Or is it that they may instruct them that they
					are to dwell with husbands that are soldiers and warriors,
					and that they should put on such ornamental attire as is
					not luxurious or lascivious, but plain? So Lycurgus commanded that all the gates and tops of houses should be
					built with saw and hatchet, and no other sort of workmen's
					instrument should be used about them; yea, he rejected
					all gayety and superfluity. Or doth this action parabolically intimate divorce, as that marriage can be dissolved
					only by the sword? Or is it that most of these nuptial
					ceremonies relate to Juno? For a spear is decreed sacred
					to Juno, and most of her statues are supported by a spear,
					and she is surnamed Quiritis, and a spear of old was called
					<hi rend="italics">quiris,</hi> wherefore they surname Mars Quirinus?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="88">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 88. Why do they call the money that is laid
				out upon the public plays <hi rend="italics">lucar?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because there are many groves consecrated to the Gods about the city, which they call <hi rend="italics">luci,</hi> and
					the revenue of these they expend upon the said plays?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="89">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 89. Why do they call the Quirinalia the Feast
				of Fools?</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.252"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because they set apart that day for
					those that were unacquainted with their own curiae, as
					Juba saith? Or was it for them that did not sacrifice with
					their tribes, as the rest did, in the Fornicalia, by reason of
					business or long journeys or ignorance, so that it was
					allowed to them to solemnize that feast upon this day?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="90">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 90. What is the reason that, when there is
				a sacrifice to Hercules, they mention no other God and no
				dog appears within the enclosure, as Varro saith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason of their naming no other God,
					because they are of opinion that Hercules was but a half
					God? And, as some say, Evander built an altar to him and
					brought him a sacrifice, whilst he was yet here among men.
					And of all creatures he had most enmity to a dog, for this
					creature always held him hard to it, as (lid Cerberus; and
					that which most of all prejudiced him was that, when
					Oeonus, the son of Licymnius, was slain for a dog's sake
					by the Hippocoontidae, he was necessitated to take up the
					cudgels, and lost many of his friends and his brother
					Iphicles.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="91">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 91. Why was it unlawful for the patricians
				to dwell about the Capitol?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because M. Manlius, whilst he dwelt
					there, affected arbitrary government; upon whose account
					the family came under an oath of abjuration that no Manlius should for the future bear the name of Marcus? Or
					was this an ancient suspicion? For the potent men would
					never leave calumniating Publicola, a most popular man,
					nor would the common people leave fearing him till he
					had plucked down his house, which seemed to hang over
					the market-place.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="92">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 92. Why do they put on a garland of oaken
				leaves on him that saves a citizen in battle?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because it is easy to find an oak everywhere in the military expeditions? Or is it because a
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.253"/>
					
					crown is sacred to Jupiter and Juno, who in their opinion
					are the city guardians? Or was it an ancient custom
					among the Arcadians, who are something akin to the oak?
					For they repute themselves the first men produced of the
					earth, as the oak among the vegetables.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="93">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 93. Why do they for the most part use vultures for soothsaying?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was this the reason, because twelve vultures
					appeared to Romulus upon the building of Rome? Or
					because of all birds this is least frequent and familiar?
					For it is not easy to meet with young vultures, but they fly
					to us unexpectedly from some remote parts; therefore the
					sight of them is portentous. Or haply they learned this
					from Hercules, if Herodotus speak true that Hercules rejoiced most in the beginning of an enterprise at the sight
					of a vulture, being of opinion that a vulture was the justest of all birds of prey. For first, he meddles not with
					any living creature, neither doth he destroy any thing that
					hath breath in it, as eagles, hawks, and other fowls do
					that prey by night, but lives only upon dead carcasses; and
					next, he passeth by all those of his kind, for none ever saw
					a vulture feeding on a bird, as eagles and hawks do, which
					for the most part pursue birds like themselves, and slay
					them, even as Aeschylus hath it,
					<quote rend="blockquote">A bird that preys on birds, how can't be clean?</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And verily this bird is not pernicious to men, for it neither
					destroys fruits nor plants, nor is hurtful to any tame animal.
					Moreover if it be (as the Egyptians fabulously pretend)
					that the whole kind of them is of the female sex, and that
					they conceive by the reception of the east wind into their
					bodies, as the trees do by receiving the west wind, it is
					most probable that very certain and sound prognostics may
					be made from them; whereas in other birds (there being
					so many rapines, flights, and pursuits about copulation)
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.254"/>
					
					there are great disturbances and uncertainties attending
					them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="94">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 94. For what reason is the temple of Aesculapius placed without the city?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because they reckoned it a wholesomer
					kind of living without the city than within? For the
					Greeks have placed the edifices belonging to Aesculapius
					for the most part on high places, where the air is pure and
					clear. Or is it that they suppose this God was fetched
					from Epidaurus? For the temple of Aesculapius is not
					close by that city, but at a great distance from it. Or is it
					that, by a serpent that went on shore out of a trireme galley into the island and disappeared, they think the God
					himself intimated to them the place of building his temple?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="95">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 95. Why was it ordained that they that were
				to live chaste should abstain from pulse?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Did they, like the Pythagoreans, abominate
					beans for the causes which are alleged, and the lathyrus
					and erebinthus as being named from Lethe and Erebus?
					Or was it because they used pulse for the most part in
					their funeral feasts and invocations of the dead? Or rather
					was it because they should bring empty and slender bodies
					to their purifications and expiations? For pulse are windy,
					and cause a great deal of excrements that require purging
					off. Or is it because they irritate lechery, by reason of
					their flatulent and windy nature?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="96">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 96. Why do they inflict no other punishment
				on Vestal Virgins, when they are defiled, than burying them
				alive?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, because they burn the
					dead, and to bury her by fire who hath not preserved
					sacred the divine fire would be unjust? Or was it that
					they judged it a wicked act to cut off a person sanctified
					by the greatest ceremonial purification, and to lay hands
					on a holy woman; and therefore they contrived a machine
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.255"/>
					
					for her to die in of herself, and let her down into a vault
					made under ground, where was placed a candle burning,
					also some bread and milk and water, and then the den was
					covered with earth on top? Neither by this execrable
					manner of devoting them are they exempt from superstition; but to this day the priests going to the place perform
					purgatory rites.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="97">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 97. What is the reason that, at the horse-race
				on the Ides of December, the lucky horse that beats is
				sacrificed as sacred to Mars; and a certain man, cutting off
				his tail, brings it to a place called Regia, and besmears the
				altar with the blood of it; but for the head, one party
				coming down from the way called Sacred, and others from
				the Suburra, do fight?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Whether was it (as some say) that, reckoning
					that Troy was taken by a horse, they punish a horse, as
					being the
					<quote rend="blockquote">Renowned Trojan race commixt with Latin boys?</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Or is it because a horse is a fierce, warlike, and martial
					beast, therefore they do sacrifice to the Gods the things
					that are most acceptable and suitable; and he that conquers is offered, because victory and prowess doth belong
					to that God? Or is it rather because to stand in battle is
					the work of God, and they that keep their ranks and files
					do conquer those that do not keep them but fly, and swiftness of foot is punished as the maintenance of cowardice;
					so that hereby it is significantly taught that there is no
					safety to them that run away?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="98">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 98. What is the reason that the censors entering upon their office do nothing before they have contracted for providing meat for the sacred geese, and for polishing the statue?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that they begin with those
					things that savor of most frugality, and such things as want
					not much charge and trouble? Or is it in grateful commemoration
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.256"/>
					
					 of what these creatures did of old, when the
					Gauls invaded Rome and the barbarians scaled the walls
					of the Capitol by night? For the geese were sensible of
					it when the dogs were asleep, and they with their gaggling
					awaked the watch? Or, seeing the censors are the con
					servers of such things as are of greatest and most necessary
					concern,&mdash;to oversee and narrowly inspect the public sacrifices, and the lives, manners, and diet of men,&mdash;do they
					presently set before their consideration the most vigilant
					creature, and by the watchfulness of these instruct the
					citizens not to disregard or neglect sacred things? As
					for the polishing of the statue, it is necessary, for the
					minium (wherewith they of old colored the statues) soon
					fades.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="99">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 99. What is the reason that of the other priests
				they depose any one that is condemned or banished, and
				substitute another in his room; but remove not the augur
				from his priesthood so long as he lives, though he be convicted of the greatest crimes? They call them augurs who
				are employed in soothsaying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason (as some say) that they will
					have none to know the mysteries of the priests who is not
					a priest? Or that the augur is bound by oath to discover
					to none the management of sacred things; therefore they
					refuse to absolve him from his oath, when he is reduced to
					a private capacity? Or is it that the name of augur is not
					a title of honor and dignity, but of skill and art? It would
					therefore be the like case to depose a musician from being
					a musician or a physician from being a physician, with that
					of prohibiting a diviner from being a diviner; seeing they
					cannot take away his faculty, though they deprive him of
					the title. Moreover they do not substitute augurs, because
					they will keep to the number of augurs that were at the
					beginning.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="100">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 100. What is the reason that in the Ides of
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.257"/>
				
				August (which at first they called Sextilis) all the menservants and maid-servants do feast, but the free women
				make it most of their business to wash and purge their
				heads?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that King Servius about this day was
					born of a captive maid-servant, and hence the servants have
					a vacation time from work; and that rinsing the head was
					a thing that took its original from a custom of the maidservants upon the account of the feast, and finally passed
					also into the free women?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="101">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 101. Why do they finify their boys with necklaces, which they call <hi rend="italics">bullae?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> What if this were for the honor of the wives
					which were taken by force? For as many other things, so
					this might be one of the injunctions laid on their posterity.
					Or did they it in honor of Tarquin's manhood? For it is
					reported of him that, whilst he was but a boy, being engaged in a battle against the Latins and Tuscans, charging
					his enemies, he fell from his horse; yet animating those
					Romans which were engaged in the charge, he led them on
					courageously. The enemies were put to a remarkable
					rout, and sixteen thousand were slain; whereupon he had
					this badge of honor bestowed upon him by his father the
					king. Or was it that by the ancients it was neither lewd
					nor dishonorable to love beautiful slaves (as now the comedies testify), but that they resolvedly abstained from freeborn servants; and lest, by coming accidentally on naked
					boys, they should ignorantly transgress, the free boys wore
					this mark of distinction? Or was this a protector of good
					order, and after a manner a curb of incontinency; they
					being ashamed to pretend to manhood before they have
					put off the badge of children? That which they say who
					follow Varro is not probable, that <hi rend="italics">boule</hi> by the Aeolians is
					called <hi rend="italics">bolla,</hi> and this is put about children as a teaching
					sign of good counsel. But consider whether they do not
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.258"/>
					
					wear it for the moon's sake. For the visible face of the
					moon, when it is halved, is not spherical, but shaped like
					a lentil or a quoit; and (as Empedocles supposeth) so is
					also the side that is turned away from us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="102">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 102. Why do they name boys when they are
				nine days old, and girls when they are eight?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Perhaps it's a natural reason, that girls are
					forwarder, for the female grows up and comes to full stature
					and perfection before the male. But they take the day
					after the seventh, because the seventh is dangerous to infants by reason of the navel-string; for with many it falls
					off at seven days, and until it falls off, an infant is more
					like a plant than an animal. Or is it, as the Pythagoreans
					reckon, that the even number is the feminine, and the odd
					number the masculine? For it is a fruitful number, and
					excels the even in respect of its composition. And if these
					numbers be divided into units, the even, like a female, hath
					an empty space in the middle; the odd number always
					leaves a segment full in the middle, wherefore this is fit
					to be compared to the male, that to the female. Or is it
					thus, that of all numbers nine is the first square number
					made of three, which is an odd and perfect number, but
					eight is the first cube made of two, an even number;
					whence a male ought to be square, superexcelling, and
					complete; but a woman, like a cube, constant, a good
					housewife, and no gadding gossip? This also may be
					added that, as eight is a cube from the root two, and nine
					a square from the root three, so the female makes use of
					two names, and the males of three.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="103">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 103. Why do they call those whose fathers
				are not known <hi rend="italics">Spurius?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> It is not verily&mdash;as the Grecians suppose
					and as the rhetoricians say in their determinations&mdash;because they are begot of some promiscuous and common
					seed (as the Greeks say <foreign lang="greek">spo/ros</foreign>). But Spurius is found
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.259"/>
					
					among first names, as Sextus, Decimus, Caius. But the
					Romans do not write all the letters of the first name; but
					either one letter, as T. for Titus, L. for Lucius, M. for
					Marcus; or two letters, as Ti. for Tiberius, Cn. for Cnaeus;
					or three, as Sex. for Sextus, and Ser. for Servius. Now
					Spurius is of those that are written with two letters, Sp.
					But with these same letters they write <hi rend="italics">without father,</hi> S.
					for <hi rend="italics">sine,</hi> and P. for <hi rend="italics">patre,</hi> which truly hath caused the mistake. Moreover, we may meet with another reason, but it
					is more absurd. They say, that the Sabines called the privities of a woman <hi rend="italics">spurious;</hi> and therefore they call him so,
					by way of reproach, who is born of a woman unmarried
					and unespoused.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="104">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 104. Why did they call Bacchus Liber
				Pater?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was the reason because they make him, as
					it were, the father of liberty to tipplers? For most men
					become very audacious and are filled with too much licentious prattle, by reason of too much drink. Or is this it,
					that he hath supplied them with a libamen, a drink-offering? Or is it, as Alexander hath said, that Bacchus is called
					Eleutherius from his having his abode about Eleutherae, a
					city of Boeotia?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="105">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 105. For what cause was it, that on high holidays it was not a custom for virgins to marry, but widows
				did marry then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is the reason, as Varro saith, that virgins,
					forsooth, are married weeping, but women with joyful
					glee, and people are to do nothing of a holiday with a
					heavy heart nor by compulsion? Or rather is it because
					it is decent for virgins to marry with more than a few present, but for widows to marry with a great many present is
					indecent? For the first marriage is zealously affected, the
					second to be deprecated; yea, they are ashamed to marry
					a second husband while their first husband lives, and they
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.260"/>
					
					grieve at doing so even when he is dead. Hence they are
					pleased more with silence than with tumults and pompous
					doings; and the feasts do attract the generality of people
					to them, so that they cannot be at leisure on holidays for
					such wedding solemnities. Or was it that they that robbed
					the Sabines of their daughters that were virgins on the
					feast-day raised thereby a war, and looked therefore upon
					it as unlucky to marry virgins on holidays?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="106">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 106. Why do the Romans worship Fortuna
				Primigenia?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because Servius, being by Fortune
					born of a servant-maid, came to rule king in Rome with
					great splendor? And this is the supposition of most
					Romans. Or rather is it that Fortune hath bestowed on
					Rome itself its very original and birth? Or may not this
					matter require a more natural and philosophical reason,
					even that Fortune is the original of all things and that
					Nature itself is produced out of things that come by Fortune, when events that come by chance fall into an order
					among themselves?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="107">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 107. Why do the Romans call the artists who
				appear in the worship of Bacchus <hi rend="italics">histriones?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it for the reason which C. Rufus tells us?
					For he says, that in ancient time, C. Sulpicius and Licinius
					Stolo, being consuls, a pestilence raging in Rome, all the
					actors upon the stage were cut off; wherefore, upon the
					request of the Romans, many and good artists came from
					Etruria, among whom he that excelled in fame and had
					been longest experienced on the public stages was called
					Histrus, and from him they named all the stage-players.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="108">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 108. Why do not men marry women that are
				near akin?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is this the reason, that they design by marriage to augment their family concerns and to procure
					many relations, by giving wives to strangers and marrying
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.261"/>
					
					wives out of other families? Or do they suspect that the
					contentions that would happen among relations upon marriage would destroy even natural rights? Or is it that,
					considering that wives by reason of weakness stand in need
					of many helpers, they would not have near akin marry
					together, that their own kindred might stand by them
					when their husbands wrong them?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="109">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 109. Why is it not lawful for the high priest
				of Jupiter, which they call Flamen Dialis, to touch meal
				or leaven?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because meal is imperfect and crude
					nourishment? For the wheat neither hath continued what
					it was, neither is it made into bread as it must be ; but it
					hath lost the faculty of seed, and hath not attained to usefulness for food. Wherefore the poet hath named meal,
					by a metaphor, <hi rend="italics">mill-murdered</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">mulh/faton</foreign>), as if the corn
					were spoiled and destroyed by grinding. Leaven, as it is
					made by corruption, corrupts the mass that it is mingled
					with, for it is made thereby looser and weaker; and fermentation is a kind of corruption, which, if it be overmuch, makes the bread sour and spoils it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="110">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 110. Why is the same high priest forbid to
				touch raw flesh?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it because custom makes them averse
					enough to raw flesh? Or is it that the same reason that
					makes them averse to meal doth also make them averse to
					flesh; for it is neither a living creature nor dressed food?
					Roasting or boiling, being an alteration and change, doth
					change its form; but fresh and raw flesh offers not a pure
					and unpolluted object to the eye, but such as is offensive
					to the eye, and like that of a raw wound.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="111">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 111. Why do they require the priest to abstain from a dog and a goat, and neither to touch or name
				them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it that they abominated the lasciviousness
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.262"/>
					
					 and stink of a goat, or that they suspected it to be a
					diseased creature? For it seems this animal is more seized
					with the falling sickness than other creatures, and is contagious to them that eat or touch it while it hath this disease; they say, the cause is the straightness of the windpipe, often intercepting the breath, a sign of which they
					make the smallness of their voice to be; for it happens to
					men that are epileptical, that they utter a voice sounding
					much like the bleat of a goat. Now in a dog there may
					be less of lasciviousness and of an ill scent; although
					some say that dogs are not permitted to go into the high
					streets of Athens&mdash;no, not into the island Delos&mdash;by
					reason of their open coition; as if kine, swine, and horses
					did use coition in bed-chambers, and not openly and lawlessly. They do not know the true reason,&mdash;that, because
					a dog is a quarrelsome creature, they therefore expel dogs
					out of sanctuaries and sacred temples, giving safe access
					to suppliants for refuge. Wherefore it is very likely that
					the priest of Jupiter, being (as it were) an animated and
					sacred image, granted for refuge to petitioners and suppliants, doth banish or fright away none. For which
					cause a couch was set for him in the porch of the house,
					and they that fell on their knees before him had indemnity from stripes or punishment that day; and if one in
					fetters came and addressed him, he was unloosed, and his
					fetters were not laid down by the door but thrown from
					the roof. It would be therefore no advantage that he
					should carry himself so mild and courteous, if there were
					a dog at the door, scaring and frighting them that petitioned for sanctuary. Neither did the ancients at all repute this creature clean; for he is offered in sacrifice to
					none of the celestial Gods, but being sent to Hecate, an
					infernal Goddess, at the three cross-ways for a supper,
					takes a share in averting calamities and in expiations. In
					Lacedaemon they cut puppies in pieces to Mars, that
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.263"/>
					
					most cruel God. In Boeotia public expiation is made by
					passing between the parts of a dog divided in twain.
					But the Romans sacrifice a dog in the cleansing month, on
					the festival which they call Lupercalia. Hence it was not
					without cause, to prohibit them whose charge it was to
					worship the highest and holiest God from making a dog
					familiar and customed to them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="112">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 112. What is the reason that the priest of
				Jupiter is forbid to touch an ivy, or to pass over that way
				that is overspread with vine branches?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Is it not of the like nature with those precepts of Pythagoras, not to eat in a chair, not to sit upon
					a measure called a choenix, and not to step over a broom?
					For the Pythagoreans do not dread and refrain from these
					things, but they prohibit other things by these. Now to
					go under a vine hath reference to wine, because it is not
					lawful for a priest to be drunk. For the wine is above
					the heads of those that are drunk, and they are depraved
					and debased thereby; whereas it is requisite that they
					should be above pleasure and conquer it, but not be subdued by it. As for the ivy,&mdash;it being unfruitful and useless to men, as also infirm, and by reason of its infirmity
					standing in need of other trees to climb upon, though by
					its shadow and sight of its greenness it doth bewitch the
					vulgar,&mdash;what if they judge it not convenient to nourish
					it about a house because it bringeth no profit, or to suffer it to clasp about any thing, seeing it is so hurtful to
					plants that bear it up, while it sticketh fast in the ground?
					Hence ivy is forbidden at the Olympic festivals, and neither
					at Athens in Juno's sacrifices, nor at Thebes in those belonging to Venus, can any wild ivy be seen; though in
					the Agrionia and Nyctelia (which are services to Bacchus
					for the most part performed in the dark) it is to be found.
					Or was this a symbol of the prohibition of revels and sports
					of Bacchus? For women that were addicted to Bacchanal
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.264"/>
					
					sports presently ran to the ivy and plucked it off, tearing
					it in pieces with their hands and gnawing it with their
					mouths, so that they are not altogether to be disbelieved
					that say it hath a spirit in it that stirreth and moveth to
					madness, transporting and bereaving of the senses, and
					that alone by itself it introduceth drunkenness without
					wine to those that have an easy inclination to enthusiasm.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="113">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Question</hi> 113. Why are not these priests allowed to
				take upon them or attempt civil authority, while they have
				a lictor and a curule chair for honor's sake, and in some
				sort of consolation for their being excluded from magistracies?</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Solution.</hi> Was it because in some places of Greece
					the dignity of priesthood was equal with kingship, and
					therefore they designated not ordinary persons to be priests?
					Or was it rather,&mdash;since they have appointed office-employments, whereas the charge of kings is unmethodical
					and indefinite,&mdash;that it would not be possible, if both fell
					out at the same time, that he should be able to attend both,
					but he must of necessity neglect one (both pressing together upon him), sometimes neglecting the worship of
					God, and sometimes injuring the subjects? Or else, seeing that there is no less necessity than power attending
					the administration of civil government, and that the ruler
					of the people (as Hippocrates saith of the physician) doth
					see weighty matters and hath to do with weighty matters,
					and from other men's calamities procures troubles peculiar
					to himself, did they think 'him not sacred enough to sacrifice to the Gods and manage the sacrifices who had been
					present at the condemnation and execution of citizens, and
					often of some of his own kindred and family, as happened
					to Brutus?</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>