<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Quomodo adulator ab amico internoscatur</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.070">
      <body>
         <head>How to know a flatterer from a friend. <lb/> To Antiochus Philopappus.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.100"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>PLATO is of opinion that it is very pardonable in a
					man to acknowledge that he has any extraordinary passion
					for himself; and yet the humor is attended with this ill
					consequent, besides several others, that it renders us incapable of making a right judgment of ourselves. For our
					affections usually blind our discerning faculties, unless we
					have learned to raise them above the sordid level of things
					congenial and familiar to us, to those which are truly noble
					and excellent in themselves. And hence it is that we are
					so frequently exposed to the attempts of a parasite, under
					the disguise and vizard of a friend. For self-love, that
					grand flatterer within, willingly entertains another from
					without, who will but soothe up and second the man in
					the good opinions he has conceived of himself. For he
					who deservedly lies under the character of one that loves
					to be flattered is doubtless sufficiently fond of himself: and
					through abundance of complaisance to his own person, not
					only wishes but thinks himself master of all those perfections which may recommend him to others. And though
					indeed it be laudable enough to covet such accomplishments, yet is it altogether unsafe for any man to fancy
					them inherent in him.</p>
            <p>Now, if truth be a ray of the divinity, as Plato says it
						is, and the source of all the good that derives upon either
						Gods or men, then certainly the flatterer must be looked
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.101"/>
						
						upon as a public enemy to all the Gods, and especially to
						Apollo; for he always acts counter to that celebrated
						oracle of his, Know thyself, endeavoring to make every
						man his own cheat, by keeping him ignorant of the good
						and ill qualities that are in him; whereupon the good
						never arrive at perfection, and the ill grow incorrigible.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Did flattery, indeed, as most other misfortunes do,
					generally or altogether wait on the debauched and ignoble
					part of mankind, the mischief were of less consequence,
					and might admit of an easier prevention. But, as worms
					breed most in sweet and tender woods, so usually the most
					obliging, the most brave and generous tempers readiliest
					receive and longest entertain the flattering insect that
					hangs and grows upon them. And since, to use Simonides's expression, it is not for persons of a narrow fortune,
					but for gentlemen of estates, to keep a good stable of
					horses; so never saw we flattery the attendant of the poor,
					the inglorious and inconsiderable plebeian, but of the grandees of the world, the distemper and bane of great families
					and affairs, the plague in kings' chambers, and the ruin of
					their kingdoms. Therefore it is a business of no small
					importance, and one which requires no ordinary circumspection, so to be able to know a flatterer in every shape
					he assumes, that the counterfeit resemblance some time or
					other bring not true friendship itself into suspicion and disrepute. For parasites,&mdash;like lice, which desert a dying man,
					whose palled and vapid blood can feed them no longer,&mdash;
					never intermix in dry and insipid business where there is
					nothing to be got; but prey upon a noble quarry, the ministers of state and potentates of the earth, and afterwards
					lousily shirk off, if the greatness of their fortune chance to
					leave them. But it will not be wisdom in us to stay till
					such fatal junctures, and then try the experiment, which
					will not only be useless but dangerous and hurtful; for it
					is a deplorable thing for a man to find himself then destitute
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.102"/>
					
					of friends, when he most wants them, and has no opportunity
					either of exchanging his false and faithless friend for a fast
					and honest one. And therefore we should rather try our
					friend, as we do our money, whether or not he be passable
					and current, before we need him. For it is not enough to
					discover the cheat to our cost, but we must so understand
					the flatterer, that he put no cheat upon us ; otherwise we
					should act like those who must needs take poison to know
					its strength, and foolishly hazard their lives to inform their
					judgment. And as we cannot approve of this carelessness,
					so neither can we of that too scrupulous humor of those
					who, taking the measures of true friendship only from the
					bare honesty and usefulness of the man, immediately suspect a pleasant and easy conversation for a cheat. For a
					friend is not a dull tasteless thing, nor does the decorum
					of friendship consist in sourness and austerity of temper,
					but its very port and gravity is soft and amiable,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">Where Love and all the Graces do reside.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Theogony, 64.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For it is not only a comfort to the afflicted,
						<quote rend="blockquote">To enjoy the courtesy of his kindest friend,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Ion, 732.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Euripides speaks; but friendship extends itself to both
						fortunes, as well brightens and adorns prosperity as allays
						the sorrows that attend adversity. And as Evenus used to
						say that fire makes the best sauce, so friendship, wherewith
						God has seasoned the circumstances of our mortality, gives
						a relish to every condition, renders them all easy, sweet,
						and agreeable enough. And indeed, did not the laws of
						friendship admit of a little pleasantry and good humor, why
						should the parasite insinuate himself under that disguise?
						And yet he, as counterfeit gold imitates the brightness and
						lustre of the true, always puts on the easiness and freedom
						of a friend, is always pleasant and obliging, and ready to
						comply with the humor of his company. And therefore it
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.103"/>
						
						is no way reasonable either, to look upon every just character that is given us as a piece of flattery; for certainly a
						due and seasonable commendation is as much the duty of
						one friend to another as a pertinent and serious reprehension; nay indeed, a sour querulous temper is perfectly
						repugnant to the laws of friendship and conversation;
						whereas a man takes a chiding patiently from a friend who
						is as ready to praise his virtues as to animadvert upon his
						vices, willingly persuading himself that mere necessity
						obliged him to reprimand, whom kindness had first moved
						to commend.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Why then, some may say, it is infinitely difficult at
					this rate to distinguish a flatterer from a friend, since there
					is no apparent difference either betwixt the satisfaction
					they create or the praises they bestow. Nay, it is observable, that a parasite is frequently more obsequious and
					obliging than a friend himself. Well, the way then to
					discover the disparity? Why, I will tell you; if you
					would learn the character of a true subtle flatterer, who
					nicks his point <hi rend="italics">secundum artem,</hi> you must not, with the
					vulgar, mistake those sordid smell-feasts and poor trencher-slaves for your men, who begin to prate as soon as they
					have washed their hands in order to dinner, as one says
					of them, and ere they are well warmed with a good cut
					of the first dish and a glass of wine, betray the narrow
					soul that acts them by the nauseous and fulsome buffoonery they vent at table. For sure it needed no great sagacity to detect the flattery of Melanthius, the parasite of
					Alexander of Pherae, who, being asked how his master
					was murdered, made answer, With a thrust which went
					in at his side, but into my belly. Nor must we, again,
					confine our notions of flatterers to those sharping fellows
					who ply about rich men's tables, whom neither fire nor
					sword nor porter can keep from supper; nor yet to such
					as were those female parasites of Cyprus, who going into
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.104"/>
					
					Syria were nick-named Steps, because they cringed so to
					the great ladies of that country that they mounted their
					chariots on their backs.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Well, but after all, who is this flatterer then, whom
					we ought so industriously to avoid?</p>
            <p>I answer: He who neither professes nor seems to flatter;
						who never haunts your kitchen, is never observed to watch
						the dial that he may nick your supper-time; who won't
						drink to excess, but will keep his brains about him; who
						is prying and inquisitive, would mix in your business, and
						wind himself into your secrets: in short, he who acts the
						friend, not with the air of a comedian or a satirist, but
						with the port and gravity of a tragedian. For, as Plato
						says, It is the height of injustice to appear just and be
						really a knave. So are we to look upon those flatterers
						as most dangerous who walk not barefaced but in disguise, who make no sport but mind their. business; for
						these often personate the true and sincere friend so exactly, that it is enough to make him fall under the like
						suspicion of a cheat, unless we be extremely curious in
						remarking the difference betwixt them. It is storied of
						Gobryas (one of the Persian nobility, who joined with
						Darius against the Magi), that he pursued one of them
						into a dark room, and there fell upon him; during the
						scuffle Darius came in and drew upon the enemy, but durst
						not push at him, lest perhaps he might wound his confederate Gobryas with the thrust; whereupon Gobryas
						bade him, rather than fail, run both through together.
						But since we can by no means admit of that vulgar saying,
						Let my friend perish, so my enemy perish with him, but
						had rather still endeavor at the discovery of a parasite
						from a friend, notwithstanding the nearness of the resemblance, we ought to use our utmost care, lest at any time
						we indifferently reject the good with the bad, or unadvisedly retain the bad with the good, the friend and flatterer
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.105"/>
						
						 together. For as those wild grains which usually
						grow up with wheat, and are of the same figure and bigness with it, are not easily winnowed from it,&mdash;for they
						either cannot pass through the holes of the sieve, if narrow, or pass together with the wheat, if larger,&mdash;so is it
						infinitely difficult to distinguish flattery from friendship,
						because the one so exquisitely mixes with all the passions,
						humors, interests, and inclinations of the other.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Now because the enjoyment of a friend is attended
					with the greatest satisfaction incident to humanity, therefore the flatterer always endeavors to entrap us by rendering his conversation highly pleasant and agreeable.
					Again, because all acts of kindness and mutual beneficence are' the constant attendants upon true friendship (on
					which account we usually say, A friend is more necessary
					than fire or water), therefore the flatterer is ready upon
					every occasion to obtrude his service upon you, and will
					with an indefatigable bustle and zeal seek to oblige you
					if he can.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the parasite observes that all true
						friendship takes its origin from a concurrence of like humors and inclinations, and that the same passions, the
						same aversions and desires, are the first cement of a true
						and lasting friendship. He therefore composes his nature,
						like unformed matter, striving to fit and adapt it by imitation to the person on whom he designs, that it may be
						pliant and yielding to any impression that he shall think
						fit to stamp upon it; and, in fine, he so neatly resembles
						the original, that one would swear,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">Sure thou the very Achilles art, and not his son.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the most exquisite fineness of a flatterer consists in
						his imitation of that freedom of discourse which friends
						particularly use in mutually reprehending each other. For
						finding that men usually take it for what it really is, the
						natural language of friendship, as peculiar to it as certain
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.106"/>
						
						notes or voices are to certain animals, and that, on the
						contrary, a shy sheepish reservedness looks both rude and
						unfriendly, he lets not even this proper character of a
						friend escape his imitation. But as skilful cooks use to
						correct luscious meats with sharp and poignant sauce, that
						they may not be so apt to overcharge the stomach; so he
						seasons his flattery now and then with a little smartness
						and severity, lest the fulsomeness of repeated dissimulation should pall and cloy the company. And yet his reprehensions always carry something in them that looks not
						true and genuine; he seems to do it, but with a kind of
						a sneering and grinning countenance at the best; and
						though his reproofs may possibly tickle the ear, yet they
						never strike effectually upon the heart. On these accounts
						then it is as difficult to discern a flatterer from a friend, as
						to know those animals again which always wear the livery
						of the last thing they touch upon. And therefore, since
						he puts so easily upon us under the disguise and appearance of a friend, it will be our business at present to unmask the hypocrite, and show him in other men's shapes
						and colors, as Plato speaks, since he has none properly his
						own.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Well then, let us enquire regularly into this affair.
					We have already asserted, that friendship generally takes
					its rise from a conformity of tempers and dispositions,
					whereby different persons come to have the same taste of
					the like humors, customs, studies, exercises, and employs,
					as these following verses import:&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Old men with old, and boys with boys agree;
					</l>
                     <l>And women's clack with women's company.
					</l>
                     <l>Men that are crazy, full of sores and pain,
					</l>
                     <l>Love to diseased persons to complain.
					</l>
                     <l>And they who labor under adverse fate,
					</l>
                     <l>Tell their sad stories to th' unfortunate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The flatterer then, observing how congenial it is to our
						natures to delight in the conversation of those who are, as
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.107"/>
						
						it were, the counterpart of ourselves, makes his first approaches to our affections at this avenue, where he gradually advances (like one making towards a wild beast in a
						pasture, with a design to tame and bring it to hand) by
						accommodating himself to the same studies, business, and
						color of life with the person upon whom he designs, till
						at last the latter gives him an opportunity to catch him,
						and becomes tractable by the man who strokes him. All
						this while the flatterer falls foul upon those courses of
						life, persons, and things he perceives his cully to disapprove, and again as extravagantly commends those he is
						pleased to honor with his approbation, still persuading
						him that his choice and dislike are the results of a solid
						and discerning judgment and not of passion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Well, then, by what signs or tokens shall we be able
					to know this counterfeit copy of ourselves from a true and
					genuine likeness?</p>
            <p>In the first place, we must accurately remark upon the
						whole tenor of his life and conversation, whether or not
						the resemblance he pretends to the original be of any continuance, natural and easy, and all of a piece; whether he
						square his actions according to any one steady and uniform
						model, as becomes an ingenuous lover of conversation and
						friendship, which is all of one thread, and still like itself;
						for this is a true friend indeed. But the flatterer, who has
						no principles in him, and leads not a life properly his own,
						but forms and moulds it according to the various humors
						and caprices of those he designs to bubble, is never one
						and the same man, but a mere dapple or trimmer, who
						changes shapes with his company, like water that always
						turns and winds itself into the figure of the channel
						through which it flows. Apes, it seems, are usually
						caught by their antic mimicry of the motions and gesticulations of men; and yet the men themselves are
						trepanned by the same craft of imitation in a flatterer,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.108"/>
						
						who adapts himself to their several humors, fencing and
						wrestling with one, singing and dancing with another. If
						he is in chase of a spark that delights in a pack of dogs,
						he follows him at the heels, hollowing almost like Phaedra,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O what a pleasure 'tis, ye Gods, to wind
						</l>
                     <l>The shrill-mouthed horn and chase the dappled hind;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 218.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and yet the hunter himself is the game he designs for the
						toils. If he be in pursuit of some bookish young gentleman, then he is always a poring, he nourishes his reverend
						beard down to his heels, wears a tattered cloak, affects the
						careless indifference of a philosopher, and can now discourse of nothing under Plato's triangles and rectangles.
						If he chance to fall into the acquaintance of a drunken,
						idle debauchee who has got an estate,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Then sly Ulysses throws away his rags,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XXII. I.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>puts off his long robe, mows down his fruitless crop of
						beard, drinks briskly, laughs modishly on the walks, and
						drolls handsomely upon the philosophical fops of the town.
						And thus, they say, it happened at Syracuse; for when
						Plato first arrived there and Dionysius was wonderfully hot
						upon the study of philosophy, all the areas in the king's
						palace were full of nothing but dust and sand, by reason
						of the great concourse of geometricians who came to draw
						their figures and demonstrate there. But no sooner was
						Plato in disgrace at court, and Dionysius finally fallen from
						philosophy to wine and women, trifles and intemperance,
						than learning fell into a general disrepute, and the whole
						body of the people, as if bewitched by some Circe or other,
						became universally stupid, idle, and infatuated. Besides
						this. I appeal to the practices of men notorious for flattery
						and popularity to back my observation. Witness he who
						topped them all, Alcibiades, who, when he dwelt at Athens,
						was as arch and witty as any Athenian of them all, kept
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.109"/>
						
						his stable of horses, played the good fellow, and was universally obliging; and yet the same man at Sparta slaved
						close to the skin, wore his cloak, and never bathed but in
						cold water. When he sojourned in Thrace, he drank and
						fought like a Thracian; and again, in Tissaphernes's company in Asia, he acted the part of a soft, arrogant, and
						voluptuous Asiatic. And thus, by an easy compliance with
						the humors and customs of the people amongst whom he
						conversed, he made himself master of their affections and
						interests. So did not the brave Epaminondas nor Agesilaus, who, though they had to do with great variety of men
						and manners, and cities of vastly different politics, were
						still the same men, and everywhere, through the whole
						circle of their conversation, maintained a port and character worthy of themselves. And so was Plato the same
						man at Syracuse that he was in the Academy, the same in
						Dionysus's court that he was in Dixon's.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But he who will take the pains to act the dissembler
					himself, by interchangeably decrying and extolling the same
					things, discourses, and ways of living, will easily perceive
					that the opinions of a flatterer are as mutable and inconstant as the colors of a polypus, that he is never consonant
					to himself nor properly his own man; that all his passions,
					his love and hatred, his joy and sorrow, are borrowed and
					counterfeit; and that, in a word, like a mirror, he only receives and represents the several faces or images of other
					men's affections and humors. Do but discommend one of
					your acquaintance a little in his company, and he will tell
					you it is a wonder you never found him out all this while,
					for his part he never fancied him in his life. Change but
					your style and commend him, he presently swears you oblige
					him in it, gives you a thousand thanks for the gentleman's
					sake, and believes your character of him to be just. Tell
					him you have thoughts of altering your course of life, as
					for instance, to retire from all public employs to privacy and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.110"/>
					
					ease; he immediately wishes that he had retreated long
					ago from the hurry and drudgery of business and the
					odium that attends it. Seem but again inclinable to an
					active life; Why now, says he, you speak like yourself;
					leisure and ease are sweet, it is true, but withal mean and
					inglorious. When you have thus trepanned him, it would
					be proper to cashier him with some such reply as this:&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">How now, my friend! What, quite another man!<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XVI. 181.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>I abhor a fellow who servilely complies with whatsoever
						I propose, and keeps pace with me in all my motions,&mdash;my
						shadow can do that better than yourself,&mdash;but my friend
						must deal plainly and impartially, and assist me faithfully
						with his judgment. And thus you see one way of discerning a flatterer from a friend.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Another difference observable betwixt them in the
					resemblance thy bear to each other is, that a true friend
					will not rashly commend nor imitate every thing, but only
					what really deserves it; for, as Sophocles says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">He shares with him his loves, but not his hates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Antigone, 523.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and will scorn to bear any part with him in any base and
						dishonorable actions, unless, as people sometimes catch
						blear eyes, he may chance insensibly to contract some ill
						habit or other by the very contagion of familiarity and conversation. Thus they say Plato's acquaintance learned his
						stoop, Aristotle's his lisp, and Alexander's the inclination of
						his neck and the rapidity of his speech. For some persons, ere they are aware, get a touch of the humors and
						infirmities of those with whom they converse. But now as
						a true friend endeavors only to copy the fairest originals, so,
						on the contrary, the flatterer, like the chameleon, which puts
						on all colors but the innocent white, being unable to reach
						those strokes of virtue which are worth his imitation, takes
						care that no failure or imperfection escape him. As unskilful
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.111"/>
						
						 painters, when they cannot hit the features and air
						of a face, content themselves with the faint resemblance in
						a wrinkle, a wart, or a scar, so he takes up with his friend's
						intemperance, superstition, cholericness, severity to his servants, distrust of his relations and domestics or the like.
						For, besides that a natural propensity to evil inclines him
						always to follow the worst examples, he imagines his assuming other men's vices will best secure him from the
						suspicion of being disaffected towards them; for their
						fidelity is often suspected who seem dissatisfied with
						faults and wish a reformation. Which very thing lost
						Dion in the good opinion of Dionysius, Samius in Philip's,
						Cleomenes in Ptolemy's, and at last proved the occasion of
						their ruin. And therefore the flatterer pretends not only
						to the good humor of a companion, but to the faithfulness
						of a friend too, and would be thought to have so great a
						respect for you that he cannot be disgusted at the very
						worst of your actions, being indeed of the same make and
						constitution with yourself. Hence you shall have him pretend a share in the most common casualties that befall
						another, nay, in complaisance, feign even diseases themselves. In company of those who are thick of hearing,
						he is presently half deaf, and with the dim-sighted can
						see no more than they do. So the parasites about Dionysius at an entertainment, to humor his blindness, stumbled
						one upon another and jostled the dishes off his table.</p>
            <p>But there are others who refine upon the former by a
						pretended fellow-suffering in the more private concernments
						of life, whereby they wriggle themselves deeper into the
						affections of those they flatter; as, if they find a man unhappily married, or distrustful of his children or domestics,
						they spare not their own family, but immediately entertain
						you with some lamentable story of the hard fortune they
						have met with in their children, their wife, their servants,
						or relations. For, by the parallel circumstances they pretend
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.112"/>
						
						 to, they seem more passionately concerned for the
						misfortunes of their friends, who, as if they had already
						received some pawn and assurance of their fidelity, blab
						forth those secrets which they cannot afterwards handsomely retract, and dare not betray the least distrust of
						their new confidant for the future. I myself knew a man
						who turned his wife out of doors because a gentleman of
						his acquaintance divorced his, though the latter lady smelt
						the intrigue afterwards by the messages the flatterer sent to
						his wife after the pretended divorce and the private visits
						he was observed to make her. So little did he understand
						the flatterer who took these following verses for the description of a crab rather than his:&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The shapeless thing's all over paunch and gut:
						</l>
                     <l>Who can the monster's mighty hunger glut?
						</l>
                     <l>It crawls on teeth, and with a watchful eye
						</l>
                     <l>Does into every secret corner pry.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For this is the true portraiture of those sharpers, who, as
						Eupolis speaks, sponge upon their acquaintance for a
						dinner.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But we will reserve these remarks for a more proper
					place. In the mean time I must not omit the other artifice
					observable in his imitation, which is this: that if at any
					time he counterfeit the good qualities of his friend, he immediately yields him the pre-eminence; whereas there is
					no competition, no emulation or envy amongst true friends,
					but whether they are equally accomplished or not, they
					bear the same even unconcerned temper of mind towards
					each other. But the flatterer, remembering that he is but
					to act another's part, pretends only to such strokes as fall
					short of the original, and is willing to confess himself outdone in any thing but his vices, wherein alone he claims
					the precedency to himself; as, if the man he is to wheedle
					be difficult and morose, he is quite overrun with choler; if
					something superstitious, he is a perfect enthusiast; if a
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.113"/>
					
					little in love, for his part he is most desperately smitten.
					I laughed heartily at such a passage, says one; But I had
					like to have died with laughter, says the other. But now
					in speaking of any laudable qualities, he inverts his style;
					as, I can run fast enough, says he, but you perfectly fly. I
					can sit an horse tolerably well, but alas! what's that to
					this Hippocentaur for good horsemanship? I have a tolerable good genius for poetry, and am none of the worst
					versifiers of the age;
					<quote rend="blockquote">But thunder is the language of you Gods, not mine.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And thus at the same time he obliges his friend both in
						approving of his abilities by his owning of them, and in
						confessing him incomparable in his way by himself coming
						short of his example. These then are the distinguishing
						characters of a friend and flatterer, as far as concerns the
						counterfeit resemblance betwixt them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But because, as we have before observed, it is common to them both to please (for a good man is no less taken
					with the company of his friends than an ill one is with a
					flatterer's), let us discriminate them here too. And the
					way will be to have an eye to the end to which they direct
					the satisfaction they create, which may be thus illustrated.
					Your perfumed oils have a fine odoriferous scent, and so, it
					may be, have some medicines too; but with this difference,
					that the former are prepared barely for the gratification of
					the sense, whilst the other, besides their odor, purge, heal,
					and fatten. Again, the colors used by painters are certainly
					very florid and the mixture agreeable; and yet so it is in
					some medicinal compositions too. Wherein then lies the
					difference? Why, in the end or use for which they are
					designed, the one purely for pleasure the other for profit.
					In like manner the civilities of one friend to another, besides the main point of their honesty and mutual advantage,
					are always attended with an overplus of delight and satisfaction.
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.114"/>
					
					 Nay, they can now and then indulge themselves
					the liberty of an innocent diversion, a collation, or a glass
					of wine, and, believe me, can be as cheerful and jocund as
					the best; all which they use only as sauce, to give a relish
					to the more serious and weighty concernments of life. To
					which purpose was that of the poet,
					<quote rend="blockquote">With pleasing chat they did delight each other;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>as likewise this too,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Nothing could part our pleasure or our love.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 643; Odyss. IV. 178.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the whole business and design of a flatterer is continually to entertain the company with some pastime or
						other, a little jest, a story well told, or a comical action;
						and, in a word, he thinks he can never overact the diverting
						part of conversation. Whereas the true friend, proposing
						no other end to himself than the bare discharge of his duty,
						is sometimes pleasant, and as often, it may be, disagreeable,
						neither solicitously coveting the one, nor industriously avoiding the other, if he judge it the more seasonable and
						expedient. For as a physician, if need require, will throw
						in a little saffron or spikenard to qualify his patient's dose,
						and will now and then bathe him and feed him up curiously, and yet again another time will prescribe him castor,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or poley, which the strongest scent doth yield
						</l>
                     <l>Of all the physic plants which clothe the field,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>or perhaps will oblige him to drink an infusion of hellebore,&mdash;proposing neither the deliciousness of the one nor
						the nauseousness of the other as his scope and design, but
						only conducting him by these different methods to one and
						the same end, the recovery of his health,&mdash;in like manner
						the real friend sometimes leads his man gently on to virtue by
						kindness, by pleasing and extolling him, as he in Homer,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.115"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dear Teucer, thou who art in high command,
						</l>
                     <l>Thus draw the bow with thy unerring hand;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and as another speaking of Ulysses,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>How can I doubt, while great Ulysses stands
						</l>
                     <l>To lend his counsel and assist our hands?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again, when he sees correction requisite, he will check
						him severely, as,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whither, O Menelaus, wouldst thou run,
						</l>
                     <l>And tempt a fate which prudence bids thee shun?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VIII. 281; Odyss. I. 65; Il. VII. 109.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and perhaps he is forced another time to second his words
						with actions, as Menedemus reclaimed his friend Asclepiades's son, a dissolute and debauched young gentleman, by
						shutting his doors upon him and not vouchsafing to speak
						to him. And Arcesilaus forbade Battus his school for
						having abused Cleanthes in a comedy of his, but after he
						had made satisfaction and an acknowledgment of his fault,
						took him into favor again. For we ought to grieve and
						afflict our friend with design merely of serving him, not of
						making a rupture betwixt us, and must apply our reprehensions only as pungent and acute medicines, with no other
						intent than the recovery of the patient. And therefore a
						friend&mdash;like a skilful musician who, to tune his instrument, winds up one string and lets down another&mdash;grants
						some things and refuses others according as their honesty
						or usefulness prompt him, whereby he often pleases, but is
						sure always to profit; whereas the parasite, who is continually upon the same humoring string, knows not how to let
						fall a cross word or commit a disobliging action, but servilely complies with all your desires, and is always in the
						tune you ask for. And therefore, as Xenophon reports of
						Agesilaus that he took some delight in being praised by
						those who would upon occasion dispraise him too, so ought
						we to judge that only he rejoices and pleases us really as a
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.116"/>
						
						friend, who will, when need requires, thwart and contradict
						us; we must suspect their conversation who aim at nothing
						but our gratification, without the least intermixture of reprehension; and indeed we ought to have ready upon such
						occasions that repartee of a Lacedaemonian who, hearing
						King Charillus highly extolled for an excellent person,
						asked, How he could be so good a man, who was never
						severe to an ill one?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>They tell us that gad-flies creep into the ears of
					bulls, and ticks into those of dogs. But I am sure the
					parasite lays so close siege and sticks so fast to the ears
					of the ambitious with the repeated praises of their worth,
					that it is no easy matter to shake him off again. And
					therefore it highly concerns them to have their apprehensions awake and upon the guard, critically to remark
					whether the high characters such men lavish out are intended for the person or the thing they would be thought
					to commend. And we may indeed suppose them more
					peculiarly designed for the things themselves, if they bestow them on persons absent rather than present; if they
					covet and aspire after the same qualities themselves which
					they magnify in others; if they admire the same perfections in the rest of mankind as well as in us, and are never
					found to falter and belie, either in word or action, the
					sentiments they have owned. And, what is the surest
					criterion in this case, we are to examine whether or no we
					are not really troubled at or ashamed of the commission
					of those very things for which they applaud us, and could
					not wish that we had said or acted the quite contrary; for
					our own consciences, which are above the reach of passion
					and will not be put upon by all the sly artifices of flattery,
					will witness against us and spurn at an undeserved commendation. But I know not how it comes to pass, that
					several persons had rather be pitied than comforted in
					adversity; and when they have committed a fault, look
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.117"/>
					
					upon those as enemies and informers who endeavor to
					chide and lecture them into a sense of their guilt, but
					caress and embrace them as friends who soothe them up in
					their vices. Indeed they who continue their applauses to
					so inconsiderable a thing as a single action, a wise saying,
					or a smart jest, do only a little present mischief; but they
					who from single acts proceed to debauch even the habits
					of the mind with their immoderate praises are like those
					treacherous servants who, not content to rob the common
					heap in the granary, filch even that which was chosen and
					reserved for seed. For, whilst they entitle vice to the
					name of virtue, they corrupt that prolific principle of action, the genius and disposition of the soul, and poison the
					fountain whence the whole stream of life derives. Thucydides observes, that in the time of war and sedition the
					names of good and evil are wont to be confounded according to men's judgment of circumstances; as, fool-hardiness is called a generous espousal of a friend's quarrel, a
					provident delay is nicknamed cowardice, modesty a mere
					pretext for unmanliness, a prudent slow inspection into
					things downright laziness.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucyd. III. 82.</note> In like manner, if you observe
					it, a flatterer terms a profuse man liberal, a timorous man
					wary, a mad fellow quick and prompt, a stingy miser
					frugal, an amorous youngster kind and good-natured, a
					passionate proud fool stout, and a mean-spirited slave
					courteous and observing. As Plato somewhere remarks,
					that a lover who is always a flatterer of his beloved object styles a flat nose lovely and graceful, an hawk nose
					princely, the black manly, and the fair the offspring of the
					Gods; and observes particularly that the appellation of
					honey-pale is nothing but the daub of a gallant who is
					willing to set off his mistress's pale complexion.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plat. Repub. V. 474 D.</note> Now
					indeed an ugly fellow bantered into an opinion that he is
					handsome, or a little man magnified into tall and portly,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.118"/>
					
					cannot lie long under the mistake nor receive any great
					injury by the cheat; but when vice is extolled by the
					name of virtue, so that a man is induced to sin not only
					without regret but with joy and triumph, and is hardened
					beyond the modesty of a blush for his enormities, this sort
					of flattery, I say, has been fatal even to whole kingdoms.
					It was this that ruined Sicily, by styling the tyranny of
					Dionysius and Phalaris nothing but justice and a hatred
					of villanous practices. It was this that overthrew Egypt,
					by palliating the ling's effeminacy, his yellings, his enthusiastic rants, and his beating of drums, with the more
					plausible names of true religion and the worship of the
					Gods. It was this that had very nigh ruined the stanch
					Roman temper, by extenuating the voluptuousness, the
					luxury, the sumptuous shows, and public profuseness of
					Antony, into the softer terms of humanity, good nature,
					and the generosity of a gentleman who knew how to use
					the greatness of his fortune. What but the charms of
					flattery made Ptolemy turn piper and fiddler ? What else
					put on Nero's buskins and brought him on the stage ?
					Have we not known several princes, if they sung a tolerable treble, termed Apollos; when they drank stoutly,
					styled Bacchuses; and upon wrestling, fencing, or the
					like, immediately dubbed by the name of Hercules, and
					hurried on by those empty titles to the commission of those
					acts which were infinitely beneath the dignity of their
					character?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>And therefore it will be then more especially our
					concern to look about us when a flatterer is upon the
					strain of praising ; which he is sensible enough of, and
					accordingly avoids all occasion of suspicion when he attacks us on that side. If indeed he meets with a tawdry
					fop, or a dull country clown in a leathern jacket, he plays
					upon him with all the liberty imaginable; as Struthias by
					way of flattery insulted and triumphed over the sottishness
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.119"/>
					
					of Bias, when he told him that he had out drunk King
					Alexander himself, and that he was ready to die of laughter at his encounter with the Cyprian. But if he chance
					to fall upon an apprehensive man, who can presently
					smoke a design, especially if he thinks he has an eye
					upon him and stands upon his guard, he does not immediately assault him with an open panegyric, but first fetches
					a compass, and softly winds about him, till he has in some
					measure tamed the untractable creature and brought it to
					his hand. For he either tells him what high characters
					he has heard of him abroad (introducing, as the rhetoricians do, some third person), how upon the exchange the
					other day he happily overheard some strangers and persons of great gravity and worth, who spake extreme honorably of him and professed themselves much his admirers; or else he forges some frivolous and false accusation
					of him, and then coming in all haste, as if he had heard
					it really reported, asks him seriously, if he can call to
					mind where he said or did such a thing. And immediately
					upon his denial of the matter of fact, which he has reason
					enough to expect, he takes occasion to fall upon the subject of his commendation; I wondered indeed, says he, to
					hear that you should calumniate your friend, who never
					used to speak ill of your enemies; that you should endeavor to rob another man of his estate, who so generously spend your own.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Others again, like painters who enhance the lustre
					and beauty of a curious piece by the shades which surround it, slyly extol and encourage men in their vices by
					deriding and railing at their contrary virtues. Thus, in
					the company of the debauched. the covetous, and the extortioner, they run down temperance and modesty as mere
					rusticity; and justice and contentment with our present
					condition argue nothing in their phrase but a dastardly
					spirit and an impotence to action. If they fall into the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.120"/>
					
					acquaintance of lubbers who love laziness and ease, they
					stick not to explode the necessary administration of public
					affairs as a troublesome intermeddling in other men's business, and a desire to bear office as an useless empty thirst
					after a name. To wheedle in with an orator, they scout
					a philosopher; and who so gracious as they with the jilts
					of the town, by laughing at wives who are faithful to their
					husbands' beds as impotent and country-bred? And, what
					is the most egregious stratagem of all the rest, the flatterer shall traduce himself rather than want a fair opportunity to commend another; as wrestlers put their body
					in a low posture, that they may the better worst their adversaries. I am a very coward at sea, says he, impatient
					of any fatigue, and cannot digest the least ill language;
					but my good friend here fears no colors, can endure all
					hardness, is an admirable good man, bears all things with
					great patience and evenness of temper. If he meets with
					one who abounds in his own sense and affects to appear
					rigid and singular in his judgment, and, as an argument
					of the rectitude and steadiness thereof, is always telling
					you of that of Homer,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let not your praise or dispraise lavish be,
					</l>
                     <l>Good Diomedes, when you speak of me,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. X. 249.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he applies a new engine to move this great weight. To
						such a one he imparts some of his private concerns, as
						being willing to advise with the ablest counsel: he has indeed a more intimate acquaintance with others, but he was
						forced to trouble him at present: for to whom should we
						poor witless men have recourse (says he) when we stand
						in need of advice Or whom else should we trust? And
						as soon as he has delivered his opinion, whether it be to
						the purpose or not, he takes his leave of him with a seeming satisfaction, as if he had received an answer from an
						oracle. Again, if he perceives a man pretends to be master
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.121"/>
						
						 of a style, he presently presents him with something
						of his own composing, requesting him to peruse and correct it. Thus Mithridates could no sooner set up for a
						physician, than some of his acquaintance desired to be cut
						and cauterized by him,&mdash;a piece of flattery that extended
						beyond the fallacy of bare words,&mdash;they imagining that he
						must needs take it as an argument of their great opinion
						of his skill, that they durst trust themselves in his hands.
						<quote rend="blockquote">For things divine take many shapes.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Alcestis, 1159, and elsewhere in Euripides.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now to discover the cheat which these insinuations of our
						own worth might put upon us (a thing that requires no ordinary circumspection), the best way will be to give him a
						very absurd advice, and to animadvert as impertinently as
						may be upon his works when he submits them to your censure. For if he makes no reply, but grants and approves
						of all you assert, and applauds every period with the
						eulogy of Very right! Incomparably well!&mdash;then you have
						trepanned him, and it is plain that, though
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He counsel asked, he played another game,
						</l>
                     <l>To swell you with the opinion of a name.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>But to proceed. As some have defined painting to
					be mute poetry, so there is a sort of silent flattery which
					has its peculiar commendation. For as hunters are then
					surest of their game when they pass under the disguise of
					travellers, shepherds or husbandmen, and seem not at all
					intent upon their sport; so the eulogies of a parasite never
					take more effectually than when he seems least of all to
					commend you. For he who rises up to a rich man when
					he comes in company, or who, having begun a motion in
					the Senate, suddenly breaks off and gives some leading
					man the liberty of speaking his sense first in the point,
					such a man's silence more effectually slows the deference
					he pays the other's judgment than if he had avowedly proclaimed it. And hereupon you shall have them always
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.122"/>
					
					placed in the boxes at the play-house, and perched upon
					the highest seats at other public entertainments; not that
					they think them suitable to their quality, but merely for
					the opportunity of gratifying great men by giving them
					place. Hence it is likewise, that they open first in all
					solemn and public assemblies, only that they may give
					place to another as an abler speaker, and they retract their
					opinion immediately, if any person of authority, riches, or
					quality contradict them. So that you may perceive all their
					concessions, cringes, and respects to be but mere courtship
					and complaisance, by this easy observation, that they are
					usually paid to riches, honor, or the like, rather than to age,
					art, virtue, or other personal endowments.</p>
            <p>Thus dealt not Apelles with Megabyzus (one of the Persian nobility), who pretending once to talk I know not
						what about lines, shades, and other things peculiar to his
						art, the painter could not but take him up, telling him
						that his apprentices yonder, who were grinding colors,
						gazed strangely upon him, admiring his gold and purple
						ornaments, while he held his tongue, but now could not
						choose but titter to hear him offer at a discourse upon an
						argument so much out of his sphere. And when Croesus
						asked Solon his opinion of felicity, he told him flatly, that
						he looked upon Tellus, an honest though obscure Athenian,
						and Biton and Cleobis, as happier than he. But the flatterer will have kings, governors, and men of estates, not
						only the most signally happy, but the most eminently
						knowing, the most virtuous, and the most prudent of
						mankind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>And now some cannot endure to hear the Stoics,
					who centre all true riches, generosity, nobility, and royalty
					itself in the person of a wise man; but with the flatterer
					it is the man of money that is both orator and poet, and,
					if he pleases, painter and fiddler too, a good wrestler, an
					excellent footman, or any thing, for they never stand with
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.123"/>
					
					him for the victory in those engagements; as Crisson, who
					had the honor to run with Alexander, let him designedly
					win the race, which the king being told of afterwards was
					highly disgusted at him. And therefore I like the observation of Carneades, who used to say that young princes and
					noblemen never arrived to a tolerable perfection in any
					thing they learned, except riding; for their preceptors
					spoil them at school by extolling all their performances,
					and their wrestling-masters by always taking the foil;
					whereas the horse, who knows no distinction betwixt a
					private man and a magistrate, betwixt the rich and the
					poor, will certainly throw his rider if he knows not how
					to sit him, let him be of what quality he pleases. And
					therefore it was but impertinently said of Bion upon this
					subject, that he who could praise his ground into a good
					crop were to blame if he bestowed any other tillage upon
					it. 'Tis granted: nor is it improper to commend a man,
					if you do him any real kindness thereby. But here is the
					disparity: that a field cannot be made worse by any commendations bestowed upon it, whereas a man immoderately
					praised is puffed up, burst, and ruined by it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Thus much then for the point of praising; proceed
					we in the next place to treat of freedom in their reprehensions. And indeed, it were but reasonable that,&mdash;as Patroclus put on Achilles's armor and led his war-horse out into the
					field, yet durst not for all that venture to wield his spear,&mdash;
					so, though the flatterer wear all the other badges and ensigns of a friend, he should not dare to counterfeit the
					plain frankness of his discourse, as being <q direct="unspecified">a great, massy,
						and substantial weapon,</q> peculiar to him.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 141.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But because, to avoid that scandal and offence which
						their drunken bouts, their little jests, and ludicrous babling humor might otherwise create, they sometimes put on
						the face of gravity, and flatter under the vizard of a frown,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.124"/>
						
						dropping in now and then a word of correction and reproof, let us examine this cheat too amongst the rest.</p>
            <p>And indeed I can compare that trifling insignificant liberty of speech to which he pretends to nothing better than
						that sham Hercules which Menander introduces in one
						of his comedies. with a light hollow club upon his shoulder;
						for, as women's pillows, which seem sufficiently stuffed to
						bear up their heads, yield and sink under their weight, so
						this counterfeit freedom in a flatterer's conversation swells
						big and promises fair, that when it shrinks and contracts
						itself it may draw those in with it who lay any stress upon
						its outward appearance. Whereas the genuine and friendly
						reprehension fixes upon real criminals, causing them grief
						and trouble indeed, but only what is wholesome and salutary; like honey that corrodes but yet cleanses the ulcerous
						parts of the body, and is otherwise both pleasant and
						profitable. But of this in its proper place. We shall discourse at present of the flatterer who affects a morose,
						angry, and inexorable behavior towards all but those upon
						whom he designs, is peevish and difficult towards his servants, animadverts severely upon the failures of his relations and domestics, neither admires nor respects a stranger
						but superciliously contemns him, pardons no man, but by
						stories and complaints exasperates one against another,
						thinking by these means to acquire the character of an irreconcilable enemy to all manner of vice, that he may be
						thought one who would not spare his favorites themselves
						upon occasion, and would neither act nor speak any thing
						out of a mean and dastardly complaisance.</p>
            <p>And if at any time he undertakes his friend, he feigns
						himself a mere stranger to his real and considerable
						crimes; but if he catch him in some petty trifling peccadillo, there he takes his occasion to rant him terribly and
						thunder him severely off; as, if he see any of his goods
						out of order, if his house be not very convenient, if his
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.125"/>
						
						beard be not shaven or his clothes unfashionable, if his
						dog or his horse be not well looked after. But if he
						slight his parents, neglect his children, treat his wife
						scornfully, his friends and acquaintance disrespectfully,
						and squander away his estate, here he dares not open his
						mouth, and it is the safest way to hold his tongue. Just
						as if the master of a wrestling-school should indulge his
						young champion scholar in drinking and wenching, and
						yet rattle him about his oil-cruise and body-brush; or as
						if a schoolmaster should severely reprove a boy for some
						little fault in his pen or writing-book, but take no notice
						of the barbarisms and solecisms in his language. For the
						parasite is like him who hearing a ridiculous impertinent
						orator finds no fault with his discourse but delivery, blaming him only for having hurt his throat with drinking cold
						water; or like one who, being to peruse and correct some
						pitiful scribble, falls foul only upon the coarseness of the
						paper and the blots and negligence of the transcriber.
						Thus the parasites about Ptolemy. when he pretended to
						learning, would wrangle with him till midnight about the
						propriety of an expression, a verse, or a story; but not a
						word all this while of his cruelty, insults, superstition, and
						oppressions of the people. Just as if a chirurgeon should
						pare a man's nails or cut his hair, to cure him of a fistula,
						wen, or other carnous excrescence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>But there are others behind, who outdo all the subtlety of the former, such as can claw and please, even
					whilst they seem to reprehend. Thus when Alexander
					had bestowed some considerable reward upon a jester,
					Agis the Argive, through mere envy and vexation, cried
					out upon it as a most absurd action; which the king
					overhearing, he turned him about in great indignation at
					the insolence, saying, What's that you prate, sirrah? Why
					truly, replied the man, I must confess, I am not a little
					troubled to observe, that all you great men who are descended
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.126"/>
					
					 from Jupiter take a strange delight in flatterers
					and buffoons; for as Hercules had his Cercopians and
					Bacchus his Silenuses about him, so I see your majesty is
					pleased to have a regard for such pleasant fellows too.
					And one time when Tiberius Caesar was present at the
					senate, there stood up a certain fawning counsellor, asserting that all free-born subjects ought to have the liberty of
					speaking their sense freely, and should not dissemble or
					conceal any thing that they might conceive beneficial to
					the public; who, having thus awakened the attention of
					his audience, silence being made, and Tiberius impatient
					to hear the sequel of the man's discourse, pursued it in
					this manner: I must tell you of a fault, Caesar, said he,
					for which we universally blame you, though no man yet
					has taken the confidence to speak it openly. You neglect
					yourself, endanger your sacred person by your too much
					labor and care, night and day, for the public. And he
					having harangued several things to the same effect, it is
					reported that Cassius Severus the orator subjoined: This
					man's freedom of speech will ruin him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Such artifices as these, I confess, are not very pernicious, but there remains one of a most dangerous consequence to weak men; and that is when a flatterer fastens
					those vices upon them which are directly contrary to those
					they are really guilty of. As Himerius, an Athenian parasite, upbraided one of the most miserable and stingy misers
					of the whole town with carelessness and prodigality, tell
					ing him he was afraid he should live to see the day when
					both he and his children should go a begging. Or, on
					the contrary, when they object niggardliness and parsimony to one that is lavish and profuse, as Titus Petronius
					did to Nero. Or when they advise arbitrary and tyrannical princes to lay aside their too much moderation and
					their unprofitable and unseasonable clemency. And like
					to these are they who shall pretend to be afraid of a
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.127"/>
					
					half-witted idiot, as of some notable shrewd fellow; and
					shall tax an ill-natured censorious man, if at any time he
					speak honorably of a person of worth, of being too lavish
					in his commendations. You are always, say they, praising
					men that deserve it not; for who is he, or what remarkable
					thing did he ever say or do? But they have yet a more
					signal opportunity of exercising their talent, when they
					meet with any difference betwixt lovers or friends ; for if
					they see brothers quarrel, or children despise their parents,
					or husbands jealous of their wives, they neither admonish
					them nor blame them for it, but inflame the difference.
					You don't understand yourself, say they; you are the occasion of all this clutter by your own soft and submissive
					behavior. If there chance to have happened some little
					love-skirmish betwixt a miss and her gallant, then the flatterer interposes boldly and adds fresh fuel to the expiring
					flame, taking the gentleman to task, and telling' him how
					many things he has done which looked a little hard, were
					not kind, and deserved a chiding.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ungrateful man ! can you forget her charms,
					</l>
                     <l>And former soft embraces in her arms</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Myrmidons of Aeschylus, Frag. 131.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Antony's friends persuaded him, when he was
						smitten with his beloved Cleopatra, that she doted on him,
						still calling him haughty and hard-hearted man. She,
						said they, has stripped herself of the glories of a crown and
						former grandeur, and now languishes with the love of you,
						attending the motion of your camp in the poor sordid
						figure of a concubine.
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But you have steeled your heart, and can unmoved
						</l>
                     <l>Behold her grief, whom once you so much loved.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. X. 329.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now he was strangely pleased to hear of his little unkindness to his mistress, and was more taken with such
						a chiding than with the highest character they could have
						given him; but was not sensible that, under the color of
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.128"/>
						
						a friendly admonition, they really corrupted and debauched
						him. For such a rebuke as this is just like the bites of
						a lecherous woman, for it only tickles and provokes, and
						pleases even whilst it pains you. And as pure wine taken
						singly is an excellent antidote against hemlock, but if
						mixed with it renders the poison incurable, because the heat
						of the wine quickens its circulation to the heart; so some
						rascally fellows, knowing very well that the liberty of reproving a friend is a quality very hardly compatible with
						flattery, and, as I may say, the best remedy against it, mix
						them both together, and flatter you under the very color
						and pretext of reprimanding you.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole thereof, Bias seems not to have answered him very pertinently, who asked him which he
						thought was the most hurtful animal, when he replied,
						Of wild creatures a tyrant, and of tame ones a flatterer.
						For he might have answered more accurately, that some
						flatterers indeed are tame creatures, those shirks who ply
						about your bath and your table; but they whose calumnies, malignity, and inquisitive meddling humor, like so
						many gins and snares, reach the ladies' very closets and
						bed-chambers, are wild, savage, and untractable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>Now one way of arming ourselves against these
					assaults will be always to remember that,&mdash;since our
					souls are made up of two different parts, the one sincere,
					honest, and reasonable, the other brutish, false, and governed by passion,&mdash;the friend always adapts his advice
					and admonitions to the improvement of the better part
					(like a good physician, who preserves and advances an
					healthful constitution where he finds it), whilst the flatterer claws and tickles the irrational part of the man only,
					debauching it from the rules of right reason by the repeated suggestion of soft and sensual delights. For as
					there are some sorts of meat which assimilate neither
					with the blood nor with the spirits, and invigorate neither
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.129"/>
					
					the nerves nor the marrow, but only provoke lust, swell
					the paunch, and breed putrid flabby flesh; so he who
					shall give himself the labor to observe will find that the
					discourses of a flatterer contribute nothing to the improvement of our prudence and understanding, but either only
					entertain us with the pleasure of some love-intrigue, or
					make us indiscreetly angry or envious, or blow us up into
					an empty troublesome opinion of ourselves, or increase
					our sorrows by pretending to share in them; or else they
					exasperate any inbred naughtiness that is in us, or our
					illiberality or distrustfulness, making them harsh, timorous,
					and jealous, with idle malicious stories, hints, and conjectures of his own. For he always fastens upon and pampers some distemper of the mind, growing, like a botch or
					bile. upon its inflamed or putrid part only. Are you
					angry? Revenge yourself, says he. Covet you any thing?
					Have it. Are you afraid? Fly. Suspect you this or
					that? Believe it.</p>
            <p>But if we find it something difficult to discover him in
						these attempts upon our passions, because they often violently overpower all the forces of our reason to the contrary, we may then trace him in other instances of his
						knavery; for he always acts consonant to himself. As, if
						you are afraid of a surfeit and thereupon are in suspense
						about your bath and diet, a friend indeed will advise you to
						act cautiously and take care of your health; but the flatterer persuades you to the bath, bids you feed freely and
						not starve yourself with mortification. If he observes you
						want briskness and spirit for action, as being unwilling to
						undergo the fatigue of a journey or a voyage, he will tell
						you presently, there is no haste; the business may be well
						enough deferred, or else transacted by proxy. If at any
						time you have promised to lend or give a friend a sum of
						money, and upon second thoughts gladly would, and yet
						are ashamed to retract your word, the flatterer puts his
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.130"/>
						
						advice in the worse scale, and inclines the balance to the
						saving side, and strips you of your squeamish modesty,
						telling you that you ought not to be so prodigal, who live
						at great expense and have others to relieve besides him.
						And therefore, unless we be mere strangers to ourselves,&mdash;to our own covetousness, shamelessness, or timidity,&mdash;the flatterer cannot easily escape our discovery;
						for he is the great patron of these disorderly passions,
						endeavoring always to wind us up to excesses of this
						kind. But enough of this.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Let us in the next place discourse of the useful and
					kind offices which the flatterer seems cheerfully ready upon
					every occasion to perform, thereby rendering the disparity
					betwixt him and the true friend extremely perplexed and
					intricate.</p>
            <p>For the temper of a friend, like the language of truth,
						is (as Euripides says) sincere, natural, without paint or varnish; but that of a flatterer, as it is corrupt and diseased in
						itself, so stands in need of many curious and exquisite remedies to correct it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 472.</note> And therefore you shall have friends
						upon an accidental rencounter, without either giving or
						receiving a formal salute, content themselves to speak their
						mutual kindness and familiarity in a nod and a smile; but
						the flatterer pursues you, runs to meet you, and extends his
						hand long before he comes at you; and if you chance but
						to see and salute him first, he swears you must excuse his
						rudeness, and will produce you witness that he did not see
						you, if you please. Thus again, a friend dwells not upon
						every trifling punctilio, is not ceremonious and punctual in
						the transacting of business, is not inquisitive, and does not
						intrude into every piece of service; but the parasite is all
						obedience, all perpetual indefatigable industry, admits no
						rival in his services, but will wait your commands, which if
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.131"/>
						
						you lay not upon him, he seems mightily afflicted, the unhappiest man in the world!</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Now these observations are argument enough to convince a man of any tolerable sense, that the friendship such
					men pretend to is not really virtuous and chaste, but rather
					a sort of impudent whorish love that obtrudes its embraces
					upon you.</p>
            <p>But, to be more particular, let us first examine the disparity betwixt their promises. For our forefathers well
						observed, that the offers of a friend run in such terms
						as these:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If I can serve you, sir, if your request
						</l>
                     <l>Be feasible by me, I'll do my best;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but the flatterer's thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">Command me freely what you will, I'll do it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIV. 195.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the comedians introduce such brave promises as
						these:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come, sir, let me but fight that fellow there;
						</l>
                     <l>I'll beat him soft as sponge or jellies are.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, no real friend will assist in the execution of a
						design, unless, being first advised with, he approve of it as
						either honest or useful. Whereas the flatterer, though
						permitted to consult and give his opinion about an undertaking, not only out of a paltry desire to comply with and
						gratify his friend at any rate, but lest he should be looked
						upon as disaffected to the business, servilely closes with and
						advances his proposal, how unreasonable soever. For there
						are few rich men or princes of this mind:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Give me a friend, though a poor beggar he,
						</l>
                     <l>Or meaner than the meanest beggar be,
						</l>
                     <l>If he his thoughts but freely will impart,
						</l>
                     <l>And boldly speak the language of his heart;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Ino of Euripides, Frag. 416.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for they, like actors in a tragedy, must have a chorus of
						their friends to join with them in the concert, or else the
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.132"/>
						
						claps of the pit to encourage them. Whereupon Merope
						in the tragedy speaks thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Make choice of those for friends, who never knew
						</l>
                     <l>The arts of wheedling and betraying you;
						</l>
                     <l>But those poor rascals never entertain,
						</l>
                     <l>Who please you only with design to gain.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Erechtheus of Euripides, Frag. 364.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But alas ! they invert the counsel, and abominate those who
						deal freely with them and advise them obstinately for the
						best, whilst pitiful cringing cheats and impostors are
						admitted not only into their houses, but into their affections and the nearest concernments of their life. You
						shall have some of them indeed more plain and simple
						than the rest, who confess themselves unworthy to consult
						about such weighty affairs, but are ready to serve you in
						the executive part of a design. But the more subtle hypocrite comes in at the consult, knits his brows, declares his
						consent by the gravity of a look or a nod, but speaks never
						a word, unless perchance, when the great man delivers his
						opinion, he cries, Lord! sir, you prevented me; I was just
						going to say so. For, as the mathematicians tell us that
						surfaces and lines, which are incorporeal and creatures of
						the understanding only, are neither bended nor moved nor
						extended of themselves, but are so affected together with
						the bodies whose extremities they are; so you shall observe the flatterer attends only the motion of another's
						sense, opinion, or passion, without any principle of action
						in himself. So that the disparity betwixt them thus far is
						easily discernible.</p>
            <p>And yet more easily in the manner they perform their
						good offices. For the kindnesses of a friend, like an animate creature, have their most proper virtues deep within,
						without any parade or pageantry on the outside. Nay,
						many times, as a faithful physician cures his patient when
						he least knows of it, so a true friend, either present or
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.133"/>
						
						absent, as occasion serves, is solicitous about your concerns, when perhaps you know nothing of it. Such was
						the excellent Arcesilaus, as in his other actions, so particularly in his kindness to Apelles, native of Chios, whom
						finding extremely indigent in his sickness, he repeated his
						visit to him with twenty drachms in his pocket; and sitting by his bedside, You have got nothing here, said he,
						but Empedocles's elements, fire, water, earth, and the surrounding air; neither, methinks, do you lie easily. And
						with that, stirring up his pillow, he put the money privately
						under his head; which when the good old woman his nurse
						found and in great wonder acquainted Apelles with, Aye,
						says he, smiling a little, this is a piece of Arcesilaus's
						thievery. And the saying that children resemble their
						parents is found true also in philosophy. For when
						Cephisocrates was impeached of high treason, and Lacydes, an intimate acquaintance of Arcesilaus, with several
						others of his friends, stood by him at his trial, the counsel
						for the state desired that the prisoner's ring, wherein lay
						the principal evidence against him, might be produced in
						court; which Cephisocrates hearing dropped it softly off
						his finger, and Lacydes observing it set his foot upon it and
						buried it in the ground. Whereupon being acquitted, and
						going afterwards to pay his respects and thanks to his
						judges, one of them (who, it seems, had taken notice of the
						passages) told him that his thanks were owing to Lacydes,
						and so related the whole story, when yet Lacydes had never
						mentioned it.</p>
            <p>Thus I am verily persuaded the Gods confer several
						benefits upon us which we are not sensible of, upon no
						other motive in the world than the mere pleasure and satisfaction they take in acts of kindness and beneficence.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, the seemingly good offices of a flatterer have nothing of that sincerity and integrity, that simplicity and ingenuousness, which recommend a kindness, but
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.134"/>
						
						are always attended with bustle and noise, hurry, sweat and
						contracting the brow, to enhance your opinion of the great
						pains he has taken for you; like a picture drawn in gaudy
						colors, with folded torn garments, and full of angles and
						wrinkles, to make us believe it an elaborate piece and done
						to the life.</p>
            <p>Besides, the flatterer is so extremely troublesome in recounting the weary steps he has taken, the cares he has
						had upon him, the persons he has been forced to disoblige,
						with a thousand other inconveniencies he has labored
						under upon your account, that you will be apt to say,
						The business was never worth all this din and clutter
						about it.</p>
            <p>For a kindness once upbraided loses its grace, turns a
						burden, and becomes intolerable. But the flatterer not
						only reproaches us with his services already past, but at the
						very instant of their performance; whereas, if a friend be
						obliged to speak of any civility done another, he modestly
						mentions it indeed, but attributes nothing to himself.
						Thus, when the Lacedaemonians supplied the people of
						Smyrna in great scarcity of provisions, and they gratefully
						resented and extolled the kindness; Why, replied the
						Spartans, it was no such great matter, we only robbed ourselves and our cattle of a dinner. For a favor thus bestowed
						is not only free and ingenuous, but more acceptable to the
						receiver, because he imagines his benefactor conferred it
						on him without any great prejudice to himself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But the temper of a flatterer is discernible from that
					of a friend not only in the easiness of his promises and the
					troublesome impertinence that attends his good offices, but
					more signally in this, that the one is ready to promote any
					base and unworthy action, the other those only which are
					fair and honest. The one labors to please, the other to
					profit you. For a friend must not, as Gorgias would have
					him, beg another's assistance in a just undertaking, and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.135"/>
					
					then think to compensate the civility by contributing to
					several that are unjust.
					<quote rend="blockquote">In wisdom, not in folly, should they join.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And if, after all, he cannot prevail upon him, he may disengage himself with the reply of Phocion to Antipater;
						Sir, I cannot be both your friend and your flatterer,&mdash;that
						is, Your friend and not your friend at the same time. For
						we ought to be assistant to him in his honest endeavors
						indeed, but not in his knaveries; in his counsels, not in his
						tricks ; in appearing as evidence for him, but not in a
						cheat; and must bear a share in his misfortunes, but not
						in his acts of injustice. For if a man ought not to be as
						much as conscious of any unworthiness in his friend, how
						much less will it become him to partake in it? Therefore,
						as the Lacedaemonians, defeated and treating of articles of
						peace with Antipater, prayed him to command them any
						thing, howsoever grievous and burthensome to the subject,
						provided it were not base and dishonorable; so a friend, if
						you want his assistance in a chargeable, dangerous, and
						laborious enterprise, embarks in the design cheerfully and
						without reserve; but if such as will not stand with his
						reputation and honor, he fairly desires to be excused.
						Whereas, on the contrary, if you offer to put a flatterer
						upon a difficult or hazardous employment, he shuffles you
						off and begs your pardon. For but sound him, as you rap
						a vessel to try whether it be whole or cracked, full or
						empty; and he shams you off with the noise of some paltry,
						frivolous excuses. But engage him in any mean, sordid,
						and inglorious service, abuse him, kick him, trample on
						him, he bears all patiently and knows no affront. For as
						the ape, who cannot keep the house like a dog or bear a
						burden like an horse or plough like an ox, serves to be
						abused, to play the buffoon, and to make sport; so the
						parasite, who can neither plead your cause nor be your
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.136"/>
						
						counsel nor espouse your quarrel, as being averse from all
						painful and good offices, denies you in nothing that may
						contribute to your pleasure, turns pander to your lust,
						pimps for a whore, provides you an handsome entertainment, looks that your bill be reasonable, and sneaks to
						your miss; but he shall treat your relations with disrespect
						and impudently turn your wife out of doors, if you commission him. So that you may easily discover him in this
						particular. For put him upon the most base and dirty actions; he will not spare his own pains, provided he can
						but gratify you.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>There remains yet another way to discover him by
					his inclinations towards your intimates and familiars. For
					there is nothing more agreeable to a true and cordial acquaintance than to love and to be beloved with many; and
					therefore he always sedulously endeavors to gain his friend
					the affections and esteem of other men. For being of
					opinion that all things ought to be in common amongst
					friends, he thinks nothing ought to be more so than they
					themselves. But the faithless, the adulterate friend of base
					alloy, who is conscious to himself of the disservice he does
					true friendship by that false coin of it which he puts upon
					us, is naturally full of emulation and envy, even towards
					those of his own profession, endeavoring to outdo them in
					their common talent of babbling and buffoonry, whilst he
					reveres and cringes to his betters, whom he dares no more
					vie with than a footman with a Lydian chariot, or lead (to
					use Simonides's expression) with refined gold. Therefore
					this light and empty counterfeit, finding he wants weight
					when put into the balance against a solid and substantial
					friend, endeavors to remove him as far as he can, like
					him who, having painted a cock extremely ill, commanded
					his servant to take the original out of sight; and if he
					cannot compass his design, then he proceeds to compliment
					and ceremony, pretending outwardly to admire him as a
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.137"/>
					
					person far beyond himself, whilst by secret calumnies he
					blackens and undermines him. And if these chance to
					have galled and fretted him only and have not thoroughly
					done their work, then he betakes himself to the advice of
					Medius, that arch parasite and enemy to the Macedonian
					nobility, and chief of all that numerous train which Alexander entertained in his court. This man taught his disciples to slander boldly and push home their calumnies;
					for, though the wound might probably be cured and skinned
					over again, yet the teeth of slander would be sure to leave
					a scar behind them. By these scars, or (to speak more
					properly) gangrenes and cancers of false accusations, fell
					the brave Callisthenes, Parmenio, and Philotas; whilst Alexander himself became an easy prey to an Agnon, Bagoas,
					Agesias, and Demetrius, who tricked him up like a barbarian statue, and paid the mortal the adoration due to a God.
					So great a charm is flattery, and, as it seems, the greatest
					with those we think the greatest men; for the exalted
					thoughts they entertain of themselves, and the desire of a
					universal concurrence in the same opinion from others, both
					add courage to the flatterer and credit to his impostures.
					Hills and mountains indeed are not easily taken by stratagem or ambuscade; but a weak mind, swollen big and lofty
					by fortune, birth, or the like, lies naked to the assaults of
					every mean and petty aggressor.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>And therefore we repeat here what we advised at
					our entrance into this discourse, that we cashier every vain
					Opinion of ourselves and all self-love. For their inbred
					flattery only disposes and prepares us to a more favorable
					reception of that from without. For, if we did but square our
					actions according to the famous oracular precept of knowing ourselves, rate things according to their true intrinsic
					value, and withal, reflecting upon our own nature and education, consider what gross imperfections and failures mix
					with our words, actions, and affections, we should not lie so
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.138"/>
					
					open to the attempts of every flatterer who designs upon us.
					For even Alexander himself, being reminded of his mortality by two things especially, the necessity of sleep and the
					use of women, began to stagger in the opinion they had
					made him conceive of his godhead. And did we in like
					manner but take an impartial survey of those troubles,
					lapses, and infirmities incident to our nature, we should
					find we stood in no need of a friend to praise and extol
					our virtues, but of one rather that would chide and reprimand us for our vices. For first, there are but few who
					will venture to deal thus roundly and impartially with their
					friends, and fewer yet who know the art of it, men generally mistaking railing and ill language for a decent and
					friendly reproof. And then a chiding, like any other physic, if ill-timed, racks and torments you to no purpose, and
					works in a manner the same effect with pain that flattery
					does with pleasure. For an unseasonable reprehension
					may be equally mischievous with an unseasonable commendation, and force your friend to throw himself upon
					the flatterer; like water which, leaving the too precipitous and rugged hills, rolls down upon the humble valleys below. And therefore we ought to qualify and allay
					the sharpness of our reproofs with a due temper of candor
					and moderation,&mdash;as we would soften light which is too
					powerful for a distempered eye,&mdash;lest our friends, being
					plagued and ranted upon every trivial occasion, should
					at last fly to the flatterer's shade for their ease and quiet.
					For all vice, Philopappus, is to be corrected by an intermediate virtue, and not by its contrary extreme, as some
					do who, to shake off that sheepish bashfulness which hangs
					upon their natures, learn to be impudent; to lay aside their
					country breeding, endeavor to be comical; to avoid the
					imputation of softness and cowardice, turn bullies; out of
					an abhorrence of superstition, commence atheists; and
					rather than be reputed fools, play the knave; forcing their
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.139"/>
					
					inclinations, like a crooked stick, to the opposite extreme,
					for want of skill to set them straight.</p>
            <p>But it is highly rude to endeavor to avoid the suspicion
						of flattery by only being insignificantly troublesome, and it
						argues an ungenteel, unconversable temper in a man to
						show his just abhorrency of mean and servile ends in his
						friendship only by a sour and disagreeable behavior; like
						the freedman in the comedy, who would needs persuade
						himself that his railing accusation fell within the limits of
						that freedom in discourse which every one had right to
						with his equals. Since therefore it is absurd to incur the
						suspicion of a flatterer by an over-obliging and obsequious
						humor, and as absurd, on the other hand, in endeavoring to
						decline it by an immoderate latitude in our apprehensions,
						to lose the enjoyments and salutary admonitions of a friendly
						conversation, and since the measures of what is just and
						proper in this, as in other things, are to be taken from
						decency and moderation; the nature of the argument seems
						to require me to conclude it with a discourse upon this
						subject.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Now seeing this liberty of animadverting on other
					men's failures is liable to so many exceptions, let us in the
					first place carefully purge it from all mixture of self-love
					and interest, lest any private motive, injury, grudge, or dissatisfaction of our own should seem to incite us to the
					undertaking. For such a chiding as this would not pass
					for an effect of kindness but of passion, and looks more
					like complaint than an admonition; for the latter has
					always something in it that sounds kind and yet awful,
					whereas the other betrays only a selfish and narrow disposition. And therefore we usually honor and revere our
					monitor, but contemn and recriminate upon a querulous
					accuser. As Agamemnon could by no means digest the
					moderate censures of Achilles, yet bore well enough with
					the severer reprimand of Ulysses,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.140"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O were thy sway the curse of meaner powers,
					</l>
                     <l>And thou the shame of any host but ours!</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIV. 84.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>being satisfied of his wisdom and good intentions; for he
						rated him purely upon the account of the public, the
						other upon his own. And Achilles himself, though of a
						rough and untractable disposition and ready enough to find
						faults where there were none,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 654.</note> yet heard Patroclus patiently when he ranted him thus:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unpitying man! no Peleus caused thy birth,
						</l>
                     <l>Nor did the tender Thetis bring thee forth;
						</l>
                     <l>But rocks, hard as thy heart, and th' angry sea
						</l>
                     <l>Clubbed to produce a monstrous man like thee.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 33.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For as Hyperides the orator desired the Athenians to consider not only whether his reflections were sharp, but also
						whether his sharpness was disinterested and incorrupt; so
						the reproofs of a friend, if they proceed from a sincere and
						disinterested affection, create veneration, awe, and confusion
						in the criminal to whom they are addressed. And if he
						once perceive that his friend, waiving all offences against
						himself, chides him purely for those committed against
						others, he can never hold out against the force of so powerful a rebuke; for the sweet and obliging temper of his
						monitor gives a keener edge to his admonitions. And
						therefore it has been wisely said, that especially in heats
						and differences with our friends we ought to have a peculiar regard to their honor and interest. Nor is it a less
						argument of friendship, for a man who is laid aside and
						out of favor himself to turn advocate in behalf of another
						equally despised and neglected; as Plato being in disgrace with Dionysius begged audience of him, which he
						readily granting in expectation of being entertained with
						an account of his grievances, Plato addressed himself to
						him after this manner: Sir, said he, if you were informed
						there were a certain ruffian come over into your island of
						Sicily with design to attempt upon your majesty's person,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.141"/>
						
						but for want of an opportunity could not execute the villany, would you suffer him to go off unpunished? No, by no
						means, Plato, replied the king; for we ought to detest and
						revenge not only the overt acts but the malicious intentions of our enemies. Well then, on the other hand, said
						Plato, if there should come a person to court out of pure
						kindness and ambition to serve your majesty, and you would
						not give him an opportunity of expressing it, were it reasonable to dismiss him with scorn and disrespect ? Whom
						do you mean, said Dionysius? Why, Aeschines, replied
						Plato, as honest and excellent a person as any in the school
						of Socrates, and of a very edifying conversation; who, having exposed himself to the difficulties of a tedious voyage
						that he might enjoy the happiness of a philosophical converse with your majesty, has met with nothing but contempt in return to the kindness he intended. This friendly
						and generous temper of mind so strangely affected Dionysius, that he hugged and embraced Plato, and treated
						Aeschines with a great deal of honor and magnificence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>In the next place, let us free our discourse from all
					contumelious language, all laughter, mockery, and scurrility, which spoil the relish of our reprehensions. For,
					as when a chirurgeon makes an incision in the flesh he
					uses decent neatness and dexterity in the operation, without the affected and superfluous gesticulations of a quack
					or mountebank, so the lancing the sores of a friend may
					admit indeed of a little humor and urbanity, but that so
					qualified that it spoil not the seriousness and gravity requisite to the work. For boldness, insolence, and ill language
					destroy its force and efficacy. And therefore the fiddler
					reparteed handsomely enough upon Philip, when he undertook to dispute with him about the touch upon his
					instrument: God forbid that your majesty should be so
					unhappy as to understand a fiddle better than I do. But
					Epicharmus was too blunt upon Hiero, who invited him to
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.142"/>
					
					supper a little after he had put some of his acquaintance
					to death, when he replied, Aye, but you could not invite
					me the other day to the sacrifice of my friends. And so
					was Antiphon too rude in his reflection upon Dionysius,
					when, on occasion of a discourse about the best sort of
					bronze, he told him that was the best in his opinion of
					which the Athenians made statues of Harmodius and
					Aristogeiton. For these scurrilous abusive jests are most
					certainly disagreeable and pain to no purpose, being but
					the product of an intemperate wit, and betraying the
					enmity and ill-nature of him who takes the liberty to use
					them; and whosoever allows himself in them does but
					wantonly sport about the brink of that pit which one day
					will swallow him up. For Antiphon was afterward executed under Dionysius; and Timagenes was in disgrace
					with Augustus Caesar, not for any extravagant freedom in
					his discourse, but only because he had taken up a foolish
					custom of never talking seriously but always scurrilously
					at every entertainment and walk where the emperor desired his company,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">Scorn all his joy, and laughter all his aim;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. II. 215.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>alleging the pleasantness of his humor as the cause of his
						favor at court.</p>
            <p>Thus you shall meet with several smart and satirical
						reflections in a comedy; but the mixture of jest and fool
						in the play, like ill sauce to good meat, abates their poignancy and renders them insignificant; so that, upon the
						whole, the poet acquires only the character of a saucy and
						foul-mouthed buffoon, and the auditors lose that advantage
						which they might otherwise reap from remarks of that
						nature.</p>
            <p>We may do well therefore to reserve our jollity and
						mirth for more suitable occasions, but we must by all
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.143"/>
						
						means be serious and candid in our admonitions; which,
						if they be upon important points, must be so animated
						with our gestures, passion, and eagerness of voice, as to
						give them weight and credit and so awaken a tender concern in the persons to whom they are addressed.</p>
            <p>We are again to time our reproofs as seasonably as we
						can; for a mistake in the opportunities, as it is of ill consequence in all other things, is so peculiarly in our reprehensions. And therefore, I presume, it is manifest, we
						ought not to fall foul upon men in their drink. For first,
						he who broaches any sour disagreeable discourse amidst
						the pleasantry and good humor of friends casts a cloud
						over the serenity of the company, and acts counter to the
						God Lysius,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*lu/sios,</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">the Releaser.</hi> See Pind. Frag. 124.</note> who, as Pindar words it, unties the band of
						all our cares. Besides, such unseasonable remonstrances
						are not without danger; for wine is apt to warm men into
						passion, and make them quarrel at the freedom you take.
						And in short, it is no argument of any brave and generous, but rather of an unmanly temper, not to dare to
						speak one's sense when men are sober, but to keep barking like a cowardly cur at table. And therefore we need
						not enlarge any further upon this topic.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>But because several persons neither will nor dare
					take their friends to task whilst they thrive and flourish in
					the world, looking upon prosperity as a state above the
					reach of a rebuke, but pour forth their invectives like a
					river that has overflown its banks, insulting and trampling
					upon them, when Fortune has already laid them at their
					feet, out of a sort of satisfaction to see their former state
					and grandeur reduced to the same level of fortune with
					themselves; it may not be improper to discourse a little
					upon this argument, and make some reply to that question
					of Euripides,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">What need is there of friends when Fortune smiles?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orestes, 667.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.144"/>
            <p>I answer, to lower those lofty and extravagant thoughts
						which are usually incident to that condition; for wisdom
						in conjunction with prosperity is a rare talent and the lot
						of but few. Therefore most men stand in need of a borrowed prudence, to depress the tumors that attend an
						exuberant felicity; but when the turn of Fortune itself has
						abated the swelling, a man's very circumstances are sufficient of themselves to read him a lecture of repentance,
						so that all other grave and austere corrections are then
						superfluous and impertinent; and it is on the contrary
						more proper in such traverses of Fortune to enjoy the company of a compassionate friend,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Ion, 732.</note> who will administer some
						comfort to the afflicted and buoy him up under the pressure of his affairs. So Xenophon relates that the presence
						of Clearchus, a person of a courteous and obliging aspect,
						gave new life and courage to his soldiers in the heat of
						a battle or any other difficult rencounter. But he who
						chides and upbraids a man in distress, like him who applies
						a medicine for clearing the sight to a distempered and inflamed eye, neither works a cure nor allays the pain, but
						only adds anger to his sorrows and exasperates the patient.
						A man in health indeed will digest a friendly lecture for
						his wenching, drinking, idleness, continual recreations and
						bathing, or unseasonable eating; but for a sick man to be
						told that all this comes of his intemperance, voluptuousness, high feeding, or whoring, is utterly insupportable
						and worse than the disease itself. O impertinent man!
						will such a one say, the physicians prescribe me castor and
						scammony, and I am just making my last will and testament, and do you lie railing and preaching to me lectures
						of philosophy? And thus men in adversity stand more in
						need of our humanity and relief than of sharp and sententious reprimands. For neither will a nurse immediately
						scold at her child that is fallen, but first help him up,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.145"/>
						
						wash him, and put him in order again, and then chide
						and whip him. They tell us a story to this purpose of
						Demetrius Phalereus, that, when he dwelt an exile at
						Thebes in mean beggarly circumstances, he was once extremely concerned to observe the philosopher Crates making towards him, expecting to be treated by him with all
						the roughness of a cynical behavior. But when Crates
						had addressed himself courteously to him, and discoursed
						him upon the point of exile, endeavoring to convince him
						that it had nothing miserable or uneasy in it, but on the
						contrary rather rescued him from the nice and hazardous
						management of public affairs,&mdash;advising him withal to repose his confidence in himself and his own conscience,&mdash;
						Demetrius was so taken and encouraged by his discourse,
						that he is reported to have said to his friends, Cursed be
						those employs which robbed me so long of the acquaintance of such an excellent person. For
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Soft, friendly words revive th' afflicted soul;
						</l>
                     <l>But sharp rebukes are only for a fool.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the way of generous and ingenuous friends.
						But they who servilely admire you in prosperity,&mdash;like
						old fractures and sprains, which (as Demosthenes<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Demosth. Ol. II p. 24, 3.</note> speaks)
						always ache and pain us when some fresh disease has befallen the body,&mdash;stick close to you in the revolution of
						your fortune, and rejoice and enjoy the change. Whereas,
						if a man must needs have a remembrancer of a calamity
						which his own indiscretion hath pulled upon him, it is
						enough you put him in mind that he owes it not to your
						advice, for you often dissuaded him from the undertaking.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. IX. 108.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Well then, you say, when is a keen reprehension allowable, and when may we chide a friend severely
					indeed? I answer, when some important occasion requires
					it, as the stopping him in the career of his voluptuousness,
					anger, or insolence, the repressing his covetous humor or
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.146"/>
					
					any other foolish habit. Thus dealt Solon with Croesus,
					puffed up and debauched with the uncertain greatness of
					his fortune, when he bade him look to the end. Thus Socrates humbled Alcibiades, forced him into unfeigned tears,
					and turned his heart, when he argued the case with him.
					Such, again, were the remonstrances and admonitions of
					Cyrus to Cyaxares, and of Plato to Dion, who, when the
					lustre and greatness of his achievements had fixed all men's
					eyes upon him, wished him to beware of arrogance and self-concept, as the readiest way to make all men abandon him.
					And Speusippus wrote to him, not to pride himself in the
					little applauses of women and children, but to take care to
					adorn Sicily with religion, justice, and wholesome laws,
					that he might render the Academy great and illustrious.
					So did not Euctus and Eulaeus, two of Perseus's favorites;
					who fawned upon and complied with him as obsequiously
					as any courtier of them all during the success of his arms,
					but after his defeat at Pydna by the Romans inveighed bitterly against him, reminding him of his past faults, till the
					man out of mere anger and vexation stabbed them both on
					the spot. And so much concerning the timing our reproofs
					in general.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Now there are several other accidental occasions
					administered by our friends themselves, which a person
					heartily solicitous for their interest will lay hold of. Thus
					some have taken an opportunity of censuring them freely
					from a question they have asked, from the relation of a
					story, or the praise or dispraise of the same actions in
					other men which they themselves have committed.</p>
            <p>Thus, they tell us, Demaratus coming from Corinth into
						Macedonia when Philip and his queen and son were at
						odds, and being after a gracious reception asked by the
						king what good understanding there was among the Grecians, replied, as being an old friend and acquaintance of
						his, Aye, by all means, sir, it highly becomes your majesty
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.147"/>
						
						to enquire about the concord betwixt the Athenians and
						Peloponnesians, when you suffer your own family to be the
						scene of so much discord and contention. And as pert
						was that of Diogenes, who, entering Philip's camp as he
						was going to make war upon the Grecians, was seized upon
						and brought before the king, who not knowing him asked
						him if he was a spy. Why, yes truly, said he, I am a spy
						upon your folly and imprudence, who without any necessity
						upon you are come hither to expose your kingdoms and
						your life to the uncertain decision of the cast of a die.
						This may perhaps seem a little too biting and satirical.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>Another seasonable opportunity of reproving your
					friend for his vices is when some third person has already
					mortified him upon the same account. For a courteous
					and obliging man will dexterously silence his accuser, and
					then take him privately to task himself, advising him&mdash;if
					for no other reason, yet to abate the insolence of his enemies&mdash;to manage himself more prudently for the future.
					For how could they open their mouths against you, what
					could they have to reproach you with, if you would but
					reform such and such vices which render you obnoxious to
					their censure? And by this means the offence that was
					given lies at his door who roughly upbraided him; whilst
					the advantage he reaps is attributed to the person who candidly advised him. But there are some who have got yet a
					genteeler way of chiding, and that is, by chastising others
					for faults which they know their friends really stand guilty
					of. As my master Ammonius, perceiving once at his afternoon lecture that some of his scholars had dined more
					plentifully than became the moderation of students, immediately commanded one of his freedmen to take his own
					son and whip him. For what? says he. The youngster,
					forsooth, must needs have vinegar sauce to his meat; and
					with that casting his eye upon us, he gave us to understand
					that we likewise were concerned in the reprehension.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.148"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Again, we must be cautious how we rebuke a friend
					in company, always remembering the repartee made upon
					Plato on that account. For Socrates having fallen one day
					very severely upon an acquaintance of his at table, Plato
					could not forbear to take him up, saying, Had it not been
					more proper, sir, to have spoken these things in private?
					To which Socrates instantly replied, And had it not been
					more proper for you to have told me so in private too
					And they say, Pythagoras one time ranted a friend of his so
					terribly before company, that the poor young man went and
					hanged himself; from which time the philosopher would
					never chide any man in the presence of another. For the
					discovery and cure of a vice, like that of a scandalous disease, ought to be in secret, and not like a public show
					transacted upon the theatre; for it is no way the part of a
					friend, but a mere cheat and trick, for one man to recommend himself to the standers-by and seek for reputation
					from the failures of another, like mountebank chirurgeons,
					who perform their operations on a stage to gain the greater practice. But besides the disgrace that attends a reproof of this nature (a thing that will never work any cure),
					we are likewise to consider that vice is naturally obstinate
					and loves to dispute its ground. For what Euripides says
					is true not only of love,
					<quote rend="blockquote">The more 'tis checked, the more it presses on,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>but of any other imperfection. If you lay a man open
						publicly for it and tell all, you are so far from reforming
						him that you force him to brave it out. And therefore, as
						Plato advises that old men who would teach the younger
						fry reverence should learn to revere them first, so certainly
						modestly to reprimand is the way to meet with a modest
						return. For he who warily attacks the criminal works
						upon his good nature by his own, and so insensibly undermines his vices. And therefore it would be much more
						proper to observe the rule in Homer
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.149"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To whisper softly in the ear,
						</l>
                     <l>Lest standers-by should chance to hear.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. I. 157.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But above all, we ought not to discover the imperfections
						of an husband before his wife, nor of a father before his
						children, nor of a lover in company of his mistress, nor of
						masters in presence of their scholars, or the like; for it
						touches a man to the quick to be rebuked before those
						whom he would have think honorably of him. And I verily believe that it was not so much the heat of the wine as
						the sting of too public a reprehension, that enraged Alexander against Clitus. And Aristomenes, Ptolemy's preceptor, lost himself by awaking the king, who had dropped
						asleep one time at an audience of foreign embassadors; for
						the court parasites immediately took this occasion to express
						their pretendedly deep resentments of the disgrace done his
						majesty, suggesting that, if indeed the cares of the government had brought a little seasonable drowsiness upon him,
						he might have been told of it in private, but should not
						have had rude hands laid upon his person before so great
						an assembly; which so affected the king, that he presently
						sent the poor man a draught of poison, and made him drink
						it up. And Aristophanes says, Cleon blamed him for railing at Athens before strangers,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, Acharn. 503.</note> whereby he incensed the
						Athenians against him. And therefore they who aim at
						the interest and reformation of their friends rather than
						ostentation and popularity, ought amongst other things to
						beware of exposing them too publicly.</p>
            <p>Again, what Thucydides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucyd. I. 70.</note> makes the Corinthians say of
						themselves, that they were persons every way qualified for
						the reprehension of other men, ought to be the character
						of every one who sets up for a monitor. For, as Lysander
						replied upon a certain Megarian, who in a council of allies
						and confederates had spoken boldly in behalf of Greece,
						This style of yours, sir, needs a state to back it; so he who
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.150"/>
						
						takes upon him the liberty of a censor must be a man of a
						regular conversation himself,&mdash;one like Plato, whose life
						was a continued lecture to Speusippus, or Xenocrates,
						who, casting his eye one time upon the dissolute Polemon
						at a disputation, reformed him with the very awfulness of
						his looks. Whereas the remonstrance of a lewd whiffling
						fellow will certainly meet with no better entertainment than
						that of the old proverbial repartee,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Physician, heal thyself.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides, <foreign lang="greek">*allwn i)atro\s,au)to\s e(/lkesi bru/wn.</foreign>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>But because several accidental emergencies in conversation will now and then invite a man, though bad
					enough himself, to correct others, the most dexterous way
					of doing it will be to involve ourselves in the same guilt
					with those we reprehend; as in this passage of Homer,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fie, what's the matter, Diomede, that we
					</l>
                     <l>Have now forgot our former gallantry?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and in this other,
						<quote rend="blockquote">We are not worth one single Hector all.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 313; VIII. 234.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Socrates would handsomely twit the young men with
						their ignorance by professing his own, pretending for his
						part he had need with them to study morality and make
						more accurate enquiries into the truth of things. For a
						confession of the same guilt, and a seeming endeavor to
						reform ourselves as well as our friends, gives credit to the
						reprimand and recommends it to their affections. But he
						who gravely magnifies himself, whilst he imperiously detracts from others, as being a man forsooth of no imperfections, unless his age or a celebrated reputation indeed
						commands our attention, is only impertinent and troublesome
						to no purpose. And therefore it was not without reason
						that Phoenix, checking Achilles for his intemperate anger,
						confessed his own unhappiness in that particular, how he
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.151"/>
						
						had like once to have slain his own father through a transport of passion had not the scandalous name of parricide
						held his hands;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 461.</note> that the hero might not imagine he took
						that liberty with him because he had never offended in the
						like kind himself. For such inoffensive reproofs leave a
						deeper impress behind them, when they seem the result
						of sympathy rather than contempt.</p>
            <p>But because a mind subject to the disorders of passion,
						like an inflamed eye that cannot bear a great and glaring
						light, is impatient of a rebuke, without some temperament
						to qualify and allay its poignancy, therefore the best
						remedy in this case will be to dash it with a little praise,
						as in the following:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Think, and subdue ! on dastards dead to fame
						</l>
                     <l>I waste no anger, for they feel no shame;
						</l>
                     <l>But you, the pride, the flower of all our host,
						</l>
                     <l>My heart weeps blood to see your glory lost!</l>
                  </lg>
							           <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>Where, Pandarus, are all thy honors now,
							</l>
                     <l>Thy winged arrows and unerring bow,
							</l>
                     <l>Thy matchless skill, thy yet unrivall'd fame,
							</l>
                     <l>And boasted glory of the Lycian name!</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIII. 116; V. 171.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And such rebukes as these are also most effectual in reclaiming those that are ready to fall into gross enormities:
						<quote rend="blockquote">O where are Oedipus and all his riddles now?</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
						<quote rend="blockquote">Is this the speech of daring Hercules?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 1688; Hercules Furens, 1250.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For a mixture of both together not only abates and takes
						off from that roughness and command which a blunt reprehension seems to carry along with it, but raises in a man a
						generous emulation of himself, whilst the remembrance of
						his past virtues shames him out of his present vices and
						makes him propose his former actions for his future example. But if you compare him with other men, as with his
						fellow-citizens, his contemporaries, or relations, then vice,
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.152"/>
						
						which loves to dispute the victory, renders him uneasy
						and impatient under the comparison, and will be apt to
						make him grumble, and in an huff bid you be gone then
						to his betters and not trouble him any longer. And therefore we ought not to fall upon other men's commendations
						before him whom we take the liberty to rebuke, unless indeed they be his parents; as Agamemnon in Homer,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">Ah! how unlike his sire is Tydeus' son!<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. V. 800.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and Ulysses in the tragedy called the Scyrians, speaking to
						Achilles,&mdash;
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dost thou, who sprang from a brave Grecian race
						</l>
                     <l>By spinning thy great ancestors disgrace?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>It is in the next place very improper for a man
					immediately to retort or recriminate upon his monitor;
					for this is the way to occasion heats and animosities
					betwixt them, and will speak him rather impatient of
					any reproof at all than desirous to recompensate the
					kindness of one with another. And therefore it is better
					to take his chiding patiently for the present; and if he
					chance afterwards to commit a fault worth your remarking upon, you have then an opportunity of repaying him
					in his own coin. For being reminded, without the least
					intimation of a former pique or dissatisfaction, that he himself did not use to overlook the slips of his friend, he
					will receive the remonstrance favorably at your hands, as
					being the return of kindness rather than of anger and
					resentment.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>Moreover, as Thucydides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">II. 464.</note> says that he is a wise
					man who will not venture to incur odium except for matters of the highest concernment, so, when we do undertake
					the ungrateful office of censor, it ought to be only upon
					weighty and important occasions. For he who is peevish
					and angry at everybody and upon every trivial fault, acting
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.153"/>
					
					rather with the imperious pedantry of a schoolmaster than
					the discretion of a friend, blunts the edge of his reprehensions in matters of an higher nature, by squandering, like
					an unskilful physician, that keen and bitter but necessary
					and sovereign remedy of his reproofs upon many slight
					distempers that require not so exquisite a cure. And therefore a wise man will industriously avoid the character of
					being a person who is always chiding and delights in finding faults. Besides that, whosoever is of that little humor
					that animadverts upon every trifling peccadillo only affords
					his friend a fairer occasion of being even with him one
					time or another for his grosser immoralities. As Philotimus the physician, visiting a patient of his who was
					troubled with an inflammation in his liver, but showed
					him his forefinger, told him: Sir, your distemper is not a
					whitlow. In like manner we may take occasion now and
					then to reply upon a man who carps at trifles in another,
					&mdash;his diversions, pleasantries, or a glass of wine,&mdash;Let
					the gentleman rather, sir, turn off his whore and leave off
					his dicing; for otherwise he is an admirable person. For
					he who is dispensed with in smaller matters more willingly
					gives his friend the liberty of reprimanding him for greater.
					But there is neither child nor brother nor servant himself
					able to endure a man of a busy inquisitive humor, who
					brawls perpetually, and is sour and unpleasant upon every
					inconsiderable occasion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>But since a weak and foolish friend, as Euripides
					says of old age, has its strong as well as its feeble part, we
					ought to observe both, and cheerfully extol the one before
					we fall foul upon the other. For as we first soften iron in
					the fire and then dip it in water, to harden it into a due
					consistence; so, after we have warmed and mollified our
					friend by a just commendation of his virtues, we may then
					safely temper him with a moderate reprehension of his
					vices. We may then say, Are these actions comparable to
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.154"/>
					
					the other? Do you not perceive the advantages of a virtuous life? This is what we who are your friends require
					of you. These are properly your own actions, for which
					nature designed you; but for the other,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let them for ever from you banished be,
					</l>
                     <l>To desert mountains or the raging sea.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VI. 347.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For as a prudent physician had rather recover his patient with sleep and good diet than with castor and scammony, so a candid friend, a good father or schoolmaster,
						will choose to reform men's manners by commendations
						rather than reproofs. For nothing in the world renders
						our corrections so inoffensive and withal so useful as to
						address ourselves to the delinquent in a kind, affectionate manner. And therefore we ought not to deal roughly
						with him upon his denial of the matter of fact, nor
						hinder him from making his just vindication; but we
						should rather handsomely help him out in his apology and
						mollify the matter. As Hector to his brother Paris,
						<quote rend="blockquote">Unhappy man, by passion overruled;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VI. 326.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>suggesting that he did not quit the field, in his encounter
						with Menelaus, out of cowardice, but mere anger and indignation. And Nestor speaks thus to Agamemnon:
						<quote rend="blockquote">You only yielded to the great impulse.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 109.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For to tell a man that he did such a thing through ignorance or inadvertency is, in my opinion, a much more
						genteel expression than bluntly to say, <q direct="unspecified">You have dealt unjustly or acted basely by me.</q> And to advise a man not to
						quarrel with his brother is more civil than to say, <q direct="unspecified">Don't
							you envy and malign him.</q> And <q direct="unspecified">Keep not company with
								that woman who debauches you</q> is softer language than
						<q direct="unspecified">Don't you debauch her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you see with what caution and moderation we
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.155"/>
						
						must reprehend our friends in reclaiming them from vices
						to which they are already subjected; whilst the prevention
						of them doth require a clear contrary method. For when
						we are to divert them from the commission of a crime, or
						to check a violent and headstrong passion, or to push on
						and excite a phlegmatic lazy humor to great things, we
						may then ascribe their failings to as dishonorable causes as
						we please.</p>
            <p>Thus Ulysses, when he would awaken the courage of
						Achilles, in one of the tragedies of Sophocles, tells him,
						that it was not the business of a supper that put him
						in such a fret, as he pretended, but because he was now
						arrived within sight of the walls of Troy. And when
						Achilles, in a great chafe at the affront, swore he would
						sail back again with his squadron and leave him to himself,
						Ulysses came upon him again with this rejoinder:
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come, sir, 'tis not for this you'd sail away;
						</l>
                     <l>But Hector's near, it is not safe to stay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, by representing to the bold and valiant the
						danger of being reputed a coward, to the temperate and
						sober that of being thought a debauchee, and to the liberal
						and magnificent the chance of being called stingy and sordid,
						we spur them on to brave actions and divert them from base
						and ignominious ones.</p>
            <p>Indeed, when a thing is once done and past remedy, we
						ought to qualify and attemperate our reproofs, and commiserate rather than reprimand. But if it be a business of
						pure prevention, of stopping a friend in the career of his
						irregularities, our applications must be vehement, inexorable, and indefatigable; for this is the proper season for a
						man to show himself a true monitor and a friend indeed.
						But we see that even enemies reprove each other for faults
						already committed. As Diogenes said pertinently enough
						to this purpose, that he who would act wisely ought to be
						surrounded either with good friends or flagrant enemies;
						
						<pb id="v.2.p.156"/>
						
						for the one always teach us well, and the other as constantly accuse us if we do ill.</p>
            <p>But certainly it is much more eligible to forbear the
						commission of a fault by hearkening to the good advice of
						our friends, than afterwards to repent of it by reason of the
						obloquy of our enemies. And therefore, if for no other
						reason, we ought to apply our reprehensions with a great
						deal of art and dexterity, because they are the most sovereign physic that a friend can prescribe, and require not
						only a due mixture of ingredients in the preparation of
						them but a seasonable juncture for the patient to take
						them in.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>But because, as it has been before observed, reproofs
					usually carry something of trouble and vexation along with
					them, we must imitate skilful physicians, who, when they
					have made an incision in the flesh, leave it not open to the
					smart and torment that attends it, but chafe and foment it
					to assuage the pain. So he who would admonish dexterously must not immediately give a man over to the sting
					and anguish of his reprehensions, but endeavor to skin
					over the sore with a more mild and diverting converse;
					like stone-cutters, who, when they have made a fracture in
					their statues, polish and brighten them afterwards. But if
					we leave them in pain with their wounds and resentments,
					and (as it were) with the scars of our reproofs yet green
					upon them, they will hardly be brought to admit of any
					lenitive we shall offer for the future. And therefore they
					who will take upon them to admonish their friends ought
					especially to observe this main point, not to leave them
					immediately upon it, nor abruptly break off the conference
					with disobliging and bitter expressions.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>