<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Amatorius</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.113">
      <body>
         <head>Of love.
				<lb/> FLAVIANUS AND AUTOBULUS, SONS OF PLUTARCH.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.254"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>FLAVIANUS. Was it not in Helicon, dear Autobulus,
				that those discourses were held concerning Love, which&mdash;
				whether thou hast already set them down in writing, or
				still carriest them in thy memory, as having often desired
				them from thy father&mdash;we are now in expectation that
				thou wilt recite to us, at our importunate request?</p>
            <p>AUTOBULUS. I was in Helicon, dear Flavianus, among
					the Muses, at what time the Thespians performed the
					Erotic solemnities. For they celebrate every four years
					certain games and festivals very magnificent and splendid
					in honor of Cupid, as well as of the Muses.</p>
            <p>FLAV. Know'st thou then what it is we all desire at thy
					hands, as many as are gathered here together to be thy
					auditors?</p>
            <p>AUTOB. No; but I shall know, when I am once by you
					informed.</p>
            <p>FLAY. Curtail, we beseech ye, your discourse at present,
					forbearing the descriptions of meadows and shades, together with the crawling ivy, and whatever else poets are
					so studious to add to their descriptions, imitating with more
					curiosity than grace Plato's Ilissus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato's Phaedrus, p. 230 B.</note> with the chaste tree
					and the gentle rising hillock covered with green grass.</p>
            <p>AUTOB. What needed my relation, dearest Flavianus,
					such a proem as this? The occasion that gave birth to
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.255"/>
					
					these discourses of itself (as it were) asks for a chorus, and
					it requires a theatre; otherwise there is nothing wanting
					of a complete drama. Therefore let us only beseech
					Memory, the mother of the Muses, to be propitious and
					assist us in the discovery of the fable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>For a long time before we were born, when our
				father had newly espoused our mother, an unlucky variance that fell out between their parents caused him to take
				a journey to Thespiae, with an intention to sacrifice to the
				God of Love; and he carried my mother also to the feast
				(for that it properly belonged to her as well to make the
				feast as to perform the sacrifice), besides several of his
				familiar acquaintance that accompanied him from his
				house. Now being arrived at Thespiae, he met with
				Daphnaeus, the son of Archidamus, who was in love with
				Lysandra, the daughter of Simon, and who was, above all
				her suitors, chiefly the most welcome and acceptable to her.
				There he also found Soclarus, the son of Aristion, who was
				come from Tithorea; together with Protogenes of Tarsus
				and Zeuxippus the Lacedaemonian, by whom he had been
				several times kindly entertained; and he said that most of
				the chief men among the Boeotians were there also. Thus
				they staved for two or three days in the city, entertaining
				each other with learned discourses, one while in the common wrestling-places, sometimes in the theatres, still keeping company together. After that, avoiding the troublesome contest of the harpers and musicians,&mdash;it being
				found out that all had been settled beforehand by favor and
				intrigue,&mdash;the greatest part brake company, as if they
				had been discamping out of an enemy's country, retired to
				Helicon, and took up their lodgings among the Muses.
				Thither the next morning came to them Anthemion and
				Pisias, persons of eminent nobility, and both allied to
				Baccho, surnamed the Fair, and in some way at difference
				one with another, by reason of the affection which they
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.256"/>
				
				severally bore to him. For there was at Thespiae, Ismenodora, of an illustrious family, and wealthy withal;
				and indeed in all other respects discreet and modest; and
				moreover she had continued a widow no little time, without
				spot or stain to her reputation, though both young and
				beautiful.</p>
            <p>Now it happened that while this brisk widow was endeavoring to make up a match between Baccho, who was
					the son of her intimate friend, and a certain just blooming
					virgin nearly allied to herself, by often talking with the
					young gentleman and much frequenting his company, she
					began to feel some sparks of kindness kindled for him in
					her own breast. Afterwards hearing him highly commended by others, and speaking many things in his praise
					herself, and finding him beloved by a great number of persons of the best rank, by degrees she fell desperately in
					love with the youth ; nevertheless with a resolution to do
					nothing unbeseeming her birth and quality, but after
					public wedlock to acknowledge him as her husband. But
					as the match seemed impracticable by reason of the distance
					of their years, so the mother of the young man suspected
					the nobility and grandeur of her house not to be correspondent to her son's condition, which rendered him incapable
					of such a preferment. Moreover, his companions that
					were wont to go a hunting with him, weighing the difference between his and the age of Ismenodora, filled his
					head with several scruples, and scaring him with continual
					frumps and scoffs, more effectually hindered the match
					than they who labored industriously and seriously to prevent it. And the young man himself felt ashamed at his
					age to be married to a widow. At last, however, shaking
					off all others, he applies himself to Pisias and Anthemion
					for their advice in a matter of so great concernment. The
					elder of these two, Anthemion, was his cousin, and Pisias
					the most earnest of his lovers. The latter therefore withstood
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.257"/>
					
					 the match with all his might, and upbraided Anthemion, as one that went about to betray the young man to
					Ismenodora. On the other side, Anthemion told Pisias,
					that he did not well to do as he did, having the reputation
					of a worthy honest man, to imitate those lewd lovers, and
					endeavor to deprive his friend of a noble house, a rich
					wife, and other great conveniences, that he might have the
					pleasure to see him frequently naked in the wrestling-places, fresh and smooth, and a stranger to female sports.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>However, to prevent the growing of any quarrel between them, through long and passionate disputes, they
				chose for umpires of the controversy my father and those
				friends that were with him. And beside them, as if they
				had been chosen on purpose, Daphnaeus pleaded for Pisias,
				and for Anthemion, Protogenes; who bitterly inveighing
				against Ismenodora, 0 Hercules, cried Daphnaeus, what
				may we not expect, when Protogenes bids defiance to love?
				he that all along has spent as well the serious as sportive
				hours of his life both in love and for love, without regard
				either to learning or his country; nor like to Laius, who was
				but live days' journey distant from home,&mdash;for his was a
				slow sort of love upon the dry land,&mdash;whereas your Cupid,
				Protogenes,
				<quote rend="blockquote">With nimble wings displayed,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>crossed the seas from Cilicia to Athens, merely to visit and
					straggle up and down with lovely boys. And indeed, such
					at first was the true cause of Protogenes's peregrination.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>At which the company falling into a loud laughter;
				How! said Protogenes, can you believe that I at this time
				wage war against love, and that I do not rather fight for
				love against intemperate desire and lascivious wantonness,
				which, under the shelter of the most honest and fairest
				names that are, let themselves loose into the most shameful acts of inordinate lust and concupiscence? Then Daphnaeus: Do ye number wedlock and the conjunction of man
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.258"/>
				
				and wife (than which there is no tie more sacred in this
				life) among the vile and dishonest actions of the world?
				Why truly, replied Protogenes, this same bond of wedlock,
				as being necessary for generation, is not undeservedly perhaps extolled by our grave politicians and lawgivers, and
				by them recommended to the multitude. But I must tell
				ye, if you mean true love, there is not a farthing's worth of
				it to be found among women. Nor do I believe that either
				you yourselves, or any other that dote so much as you pretend to do upon women and virgins, love them any otherwise than as flies love milk, or bees love honey-combs; or
				as cooks and butchers fat up calves and poultry in the dark,
				not out of any extraordinary affection which they bear to
				these creatures, but for the gain which they make of them.
				But as Nature prompts all men to the use of bread and
				meat with moderation and so far as may suffice the appetite, the excess of which becomes a vice, under the name
				of gluttony or gormandizing; thus it is natural for men and
				women to desire the pleasures of mutual enjoyment, but as
				for that impetuous concupiscence that hurries the greatest
				part of mankind with so much strength and violence, it is
				not properly called love. For love that is bred in a young
				and truly generous heart, by means of friendship, terminates
				in virtue; whereas all our desires towards women, let them
				be taken in the best sense he can, serve us only to reap the
				fruit of pleasure, and to assist us in the fruition of youth
				and beauty. As Aristippus testified to one that would have
				put him out of conceit with Lais, for that, as he said, she
				did not truly love him; no more, said he, am I beloved by
				pure wine or good fish, and yet I willingly make use of
				both. For the end of desire is pleasure and enjoyment.
				But love, having once lost the hopes of friendship, will
				neither tarry, nor cherish for beauty's sake that which is
				irksome, though never so gaudy in the flower of youth, if
				it bring not forth the fruit of a disposition propense to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.259"/>
				
				friendship and virtue. And therefore it is that you hear a
				certain husband in a tragedy thus talking to his wife:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou hat'st me? True;&mdash;and I thy proud disdain
				</l>
                     <l>Will brook with patience, careless of the pain,
				</l>
                     <l>So long as my dishonor gives me gain.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now I take him to be not at all a more amorous man than
					this, that can endure, for the sake of his carnal pleasure, and
					not for gain, the plague of a curst ill-natured shrew, that is
					always scolding. The first of which love-martyrs Philippides the comedian thus derided in the person of Stratocles
					the rhetorician:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>She lowers and growls and turns her tail
					</l>
                     <l>With fury so unkind,
					</l>
                     <l>The wittol blest would think himself,
					</l>
                     <l>To kiss her coif behind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this be the passion you talk of which is to be called
					Love, it is a spurious and effeminate love that sends us to
					the women's chambers, as it were to the Cynosarges at
					Athens. Or rather, as they say there is a sort of generous
					and true bred mountain eagle, which Homer calls the black
					eagle and eagle of prey, and then again there is another
					sort of bastard eagle, that takes fish and birds that are lazy
					and slow of flight, and wanting food makes a shrill and
					mournful noise for hunger; thus the true genuine love is
					that of boys, not flaming with concupiscence, as according
					to Anacreon the love of maids and virgins does, neither
					besmeared with odoriferous ointments, nor alluring with
					smiles and rolling glances; but you shall find him plain
					and simple and undebauched with pleasures in the schools
					of the philosophers, or in the wrestling-lists and places of
					public exercise, smart and generous in the chase of youth,
					and exhorting to virtue all that he finds to be fit objects of
					his diligence; whereas that other love, nice and effeminate,
					and always nestling in the bosoms and beds of women, pursuing soft pleasures, and wasted with unmanly delights,
					that have no gust of friendship or heavenly ravishment of
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.260"/>
					
					mind, is to be despised and rejected of all mankind. This
					indeed Solon did, when he forbade slaves and servants the
					use of male familiarity and of dry ointment, but granted
					them the liberty to accompany with women; as looking
					upon friendship to be laudable and civil, but pleasure to
					be a vulgar thing and unbecoming a man born free.
					Whence it appears that to make love to a slave boy is
					ignoble and unworthy of a freeman ; for this is mere mischievous love of copulation, like the affection toward
					women.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Now while Protogenes was desirous to say more,
				Daphnaeus interrupting him said: Truly you have done
				well to put us in mind of Solon, and we may make use of
				him as the judge of a person addicted to love. Hear what
				he says:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then dote upon the flowery youth of boys,
				</l>
                     <l>Their fragrant breath admiring and soft thighs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Add to this of Solon that other of Aeschylus:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ungrateful, for the kisses of my lips,
					</l>
                     <l>Not to revere the glory of my lips.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These are proper judges of love; but others there are who
					deride all those that would have lovers inspect thighs and
					haunches, like so many sacrificers and diviners. And for
					my part I draw from hence a very strong argument on the
					behalf of the women. For if male converse, which is
					altogether against nature, neither extinguishes nor is any
					ways noxious to amorous affection, much more probable is it
					that the love of women, which is according to nature, should
					reach to the consummation of friendship, by virtue of that
					obsequious beauty which attends it. For I must tell you,
					Protogenes, the submission of the female to the male was
					by the ancients expressed by the word <foreign lang="greek">xa/ris</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">grace or favor</hi>).
					For which reason Pindar observes that Vulcan was by
					Juno brought forth without the graces; and Sappho tells
					a young virgin, not yet ripe for matrimony,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.261"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">A little child thou seem'st, and without grace.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And a certain person puts the question to Hercules,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>By force or by persuasion did the maid
					</l>
                     <l>Her favors yield?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the submission of males to males, whether it be by
					compulsion and strength, like a violent and forcible rape,
					or whether it be voluntary,&mdash;men suffering themselves
					weakly and effeminately to be covered by each other, like
					four-footed beasts, and counterfeiting the act of generation
					in defiance of nature (as Plato says),&mdash;is void of all grace,
					brutish, and contrary to the end of venereal pleasure.
					Wherefore I am apt to believe that Solon wrote those lines
					when he was young, brisk, and full of seed (as Plato
					phrases it), but when he was grown into years, he sang
					another note:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sports of Venus, now, are my delight,
					</l>
                     <l>Or else with Bacchus to carouse;
					</l>
                     <l>At other times the Muses' charms invite;
					</l>
                     <l>These are the chiefest pleasures mankind knows;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if he had altered his course of life, and retired from the
					storms and tempests of pederastic fury into the calms of
					wedlock and philosophy. Now then, Protogenes, let us
					but consider the truth of the matter, we shall find the passion of lovers to be the same, whether it be for boys or for
					women; or if, out of a contentious humor, you will distinguish them, you shall find that this affection for boys
					does not keep itself within bounds, but like a late-born
					issue, clandestinely brought forth in the dark and out of
					season, it strives to expel the truly genuine and legitimate
					love, which is much the more ancient. For give me leave
					to tell ye, my dear friend, it is but (as it were) of yesterterday's standing or of the day before&mdash;since young boys
					began to strip and show themselves naked in the public
					places of exercise&mdash;that this frenzy, getting in by degrees
					and crowding in there, afterwards by little and little became
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.262"/>
					
					 better fledged and gathered strength of wings in the
					wrestling- rings, so that now the insolence of it can no
					longer be so restrained but that still it will be affronting and
					adulterating conjugal love, which is the coadjutrix of Nature and helps to immortalize mortal mankind, raising up
					and immediately restoring again by generation our human
					nature when it has been extinguished by death. But this
					same Protogenes denies there is any pleasure in male concupiscence, for he is ashamed and afraid to acknowledge
					it. Therefore there must be some decent pretence for the
					feeling and handling these adult and lovely youths. And
					truly he has found out a very clever excuse, alleging it to
					be for the sake of friendship and virtue. Therefore he
					rolls himself in the dust, washes with cold water, erects his
					brows, and outwardly pretends to philosophy and chastity,
					for fear of the law; but when darkness covers the earth,
					and all people have betaken themselves to their rest,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Sweet the ripe fruit he finds, its keeper gone.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now if it be as Protogenes says, that no carnal conjunction
					attends these masculine familiarities, how can it be love,
					when Venus is absent; seeing that of all the Goddesses,
					she it is that Cupid is bound to obey and attend, and that
					he has no honor or power but what she confers upon him?
					But if there be a sort of love without Venus, as a man
					may be drunk without wine by drinking the decoctions of
					figs or barley, the disturbance of such a love must prove
					fruitless and to no end, and consequently loathsome and
					offensive.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>These things thus said, it was apparent that Pisias
				found himself touched to the quick, and much concerned
				for what Daphnaeus had spoken. But after he had been
				silent awhile, O Hercules, said he, what a strange impudence and levity is this in men, to acknowledge themselves
				tied to women by their generating parts, like dogs to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.263"/>
				
				hitches; by this means expelling and banishing love from
				the places of exercise, from the public porticos, and from
				conversing under the open sky and sunshine, to the stews,
				poniards, philters, and sorceries of lascivious women; for
				it is not convenient for the chaste either to love or to
				be beloved. At which words, as my father told me, he
				took Protogenes by the hand, and repeated to him these
				verses:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Words such as these the Argive courage warm;
				</l>
                     <l>And the affronted youth provoke to arm.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For surely (he added) the exorbitant language of Pisias
					gives us good reason to take Daphnaeus's part, while he
					introduces over the head of wedlock a society void of love,
					and utterly a stranger to that same friendship which
					descends and is inspired from above; which, if real affection and submission be wanting, can hardly be restrained
					by all the curbs and yokes of shame and fear. Then
					Pisias: For my part, said he, I give little heed to this
					argument; for as for Daphnaeus, I find him in the same
					condition with brass. For as brass is not so easily melted
					by the fire as by the force of the same melted and liquid
					metal being poured upon it, which mollifies both alike, and
					causes them to run and mix together; so it is not the beauty
					of Lysandra that inflames him, but the conversing along
					with one that is already inflamed and full of fire, that sets
					him all in a flame himself; and it is apparent that, unless
					he makes haste to us, he will suddenly be melted with his
					own heat. But I perceive, said he, the same thing will
					befall me which Anthemion has most reason to desire, that
					I too shall offend the judges; and therefore I shall say
					no more. Then Anthemion: 'Tis very true indeed, your
					fear is just; for you ought at the first to have spoken to
					the purpose, and what was proper to the argument in
					hand.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>To this Pisias replied: I am willing enough that
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.264"/>
				
				every woman should have her lover; but withal, it very
				much concerns Baccho to have a care how he entangles
				himself in Ismenodora's wealth; lest, while we match him
				with so much grandeur and magnificence, we consume him
				to nothing, like tin among brass. For I must tell you, it
				would be a hard matter for so young a stripling as he is,
				though he should marry a plain and ordinary woman, to
				keep the upper hand, like wine mixed with water. But
				we see her already design superiority and command; else
				why should she refuse so many suitors of great wealth and
				noble extraction that court her daily, to woo herself a mere
				boy, that has but newly assumed the robes of manhood
				and is more fit to go to school than to marry. And therefore those husbands that are wise, without any admonition,
				out of their own foresight, clip their wives' wings themselves; that is, they prune away their riches, that prompt
				them to luxury and vanity, and render them inconstant and
				foolish. For many times, by the help of these wings, they
				soar out of their husbands' reach and fly quite away; or if
				they stay at home, better it were for a man to be chained
				with fetters of gold, as they chain their prisoners in Ethiopia, than to be tied to the riches of a wife.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>However, said Protogenes, he has not hinted to us in
				the least the hazard we run of inverting absurdly and
				ridiculously the counsel of Hesiod, whose words are
				these:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Take to thy home a woman for thy bride
				</l>
                     <l>When in the ripeness of thy manhood's pride:
				</l>
                     <l>Thrice ten thy sum of years, the nuptial prime;
				</l>
                     <l>Nor far fall short, nor far exceed the time.
				</l>
                     <l>Four years the ripening virgin should consume,
				</l>
                     <l>And wed the fifth of her expanded bloom.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 696, translated by Elton.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Quite contrary to this precept, we are going about to
					couple a young lad, scarce ripe for marriage, to a lady
					much older than himself; like those that graft the tender
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.265"/>
					
					scions of dates and fig-trees upon old stocks, to make them
					bear fruit before their season. But you will say, The woman
					is in love up to the cars, and burns with desire. Who is he
					that will hinder her from masquerading before his doors,
					from singing her amorous lamentations at his windows,
					from adorning his statues with chaplets and garlands of
					flowers, from duelling her rivals, and winning him from
					them all by feats of arms? For these are acts that demonstrate the height of a passionate affection. Let her knit
					her brows, refrain all manner of pomp of luxury; let her
					put on a garb and countenance suitable to such a violent
					passion. But if bashful and modest, let her sit at home,
					expecting her suitors and gallants to come and court her
					there. But who would not fly and abominate a woman
					that professes love, and loathe the idea of taking one to
					wife who makes such an impudent incontinence the first
					step to future nuptials?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>When Protogenes had thus concluded; Do you not
				see, Anthemion, saith my father, how they again make
				common cause against us, enforcing us still to continue our
				discourse of nuptial love, who deny not ourselves to be the
				upholders of it, nor ever avoided the being one of that
				celebrated chorus? Most certainly I do, replied Anthemion;
				therefore proceed in the defence of conjugal affection; and
				let us have also your assistance in maintaining the argument about riches, with which Pisias chiefly seems to scare
				us. 'Tis the least we can do, said my father; for what in
				the world will not be made a reproach to womankind,
				should we reject Ismenodora because she is in love and
				wealthy to boot? Grant that she is imperious as well as
				rich. What then if she is beautiful and young? What
				if she is somewhat stately and haughty, by reason of her
				illustrious birth? There is nothing of crabbedness, nothing
				scornful, nothing sour, nothing troublesome, in women
				truly chaste and modest. And yet their very chastity gains
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.266"/>
				
				them the name of shrews and furies. But you will say,
				since it may be a man's misfortune to be so hampered,
				would it not be better to marry some Thracian Abrotonon
				or some Milesian Bacchis, whom he can get in the market
				for money and a handful of nuts? And yet we have
				known some men that have been miserably henpecked by
				this sort of underlings. The Samian minstrels and morris-dancers, such as were Aristonica, Oenanthe with her tabor
				and pipe, and Agathoclia, insulted over the diadems of
				sovereigns. The Syrian Semiramis was a poor wench, kept
				by one of Ninus's slaves, partly as his servant, partly as his
				harlot, till Ninus, meeting her and taking a fancy to her,
				at length doted upon her to that degree, that she not only
				governed him as she pleased herself, but contemned him;
				so that, finding she had got the absolute mastery over him,
				she became so bold as to desire him to do her the favor to
				see her sit but one day upon his throne, with the royal
				diadem upon her head, dispatching the public business.
				To which the king consenting, and giving order to all his
				officers to yield her the same obedience as to himself, at
				first she was very moderate in her commands, only to make
				trial of the guards about her; but when she saw that they
				obeyed her without the least hesitation or murmuring, she
				commanded them first to lay hold of Ninus himself, then
				to bind him, at length to kill him. Which being done, she
				took the government upon herself, and reigned victoriously
				over all Asia with great splendor and renown.</p>
            <p>And was not Belestiche a barbarian courtesan bought
					in the market, in whose honor the Alexandrians erected
					temples and altars, with inscriptions to Venus Belestiche
					as marks of the king's affection to her? And as for her
					who is in this very city enshrined in the same temple and
					honored with the same solemnities as Cupid, and whose
					gilded statue stands among kings and queens at Delphi,
					&mdash;I would fain know what dowry of hers it was that
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.267"/>
					
					brought so many lovers into such subjection to her.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The famous courtesan Phryne was a native of Thespiae, where her marble
						statue stood in the temple of Love. She also sent her own statue by Praxiteles
						(who was her lover) to the temple at Delphi. See Pausanias, X. 15, 1. (G.)</note> But
					as those great men, through their softness and effeminacy,
					became a prey to those women; so on the other side, men
					of low and mean condition, having married women both
					wealthy and of splendid extraction, neither lowered sail
					nor abated any thing of their courage and greatness of
					mind, but lived together with their wives, always honoring
					them, and keeping that superiority over them which was
					their right and due. But he that contracts and reduces
					his wife within a narrow compass, and makes her less, like
					a ring that is too big for the finger, to prevent her from
					dropping off, is like to those that dock off their mares'
					tails and clip their manes, and then lead them to a river or
					pond; for it is reported, that when those mares perceive
					themselves so ill favoredly shorn and disfigured, they lose
					their natural courage, and will afterwards suffer themselves
					to be covered by asses.</p>
            <p>Now, as it is a base thing to prefer the riches of a woman
					above her virtue or nobility, so is it as great folly to reject
					wealth, when accompanied with virtue and illustrious parentage. Antigonus writing to a captain of his, whom he
					had ordered to fortify the hill Munychia, bade him not only
					make the collar strong but keep the dog lean; intimating
					thereby that he should take care to impoverish the Athenians. But there is no necessity for the husband of a rich
					and beautiful wife to make her poor or to disfigure her;
					but by self-control and prudence, and by seeming not to
					admire any thing extravagantly in her, to carry himself so
					that she may perceive that, as he designs not to be a tyrant,
					so she must not expect him to be her subject; giving his
					own character that weight in the balance, that the scale
					may be turned without offence and for the good of both.
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.268"/>
					
					Now, as for Ismenodora, her years are fit for marriage, and
					she is a woman most likely to bear children; nay, I am
					informed that she is now in her prime. For, continued he,
					smiling upon Pisias, she is not elder than any of her
					rivals; neither has she any gray hairs, as some that keep
					company with Baccho. Now if those people think their
					converse with the young gentleman no way misbecoming
					their gravity, what hinders but that she may affect and
					cherish him better than any young virgin whatever? For
					I must needs say, it is a difficult matter many times rightly
					to mix and blend the tempers of young people; in regard
					it will require some time to make them sensible of several
					extravagancies which they may commit, until they have
					laid aside the pride and wantonness which is incident to
					youth. For many a blustering tempest will happen between the new-married couple before they can be brought
					to endure the yoke, and draw quietly together, more especially if the God of Love appear among them; and youthful wantonness&mdash;like the wind in the absence of the pilot
					&mdash;will disturb and confuse the happiness of the match,
					while the one has not skill to govern and the other refuses
					to be governed. Now then, if it be so that nurses are
					sought for to look after sucking infants, and schoolmasters
					to teach children; if masters of exercise direct young
					striplings, and the lover his youth; if the law and the
					captain-general govern those that are of age, so that no
					man can be said to be at his own liberty to do what he
					list; where is the absurdity for a wife, that has wit and
					discretion and the advantage of years, to govern and direct
					the life and conversation of a youthful husband, profitable
					to him as exceeding him in wisdom, and augmenting the
					pleasure of her society by the sweetness of her disposition
					and reality of affection? To conclude, said he, we that
					are Boeotians ourselves ought to reverence Hercules, and
					not to be offended with those that marry women elder than
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.269"/>
					
					themselves; knowing, as we do, that even Hercules himself gave his own wife Megara, being then three and thirty
					years old, to Iolaus his son, being no more than sixteen
					years of age.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>While they were in the midst of these discourses,
				one of Pisias's companions and friends, as my father reported, came galloping towards them out of the city, whip
				and spur, to bring the news of a strange and wonderful
				accident. For Ismenodora, believing that Baccho no way
				disliked being married to her, but only was deterred by the
				importunities of his friends that dissuaded him from the
				match, resolved not to let the young man escape her. To
				this purpose she sent for certain sparks of her acquaintance, whom she knew to be stout and resolute young
				gentlemen, and some women that were well-wishers to her
				amours, and observing the hour that Baccho was wont to
				pass by her house to the wrestling-place, well attended and
				decently garbed, one day when he came near the outermost
				door, anointed as he was for the exercise, with two or three
				more in the same posture, she met him in the street, and
				gently twitched his upper coat. This signal being given,
				her friends rushed forth, and fairly and softly catching
				him up in his mandilion and doublet, in a huddle together
				they carried him into the house, and locked the door fast
				after them. Then came the women also, and pulling off
				his mandilion, threw about him a costly nuptial garment.
				The servants likewise, running up and down from one place
				to another, adorned the posts not only of Ismenodora's
				but of Baccho's house with olive and laurel boughs; and
				a minstrel likewise was ordered to pipe along the street.
				The story thus related, the Thespians and strangers some
				of them laughed, some others were heinously offended,
				and did what they could to exasperate the presidents of
				the public exercises. For they have a great command over
				the young gentlemen, and keep a severe and vigilant eye
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.270"/>
				
				upon all their actions. And now there was not a word
				said of the sports that were intended; but all the people,
				forsaking the theatre, flocked to Ismenodora's house, discoursing and debating the matter one among another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But when Pisias's friend, with his horse all foaming
				and in a sweat, as if he had brought intelligence from the
				army in tithe of war, had delivered his news, being hardly
				able to speak for want of breath, and concluding his story
				with saying that Ismenodora had ravished Baccho; my
				father told me, that Zeuxippus fell a laughing, and as he
				was a great admirer of that poet, repeated the verses of
				Euripides:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wanton with wealth, fair lady, thou hast done
				</l>
                     <l>No more than nature teaches every one.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But Pisias, starting up out of his seat, made a great exclamation, crying out: O ye Gods! when will ye put an
					end to this licentiousness, that will in the end subvert our
					city? For now all things are running into disorder through
					violation of the laws; but perhaps it is now looked upon
					as a slight matter to transgress the law and violate justice,
					for even the law of nature is transgressed and broken by
					the insolent anarchy of the female sex. Was ever there
					any such thing committed in the island of Lemnos? Let
					us go, said he, let us go and deliver up the wrestling-place
					and the council house to the women, if the city be so effeminate as to put up with these indignities. Thus Pisias
					brake from the company in a fury; nor would Protogenes
					leave him, partly offended at what had happened, and
					partly to assuage and mollify his friend. But Anthemion:
					'Twas a juvenile bold attempt, said he, and a truly Lemnian one&mdash;I venture to say so since we are now by ourselves&mdash;of a lady warmly in love. To whom Soclarus
					smiling: Do you then believe, said he, that this was a real
					ravishment and force, and not rather a stratagem of the
					young man's own contrivance (for he has wit at will), to
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.271"/>
					
					the end he might escape out of the hands of his ruder male
					lovers into the embraces of a fair and rich widow? Never
					say so, said Anthemion, nor have such a suspicion of Baccho. For were he not naturally, as he is, of a plain and
					open temper, he would still never have concealed this thing
					from me, to whom he has always imparted his secrets, and
					whom he knew to be always a favorer of Ismenodora's design. But, according to the saying of Heraclitus, it is a
					hard matter to withstand love, not anger; for whatever love
					has a desire to, it will purchase with the hazard of life,
					fortune, and reputation. Now where is there a more modest and orderly woman in all our city than Ismenodora?
					When did you ever hear an ill word spoken of her? Or
					when did ever any thing done in her house give the least
					suspicion of an ill act? Rather we may say that she seems
					to be inspired beyond other women with something above
					human reason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Then Pemptides smiling: Truly, said he, there is a
				certain disease of the body, which they call sacred; so that
				it is no wonder if some men give the appellation of sacred
				and divine to the most raging and vehement passion of the
				mind. But as in Egypt once I saw two neighbors hotly
				contending about a serpent which crept before them in the
				road, while both concluded it to be good luck, and each
				assumed the happy omen to himself; so seeing some of
				you at this time haling love into the chambers of men,
				others into the cabinets of the women, as a divinely transcendent good, I do not wonder, since it is a passion so
				powerful and greatly esteemed, that it is magnified and
				held in greatest veneration by those that have most reason
				to clip its wings and expel and drive it from them. Hitherto therefore I have been silent, perceiving the debate to
				be rather about a particular concern, than any thing for
				the public good. But now that Pisias is gone, I would
				willingly understand from one of you, upon what account
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.272"/>
				
				it was that they who first discoursed of love were so fond
				to deify it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>So soon as Pemptides had done, and my father was
				about to say something in answer to his question, another
				messenger came from the city in Ismenodora's name, requesting Anthemion to come to her; for that the tumult increased,
				and the presidents of the games could not agree, while one
				was of opinion that Baccho was to be demanded and delivered into their hands, and the other thought it an impertinence to meddle with that which nothing concerned them.</p>
            <p>Thus Anthemion being gone, my father addressed himself to Pemptides by name, and so entered into the following discourse: You seem to me, sir, to have hit upon a
					very strange and nice point, or rather, as I may so say, to
					have endeavored to stir things which are not to be moved,
					in reference to the opinion which we have of the Gods,
					while you demand a reason and demonstration of every
					thing in particular. For it is sufficient to believe according to the faith of our forefathers and the instructions of
					the country where we have been bred and born, than which
					we cannot utter or invent a more certain argument;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For surely all the wit of human brain
					</l>
                     <l>This part of knowledge never could attain.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Bacchae, 203.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For this is a foundation and basis common to all piety and
					religion; of which if the steady rule and decreed maxims
					be once disordered and shaken, all the rest must totter and
					become suspected. And no question but you have heard
					what a clamor was raised against Euripides when he made
					this beginning of his Melanippe:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Jupiter, if his name be so;
					</l>
                     <l>'Tis only by hearsay that I know.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Melanippe, Frag. 483 and 484.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But when he exhibited the tragedy a second time, he seems
					to have had such a confidence in the lofty style and elaborate eloquence of his work, that he thus altered the verse:
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.273"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Jove, for we own he has received that name
					</l>
                     <l>From truth alone, and not from common fame.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristoph. Frogs, 1244.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>What difference then is there between calling in question
					the name of Jupiter and Minerva, and doubting of the
					name of Cupid or Love? For it is not of late that Love
					has challenged altars and sacrifices, neither is he a foreigner
					started up out of any barbarian superstition, as were the
					Attae and the Adonii, introduced by I know not what sort
					of hermaphrodites and idle women. Nor has he clandestinely crept into honors no way becoming him, to avoid the
					accusation of bastardy and being unduly enrolled in the
					catalogue of the Gods. But when you hear Empedocles
					thus saying,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And friendship too (observe my song)
					</l>
                     <l>Is like to these, both broad and long;
					</l>
                     <l>But this thou must not think to find
					</l>
                     <l>With eyes of body, but of mind,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>you ought to believe all this to be said of Love. For Love
					is no more visible than any of the rest of the ancient Deities, but apprehended only by opinion and belief; for every
					one of which if you require a reason and demonstrative
					argument, by enquiring after every temple and making a
					sophistical doubt upon every altar, you shall find nothing
					free from inquisition and malicious slander. For, that I
					may go no farther, observe but these:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I do not Venus see with mortal eyes,
					</l>
                     <l>The Goddess unto whom we sacrifice;
					</l>
                     <l>Yet this is she that mighty Cupid bare,
					</l>
                     <l>Whose offspring all terrestrial beings are.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Frag. 890.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore Empedocles gives her the epithet of the Giver
					of Life, and Sophocles calls her Fruitful; both very aptly
					and pertinently. For indeed the great and wonderful work
					of generation is properly the work of Venus, where Love
					is only an assistant when present with Venus; but his absence renders the act itself altogether irksome, dishonorable,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.274"/>
					
					 harsh, and ungrateful. For the conjunction of man
					and woman without true affection, like hunger and thirst,
					terminates in satiety, and produces nothing truly noble or
					commendable; but when the Goddess by means of Love
					puts away all loathsome glut of pleasure, she perpetuates
					delight by a continual supply of friendship and harmony
					of temper. Therefore Parmenides asserts Love to be the
					most ancient of all the works of Venus, writing thus in his
					Cosmogony:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of all the Gods that rule above,
					</l>
                     <l>She first brought forth the mighty Love.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But Hesiod, in my opinion, seems more philosophically
					to make Love the eldest of all the Gods, as from whom
					all the other Deities derive their beginning. Therefore,
					should we deprive Love of the honors which are decreed
					him, the ceremonies we ascribe to Venus will be no longer
					in request. For it is not sufficient to say, that some men
					reproach Love and load him with contumelies, but abstain
					from giving her an ill word; for upon the same theatre we
					hear these scandals fixed upon both:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love, idle of himself, takes up his rest
					</l>
                     <l>And harbors only in the slothful breast.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Danae, Frag. 324.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in another place thus upon Venus:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>She does not the name of Cypris only own,
					</l>
                     <l>But by a hundred other names is known:
					</l>
                     <l>She's hell on earth, continued violence,
					</l>
                     <l>And rage subduing all the force of sense.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, Frag. 856.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>As indeed we may say of the rest of the Gods, that there
					is not one that has escaped the scandalous jibes of illiterate
					scurrility. Look upon Mars, as in a brazen sculpture, possessing the place just opposite to Love, how highly has he
					been honored, how lowly degraded by men?
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Swine-snouted Mars, and as a beetle blind,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>'Tis he, fair dames, disorders all mankind.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles. Frag. 754.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Homer also gives him the epithets of murderous and Jacka-both-sides.
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.275"/>
					
					 Moreover, Chrysippus, explaining the name
					of this Deity, fixes a villanous accusation upon him. For,
					says he, Ares is derived from <foreign lang="greek">a)nairei=n</foreign>, which signifies <hi rend="italics">to destroy;</hi> thereby affording an occasion for some to give the
					name of Ares or Mars to that same proneness and perverse inclination of men to wrath and passion, and to
					quarrel and fight one with another. Others affirm Venus
					to be nothing but our concupiscence; that Mercury is no
					more than the faculty of speech; that the Muses are only
					the names for the arts and sciences; and that Minerva
					is only a fine word for prudence. And thus you see into
					what an abyss of atheism we are like to plunge ourselves,
					while we go about to range and distribute the Gods among
					the various passions, faculties, and virtues of men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>I plainly perceive it, replied Pemptides; for I
				neither believe it lawful to make the Gods to be passions, nor on the other side, to make the passions to be
				Deities. To whom my father: Well then, said he, do
				you believe Mars to be a God, or a passion of ours? To
				which when Pemptides replied, that he thought Mars to
				be the Deity that rectified the angry and courageous part
				of man; my father presently retorted upon him: Why
				then? said he, shall our passionate part, and those wrathful
				inclinations within us that provoke us to mischief and
				bloodshed, have a Deity to overrule and govern them; and
				will you not allow the same guardianship over our better
				propensities to love, friendship, society, and peace? Is
				there a Deity called Enyalius and Stratius that presides
				and has the superintendence over those that kill and are
				slain, a Deity that bears rule in matters of arms, all warlike preparations, assaults of cities, and depredations of
				countries, and distributes rewards as he sees occasion ; and
				shall there be no Deity to be a witness and overseer,
				a supreme governor and director, of conjugal affection,
				which terminates in concord and happy society? Nay,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.276"/>
				
				do we find that they who make it their sport to hunt wild
				goats, hares, and deer, are not without their forest Deity
				to encourage them; and they that make it their business
				to trepan wolves and bears into snares and pitfalls, pray
				for good luck to Aristaeus,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who first of all for the wild beasts of prey
				</l>
                     <l>With gins and snares in secret ambush lay;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and that Hercules, having bent his bow, before he let fly
					at the bird which he intended to hit, invoked another
					Deity, as we find in Aeschylus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hunter Apollo, and to hunters kind,
					</l>
                     <l>Direct this arrow to the mark designed;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Prometheus Released of Aeschylus, Frag. 195.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but for men that hunt the most noble game of love and
					friendship, is there no God nor so much as one Daemon
					to assist and prosper so laudable an enterprise? Truly,
					Daphnaeus, for my part, I cannot believe a man to be a
					more inconsiderable plant than an oak or mulberry tree,
					or the vine which Homer reverently calls by the name of
					Hemeris, considering that man in his due season also is
					endued with a powerful faculty to bud and pleasantly put
					forth the beauties both of his body and mind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>To whom Daphnaeus: In the name of all the Gods,
				who ever thought otherwise? All those must certainly, replied my father, who believe the care of ploughing, sowing, and planting is an employment becoming the Gods
				(and have they not for this purpose certain Nymphs attending them, called Dryads,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Who with the trees they cherish live and die?&mdash;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and does not
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The joyous Bacchus send increase of fruit,
					</l>
                     <l>The chaste autumnal light, to every tree?&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Pindar sings), and who yet will not allow that the
					nourishment and growth of children and young people,
					who in the flower of their age are to be formed and shaped
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.277"/>
					
					into several varieties of beauty, is under the care and
					tuition of any Deity; or that there is any Divinity to take
					care that man, being once born, may be guided and conducted in the true paths of virtue, and to prevent the tender plant from being bowed and bent the wrong way for
					want of a good instructor, or by the depraved conversation
					of those with whom he lives. For my part, I look upon
					it as a heinous piece of indignity and ingratitude thus to
					say, while we are all the time enjoying the bounty and
					benignity of God, which he is ready to disperse and diffuse
					over all, and which never abandons the distresses and
					needs of mortals. And yet in many of these needs the
					duty to be performed is rather necessary than pleasant.
					Thus our being delivered from the mother's womb is no
					such delightful thing, as being attended with pain and
					issues of blood; and yet there is a celestial midwife and
					overseer that takes particular care of that necessity, which
					is Lucina. And indeed a man had better never be born,
					than to be made bad and wicked for want of a good tutor
					and guardian. Nay, we find that the divine power does
					not desert us in our sickness, nor after we are dead; there
					being still some Deity or other who claims some certain
					peculiar employment or function, even upon those occasions. Among the rest, there is one that helps to convey
					the souls of such as have ended this life into the other
					world, and lays them asleep, according to this of the poet:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For shady night ne'er brought me forth to play
					</l>
                     <l>With artful touch upon the tuneful lyre,
					</l>
                     <l>Nor to be mistress of prophetic fire,
					</l>
                     <l>Nor pains of rude distempers to allay;
					</l>
                     <l>But to convey the souls of the deceased
					</l>
                     <l>Each one to their appointed place of rest.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Nauck, Frag. Adesp. 333</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheless these ministerial functions have many difficulties and troubles which attend them; whereas we cannot imagine any employment more holy, any exercise more
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.278"/>
					
					sacred, or any contention for prize and glory more becoming a Deity, than to direct and assist the lawful endeavors
					and pursuits of lovers in their prime of years and beauty.
					There is nothing dishonorable, nothing of forced necessity
					in this; but gentle persuasion and alluring grace, rendering labor delightful, leads to virtue and friendship, which
					never attains the true accomplishment of the end it aims
					at without some divine assistance, nor can have any other
					conductor and master than Cupid himself, who is the friend
					and companion of the Muses, the, Graces, and Venus his
					own mother. For, according to Melannippides,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great Love it is, that in the heart of man
					</l>
                     <l>Sows the sweet harvest of unstained desire;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and he always mingles those things that are sweetest with
					those that are fairest. What do you say, Zeuxippus? Can
					we believe it to be otherwise?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>In truth, I judge it so, replied Zeuxippus; and I
				think it would be absurd to affirm the contrary. And
				would it not be absurd indeed, said my father, since there
				are four sorts of friendships, according to the determination of the ancients,&mdash;the first, say they, is natural, the
				next is that of kindred and relations, the third is that of
				friends and acquaintance, and last is that of lovers,&mdash;if
				three of these have their several tutelar Deities, under the
				names of the patron of friendship, the patron of hospitality, and he who knits affection between those of the same
				race and family; while only amorous affection, as if it
				were unhallowed and under interdiction, is left without any
				guardian or protector, which indeed requires the greatest
				care and government above all the rest? All that you say,
				replied Zeuxippus, is undeniable.</p>
            <p>By the way, replied my father, we may here take notice
					of what Plato says upon this subject, as pertinent to our
					discourse. For he says, that there is a certain madness transmitted from the body to the soul, proceeding from a malignant
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.279"/>
					
					 mixture of ill-humors, or a noxious vapor or rather
					pernicious spirit that possesses the heart; which madness
					is a rugged and terrible disease. The other is a kind of
					fury, partaking something of divine inspiration; neither
					is it engendered within, but is an insufflation from without,
					and a disturbance of the rational and considerative faculty,
					deriving its beginning and motion from some stronger
					power; the common affection of which is called the enthusiastic passion. For as <foreign lang="greek">e)/mpnoos</foreign> signifies <hi rend="italics">filled with
						breath,</hi> and <foreign lang="greek">e)/mfrwn</foreign> denotes <hi rend="italics">replete with prudence;</hi> so this
					commotion of the soul is called enthusiasm (from <foreign lang="greek">e)/nqeos</foreign>) by
					reason it participates of a more divine power. Now the
					prophetic part of enthusiasm derives itself from the inspiration of Apollo possessing the intellect of the soothsayer; but Bacchanal fury proceeds from Father Bacchus.
					<quote rend="blockquote">And with the Corybantes ye shall dance,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>says Sophocles. For as for the extravagancies of the
					priests of Cybele, the mother of the Gods, and those
					which are called panic terrors and ejaculations, they are
					all of the same nature with the Bacchanal orgies. There
					is also a third sort of enthusiasm, proper to the Muses,
					which, possessing an even tempered and placid soul, excites and rouses up the gifts of poetry and music. But as
					for that same warlike fury which is called Arimanian, it is
					well known to descend from the God of War; a sort of
					fury, wherein there is no grace nor musical sweetness, calling forth tearful Mars, and rousing up the people to discord and tumult.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aeschylus, Suppliants, 665.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There remains yet one sort more of alienation of the
					understanding in man, the same neither obscure, nor yet
					altogether calm and quiet; concerning which I would fain
					ask Pemptides,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which of the Gods it is who shakes the spear
					</l>
                     <l>That beareth fruit so lovely and so fair.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.280"/>
            <p>But without expecting a resolution of this question, I mean
					that erotic fury that possesses lovely youths and chaste
					women, yet a hot and vehement transport. For do we not
					see how the warrior lays down his arms, and submits to
					this more prevalent rage?
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>His grooms, o'erjoyed he had the war forsook,
					</l>
                     <l>His ponderous arms from off his shoulders took;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 121.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and thus having renounced the hazards of battle, he sits
					down a quiet spectator of other men's dangers. As for
					these Bacchanalian motions and frisking of the Corybantes,
					there is a way to allay those extravagant transports, by
					changing the measure from the Trochaic and the tone from
					the Phrygian. And the Pythian prophetess, descending
					from her tripos and quitting the prophetic exhalation, becomes sedate and calm again. Whereas the fury of love,
					wherever it seizes either man or woman, sets them in a
					flame; no music, no appeasing incantations, no changes of
					place are able to quench or put a stop to it; but being in
					presence, they love; being absent, they desire; by day
					they prosecute their importunate visits; by night they
					serenade at the windows; sober, they are continually calling upon their loves; and when they are fuddled, are
					always teasing the company with their love songs and
					madrigals. Neither, as one was pleased to say, are poetical fancies, by reason of their lively expressions, rightly
					called waking dreams; but the dialogues of persons enamored, discoursing with their absent loves, and dallying,
					embracing, and expostulating with them as if they were
					present, much rather deserve this name. For the sight
					seems to delineate other fancies in the water, that quickly
					glide away and slip out of the mind; whereas the imaginations of lovers, being as it were enamelled by fire, leave the
					images of things imprinted in the memory, moving, living,
					speaking, and remaining for a long time. So that Cato
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.281"/>
					
					the Roman was wont to say, that the soul of a lover dwelt
					in the soul of the person beloved, for that there is settled
					and fixed in the one the form, shape, manners, conversation and actions of the other; by which being led, the lover
					quickly dispatches a long journey,&mdash;as the Cynics say
					they have found a compendious and direct road to virtue,
					&mdash;and he is carried from love to friendship, as it were with
					wind and tide, the God of Love assisting his passion. In
					short then I say, that the enthusiasm of lovers is neither
					void of divine inspiration, neither is it under the guardianship and conduct of any other Deity but him whose festivals we solemnize, and to whom we offer our oblations.
					Nevertheless, in regard we measure the excellency of a
					Deity by his puissance and by the benefit which we receive
					at his hands, and esteem power and virtue to be the two
					chiefest and most divine of all human blessings, it may
					not be unseasonable to consider whether Love be inferior
					in power to any other of the Gods. For, according to
					Sophocles,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great is the puissance of the Cyprian Queen,
					</l>
                     <l>And great the honor which her triumphs win.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Trachin. 497.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Great is also the dominion of Mars; and indeed we see the
					power of all the rest of the Gods divided in some measure
					between these two,&mdash;the one being most naturally allied
					to the beautiful, the other most mighty in the resistance
					of evil, and both being originally bred in the soul, as Plato
					says of his ideas.</p>
            <p>Now then let us consider, the venereal delight is a thing
					that may be purchased for a drachm, and there is no man
					that ever underwent any pain or danger for the sake of
					venereal enjoyments, unless he were inflamed with the
					fires of love. Insomuch, that not to mention such courtesans as either Phryne or Lais, we find that the harlot
					Gnathaenion,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.282"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>By lanthorn-light, at evening late,
					</l>
                     <l>Waiting and calling for some mate,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>is often passed by and neglected;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if some spirit blow the fire,
					</l>
                     <l>Kindled by love's extreme desire,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>this makes the pleasure equally esteemed and valued with
					the treasures of Tantalus and all his vast dominions. So
					faint and so soon cloyed is venereal desire, unless rendered
					grateful by the charms and inspiration of love. Which
					is more evidently confirmed by this; for that many men
					admit others to partake of their venereal pleasures, prostituting not only their mistresses and concubines, but also their
					own wives, to the embraces of their friends ; as it is reported
					of the Roman Gabba, who inviting Maecenas to his house,
					and perceiving him winking and nodding upon his wife,
					turned away his head upon his pillow, as if he had been
					asleep, while they dallied together; yet at the same time,
					when one of the servants came creeping out of the next
					room, to steal a bottle of wine from the cupboard, presently
					turning about with his eyes open, Varlet, said he, 'tis only
					to pleasure Maecenas that I sleep. But this perhaps is not
					so strange, considering that Gabba was a low buffoon.</p>
            <p>At Argos there was a great animosity between Nicostratus and Phayllus, so that they always opposed each other
					and quarrelled at the council-board. Now when King
					Philip made a visit to that city, Phayllus bethought himself, that he could not miss the highest preferment the government could afford, if he could but oblige the king with
					the company of his wife, who was both beautiful and young.
					Nicostratus, smelling this design, walked to and fro before
					Phayllus's house with some of his servants, to observe who
					went in and out. They had not stayed long, but out came
					Phayllus's wife, whom he had dressed up in high shoes,
					with a mantle and cap after the Macedonian fashion, like
					one of the king's pages, in which disguise she secretly
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.283"/>
					
					passed in to the king's lodgings. Since then there ever
					were and still are so many lovers, did you ever know of
					any one that ever prostituted his particular male friend,
					though it were to gain the honors ascribed to Jupiter himself? Truly, I believe there never was any such. For
					why? There never was any one that would pretend to
					oppose and contend with a tyrant; but there are many
					rivals and competitors, that will quarrel and fight for boys
					that are beautiful and in the prime of their years. It is
					reported of Aristogiton the Athenian, Antileon of Metapontum, and Melanippus of Agrigentum, that they never contested with tyrants, though they wasted and ruined the commonwealth and indulged the impetuosity of their lust, until
					they found them attempting their own male concubines:
					then they withstood them with the utmost peril of their
					lives, as if they had been to defend their temples and their
					most sacred sanctuaries. Alexander also is said to have sent
					to Theodorus, the brother of Proteas, in these words: Send
					me that musical girl that plays and sings so well, and take
					ten talents for her, unless thou lovest her thyself. Another
					time, when one of his minions, Antipatridas, came to be
					jovial with him, and brought a minstrel in his company to
					complete the mirth, being greatly affected with the girl's
					playing and singing, he asked Antipatridas whether he had
					any extraordinary kindness for her? He answered, that he
					loved her as his eyes. Then all the plagues of mankind
					light upon thee, quoth the prince. However, he would not
					so much as touch the girl.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Consider also what vast power love has over martial
				men and warriors, not slothful, as Euripides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Danae, Frag. 324.</note> will have it
				to be, nor unwarlike, nor
				<quote rend="blockquote">Slumbering on a girl's soft cheek.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Antigone, 784.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For a man that is once inflamed with love wants not
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.284"/>
					
					Mars himself to be his second, when he is to engage
					with his enemies; but confiding in the Deity that is within
					him,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ventures through fire and seas, and blustering storms,
					</l>
                     <l>While love of friend his daring courage warms;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and breaks through all opposition, if his mistress require
					any proof of his valor. Therefore we read in Sophocles,
					that the daughters of Niobe being wounded with arrows to
					death, one of them, as she lay wallowing in blood, calls
					out for no other help or succor to assist her in her revenge,
					but her lover.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where is my love? she cried;
					</l>
                     <l>Were I but armed with that,
					</l>
                     <l>I yet would be revenged
					</l>
                     <l>For my untimely fate.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Niobe, Frag. 407.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>You know the reason why Cleomachus the Pharsalian fell
					in battle. I am a stranger to the story, replied Pemptides,
					and would willingly therefore hear it. Certainly it is very
					well worth your knowledge, said my father.</p>
            <p>In the heat of the war between the Chalcidians and the
					Eretrians, Cleomachus went with the Thessalian force to
					aid the Chalcidians; at what time it was evident that the
					Chalcidians were the stronger in foot, but they found it a
					difficult thing to withstand the force of the enemies' horse.
					Thereupon they requested Cleomachus, being their confederate and a man signalized for his courage, to give the
					first onset upon the enemies' cavalry. Presently the youth
					whom he most entirely loved being present, he asked him
					whether he would stay and be a spectator of the combat.
					To which when the lad gave his consent, and after many
					tender kisses and embraces had put on his helmet, Cleomachus's love redoubling his courage, being surrounded
					with some few of the flower of the Thessalian horse, he
					charged into the thickest of the enemy and put them to
					the rout; which the heavy-armed infantry seeing, they betook
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.285"/>
					
					 themselves also to flight, so that the Chalcidians
					obtained a noble victory. However, Cleomachus was
					there slain, and the Chalcidians show his monument erected
					in the market-place, with a fair pillar standing upon it to
					this day; and whereas they abominated pederasty before,
					after that they admired and affected it above all other
					pleasures. Nevertheless, Aristotle tells us that Cleomachus indeed lost his life after the victorious battle which
					he gained from the Eretrians, but as for that Cleomachus
					who was thus kissed by his male concubine, that he was
					of Chalcis in Thrace, and sent to aid the Chalcidians in
					Euboea. Which is the reason of that same ballad generally sung among them:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fair youths, whose mothers brought you forth
					</l>
                     <l>Lovely in form, and noble for your birth;
					</l>
                     <l>Envy not men of courage, prompt in arms,
					</l>
                     <l>The kind fruition of your tempting charms.
					</l>
                     <l>For softest love with daring valor reigns
					</l>
                     <l>In equal honor through Chalcidian plains.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Dionysius the poet, in his poem entitled Causes, informs
					us that the name of the lover was Anton, and that the
					youth beloved was called Philistus.</p>
            <p>And is it not a custom among you Thebans, Pemptides,
					for the lover to present the beloved with a complete suit
					of armor when he is come of age? And Pammenes, a
					very great soldier but very amorously given, quite altered
					the method of embattling the heavy-armed infantry, and
					blames Homer, as one that knew not what belonged to
					love, for marshalling the several divisions of the Achaeans
					according to their tribes and clans, and not placing the
					lover by his beloved, so that the close order which he
					afterwards describes might have been the consequence, in
					which
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Spears lean on spears, on targets targets throng,
					</l>
                     <l>Helms stuck to helms, and man drove man along;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIII. 131.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.286"/>
            <p>the only way to render a battalion invincible. For men
					will desert those of the same tribe or family, nay, their
					very children and parents; but never any enemy could
					pierce or penetrate between a lover and his darling minion,
					in whose sight many times when there is no necessity the
					lover delights to show his courage and contempt of danger;
					like Thero the Thessalian, who clapping his left hand to
					the wall, and then drawing his sword, struck off his thumb,
					thereby challenging his rival to do the same. Or like another, who falling in battle upon his face, as his enemy was
					about to follow his blow, desired him to stay till he could
					turn, lest his male concubine should see that he had been
					wounded in the back.</p>
            <p>And therefore we find that the most warlike of nations
					are most addicted to love, as the Boeotians, Lacedaemonians, and Cretans. And among the most ancient heroes
					none were more amorous than Meleager, Achilles, Aristomenes, Cimon, and Epaminondas; the latter of which
					had for his male concubines Asopichus and Caphisodorus,
					who was slain with him at the battle of Mantinea and lies
					buried very near him. And when . . . had rendered himself most terrible to the enemy and' most resolute, Eucnamus the Amphissean, that first made head against him and
					slew him, had heroic honors paid him by the Phocians.
					It would be a task too great to enumerate the amours
					of Hercules; but among the rest, Iolaus is honored and
					adored to this day by many, because he is thought to have
					been the darling of that hero; and upon his tomb it is
					that lovers plight their troths and make reciprocal vows
					of their affection. Moreover, Hercules, being skilled in
					physic, is said to have recovered Alcestis from death's door
					in kindness to Admetus, who, as he had a great love for
					his wife, so was greatly beloved by the hero. For it is
					said that even Apollo, doting upon Admetus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Became his slave for a long weary year.</quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.287"/>
            <p>And here, methinks, we have very opportunely mentioned
					Alcestis; for although the temper of women has little to
					do with Mars, Love many times drives them to daring attempts beyond their own nature, even to death. And if
					there be any credit to be given to the fables of the poets,
					the stories of Alcestis, Protesilaus, and Eurydice the wife
					of Orpheus, plainly evince us that Pluto himself obeys no
					other God but Love. For, as Sophocles says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To others&mdash;be their fame or birth whate'er&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>Nor equity nor favor will he show;
					</l>
                     <l>But rigorous, and without remorse severe,
					</l>
                     <l>His downright justice only makes them know;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but to lovers he pays a reverence: to them alone is he
					neither implacable nor inexorable. And therefore, although it is a very good thing to be initiated into the
					Eleusinian ceremonies, still I find the condition of those
					much better in hell who are admitted into the mysteries of
					love; which I speak as neither altogether confiding in
					fables, nor altogether misbelieving them. For they speak
					a great deal of sense, and many times, by a certain kind
					of divine good hap, hit upon the truth, when they say
					that lovers are permitted to return from hell to sunlight
					again; but which way and how, they know not, as wandering from the right path, which Plato, first of all men,
					by the assistance of philosophy found out. For there are
					several slender and obscure emanations of truth dispersed
					among the mythologies of the Egyptians; only they want
					an acute and experienced huntsman, who is skilled in
					tracing out great mysteries by small tracks. And therefore
					let them go.</p>
            <p>And now, since we find the power of love to be so great,
					let us take a little notice of that which we call the benevolence and favor of it towards men; not whether it confers many benefits upon those that are addicted to it,&mdash;for
					that is a thing apparent to all men,&mdash;but whether the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.288"/>
					
					blessings that men receive by it are more and greater than
					any other. And here Euripides, notwithstanding that he
					was a person so amorous as he was, admires the meanest
					gift it has; for, says he,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love into men poetic fire infuses,
					</l>
                     <l>Though ne'er before acquainted with the Muses.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Stheneboea of Euripides, Frag. 666.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And he might well have said, that love makes a man wise
					and prudent that was a fool and sottish before, and a coward bold and daring, as we have already shown; as when
					we heat wood in the fire to make it strong, when before it
					was weak. In like manner, he that was a sordid miser
					before, falling once in love, becomes liberal and lofty-minded, his covetous and pinching humor being mollified
					by love, like iron in the fire, so that he is more pleased
					with being liberal to the objects of his love, than before
					delighted to receive from others. For ye all know that
					Anytus, the son of Anthemion, fell in love with Alcibiades; who, understanding that Anytus had invited several of his friends to a noble and splendid banquet, came
					into the room in masquerade, and going to the table, after
					he had taken one half of the silver cups and other plate,
					went his way. Which when some of the guests took very
					ill, and told Anytus that the young lad had demeaned himself very rudely and saucily; Not so, said Anytus, but very
					civilly, since, when it was in his power to have taken all
					the rest, he was so civil as to leave me some.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Pleased with this story, O Hercules, quoth Zeuxippus, how have you almost raced out of mind that hereditary hatred which I had conceived against Anytus, for his
				ill opinion of Socrates and philosophy, since he was become so gentle and generous in his amours. Be it so, said
				my father; but let us proceed. Love is of that nature,
				that it renders those that were severe and morose before
				both affable and pleasant in their humor. For as
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.289"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The burning tapers make the house more light,
				</l>
                     <l>And all things look more glorious to the sight;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so the heat of love renders the soul of man more lively
					and cheerful. But most men go quite contrary to reason
					in this particular. For when they behold a glittering light
					in a house by night, they admire and look upon it as something celestial; but when they see a narrow, pitiful, abject
					soul of a sudden replenished with understanding, generosity, sense of honor, courtesy, and liberality, they do not
					believe themselves constrained to say, as Telemachus in
					Homer,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Surely some God within this house resides.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIX. 40.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the love of the Graces, tell me, said Daphnaeus, is it
					not a thing altogether as much savoring of divinity, that a
					man who contemns all other things, not only his friends
					and familiar acquaintance, but also the laws, the magistrates, even kings and princes themselves, who fears nothing, is astonished at nothing, cares for nothing, but thinks
					himself able to defy the <q direct="unspecified">barbed lightning,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Pyth. I. 7.</note> yet, so soon
					as he beholds the object of his burning love,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As dunghill cravens, by a sudden blow,
					</l>
                     <l>Hang their loose wings with little list to crow,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>should presently lose all his prowess, and that all his
					bravery should fail him, as if his heart were quite sunk to
					the bottom of his body? And it were not impertinent to
					make mention of Sappho here among the Muses. For
					the Romans report in their stories that Cacus, the son
					of Vulcan, vomited fire and flames out of his mouth. And
					indeed Sappho speaks as if her words were mixed with
					fire, and in her verses plainly discovers the violent heat of
					her heart, according to that of Philoxenus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Seeking for cure of love-inflicted wounds,
					</l>
                     <l>From pleasing numbers and melodious sounds.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.290"/>
            <p>And here, Daphnaeus, if the love of Lysandra have not
					buried in oblivion your former sportive dalliances, I would
					desire you to call to mind and oblige us with the repetition
					of those elegant raptures of Sappho, wherein she tells us
					how that, when the person beloved by her appeared, her
					speech forsook her, her body was all over in a sweat; how
					she grew pale and wan, and was surprised with a sudden
					trembling and dizziness. To this Daphnaeus consented;
					and so soon as he had recited the verses, said my father:
					So Jupiter help me, is not this an apparent seizure of something more than human upon the soul? Can this be other
					than some celestial rapture of the mind? What do we
					find equal to it in the Pythian prophetess, when she sits
					upon the tripod? Where do we find the flutes which are
					used in the Bacchanalian orgies, or the tabors played upon
					in the ceremonies of the Mother of the Gods, rouse up
					such noble transports among that fanatic sort of enthusiasts?
					Many there are that behold the same body and the same
					beauty, but the lover only admires and is ravished with it.
					And what is the reason, do ye think? For we do not perceive or understand it from Menander, when he says:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis the occasion that infects the heart,
					</l>
                     <l>For only he that's wounded feels the smart.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But it is the God of Love that gives the occasion, seizing
					upon some, and letting others go free. What therefore
					had been more seasonable for me to have spoken before,
					since it is now chopped into my mouth (as Aeschylus says),
					I think I will not even now let go, as being a matter of
					great importance. For it may be, my dear friend, there is
					not any thing in the world which was not made perceptible
					by sense, but what gained credit and authority at the first
					either from fables, or from the law, or else from rational
					discourse. And therefore poets, lawgivers, and in the
					third place philosophers, were all along the first that instructed and confirmed us in our opinion of the Gods.
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.291"/>
					
					For all agree that there are Gods; but concerning their
					number, their order, their essence and power, they vastly
					differ one among another. For the philosophers' Deities
					are subject neither to age nor diseases, neither do they
					undergo any labor or pain,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Exempted from the noise and hurry
					</l>
                     <l>Of busy Acherontic ferry.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore they will not admit poetical Deities, like Strife
					and Prayers;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. IX. 502.</note> nor will they acknowledge Fear and Terror
					to be Gods or the sons of Mars. They also differ from
					the lawgivers in many things. Thus Xenophanes told the
					Egyptians not to worship Osiris as a God if they thought
					him to be mortal, and if they thought him to be a God not
					to bewail him. Then again, the poets and lawgivers vary
					from the philosophers, and will not so much as hear them,
					while they deify certain ideas, numbers, unities, and spirits;
					such is the wild variety and vast difference of opinions
					among this sort of people. Therefore, as there were at
					Athens the three factions of the Parali, Epacrii, and
					Pedieis, that could never agree but were always at variance
					one with another, yet when they were assembled, gave
					their suffrages unanimously for Solon, and chose him with
					one consent for their peacemaker, governor, and lawgiver,
					as to whom the highest reward of virtue was, without all
					doubt or question, due; so the three different sects or factions in reference to the Gods, in giving their opinions
					some for one and some for another, as being by no means
					willing to subscribe one to another, are all positive in their
					consent as to the God of Love. Him the most famous of
					the poets, and the numerous acclamations of the philosophers and lawgivers, have enrolled in the catalogue of the
					Gods <q direct="unspecified">with loud praises and harmonious acclaim,</q> as
					Alcaeus says of the Mitylenaeans when they chose Pittacus
					for their prince. So Hesiod, Plato, and Solon bring forth
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.292"/>
					
					Cupid out of Helicon, and conduct him in pomp and state
					into the Academy, to be our king, governor, and director,
					drawn in by friendship and intercourse with all their
					pairs of horses,&mdash;not the friendship which, as Euripides
					says, is
					<quote rend="blockquote">With fetters bound, but not of brass,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Pirithous, Frag. 598.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if the bonds of love were only the cold and ponderous
					chains of necessity, made use of as a colorable pretence to
					excuse and qualify shame, but such friendship as is carried
					upon winged chariots to the most lovely objects that exist,
					and to sights more divine than this earth affords. But on
					this point others have better discoursed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>After my father had thus delivered himself; Do you
				not perceive, said Soclarus, how, being fallen a second time
				into the same matter, you have as it were by force constrained yourself, and unjustly deprived us&mdash;if I may
				speak what I think&mdash;of that same sacred discourse which
				you were entering into? For as before you gave us a hint
				concerning Plato and the Egyptians, but passed them over
				as if it had been done against your will; so you do now
				again. Now as to what has been notably uttered by Plato,
				or rather by our Goddesses here (the Muses) through Plato's
				mouth, do not trouble yourself to tell us this, even although
				we should request it. But whereas you have obscurely
				hinted that the fables of the Egyptians accord with Plato's
				opinion concerning love, we know you have too great
				kindness for us to conceal your knowledge from us; and
				though it be but a little of those important matters, it shall
				suffice us. Thereupon the rest of the company declaring
				their readiness to give attention, my father thus began:
				The Egyptians, said he, and also the Grecians set up two
				Deities of love; the one vulgar, the other celestial; to
				which they add a third, which they believe to be the sun;
				and as for Venus, they pay her a very great veneration,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.293"/>
				
				We ourselves also do find that there is a great affinity and
				resemblance between the sun and the God of Love. For
				neither of them is material fire, as some conjecture. All
				that we acknowledge is only this, that there is a certain
				soft and generative heat and warmth proceeding from the
				sun, which affords to the body nourishment, light, and relaxation of cold; whereas that warmth which comes from
				love works the same effects in the soul. And as the sun
				breaking forth from the clouds and after a thick fog is
				much hotter; so love, after passionate anger and jealousies
				are over, and the beloved one is again reconciled, grows
				more delightful and fervent. Moreover, as some believe
				the sun to be kindled and extinguished, they also imagine
				the same things concerning love, as being mortal and unstable. For neither can a constitution not enured to
				exercise endure the sun, nor the disposition of an illiterate
				and ill-tutored soul brook love without trouble and pain;
				for both are alike distempered and diseased, for which they
				lay the blame upon the power of the God, and not their
				own weakness. Herein only there may seem to be some
				difference between them; for that the sun displays to the
				sight upon the earth both beauty and deformity at once,
				but love is a luminary that affords us the view of beautiful
				objects only, and persuades lovers to cast their eyes only
				upon what is pleasing and delightful, and with a careless
				eye to overlook all other things. On the other side, they
				that attribute the name of Venus to the moon, although
				they have no convincing proof, still have hit upon a certain
				similarity. For that the moon is celestial and divine, and
				the region of mixture between mortal and immortal; but
				it is weak of itself, obscure and dark without the presence
				of the sun; as Venus is where love is absent. Therefore
				more properly and with more probability the moon is
				likened to Venus, and the sun to Love, rather than to any
				other of the Gods.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.294"/>
            <p>Nevertheless, we must not therefore say they are all one.
					For neither are the soul and body the same, but distinct;
					as the sun is visible, but love is perceptible only by sense.
					And if it might not be thought too harsh a saying, a man
					might affirm that the sun and love act contrary to one
					another. For the sun diverts the understanding front
					things intelligible to sensible objects, alluring and fascinating the sight with the grace and splendor of his rays, and
					persuading us to search for other things, and even for
					truth itself, within and about himself, and nowhere else.
					And we appear to be passionately in love with the sun,
					because, as Euripides says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He always on the earth displays
					</l>
                     <l> glory of his burning rays,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 193.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for want of our knowledge of another life, or rather,
					through our forgetfulness of those things which love calls
					to our remembrance. For as, when we are newly awaked
					and come into a bright and dazzling light, we forget whatever appeared to the soul in our dreams; so the sun seems
					to stupefy our recollection and impoison our understanding,
					when we change from the former life and enter this world,
					so that in our pleasure and admiration we forget all other
					considerations besides that of the present life. Though
					there indeed are the real substances proper for the contemplation of the soul; here, as in sleep, it embraces only
					dreams, and gazes in admiration and astonishment at what
					appears to it most beautiful and divine, while
					<quote rend="blockquote">Fallacious charming dreams about it fly;&mdash;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>it being persuaded that here every thing is goodly and
					highly to be prized, unless it happens upon some divine and
					chaste love to be its physician and preserver. This love, entering through the body, becomes a guide to lead the soul
					from the world below to truth and the fields of truth,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.295"/>
					
					where full, pure, deceitless beauty dwells; and leading
					forth and guiding upward those that now after a long time
					are eager to embrace and live with such beauty, it stands
					by them, like a friendly mystagogue at the sacred ceremonies of initiation. But no sooner is the soul sent from
					thence again, but love is no longer able to make her approaches of herself, but by the body. And therefore as
					geometricians, when children are not able of themselves to
					apprehend the intelligible ideas of incorporeal and impassible substance, form and set before their eyes the tangible
					and visible imitations of spheres, cubes, and dodecahedrons; in like manner celestial love, having framed lovely
					mirrors to represent lovely objects,&mdash;things mortal and
					passible to represent things divine, and sensible objects to
					represent those perceptible only to the eye of reason,
					&mdash;shows them to us glittering in the forms, colors, and
					shape of youth in its prime, and first insensibly moves the
					memory inflamed by the sight of these objects.</p>
            <p>Whence it comes to pass that some, through the stupidity of their friends and acquaintance, endeavoring by force
					and against reason to extinguish that flame, have enjoyed
					nothing of true benefit thereby, but only either disquieted
					themselves with smoke and trouble, or else rushing headlong into obscure and irregular pleasures, obstinately cast
					themselves away. But as many as by sober and modest
					ratiocination have sincerely extinguished the raging heat
					of the fire, and left behind only a warm and glowing heat
					in the soul,&mdash;which causes no violent earthquake, as it was
					once called, rousing the seed and causing a gliding of
					atoms compressed by smoothness and titillation, but a wonderful and engendering diffusion, as in a blossoming and
					well-nourished plant, which opens the pores of obedience
					and affection,&mdash;these, I say, in a short time passing by
					the bodies of those whom they love, penetrate more inwardly and fall to admire their manners and dispositions;
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.296"/>
					
					and calling off their eyes from the body, they converse together, and contemplate one another in their discourses and
					in their actions, provided there be but the least scrip or
					appearance of beauty in the understanding. If not, they
					let them go, and turn their affections upon others, like bees
					that will not fasten upon many plants and flowers, because
					they cannot gather honey from them. But where they find
					any footstep, any emanation, any resemblance of a divinity,
					ravished with delight and admiration as they recall it to
					memory, they attract it to themselves, and are revived by
					striving to attain to what is truly amiable, happy, and beloved by all mankind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>True it is, that the poets, according to their sportive
				humor, seem to write many things in merriment concerning
				this Deity, and to make him the subject of their lascivious
				songs in the height of their revelling jollity, making but
				little serious mention of him; whether out of judgment
				and reason, or being assured of the truth by divine inspiration, is the question. Among the rest, there is one thing
				which they say very oddly concerning the birth and generation of this God:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Young Zephyr, doting on his golden hair,
				</l>
                     <l>At last the silver-slippered Iris won;
				</l>
                     <l>And thus embraced, at length she bore a son,
				</l>
                     <l>Of all the Gods the shrewdest and most fair:</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Alcaeus.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>unless the grammarians have likewise persuaded you, by
					saying that this fable was invented to set forth the variety
					and gay diversity of passions that attend on love.</p>
            <p>To whom Daphnaeus: To what other end or purpose
					could it be? Hear me then. said my father; for 'tis no
					more than what the celestial meteor constrains us to say.
					The affection of the sight in the case of the rainbow (or
					Iris) is caused by reflection. For when the sight lights
					upon a cloud somewhat of a dewy substance, but smooth,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.297"/>
					
					and moderately thick withal, and we behold the repercussion of the sunbeams upon it, together with the light and
					splendor about the sun, it begets an opinion in us that the
					apparition is in the cloud. In like manner, this same
					subtle invention of love-sophistry in generous and noble
					souls causes a repercussion of the memory from objects
					that here appear and are called beautiful, to the beauty
					really divine, truly amiable and happy, and by all admired.
					But most people pursuing and taking hold of the fancied
					image of this beauty in boys and women, as it were seen in
					a mirror, reap nothing more assured and certain than a
					little pleasure mixed with pain. But this seems to be no
					more than a delirium or dizziness of the vulgar sort, beholding their empty and unsatisfied desires in the clouds,
					as it were in so many shadows; like children who, thinking to catch the rainbow in their hands, snatch at the apparition that presents itself before their eyes. But a
					generous and modest lover observes another method; for
					his contemplations reflect only on that beauty which is
					divine and perceptible by the understanding; but lighting
					upon the beauty of a visible body, and making use of it as
					a kind of organ of the memory, he embraces and loves,
					and by conversation argumenting his joy and satisfaction
					still more and more inflames his understanding. But
					neither do these lovers conversing with bodies rest satisfied
					in this world with a desire and admiration of this same
					light; neither when they are arrived at another world after
					death, do they return hither again as fugitives, to hover about
					the doors and mansions of new-married people and disturb
					their dreams with ghosts and visions; which sort of visions
					really come only from men and women given to pleasure
					and corporeal delights, who by no means deserve the name
					and characters of true lovers. Whereas a lover truly
					chaste and amorous, being got to the true mansion of
					beauty, and there conversing with it as much as it is lawful
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.298"/>
					
					 for him to do, mounted upon the wings of chaste desire,
					becomes pure and hallowed; and being initiated into sacred
					orders, continues dancing and sporting about his Deity, till
					returning again to the meadows of the Moon and Venus,
					and there laid asleep, he becomes ready for a new nativity.
					But these are points too high for the discourse which we
					have proposed to ourselves.</p>
            <p>To return therefore to our purpose; Love, according to
					Euripides, with all the rest of the Gods, delights
					<quote rend="blockquote">When mortals here his honored name invoke;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 7.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>on the other side, he is no less offended when any affront
					or contempt is put upon him, as he is most kind and benign to those that entertain him with proper respect. For
					neither does Jupiter surnamed the Hospitable so severely
					prosecute injuries done to strangers and suppliants, nor is
					Jupiter Genitalis so rigorous in accomplishing the curses
					of parents disobeyed, as Love is to listen to the complaints
					of injured lovers; being the scourger and punisher of
					proud, ill-natured, and ill-bred people. For, not to mention
					Euxynthetus and Leucomantis, at this day in Cyprus called
					the Peeper, 'tis a hundred to one but you have heard of the
					punishment inflicted upon Gorgo the Cretan, not much unlike to that of Leucomantis, only that Gorgo was turned
					into a stone as she looked out of a window to see her love
					going to his grave. With this Gorgo Asander fell in love,
					a young gentleman virtuous and nobly descended, but reduced from a flourishing estate to extremity of poverty.
					However, he did not think so meanly of himself but that,
					being her kinsman, he courted this Gorgo for a wife,
					though she had many suitors at the same time by reason
					of her great fortune; and he so carried this business that,
					notwithstanding his numerous and wealthy rivals, he had
					gained the good-will of all her guardians and nearest relations.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.299"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Now as for those things which they say are the
				causes that beget love, they are not peculiar to this or the
				other sex, but common to both. For it cannot be that
				those images that enter into amorous persons and whisk
				about from one part to another, by their various forms
				moving and tickling the mass of atoms that slide into the
				seed, can come from young boys, and that the same cannot
				come from young women. But as to these noble and
				sacred remembrances with which the soul is winged, recalling that same divine, real, and Olympic beauty, what
				should hinder but that these may pass from boys and young
				men, and also from virgins and young women, whenever
				a disposition chaste and good-natured appears united with
				bloom of youth and grace of body? For, as a handsome
				and well-made shoe shows the proportion of the foot (as
				Ariston says), so they that have judgment in these matters
				can discern the splendid, upright, and uncorrupted footsteps of a noble and generous soul in beautiful forms and
				features, and bodies undefiled. For, if a voluptuous person, who when the question was put to him,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To which are your hot passions most inclined,
				</l>
                     <l>Or to the male, or to the female kind?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>answered thus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis the same thing to me
					</l>
                     <l>Where'er I beauty see,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>was thought to have returned a proper and pertinent answer and one that accorded with his passions, is it possible
					that a noble and generous lover directs his amours not to
					loveliness and good-nature, but only to the parts that distinguish the sex? For certainly a man that delights in
					horses will no less value the mettle and swiftness of Podargus, than of Aetha that was Agamemnon's mare; and
					he that is a good huntsman does not only delight in dogs,
					but mixes with his cry the bitches of Crete and Laconia;
					and shall he that is a lover as well as of civil behavior
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.300"/>
					
					carry himself with an inequality more to one than to
					another, and make a distinction, as of garments, between
					the love of men and women? But some say that beauty
					is the flower of virtue. Will they then affirm, that the
					female sex never blossoms nor makes any show of tendency
					to virtue? It were absurd to think so. Therefore was
					Aeschylus in the right when he said, that he could never
					mistake the fire in the eye of a young woman who had
					once known a man. Now then are those signs and marks of
					lasciviousness, wantonness, and impudence to be discovered
					in the visages of women, and shall there be no light shining
					in their faces for the discovery of modesty and chastity?
					Nay, shall there be many such signs, and those apparent,
					and shall they not be able to allure and provoke love?
					Both are contrary to reason, and dissonant from truth.
					But every one of these things is common to both sexes, as
					we have showed.</p>
            <p>Now then, Daphnaeus, let us confute the reason that
					Zeuxippus has but now alleged, by making love to be all
					one with inordinate desire that hurries the soul to intemperance. Not that it is his opinion, but only what he has
					frequently heard from men morose and no way addicted to
					love. Of this class there are some who, marrying poor
					silly women for the sake of some petty portion, and having
					nothing to do with them and their money but to make
					them perpetual drudges in pitiful mechanic employments,
					are every day brawling and quarrelling with them.
					Others, more desirous of children than of wives, like cicadae that spill their seed upon squills or some such like
					herb, discharge their lust in haste upon the next they
					meet with; and having reaped the fruit they sought for,
					bid marriage farewell or else regard it not at all, neither
					caring to love nor to be beloved. And in my opinion, the
					words <foreign lang="greek">ste/rgein</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">ste/rgesqai</foreign>, which signify <hi rend="italics">dearly to love</hi> and
					<hi rend="italics">dearly to be beloved again,</hi> differing but one letter from
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.301"/>
					
					          <foreign lang="greek">ste/gein</foreign>, which signifies <hi rend="italics">to contain</hi> or <hi rend="italics">endure,</hi> seem to me to
					import and denote that mutual kindness called conjugal,
					which is intermixed by time and custom with necessity.
					But in that wedlock which love supports and inspires, in
					the first place, as in Plato's Commonwealth, there will be
					no such language as <q direct="unspecified">thine</q> and <q direct="unspecified">mine.</q> For properly to
					speak, there is not community of goods among all friends;
					but only where two friends, though severed in body, yet
					have their souls joined and as it were melted together, and
					neither desire to be two nor believe themselves to be
					separate persons. And, in the second place, there will be
					that mutual respect and reverence, which is the chiefest
					happiness of wedlock. Now as to that respect that
					comes from without, carrying with it more force of law
					than voluntary and reciprocal duty, or that comes by fear
					and shame,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And many other curbs, that loose desire
					</l>
                     <l>And lawless frisks of wanton heat require,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, Frag. 784.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>these are always present with those who are coupled in
					matrimony. Whereas in love there is so much continency,
					so much modesty, and so much of loyal affection, that even
					if it happen upon an intemperate and lascivious soul, it is
					thereby diverted from all other amours, by cutting off all
					malapert boldness and bringing down the insolence of imperious pride; instead of which it introduces modest bashfulness, silence, and submission, and adorning it with decent
					and becoming behavior, makes it for ever after the obedient
					observer of one lover. Most certainly you have heard of
					that celebrated and highly courted courtesan Lais, how her
					beauty inflamed all Greece, or rather how two seas strove
					for her. This famous beauty, being seized with an ardent
					affection for Hippolochus the Thessalian, leaving the Acrocorinthus, as the poet describes it,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">With sea-green water all encompassed round,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Euripides, Frag. 1069.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.302"/>
            <p>and privately avoiding the great army (as I may call it) of
					those that courted her favor, withdrew herself modestly to
					the enjoyment of him only; but the women, incensed with
					jealousy and envying her surpassing beauty, dragged her
					into the temple of Venus, and there stoned her to death;
					for which reason it is called to this day the temple of Venus the Murderess. We ourselves have known several
					young damsels, mere slaves, who never would submit to
					the embraces of their masters, and private men who have
					disdained the company of queens, when love had the absolute dominion of their hearts. For, as in Rome, when
					there is a dictator chosen, all other chief magistrates lay
					down their offices; so all such persons, where love is truly
					predominant, are immediately free and manumitted from
					all other lords and masters, and afterwards live like servants
					in the temple of Love. And indeed a virtuous and generous lady, once linked to her lawful husband by an unfeigned
					affection, will sooner choose the embraces of bears and
					dragons, than to be the bed-fellow of any other person
					whatsoever but her only spouse.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Of this although we might produce examples without number, yet among you, that are now joined (as it
				were) in the same dance and festival with Love,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The dialogue is supposed to be held at the festival of Love. See &sect;&sect; 1 and 2 (G).</note> it will
				not be from the purpose to relate the story of Camma the
				Galatian. For she being a woman of transcendent beauty,
				and married to Sinatus the tetrarch, Synorix, one of the
				most powerful men in all Galatia, fell desperately in love
				with her; and that he might enjoy her, murdered her husband Sinatus, since he could not prevail with her either by
				force or persuasion, while her husband was alive. Thereupon Camma, having no other sanctuary for the preservation of her chastity nor consolation in her affliction, retired
				to the temple of Diana, where she remained a votaress to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.303"/>
				
				the Goddess, not admitting any person so much as to speak
				to her, though she had many suitors that sought her in
				wedlock. But when Synorix boldly presumed to put the
				question to her, she neither seemed to reject his motion,
				neither did she upbraid him with the crime he had committed; as if he had been induced to perpetrate so vile an
				act, not out of any malicious intent to Sinatus, but merely
				out of a pure and ardent love and affection to her. Thereupon he came with greater confidence, and demanded her
				in marriage. She, on the other side, met him no less
				cheerfully; and leading him by the hand to the altar of the
				Goddess, after she had poured forth a small quantity of
				hydromel well tempered with a rank poison, as it were an
				atonement offering to the Goddess, she drank off the one
				half of that which remained herself, and gave the other
				half to the Galatian. And then, so soon as she saw he
				had drunk it off, she gave a loud groan, and calling her
				deceased husband by his name; This day, said she, my
				most dear and beloved husband, I have long expected, as
				having lived, deprived of thee, a desolate and comfortless
				life. But now receive me joyfully; for for thy sake I have
				revenged myself upon the most wicked among men, willing
				to have lived with thee, and now no less rejoicing to die
				with him. Thus Synorix, being carried out of the temple,
				soon after expired; but Camma, surviving him a day and
				a night, is reported to have died with an extraordinary resolution and cheerfulness of spirit.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Now in regard there have been many such, as well
				among us as among the barbarians, who can bear with
				those that reproach Venus that, being coupled and present with Love, she becomes a hindrance of friendship?
				Whereas any sober and considerate person may rather revile the company of male with male, and justly call it intemperance and lasciviousness,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.304"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A vile affront to Nature, no effect
				</l>
                     <l>Of lovely Venus or of chaste respect.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, as for those that willingly prostitute their
					bodies, we look upon them to be the most wicked and flagitious persons in the world, void of fidelity, neither endued
					with modesty nor any thing of friendship; and but too
					truly and really, according to Sophocles,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>They who ne'er had such friends as these,
					</l>
                     <l>Believe their blessing double;
					</l>
                     <l>And they that have them, pray the Gods
					</l>
                     <l>To rid them of the trouble.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Frag. 778.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And as for those who, not being by nature lewd and wicked,
					were circumvented and forced to prostitute themselves,
					there are no men whom these always look upon with greater
					suspicion and more perfect hatred than those that deluded
					and flattered them into so vile an act, and they bitterly
					revenge themselves when they find an opportunity. For
					Crateas killed Archelaus, who had rid him in his youth;
					and Pytholaus slew Alexander of Pherae. Periander tyrant of the Ambraciotes asked his minion, whether he were
					not yet with child; which the lad took so heinously that
					he stabbed him.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, among women that are married, these
					are but the beginnings of friendship, as it were, a communicating and imparting of great and sacred mysteries.
					The pleasure of coition is the least thing; but the honor,
					the submission to mutual love and fidelity which daily
					germinates from this, convince us that neither the Delphians raved, who gave the name of Arma (union) to Venus,
					nor that Homer was in an error, who called the conjunction
					of man and woman by the name of friendship; but that
					Solon was a lawgiver the most experienced in conjugal
					affairs, who decreed that a husband should lie with his
					wife thrice a month at least,&mdash;not for pleasure's sake, but
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.305"/>
					
					that, as cities renew their treaties one with another at such
					a time, so the alliance of matrimony might be renewed by
					this enjoyment, after the jars which may have arisen in the
					mean time. But you will say, there are many men in love
					with women that act amiss and furiously. But are there
					not more enormities committed by those that are enamored
					upon boys?
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>So often as these eyes of mine behold
					</l>
                     <l>That beardless youth, that smooth and lovely boy,
					</l>
                     <l>I faint and fall; then wish I him to hold
					</l>
                     <l>Within mine arms, and so to die with joy;
					</l>
                     <l>And that on tomb were set, where I do lie,
					</l>
                     <l>An epigram, mine end to testify.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But though there is this raging passion after boys, as well
					as a dotage upon women, yet can neither be said to be truly
					love. And therefore it is an absurdity to aver that women
					are not capable even of other virtues. For why speak of
					so many signals of their chastity, prudence, justice, and
					fidelity, when we find others no less eminent for their fortitude, resolution, and magnanimity; after all which, to tax
					them of being naturally incapable of friendship only&mdash;not
					to mention the other virtues&mdash;is a hard case. For they
					are naturally lovers of their children, affectionate to their
					husbands; and this same natural affection of theirs, like a
					fertile soil, as it is capable of friendship, so is no less pliable to persuasion, nor less accompanied with all the graces.
					But as poetry, adapting to speech the conditements of melody, measure, and rhythm, renders the wholesome and instructive part of it so much the more moving, and the
					noxious part so much the more apt to corrupt the mind;
					so, Nature having adorned a woman with the charms of
					beauty and persuasive language, a lascivious woman makes
					use of these perfections to please herself and deceive others,
					but in a modest and sober woman they work wonders
					towards the gaining and fixing the good will and favor of
					her husband. Therefore Plato exhorted Xenocrates, otherwise
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.306"/>
					
					 generous and brave, but very morose in his humor,
					to sacrifice to the Graces; but he would have exhorted a
					virtuous and modest woman to sacrifice to Love, for his
					propitious favor to her marriage, in ordering it so that her
					behavior may prove a sufficient charm to keep her husband
					at home,... and that he may not ramble after other
					women, and then be forced to exclaim, as in the comedy,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Curse to this rage of mine, so given to roam;
					</l>
                     <l>What a good wife do I abuse at home!</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For in wedlock to love is a far greater blessing than to be
					beloved; since it preserves and keeps people from falling
					into many errors, nay, all those that corrupt and ruin
					matrimony.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>As for those passionate affections which at the beginning of conjugal love raise certain fits, which are somewhat sharp and biting, most fortunate Zeuxippus, I would
				not have you fear them, like an ulcer or scarification.
				Though perhaps it would not be amiss, if it should cost
				you some small wound to be joined to a virtuous woman,
				like trees that grow together when grafted by incision upon
				a proper stock. The beginning of conception itself is a
				kind of exulceration; for there can be no mixture of
				things that are not affected reciprocally one by the other.
				The very mathematical rudiments do not a little perplex
				little children at the first, and philosophy troubles the
				brains of young beginners; but this corroding humor is
				not lasting, either to these or to lovers. Insomuch that a
				man would think that love at first resembled the mixture
				of two liquors, which, when once they begin to incorporate, by their ebullition discover some little disgusts;
				for so love at the beginning bubbles up with a kind of
				effervency, till being settled and purified it acquires a firm
				and stable constitution. For this indeed is properly that
				kind of mixture which is called a thorough mixture;
				whereas the love of other friends, conversing and living
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.307"/>
				
				together, is like the touches and interweavings of Epicurus's atoms, subject to raptures and separations, but can
				never compose such a union as proceeds from love assisting conjugal society. For neither are the pleasures received
				from any other source so great, nor the benefits conferred
				on others so lasting, nor is the glory and beauty of any
				other friendship so noble and desirable,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As when the man and wife at board and bed
				</l>
                     <l>Under one roof a life of concord lead.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VI. 183.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, it is a thing warranted by law; while Nature
					shows us that even the Gods themselves stood in need of
					love for the sake of common procreation. Thus the poets
					tell us that earth is in love with the showers, and heaven
					with the earth; and the natural philosophers are of opinion
					that the sun is in love with the moon, that they copulate
					every month, and that the moon conceives by virtue of that
					conjunction. And it would of necessity follow that the
					earth, which is the common mother of all mankind, of all
					animals, and of all manner of plants, would one day cease
					and be extinguished, should that same ardent love and
					desire infused by the God forsake matter, and matter cease
					to pursue and lust after the principles and motions of generation.</p>
            <p>But that we may not seem to wander too far or spend
					our time in trifles, you yourselves are not ignorant that
					these pederasties are by many said to be the most uncertain and least durable things in the world, and that they are
					derided by those that make use of them, who affirm that
					the love of boys, like an egg, may be destroyed by a
					hair;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, by the sprouting of the beard. (G.)</note> and the lovers themselves are like the wandering
					Scythians, who, having spent their spring in flowery and
					verdant pastures, presently dislodge from thence, as out of
					an enemy's country. And Bion the Sophister was yet
					more sharp and satirical, when he called the beards of
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.308"/>
					
					young and beautiful striplings by the names of Harmodii
					and Aristogitons (i.e. tyrant-killers), since by that budding
					show of manhood their lovers are delivered from their
					pleasant tyranny. But these imputations are not justly
					charged upon true lovers. Elegant therefore was that
					which was said by Euripides. For as he was clasping and
					embracing the fair Agatho, after the down began to sprout
					forth upon his chin, he cried that the very autumn of
					lovely youths was pleasing and delightful. But I say more
					than this, that the love of virtuous women does not decay
					with the wrinkles that appear upon their faces, but remains and endures to their graves and monuments. Then
					again, we shall find but few male couples of true lovers,
					but thousands of men and women conjoined together in
					wedlock, who have reciprocally and inviolably observed a
					community of affection and loyalty to the end of their
					lives. I shall instance only one example, which happened
					in our time, during the reign of Caesar Vespasian.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Julius, who was the first that occasioned the revolt
				in Galatia, among many other confederates in the rebellion
				had one Sabinus, a young gentleman of no mean spirit,
				and for fame and riches inferior to none. But having
				undertaken a very difficult enterprise, they miscarried; and
				therefore expecting nothing but death by the hand of justice, some of them killed themselves, others made their
				escapes as well as they could. As for Sabinus, he had all
				the opportunities that could be to save himself by flying
				to the barbarians; but he had married a lady, the best of
				women, which they called by the name of Empone, as
				much as to say a heroess. This woman it was not in his
				power to leave, neither could he carry her conveniently
				along with him. Having therefore in the country certain
				vaults or cellars under ground, where he had hid his
				treasures and movables of greatest value, which were only
				known to two of his freed bondmen, he dismissed all the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.309"/>
				
				rest of his servants, as if he had intended to poison himself. And taking along with him his two faithful and trusty
				servants, he hid himself in one of the vaults, and sent
				another of his enfranchised attendants, whose name was
				Martalius, to tell his wife that her husband had poisoned
				himself and that the house and his corpse were both burnt
				together, designing by the lamentation and unfeigned grief
				of his wife to make the report of his death the more
				easily believed; which fell out according to his wish. For
				the lady, so soon as she heard the news, threw herself
				upon the floor, and continued for three days together without meat or drink, making the most bitter outcries, and
				bewailing her loss with all the marks of a real and unfeigned anguish; which Sabinus understanding, and fearing her sorrow might prevail with her to lay violent hands
				upon herself, he ordered the same Martalius to tell her
				that he was yet alive and lay hid in such a place; however, that she should for a while continue her mourning,
				and be sure so to counterfeit her grief that she should not
				be discovered. And indeed in all other things the lady
				acted her part so well, and managed her passion to that
				degree, that no woman could do it better. But having
				still a longing desire to see her husband, she went to him
				in the night and returned again so privately that nobody
				took any notice of her. And thus she continued keeping
				him company for seven months together, that it might be
				said to differ very little from living in hell itself. Where
				after she had so strangely disguised Sabinus with a false
				head of hair, and such odd sort of habit, that it was impossible for him to be known, she carried him to Rome
				along with her undiscovered to several that met him. But
				not being able to obtain his pardon, she returned with him
				back to his den, and for many years lived with him under
				ground; only between whiles she went to the city, and
				there showed herself in public to several ladies, her friends
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.310"/>
				
				and familiar acquaintance. But that which was the most
				incredible of all things, she so ordered her business that
				none of the ladies perceived her being with child, though
				she bathed at the same time with them. For such is the
				nature of that same ointment wherewith the women anoint
				their hair to make it of a red-golden color, that by its fatness and oiliness it plumps and swells up the flesh of the
				body, and brings it up to an embonpoint. So that the
				lady, no less liberal of her ointment than diligent to chafe
				and rub her body limb by limb, by the proportionable
				rising and swelling of her flesh in every part, concealed
				the swelling of her belly. And when she came to be
				delivered, she endured the pains of her child-bearing alone
				by herself, like a lioness, hiding herself in her den with her
				husband; and there, as I may say, she bred up in private
				her two male whelps. For at that time she was delivered
				of two boys, of which there was one who was slain in
				Egypt; the other, whose name was also Sabinus, was but
				very lately with us at Delphi.</p>
            <p>For this reason Caesar put the lady to death; but dearly
					paid for the murder by the utter extirpation of his whole
					posterity, which in a short time after was utterly cut off
					from the face of the earth. For during his whole reign,
					there was not a more cruel and savage act committed;
					neither was there any other spectacle which in all probability the Gods and Daemons more detested, or any from
					which they more turned away their eyes in abomination
					of the sight. Besides, she abated the compassion of the
					spectators by the stoutness of her behavior and the grandeur of her utterance, than which there was nothing that
					more exasperated Vespasian; when, despairing of her
					husband's pardon, she did as it were challenge the emperor
					to exchange her life for his, telling him withal, that she
					accounted it a far greater pleasure to live in darkness under
					ground as she had done, than to reign in splendor like
					him.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.311"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Here, as my father told me, ended the discourse
				concerning Love in the neighborhood of Thespiae; at what
				time they saw one of Pisias's friends, by name Diogenes,
				coming at a good round pace towards them; to whom when
				Soclarus, while he was yet at a distance, cried out, No
				tidings of war, Diogenes, I hope? No, no, said he, that
				ne'er can be at a wedding; and therefore mend your pace,
				for the nuptial sacrifice stays only for your coming. All
				the rest of the company were exceeding glad, only Zeuxippus asked whether Pisias were still angry. On the contrary, said Diogenes, as he before opposed the match, so
				now he was the first to approve what Ismenodora had
				done; and at the same time, putting on a garland upon his
				head and throwing a white nuptial robe about his shoulders,
				he is to march before all the company through the marketplace, to give thanks to the God of Love.</p>
            <p>Well done, by Jupiter, come away, come away then,
					cried my father, that we may laugh and be merry with our
					friend, and adore the Deity. For there is no doubt that he
					is propitiously present with his favor and approbation.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>