<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De superstitione</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1928</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.452"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>SUPERSTITION (DE SUPERSTITIONE) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p> Plutarch's essay on Superstition is, in the main, an attempt to prove that
					superstition is worse than atheism. Its somewhat impassioned tone savours
					more of the emotional sermon than of the carefully reasoned discourse, and
					suggests that it was originally prepared for public presentation. </p>
            <p>Wyttenbach was disturbed because in the catalogue of Lamprias, in which this
					essay is No. 155, the title is given as <foreign lang="greek">*peri\
						deisidaimoni/as pro\s *)epi/koupon</foreign>, and he thought that this
					title might refer to some other treatise of Plutarch. The explanation is so
					simple that the only surprising thing is that it should have escaped a man
					of Wyttenbach's acumen. On the first page of the essay are the words,
					<q direct="unspecified">the universe . . . atoms and void . . . assumption is
						false.</q> Then, as now, librarians and reviewers looked at the
					first page, and reached their conclusions ; so it was only natural that the
					compiler of the catalogue should conclude that the rest of the book was
					equally hostile to Epicurus. On the other hand, this affords interesting
					evidence that the compiler of the catalogue of Lamprias probably had a copy
					of Plutarch's works before him when he drew up his list. </p>
            <p>The ms. tradition of this essay is better than of many others, and one ms.
					(D) has preserved many <pb id="v.2.p.453"/> excellent readings.a Only one
					passage, a quotation (170 b), presents serious difficulty, and of this
					Professor Goodwin remarked: <q direct="unspecified">As to the original Greek, hardly a word
						can be made out with certainty.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>Mention should be made of a separate edition and a parallel English
					translation of this essay in a book entitled <q direct="unspecified">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*peri\ deisidaimoni/as</foreign>. Plutarchus and Theophrastus on
						Superstition with various appendices and a life of Plutarchus. Printed
						a.d. 1828. (Privately) printed by Julian Hibbert . . . Kentish
						Town.</q> The translation is very literal, but is sometimes an
					improvement on that of William Baxter in the translation of Plutarch by
					<q direct="unspecified">Several Hands</q> (London, 1684-94). Intimate and amusing
					is the preface of the author, who, in his notes, admits that he has never
					read Plato, but ends his preface with these words : <q direct="unspecified">I terminate this
						my Preface by consigning all ' Greek Scholars ' to the special care of
						Beelzebub.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>A spirited defence of this essay (if any defence is needed) may be found in
					John Oakesmith's The Religion of Plutarch (London, 1902), chap. ix. pp. 179
					ff. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In spite of the fact that Pohlenz in his preface to Vol. I.
						(Leipzig, 1925) of the Moralia (p. xiv) uses these words: <q direct="unspecified">
							Codicem Paris D e recensione libidinosissima ortum</q>! Paton,
						who edited this essay, accepts the readings of D a good part of the
						time, and his edition would have been more intelligible had he accepted
						them more often.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.455"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Ignorance and blindness in regard to the gods divides itself at the very
					beginning into two streams, of which the one produces in hardened
					characters, as it were in stubborn soils, atheism, and the other in tender
					characters, as in moist soils, produces superstition.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of
						Alexander</hi>, chap. lxxv. (p. 706 B) and <hi rend="italics">Life
							of Camillus</hi>, chap. vi. (p. 132 C).</note> Every false
					judgement, and especially concerning these matters, is a mischievous thing ;
					but where emotion also enters, it is most mischievous. For every emotion is
					likely to be a delusion that rankles ; and just as dislocations of the
					joints accompanied by lacerations are hardest to deal with, so also is it
					with derangements of the soul accompanied by emotion. </p>
            <p>A man thinks that in the beginning the universe was created out of atoms and
					void. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aimed at the theories of Epicurus, and possibly of
						Democritus.</note> His assumption is false, but it causes no sore, no
					throbbing, no agitating pain. </p>
            <p>A man assumes that wealth is the greatest good. This falsehood contains
					venom, it feeds upon his soul, distracts him, does not allow him to sleep,
					fills him with stinging desires, pushes him over precipices, chokes him, and
					takes from him his freedom of speech. </p>
            <p>Again, some people think that virtue and vice are corporeal.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aimed at
					the Stoics, who referred all qualities to the body. Cf. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1084 A.</note> This piece of ignorance
					is disgraceful, <pb id="v.2.p.457"/> perhaps, but it is not worthy of
					wailings or lamentations. But consider judgements and assumptions that are
					like this : <quote rend="blockquote">Poor virtue ! A mere name thou art, I
						find, But I did practise thee as real !<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
							Frag.</hi> p. 910, Adespota, No. 374.</note>
               </quote> and thereby
					I gave up wrongdoing which is productive of wealth, and licentiousness which
					begets every sort of pleasure. These it is right and proper that we pity,
					and at the same time loathe, because their presence engenders many
					distempers and emotions, like maggots and grubs, in men's souls. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>To come now to our subject: atheism, which is a sorry judgement that there is
					nothing blessed or incorruptible, seems, by disbelief in the Divinity, to
					lead finally to a kind of utter indifference, and the end which it achieves
					in not believing in the existence of gods is not to fear them. But, on the
					other hand, superstition, as the very name (dread of deities) indicates, is
					an emotional idea and an assumption productive of a fear which utterly
					humbles and crushes a man, for he thinks that there are gods, but that they
					are the cause of pain and injury. In fact, the atheist, apparently, is
					unmoved regarding the Divinity, whereas the superstitious man is moved as he
					ought not to be, and his mind is thus perverted. For in the one man
					ignorance engenders disbelief in the One who can help him, and on the other
					it bestows the added idea that He causes injury. Whence it follows that
					atheism is falsified reason, and superstition is an emotion engendered from
					false reason. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Clear it is that all distempers and emotions of the soul are disgraceful, but
					in some of them are to <pb id="v.2.p.459"/> be found pride, loftiness, and
					exaltation, owing to their uplifting power ; and no one of them, we might
					say, is destitute of an impulse to activity. But this general complaint may
					be made against every one of the emotions, that by their urgings to be up
					and doing they press hard upon the reasoning power and strain it. But fear
					alone, lacking no less in boldness than in power to reason, keeps its
					irrationality impotent, helpless, and hopeless. It is on this ground that
					the power of fear to tie down the soul, and at the same time to keep it
					awake, has come to be named both terror and awe.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The derivations of
						<q direct="unspecified">terror</q> from <q direct="unspecified">tie,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">awe</q> from <q direct="unspecified">awake</q> are not more fanciful than
						those in which Plutarch indulges.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Of all kinds of fear the most impotent and helpless is superstitious fear. No
					fear of the sea has he who does not sail upon it, nor of war he who does not
					serve in the army, nor of highwaymen he who stays at home, nor of a
					blackmailer he who is poor, nor of envy he who holds no office, nor of
					earthquake he who is in Gaul,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle,
						<hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, iii. 7, and Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, ii. 80 (195).</note> nor of the
					lightning-stroke he who is in Ethiopia; but he who fears the gods fears all
					things, earth and sea, air and sky, darkness and light, sound and silence,
					and a dream. Slaves in their sleep forget their masters, sleep makes light
					the chains of prisoners, and the inflammations surrounding wounds, the
					savage gnawing of ulcers in the flesh, and tormenting pains are removed from
					those who are fallen asleep : Dear soothing balm of sleep to help my ill,
					How sweet thy coming in mine hour of need.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Orestes</hi>, 211-12.</note> Superstition does not
					give one a right to say this; <pb id="v.2.p.461"/> for superstition alone
					makes no truce with sleep, and never gives the soul a chance to recover its
					breath and courage by putting aside its bitter and despondent notions
					regarding God ; but, as it were in the place of torment of the impious, so
					in the sleep of the superstitious their malady calls up fearful images, and
					horrible apparitions and divers forms of punishment, and, by keeping the
					unhappy soul on the rack, chases it away from sleep by its dreams, lashed
					and punished by its own self as if by another, and forced to comply with
					dreadful and extraordinary behests. When, later, such persons arise from
					their beds, they do not contemn nor ridicule these things, nor realize that
					not one of the things that agitated them was really true, but, trying to
					escape the shadow of a delusion that has nothing bad at the bottom, during
					their waking hours they delude and waste and agitate themselves, putting
					themselves into the hands of conjurors and impostors who say to them :
					<quote rend="blockquote">If a vision in sleep is the cause of your fear
						And the troop of dire Hecate felt to be near,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
							Frag.</hi> p. 910, Adespota, No. 375.</note>
               </quote> then call
					in the old crone who performs magic purifications, dip yourself in the
					ocean, and sit down on the ground and spend the whole day there, <quote rend="blockquote">Greeks from barbarians finding evil ways !
						<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">The Trojan Women</hi>,
							764.</note>
               </quote> because of superstition, such as smearing with
					mud, wallowing in filth, immersions, casting oneself down with face to the
					ground, disgraceful besieging of the gods, and uncouth prostrations. <q direct="unspecified">
						To sing with the mouth aright</q> was the injunction given to the
					harp-players by those who thought to preserve the good old forms of music;
					and we hold it to be <pb id="v.2.p.463"/> meet to pray to the gods with the
					mouth straight and aright, and not to inspect the tongue laid upon the
					sacrificial offering to see that it be clean and straight, and, at the same
					time, by distorting and sullying one's own tongue with strange names and
					barbarous phrases, to disgrace and transgress the god-given ancestral
					dignity of our religion. </p>
            <p>Nor is there lack of humour in what the comic poet <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably some poet
					of the new Comedy; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 438.</note> has somewhere said with
					reference to those who cover their bedsteads with gold and silver : <quote rend="blockquote">The one free gift the gods bestow on us. Our sleep,
						why make its cost to you so much ?</quote> But to the superstitious man
					it is possible to say, <q direct="unspecified">The gift of sleep which the gods bestow on us
						as a time of forgetfulness and respite from our ills ; why do you make
						this an everlastingly painful torturechamber for yourself, since your
						unhappy soul cannot run away to some other sleep ?</q> Heracleitus
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmenta der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p.
						95.</note> says that people awake enjoy one world in common, but of
					those who are fallen asleep each roams about in a world of his own. But the
					superstitious man enjoys no world in common with the rest of mankind ; for
					neither when awake does he use his intelligence, nor when fallen asleep is
					he freed from his agitation, but his reasoning power is sunk in dreams, his
					fear is ever wakeful, and there is no way of escape or removal. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>A despot much feared in Samos was Polycrates, as was Periander in Corinth,
					but nobody feared these men after he had removed to a free State governed by
					its own people. But as for the man who fears <pb id="v.2.p.465"/> the rule
					of the gods as a sullen and inexorable despotism, where can he remove
					himself, where can he flee, what country can he find without gods, or what
					sea ? Into what part of the universe shall you steal away and hide yourself,
					poor wretch, and believe that you have escaped God ? There is a law even for
					slaves who have given up all hope of freedom, that they may demand a sale,
					and thus exchange their present master for one more mild. But superstition
					grants no such exchange ; and to find a god whom he shall not fear is
					impossible for him who fears the gods of his fathers and his kin, who
					shudders at his saviours, and trembles with terror at those gentle gods from
					whom we ask wealth, welfare, peace, concord, and success in our best efforts
					in speech and action. </p>
            <p>Then again these same persons hold slavery to be a misfortune, and say,
					<quote rend="blockquote">For man or woman 'tis disaster dire Sudden to
						be enslaved, and masters harsh To get.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown tragic poet;
							<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
								Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 910, Adespota, No. 376.</note>
               </quote> But
					how much more dire, think you, is the lot of those for whom there is no
					escape, no running away, no chance to revolt ? For a slave there is an altar
					to which he can flee, and there are many of our shrines where even robbers
					may find sanctuary, and men who are fleeing from the enemy, if once they lay
					hold upon a statue of a god, or a temple, take courage again. These are the
					very things that most inspire a shuddering fear and dread in the
					superstitious man, and yet it is in them that those who are in fear of the
					most dreadful fate place their hopes. Do not drag the superstitious man <pb id="v.2.p.467"/> away from his shrines, for it is in them that he
					suffers punishment and retribution. </p>
            <p>What need to speak at length ? <q direct="unspecified">In death is the end of life for all
					men,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Demosthenes, Or. xviii. (<hi rend="italics">On
						the Crown)</hi>, 97; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 333 C.</note> but not the end of superstition ; for
					superstition transcends the limits of life into the far beyond, making fear
					to endure longer than life, and connecting with death the thought of undying
					evils, and holding fast to the opinion, at the moment of ceasing from
					trouble, that now is the beginning of those that never cease. The abysmal
					gates of the nether world swing open, rivers of fire and offshoots of the
					Styx are mingled together, darkness is crowded with spectres of many
					fantastic shapes which beset their victim with grim visages and piteous
					voices, and, besides these, judges and torturers and yawning gulfs and deep
					recesses teeming with unnumbered woes. Thus unhappy superstition, by its
					excess of caution in trying to avoid everything suggestive of dread,
					unwittingly subjects itself to every sort of dread. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Nothing of this kind attaches to atheism, but its ignorance is distressing,
					and to see amiss or not to see at all in matters of such importance is a
					great misfortune for the soul; for it is as if the soul had suffered the
					extinction of the brightest and most dominant of its many eyes, the
					conception of God. But superstition is attended by emotion, as has already
					been said, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi>, 165 B.</note> and by sore
					distress and disturbance and mental enslavement from the very beginning.
					Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted freely from the <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 47
						D.</note> says that music, the creator of <pb id="v.2.p.469"/> harmony
					and order, was given to mankind by the gods not for the sake of pampering
					them or tickling their ears, but so that whatever in a man's body is
					disturbing and errant, affecting the cycles and concords of his soul, and in
					many instances, for lack of culture and refinement, waxing wanton because of
					licentiousness and error, music should, in its own way, disengage and bring
					round and restore to its proper place again. <quote rend="blockquote">Whatsoever things there be Which by Zeus are not held dear,</quote>
					says Pindar,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Pythian Odes</hi>, i. 13 (25); quoted
						also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 746 B and 1095 E.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">In affrighted panic flee When the Muses' voice they
						hear.</quote> In fact they become provoked and angry ; and tigers, they
					say, surrounded by the sound of beaten drums go utterly mad, and get so
					excited that they end by tearing themselves to pieces.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 144 D.</note> There is less harm,
					therefore, for those who, as the result of deafness or impairment of
					hearing, have a feeling of indifference and insensibility toward music.
					Teiresias laboured under a misfortune in not being able to see his children
					or his intimate friends, but greater was the misfortune of Athamas <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">All
						these were victims of a god-sent madness.</note> and Agave,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">All
							these were victims of a god-sent madness.</note> who saw them as lions
					and deer ; and for Heracles<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">All these were victims of a god-sent
						madness.</note> in his madness it would undoubtedly have been better
					neither to see his sons, nor to realize that they were present, than to
					treat his nearest and dearest as enemies. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>What then ? Does it not seem to you that the feeling of the atheists compared
					with the superstitious presents just such a difference? The former do not
					see the gods at all, the latter think that they do exist and are evil. The
					former disregard them, the latter conceive their kindliness to be frightful,
					<pb id="v.2.p.471"/> their fatherly solicitude to be despotic, their
					loving care to be injurious, their slowness to anger to be savage and
					brutal. Then again such persons give credence to workers in metal stone, or
					wax, who make their images of gods in the likeness of human beings,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or,
						as given in most MSS., <q direct="unspecified">that the bodies of the gods are like the bodies
						of men.</q>
               </note> and they have such images fashioned, and dress them up,
					and worship them. But they hold in contempt philosophers and statesmen, who
					try to prove that the majesty of God is associated with goodness,
					magnanimity, kindliness, and solicitude. So the atheists have more than
					enough of indifference and distrust of the Beings who can help them, whereas
					the superstitious experience equal agitation and fear towards the things
					that can help them. Or, in fine, atheism is an indifferent feeling towards
					the Deity, which has no notion of the good, and superstition is a multitude
					of differing feelings with an underlying notion that the good is evil. For
					the superstitious fear the gods, and flee to the gods for help; they flatter
					them and assail them with abuse, pray to them and blame them. It is the
					common lot of mankind not to enjoy continual good fortune in all things.
					<quote rend="blockquote">Age and illness not their lot, Toil and labour
						they know not, 'Scaped is Acheron's loud strait,</quote> says Pindar
					<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 143 (ed. Christ). Cited by
						Plutarch again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 763 C and 1075
						A.</note> of the gods, but human experiences and actions are linked with
					chance circumstances which move now in one course and now in another. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Come now, observe the atheist in circumstances not desired by him, and take
					note of his attitude. If he be moderate in general, you will note that he
					takes <pb id="v.2.p.473"/> his present fortune without a word, and tries to
					procure for himself means of help and comfort; but if he be given to
					impatience or violent emotion, you will note that he directs all his
					complaints against Fortune and Chance, and exclaims that nothing comes about
					according to right or as the result of providence, but that the course of
					all human affairs is confusion and disorder, and that they are all being
					turned topsy-turvy. This, however, is not the way of the superstitious man;
					but if even the slightest ill befall him, he sits down and proceeds to
					construct, on the basis of his trouble, a fabric of harsh, momentous, and
					practically unavoidable experiences which he must undergo, and he also loads
					himself with fears and frights, suspicions and trepidations, and all this he
					bitterly assails with every sort of lamentation and moaning. For he puts the
					responsibility for his lot upon no man nor upon Fortune nor upon occasion
					nor upon himself, but lays the responsibility for everything upon God, and
					says that from that source a heaven-sent stream of mischief has come upon
					him with full force ; and he imagines that it is not because he is unlucky,
					but because he is hateful to the gods, that he is being punished by the
					gods, and that the penalty he pays and all that he is undergoing are
					deserved because of his own conduct. </p>
            <p>The atheist, when he is ill, takes into account and calls to mind the times
					when he has eaten too much or drunk too much wine, also irregularities in
					his daily life, or instances of over-fatigue or unaccustomed changes of air
					or locality ; and again when he has given offence in administering office,
					and has encountered disrepute with the masses or calumny with <pb id="v.2.p.475"/> a ruler, he looks to find the reason in himself and his
					own surroundings : <quote rend="blockquote">Where did I err, and what have I
						done ? What duty of mine was neglected ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pythagoras, <hi rend="italics">Carmina aurea</hi>, 42; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 515 F.</note>
               </quote> But in the
					estimation of the superstitious man, every indisposition of his body, loss
					of property, deaths of children, or mishaps and failures in public life are
					classed as <q direct="unspecified">afflictions of God</q> or <q direct="unspecified">attacks of an evil
						spirit.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, iii. 29 (72).</note> For this reason he has no heart to relieve the
					situation or undo its effects, or to find some remedy for it or to take a
					strong stand against it, lest he seem to fight against God and to rebel at
					his punishment; but when he is ill the physician is ejected from the house,
					and when he is in grief the door is shut on the philosopher who would advise
					and comfort him. <q direct="unspecified">Oh, sir,</q> he says, <q direct="unspecified">leave me to pay
						my penalty, impious wretch that I am, accursed, and hateful to the gods
						and all the heavenly host.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps the language was suggested by the words in Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Tyrannus</hi>, 1340.</note> 
            </p>
            <p>It is possible in the case of a man unconvinced of the existence of gods,
					when he is in grief and great distress in other ways, to wipe away a tear,
					cut his hair, and take off his cloak ; but what words can you address to the
					superstitious man, or in what way shall you help him ? He sits outside his
					house with sackcloth on and filthy rags about him ; and oftentimes he rolls
					naked in the mire as he confesses divers sins and errors of
					his&mdash;eating this or drinking that, or walking in a path forbidden
					by his conscience. But if he is very fortunate, and but mildly yoked with
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.477"/> superstition, he sits in his house, subjecting himself
					to fumigation, and smearing himself with mud, and the old crones, as Bion
					says, <q direct="unspecified">bring whatever chance directs and hang and fasten it on him as
						on a peg.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Tiribazus, they say, when an attempt was made by the Persians to arrest him,
					drew his sword, being a man of great strength, and fought desperately. But
					when the men protested and cried out that they were arresting him by the
					King's command, he instantly threw down his sword and held out his hands to
					be bound. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch, in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Artaxerxes</hi>, chap. xxix. (p. 1026 C), represents Tiribazus as fighting to the end, but this may have bee on another occasion.</note> Is not what actually happens just like this ? The rest of men
					fight desperately against misfortunes, and force their way through
					difficulties, contriving for themselves means to escape and avert things
					undesired ; but the superstitious man, without a word from anybody, says all
					to himself, <q direct="unspecified">This you have to undergo, poor soul, by the dispensation
						of Providence and by God's command,</q> and casts away all hope,
					gives himself up, runs away, and repulses those who would help him. </p>
            <p>Many ills of no great moment are made to result fatally by men's
					superstition. Midas of old, dispirited and disturbed, as it appears, as the
					result of some dreams, reached such a state of mind that he committed
					suicide by drinking bull's blood. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch, in trying to be a physician of the soul to cure superstition, has here unwittingly turned homeopath. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> B. Perrin's note on chap. xxxi. (p. 128 A) of the Life of Themistocles in <hi rend="italics">Plutarch's Themistocles and Aristides</hi> (New York, 1901), page 256. To the references there given should be added Nicander, <hi rend="italics">Alexipharmaca</hi>, 312.</note> And Aristodemus, king of the Messenians
					in the war against the Spartans, when dogs howled like wolves, and
					quitch-grass began to grow around his ancestral 
					<pb id="v.2.p.479"/> hearth, and the seers were alarmed by these signs, lost
					heart and hope by his forebodings, and slew himself by his own hand.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Other portents which disheartened Aristodemus are related by Pausanias, iv. 13.</note> It
					would perhaps have been the best thing in the world for Nicias, general of
					the Athenians, to have got rid of his superstition in the same way as Midas
					and Aristodemus,rather than to be affrighted at the shadow on the moon in
					eclipse and sit inactive while the enemy's wall was being built around him,
					and later to fall into their hands together with forty thousand men, who
					were either slain or captured alive, and himself meet an inglorious end.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The details regarding Nicias are to be found in Thucydides, vii. 35-87, and in Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Nicias</hi>, chap. xxiii. (p. 538 D) ff.</note>
					For the obstruction of light caused by the earth's coming between sun and
					moon is nothing frightful, nor is the meeting of a shadow with the moon at
					the proper time in its revolutions anything frightful, but frightful is the
					darkness of superstition falling upon man, and confounding and blinding his
					power to reason in circumstances that most loudly demand the power to
					reason. <quote rend="blockquote">Glaucus, see, the mighty ocean Even now with billows roars, Round
						about the Gyrian summits Sheer in air a dark cloud soars, Sign of storm . .
						. ;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A fragment from Archilochus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 696, Archilochus, No. 54.</note>
               </quote> when the pilot sees this, he prays that he may escape the storm, and
					calls upon the Saviours,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Castor and Pollux.</note> but while he is praying he throws the helm over,
					lowers the yard, and 
					<pb id="v.2.p.481"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Furling the big main sail, Hastens to make his escape
						Out from the murky sea.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 730; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 475 F, and Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 910, Adespota, No. 377.</note>
               </quote> Hesiod advises <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 465-8.</note> that the farmer before ploughing
					and sowing should Pray to Zeus of the world below and to holy Demeter with
					his hand on the plough-handle ; and Homer says <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 193 ff.</note> that Ajax, as he was about
					to engage in single combat with Hector, bade the Greeks pray to the gods for
					him, and then, while they were praying, donned his armour; and when
					Agamemnon enjoined <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi>ii. 382.</note> on the fighting men, <quote rend="blockquote">See that each spear is well
						sharpened, and each man's shield in good order,</quote> at the same time he asked in
					prayer from Zeus, <quote rend="blockquote">
						Grant that I raze to the level of earth the palace of
						Priam;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 413-414.</note>
               </quote> for God is brave hope, not cowardly excuse. But the Jews, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps the reference is to the capture of Jerusalem by Pompey in 63 B.C. (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Dio Cassius, xxxvii. 16), or possibly to its capture by Antony in 28 B.C. (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Dio Cassius, xlix. 22). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Josephus, <hi rend="italics">Antiquitates Jud.</hi> xii. 6. 2, and 1 Maccabees, ii. 32 ff.</note> because
					it was the Sabbath day, sat in their places immovable, while the enemy were
					planting ladders against the walls and capturing the defences, and they did
					not get up, but remained there, fast bound in the toils of superstition as
					in one great net. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Such are the characteristics of superstition in undesired and critical (as
					they are called) circumstances and occasions, but it is not one bit better
					than atheism even under pleasurable conditions. The pleasantest things that
					men enjoy are festal 
					<pb id="v.2.p.483"/> days and banquets at the temples, initiations and
					mystie rites, and prayer and adoration of the gods. Note that the atheist on
					these occasions gives way to insane and sardonic laughter at such
					ceremonies, and remarks aside to his cronies that people must cherish a vain
					and silly conceit to think that these rites are performed in honour of the
					gods ; but with him no harm is done save this. On the other hand the
					superstitious man, much as he desires it, is not able to rejoice or be glad
					: <quote rend="blockquote">The city is with burning incense filled; Full too of joyous hymns and
						doleful groans <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Tyrannus</hi>, 4; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 95 C, 445 D, and 623 C.</note>
               </quote> is the soul of the superstitious man. When the garland is on
					his head he turns pale, he offers sacrifice and feels afraid, he prays with
					quavering voice, with trembling hands he sprinkles incense, and, in a word,
					proves how foolish are the words of Pythagoras, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 413 B.</note> who said that we reach our
					best when we draw near to the gods. For that is the time when the
					superstitious fare most miserably and wretchedly, for they approach the
					halls or temples of the gods as they would approach bears' dens or snakes'
					holes or the haunts of monsters of the deep. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Hence it occurs to me to wonder at those who say that atheism is impiety, and
					do not say the same of superstition. Yet Anaxagoras was brought to trial for
					impiety on the ground that he had said the sun is a stone ; but nobody has
					called the Cimmerians impious because they do not believe even in the
					existence of the sun at all. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xi. 13-19. </note> What say you ? The 
					<pb id="v.2.p.485"/> man who does not believe in the existence of the gods
					is unholy ? And is not he who believes in such gods as the superstitious
					believe in a partner to opinions far more unholy ? Why, for my part, I
					should prefer that men should say about me that I have never been born at
					all, and there is no Plutarch, rather than that they should say <q direct="unspecified">
						Plutarch is an inconstant fickle person, quick-tempered, vindictive over
						little accidents, pained at trifles. If you invite others to dinner and
						leave him out, or if you haven't the time and don't go to call on him,
						or fail to speak to him when you see him, he will set his teeth into
						your body and bite it through, or he will get hold of your little child
						and beat him to death, or he will turn the beast that he owns into your
						crops and spoil your harvest</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably a covert reference to Artemis who sent the Calydonian boar to ravage the fields; Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 533 ff.</note> 
            </p>
            <p>When Timotheus, in a song at Athens, spoke of Artemis as <quote rend="blockquote">Ecstatic Bacchic
					frantic fanatic,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi>, iii. p. 620, Timotheus, No. 1; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 22 A.</note>
               </quote> Cinesias, the song-writer, standing up in his place among
					the audience, exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">May you have a daughter like that!</q>
					It is a fact that the superstitious make assumptions like that, and even
					worse than that, about Artemis : If hasting in fear from a hanging corpse,
					If near to a woman in childbirth pain, If come from a house where the dead
					are mourned, Polluted you entered the holy shrine, Or if from the triple
					cross-roads come 
					<pb id="v.2.p.487"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Drawn to the place by cleansing rites For the part you
						bear to the guilty one.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. p. 680; Lobeck, <hi rend="italics">Aglaophamus</hi>, p. 633, and Wilamowitz-Moellendorff, <hi rend="italics">Lesebuch</hi> (berli, 1902), p. 336.</note>
               </quote> 
            </p>
            <p>And they think no more reasonably than this about Apollo and about Hera and
					about Aphrodite. For they tremble at all of these and dread them. And yet
					what did Niobe say regarding Leto that was So irreverent as is the belief
					which superstition has fixed in the minds of the unthinking regarding the
					goddess, that, because she was derided, she required that the unhappy
					woman's <quote rend="blockquote">Daughters six that she bore and six sons in the prime of young
						manhood <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 604.</note>
               </quote> be shot dead ? So insatiable was she in doing harm to others, and
					so implacable ! For if it were really true that the goddess cherishes anger,
					and hates wickedness, and is hurt at being ill spoken of, and does not laugh
					at man's ignorance and blindness, but feels indignation thereat, she ought
					to require the death of those who falsely impute to her such savagery and
					bitterness, and tell and write such stories. At any rate, we bring forward
					the bitterness of Hecuba as something barbaric and savage when she says, <quote rend="blockquote">I
						wish I might eat up his liver, Biting it 'tween my teeth.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 212.</note>
               </quote> And yet of the
					Syrian goddess <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example, Athenaeus, 346 d, or Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Attic. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 167, Menander, No. 544.</note> the superstitious 
					<pb id="v.2.p.489"/> believe that if anybody eats sprats or anchovies, she
					will gnaw through the bones of his shins, inflame his body with sores, and
					dissolve his liver. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Is it, then, an unholy thing to speak meanly of the gods, but not unholy to
					have a mean opinion of them ? Or does the opinion of him who speaks malignly
					make his utterance improper ? It is a fact that we hold up malign speaking
					as a sign of animosity, and those who speak ill of us we regard as enemies,
					since we feel that they must also think ill of us. You see what kind of
					thoughts the superstitious have about the gods ; they assume that the gods
					are rash, faithless, fickle, vengeful, cruel, and easily offended ; and, as
					a result, the superstitious man is bound to hate and fear the gods. Why not,
					since he thinks that the worst of his ills are due to them, and will be due
					to them in the future ? As he hates and fears the gods, he is an enemy to
					them. And yet, though he dreads them, he worships them and sacrifices to
					them and besieges their shrines ; and this is nothing surprising ; for it is
					equally true that men give welcome to despots, and pay court to them, and
					erect golden statues in their honour, but in their hearts they hate them and
					<q direct="unspecified">shake the head.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Antigone</hi>, 291.</note> Hermola&uuml;s <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. lv. (p. 696 C).</note> attended upon
					Alexander, Pausanias <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is said that Pausanias later helped to kill Philip. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Politics</hi>, v. 10; Diodorus Siculus, xv. 94-95; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 45; Valerius Maximus, i. 8, ext. 9.</note> served as bodyguard for Philip, and Chaerea <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cassius Chaerea fomented the conspiracy which resulted in the death of Caligula; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Annals</hi>, i. 32; Suetonius, <hi rend="italics">Caligula</hi>, 56-58.</note> for Gaius
					Caligula, yet each one of these must have said as he followed along : Verily
					I would have vengeance if only my strength were sufficient. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxii. 20.</note>
					          <pb id="v.2.p.491"/>
				        </p>
            <p>The atheist thinks there are no gods ; the superstitious man wishes there
					were none, but believes in them against his will; for he is afraid not to
					believe. And yet, as Tantalus would be glad indeed to get out from under the
					rock suspended above his head, so the superstitious man would be glad to
					escape his fear by which he feels oppressed no less than Tantalus by his
					rock, and he would call the condition of the atheist happy because it is a
					state of freedom. But, as things are, the atheist has neither part nor lot
					in superstition, whereas the superstitious man by preference would be an
					atheist, but is too weak to hold the opinion about the gods which he wishes
					to hold. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Moreover, the atheist has no part in causing superstition, but superstition
					provides the seed from which atheism springs, and when atheism has taken
					root, superstition supplies it with a defence, not a true one or a fair one,
					but one not destitute of some speciousness. For it is not because these
					people saw in the heavens anything to find fault with, or anything not
					harmonious or well-ordered in the stars or seasons, or in the revolutions of
					the moon or in the movements of the sun around the earth, <q direct="unspecified">artisans
						of day and night,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 40 C. Plutarch quotes the phrase more accurately in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 937 E, 938 E, and 1006.</note> or in the feeding and growth of living
					creatures, or in the sowing and harvesting of crops, as the result of which
					they decided against the idea of a God in the universe; but the ridiculous
					actions and emotions of superstition, its words and gestures, magic charms
					and spells, rushing about and beating of drums, impure purifications and
					dirty sanctifications, barbarous and outlandish penances and mortifications
					at the shrines&mdash;all these give occasion to some to say that it were
					better there should be no gods at all than gods who accept with <pb id="v.2.p.493"/> pleasure such forms of worship, and are so overbearing,
					so petty, and so easily offended. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Would it not then have been better for those Gauls <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Caesar, <hi rend="italics">Gallic War</hi>, vi. 16 and Strabo, iv. 4. 5.</note> and Scythians <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, iv. 70-72.</note> to have
					had absolutely no conception, no vision, no tradition, regarding the gods,
					than to believe in the existence of gods who take delight in the blood of
					human sacrifice and hold this to be the most perfect offering and holy rite
					? Again, would it not have been far better for the Carthaginians to have
					taken Critias or Diagoras <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Both Critias and Diagoras were famous atheists of antiquity. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Adersus Mathematicos</hi>, ix. 54; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 880 D, 1075 A.</note> to draw up their law-code at the very beginning,
					and so not to believe in any divine power or god, rather than to offer such
					sacrifices as they used to offer to Cronos? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch says (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 175 A and 522 A) that the practice was stopped by Gelon, tyrant of Syracuse, after his victory oer the Carthaginians in 480 B.C. But <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diodorus, xx. 14, which suggests that the practice was later revived. Cronos here is, of course, the Greek equivalent of Phoenician El (Hebrew Moloch or Baal). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> G. F. Moore in the <hi rend="italics">Journal of Biblical Lit.</hi> xvi. (1897), p. 161.</note> These were not in the manner
					that Empedocles describes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 275.</note> in his attack on those who sacrifice living
					creatures : <quote rend="blockquote">Changed in form is the son beloved of his father so pious, Who
						on the altar lays him and slays him. What folly !</quote> No, but with full
					knowledge and understanding they themselves offered up their own children,
					and those who had no children would buy little ones from poor people and cut
					their throats as if they were so many lambs or young birds ; meanwhile the
					mother stood by without a tear or moan ; but should she utter a single moan
					or let fall a single tear, she had to forfeit the money, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Since the bad omen of her conduct would nullify the good effect of the sacrifice.</note> and her child was
					sacrificed nevertheless ; and the whole area before the statue was filled
					with a loud noise of flutes and drums so that the cries of wailing should
					not reach the ears of the people. Yet, 
					<pb id="v.2.p.495"/> if Typhons or Giants were ruling over us after they had
					expelled the gods, with what sort of sacrifices would they be pleased, or
					what other holy rites would they require? Amestris, the wife of Xerxes,
					caused twelve human beings to be buried alive <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, vii. 114; but compare iii. 35.</note> as an offering in her behalf
					to propitiate Hades, of whom Plato says <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The reference is probably to Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, pp. 403 A-404B, where are repeated the popular etymologies of Pluto from <foreign lang="greek">plou=tos</foreign> (wealth), and Hades from <foreign lang="greek">pa/nta ta\ kala\ ei)de/nai</foreign> (all-knowing of good).</note> that it is because he is humane and
					wise and rich, and controls the souls of the dead by persuasion and reason,
					that he has come to be called by this name. Xenophanes, the natural
					philosopher, seeing the Egyptians beating their breasts and wailing at their
					festivals, gave them a very proper suggestion: <q direct="unspecified">If these beings are
						gods,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">do not bewail them; and if they are men,
							do not offer sacrifices to them.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The saying is quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 379 B and 763 C, and referred to in 228 E, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, ii. 23, 27.</note> 
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>But there is no infirmity comprehending such a multitude of errors and
					emotions, and involving opinions so contradictory, or rather antagonistic,
					as that of superstition. We must try, therefore, to escape it in some way
					which is both safe and expedient, and not be like people who incautiously
					and blindly run hither and thither to escape from an attack of robbers or
					wild beasts, or from a fire, and rush into trackless places that contain
					pitfalls and precipices. For thus it is that some persons, in trying to
					escape superstition, rush into a rough and hardened atheism, thus
					overleaping true religion which lies between. <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An application of the Aristotelian doctrine that virtue is the mean between two extremes (vices).</note> 
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>