<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De amicorum multitudine</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.073">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.464"/>
         <head>Of large acquaintance; or, an essay to prove the folly of seeking many friends.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Menon the Thessalian, a person who had no mean
					opinion of his own parts, who thought himself well accomplished in all the arts of discourse and to have reached (as
					Empedocles words it) the highest pitch of wisdom, was
					asked by Socrates, What is virtue? And he answered
					readily enough, and as impertinently, that there is one
					virtue belonging to childhood, another to old age; that
					there are distinct virtues in men and women, magistrates
					and private persons, masters and servants. Excellently
					well! replied Socrates in raillery, when you were asked
					about one virtue, you have raised, as it were, a whole
					swarm; conjecturing, not without reason, that the man
					therefore named many because he knew the nature of
					none. And may not we ourselves expect and deserve as
					justly to be scoffed and rallied, who having not yet contracted one firm friendship seem nevertheless exceeding
					cautious of too many? It is almost the same thing as if
					one maimed and blind should appear solicitous lest like
					Briareus he may chance to be furnished with a hundred
					hands, and become all over eyes like Argus. However,
					we cannot but extol the sense of that young man in Menander the poet, who said that he counted every man
					wonderfully honest and happy who had found even the
					shadow of a friend.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.465"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But all the difficulty lies in finding him; and the
					chiefest reason is that, instead of one choice true friend,
					nothing under a multitude will content us; like women of
					the town who admit the embraces of all gallants that
					come, at the gay appearance of the last which comes we
					neglect and slight the former, and so are unable to hold
					them. Or rather, like the foster-child of Hypsipyle, who
					<q direct="unspecified">in a green meadow sat cropping the flowers one after
						another, snatching each prize with delighted heart, insatiable in his childish joy,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <quote rend="blockquote" lang="greek">
							              <l>Ei)s to\n leimw=na kaqi/sas</l>
							              <l>e)/drepen e(/teron e)f' e(te/rw|</l>
							              <l>ai)ro/menos a)/greuma a)nqe/wn</l>
							              <l>h(dome/na| yuxa=|,</l>
							              <l>to\ nh/pion a)/plhston e)/xwn.</l>
                  </quote>
							
							From the Hypsipyle of Euripides.</note> &mdash;so we of riper years, from
					an inbred affection of novelty and disdain of things already
					possessed, take up presently with the first promising aspect
					of every fresh and new-blooming friend, and lay all at
					once the foundations of several acquaintances; but we
					leave each unfinished, and when we have scarce fixed on
					one, our love immediately palls there, while we passionately pursue some other.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, in this affair,&mdash;to begin at the beginning
						(at the domestic altar, as the saying is),&mdash;let us ask the
						opinion and counsel of our forefathers, and consider what
						report the records of antiquity make concerning true
						friends. They are, we find, always reckoned in pairs; as
						Theseus and Pirithous, Achilles and Patroclus, Orestes
						and Pylades, Phintias and Damon, Epaminondas and
						Pelopidas. Friendship (so to speak) is a creature sociable,
						but affects not a herd or a flock; and that we usually
						esteem a friend another self, and call him <foreign lang="greek">e(tai=ros</foreign> (companion)
						as much as to say <foreign lang="greek">e(/teros</foreign> (the other one), is a convincing
						argument that the number two is the adequate and complete measure of friendship. And in truth, a great
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.466"/>
						
						number of friends or servants is not to be purchased at an
						easy rate. That which procures love and friendship in the
						world is a sweet and obliging temper of mind, a lively
						readiness in doing good offices, together with a constant
						habit of virtue; than which qualifications nothing is more
						rarely found in nature. Therefore to love and to be beloved much can have no place in a multitude; but the
						most eager affection, if divided among numerous objects,
						like a river divided into several channels, must needs flow
						at length very weak and languid. Upon this score, those
						animals love their young most which generate but one;
						and Homer, describing a beloved child, calls it the only-begotten and born in old age,&mdash;that is, at such a time
						when the parents neither have nor hope for another.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 482.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Yet I do not assert we ought to confine ourselves to
					one only friend; but among the rest, there should be one
					eminently so, like a well-beloved and only son, not casually
					picked up at a tavern or eating-house or in a tennis-court,
					nor at a game of hazard, nor at an accidental meeting in
					the wrestling-place or the market,&mdash;as is too common nowadays,&mdash;but one chosen upon long and mature deliberation,
					with whom (according to that celebrated proverb) we have
					eaten a bushel of salt.</p>
            <p>The palaces of noble men and princes appear guarded
						with splendid retinues of diligent obsequious servants, and
						every room is crowded with a throng of visitors, who
						caress the great man with all the endearing gestures and
						expressions that wit and breeding can invent; and it may
						be thought, I confess, at first sight, that such are very fortunate in having so many cordial, real friends at their command; whereas it is all bare pageantry and show. Change
						the scene, and you may observe a far greater number of
						flies as industriously busy in their kitchens; and as these
						would vanish, were the dishes empty and clean, so neither
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.467"/>
						
						would that other sort of insect pay any farther respect,
						were nothing to be got by it.</p>
            <p>There are chiefly these requisites to a true friendship:
						virtue, as a thing lovely and desirable; familiarity, as pleasant; and advantage, as necessary. For we must first choose
						a friend upon a right judgment made of his excellent
						qualities; having chosen him, we must perceive a pleasure
						in his conversation, and upon occasion he must be useful
						to us in our concerns. All which (especially judgment in
						our choice, the main point of all) are inconsistent with a
						numerous acquaintance.</p>
            <p>And first of all (to draw a parallel in other matters), if
						there is no small time required to select a great many persons together who can dance and sing in exact time to the
						same tune, manage oars with a like strength and vigor, be
						fit stewards of our estates or tutors of our children, certainly we must acknowledge it much more difficult to meet
						with a considerable number of friends, ready to enter with
						us the trial of all manner of fortune, of whom every one
						will
						
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Of his good fortune yield thy part to thee,</l>
							           <l>And bear like part of thy calamity.</l>
               </quote>
						
						Even a ship at sea runs not the risk of so many storms,
						nor are any castles, forts, and havens secured with walls,
						ramparts, and dams against the apprehension of so many
						dangers, as are the misfortunes against which a constant
						approved friendship mutually undertakes to afford a defence and refuge. Whoever without due trial put themselves upon us for friends we examine as bad money; and
						the cheat being discovered, we are glad if of their own
						accord they withdraw; or if they persist, at least we wish
						with great impatience fairly to get rid of them.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, Frag. 778.</note> Yet we
						must own it is a hard and troublesome task to cast off a disagreeable acquaintance; for as unwholesome meats which
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.468"/>
						
						nauseate the stomach can neither be retained without hazard of health, nor yet ejected sincere as they were taken,
						but wholly disguised and defiled with other humors; so a
						mistaken false friend must either be still entertained, and
						remain a mere vexation to us as well as uneasy to himself,
						or else by a kind of convulsion be thrown up like bile,
						leaving behind the continual torment of private grudgings
						and hatred.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Therefore it highly concerns us not to be too rash in
					fastening on the next that may accidentally offer, nor presently to affect every one that pretends to be fond of our
					friendship. Let the search rather begin on our own part,
					and our choice fix on those who approve themselves really
					worthy of our respect. What is cheap and with ease obtained is below our notice; and we trample under foot
					bushes and brambles that readily catch hold of us, while
					we diligently clear our way to the vine and olive; so it is
					always best not to admit to our familiarity persons who
					officiously stick and twist themselves about us, but we
					ought rather of our own accord to court the friendship of
					those who are worthy of our regard, and who prove advantageous to ourselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Therefore, as Zeuxis replied to some who blamed the
					slowness of his pencil,&mdash;that he therefore spent a long
					time in painting, because he designed his work should last
					for a long eternity,&mdash;so he that would secure a lasting
					friendship and acquaintance must first deliberately judge
					and thoroughly try its worth, before he settles it. Suppose
					then it is hard to make a right judgment in choosing many
					friends together, it may still be asked whether we may not
					maintain a familiarity with many persons, or whether that
					too is impossible. Now familiarity and converse are the
					genuine products and enjoyments of true friendship, and
					the highest pleasure the best friends aim at is continual
					intercourse and the daily frequenting one another's company.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.469"/>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
               <l>No more shall meet Achilles and his friend;</l>
						         <l>No more our thoughts to those we loved make known,</l>
						         <l>Or quit the dearest, to converse alone.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. XXIII. 77.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </quote>
            <p>And, as Menelaus says of Ulysses:&mdash;</p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
               <l>There with commutual zeal we both had strove</l>
						         <l>In acts of dear benevolence and love,&mdash;</l>
						         <l>Brothers in peace, not rivals in command,&mdash;</l>
						         <l>And death alone dissolved the friendly band.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>See Odyss. IV. 178.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </quote>
            <p>Now much acquaintance has a clear contrary effect; and
						whereas single friendship by kind discourses and good
						offices cements, unites, and condenses as it were two par
						ties,&mdash;
						
						
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>As when the fig-tree's juice curdles and binds white milk,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>See Il. V. 902.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
						
						as Empedocles says; this on the other hand unties, rends, and
						breaks the bond, distracts our inclinations with too much
						variety; and the agreeable just mixture of affection, the
						very cement of true friends, is wholly lost in so loose and
						confused a conversation. Hence at once arises great inequality with respect to the services of friendship, and a
						foolish diffidence in the performance of them. For multiplicity of friends renders those very parts of friendship
						vain and useless whence advantage was most expected;
						neither can we hope it should be otherwise, if we consider
						how <q direct="unspecified">one man is acted upon by his nature and another by
							his cares and anxieties.</q> Nature hath not bestowed the
						same inclinations on all, nor are we all born to the same
						fortune; and the occasions of our actions, like the wind,
						may often favor one of our acquaintance while they stand
						cross to another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>However, suppose by great chance all should agree
					to crave assistance in the same affair, whether at a consult,
					exercise of a public trust in the government, canvassing
					for preferment, entertaining guests, or the like; yet it is
					exceeding hard to satisfy all. But now if they are engaged
					in diverse concerns at the very same moment of time, and
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.470"/>
					
					every one should make his particular request to you, one
					to take a voyage with him, another to assist in pleading his
					cause, a third to prosecute a criminal, a fourth to help in
					managing his trade, another to celebrate his wedding, and
					another to attend a funeral,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>And the whole city's filled with incense smoke,</l>
						            <l>And songs of triumph mixt with groans resound;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Sophocles, Oed. Tyr. 4.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					
					I say, in this case, it is utterly impossible to answer the
					requests of all, to gratify none is absurd, and to serve only
					one and disoblige the rest is a thing grievous and intolerably rude;&mdash;<q direct="unspecified">for no one, when he loves a friend, will bear
						to be neglected.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Menander.</note> If indeed you could persuade that
					inadvertency was the cause of the omission, you might
					more easily hope a pardon; and to plead forgetfulness is a
					sort of excuse which perhaps might pass without much
					angering your friend; but to allege <q direct="unspecified">I could not be advocate in your cause, being of counsel for another,</q> or <q direct="unspecified">I
						could not visit you in a fever, because I was invited to a
						feast elsewhere,</q> while it is thus confessed that we neglect
					one friend to pay our respects to another, is so far from
					extenuating the offence, that it highly aggravates it, and
					adds all the jealousies of rivalry.</p>
            <p>But commonly men overlook these and such like inconveniences of a numerous acquaintance, and take only a
						prospect of its advantages, not in the least reflecting that
						whoever employs many assistants in his affairs must in
						gratitude repay his service to as many when they need it;
						and as Briareus, who with his hundred hands was daily
						obliged for his bare subsistence to feed fifty stomachs, could
						thrive no better than ourselves, who supply a single one
						with two hands, so a man of many friends cannot boast any
						other privilege but that of being a slave to many, and of
						sharing in all the business, cares, and disquiet that may
						befall them. Nor can Euripides help him by advising that
						
						<pb id="v.1.p.471"/>
						
						         <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Best suited to the state</l>
							           <l>Of mortal life are mutual friendships formed</l>
							           <l>With moderation, such as take not root</l>
							           <l>Deep in the soul, affections that with ease</l>
							           <l>May be relaxed, or closer bound at will,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <bibl>Eurip. Hippol. 253.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
						
						that is, we may pull in and let out our friendships like a sail,
						as the wind happens to blow. Let us rather, good Euripides, turn this saying of yours to enmity; for heats and animosities ought to be moderate, and never reach the inmost
						recesses of the soul; hatred, anger, complaints, and jealousies
						may with good reason be readily appeased and forgotten.
						Therefore it is far more advisable, as Pythagoras directs,
						<q direct="unspecified">not to shake hands with too many,</q>&mdash;that is, not to make
						many friends,&mdash;nor to affect that popular kind of easiness
						which courts and embraces every acquaintance that occurs,
						but carries with it on the reverse a thousand mischiefs;
						among which (as was before hinted) to bear part of the
						same cares, to be affected with the same sorrows, and to be
						embroiled in the same enterprises and dangers with any
						great number of friends will be a sort of life hardly tolerable even to the most ingenuous and generous tempers.
						What Chilon the wise man remarked to one who said he
						had no enemies, namely, <q direct="unspecified">Thou seemest rather to have no
							friends,</q> has a great deal of truth; for enmities always
						keep pace and are interwoven with friendships.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>And it is impossible any should be friends that resent
					not mutually the affronts and injuries offered unto either,
					and that do not hate alike and in common. They also who
					are enemies to yourself will presently suspect and hate
					your friend; nay, your other friends too will often envy,
					calumniate, and undermine him. Wherefore what the
					oracle foretold Timesias concerning his planting a colony,
					that an hive of bees should be changed into a nest of wasps,
					may not impertinently be applied to those who seek after
					a hive of friends, but light before they know it upon a
					wasps-nest of enemies.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.472"/>
            <p>Besides, we should do well to consider that the kindest
						affections of friends seldom compensate for the misfortunes
						that befall us from the malice of enemies. It is well known
						how Alexander treated the familiars of Philotas and Parmenio; Dionysius, those of Dion; Nero, those of Plautus;
						and Tiberius, those of Sejanus; all shared the same hard
						fate of being racked and tortured to death. For as the
						gold and riches Creon's daughter was adorned with could
						not secure the good old father from being consumed in her
						flames, endeavoring too officiously to rescue her; so not a
						few partake of the calamities and ruin of their friends,
						before they have reaped the least advantage from their prosperity; a misfortune to which philosophers and the bestnatured men are the most liable. This was the case of
						Theseus, who for the sake of his dear Pirithous shared his
						punishment, and was bound with him in the same eternal
						chains.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Pirith. Frag. 598.</note> Thus in the plague of Athens, says Thucydides,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucyd. II. 51.</note>
						the most generous and virtuous citizens, while without
						regard to their own safety they visited their sick, frequently
						perished with their friends.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Such accidents as these ought to admonish us not to
					be too prodigal of our virtue, nor inconsiderately to prostitute our perfections to the enjoyment of every little thing
					that pretends to be our humble admirer; rather let us reserve them for the worthy, for those who can love and share
					another's joys and sorrows like ourselves. And truly, this
					alone renders it most unlikely that many men should remain
					friends, that real friendship has always its origin from likeness. For, we may observe, even brute and inanimate
					beings affect their like, very readily mixing and uniting
					with those of their own nature; while with great reluctance
					and a kind of indignation they shrink from and avoid whatever differs from themselves, and force can scarce oblige
					them to the loathed embraces. By what motive then can
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.473"/>
					
					we imagine any league of amity can be kept inviolable
					amidst a multitude, where manners admit of so much variety, where desires and humors will be perpetually jarring,
					where the several courses of life must needs be almost as
					unlike as constitutions and faces? A musical concord consists of contrary sounds, and a due composition of flat and
					sharp notes makes a delightful tune; but as for friendship,
					that is a sort of harmony all of a piece, and admits not the
					least inequality, unlikeness, or discords of parts, but here
					all discourses, opinions, inclinations, and designs serve one
					common interest, as if several bodies were acted and informed by the same soul.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Now is there any person living of that industrious,
					pliant, and universal humor, who can take the pains exactly
					to imitate all shapes, and will not rather deride the advice
					of Theognis<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theognis, vs. 215.</note> as absurd and impossible, namely, to learn
					the craft of the polypus, which puts on the hue of every
					stone it sticks to? However, the changes of this fish are
					only superficial, and the colors are produced in the skin,
					which by its closeness or its laxity receives various impressions from neighboring objects; whereas the resemblance
					betwixt friends must be far more than skin-deep, must be
					substantial, such as may be traced in every action of their
					lives, in all their affections, dispositions, words and purposes, even to their most retired thoughts. To follow the
					advice of Theognis would be a task worthy of a Proteus,
					who was neither very fortunate nor very honest, but could
					by enchantment transform himself in an instant from one
					shape to another. Even so, he that entertains many friends
					must be learned and bookish among the learned, go into
					the arena with wrestlers, drudge cheerfully after a pack of
					hounds with gentlemen that love hunting, drink with debauchees, and sue for office with politicians; in fine, he
					must have no proper principles of actions and tumors of
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.474"/>
					
					his own, but those of the present company he converses
					with. Thus, as the first matter of the philosophers is
					originally without shape or color, yet being the subject of
					all natural changes takes by its own inherent forces the
					forms of fire, water, air, and solid earth; so a person that
					affects a numerous friendship must possess a mind full of
					folds and windings, subject to many passions, inconstant as
					water, and easy to be transformed into an infinite variety
					of shapes. But real friendship requires a sedate, stable,
					and unalterable temper; so that it is a rare thing and next
					a miracle to find a constant and sure friend.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>