<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De animae procreatione in Timaeo</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.134">
      <body>
         <head>Concerning the procreation of the soul as discoursed in Timaeus.
				<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Boeckh's dissertation 
					<hi rend="italics">Ueber die Bildung der Weltseele im Timaeos des Platon,</hi> 
					now reprinted in his Kleine Schriften, III. pp. 109&ndash;180. For the passages relating to music, see Westphal's 
					<hi rend="italics">Harmonik und Melop&ouml;ie der Griecihen,</hi> 
					pp. 134&ndash;136. See also the note prefixed to Plutarch on Music, vol. I. p. 102. (G.)</note>
				        <lb/>
				The father to Autobulus and Plutarch wisheth health.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.326"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Since it is your opinion that it would be requisite for
				me to collect together what I have discoursed and written
				dispersedly in several treatises explaining, as we apprehended his sense and meaning, what opinion Plato had
				concerning the soul, as requiring a particular commentary
				by itself; therefore I have compiled this discourse, which
				asks for your consideration and pardon not only because
				the matter itself is by no means easy to be handled, but
				also because the doctrines herein contained are somewhat
				contrary to those held by most of the Platonic philosophers.
				And I will first rehearse the words as they run originally
				in the text itself of Timaeus.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 35 A&ndash;B.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">There being one substance not admitting of division, but
					continuing still the same, and another liable to be divided
					among several bodies, out of both these he produced for a middle mixture a third sort of Substance, partaking of the nature
					of the Same and of the nature of the Other, and placed it
					in the midst between that which was indivisible and that
					which was subject to be corporeally divided. Then taking
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.327"/>
					
					all three, he blended them into one form, forcibly adapting
					to the Same the nature of the Other, not readily condescending to a mixture. Now when he had thus mixed
					them with the Substance, and reduced the three into one,
					he again divided this whole matter into so many parts as
					were thought to be necessary; every one of these parts
					being composed of the Same, the Other, and the Substance
					And thus he began his division.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By the way, it would be an endless toil to recite the contentions and disputes that have from hence arisen among
					his interpreters, and to you indeed superfluous, who are not
					ignorant yourselves of the greatest part.</p>
            <p>But seeing that Xenocrates won to his opinions several
					of the most eminent philosophers, while he defined the
					substance of the soul to be number moved by itself; and
					that many adhered to Crantor the Solian, who affirmed the
					soul to consist partly of an essence perceptible to the mind,
					partly of a nature concerned with sensible things and subject to opinions; I am apt to believe that the perspicuity
					of these matters clearly dilucidated will afford you a fair
					entrance into the knowledge of the rest.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Nor does either of the two conjectures require many
				words of explanation. For the one side pretends that by
				the mixture of the' divisible and indivisible substance no
				other thing is meant than the generation or original of
				number, seeing that the unit is undividable but multitude
				is subject to division; however, that out of these is begot
				number, unity terminating plurality and putting a period to
				infinity, which they call the unlimited binary. This binary
				Zaratas, the scholar of Pythagoras, named the mother, but
				the unit the father of number; and therefore he believed
				those numbers were the best which approached nearest in
				resemblance to the unit. Nevertheless, this number cannot be said to be the soul; for it neither has the power to
				move, neither can it be moved. But the Same and the
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.328"/>
				
				Other being blended together, of which one is the original
				of motion and mutation, the other of rest and stability,
				from these two springs the soul, which is no less active or
				passive itself to stay or to be stayed, than to move or to
				be moved.</p>
            <p>But the followers of Crantor, supposing the proper function of the soul to consist in judging of those things which
					are discernible to the understanding and those which are
					liable to sense, as also of the differences and similitudes of
					these things, as well in themselves as in reference one to
					another, allege the soul to be composed of all, to the end
					she may have a true knowledge of the whole. Now the
					things of which the All is composed are fourfold,&mdash;the
					intelligible nature, always immutable and still the same,
					and the sensitive nature, which is passive and subject to
					alteration; and also the nature of the Same, and the nature
					of the Other, in regard the two former in some measure
					participate also of diversity and identity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>All these philosophers likewise equally hold that the
				soul neither derives its beginning from time nor is the product of generation, but that it is endued with several faculties and virtues, into which Plato, as it were, melting and
				dissolving its substance for contemplation's sake, supposes
				it in his discourse to have had its original from procreation and mixture.</p>
            <p>The same was his opinion concerning the world; for he
					knew it to be uncreated and without end, but not perceiving it so easy to apprehend how the structure was reared,
					or by what order and government supported, unless by admitting its beginning and the causes thereto concurring, he
					followed that method to instruct himself. These things
					being thus generally by them laid down, Eudorus will
					allow to neither side any share of probability; and indeed
					to me they both seem to have wandered from the opinion
					of Plato, if we intend to make the most likely rule our
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.329"/>
					
					guide,&mdash;which is not to advance our own conceits, but to
					come as close as we can to his sense and meaning. Now
					as to this same mixture (as they call it) of the intelligible
					and sensitive substance, no reason appears why it should be
					more the original of the soul than of any other thing that
					ye can name. For the whole world itself and every one of
					its parts pretend to no other composition than of a sensitive
					and an intelligible substance, of which the one affords matter and foundation, the other form and figure to the whole
					mass. And then again, whate'er there is of material substance, framed and structured by participation and assimilation of the intelligible nature is not only to be felt but
					visible to the eye; whenas the soul still soars above the
					reach of all natural apprehension. Neither did Plato ever
					assert the soul to be number, but a perpetually self-moving
					nature, the fountain and principle of motion. Only he
					embellished and adorned the substance of it with number,
					proportion, and harmony; as being a subject capable of
					receiving the most goodly form which those ornaments
					could produce. So that I cannot believe it to be the same
					thing to compose the soul according to number, and to affirm the soul to be number itself. Nor can it be said to be
					harmony because harmoniously composed, as he has clearly
					demonstrated in his Treatise of the Soul. But plain it is,
					that those philosophers understood not the meaning of the
					Same and the Other. For they tell us how the Same contributes rest, the Other motion toward the generation of
					the soul. Though Plato himself, in his treatise entitled the
					Sophist, disposes and distinguishes Essence, the Same, the
					Other, together with Motion and Rest, as being five things
					altogether differing one from another and void of mutual
					affinity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>But these men are generally, as the most part of
				Plato's readers, timorous and vainly perplexed, using all
				their endeavors by wresting and tormenting his sense to
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.330"/>
				
				conceal and hide what he has written, as if it were some
				terrible novelty not fit for public view, that the world and
				the soul neither had their beginning and composition from
				eternity, nor had their essence from a boundless immensity
				of time,&mdash;of which we have particularly spoken already.
				So that now it shall suffice to say no more than this, that
				these writers confound and smother (if they do not rather
				utterly abolish) his eager contest and dispute in behalf of
				the Gods, wherein Plato confesses himself to have been
				transported with an ambitious zeal, even beyond the
				strength of his years, against the atheists of his time.
				For if the world had no beginning, Plato's opinion vanishes,&mdash;that the soul, much elder than the body, is the
				principle of all motion and alteration, or (to use his own
				words) their chieftain and first efficient cause, whose mansion
				is in Nature's secret retirements. But what the soul is,
				what the body, and why the soul is said to have been elder
				than the body, shall be made appear in the progress of this
				discourse. The ignorance of this seems to have been the
				occasion of much doubt and incredulity in reference to the
				true opinion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>First therefore, I shall propose my own sentiments
				concerning these things, desiring to gain credit no otherwise than by the most probable strength of arguments,
				explaining and reconciling to the utmost of my ability
				truth and paradox together; after which I shall apply
				both the explication and demonstration to the words of
				the text. In my opinion then the business lies thus.
				The world, saith Heraclitus, neither did any one of all
				the Gods nor any mortal man create,&mdash;as if he had been
				afraid that, not being able to make out the creation by a
				Deity, we should be constrained to acknowledge some man
				to have been the architect of the universe. But certainly
				far better it is, in submission to Plato's judgment, to avow,
				both in discourse and in our songs of praise, that the
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.331"/>
				
				glory of the structure belongs to God,&mdash;for the frame
				itself is the most beautiful of all masterpieces, and God
				the most illustrious of all causes,&mdash;but that the substance
				and materials were not created, but always ready at the
				ordering and disposal of the Omnipotent Builder, to give
				it form and figure, as near as might be, approaching to
				his own resemblance. For the creation was not out of
				nothing, but out of matter wanting beauty and perfection,
				like the rude materials of a house, a garment, or a statue,
				lying first in shapeless confusion. For before the creation of the world there was nothing but a confused heap;
				yet was that confused heap neither without a body, without motion, nor without a soul. The corporeal part was
				without form or consistence, and the moving part stupid
				and headlong; and this was the disorder of a soul not
				guided by reason. God neither incorporated that which
				is incorporeal, nor conveyed a soul into that which had
				none before; like a person either musical or poetical, who
				does not make either the voice or the movement, but only
				reduces the voice with harmony, and graces the movement
				with proper measures. Thus God did not make the tangible and resistant solidity of the corporeal substance, nor
				the imaginative or moving faculties of the soul; but taking these two principles as they lay ready at hand,&mdash;the
				one obscure and dark, the other turbulent and senseless,
				both imperfect without the bounds of order and decency,
				&mdash;he disposed, digested, and embellished the confused
				mass. so that he brought to perfection a most absolute and
				glorious creature. Therefore the substance of the body
				is no other than that all-receiving Nature, the seat and
				nurse of all created beings.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But the substance of the soul, in Philebus, he called
				an infinite being, the privation of number and proportion;
				having neither period nor measure either of diminution
				or excess or distinction or dissimilitude. But as to that
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.332"/>
				
				order which he alleges in Timaeus to be the mixture of
				nature with the indivisible substance, but which being
				applied to bodies becomes liable to division,&mdash;he would
				not have it thought to be a bulk made up by units or
				points, nor longitude and breadth, which are qualities more
				consentaneous to bodies than to the soul, but that disorderly unlimited principle, moving both itself and other
				substances, that which he frequently calls necessity, and
				which within his treatise of laws he openly styles the disorderly, ill-acting, or harm-doing soul. For such was this
				soul of herself; but at length she came to partake of understanding, ratiocination, and harmony, that she might
				be the soul of the world. Now that all-receiving principle of matter enjoyed both magnitude, space, and distance; but beauty, form, and measure of proportion it
				had none. However, all these it obtained, to the end
				that, when it came to be thus embellished and adorned,
				it might assume the form of all the various bodies and
				organs of the earth, the sea, the heavens, the stars, and
				of all those infinite varieties of plants and living creatures. Now as for those who attribute to this matter, and
				not to the soul, that which in Timaeus is called necessity,
				in Philebus vast disproportion and unlimited exorbitancy
				of diminution and excess,&mdash;they can never maintain it
				to be the cause of disorder, since Plato always alleges
				that same matter to be without any form or figures, and
				altogether destitute of any quality or effectual virtue properly belonging to it; comparing it to such oils as have no
				scent at all, which the perfumers mix in their tinctures.
				For there is no likelihood that Plato would suppose that
				to be the cause and principle of evil which is altogether
				void of quality in itself, sluggish, and never to be roused
				on to action, and yet at the same time brand this immensity with the harsh epithets of base and mischievous,
				and call it necessity repugnant and contumaciously rebellious
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.333"/>
				
				 against God. For this same necessity, which renverses heaven (to use his own phrase in his Politicus) and
				turns it the quite contrary way from decency and symmetry, together with innate concupiscence, and that inbred
				confusion of ancient nature, hurly-burly'd with all manner of disorder, before they were wrought and kneaded
				into the graceful decorum of the world,&mdash;whence came
				they to be conveyed into several varieties of forms and
				beings, if the subject, which is the first matter, were void
				of all quality whatsoever and deprived of all efficient
				cause; more especially the Architect being so good of
				himself, and intending a frame the nearest approaching to
				his own perfections? For besides these there is no third
				principle. And indeed, we should stumble into the perplexed intricacies of the Stoics, should we advance evil
				into the world out of nonentity, without either any preceding cause or effect of generation, in regard that among
				those principles that have a being, it is not probable that
				either real good or that which is destitute of all manner
				of quality should afford birth or substance to evil. But
				Plato escaped those pitfalls into which they blundered
				who came after him; who, neglecting what he carefully
				embraced, the third principle and energetic virtue in the
				middle between God and the first matter, maintain the
				most absurd of arguments, affirming the nature of evils to
				have crept in spontaneously and adventitiously, I know
				not how nor by what strange accidents. And yet they
				will not allow an atom of Epicurus so much as a moment's liberty to shift in its station, which, as they say,
				would infer motion out of nonentity without any impulsive cause; nevertheless themselves presuming all this
				while to affirm that vice and wickedness, together with a
				thousand other incongruities and vexations afflicting the
				body, of which no cause can be ascribed to any of the
				principles, came into being (as it were) <q direct="unspecified">by consequence.</q>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.334"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Plato however does not so; who, despoiling the first
				matter of all manner of distinction, and separating from
				God, as far as it is possible, the causes of evil, has thus
				delivered himself concerning the world, in his Politicus.
				<q direct="unspecified">The world,</q> saith he, <q direct="unspecified">received from the Illustrious
					Builder all things beautiful and lovely; but whatsoever
					happens to be noxious and irregular in heaven, it derives
					from its ancient habit and disposition, and conveys them
					into the several creatures.</q> And a little farther in the
				same treatise he saith: <q direct="unspecified">In process of time, when oblivion had encroached upon the world, the distemper of its
					ancient confusion more prevailed, and the hazard is, lest
					being dissolved it should again be sunk and plunged into
					the immense abyss of its former irregularity.</q> But there
				can be no dissimilitude in the first matter, as being void
				of quality and distinction.</p>
            <p>Of which when Eudemus with several others was altogether ignorant, he seems deridingly to cavil with Plato,
					and taxes him with asserting the first matter to be the
					cause, the root, and principle of all evil, which he had at
					other times so frequently dignified with the tender appellations of mother and nurse. Whereas Plato gives to matter only the titles of the mother and nurse; but the cause
					of evil he makes to be the moving force residing within
					it, not governed by order and reason though not without
					a soul neither, which, in his treatise of the Laws, he calls
					expressly the soul repugnant and in hostility with that
					other propitiously and kindly acting. For though the soul
					be the principle of motion, yet is it the understanding
					and intelligence which measures that motion by order and
					harmony, and is the cause of both. For God could not
					have brought to rest mere sleepy and sluggish matter, but
					he brought it to rest when it had been troubled and disquieted by a senseless and stupid cause. Neither did he
					infuse into nature the principles of alteration and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.335"/>
					
					affections; but when it was under the pressure of those
					unruly disorders and alterations, he discharged it of its
					manifold enormities and irregularities, making use of
					symmetry, proportion, and number. For these are the
					most proper instruments, not by alteration and lawless
					motion to distract the several beings with passions and
					distinctions, but rather to render them fixed and stable,
					and nearest in their composition to those things that in
					themselves continue still the same upon the equal poise
					of diuturnity. And this, in my judgment, is the sense
					and meaning of Plato.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Of which the easy reconciliation of his seeming
				incongruities and contradiction of himself may serve for
				the first proof. For indeed no men of judgment would
				have objected to the most Bacchanalian sophister, more
				especially to Plato, the guilt of so much inconvenience and
				impudent rashness in a discourse by him so elaborately
				studied, as to affirm the same nature in one place never to
				have been created, in another to have been the effects of
				generation;&mdash;in Phaedrus to assert the soul eternal, in
				Timaeus to subject it to procreation. The words in Phaedrus need no repetition, as being familiar to nearly every
				one, wherein he proves the soul to be incorruptible in regard it never had a beginning, and to have never had a
				beginning because it moves itself. But in Timaeus, <q direct="unspecified">God,</q>
				saith he, <q direct="unspecified">did not make the soul a junior to the body, as
					now we labor to prove it to have been subsequent to the
					body. For he would never have suffered the more ancient,
					because linked and coupled with the younger, to have been
					governed by it; only we, guided I know not how by chance
					and inconsiderate rashness, frame odd kind of notions to
					ourselves. But God most certainly composed the soul excelling the body both in seniority of origin and in power,
					to be mistress and governess of her inferior servant.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 34 B.</note>
				
				           <pb id="v.2.p.336"/>
				
				And then again he adds, how that the soul, being turned
				upon herself, began the divine beginning of an eternal and
				prudent life. <q direct="unspecified">Now,</q> saith he, <q direct="unspecified">the body of heaven
					became visible; but the soul being invisible, nevertheless
					participating of ratiocination and harmony, by the best of
					intelligible and eternal beings she was made the best of
					things created.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 36 E.</note> Here then he determines God to be the
				best of sempiternal beings, the soul to be the most excellent of temporal existences. By which apparent distinction
				and antithesis he denies that the soul is eternal, and that
				it never had a beginning.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>And now what other or better reconciliation of these
				seeming contrarieties than his own explanation, to those
				that are willing to apprehend it? For he declares to have
				been without beginning the never procreated soul, that
				moved all things confusedly and in an irregular manner
				before the creation of the world. But as for that which
				God composed out of this and that other permanent and
				choicest substance, making it both prudent and orderly,
				and adding of his own, as if it were for form and beauty's
				sake, intellect to sense, and order to motion, and which he
				constituted prince and chieftain of the whole,&mdash;that he
				acknowledges to have had a beginning and to have proceeded from generation. Thus he likewise pronounces the
				body of the world in one respect to be eternal and without
				beginning, in another sense to be the work of creation. To
				which purpose, where he says that the visible structure,
				never in repose at first but restless in a confused and tempestuous motion, was at length by the hand of God disposed
				and ranged into majestic order,&mdash;where he says that the
				four elements, fire and water, earth and air, before the
				stately pile was by them embellished and adorned, caused
				a prodigious fever and shivering ague in the whole mass of
				matter, that labored under the combats of their unequal
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.337"/>
				
				mixtures,&mdash;by his urging these things, he gives those
				bodies room in the vast abyss before the fabric of the
				universe.</p>
            <p>Again, when he says that the body was younger than
					the soul, and that the world was created, as being of a
					corporeal substance that may be seen and felt,&mdash;which sort
					of substances must necessarily have a beginning and be
					created,&mdash;it is evidently demonstrable from thence that he
					ascribes original creation to the nature of bodies. But he
					is far from being repugnant or contradictory to himself in
					these sublimest mysteries. For he does not contend, that
					the same body was created by God or after the same manner, and yet that it was before it had a being,&mdash;which
					would have been to act the part of a juggler; but he instructs us what we ought to understand by generations and
					creation. Therefore, says he, at first all these things were
					void of measure and proportion; but when God first
					began to beautify the whole, the fire and water, earth and
					air, having perhaps some prints and footsteps of their
					forms, lay in a huddle jumbled all together,&mdash;as probable
					it is that all things are, where God is absent,&mdash;which then
					he reduced to a comely perfection varied by number and
					order. Moreover, having told us before that it was a work
					not of one but of a twofold proportion to bind and fasten
					the bulky immensity of the whole, which was both solid
					and of a prodigious profundity, he then comes to declare
					how God, after he had placed the water and the earth in
					the midst between the fire and the air, incontinently closed
					up the heavens into a circular form. Out of these materials, saith he, being four in number, was the body of the
					world created, agreeing in proportion, and so amicably corresponding together, that being thus embodied and confined within their proper bounds, it is impossible that any
					dissolution should happen from their own contending force,
					unless he that riveted the whole frame should go about
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.338"/>
					
					again to rend it in pieces;&mdash;most apparently teaching us,
					that God was not the parent and architect of the corporeal
					substance only, or of the bulk and matter, but of the
					beauty and symmetry and similitude that adorned and graced
					the whole. The same we are to believe, he thought, concerning the soul; that there is one which neither was
					created by God nor is the soul of the world, but a certain
					self-moving and restless efficacy of a giddy and disorderly
					agitation and impetuosity, irrational and subject to opinion;
					while the other is that which God himself, having accoutred and adorned it with suitable numbers and proportions,
					has made queen regent of the created world, herself the
					product of creation also.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Now that Plato had this belief concerning these
				things, and did not for contemplation's sake lay down these
				suppositions concerning the creation of the world and the
				soul,&mdash;this, among many others, seems to be an evident
				signification that, as to the soul, he avers it to be both
				created and not created, but as to the world, he always
				maintains that it had a beginning and was created, never
				that it was uncreated and eternal. What necessity therefore of bringing any testimonies out of Timaeus? For the
				whole treatise, from the beginning to the end, discourses of
				nothing else but of the creation of the world. As for the
				rest, we find that Timaeus, in his Atlantic, addressing himself in prayer to the Deity, calls God that being which of
				old existed in his works, but now was apparent to reason.
				In his Politicus, his Parmenidean guest acknowledges that
				the world, which was the handiwork of God, is replenished
				with several good things, and that, if there be any thing
				in it which is vicious and offensive, it comes by mixture of its
				former incongruous and irrational habit. But Socrates, in
				the Politics, beginning to discourse of number, which some
				call by the name of wedlock, says: <q direct="unspecified">The created Divinity
					has a circular period, which is, as it were, enchased and
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.339"/>
					
					involved in a certain perfect number;</q> meaning in that
				place by created Divinity no other than the world itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>The first pair of these numbers consists of one and
				two, the second of three and four, the third of five and
				six; neither of which pairs make a tetragonal
				number, either by themselves or joined with any
				other figures. The fourth consists of seven and
				eight, which, being added all together, produce
				a tetragonal number of thirty-six. But the quaternary of
				numbers set down by Plato have a more perfect generation, of even
				numbers multiplied by even distances, and
				of odd by uneven distances.
				This quaternary contains the
				unit, the common original of
				all even and odd numbers.
				Subsequent to which are two
				and three, the first plane
				numbers; then four and nine, the first squares; and next
				eight and twenty-seven, the first cubical numbers (not
				counting the unit). Whence it is apparent, that his intention was not that the numbers should be placed in a
				direct line one above another, but apart and oppositely
				one against the other, the even by themselves, and the odd
				by themselves, according to the scheme here given. In
				this manner similar numbers will be joined together, which
				will produce other remarkable numbers, as well by addition as by multiplication.
				
				<!--<figure><head>[see figure on page]</head></figure>
					<figure><head>[see figure on page]</head></figure>--></p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>By addition thus: two and three make five, four
				and nine make thirteen, eight and twenty-seven make thirty-five. Of all which numbers the Pythagoreans called
				five the nourisher, that is to say, the breeding or fostering
				sound, believing a fifth to be the first of all the intervals
				of tones which could be sounded. But as for thirteen,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.340"/>
				
				they called it the remainder, despairing, as Plato himself
				did, of being ever able to divide a tone into equal parts.
				Then five and thirty they named harmony, as consisting
				of the two cubes eight and twenty-seven, the first that rise
				from an odd and an even number, as also of the four numbers, six, eight, nine, and twelve, comprehending both harmonical and arithmetical proportion. Which nevertheless
				will be more conspicuous, being made out in a scheme to
				the eye.</p>
            <p>Admit a right-angled parallelogram, A B C D, the
					lesser side of which A B consists of five, the longer side
					A C contains seven squares. Let the
					lesser division be unequally divided
					into two and three squares, marked by
					E; and the larger division in two unequal divisions more of three and four
					squares, marked by F. Thus A E F
					G comprehends six, E B G I nine, F
					G C H eight, and G I H D twelve.
					By this means the whole parallelogram, containing thirty-five little square areas, comprehends all the proportions of the first concords of music
					in the number of these little squares. For six is exceeded
					by eight in a sesquiterce proportion (3:4), wherein the
					diatessaron is comprehended. And six is exceeded by nine
					in a sesquialter proportion (2:3), wherein also is included
					the fifth. Six is exceeded by twelve in duple proportion
					(1:2), containing the octave; and then lastly, there is the
					sesquioctave proportion of a tone in eight to nine. And
					therefore they call that number which comprehends all
					these proportions harmony. This number is 35, which
					being multiplied by 6, the product is 210, which is the
					number of days, they say, which brings those infants to
					perfection that are born at the seventh month's end.
					
					<!--<figure><head>[see figure on page]</head></figure>--></p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>To proceed by way of multiplication,&mdash;twice 3
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.341"/>
				
				make 6, and 4 times 9 thirty-six, and 8 times 27 produce 216. Thus six appears to be a perfect number, as
				being equal in its parts; and it is called matrimony, by
				reason of the mixture of the first even and odd. Moreover it is composed of the original number, which is one,
				of the first even number, which is two, and the first
				odd number, which is three. Then for 36, it is the first
				number which is as well quadrangular as triangular, being
				quadrangular from 6, and triangular from 8.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note on Platonic Questions, No. V. &sect; 2. Thirty-six is called the triangular of eight, because a triangle thus made of thirty-six points will have eight points on each side. (G.)</note> The same
				number arises from the multiplication of the first two
				square numbers, 4 and 9; as also from the addition of
				the three cubical numbers, 1, 8, and 27, which being put
				together make up 36. Lastly, you have a parallelogram
				with unequal sides, by the multiplication of 12 by 3, or 9
				by 4. Take then the numbers of the sides of all these
				figures, the 6 of the square, the 8 of the triangle, the 9
				for the one parallelogram, and the 12 for the other; and
				there you will find the proportions of all the concords.
				For 12 to 9 will be a fourth, as nete to paramese. To
				eight it will prove a fifth, as nete to mese. To six it will
				be an octave, as nete to hypate. And the two hundred
				and sixteen is the cubical number proceeding from six
				which is its root, and so equal to its own perimeter.
				
				<!--<figure><head>[see figure on page]</head></figure>--></p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Now these numbers aforesaid being endued with all
				these properties, the last of them, which is 27, has this
				peculiar to itself, that it is equal to all those that precede
				together; besides, that it is the periodical number of the
				days wherein the moon finishes her monthly course; the
				Pythagoreans make it to be the tone of all the harmonical
				intervals. On the other side, they call thirteen the remainder, in regard it misses a unit to be half of twenty-seven.
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.342"/>
				
				Now that these numbers comprehend the proportions of
				harmonical concord, is easily made apparent. For the
				proportion of 2 to 1 is duple, which contains the diapason; as the proportion of 3 to 2 sesquialter, which embraces the fifth; and the proportion of 4 to 3 sesquiterce,
				which comprehends the diatessaron; the proportion of 9
				to 3 triple, including the diapason and diapente; and that
				of 8 to 2 quadruple, comprehending the double diapason.
				Lastly, there is the sesquioctave in 8 to 9, which makes
				the interval of a single tone. If then the unit, which is
				common, be counted as well to the even as the odd numbers, the whole series will be equal to the sum of the
				decade. For the even numbers<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, in the quaternary, &sect; 11. See the diagram, p. 339. (G.)</note> (1 + 2 + 4 + 8) give 15,
				the triangular number of five. On the other side, take the
				odd numbers, 1, 3, 9, and 27, and the sum is 40; by
				which numbers the skilful measure all musical intervals,
				of which they call one a diesis, and the other a tone.
				Which number of 40 proceeds from the force of the
				quaternary number by multiplication. For every one of
				the first four numbers being by itself multiplied by four,
				the products will be 4, 8, 12, 16, which being added
				all together make 40, comprehending all the proportions
				of harmony. For 16 is a sesquiterce to 12, duple to 8,
				and quadruple to 4. Again, 12 holds a sesquialter proportion to 8, and triple to 4. In these proportions are
				contained the intervals of the diatessaron, diapente, diapason, and double diapason. Moreover, the number 40 is
				equal to the two first tetragons and the two first cubes
				being taken both together. For the first tetragons are 1
				and 4, the first cubes are 8 and 27, which being added
				together make 40. Whence it appears that the Platonic
				quaternary is much more perfect and fuller of variety than
				the Pythagoric.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>But since the numbers proposed did not afford space
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.343"/>
				
				sufficient for the middle intervals, therefore there was a
				necessity to allow larger bounds for the proportions. And
				now we are to tell you what those bounds and middle
				spaces are. And first, concerning the medieties (or mean
				terms); of which that which equally exceeds and is exceeded by the same number is called arithmetical; the
				other, which exceeds and is exceeded by the same proportional part of the extremes, is called sub-contrary. Now
				the extremes and the middle of an arithmetical mediety
				are 6, 9, 12. For 9 exceeds 6 as it is exceeded by 12,
				that is to say, by the number three. The extremes and
				middle of the sub-contrary are 6, 8, 12, where 8 exceeds
				6 by 2, and 12 exceeds 8 by 4; yet 2 is equally the third
				of 6, as 4 is the third of 12. So that in the arithmetical
				mediety the middle exceeds and is exceeded by the same
				number; but in the sub-contrary mediety, the middle term
				wants of one of the extremes, and exceeds the other by
				the same part of each extreme; for in the first 3 is the
				third part of the mean; but in the latter 4 and 2 are third
				parts each of a different extreme. Whence it is called
				sub-contrary. This they also call harmonic, as being that
				whose middle and extremes afford the first concords;
				that is to say, between the highest and lowermost lies the
				diapason, between the highest and the middle lies the diapente, and between the middle and lowermost lies the
				fourth or diatessaron. For suppose the highest extreme
				to be placed at nete and the lowermost at hypate, the
				middle will fall upon mese, making a fifth to the uppermost extreme, but a fourth to the lowermost. So that
				nete answers to 12, mese to 8, and hypate to 6.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Now the more readily to find out these means Eudorus hath taught us an easy method. For after you have proposed the extremities, if you take the half part of each and
				add them together, the product shall be the middle, alike in
				both duple and triple proportions, in arithmetical mediety.
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.344"/>
				
				But as for sub-contrary mediety, in duple proportion, first
				having fixed the extremes, take the third part of the lesser
				and the half of the larger extreme, and the addition of
				both together shall be the middle; in triple proportion,
				the half of the lesser and the third part of the larger extreme shall be the mean. As for example, in triple proportion, let 6 be the least extreme, and 18 the biggest; if
				you take 3 which is the half of 6, and 6 which is the third
				part of 18, the product by addition will be 9, exceeding
				and exceeded by the same proportional parts of the extremes. In this manner the mediums are found out; and
				these are so to be disposed and placed as to fill up the duple
				and triple intervals. Now of these proposed numbers,
				some have no middle space, others have not sufficient.
				Being therefore so augmented that the same proportions
				may remain, they will afford sufficient space for the aforesaid mediums. To which purpose, instead of a unit they
				choose the six, as being the first number including in itself
				a half and third part, and so multiplying all the figures
				below it and above it by 6, they make sufficient room to
				receive the mediums, both in double and triple distances,
				as in the example below:&mdash;
				
				<!--<figure><head>[see figure on page]</head></figure>--></p>
            <p>Now Plato laid down this for a position, that the intervals of sesquialters, sesquiterces, and sesquioctaves having
					once arisen from these connections in the first spaces, the
					Deity filled up all the sesquiterce intervals with sesquioctaves, leaving a part of each, so that the interval left of the
					part should bear the numerical proportion of 256 to 243.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 36 A.</note>
					From these words of Plato they were constrained to enlarge
					their numbers and make them bigger. Now there must be
					two numbers following in order in sesquioctave proportion.
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.345"/>
					
					But the six does not contain a sesquioctave; and if it
					should be cut up into parts and the units bruised into fractions, this would strangely perplex the study of these things.
					Therefore the occasion itself advised multiplication; so
					that, as in changes in the musical scale, the whole scheme
					was extended in agreement with the first (or base) number.
					Eudorus therefore, imitating Crantor, made choice of 384
					for his first number, being the product of 64 multiplied by
					6; which way of proceeding the number 64 led them to
					having for its sesquioctave 72. But it is more agreeable
					to the words of Plato to introduce the half of 384. For
					the remainder of that will bear a sesquioctave proportion
					in those numbers which Plato mentions, 256 and 243, if we
					make use of 192 for the first number. But if the same
					number be made choice of doubled, the remainder (or
					leimma) will have the same proportion, but the numbers
					will be doubled, i.e. 512 and 486. For 256 is in sesquiterce proportion to 192, as 512 to 384. Neither was
					Crantor's reduction of the proportions to this number without reason, which made his followers willing to pursue it;
					in regard that 64 is both the square of the first cube, and
					the cube of the first square; and being multiplied by 3,
					the first odd and trigonal, and the first perfect and sesquialter number, it produces 192, which also has its sesquioctave, as we shall demonstrate.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>But first of all, we shall better understand what this
				leimma or remainder is and what was the opinion of Plato,
				if we do but call to mind what was frequently bandied in
				the Pythagorean schools. For interval in music is all that
				space which is comprehended by two sounds varied in pitch.
				Of which intervals, that which is called a tone is the full
				excess of diapente above diatessaron; and this being divided
				into two parts, according to the opinion of the musicians,
				makes two intervals, both which they call a semitone. But
				the Pythagoreans, despairing to divide a tone into equal
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.346"/>
				
				parts, and therefore perceiving the two divisions to be unequal, called the lesser leimma (or defect), as being lesser
				than the half. Therefore some there are who make the
				diatessaron, which is one of the concords, to consist of two
				tones and a half; others, of two tones and leimma. In
				which case sense seems to govern the musicians, and
				demonstration the mathematicians. The proof by demonstration is thus made out. For it is certain from the
				observation of instruments that the diapason has double
				proportion, the diapente a sesquialter, the diatessaron a
				sesquiterce, and the tone a sesquioctave proportion. Now
				the truth of this will easily appear upon examination, by
				hanging two weights double in proportion to two strings,
				or by making two pipes of equal hollowness double in
				length, the one to the other. For the bigger of the pipes
				will yield the deep sound, as hypate to nete; and of the
				two strings, that which is extended by the double weight
				will be acuter than the other, as nete to hypate; and this
				is a diapason. In the same manner two longitudes or ponderosities, being taken in the proportion of 3:2, will produce a diapente; and three to four will yield a diatessaron;
				of which the latter carries a sesquiterce, the former a sesquialter proportion. But if the same inequality of weight
				or length be so ordered as nine to eight, it will produce a
				tonic interval, no perfect concord, but harmonical enough;
				in regard the strings being struck one after another will
				yield so many musical and pleasing sounds, but all together
				a dull and ungrateful noise. But if they are touched in
				consort, either single or together, thence a delightful melody will charm the ear. Nor is all this less demonstrable
				by reason. For in music, the diapason is composed of the
				diapente and diatessaron. But in numbers, the duple is
				compounded of the sesquialter and sesquiterce. For 12
				is a sesquiterce to 9, but a sesquialter to 8, and a duple to
				6. Therefore is the duple proportion composed of the
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.347"/>
				
				sesquialter and sesquiterce, as the diapason of the diapente
				and diatessaron. For here the diapente exceeds the diatessaron by a tone; there the sesquialter exceeds the sesquiterce by a sesquioctave. Whence it is apparent that
				the diapason carries a double proportion, the diapente a
				sesquialter, the diatessaron a sesquiterce, and the tone a
				sesquioctave.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>This being thus demonstrated, let us see whether
				the sesquioctave will admit a division into two equal parts;
				which if it will not do, neither will a tone. However, in
				regard that 9 and 8, which make the first sesquioctave,
				have no middle interval, but both being doubled, the space
				that falls between causes two intervals, thence it is apparent that, if those distances were equal, the sesquioctave
				also might be divided into equal parts. Now the double
				of 9 is 18, that of 8 is 16, the intermedium 17; by which
				means one of the intervals becomes larger, the other lesser;
				for the first is that of 18 to 17, the second that of 17 to
				16. Thus the sesquioctave proportion not being to be
				otherwise than unequally divided, consequently neither will
				the tone admit of an equal division. So that neither of
				these two sections of a divided tone is to be called a semitone, but according as the mathematicians name it, the
				remainder. And this is that which Plato means, when he
				says, that God, having filled up the sesquiterces with sesquioctaves, left a part of each; of which the proportion is
				the same as of 256 to 243. For admit a diatessaron in two
				numbers comprehending sesquiterce proportion, that is to
				say, in 256 and 192; of which two numbers, let the lesser
				192 be applied to the lowermost extreme, and the bigger
				number 256 to the uppermost extreme of the tetrachord.
				Whence we shall demonstrate that, this space being filled
				up by two sesquioctaves, such an interval remains as lies
				between the numbers 256 and 243. For the lower string
				being forced a full tone upward, which is a sesquioctave, it
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.348"/>
				
				makes 216; and being screwed another tone upward it
				makes 243. Which 243 exceeds 216 by 27, and 216 exceeds 192 by 24. And then again of these two numbers,
				27 is the eighth of 216, and 24 the eighth of 192. So
				the biggest of these two numbers is a sesquioctave to
				the middle, and the middle to the least; and the distance
				from the least to the biggest, that is from 192 to 243, consists of two tones filled up with two sesquioctaves. Which
				being subtracted, the remaining interval of the whole between 243 and 256 is 13, for which reason they called
				this number the remainder. And thus I am apt to believe
				the meaning and opinion of Plato to be most exactly explained in these numbers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Others, placing the two extremes of the diatessaron, the acute part in 288, and the lower sound in 216,
				in all the rest observe the same proportions, only that
				they take the remainder between the two middle intervals.
				For the base, being forced up a whole tone, makes 243;
				and the upper note, screwed downward a full tone, begets 256. Moreover 243 carries a sesquioctave proportion to 216, and 288 to 256; so that each of the intervals
				contains a full tone, and the residue is that which remains
				between 243 and 256, which is not a semitone, but something less. For 288 exceeds 256 by 32, and 243 exceeds
				216 by 27; but 256 exceeds 243 by 13. Now this excess is less than half of the former. So it is plain that the
				diatessaron consists of two tones and the residue, not
				of two tones and a half. Let this suffice for the demonstration of these things. Nor is it a difficult thing to
				believe, by what has been already said, wherefore Plato,
				after he had asserted that the intervals of sesquialter,
				sesquiterce, and sesquioctave had arisen, when he comes
				to fill up the intervals of sesquiterces with sesquioctaves,
				makes not the least mention of sesquialters; for that
				the sesquialter is soon filled up, by adding the sesquiterce
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.349"/>
				
				 to the sesquioctave, or the sesquioctave to the sesquiterce.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>Having therefore shown the manner how to fill up
				the intervals, and to place and dispose the medieties, had
				never any person taken the same pains before, I should
				have recommended the further consideration of it to the
				recreation of your fancies; but in regard that several
				most excellent musicians have made it their business to
				unfold these mysteries with a diligence more than usually
				exact,&mdash;more especially Crantor, Clearchus, and Theodorus, all born in Soli,&mdash;it shall suffice only to show how
				these men differed among themselves. For Theodorus,
				varying from the other two, and not observing two distinct
				files or rows of numbers, but placing the duples and triples
				in a direct line one before another, grounds himself upon
				that division of the substance which Plato calls the division
				in length, making two parts (as it were) out of one, not
				four out of two. Then he says, that the interposition
				of the mediums ought to take place in that manner, to
				avoid the trouble and confusion which must arise from
				transferring out of the first duple into the first triple the
				intervals which are ordained for the supplement of both.
				... But as for those who take Crantor's part, they so
				dispose their numbers as to place planes with planes,
				tetragons with tetragons, cubes with cubes, opposite to
				one another, not taking them in file, but alternatively odd
				to even. [Here is some great defect in the original.]</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>... Which, being in themselves permanently the
				same, afford the form and species; but being subject to
				corporeal division, they become the matter and subject to
				receive the other's impression, the common mixture being
				completed out of both. Now the indivisible substance,
				which is always one and the same, is not to be thought to
				be incapable of division by reason of its smallness, like
				the most minute of bodies, called atoms. But as it is unmixed,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.350"/>
				
				 and not to be any way affected, but pure and altogether of one sort, it is said not to consist of parts, but
				to be indivisible. By means of which purity, when it
				comes in any manner whatsoever to approach and gently
				touch compounded divisible and differing substances, all
				their variety ceases and they crowd together into one habit
				by sympathy and similitude. If now any one will call
				that substance which admits corporeal separation matter, as a nature subject to the former and partaking of it,
				the use of that equivocal term will nothing disadvantage
				our discourse. But they are under a mistake that believe
				the corporeal to be blended with the indivisible matter.
				First, for that Plato does not here make use of any one of
				its names; whereas in other places he calls it the receptacle and nurse, capable of both receiving and fostering the
				vast infinity of created beings; not divisible among bodies,
				but rather the body itself parted and divided into single
				individuals. Then again, what difference would there be
				between the creation of the world and that of the soul, if
				the composition of each proceeded from both matter and
				the intelligible essence? Certainly Plato, as endeavoring to separate the generation of the body from that of
				the soul, tells us that the corporeal part was by God seated
				and deposited within it, and that it was outwardly covered
				and enveloped by it; and after he had thus wrought the
				soul to its perfection out of proportion, he then proceeds
				to this argument concerning matter, of which he had no
				occasion to make mention before when he was producing
				the soul, as being that which had not its existence from
				matter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>The same may be said against the followers of Posidonius. For they seem not altogether to separate the soul
				from matter; but imagining the essence of limitations to
				be divisible in reference to bodies, and intermixing it with
				the intelligible essence, they defined the soul to be an idea
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.351"/>
				
				(or essential form) of that which has extension in every
				direction, subsisting in an harmonical proportion of numbers. For (they say) all mathematical objects are disposed between the first intelligible and sensible beings;
				and since the soul contains the sempiternal nature of
				things intelligible and the pathetic nature of things subjected to sense, it seems but rational that it should consist
				of a substance between both. But they were ignorant
				that God, when the soul was already brought to perfection,
				afterwards making use of the limitations of bodies to form
				and shape the matter, confined and environed the dissipated and fleeting substance within the compass of certain
				surfaces composed of triangles adapted together. And it
				is even more absurd to make the soul an idea. For the
				soul is always in motion; the idea is incapable of motion;
				the one never to be mixed with that which is subjected to
				sense, the other wrought into the substance of the body.
				Moreover, God could be said only to imitate an idea, as his
				pattern; but he was the artificer of the soul, as of a work of
				perfection. Now enough has been already said to show that
				Plato does not assert number to be the substance of the
				soul, only that it is ordered and proportioned by number.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>However this is a common argument against both the
				former opinions, that neither in corporeal limits nor in
				numbers there is the least footstep or appearance of that
				power by which the soul assumes to itself to judge of what
				is subject to sense. For it was the participation of the
				intelligible principle that endued it with understanding and
				the perceiving faculty. But as for opinion, belief, imagination, and its being affected with qualities relating to the
				body, no man could ever dream that they proceeded simply
				either from units, or lines, or surfaces. For not only the
				souls of mortals have a power to judge of what is subject
				to sense; but the soul of the world also, says Plato, <q direct="unspecified">when
					it revolves upon itself, and happens once to touch upon any
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.352"/>
					
					fluid and roving substance or upon any thing indivisible,
					then being moved throughout its whole self, it gives notice
					with what this or that thing is identical, to what heterogeneal, and in what relations especially and in what manner it happens to be and to be affected towards each created
					thing.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 37 A.</note> Here he gives at the same time an intimation of
				the ten Categories or Predicaments; but afterwards he
				gives us a clearer manifestation of these things. <q direct="unspecified">For
					when true reason,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">is fixed upon what is subject
						to sense, and the circle of the Other, observing a just and
						equal motion, conveys its intelligence to the whole soul,
						then both opinion and belief become steadfast and certain;
						on the other side, when it is settled upon ratiocination, and
						the circle of the Same. turning readily and easily, furnishes
						its intimations, then of necessity knowledge arrives to perfection. And indeed, whoever shall affirm that any thing in
						which these two operations take place is any thing besides
						a soul, may deservedly be thought to speak any thing rather
						than the truth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>From whence then does the soul enjoy this motion
					whereby it comprehends what is subject to sense, different
					from that other intelligible motion which ends in knowledge? This is a difficult task to resolve, unless we steadfastly assert that Plato here did not compose the soul, so
					singly considered, but the soul of the world also, of the
					parts above mentioned,&mdash;of the more worthy indivisible
					substance, and of the less worthy divisible in reference
					to bodies. And this soul of the world is no other than
					that motion which gives heat and vigor to thought and
					fancy, and sympathizes with what is subject to sense, not
					created, but existing from eternity, like the other soul. For
					Nature, which had the power of understanding, had also
					the power of opining. But the intelligible power is subject neither to motion nor affection, being established upon
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.353"/>
					
					a substance that is still the same. The other is movable
					and fleeting, as being engaged to an unstable, fluctuating,
					and disunited matter. In regard the sensible substance
					was so far from any order, that it was without shape and
					boundless. So that the power which is fixed in this was
					capable of producing no clear and well-grounded notions
					and no certain or well-ordered movements, but only sleepy
					dreams and deliriums, which amuse and trouble corporeal
					stupidity; unless by accident they lighted upon the more
					worthy substance. For it was in the middle between the
					sensible and discerning faculty, and had a nature conformable and agreeable to both; from the sensible apprehending
					substance, and borrowing from judgment its power of discerning things intelligible.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>And this the express words of Plato declare.
				<q direct="unspecified">For this is my opinion,</q> saith he, <q direct="unspecified">in short, that
					being, place, and generation were three distinct things
					even before the heavens were created.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 52 D.</note> By place he
				means matter, as being the seat and receptacle; by being or existence, the intelligible nature; and by generation, the world not being yet created, he designs only that
				substance which was subject to change and motion, disposed between the forming cause and the thing formed,
				transmitting hither those shapes and figures which were
				there contrived and moulded. For which reason it was
				called divisible; there being a necessity of distributing
				sense to the sensitive, and imagination to the imaginative
				faculty. For the sensitive motion, being proper to the
				soul, directs itself to that which is outwardly sensible. As
				for the understanding, it was fixed and immovable of itself,
				but being settled in the soul and becoming its lord and
				governor, it turns upon itself, and accomplishes a circular
				motion about that which is always permanent, chiefly laboring to apply itself to the eternally durable substance.
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.354"/>
				
				With great difficulty therefore did they admit a conjunction,
				till the divisible at length intermixing with the indivisible,
				and the restlessly hurried with the sleepy and motionless,
				constrained the Other to meet and join with the Same.
				Yet the Other was not motion, as neither was the Same
				stability, but the principle of distinction and diversity.
				For both the one and the other proceed from a different
				principle; the Same from the unit, the Other from the
				duad; and these were first intermixed with the soul, being
				fastened and bound together by number, proportion, and
				harmonical mediums; so that the Other being riveted into
				the Same begets diversity and disagreement; and the
				Same being fermented into the Other produces order.
				And this is apparent from the first powers of the soul,
				which are judgment and motion. Motion immediately
				shows itself in the heavens, giving us an example of
				diversity in identity by the circumvolution of the fixed
				stars, and of identity in diversity by the order of the
				planets. For in them the Same bears the chiefest sway;
				in terrestrial bodies, the contrary principle. Judgment
				has two principles,&mdash;understanding from the Same, to
				judge of things in general, and sense from the Other, to
				judge of things in particular. Reason is a mixture of
				both, becoming intellect in reference to things intelligible,
				and opinion in things subject to sense; making use of the
				interdisposed organs of imagination and memory, of which
				these in the Same produce the Other, and those in the
				Other make the Same. For understanding is the motion
				of the considerative faculty about that which is permanent
				and stable. Opinion is a continuance of the perceptive
				faculty upon that which is continually in motion. But as
				for fancy or imagination, being a connection of opinion
				with sense, the Same has placed it in the memory; and
				the Other moves it again in the difference between past
				and present, touching at the same time upon diversity
				and identity.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.355"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>But now let us take a draught of the corresponding
				composition of the soul from the structure of the body of
				the universe. There we find fire and earth, whose nature
				is such as not to admit of mixture one with another but
				with great difficulty, or rather is altogether obstinately
				refractory to mixture and constancy. God therefore, placing air and water in the middle between both,&mdash;the air
				next the fire, the water next the earth,&mdash;first of all tempered the middlemost one with another, and next, by the
				assistance of these two, he brought the two extreme elements not only to mix with the middlemost, but also to a
				mutual closure or conjunction between themselves. Then
				he drew together those contrary powers and opposing extremes, the Same and the Other, not immediately, the one
				adjoining to the other, but placing other substances between; the indivisible next the Same, and the divisible
				next the Other, disposing each to each in convenient order,
				and mixing the extremes with the middlemost. After
				which manner he interweaved and tissued the whole into
				the form and composition of the soul, completing, as far as
				it was possible, similitude out of things different and various, and one out of many. Therefore it is alleged by some,
				that Plato erroneously affirmed the nature of the Other to
				be an enemy to mixture, as being not only capable to receive it, but a friend of change. Whereas that should
				have been rather said of the nature of the Same; which,
				being stable and an utter adversary to mutability, is so far
				from an easy and willing condescension to mixture, that it
				flies and abhors it, to the end it may preserve itself pure
				and free from alteration. But they who make these objections against Plato betray their own ignorance, not
				understanding that the Same is the idea (or essential form)
				of those things that always continue in the same state and
				condition, and that the Other is the idea of those things
				which are subject to be variously affected; and that it is the
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.356"/>
				
				peculiar nature of the one to disjoin and separate into
				many parts whatever it happens to lay hold upon, and of
				the other to cement and assimilate scattered substances, till
				they resume one particular form and efficacy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>And these are the powers and virtues of the soul
				of the universe. And when they once enter into the organs of corruptible bodies, being themselves incorruptible, there the form of the binary and boundless principle
				shows itself most briskly, while that of the unmixed and
				purer principle lies as it were dormant in obscurity. And
				thus it happens, that a man shall rarely observe any human passion or motion of the understanding, void of
				reason, where there shall not something appear either
				of desire or emulation, joy or grief. Several philosophers
				therefore will have the passions to be so many sorts of
				reasonings, seeing that desire, grief, and anger are all the
				effects of judgment. Others allege the virtues themselves
				to be derived from passions; fortitude depending on fear,
				temperance on voluptuousness, and justice on love of gain.
				Now the soul being both speculative and practical, contemplating as well generals as particulars, and seeming to
				comprehend the one by the assistance of the intellect and
				the other by the aid of sense, common reason, which encounters the Same in the Other and the Other in the Same,
				endeavors by certain limits and distinctions to separate one
				from many and the divisible from the indivisible; but she
				cannot accomplish her design nor be purely in one or the
				other, in regard the principles are so oddly interwoven and
				intermixed and confusedly huddled together.</p>
            <p>For this reason did God constitute a receptacle for the
					Same and the Other, out of the indivisible and divisible
					substance, to the end there might be order in variety.
					Now this was generation. For without this the Same could
					have no variety, and therefore no motion or generation;
					and the Other could have no order, and therefore no consistence
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.357"/>
					
					 or generation. For should we grant the Same to
					be different from the Other, and the Other to be the Same
					with itself, such a commixture would produce nothing
					generative, but would want a third something, like matter, to receive both and be disposed of by both. And this
					is that matter which God first composed, when he bounded
					the movable nature of bodies by the steadfastness of
					things intelligible.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Now then, as voice, merely voice, is only an insignificant and brutish noise, but speech is the expression
				of the mind by significant utterance; as harmony consists
				of sounds and intervals,&mdash;a sound being always one and
				the same, and an interval being the difference and diversity of sounds, while both being mixed together produce air and melody;&mdash;thus the passive nature of the
				soul was without limits and unstable, but afterwards became determinate, when limits were set and a certain form
				was given to the divisible and manifold variety of motion.
				Thus having comprised the Same and the Other, by the
				similitudes and dissimilitudes of numbers which produce
				concord out of disagreement, it becomes the life of the
				world, sober and prudent, harmony itself, and reason
				overruling necessity mixed with persuasion. This necessity is by most men called fate or destiny, by Empedocles
				friendship and discord, by Heraclitus the opposite straining harmony of the world, as of a bow or harp, by Parmenides light and darkness, by Anaxagoras mind and
				infinity, by Zoroaster God and Daemon, naming one Oromasdes, the other Arimanius. Though as for Euripides,
				he makes use of the disjunctive erroneously for the copulative, where he says,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Jove, whether he be
				</l>
                     <l>Necessity, that Nature's force controls,
				</l>
                     <l>Or the intelligence of human souls.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For, indeed, the powers which bear dominion over the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.358"/>
					
					universe are necessity and wisdom. This is that therefore
					which the Egyptians intimate in their fables, feigning that,
					when Horus was punished and dismembered, he bequeathed
					his spirit and blood to his father, but his flesh and his fat
					to his mother. There is no part of the soul which remains
					pure and unmixed, or separate from the rest; for, according to the opinion of Heraclitus, <q direct="unspecified">harmony latent is of
						greater value than that which is visible,</q> as being that
					wherein the blending Deity concealed and sunk all varieties and dissimilitudes. Nevertheless, there appears in
					the irrational part a turbulent and boisterous temerity;
					in the rational part, an orderly and well-marshalled prudence; in the sensitive part, the constraint of necessity;
					but in the understanding, entire and perfect command of
					itself. The limiting and bounding power sympathizes
					with the whole and the indivisible, by reason of the nearness of their relations; on the other side, the dividing
					power fixes itself upon particulars, by virtue of the divisible substance; and the whole rejoices at the mutation of
					the Same by means of the Other, as occasion requires. In
					the like manner, the various inclinations of men to virtue
					and vice, to pleasure and toil, as also the enthusiasms and
					raptures of lovers, the combats of honor with lustful desires, plainly demonstrate the mixture of the divine and
					impassible with the moral and corporeal part; of which
					Plato himself calls the one concupiscence of pleasures,
					natural to ourselves; the other an opinion introduced from
					without, aspiring to the chiefest good. For passible qualities of the soul arise from herself; but she participates
					of understanding, as being infused from without, by the
					more worthy principle.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Nor is the celestial nature privileged from this
				double society and communion. For sometimes it is seen
				to incline one way or the other, but it is set right again
				by the more powerful revolution of the Same, and governs
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.359"/>
				
				the world. Nay, there shall come a time, as it has happened already, when the world's moving wisdom shall
				grow dull and drowsy, drowned in oblivion of its own
				duty; while that which is familiar and agreeable to the
				body from the beginning draws and winds back the right-hand motion of the universe, causing the wheels to go
				slow and heavy. Yet shall it not be able to dash in pieces
				the whole movement, for that the better part, rousing and
				recollecting herself and observing the pattern and exemplar of God, shall with his aid reduce all things again
				into their former order. Thus it is demonstrable by many
				proofs, that the soul was not altogether the workmanship
				of the Deity, but that having in itself a certain portion of
				innate evil, it was by him digested and beautified who
				limited infinity by unity, to the end it might be a substance within the compass of certain limits; intermixing
				order and mutation, variety and resemblance, by the force
				of the Same and the Other; and lastly working into all
				these, as far as it was possible, a mutual community and
				friendship by the assistance of numbers and harmony.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Concerning which things, although you have heard
				frequent discourses, and have likewise read several arguments and disputes committed to writing upon the same
				subjects, it will not be amiss for me also to give a short
				account, after a brief repetition of Plato's own words.
				<q direct="unspecified">God,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">in the first place withdrew one part
					from the whole; which done, he took away the double of
					that; then a third part, sesquialter in proportion to the
					second, and triple to the first; then a fourth part, double
					to the second; next a fifth part, being the triple of the
					third; then a sixth, eight times the first; and lastly a
					seventh, being twenty-seven times the first. This done,
					he filled up the duple and triple intervals, retrenching
					also from thence certain other particles, and placing them
					in the midst of those intervals; so that in every interval
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.360"/>
					
					there might be two medieties, the one exceeding and being
					exceeded by one and the same part of the extremes, the
					other exceeding and being exceeded by the same number.
					Now in regard that from these connections in the first
					spaces there arose the intervals of sesquialters, sesquiterces, and sesquioctaves, he filled up all the sesquiterce
					intervals with sesquioctaves, leaving a part of each, so
					that the interval left of the part might bear the numerical proportion of 256 to 243.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Timaeus, p. 35 B.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Here the question will be first concerning the quantity,
					next concerning the order, and in the third place concerning the force and virtue of the numbers. As to the quantity, we are to consider which he takes in the double and
					triple intervals. As to the order, whether they are to be
					placed in one row, according to the direction of Theodorus,
					or (as Crantor will have them) in the form of a <foreign lang="greek">*l</foreign>, placing
					the unit at the top, and the duples and triples apart by
					themselves in two several files. Lastly, we are to examine
					of what use and virtue they are in the structure and composition of the soul.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>As to the first, we shall relinquish the opinion of
				those who affirm that it is enough, in proportions, to consider the nature of the intervals, and of the medieties
				which fill up their vacancies; and that the demonstration
				can be made out for any numbers whatsoever that have
				spaces sufficient to receive the aforesaid proportions. For
				this being granted, it makes the demonstration obscure,
				without the help of schemes, and drives us from another
				theory, which carries with it a delight not unbecoming
				philosophy.</p>
            <p>Beginning therefore from the unit, let us place
					the duples and triples apart; and there will be
					on the one side, 2, 4, 8; on the other 3, 9, 27;
					&mdash;seven numbers in all, proceeding forward by
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.361"/>
					
					multiplication four steps from the unit, which is assumed
					as the common base.... For not only here, but upon
					other occasions, the sympathy of the quaternary number
					with the septenary is apparent. There is this peculiar to
					that tetractys or quaternary number thirty six, so much
					celebrated by the Pythagoreans, which is more particularly
					worthy admiration,&mdash;that it is composed of the first four
					even numbers and the first four odd numbers; and it is the
					fourth connection made of numbers put together in order.
					The first connection is of one and two; the second of odd
					numbers.... For placing the unit, which is common to
					both, before, he first takes eight and then twenty-seven, as
					it were pointing out with the finger where to place each
					particular sort.</p>
            <p>[These places are so depraved in the original, that the
					sense is lost.]</p>
            <p>But it belongs to others to explain these things more accurately and distinctly; while we content ourselves with only
					what remains, as peculiarly proper to the subject in hand.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>For it was not out of vain-glory, to boast his skill in
				the mathematical sciences, that Plato inserted in a treatise
				of natural philosophy this discourse of harmonical and
				arithmetical medieties, but believing them both apt and
				convenient to demonstrate the structure and composition
				of the soul. For some there are who seek these proportions in the swift motions of the spheres of the planets;
				others rather in the distances, others in the magnitude of
				the stars; others, more accurate and nice in their enquiry,
				seek for the same proportions in the diameters of the
				epicycles; as if the Supreme Architect, for the sake of
				these, had adapted the soul, divided into seven parts, to
				the celestial bodies. Many also there are, who hither
				transfer the inventions of the Pythagoreans, tripling the
				distances of bodies from the middle. This is done by
				placing the unit next the fire; three next the Antichthon,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.362"/>
				
				or earth which is opposite to our earth; nine next the
				Earth; 27 next the Moon; 81 next to Mercury; 243 upon
				Venus; and 729 upon the Sun. The last (729) is both a
				tetragonal and cubical number, whence it is, that they also
				call the sun a tetragon and a cube. By this way of tripling they also reduce the other stars to proportion. But
				these people may be thought to dote and to wander very
				much from reason, if there be any use of geometrical
				demonstration, since by their mistakes we find that the
				most probable proofs proceed from thence; and although
				geometers do not always make out their positions exactly,
				yet they approach the nearest to truth when they say that
				the diameter of the sun, compared with the diameter of
				the earth, bears the proportion of 12 to 1; while the diameter of the earth to that of the moon carries a triple proportion. And for that which appears to be the least of the
				fixed stars, the diameter of it is no less than the third part
				of the diameter of the earth, and the whole globe of the earth
				to the whole globe of the moon is as twenty-seven to one.
				The diameters of Venus and the earth bear a duple, the
				globes or spheres of both an octave proportion. The
				width of the shadow which causes an eclipse holds a triple
				proportion to the diameter of the moon; and the deviation
				of the moon from the middle of the signs, either to the
				one or the other side, is a twelfth part. Her positions as to
				the sun, either in triangular or quadrangular distances, give
				her the form when she appears as in the first quarter and
				gibbous; but when she comes to be quite round, that is,
				when she has run through half the signs, she then makes
				(as it were) a kind of diapason harmony with six notes. But
				in regard the motions of the sun are slowest when he arrives
				at the solstices, and swiftest when he comes to the equinoxes, by which he takes from the day or adds to the
				night, the proportion holds thus. For the first thirty days
				after the winter solstice, he adds to the day a sixth part of
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.363"/>
				
				the length whereby the longest night exceeds the shortest;
				the next thirty days he adds a third part; to all the rest
				till the equinox he adds a half; and so by sextuple and
				triple distances he makes even the irregularity of time.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Chaldaeans make the spring to hold the
					proportion of a diatessaron to autumn; of a diapente to
					the winter, and of a diapason to the summer. But if
					Euripides rightly divides the year, where he says,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Four months the parching heats of summer reign,
					</l>
                     <l>And four of hoary winter's cold complain;
					</l>
                     <l>Two months doth vernal pride the fields array,
					</l>
                     <l>And two months more to autumn tribute pay,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>then the seasons shall be said to change in octave proportion.</p>
            <p>Others there are, who fancy the earth to be in the lowest string of the harp, called proslambanomenos; and so
					proceeding, they place the moon in hypate, Mercury and
					Venus in the diatoni and lichani; the sun they likewise
					place in mese, as in the midst of the diapason, a fifth
					above the earth and a fourth from the sphere of the fixed
					stars.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>But neither doth this pleasant conceit of the latter
				come near the truth, neither do the former attain perfect
				accuracy. However, they who will not allow the latter to
				depend upon Plato's sentiments will yet grant the former
				to partake of musical proportions; so that, there being five
				tetrachords, called <foreign lang="greek">u(pa/twn, me/swn, sunhmme/nwn, diezeugme/nwn</foreign>, and
				<foreign lang="greek">u(perbolai/wn</foreign>, in these five distances they place all the planets;
				making the first tetrachord from the Moon to the Sun and
				the planets which move with the Sun, that is, Mercury and
				Venus; the next from the Sun to the fiery planet of Mars;
				the third between this and Jupiter; the fourth from thence
				to Saturn; and the fifth from Saturn to the sphere of the
				fixed stars. So that the sounds and notes which bound the
				five tetrachords bear the same proportion with the intervals
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.364"/>
				
				 of the planets. Still further, we know that the
				ancient musicians had two notes called hypate, three called
				nete, one mese, and one paramese, thus confining their
				scale to seven standing notes, equal in number to the number of the planets. But the moderns, adding the proslambanomenos, which is a full tone in descent from hypate,
				have multiplied the scheme into the double diapason, and
				thereby confounded the natural order of the concords; for
				the diapente happens to be before the diatessaron, with the
				addition of the whole tone in the bass. Whereas Plato
				makes his addition in the upper part; for in his Republic<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">X. p. 617 B.</note>
				he says, that every one of the eight spheres rolls about a
				Siren which is fixed upon each of the tuneful globes, and
				that they all sing one counterpoint without diversity of
				modulation, taking every one their peculiar concords,
				which together complete a melodious consort.</p>
            <p>These Sirens sing for their pleasure divine and heavenly
					tunes, and accompany their sacred circuit and dance with
					an harmonious song of eight notes. Nor was there necessity of a fuller chorus, in regard that within the confines
					of eight notes lay the first bounds and limits of all duple
					and triple proportions; the unit being added to both the
					even and odd numbers. And certainly from hence it was
					that the ancients raised their invention of nine Muses; of
					which eight were employed in celestial affairs, as Plato
					said; the ninth was to take care of things terrestrial, and
					to reduce and reform the inequality and confusion of error
					and jarring variance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>Now then consider whether the soul does not roll
				and turn and manage the heavens and the celestial bodies
				by means of those harmonious concords and equal motions
				that are wrought and fermented within her, being herself
				most wise and most just. And such she became by virtue of harmonical proportions, whose images representing
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.365"/>
				
				things incorporeal are imprinted into the discernible and
				visible parts and bodies of the world. But the chief and
				most predominating power is visibly mixed in the soul,
				which renders her harmonious and obedient to herself, the
				other parts unanimously yielding to her as the most supreme and the divinest part of all. For the Sovereign
				Artificer and Creator finding a strange disorder and erroneous confusion in the motions of the decomposed and
				unruly soul, which was still at variance with herself, some
				things he divided and separated, others he brought together and reconciled to a mutual sympathy, making use
				of harmony and numbers. By virtue of which, the slightest and meanest of insensible substances, even stocks and
				stones, the rinds of trees, and sometimes even the rennets
				of beasts, by various mixtures, compositions, and temperatures, may become the charming objects of the sight, or
				afford most pleasing perfumes and wholesome medicaments
				for the relief of mankind, or be wrought and hollowed to
				send forth pleasing musical sounds. And for this reason
				it was that Zeno of Citium encouraged and persuaded
				youth to frequent the theatres, there to observe the variety
				of melodious sounds that proceeded from horns or cornets,
				wooden hautboys, flutes and reeds, or any other musical
				instruments to which the contrivance of art had rightly
				applied the reason of number and proportion. Not that
				we will here maintain, with the Pythagoreans, that all
				things resemble number, for that requires a long discourse
				to prove it. But where mutual society and sympathy arise
				out of discord and dissimilitude, that the cause of this is
				moderation and order, produced by the power of harmony
				and number, was a thing not concealed even from the
				poets. And these give to what is friendly and kind the
				epithet <q direct="unspecified">evenly fitted;</q> while, on the other side, men of
				rugged and malicious dispositions they called <q direct="unspecified">unevenly
					tempered,</q> as if enmity and discord were nothing but a
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.366"/>
				
				sort of a disproportion. For this reason, he who writes
				Pindar's elegy gives him this encomium,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">To foreigners agreeable, to citizens a friend;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <foreign lang="greek">)/*armenos h(n cei/noisin a)nh\r o(/de, kai\ fi/los a)stoi=s</foreign>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>the poet plainly inferring complacency of humor and the
					aptitude of a person to fit himself to all tempers to be an
					excellency aspiring to virtue itself. Which Pindar himself also testifies, saying of Cadmus, that he listened to
					true music from Apollo himself.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Boeckh's note on Pindar, Frag. 8. The quotation from Pindar is corrupt; but the sense given above is derived from other quotations of the same passage. (G.)</note> Nor must we believe
					that the theologists, who were the most ancient philosophers, ordered the pictures and statues of the Gods to be
					made with musical instruments in their hands because they
					thought the Gods no better than pipers or harpers, but to
					signify that no work was so becoming to the Gods as
					accord and harmony.</p>
            <p>Now then, as it would be absurd and ridiculous for any
					man to search for sesquiterces, sesquialters, and duples in
					the neck, or belly, or sides of a lute or harp,&mdash;though
					every one of these must also be allowed their symmetry
					of length and thickness,&mdash;the harmony and proportion of
					concords being to be sought for in the sound; so it is most
					probable that the bodies of the stars, the distances of
					spheres, and the swiftness of the motions and revolutions,
					have their sundry proportions, as well one to another as to
					the whole fabric, like instruments of music well set and
					tuned, though the measure of the quantity be unknown to
					us. However, we are to imagine that the principal effect
					and efficacy of these numbers and proportions, which the
					Supreme Architect made use of, is that same agreement,
					harmony, and consent of the soul with itself, by means of
					which she replenished the heavens themselves, when she
					came to actuate and perform her office there, with so
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.367"/>
					
					many infinite beauties, and by which she governs the
					earth by virtue of the several seasons, and other alterations wisely and artificially measured and varied as well
					for the generation as preservation of all terrestrial productions.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>