<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De vitioso pudore</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.104">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.60"/>
         <head>Of bashfulness.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Some plants there are, in their own nature wild and
				barren, and hurtful to seed and garden-sets, which yet
				among able husbandmen pass for infallible signs of a rich
				and promising soil. In like manner, some passions of the
				mind not good in themselves yet serve as first shoots and
				promises of a disposition which is naturally good, and also
				capable of much improvement by cultivation. Among
				these I rank bashfulness, the subject of our present discourse; no ill sign indeed, but the cause and occasion of
				a great deal of harm. For the bashful oftentimes run into
				the same enormities as the most hardened and impudent,
				with this difference only, that the former feel a regret for
				such miscarriages, but the latter take a pleasure and satisfaction therein. The shameless person is without sense of
				grief for his baseness, and the bashful is in distress at the
				very appearance of it. For bashfulness is only modesty
				in the excess, and is aptly enough named <foreign lang="greek">duswpi/a</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">the
					being put out of countenance</hi>), since the face is in some
				sense confused and dejected with the mind. For as that
				grief which casts down the eyes is termed dejection, so
				that kind of modesty which cannot look another in the
				face is called bashfulness. The orator, speaking of a
				shameless fellow, said he carried harlots, not virgins, in
				his eyes;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">*ou) ko/ras a)lla\ po/rnas. *ko/rh</foreign> means either <hi rend="italics">maiden</hi> or <hi rend="italics">the pupil of the eye.</hi> (G.)</note> on the other hand, the sheepishly bashful betrays
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.61"/>
				
				 no less the effeminacy and softness of his mind in
				his looks, palliating his weakness, which exposes him to
				the mercy of impudence, with the specious name of modesty. Cato indeed was wont to say of young persons, he
				had a greater opinion of such as were subject to color than
				of those that looked pale; teaching us thereby to look with
				greater apprehension on the heinousness of an action than
				on the reprimand which might follow, and to be more afraid
				of the suspicion of doing an ill thing than of the danger
				of it. However, too much anxiety and timidity lest we
				may do wrong is also to be avoided; because many men
				have become cowards and been deterred from generous
				undertakings, no less for fear of calumny and detraction
				than by the danger or difficulty of such attempts.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>While therefore we must not suffer the weakness in
				the one case to pass unnoticed, neither must we abet or
				countenance invincible impudence in the other, such as is
				reported of Anaxarchus,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Whose dog-like carriage and effrontery,</l>
					             <l>Despising infamy, out-faced disgrace.</l>
               </quote>
				
				A convenient mien between both is rather to be endeavored after, by repressing the over impudent, and animating the too meek temper. But as this kind of
				cure is difficult, so is the restraining such excesses not
				without danger; for as a gardener, in stubbing up
				some wild or useless bushes, makes at them carelessly with his spade, or burns them off the ground, but
				in dressing a vine, or grafting an apple, or pruning an
				olive, carries his hand with the greatest wariness and deliberation, that he may not unluckily injure the tree; so a
				philosopher, in removing envy, that useless and untractable
				plant, or covetousness or immoderate love of pleasure from
				the mind of youth, may cut deep safely, and make a large
				scar; but if he be to apply his discourse to some more sensible or delicate part, such as the restraining excess of
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.62"/>
				
				bashfulness, it lies upon him to be very careful not to cut off
				or eradicate modesty with the contrary vice. For nurses who
				too often wipe away the dirt from their infants are apt to
				tear their flesh and put them to pain. And in like manner we must not so far extirpate all bashfulness in youth as
				to leave them careless or impudent; but as those that pull
				down private houses adjoining to the temples of the Gods
				prop up such parts as are contiguous to them, so in undermining bashfulness, due regard is to be had to adjacent
				modesty, good nature, and humanity. And yet these are
				the very qualities by which bashfulness insinuates itself
				and becomes fixed in a man, flattering him that he is good-natured, courteous, and civil, and has common sense, and
				that he is not obstinate and inexorable. The Stoics, therefore, in their discourses of modesty, distinguish all along
				betwixt that and bashfulness, leaving not so much as
				ambiguity of terms for a pretence to the vice. However, asking their good leave, we shall make bold to use
				such words indifferently in either sense; or rather we
				shall follow the example of Homer, whose authority we
				have for it, that
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Much harm oft-times from modesty befalls,</l>
					             <l>Much good oft-times.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Il. XXIV. 44.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				And it was not done amiss of him to make mention of
				the hurtfulness of it first, because modesty becomes profitable only through reason, which cuts off what is superfluous and leaves a just mean behind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>In the first place, therefore, the bashful man must be
				persuaded and satisfied that that distemper of the mind is
				prejudicial to him, and that nothing which is so can be
				eligible. And withal, he must be cautious how he suffers
				himself to be cajoled and led by the nose with the titles
				of courteous or sociable, in exchange for those of grave,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.63"/>
				
				great, and just; nor like Pegasus in Euripides, who, when
				Bellerophon mounted him,
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>With trembling stooped more than his lord desired,</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Eurip. Bellerophon, Frag. 311.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				must he debase himself and yield to all who make their
				addresses to him, for fear of appearing hard and ungentle.</p>
            <p>It is recorded of Bocchoris, king of Egypt, a man of a
					very cruel nature, that the goddess Isis sent a kind of a
					serpent (called aspis), which winding itself about his head
					cast a shadow over him from above, and was a means to
					him of determining causes according to equity. But bashfulness, on the contrary, happening upon remiss and spiritless tempers, suffers them not to express their dislike of
					any thing or to argue against it, but perverts many times the
					sentence of arbitrators, and stops the mouths of skilful
					pleaders, forcing them often to act and speak contrary to
					their conviction. And the most reckless man will always
					tyrannize and domineer over such a one, forcing his bashfulness by his own strength of impudence. Upon this
					account it is that bashfulness, like a low piece of soft
					ground, can make no resistance and decline no encounter,
					but is exposed to the meanest actions and vilest passions.
					But, above all, this is the worst guardian of raw and inexperienced youth. For, as Brutus said, he seems to have
					had but an ill education that has not learned to deny any'
					thing. And no better overseer is it of the marriage-bed
					or the woman's apartment; as the repentant lady in
					Sophocles accuses the spark that had debauched her,&mdash;
					
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thy tongue, thy flattering tongue prevailed.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Sophocles, Frag. 772.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
					
					So this vice, happening upon a disposition inclinable to
					debauchery, prepares and opens the way, and leaves all
					things easy and accessible to such as are ready to prefer
					their wicked designs. Presents and treats are irresistible
					baits for common mercenary creatures; but importunity,
					
					<pb id="v.1.p.64"/>
					
					befriended with bashfulness on their side, has sometimes
					undone the modestest women. I omit what inconveniences
					this kind of modesty occasions, when it obliges men to
					lend their money to such whose credit is blown upon in
					the world, or to give bail for those they dare not trust;
					we do this, it is true, with an ill-will, and in our heart
					reflect upon that old saying, Be bail, and pay for it, yet
					cannot make use of it in our practice.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>How many this fault.has ruined, it is no easy thing
				to recount. Creon in the play gave a very good lesson for
				others to follow, when he told Medea,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>'Tis better now to brave thy direst hate,</l>
					             <l>Than curse a foolish easiness too late.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Eurip. Medea, 290.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				Yet afterwards, being wrought upon through his bashfulness to grant her but one day longer, he ruined himself
				and family by it. For the same reason, some, suspecting
				designs against them of murder or poisoning, have neglected to provide for their safety. Thus Dion could not
				be ignorant of the treachery of Callippus, yet thought it
				unfit to entertain such thoughts of his pretended friend and
				guest, and so perished. So again, Antipater, the son of
				Cassander, having entertained Demetrius at supper, and
				being engaged by him for the next night, because he was
				unwilling to distrust one who had trusted him, went, and
				had his throat cut after supper. Polysperchon had promised Cassander for an hundred talents to murder Hercules, the son of Alexander by Barsine. Upon this he
				invites him to sup; but the young man, having some
				suspicion of the thing, pretends himself indisposed. Polysperchon coming to him said: Sir, above all things endeavor after your father's courteous behavior and obliging
				way to his friends, unless haply you look on us with suspicion as if we were compassing your health. The young
				man out of mere modesty was prevailed upon to go, and
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.65"/>
				
				was strangled as he sat at meat. It is not therefore (as
				some will have us believe) insignificant or ridiculous, but
				on the contrary very wise advice, which Hesiod gives,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Welcome a friend, but never call thy foe.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Hesiod, Works and Days, 342</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Be not bashful and mealy-mouthed in refusing him that
					you are satisfied has a pique against you; but never reject
					him that seemeth to put his trust in you. For if you
					invite, you must expect to be invited again; and some
					time or other your entertainment will be repaid you, if
					bashfulness have once softened or turned the edge of that
					diffidence which ought to be your guard.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>To the end therefore that we may get the better of
				this disease, which is the cause of so many evils, we must
				make our first attempts (as our custom is in other things)
				upon matters of no great difficulty. As, if one drink to
				you after you have taken what is sufficient, be not so foolishly modest to do violence to your nature, but rather
				venture to pass the glass. Another, it may be, would tempt
				you to play at dice while drinking; be not over-persuaded
				into a compliance, for fear of being the subject of his
				drollery, but reply with Xenophanes, when Lasus of
				Hermione called him coward because he refused to play
				at dice: Yes, said he, I confess myself the greatest coward in the world, for I dare not do an ill thing. Again,
				you light upon an impertinent talker, that sticks upon you
				like a burr; don't be bashful, but break off the discourse.
				and pursue your business. These evasions and repulses,
				whereby our resolution and assurance are exercised in matters of less moment, will accustom us to it by degrees in
				greater occasions. And here it will be but seasonable to
				give you a passage, as it is recorded of Demosthenes. The
				Athenians having one time been moved to send succors to
				Harpalus, and themselves to engage in a war against Alexander, it happened that Philoxenus, Alexander's admiral,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.66"/>
				
				unexpectedly arrived on their coast; and the people being
				so astonished as to be speechless for very fear, Demosthenes cried out: How would they endure the sun, who
				are not able to look against a lamp! Or how would
				you comport yourself in weightier concerns, while you
				prince or the people had an awe over you, if you cannot
				refuse a glass of wine when an acquaintance offers it, or
				turn off an impertinent babbler, but suffer the eternal
				trifler to walk over you without telling him, Another time,
				good sir, at present I am in haste.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Besides all this, the exercising such a resolution is
				of great use in praising others. If one of my friend's
				harpers play lewdly, or a comedian he has hired at a
				great rate murder a piece of Menander in the acting,
				although the vulgar clap their hands and admire, I think
				it no moroseness or ill-breeding to sit silently all the while,
				without servilely joining in the common applauses contrary to my judgment. For if you scruple to deal openly
				with him in these cases, what will you do, should he repeat
				to you an insipid composition of his own, or submit to your
				revisal a ridiculous oration? You will applaud, of course,
				and enter yourself into the list of common parasites and
				flatterers! But how then can you direct him impartially
				in the greatest administrations of his life? how be free with
				him where he fails in any duties of his trust or marriage,
				or neglects the offices incumbent on him as a member of
				the community? I must confess, I cannot by any means
				approve of the reply Pericles made to a friend who besought him to give false evidence, and that too upon oath,
				when he thus answered: As far as the altar I am wholly
				at your service. Methinks he went too far. But he that
				has long before accustomed himself not to commend any
				thing against his judgment, or applaud an ill voice, or
				seem pleased with indecent scurrilities, will never suffer
				things to come to that issue; nor will any one be so bold
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.67"/>
				
				as to solicit him in this manner: Swear on my side, give
				false evidence, or bring in an unjust verdict.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>After the same manner we may learn to refuse such
				as come to borrow considerable sums of us, if we have used
				to deny in little matters where refusal is easy. As Archelaus, king of Macedon, sat at supper, one of his retinue, a
				fellow who thought there was nothing so honest as to receive, begged of him a golden cup. But the king commanded a waiter to give it immediately to Euripides: For
				you, sir, said he, are fit indeed to ask any thing, but to receive nothing; and he deserves to receive, though he lacks
				the confidence to ask. Thus wisely did he make his judgment, and not bashful timidity, his guide in bestowing favors.
				Yet we oftentimes, when the honesty, nearness, and necessities of our friends and relations are not motives sufficient
				to prevail with us to their relief, can give profusely to impudence and importunity, not out of any willingness to
				bestow our money so ill, but merely for want of confidence
				and resolution to deny. This was the case of Antigonus
				the elder. Being wearied out with the importunity of Bias,
				Give, said he to his servants, one talent to Bias and necessity. Yet at other times he was as expert at encountering
				such addresses as any prince, and dismissed them with as
				remarkable answers. Thus a certain Cynic one day begging of him a groat, he made answer, That is not for a
				prince to give. And the poor man replying, Then bestow
				a talent, he reparteed briskly, Nor that for a Cynic (or, for
				a dog) to receive. Diogenes went about begging to all the
				statues in the Ceramicus; and his answer to some that
				wondered at his fancy in it was, he was practising how to
				bear a repulse. But indeed it chiefly lies upon us to exercise ourselves in smaller matters to refuse an unreasonable
				request, that we may not be at loss how to refuse on occasions of greater magnitude. For no one, as Demosthenes
				says, who has spent all the money that he had in unnecessary
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.68"/>
				
				 expenses, will have plenty of money that he has not
				for his necessary expenses.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosth. Olynth. III. p. 33, 25. &sect; 19.</note> And our disgrace is increased
				many fold, if we want what is necessary or decent, and
				abound in trifles and fopperies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Yet bashfulness is not only a bad steward of our estate, but even in weightier concerns it refuses to hearken to
				the wholesome advice of right reason. Thus, in a dangerous fit of sickness, we send not to the ablest physician, for
				fear of giving offence to another of our acquaintance. Or,
				in taking tutors and governors for our children, we make
				choice of such as obtrude themselves upon us, not such as
				are better qualified for that service. Or, in our lawsuits,
				we regard not to obtain counsel learned in the law, because we must gratify the son of some friend or relation,
				and give him an opportunity to show himself in the world.
				Nay, lastly, you shall find some that bear the name of
				philosophers, who call themselves Epicureans or Stoics, not
				out of choice, or upon the least conviction, but merely
				to oblige their friends or acquaintance, who have taken
				advantage of their modesty. Since then the case is so
				with us, we ought to prepare and exercise ourselves in
				things that we daily meet with and of course, not so much
				as indulging that foolish weakness in the choice of a barber or fuller, or in lodging in a paltry inn when better
				accommodation is to be had, to oblige the landlord who has
				cringed to us. But if it be merely to break ourselves of
				such follies, in those cases still we should make use of the
				best, though the difference be but inconsiderable; as the
				Pythagoreans were strict in observing not to cross their
				right knee with the left, or to use an even number with an
				odd, though all things else were indifferent. We must observe also, when we celebrate a sacrifice or keep a wedding
				or make a public entertainment, to deny ourselves so far as
				not to invite any that have been extremely complacent to us or
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.69"/>
				
				that put themselves upon us, before those who are known for
				their good-humor or whose conversation is like to prove
				beneficial. For he that has accustomed himself thus far
				will hardly be caught and surprised, nay, rather he shall not
				so much as be tempted, in greater instances.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>And thus much may suffice concerning exercising
				ourselves. My first use of what has been said is to observe,
				that all passions and distempers of the mind are still accompanied with those very evils which by their means we
				hoped to avoid. Thus disgrace pursues ambition; pain
				and indisposition, sensuality; softness and effeminacy are
				fretted with troubles; contentiousness with disappointment
				and defeats. But this is nowhere more conspicuous than in
				bashfulness, which, endeavoring to avoid the smoke of reproach, throws itself into the fire. Such men, wanting
				confidence to withstand those that unreasonably importune
				them, afterwards feel shame before those who justly accuse
				them, and for fear of a slight private rebuke incur more
				public disgrace. For example, not having the heart to
				deny a friend that comes to borrow, in short time they are
				reduced to the same extremity themselves, and exposed
				openly. Some again, after promising to help friends in
				a lawsuit, are ashamed to face the opposite party, and are
				forced to hide their heads and run away. Many have been
				so unreasonably weak in this particular as to accept of disadvantageous proposals of marriage for a daughter or sister,
				and upon second thoughts have been forced to bring themselves off with an arrant lie.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>One made this observation of the people of Asia,
				that they were all slaves to one man, merely because they
				could not pronounce that syllable No; but he spake only in
				raillery. But now the bashful man, though he be not able
				to say one word, has but to raise his brows or nod downward, as if he minded not, and he may decline many
				ungrateful and unreasonable offices. Euripides was wont
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.70"/>
				
				to say, Silence is an answer to a wise man;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Frag. 967. The verse is found also in Menander, Monos. 222. (G.)</note> but we seem
				to have greater occasion for it in our dealings with fools
				and unreasonable persons, for men of breeding and sense
				will be satisfied with reason and fair words. Upon this account we should be always provided with some notable
				sayings and choice apothegms of famous and excellent men,
				to repeat to the bashful,&mdash;such as that of Phocion to
				Antipater, You cannot have me for both a friend and a
				flatterer; and that of his to the Athenians, when they
				called upon him to come in for his share to defray the expenses of a festival; I am ashamed, said he, pointing to
				Callicles his creditor, to contribute towards your follies, without paying this man his due. For, as Thucydides says,
				It is an ill thing to be ashamed of one's poverty, but much
				worse not to make use of lawful endeavors to avoid it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucyd. II. 40.</note>
				But he that is so foolishly good-natured that he cannot answer one that comes to borrow,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>My friend, no silver white have I in all my caves,&mdash;</l>
               </quote>
				
				but gives him a promise to be better provided,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The wretch has made himself a slave to shame,</l>
					             <l>And drags a tiresome, though an unforged chain.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Eurip. Pirithous, Frag. 598.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				Persaeus, being about to accommodate a friend with a sum
				of money, paid it publicly in the market, and made the
				conditions before a banker, remembering, it may be, that
				of Hesiod,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Seem not thy brother's honesty to doubt;</l>
					             <l>Yet, smiling, call a witness to his hand.</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Hesiod, Works and Days, 371.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				But when his friend marvelled and asked, How now,
				so formally and according to law? Yea, quoth he,
				because I would receive my money again as a friend, and
				not have to trouble the law to recover it. For many out
				of bashfulness, not taking care to have good security at
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.71"/>
				
				first, have been forced afterwards to break with their
				friends, and to have recourse to law for their money.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Again, Plato writing to Dionysius, by Helicon of
				Cyzicus, gives the bearer a good character for honesty and
				moderation, but withalin the postscript tells him, Yet this
				I write of a man, who, as such, is by nature an animal
				subject to change. Xenocrates, though a man of rigid
				morals, was prevailed upon by this kind of modesty to
				recommend to Polysperchon a person, as it proved in the
				end, not so honest as he was reputed. For when
				the Macedonian in compliment bade him call for whatever
				he wanted, he presently desired a talent of silver. Polysperchon ordered it accordingly to be paid him, but despatched away letters immediately to Xenocrates, advising
				him for the future to be better acquainted with those he
				recommended. Now all this came to pass through Xenocrates's ignorance of his man; but we oftentimes give
				testimonials and squander away our money to advance
				such as we are very well satisfied have no qualification or
				desert to recommend them, and this too with the forfeiture
				of our reputation, and without the pleasure that men have
				who are profuse upon whores and flatterers, but all the
				while in an agony, and struggling with that impudence
				which does violence to our reason. Whereas, if at any
				time, that verse can here be properly used,&mdash;
				
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>I know the dreadful consequence, and fear,</l> 
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <bibl>Eurip. Medea, 1078.</bibl>
                  </note>
               </quote>
				
				when such persons are at a man to forswear himself, or to
				give a wrong sentence, or to vote for an unjust bill, or lastly to be bound for one that will never be able to pay the
				debt.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>All passions of the mind have repentance still pursuing them closely, but it overtakes this of bashfulness in
				the very act. For we give with regret, and we are in confusion
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.72"/>
				
				 while we bear false witness; our reputation is
				questioned when we engage for others, and when we fail
				we are condemned by all men. From this imperfection
				also it proceeds, that many things are imposed upon us not
				in our power to perform, as to recommend such a man to
				court, or to carry up an address to the governor, because
				we dare not, or at least we will not, confess that we are
				unknown to the prince or that another has more of his ear.
				Lysander, on the other hand, when he was in disgrace at
				court, but yet for his great services was thought to preserve
				something of his former esteem with Agesilaus, made no
				scruple to dismiss suitors, directing them to such as were
				more powerful with the king. For it is no disgrace not to
				be able to do every thing; but to undertake or pretend to
				what you are not made for is not only shameful, but extremely troublesome and vexatious.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>But to proceed to another head, we must perform
				all reasonable and good offices to those that deserve them,
				not forced thereto by fear of shame, but cheerfully and
				readily. But where any thing prejudicial or unhandsome
				is required of us, we ought to remember the story that is
				related of Zeno. Meeting a young man of his acquaintance that slunk away under a wall, as if he would not be
				seen, and having learned from him that he withdrew from a
				fiend that importuned him to perjure himself, What, replied he, you novice! is that fellow not afraid or ashamed
				to require of thee what is unreasonable and unjust, and
				darest thou not stand against him in that which is just
				and honest? For he that first started that doctrine, that
				knavery is the best defence against a knave, was but an ill
				teacher, advising us to keep off wickedness by imitating it.
				But for such as presume upon our modesty, to keep them
				off with their own weapons, and not gratify their unreasonable impudence with an easy compliance, is but just and
				good, and the duty of every wise man.</p>
            <pb id="v.1.p.73"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Neither is it a hard matter to put off some mean
				and ordinary people, which will be apt to prove troublesome to you in that nature. Some shift them off with a
				jest or a smart repartee; as Theocritus, being asked in the
				bath to lend his flesh-brush by two persons, whereof one
				was a stranger to him, and the other a notorious thief,
				made answer: You, sir, I know not well enough, and you
				I know too well. And Lysimache, the priestess of Minerva
				Polias in Athens, when the muleteers that brought the provision for the festival desired her to let them drink, replied,
				No; for I fear it may grow into a custom. So again, when
				a captain's son, a young fluttering bully but a great coward,
				petitioned Antigonus for promotion, the latter answered:
				Sir, it is my way to reward my soldiers for their valor, not
				their parentage.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>But if he that is importunate with us prove a man
				of great honor or interest (and such persons are not easily
				answered with excuses, when they come for our vote in the
				senate or judicial cases), at such a time perhaps it will be
				neither easy nor necessary to behave ourselves to them as
				Cato did towards Catulus. Catulus, a person of the highest
				rank among the Romans, and at that time censor, once
				waited on Cato, who was then quaestor and still a young
				man, on behalf of a friend whom Cato had fined; and when
				he had used a great deal of importunity to no purpose, yet
				would not be denied, Cato grew out of patience, and told
				him, It would be an unseemly sight to have the censor
				dragged hence by my officers. Catulus at this went away,
				out of countenance and very angry. But consider whether
				the answers of Agesilaus and Themistocles have not in them
				much more of candor and equity. Agesilaus, being bidden
				by his own father to give sentence contrary to law, replied:
				I have been always taught by you to be observant of the
				laws, and I shall endeavor to obey you at this time,by
				doing nothing contrary to them. And Themistocles, when
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.74"/>
				
				Simonides tempted him to commit a piece of injustice, said:
				You would be no good poet, should you break the laws of
				verse; and should I judge against the law, I should make
				no better magistrate.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>For it is not because of blunders in metre in
				lyric songs, as Plato observes, that cities and friends are
				set at variance to their utter ruin and destruction, but because of their blunders with regard to law and justice.
				Yet there are a sort of men that can be very curious and
				critical in their verses and letters and lyric measures, and
				yet would persuade others to neglect that justice and honesty which all men ought to observe in offices, in passing
				judgments, and in all actions. But these men are to be
				dealt with after the following manner. An orator perhaps
				presses you to show him favor in a cause to be heard before
				you, or a demagogue importunes you when you are a senator: tell him you are ready to please him, on condition
				that he make a solecism in the beginning of his oration, or
				be guilty of some barbarous expression in his narration.
				These terms, for shame, he will not accept; for some we
				see so superstitiously accurate as not to allow of two vowels meeting one another. Again, you are moved by a person of quality to something of ill reputation: bid him come
				over the market-place at full noon dancing, or making
				buffoon-like grimaces; if he refuse, question him once
				more, whether he think it a more heinous offence to make
				a solecism or a grimace, than to break a law or to perjure
				one's self, or to show more favor to a rascal than to an
				honest man. Nicostratus the Argive, when Archidamus
				promised him a vast sum of money and his choice of the
				Spartan ladies in marriage, if he would deliver up the town
				Cromnum into his hands, returned him this answer: He
				could no longer believe him descended from Hercules, he
				said, because Hercules traversed the world to destroy wicked
				men, but Archidamus made it his business to debauch those
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.75"/>
				
				that were good. In like manner, if one that stands upon
				his quality or reputation presses us to do any thing dishonorable, we must tell him freely, he acts not as becomes a
				person of his character in the world.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>But if it be a man of no quality that shall importune
				you, you may enquire of the covetous man, whether he
				would lend you a considerable sum without any other security than your word; desire the proud man to give you the
				higher seat; or the ambitious, to quit his pretensions to
				some honor that lies fair for him. For, to deal plainly, it
				is a shameful thing that these men should continue so stiff,
				so resolute, and so unmoved in their vicious habits, while
				we, who profess ourselves lovers of justice and honesty,
				have too little command of ourselves not to give up and
				betray basely the cause of virtue. If they that would practise upon our modesty do this out of desire of glory or
				power, why should we contract disgrace or infamy to ourselves, to advance the authority or set off the reputation of
				others?&mdash;like those who bestow the reward wrongfully in
				public games, or betray their trust in collecting the poll,
				who confer indeed garlands and honors upon other men,
				but at the same time forfeit their own reputation and good
				word. But suppose it be matter of interest only that puts
				them upon it; why should it not appear an unreasonable
				piece of service for us to forego our reputation and conscience to no other purpose than to satisfy another man's
				avarice or make his coffers the heavier? After all, these I
				am afraid are the grand motives with most men in such
				cases, and they are even conscious that they are guilty; as
				men that are challenged and compelled to take too large a
				glass raise an hundred scruples and make as many grimaces before they drink.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>This weakness of the mind may be compared to a
				constitution of body that can endure neither heat nor
				cold. For let them be praised by those that thus impudently
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.76"/>
				
				 set upon them, and they are at once mollified
				and broken by the flattery; but let them be blamed or so
				much as suspected by the same men after their suit has
				been refused, and they are ready to die for woe and fear.
				We ought therefore to prepare and fortify ourselves against
				both extremes, so as to be made a prey neither to such as
				pretend to frighten, nor to such as would cajole us. Thucydides is of opinion, since there is a necessary connection
				between envy and great undertakings, that he takes the
				wisest counsel who incurs envy by aiming the highest.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thucyd. II. 64.</note>
				But we who esteem it less difficult to avoid the envy of all
				men than to escape the censure of those we live among,
				ought to order things so as rather to grapple with the unjust hatred of evil men, than to deserve their just accusation
				after we have served their base ends. We ought to go
				armed against that false and counterfeit praise such men
				are apt to fling upon us, not suffering ourselves like swine
				to be scratched and tickled by them, till, having got the advantage of us, they use us after their own pleasure. For
				they that reach out their ears to flatterers differ very little
				from such as stand fair and quiet to be tripped up, excepting
				that the former catch the more disgraceful fall. These put
				up with the affronts and forbear the correction of wicked
				men, to get the reputation of good-natured or merciful; or
				else are drawn into needless and perilous quarrels at the
				instance of flatterers, who bear them in hand all the while
				for the only men of judgment, the only men not to be
				caught with flattery, and call them the only men who have
				mouths and voices. Bion used to compare these men to
				pitchers: Take them, said he, by the ears, and you may
				move them as you please. Thus Alexinus, the sophist, was
				reporting many scandalous things in the lyceum of Stilpo
				the Megarian; but when one present informed him that
				Stilpo always spake very honorably of him, Why truly,
				
				<pb id="v.1.p.77"/>
				
				says he, he is one of the most obliging and best of men.
				But now Menedemus, when it was told him that Alexinus
				often praised him, replied: That may be, but I always talk
				against him; for he must be bad who either praises a bad
				man or is blamed by an honest one. So wary was he of
				being caught by such baits, agreeably to that precept
				of Hercules in Antisthenes,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Antisthenes, in his tenth tome, had a book entitled <hi rend="italics">Hercules or De Prudentia</hi> or
					<hi rend="italics">De Robore</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">(*hraklh=s h)\ peri\ fronh/sews h)\ i)sxu/os</foreign>), mentioned by Diogenes Laertius in
					his life. See Diogenes Laert. VI. 1, 9.</note> who cautioned his sons not to
				be thankful to such as were used to praise them,&mdash;thereby
				meaning no more than that they should be so far from
				being wheedled thereby as not even to return their flatteries. That of Pindar was very apposite, and enough to
				be said in such a case: when one told him, I cry you up
				among all men, and speak to your advantage on all occasions; and I, replied he, am always very thankful, in that
				I take care you shall not tell a lie.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>I shall conclude with one general rule, of sovereign
				use against all the passions and diseases of the mind, but
				particularly beneficial to such as labor under the present
				distemper, bashfulness. And it is this: whenever they
				have given way to this weakness, let them store up carefully such failings in their memory, and taking therein deep
				and lively impressions of what remorse and disquiet they
				occasioned, bestow much time in reflecting upon them and
				keeping them fresh. For as travellers that have got a
				dangerous fall against such a stone, or sailors shipwrecked
				upon a particular promontory, keeping the image of their
				misfortune continually before them, appear fearful and apprehensive not only of the same but even the like dangers;
				so they that keep in mind the disgraceful and prejudicial
				effects of bashfulness will soon be enabled to restrain themselves in like cases, and will not easily slip again on any
				occasion.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>