<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De curiositate</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">W. C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>W. C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1939</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.6.p.471"/>
            <head>ON BEING A BUSYBODY
					(DE CURIOSITATE)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					This essay, which was apparently written only a short
					time before <hi rend="italics">De Garrulitate</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">And no doubt also before <hi rend="italics">De Tranquillitate</hi> (so rightly Brokate).</note> has much the same
					interest and charm as that pleasant work. The
					essays are akin in many ways ; portions of the later
					treatise are merely a reshaping of ideas and commonplaces which the earlier had adumbrated.
				</p>
            <p>
					The source of much of this work has been traced to
					Ariston of Chios by O. Hense (<hi rend="italics">Rhein. Mus.</hi>,x Iv. 541 if.);
					and F. Krauss<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Die Rhetorischen Schriften Plutarchs</hi>, Munich Diss., N&uuml;rnberg, 1912, pp. 67 ff. See also the interesting table (p. 87) of rhetorical figures which places our essay in the very centre of Plutarch's literary activity.</note> has shown with some success the
					relation to diatribe literature.
				</p>
            <p>
					The essay was already known to Aulus Gellius
					(xi. 16), who speaks with feeling of the difficulty of
					rendering <foreign lang="greek">polupragmosu/nh</foreign> in Latin<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is hard to render it in English also. The translator uses the word <q direct="unspecified">curiosity</q> - Ed.</note>; nor has it been
					unknown to English moralists. Jeremy Taylor has
					again borrowed largely from it in his <hi rend="italics">Holy Living</hi>, ii. 5.
				</p>
            <p>
					In the translation of this and the preceding essay
					I am greatly indebted to Mr. Tucker's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Select Essays of Plutarch</hi>, Oxford, Clarendon, 1913.</note> spirited version, from which I have taken numerous phrases and
					sometimes whole sentences.
				</p>
            <p>
					The work is No. 97 in the Lamprias catalogue.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.6.p.473"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>It is perhaps best to avoid a house which has no
					ventilation, or is gloomy, or cold in winter, or unhealthy ; yet if familiarity has made you fond of
					the place, it is possible to make it brighter, better
					ventilated, and healthier by altering the lights, shifting the stairs, and opening some doors and closing
					others. Even some cities have gained by such
					changes. So in the case of my own town,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Chaeroneia</note> which used
					to face the west and receive the full force of the sun
					in the late afternoon from Parnassus, they say that
					it was turned by Chaeron to face the east. And
					Empedocles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, i. p. 284, A 14; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 1126 b.</note> the natural philosopher, by blocking
					up a certain mountain gorge, which permitted the
					south wind to blow a dire and pestilential draught
					down upon the plains, was thought to have shut
					plague out of his country.
				</p>
            <p>
					Since, then, there are certain unhealthy and injurious states of mind which allow winter and darkness to enter the soul, it is better to thrust these out
					and to make a clean sweep to the foundations, thus
					giving to ourselves a clear sky and light and pure air ;
					but if that is impossible, it is best at least to interchange and readjust them in some way or other,
					turning or shifting them about.
					<pb id="v.6.p.475"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Such a malady of the mind, to take the first instance,
					is curiosity, which is a desire to learn the troubles of
					others,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Menander's typical curious slave, a <foreign lang="greek">polupra/gmwn</foreign>, who says (Frag. 850 Kock): <foreign lang="greek">ou)de\n gluku/tero/n e)stin h)\ pa/nt' ei)de/nai</foreign>.</note> a disease which is thought to be free from
					neither envy nor malice :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Why do you look so sharp on others' ills,
						</l>
                  <l>Malignant man, yet overlook your own?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 476, ades. 359; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 469 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					Shift your curiosity from things without and turn it
					inwards ; if you enjoy dealing with the recital of
					troubles, you have much occupation at home :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Great as the water flowing down Alizon,
						</l>
                  <l>Many as the leaves around the oak,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A verse of unknown origin; the text is probably corrupt.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					so great a quantity of transgressions will you find in
					your own life, of afflictions in your own soul, of oversights in the performance of your own obligations.
				</p>
            <p>
					For as Xenophon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Oeconomicus</hi>, viii. 19, 20.</note> says that good householders
					have a special place for sacrificial utensils, and a
					special place for dinner-ware, and that farming implements should be stored elsewhere, and apart from
					them the weapons of war; even so in your own case
					you have one store of faults arising from envy, another
					from jealousy, another from cowardice, another from
					pettiness. Assault these, examine these! Block up
					the windows and the side-doors of your curiosity that
					open on your neighbours' property, and open up
					others leading to your own-to the men's quarters,
					to the women's quarters, to the living-rooms of your
					servants! Here this curiosity and meddlesomeness
					of yours will have an occupation not unhelpful or
					<pb id="v.6.p.477"/>
					
					malicious, but useful and salutary if each one will but
					say to himself,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Where did I err? And what deed have I done?
						What duty neglected?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">Pythagoras,</q> 
                     <hi rend="italics">Carmina Aurea</hi>, 42; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 168 b.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But as it is, like the Lamia in the fable, who,
					they say, when at home sleeps in blindness with her
					eyes stored away in a jar, but when she goes abroad
					puts in her eyes and can see, so each one of us, in
					our dealings with others abroad, puts his meddlesomeness, like an eye, into his maliciousness ; but
					we are often tripped up by our own faults and vices
					by reason of our ignorance of them, since we provide
					ourselves with no sight or light by which to inspect
					them. Therefore the busybody is also more useful
					to his enemies than to himself,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 87 b-c.</note> for he rebukes and
					drags out their faults and demonstrates to them
					what they should avoid or correct, but he neglects the
					greater part of his own domestic errors through his
					passionate interest in those abroad. So Odysseus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xi. 88 ff.; Ps.-Lucian, <hi rend="italics">De Astrologia</hi>, 24.</note>
					refused to converse even with his mother until he
					had learned from the seer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Teiresias.</note> the matters by reason
					of which he had come to the House of Hades ; and
					when he had his answer, he both turned to his mother
					and also made inquiries of the other women,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xi. 229 ff.</note> asking
					who was Tyro, who the beautiful Chloris, why Epicaste
					met her death
					<quote rend="blockquote">Tying a noose, sheer-hung, from the high roof.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 278; Epicaste is better known as Jocasta, the mother of Oedipus.</note>
               </quote>
					          <pb id="v.6.p.479"/>
					
					But we, while treating our own affairs with considerable laxity and ignorance and neglect, pry into the
					pedigrees of the rest of the world : our neighbour's
					grandfather was a Syrian and his grandmother a
					Thracian<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, both were probably slaves.</note>; so-and-so owes three talents and has not
					paid the interest. We inquire also into such matters
					as where so-and-so's wife was coming back from,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>, where she had been.</note> and
					what A and B's private conversation in the corner was
					about. Yet Socrates went about seeking to solve the
					question of what arguments Pythagoras used to carry
					conviction ; and Aristippus, when he met Ischomachus at Olympia, asked him by what manner of
					conversation Socrates succeeded in so affecting the
					young men. And when Aristippus had gleaned a
					few odd seeds and samples of Socrates' talk, he was
					so moved that he suffered a physical collapse and
					became quite pale and thin. Finally he sailed for
					Athens and slaked his burning thirst with draughts
					from the fountain-head, and engaged in a study of the
					man and his words and his philosophy, of which the
					end and aim was to come to recognize one's own
					vices and so rid oneself of them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Yet there are some who cannot bear to face
					their own lives, regarding these as a most unlovely
					spectacle, or to reflect and revolve upon themselves,
					like a light, the power of reason, but their souls, being
					full of all manner of vices, shuddering and frightened
					at what is within, leap outwards and prowl about
					other people's concerns and there batten and make
					fat their own malice. For as a domestic fowl will
					often, though its own food lies near at hand, slip
					into a corner and there scratch
					<pb id="v.6.p.481"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Where one sole barley grain perhaps appears
						</l>
                  <l>In the dung-heap,<note resp="ed" place="unspecifed" anchored="yes">Perhaps a verse of Callimachus (Frag. anon. 374 ed. Schneider).</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					in the same way busybodies, passing over topics and
					narratives which are in plain view and matters concerning which no one prevents their inquiring or is
					vexed if inquiry is made, pick out the hidden and
					obscure troubles of every household. And yet it was
					surely a clever answer that the Egyptian gave to the
					man who asked him what he was carrying wrapped
					up : <q direct="unspecified">That's why it <hi rend="italics">is</hi> wrapped up.</q> And why,
					if you please, are <hi rend="italics">you</hi> inquisitive about what is concealed? If it were not something bad, it would not
					be concealed. Yet it is not customary to walk into
					the house of someone else without at least first knocking on the door; but nowadays there are doormen and
					formerly there were knockers to be struck at the
					door and give warning, so that the stranger might not
					catch the mistress of the house or the unmarried
					daughter unawares, or a slave being punished or the
					maid-servants screaming. But it is for these very
					things that the busybody slips in. A sober and respectable household he would not willingly enter as a
					spectator even if he were invited to come ; but the
					matters to conceal which keys and bolts and streetdoors are used-these are what he uncovers and
					communicates to outsiders. And yet <q direct="unspecified">the winds
						with which we are most vexed,</q> as Ariston<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, i. pp. 89-90, Frag. 401.</note> says,
					<q direct="unspecified">are those which pull up our garments,</q> but the
					busybody strips off not only the mantles and tunics
					of those near him, but also their very walls ; he
					flings the doors wide open and makes his way, like
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.483"/>
					
					a piercing wind, <q direct="unspecified">through the maiden of tender
						skin,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 519; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 465 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and creeps in, searching out with slanderous
					intent drunken revels and dances and all-night
					festivals.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>And like Cleon in the comedy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Knights</hi>, 79; <hi rend="italics">Klopidai</hi> (Thief-deme) is a play upon the actual deme <hi rend="italics">Kropidai</hi>.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">His hands in Beggar-town, his mind on Thefton,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or better, Theevingen.</note>
               </quote>
					so the mind of the busybody is at the same time in
					mansions of the rich, in hovels of the poor, in royal
					courts, and in bridal chambers of the newly-wed. He
					searches out everybody's business, that of strangers
					and that of rulers, nor is this search of his without
					danger; but just as though a man should taste aconite<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 49 e.</note>
					through curiosity about its properties, he would find
					that he had killed the taster before he had got his
					taste, so those who search out the vices of those more
					powerful than themselves destroy themselves before
					they acquire their knowledge. For instance those
					who scarcely glance<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Memorabilia</hi>, iv. 3. 14.</note> at these sunbeams which have
					been poured down so lavishly upon us all, but recklessly dare to gaze upon the orb itself and to rend
					its radiance apart, striving to force their way within,
					are blinded. This is the reason why Philippides,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 508 c, <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
               </note>
					the comic poet, made an excellent reply when King
					Lysimachus once said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Which one of my
						possessions may I share with you?</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Anything,
							Sire,</q> said Philippides, <q direct="unspecified">except your secrets.</q> For
					only the most pleasant and most decorous attributes
					of kings are displayed openly-their banquets and
					wealth and festivals and favours ; but if there is anything
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.485"/>
					
					secret, do not approach it, but let it be! The
					joy of a prosperous king is not concealed, nor is his
					laughter when he is amused, nor his outlay on entertainment and favours ; but it is time for alarm when
					something is hidden, something dark, unsmiling, unapproachable, a storehouse of festering wrath, or the
					meditation of a punishment indicative of sullen anger,
					or jealousy of a wife, or some suspicion against a son,
					or distrust of a friend. Beware of this darkening
					and gathering cloud! That which is now hidden will
					be disclosed to you when the cloud bursts forth amid
					crashes of thunder and bolts of lightning!
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>What escape is there, then, from this vice? By
					a process of shifting and diverting our inquisitiveness,
					as has been said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 515 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and, if possible, by turning the
					soul to better and more pleasant subjects. Direct
					your curiosity to heavenly things and things on
					earth, in the air, in the sea. Are you by nature fond
					of small or of great spectacles? If of great ones,
					apply your curiosity to the sun : where does it set and
					whence does it rise? Inquire into the changes in the
					moon, as you would into those of a human being :
					what becomes of all the light she has spent and from
					what source did she regain it, how does it happen that
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>When out of darkness first she comes anew,
						</l>
                  <l>She shows her face increasing fair and full;
						</l>
                  <l>And when she reaches once her brightest sheen,
						</l>
                  <l>Again she wastes away and comes to naught?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 315, Sophocles, Frag. 787 (871 ed. Pearson); the full quotation may be found in <hi rend="italics">Life of Demetrius</hi>, xlv. (911 c-d). <hi rend="superscript">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="superscript">Moralia</hi>, 282 b.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And these are secrets of Nature, yet Nature is not
					vexed with those who find them out. Or suppose
					you have renounced great things. Then turn your
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.487"/>
					
					curiosity to smaller ones : how are some plants
					always blooming and green and rejoicing in the display of their wealth at every season, while others are
					sometimes like these, but at other times, like a human
					spendthrift, they squander all at once their abundance
					and are left bare and beggared? Why, again, do
					some plants produce elongated fruits, others angular,
					and still others round and globular?
				</p>
            <p>
					But perhaps you will have no curiosity about these
					subjects since there is nothing evil in them. Yet if
					your zest for meddling must by all means be for ever
					feeding and dwelling on depraved things, like a
					maggot on dead matter, let us escort it to history and
					supply it with an unstinted abundance of evils. For
					there you will find
					<quote rend="blockquote">The deaths of men, the shufflings off of life,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Suppliants</hi>, 937; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 937 f.</note>
               </quote>
					seductions of women, assaults of slaves, slanders of
					friends, compounding of poisons, envies, jealousies,
					shipwrecks of households, overthrow of empires.
					Glut and enjoy yourself and cause no trouble or pain
					to any of your associates!
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But curiosity apparently takes no pleasure in
					stale calamities, but wants them hot and fresh ; it
					enjoys the spectacle of novel tragedies and has not
					much zest for association with the comic and more
					cheerful side of life. Consequently when anyone
					tells the tale of a wedding or a sacrifice or a complimentary escort, the busybody is a careless and inattentive listener, and declares that he has already
					heard most of the details and urges the narrator to
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.489"/>
					
					cut them short or skip them. But if someone sitting
					near at hand narrates the seduction of a maiden or
					the adultery of a wife or the framing of a law-suit or
					a quarrel of brothers, the busybody neither dozes
					off to sleep nor pleads an engagement,
					<quote rend="blockquote">But asks more speech and proffers both his ears<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Callimachus, Frag. anon. 375 ed. Schneider.</note>;</quote>
					and that saying,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 913, ades. 386.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Alas!
						</l>
                  <l>How much more readily than glad events
						</l>
                  <l>Is mischance carried to the ears of men!</l>
               </quote>
					is spoken truly when applied to busy bodies. For as
					cupping-glasses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 469 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 600 c.</note> draw from the flesh what is worst in
					it, so the ears of busy bodies attract the most evil
					stories. Or rather, as cities have certain unlucky and
					dismal gates through which they lead out condemned
					criminals and cast out the refuse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 271 a.</note> and the scapegoats, while nothing undefiled or sacred either goes
					in or out through them, so also the ears of busy bodies
					give passage and thoroughfare to nothing good or
					decent, but only to gruesome tales, serving, as they
					do, as conveyance for foul and polluted narratives.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The only song that's heard within my house
						</l>
                  <l>Is wailing cries.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 463 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					This is the one Muse and Siren for busybodies, this
					is the sweetest of all music to their ears.
				</p>
            <p>
					For curiosity is really a passion for finding out
					whatever is hidden and concealed, and no one conceals a good thing when he has it; why, people even
					pretend to have good things when they have them
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.491"/>
					
					not. Since, then, it is the searching out of troubles
					that the busybody desires, he is possessed by the
					affliction called <q direct="unspecified">malignancy,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A term better expressed by the German <hi rend="italics">Schadenfreude</hi>.</note> brother to envy and
					spite. For envy is pain at another's good, while
					malignancy is joy at another's evil<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1046 b.</note>; and both spring
					from a savage and bestial affliction, a vicious nature.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>So painful for all of us is the revelation of our
					own troubles that many die rather than reveal to
					physicians some hidden malady. Just imagine Herophilus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of Chalcedon, a great anatomist of the Alexandrian age (<hi rend="italics">flor. circa</hi> 300 b.c.).</note> or Erasistratus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of Ceos, worked in Alexandria at the height of his fame (258 b.c.).</note> or Asclepius himself, when
					he was a mortal man,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Asclepius, the son of Apollo, was deified after death as the god of medicine.</note> carrying about their drugs and
					instruments, calling at one house after another, and
					inquiring whether a man had an abscess in the anus
					or a woman a cancer in the womb! And yet the
					inquisitiveness of this profession is a salutary thing.
					Yet everyone, I imagine, would have driven such a
					man away, because he does not wait to be sent for, but
					comes unsummoned to investigate others' infirmities.
					And busybodies search out these very matters and
					others still worse, not to cure, but merely to expose
					them. For this reason they are hated deservedly.
					For example, we are annoyed and displeased with
					customs-officials, not when they pick up those articles
					which we are importing openly, but when in the
					search for concealed goods they pry into baggage and
					merchandize which are another's property. And yet
					the law allows them to do this and they would lose<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Since the collection of taxes and duties was farmed out to individuals, they would be the losers in failing to make a minute search for dutiable articles.</note>
					by not doing so. But busybodies ruin and abandon
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.493"/>
					
					their own interests in their excessive occupation with
					those of others. Only rarely do they visit the farm,
					for they cannot endure the quiet and silence of being
					alone. But if, after a long absence, they do chance to
					put in there, they have more of an eye for their
					neighbours' vines than for their own, and they ask
					how many of their neighbours' cattle have died, or
					how much of his wine has turned sour. But they are
					soon sated with such news and run away. Yet the
					true and genuine farmer does not care to hear even
					news that makes its own way from the city ; he says<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 473, ades. 347; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 511 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, where it is the typical Athenian slave of whom his farmer-master complains.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Then he will tell me while he digs
						</l>
                  <l>On what terms peace was made. The cursed scamp
						</l>
                  <l>Now strolls around and meddles with these things.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>And the busybody, shunning the country as
					something stale and uninteresting and undramatie,
					pushes into the bazaar and the market-place and the
					harbours : <q direct="unspecified">Is there any news?</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Weren't you at
						market early this morning? Well then, do you
						suppose the city has changed its constitution in three
						hours?</q> If, however, someone really does have
					something of that nature to tell him, he dismounts
					from his horse, grasps his informant's hand, kisses
					him, and stands there listening. But if someone
					meets him and tells him that there is no news, he
					exclaims as though he were annoyed, <q direct="unspecified">What do you
						mean? Haven't you been at market? Didn't you
						pass the War Office? Didn't you interview the new
						arrivals from Italy either?</q> It is for this reason that
					the legislation of the Locrian magistrates was excellent. For if anyone who had been out of town came
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.495"/>
					
					up and asked, <q direct="unspecified">Is there any news?</q> they fined him.
					Just as cooks<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The professional cook was also a butcher.</note> pray for a good crop of young animals
					and fishermen for a good haul of fish, in the same way
					busybodies pray for a good crop of calamities, a good
					haul of difficulties, for novelties, and changes, that
					they, like cooks and fishermen, may always have
					something to fish out or butcher.
				</p>
            <p>
					Another good law was that of the legislator of
					Thurii,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Charondas.</note> for he forbade the lampooning on the comic
					stage of all citizens except adulterers and busybodies.
					And indeed adultery does seem to be a sort of curiosity
					about another's pleasure and a searching out and
					examination of matters which are closely guarded
					and escape general observation, while curiosity is an
					encroaching, a debauching and denuding of secret
					things.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Since a natural consequence of much learning is
					to have much to say (and for this reason Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Numa</hi>, viii. (65 b); <hi rend="italics">De Vita et Poesi Homeri</hi>, 149 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 420); Lucian, <hi rend="italics">Vitarum Auctio</hi>, 3.</note>
					enjoined upon the young a five years' silence which
					he called a <q direct="unspecified">Truce to Speech</q>), a necessary concomitant of inquisitiveness is to speak evil.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 508 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> For
					what the curious delight to hear they delight to tell,
					and what they zealously collect from others they
					joyously reveal to everyone else. Consequently, in
					addition to its other evils, their disease actually
					impedes the fulfilment of their desires.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 502 e-f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> For everyone is on his guard to hide things from them and is
					reluctant to do anything while a busybody is looking,
					or to say anything while one is listening, but defers
					consultation and postpones the consideration of
					business until such an inquisitive person is out of
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.497"/>
					
					the way. And if, when either some secret matter is
					under discussion or some important business is being
					transacted, a busybody comes on the scene, men drop
					the matter from the discussion and conceal it, as one
					does a tidbit when a cat runs by. Consequently these
					persons are often the only ones to whom those matters
					are not told or shown which everyone else may hear
					and see.
				</p>
            <p>
					For the same reason the busybody is deprived of
					everybody's confidence<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 503 c-d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>: we should prefer, on any
					account, to entrust our letters and papers and seals
					to slaves and strangers rather than to inquisitive
					friends and relatives. That noble Bellerophon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Il.</hi>, vi. 168.</note> did
					not break the seal even on a letter accusing himself
					which he was carrying, but kept his hands from the
					king's letter by reason of that same continence which
					kept him from the king's wife. Inquisitiveness, in
					fact, is indicative of incontinence no less than is
					adultery, and in addition, it is indicative of terrible
					folly and fatuity. For to pass by so many women
					who are public property open to all and then to be
					drawn toward a woman who is kept under lock and
					key and is expensive, and often, if it so happens,
					quite ugly, is the very height of madness and
					insanity. And it is this same thing which busybodies do : they pass by much that is beautiful to
					see and to hear, many matters excellent for relaxation and amusement, and spend their time digging
					into other men's trifling correspondence, gluing their
					ears to their neighbours' walls, whispering with slaves
					and women of the streets, and often incurring danger,
					and always infamy.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>For this reason the most useful means possible
					for turning the busybody from his vice is for him to
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.499"/>
					
					remember what he has previously learned.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">With this chapter may be compared chapter 19 of <hi rend="italics">De Vitioso Pudore</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 536 c-d).</note> For, as
					Simonides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the same story, illustrating the avarice of Simonides, in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 555 f; there the box containing his fees is full of silver.</note> used to say that when he opened his
					boxes after some time, he always found the fee-box
					full, but the thanks-box empty, so if one opens from
					time to time the deposit-box of inquisitiveness and
					examines it, full as it is of many useless, futile, and
					unlovely things, perhaps this procedure would give
					sufficient offence, so completely disagreeable and silly
					would it appear. Suppose a man should run over the
					works of the ancients and pick out the worst passages
					in them and keep a book compiled from such things as
					<q direct="unspecified">headless lines</q> in Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lines which begin with a short syllable instead of the long one demanded by the metre: <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 397 d, 611 b; Athenaeus, xiv. 632 d.</note> and solecisms in the
					tragedians and the unbecoming and licentious language applied to women by which Archilochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 45 a.</note> makes
					a sorry spectacle of himself, would he not deserve that
					curse in the tragedy,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Be damned, compiler of men's miseries?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 913, ades. 388; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 855 b.</note>
               </quote>
					And even without this curse, such a man's treasurehouse of other people's faults is unbecoming and useless. It is like the city populated by the vilest and
					most intractable of men which Philip founded and
					called Roguesborough.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. gr. Historiker</hi>, ii. B, p. 561, Theopompus, Frag. 110.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Busybodies, however, by gleaning and gathering
					the blunders and errors and solecisms, not of lines or
					poems, but of lives, carry about with them a most
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.501"/>
					
					inelegant and unlovely record-box of evils, their
					own memory. Therefore just as at Rome there are
					some who take no account of paintings or statues
					or even, by Heaven, of the beauty of the boys
					and women for sale, but haunt the monster-market,
					examining those who have no calves, or are weasel-armed,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, with exceptionally short arms.</note> or have three eyes, or ostrich-heads, and
					searching to learn whether there has been born
					some
					<quote rend="blockquote">Commingled shape and misformed prodigy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 680, Euripides, Frag. 996; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Theseus</hi>, xv. (6 d).</note>
               </quote>
					yet if one continually conduct them to such sights,
					they will soon experience satiety and nausea ; so let
					those who are curious about life's failures, the blots
					on the scutcheon, the delinquencies and errors in
					other people's homes, remind themselves that their
					former discoveries have brought them no favour or
					profit.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>The greatest factor, however, in ridding ourselves of this affliction is the habit of beginning early
					to train and teach ourselves to acquire this self-control. It is, in fact, by habituation that the disease
					has come to increase, advancing, as it does, little by
					little. How this habit is acquired, we shall learn when
					we discuss the proper training. So first let us begin
					with the most trifling and unimportant matters.
					What difficulty is there about refraining from reading the inscriptions on tombs as we journey along
					the roads? Or what is there arduous in just glancing at the writing on walls when we take our
					walks? We have only to remind ourselves that
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.503"/>
					
					nothing useful or pleasant has been written there:
					merely so-and-so <q direct="unspecified">commemorates</q> so-and-so <q direct="unspecified">wishing him well,</q> and someone else is the <q direct="unspecified">best of
						friends,</q> and much twaddle of this sort.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">I quote Shilleto's note: <q direct="unspecified">Plutarch rather reminds one, in his evident contempt for <hi rend="italics">Epitaphs</hi>, of the cynic who asked, <q direct="unspecified">Where are all the bad people buried?</q> Where indeed?</q>
               </note> It may
					seem that no harm will come from reading these, but
					harm you it does by imperceptibly instilling the
					practice of searching out matters which do not concern you. And as hunters do not allow young hounds
					to turn aside and follow every scent, but pull them up
					and check them with the leash, keeping their sense
					of smell pure and untainted for their proper task in
					order that it may keep more keenly to the trail,
					<quote rend="blockquote">With nostrils tracking down the paths of beasts<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From an unknown poet: Empedocles? (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xv. 176).</note>;</quote>
					so one should be careful to do away with or divert to
					useful ends the sallies and wanderings of the busybody, directed as they are to everything that one
					may see and hear. For as eagles and lions<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 966 c. <q direct="unspecified">Eagles</q> is probably corrupt. Pohlenz suggests <q direct="unspecified">cats.</q>
               </note> draw in
					their claws when they walk so that they may not
					wear off the sharpness of the tips, so, if we consider
					that curiosity for learning has also a sharp and keen
					edge, let us not waste or blunt it upon matters of no
					value.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>In the second place, then, let us accustom ourselves not to look inside when we pass another's door,
					nor with our curious gaze to clutch, as it were by
					main force, at what is happening within, but let us
					ever keep ready for use the saying of Xenocrates,
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.505"/>
					
					that it makes no difference whether it is the feet or
					the eyes that we set within another's house ; for
					what the eyes behold is neither just nor honourable,
					and not even pleasant.
					<quote rend="blockquote">Unsightly, stranger, are the things within,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 617, Euripides, Frag. 790, probably from the <hi rend="italics">Philoctetes</hi>.</note>
               </quote>
					since the greater part of what we see inside is of this
					sort-kitchen utensils lying about and servant-girls
					sitting in idleness, and nothing important or pleasurable. And this practice of throwing sidelong and
					furtive glances, distorting the soul as it does, is
					shameful, and the habit it implants is depraved. For
					instance, when Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, xii. 58.</note> saw the Olympic victor
					Dioxippus making his triumphal entry in his chariot
					and unable to tear his eyes away from a beautiful
					woman who was among the spectators of the procession, but continually turning around and throwing
					side-glances in her direction, <q direct="unspecified">Do you see,</q> said the
					Cynic, <q direct="unspecified">how a slip of a girl gets a strangle-hold on
						our athlete?</q> And you may observe how every
					kind of spectacle alike gets a strangle-hold on busybodies and twists their necks round when they once
					acquire a habit and practice of scattering their glances
					in all directions. But, as I think, the faculty of
					vision should not be spinning about outside of us,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, outside of the control of reason.</note>
					like an ill-trained servant girl, but when it is sent on
					an errand by the soul it should quickly reach its
					destination and deliver its message, then return again
					in good order within the governance of the reason
					and heed its command. But as it is, the words of
					Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Electra</hi>, 724-725.</note> come true :
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.507"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Then the Aenianian's hard-mouthed yearlings break
						</l>
                  <l>From his control and bolt;</l>
               </quote>
					that is, the senses which have not received what we
					called above right instruction and training run away,
					dragging the intellect with them, and often plunge it
					into deep disaster. Consequently, though that story
					about Democritus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, ii. p. 89, A 27.</note> is false, that he deliberately
					destroyed his sight by fixing his eyes on a red-hot
					mirror and allowing its heat to be reflected on his
					sight, in order that his eyes might not repeatedly
					summon his intellect outside and disturb it, but
					might allow his mind to remain inside at home and
					occupy itself with pure thinking, blocking up as it
					were windows which open on the street; yet nothing
					is more true than this, that those who make most
					use of the intellect make fewest calls upon the senses.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch is thinking of some such passage as Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 66 a.</note>
					We observe, for instance, that men have built their
					sanctuaries of the Muses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, halls devoted to learning, such as the Museion at Alexandria and the Academy at Athens.</note> far from cities and that
					they have called night <q direct="unspecified">kindly</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Agamemnon</hi>, 265.</note> from a belief that
					its quiet and absence of distraction is greatly conducive to the investigation and solution of the problems in hand.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Yet truly, neither is this<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 520 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> a difficult nor arduous
					task: when men are reviling and abusing each other
					in the market-place, not to approach them, or when a
					crowd is running to see something or other, to remain
					seated, or, if you are without self-control, to get up
					and go away. For you will reap no advantage from
					mixing yourself with busy bodies, whereas you will
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.509"/>
					
					obtain great benefit from forcibly turning aside your
					curiosity and curtailing it and training it to obey
					reason.
				</p>
            <p>
					And after this it is well to make our training more
					intensive and pass by a theatre where a successful
					performance is in progress ; and, when our friends
					urge us to see a certain dancer or comedian, to thrust
					them aside ; and, when shouts are heard on the racecourse or in the circus, not to turn round. For as
					Socrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 513 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> used to advise the avoidance of such foods
					as tempt us to eat when we are not hungry and
					such drinks as tempt us to imbibe when we are not
					thirsty, so we also should avoid and guard against
					such sights and sounds as master and attract us without fulfilling any need of ours. Thus Cyrus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, v. 1. 8; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 31 c.</note> was
					unwilling to see Pantheia ; and when Araspes declared that the woman's beauty was worth seeing,
					Cyrus said, <q direct="unspecified">Then this is all the more reason for
						keeping away from her. For if, persuaded by you, I
						should go to her, perhaps she herself might tempt
						me, when I couldn't spare the time, to go to see her
						again and sit by her, to the neglect of many important
						matters.</q> So too Alexander<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, xxii. (677 b); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 97 d, 338 e.</note> would not go to see
					Darius's wife who was said to be very beautiful, but
					although he visited her mother, an elderly woman,
					he could not bring himself to see the young and
					beautiful daughter. Yet we peep into women's
					litters and hang about their windows, and think we
					are doing nothing wrong in thus making our curiosity
					prone to slip and slide into all kinds of vice.
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.511"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Since, therefore, for the attainment of justice
					you may sometimes forgo an honest gain that you may
					accustom yourself to keep clear of dishonest profit, so
					likewise, for the attainment of continence, you may
					sometimes keep aloof from your own wife in order
					that you may never be stirred by another's. Then
					apply this habit to inquisitiveness and endeavour
					sometimes not to hear or see some of the things that
					concern you, and when someone wishes to tell you
					something that has happened in your house, put him
					off and refuse to hear words that are supposed to have
					been spoken about you. It was, in fact, curiosity
					which involved Oedipus in the greatest calamities.
					Believing that he was no Corinthian, but a foreigner, and seeking to discover his identity, he
					encountered La&iuml;us ; and when he had killed La&iuml;us
					and had taken, in addition to the throne, his own
					mother to wife, though seeming to all to be blessed
					by fortune, he began again to try to discover his
					identity. And although his wife attempted to prevent him, all the more vigorously did he cross-examine
					the old man who knew the truth, bringing every form
					of compulsion to bear. And at last, when circumstances were already bringing him to suspect the truth
					and the old man<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The herdsman who had saved Oedipus on Cithaeron.</note> cried out,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Alas! I stand on the dread brink of speech,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Rex</hi>, 1169.</note>
               </quote>
					Oedipus was none the less so inflamed and maddened
					by his affliction<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Curiosity.</note> that he replied,
					<quote rend="blockquote">And I of hearing, and yet hear I must<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi>, 1170.</note>;</quote>
					so bitter-sweet, so uncontrollable is the itching of
					curiosity, like the itching of a sore which gets bloody
					whenever we scratch it. But the man who has got
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.513"/>
					
					rid of this disease and is gentle by nature will say,
					if he is ignorant of something unpleasant,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Forgetfulness of evil, sovereign queen,
						</l>
                  <l>How wise you are!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Orestes</hi>, 213.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>We must, therefore, also habituate ourselves to
					things like these: when a letter is brought to us, not
					to open it quickly or in a hurry, as most people do, who
					go so far as to bite through the fastenings with their
					teeth if their hands are too slow ; when a messenger
					arrives from somewhere or other, not to rush up, or
					even to rise to our feet; when a friend says, <q direct="unspecified">I have
						something new to tell you,</q> to say, <q direct="unspecified">I should prefer
							that you had something useful or profitable.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					When I was once lecturing in Rome, that famous
					Rusticus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably Arulenus Rusticus, put to death in or after 93 a.d. for having in his biography of Paetus Thrasea called his subject <hi rend="italics">sanctus</hi> (Dio, lxvii. 13. 2, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Agricola</hi>, 2).</note> whom Domitian later killed through envy
					at his repute, was among my hearers, and a soldier
					came through the audience and delivered to him a
					letter from the emperor. There was a silence and I,
					too, made a pause, that he might read his letter ; but
					he refused and did not break the seal until I had
					finished my lecture and the audience had dispersed.
					Because of this incident everyone admired the dignity
					of the man.
				</p>
            <p>
					But when one nourishes his curiosity upon permissible material until he renders it vigorous and
					violent, he is no longer able to master it easily, since
					it is borne, by force of habit, toward forbidden things.
					And such persons pry into their friends' correspondence, thrust themselves into secret meetings, become spectators of sacred rites which it is an impiety
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.515"/>
					
					for them to see, tread consecrated ground, investigate
					the deeds and words of kings.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>And yet surely in the case of despots,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Politics</hi>, v. (viii.) 9. 3 (1313 b 12 ff.).</note>
					who have to know everything, it is the tribe of socalled <q direct="unspecified">Ears</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Jackals</q> that makes them
					most detested. It was Darius Nothus, who had no
					confidence in himself and regarded everyone with
					fear and suspicion, who first instituted <q direct="unspecified">Listeners</q> ;
					and <q direct="unspecified">Jackals</q> were distributed by the Dionysii <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Dion</hi>, xxviii. (970 b-c).</note>
					among the people of Syracuse. Consequently when
					the revolution came, these were the first persons
					whom the Syracusans arrested and crushed to death.
					And in fact the tribe of informers is from the same
					clan and family as busy bodies. But while informers
					search to see whether anyone has planned or committed a misdemeanour, busy bodies investigate and
					make public even the involuntary mischances of their
					neighbours. And it is said that the person called
					<hi rend="italics">aliterios</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Transgressor, or outlaw; Plutarch rejects this explanation in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 297 a.</note> first acquired his name from being a busybody. For it appears that when there was a severe
					famine at Athens and those who possessed wheat
					would not contribute it to the common stock, but
					ground<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The verb <foreign lang="greek">a)lei=n</foreign>, from which <foreign lang="greek">a)lith/rios</foreign> is here derived.</note> it in their houses secretly by night, some
					persons went about listening for the noise of the. mills,
					and so acquired the name <hi rend="italics">aliterioi</hi>. It was in the
					same way, they say, that the <hi rend="italics">sycophant</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Informer; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Solon</hi>, xxiv. (91 e); Athenaeus, 74 e-f.</note> won his
					name. Since the export of figs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">su=ka</foreign>.</note> was prohibited, men
					who revealed<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">fai/nein</foreign>, from which the noun -<foreign lang="greek">fa/nths</foreign>.</note> and gave information against those
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.517"/>
					
					who did export them were called <hi rend="italics">sycophants</hi>. So it is
					well worth the while of busybodies to consider this
					fact also, that they may be ashamed of the resemblance and relationship of their own practice to that
					of persons who are very cordially hated and loathed.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>