<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De defectu oraculorum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.5.p.348"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>THE OBSOLESCENCE OF
					ORACLES
					(DE DEFECTU ORACULORUM)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					Plutarch's answer to the question why many
					oracles in Greece have ceased to function is that the
					population is now much less than it was, and so there
					is less need for oracles now than in earlier times.
					For example, at Delphi there used to be twro prophetic priestesses with a third held in reserve ; now
					there is only one, and yet she is sufficient for every
					need.
				</p>
            <p>
					The statement of this simple fact hardly requires
					twenty-nine folio pages, but in this essay, as in the
					two preceding, there is much of the conversation of
					cultured persons which is not directly connected with
					the subject. Thus we find a discussion of whether
					the year is growing shorter, whether the number of
					the worlds is one or some number not more than five
					or is one hundred and eighty-three. We have further
					discussion of the number five, some astronomy, and
					a good deal of geometry, some interesting bits of
					information about Britain and the East and a rather
					long discussion of the <hi rend="italics">daimones</hi>, the beings a little
					lower than the gods and considerably higher than
					mortals ; perhaps the translation <q direct="unspecified">demi-gods</q> might
					best convey the idea in English. These beings are
					thought by many persons to be in charge of the
					oracles ; certainly the god himself does not appear
					personally at his oracles ; and in the case of the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.349"/>
					
					oracle at Delphi some account is given of the accidental discovery by a shepherd of the peculiar
					powers of the exhalation from the cleft in the
					rocks.
				</p>
            <p>
					Students of English literature will be interested in
					the dramatic description of the announcement of the
					death of Pan ; and students of religion will be interested in the essay as a very early effort to reconcile science and religion. That the essay had an
					appeal to theologians is clear from the generous
					quotations made from it by Eusebius and Theodoretus.
					We could wish that they had quoted even more,
					since their text is usually superior to that contained
					in the manuscripts, which in some places are quite
					hopeless. The mss. have also an unusual number of
					lacunae. Much has been done in the way of correction, sometimes perhaps too much, since Plutarch's
					thought is not always necessarily so logical as the
					editors would make it.
				</p>
            <p>
					Some parts of the essay make rather difficult
					reading, but it also contains passages of considerable
					interest and even beauty.
				</p>
            <p>
					The essay is No. 88 in Lamprias's list of Plutarch's
					works.
				</p>
            <p>
					The conversation is professedly narrated by
					Plutarch's brother Lamprias to Terentius Priscus,
					but some have thought that Plutarch has used the
					person of Lamprias to represent himself, possibly
					because of the official position held by Plutarch at
					Delphi.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.5.p.351"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="0">
            <p>(The persons taking part in the conversation are : Lamprias, Demetrius, Cleombrotus, Ammonius, Philip, Didymus, and Heracleon.)</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>The story<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The numerous other references to this story may be found most conveniently in Frazer's <hi rend="italics">Pausanias</hi>, v. p. 315.</note> is told, my dear Terentius Priscus,
					that certain eagles or swans, flying from the uttermost parts of the earth towards its centre, met in
					Delphi at the omphalus, as it is called ; and at a later
					time Epimenides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, ii. p. 191, Epimenides, no. b 11.</note> of Phaestus put the story to test
					by referring it to the god and upon receiving a vague
					and ambiguous oracle said,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Now do we know that there is no mid-centre of earth or of
						ocean;
						</l>
                  <l>Yet if there be, it is known to the gods, but is hidden from
						mortals.</l>
               </quote>
					Now very likely the god repulsed him from his attempt
					to investigate an ancient myth as though it were a
					painting to be tested by the touch. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Yet a short
					time before the Pythian games, which were held
					when Callistratus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The year 83-84 a.d.</note> was in office in our own day, it
					happened that two revered men coming from opposite
					ends of the inhabited earth met together at Delphi,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.353"/>
					
					Demetrius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Inscript. Graec.</hi> xiv. no. 2548 <foreign lang="greek">qeoi=s toi=s tou= h(gemonikou= *praitwri/ou *skrib</foreign>(<foreign lang="greek">w/nios&gt;</foreign>) (others <foreign lang="greek">skri=ba</foreign>) <foreign lang="greek">*dhmh/trios</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">*)okeanw=| kai\ *thqu/i *dhmh/tri</foreign>(<foreign lang="greek">os</foreign>). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Huebner, <hi rend="italics">Ephemeris Epigr.</hi> iii. 312; Clark, <hi rend="italics">Archaeol. Jour.</hi> xlii. p. 425; Dessau, in <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xlvi. (1911) pp. 156 ff.</note> the grammarian journeying homeward
					from Britain to Tarsus, and Cleombrotus of Sparta,
					who had made many excursions in Egypt and about
					the land of the Cave-dwellers, and had sailed beyond
					the Persian Gulf; his journevings were not for
					business, but he was fond of seeing things and
					of acquiring knowledge; he had wealth enough,
					and felt that it was not of any great moment to
					have more than enough, and so he employed his
					leisure for such purposes ; he was getting together
					a history to serve as a basis for a philosophy that had
					as its end and aim theology, as he himself named it.
					He had recently been at the shrine of Ammon, and
					it was plain that he was not particularly impressed by
					most of the things there, but in regard to the everburning lamp he related a story told by the priests
					which deserves special consideration ; it is that the
					lamp consumes less and less oil each year, and they
					hold that this is a proof of a disparity in the years,
					which all the time is making one year shorter in
					duration than its predecessor ; for it is reasonable
					that in less duration of time the amount consumed
					should be less.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>The company was surprised at this, and Demetrius went so far as to say that it was ridiculous to try
					in this way to draw great conclusions from small data,
					not, as Alcaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 184, Alcaeus, no. 113.</note> puts it, <q direct="unspecified">painting the lion from a
						single claw,</q> but with a wick and lamp postulating a
					mutation in the heavens and the universe, and doing
					away completely with mathematical science.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.355"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Neither of these things,</q> said Cleombrotus,
					<q direct="unspecified">will disturb these men ; certainly they will not
						concede any superior accuracy to the mathematicians,
						since it is more likely that a set period of time, in
						movements and cycles so far away, should elude
						mathematical calculation than that the measurement
						of the oil should elude the very men who were always
						giving careful attention to the anomaly and watching it closely because of its strangeness. Besides,
						Demetrius, not to allow that small things are indication of great stands directly in the way of many arts ;
						for it will result in taking away from us the demonstration of many facts and the prognostication of many
						others. Yet you people try to demonstrate to us
						also a matter of no small importance : that the heroes
						of old shaved their bodies with a razor, because you
						meet with the word <q direct="unspecified">razor</q> in Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 173.</note>; also that
						they lent money on interest because Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iii. 367-368.</note> somewhere says that <q direct="unspecified">a debt is owing, not recent nor
							small,</q> the assumption being that <q direct="unspecified">owing</q> signifies
						<q direct="unspecified">accumulating.</q> And again when Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 394, for example; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 923 b. Further explanation of the idea that <foreign lang="greek">qoo/s</foreign> may mean <q direct="unspecified">conical</q> may be found in the <hi rend="italics">Life and Poetry of Homer</hi>, 21 (Bernardakis's edition, vol. vii. p. 347).</note> speaks of
						the night as <q direct="unspecified">swift,</q> you cling to the expression with
						great satisfaction and say that it means this : that the
						Earth's shadow is by him called conical, being caused
						by a spherical body ; and as for the idea that medical
						science can predict a pestilential summer by a multitude of spiders' webs or by the fig-leaves in the spring
						when they are like crows' feet, who of those that
						insist that small things are not indications of great
						will allow this to go unchallenged ? Who will endure
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.357"/>
						
						that the magnitude of the sun be measured by reference to a quart or a gill, or that, in the sun-diai here,
						the inclination of the acute angle which its shadow
						makes with the level plane be called the measurement of the elevation of the ever-visible pole above
						the horizon ? This was what one might hear from
						the priests of the prophetic shrine there ; so some
						other rejoinder must be offered to them, if we would
						make for the sun the wonted order of its course
						immutable, in accord with the tradition of the ages.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Thereupon Ammonius the philosopher, who was
					present, exclaimed, <q direct="unspecified">Not for the sun only, but for
						the whole heavens. For the sun's course in passing
						from solstice to solstice must inevitably become
						shorter and not continue to be so large a part of the
						horizon as the mathematicians say it is, since the
						southern portion is constantly subject to a contracting movement, which brings it closer to the northern
						portion ; and so our summer must become shorter
						and its temperature lower, as the sun turns about
						within narrower limits and touches fewer parallels
						of latitude at the solstitial points ; moreover, the
						phenomenon observed at Syen&ecirc;,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Syen&ecirc; was on the Tropic of Cancer, and because of the fact that on the day of the summer solstice the sun was directly overhead it was used by Eratosthenes (third century b.c.) as one of the termini in calculating the circumference of the Earth. Cleomedes, <hi rend="italics">On the Circular Movement of Heavenly Bodies</hi>, i. 10, describes Eratosthenes' method.</note> where the upright
						rods on the sun-dials cast no shadow at the time of
						the summer solstice, is bound to be a thing of the
						past; many of the fixed stars must have gone below
						the horizon, and some of them must be touching one
						another, or have become coalescent, as the space
						separating them has disappeared ! But if, on the
						other hand, they are going to assert that, while all
						the other bodies are without change, the sun displays
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.359"/>
						
						irregularity in its movements, they will not be able
						to state the cause of the acceleration which affects the
						sun alone among so many bodies, and they will throw
						into confusion almost all the celestial mechanics,
						and into complete confusion those relating to the
						moon, so that they will have no need of measures of
						oil to prove the difference. In fact, the eclipses will
						prove it, as the sun more frequently casts a shadow
						on the moon and the moon on the earth ; the other
						facts are clear, and there is no need to disclose in
						further detail the imposture in the argument.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> said Cleombrotus, <q direct="unspecified">I myself actually saw
						the measure ; for they had many of them to show,
						and that of this past year failed to come up to the
						very oldest by not a little.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said Ammonius, taking up the argument
					again, <q direct="unspecified">this fact has escaped the notice of the other
						peoples among whom ever-burning fires have been
						cherished and kept alive for a period of years which
						might be termed infinite ? But on the assumption
						that the report is true, is it not better to assign the
						cause to some coldness or moisture in the air by which
						the flame is made to languish, and so very likely does
						not take up nor need very much to support it ? Or,
						quite the reverse, may we assign the cause to spells of
						dryness and heat ? In fact, I have heard people say
						before this regarding fire, that it burns better in the
						winter,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Comment. on Hesiod, Works and Days</hi>, 559 (Bernardakis's edition, vol. vii. p. 78).</note> being strongly compacted and condensed by
						the cold ; whereas in warm, dry times it is very weak
						and loses its compactness and intensity, and if it burns
						in the sunlight, it does even worse, and takes hold of
						the fuel without energy, and consumes it more slowly.
						Best of all, the cause might be assigned to the oil
						itself; for it is not unlikely that in days of old it
						
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.361"/>
						
						contained incombustible material and water, being
						produced from young trees ; but that later, being
						ripened on full-grown trees and concentrated, it
						should, in an equal quantity, show more strength and
						provide a better fuel, if the people at Ammon's shrine
						must have their assumption preserved for them in
						spite of its being so strange and unusual.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>When Ammonius had ceased speaking, I said,
					<q direct="unspecified">Won't you rather tell us all about the oracle,
						Cleombrotus ? For great was the ancient repute of
						the divine influence there, but at the present time it
						seems to be somewhat evanescent.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					As Cleombrotus made no reply and did not look up,
					Demetrius said, <q direct="unspecified"/>There is no need to make any
					inquiries nor to raise any questions about the state
					of affairs there, when we see the evanescence of the
					oracles here, or rather the total disappearance of all
					but one or two ; but we should deliberate the reason
					wrhy they have become so utterly weak. What need
					to speak of others, when in Boeotia, which in former
					times spoke with many tongues because of its oracles,
					the oracles have now failed completely, even as if they
					were streams of flowing water, and a great drought in
					prophecy has overspread the land ? For nowhere
					now except in the neighbourhood of Lebadeia has
					Boeotia aught to offer to those who would draw from
					the well-spring of prophecy. As for the rest, silence
					has come upon some and utter desolation upon others.
					And yet at the time of the Persian Wars many had
					gained a high repute, that of Ptoan Apollo no less
					than that of Amphiara&uuml;s ; Mys, as it seems, made
					
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.363"/>
					
					trial of both.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The mss. show several lacunae and corruptions here; the general sense must be restored from Herodotus, viii. 133-135. For some unexplained reason Plutarch in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Aristeides</hi>, chap. xix. (330 c) and Pausanias, ix. 23, lay this scene at the oracle of Trophonius at Lebadeia.</note> The prophetic priest of this oracle,
					accustomed in former times to use the Aeolic dialect,
					on that occasion took the side of the barbarians and
					gave forth an oracle such that no one else of those
					present comprehended it, but only Mys himself, since
					it is quite clear from the inspired language then used
					by the prophetic priest that it is not for barbarians
					ever to receive a word in the Greek tongue subservient
					to their command.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Themistocles</hi>, chap. vi. (114 d); <hi rend="italics">Life of Cato the Elder</hi>, chap. xxiii. (350 c).</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;The minion who was sent to the oracle of Amphiara&uuml;s had, in his sleep<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The oracle of Amphiara&uuml;s was an incubation oracle: the consultants went to sleep in the shrine and received their answer in dreams.</note> there, a vision of a servant of the
					god who appeared to him and tried first to eject him by
					word of mouth, alleging that the god was not there ;
					then next he tried to push him away with his hands,
					and, when the man persisted in staying, took up a
					large stone and smote him on the head. All this was
					in harmony, as it were, with events to come ; for
					Mardonius was vanquished while the Greeks were
					led, not by a king, but by a guardian and deputy of a
					king<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mardonius was defeated at Plataea in 479 b.c. by the Greeks under the command of Pausanias, who was regent of Sparta and guardian of Pleistarchus, son of Leonidas.</note>; and he fell, struck by a stone j ust as the Lydian
					dreamed that he was struck in his sleep.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">That time, too, was the most flourishing period of
						the oracle at Tegyrae, which place also by tradition is
						the birthplace of the god ; and of the two streams of
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.365"/>
						
						water that flow past it, the inhabitants even to this
						day call the one <q direct="unspecified">Palm</q> and the other <q direct="unspecified">Olive.</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch gives more information about Tegyrae in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Pelopidas</hi>, chap. xvi. (286 b).</note>
						Now in the Persian Wars, when Echecrates was the
						prophetic priest, the god prophesied for the Greeks
						victory and might in war ; and in the Peloponnesian
						War, when the people of Delos had been driven out
						of their island,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the year 421 b.c. (Thucydides, v. 1).</note> an oracle, it is said, was brought to
						them from Delphi directing them to find the place
						where Apollo was born, and to perform certain
						sacrifices there. While they were wondering and
						questioning the mere possibility that the god had been
						born, not in their island, but somewhere else, the
						prophetic priestess told them in another oracle that a
						crow would show them the spot. So they went away
						and, when they reached Chaeroneia, they heard the
						woman who kept their inn conversing about the
						oracle with some strangers who were on their way
						to Tegyrae. The strangers, as they were leaving,
						bade good-bye to the woman and called her by her
						name, which actually was <q direct="unspecified">Crow.</q> Then the Delians
						understood the meaning of the oracle and, having
						offered sacrifice in Tegyrae, they found a way to
						return home a short time thereafter. There have
						been also more recent manifestations than these at
						these oracles, but now the oracles are no more ; so
						it is well worth while, here in the precinct of the
						Pythian god, to examine into the reason for the
						change.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Proceeding onward from the temple, we had
					by this time reached the doors of the Cnidian Clubhouse.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the north-east corner of the sacred precinct. The foundations may still be seen.</note> Accordingly we passed inside, and there we
					saw sitting and waiting for us the friends to whom
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.367"/>
					
					we were going. There was quiet among the other
					people there because of the hour, as they were engaged
					in taking a rub-down or else watching the athletes.
					Then Demetrius with a smile said, <q direct="unspecified">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Shall I tell you
						a falsehood or speak out the truth?</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv. 140.</note> You seem to
						have on hand nothing worth considering ; for I see
						that you are sitting about quite at your ease and
						with faces quite relaxed.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> said Heracleon of Megara in reply, <q direct="unspecified">for
						we are not investigating which of the two lambdas in
						the verb <q direct="unspecified">hurl</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Present <foreign lang="greek">ba/llw</foreign>, future <foreign lang="greek">balw=</foreign>.</note> is the one that it loses in the future
						tense ; nor from what positives the adjectives <q direct="unspecified">worse</q>
						and <q direct="unspecified">better</q> and <q direct="unspecified">worst</q> and <q direct="unspecified">best</q> are formed ; for
						these and similar problems may set the face in hard
						lines, but the others it is possible to examine in a
						philosophic spirit, without knitting the brows, and to
						investigate quietly without any fierce looks or any
						hard feelings against the company.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Then permit us to come in,</q> said Demetrius,
					<q direct="unspecified">and with us a subject which has naturally occurred
						to us, one which is related to the place and concerns
						all of us on account of the god ; and beware of
						knitting your brows when you attack it!</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>When, accordingly, we had joined their company
					and seated ourselves among them and Demetrius had
					laid the subject before them, up sprang at once
					the Cynic Didymus, by nickname Planetiades, and,
					striking the ground two or three times with his staff,
					cried out, <q direct="unspecified">Aha ! a difficult matter to decide and one
						requiring much investigation is that which you have
						come bringing to us ! It is indeed a wonder, when
						so much wickedness has been disseminated upon
						earth that not only Modesty and Righteous Indignation, as Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 199.</note> said long ago, have deserted the life
						
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.369"/>
						
						of mankind, but that Divine Providence also has
						gathered up its oracles and departed from every
						place ! Quite the contrary, I propose that you discuss how it happens that the oracle here has not also
						given out, and Heracles for a second time, or some
						other god, has not wrested away the tripod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 387 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note> which
						is constantly being occupied with shameful and
						impious questions which people propound<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 408 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> to the
						god, some of whom try to make a test of him as
						though his wisdom were an affectation, while others
						init questions about treasures or inheritances or unawful marriages ; so Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 169 e.</note> is proved to be
						utterly wrong in asserting that men are at their
						best when they approach the gods. Thus those
						maladies and emotions of the soul which it would be
						good to disclaim and conceal in the presence of an
						older man, they bring naked and exposed before
						the god.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					He would have said more, but Heracleon seized
					hold of his cloak, and I, being about as intimate with
					him as anybody, said, <q direct="unspecified">Cease provoking the god, my
						dear Planetiades ; for he is of a good and mild disposition,
						<quote rend="blockquote">And towards mortal men he hath been judged the most
							gentle,</quote>
						as Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 394 a and 1102 e; Pindar, Frag. 149 (ed. Christ).</note> says. And whether he be the sun<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 386 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and the note.</note> or
						the lord and father of the sun and of all that lies
						beyond our vision,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The language is reminiscent of <foreign lang="greek">e)pe/keina th=s ou)si/as</foreign> (Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi> 509 b).</note> it is not likely that he should deny
						his utterance to people of the present day because of
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.371"/>
						
						their unworthiness, when he is responsible for their
						birth and nurture and their existence and power to
						think ; nor is it likely withal that Providence, like a
						benign and helpful mother, who does everything for
						us and watches over us, should cherish animosity in
						the matter of prophecy only, and take away that
						from us after having given it to us at the beginning,
						as if the number of wicked men included among a
						larger population were not larger at that earlier time
						when the oracles were established in many places in
						the inhabited world ! Come, sit down again and
						make a <q direct="unspecified">Pythian truce<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The sacred truce, made throughout the Greek world, for the duration of the Pythian games.</note>
                  </q> with evil, which you are
						wont to chastise with words every day, and join us in
						seeking some other reason for what is spoken of as
						the obsolescence of oracles ; but keep the god benign
						and provoke him not to wrath.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					What I had said was so far effective that Planetiades
					went out through the door without another word.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>There was quiet for a moment, and then
					Ammonius, addressing himself to me, said, <q direct="unspecified">See
						what it is that we are doing, Lamprias, and concentrate your thoughts on our subject so that we shall
						not relieve the god of responsibility. The fact is that
						the man who holds that the obsolescence of such
						of the oracles as have ceased to function has been
						brought about by some other cause and not by the
						will of a god gives reason for suspecting that he
						believes that their creation and continued existence
						was not due to the god, but was brought about in
						some other way. For prophecy is something created
						by a god, and certainly no greater or more potent
						force exists to abolish and obliterate it. Now I do not
						like what Planetiades said, and one of the reasons is
						the inconsistency which it creates regarding the god,
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.373"/>
						
						who in one way turns away from wickedness and
						disavows it, and again in another way welcomes its
						presence ; just as if some king or despot should shut
						out bad men at certain doors and let them in at others
						and have dealings with them. Now moderation,
						adequacy, excess in nothing, and complete selfsufficiency are above all else the essential characteristics of everything done by the gods ; and if anyone
						should take this fact as a starting-point, and assert
						that Greece has far more than its share in the general
						depopulation which the earlier discords and wars have
						wrought throughout practically the whole inhabited
						earth, and that to-day the whole of Greece would
						hardly muster three thousand men-at-arms, which is
						the number that the one city of the Megarians sent
						forth to Plataeae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ix. 21 and 28.</note> (for the god's abandoning of many
						oracles is nothing other than his way of substantiating
						the desolation of Greece), in this way such a man
						would give some accurate evidence of his keenness in
						reasoning. For who would profit if there were an
						oracle in Tegyrae, as there used to be, or at Ptoiim,
						where during some part of the day one might possibly
						meet a human being pasturing his flocks ? And
						regarding the oracle here at Delphi, the most ancient
						in time and the most famous in repute, men record
						that for a long time it was made desolate and unapproachable by a fierce creature, a serpent; they
						do not, however, put the correct interpretation upon
						its lying idle, but quite the reverse ; for it was the
						desolation that attracted the creature rather than
						that the creature caused the desolation. But when
						Greece, since God so willed, had grown strong in
						cities and the place was thronged with people, they
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.375"/>
						
						used to employ two prophetic priestesses who were
						sent down in turn ; and a third was appointed to be
						held in reserve. But to-day there is one priestess
						and we do not complain, for she meets every need.
						There is no reason, therefore, to blame the god ; the
						exercise of the prophetic art which continues at the
						present day is sufficient for all, and sends away all
						with their desires fulfilled. Agamemnon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 96.</note> for example, used nine heralds and, even so, had difficulty in
						keeping the assembly in order because of the vast
						numbers ; but here in Delphi, a few days hence, in
						the theatre you will see that one voice reaches all.
						In the same way, in those days, prophecy employed
						more voices to speak to more people, but to-day,
						quite the reverse, we should needs be surprised at the
						god if he allowed his prophecies to run to waste, like
						water, or to echo like the rocks with the voices of
						shepherds and flocks in waste places.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>When Ammonius had said this and I remained
					silent, Cleombrotus, addressing himself to me, said,
					<q direct="unspecified">Already you have conceded this point, that the god
						both creates and abolishes these prophetic shrines.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">No indeed,</q> said I, <q direct="unspecified">my contention is that no
						prophetic shrine or oracle is ever abolished by the
						instrumentality of the god. He creates and provides many other things for us, and upon some of
						these Nature brings destruction and disintegration ;
						or rather, the matter composing them, being itself a
						force for disintegration, often reverts rapidly to its
						earlier state and causes the dissolution of what was
						created by the more potent instrumentality ; and
						it is in this way, I think, that in the next period
						there are dimmings and abolitions of the prophetic
						agencies ; for while the god gives many fair things to
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.377"/>
						
						mankind, he gives nothing imperishable, so that, as
						Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 311, Sophocles, no. 766 (no. 850 Pearson). The same thought is in the <hi rend="italics">Oedipus at Colonus</hi>, 607.</note> puts it, <q direct="unspecified">the works of gods may die, but
							not the gods.</q> Their presence and power wise men
						are ever telling us we must look for in Nature and in
						Matter, where it is manifested, the originating influence being reserved for the Deity, as is right. Certainly it is foolish and childish in the extreme to
						imagine that the god himself after the manner of
						ventriloquists (who used to be called <q direct="unspecified">Eurycleis,</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurycles was a famous ventriloquist. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Sophist</hi>, 252 c, and Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Wasps</hi>, 1019, with the scholium.</note>
						but now <q direct="unspecified">Pythones</q>) enters into the bodies of his
						prophets and prompts their utterances, employing
						their mouths and voices as instruments.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 397 c and 404 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> For if he
						allows himself to become entangled in mens needs,
						he is prodigal with his majesty and he does not
						observe the dignity and greatness of his preeminence.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">You are right,</q> said Cleombrotus; &ldquo;but
					since it is hard to apprehend and to define in what
					way and to what extent Providence should be
					brought in as an agent, those who make the god
					responsible for nothing at all and those who make
					him responsible for all things alike go wide of
					moderation and propriety. They put the case well
					who say that Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 48 e ff., for example.</note> by his discovery of the element
					underlying all created qualities, which is now called
					<q direct="unspecified">Matter</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Nature,</q> has relieved philosophers of
					many great perplexities ; but, as it seems to me,
					those persons have resolved more and greater perplexities
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.379"/>
					
					who have set the race of demigods midway
					between gods and men,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Comment. on Hesiod, Works and Days</hi>, 122 (Bernardakis's edition, vol. vii. p. 52); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also 390 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and have discovered a force
					to draw together, in a way, and to unite our common
					fellowship - whether this doctrine comes from the
					wise men of the cult of Zoroaster, or whether it is
					Thracian and harks back to Orpheus, or is Egyptian,
					or Phrygian, as we may infer from observing that
					many things connected with death and mourning in
					the rites of both lands are combined in the ceremonies
					so fervently celebrated there. Among the Greeks,
					Homer, moreover, appears to use both names in
					common and sometimes to speak of the gods as demigods ; but Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Comment. on Hesiod, Works and Days</hi>, 122 (Bernardakis's edition, vol. vii. p. 52); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also 390 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> was the first to set forth clearly
					and distinctly four classes of rational beings : gods,
					demigods, heroes, in this order, and, last of all, men ;
					and as a sequence to this, apparently, he postulates
					his transmutation, the golden race passing selectively
					into many good divinities, and the demigods into
					heroes.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo; Others postulate a transmutation for bodies and
					souls alike ; in the same manner in which water is
					seen to be generated from earth, air from water, and
					fine from air, as their substance is borne upward, even
					so from men into heroes and from heroes into demigods the better souls obtain their transmutation.
					But from the demigods a few souls still, in the long
					reach of time, because of supreme excellence, come,
					after being purified, to share completely in divine
					qualities. But with some of these souls it comes to
					pass that they do not maintain control over themselves, but yield to temptation and are again clothed
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.381"/>
					
					with mortal bodies and have a dim and darkened
					life, like mist or vapour.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Hesiod thinks that with the lapse of certain
					periods of years the end comes even to the demigods ;
					for, speaking in the person of the Naiad, he indirectly
					suggests the length of time with these words:<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Frag. 183 (ed. Rzach); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the Latin version of Ausonius, p. 93, ed. Peiper (1886). See also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 989 a; Martial, x. 67; Achilles Tatius, iv. 4. 3.</note>
					             <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Nine generations long is the life of the crow and his
						cawing,
						</l>
                     <l>Nine generations of vigorous men.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                           <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Birds</hi>, 609.</note> Lives of four crows
						together
						</l>
                     <l>Equal the life of a stag, and three stags the old age of a
						raven ;
						</l>
                     <l>Nine of the lives of the raven the life of the Phoenix doth
						equal;
						</l>
                     <l>Ten of the Phoenix we Nymphs, fair daughters of Zeus of
						the aegis.</l>
                  </quote>
					Those that do not interpret <q direct="unspecified">generation</q> well make
					an immense total of this time ; but it really means
					a year, so that the sum of the life of these divinities
					is nine thousand, seven hundred and twenty years,
					less than most mathematicians think, and more than
					Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Frag. 165 (ed. Christ); quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 757 f.</note> has stated when he says that the Nymphs
					live
					<quote rend="blockquote">Allotted a term as long as the years of a tree,</quote>
					and for this reason he calls them Hamadryads.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					While he was still speaking Demetrius, interrupting
					him, said, <q direct="unspecified">How is it, Cleombrotus, that you can say
						that the year has been called a generation ? For
						neither of a man <q direct="unspecified">in his vigour</q> nor <q direct="unspecified">in his eld,</q> as
						some read the passage, is the span of human life such
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.383"/>
						
						as this. Those who read <q direct="unspecified">in their vigour</q> make a
						generation thirty years, in accord with Heracleitus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 76, Heracleitus, no. a 19.</note>
						a time sufficient for a father to have a son who is a
						father also ; but again those who write <q direct="unspecified">in their eld</q>
						and not <q direct="unspecified">in their vigour</q> assign an hundred and eight
						years to a generation ; for they say that fifty-four
						marks the limit of the middle years of human life, a
						number which is made up of the first number, the
						first two plane surfaces, two squares and two cubes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is 1 + (1x2) + (1x3) + 4 + 9 + 8 + 27 = 54.</note>
						numbers which Plato also took in his <hi rend="italics">Generation of the
							Soul</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 34 c - 35 a.</note> The whole matter as stated by Hesiod seems
						to contain a veiled reference to the <q direct="unspecified">Conflagration,</q>
						when the disappearance of all liquids will most likely
						be accompanied by the extinction of the Nymphs,
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Who in the midst of fair woodlands,
							</l>
                     <l>Sources of rivers, and grass-covered meadows have their
							abiding.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xx. 8-9.</note>
                     </l>
                  </quote>
               </q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> said Cleombrotus, <q direct="unspecified">I hear this from
					many persons, and I observe that the Stoic <q direct="unspecified">Conflagration,</q> just as it feeds on the verses of Heracleitus and Orpheus, is also seizing upon those of
					Hesiod. But I cannot brook this talk of universal
					destruction ; and such impossibilities, in recalling to
					our minds these utterances, especially those about
					the crow and the stag, must be allowed to revert
					upon those that indulge in such exaggeration. Does
					not a year include within itself the beginning and the
					end of <q direct="unspecified">all things which the Seasons and the Earth
						make grow,</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 97, Heracleitus, no. b 100.</note> and is it not foreign to men's ways to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.385"/>
					
					call it a <q direct="unspecified">generation</q>? As a matter of fact you
					yourselves surely agree that Hesiod by the word
					<q direct="unspecified">generation</q> means a man's life. Is not that so ?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> said Demetrius.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">And this fact also is clear,</q> said Cleombrotus,
					&ldquo;that often the measure and the things measured are
					called by the same name, as, for example, gill, quart,
					gallon, and bushel.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Censorinus, <hi rend="italics">De die natali ad Iu. Caerellium</hi>, xviii. 11, and Geffcken in <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xlix. 336.</note> In the same way, then, in which
					we call unity a number, being, as it is, the smallest
					number and the first ; so the year, which we use as
					the first measure of man's life, Hesiod has called by the
					same name as the thing measured, a <q direct="unspecified">generation.</q>
					The fact is that the numbers which those other
					persons produce have none of those notable and
					conspicuous qualities which may be inherent in
					numbers. The number nine thousand, seven hundred
					and twenty<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 415 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> has been produced by adding together
					the first four numbers and multiplying them by four,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">(1 + 2 + 3 + 4) x 4 = 40.</note>
					or by multiplying four by ten. Either process gives
					forty, and when this is multiplied five times by three
					it gives the specified number.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">40 x 3<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> = 9720.</note> But concerning these
					matters there is no need for us to disagree with
					Demetrius. In fact, even if the period of time in
					which the soul of the demigod or hero changes its life<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 415 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					be longer or shorter, determinate or indeterminate,
					none the less the proof will be there on the basis which
					he desires, fortified by clear testimony from ancient
					times, that in the confines, as it were, between gods
					and men there exist certain natures susceptible to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.387"/>
					
					human emotions and involuntary changes, whom it is
					right that we, like our fathers before us, should regard
					as demigods, and, calling them by that name, should
					reverence them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>&ldquo;As an illustration of this subject, Xenocrates,
					the companion of Plato, employed the order of the
					triangles ; the equilateral he compared to the nature
					of the gods, the scalene to that of man, and the
					isosceles to that of the demigods ; for the first is
					equal in all its lines, the second unequal in all, and the
					third is partly equal and partly unequal, like the
					nature of the demigods, which has human emotions
					and godlike power. Nature has placed within our ken
					perceptible images and visible likenesses, the sun and
					the stars for the gods, and for mortal men beams of
					light,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">All last night the northern streamers flashed across the western sky.</q>
               </note> comets, and meteors, a comparison which
					Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 674, Euripides, no 971. Plutarch quotes the lines again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1090 c.</note> has made in the verses :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>He that but yesterday was vigorous
						</l>
                  <l>Of frame, even as a star from heaven falls,
						</l>
                  <l>Gave up in death his spirit to the air.</l>
               </quote>
					But there is a body with complex characteristics which
					actually parallels the demigods, namely the moon ;
					and when men see that she, by her being consistently
					in accord with the cycles through which those beings
					pass,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 361 c, and the lines of Empedocles there quoted.</note> is subject to apparent wanings and waxings and
					transformations,some call her an earth-like star, others
					a star-like earth,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 935 c.</note> and others the domain of Hecate,
					who belongs both to the earth and to the heavens.
					Now if the air that is between the earth and the
					moon were to be removed and withdrawn, the unity
					and consociation of the universe would be destroyed,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.389"/>
					
					since there would be an empty and unconnected space
					in the middle ; and in just the same way those who
					refuse to leave us the race of demigods make the
					relations of gods and men remote and alien by doing
					away with the <q direct="unspecified">interpretative and ministering nature,</q>
					as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Republic</hi>, 260 d, and <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 202 e.</note> has called it ; or else they force us to a
					disorderly confusion of all things, in which we bring
					the god into men's emotions and activities, drawing
					him down to our needs, as the women of Thessaly are
					said to draw down the moon.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 400 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> This cunning deceit of
					theirs, however, gained credence among women
					when the daughter of Hegetor, Aglaonic&ecirc;, who was
					skilled in astronomy, always pretended at the time of
					an eclipse of the moon that she was bewitching it and
					bringing it down.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 145 c.</note> But as for us, let us not listen to
					any who say that there are some oracles not divinely
					inspired, or religious ceremonies and mystic rites which
					are disregarded by the gods; and on the other hand let
					us not imagine that the god goes in and out and is
					present at these ceremonies and helps in conducting
					them ; but let us commit these matters to those ministers of the gods to whom it is right to commit them, as
					to servants and clerks, and let us believe that demigods are guardians of sacred rites of the gods and
					prompters in the Mysteries, while others go about as
					avengers of arrogant and grievous cases of injustice.
					Still others Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 123, 126; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 361 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> has very impressively addressed as
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Holy
						</l>
                  <l>Givers of wealth, and possessing in this a meed that is kingly,</l>
               </quote>
					implying that doing good to people is kingly. For
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.391"/>
					
					as among men, so also among the demigods., there
					are different degrees of excellence, and in some there
					is a weak and dim remainder of the emotional and
					irrational, a survival, as it were, while in others this is
					excessive and hard to stifle. Of all these things there
					are, in many places, sacrifices, ceremonies, andlegends
					which preserve and jealously guard vestiges and tokens
					embodied here and there in their fabric.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>&ldquo;Regarding the rites of the Mysteries, in which
					it is possible to gain the clearest reflections and
					adumbrations of the truth about the demigods, <q direct="unspecified">let
						my lips be piously sealed,</q> as Herodotus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, ii. 171; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 607 c and 636 d.</note> says ; but
					as for festivals and sacrifices, which may be compared
					with ill-omened and gloomy days, in which occur the
					eating of raw flesh, rending of victims, fasting, and
					beating of breasts, and again in many places scurrilous
					language at the shrines, and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Frenzy and shouting of throngs in excitement
						</l>
                  <l>With tumultuous tossing of heads in the air,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Frag. 208 (ed. Christ). <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 623 b and 706 e.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					I should say that these acts are not performed for any
					god, but are soothing and appeasing rites for the
					averting of evil spirits. Nor is it credible that the gods
					demanded or welcomed the human sacrifices of
					ancient days, nor would kings and generals have
					endured giving over their children and submitting
					them to the preparatory rites and cutting their
					throats to no purpose save that they felt they were
					propitiating and offering satisfaction to the wrath and
					sullen temper of some harsh and implacable avenging
					deities, or to the insane and imperious passions of
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.393"/>
					
					some who had not the power or desire to seek satisfaction in a natural and normal way. But as Heracles
					laid siege to Oechalia for the sake of a maiden,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Iol&ecirc;; <hi rend="italics">cf. e.g.</hi> Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Trachiniae</hi>, 475-478.</note>
					so powerful and impetuous divinities, in demanding
					a human soul which is incarnate within a mortal
					body, bring pestilences and failures of crops upon
					States and stir up wars and civil discords, until they
					succeed in obtaining what they desire. To some,
					however, comes the opposite ; for example, when
					I was spending a considerable time in Crete, I noted
					an extraordinary festival being celebrated there in
					which they exhibit the image of a man without a
					head, and relate that this used to be Molus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A son of Deucalion.</note> father
					of Meriones, and that he violated a young woman ;
					and when he was discovered, he was without a head.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">As for the various tales of rapine and wanderings of the gods, their concealments and banishment
					and servitude, which men rehearse in legend and in
					song, all these are, in fact, not things that were done
					to the gods or happened to them, but to the demigods;
					and they are kept in memory because of the virtues
					and power of these beings ; nor did Aeschylus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Supplices</hi>, 214.</note> speak
					devoutly when he said
					<quote rend="blockquote">Holy Apollo, god from heaven banned;</quote>
					nor Admetus in Sophocles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 311, Sophocles, no. 767 (no. 851 Pearson).</note>
					             <quote rend="blockquote">My cock it was that sent him to the mill.</quote>
					But the greatest error in regard to the truth is that
					of the theologians of Delphi who think that the god
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.395"/>
					
					once had a battle here with a serpent for the possession
					of the oracle, and they permit poets and prose-writers
					to tell of this in their competitions in the theatres,
					whereby they bear specific testimony against the
					most sacred of the rites that they perform.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					At this Philip the historian, who was present,
					expressed surprise, and inquired against what hallowed
					rites Cleombrotus thought that the competition bore
					testimony. <q direct="unspecified">These,</q> said Cleombrotus, <q direct="unspecified">which
						have to do with the oracle here, and in which the city
						recently initiated all the Greeks west of Thermopylae
						and extended the rites as far as Temp&ecirc;. For the
						structure which is erected here near the threshing-floor<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At the right of the second section of the sacred way, as one progresses upwards toward the temple of Apollo.</note> every eight years<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 293 b-e.</note> is not a nest-like serpent's
						den, but a copy of the dwelling of a despot or king.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, a copy of the primitive circular house.</note>
						The onset upon it, which is made in silence through
						the way called <q direct="unspecified">Dolon's Way,</q> by which the Labyadae
						with lighted torches conduct the boy, who must have
						two parents living, and, after, applying fire to the
						structure and upsetting the table, flee through the
						doors of the temple without looking back ; and finally
						the wanderings and servitude of the boy and the
						purifications that take place at Temp&ecirc;  all prompt a
						suspicion of some great and unholy deed of daring.
						For it is utterly ridiculous, my good friend, that
						Apollo, after slaying a brute creature, should flee to
						the ends of Greece in quest of purification and, after
						arriving there, should offer some libations and perform those ceremonies which men perform in the
						effort to placate and mollify the wrath of spirits whom
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.397"/>
						
						men call the <q direct="unspecified">unforgetting avengers,</q> as if they
						followed up the memories of some unforgotten foul
						deeds of earlier days. And as for the story which I
						have heard before about this flight and the removal
						to another place, it is dreadfully strange and paradoxical, but if it has any vestige of truth in it, let us
						not imagine that what was done in those days about
						the oracle was any slight or common affair. But that
						I may not seem to be doing what is described by
						Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 235, Empedocles, no. b 24.</note> as
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Putting the heads of myths together,
							</l>
                     <l>Bringing no single path to perfection,</l>
                  </quote>
						permit me to add to what was said at the outset the
						proper conclusion, for we have already come to it.
						Let this statement be ventured by us, following the
						lead of many others before us, that coincidently with
						the total defection of the guardian spirits assigned to
						the oracles and prophetic shrines, occurs the defection of the oracles themselves ; and when the spirits
						flee or go to another place, the oracles themselves lose
						their power, but when the spirits return many years
						later, the oracles, like musical instruments, become
						articulate, since those who can put them to use are
						present and in charge of them.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>When Cleombrotus had expounded these
					matters, Heracleon said, <q direct="unspecified">There is no unsanctified or
						irreligious person present, or anyone who holds
						opinions about the gods that are out of keeping with
						ours ; but let us ourselves be stringently on our guard
						lest we unwittingly try to support the argument with
						extraordinary and presumptuous hypotheses.</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">That is a very good suggestion,</q> said Philip,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.399"/>
					
					          <q direct="unspecified">but which of the theses of Cleombrotus makes you
						the most uncomfortable?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">That it is not the gods,</q> said Heracleon, <q direct="unspecified">who
						are in charge of the oracles, since the gods ought
						properly to be freed of earthly concerns; but that it
						is the demigods, ministers of the gods, who have them
						in charge, seems to me not a bad postulate ; but to
						take, practically by the handful, from the verses of
						Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 267, Empedocles, no. b 115.</note> sins, rash crimes, and heaven-sent
						wanderings, and to impose them upon the demigods,
						and to assume that their final fate is death, just as
						with men, I regard as rather too audacious and uncivilized.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Cleombrotus was moved to ask Philip who the
					young man was and whence he carne ; and after
					learning his name and his city he said, <q direct="unspecified">It is not
						unwittingly, Heracleon, that we have become involved in strange arguments ; but it is impossible,
						when discussing important matters, to make any
						progress in our ideas toward the probable truth
						without employing for this purpose important principles. But you unwittingly take back what you
						concede ; for you agree that these demigods exist,
						but by your postulating that they are not bad nor
						mortal you no longer keep them ; for in what respect
						do they differ from gods, if as regards their being
						they possess immortality and as regards their virtues
						freedom from all emotion or sin ?</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>As Heracleon was reflecting upon this in
					silence, Philip said, &ldquo;Not only has Empedocles
					bequeathed to us bad demigods, Heracleon, but so
					also have Plato, Xenocrates, and Chrysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 1104 (p. 321).</note>; and,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.401"/>
					
					in addition, Demolitus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, ii. p. 94, Democritus, no. 166; and <hi rend="italics">Life of Timoleon</hi>, chap. i. (235 b).</note> by his prayer that he may
					meet with <q direct="unspecified">propitious spirits,</q> clearly recognized that
					there is another class of these which is perverse and
					possessed of vicious predilections and impulses.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">As for death among such beings, I have heard the
						words of a man who was not a fool nor an impostor.
						The father of Aemilianus the orator, to whom some
						of you have listened, was Epitherses, who lived in
						our town and was my teacher in grammar. He said
						that once upon a time in making a voyage to Italy
						he embarked on a ship carrying freight and many
						passengers. It was already evening when, near the
						Echinades Islands, the wind dropped, and the ship
						drifted near Paxi. Almost everybody was awake,
						and a good many had not finished their after-dinner
						wine. Suddenly from the island of Paxi was heard
						the voice of someone loudly calling Thamus, so that
						all were amazed. Thamus was an Egyptian pilot, not
						known by name even to many on board. Twice he
						was called and made no reply, but the third time he
						answered ; and the caller, raising his voice, said,
						<q direct="unspecified">When you come opposite to Palodes, announce
							that Great Pan is dead.</q> On hearing this, all, said
						Epitherses, were astounded and reasoned among
						themselves whether it were better to carry out the
						order or to refuse to meddle and let the matter go.
						Under the circumstances Thamus made up his mind
						that if there should be a breeze, he would sail past
						and keep quiet, but with no wind and a smooth sea
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.403"/>
						
						about the place he would announce what he had
						heard. So, when he came opposite Palodes, and
						there was neither wind nor wave, Thamus from the
						stern, looking toward the land, said the words as he
						had heard them : <q direct="unspecified">Great Pan is dead.</q> Even before
						he had finished there was a great cry of lamentation, not of one person, but of many, mingled with
						exclamations of amazement. As many persons were
						on the vessel, the story was soon spread abroad in
						Rome, and Thamus was sent for by Tiberius Caesar.
						Tiberius became so convinced of the truth of the
						story that he caused an inquiry and investigation to
						be made about Pan ; and the scholars, who were
						numerous at his court, conjectured that he was the
						son born of Hermes and Penelop&ecirc;.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 145.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Moreover, Philip had several witnesses among
					the persons present who had been pupils of the old
					man Aemilianus.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Demetrius said that among the islands lying
					near Britain<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably the Scilly islands; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 941 a - 942 a.</note> were many isolated, having few or
					no inhabitants, some of which bore the names of
					divinities or heroes. He himself, by the emperor's
					order, had made a voyage for inquiry and observation
					to the nearest of these islands which had only a few
					inhabitants, holy men who were all held inviolate by
					the Britons. Shortly after his arrival there occurred
					a great tumult in the air and many portents ; violent
					winds suddenly swept down and lightning-flashes
					darted to earth. When these abated, the people of
					the island said that the passing of someone of the
					mightier souls had befallen. <q direct="unspecified">For,</q> said they, <q direct="unspecified">as
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.405"/>
						
						a lamp when it is being lighted has no terrors, but
						when it goes out is distressing to many,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the interesting account which Plutarch gives in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 941 a ff., and Lucretius's statement that a smouldering lamp may cause apoplexy.</note> so the great
						souls have a kindling into life that is gentle and inoffensive, but their passing and dissolution often, as
						at the present moment, fosters tempests and storms,
						and often infects the air with pestilential properties.</q>
					Moreover, they said that in this part of the world
					there is one island where Cronus is confined, guarded
					while he sleeps by Briareus ; for his sleep has been
					devised as a bondage for him, and round about him
					are many demigods as attendants and servants.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Cleombrotus here took up the conversation and
					said, <q direct="unspecified">I too have similar stories to tell, but it is
						sufficient for our purpose that nothing contravenes
						or prevents these things from being so. Yet we
						know,</q> he continued, &ldquo;that the Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 1049 (p. 309).</note> entertain
					the opinion that I mention, not only against the demigods, but they also hold that among the gods, who
					are so very numerous, there is only one who is eternal
					and immortal, and the others they believe have come
					into being, and will suffer dissolution.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">As for the scoffing and sneers of the Epicureans<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">H. Usener, <hi rend="italics">Epicurea</hi> (Leipzig, 1887), 394.</note>
						which they dare to employ against Providence also,
						calling it nothing but a myth, we need have no fear.
						We, on the other hand, say that their <q direct="unspecified">Infinity</q> is a
						myth, which among so many worlds has not one that
						is directed by divine reason, but will have them all
						produced by spontaneous generation and concretion.
						If there is need for laughter in philosophy, we should
						laugh at those spirits, dumb, blind, and soulless, which
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.407"/>
						
						they shepherd for boundless cycles of years, and which
						make their returning appearance everywhere, some
						floating away from the bodies of persons still living,
						others from bodies long ago burned or decayed,
						whereby these philosophers drag witlessness and
						obscurity into the study of natural phenomena ; but
						if anyone asserts that such demigods exist, not only
						for physical reasons, but also for logical reasons, and
						that they have the power of self-preservation and
						continued life for a long time, then these philosophers
						feel much aggrieved.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>After these remarks Ammonius said, <q direct="unspecified">It
					seems to me that Theophrastus was right in his
					pronouncement. What, in fact, is there to prevent
					our accepting an utterance that is impressive and
					most highly philosophical ? For if it be rejected, it
					does away with many things which are possible but
					cannot be proved ; and if it be allowed as a principle,
					it brings in its train many things that are impossible
					or non-existent.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Some editors would insert a negative in the last sentence.</note> The one thing that I have heard
					the Epicureans say with reference to the demigods
					introduced by Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. 267, Empedocles, no. b 115.</note> is that it is not possible,
					if they are bad and sinful, that they should be happy
					and of long life, inasmuch as vice has a large measure
					of blindness and the tendency to encounter destructive agencies, so that argument of theirs is silly. For
					by this reasoning Epicurus will be shown to be a
					worse man than Gorgias the sophist, and Metrodorus
					worse than Alexis the comic poet; for Alexis lived
					twice as long as Metrodorus and Gorgias more than
					a third as long again as Epicurus. It is in another
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.409"/>
					
					sense that we speak of virtue as something strong,
					and vice as something weak, not with reference to
					permanence or dissolution of the body. For example,
					many of the animals that are sluggish in movement and slow in their reactions and many that are
					lascivious and ungovernable live a longer time than
					the quick and the clever. Therefore they do not
					well who make God's eternal existence to be the
					result of watchfulness and the thrusting aside of
					destructive agencies. No, immunity from emotion
					and destruction ought to reside in the blessed Being,
					and should require no activity on His part. Perhaps,
					however, to speak thus with reference to people that
					are not present does not show great consideration.
					So it is right that Cleombrotus should resume the
					topic which he discontinued a few moments ago
					about the migration and flight of the demigods.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Then Cleombrotus continued, <q direct="unspecified">I shall be surprised if it does not appear to you much more strange
					than what has already been said. Yet it seems to be
					close to the subject of natural phenomena and Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 421 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					has given the key-note for it, not by an unqualified
					pronouncement, but as the result of a vague concept,
					cautiously suggesting also the underlying idea in an
					enigmatic way ; but, for all that, there has been loud
					disparagement of him on the part of other philosophers. But there is set before us for general use a
					bowl of myths and stories combined, and where could
					one meet with more kindly listeners for testing these
					stories, even as one tests coins from foreign lands ?
					So I do not hesitate to favour you with a narrative
					about a man, not a Greek, whom I had great difficulty
					in finding, and then only by dint of long wanderings,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.411"/>
					
					and after paying large sums for information. It
					was near the Persian Gulf that I found him, where he
					holds a meeting with human beings once every year ;
					and there I had an opportunity to talk with him and
					met with a kindly reception. The other days of his
					life, according to his statement, he spends in association with roving nymphs and demigods. He was the
					handsomest man I ever saw in personal appearance
					and he never suffered from any disease, inasmuch as
					once each month he partook of the medicinal and
					bitter fruit of a certain herb. He was practised in the
					use of many tongues ; but with me, for the most part,
					he spoke a Doric which was almost music. While he
					was speaking, a fragrance overspread the place, as
					his mouth breathed forth a most pleasant perfume.
					Besides his learning and his knowledge of history,
					always at his command, he was inspired to prophesy
					one day in each year when he went down to the
					sea and told of the future. Potentates and kings'
					secretaries would come each year and depart. His
					power of prophecy he referred to the demigods. He
					made most account of Delphi and there was none of
					the stories told of Dionysus or of the rites performed
					here of which he had not heard ; these too he assert ed
					were the momentous experiences of the demigods
					and so, plainly, were those which had to do with
					the Python. And upon the slayer of that monster
					was not imposed an exile of eight full years,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 293 b-c.</note> nor,
					following this, was he exiled to Temp&ecirc;; but after
					he was expelled, he fared forth to another world,
					and later, returning from there, after eight cycles
					of the Great Years, pure and truly the <q direct="unspecified">Radiant
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.413"/>
						
						One,</q> he took over the oraele which had been
					guarded during this time by Themis. Such also, he
					said, were the stories about Typhons and Titans<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 360 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>;
					battles of demigods against demigods had taken
					place, followed by the exile of the vanquished, or else
					judgement inflicted by a god upon the sinners, as, for
					example, for the sin which Typhon is said to have
					committed in the case of Osiris, or Cronus in the case
					of Uranus ; and the honours once paid to these
					deities have become quite dim to our eyes or have
					vanished altogether when the deities were transferred
					to another world. In fact, I learn that the Solymi,
					who live next to the Lycians, paid especial honour to
					Cronus. But when lie had slain their rulers, Arsalus,
					Dryus, and Trosobius, he fled away from that place
					to some place or other, where they cannot say ; and
					then he ceased to be regarded, but Arsalus and those
					connected with him are called the <q direct="unspecified">stern gods,</q> and
					the Lycians employ their names in invoking curses
					both in public and in private. Many accounts
					similar to these are to be had from theological
					history. But, as that man said, if we call some of the
					demigods by the current name of gods, that is no cause
					for wonder ; for each of them is wont to be called
					after that god with whom he is allied and from whom'
					he has derived his portion of power and honour. In
					fact, among ourselves one of us is D&iuml;us, another
					Athenaeus, another Apollonius or Dionysius or
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.415"/>
					
					Hermaeus ; but only some of us have, by chance, been
					rightly named ; the majority have received names
					derived from the gods which bear no relation to the
					persons, but are only a travesty.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Cleombrotus said nothing more, and his account
					appeared marvellous to all. But when Heraeleon
					inquired in what way this was related to Plato and
					how he had given the key-note for this topic, Cleombrotus said, <q direct="unspecified">You well remember that he summarily
						decided against an infinite number of worlds, but had
						doubts about a limited number; and up to five<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 55 c-d; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 389 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 430 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
						he conceded a reasonable probability to those who
						postulated one world to correspond to each element,
						but, for himself, he kept to one. This seems to be
						peculiar to Plato, for the other philosophers conceived a fear of plurality,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Caelo</hi>, i. 8 (276 a 18).</note> feeling that if they did
						not limit matter to one world, but went beyond one,
						an unlimited and embarrassing infinity would at once
						fasten itself upon them.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> said I, <q direct="unspecified">did your far-away friend set a
						limit to the number of worlds, as Plato did, or did you
						not go so far as to sound him on this point when you
						had your interview with him ?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Was it not likely,</q> said Cleombrotus, <q direct="unspecified">that on
						anything touching these matters, if on nothing else,
						I should be an inquisitive and eager listener, when he
						so graciously put himself at my disposal and gave me
						the opportunity ? He said that the worlds are not
						infinite in number, nor one, nor five, but one hundred
						and eighty-three,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Proclus on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, p. 138 b.</note> arranged in the form of a triangle,
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.417"/>
						
						each side of the triangle having sixty worlds ; of the
						three left over each is placed at an angle, and those
						that are next to one other are in contact and revolve
						gently as in a dance. The inner area of the triangle is
						the common hearth of all, and is called the Plain of
						Truth, in which the accounts, the forms, and the
						patterns of all things that have come to pass and of
						all that shall come to pass rest undisturbed ; and
						round about them lies Eternity, whence Time, like
						an ever-flowing stream, is conveyed to the worlds.
						Opportunity to see and to contemplate these things
						is vouchsafed to human souls once in ten thousand
						years if they have lived goodly lives ; and the best of
						the initiatory rites here are but a dream of that
						highest rite and initiation; and the words of our
						philosophic inquiry are framed to recall these fair
						sights there  else is our labour vain. This,</q> said he,
					<q direct="unspecified">is the tale I heard him recite quite as though it
						were in some rite of mystic initiation, but without
						offering any demonstration or proof of what he
						said.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Then I, addressing Demetrius, said, <q direct="unspecified">How do
					the verses about the suitors run, when they are
					marvelling at Odysseus as he handles the bow?</q>
					And when Demetrius had recalled them to my mind,
					I said, <q direct="unspecified">It occurs to me to say this of your far-away
						friend :
						<quote rend="blockquote">Surely he liked to see, or else was given to filching<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xxi. 397.</note>
                  </quote>
						beliefs and tales of all sorts. He had ranged widely
						in literature and was no foreigner, but a Greek by
						birth, and replete with Greek culture to a high degree.
						The number of his worlds convicts him, since it is not
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.419"/>
						
						Egyptian nor Indian, but Dorian and from Sicily,
						being the idea of a man of Himera named Petron.
						Petron's own treatise I have never read nor am I sure
						that a copy is now extant; but Hippys<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 6, M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> vol. ii. p. 14.</note> of Rhegium,
						whom Phanias<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 22, M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> vol. ii. p. 300.</note> of Eresus mentions, records that this
						was the opinion and the account of it given by
						Petron : that there are one hundred and eighty-three
						worlds in contact with one another according to
						element; but what this is, <q direct="unspecified">to be in contact according
							to element,</q> he does not explain further nor subjoin
						any plausible proof.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Demetrius, joining in, said, <q direct="unspecified">What plausible proof
						could there be in matters of this sort in which even
						Plato, without stating anything reasonable or plausible, simply set down his own account ?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">But,</q> said Heracleon, <q direct="unspecified">we hear you grammarians attributing this view to Homer on the ground
						that he distributed the universe into five worlds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 390 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xv. 187.</note>:
						the heavens, the water, the air, the earth, and
						Olympus. Of these he leaves two to be held in
						common, the earth for all below and Olympus for
						all above, and the three that lie between were assigned
						to the three gods. In this wise Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 31 a, and 55 c; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 390 a and 887 b.</note> also, apparently, associated the fairest and foremost forms and
						figures with the different divisions of the universe,
						and called them five worlds, one of earth, one of
						water, one of air, one of fire, and last of all, the one
						which includes all these, the world of the dodecahedron, of wide expanse and many turnings, to
						which he assigned a form appropriate to the cycles
						and movements of the soul.</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.421"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Why,</q> said Demetrius, <q direct="unspecified">do we call up Homer in
						the present instance ? Enough of legends ! Plato,
						however, is very far from calling the five different
						divisions of the world five different worlds ; and in
						those passages again, in which he contends against
						those who postulate an infinite number of worlds, he
						says that his opinion is that this world is the only-begotten and beloved of God, having been created
						out of the corporeal whole, entire, complete, and
						sufficient unto itself. Wherefore one might well be
						surprised that he, in stating the truth himself, has
						supplied others with a source for a doctrine that is
						unconvincing and lacking in reason. For not to defend the idea of a single world implied somehow an
						assumption of the infinity of the whole universe ;
						but to make the worlds definitely just so many,
						neither more nor less than five, is altogether contrary
						to reason and devoid of all plausibility  unless,</q> he
					added, with a glance at me, <q direct="unspecified">you have anything
						to say.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">It appears,</q> said I, <q direct="unspecified">that we have already discontinued our discussion about oracles, feeling it to
						be completed, and are now taking up another topic
						just as large.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Not discontinued that topic,</q> said Demetrius,
					<q direct="unspecified">but not passing over this one which claims our
						attention. We will not spend much time on it, but
						only touch upon it long enough to inquire into its
						plausibility ; and then we will follow up the original
						proposition.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">In the first place, then,</q> said I, &ldquo;the considerations that prevent our making an infinite
					number of worlds do not preclude our making more
					than one. For it is possible for God and prophecy
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.423"/>
					
					and Providence to exist in more worlds than one, and
					for the incidence of chance to be reduced to the very
					smallest limits, while the vast majority of things and
					those of the highest importance attain to genesis
					and transmutation in a quite orderly sequence,
					none of which things does infinity, by its nature,
					admit. Then again it is more consistent with reason
					that the world should not be the only-begotten of
					God and quite alone. For He, being consummately
					good, is lacking in none of the virtues, and least of all
					in those which concern justice and friendliness ; for
					these are the fairest and are fitting for gods. Nor is
					it in the nature of God to possess anything to no
					purpose or for no use. Therefore there exist other
					gods and other worlds outside, in relation with
					which He exercises the social virtues. For not in
					relation with Himself nor with any part of Himself
					is there any exercise of justice or benevolence or
					kindness, but only in relation with others. Thus it
					is not likely that this world, friendless, neighbourless,
					and unvisited, swings back and forth in the infinite
					void, since we see that Nature includes individual
					things in classes and species, like seeds in pods and
					envelopes. For there is nothing in the whole list of
					existing things for which there is not some general
					designation, nor does anything that does not possess
					certain qualities, either in common with others or
					solely by itself, obtain such an appellation. Now the
					world is not spoken of as having qualities in common
					with others. It has its qualities, therefore, solely by
					itself, by virtue of the difference when it is compared
					with other things which are akin to it and similar in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.425"/>
					
					appearance, since it has been created with such
					qualities as it possesses. If in all creation such a
					thing as one man, one horse, one star, one god, one
					demigod does not exist, what is there to prevent
					creation from having, not one world, but more than
					one ? For he who says that creation has but one
					land and one sea overlooks a matter which is perfectly
					plain, the doctrine of similar parts<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes"/>; for we divide the
					earth into parts which bear similar names, and the
					sea likewise. A part of the world, however, is not
					a world, but something combined from the differing
					elements in Nature.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>&ldquo;Again, as for the dread which some people
					especially have felt, and so use up the whole of
					matter on the one world, so that nothing may be left
					over outside to disturb the structure of it by resisting
					or striking itthis fear of theirs is unwarranted. For
					if there are more worlds than one, and each of them
					has received, as its meet portion, substance and
					matter having a restricted measure and limit, then
					there will be nothing left unplaced or unorganized,
					an unused remnant, as it were, to crash into them
					from the outside. For the law of reason over each
					world, having control over the matter assigned to
					each, will not allow anything to be carried away from
					it nor to wander about and crash into another world,
					nor anything from another world to crash into it,
					because Nature has neither unlimited and infinite
					magnitude nor irrational and disorganized movement.
					Even if any emanation is carried from some worlds to
					others, it is certain to be congenial, agreeable, and to
					unite peaceably with all, like the rays of starlight and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.427"/>
					
					their blending ; and the worlds themselves must
					experience joy in gazing at one another with kindly
					eyes; and for the many good gods in each, they must
					provide opportunities for visits and a friendly welcome. Truly in all this there is nothing impossible
					or fabulous or contrary to reason unless, indeed,
					because of Aristotle's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Caelo</hi>, i. 7 (276 a 18).</note> statements some persons shall
					look upon it with suspicion as being based on physical
					grounds. For if each of the bodies has its own
					particular place, as he asserts, the earth must of
					necessity turn toward the centre from all directions
					and the water be above it, settling below the lighter
					elements because of its weight. If, therefore, there
					be more worlds than one, it will come to pass that in
					many places the earth will rest above the fire and the
					air, and in many places below them ; and the air and
					the water likewise, in some places existing in positions in keeping with nature and in other places in
					positions contrary to nature. As this, in his opinion,
					is impossible, the inference is that there are neither
					two worlds nor more, but only this one, composed of
					the whole of matter and resting firmly in keeping
					with Nature, as befits the diversity of its bodies.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>All this, however, has been put in a way that is
					more plausible than true. Look at it in this way, my
					dear Demetrius,&rdquo; said I ; &ldquo;when he says of the
					bodies that some have a motion towards the centre
					and downwards, others away from the centre and
					upwards, and others around the centre and in a
					circular path, in what relation does he take the
					centre ?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 925 b and 1054 b.</note> Certainly not in relation to the void, for
					according to him it does not exist. And according to
					those for whom it does exist, it has no centre, just
					as it has no point where it begins or where it ends ;
					
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.429"/>
					
					for these are limitations, and the infinite has no limitations. And if a man could force himself, by reasoning, to dare the concept of a violent motion of the
					infinite, what difference, if referred to this, is created
					for the bodies in their movements ? For in the void
					there is no power in the bodies, nor do the bodies
					have a predisposition and an impetus, by virtue of
					which they cling to the centre and have a universal
					tendency in this one direction. It is equally difficult,
					in the case of inanimate bodies and an incorporeal and
					undifferentiated position, to conceive of a movement
					created from the bodies or an attraction created by
					the position. Thus one conclusion is left : when the
					centre is spoken of it is not with reference to any
					place, but with reference to the bodies. For in this
					world of ours, which has a single unity in its organization from numerous dissimilar elements, these differences necessarily create various movements towards
					various objects. Evidence of this is found in the fact
					that everything, when it undergoes transformation,
					changes its position coincidently with the change
					in its substance. For example, dispersion distributes
					upwards and round about the matter rising from the
					centre and condensation and consolidation press it
					down towards the centre and drive it together.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>&ldquo;On this topic it is not necessary to use more
					words at present. The truth is that whatever cause
					one may postulate as the author of these occurrences
					and changes, that cause will keep each of the worlds
					together within itself; for each world has earth and
					sea, and each has its owTn centre and occurrences that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.431"/>
					
					affect its component bodies; it has its own transmutations and a nature and a power which preserves
					each one and keeps it in place. In what lies beyond,
					whether it be nothing or an infinite void, no centre
					exists, as has been said; and if there are several
					worlds, in each one is a centre which belongs to it
					alone, with the result that the movements of its
					bodies are its own, some towards it, some away from
					it, and some around it, quite in keeping with the
					distinctions which these men themselves make. But
					anyone who insists that, while there are many centres,
					the heavy substances are impelled from all sides
					towards one only,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 928 a-b.</note> does not differ at all from him
					who insists that, while there are many men, the blood
					from all shall flow together into a single vein and the
					brains of all shall be enveloped in a single membrane,
					deeming it a dreadful thing in the case of natural
					bodies if all the solids shall not occupy one place only
					and the fluids also only one place. Such a man as
					that will be abnormal, and so will he be who is indignant
					if everything constituting a whole has its own parts,
					of which it makes use in their natural arrangement
					and position in every case. For that would be preposterous, and so too if anybody called that a world
					which had a moon somewhere inside it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Instead of revolving around it.</note>; as well call
					that a man who carries his brains in his heels or his
					heart in his head!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi> vii. 45.</note> But to make more worlds than
					one, each separate from the other, and to delimit
					and distinguish the parts belonging to each to go
					with the whole is not preposterous. For the land
					and the sea and the heavens in each will be placed
					to accord with nature, as is fitting ; and each of
					the worlds has its above and below and its round
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.433"/>
					
					about and its centre, not with reference to another
					world or the outside, but in itself and with reference
					to itself.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>&ldquo;As for the stone which some assume to exist
					in the regions outside the world, it does not readily
					afford a concept regarding either its fixity or its
					motion. For how is it either to remain fixed, if it
					has weight, or to move towards the world like other
					heavy substances when it is no part of the world and
					has no place in the order of its being ? Land
					embraced in another world and bound up with it
					ought not to raise any question as to how it comes
					about that it does not break away from the whole
					and transfer itself to our world, because we see the
					nature and the tension under which each of the parts
					is held secure. For if we take the expressions
					' below ' and ' above ' as referring, not to the world,
					but outside of it,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1054 b.</note> we shall become involved in the
					same difficulties as Epicurus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 299.</note> who would have all his
					atoms move to places under our feet, as if either the
					void had feet, or infinity granted us to conceive of
					<q direct="unspecified">below</q> and <q direct="unspecified">above</q> within itself! Wherefore we
					may well wonder at Chrysippus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, i. 551 (p. 174), and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1054 c.</note> or rather be quite
					unable to understand what possessed him to assert
					that the world has been firmly set in the centre and
					that its substance, having pre-empted the central
					place from time eternal, thereby gains the greatest
					help towards its permanence, and that is as much
					as to say its immunity from destruction. This is
					actually what he says in the fourth book of his work
					on <hi rend="italics">Things Possible</hi>, where he indulges in a day-dream
					of a central place in the infinite and still more preposterously ascribes the cause of the permanence of
					the world to the non-existent centre ; yet in other
					
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.435"/>
					
					works lie has often said that substance is regulated
					and held together by its movements towards its own
					centre and away from its own centre.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>&ldquo;Then again, who could feel alarm at the
					other notions of the Stoics, who ask how there shall
					continue to be one Destiny and one Providence, and
					how there shall not be many supreme gods bearing
					the name of Zeus or Zen, if there are more worlds
					than one ? For, in the first place, if it is preposterous
					that there should be many supreme gods bearing this
					name, then surely these persons' ideas will be far
					more preposterous ; for they make an infinite number
					of suns and moons and Apollos and Artemises and
					Poseidons in the infinite cycle of worlds. But the
					second point is this : what is the need that there
					be many gods bearing the name of Zeus, if there
					be more worlds than one, and that there should
					not be in each world, as pre-eminent governor and
					ruler of the whole, a god possessing sense and reason,
					such as the one who among us bears the name of Lord
					and Father of all ? Or again, what shall prevent all
					worlds from being subject to the Destiny and Providence of Zeus, and what shall prevent his overseeing
					and directing them all in turn and supplying them all
					with first principles, material sources, and schemes of
					all that is being carried out ? Do we not in this
					world of ours often have a single body composed
					of separate bodies,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 142 e; Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Adversus Mathematicos</hi>, vii. 102.</note> as, for example, an assembly of
					people or an army or a band of dancers, each one of
					whom has the contingent faculty of living, thinking,
					and learning, as Chrysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 367 (p. 124).</note> believes, while in the
					whole universe, that there should be ten worlds, or
					fifty, or an hundred even, living under one reasoned
					plan, and organized under one government, is an
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.437"/>
					
					impossibility ? Yet such an organization is altogether
					appropriate for the gods. For we must not make
					them unable to go out, like the queens in a hive of
					bees, nor keep them imprisoned by enclosing them
					with matter, or rather fencing them about with it,
					as those<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 1055 (p. 311).</note> do who make the gods to be atmospheric
					conditions, or regard them as powers of waters or of
					fire blended therewith, and bring them into being at
					the same time with the world, and burn them up with
					it, since they are not unconfined and free like drivers
					of horses or pilots of ships, but, just as statues are
					riveted and welded to their bases, so they are enclosed and fastened to the corporeal; and are
					partners with it even unto destruction, dissolution,
					and transmutation, of whatsoever sort may befall.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">That other concept is, I think, more dignified
					and sublime, that the gods are not subject to outside
					control, but are their own masters, even as the twin
					sons of Tyndare&uuml;s<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Castor and Pollux, the protectors of sailors.</note> come to the aid of men who are
					labouring in the storm,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Soothing the oncoming raging sea,
						</l>
                     <l>Taming the swift-driving blasts of the winds,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Repeated with some variants by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1103 c-d; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 730.</note>
                     </l>
                  </quote>
					not, however, sailing on the ships and sharing in the
					danger, but appearing above and rescuing ; so, in the
					same way, one or another of the gods visits now this
					world and now that, led thither by pleasure in the
					sight, and co-operates with Nature in the directing
					of each. The Zeus of Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiii. 3.</note> turned his gaze not
					so very far away from the land of Troy towards the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.439"/>
					
					Thracian regions and the wandering tribes about the
					Danube; but the real Zeus has a fair and fitting
					variety of spectacles in numerous worlds, not viewing
					the infinite void outside nor concentrating his mind
					upon himself and nothing else, as some have
					imagined,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">The Eudemian Ethics</hi>, vii. 12. 16 (1245 b 14).</note> but surveying from above the many works
					of gods and men and the movements and courses of
					the stars in their cycles. In fact, the Deity is not
					averse to changes, but has a very great joy therein,
					to judge, if need be, by the alternations and cycles in
					the heavens among the bodies that are visible there.
					Infinity is altogether senseless and unreasoning, and
					nowhere admits a god, but in all relations it brings
					into action the concept of chance and accident. But
					the Oversight and Providence in a limited group and
					number of worlds, when compared with that which
					has entered one body and become attached to one
					and reshapes and remodels it an infinite number of
					times, seems to me to contain nothing involving less
					dignity or greater labour.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>Having spoken at this length, I stopped.
					Philip, after no long interval, said, <q direct="unspecified">That the truth
						about these matters is thus or otherwise is not for
						me to assert. But if we eliminate the god from one
						world, there is the question why we make him the
						creator of only five worlds and no more, and what
						is the relation of this number to the great mass of
						numbers ; and I feel that I would rather gain a
						knowledge of this than of the meaning of the E<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The meaning is discussed in the second essay of this volume.</note>
						dedicated here. For the number five represents
						neither a triangle nor a square, nor is it a perfect
						number nor a cube, nor does it seem to present any
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.441"/>
						
						other subtlety for those who love and admire such
						speculations. Its derivation from the number of
						elements, at which the Master<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably Pythagoras, but possibly Plato.</note> hinted darkly, is in
						every way hard to grasp and gives no clear intimation
						of the plausibility which must have drawn him on to
						assert that it is likely that when five bodies with
						equal angles and equal sides and enclosed by equal
						areas are engendered in matter the same number of
						worlds should at once be perfected from them.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> said I, <q direct="unspecified">Theodorus of Soli<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1027 d.</note> seems to
					follow up the subject not ineptly in his explanations
					of Plato's mathematical theories. He follows it up
					in this way : a pyramid, an octahedron, an icosahedron, and a dodecahedron, the primary figures
					which Plato predicates, are all beautiful because of
					the symmetries and equalities in their relations, and
					nothing superior or even like to these<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The five solids of which each has the same number of sides on all its faces, and all its solid angles made up of the same number of plane angles. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 53 c - 56 c, and Grote's <hi rend="italics">Plato</hi>, iii. 269.</note> has been left
					for Nature to compose and fit together. It happens,
					however, that they do not all have one form of
					construction, nor have they all a similar origin, but
					the pyramid is the simplest and smallest, while the
					dodecahedron is the largest and most complicated.
					Of the remaining two the icosahedron is more than
					double the octahedron in the number of its triangles.
					For this reason it is impossible for them all to derive
					their origin from one and the same matter. For those
					that are simple and small and more rudimentary
					in their structure would necessarily be the first to
					respond to the instigating and formative power, and
					to be completed and acquire substantiality earlier
					than those of large parts and many bodies, from
					which class comes the dodecahedron, which requires
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.443"/>
					
					more labour for its construction. Hence it follows
					that the only primal body is the pyramid, and not one
					of the others, since by their nature they are outdistanced by it in coming into being. Accordingly,
					the remedy which exists for this strange state of
					affairs consists in the division and separation of matter
					into five worlds, one where the pyramid shall acquire
					substantiality first, another for the octahedron, and
					another for the icosahedron ; then from the one that
					first acquires substantiality in each world the rest
					will have their origin, since a transmutation for everything into everything takes place according to the
					adaptability of parts to fit together, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 55 e ff.</note> himself
					has indicated, going into the details of nearly all cases.
					But for us it will suffice to acquire the knowledge
					in brief form. Since air is formed when fire is extinguished, and when rarefied again gives off fire out of
					itself, we must observe the behaviour of each of the
					generative elements and their transmutations. The
					generative elements of fire are the pyramid,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Does Plutarch (or Plato before him) see an etymological relation between <q direct="unspecified">pyramid</q> and <q direct="unspecified">pyr</q> (fire)? See also 428 d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> composed of twenty-four primary triangles, and likewise
					for air the octahedron, composed of forty-eight of the
					same. Therefore one element of air is produced
					from two corpuscles of fire combined and united ; and
					that of air again, when divided, is separated into two
					corpuscles of fire, and again, when compressed and
					condensed, it goes off into the form of water. The
					result is that in every case the one which first acquires
					substantiality always affords the others a ready means
					of coming into being through transmutation ; and it
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.445"/>
					
					is not one alone that first exists, but another in a
					different environment is endowed with movement,
					which takes the lead and forestalls the others in
					coming into being, and thus the name of being first
					is kept by all.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Manfully and zealously,</q> said Ammonius,
					<q direct="unspecified">have these matters been worked out by Theodorus ;
						but I should be surprised if it should not appear that
						he has made use of assumptions which nullify each
						other. For he insists that all the five shall not undergo
						construction at the same time, but the simplest always,
						which requires the least trouble to construct, shall
						first issue forth into being. Then, as a corollary to
						this, and not conflicting with it, he lays down the
						principle that not all matter brings forth the simplest
						and most rudimentary form first, but that sometimes
						the ponderous and complex forms, in the time of their
						coming into being, are earlier in arising out of matter.
						But apart from this, five bodies having been postulated
						as primary, and on the strength of this the number of
						worlds being put as the same, he adduces probability
						with reference to four only ; the cube he has taken off
						the board, as if he were playing a game with counters,
						since, because of its nature, it cannot transmute itself
						into them nor confer upon them the power of transmutation into itself, inasmuch as the triangles are not
						homologous triangles. For in the others the common
						triangle which underlies them all is the half-triangle ;
						but in this, and peculiar to it alone, is the isosceles
						triangle, which makes no convergence towards the
						other nor any conjunction that would unify the two.
						If, therefore, there are five bodies and five worlds, and
						in each one body only has precedence in coming into
						being, then where the cube has been the first to come
						
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.447"/>
						
						into being, there will be none of the others, since,
						because of its nature, it cannot transmute itself into
						any one of them. I leave out of account the fact that
						they make the element of the dodecahedron, as it is
						called, something else and not that scalene from
						which Plato constructs the pyramid and the octahedron and the icosahedron. So,</q> added Ammonius,
					laughing,<q direct="unspecified">either you must solve these problems
						or else contribute something of your own concerning this difficulty in which we all find ourselves
						involved.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">For the present, at least,</q> said I, &ldquo;I have
					nothing more plausible to offer; but perhaps it is better
					to submit to examination on views of one's own rather
					than on another's. I repeat, therefore, what I said
					at the beginning, that if two natures be postulated,
					one evident to the senses, subject to change in creation and dissolution, carried now here now there,
					while the other is essentially conceptual and always
					remains the same, it is a dreadful thing that, while
					the conceptual nature has been parcelled out and
					has variety within itself, we should feel indignant
					and annoyed if anyone does not leave the corporeal
					and passive nature as a unity knit together and converging upon itself, but separates and parts it. For
					it is surely fitting that things permanent and divine
					should hold more closely together and escape, so far
					as may be, all segmentation and separation. But
					even on these the power of Differentiation has laid
					its hand and has wrought in things conceptual dissimilarities in reasons and ideas, which are vaster
					than the separations in location. Wherefore Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Sophist</hi>, 256 c; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 391 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					opposing those who declare for the unity of the whole,
					says that these five things exist: Being, Identity,
					
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.449"/>
					
					Differentiation, and, to crown all, Movement and
					Rest. Granted, then, that these five exist, it is not
					surprising if each of these five corporeal elements has
					been made into a copy and image of each of them
					respectively, not unmixed and unalloyed, but it is
					because of the fact that each of them participates
					most in its corresponding faculty. The cube is
					patently a body related to rest because of the security
					and stability of its plane surfaces. In the pyramid
					everybody may note its fiery and restless quality in
					the simplicity of its sides and the acuteness of its
					angles. The nature of the dodecahedron, which is
					comprehensive enough to include the other figures,
					may well seem to be a model with reference to all
					corporeal being. Of the remaining two, the icosahedron shares in the nature of Differentiation mostly,
					and the octahedron in that of Identity. For this
					reason the octahedron contributed air, which in a
					single form holds all being in its embrace, and the
					icosahedron water, which by admixture assumes the
					greatest variety of qualities. If, therefore, Nature
					demands an equal distribution in all things, there is
					a reasonable probability that the wrorlds which have
					been created are neither more nor less in number
					than the patterns, so that each pattern in each world
					may have the leading rank and power just as it has
					acquired it in the construction of the primary bodies.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>&ldquo;However, let this be a comfort for him that
					wonders because we divide Nature into so many
					classes in its generation and transmutation. But
					here is another matter<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 387 f ff., <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> which I ask you all to consider,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.451"/>
					
					and to give your undivided attention to it: of
					those numbers which come at the very first (I mean
					the number one and the indeterminate duality), the
					second, being the element underlying all formlessness
					and disarrangement, has been called infinity; but
					the nature of the number one limits and arrests what
					is void and irrational and indeterminate in infinity,
					gives it shape, and renders it in some way tolerant
					and receptive of definition, which is the next step
					after demonstration regarding things perceptible.
					Now these first principles make their appearance at
					the beginning in connexion with number; rather,
					however, larger amounts are not number at all unless
					the number one, created from the illimitability of
					infinity, like a form of matter, cuts off more on
					one side and less on the other. Then, in fact, any of
					the larger amounts becomes number through being
					delimited by the number one. But if the number
					one be done away with, once more the indeterminate
					duality throws all into confusion, and makes it to be
					without rhythm, bounds, or measure. Inasmuch as
					form is not the doing away with matter, but a shaping
					and ordering of the underlying matter, it needs must
					be that both these first principles be existent in
					number, and from this has arisen the first and greatest
					divergence and dissimilarity. For the indeterminate
					first principle is the creator of the even, and the better
					one of the odd. Two is the first of the even numbers
					and three the first of the odd ; from the two combined comes five,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 388 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> which in its composition is common
					to both numbers and in its potentiality is odd. For
					when the perceptible and corporeal was divided into
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.453"/>
					
					several parts because of the innate necessity of
					differentiation, that number had to be neither the
					first even nor the first odd, but the third number,
					which is formed from these two, so that it might
					be produced from both the primary principles, that
					which created the even and that which created the
					odd, because it was not possible for the one to
					be divorced from the other ; for each possesses the
					nature and the potentiality of a first principle. So
					when the twro were paired, the better one prevailed
					over the indeterminate as it was dividing the corporeal
					and checked it; and when matter was being distributed to the two, it set unity in the middle and
					did not allow the whole to be divided into two parts,
					but there has been created a number of worlds by
					differentiation of the indeterminate and by its being
					carried in varying directions ; yet the power of
					Identity and Limitation has had the effect of making
					that number odd, but the kind of odd that did not
					permit Nature to progress beyond what is best. If
					the number one were unalloyed and pure, matter
					would not have any separation at all ; but since it has
					been combined with the dividing power of duality, it
					has had to submit to being cut up and divided, but
					there it stopped, the even being overpowered by the
					odd.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>&ldquo;It was for this reason that among the people
					of olden time it was the custom to call counting
					<q direct="unspecified">numbering by fives,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 374 a and 387 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> I think also that <q direct="unspecified">panta</q>
					(all) is derived from <q direct="unspecified">pente</q> (five) in accord with
					reason, inasmuch as the pentad is a composite of the
					first numbers.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 374 a and 387 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> As a matter of fact, when the others
					are multiplied by other numbers, the result is a
					number different from themselves ; but the pentad,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.455"/>
					
					if it be taken an even number of times, makes ten
					exactly ; and if an odd number of times, it reproduces
					itself.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 388 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> I leave out of account the fact that it is the
					first composite of the first two squares, unity and the
					tetrad<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 391 a.</note>; and that it is the first whose square is equal
					to the two immediately preceding it, making with
					them the most beautiful of the right-angled triangles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 373 f.</note>;
					and it is the first to give the ratio 1 1/2 : 1.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 389 d.</note> However,
					perhaps these matters have not much relation to
					the subject before us; but there is another matter
					more closely related, and that is the dividing power of
					this number, by reason of its nature, and the fact that
					Nature does distribute most things by fives. For
					example, she has allotted to ourselves five senses and
					five parts to the soul<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 390 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 410 b, 440 e - 441 a; and much diffused in <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 70 ff.</note>: physical growth, perception,
					appetite, fortitude, and reason; also five fingers on
					each hand, and the most fertile seed when it is divided
					five times, for there is no record that a woman ever
					had more than five children together at one birth.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 264 b; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animalium</hi>, vii. 4 (584 b 33); since Plutarch's time there have been a few authenticated cases of sextuplets.</note>
					The Egyptians have a tradition<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 355 d-f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that Rhea gave birth
					to five gods, an intimation of the genesis of the five
					worlds from one single Matter; and in the universe
					the surface of the earth is divided among five zones,
					and the heavens by five circles, two arctic, two tropic,
					and the equator in the middle. Five, too, are the
					orbits of the planets, if the Sun and Venus and Mercury
					follow the same course. The organization of the world
					also is based on harmony, just as a tune with us is seen
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.457"/>
					
					to depend on the five notes of the tetrachord<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 389 e, 1028 f, 1138 f - 1139 e.</note>:
					lowest, middle, conjunct, disjunct, and highest ; and
					the musical intervals are five : quarter-tone, semitone,
					tone, tone and a half, and double tone. Thus it
					appears that Nature takes a greater delight in making
					all things in fives than in making them round, as
					Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Caelo</hi>, ii. 4 (286 b 10).</note> has said.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">&lsquo;Why, then,&rsquo; someone will say, &lsquo;did Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 55 c.</note>
					refer the number of his five worlds to the five geometric figures, saying that God used up the fifth
					construction on the universe in completing its
					embellishment?&rsquo; Further on, where he suggests the
					question about there being more worlds than one,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 31 a; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 389 f and 421 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					whether it is proper to speak of one or of five as in
					truth naturally existent, it is clear that he thinks that
					the idea started from this source. If, therefore, we
					must apply reasonable probability to his conception,
					let us consider that variations in movement necessarily
					follow close upon the variations in the bodies and their
					shapes, as he himself teaches<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 57 c.</note> when he makes it plain
					that whatever is disunited or united changes its place
					at the same time with the alteration of its substance.
					For example, if fire is generated from air by the
					breaking up of the octahedron and its resolution into
					pyramids, or again if air is generated from fire by its
					being forced together and compressed into an octahedron, it is not possible for it to stay where it was
					before, but it escapes and is carried to some other
					place, forcing its way out and contending against
					anything that blocks its course or keeps it back.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.459"/>
					
					What takes place he describes more clearly by a
					simile,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 52 e.</note> saying that in a manner like to &lsquo;grain and
					chaff being tossed about and winnowed by the fans
					and other tools used in cleaning the grain&rsquo; the
					elements toss matter about and are tossed about by
					it; and like always draws near1 to like, some things
					occupying one place and others another, before the
					universe becomes completely organized out of the
					elements. Thus, when matter was in that state in
					which, in all probability, is the universe from which God
					is absent, the first five properties, having tendencies
					of their own, were at once carried in different directions, not being completely or absolutely separated,
					because, when all things were amalgamated, the
					inferior always followed the superior in spite of
					Nature.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Some would prefer to make Plutarch say &lsquo;in keeping with Nature.&rsquo;</note> For this reason they produced in the
					different kinds of bodies, as these were carried some
					in one direction and others in another, an equal
					number of separate divisions with intervals between
					them, one not of pure fire, but fiery, another not of
					unmingled ether, but ethereal, another not of earth
					by itself alone, but earthy ; and above all, in keeping
					with the close association of air with water, they
					contrived, as has been said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 428 d-e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that these should come
					away filled with many foreign elements. It was not
					the Deity who parted substance and caused it to rest
					in different places, but, after it had been parted by its
					own action and was being carried in diverse ways in
					such great disarray, he took it over and set it in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.461"/>
					
					order and fitted it together by the use of proportions
					and means. Then, after establishing Reason in each as
					a governor and guardian, he creatjed as many worlds
					as the existing primal bodies. Let this, then, be an
					offering for the gratification of Plato on Ammonius's
					account, but as for myself, I should not venture to
					assert regarding the number of wbrlds that they are
					just so many ; but the opinion that sets their number
					at more than one, and yet not infinite, but limited in
					amount, I regard as no more irrational than either
					of the others, when I observe the dispersiveness and
					divisibility implicit by nature in Matter, and that it
					neither abides as a unit nor is permitted by Reason to
					progress to infinity. But if in any other place we have
					recalled the Academy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 387 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> to our mind, let us do so here
					as well, and divest ourselves of excessive credulity
					and, as if we were in a slippery place in our discussion
					about infinity, let us merely keep a firm footing.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>When I had said this, Demetrius remarked,
					<q direct="unspecified">Lamprias gives the right advice ; for
						<quote rend="blockquote">The gods make us to slip by many forms</quote>
						not &lsquo;of tricks,&rsquo; as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 674, Euripides, no. 972.</note> says, but of facts,
						whenever we make bold to pronounce opinions about
						such matters as if we understood them. &lsquo;But the
						discussion must be carried back,&rsquo; as the same writer
						says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 390 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> to the assumption made at the beginning. For
						what was said then, that when the demigods withdraw and forsake the oracles, these lie idle and
						inarticulate like the instruments of musicians, raises
						another question of greater import regarding the
						causative means and power which they employ to
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.463"/>
						
						make the prophetic priests and priestesses possessed
						by inspiration and able to present their visions. For
						it is not possible to hold that the desertion by the
						demigods is the reason for the silence of the oracles
						unless we are convinced as to the manner in which
						the demigods, by having the oracles in their charge
						and by their presence there, make them active and
						articulate.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Here Ammonius joined in and said, <q direct="unspecified">Do you really
						think that the demigods are aught else than souls that
						make their rounds, &lsquo;in mist apparelled,&rsquo; as Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 125.</note>
						says ? To my mind the difference between man and
						man in acting tragedy or comedy is the difference
						between soul and soul arrayed in a body suitable for
						its present life. It is, therefore, not at all unreasonable
						or even marvellous that souls meeting souls should
						create in them impressions of the future, exactly as
						we do not convey all our information to one another
						through the spoken word, but by writing also, or
						merely by a touch or a glance, we give much information about what has come to pass and intimation
						of what is to come. Unless it be, Lamprias, that you
						have another story to tell. For not long ago a rumour
						reached us about your having had a long talk on these
						subjects with strangers at Lebadeia, but the man who
						told of it could recall none of it with exactness.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">You need not be surprised,</q> said I, <q direct="unspecified">since many
						activities and distractions occurring in the midst of it,
						because it was a day for oracles and sacrifice, made
						our conversation desultory and disconnected.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">But now,</q> said Ammonius, <q direct="unspecified">you have listeners
						with nothing to distract them and eager to seek and
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.465"/>
						
						gain information on this point or that ; all strife and
						contention is banished and a sympathetic hearing
						and freedom of statement, as you observe, is granted
						for all that may be said.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>As the others also joined in the request, I, after
					a moment of silence, continued, &ldquo;As a matter of fact,
					Ammonius, by some chance you happen to be the one
					who provided the opening and approach for what was
					said on that occasion. For if the souls which have
					been severed from a body, or have had no part with
					one at all, are demigods according to you and the
					divine Hesiod,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 123.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Holy dwellers on earth and the guardian spirits of mortals,</quote>
					why deprive souls in bodies of that power by virtue
					of which the demigods possess the natural faculty
					of knowing and revealing future events before they
					happen ? For it is not likely that any power or portion accrues to souls when they have left the body,
					if they did not possess them before ; but the souls
					always possess them ; only they possess them to
					a slight degree while conjoined with the body, some
					of them being completely imperceptible and hidden,
					others weak and dim, and about as ineffectual and
					slow in operation as persons that try to see in a fog or
					to move about in water, and requiring much nursing
					and restoring of the functions that properly belong to
					them and the removal and clearing away of the covering which hides them. Just as the sun does not
					become bright when it bursts through the clouds,
					but is bright always, and yet in a fog appears to us
					indistinct and dim, even so the soul does not acquire
					the prophetic power when it goes forth from the body
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.467"/>
					
					as from a cloud ; it possesses that power even now,
					but is blinded by being combined and commingled
					with the mortal nature. We ought not to feel surprised or incredulous at this when we see in the
					soul, though we see naught else, that faculty which
					is the complement of prophecy, and which we call
					memory, and how great an achievement is displayed
					in preserving and guarding the past, or rather what
					has been the present, since nothing of all that has
					come to pass has any existence or substantiality,
					because the very instant when anything comes to
					pass, that is the end of it  of actions, words, experiences alike ; for Time like an everflowing stream
					bears all things onward. But this faculty of the soul
					lays hold upon them, I know not how, and invests with
					semblance and being things not now present here.
					The oracle given to the Thessalians about Arn&ecirc;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, i. 12.</note> bade
					them note
					<quote rend="blockquote">A deaf man's hearing, a blind man's sight.</quote>
					But memory is for us the hearing of deeds to which
					we are deaf and the seeing of things to which we are
					blind. Hence, as I said, it is no wonder that, if it has
					command over things that no longer are, it anticipates
					many of those which have not yet come to pass, since
					these are more closely related to it, and with these
					it has much in common ; for its attachments and
					associations are with the future, and it is quit of all
					that is past and ended, save only to remember it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>&ldquo;Souls therefore, all possessed of this power,
					which is innate but dim and hardly manifest, nevertheless oftentimes disclose its flower and radiance in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.469"/>
					
					dreams, and some in the hour of death,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, 39 b.</note> when the
					body becomes cleansed of all impurities and attains
					a temperament adapted to this end, a temperament
					through which the reasoning and thinking faculty of
					the souls is relaxed and released from their present
					state as they range amid the irrational and imaginative realms of the future. It is not true, as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 674, Euripides, no. 973; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 399 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					says, that
					<quote rend="blockquote">The best of seers is he that guesses well;</quote>
					no, the best of seers is the intelligent man, following
					the guidance of that in his soul which possesses sense
					and which, with the help of reasonable probability,
					leads him on his way. But that which foretells the
					future, like a tablet without writing, is both irrational
					and indeterminate in itself, but receptive of impressions and presentiments through what may be done
					to it, and inconsequently grasps at the future when
					it is farthest withdrawn from the present. Its withdrawal is brought about by a temperament and disposition of the body as it is subjected to a change
					which we call inspiration. Often the body of itself
					alone attains this disposition. Moreover the earth
					sends forth for men streams of many other potencies,
					some of them producing derangements, diseases, or
					deaths ; others helpful, benignant, and beneficial, as
					is plain from the experience of persons who have
					come upon them. But the prophetic current and
					breath is most divine and holy, whether it issue by
					itself through the air or come in the company of
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.471"/>
					
					running waters ; for when it is instilled into the body,
					it creates in souls an unaccustomed and unusual
					temperament, the peculiarity of which it is hard to
					describe with exactness, but analogy offers many
					comparisons. It is likely that by warmth and diffusion
					it opens up certain passages through which impressions of the future are transmitted, just as wine,
					when its fumes rise to the head, reveals many unusual
					movements and also words stored away and unperceived.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>For Bacchic rout
						</l>
                  <l>And frenzied mind contain much prophecy,</l>
               </quote>
					according to Euripides,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Bacchae</hi>, 298.</note> when the soul becomes hot
					and fiery, and throw's aside the caution that human
					intelligence lays upon it, and thus often diverts and
					extinguishes the inspiration.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>&ldquo;At the same time one might assert, not without reason, that a dryness engendered with the heat
					subtilizes the spirit of prophecy and renders it
					ethereal and pure ; for this is &lsquo;the dry soul,&rsquo; as
					Heracleitus has it.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">&lsquo;A dry soul is best (and/or wisest)&rsquo; is the dictum of Heracleitus, which is often quoted; see Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 100, Heracleitus, no. b 118; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 995 e, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Romulus</hi>, chap. xxviii. (36 a).</note> Moisture not only dulls sight and
					hearing, but when it touches mirrors and combines
					with air, it takes away their brightness and sheen.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 736 a-b.</note>
					But again the very opposite of this may not be
					impossible : that by a sort of chilling and compacting
					of the spirit of inspiration the prophetic element in
					the soul, as when steel is dipped in cold water, is
					rendered tense and keen. And further, just as tin
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.473"/>
					
					when alloyed with copper, which is loose and porous
					in texture, binds it together and compacts it,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Generatione Animalium</hi>, ii. 8 (747 a 34).</note> and
					at the same time makes it brighter and cleaner, even
					so there is nothing to prevent the prophetic vapour,
					which contains some affinity and relationship to souls,
					from filling up the vacant spaces and cementing all
					together by fitting itself in. For one thing has
					affinity and adaptability for one thing, another for
					another, just as the bean<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> H. Bl&uuml;mner, <hi rend="italics">Gewerbe und K&uuml;nste bei Griechen und R&ouml;mern</hi> (Leipzig, 1875), i. 236.</note> seems to further the
					dyeing of purple and sodium carbonate<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 238.</note> that of
					scarlet, when mixed with the dye ;
					<quote rend="blockquote">All in the linen is blended the splendour of glorious scarlet,</quote>
					as Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 255, Empedocles, no. b 93.</note> has said. But regarding the Cydnus
					and the sacred sword of Apollo in Tarsus we used
					to hear you say, my dear Demetrius, that the
					Cydnus will cleanse no steel but that, and no other
					water will cleanse that sword. There is a similar
					phenomenon at Olympia, where they pile the ashes
					against the altar and make them adhere all around
					by pouring on them water from the Alpheius ; but,
					although they have tried the waters of other rivers,
					there is none with which they can make the ashes
					cohere and stay fixed in their place.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>&ldquo;It is not, therefore, anything to excite
					amazement if, although the earth sends up many
					streams, it is only such as these that dispose souls to
					inspiration and impressions of the future. Certainly
					the voice of legend also is in accord with my statement;
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.475"/>
					
					for they record that here the power hovering
					about this spot was first made manifest when a
					certain shepherd fell in by accident and later gave
					forth inspired utterances, which those who came into
					contact with him at first treated with disdain ; but
					later, when what he had foretold came to pass, they
					were amazed. The most learned of the people of
					Delphi still preserve the tradition of his name, which
					they say was Coretas. But I incline most to the
					opinion that the soul acquires towards the prophetic
					spirit a close and intimate connexion of the sort that
					vision has towards light, which possesses similar
					properties. For, although the eye has the power of
					vision, there is no function for it to perform without
					light<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 436 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 508 a - 509 b.</note>; and so the prophetic power of the soul, like an
					eye, has need of something kindred to help to kindle
					it and stimulate it further. Hence many among
					earlier generations regarded Apollo and the Sun as
					one and the same god ; but those who understood and
					respected fair and wise analogy conjectured that as
					body is to soul, vision to intellect, and light to truth,
					so is the power of the sun to the nature of Apollo ;
					and they would make it appear that the sun is his
					offspring and progeny, being for ever born of him that
					is for ever. For the sun kindles and promotes and
					helps to keep in activity the power of vision in our
					perceptive senses, just as the god does for the power
					of prophecy in the soul.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>&ldquo;Those, however, who had reached the conclusion that the two are one and the same god very
					naturally dedicated the oracle to Apollo and Earth in
					common, thinking that the sun creates the disposition
					and temperament in the earth from which the prophet-inspiring
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.477"/>
					
					vapours are wafted forth. As Hesiod,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 117.</note> then,
					with a better understanding than some philosophers,
					spoke of the Earth itself as
					<quote rend="blockquote">Of All the unshaken foundation,</quote>
					so we believe it to be everlasting and imperishable.
					But in the case of the powers associated with the earth
					it is reasonable that there should come to pass disappearances in one place and generation in another
					place, and elsewrhere shifting of location and, from
					some other source, changes in current,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 432 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and that such
					cycles should complete many revolutions within it in
					the whole course of time, as we may judge from what
					happens before our eyes. For in the case of lakes and
					rivers, and even more frequently in hot springs, there
					have occurred disappearances and complete extinction in some places, and in others a stealing away, as
					it were, and sinking under ground<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A not uncommon phenomenon in Greece; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 557 e.</note>; later they came
					back, appearing after a time in the same places or
					flowing out from below somewhere near. We know
					also of the exhaustion of mines, some of which have
					given out recently, as for example the silver mines
					of Attica and the copper ore in Euboea from which
					the cold-forged sword-blades used to be wrought, as
					Aeschylus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 107, Aeschylus, no. 356. The hardness and temper of cold-forged copper is well attested.</note> has said,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Euboean sword, self-sharpened, in his hand.</quote>
					And it is no long time since the rock in Euboea ceased
					to yield, among its other products, soft petrous
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.479"/>
					
					filaments like yarn.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An interesting early notice of the use of asbestos.</note> I think some of you have seen
					towels, nets, and women's head-coverings from there,
					which cannot be burned by fire ; but if any become
					soiled by use, their owners throw them into a blazing
					fire and take them out bright and clear. To-day all
					this has disappeared, and there are scarcely any
					attenuated fibres or hairs, as it were, running through
					the mines.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">And yet the school of Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Meteorologica</hi>, i. 3 (340 b 29); Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Divinatione</hi>, i. 19 (38); ii. 57 (117).</note> would make
					it appear that exhalation is the author of all these
					changes that have taken place in the earth, and that
					things of this nature must of necessity follow with it
					in disappearing, changing their locality, and bursting
					forth once more in full vigour. Plainly the same sober
					opinion is to be held regarding the spirits that inspire
					prophecy ; the power that they possess is not everlasting and ageless, but is subject to changes. For
					excessive rains most likely extinguish them, and they
					probably are dispersed by thunderbolts, and especially, when the earth is shaken beneath by an earthquake and suffers subsidence and ruinous confusion
					in its depths, the exhalations shift their site or find
					completely blind outlets, as in this place they say
					that there are still traces of that great earthquake
					which overthrew the city. And in Orchomenos they
					relate that a pestilence raged and many persons died
					of it, and the oracle of Teiresias become altogether
					obsolescent and even to this day remains idle and
					mute. And if a like fate has befallen those in Cilicia,
					as we have been told, there is nobody, Demetrius,
					who could give us more certain information than you.</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.481"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">I do not know,</q> said Demetrius, <q direct="unspecified">the state
					of affairs there at present; for as you all know, I have
					been out of the country for a long time now. But,
					when I was there, both the oracle of Mopsus and
					that of Amphilochus were still flourishing. I have a
					most amazing thing to tell as the result of my visit
					to the oracle of Mopsus. The ruler of Cilicia was
					himself still of two minds towards religious matters.
					This, I think, was because his scepticism lacked
					conviction, for in all else he was an arrogant and
					contemptible man. Since he kept about him certain
					Epicureans, who, because of their admirable naturestudies, forsooth, have an arrogant contempt, as they
					themselves aver,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 395 Usener; Diogenes Laertius, x. 135.</note> for all such things as oracles, he
					sent in a freedman, like a spy into the enemy's
					territory, arranging that he should have a sealed
					tablet, on the inside of which was written the inquiry
					without anyone's knowing what it was. The man
					accordingly, as is the custom, passed the night in the
					sacred precinct and went to sleep, and in the morning
					reported a dream in this fashion : it seemed to him
					that a handsome man stood beside him who uttered
					just one word &lsquo;Black&rsquo; and nothing more, and was
					gone immediately. The thing seemed passing strange
					to us, and raised much inquiry, but the ruler was
					astounded and fell down and worshipped ; then
					opening the tablet he showed written there the
					question : &lsquo;Shall I sacrifice to you a white bull or a
					black?&rsquo; The result was that the Epicureans were
					put to confusion, and the ruler himself not only duly
					performed the sacrifice, but ever after revered
					Mopsus.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>When Demetrius had told this tale he lapsed
					into silence. But I, wishing to crown, as it were,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.483"/>
					
					the discussion, glanced again towards Philip and
					Ammonius who were sitting side by side. They
					seemed to me to be desirous of saying something to
					us, and again I checked myself. Then Ammonius
					said, <q direct="unspecified">Philip also has some remarks to make,
						Lamprias, about what has been said ; for he himself
						thinks, as most people do, that Apollo is not a different
						god, but is the same as the sun.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 376 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 1130 a, for example.</note> But my difficulty is
						greater and concerns greater matters. I do not know
						how it happened, but a little time ago we yielded to
						logic in wresting the prophetic art from the gods and
						transferring it merely to the demigods. But now it
						seems to me that we are thrusting out these very
						demigods, in their turn, and driving them away from
						the oracle and the tripod here, when we resolve the
						origin of prophecy, or rather its very being and power,
						into winds and vapours and exhalations. For these
						temperings and heatings and hardenings that have
						been spoken of serve only the more to withdraw
						repute from the gods and suggest in regard to the
						final cause some such conclusion as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Cyclops</hi>, 332-333.</note> makes
						his Cyclops employ :
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>The earth perforce, whether it will or no,
							</l>
                     <l>Brings forth the grass to fat my grazing flocks.</l>
                  </quote>
						But there is one difference : he says that he does not
						offer them in sacrifice to the gods, but to himself and
						to his &lsquo;belly, greatest of divinities,&rsquo; whereas we offer
						both sacrifices and prayers as the price for our oracles.
						What possesses us to do so, if our souls carry within
						themselves the prophetic power, and it is some
						particular state of the air or its currents which stirs
						this to activity ? And what is the significance of the
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.485"/>
						
						libations poured over the victims and the refusal to
						give responses unless the whole victim from the hoofjoints up is seized with a trembling and quivering, as
						the libation is poured over it ? Shaking the head is
						not enough, as in other sacrifices, but the tossing and
						quivering must extend to all parts of the animal alike
						accompanied by a tremulous sound ; and unless this
						takes place they say that the oracle is not functioning,
						and do not even bring in the prophetic priestess.
						Yet it is only on the assumption that they ascribe the
						cause almost entirely to a god or a demigod that it is
						reasonable for them to act and to believe thus ; but
						on the basis of what you say it is not reasonable. For
						the presence of the exhalation, whether the victim be
						excited or not, will produce the inspiration and will
						dispose the soul auspiciously, not only the soul of
						the priestess, but that of any ordinary person with
						whom it may come into contact. Wherefore it is
						silly to employ one woman alone for the purpose
						of the oracles and to give her trouble by watching
						her to keep her pure and chaste all her life. As a
						matter of fact, this Coretas, who the people of
						Delphi say was the first, because he fell in, to
						supply any means of knowing about the power
						with which the place is endowed, was not, I think,
						any different from the rest of the goatherds and
						shepherds, if so be that this is not a fable or a
						fabrication as I, for one, think it is. When I take
						into account the number of benefactions to the
						Greeks for which this oracle has been responsible,
						both in wars and in the founding of cities, in cases of
						pestilence and failure of crops, I think it is a dreadful
						thing to assign its discovery and origin, not to God and
						Providence, but to chance and accident. But regarding
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.487"/>
						
						these matters,</q> he added, <q direct="unspecified">I wish that Lamprias
							would say something to us. Will you wait ?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Certainly I will,</q> said Philip, <q direct="unspecified">and so will all
						who are here. For what you have said has set us all
						thinking.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>Then I, addressing myself to him, said, &ldquo;Not
					only has it set me thinking, Philip, but it has filled
					me with confusion, if, in the presence of so many men
					such as you all are, I seem, in contradiction to my
					years, to give myself airs over the plausibility of my
					argument and to upset or disturb any of the beliefs
					regarding the Deity which have been conceived in
					truth and in piety. I shall defend myself by citing
					Plato as my witness and advocate in one. That
					philosopher<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 97 b-c.</note> found fault with Anaxagoras, the one of
					early times, because he was too much wrapped up in
					the physical causes and was always following up and
					pursuing the law of necessity as it was worked out in
					the behaviour of bodies, and left out of account the
					purpose and the agent, which are better causes and
					origins. Plato himself was the first of the philosophers,
					or the one most prominently engaged in prosecuting
					investigations of both sorts, to assign to God, on the
					one hand, the origin of all things that are in keeping
					with reason, and on the other hand, not to divest
					matter of the causes necessary for whatever comes
					into being, but to realize that the perceptible universe, even when arranged in some such orderly way
					as this, is not pure and unalloyed, but that it takes
					its origin from matter when matter comes into conjunction with reason. Observe first how it is with the
					artists. Take as our first example the far-famed
					stand and base for the mixing-bowl here which
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.489"/>
					
					Herodotus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The stand, dedicated by Alyattes (king of Lydia from 617 to 560 b.c.), was of wrought iron and welded together, not riveted. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, i. 25; Pausanias, x. 16. 1. Of interest also in this connexion is the dedication recorded in the Sigeum inscription. <hi rend="italics">C.I.G.</hi> i. 8, or Roberts, <hi rend="italics">Introduction to Greek Epigraphy</hi>, no. 42 (p. 78).</note> has styled the ' bowl-holder '; it came to
					have as its material causes fire and steel and softening
					by means of fire and tempering by means of water,
					without which there is no expedient by which this
					work could be produced ; but art and reason supplied
					for it the more dominant principle which set all these
					in motion and operated through them. And, indeed,
					the author and creator of these likenesses and portraits here stands recorded in the inscription<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 502, Simonides, no. 160; or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, ii. p. 399 (L.C.L.). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Pausanias, x. 25. 1.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thasian by race and descent, Aglaophon's son Polygnotus
						</l>
                  <l>Painted the taking of Troy, showing her citadel's sack;</l>
               </quote>
					so that it may be seen that he painted them. But
					without pigments ground together, losing their own
					colour in the process, nothing could achieve such a
					composition and sight. Does he, then, who is desirous
					of getting hold of the material cause, as he investigates and explains the behaviour of the red earth of
					Sinop&ecirc; and the changes to which it is subject when
					mixed with yellow ochre, or of the light-coloured
					earth of Melos when mixed with lamp-black, take
					away the repute of the artist ? And he that goes into
					the details of the hardening and the softening of
					steel, how it is relaxed by the fire, and becomes pliant
					and yielding for those who forge and fashion it, and
					then, plunged anew into clear water, is contracted
					and compacted by the coldness because of the softness and looseness of texture previously engendered
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.491"/>
					
					by the fire, and acquires a tenseness and firmness
					which Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> ix. 393.</note> has called &lsquo;the brawn of steel&rsquo;  does
					such an investigator any the less preserve intact for
					the artist the credit for the creation of the work ? I
					think not. In fact there are some who question the
					properties of medicinal agents, but they do not do
					away with medical science. And thus when Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 433 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 507 c-d, and 508 d.</note>
					declared that we see by the commingling of the
					irradiation from our eyes with the light of the sun,
					and that we hear by the vibration of the air, he
					certainly did not mean by this to abrogate the
					fundamenta! fact that it is according to the design of
					Reason and Providence that we have been endowed
					with sight and hearing.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>&ldquo;To sum up, then: while every form of creation
					has, as I say, two causes, the very earliest theological
					writers and poets chose to heed only the superior one,
					uttering over all things that come to pass this common
					generality :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Zeus the beginning, Zeus in the midst, and from Zeus comes
						all being<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Orphic Frag.</hi> vi. 10 (21 a, 2); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Mullach, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Phil. Graec.</hi> i. p. 169. 11.</note>;</quote>
					but as yet they made no approach towards the compelling and natural causes. On the other hand the
					younger generation which followed them, and are
					called physicists or natural philosophers, reverse the
					procedure of the older school in their aberration from
					the beautiful and divine origin, and ascribe everything
					to bodies and their behaviour, to clashes, transmutations, and combinations. Hence the reasoning
					of both parties is deficient in what is essential to it,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.493"/>
					
					since the one ignores or omits the intermediary and the
					agent, the other the source and the means. He who
					was the first to comprehend clearly both these points
					and to take, as a necessary adjunct to the agent that
					creates and actuates, the underlying matter, which
					is acted upon, clears us also of all suspicion of wilful
					misstatement. The fact is that we do not make the
					prophetic art godless or irrational when we assign to
					it as its material the soul of a human being, and
					assign the spirit of inspiration and the exhalation as an
					instrument or plectrum for playing on it. For, in the
					first place, the earth, which generates the exhalation,
					and the sun, which endows the earth with all its power
					of tempering and transmutation, are, by the usage
					of our fathers, gods for us. Secondly, if we leave
					demigods as overseers, watchmen, and guardians of
					this tempered constitution, as if it were a kind of
					harmony, slackening here and tightening there on
					occasion, taking from it its too distracting and
					disturbing elements and incorporating those that are
					painless and harmless to the users, we shall not
					appear to be doing anything irrational or impossible.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>Nor again, in offering the preliminary sacrifice
					to learn the god's will and in putting garlands on
					victims or pouring libations over them, are we doing
					anything to contradict this reasoning. For when the
					priests and holy men say that they are offering
					sacrifice and pouring the libation over the victim and
					observing its movements and its trembling, of what
					else do they take this to be a sign save that the god
					is in his holy temple ? For what is to be offered in
					sacrifice must, both in body and in soul, be pure,
					unblemished, and unmarred. Indications regarding
					the body it is not at all difficult to perceive, but they
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.495"/>
					
					test the soul by setting meal before the bulls and peas
					before the boars ; and the animal that does not eat of
					this they think is not of sound mind. In the case of
					the goat, they say, cold water gives positive proof;
					for indifference and immobility against being suddenly
					wet is not characteristic of a soul in a normal state.
					But for my part, even if it be firmly established that
					the trembling is a sign of the god's being in his holy
					temple and the contrary a sign of his not being there,
					I cannot see what difficulty in my statements results
					therefrom. For every faculty duly performs its
					natural functions better or worse concurrently with
					some particular time ; and if that time escapes our
					ken, it is only reasonable that the god should give
					signs of it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>&ldquo;I think, then, that the exhalation is not in
					the same state all the time, but that it has recurrent
					periods of weakness and strength. Of the proof on
					which I depend I have as witnesses many foreigners
					and all the officials and servants at the shrine. It is a
					fact that the room in which they seat those who would
					consult the god is filled, not frequently or with any
					regularity, but as it may chance from time to time,
					with a delightful fragrance coming on a current of air
					which bears it towards the worshippers, as if its source
					were in the holy of holies ; and it is like the odour
					which the most exquisite and costly perfumes send
					forth. It is likely that this efflorescence is produced
					by warmth or some other force engendered there.
					If this does not seem credible, you will at least all
					agree that the prophetic priestess herself is subjected
					to differing influences, varying from time to time,
					which affect that, part of her soul with which the spirit
					of inspiration comes into association, and that she
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.497"/>
					
					does not always keep one temperament, like a perfect
					concord, unchanged on every occasion. For many
					annoyances and disturbances of which she is conscious,
					and many more unpereeived, lay hold upon her body
					and filter into her soul; and whenever she is replete
					with these, it is better that she should not go there
					and surrender herself to the control of the god, when
					she is not completely unhampered (as if she were a
					musical instrument, well strung and well tuned), but
					is in a state of emotion and instability. Wine, for
					example, does not always produce the same state of
					intoxication in the toper,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 406 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> nor the music of the flute
					the same state of exaltation in the votary ; but the
					same persons are roused now to less, now to more,
					extravagant conduct by the Bacchic revels or stimulated by the wine, as the temperament within them
					becomes different. But especially does the imaginative faculty of the soul seem to be swayed by the
					alterations in the body, and to change as the body
					changes, a fact which is clearly shown in dreams ; for
					at one time we find ourselves beset in our dreams by
					a multitude of visions of all sorts, and at another time
					again there comes a complete calmness and rest free
					from all such fancies. We ourselves know of Cleon
					here from Daulia and that he asserts that in all the
					many years he has lived he has never had a dream ;
					and among the older men the same thing is told of
					Thrasymedes of Heraea. The cause of this is the
					temperament of the body, just as that of persons who
					are prone to melancholy, at the other extreme, is
					subject to a multitude of dreams and visions ; wherefore they have the repute of possessing the faculty of
					dreaming straight; for since they turn now to this
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.499"/>
					
					and now to that in their imagery, like persons who
					shoot many arrows, they often manage to hit the
					mark.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="51">
            <p>&ldquo;Whenever, then, the imaginative and prophetic faculty is in a state of proper adjustment for
					attempering itself to the spirit as to a drug, inspiration
					in those who foretell the future is bound to come ;
					and whenever the conditions are not thus, it is bound
					not to come, or when it does come to be misleading,
					abnormal, and confusing, as we know in the case
					of the priestess who died not so long ago. As it
					happened, a deputation from abroad had arrhed to
					consult the oracle. The victim, it is said, remained
					unmoved and unaffected in any way by the first
					libations ; but the priests, in their eagerness to
					please, went far beyond their wonted usage, and only
					after the victim had been subjected to a deluge and
					nearly drowned did it at last give in. What, then,
					was the result touching the priestess ? She went
					down into the oracle unwillingly, they say, and halfheartedly ; and at her first responses it was at once
					plain from the harshness of her voice that she was not
					responding properly ; she was like a labouring ship
					and was filled with a mighty and baleful spirit.
					Finally she became hysterical and with a frightful
					shriek rushed towards the exit and threw herself
					down, with the result that not only the members of
					the deputation fled, but also the oracle-interpreter
					Nicander and those holy men that were present.
					However, after a little, they went in and took her
					up, still conscious ; and she lived on for a few
					days.
				</p>
            <p>
					&ldquo;It is for these reasons that they guard the chastity of the priestess, and keep her life free from all
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.501"/>
					
					association and contact with strangers, and take the
					omens before the oracle, thinking that it is clear to the
					god when she has the temperament and disposition
					suitable to submit to the inspiration without harm to
					herself. The power of the spirit does not affect all
					persons nor the same persons always in the same way,
					but it only supplies an enkindling and an inception,
					as has been said, for them that are in a proper state
					to be affected and to undergo the change. The power
					comes from the gods and demigods, but, for all that,
					it is not unfailing nor imperishable nor ageless, lasting
					into that infinite time by which all things between
					earth and moon become wearied out, according to our
					reasoning. And there are some who assert that the
					things above the moon also do not. abide, but give
					out as they confront the everlasting and infinite, and
					undergo continual transmutations and rebirths.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="52">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">These matters,</q> I added, <q direct="unspecified">I urge upon you
					for your frequent consideration, as well as my own,
					in the belief that they contain much to which
					objections might be made, and many suggestions
					looking to a contrary conclusion, all of which the
					present occasion does not allow us to follow out. So
					let them be postponed until another time, and likewise the question which Philip raises about the Sun
					and Apollo.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>