<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Bruta animalia ratione uti</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.130">
      <body>
         <head>That brute beasts make use of reason
				<lb/> Ulysses, Circe, Gryllus.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.218"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>ULYSSES. All these things, Circe, I believe that I
				have learned and well remember. But I would willingly ask thee, whether thou hast any Grecians here,
				which being men thou hast transformed into wolves and
				lions.</p>
            <p>CIRCE. Very many, dearest Ulysses, but wherefore do
					you ask the question?</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Because in good truth I am of opinion I
					should gain a high reputation among the Greeks, if by
					thy favor I could restore these men to human shape again,
					and not suffer them through any negligence of mine to
					wax old in the bodies of beasts, where they lead a miserable and ignominious life.</p>
            <p>CIRCE. Surely, this man, fool as he is, believes it requisite that his ambition should be unfortunate not only to
					himself and his friends, but to those that nothing belong
					to him.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Thou art now jumbling and mixing another
					villanous potion of twittle twattle, and wouldst plainly
					turn me into a beast too, if thou couldst make me believe
					that it were a misfortune to be transformed from a beast
					to a man.</p>
            <p>CIRCE. What hast thou made thyself better than a
					beast, who, forsaking an immortal life, free from the miseries of old age, with me, art making such haste through
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.219"/>
					
					a thousand threatening calamities to a mortal and (as
					I may say) old wife, pursuing an empty good and a shadow
					instead of real truth, and all this, thinking to be more conspicuous and famous than thou art.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Well, Circe, let it be as thou sayest; for
					why should we be always contending about the same
					thing? However, do me the favor to restore these men,
					and give them into my custody.</p>
            <p>CIRCE. By Hecate, not so fast neither; these are no
					ordinary fellows. But ask them first whether they are
					willing. If they refuse, do you, being such an eloquent
					gentleman, discourse them and persuade them; if you
					cannot persuade them, being too hard for ye at your own
					weapon, then let it suffice ye that you have ill consulted
					your own and the good of your friends.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Blessed woman, wherefore dost thou mock
					me thus? For how can they either talk or hear reason,
					so long as they are asses, hogs, and lions?</p>
            <p>CIRCE. Be of good comfort, most ambitious of men; I
					will so order the business, that they shall both understand
					and discourse; or rather, let one suffice to hear and return
					answers instead of all the rest. Look ye, here is one at
					hand; pray talk to him.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Prithee, Circe, by what name shall we call
					him? Who is this fellow of all the men in the world?
					CIRCE. What's this to the purpose? Call him Gryllus,
					if you please; and for my part, I'll leave ye together,
					that ye may not suspect him for speaking contrary to his
					mind to please me.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>GRYLLUS. Save ye, Mr. Ulysses.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. And you too, by Jove, Mr. Gryllus.</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. What is't your worship would have with
					me?</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Knowing you were all born men, I pity the
					condition ye are now in; and I pity ye the more, for that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.220"/>
					
					being Greeks ye are fallen under this misfortune; and
					therefore I made it my request to Circe that she would
					restore ye again to your former shape, as many of you as
					were desirous, to the end ye might return home again
					with us.</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. Hold, Mr. Ulysses, not a word more of this,
					I beseech your worship. For we all contemn thee, as one
					that none but fools call cunning, and as vainly vauntest
					thyself to be wiser than other men, and yet art afraid of
					being changed from worse to better; like children that
					are frightened at physician's doses and hate going to
					school, although the medicines and the precepts make
					them healthy and learned of diseased and fools; just so
					thou refusest to be transformed out of one thing into
					another. And now thy bones rattle in thy skin for dread
					of living with Circe, lest she should transform thee into a
					hog or a wolf; and thou wouldst persuade us living in
					plenty of all enjoyments not only to forsake these blessings, but to abandon her that has so well provided for us,
					to sail along with thee, and to become men again, the most
					miserable of all creatures.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. In my opinion, Gryllus, this same wicked cup
					has not only deprived thee of thy shape, but of thy sense
					and reason too; or else thou art got drunk with those
					opinions which are everywhere exploded as nasty and
					villanous, unless some voluptuous pleasure of custom and
					habit has bewitched thee to this body.</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. Neither of these, O king of the Cephallenians.
					But if thou art come hither to dispute, and not to rail and
					swagger, we shall soon convince thee, having experience
					of both manners of living, that our way is to be preferred
					before that which thou so much applaudest.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Nay, then go on; I'll listen with both ears to
					hear this paradox discussed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>GRYLLUS. Have at ye then, sir. But it behooves us
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.221"/>
				
				to begin first with those virtues which you so presumptuously
				assume to yourselves, and for which you so highly advance
				yourselves before the beasts, such as justice, prudence,
				fortitude, &amp;c. Now answer me, thou the wisest among
				mortals; for I have heard thee telling a story to Circe of
				the territory of the Cyclops, that being neither ploughed
				nor planted by any person, it is so fertile and generously
				productive, that it bears all sorts of fruits and herbs spontaneously Now which do you prefer, this country, or
				your own goat-feeding stony Ithaca, which being cultivated
				with great labor and hardship, yet answers the expectations of the husbandmen with only a mean and scanty
				return? Now take it not amiss that I forewarn ye lest
				your love to your country sway ye to give an answer contrary to truth.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. No, no, I will not lie for the matter; I must
					confess I love and honor my own country more; but I
					applaud and admire theirs far beyond it.</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. Hence we must conclude that it is so as the
					wisest of men has affirmed; that there are some things to
					be praised and approved, others to be preferred by choice
					and affection. And I suppose you believe the same concerning the soul. For the same reasons hold in reference
					to the soul as to the ground; that such a soul should be
					the best, that produces virtue like spontaneous fruit, without labor and toil.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Grant all this.</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. Then you confess that the souls of beasts are
					the more perfect, and more fertilely endued for the production of virtue; seeing that without any command or instruction&mdash;as it were without sowing or ploughing&mdash;it
					produces and increases that virtue which is requisite for
					every one.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Prithee, Gryllus, don't rave, but tell me what
					those virtues are that beasts partake of?</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.222"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>GRYLLUS. Rather what virtues do they not partake of
				in a higher degree than the wisest of men? Look upon
				fortitude in the first place, of which you vaunt and brag to
				have such a terrible share, being not ashamed of the magnificent titles of Ulysses the bold and city-stormer, when
				indeed, like a pitiful knave as thou art, thou dost only
				circumvent by tricks and artifices men that understand
				only the simple and generous way of making war, ignorant
				altogether of fraud and faith-breaking, and by that means
				coverest thy deceit with the name of virtue, which never
				admits of any such coney-catching devices. But do you observe the combats and warfare of beasts, as well one
				against another as against yourselves, how free from craft
				and deceit they are, and how with an open and naked
				courage they defend themselves by mere strength of body;
				and how, neither afraid of the law that calls them forth to
				battle nor the severe edicts against deserters, but only out
				of scorn to be overcome, they fight with obstinacy to the
				last for conquest and victory. For they are not vanquished when their bodies are worsted, neither does despair cowardize them, but they die upon the spot. And
				you shall see many times that the strength of many, while
				they are expiring, being retired and crowded together in
				some part of the body, still makes resistance against the
				victor, and pants and fumes till at length it fails like extinguished fire that goes out for want of fuel. But there
				is no crying for quarter, no begging of mercy, no acknowledgment of being beaten; nor will the lion be a slave to
				the lion, nor the horse to the horse, as one man is a slave
				to another, willingly and patiently embracing servitude,
				which derives its name (<foreign lang="greek">doulei/a</foreign>) from that of cowardice
				(<foreign lang="greek">deili/a</foreign>). On the other side, such beasts as men by nets and
				treacherous snares get into their power, if fully grown,
				rather choose to die than serve, refusing nourishment and
				suffering extremity of drought. But as for their young
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.223"/>
				
				ones,&mdash;being tractable and supple by reason of their
				age, and fed with the deceitful mixtures and food that
				men provide for them, their inbred fierceness languishing
				through the taste of preternatural delights,&mdash;they suffer
				that which is called domestication, which is only an effeminating of their natural fury.</p>
            <p>Whence it is apparent that beasts are naturally inclined
					to be courageous and daring, but that the martial confidence of men is preternatural. Which, most noble Ulysses,
					you may chiefly observe from hence; for that in beasts
					Nature keeps an equal balance of strength; so that the
					female, being but little inferior to the male, undergoes all
					necessary toils, and fights in defence of her young ones.
					And thus you hear of a certain Cromyonian sow, which,
					though a female, held Theseus tack, and found him work
					sufficient. Neither had the wisdom of that same female
					Sphinx that sat on Phicium, with all her riddles and enigmas, availed her, had she not far excelled the Cadmeans
					in strength and fortitude. Not far from whence the Telmesian fox had his den, a great propounder of questions
					also; not to omit the female serpent that fought with
					Apollo for his oracle at Delphi. Your king also took the
					mare Aetha from the Sicyonian, as a bribe to discharge
					him from going to the wars; and he did well, thereby
					showing how much he esteemed a valiant and generous
					mare above a timorous coward. You yourself have also
					seen female panthers and lionesses little inferior to the
					males in strength and courage; when your own wife,
					though a Lacedaemonian, when you were hectoring and
					blustering abroad, sat at home in the chimney-corner, not
					daring to do so much as the very swallows in encountering
					those who plagued both her and her family. Why need I
					still speak of the Carian and Maeonian women? Whence
					it is apparent that fortitude is not natural to men, for then
					the women would partake of the same strength with men.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.224"/>
					
					So that the fortitude which you exercise is only constrained
					by law, not natural and voluntary, but subservient to the
					manners of the place and enslaved to reproach, a thing
					made up only of glorious words and adventitious opinion.
					And you undergo labor and throw yourself into danger,
					not out of real valor and boldness, but because ye are
					more afraid of other things. Therefore, as among thy own
					companions he that first makes haste to snatch up the light
					oar does it not because he contemns it, but because he is
					loath to be troubled with the more heavy; so he that
					endures a blow to avoid a wound, and defends himself
					against an enemy to preserve himself from wounds and
					death, does it not out of daring courage against the one,
					but out of fear of the other. Thus your fortitude is only
					a prudent fear; and your courage a knowing timidity,
					which understandingly does one thing to avoid another.</p>
            <p>In short, if you believe yourselves superior to the beasts
					in fortitude, why do your poets call those that behave
					themselves most valiantly against their enemies wolf-breasted, lion-hearted, and compare them to wild boars;
					but never call the courage of lions man-like, or resemble
					the strength of a wild boar to that of a man? But as they
					call the swift wind-footed, and the beautiful Godlike-formed, hyperbolizing in their similes; so when they extol
					the gallantry of the stout in battle, they derive their comparisons from the superior in bravery. The reason is,
					because courage is as it were the tincture and edge of fortitude; which the beasts make use of unmixed in their
					combats, but in you being mixed with reason, like wine
					diluted with water, it gives way to danger and loses the
					opportunity. And some of you there are who deny that
					courage is requisite in battle, and therefore laying it aside
					make use of sober reason; which they do well for their
					preservation, but are shamefully beside the cushion, in
					point of strength and revenge. How absurd is it therefore
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.225"/>
					
					for you to complain of Nature, because she did not furnish
					your bodies with goads and teeth and crooked claws to
					defend yourselves, when at the same time you would disarm the soul of her natural weapons?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>ULYSSES. In good truth, Gryllus, you are grown, in
				my conceit, a notable sophister, to discourse at this rate
				out of a hog's snout, and yet to handle your argument so
				strenuously. But why have you not all this while spoke
				a word of temperance?</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. Because I thought you would have contradicted first what I have already said. But you are in haste
					to hear what I have to say concerning temperance, because
					that, being the husband of a most temperate and chaste
					wife, you believe you have set us an example of temperance by abstaining from Circe's embraces. And yet in
					this you differ nothing from all the beasts; for neither do
					they desire to approach their superiors, but they pursue
					their pleasures and amours among those of their own tribe.
					No wonder is it then, if&mdash;like the Mendesian goat in
					Egypt, which is reported to have been shut up with several most beautiful women, yet never to have offered copulation with them, but when he was at liberty, with a lustful
					fury flew upon the she-goats&mdash;so thou, though a man
					addicted greatly to venereal pleasures, yet being a man,
					hast no desire to sleep with a goddess. And for the chastity of thy Penelope, the ten thousand rooks and daws that
					chatter it abroad do but make it ridiculous and expose
					it to contempt, there being not one of those birds but,
					if she loses her mate, continues a widow, not for a small
					time, but for nine ages of men; so that there is not one of
					those female rooks that does not surpass in chastity thy
					fair Penelope above nine times.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But because thou believest me to be a sophister, I
				shall observe a certain order in my discourse, first giving
				thee the definition of temperance, and then dividing desire
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.226"/>
				
				according to the several kinds of it. Temperance then is
				the contracting and well governing our desires, pruning off
				those that are superfluous and encroaching upon our wills,
				and ruling those that are necessary by the standards of
				reason and moderation. Now in desires you observe a vast
				number of distinctions. For it is both natural and necessary to drink; but as for venereal desires, which derive
				their originals from Nature, there is a time when they may
				be restrained without any inconvenience; these are therefore called natural but not necessary. But there is another
				sort, which are neither natural nor necessary, but infused
				from without by vain opinion through the mistake of right
				and true; and it is these that want but very little of ruining all your natural desires with their number, like a multitude of foreigners outnumbering the natives and expelling
				them from their habitations. But the beasts, having their
				souls unmixed and not to be overcome by these adventitious
				passions, and living lives as distant from vain opinion as
				from the sea, are inferior to you in living elegantly and superfluously, but they are extremely wary in preserving
				temperance and the right government of their desires, as
				being neither troubled with many, nor those foreign to
				their natures. And therefore formerly I was no less
				smitten with the glister of gold than thou art now, as believing nothing else that a man could possess to be comparable to it. Silver also and ivory inveigled me with the
				same desires; and he that enjoyed these things in the
				greatest measure seemed to be a man most happy and beloved of God, whether a Phrygian or a Carian, whether
				more meanly descended than Dolon or more miserable than
				Priam. From thenceforward being altogether swayed by
				my desires, I reaped no other pleasure nor delight in any
				other blessings of my life, with which I abounded, believing that I wanted still and missed my share of those that
				were the chiefest and the greatest. Therefore, I remember,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.227"/>
				
				 when I beheld thee in Crete, at some solemnity, most
				pompously attired, I neither envied thy wisdom nor thy
				virtue; but the extraordinary fineness and exquisite workmanship of thy tunic, and the glistering of thy purple
				upper garment, and the beauty of the ornaments struck me
				with admiration. And the golden clasp, methought, was
				a pretty toy that had something of extraordinary graving
				in it; and bewitched with these baubles, I followed thee
				as the women did. But now being altogether estranged
				from those vain opinions, and having my understanding
				purified, I tread both gold and silver under my feet as I do
				the common stones; nor did I ever sleep more soundly
				upon thy carpets and tapestries, than now I do, rolled over
				head and ears in the deep and soft mud. None of those
				adventitious desires reside in our souls, but for the most
				part our manner of living is accustomed to necessary
				pleasures and desires; and as for those pleasures which
				are not necessary but only natural, we make such a use of
				them as is neither without order nor moderation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>And therefore let us consider these in the first place.
				The pleasure then that affects the sense of smelling with
				sweet odors and fragrant exhalations, besides that it has
				something in it which is pure in itself, and as it were bestowed upon us gratis, contributes also in some measure to
				the distinction of nourishment. For the tongue is said to
				be the judge of sweet, sour, and tart, only when the juices
				have come to be mingled and concorporate with the tasting
				faculty, and not before. But our smell, before the taste,
				becoming sensible of the virtue and qualities of every
				thing, and being more accurate than the tasters attending
				upon princes, admits what is familiar to Nature, and expels
				whatever is disagreeable to it; neither will it suffer it to
				touch or molest the taste, but accuses and declares the
				offensiveness of the thing smelt, before it do any harm.
				As to other things, it troubles us not at all as it does you,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.228"/>
				
				whom it constrains for the sake of the sweet scents of
				cinnamon, nard, malobathrum, and Arabian reed, to seek
				out for things dissimilar, and to jumble them together
				with a kind of apothecary's or perfumer's art, and at vast
				expense to purchase an unmanly and effeminate delight,
				for nothing profitable or useful. Now being such, this
				sense of smelling has not only corrupted all the female
				sex but the greatest part of men, insomuch that they care
				not to converse with their own wives, unless perfumed with
				precious ointments and odoriferous compositions. Whereas sows, she-goats, and other females attract the boars, he-goats, and the males of their own kind, by their own proper
				scents; and smelling of the pure dew, the meadows, and
				the fresh grass, they are incited to copulation out of common affection; the females without the coynesses of
				women, or the practice of little frauds and fascinations,
				to inflame the lust of their mates; and the males, not with
				amorous rage and frenzy stimulated, and enforced to purchase the act of generation with expensive hire or servile
				assiduity, but enjoying their seasonable amours without deceit or purchase of the satisfaction of their venery. For
				Nature in the spring-time, even as she puts forth the buds
				of plants, likewise awakens the desires of animals, but
				presently quenches them again, neither the female admitting the male nor the male attempting the female after
				conception. And thus pleasure has but a small and slender esteem among us; but Nature is all in all. So that
				even to this very day, we beasts were never yet tainted
				with coupling male with male, and female with female.
				Of which nevertheless there are many examples to be
				produced among the greatest and most celebrated persons;
				for I pass by those not worth remembrance.</p>
            <p>Agamemnon hunted all Boeotia in pursuit of Argynnus,
					who fled his embraces; and after he had falsely accused
					the sea and winds, bravely flung himself into the lake Copais,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.229"/>
					
					 to quench his love and free himself from the ardor
					of his lust.</p>
            <p>Hercules in like manner pursuing his beardless friend,
					forsook his choicest associates and abandoned the fleet.</p>
            <p>In the vaulted room belonging to Apollo surnamed
					Ptous, one of you men secretly wrote this inscription,
					Achilles the fair; when Achilles at that time had a son.
					[And I hear the inscription is still remaining.]<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It seems incredible that Plutarch could have put this into the mouth of Gryllus, even by carelessness. (G.)</note> Yet if a
					cock tread a cock in the absence of the hen, he is burned
					alive, upon the signification of the soothsayer that it portends some fatal calamity. This is a plain confession in
					men themselves, that the beasts excel them in chastity,
					and that force is not to be put upon Nature for the sake
					of pleasure. But your incontinence is such, that Nature,
					though she have the law to assist her, is not able to keep
					it within bounds; insomuch that, like a rapid inundation,
					those inordinate desires overwhelm Nature with continual
					violence, trouble, and confusion. For men have copulated
					with she-goats, sows, and mares; and women have run
					mad after male beasts. And from such copulations sprang
					the Minotaurs and Silvans, and, as I am apt to believe, the
					Sphinxes and Centaurs. It is true, that sometimes, constrained by hunger, a dog or a bird has fed upon human
					flesh; but never yet did any beast attempt to couple with
					human kind. But men constrain and force the beasts to
					these and many other unlawful pleasures.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Now being thus wicked and incontinent in reference
				to the aforesaid lustful desires, it is no less easy to be
				proved that men are more intemperate than beasts, even in
				those things which are necessary, that is to say, in eating
				and drinking, the pleasure of which we always enjoy with
				some benefit to ourselves. But you, pursuing the pleasures
				of eating and drinking beyond the satisfaction of nature,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.230"/>
				
				are punished with many and tedious diseases, which,
				arising from the single fountain of superfluous gormandizing, fill your bodies with all manner of wind and vapors not easy for purgation to expel. In the first place,
				all sorts of beasts, according to their kind, feed upon one
				sort of food, which is proper to their natures; some upon
				grass, some upon roots, and others upon fruits. They that
				feed upon flesh never mind any other sort of food. Neither
				do they rob the weaker animals of their nourishment. But
				the lion suffers the hart, and the wolf the sheep, to feed
				upon what Nature has provided for them. But man, such
				is his voracity, falls upon all, to satisfy the pleasures of his
				appetite; tries all things, tastes all things; and, as if he
				were yet to seek what was the most proper diet and most
				agreeable to his nature, among all the creatures is the only
				all-devourer. And first he makes use of flesh, not for
				want, as having the liberty to take his choice of herbs
				and fruits, the plenty of which is inexhaustible; but out of
				luxury and being closed with necessaries, he seeks after inconvenient and impure diet, purchased by the slaughter of
				living creatures; by that means showing himself more
				cruel than the most savage of wild beasts. For blood,
				murder, and flesh are proper to nourish the kite, the wolf,
				and dragon; but to men they are delicious viands. Then
				making use of all, he does not do like the beasts, which
				abstain from most creatures and are at enmity only with a
				few, and that only compelled by the necessities of hunger;
				but neither fowl nor fish nor any thing that lives upon the
				land escapes your tables, though they bear the epithets of
				human and hospitable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Let it be so, that nothing will serve ye but to devour
				whatever comes near ye, to pamper and indulge your
				voracious appetites. Yet where is the benefit and pleasure
				of all this? But such is the prudence of the beasts, as
				not to admit of any vain and unprofitable arts. And as
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.231"/>
				
				for those that are necessary, they do not acquire them, as
				being introduced by others or taught for reward; neither
				do they make it their study to soder and fasten one contemplation to another, but they are supplied by their own
				prudence with such as are true-born and genuine. It is
				true, we hear the Egyptians are generally physicians. But
				the beasts are not only every one of them notionally endued with knowledge and art which way to cure themselves, but also to procure their food and repair their
				strength, to catch their prey by slight and cunning, to
				guard themselves from danger; neither are some of
				them ignorant how to teach the science of music so
				far as is convenient for them. For from whom did we
				hogs learn to run to the rivers, when we are sick, to
				search for crawfish? Who taught the tortoises, when
				they have eaten vipers, to physic themselves with origanum? Who taught the Cretan goats, when shot with
				arrows that stick in their bodies, to betake themselves to
				dittany, which they have no sooner eaten, but the heads
				of the darts fall out of the wound? Now if you say that Nature is the schoolmistress that teaches them these things,
				you acknowledge the prudence of beasts to be derived from
				the chiefest and wisest original of understanding; which
				if you think not proper to call reason and wisdom, it is
				time for ye to find out a more glorious and honorable
				name for it. Indeed by its effects it shows itself to be
				greater and more wonderful in power; not illiterate or
				without education, but instructed by itself and wanting
				nothing from without; not weak and imperfect, but,
				through the vigor and perfection of its natural virtue,
				supporting and cherishing that natural contribution of
				understanding which others attain to by instruction and
				education. So that, whatever men acquire and contemplate in the midst of their luxury and wantonness, those
				things our understanding attains to through the excellency
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.232"/>
				
				of our apprehensions, even contrary to the nature of the
				body. For not to speak of whelps that learn to draw dry
				foot, and colts that will practise figure-dances; there are
				crows that will speak, and dogs that will leap through
				hoops as they turn around. You shall also see horses and
				bulls upon the theatres lie down, dance, stop, and move
				their bodies after such a manner as would puzzle even
				men to perform the same things; which, though they are
				of little use, yet being learned and remembered by beasts,
				are great arguments of their docility.</p>
            <p>If you doubt whether we learn arts, be convinced that
					we teach them. For partridges teach their young ones to
					hide themselves by lying upon their backs just before a
					clod of earth, to escape the pursuit of the fowlers. And
					you shall observe the old storks, when their young ones
					first begin to take wing, what care they take to instruct
					them upon the tops of houses. Nightingales also teach
					their young ones to sing; insomuch that nightingales taken
					young out of the nest, and bred up by hand in cages, sing
					worse, as being deprived of their instructors before their
					time. So that after I had been a while transformed into
					this shape, I admired at myself, that I was so easily persuaded by idle arguments of the sophisters to believe that
					all other creatures were void of sense and reason except
					man.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>ULYSSES. What then, Gryllus? Does your transmutation inform ye also that sheep and asses are rational
				creatures?</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. From these very creatures, most worthy and
					best of men, Ulysses, the nature of beasts is chiefly to be
					discerned to be as it is, neither void of reason nor understanding. For as one tree is neither more or less than
					another without a soul, but all are together in the same
					condition of insensibility (for there is no tree that is endued
					with a soul); so neither would one animal seem to be
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.233"/>
					
					more slow to understand or more indocible than another, if
					all did not partake of reason and understanding, though
					some in a less, some in a greater measure. For you must
					consider that the stupidity and slothfulness of some is an
					argument of the quickness and subtlety of others, which
					easily appears when you compare a fox, a wolf, or a bee
					with a sheep or ass; as if thou shouldest compare thyself
					to Polyphemus, or thy grandfather Autolycus with the
					Corinthian [mentioned in] Homer. For I do not believe
					there is such difference between beast and beast, in point
					of reason and understanding and memory, as between man
					and man.</p>
            <p>ULYSSES. Have a care, Gryllus; it is a dangerous thing
					to allow them reason that have no knowledge of a Deity.</p>
            <p>GRYLLUS. Must we then deny that thou, most noble
					Ulysses, being so wise and full of stratagems as thou art,
					wast begotten by Sisyphus? . . .</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>