<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De cohibenda ira</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">W. C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>W. C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1939</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.6.p.90"/>
            <head>ON THE CONTROL OF ANGER
					(DE COHIBENDA IRA)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					The subject of this essay is not the emotion of anger
					itself, but the cure best applicable to the passion.
					In form it is a dialogue, but, apart from the beginning
					and the end, it is as undramatic as the later works of
					Plato. The principal speaker, Fundanus, treats the
					subject in a manner partly general and partly specific,
					and concludes with a pleasant history of his own cure.
					Hirzel (<hi rend="italics">Der Dialog</hi>, ii. p. 170) has described the work
					as a monument (<hi rend="italics">Ehrendenkmal</hi>) to the memory of
					Fundanus, dedicated to Sulla.
				</p>
            <p>
					Scholars concerned in the investigation of the
					sources used by Plutarch for this discourse have
					arrived at varying results : some<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wilamowitz, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxix. 152; Schlemm, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxxviii. 587 ff.</note> have imagined
					that Stoic writers were used, others<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Allers, <hi rend="italics">De Senecae Librorum de Ira Fontibus</hi>, p. 9; Pohlenz, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxxi. 321 ff.; accepted by Daebritz, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, i. 8. 1562. In <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xl. 292, note 1, Pohlenz attempts to refute Schlemm's arguments.</note> that the Peripatetic Hieronymus of Rhodes was Plutarch's principal authority. The numerous parallels to Seneca's
					<hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi> have been used by both parties to substantiate
					their theories, but it is more likely that Plutarch,
					while borrowing numerous <hi rend="italics">loci communes</hi> and examples
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.91"/>
					
					from earlier writers,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Books on <q direct="unspecified">Anger</q> were very plentiful in Cicero's day (<hi rend="italics">Epp. ad Quint. Frat.</hi>, i. 1. 37).</note> constructed for himself the main
					features of the dialogue. The self-portrayal of
					Fundanus and his cure, the frame-work of the whole
					discourse, is clearly Plutarch's own device. The
					author's debt to preceding literature is, as always,
					immense, yet the creation of such a work as this is
					by selection and arrangement; and for that Plutarch
					is alone responsible.
				</p>
            <p>
					The essay was known to Aulus Gellius (i. 26), who
					relates a pleasant anecdote of Plutarch and a rascally
					slave who ventured to reprove the philosopher for his
					anger. Among English writers Jeremy Taylor has
					made admirable use of the essay by paraphrase and
					even translation, in his <hi rend="italics">Holy Living</hi>, iv. 8.
				</p>
            <p>
					The ms. tradition is good.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There is extant also a free Syriac translation (ed. Lagarde, <hi rend="italics">Analecta Syriaca</hi>, Leipzig, 1858) which helps occasionally in the constitution of the text.</note> The work is apparently
					missing in the Lamprias catalogue, since <foreign lang="greek">*peri\ o)rgh=s</foreign>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Patzig, <hi rend="italics">Quaest. Plut.</hi>, p. 42.</note>
					(No. 93) almost certainly refers to a different work
					from which Stobaeus has preserved a fragment
					(Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 138).
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.6.p.93"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
					(Speakers in the Dialogue: Sulla and Fundanus)
				</p>
            <p>
					Sulla.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sextius Sulla, a friend of Plutarch (<hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 636 a, and <hi rend="italics">Prosopographia Imperii Romani</hi>, iii. p. 239).</note> A good plan, as it seems to me, Fundanus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">C. Minicius Fundanus, a friend of Pliny (<hi rend="italics">Epp.</hi>, v. 16); <hi rend="italics">cf. Pros. Imp. Rom.</hi>, ii. p. 377.</note> is that which painters follow : they scrutinize
					their productions from time to time before they
					finish them. They do this because, by withdrawing
					their gaze and by inspecting their work often, they
					are able to form a fresh judgement, and one which is
					more likely to seize upon any slight discrepancy,
					such as the familiarity of uninterrupted contemplation will conceal. Since, therefore, it is impossible
					for a man to contemplate himself from time to time
					by getting apart from himself and interrupting his
					consciousness of himself by breaking its continuity
					(and this is what, more than anything else, makes
					every man a poorer judge of himself than of others),
					the next best course would be for him to inspect
					his friends from time to time and likewise to offer
					himself to them, not to see if he is grown old suddenly
					or if his body is better or worse, but for them to
					examine both his behaviour and his character to learn
					whether time has added some excellence or taken
					away some vice. As for me, since I have returned to
					Rome after a year's absence and this is now the fifth
					month that I have been with you constantly, I do not
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.95"/>
					
					find it altogether surprising that, of the virtues which
					were already yours by gift of Nature, there has been
					so great an increment and increase ; but when I see
					that that violent and fiery tendency of yours toward
					anger has become so gentle and submissive to reason,
					it occurs to me to say with reference to your temper
					<quote rend="blockquote">O wonder, how much milder has it grown!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xxii. 373.</note>
               </quote> 
					Yet this mildness has brought about no inactivity or
					feebleness in you, but, like the earth when it has been
					subdued by cultivation, it has received a smoothness
					and depth conducive to fruitful action in place of that
					impetuousness of yours and quickness of temper.
					For that reason it is evident that the spirited part of
					your soul is not withering away through any abatement of vigour caused by age, nor yet spontaneously,
					but that it is receiving the skilful treatment of some
					excellent precepts. And yet - for I shall tell you the
					plain truth - when our friend Eros<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This friend of Plutarch is mentioned again in connexion with Fundanus in 464 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> told me all this,
					I suspected that he was bearing witness, by reason
					of his goodwill, to qualities that were not actually
					present in you, yet should be so in men of breeding, although, as you know, he is by no means
					the sort of man to surrender his own opinion as a
					favour to anyone. But as things are, Eros stands
					acquitted of the charge of bearing false witness, and
					do you, since our journey<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Hirzel, <hi rend="italics">Der Dialog</hi>, ii. p. 168, note 4.</note> gives us leisure for conversation, tell me, as though you were recounting
					some medical treatment, what remedy you used that
					you have made your temper so obedient to the rein
					and tender-mouthed, so mild and subservient to
					reason.
				</p>
            <p>
					Fundanus. Well, what about you, my generous
					friend Sulla? Are you careful not to let your
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.97"/>
					
					goodwill and friendship for me make you overlook
					some of my real qualities? For since on many
					occasions not even Eros himself can keep his temper
					in its place in that Homeric<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xx. 23, cited in full 506 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> obedience, but when it
					becomes too exasperated through hatred of evil, it
					is reasonable to suppose that I appear more gentle
					to him, just as in changes of key certain high notes
					assume the position of low notes in contrast with other
					high notes.</p>
            <p>
					Sulla. Neither of these suppositions is true,
					Fundanus. Please do as I ask.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Fundanus. One of those excellent precepts
					of Musonius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 36 ed. Hense.</note> which I remember, Sulla, is : <q direct="unspecified">He
						that wishes to come through life safe and sound
						must continue throughout his life to be under treatment.</q> For I do not think that reason should
					be used in one's cure as we use hellebore, and be
					washed out of the body together with the disease,
					but it must remain in the soul and keep watch
					and ward over the judgements. For the power
					of reason is not like drugs, but like wholesome
					food, engendering an excellent state, together with
					great vigour, in those who become accustomed to
					it; but exhortations and admonitions, if applied
					to the passions when they are at their height and
					swollen, can scarcely accomplish anything at all,
					and that with difficulty. They are no better than
					those aromatic preparations which rouse epileptics
					when they lie prostrate, but do not rid them
					of the disease. Yet the other passions, even at
					their height, do in some sort yield and admit
					reason, when it comes from without to the rescue,
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.99"/>
					
					into the soul; but temper does not, as Melanthius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 760; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 551 a. The poet is not the Athenian tragic poet, but Melanthius of Rhodes (<hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 150 b.c.), according to Wilamowitz, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxix. 150 ff.</note>
					says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Shunt off the mind, and then do dreadful deeds,</quote>
					but on the contrary, it shuts out sense completely and
					locks it out, and just like those who burn themselves up in their own homes, it makes everything
					within full of confusion and smoke and noise, so that
					the soul can neither see nor hear anything that might
					help it. For this reason a ship deserted by her crew
					in the midst of a storm far out at sea<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1103 c.</note> will more
					easily be able to take on a pilot from the outside, than
					will a man who is being tossed upon the billows of
					passion and anger admit the reasoning of another,
					unless he has his own powers of reason prepared to
					receive it. But just as those who expect a siege
					collect and store up all that is useful to them if they
					despair of relief from without, so it is most important
					that we should acquire far in advance the reinforcements which philosophy provides against temper and
					convey them into the soul in the knowledge that,
					when the occasion for using them comes, it will not
					be possible to introduce them with ease. For the
					soul hears nothing from the outside because of its
					tumult unless it has its own reason within, which, like
					a boatswain who directs the rowers, will promptly
					catch and understand every order given. Yet if
					the soul has heard words of advice which have been
					quietly and mildly spoken, it despises them; and
					toward any who insist in a rougher fashion, it grows
					exasperated. In fact, temper is overbearing and
					stubborn and altogether difficult for anyone other
					than itself to move, and, like a well-fortified tyranny,
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.101"/>
					
					must have its destroyer born and bred in the same
					household.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>To be sure, when anger persists and its outbursts
					are frequent, there is created in the soul an evil state
					which is called irascibility,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 411 b-c.</note> and this usually results in
					sudden outbursts of rage, moroseness, and peevishness when the temper becomes ulcerated, easily
					offended, and liable to find fault for even trivial
					offences, like a weak, thin piece of iron which is always
					getting scratched. But if judgement at once opposes
					the fits of anger and represses them, it not only cures
					them for the present, but for the future also it renders
					the soul firm and difficult for passion to attack. In
					my own case, at any rate, when I had opposed anger
					two or three times, it came about that I experienced
					what the Thebans did, who, when they had for the
					first time<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At the battle of Leuctra, 371 b.c.</note> repulsed the Spartans, who had the reputation of being invincible, were never thereafter defeated by them in any battle ; for I acquired the
					proud consciousness that it is possible for reason to
					conquer. Not only did I see that anger ceases when
					cold water is sprinkled on it, as Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is apparently from a lost work, though not included in Rose's collection of fragments. In <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, x. 60 (898 a 4), however, Aristotle observes that fear is a process of cooling; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">De Partibus Animalium</hi>, ii. 4 (651 a 8 ff.).</note> says, but
					that it is also extinguished when a poultice of fear is
					applied to it. And, by Heaven, if joy comes on the
					scene, in the case of many the temper has been
					quickly <q direct="unspecified">warmed,</q> as Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xxiii. 598, 600, <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>; for Plutarch's interpretation of <foreign lang="greek">i)ai/nesqai</foreign> see <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 947 d: <foreign lang="greek">a)le/an tw=| sw/mati meq' h(donh=s, o(/per *(/omhros i)ai/nesqai ke/klhken</foreign>; see also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 735 f.</note> says, or dissipated.
					Consequently I came to the opinion that this passion
					is not altogether incurable, for those, at least, who
					wish to cure it.
				</p>
            <p>
					For anger does not always have great and powerful
					beginnings ; on the contrary, even a jest, a playful
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.103"/>
					
					word, a burst of laughter or a nod on the part of
					somebody, and many things of the kind, rouse many
					persons to anger ; just as Helen, by thus addressing
					her niece,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Electra, virgin for so long a time,</quote>
					provoked her to reply,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Too late you're wise ; but once you left your home
						</l>
                  <l>Disgraced.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Orestes</hi>, 72, 99.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And so was Alexander provoked by Callisthenes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 623 f - 624 a; Athenaeus, x. 434 d.</note>
					who said, when the great bowl was going its rounds,
					<q direct="unspecified">I do not care to have a drink of Alexander and then
						have to call in Asclepius.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A jibe at Alexander's assumed divinity, <q direct="unspecified">Alexander</q> taking the place of Dionysus, the wine god, until the physician god, Asclepius, would have to be called in; on the authenticity of the story see Macurdy, <hi rend="italics">Jour. Hell. Stud.</hi>, 1. (1930), 294-297.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>And so, just as it is an easy matter to check a
					flame which is being kindled in hare's fur<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 138 f.</note> or candlewicks or rubbish, but if it ever takes hold of solid
					bodies having depth, it quickly destroys and consumes
					<quote rend="blockquote">With youthful vigour lofty craftsmen's work,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 107, Frag. 357.</note>
               </quote>
					as Aeschylus has it; so the man who at the beginning
					gives heed to his temper and observes it while it is
					still smoking and catching flame little by little from
					some gossip or rubbishy scurrility need have no great
					concern about it ; on the contrary, he has often
					succeeded in extinguishing it merely by keeping
					silent and ignoring it. For he who gives no fuel to
					fire puts it out, and likewise he who does not in the
					beginning nurse his wrath and does not puff himself
					up with anger takes precautions against it and destroys it. I was therefore not satisfied with what
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.105"/>
					
					Hieronymus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of Rhodes, Peripatetic philosopher of the third century b.c.</note> says - although he contributes other
					useful remarks and advice - in the passage where he
					declares that we have no perception of anger when it
					comes into being, but only when it has already come
					into being and exists, the reason being the swiftness
					with which it acts. For the truth is that none of the
					emotions, at the time when they are gathering and
					beginning to move, has a birth and increase so easy
					to perceive.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">De Amore</hi>, 4 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 134).</note> Indeed Homer also skilfully teaches
					us this lesson when he causes Achilles to be suddenly
					overwhelmed by grief on receiving the report,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of Patroclus's death, brought by Antilochus: <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xviii. 22.</note> in
					the passage where the poet says :
					<quote rend="blockquote">He spoke, and a black cloud of grief closed round
						Achilles;</quote>
					but Homer portrays Achilles as being slow to lose
					his temper with Agamemnon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, i. 101 ff.</note> and as becoming
					inflamed only when many words had been spoken.
					Yet if either one of the men had held back their
					words at the beginning and prevented their utterance, the quarrel would not have had so great a
					growth or have reached such magnitude. That is
					the reason why Socrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 13. 3.</note> as often as he perceived
					himself being moved to too great harshness against
					any of his friends, betaking himself to coast
					<quote rend="blockquote">Before the storm along some promontory,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Author unknown: Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi>, iii. p. 721; Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica</hi>, ii. p. 163; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, iii. p. 473; quoted more fully in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 129 a, 503 a.</note>
               </quote>
					would lower his voice, cause a smile to spread over his
					face, and make the expression of his eyes more gentle,
					preserving himself from fault and defeat by setting
					up within himself an influence to counteract his
					passion.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>For the first way, my friend, to dethrone temper
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.107"/>
					
					as you would a tyrant, is not to oey or hearken when
					it bids us cry aloud and look fierce and beat our
					breasts, but to keep quiet and not intensify the
					passion, as we would a disease, by tossing about and
					making a clamour. It is quite true that lovers'
					practices, such as serenading in concert or alone and
					crowning the beloved's door with garlands, do in some
					way or other bring an alleviation that is not without
					charm or grace :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>I came, but did not shout your name or race ;
						</l>
                  <l>I merely kissed the door. If this be sin,
						Then I have sinned.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Callimachus, <hi rend="italics">Epigram</hi> 43 (42), vv. 5, 6 (<hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi>, xii. 118). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Propertius, ii. 30. 24: <foreign lang="la">Hoc si crimen erit, crimen amoris erit</foreign>.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					So too the surrender of mourners to weeping and
					wailing carries away much of their grief together with
					their tears. But temper is the more readily fanned
					into flame by what people in that state do and say.
				</p>
            <p>
					The best course, therefore, is for us to compose
					ourselves, or else to run away and conceal ourselves,
					and anchor ourselves in a calm harbour, as though we
					perceived a fit of epilepsy coming on,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 10. 3.</note> so that we may
					not fall, or rather may not fall upon others ; and we
					are especially likely to fall most often upon our
					friends. For we do not love or envy or fear everyone
					indiscriminately, but there is nothing that temper will
					not touch and assail: we grow angry with enemies
					and friends, with children and parents, yes, even with
					the gods, with wild beasts and soulless implements, as
					Thamyris did :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Breaking the lyre-arms, overlaid with gold,
						Breaking his melodious, taut-strung lyre<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 183, Sophocles, Frag. 223 (Frag. 244 ed. Pearson). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, ii. 594-600.</note>;</quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.6.p.109"/>
					
					and Pandarus, who invoked a curse on himself if he
					did not <q direct="unspecified">break with his hands</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, v. 216.</note> his bow and burn
					it. And Xerxes not only branded and lashed the sea,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, vii. 35.</note>
					but also sent a letter to Mount Athos<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Contrast <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> vii. 24.</note>: <q direct="unspecified">Noble
						Athos, whose summit reaches heaven, do not put in
						the way of my deeds great stones difficult to work.
						Else I shall hew you down and cast you into the
						sea.</q> For temper can do many terrible things, and
					likewise many that are ridiculous ; therefore it is
					both the most hated and the most despised of the
					passions. It will be useful to consider it in both of
					these aspects.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>As for me - whether rightly I do not know - I
					made this start in the treatment of my anger : I
					began to observe the passion in others, just as the
					Spartans used to observe in the Helots<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 239 a, and the note.</note> what a thing
					drunkenness is. And first, as Hippocrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Prognosticon</hi>, 2 (vol. l. p. 79 ed. K&uuml;hlewein).</note> says that
					the most severe disease is that in which the
					countenance of the sufferer is most unlike itself, so I
					observed that those who are transported by anger
					also change most in countenance, colour, gait, and
					voice,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 35.</note> and thus formed for myself a picture of that
					passion and was exceedingly uncomfortable to think
					that I should ever appear so terrible and deranged to
					my friends and my wife and daughters, not merely
					savage and unfamiliar to their sight, but also speaking with so harsh and rough a voice as were others
					of my intimate friends whom I used to meet at times
					when anger had made them unable to preserve their
					character or bearing or grace of speech or their
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.111"/>
					
					winning and affable manners. The ease of Gaius
					Gracchus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of the Gracchi</hi>, ii. (825 b), and Ziegler's references <hi rend="italics">ad loc</hi>.</note> the orator will serve as illustration. He
					was not only severe in his disposition, but spoke too
					passionately; so he caused a pitch-pipe to be made
					of the sort which musicians use to lead the voice up
					and down the scales to the proper note; with this
					in hand his servant used to stand behind him as he
					spoke and give him a decorous and gentle tone which
					enabled Gracchus to remit his loud cries and remove
					from his voice the harsh and passionate element; just
					as the shepherds'
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Wax-joined pipe, clear sounding,
						</l>
                  <l>Drones a slumberous strain,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Prometheus</hi>, 574-575: Io speaks with reference to the piping of Argus as he guards her.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					so did he charm and lay to rest the rage of the orator.
					But as for me, if I had some attentive and clever
					companion, I should not be vexed if he held a mirror<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 36. 1-3.</note>
					up to me during my moments of rage, as they do for
					some persons after bathing, though to no useful purpose. For to see oneself in a state which nature did
					not intend, with one's features all distorted, contributes in no small degree toward discrediting that
					passion. In fact, those who delight in pleasant fables
					tell us that when Athena<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alcibiades</hi>, ii. (192 e); Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Ars Amatoria</hi>, iii. 505 ff.; <hi rend="italics">Fasti</hi>, vi. 699 ff.; Athenaeus, xiv. 616 e ff.; Tzetzes, <hi rend="italics">Chiliades</hi>, i. 364 ff.</note> played on the pipes, she
					was rebuked by the satyr and would give no heed :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>That look becomes you not; lay by your pipes
						</l>
                  <l>And take your arms and put your cheeks to rights<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 911, ades. 381.</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					but when she saw her face in a river, she was vexed
					and threw her pipes away. Yet art makes melody
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.113"/>
					
					some consolation for unsightliness. And Marsyas,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 713 d.</note>
					it seems, by a mouthpiece and cheek-bands repressed
					the violence of his breath and tricked up and concealed the distortion of his face :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>He fitted the fringe of his temples with gleaming gold
						</l>
                  <l>And his greedy mouth he fitted with thongs bound behind<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Simonides, according to Tzetzes, <hi rend="italics">Chiliades</hi>, i. 372 (Frag. 177 Bergk, 160 Diehl, 115 Edmonds); attributed by Schneidewin to Simias Rhodius (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Powell, <hi rend="italics">Coll. Alex.</hi>, p. 111).</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					but anger, which puffs up and distends the face in an
					unbecoming way, utters a voice still more ugly and
					unpleasant,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Stirring the heart-strings never stirred before.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 907, ades. 361; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 43 d; 501 a, 502 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; 657 c.</note>
               </quote>
					For when the sea is disturbed by the winds and casts
					up tangle and seaweed, they say that it is being
					cleansed ; but the intemperate, bitter, and vulgar
					words which temper casts forth when the soul is
					disturbed defile the speakers of them first of all and
					fill them with disrepute, the implication being that
					they have always had these traits inside of them and
					are full of them, but that their inner nature is now
					laid bare by their anger. Hence for a mere word,
					the <q direct="unspecified">lightest of things,</q> as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A combination of <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 935 a and 717 d, as in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 90 c, 505 c, 634 f; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Schlemm, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxxviii. 596.</note> says, they incur
					the <q direct="unspecified">heaviest of punishments,</q> being esteemed as
					hostile, slanderous, and malicious.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>When I, accordingly, observe these things, and
					store them carefully away, it occurs to me to lay up
					and quite thoroughly remember for my own use that,
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.115"/>
					
					just as it is a good thing in a fever, so it is an even
					better thing in anger, to keep the tongue soft and
					smooth. For if the tongue of men who are sick of a
					fever is in an unnatural state, it is a bad symptom,
					but not the cause of their malady; but when the
					tongue of angry men becomes rough and foul and
					breaks out in unseemly speeches, it brings forth
					insolence which creates irremediable enmity and
					argues a festering malevolence within. For unmixed
					wine produces nothing so intemperate and odious as
					anger does : words flown with wine go well with
					laughter and sport, but those which spring from anger
					are mixed with gall; and whereas the man who keeps
					silent at a drinking-bout is disagreeable and irksome
					to the company, there is nothing more dignified, if
					one is angry, than holding one's peace, as Sappho<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 27 ed. Bergk, 126 ed. Diehl, 137 ed. Edmonds; it is unlikely that Plutarch wrote the Aeolic accents which are here restored.</note>
					advises :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>When anger swells within the breast,
						</l>
                  <l>Restrain the idly barking tongue.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But it is not these considerations only that
					constant watching of those who are in the grip of
					anger furnishes us, but also an understanding of
					the general nature of ill temper - that it is not well-bred, nor manly, nor possessing any quality of pride
					or greatness. Yet most people think its turbulence
					to be activity, its blustering to be confident boldness, its obstinacy force of character; and some
					claim that even its cruelty is magnificence in action
					and its implacability firmness in resolution and its
					moroseness hatred of evil,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 462 e, 482 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> but they are wrong in this.
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.117"/>
					
					For the actions and the motions and the whole demeanour of angry persons declare their utter littleness
					and weakness, not only when they rend little children
					and rage bitterly against women and think it proper
					to punish dogs and horses and mules, as Ctesiphon
					the pancratiast did, who thought it right to kick back
					at his mule ; but also in the butcheries that tyrants
					perpetrate, their meanness of soul is apparent in
					their cruelty and their perverted state in their action,
					and is like the bites of vipers, which, when thoroughly
					inflamed with rage and pain, eject their excessive
					fiery passion upon those who have hurt them. For
					just as with the flesh a swelling results from a great
					blow, so with the weakest souls the inclination to
					inflict a hurt produces a flaring up of temper as great
					as the soul's infirmity is great.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The cruel tyrant, like the viper, indulges in rages as a sort of defence-reaction, a proof of inherent weakness.</note> That is also the
					reason why women are more prone to anger than
					men, and sick persons than healthy, and old men than
					men in their prime, and the unfortunate than the
					prosperous. Most prone to anger, for instance, are
					the miser with his steward, the glutton with his cook,
					the jealous man with his wife, the conceited man when
					he has been maligned ; but worst of all are
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Men who court too eagerly
						</l>
                  <l>Ambition in the towns :
						</l>
                  <l>Manifest is the pain they bring,</l>
               </quote>
					as Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 210 ed. Bergk, 229 ed. Boeckh; p. 609 ed. Sandys.</note> has it. In like manner from the pain and
					suffering of the soul, caused generally by weakness,
					there arises the outburst of passion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Coriolanus</hi>, xv. (220 e).</note> which is not, as
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.119"/>
					
					someone<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 411 b; contrast <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 449 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>. Plutarch seems to be unwilling to name Plato when he is forced to contradict him. But see Pohlenz, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxxi. 332 (on Philodemus, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, xxxi. 24).</note> has said, like <q direct="unspecified">sinews of the soul,</q> but
					like the strainings and convulsions of the soul when
					it is stirred too vehemently in its impulse to defend
					itself.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>These base examples, to be sure, were not
					pleasant to observe, but merely unavoidable ; but in
					discussing those who deal with transports of rage in a
					mild and gentle way I offer instances which are very
					beautiful both to hear and to witness, and I begin
					with a word of scorn for those who say,
					<quote rend="blockquote">It was a man you wronged : should a man bear this?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 912, ades. 382.</note>
               </quote> 
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Trample him underfoot, tread on his neck,
						</l>
                  <l>And bring him to the ground!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi>, iii. p. 694; Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica</hi>, i. p. 265; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi>, ii. p. 304: an anonymous tetrameter attributed by Meineke to Archilochus.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					and other provocative expressions, by using which
					some err in transferring anger from the women's
					quarters to the men's. For although courage gets
					along well with justice in all other respects, yet,
					as it seems to me, it fights for the possession of
					gentleness alone, as belonging rather to itself. But
					although cases do occur in which even baser men gain
					the mastery over their betters, yet to erect in the
					soul a trophy of victory over anger (which Heracleitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, i. p. 170, Frag. 85; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Coriolanus</hi>, xxii. (224 c), and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 755 d. But Heracleitus's meaning is probably that it is Love, not Anger, which it is difficult to contend against.</note> says it is difficult to contend against: <q direct="unspecified">for
						whatever it wishes, it buys at the price of the soul</q>)
					is proof of a great and victorious strength which
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.121"/>
					
					possesses against the passions the weapons of its
					judgements, as in very truth its nerves and sinews.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps a correction (as 457 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>) of Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 411 b (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 449 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>).</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					For this reason I always strive to collect and
					to peruse, not only these sayings and deeds of the
					philosophers, who are said by fools to have no bile,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, our <q direct="unspecified">no guts</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Archilochus, Frag. 131, Bergk, and Capps's note on Menander, <hi rend="italics">Perikeiromene</hi>, 259.</note>
					but even more those of kings and despots. There is,
					for instance, the remark of Antigonus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 182 c; Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 22. 2.</note> to his soldiers
					who were reviling him near his tent in the belief that
					he could not hear them : he merely thrust out his
					staff and cried, <q direct="unspecified">Good heavens! will you not go
						somewhere farther off to abuse me?</q> And there is
					the case of Arcadion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Athenaeus, vi. 249 c-d: Arcadion, while in flight from Macedonia, accidentally met Philip who asked him how long he was going to stay in exile. This is Arcadion's reply.</note> the Achaean who was always
					railing against Philip and advising flight
					<quote rend="blockquote">Until one comes to men who know not Philip<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A parody of Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xi. 122; xxiii. 269.</note>;</quote>
					when Arcadion later visited Macedonia on some
					chance or other, Philip's friends thought that he
					should not be let off but punished. Yet Philip, when
					he met him, treated him kindly and sent him friendly
					presents and gifts ; and later bade his friends inquire
					how Arcadion now spoke of him to the Greeks.
					When all testified that the fellow had become a
					wonderful eulogist of the king, Philip said, <q direct="unspecified">Then I
						am a better physician than you.</q> So in Olympia<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 143 f; 179 a with Nachst&auml;dt's note <hi rend="italics">ad loc</hi>.</note>
					when Philip was being defamed, and some persons
					said that the Greeks should smart for it since they
					spoke evil of Philip though they were being well
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.123"/>
					
					treated by him, Philip said, <q direct="unspecified">What will they do,
						then, if they are badly treated?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Likewise admirable was the behaviour of Peisistratus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 189 c, and Nachst&auml;dt <hi rend="italics">ad loc</hi>.</note> to Thrasybulus, and of Porsenna<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid</hi>. 305 f; <hi rend="italics">Life of Publicola</hi>, xvii. (106 a-d) with Lindskog's note.</note> to Mucius,
					and of Magas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 449 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> to Philemon. For when Magas had
					been publicly ridiculed by Philemon in a comedy at
					the theatre :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>A. For you some letters, Magas, from the king.
						</l>
                  <l>B. Unhappy Magas, who no letters know!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi>, ii. p. 522, Frag. 144.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					Magas later captured Philemon, who had been cast
					ashore by a storm at Paraetonium, and ordered a
					soldier merely to touch Philemon on the neck with
					a naked sword and then depart courteously ; and
					Magas sent dice and a ball to Philemon, as to a
					senseless child, and sent him on his way. So also
					Ptolemy, when he was jeering at a pedant for his
					ignorance, asked him who was Peleus' father ; and
					the pedant replied, <q direct="unspecified">I shall tell you if you will first
						tell me who was the father of Lagus.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Officially the father of Ptolemy I, who, however, was commonly thought to have been the bastard son of Philip of Macedon.</note> This was a
					jest at the dubious birth of the king, and everyone
					was indignant at its improper and inopportune
					character; but Ptolemy said, <q direct="unspecified">If it is not the part
						of a king to take a jest, neither is it to make one.</q>
					But Alexander had behaved more harshly than was
					his custom toward Callisthenes and Cleitus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, lv. (696 d-e); 449 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 17. 1.</note> And
					so Porus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 181 e, 332 e; <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, ix. (699 c), and Ziegler's note.</note> when he was taken captive, requested
					Alexander to treat him <q direct="unspecified">like a king.</q> When
					Alexander asked, <q direct="unspecified">Is there nothing more?</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">In
						the words <q direct="unspecified">like a king,</q>
               </q> replied Porus, <q direct="unspecified">there is
							
							<pb id="v.6.p.125"/>
							
							everything.</q> For this reason also they call the king
					of the gods Meilichios, or the Gentle One, while the
					Athenians, I believe, call him Maimactes, or the
					Boisterous<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But <q direct="unspecified">Gentle</q> when propitiated. See Hesychius and Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Lexicon d. gr. u. r&ouml;m. Mythologie, s.v.</hi>; and Hewitt, <hi rend="italics">Harvard Stud. Class. Phil.</hi>, xix. (1908), 75-78.</note>; but punishment is the work of the
					Furies and spirits, not of the high gods and Olympian deities.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Just as, then, someone said of Philip<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 40 e, 215 b. For the thought see Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Pythian Odes</hi>, iv. 484.</note> when
					he had razed Olynthus to the ground, <q direct="unspecified">But he could
						not possibly repeople a city so large,</q> so one may
					address Anger and say, <q direct="unspecified">You are able to overturn
						and destroy and throw down, but to raise up and preserve and spare and forbear is the work of mildness
						and forgiveness and moderation in passion, the work
						of a Camillus or a Metellus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch probably means Q. Caecilius Metellus Macedonicus; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 202 a.</note> or an Aristeides or a
						Socrates; but to attach oneself to the wound and to
						sting is the part of an ant or a horse-fly.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 34. 1; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Socrates' comparison of himself to a gad-fly in <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, 30 e.</note> As I
					study, however, anger's method of defending itself, I
					find it for the most part ineffectual, since it spends
					itself in biting the lips<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, i. 19. 2-3.</note> and gnashing the teeth,
					in vain attacks and railings coupled with senseless
					threats, and eventually resembles children<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 447 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> running
					races, who, through lack of self-control, fall down
					ridiculously before they reach the goal toward which
					they are hastening. Therefore there was point in
					what the Rhodian said to the Roman general's
					servant who was shouting and talking insolently :
					<q direct="unspecified">What <hi rend="italics">you</hi> say,</q> said the Rhodian, <q direct="unspecified">matters nothing
						
						<pb id="v.6.p.127"/>
						
						to me, but what your master doesn't say.</q> And
					Sophocles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 210. 8, 9, ed. Pearson, vol. i. pp. 152 ff., where see he careful discussion of the relation of this passage to <hi rend="italics">Ox. Pap.</hi>, ix. 1175; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, Sophocles, Frag. 768.</note> when he has armed Neoptolemus and
					Eurypylus, says
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Without a vaunt, without reviling, they
						</l>
                  <l>Have rushed within the ring of brazen arms.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					For although there are barbarians who poison their
					steel, true bravery has no need of bitter gall,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The poison of anger.</note> for it
					has been dipped in reason ; but rage and fury are
					rotten and easily broken. At any rate the Spartans<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 238 b, with Nachst&auml;dt <hi rend="italics">ad loc</hi>.</note>
					use the playing of pipes to remove from their fighting
					men the spirit of anger, and they sacrifice to the
					Muses before battle in order that reason may
					remain constant within them ; and when they have
					routed the enemy, they do not pursue,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, iv. 8. 11.</note> but sound
					the recall to their high spirits, which, like small
					daggers,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 35. 1: <foreign lang="la">tale ira telum est: vix retrahitur</foreign>.</note> are manageable and can be easily withdrawn. Yet wrath has slain thousands before its revenge was accomplished, as, for instance, Cyrus t and
					Pelopidas the Theban.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably Cyrus the Younger, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, i. 8. 26-27; but Cyrus the Great may be meant, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 21, which is not, however, quite in point; nor is Herodotus, i. 205 ff.</note> But Agathocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 176 e; Diodorus, xx. 63. Agathocles was the son of a potter.</note> endured
					with mildness the revilings of those he was besieging,
					and when one of them cried out, <q direct="unspecified">Potter, how will
						you get pay for your mercenaries?</q>, Agathocles
					laughed and said, <q direct="unspecified">If I take this town.</q> And there
					is the case of Antigonus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The One=eyed; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 22. 4-5; related of Agathocles in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 176 e-f.</note> who, when some men on the
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.129"/>
					
					wall of a town jeered at him because of his deformity,
					said to them, <q direct="unspecified">Why, I thought my face was handsome!</q> But when he took the town he sold as slaves
					those who jeered at him, protesting that he would
					have speech with their masters if they reviled him
					again.
				</p>
            <p>
					I observe also that both advocates and orators
					commit serious mistakes because of anger; and
					Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, iii. 27 (875 a 34 ff.); cited by Stobaeus, iii. p. 551 ed. Hense.</note> relates that the friends of Satyrus the
					Samian, when he was to plead, stopped up his ears
					with wax, that he might not spoil his case through
					temper at the insults of his enemies. And as for
					ourselves, does it not happen often that the punishment of a delinquent slave eludes our power? For
					slaves are made afraid by threatening words and run
					away.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, iii. 5. 4.</note> The words, therefore, which nurses use with
					children, <q direct="unspecified">Stop crying and you shall have it!</q> may,
					not without benefit, be applied to temper : <q direct="unspecified">Stop
						hurrying and shouting and making haste, and you
						shall have what you want better and more easily!</q>
					For if a father sees his son trying to cut something
					in two or to make a notch in it with a knife, he takes
					the knife himself and does it; so likewise, if reason
					takes upon itself the punishment which temper would
					inflict, it chastises the person who deserves it safely
					and harmlessly and for that person's good, and does
					not, as temper often does, punish itself instead.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, v. 3. 7.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But however true it is that all the passions have
					need of a process of habituation, which tames as it
					were and subdues by rigorous training the irrational
					and obstinate element of the soul, there is no passion
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.131"/>
					
					that we can better learn to control by practising on
					servants than temper. For no envy or fear or rivalry
					enters into our relations with them, but frequent
					fits of anger bring about many conflicts and errors,
					and because of the absolute power we possess, there
					being no one to oppose or prevent us, these cause us
					to slide and fall, since we are, as it were, on slippery
					ground. For it is impossible that irresponsible power
					under the influence of passion should be free from
					error, unless he who wields this power shall encompass it with a bulwark of gentleness, and shall hold
					out against many pleas of wife and friends, all
					charging him with laxity and easy-going ways. By
					such charges I myself used to be very greatly exasperated against my slaves, in the conviction that
					they were being ruined by not being punished. At
					long last, however, though late it was, I came to
					perceive that, in the first place, it is better to make
					them worse by forbearance than by harshness and
					anger to pervert my own self for the correction of
					the others. In the second place, when I observed
					that many, just because they were not being punished, were often ashamed to be bad, and made
					pardon, rather than correction, the starting-point
					of reformation, and, I swear, performed their duties
					more zealously for the kind of master who gave
					orders silently with a nod than for the others who
					used blows and branding-irons, I began to be convinced that reason is more fit than anger to govern.
					For it is not as the Poet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer), <hi rend="italics">Cypria</hi>, Frag. 20 ed. Kinkel; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Cleomenes</hi>, ix. (xxx.) (808 e); Plato, <hi rend="italics">Euthyphro</hi>, 12 a-b.</note> has said,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Where fear is, there is also reverence;</quote>
					but, on the contrary, in those who revere there is
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.133"/>
					
					engendered the kind of fear that corrects behaviour,
					whereas continual and unmerciful beating produces,
					not repentance for wrongdoing, but rather the farsighted cunning to do wrong without detection. In
					the third place, I always keep in mind and reflect in
					privacy that he who taught us the use of the bow did
					not forbid us to shoot, but only to miss the mark,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 451 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and
					that the infliction of punishment will not be hindered
					by our teaching how to inflict it at the right time,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">When it is really deserved.</note> with
					moderation, and in a useful and suitable manner ;
					and, remembering these things, I try to get rid of my
					anger, if possible, by not depriving those who are to
					be punished of the right to speak in their defence, but
					by listening to their plea. For both the passage of
					time gives a pause to passion and a delay which dissolves it, and also the judgement discovers a suitable
					manner of punishment and an adequate amount ;
					furthermore, the man who suffers punishment has no
					pretext left for opposing the correction if punishment
					is inflicted, not in anger, but after the accused has
					been proved guilty ; and finally, the most shameful
					thing is avoided-that the slave should seem to be
					making a juster plea than his master.
				</p>
            <p>
					And so, just as Phocion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Phocion</hi>, xxii. (751 e); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 188 d.</note> after Alexander's death,
					trying to keep the Athenians from revolting prematurely or believing the report too quickly, said to
					them, <q direct="unspecified">If, men of Athens, he is dead to-day, he will
						be dead to-morrow also, and the day after</q> ; in like
					manner, I think, the man who, urged on by anger, is
					in a hurry for vengeance, should suggest to himself,
					<q direct="unspecified">If this person is guilty of wronging you to-day, he
						will still be guilty to-morrow also, and the day after ;
						
						<pb id="v.6.p.135"/>
						
						no harm will be done if he shall be punished somewhat
						late, but if he is punished in haste he will always be
						thought to have suffered without offending ; and this
						has happened many times in the past.</q> For which of
					us is so harsh that he scourges and chastises a slave
					because five or ten days ago he overroasted the meat
					or upset the table or carne too slowly at our bidding?
					And yet these are the very things which cause us to
					be excited and in a cruel and implacable mood at
					the moment they happen and are still fresh in our
					memory. For as the shapes of persons seen through
					a fog, so things seen through a mist of rage appear
					greater than they are.
				</p>
            <p>
					These are the reasons why we should immediately
					call to mind such instances and precepts ; and when
					we are free from all suspicion of passion, if the
					offence still appears evil to the clear and settled
					judgement, we should attend to it then and not
					dismiss or abandon the punishment, as we leave food
					when we have lost our appetite. And nothing
					is so much the cause of our punishing in a rage as
					that, when our anger is over, we do not punish, but
					leave things alone. We are very much like lazy
					oarsmen, who during calm weather lie in port, and
					later, at the risk of their lives, avail themselves of
					a wind to go sailing. And so do we condemn reason
					for remissness and softness in punishment and
					hasten on to the deed rashly and to our peril when
					anger, like a gale, is upon us. For while a hungry
					man indulges in food as nature dictates, yet
					punishment is indulged in by one who is not hungry
					or thirsty for it, nor does he need anger as a relish
					to stimulate him to punish ; on the contrary, when he
					finds himself very far removed from the desire to
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.137"/>
					
					punish, he brings up reason to reinforce him and
					punishes under compulsion. Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 608 ed. Rose.</note> relates that
					in Etruria in his day slaves were scourged to the
					music of pipes. But one should not, in that spirit,
					through a craving for the punishment as for a kind of
					enjoyment, gorge oneself with it, and rejoice while
					inflicting chastisement and after inflicting it repent<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 550 e, where the whole context may be compared with this chapter. See also Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, i. 17-18.</note>
					- of these the first is bestial, the second womanish -
					but without either sorrow or pleasure one should mete
					out punishment in reason's own good time, leaving
					anger no excuse.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>However this, perhaps, will not appear to be a
					cure for anger, but a temporary reprieve and prophylactic<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the phrase <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 420 e.</note> against those errors which some men commit
					in anger. And yet, though the swelling of the spleen
					is but a symptom of fever, reducing it assuages the
					fever, as Hieronymus says. But when I contemplated the origin of anger itself, I observed that
					different persons are liable to anger from different
					causes ; yet in the case of practically all of them there
					is present a belief that they are being despised or
					neglected.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, ii. 3 (1380 a 8 ff.).</note> For this reason we should assist those
					who endeavour to avoid anger, by removing as far as
					possible the act that rouses wrath from any suspicion
					of contempt or arrogance and by imputing it to
					ignorance or necessity or emotion or mischance. So
					Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Antigone</hi>, 563-564; quoted with the same textual variants in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Phocion</hi>, i. (742 a).</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>O king, not even the reason Nature gives
						</l>
                  <l>Stays with the unfortunate, but goes astray ;</l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.6.p.139"/>
					
					and so likewise Agamemnon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xix. 138.</note> ascribes the taking
					away of Briseis to divine infatuation :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>I wish again to make amends, to give
						</l>
                  <l>You countless ransom.</l>
               </quote>
					Supplication, indeed, is the act of one who does not
					despise ; and when he that has done an injury shows
					himself humble, he removes all notion of contempt.
					But the man in a rage should not wait for such
					humility, but should take to himself the reply of
					Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Fabius Maximus</hi>, x. (179 f); Diogenes Laertius, vi. 54.</note>: when someone said to him, <q direct="unspecified">They are
						laughing at you, Diogenes,</q> he answered, <q direct="unspecified">But I
							am not laughed down.</q> Just so the angry man
					should not consider himself despised, but rather
					despise the man who gave the offence as acting from
					weakness or rashness, carelessness or illiberality,
					dotage or childishness. But such a notion must not
					on any account be entertained toward servants or
					friends ; for our servants presume on our upright
					character, our friends on our affection, and both
					disregard us, not as being impotent or ineffectual,
					but because of our reasonableness or our goodwill.
					As it is, thinking ourselves despised, we not only
					treat harshly wife and slaves and friends, but also
					through rage often fall out with innkeepers and
					sailors and drunken muleteers ; we even rage
					against dogs that bark at us and asses that jostle
					us,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 563 c.</note> like the man who wished to beat the assdriver, but when the driver cried out, <q direct="unspecified">I am an
						Athenian,</q> indicated the ass and said, <q direct="unspecified">You at
							any rate are not an Athenian,</q> and fell to beating it
					with many blows.
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.141"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Furthermore it is especially selfishness and
					peevishness, together with luxury and softness, which
					beget in us those continuous or oft-recurring fits of
					anger that are gathered together in the soul little by
					little, like a swarm of bees or wasps. And so there is
					nothing more conducive to gentleness than graciousness and simplicity toward servants and wife and
					friends if a man is able to get along with what comforts
					he has and is in no need of many superfluities :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>But he who liked his meat not overdone
						</l>
                  <l>Nor underdone, nor medium, nor boiled
						</l>
                  <l>Too much ; and liked no food enough to praise<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 472, ades. 343.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					who will drink no wine if there is no snow with it,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 25. 4.</note>
					nor eat bread purchased in the market, nor touch food
					served on cheap or earthenware dishes, nor sleep upon
					a bed that does not billow like the sea stirred to its
					depths ; he who with rods and blows makes his
					servants at table hasten about running and crying
					out and sweating as though they were bringing
					poultices for boils,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A matter evidently requiring urgent haste.</note> such a man is enslaved to an
					impotent, querulous, and discontented mode of life.
					His many shocks of anger are like a chronic cough
					by which he reduces himself to a condition where
					anger becomes a running sore. We must, therefore,
					accustom the body to contentment by plain living
					and to self-sufficiency, for those who need but little
					are not disappointed of much.
				</p>
            <p>
					And, to begin with our food, it is no great hardship
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.143"/>
					
					if we partake in silence of whatever is set before
					us and do not, by being repeatedly choleric and
					peevish, thrust upon ourselves and our friends the
					worst sauce for meat, anger.
					<quote rend="blockquote">No more unpleasant supper could there be<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xx. 392.</note>
               </quote>
					than that wherein servants are beaten and wife is
					reviled because something is burned or smoked or not
					salted enough, or because the bread is too cold.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 25.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Arcesila&uuml;s was once entertaining his friends and
					with them some foreign guests, and when dinner was
					served, there was no bread, since the slaves had
					neglected to buy any. In such a predicament which
					one of us would not have rent the walls asunder with
					outcries? But Arcesilaus merely smiled and said,
					<q direct="unspecified">How lucky it is that the wise man takes to the
						flowing bowl!</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There being no bread for the <hi rend="italics">deipnon</hi>, the <hi rend="italics">symposium</hi> will come earlier.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Once when Socrates took Euthydemus home with
					him from the palaestra, Xanthippe came up to them
					in a rage and scolded them roundly, finally upsetting
					the table.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 471 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, of Pittacus.</note> Euthydemus, deeply offended, got up
					and was about to leave when Socrates said, <q direct="unspecified">At your
						house the other day did not a hen fly in and do
						precisely this same thing, yet we were not put out
						about it?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					For we should receive our friends affably and with
					laughter and cheerful friendliness, not with frowning
					brows, or striking fear and trembling into our servants. We must, further, accustom ourselves to
					make cheerful use of any kind of table utensils and
					not to prefer this service to that, as some men do
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.145"/>
					
					who select one goblet or horn out of the many they
					have, and will drink from no other, as they relate of
					Marius. Some have this same feeling about oil-flasks and strigils, of which they have a liking for but
					one out of many ; and so when one of these preferred
					objects is broken or lost, they take it hard and punish
					severely. Therefore anyone who is prone to anger
					should abstain from rare and curiously wrought things,
					like drinking-cups and seal-rings and precious stones ;
					for their loss drives their owner out of his senses more
					than do objects which are easily procured and may
					be seen everywhere. This is the reason why, when
					Nero had had an octagonal tent built, a huge structure
					which was a sight to be seen because of its beauty
					and costliness, Seneca remarked, <q direct="unspecified">You have proved
						yourself a poor man, for if you ever lose this you will
						not have the means to procure another like it,</q>
					And indeed it did so happen that the ship which
					conveyed it was sunk and the tent lost. But Nero
					remembered Seneca's saying and bore his loss with
					greater moderation.
				</p>
            <p>
					A cheerful behaviour toward the affairs of life makes
					a master cheerful and gentle toward his slaves also ;
					and if to slaves, he will evidently be so to his friends
					as well as to those who are subject to his rule. And
					in fact we observe that ne wly purchased slaves inquire
					about their new master, not whether he is superstititious or envious, but whether he is ill-tempered<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">De Calumnia</hi>, Frag. 1 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 128).</note>;
					and, speaking generally, we see that if anger is
					present in a home, husbands cannot endure even
					their wives' chastity, nor wives even their husbands'
					love, nor friends even familiar intercourse with one
					another. Thus neither marriage nor friendship is
					tolerable if anger is there, but without anger even
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.147"/>
					
					drunkenness is easily borne. For the wand of
					Dionysus suffices to punish the drunkard, unless hot
					temper is added and makes the undiluted drink<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Choreius</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Lyaeus</hi>, epithets of Dionysus.</note>
					cause of savagery and madness instead of a dispeller
					of care and an inspirer of the dance. Madness pure
					and simple can indeed be cured by Anticyra<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A town on the Corinthian Gulf in Phocis, famous for its hellebore; see Rolfe's note on Aulus Gellius, xvii. 15. 6 (L.C.L., vol. iii. p. 260).</note>; but if
					madness is mingled with anger, it produces tragedies
					and tales of horror.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Surely we should allow no place to anger even
					in jest, for that brings enmity in where friendliness
					was ; nor in learned discussions, for that turns love
					of learning into strife ; nor when rendering judgement, for that adds insolence to authority ; nor in
					teaching, for that engenders discouragement and
					hatred of learning; nor in prosperity, for that
					increases envy ; nor in adversity, for that drives away
					compassion when men become irritable and quarrel
					with those who sympathize with them, as Priam<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xxiv. 239-240.</note> did :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Be gone, you wretched, shameful men! Have you
						</l>
                  <l>No cause for grief at home that you have come
						</l>
                  <l>To trouble me?</l>
               </quote>
					But a cheerful disposition in some circumstances is
					helpful, others it adorns, and still others it helps to
					sweeten ; by its gentleness it overcomes both anger
					and all moroseness. Thus Eucleides,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 489 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> when his
					brother said to him after a quarrel, <q direct="unspecified">Damned if I
						don't get even with you!</q> answered, <q direct="unspecified">But as for
							me, may I be damned if I don't convince you!</q> and
					so at once turned him from his purpose and won him
					over. And Polemon, when a man who was fond of
					precious stones and quite mad about expensive seal-rings
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.149"/>
					
					reviled him, made no answer, but fixed his gaze
					on one of the seal-rings and eyed it closely. The man,
					accordingly, was pleased and said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Do not
						look at it in this light, Polemon, but under the sun's
						rays, and it will appear to you far more beautiful.</q>
					Aristippus, again, when anger had arisen between
					him and Aeschines and someone said, <q direct="unspecified">Where now,
						Aristippus, is the friendship of you two?</q> replied,
					<q direct="unspecified">It is asleep, but I shall awaken it</q> ; and, going to
					Aeschines, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Do I appear to you so utterly
						unfortunate and incurable as not to receive correction
						from you?</q> And Aeschines replied, <q direct="unspecified">No wonder if
							you, who are naturally superior to me in all things,
							should in this matter also have discerned before I
							did the right thing to do.</q>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>For not a woman only, even a child,
						</l>
                  <l>Tickling the bristly boar with tender hand,
						</l>
                  <l>May throw him easier than a wrestler might.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 912, ades. 383.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					But we who tame wild beasts and make them gentle
					and carry about in our arms young wolves and lions'
					cubs,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 482 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> then under the impulse of rage cast off children,
					friends, and companions and let loose our wrath, like
					some wild beast, on servants and fellow-citizens - we,
					I say, do not well to use a cozening word for our anger
					by calling it <q direct="unspecified">righteous indignation,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 456 f, 449 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> but it is
					with anger, I believe, as with the other passions and
					diseases of the soul: we can rid ourselves of none of
					them by calling one <q direct="unspecified">foresight,</q> another <q direct="unspecified">liberality,</q>
					another <q direct="unspecified">piety.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>And yet, as Zeno<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, i. p. 36, Frag. 128.</note> used to say that the seed
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.151"/>
					
					was a mixture and compound drawn from all the
					faculties of the soul, so temper appears to be a
					mixture of seeds drawn from all the passions. For
					it is drawn from pain and pleasure, and from insolence ; and although it has envy's malicious joy in
					the ills of others, it is even worse than envy ; for
					the object of its striving is, not that it may itself
					avoid suffering evil, but that at the cost of suffering
					evil, it may utterly ruin its antagonist; and the
					most unlovely kind of desire is innate in it, inasmuch
					as it is a craving to pain someone else. And that is
					why, when we approach the houses of profligates,
					we hear a flute-girl still playing in the early morning,
					and we see <q direct="unspecified">muddy dregs of wine,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sophocles, Frag. 783 ed. Pearson, with the notes <hi rend="italics">ad loc</hi>.</note> as someone
					has said, <q direct="unspecified">and mangled fragments of garlands,</q> and
					tipsy servants reeling at the doors ; but the tokens
					of savage and irascible men you will see on the faces
					of their servants and in the marks branded upon
					them and their fetters.
					<quote rend="blockquote">The only music heard within the house</quote>
					of an angry man
					<quote rend="blockquote">Is wailing cries,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 913, ades. 387; quoted more completely in 518 b-c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
               </quote>
					as the stewards are being lashed within and the
					serving-maids being tortured, so that those who
					witness the anguish caused by anger in gratifying its
					desires and ministering to its pleasures must feel pity,
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>However, those of whom it is true that righteous indignation causes them frequently to be overwhelmed by anger should get rid of its excessive
					and violent form, together with their extreme confidence in those with whom they live.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 89 d.</note> For such
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.153"/>
					
					confidence more than any other cause increases the
					spirit of wrath, when, for example, one who has been
					accounted honourable proves to be base,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Nothing fans the flame of human resentment so much as the discovery that one's bosom has been utilized as a snake sanatorium.</q> - H. H. Monro.</note> or one
					whom we have supposed a true friend quarrels and
					finds fault with us. As for my own temperament,
					you doubtless know how strong are the impulses
					which incline it to be of goodwill toward my fellowmen and to trust them. Consequently, like men
					who attempt to walk on empty air, the more I give
					myself up to loving a person the more I go astray, and
					when I stumble and fall, the greater my distress ; and
					although I may no longer be able to reduce my too
					great propensity and eagerness to love, yet I may
					perhaps be able to use Plato's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Epistle</hi> xiii. 360 c; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 474 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 533 b-c.</note> caution as a curb
					against excessive trust. For Plato says that he praises
					Helicon the mathematician in such terms as he uses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">dediw\s de\ le/gw tau=ta, o(/ti u(pe\r a)nqrw/pou do/can a)pofai/nomai, ou) fau/lou zw/|ou a)ll' eu)metabo/lou</foreign>: <q direct="unspecified">This, however, I say with trepidation, since I am uttering an opinion about a man, and man, though not a worthless, is an inconstant creature.</q> - (Bury in L.C.L.)</note>
					because man is by nature an animal readily subject
					to change ; and that he does well to fear those who
					have been educated in the city lest, being men and
					the seeds of men,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 853 c.</note> they may reveal somewhere the
					weakness inherent in their nature. But when
					Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 853 ed. Pearson; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 311, Frag. 769; quoted again in 481 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> says
					<quote rend="blockquote">Search out most human traits; you'll find them base,</quote>
					he seems to go too far in trampling upon and belittling
					us. This peevish and censorious judgement does,
					however, tend to make us more considerate in our
					outbursts of temper ; for it is the sudden and the
					unexpected that throw men off their bearings.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 449 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.6.p.155"/>
					
					But we should, as Panaetius also has somewhere
					remarked, make use of the precept of Anaxagoras,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 474 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 118 d and the references <hi rend="italics">ad loc</hi>.; Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, ii. p. 14, 33.</note>
					and just as he, at the death of his son, said, <q direct="unspecified">I knew
						that I had begotten a mortal</q> ; so on each occasion
					we should remark with reference to the faults which
					exasperate us : <q direct="unspecified">I knew that I had not bought a
						philosopher for a slave,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">I knew that the friend I
							had made was not incapable of error,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">I knew
								that my wife was a woman.</q> And if we keep repeating to ourselves Plato's question, <q direct="unspecified">Can it be
									that I am like that?</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 40 d, 88 e, 129 d. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Horace, <hi rend="italics">Satires</hi>, i. 4. 136: <foreign lang="la">numquid ego illi | imprudens olim faciam simile</foreign>?; <q direct="unspecified">There but for the grace of God go I.</q>
               </note> and turn our reason inward
					instead of to external things, and substitute caution
					for censoriousness, we shall no longer make much use
					of <q direct="unspecified">righteous indignation</q> toward others when we
					observe that we ourselves stand in need of much
					indulgence. But as it is, everyone of us, when we are
					angry and inflicting punishment, brings out the injunctions of an Aristeides or a Cato : <q direct="unspecified">Do not steal!</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Do not lie!</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Why are you so lazy?</q> ; and -
					what is most disgraceful of all - while angry we chide
					others for being angry and punish by rage faults
					which have been committed in a rage, not like
					physicians, who
					<quote rend="blockquote">With bitter drugs can purge the bitter bile<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, Frag. 854 ed. Pearson, with the note; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 312, Frag. 770; quoted in a different form 468 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 923 f.</note>;</quote>
					but rather make more intense the malady and
					aggravate it.
				</p>
            <p>
					Whenever, therefore, I have become engaged in
					these reflections, at the same time I try to do away
					with some part of my inquisitiveness. For to search
					I out with great precision and detect and drag into the
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.157"/>
					
					light every little concern of a slave, every action of a
					friend, every pastime of a son, every whisper of a wife,
					produces frequent, or rather continual and daily, fits
					of anger, of which the sum total is a morose and
					intractable disposition. It may be, as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 675, Frag. 974; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 811 d. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Lucan, v. 340 ff.; and perhaps Horace, <hi rend="italics">Ars Poetica</hi>, 191-192.</note>
					says, that God
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Will intervene in matters grown too great,
						</l>
                  <l>But small things he lets pass and leaves to Fate ;</l>
               </quote>
					but I am of the opinion that a man of sense should
					commit nothing to Fate, nor overlook anything at all,
					but should trust and use for some things his wife, for
					others servants, for others friends, as a ruler makes
					use of overseers and accountants and administrators,
					but himself keeps under his own control the most
					important and weighty matters by the use of reason.
					For as small writing strains the eyes, so do trifling
					matters, by causing a greater strain, prick and stir up
					anger,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, ii. 26; iii. 11.</note> which becomes a bad habit that affects more
					important matters.
				</p>
            <p>
					Accordingly, in addition to all these considerations,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Erasmus, followed by Amyot, believed this concluding paragraph to be a Christian appendix added to Plutarch's work. This is very unlikely.</note>
					I have been wont to regard as great and divine that
					saying of Empedocles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, i. p. 369, Frag. 144; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Herrick: <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>To starve thy sin, not bin, </l>
                     <l>That is to keep thy Lent.</l>
                  </quote>
               </note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Fast from evil,</q> and to
					applaud also those other vows made in prayer as
					being neither ungracious nor inappropriate to a
					philosopher : to abstain from love and wine for a
					year, honouring God by continence ; or again to
					refrain from lying for a stated time, paying close heed
					to ourselves that we shall be truthful always whether
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.159"/>
					
					In jest or earnest. Then with these I compared my
					own vow, thinking it no less sacred and pleasant in
					the sight of God : first, to pass a few days without
					anger, sober and wineless days, as it were, as though
					I were offering a sacrifice of honey unmixed with
					wine<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Like the offerings to the Eumenides, Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Eumenides</hi>, 107; Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Coloneus</hi>, 100, 481; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Wyttenbach's note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 132 e.</note>; then I would do so for a month or two, and
					so, making trial of myself little by little, in time I
					made some progress in my forbearance, continently
					observing and keeping myself courteous in speech,
					placid, and free from anger, and pure of the taint of
					evil words and offensive actions and of passion which,
					at the price of a little unsatisfying pleasure, brings
					great perturbations of spirit and the most shameful
					repentance. By such means, I think - and God also
					gave me help - experience has shown the truth of
					that judgement: this placid and gentle and humane
					spirit is not so agreeable and pleasant and free from
					sorrow to any of those brought in contact with it as
					it is to those who themselves possess it.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>