<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De primo frigido</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.127">
      <body>
         <head>Concerning the first principle of cold.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.309"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Is there then, Favorinus, any first or principal power
				or existence of cold, as fire is the principle of heat, by the
				presence and imparting of which all other things of the
				same nature become cold? Or rather is not cold the privation of heat, as they say darkness is the privation of light,
				and rest the privation of motion? In regard that cold
				seems to be firm and stable, and heat always in motion;
				and for that the refrigeration of hot things is not caused
				by the presence of any active power, but by the departure
				of the heat. For we find the heat go off in great quantity, and then that which remains grows cold. Thus the
				vapor which boiling water sends forth ceases also when
				the heat is gone. Therefore refrigeration, expelling the
				heat, diminishes the quantity, while nothing supplies the
				place of it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>First, we might question this way of arguing, as being
				that which would abolish several manifest faculties, as
				being neither qualities nor habits, but the privations of
				habits and qualities; so as to make ponderosity the privation of levity, hardness the privation of softness, black of
				white, bitter of sweet, and so with other things which are
				naturally opposed to each other in their power and not as
				a privation to a habit. Or else for this reason, because all
				privation is a thing altogether sluggish and without action,
				as blindness, deafness, silence, and death; for they are the
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.310"/>
				
				departure of forms, and the utter defacings of substances,
				not being natures nor substances of themselves; but cold,
				wherever it resides, causes no less affections and alterations
				in bodies than heat. For many things are congealed by
				cold, many things thereby condensed. So that whatever
				is solid in it and difficult to be moved cannot be said to be
				sluggish and void of action, but firm and ponderous, as
				being supported by its own strength, which is endued with
				a power to preserve it in its proper station. Wherefore
				privation is the deficiency and departure of the opposite
				power, but many things are subject to be cold, though
				abounding with heat within themselves. And there are
				some things which cold the more condenses and consolidates the hotter they are, as iron quenched in water. The
				Stoics also affirm, that the spirit which is in the bodies of
				infants is quickened by refrigeration, and changing its
				Nature, turns to a soul. But this is a thing much to be
				disputed. Neither is it rational to believe that cold, which
				is the productive agent in many other things, can be a
				privation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Besides, no privation is capable of more and less. Neither can any man say, that one among those that cannot see is
				more blind than another, or that one among those that cannot speak is more silent than another, or that any thing is
				more dead than another among those things that never had
				life. But in cold things there is more and less, and excess
				and diminution to several degrees; in a word, there is both
				intensity and remission as well as in hot things; because
				the matter suffers in some things more violently, in others
				more languidly, and therefore some things are hotter, some
				things colder than others, according to the nature of the
				matter. For there is no mixture of habit with privation.
				Neither does any power admit of privation opposite to it,
				nor associate with it in the same subject, but it withstands
				it altogether. Hot things allow themselves to be mixed
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.311"/>
				
				with cold things to a certain degree, as black with white,
				heavy with light, and sour with sweet,&mdash;this community
				and harmony of colors, sounds, medicaments, and sauces
				generating several tastes and pleasures grateful to the
				senses. But the opposition of privation and habit is an
				antipathy never to be reconciled; the being of the one
				enforcing the destruction of the other. Which destruction, if it fall out seasonably, according to the opposition
				of contrary powers, the arts make great use of, but chiefly
				Nature, not only in her other creations, but especially in
				the alterations of the air, and in all other things of which
				the Deity being the adorner and dispenser obtains the
				attribute of harmonical and musical. Not that those attributes are given him for the disposal of deep and shrill,
				black and white, so as to make them agree together; but
				for his governing in the world the sympathies and antipathies of cold and heat in such a manner that they may
				unite and separate again, and for reducing both to a decent
				order, by taking that which we called <q direct="unspecified">the overmuch</q>
				from both.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Then again, we find that there is the same sense and
				feeling of cold as of heat; but privation is neither to be
				seen, heard, or felt, neither is it known to any of the other
				senses. For the object of sense is substance; but where
				no substance appears, there we understand privation to
				be,&mdash;which is a negation of substance, as blindness of
				sight, silence of voice, and vacuity of corporeal substance.
				For there is no sense or perception of vacuity by feeling;
				but where there is no body to be felt, there a vacuity is
				implied. Neither do we hear silence; but where we do
				not hear any thing at all, there we imply silence. In
				like manner we have no perception of blindness, nakedness, or being unarmed; but we know them from the
				negation of our sense. Therefore if cold were a privation
				of heat, there would be no being sensible of cold; but
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.312"/>
				
				only where heat ceased to be, there cold would be implied.
				But if, as heat is perceptible by the warmth and laxative
				softness of the flesh, so cold is no less perceptible by the
				contraction and condensation of it, it is from thence apparent, that there is some peculiar original and fountain of
				cold as well as heat.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Further then, privation of every kind is something
				single and simply particular; but in substances there are
				several differences and efficacies. For silence is a thing
				but of one sort; but of sounds there are great variety,
				sometimes molesting, sometimes delightful to the sense.
				There are also the same differences in colors and figures,
				which vary as they occur to the senses. But that which is
				not to be felt, which is without color and void of quality,
				can never be distinguished, but is always like itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Is cold therefore to be numbered among those privations that are not distinguished in their action? Rather
				the contrary, in regard that pleasures very great and beneficial to our bodies arise from cold things; as no less terrible mischiefs, pains, and stupefaction on the other side;
				which the heat does not always avoid and give way to, but
				many times enclosed within the body, withstands and opposes. Which contention of theirs is called quivering and
				shaking, at what time, if the cold overcome the heat,
				thence proceed numbness and stiffness of the limbs; but
				if the cold be vanquished by the heat, there follow a
				pleasing warmth and opening of the skin, which Homer
				expresses by the word <foreign lang="greek">i)ai/nesqai.</foreign> These things are past dispute; and chiefly by these passive qualities it is, that we
				find cold to be opposite to heat, as substance to substance, or
				passive quality to passive quality, not as negation or privation; neither is it the destruction or abolishing of hot, but
				a kind of nature and power tending to its destruction.
				Otherwise we should exempt the winter out of the seasons,
				and the north winds out of the number of the winds, as
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.313"/>
				
				being privations of the warmer seasons and the southern
				gales, and not having any proper original.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Now in regard there are four first bodies in the universe, which, by reason of their number, their being uncompounded, and their efficacy, are allowed for the most
				part to be the principles and beginnings of all other,&mdash;
				that is to say, fire and water, air and earth,&mdash;is there not
				the same necessity that there should be as many first and
				uncompounded qualities? And what are they but heat
				and cold, drought and moisture, by virtue of which it
				comes to pass that all the principles act and suffer? Thus,
				as there are in grammar lengthenings and shortenings of
				sounds, in music, deep and acute sounds, though not one
				of them is the privation of the other; we must leave the
				dry opposed to the moist principles, and the hot to the
				cold, if we intend to have the effects answerable to reason
				and what is visible in Nature. Unless, as it was the
				opinion of the ancient Anaximenes, we will not allow
				either cold or hot to be in substance, but only to be common passive qualities accompanying the alterations of the
				matter. For he affirms the contraction and condensation
				of the matter to be cold; but the rarefication and laxation
				of it (for by that word he calls it) to be hot. Whence it
				may not be improperly said, that a man breathes hot and
				cold at once. For the breath grows cold being compressed
				and thickened by the lips, but coming out of the open
				mouth it is hot, as being rarefied by that emission. But for
				this, Aristotle convinces the same person of ignorance;
				for that when we blow with the mouth open, we blow hot
				from our own bodies; but when we blow with compressed
				lips, we do not breathe forth the air from ourselves, but the
				air that is before our mouths, being cold, is thrust forward,
				and lights upon what is next it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But if we must grant that both heat and cold are substances, let us proceed a little farther in our discourse, and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.314"/>
				
				enquire what sort of substance is cold, and what is its first
				principle and nature.</p>
            <p>They then who affirm that there are certain irregular
					triangular figures in our body, and tell us also that shuddering, trembling, and quivering, and whatever else we
					suffer of the same nature, proceed from the roughness of
					those figures, if they mistake in the parts, nevertheless
					derive the beginning from whence they ought. For we
					ought to begin the question&mdash;as it were from Vesta&mdash;
					from the substance of all things. By which it chiefly appears wherein a philosopher differs from a physician, a
					husbandman, or a piper. For it is sufficient for these to
					contemplate the last causes. For if the consideration of
					the nearest causes of the affection go no farther than to
					find that the cause of a fever is intenseness of heat, or the
					lighting of some humor where it ought not to be, that the
					cause of blasting is the scorching heat of the sun after
					rain, and that the cause why pipes give a bass sound is
					the inclination of the pipes or the bringing them near one
					to another; this is enough for the artist to know in reference to his business. But when a philosopher for contemplation's sake scrutinizes into the truth, the knowledge
					of remote causes is not the end but the beginning of his
					proceeding in search of the first and ultimate causes.
					Wherefore Plato and Democritus, enquiring after the cause
					of heat and gravity, did not stop at the consideration of
					earth and fire, but bringing things perceptible to sense to
					beginnings intelligible only by the mind, they went on
					even to the smallest, as it were the seeds of what they
					sought for.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>But it is much the better way for us in the first place
				to move forward upon those things which are perceptible
				to sense, wherein Empedocles, Strato, and the Stoics
				placed the substances of active qualities; the Stoics
				ascribing primitive cold to the air, Empedocles and Strato
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.315"/>
				
				to the water; and perhaps there might be somebody else
				who might affirm the earth to be the substance of cold.
				But first let us consider the opinions of those already
				named.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that fire is both hot and bright, therefore
					there must be something opposite to fire which is cold and
					dark. For as dark is opposite to light, so is cold to hot.
					Besides, as dark confounds the sight, so cold confounds
					the feeling. But heat diffuses the sense of feeling, as
					light diffuses the sense of seeing. Therefore that which is
					first dark in nature is first cold. Now that the air is first
					dark, was not unknown to the poets; for that they call the
					air darkness:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The thickened air the fleet with darkness covered,
						</l>
                     <l>Nor could the moonlight be from heaven discovered.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IX. 144.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And again:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then darkness scattered and the fog dispelled,
						</l>
                     <l>The sun brake forth, and all the fight beheld.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVI. 649.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>They also call the air, when it is without light <foreign lang="greek">knefas,</foreign> as
					being as it were <foreign lang="greek">keno\n fa/ous</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">void of light.</hi>) The air collected
					and condensed into a cloud is called <foreign lang="greek">ne/fos,</foreign> from its negation
					of light (<foreign lang="greek">nh/-fa/os</foreign>). The words also <foreign lang="greek">a)xlu/s</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">o(mi/xlh</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">mist</hi>),
					and whatever else restrains the perception of light from the
					sense, are but distinctions of the air; insomuch that the
					same part of it which is invisible and without color (<foreign lang="greek">a)eide/s</foreign>
					and <foreign lang="greek">a)xrwston</foreign>) is called Hades and Acheron. So that, as
					the air grows dark when the splendor of it fails, in like
					manner when heat fails, that which is left is no more than
					cold air, which by reason of its coldness is called Tartarus.
					And this Hesiod makes manifest, when he calls it <foreign lang="greek">*ta/rtaron</foreign>
					          <foreign lang="greek">h)ero/enta</foreign> (or <hi rend="italics">cloudy Tartarus</hi>); and when a man quakes and
					shivers for cold, he is said to tartarize. And so much for
					this.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.316"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But in regard corruption is the alteration of those
				things that are corrupted into that which is contrary to
				every one of them, let us consider whether it be a true
				saying, <q direct="unspecified">The death of fire is the generation of air.</q> For
				fire dies like a living creature, being quenched by force or
				going out of its own accord. Now quenching makes the
				alteration of it into air more conspicuous. For smoke is
				a sort of air, or, according to Pindar, a fuliginous vapor
				and exhalation, <q direct="unspecified">lashing the air with steaming smoke.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pind. Isthm. IV. 112.</note>
				On the other side, when fire goes out for want of fuel, as
				in candles, you shall observe a thick and cloudy air ascending from the top of them. Moreover, the vapor steaming
				from our bodies upon the pouring of cold water after hot
				bathing or sweating sufficiently declares the alteration of
				extinguished heat into air, as being naturally opposite to
				air; whence it follows that the air was at first dark and
				cold.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Then again, congelation, which is the most forcible
				and violent of all things that befall our bodies by reason
				of cold, is the affection of water, but the action of air.
				For water of itself is easily diffused, loose in its parts, and
				not readily congealed together; but it is thickened and
				compressed by the air, by reason of the coldness of it.
				Which is the reason of the proverb:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if the southern wind provoke the north,
					</l>
                     <l>Snow straight will cover all the earth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the southern wind preparing the moisture as matter,
					presently the north wind receives and congeals it. And
					this is manifest from the consideration of snow; for ere
					it falls, you shall observe a thin and sharp cold air breathing before it. Aristotle also tells us, that whetstones of
					lead [?] will melt and run in the winter through excess of
					freezing cold, merely upon the setting of the water near
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.317"/>
					
					them. For it is probable that the air compresses and
					gripes the bodies so close together, that at length it breaks
					and crumbles them in pieces.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And therefore water drawn from a fountain soonest
				congeals; for the more of cold in the air overcomes the
				less of cold in the water. Thus if a man takes cold
				water out of a well and puts it into a vessel, and then lets
				the vessel down again into the well, so that it may not
				touch the water but hang for some time in the air, the
				water will be much colder. Whence it is apparent, that
				the coldness of the water is not the first cause of coldness,
				but the coldness of the air. For you do not find that any
				of your great rivers are ever thoroughly frozen, by reason
				of their depth. For the air doth not pierce through the
				whole; only so much as it can seize and embrace with its
				cold quality generally freezes, and no more. Therefore
				the barbarians never cross over frozen rivers till they have
				sent a fox before to try the depth of the ice. For if the
				ice be not very thick, but only superficial, the fox, perceiving it by the noise of the water floating underneath, returns. And some there are that melt the ice with hot
				water to make way for their lines, when they go to catch
				fish in winter. So that nothing suffers from cold in the
				depth of the water. Nevertheless, so great has been the
				alteration of the upper parts of the water by congelation,
				that several vessels riding in the stream have been bruised
				and broken by the forcible compressure and griping of
				the congelation; as we have heard from them who lately
				had their winter quarters with Caesar upon the Danube.
				And indeed, what happens to ourselves is sufficient to demonstrate the truth of this. For after hot bathings and
				sweatings, we are most sensible of cold, at what time, our
				bodies being open and the skin relaxed, we give a freer
				entrance to the cold together with the ambient air. And
				after the very same manner the water itself suffers. For
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.318"/>
				
				it sooner freezes if it be first heated, as being thereby rendered more easy for the air to work upon. And therefore
				they who lade out scalding water, and let it fall again from
				a good height in the air, do it to no other purpose than to
				mix it with a great deal of air. And therefore, Favorinus,
				the arguments that attribute the first power of cold to the
				air are grounded upon these probabilities.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Those that allow it to water lean upon principles
				of the same nature. And this was intimated by Empedocles, where he says:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Behold the sun, how warm he is,
					</l>
                     <l>And shining everywhere;
					</l>
                     <l>But rain and tempests cold and dark
					</l>
                     <l>With horror fill the air.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And thus opposing cold to heat, and dark to bright, he
					gives us to understand that black and cold are both of the
					same substance, as also are bright and hot. Now that
					black is proper to the water and not to the air, sense itself
					bears witness, nothing being darkened by the air, all things
					being clouded and blackened by water. So that if you
					throw the whitest wool that is, or a white garment into the
					water, it comes out black, and so remains, till the moisture
					be dried up again by the heat, or squeezed forth by presses
					or weights. Also when the ground is watered, the places
					that receive the drops grow black, the rest retaining their
					former color. And therefore the deepest waters, by reason of their quantity, always appear blackest, but the parts
					which are next the air afford a lovely and smiling brightness. But of all liquids, oil is the most transparent, because of the great quantity of air that is in it. And of
					this, the lightness of it is an unquestionable proof; the
					reason why it swims above all things, as carried upward
					by the air. Being poured forth upon the waves, it will
					cause calmness upon the sea, not because it is so slippery
					that the winds can have no power over it, as Aristotle
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.319"/>
					
					thought, but because the waves will fall and sink when
					smitten by any moist body. And this is also peculiar to
					oil, that it shines and causes a transparency at the bottom of the water, while the watery humors are dispersed
					by the air. For being spurted out of the mouth into the
					sea, not only by those that sail in the night, but also by
					those that dive for sponges to the bottom of the sea, it
					will cast a light in the water. Water therefore has more
					of blackness than the air, but less of cold. Oil therefore,
					partaking more of air than most liquid things, is least
					cold, nor will it easily or suddenly freeze; for the air
					which is mixed with it will not suffer the congelation to
					grow hard. And therefore, as for needles, steel buckles,
					and such sort of small iron and steel wares, they never
					quench them in water but in oil, fearing lest the over-coldness of the water should make them too brittle. And
					indeed the truth is more truly enquired into from the consideration of these experiments, than those of colors.
					For hail, snow, and ice, as they are most transparent, so
					are most cold; and pitch, as it is hotter, so it is blacker
					and darker than honey.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>This makes me admire at those who affirm the air
				to be cold because it is dark and obscure, unless it be because they find others affirming it to be hot because it is
				light. For dark is not so proper and familiar to cold, as
				heavy and stable; for many things that are void of heat
				partake of splendor and light, but there is nothing cold
				that is light, nimble, or apt to ascend upward. Even the
				clouds themselves, while they preserve the nature of air,
				tower aloft in the sky; but changing into moisture, they
				presently fall down, and having admitted coldness, they
				lose their lightness as well as their heat. And so on the
				other side, having regained their heat, they again return
				to motion, their substance being carried upward as soon as
				it is changed into air.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.320"/>
            <p>Neither is the argument produced from corruption true.
					For nothing that perishes is corrupted <hi rend="italics">into</hi> what is opposite, but <hi rend="italics">by</hi> what is opposite to it; as fire extinguished by
					water changes into air. And therefore Aeschylus spake
					not merely like a tragedian but like a philosopher, when
					he said,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The water curb, that punishment of fire.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner Homer opposed in battle Vulcan to the
					river, and Apollo to Neptune, more like a philosopher
					than a poet or mythologist. And Archilochus spoke not
					amiss of a woman whose thoughts were contrary to her
					words, when he said,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>She, weaving subtle trains and sly vagaries,
						</l>
                     <l>Fire in one hand, in th' other water carries.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Among the Persians there were several customs of supplication, of which the chiefest, and that which would admit
					of no refusal, was when the suppliant, taking fire in his
					hand and entering into a river, threatened, if his supplications were denied, to throw the fire into the water. But
					though his suit were granted him, yet he was punished for
					threatening, as being against the law and contrary to Nature. And this is a vulgar proverb in everybody's mouth,
					to mix fire with water, spoken of those that would attempt
					impossibilities; to show that water is an enemy to fire,
					and being extinguished thereby, is destroyed and punished
					by it,&mdash;not by the air, which, upon the change and destruction of it, receives and entertains the substance of it.
					For if that into which the thing destroyed is changed be
					contrary to it, why does fire seem contrary to air more than
					water? For air changes into water by condensation, but
					into fire by dissipation; as, on the other side, water is
					turned into air by separation, into earth by condensation.
					Which, in my opinion, happens by reason of the propriety and near affinity between both, not from any thing of
					contrariety and hostility one to another. Others there are,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.321"/>
					
					that, which way soever they maintain it, spoil the argument. For it is most irrational to say that water is congealed by the air, when they never saw the air congealed
					in their lives. For clouds, fogs, and mists are no congelations, but thickenings and condensations of the air moist
					and full of vapors; but a dry air void of moisture never
					undergoes refrigeration to such a degree. For there are
					some mountains that never admit of a cloud, nor dew, nor
					mist, their tops being so high as to reach into an air that
					is pure and void of moisture. Whence it is manifest that
					it is the condensation and consistency below, which contributes that cold and moisture to the air which is mixed
					with it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Now that great rivers never freeze downwards is
				but consentaneous to reason. For those parts which are
				frozen above transmit no exhalation outward; for this,
				being penned up within and forced downward, affords
				heat to the moisture at the bottom. A clear demonstration of which is this, that when the ice is dissolved, you
				may observe a steam arising out of the water upwards in
				a very great quantity. And therefore the bodies of living
				creatures are warmest within in the winter, for that the
				heat is driven inward by the ambient cold. Now those
				upward exhalations and ascensions of the vapors deprive
				the waters not only of their heat but of their coolness.
				And therefore they that vehemently desire their drink to
				be cold never move the snow nor the moisture that is
				pressed out of it; for motion would deprive them both of
				the virtue which is required from them.</p>
            <p>Now that this virtue is not the virtue of air, but of water,
					a man may collect by reasoning thus from the beginning.
					First, it is not probable that the air, which is next the sky,
					and touching the fiery substance is also touched by it,
					should be endued with a contrary virtue; for otherwise it
					is not possible that the extremities of the one should touch
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.322"/>
					
					and be contiguous to the extremities of the other. Nor is
					it agreeable to reason that Nature should constitute that
					which is corrupted next in order to that which corrupts, as
					if she were not the author of community and harmony but
					of combat and contention. For she makes use of contrary things in sustaining the universe; but she does not
					use them pure and unmixed, nor so that they will be in
					hostility; but she uses such as have alternately a certain
					position and order which is not destructive, but which inclines them to communicate and co-operate one with another, and to effect a harmony between the opposing
					qualities. And this is the nature of the air, being expanded under the fire above the water, contingent and
					adhering to both, neither hot in itself nor cold, but containing an intermixture and communion of hot and cold,
					harmlessly intermixed in herself; and lightly cherishing
					the contrary extremities.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Therefore the air is of an equal temper in all
				places, but winter is not in all places alike nor equally
				cold; but some parts of the habitable world are cold and
				moist, others hot and dry, not by chance, but because there
				is but one substance of heat and dryness. For the greatest part of Africa is hot and without water. But they
				that have travelled Scythia, Thrace, and the Pontic regions
				report them to be full of vast lakes, and large and deep
				rivers. And as for those regions lying between, those
				parts that join upon lakes and marshes are most cold by
				reason of the exhalations from the water. Posidouius
				therefore, affirming the freshness and moistness of the air
				of marshes to be the cause of its cold, has no way disturbed the probability of our argument, but rather added
				to the strength of it; for the air would not always be
				the colder the fresher it is, unless cold has its original
				from moisture. And therefore Homer much more truly
				shows us the fountain of cold, when he says,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.323"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Chill from the river blows the wind
					</l>
                     <l>Before the coming morn.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. V. 469.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Then again it many times happens that our sense deceives
					us. So that when we feel cold garments or cold wool, we
					believe we feel them to be moist, by reason of the substance which is common to both, and of their natures
					which are coherent and familiar one with another. But
					in climates where the cold is extreme, it oftentimes breaks
					and cracks both pots and vessels, whether made of earth
					or brass,&mdash;none empty, but all full, the cold giving force
					and might to the liquor within,&mdash;which made Theophrastus say, that the air breaks those vessels, making use of
					the cold as of a hammer; whether more eloquently or
					more truly spoken, I leave you to judge. For then vessels full of pitch or milk should be more subject to be
					broken by the air.</p>
            <p>But water seems to be cold of itself, and that primitively
					too; for in respect of the coldness of it, it is opposite to
					the heat of the fire; as to drought in respect of its moisture, and to ponderosity in regard of its lightness. Lastly,
					fire is altogether of a dissipating and dividing nature;
					water, of a nature to fasten and contain, holding and joining together by virtue of its moisture. Which was the
					reason why Empedocles called fire <q direct="unspecified">a pernicious contention,</q> but water a <q direct="unspecified">tenacious friendship.</q> For the nourishment of fire is that which changes into fire, and it
					changes that which is as it were of kin and familiar to it.
					What is contrary to it, as water, cannot be changed by it,
					or at least only with great difficulty. True it is, that as
					for itself, as I may so say, it cannot be burned; but as for
					green wood and wet straw, it overcomes them with much
					struggling, while the heat and cold contending together,
					by reason of their moisture and their natural antipathy,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.324"/>
					
					produce only a dull flame, clouded with smoke, that makes
					little progress upon the materials.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Compare these arguments with theirs, and consider
				them well. But Chrysippus, believing the air to be the
				primitive cold, because it is dark, makes mention only of
				those that say the water lies at farther distance from the
				sky than the air. And being desirous to give some answer
				to them, <q direct="unspecified">If so,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">we may as well affirm the
					earth to be primitively cold, because it is the farthest distant from the sky;</q> rejecting that, as altogether improbable and absurd. But for my part, I am of opinion that
				there might be many probable and rational arguments
				brought for the earth; beginning with that which Chrysippus chiefly makes use of for the air. What is this? First,
				that it is dark. For if he, assuming these two contrarieties of faculties, believes that the one follows the other of
				necessity, then there might be produced a thousand oppositions and repugnances of the earth in respect of the sky,
				which would of necessity follow upon this which we have
				mentioned. For it is not to be opposed only as heavy to
				light, or as that which tends downward to that which
				moves upward, or as slow and stable to swift and full
				of motion; but as that which is heaviest to that which
				is most thin, or lastly, as that which is immovable of itself
				to that which moves spontaneously, and as possessing the
				middle space to that which is in a perpetual circular motion. Would it not be absurd to aver that the opposition
				of heat to cold is accompanied with so many and such
				remarkable contrarieties? But fire is bright, the earth is
				dark, nay, the very darkest and most void of light of
				all things. The air first of all participates of light, is
				soonest altered, and being replenished with radiancy, diffuses the splendor of it far and near, and shows itself
				a vast body of light. For the sun rising, as one of the
				dithyrambic authors writes,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.325"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Presently doth fill
					</l>
                     <l>The spacious house of the air-prancing winds.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>From thence the descending air disposes a part of her
					brightness to the sea and lakes, and the hidden depths of
					profound rivers laugh and smile so far as the air penetrates
					into them. Only the earth of all bodies remains without
					light, and impenetrable to the beams of the sun and moon.
					But it is cherished and comforted by them, and suffers a
					small part of it to be warmed and softened by entrance of
					the heat. But the solidness of it will not admit the brightness of light, only the surface of it is enlightened; but the
					innermost parts of it are called by the names of Darkness,
					Chaos, and Hades; and Erebus is nothing else but that
					same perpetual darkness and horror in the body of the
					earth. Besides, the mythologists tell us that Night was the
					daughter of the Earth; and the mathematicians show that
					it is the shadow of the earth eclipsing the body of the sun.
					For the air is filled with darkness by the earth, as with
					light by the sun; and that part of the air which is void
					of all light is that same length of the night which is
					caused by the shadow of the earth. And therefore both
					men and many beasts make use of the exterior air, and
					ramble in the dark, guided only by some footsteps of light
					and certain effluxes of a dim twinkling that are scattered
					through it; but he that keeps house and shuts himself up
					in his chamber, as being encompassed by the earth, remains altogether blind and without light. Also the hides
					and horns of beasts will not admit of light by reason of
					their solidness; but being burnished and shaved, they become transparent, the air being intermixed with them.
					Moreover, I am of opinion that the earth is everywhere
					by the poets said to be black, by reason of the darkness
					of it and want of light. So that the antithesis of light
					and darkness is much more remarkable in reference to the
					earth, than in respect of the air.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.326"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>But this is nothing to the question. For we have
				shown that there are many cold things which are bright
				and transparent, and many hot things which are obscure
				and dark. But ponderosity, stability, density, and immutability are qualities more properly belonging to cold, of
				none of which the air partakes, but of all of which the
				earth has a far greater share than the water. And yet in
				all these things cold, by the judgment of sense itself,
				appears to be hard, to cause hardness, and to make resistance. For Theophrastus tells us of fish that have been
				frozen by extremity of cold, when they have chanced to
				bounce ashore, that their bodies have been broken and
				crumbled to pieces like a vessel of glass or potter's clay.
				You yourself have heard at Delphi, how that certain persons ascending to the top of Parnassus to succor the Thyades that were overtaken with a violent storm of wind and
				hail, their coats were frozen so hard and into a substance
				so like wood, that being spread upon the ground they
				broke and crumbled to pieces. It also stiffens the nerves
				and deprives the tongue of motion, congealing the moist
				and softer parts of the body.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>This being obvious to sight, let us consider the
				effect. Every faculty, wherever it prevails, changes into
				itself whatever it overcomes. Thus whatever is overcome
				by heat is set on fire; that which is vanquished by wind is
				changed into air. That which falls into water becomes
				well moistened, unless quickly saved. Of necessity, therefore, those things which are violently affected by cold must
				be changed into the primitive cold. For freezing is an
				excess of refrigeration; which congelation ends in alteration and petrifaction, when the cold, prevailing every way,
				congeals the liquid substance and presses forth the heat;
				so that the bottom of the earth is, as it were, a kind of
				congelation, and altogether ice. For there the cold inhabits simple and unmixed, and removed hard and rigid at
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.327"/>
				
				the greatest distance from the sky. But as for those
				things which are conspicuous, as rocks and precipices,
				Empedocles believes them to be thrust forth and supported
				by the fire that burns in the bottom of the earth. Which
				appears the more, in regard that, wherever the heat is
				pressed forth and vanishes away, all those things are congealed or stiffened by the cold; and therefore congelations
				are called <foreign lang="greek">pa/goi</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">stiffened</hi>). And the extremities of many
				things where heat fails, growing black, make them look
				like brands when the fire is out. For cold congeals some
				things more, some things less; more especially such things
				wherein it is primitively existent. For as, if it be the
				nature of hot to render light, that which is hottest is lightest; if of moist to soften, that which is moistest is softest;
				so if it be the nature of cold to congeal, of necessity that
				which is coldest must be most congealed,&mdash;that is to say
				the earth,&mdash;and that which is most cold must be that
				which is by nature and primitively cold, which is no more
				than what is apparent to sense. For mud is colder than
				water, and earth being thrown upon fire puts it out. Your
				smiths also, when their iron is melted and red hot, strew
				upon it the dust of marble to cool it and stop the running
				of it too fluidly. Dust also cools the bodies of the wrestlers, and dries up their sweat.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>To go no farther, what means our own yearly practice to alter our lodgings and habitations, while we remove
				in the winter so far as we can into the upper parts of our
				buildings, but in the summer descend again and seek convenient refuge in the lower edifices, sometimes enjoying
				ourselves under ground in the very arms of the earth?
				Do we not do it, as being guided by our senses for coolness's sake to the earth, and thereby acknowledging that
				to be the seat of primitive cold? And certainly our coveting to live near the sea in winter may be thought to be a
				kind of flight from the earth, since we seem to forsake it,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.328"/>
				
				as far as we can, by reason of the nipping frosts, and run
				to encircle themselves with the air of the sea for warmth's
				sake; and then again in the summer, by reason of the
				scorching heat, we desire the earth-born upland air, not
				because it is cold of itself, but because it had its original
				and blossomed from the primitive natural cold, and is imbued with that power which is in the earth, as iron is
				imbued with the virtue of the water wherein it is quenched.
				Then again, of river waters we find those are the coldest
				that flow upon gravel and stones and fall down from mountains; and of well-waters, those which are in the deepest
				wells. For with these the exterior air is no longer mixed,
				by reason of the depth of the wells, and the other arise
				out of the pure and unmixed earth; like the river that
				falls from the mountain Taenarum, which they call the
				water of Styx, rising out of a rock with a parsimonious
				spring, but so cold that no other vessel except the hoof of
				an ass will hold it; for all other sorts of vessels it breaks
				and cracks to pieces.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>The physicians also tell us that the nature of all
				sorts of earth is binding and restrictive; and they number
				up several sorts of metals which are made use of in physic by reason of their styptic and binding qualities. For
				the element of earth is fit neither to cut nor to move,
				neither has it any points, neither is it subject to be softened or melted, but is firm and stable like a cube; and
				therefore it has both ponderosity and coldness, and the
				faculty to thicken and condense moist things; and it causes
				tremblings and quiverings in bodies by reason of its inequality; and if it get the better by the utter expulsion and
				extinguishing of the heat, it occasions a frozen and deadly
				habit of body. Therefore earth either does not consume
				by burning, or else burns with a very slow and difficult
				progress. But the air many times darts forth flame from
				itself; and being once set on fire, it grows fluid and flashes
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.329"/>
				
				out in lightning. Heat also feeds upon moisture; for it is
				not the solid part of the wood, but the moist and oily part,
				that is combustible; which being consumed, the solid and
				dry is left behind in the ashes. Neither do they arrive at
				their mark, who, pretending to burn the ashes also, sprinkle
				them with oil and grease; for when the liquid is consumed,
				the earthy part remains, do what they can. Therefore,
				because the earth is not only of a nature not to be moved
				from its station, but also unalterable in its substance and
				always abiding in the habitation of the Gods, the ancients
				well called it Hestia or Vesta (from <hi rend="italics">standing</hi>), by reason
				of its immobility and concretion; of which cold is the
				bond or ligament, as Archelaus the philosopher termed it,
				which nothing is able to unloosen or soften, as not being
				capable of heat and warmth.</p>
            <p>As for those who say they have been sensible of the
					cold of air and water, but never felt the earth so cold, they
					consider only the surface of the earth, which is a mixture
					of air, water, sun, and heat. They are no better than
					people who deny the aether to be naturally and primitively hot, but believe it to be either scalding water or red
					hot iron, because they feel and handle the one, but are not
					sensible of the pure and celestial fire. In like manner,
					neither do they see the earth which lies concealed at the
					bottom, though that be what is chiefly to be taken for the
					earth, separated from all other things. We may see some
					token of this lower earth in these rocks here about us,
					which from their depths send forth a cold vapor so sharp
					and vehement that it is hard to be endured. They also
					that desire cool drink throw small flint stones into water.
					For it becomes denser and quicker to the taste, through
					the cold which is carried upward fresh and unmixed from
					the stones.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Therefore it was the opinion of the ancient philosophers and learned men, that terrestrial and celestial things
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.330"/>
				
				were not to be mixed together, not so much out of a local
				consideration of uppermost and lowermost, in respect of
				place, but with a respect to the difference of faculties,
				attributing hot and splendent, swift and light to the immortal and sempiternal Nature, but believing dark and cold
				and slow to be the unhappy portion of the dead under the
				shackles of corruption. Since the body of a living creature, while it breathes and flourishes (as the poets say),
				enjoys both heat and life; but being deprived of these,
				and only the terrestrial parts remaining, presently cold and
				stiffness take place, as if heat were naturally existent in
				every thing else but only the earth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>These things, dear Favorinus, compare with what
				has been said by others; and if they neither come too
				short of probability nor too much exceed it, bid all their
				opinions farewell, as believing it much more becoming a
				philosopher to pause in dubious matters, rather than over
				hastily to side with any one particular party.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>