<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De sollertia animalium</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1957</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.12.p.311"/>
            <head>WHETHER LAND OR SEA ANIMALS ARE CLEVERER (DE SOLLERTIA ANIMALIUM) <lb/> INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					There can be little doubt that Plutarch composed
					this pleasant work from <hi rend="italics">commentarii</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">u(pomnh/mata</foreign>)
					derived not merely from Aristotle (mentioned specifically in 965 d and quoted often), but also from various
					other compendia, the remains of which are to be
					seen in Aelian's and Pliny's natural histories and
					elsewhere.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the sources see Ziegler's article <q direct="unspecified">Plutarchos</q> in Pauly-Wissowa, col. 738, and, of the authorities he cites, particularly Wellmann's papers in <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxvi, xxvii, and li, and Max Schuster, <hi rend="italics">Untersuchungen zu Plutarchs De Sollertia Animalium</hi> (Diss. Munich, 1917). There is also an amusing work of Philo, surviving only in an Armenian version, which is most conveniently accessible in Aucher's Latin translation in vol. 8 of the <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca Sacra</hi> edition (Schwickert, Leipzig, 1830): <hi rend="italics">De Ratione quam habere etiam Bruta Animalia dicebat Alexander</hi>. In the first part of this work Alexander presents the arguments for animal intelligence, which Philo himself attempts to refute in a somewhat summary fashion at the end. The occasional parallels with Plutarch will be cited as Philo, with Aucher's section and page numbers. Antigonus of Carystus, <hi rend="italics">Historia Mirabilium</hi>, will be cited from O. Keller's edition of the <hi rend="italics">Naturalium Rerum Scriptores Graeci</hi> (Teubner, 1877) and Aelian's <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi> from R. Hercher's Teubner (not Didot) edition.</note> In fact, if one reads Plutarch and Aelian
					and Pliny side by side, one may acquire the impression that they had before them substantially the
					same sources, and that these were numerous. Whereas
						
					<pb id="v.12.p.312"/>
					
					Pliny and Aelian appear to adopt nearly everything their authorities may have offered (for they
					were writing factual commentaries), Plutarch, as
					always, selects. It is possible, in some cases, that
					Plutarch's mss. (which are not good and also contain
					lacunae) may have been interpolated from Aelian's ;
					and the reverse is likewise possible. This is a very
					difficult matter, but the hope may be entertained
					that some main sources of Plutarch and Aelian, if not
					of Pliny, and the as yet unassessed evidence of Philo,
					may eventually be disentangled for substantial sections, though this is not the place to attempt such a
					feat.
				</p>
            <p>
					The title is not well chosen, since the victory is
					awarded to neither side. The real point of the dialogue seems to be, in its second as well as its first
					part, that all animals of whatever provenance are
					intelligent.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Schuster thinks, rather, that Plutarch's chief aim is to make clear a moral and juridical relationship between man and beasts.</note> The occasionally bantering tone may
					serve to indicate that we have before us something
					of a school exercise from Plutarch's own academy,
					with perhaps the first draft of the second part composed by pupils.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Schuster, pp. 57 ff. Aristotimus and Phaedimus were doubtless actual pupils of Plutarch.</note> Note the carefully established
					details : the contest will take place at a fixed time
					(960 b, 963 b) before their fellow-pupils and a specially
					appointed judge (965 c-e). More or less elaborate
					preparation has been made by the contestants (960 b,
					975 d).<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch lays special emphasis on preparation: <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 80 d, 652 b.</note> Because of the occasion the school has been
					granted a holiday.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.313"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					In the first part (chapters 1-8), the author demonstrates through the authoritarian voice of his own
					father that the Stoics, in so far as they affirm the
					irrationality of animals, contradict their own tenets.
					The second part proves that animals of all kinds are
					rational (chapters 9-36) ; the last small section, while
					refusing to award first honours in the debate, appears
					to contain Plutarch's exhortation to his pupils to
					continue the fight against the Stoics. For an excellent summary with sympathetic comments see E. R.
					Dodds, <hi rend="italics">Greece and Rome</hi>, ii (1932/3), pp. 104-105.
				</p>
            <p>
					D' Agostino<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">V. D' Agostino, <hi rend="italics">Archivo Italiano di Psicologia</hi>, xi (1933), pp. 21 ff., a useful summarizing article.</note> and others have shown that there is
					little originality in Plutarch's animal psychology, while
					not denying our author considerable vivacity in
					presentation. While it is true that whole sections, like
					976 a-d, are drawn from the identical source that
					Aelian (<hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, viii. 4-6) used, yet one
					has only to compare the use these authors have made
					of precisely the same material to recognize the great
					superiority of Plutarch. The principal sources have
					been disputed<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hirzel, <hi rend="italics">Der Dialog</hi>, ii, p. 179, n. 1. All of Hirzel's discussion is worth reading, though there are occasional slips, as when he affirms (p. 173, n. 2) that the story in 969 e f. goes back to Plutarch's own experience. This is quite unlikely in view of Aelian's version of the same story; nor has Aelian drawn from Plutarch as some, including Wyttenbach, have thought.</note>: Chrysippus, Theophrastus, Hagnon, Alexander of Myndus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the difficulty and danger involved in identifying the sources exactly see the lists of authorities furnished by Pliny in his first book. Alexander of Myndus, for example, does not appear at all as a source for books 8-11.</note> Juba, Xenocrates have
					all been suggested, but there can be little doubt (as
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.314"/>
					
					with <hi rend="italics">De Tranquillitate</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the introduction in the Loeb edition.</note> and many other works) that
					a considerable variety of sources has been utilized.
					Now that Schl&auml;pfer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Plutarch und die klassischen Dichter</hi>, Z&uuml;rich, 1950, especially pp. 59-60.</note> has demonstrated that Plutarch
					had himself read and meditated upon great sections
					of classical poetry, critics may perhaps be more
					willing to allow our author first-hand familiarity with
					a wider range of prose, and works of reference as
					well.
				</p>
            <p>
					It is by no means impossible that the work is incomplete in our mss. ; there are, at least, several
					demonstrable lacunae and it is possible that it was
					considerably longer and may even have justified its
					title when it left Plutarch's hands.
				</p>
            <p>
					As for the date of the dialogue, the <hi rend="italics">terminus post
					quem</hi> is a.d. 70 (not 79, as it cannot be certainly
					inferred from 974 a that Vespasian was then dead) ;
					it is probably a work of Plutarch's youth, preceding
					in any case the <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">Symposiacs</hi>. It may
					well date from Plutarch's anti-Stoic period which
					produced the <hi rend="italics">De Facie</hi>, the <hi rend="italics">De Communibus Notitiis</hi>,
					and the other anti-Chrysippean polemics. It has
					much in common with the <hi rend="italics">Gryllus</hi> and the fragments
					of <hi rend="italics">De Esu Carnium</hi> and some correspondence with
					the <hi rend="italics">Amatorius</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But allowance must be made for exaggerated and partially false premises in Hartman, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, p. 567. A modified chronological scheme of Plutarch's writings has lately been proposed by T. Sinko (<hi rend="italics">Polish Acad. Cracow</hi>, 1947), but it is too complicated to be examined here.</note> It may, in fact, have been written
					during nearly the same period as that in which the
					elder Pliny (whose preface is dated a.d. 77) was
					compiling his own <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.315"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The citations in D'Arcy Thompson's Oxford translation of Aristotle's <hi rend="italics">Historia Animalium</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Loeb edition of A. L. Peck is still awaited at this date of writing. It should be noted that quotations from the ninth book, in particular, are liable to peculiar suspicion and may not proceed from the great naturalist himself.</note> are somewhat
					inaccurate and inconsistent, being, as he says, <q direct="unspecified">compiled at various times and at long intervals during
						many years.</q> Nevertheless the work is of great
					value and it may be hoped that the notes in this
					edition that rely on it (and these are many) have
					been adequately sifted. Also to be constantly and
					gratefully consulted are Thompson's <hi rend="italics">A Glossary of
					Greek Fishes</hi> (Oxford, 1947) and <hi rend="italics">A Glossary of Greek
					Birds</hi> (2nd edition, Oxford, 1936). There will be
					many references to Thompson's Aristotle ; but if the
					creature in question is a bird or a fish, it is to be
					understood that supplementary and often corrective
					material is to be found in the Glossaries. There is,
					further, a tribute of admiration due to A. W. Mair's
					L.C.L. edition of Oppian, with its exhaustive notes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Even the extremely hostile review in <hi rend="italics">Phil. Woch.</hi> li (1931), pp. 1569 ff., exempts the notes from censure.</note>
					Rackham (L.C.L. Pliny, vol. Ill, books viii-xi) is very
					interesting on the text, but has almost completely
					denied himself the privilege of citing parallel passages.
				</p>
            <p>
					The debunking of many of Plutarch's stories, if
					such a task is necessary, has been pleasantly done
					in the leisurely course of Bergen Evans' <hi rend="italics">The Natural
					History of Nonsense</hi> (New York, 1946). It should be
					added, however, that modern scientific speculation
					is approaching somewhat closer to one of Plutarch's
					main tenets, if one may judge from such a work as
					W. C. Allee's <hi rend="italics">Co&ouml;peration Among Animals</hi> (New York,
					1951 : a revision of his earlier <hi rend="italics">The Social Life of</hi>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.316"/>
					
					          <hi rend="italics">Animals</hi>) ; and on the thesis of animal intelligence
					see Evans himself, p. 173, and the authorities cited
					there, note 1.
				</p>
            <p>
					Both the translation and the notes of this and the
					following essays have benefited immeasurably from
					an exhaustive criticism generously given them by
					Professor Alfred C. Andrews of the University of
					Miami, Florida. He has in fact supplied a number of
					valuable notes and also the Appendix, a classified
					zoological index. It must be understood, however,
					that any errors remaining are to be attributed solely
					to the editor.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Since our text was formed and our translation and notes composed a year or more before the appearance of the new Teubner edition, almost no new references have been added which are not purely textual. The curious reader is referred to Hubert's wealth of illustration to supplement our contributions.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The dialogue is no. 147 in the catalogue of Lamprias. According to this document Plutarch wrote
					another work (no. 135) on the same subject: <hi rend="italics">Do
					Beasts Possess Reason</hi>? But no. 127, <foreign lang="greek">*peri\ zw/|wn
					a)lo/gwn poihtiko/s</foreign>, is probably the same as our
					<hi rend="italics">Gryllus</hi>, the following dialogue in this edition.
				</p>
            <p>
					Abbreviations used in citing Modern Authors
				</p>
            <p>
					Brands = J. P. J. M. Brands, <hi rend="italics">Grieksche Diernamen</hi>,
					Purmerend, 1935.
				</p>
            <p>
					Cotte = J. Cotte, <hi rend="italics">Poissons et animaux aquatiques au
					temps de Pline</hi>, Paris, 1945.
				</p>
            <p>
					Keller = Otto Keller, <hi rend="italics">Die antike Tierwelt</hi>, Leipzig,
					1909-1913.
				</p>
            <p>
					Mair = A. W. Mair, <hi rend="italics">Oppian, Colluthus, Tryphiodorus</hi>,
					L.C.L., 1928.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.317"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Saint-Denis = E. de Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">Le Vocabulaire des
					animaux marius en latin classique</hi>, Paris, 1947.
				</p>
            <p>
					Schmid = Georg Schmid, <q direct="unspecified">Die Fische in Ovids
						Halieuticon,</q> 
               <hi rend="italics">Philologus</hi>, Supplementband xi
					(1907-1910), pp. 253-350.
				</p>
            <p>
					Thompson, Aristotle = D'Arcy W. Thompson, The
					Works of Aristotle, vol. IV, <hi rend="italics">Historia animalium</hi>,
					Oxford, 1910.
				</p>
            <p>
					Thompson, Birds = D'Arcy W. Thompson, <hi rend="italics">A Glossary
					of Greek Birds</hi>, rev. ed., Oxford, 1936.
				</p>
            <p>
					Thompson, Fishes = D'Arcy W. Thompson, <hi rend="italics">A Glossary
					of Greek Fishes</hi>, Oxford, 1947.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.319"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
					(The speakers in the dialogue are Autobulus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch's father; on controversial points connected with this identification see Ziegler in Pauly-Wissowa, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">Plutarchos,</q> 642 ff.</note> Soclarus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A friend of the household who appears in several of the <hi rend="italics">Symposiacs</hi> and in the <hi rend="italics">Amatorius</hi> also; he is not improbably the L. Mestrius Soclarus of <hi rend="italics">Inscr. Gr.</hi> ix. 1. 61.</note>
					Optatus, Aristotimus, Phaedimus, and Heracleon.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A speaker also in <hi rend="italics">De Defectu Oraculorum</hi> (<hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 412 e). Of the other speakers in this dialogue, nothing definite is known except what may be inferred from the present work.</note>)
				</p>
            <p>Autobulus. When Leonidas was asked what sort
					of a person he considered Tyrtaeus to be, he replied,
					<q direct="unspecified">A good poet to whet the souls of young men,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 235 f, where it is an anonymous saying; but the <hi rend="italics">Life of Cleomenes</hi>, ii (xxiii = 805 d) also attributes it to Leonidas.</note> on
					the ground that by means of verses the poet inspired
					in young men keenness, accompanied by ardour and
					ambition whereby they sacrificed themselves freely
					in battle. And I am very much afraid, my friends,
					that the <hi rend="italics">Praise of Hunting</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The authorship of this work has been endlessly disputed, but present opinion (<hi rend="italics">pace</hi> Sinko, <hi rend="italics">Eos</hi>, xv. pp. 113 ff. and Hubert, <hi rend="italics">Woch. f. klass. Phil.</hi> xxviii, pp. 371 ff.) holds that it is Plutarch himself who wrote it (Schuster, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 8 ff.). Bernardakis (vii, pp. 142-143) included this passage (959 b-d) as a fragment of the lost work.</note> which was read aloud to
					us yesterday may so immoderately inflame our young
					men who like the sport that they will come to consider all other occupations as of minor, or of no,
					importance and concentrate on this.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">There canot be two passions more nearly resembling each other than hunting and philosophy</q> (Huxley, <hi rend="italics">Hume</hi>, p. 139), and see Shorey's note on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 432 b (L.C.L.); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>, however, <hi rend="italics">Rep.</hi> 535 d, 549 a. See also Isocrates, <hi rend="italics">Areopagiticus</hi>, 43 f.; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cynegetica</hi>, i. 18; xii. 1. ff.; <hi rend="italics">Cyr.</hi> viii. 1. 34-36; Pollux, preface to book v; the proems of Grattius, Nemesianus, Arrian, etc.</note> As a matter
					of fact, I myself caught the old fever all over again
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.321"/>
					
					in spite of my years and longed, like Euripides'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Hippolytus</hi>, 218 f. It follows from the fuller quotation in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 52 c that Plutarch's text of Euripides inverted the order of these lines as given in our mss. of the tragedian.</note>
					Phaedra,
					<quote rend="blockquote">To halloo the hounds and chase the dappled deer;</quote>
					so moved was I by the discourse as it brought its
					solid and convincing arguments to bear.
				</p>
            <p>
					Soclarus. Exactly so, Autobulus. That reader
					yesterday seems to have roused his rhetoric from its
					long disuse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably an autobiographical detail.</note> to gratify the young men and share
					their vernal mood.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The word is found only here, but may well be right if Plutarch is in a poetical, as well as a playful, humour.</note> I was particularly pleased with his
					introduction of gladiators and his argument that it is
					as good a reason as any to applaud hunting that after
					diverting to itself most of our natural or acquired
					pleasure in armed combats between human beings
					it affords an innocent spectacle of skill and intelligent
					courage pitted against witless force and violence. It
					agrees with that passage of Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 27 from the <hi rend="italics">Aeolus</hi> (so Stobaeus); Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> pp. 370 f.; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 98 e. The text is somewhat confused.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Slight is the strength of men ;
					</l>
                  <l>But through his mind's resource
					</l>
                  <l>He subdues the dread
					</l>
                  <l>Tribes of the deep and races
					</l>
                  <l>Bred on earth and in the air.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Autobulus. Yet that is the very source, my
					dear Soclarus, from which they say insensibility
					spread among men and the sort of savagery that
					learned the taste of slaughter on its hunting trips<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 20.</note>
					and has grown accustomed to feel no repugnance for
					the wounds and gore of beasts, but. to take pleasure
					in their violent death. The next step is like what
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.323"/>
					
					happened at Athens<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 998 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> and <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Graec. Frag.</hi> i. p. 269, Ephorus, frag. 125; it is not, however, accepted as from Ephorus by Jacoby (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Sallust, <hi rend="italics">Catiline</hi>, li. 28-31). We must remember, during the following discussion, that zoology used to be the handmaid of ethics.</note>: the first man put to death
					by the Thirty was a certain informer who was said to
					deserve it, and so was the second and the third ; but
					after that they went on, step by step, until they were
					laving hands on honest men and eventually did not
					spare even the best of the citizens. Just so the first
					man<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 993 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. The Age of Cronus, when beasts were unharmed, is admirably described in Plato, <hi rend="italics">Politicus</hi>, 270 c ff.</note> to kill a bear or a wolf won praise ; and perhaps
					some cow or pig was condemned as suitable to slay
					because it had tasted the sacred meal placed before
					it.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">That is, they put grain on the altar to make the animal volunteer, as it were, to die</q> (Post); and the consent of the victim was secured by pouring water on it to make it shake its head. See <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 729 e and the article <q direct="unspecified">Opfer</q> in <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, xviii. 612.</note> So from that point, as they now went on to eat
					the flesh of deer and hare and antelope, men were
					introduced to the consumption of sheep and, in some
					places, of dogs and horses.
					<quote rend="blockquote">The tame goose and the dove upon the hearth,</quote>
					as Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 314, frag. 782; Pearson, vol. III, p. 68, frag. 866.</note> says, were dismembered and carved
					for food - not that hunger compelled men as it does
					weasels and cats, but for pleasure and as an appetizer.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 991 d, 993 b, 995 c <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. Or <q direct="unspecified">as meat to go with their bread</q>; for fowl is not ordinarily an appetizer.</note>
					Thus the brute<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From this point to the end of chapter 5 (963 f) the greater part of the text is excerpted by Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 20-24 (pp. 211-220, ed. Nauck). This indirect transmission, with its not infrequent changes, omissions, and variations, gives valuable evidence; but obvious errors on either side have not been mentioned here.</note> and the natural lust to kill in man
					were fortified and rendered inflexible to pity, while
					gentleness was, for the most part, deadened. It was
					in this way, on the contrary, that the Pythagoreans,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 964 f, 993 a <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 86 d, 729 e. <q direct="unspecified">The practice is correctly stated; the alleged motive is not. The taboo on meat stemmed from belief in the transmigration of souls</q> (Andrews).</note>
					to inculcate humanity and compassion, made a
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.325"/>
					
					practice of kindness to animals ; for habituation has
					a strange power to lead men onward by a gradual
					familiarization of the feelings.
				</p>
            <p>
					Well, we have somehow fallen unawares into a
					discussion not unconnected with what we said yesterday nor yet with the argument that is presently to
					take place to-day. Yesterday, as you know, we
					proposed the thesis that all animals partake in one
					way or another of reason and understanding, and
					thereby offered our young hunters a field of competition not lacking in either instruction or pleasure :
					the question whether land or sea animals have
					superior intelligence. This argument, it seems, we
					shall to-day adjudicate if Aristotimus and Phaedimus
					stand by their challenges ; for Aristotimus put himself at his comrades' disposal to advocate the land as
					producer of animals with superior intelligence, while
					the other will be pleader for the sea.
				</p>
            <p>
					Soclarus. They'll stand by their word, Autobulus ;
					they'll be here any minute now. Early this morning
					I observed them both preparing for the fray. But,
					if you like, before the contest begins, let us review
					the discussion of whatever topics are germane to our
					conversation of yesterday, but were not then discussed, either because no occasion offered, or, since
					we were in our cups, were treated too lightly. I
					thought, in fact, that I caught the reverberation of
					a material objection from the Stoa<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 49 ff., 172 ff.; and Pohlenz, <hi rend="italics">B.P.W.</hi> xxiii (1903), col. 966, on Chrysippus, frag. 182.</note>: just as the
					immortal is opposed to the mortal and the imperishable to the perishable, and, of course, the incorporeal
					to the corporeal; just so, if there is rationality, the
					irrational must exist as its opposite and counterpart.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.327"/>
					
					This alone, among all these pairings, must not be
					left incomplete and mutilated.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Autobulus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There seems to be a great deal more anti-Stoic polemic in the following speeches than von Arnim has admitted into his compilation. See especially the notes on 961 c ff. <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> But who ever, my dear Soclarus,
					maintained that, while rationality exists in the universe, there is nothing irrational ? For there is a
					plentiful abundance of the irrational in all things
					that are not endowed with a soul; we need no other
					sort of counterpart for the rational: everything that
					is soulless, since it has no reason or intelligence, is by
					definition in opposition to that which, together with
					a soul, possesses also reason and understanding. Yet
					suppose someone were to maintain that nature must
					not be left maimed, but that that part of nature
					which, is endowed with a soul should have its irrational
					as well as its rational aspect, someone else is bound
					to maintain that nature endowed with a soul must
					have both an imaginative and an unimaginative part,
					and both a sentient part and an insentient. They
					want nature, they say, to have these counteractive
					and contraposed positives and negatives of the
					same kind counterbalanced, as it were. But if it is
					ridiculous to require an antithesis of sentient and
					insentient within the class of living things, or an
					antithesis of imaginative and unimaginative, seeing
					that it is the nature of every creature with a soul
					to be sentient and imaginative from the hour of its
					birth, so he, also, is unreasonable who demands a
					division of the living into a rational and an irrational
					part - and that, too, when he is arguing with men
					who believe that nothing is endowed with sensation
					which does not also partake of intelligence and that
					there is no living thing which does not naturally
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.329"/>
					
					possess both opinion and reason, just as it has sensation and appetite. For nature, which, they<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle and Theophrastus <hi rend="italics">passim</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 646 c, 698 b.</note> rightly
					say, does everything with some purpose and to some
					end, did not create the sentient creature merely to
					be sentient when something happens to it. No, for
					there are in the world many things friendly to it,
					many also hostile ; and it could not survive for a
					moment if it had not learned to give the one sort a
					wide berth while freely mixing with the other. It
					is, to be sure, sensation that enables each creature
					to recognize both kinds ; but the acts of seizing or
					pursuing that ensue upon the perception of what is
					beneficial, as well as the eluding or fleeing of what is
					destructive or painful, could by no means occur in
					creatures naturally incapable of some sort of reasoning and judging, remembering and attending. Those
					beings, then, which you deprive of all expectation,
					memory, design, or preparation, and of all hopes,
					fears, desires, or griefs - they will have no use for eyes
					or ears either, even though they have them. Indeed,
					it would be better to be rid of all sensation and
					imagination that has nothing to make use of it,
					rather than to know toil and distress and pain while
					not possessing any means of averting them.
				</p>
            <p>
					There is, in fact, a work of Strato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 112, ed. Wehrli (<hi rend="italics">Die Schule des Aristoteles</hi>, v, p. 34).</note> the natural
					philosopher, which proves that it is impossible to
					have sensation at all without some action of the intelligence. Often, it is true, while we are busy
					reading, the letters may fall on our eyes, or words
					may fall on our ears, which escape our attention since
					our minds are intent on other things ; but later the
					mind recovers, shifts its course, and follows up every
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.331"/>
					
					detail that had been neglected ; and this is the
					meaning of the saying<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A frequently occurring quotation, attributed to Epicharmus in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 336 b (Kaibel, <hi rend="italics">Com. Graec. Frag.</hi> i, p. 137, frag. 249; Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 200, frag. 12); see also <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 98 c and 975 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. The fullest interpretation is that of Schottlaender, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, lxii, pp. 437 f.; and see also Wehrli's note, pp. 72 f.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Mind has sight and Mind has hearing ;
					</l>
                  <l>Everything else is deaf and blind,</l>
               </quote>
					indicating that the impact on eyes and ears brings
					no perception if the understanding is not present.
					For this reason also King Cleomenes, when a recital
					made at a banquet was applauded and he was asked
					if it did not seem excellent, replied that the others
					must judge, for his mind was in the Peloponnesus.
					So that, if we are so constituted that to have sensation
					we must have understanding, then it must follow
					that all creatures which have sensation can also
					understand.
				</p>
            <p>
					But let us grant that sensation needs no help of
					intelligence to perform its own function ; nevertheless, when the perception that has caused an animal
					to distinguish between what is friendly and what
					is hostile is gone, what is it that from this time on
					remembers the distinction, fears the painful, and
					wants the beneficial ? And, if what it wants is not
					there, what is there in animals that devises means of
					acquiring it and providing lairs and hiding-places
					 - both traps for prey and places of refuge from
					attackers ? And yet those very authors<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Stoics again; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> iii, p. 41, Chrysippus, frag. 173 of the <hi rend="italics">Ethica</hi>.</note> rasp our
					ears by repeatedly defining in their <hi rend="italics">Introductions</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or <q direct="unspecified">elementary treatises</q>: titles used by Chrysippus (von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> ii, pp. 6 f.; iii, p. 196).</note>
					          <q direct="unspecified">purpose</q> as <q direct="unspecified">an indication of intent to complete,</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.333"/>
					
					          <q direct="unspecified">design</q> as <q direct="unspecified">an impulse before an impulse,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">preparation</q> as <q direct="unspecified">an act before an act,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">memory</q>
					as <q direct="unspecified">an apprehension of a proposition in the past tense
						of which the present tense has been apprehended by
						perception.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, by sensation we apprehend the proposition <q direct="unspecified">Socrates is snub-nosed,</q> by memory the proposition <q direct="unspecified">Socrates was snub-nosed.</q> The literature on this complicated subject has been collected and analysed in <hi rend="italics">Class. Rev.</hi> lxvi (1952), pp. 146 f.</note> For there is not one of these terms
					that does not belong to logic; and the acts are all
					present in all animals as, of course, are cognitions
					which, while inactive, they call <q direct="unspecified">notions,</q> but when
					they are once put into action, <q direct="unspecified">concepts.</q> And
					though they admit that emotions one and all are
					<q direct="unspecified">false judgements and seeming truths,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> i, pp. 50 f; iii, pp. 92 ff.; see also <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 449 c.</note> it is extraordinary that they obviously fail to note many things
					that animals do and many of their movements that
					show anger or fear or, so help me, envy or jealousy.
					They themselves punish dogs and horses that make
					mistakes, not idly but to discipline them; they are
					creating in them through pain a feeling of sorrow,
					which we call repentance.
				</p>
            <p>
					Now pleasure that is received through the ears is
					a means of enchantment, while that which comes
					through the eyes is a kind of magic : they use both
					kinds against animals. For deer and horses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xii. 44, 46; Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 29.</note> are
					bewitched by pipes and flutes, and crabs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Dolphins also are caught by music: Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 137.</note> are involuntarily lured from their holes by lotus pipes e ;
					it is also reported that shad will rise to the surface
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.335"/>
					
					and approach when there is singing and clapping.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi, 32; Athenaeus, 328 f, on the <hi rend="italics">trichis</hi>, which is a kind of <hi rend="italics">thrissa</hi> (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Athenaeus, 328 e); and see Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> i. 244 (L.C.L.).</note>
					The horned owl,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 52 b (where the L.C.L., probably wrongly, reads <q direct="unspecified">the ape</q>); 705 a; Athenaeus, 390 f; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xv. 28; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 68; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 13 (597 b 22 ff.) and the other references of Hubert at <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 705 a and Gulick on Athenaeus, 629 f. Contrast Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i, 39, on doves. Porphyry omits this sentence.</note> again, can be caught by the magic
					of movement, as he strives to twist his shoulders in
					delighted rhythm to the movements of men dancing
					before him.
				</p>
            <p>
					As for those who foolishly affirm that animals do
					not feel pleasure or anger or fear or make preparations or remember, but that the bee <q direct="unspecified">as it were</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A favourite expression of Aristotle's; but it is the Stoics who are being reproved here (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, p. 240, Chrysippus, frag. 887). This seems to be the only appearance of the word in Plutarch, unless Pohlenz is right in conjecturing it at <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 600 f, or Rasmus at 1054 c in other Stoic quotations.</note>
					remembers and the swallow <q direct="unspecified">as it were</q> prepares her
					nest and the lion <q direct="unspecified">as it were</q> grows angry and the
					deer <q direct="unspecified">as it were</q> is frightened-I don't know what
					they will do about those who say that beasts do not
					see or hear, but<q direct="unspecified">as it were</q> hear and see ; that they
					have no cry but <q direct="unspecified">as it were</q> ; nor do they live at all
					but <q direct="unspecified">as it were.</q> For these last statements (or so I
					believe) are no more contrary to plain evidence than
					those that they have made.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Soclarus. Well, Autobulus, you may count me
					also as one who believes your statements ; yet on
					comparing the ways of beasts with human customs
					and lives, with human actions and manner of living,
					I find not only many other defects in animals, but
					this especially : they do not explicitly aim at virtue,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On animals possessing <hi rend="italics">aret&ecirc;</hi> see Aelian's preface to the first book of <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 986 f <hi rend="italics">infra; al.</hi>
               </note>
					for which purpose reason itself exists ; nor do they
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.337"/>
					
					make any progress in virtue or have any bent for it;
					so that I fail to see how Nature can have given them
					even elementary reason, seeing that they cannot
					achieve its end.
				</p>
            <p>
					Autobulus. But neither does this, Soclarus, seem
					absurd to those very opponents of ours ; for while
					they postulate that love of one's offspring<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 495 c and the whole fragment, <hi rend="italics">De Amore Prolis</hi> (493 a - 497 e).</note> is the
					very foundation of our social life and administration
					of justice, and observe that animals possess such love
					in a very marked degree, yet they assert and hold
					that animals have no part in justice. Now mules<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Generatione Animal.</hi> ii, 7 (746 b 15 ff.), ii. 8 (747 a 23 ff.); for Aristotle's criticism of Empedocles' theory see H. Cherniss, <hi rend="italics">Aristotle's Criticism of the Presocratics</hi>, p. 143, n. 573. Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 173, mentions some cases of the fertility of mules, see also Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Divinatione</hi>, i. 36; ii. 49; Herodotus, iii. 151 ff.</note>
					are not deficient in organs ; they have, in fact,
					genitals and wombs and are able to use them with
					pleasure, yet cannot attain the end of generation.
					Consider another approach : is it not ridiculous to
					keep affirming that men like Socrates and Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Finibus</hi>, iv. 21.</note> are
					involved in vice no less vicious than that of any slave
					you please, that they are just as foolish and intemperate and unjust, and at the same time to stigmatize
					the alloyed and imprecise virtue of animals as absence
					of reason rather than as its imperfection or weakness ?
					And this, though they acknowledge that vice is
					a fault of reason and that all animals are infected
					with vice : many, in fact, we observe to be guilty of
					cowardice and intemperance, injustice and malice.
					He, then, who holds that what is not fitted by nature to receive the perfection of reason does not even
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.339"/>
					
					receive any reason at all is, in the first place, no
					better than one who asserts that apes are not naturally ugly or tortoises naturally slow for the reason
					that they are not capable of possessing beauty or
					speed. In the second place, he fails to observe the
					distinction which is right before his eyes : mere
					reason is implanted by nature, but real and perfect
					reason<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, vii. 54.</note> is the product of care and education. And
					this is why every living creature has the faculty of
					reasoning ; but if what they seek is true reason and
					wisdom, not even man may be said to possess it.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Deorum</hi>, ii. 13. 34.</note>
					For as one capacity for seeing or flying differs from
					another (hawks and cicadas do not see alike, nor do
					eagles and partridges fly alike), so also not every
					reasoning creature has in the same way a mental
					dexterity or acumen that has attained perfection.
					For just as there are many examples in animals of
					social instincts and bravery and ingenuity in ways
					and means and in domestic arrangements, so, on
					the other hand, there are many examples of the opposite : injustice, cowardliness, stupidity.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 992 d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> And the very
					factor which brought about our young men's contest
					to-day provides confirmation. It is on an assumption
					of difference that the two sides assert, one that land
					animals, the other that sea animals, are naturally
					more advanced toward virtue. This is clear also if
					you contrast hippopotamuses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 71; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ii. 7 (502 a 9-15), though the latter passage may be interpolated. Porphyry reads <q direct="unspecified">contrast river-horses with land-horses.</q>
               </note> with storks<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> ix. 13 (615 b 23 ff.); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 23; Philo, 61 (p. 129).</note>: the
					latter support their fathers, while the former kill
					them<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">And eat them: Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 19.</note> in order to consort with their mothers. The
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.341"/>
					
					same is true if you compare doves<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> vi. 4 (562 b 17); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 45.</note> with partridges<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 8 (613 b 27 ff.); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 16, and <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> iv. 1. 16; of peacocks in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 161.</note>;
					for the partridge cock steals the eggs and destroys
					them since the female will not consort with him
					while she is sitting, whereas male doves assume a
					part in the care of the nest, taking turns at keeping
					the eggs warm and being themselves the first to feed
					the fledglings ; and if the female happens to be away
					for too long a time, the male strikes her with his
					beak and drives her back to her eggs or squabs. And
					while Antipater<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> iii, p. 251, Antipater of Tarsus, frag. 47. We know from Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Aetia Physica</hi>, 38 that Antipater wrote a book on animals. On the other hand, Dyroff (<hi rend="italics">Bl&auml;tter f. d. bay. Gymn.</hi> xxiii, 1897, p. 403) argued for Antipater of Tyre; he believed, in fact, that the present work was mainly directed against this Antipater. Schuster, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 77, has shown this to be unlikely.</note> was reproaching asses and sheep
					for their neglect of cleanliness, I don't know how he
					happened to overlook lynxes and swallows<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 7 (612 b 30 f.); Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 727 d-e; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 92; Philo, 22 (p. 111).</note>; for
					lynxes dispose of their excrement by concealing and
					doing away with it, while swallows teach their nestlings to turn tail and void themselves outward.
				</p>
            <p>
					Why, moreover, do we not say that one tree is less
					intelligent than another, as a sheep is by comparison with a dog ; or one vegetable more cowardly than
					another, as a stag is by comparison with a lion ? Is
					the reason not that, just as it is impossible to call one
					immovable object slower than another, or one dumb
					thing more mute than another, so among all the creatures to whom Nature has not given the faculty of
					understanding, we cannot say that one is more cowardly or more slothful or more intemperate ? Whereas it,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.343"/>
					
					is the presence of understanding, of one kind in one
					animal, of another kind in another, and in varying
					degree, that has produced the observable differences.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Soclarus. Yet it is astonishing how greatly man
					surpasses the animals in his capacity for learning and
					in sagacity and in the requirements of justice and
					social life.
				</p>
            <p>
					Autobulus. There are in fact, my friend, many
					animals wliich surpass all men, not only in bulk and
					swiftness, but also in keen sight and sharp hearing<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Alexander of Aphrodisias, <hi rend="italics">De Fato</hi>, 27; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 10; x. 191.</note>;
					but for all that man is not blind or crippled or earless. We can run, if less swiftly than deer ; and
					see, if less keenly than hawks ; nor has Nature deprived us of strength and bulk even though, by
					comparison with, the elephant and the camel, we
					amount to nothing in these matters.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ii. 145, reports a singular deduction from this theme; see also Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Beneficiis</hi>, ii. 29. 1.</note> In the same
					way, then, let us not say of beasts that they are
					completely lacking in intellect and understanding
					and do not possess reason even though their understanding is less acute and their intellect inferior to
					ours ; what we should say is that their intellect, is
					feeble and turbid, like a dim and clouded eye. And
					if I did not expect that our young men, learned and
					studious as they are, would very shortly present us
					here, one with a large collection of examples drawn
					from the land, the other with his from the sea, I
					should not have denied myself the pleasure of giving
					you countless examples of the docility and native
					capacity of beasts - of which fair Rome<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See, for example, 968 c, e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> has provided
					us a reservoir from which to draw in pails and buckets,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.345"/>
					
					as it were, from the imperial spectacles. Let us
					leave this subject, therefore, fresh and untouched
					for them to exercise their art upon in discourse.
				</p>
            <p>
					There is, however, one small matter which I should
					like to discuss with you quietly. It is my opinion
					that each part and faculty has its own particular
					weakness or defect or ailment which appears in
					nothing else, as blindness in the eye, lameness in the
					leg, stuttering in the tongue. There can be no
					blindness in an organ which was not created to see,
					or lameness in a part which was not designed for
					walking ; nor would you ever describe an animal
					without a tongue as stuttering, or one voiceless by
					nature as inarticulate. And in the same way you
					would not call delirious or witless or mad anything
					that was not endowed by Nature with reason or intelligence or understanding ; for it is impossible to ail
					where you have no faculty of which the ailment is
					a deficiency or loss or some other kind of impairment. Yet certainly you have encountered mad
					dogs, and I have also known of mad horses; and
					there are some who say that cattle and foxes also
					go mad.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">So too, perhaps, wolves in Theocritus, iv. 11.</note> But dogs will do, since no one questions the
					fact in their case, which provides evidence that the
					creature possesses reason and a by no means despicable intellectual faculty. What is called rabies and
					madness is an ailment of that faculty when it becomes
					disturbed and disordered. For we observe no derangement either of the dogs' sight or of their hearing; yet, just as when a human being suffers from
					melancholy or insanity, anyone is absurd who does
					not admit that it is the organ that thinks and reasons
					and remembers which has been displaced or damaged
					(we habitually say, in fact, of madmen that they <q direct="unspecified">are
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.347"/>
						
						not themselves,</q> but have <q direct="unspecified">fallen out of their wits</q>),
					just so, whoever believes that rabid dogs have any
					other ailment than an affliction of their natural organ
					of judgement and reason and memory so that, when
					this has become infected with disorder and insanity,
					they no longer recognize beloved faces and shun
					their natural haunts - such a man, I say, either must
					be disregarding the evidence or, if he does take note
					of the conclusion to which it leads, must be quarrelling with the truth.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Stoics again; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Galen, <hi rend="italics">De Hippocratis et Platonis Placitis</hi>, v. 1 (p. 431 K&uuml;hn).</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Soclarus. Your inference seems quite justified.
					For the Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> iii, p. 90.</note> and Peripatetics strenuously argue
					on the other side, to the effect that justice could
					not then come into existence, but would remain
					completely without form or substance, if all the
					beasts partake of reason. For<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From this point to the end of chapter 6 (964 c) the text is quoted by Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, i. 4-6 (pp. 88-89, ed. Nauck); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the note on 959 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> either we are necessarily unjust if we do not spare them ; or, if we
					do not take them for food, life becomes impracticable
					or impossible ; in a sense we shall be living the life
					of beasts once we give up the use of beasts.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 86 d.</note> I omit
					the numberless hosts of Nomads and Troglodytes who
					know no other food but flesh. As for us who believe
					our lives to be civilized and humane, it is hard
					to say what pursuit on land or sea, what aerial art,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is beasts, fish, and fowl in earth, sea, and air.</note>
					what refinement of living, is left to us if we are to
					learn to deal innocently and considerately with all
					creatures, as we are bound to if they possess reason
					and are of one stock with us. So we have no help or
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.349"/>
					
					cure for this dilemma which either deprives us of life
					itself or of justice, unless we do preserve that ancient
					limitation and law by which, according to Hesiod,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 277-279; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 50; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 43.</note>
					he who distinguished the natural kinds and gave
					each class its special domain:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To fish and beasts and winged birds allowed
					</l>
                  <l>Licence to eat each other, for no right
					</l>
                  <l>Exists among them; right, he gave to men</l>
               </quote>
					for dealing with each other. Those who know nothing
					of right action toward us can receive no wrong from
					us either.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This seems to have been Plutarch's own attitude toward the question, at least later on in life; see <hi rend="italics">Life of Cato Maior</hi>, v. 2 (339 a).</note> For those who have rejected this argument have left no path, either broad or narrow, by
					which justice may slip in.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Autobulus. This, my friend, has been spoken
					<q direct="unspecified">from the heart.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Euripides, frag. 412 (Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 486); quoted more completely in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 63 a.</note> We certainly must not allow
					philosophers, as though they were women in difficult
					labour, to put about their necks a charm for speedy
					delivery so that they may bring justice to birth for
					us easily and without hard labour. For they themselves do not concede to Epicurus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Usener, <hi rend="italics">Epicurea</hi>, p. 351; see Bailey on Lucretius, ii. 216 ff.; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 1015 b-c.</note> for the sake of the
					highest considerations, a thing so small and trifling as
					the slightest deviation of a single atom-which would
					permit the stars and living creatures to slip in by
					chance and would preserve from destruction the
					principle of free will. But, seeing that they bid him
					demonstrate whatever is not obvious or take as his
					starting-point something that is obvious, how are they
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.351"/>
					
					in any position to make this statement about animals<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That they are irrational.</note>
					a basis of their own account of justice, when it is
					neither generally accepted nor otherwise demonstrated by them?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For this difficult and corrupt passage the admirable exposition and reconstruction of F. H. Sandbach (<hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> xxxv, p. 114) has been followed.</note> For justice has another way to
					establish itself, a way which is neither so treacherous
					nor so precipitous, nor is it a route lined with the
					wreckage of obvious truths. It is the road which,
					under the guidance of Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 782 c.</note> my son and your companion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch himself; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 734 e.</note> Soclarus, points out to those who have no
					love of wrangling, but are willing to be led and to
					learn. For certain it is that Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 366, frag. B 135; and see Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, i, 13. 2 (1373 b 14).</note> and Heraclitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> i, p. 169, frag. B 80; Bywater, frag. 62.</note> accept as true the charge that man is not
					altogether innocent of injustice when he treats animals as he does; often and often do they lament and exclaim against Nature, declaring that she is <q direct="unspecified">Necessity</q> and <q direct="unspecified">War,</q> that she contains nothing unmixed
					and free from tarnish, that her progress is marked
					by many unjust inflictions. As an instance, say. even
					birth itself springs from injustice, since it is a union
					of mortal with immortal, and the offspring is nourished
					unnaturally on members torn from the parent.
				</p>
            <p>
					These strictures, however, seem to be unpalatably
					strong and bitter ; for there is an alternative, an
					inoffensive formula which does not, on the one hand,
					deprive beasts of reason, yet does, on the other,
					preserve the justice of those who make fit use of
					them. When the wise men of old had introduced this,
					gluttony joined luxury to cancel and annul it;
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.353"/>
					
					Pythagoras,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 959 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 729 e; frag. xxxiv. 145 (vol. VII, p. 169 Bernardakis).</note> however, reintroduced it, teaching us how to
					profit without injustice. There is no injustice, surely,
					in punishing and slaying animals that are anti-social
					and merely injurious, while taming those that are
					gentle and friendly to man and making them our
					helpers in the tasks for which they are severally
					fitted by nature<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf., e.g.</hi>, Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 352 e.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">Offspring of horse and ass and seed of bulls</quote>
					which Aeschylus'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Prometheus Unbound</hi>, frag. 194 (Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 65; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 98 c.</note> Prometheus says that he bestowed
					on us
					<quote rend="blockquote">To serve us and relieve our labours;</quote>
					and thus we make use of dogs as sentinels and keep
					herds of goats and sheep that are milked and shorn.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">There are significant undercurrents here. Of the animals domesticated by man. Plutarch first mentions only the horse, the ass, and the ox, nothing their employment as servants of man, not as sources of food. Next come dogs, then goats and sheep. The key factor is that in the early period the cow, the sheep, and the goat were too valuable as sources of milk and wool to be recklessly slaughtered for the sake of their meat. The pig was the only large domestic animal useful almost solely as a source of meat</q> (Andrews).</note>
					For living is not abolished nor life terminated when
					a man has no more platters of fish or pate de foie gras
					or mincemeat of beef or kids' flesh for his banquets<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Plutarch's choice of examples of table luxury is apt. The enthusiasm of many Greek epicures for fish scandalized conservative philosophers. Pate de foie gras ranked high as a delicacy, more especially in the Roman period; the mincemeat mentioned is surely the Roman <hi rend="italics">isicia</hi>, dishes with finely minced beef or pork as the usual basis, many recipes for which appear in Apicius</q> (Andrews).</note>
					 - or when he no longer, idling in the theatre or
					hunting for sport, compels some beasts against their
					will to stand their ground and fight, while he destroys
					others which have not the instinct to fight back even
					in their own defence. For I think sport should be
					joyful and between playmates who are merry on
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.355"/>
					
					both sides, not the sort of which Bion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bion and Xenocrates were almost alone among the Greeks in expressing pity for animals.</note> spoke when
					he remarked that boys throw stones at frogs for fun,
					but the frogs don't die for <q direct="unspecified">fun,</q> but in sober earnest.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Hartman, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, p. 571; [Aristotle], <hi rend="italics">Eud. Eth.</hi> vii. 10. 21 (1243 a 20).</note>
					Just so, in hunting and fishing, men amuse themselves with the suffering and death of animals, even
					tearing some of them piteously from their cubs and
					nestlings. The fact is that it is not those who make
					use of animals who do them wrong, but those who
					use them harmfully and heedlessly and in cruel ways.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Soclarus. Restrain yourself, Autobulus, and
					turn off the flow of these accusations.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 940 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>. Possibly a reference to the water-clock used in the courts.</note> I see a good
					many gentlemen approaching who are all hunters;
					you will hardly convert them and you needn't hurt
					their feelings.
				</p>
            <p>
					Autobulus. Thanks for the warning. Eubiotus,
					however, I know quite well and my cousin Ariston,
					and Aeacides and Aristotimus here, the sons of Dionysius of Delphi, and Nicander, the son of Euthydamus,
					all of them <q direct="unspecified">expert,</q> as Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, viii. 159.</note> expresses it, in the
					chase by land - and for this reason they will be on
					Aristotimus' side. So too yonder comes Phaedimus
					with the islanders and coast-dwellers about him,
					Heracleon from Megara and the Euboean Philostratus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Whose hearts are on deeds of the sea.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, ii. 614; <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, v. 67.</note>
               </quote>
					And here is my contemporary Optatus: like Diomedes, it is
					<quote rend="blockquote">Hard to tell the side on which he ranges,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, v. 85.</note>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.357"/>
					
					for <q direct="unspecified">with many a trophy from the sea, many likewise
						from the chase on the mountain, he has glorified</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Verses of an unknown poet, as recognized by Hubert.</note> the
					goddess<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Artemis; on the combined cults see Farnell, <hi rend="italics">Cults of the Greek States</hi>, ii, pp. 425 ff.</note> who is at once the Huntress and Dictynna.
					It is evident that he is coming to join us with no intention of attaching himself to either side. Or am
					I wrong, my dear Optatus, in supposing that you will
					be an impartial and neutral umpire between the
					young men ?
				</p>
            <p>
					Optatus. It is just as you suppose, Autobulus.
					Solon's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, xx. 1 (89 a-b); <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 550 c, 823 f; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>, viii. 5. A fairly well attested law, but <q direct="unspecified">the name of Solon is used as the collective term for the legislative activity of the past</q> (Linforth, <hi rend="italics">Solon the Athenian</hi>, p. 283). The penalty was disfranchisement. Lysias, xxxi. shows that this law was unknown in his time.</note> law, which used to punish those who adhered
					to neither side in a factious outbreak, has long since
					fallen into disuse.
				</p>
            <p>
					Autobulus. Come over here, then, and take your
					place beside us so that, if we need evidence, we shall
					not have to disturb the tomes of Aristotle,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The zoological works, such as the <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">Generation of Animals</hi>, which once extended to fifty volumes (Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 44).</note> but may
					follow you as expert and return a true verdict on the
					arguments.
				</p>
            <p>
					Soclarus. Well then, my young friends, have you
					reached any agreement on procedure ?
				</p>
            <p>
					Phaedimus. We have, Soclarus, though it occasioned considerable controversy ; but at length, as
					Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 678, frag. 989; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 644 d.</note> has it,
					<quote rend="blockquote">The lot, the child of chance,</quote>
					made arbiter, admits into court the case of the land
					animals before that of creatures from the sea.
				</p>
            <p>
					Soclarus. The time has come, then, Aristotimus,
					for you to speak and us to hear.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.359"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Aristotimus. The court is open for the litigants . . . <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Here follows a long lacuna not indicated in the mss., the contents of which cannot even be conjectured.</note> And there are some fish that waste
					their milt by pursuing the female while she is laying
					her eggs.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The milt is, of course, for the fertilization of the eggs, as Aristotimus should have learned from Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">e.g., Historia Animal.</hi> vi. 13, 567 b 3 ff.)</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					There is also a type of mullet called the grayfish<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On this type <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 2 (591 a 23) and in Athenaeus, vii. 307 a, where variants of the name occur. <q direct="unspecified">The same name was applied to a type of shark as well as to a type of mullet, an apt application in both instances</q> (Andrews).</note>
					which feeds on its own slime<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 643 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> iii. 432 ff.). Pliny (<hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 128, 131) tells the same story of the purplefish.</note>; and the octopus sits
					through the winter devouring himself,
					<quote rend="blockquote">In fireless home and domicile forlorn,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 524; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 978 f <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> and the note; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 1059 e; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 27, xiv. 26. See also Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 2 (591 a 5); Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 244; Lucilius, frag. 925 Warmington (L.C.L.).</note>
               </quote>
					so lazy or insensible or gluttonous, or guilty of all of
					these charges, is he. So this also is the reason, again,
					why Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 823 d-e.</note> in his Laws enjoined, or rather prayed,
					that his young men might not be seized by <q direct="unspecified">a love
						for sea hunting.</q> For there is no exercise in bravery
					or training in skill or anything that contributes to
					strength or fleetness or agility when men endure
					toil in contests with bass or conger or parrot-fish ;
					whereas, in the chase on land, brave animals give
					play to the courageous and danger-loving qualities
					of those matched against them, crafty animals sharpen
					the wits and cunning of their attackers, while swift
					ones train the strength and perseverance of their
					pursuers. These are the qualities which have made
					hunting a noble sport, whereas there is nothing
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.361"/>
					
					glorious about fishing. No, and there's not a god,
					my friend, who has allowed himself to be called
					<q direct="unspecified">conger-killer,</q> as Apollo is <q direct="unspecified">wolf-slayer,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For Apollo's connexion with wolves see Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> x. 26; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> or <q direct="unspecified">surmullet-slayer,</q> as Artemis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On Artemis, <q direct="unspecified">The Lady of Wild Beasts</q> (<hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxi. 470), see <hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi>, 4th series, iv (1951), pp. 230 ff.</note> is <q direct="unspecified">deer-slaying.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This accusation is answered in 983 e-f <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					And what is surprising in this when it's a more
					glorious thing for a man to have caught a boar or
					a stag or, so help me, a gazelle or a hare than to
					have bought one ? As for your tunny<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 980 a <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and your
					mackerel and your boriito ! They're more honourable to buy than to catch oneself. For their lack of
					spirit or of any kind of resource or cunning has made
					the sport dishonourable, unfashionable, and illiberal.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>In general, then, the evidence by which the
					philosophers demonstrate that beasts have their
					share of reason is their possession of purpose<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 961 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and
					preparation and memory and emotions and care for
					their young<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the essay <hi rend="italics">De Amore Prolis, Mor.</hi> 493 a ff. <hi rend="italics">passim</hi>.</note> and gratitude for benefits and hostility
					to what has hurt them ; to which may be added
					their ability to find what they need and their manifestations of good qualities, such as courage<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, at least, held that, philosophically speaking, no beast is brave; <hi rend="italics">Laches</hi>, 196 d; <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 430 b.</note> and
					sociability and continence and magnanimity. Let
					us ask ourselves if marine creatures exhibit any of
					these traits, or perhaps some suggestion of them,
					that is extremely faint and difficult to discern (the
					observer only coming at long last to the opinion that
					it may be descried) ; whereas in the case of terrestrial and earth-born animals it is easy to find remarkably plain and unanswerable proofs of every one of
					the points I have mentioned.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.363"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					In the first place, then, behold the purposeful
					demonstrations and preparations of bulls<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> ii. 57.</note> stirring
					up dust when intent on battle, and wild boars whetting their tusks.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 1; Philo, 51 (p. 125); Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xiii. 474 f.</note> Since elephants' tusks are blunted
					by wear when, by digging or chopping, they fell the
					trees that feed them, they use only one tusk for
					this purpose and keep the other always pointed and
					sharp for defence.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 8; viii. 71 of the rhinoceros; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 56; Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 102.</note> Lions<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 520 f; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 30.</note> always walk with paws
					clenched and claws retracted so that these may not
					be dulled by wear at the point or leave a plain trail
					for trackers ; for it is not easy to find any trace of a
					lion's claw ; on the contrary, any sign of a track that
					is found is so slight and obscure that hunters lose the
					trail and go astray. You have heard, I am sure, how
					the ichneumon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 16 ff.), where, however, the animal's opponent is the asp. (So also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 22; v. 48; vi. 38.) But <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 980 e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 25; x. 47; Nicander, <hi rend="italics">Theriaca</hi>, 201.</note> girds itself for battle as thoroughly
					as any soldier putting on his armour, such a quantity
					of mud does it don and plaster about its body when
					it plans to attack the crocodile. Moreover, we see
					house-martins<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 7 (612 b 21 ff.); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 92; Philo, 22 (p. 110); <hi rend="italics">Yale Class. Studies</hi>, xii. 139, on <hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi> x. 4. 6.</note> preparing for procreation : how well
					they lay the solid twigs at the bottom to serve as a
					foundation, then mould the lighter bits about them ;
					and if they perceive that the nest needs a lump of
					mud to glue it together, they skim over a pond or
					lake, touching the water with only the tips of their
					feathers to make them moist, yet not heavy with
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.365"/>
					
					dampness; then they scoop up dust and so smear
					over and bind together any parts that begin to sag
					or loosen. As for the shape of their work, it has no
					angles nor many sides, but is as smooth and circular
					as they can make it; such a shape is, in fact, both
					stable and capacious and provides no hold on the
					outside for scheming animals.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <foreign lang="greek">qhri/a</foreign> may be <q direct="unspecified">serpents</q> here, or any wild beast, perhaps, such as members of the cat family that relish a diet of birds.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					There is more than one reason<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For a collection of the <hi rend="italics">loci communes</hi> dealing with swallow, bee, ant, spider, etc., see Dickerman in <hi rend="italics">Trans. Am. Philol. Assoc.</hi> xlii (1911), pp. 123 ff.</note> for admiring
					spiders'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 39 (623 a 7 ff.); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 21; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 79-84; Philo, 17 (p. 107); Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Imagines</hi>, ii. 28.</note> webs, the common model for both women's
					looms and fowlers'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Commonly taken as <q direct="unspecified">fishermen,</q> but this seems unlikely here.</note> nets ; for there is the fineness of
					the thread and the evenness of the weaving, which has
					no disconnected threads and nothing like a warp, but
					is wrought with the even continuity of a thin membrane and a tenacity that comes from a viscous substance inconspicuously worked in. Then too, there
					is the blending of the colours that gives it an airy,
					misty look, the better to let it go undetected ; and
					most notable of all is the art itself, like a charioteer's
					or a helmsman's, with which the spinner handles her
					artifice. When a possible victim is entangled, she
					perceives it, and uses her wits, like a skilled handler
					of nets, to close the trap suddenly and make it tight.
					Since this is daily under our eyes and observation,
					my account is confirmed. Otherwise it would seem
					a mere fiction, as I formerly regarded the tale of the
					Libyan crows<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Anth. Pal.</hi> ix. 272; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 48; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 125; Avianus, fable 27.</note> which, when they are thirsty, throw
					stones into a pot to fill it and raise the water until
					it is within their reach ; but later when I saw a dog
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.367"/>
					
					on board ship, since the sailors were away, putting
					pebbles into a half empty jar of oil, I was amazed at
					its knowing that lighter substances are forced upward
					when the heavier settle to the bottom.
				</p>
            <p>
					Similar tales are told of Cretan bees and of geese
					in Cilicia.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 510 a-b, which adds the detail that the geese's flight is by night. Contrast Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii, 1, Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 60, of cranes.</note> When the bees are going to round some
					windy promontory, they ballast themselves with
					little stones<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> v. 13; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 24, and Ernout, <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>; Dio Chrysostom, xliv, 7. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 979 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, of the sea hedgehog; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 69.</note> so as not to be carried out to sea ;
					while the geese, in fear of eagles, take a large stone
					in their beaks whenever they cross Mt. Taurus, as it
					were reining in and bridling their gaggling loquacity
					that they may pass over in silence unobserved. It is
					well known, too, how cranes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 979 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 13; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 63, of geese; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> i. 624; Lucan, v. 713 ff.</note> behave when they fly.
					Whenever there is a high wind and rough weather
					they do not fly, as on fine days, in line abreast or
					in a crescent-shaped curve ; but they form at once
					a compact triangle with the point cleaving the gale
					that streams past, so that there is no break in the
					formation. When they have descended to the ground,
					the sentinels that stand watch at night support themselves on one foot and with the other grasp a stone
					and hold it firmly<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 979 d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 59.</note>; the tension of grasping this
					keeps them awake for a long time ; but when they
					do relax, the stone escapes and quickly rouses the
					culprit.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the anecdote of Alexander in Ammianus Marcellinus, xvi. 5. 4; of Aristotle in Diogenes Laertius, v. 16.</note> So that I am not at all surprised that
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.369"/>
					
					Heracles tucked his bow under his arm:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Embracing it with mighty arm he sleeps,
					</l>
                  <l>Keeping his right hand gripped about the club.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 919, Adespoton 416.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					Nor, again, am I surprised at the man who first
					guessed how to open an oyster<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, by dropping it in hot water.</note> when I read of the
					ingenuity of herons. For they swallow a closed
					mussel and endure the discomfort until they know
					that it has been softened and relaxed by their internal
					heat; then they disgorge it wide open and unfolded
					and extract the meat.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 20; another procedure is described in v. 35. See also Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 115, of the shoveller duck; Philo, 31 (p. 116); Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 41; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>It is impossible to relate in full detail all
					the methods of production and storage practised by
					ants, but it would be careless to omit them entirely.
					Nature has, in fact, nowhere else so small a mirror of
					greater and nobler enterprises. Just as you may see
					greater things reflected in a drop of clear water, so
					among ants there exists the delineation of every
					virtue.
					<quote rend="blockquote">Love and affection are found,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xiv. 216.</note>
               </quote>
					namely their social life. You may see, too, the reflection of courage in their persistence in hard labour.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laches</hi>, 192 b ff.; we have here the four Platonic virtues, with Love added.</note>
					There are many seeds of temperance and many of
					prudence and justice. Now Cleanthes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> i, p. 116, frag. 515; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 50.</note> even though
					he declared that animals are not endowed with
					reason, says that he witnessed the following spectacle:
					some ants came to a strange anthill carrying a dead
					ant. Other ants then emerged from the hill and
					seemed, as it were, to hold converse with the first
					party and then went back again. This happened
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.371"/>
					
					two or three times until at last they brought up a
					grub to serve as the dead ant's ransom, whereupon
					the first party picked up the grub, handed over the
					corpse, and departed.
				</p>
            <p>
					A matter obvious to everyone is the consideration
					ants show when they meet : those that bear no load
					always give way to those who have one and let them
					pass.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 25.</note> Obvious also is the manner in which they
					gnaw through and dismember things that are difficult
					to carry or to convey past an obstacle, in order that
					they may make easy loads for several. And Aratus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaenomena</hi>, 956; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Vergil, <hi rend="italics">Georgics</hi>, i. 379 f.; Theophrastus, <hi rend="italics">De Signis</hi>, 22.</note>
					takes it to be a sign of rainy weather when they spread
					out their eggs and cool them in the open:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>When from their hollow nest the ants in haste
					</l>
                  <l>Bring up their eggs;</l>
               </quote>
					and some do not write <q direct="unspecified">eggs</q> here, but <q direct="unspecified">provisions,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not <hi rend="italics">oia</hi>, but <hi rend="italics">eia</hi>: <q direct="unspecified">What the ants really carry out in Aratus and Vergil is their pupas, but these are commonly called &lsquo;eggs&rsquo; to this day</q> (Platt, <hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> v. p. 255). The two readings in this passage seem to show that Plutarch had at hand an edition with a commentary; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also 976 f <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, on the interpretation of Archilochus, and <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 22 b.</note>
					in the sense of stored grain which, when they notice
					that it is growing mildewed and fear that it may
					decay and spoil, they bring up to the surface. But
					what goes beyond any other conception of their
					intelligence is their anticipation of the germination
					of wheat. You know, of course, that wheat does not
					remain permanently dry and stable, but expands
					and lactifies in the process of germination. In order,
					then, to keep it from running to seed and losing its
					value as food, and to keep it permanently edible,
					the ants eat out the germ from which springs the
					new shoot of wheat.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 109, and Ernout <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
               </note>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.373"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					I do not approve of those who, to make a complete
					study of anthills, inspect them, as it were, anatomically. But, be that as it may, they report that the
					passage leading downward from the opening is not
					at all straight or easy for any other creature to traverse; it passes through turns and twists<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The intricate galleries of anthills were used for purposes of literary comparisons by the ancients: see the fragment of Pherecrates in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 1142 a and Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Thesmophoriazusae</hi>, 100 (on Timothe&uuml;s and Agathon respectively).</note> with
					branching tunnels and connecting galleries and terminates in three hollow cavities. One of these is
					their common dwelling-place, another serves as
					storeroom for provisions, while in the third they
					deposit the dying.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 43 divides into men's apartments, women's apartments, and storerooms; see also Philo, 42 (p. 120), and Boulenger, <hi rend="italics">Animal Mysteries</hi>, pp. 128 ff. for a modern account. On the social life of ants (and animals) as contrasted with that of humans see Dio Chrysostom, xl. 32, 40 f.; xlviii. 16.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>I don't suppose that you will think it out of
					order if I introduce elephants directly on top of ants
					in order that we may concurrently scrutinize the
					nature of understanding in both the smallest and
					the largest of creatures, for it is neither suppressed
					in the latter nor deficient in the former. Let others,
					then, be astonished that elephants learn, or are
					taught, to exhibit in the theatre all the many postures
					and variations of movement that they do,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 98 e.</note> these
					being so varied and so complicated to memorize and
					retain that they are not at all easy even for human
					artists. For my part, I find the beast's understanding
					better manifested in his own spontaneous and uninstructed feelings and movements, in a pure, as it
					were, and undiluted state.
				</p>
            <p>
					Well, not very long ago at Rome,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 6, which shows that Plutarch is drawing on literature, not personal observation; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 11, for the elaborateness of the manoeuvres; Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Vita Apoll.</hi> ii. 13; Philo, 54 (p. 126); see also 992 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> where a large
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.375"/>
					
					number of elephants were being trained to assume
					dangerous stances and wheel about in complicated
					patterns, one of them, who was the slowest to learn
					and was always being scolded and often punished,
					was seen at night, alone by himself in the moonlight,
					voluntarily rehearsing his lessons and practising
					them.
				</p>
            <p>
					Formerly in Syria, Hagnon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of Tarsus, pupil of Carneades.</note> tells us, an elephant
					was brought up in its master's house and every day
					the keeper, when he received a measure of barley,
					would filch away and appropriate half of it; but
					on one occasion, when the master was present and
					watching, the keeper poured out the whole measure.
					The elephant gave a look, raised its trunk, and made
					two piles of the barley, setting aside half of it and
					thus revealing as eloquently as could be the dishonesty of its keeper. And another elephant, whose
					keeper used to mix stones and dirt in its barley
					ration, when the keeper's meat was cooking, scooped
					up some ashes and threw them into the pot.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 52.</note> And
					another in Rome, being tormented by little boys
					who pricked its proboscis with their writing styluses,
					grabbed one of them and raised him into the air as
					if to dash him to death ; but when the spectators
					cried out, it gently set the child down on the ground
					again and passed along, thinking it sufficient punishment for one so young to have been frightened.
				</p>
            <p>
					Concerning wild elephants who are self-governing
					they tell many wonderful tales, particularly the one
					about the fording of rivers<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 11, gives a different account; still different is Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 15, and <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Vita Apoll.</hi> ii. 15.</note>: the youngest and
					smallest volunteers his services to go first into the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.377"/>
					
					stream. The others wait on the bank and observe
					the result, for if his back remains above water, those
					that are larger than he will have a wide margin of
					safety to give them confidence.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>At this point in my discourse, I imagine that I
					shall do well not to omit the case of the fox, since it
					is so similar. Now the story-books<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The authorities on Deucalion's Flood are assembled by Frazer on Apollodorus, i. 7. 2 (L.C.L.), and more completely in his <hi rend="italics">Folk-Lore in the Old Testament</hi>, i, pp. 146 ff. Plutarch is the only Greek author to add the Semitic dove story, though Lucian (<hi rend="italics">De Dea Syria</hi>, 12 ff.) was to add to the other major contaminations.</note> tell us that when
					Deucalion released a dove from the ark, as long as
					she returned, it was a certain sign that the storm was
					still raging ; but as soon as she flew away, it was a
					harbinger of fair weather. So even to this day the
					Thracians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 949 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> and the note.</note> whenever they propose crossing a frozen
					river, make use of a fox as an indicator of the solidity
					of the ice. The fox moves ahead slowly and lays
					her ear to the ice ; if she perceives by the sound that
					the stream is running close underneath, judging that
					the frozen part has no great depth, but is only thin
					and insecure, she stands stock still and, if she is permitted, returns to the shore ; but if she is reassured
					by the absence of noise, she crosses over. And let
					us not declare that this is a nicety of perception unaided by reason ; it is, rather, a syllogistic conclusion
					developed from the evidence of perception : <q direct="unspecified">What
						makes noise must be in motion ; what is in motion is
						not frozen ; what is not frozen is liquid ; what is
						liquid gives way.</q> So logicians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Specifically Chrysippus (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 726 f.). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Outlines of Pyrrhonism</hi>, i. 69 (the whole passage i. 62-72 is worth reading); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 59; Philo, 45 (p. 122).</note> assert that a dog,
					at a point where many paths split off, makes use
					of a multiple disjunctive<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the form of the syllogism see Diogenes Laertius, vii. 81.</note> argument and reasons
					with himself: <q direct="unspecified">Either the wild beast has taken this
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.379"/>
						
						path, or this, or this. But surely it has not taken
						this, or this. Then it must have gone by the remaining road.</q> Perception here affords nothing but the
					minor premiss, while the force of reason gives
					the major premisses and adds the conclusion to the
					premisses. A dog, however, does not need such a
					testimonial, which is both false and fraudulent ; for
					it is perception itself, by means of track and spoor,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Shorey on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 427 e (L.C.L., vol. I, p. 347, note <hi rend="italics">e</hi>).</note>
					which indicates the way the creature fled ; it does
					not bother with disjunctive and copulative propositions. The dog's true capacity may be discerned
					from many other acts and reactions and the performance of duties, which are neither to be smelled out
					nor seen by the eye, but can be carried out or perceived only by the use of intelligence and reason.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the philosophic dog see Plato, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> 376 b; the scholia of Olympiodorus add that Socrates' famous oath <q direct="unspecified">by the dog</q> was symbolic of the creature's rational nature. See also Sinclair, <hi rend="italics">Class. Rev.</hi> xlii (1948), p. 61; the parallel passages are collected by J. E. B. Mayor, <hi rend="italics">Class. Rev.</hi> xii (1898), pp. 93 ff.</note>
					I should only make myself ridiculous if I described
					the dog's self-control and obedience and sagacity on
					hunting parties to you who see and handle these
					matters every day.
				</p>
            <p>
					There was a Roman named Calvus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 10.</note> slain in the
					Civil Wars, but no one was able to cut off his head
					until they encircled and stabbed to death the dog
					who guarded his master and defended him. And
					King Pyrrhus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 142.</note> on a journey chanced upon a dog
					guarding the body of a murdered man ; in answer
					to his questions he was told that the dog had remained there without eating for three days and
					refused to leave. Pyrrhus gave orders for the corpse
					to be buried and the dog cared for and brought along
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.381"/>
					
					in his train. A few days later there was an inspection
					of the soldiers, who marched in front of the king
					seated on his throne, while the dog lay quietly by his
					side. But when it saw its master's murderers filing
					past, it rushed at them with furious barking and, as it
					voiced its accusation, turned to look at the king so
					that not only he, but everyone present, became suspicious of the men. They were at once arrested and
					when put to the question, with the help of some
					bits of external evidence as well, they confessed the
					murder and were punished.
				</p>
            <p>
					The same thing is said to have been done by
					the poet Hesiod's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 984 d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. A different account, omitting the dog, will be found in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 162 c-f (where see Wyttenbach's note); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Pollux, <hi rend="italics">Onomasticon</hi>, v. 42 and Gabath&uuml;ler on <hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi> vii. 55 (<hi rend="italics">Hellenistische Epigramme auf Dichter</hi>, p. 31).</note> dog, which convicted the sons of
					Ganyctor the Naupactian, by whom Hesiod had been
					murdered. But a matter which carne to the attention
					of our fathers when they were studying at Athens
					is even plainer than anything so far mentioned. A
					certain fellow slipped into the temple of Asclepius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The same story in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 13, indicates a literary source. See now E. R. Dodds, <hi rend="italics">The Greeks and the Irrational</hi>, p. 114 and n. 65.</note>
					took such gold and silver offerings as were not bulky,
					and made his escape, thinking that he had not been
					detected. But the watchdog, whose name was
					Capparus, when none of the sacristans responded to
					its barking, pursued the escaping temple-thief. First
					the man threw stones at it, but could not drive it
					away. When day dawned, the dog did not approach
					close, but followed the man, always keeping him in
					sight, and refused the food he offered. When he
					stopped to rest, the dog passed the night on guard ;
					when he struck out again, the dog got up and
					kept following, fawning on the other people it met
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.383"/>
					
					on the road and barking at the man and sticking to
					his heels. When those who were investigating the
					robbery learned this from men who had encountered
					the pair and were told the colour and size of the dog,
					they pursued all the more vigorously and overtook
					the man and brought him back from Crommyon. On
					the return the dog led the procession, capering and
					exultant, as though it claimed for itself the credit for
					pursuing and capturing the temple-thief. The people
					actually voted it a public ration of food and entrusted
					the charge of this to the priests in perpetuity, thereby
					imitating the ancient Athenian kindness to the mule.
					For when Pericles was building the Hecatompedon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Better known as the Parthenon; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 349 d, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pericles</hi>, xiii. 7 (159 e).</note>
					on the Acropolis, stones were naturally brought by
					numerous teams of draught-animals every day. Now
					one of the mules who had assisted gallantly in the
					work, but had now been discharged because of old
					age, used to go down every day to the Ceramicus
					and meet the beasts which brought the stones,
					turning back with them and trotting along by their
					side, as though to encourage and cheer them on.
					So the people of Athens, admiring its enterprise,
					gave orders for it to be maintained at the public
					expense, voting it free meals, as though to an athlete
					who had succumbed to old age.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Cato Maior</hi>, v. 3 (339 a-b). Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 49, agrees in the main with Plutarch's account; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> vi. 24 (577 b 34), says merely that a public decree was passed forbidding bakers to drive the creature away from their trays. He adds that the mule was 80 years old and is followed by Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 175.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There is probably a lacuna before this chapter.</note> Therefore those who deny that there is any
					kind of justice owed to animals<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 999 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; 964 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> by us must be
					conceded to be right so far as marine and deep-sea
					creatures<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> additional sources cited by Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 43.</note> are concerned ; for these are completely
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.385"/>
					
					lacking in amiability, apathetic, and devoid of all
					sweetness of disposition. And well did Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xvi. 34.</note> say
					<quote rend="blockquote">The gray-green sea bore you,</quote>
					with reference to a man regarded as uncivilized and
					unsociable, implying that the sea produces nothing
					friendly or gentle. But a man who would use such
					speech in regard to land animals is himself cruel and
					brutal. Or perhaps you will not admit that there was
					a bond of justice between Lysimachus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 821 a; the companion and successor of Alexander (<hi rend="italics">c.</hi> 360-281 b.c.). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 143; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 25; and ii. 40 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> vi. 29), of eagles. It may be conjectured that ii. 40 was derived from an original in which <foreign lang="greek">a)etw=n</foreign> was confused with <foreign lang="greek">kunw=n</foreign>, as <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and the
					Hyrcanian dog which alone stood guard by his
					corpse and, when his body was cremated, rushed into
					the flames and hurled itself upon him.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Similar stories in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 40.</note> The same is
					reported to have been done by the eagle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Dog</q> and <q direct="unspecified">eagle</q> are again confused; but the <q direct="unspecified">hovering</q> is here decisive. (<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Wilamowitz, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, lxiii, p. 380.) The dog reappears in Pollux, v. 42 (where it is King Pyrrhus), an eagle in a similar tale in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 18, while Pyrrhus is the name of a dog in Pliny, viii. 144.</note> which was
					kept by Pyrrhus, not the king, but a certain private
					citizen ; when he died, it kept vigil by his body ; at
					the funeral it hovered about the bier and finally
					folded its wings, settled on the pyre and was consumed with its master's body,
				</p>
            <p>
					The elephant of King Porus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, lx. 13 (699 b-c), with Ziegler's references <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
               </note> when he was wounded
					in the battle against Alexander, gently and solicitously pulled out with its trunk many<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Each one of the spears</q> in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>.</note> of the javelins
					sticking in its master. Though it was in a sad state
					itself, it did not give up until it perceived that the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.387"/>
					
					king had lost much blood and was slipping off; then,
					fearing that he would fall, it gently kneeled and
					afforded its master a painless glide.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Other stories of humane elephants in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 46; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Bucephalas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 154; Gellius, <hi rend="italics">Noctes Atticae</hi>, v. 2; and see the parallels collected by Sternbach, <hi rend="italics">Wiener Studien</hi>, xvi, pp. 17 f. The story is omitted by Plutarch in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander.</hi>
               </note> unsaddled would permit his groom to
					mount him ; but when he was all decked out in his
					royal accoutrements and collars, he would let no one
					approach except Alexander himself. If any others
					tried to come near, he would charge at them loudly
					neighing and rear and trample any of them who
					were not quick enough to rush far away and escape.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>I am not unaware that you will think that my
					examples are rather a hodge-podge ; but it is not
					easy to find naturally clever animals doing anything
					which illustrates merely one of their virtues. Their
					probity, rather, is revealed in their love of offspring
					and their cleverness in their nobility ; then, too,
					their craftiness and intelligence is inseparable from
					their ardour and courage. Those, nevertheless, who
					are intent on classifying and defining each separate
					occasion will find that dogs give the impression of a
					mind that is at once civil and superior when they
					turn away from those who sit on the ground - which
					is presumably referred to in the lines<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, xiv. 30 f.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 146; Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 24; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, ii. 3. 6 (1380 a 24).</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The dogs barked and rushed up, but wise Odysseus
					</l>
                  <l>Cunningly crouched; the staff slipped from his hand;</l>
               </quote>
					for dogs cease attacking those who have thrown
					themselves down and taken on an attitude that
					resembles humility.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 48, of the lion.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.389"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					They relate further that the champion of the
					Indian dogs, one greatly admired by Alexander,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There are nearly as many emendations of this phrase as there have been scholars interested in Plutarch's text. Van Herwerden's version, as having the liveliest sense, has been preferred. It is by no means certain, however, though supported by Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 1; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 149; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Pollux, v. 43-44 and the parallels cited by Bethe <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi> See also Aelian, iv. 19 and Diodorus, xvii. 94.</note>
					when a stag was let loose and a boar and a bear, lay
					quiet and still and disregarded them ; but when a
					lion appeared, it sprang up at once to prepare for
					the fray, showing clearly that it chose to match itself
					with the lion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 149 f., adds the elephant as a worthy match.</note> and scorned all the others.
				</p>
            <p>
					Hounds that hunt hares, if they themselves kill
					them, enjoy pulling them to pieces<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">So <q direct="unspecified">break up</q>; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cynegetica</hi>, vii. 9.</note> and eagerly lap
					up the blood ; but if, as frequently happens, a hare
					in desperation exhausts all its breath in a final sprint
					and expires, the hounds, when they come upon it
					dead, will not touch it at all, but stand there wagging
					their tails, as much as to say that they do not strive
					for food, but for victory and the honour of winning.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>There are many examples of cunning, but I
					shall dismiss foxes and wolves<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Pythians</hi>, ii. 84; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cynegetica</hi>, iii. 266.</note> and the tricks of
					crane and daw (for they are obvious), and shall take
					for my witness Thales,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Omitted in Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>, not without reason. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 42.</note> the most ancient of the Wise
					Men,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the <hi rend="italics">Septem Sapientium Convivium</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 146 b ff.).</note> not the least of whose claims to admiration,
					they say, was his getting the better of a mule by a
					trick. For one of the mules that were used to carry
					salt, on entering a river, accidentally stumbled and,
					since the salt melted away, it was free of its burden
					when it got up. It recognized the cause of this and
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.391"/>
					
					bore it in mind. The result was that every time it
					crossed the river, it would deliberately lower itself
					and wet the bags, crouching and bending first to
					one side, then to the other. When Thales heard of
					this, he gave orders to fill the bags with wool and
					sponges instead of salt and to drive the mule laden
					in this manner. So when it played its customary
					trick and soaked its burden with water, it came to
					know that its cunning was unprofitable and thereafter
					was so attentive and cautious in crossing the river
					that the water never touched the slightest portion
					of its burden even by accident.
				</p>
            <p>
					Partridges<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 992 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 494 e and the references there; add Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 103; Philo, 35 (p. 117) (probably referring to partridges, though the Latin version reads <hi rend="italics">palumbae</hi>); Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 39; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 16; xi. 38; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> 613 b 31.</note> exhibit another piece of cunning, combined with affection for their young. They teach
					their fledglings, who are not yet able to fly, to lie on
					their backs when they are pursued and to keep above
					them as a screen some piece of turf or rubbish. The
					mothers meanwhile lure the hunters in another
					direction and divert attention to themselves, fluttering along at their feet and rising only briefly until,
					by making it seem that they are on the point of
					being captured, they draw them far away from their
					young.
				</p>
            <p>
					When hares<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xiii. 11; vi. 47.</note> return for repose, they put to sleep
					their leverets in quite different places, often as much
					as a hundred feet apart, so that, if man or dog comes
					near, they shall not all be simultaneously in danger.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.393"/>
					
					The hares themselves run to and fro and leave tracks
					in many places, but last of all with a great leap they
					leave their traces far behind, and so to bed.
				</p>
            <p>
					The she-bear, just prior to the state called hibernation,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 3; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 126 f.; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> iii. 173 (L.C.L.).</note> before she becomes quite torpid and heavy
					and finds it difficult to move, cleans out her Iair and,
					when about to enter, approaches it as lightly and
					inconspicuously as possible, treading on tiptoe, then
					turns around and backs into the den.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These precautions seem to have been successful (though <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the implications of Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 128), since Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 17, 600 b 6 f.) says that <q direct="unspecified">either no one (or very few)</q> has ever caught a pregnant bear. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 95 and Amm. Marc. xxii. 15. 22, of the hippopotamus entering a field backwards.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Hinds are inclined to bear their young beside a
					public road where carnivorous animals do not come<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 5, 611 a 17) notes that highways were shunned by wild animals because they feared men. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 35 and Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> ii. 207 (L.C.L.).</note>;
					and stags, when they observe that they have grown
					heavy by reason of their fat and surplus flesh, vanish
					and preserve themselves by hiding when they do not
					trust to their heels.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 113; [Aristotle], <hi rend="italics">De Mir. Ausc.</hi> 5; <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> 611 a 23.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The way in which hedgehogs defend and guard
					themselves has occasioned the proverb<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Shorey on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 423 e (L.C.L.); Leutsch and Schneidewin, <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi Graeci</hi>, i, p. 147, Zenobius, v. 68; attributed by Zenobius to Archilochus (Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica</hi>, i, p. 241, frag. 103; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi>, ii, p. 174, frag. 118) and to Homer. Zenobius also quotes five lines from Ion, of which the last two are Plutarch's next quotation.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">The fox knows many tricks, but the hedgehog one big one;</quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.395"/>
					
					for when the fox approaches, as Ion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 739; frag. 38, verses 4 f. (see the preceding note).</note> says, it,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Curling its spiny body in a coil,
					</l>
                  <l>Lies still, impregnable to touch or bite.</l>
               </quote>
					But the provision that the hedgehog makes for its
					young is even more ingenious. When autumn comes,
					it creeps under the vines and with its paws shakes
					down to the ground grapes from the bunches and,
					having rolled about in them, gets up with them
					attached to its quills. Once when I was a child I
					saw one, like a creeping or walking bunch of grapes!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The mss. add an unnecessary explanation: <q direct="unspecified">so covered with fruit was it as it walked.</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 133; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 10; <hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi> vi. 169.</note>
					Then it goes down into its hole and delivers the load
					to its young for them to enjoy and draw rations from.
					Their lair has two openings, one facing the south,
					the other the north ; when they perceive that the
					wind will change, like good skippers who shift sail,
					they block up the entrance which lies to the wind and
					open the other.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 979 a <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 b 4 ff.); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 133; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> viii. 138, of squirrels. On animals who predict the weather see Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xviii. 361-364.</note> And a man in Cyzicus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>) says Byzantium (and see <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, 979 b).</note> observing
					this acquired a reputation for being able to predict
					unaided which way the wind would blow.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Elephants, as Juba<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iii, p. 474; Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der griech. Hist.</hi> iii, pp. 146 f., frag. 51 a, 53; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 24; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 15; vi. 61; and see the criticism in 977 d-e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. On the mutual assistance of elephants see Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Vita Apoll.</hi> ii. 16.</note> declares, exhibit a social
					capacity joined with intelligence. Hunters dig pits
					for them, covering them with slender twigs and
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.397"/>
					
					light rubbish; when, accordingly, any elephant of a
					number travelling together falls in, the others bring
					wood and stones and throw them in to fili up the
					excavation so that their comrade can easily get out.
					He also relates that, without any instruction, elephants pray to the gods, purifying themselves in
					the sea<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 1 f.; Dio Cassius, xxxix. 38. 5.</note> and, when the sun<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The moon in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iv. 10, but the sun in vii. 44; of tigers in Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Vita Apoll.</hi> ii. 28.</note> rises, worshipping it
					by raising their trunks, as if they were hands of
					supplication. For this reason they are the animal
					most loved of the gods, as Ptolemy Philopator<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 44: Ptolemy IV (<hi rend="italics">c.</hi> 244-205 b.c.), who reigned 221-205. The decisive defeat of Antiochus III was at Raphia in 217. For the gods loving elephants see Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 2; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> has
					testified ; for when he had vanquished Antiochus
					and wished to honour the gods in a really striking
					way, among many other offerings to commemorate
					his victory in battle, he sacrificed four elephants.
					Thereafter, since he had dreams by night in which
					the deity angrily threatened him because of that
					strange sacrifice, he employed many rites of appeasement and set up as a votive offering four bronze
					elephants to match those he had slaughtered.
				</p>
            <p>
					Social usages are to be found no less among lions.
					For young lions take along with them to the hunt the
					old and slow; when the latter are tired out, they rest
					and wait, while the young lions hunt on. When they
					have taken anything, they summon the others by a
					roaring like the bleat of a calf; the old ones hear it
					at once and come to partake in common of the prey.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 1.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>The loves of some animals are wild and furious,
					while others have a refinement which is not far from
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.399"/>
					
					human and an intercourse conducted with much
					grace. Such was the elephant which at Alexandria
					played the rival to Aristophanes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 38 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> vii. 43); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 13.</note> the grammarian.
					They were, in fact, in love with the same flower-girl;
					nor was the elephant's love the less manifest: as he
					passed by the market, he always brought her fruit
					and stood beside her for a long time and would insert
					his trunk, like a hand,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> ii. 524 for additional authorities.</note> within her garments and
					gently caress her fair breasts.
				</p>
            <p>
					The serpent that fell in love with an Aetolian
					woman<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Told somewhat differently, and of a Jewish woman, in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 17.</note> used to visit her at night and slip under
					some part of her body next the skin and coil about
					her without doing her any harm at all, either intentional or accidental ; but always at daybreak it
					was decent enough to glide away. And this it did
					constantly until the kinsmen of the woman removed
					her to a house at some distance. The serpent did
					not come to her for three or four nights ; but all
					the time, we may suppose, it was going about in
					search of her and missing its goal. At last, when it
					had somehow found her with difficulty, it embraced
					her, not with that former gentleness it had used, but
					rather more roughly, its coils binding her hands to
					her body, and with the end of its tail it lashed the
					calves of her legs, displaying a light and tender anger
					that had in it more indulgence than punishment.
				</p>
            <p>
					As for the goose in Aegium that loved a boy and
					the ram that set his heart on Glauce<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Also a goose in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 51. Both stories are in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> v. 29 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> i. 6; viii. 11); for Glauce see also Gow's note on Theocritus, iv. 31.</note> the harp-player,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.401"/>
					
					since these are famous tales and I rather
					imagine you have had enough of such to spoil your
					appetite for more,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">More in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xii. 37; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> I omit them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>As for starlings<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Gellius, <hi rend="italics">Noctes Atticae</hi>, xiii. 21. 25; Alciphron, <hi rend="italics">Epp.</hi> iii. 30. 1; Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Vita Apoll.</hi> i. 7; vi. 36; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> and crows and parrots which
					learn to talk and afford their teachers so malleable
					and imitative a vocal current to train and discipline,
					they seem to me to be champions and advocates of
					the other animals in their ability to learn, instructing
					us in some measure that they too are endowed both
					with rational utterance<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the <foreign lang="greek">lo/gos proforiko/s</foreign> see, <hi rend="italics">e.g., Mor.</hi> 777 b-c.</note> and with articulate voice ;
					for which reason it is quite ridiculous to admit a
					comparison of them with creatures who have not
					enough voice even to howl or groan.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> iv. 9 (535 b 14 ff.).</note> And what
					music, what grace do we not find in the natural, untaught warbling of birds ! To this the most eloquent
					and musical of our poets bear witness<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>, Bacchylides, iii. 97; <hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi> vii. 414.</note> when they
					compare their sweetest songs and poems to the singing of swans and nightingales. Now since there is
					more reason in teaching than in learning, we must
					yield assent to Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> iv. 19 (535 b 17); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> ix. 1 (608 a 18); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 40.</note> when he says that animals
					do teach: a nightingale, in fact, has been observed
					instructing her young how to sing. A further proof
					that supports him is the fact that birds which have
					been taken young from the nest and bred apart from
					their mothers sing the worse for it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 992 b-c <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; for the birds
					that are bred with their mothers are taught and
					learn, not for pay or glory, but for the joy of rivalling
					each other in song and because they cherish the
					beautiful in their utterance rather than the useful.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.403"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					On this subject I have a story to tell you which I
					heard myself from many Greeks and Romans who
					were eye-witnesses. A certain barber at Rome had
					his shop directly opposite the precinct which they
					call the Market of the Greeks.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Graecostadium</hi> (see Platner and Ashby, <hi rend="italics">A Topographical Dictionary of Rome, s.v.</hi>) or <hi rend="italics">Forum Graecorum</hi>.</note> He bred up a
					wonderful prodigy of a jay<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 2 (p. 191. 8, ed. Nauck); Gow on Theocritus, v. 136; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 13 (615 b 19 f.). See also the talking birds in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 118-134.</note> with a huge range of
					tones and expressions, which could reproduce the
					phrases of human speech and the cries of beasts and
					the sound of instruments - under no compulsion, but
					making it a rule and a point of honour to let nothing
					go unrepeated or unimitated. Now it happened that
					a certain rich man was buried from that quarter to
					the blast of many trumpets and, as is customary,
					there was a halt in front of the barber-shop while
					the trumpeters, who were applauded and encored,
					played for a long time. From that day on the jay
					was speechless and mute, not letting out even a
					peep to request the necessities of life ; so those
					who habitually passed the place and had formerly
					wondered at her voice, were now even more astonished at her silence. Some suspected that she
					had been poisoned by rival bird-trainers, but most
					conjectured that the trumpets had blasted her hearing and that her voice had been simultaneously
					extinguished. Now neither of these guesses was
					correct: it was self-discipline, it would seem, and her
					talent for mimicry that had sought an inner retreat
					as she refitted and prepared her voice like a musical
					instrument. For suddenly her mimicry returned
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.405"/>
					
					and there blazed forth none of those old familiar
					imitations, but only the music of the trumpets,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is also the accomplishment of a homonymous bird in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 19.</note>
					reproduced with its exact sequences and every
					change of pitch and rhythm and tone. I conclude,
					as I said before,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 973 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that self-instruction implies more
					reason in animals than does readiness to learn from
					others.
				</p>
            <p>
					Still, I believe that I should not pass over one
					example at least of a dog's learning,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the bears that acted a farce in <hi rend="italics">Script. Hist. Aug., Vita Car.</hi> xix. 2.</note> of which I
					myself was a spectator at Rome. The dog appeared
					in a pantomime with a dramatic plot and many
					characters and conformed in its acting at all points
					with the acts and reactions required by the text.
					In particular, they experimented on it with a drug
					that was really soporific, but supposed in the story
					to be deadly. The dog took the bread that was
					supposedly drugged, swallowed it, and a little later
					appeared to shiver and stagger and nod until it
					finally sprawled out and lay there like a corpse,
					letting itself be dragged and hauled about, as the
					plot of the play prescribed. But when it recognized
					from the words and action that the time had come,
					at first it began to stir slightly, as though recovering
					from a profound sleep, and lifted its head and looked
					about. Then to the amazement of the spectators it
					got up and proceeded to the right person and fawned
					on him with joy and pleasure so that everyone, and
					even Caesar himself (for the aged Vespasian<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Vespasian became emperor in a.d. 69 when he was 60 years old and died ten years later, so that this incident can be dated only within the decade.</note> was
					present in the Theatre of Marcellus), was much
					moved.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.407"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On this chapter see T. Weidlich, <hi rend="italics">Die Sympathie in Altertum</hi>, p. 42.</note> Yet perhaps it is ridiculous for us to make a
					parade of animals distinguished for learning when
					Democritus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> ii, p. 173, frag. 154; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bailey on Lucretius, v. 1379 (vol. iii, p. 1540 of his edition); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xii. 16.</note> declares that we have been their pupils
					in matters of fundamental importance : of the spider
					in weaving and mending, of the swallow in homebuilding, of the sweet-voiced swan and nightingale<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 973 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					in our imitation of their song. Further, of the three
					divisions of medicine,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As given here, cure by (1) drugs, (2) diet, (3) surgery. There are five divisions in Diogenes Laertius, iii. 85; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> we can discern in animals a
					generous portion of each ; for it is not cure by drugs
					alone of wrhich they make use. After devouring a
					serpent tortoises<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 918 c, 991 e; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 12 and Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 24); of wounded partridges and storks and doves in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> v. 46 (Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> 612 a 32).</note> take a dessert of marjoram, and
					weasels<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 28).</note> of rue. Dogs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 6); add Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Outlines of Pyrrhonism</hi>, i. 71.</note> purge themselves when
					bilious by a certain kind of grass. The snake<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xx. 254. Other details of snake diet in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 4.</note>
					sharpens and restores its fading sight with fennel.
					When the she-bear comes forth from her lair,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As in 971 d-e <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> the
					first thing she eats is wild arum<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably the Adam-and-Eve (<hi rend="italics">Arum maculatum</hi> L.), since the Italian arum (<hi rend="italics">Arum italicum</hi> Mill.) was cultivated. See Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 17 (600 b 11); ix. 6 (611 b 34); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 129; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 3. Oribasius (<hi rend="italics">Coll. Med.</hi> iii. 24. 5) characterizes wild arum as an aperient.</note>; for its acridity
					opens her gut which has become constricted. At
					other times, when she suffers from nausea,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">When she has swallowed the fruit of the mandrake, according to Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 101.</note> she
					resorts to anthills and sits, holding out her tongue
					all running and juicy with sweet liquor until it is
					covered with ants ; these she swallows<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 4 (594 b 9); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 3; Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> i. 57.</note> and is
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.409"/>
					
					alleviated. The Egyptians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 35; vii. 45; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 97; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Deorum</hi>, ii. 50.</note> declare that they have
					observed and imitated the ibis' clyster-like purging
					of herself with brine ; and the priests make use of
					water from which an ibis has drunk to purify themselves ; for if the water is tainted or unhealthy in
					any way, the ibis will not approach it.
				</p>
            <p>
					Then, too, some beasts cure themselves by a short
					fast, like wolves<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iv. 15; see the hippopotamus in Amm. Marc. xx. 15. 23.</note> and lions who, when they are surfeited with flesh, lie still for a while, basking in the
					sun. And they say a tigress, if a kid is given her,
					will keep fasting for two days without eating ; on
					the third, she grows hungry and asks for some
					other food. She will even pull her cage to pieces,
					but will not touch the kid which she has now come
					to regard as a fellow-boarder and room mate.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of a leopard in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 2. This account seems to indicate a lacuna in our text explaining why the tigress did not eat the kid in the first place: <q direct="unspecified">because she had already had enough to eat.</q>
               </note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Yet again, they relate that elephants employ
					surgery : they do, in fact, bring aid to the wounded<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For an example see the anecdote of Porus in 970 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 977 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Juba, frag. 52 (Jacoby); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 45.</note>
					by easily and harmlessly drawing out spears and
					javelins and arrows without any laceration of the
					flesh. And Cretan goats,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 991 f <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Philo, 38 (p. 119); Vergil, <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi> xii. 415; Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 3); Pease, <hi rend="italics">Melanges Marouzeau</hi>, 1948, p. 472.</note> when they eat dittany,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cretan dittany (<hi rend="italics">Origanum dictamnus</hi> L.); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xx. 156.</note>
					easily expel arrows from their bodies and so have
					presented an easy lesson for women with child to
					take to heart, that the herb has an abortive property<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pease, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 471.</note>;
					for there is nothing except dittany that the goats,
					when they are wounded, rush to search for.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.411"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>These matters, though wonderful, are less surprising than are those creatures which have cognition
					of number and can count,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iv. 53.</note> as do the cattle near Susa.
					At that place they irrigate the royal park with water
					raised in buckets by wheels, and the number of
					bucketfuls is prescribed. For each cow raises one
					hundred bucketfuls each day, and more you could
					not get from her, even if you wanted to use force.
					In fact, they often try to add to the number to see ;
					but the cow balks and will not continue when once
					she has delivered her quota, so accurately does she
					compute and remember the sum, as Ctesias<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 53 b, ed. Gilmore (p. 196); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 1.</note> of
					Cnidus has related.
				</p>
            <p>
					The Libyans laugh at the Egyptians for telling a
					fabulous tale about the oryx,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> ii. 446.</note> that it lets out a cry<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A sneeze, according to Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ii. 107; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 8.</note>
					at that very day and hour when the star rises that
					they call Sothis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 359 d, 376 a.</note> which we call the Dog Star or
					Sirius. At any rate, when this star rises flush with
					the sun, practically all the goats turn about and look
					toward the east; and this is the most certain sign
					of its return and agrees most exactly with the tables
					of mathematical calculation.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">They watched for the first sight of Sirius before daybreak about June 20; the date shifted in the Egyptian calendar.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>But that my discourse may add its finishing
					touch and terminate, let me <q direct="unspecified">make the move from
						the sacred line</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 783 b with Fowler's note; also 1116 e; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 739 a; and Gow on Theocritus, vi. 18. The meaning is probably something like <q direct="unspecified">let me play my last trump,</q> or <q direct="unspecified">commit my last reserve.</q>
               </note> and say a few words about the
					divine inspiration and the mantic power of animals.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.413"/>
					
					It is, in fact, no small or ignoble division of divination,
					but a great and very ancient one, which takes its
					name from birds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ornithoscopy or ornithomancy (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Leviticus xix. 26); Latin <hi rend="italics">augurium, auspicium</hi>. See also Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 244 d, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 85 b.</note>; for their quickness of apprehension and their habit of responding to any manifestation, so easily are they diverted, serves as an instrument for the god, who directs their movements, their
					calls or cries, and their formations which are sometimes contrary, sometimes favouring, as winds are ;
					so that he uses some birds to cut short, others to speed
					enterprises and inceptions to the destined end. It is
					for this reason that Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps <hi rend="italics">Ion</hi>, 159; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 405 d for the phrase.</note> calls birds in general
					<q direct="unspecified">heralds of the gods</q>; and, in particular, Socrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 85 b.</note>
					says that he considers himself a <q direct="unspecified">fellow-slave of the
						swans.</q> So again, among monarchs Pyrrhus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 184 d; <hi rend="italics">Life of Pyrrhus</hi>, x. 1 (388 a-b); <hi rend="italics">Life of Aristides</hi>, vi. 2 (322 a); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 45.</note> liked
					to be called an Eagle and Antiochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 184 a. This Antiochus was not, strictly speaking, a king, but the younger son of Antiochus II.</note> a Hawk. But
					when we deride, or rail at, stupid and ignorant
					people we call them <q direct="unspecified">fish.</q> Really, we can produce
					cases by the thousand of signs and portents manifested to us by the gods through creatures of land
					and air, but not one such can the advocate for
					aquatic creatures name.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This charge is answered in 976 c <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> No, they are all <q direct="unspecified">deaf
						and blind<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the fragment of Epicharmus cited above in 961 a.</note>
               </q> so far as foreseeing anything goes, and
					so have been cast aside into the godless and titanic<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 701 b-c (and Shorey, <hi rend="italics">What Plato Said</hi>, p. 629); 942 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> and Cherniss' note (<hi rend="italics">Class. Phil.</hi> xlvi, 1951, p. 157, n. 95); see also 996 c <hi rend="italics">c infra</hi> with the note.</note>
					region, as into a Limbo of the Unblessed, where the
					rational and intelligent part of the soul has been
					extinguished. Having, however, only a last remnant
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.415"/>
					
					of sensation that is clogged with mud and deluged
					with water, they seem to be at their last gasp rather
					than alive.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Heracleon. Raise your brows, dear Phaedimus, and rouse yourself to defend us the sea folk, the
					island-dwellers ! This bout of argument has become
					no child's play, but a hard-fought contest, a debate
					which lacks only the actual bar and platform.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, it is so realistic that one might imagine oneself in the lawcourts or the public assembly.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Phaedimus. Not so, Heracleon, but an ambush
					laid with malice aforethought has been disclosed.
					While we are still tipsy and soused from yesterday's
					bout, this gentleman, as you see, has attacked us
					with premeditation, cold sober. Yet there can be
					no begging off. Devotee of Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 272, ed. Turyn (228 Schroeder, 215 Bowra); <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 783 b; Leutsch and Schneidewin, <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi Graeci</hi>, i, p. 44; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 421 d.</note> though I am, I
					do not want to be addressed with the quotation
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To excuse oneself when combat is offered
					</l>
                  <l>Has consigned valour to deep obscurity;</l>
               </quote>
					for we have much leisure<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps merely a passing allusion to some such passage as Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 258 e rather than, as Bernardakis thought, a quotation from an unknown tragic poet (Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 869, Adesp. 138).</note>; and it is not our discourse
					that will be idle, but our dogs and horses, our nets and
					seines of all kinds, for a truce is granted for to-day
					because of our argument to every creature both on
					land and sea. Yet do not fear : I shall use it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Either <q direct="unspecified">our leisure</q> or <q direct="unspecified">the truce,</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the holiday Plutarch has given his pupils (see the Introduction to this essay).</note> with
					moderation, introducing no opinions of philosophers
					or Egyptian fables or unattested tales of Indians or
					Libyans. But those facts that may be observed
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.417"/>
					
					everywhere and have as witnesses the men who
					exploit the sea and acquire their credit from direct
					observation, of these I shall present a few. Yet there
					is nothing to impede illustrations drawn from land
					animals : the land is wide open for investigation by
					the senses. The sea, on the other hand, grants us
					but a few dubious glimpses. She draws a veil over
					the birth and growth, the attacks and reciprocal
					defences, of most of her denizens. Among these
					there are no few feats of intelligence and memory
					and community spirit that remain unknown to us
					and so obstruct our argument. Then too, land
					animals<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 1.</note> by reason of their close relationship and
					their cohabitation have to some extent been imbued
					with human manners ; they have the advantage of
					their breeding and teaching and imitation, which
					sweetens all their bitterness and sullenness, like
					fresh water mixed with brine, while their lack of
					understanding and dullness are roused to life by
					human contacts. Whereas the life of sea creatures,
					being set apart by mighty bounds from intercourse
					with men and having nothing adventitious or acquired from human usage, is peculiar to itself, indigenous, and uncontaminated by foreign ways, not
					by distinction of Nature, but of location. For their
					Nature is such as to welcome and retain such instruction as reaches them. This it is that renders many
					eels tractable, like those that are called sacred in
					Arethusa<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 4.</note>; and in many places there are fish which
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.419"/>
					
					will respond to their own names,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 193: Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xii. 30.</note> as the story goes
					of Crassus'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Crassus</hi>, but derived from the same source as Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 4; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the remarks in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, vii. 4 (82 a). The story is also recounted in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 89 a, 811 a; Macrobius, <hi rend="italics">Sat.</hi> iii. 15. 4; Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 5. Hortensius, too, wept bitterly at the death of his pet moray (Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 172).</note> moray, upon the death of which he
					wept. And once when Domitius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">L. Domitius Ahenobarbus, consul in 54 b.c., a bitter political opponent of Crassus and the Triumvirate.</note> said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Isn't
						it true that you wept when a moray died ?</q> he
					answered, <q direct="unspecified">Isn't it true that you buried three wives
						and didn't weep ?</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The priests' crocodiles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>
               </note> not only recognize the
					voice of those who summon them and allow themselves to be handled, but open their mouths to let
					their teeth be cleaned by hand and wiped with
					towels. Recently our excellent Philinus came back
					from a trip to Egypt and told us that he had seen in
					Antaeopolis an old woman sleeping on a low bed
					beside a crocodile, which was stretched out beside
					her in a perfectly decorous way.
				</p>
            <p>
					They have long been telling the tale that when
					King Ptolemy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>, does not know which Ptolemy is meant; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the story of Apis and Germanicus in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 185; Amm. Marc. xxii. 14. 8.</note> summoned the sacred crocodile and
					it would not heed him or obey in spite of his entreaties
					and requests, it seemed to the priests an omen of his
					death, which came about not long after ; whence it
					appears that the race of water creatures is not wholly
					unendowed with your precious gift of divination.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 975 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 55.</note>
					Indeed, I have heard that near Sura,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 5; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xxxii. 17.</note> a village in
					Lycia between Phellus and Myra, men sit and watch
					the gyrations and flights and pursuits of fish and
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.421"/>
					
					divine from them by a professional and rational
					system, as others do with birds.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>But let these examples suffice to show that sea
					animals are not entirely unrelated to us or cut off
					from human fellowship. Of their uncontaminated
					and native intelligence their caution is strong evidence. For nothing that swims and does not merely
					stick or cling to rocks is easily taken or captured
					without trouble by man as are asses by wolves, bees
					by bee-eaters,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A bird: Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 13 (615 b 25); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> v. 11; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 99.</note> cicadas by swallows, and snakes by
					deer, which easily attract them.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 6; v. 48.</note> This, in fact, is
					why deer are called <hi rend="italics">elaphoi</hi>, not from their swiftness,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Elaphrotes</hi>.</note>
					but from their power of attracting snakes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Helxis opheos</hi>, a fantastic etymology. Neither derivation is correct, <hi rend="italics">elaphos</hi> being related to the Lithuanian <hi rend="italics">elnis</hi>, <q direct="unspecified">deer.</q> For the references see Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> ii. 234.</note> So too
					the ram draws the wolf by stamping and they say
					that very many creatures, and particularly apes, are
					attracted to the panther by their pleasure in its
					scent.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 13); add Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 6; v. 40.</note> But in practically all sea-creatures any sensation is suspect and evokes an intelligently inspired
					defensive reaction against attack, so that fishing has
					been rendered no simple or trivial task, but needs all
					manner of implements and clever and deceitful tricks
					to use against the fish.
				</p>
            <p>
					This is perfectly clear from ready examples: no
					one wants to have an angler s rod too thick, though
					it needs elasticity to withstand the thrashing of such
					fish as are caught; men select, rather, a slender rod
					so that it may not cast a broad shadow and arouse
					suspicion.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Gow on Theocritus, xxi. 10.</note> In the next place, they do not thicken
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.423"/>
					
					the line with many plies when they attach the loop
					and do not make it rough ; for this, too, betrays the
					lure to the fish. They also contrive that the hairs
					which form the leader shall be as white as possible ;
					for in this way they are less conspicuous in the sea
					because of the similarity of colour. The remark of
					the Poet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxiv. 80-82.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Like lead she<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Iris going to visit Thetis.</note> sank into the great sea depths,
					</l>
                  <l>Like lead infixed in hora of rustic ox
					</l>
                  <l>Which brings destruction to the ravenous fish -</l>
               </quote>
					some misunderstand this and imagine that the
					ancients used ox-hair for their lines, alleging that
					<hi rend="italics">keras</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It means, of course, <q direct="unspecified">horn</q> as above in Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxiv. 81.</note> means <q direct="unspecified">hair</q> and for this reason <hi rend="italics">keirasthai</hi>
					means <q direct="unspecified">to have one's hair cut</q> and <hi rend="italics">koura</hi> is a <q direct="unspecified">haircut</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or <q direct="unspecified">lock of hair.</q>
               </note> and the <hi rend="italics">keroplastes</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Horn-fashioner,</q> so called from the horn-like bunching together of the hair: see the scholia on <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxiv. 81.</note> in Archilochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi>, ii, p. 126, frag. 57; Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anth. Lyrica</hi>, i, p. 228, frag. 59. See the note on 967 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> is one
					who is fond of trimming and beautifying the hair.
					But this is not so : they use horse-hair which they
					take from males, for mares by wetting the hair with
					their urine make it weak.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 915 f - 916 a.</note> Aristarchus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not Aristotle, as the mss. read. See Platt, <hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> v. 255.</note> declares
					that there is nothing erudite or subtle in these lines ;
					the fact is that a small piece of horn was attached
					to the line in front of the hook, since the fish, when
					they are confronted by anything else, chew the line
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.425"/>
					
					in two.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">The section of horn was put around the line. It was therefore a tube. It was in front of the hook as one held it in his hand and attached it to the line. It was therefore at the hook end of the leader. Its hardness prevented the line from being severed. Its neutral coloration prevented the fish from being frightened off. Note that Oppian (<hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 147) comments on the use of a hook with an abnormally long shank for the same purpose</q> (Andrews).</note> They use rounded hooks<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A prototype of the Sobey hook.</note> to catch mullets
					and bonitos, whose mouths are small<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (621 a 19); Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 144.</note>; for they are
					wary of a broader hook. Often, indeed, the mullet
					suspects even a rounded hook and swims around it,
					flipping the bait with its tail and snatching up bits
					it has dislodged ; or if it cannot do this, it closes its
					mouth and purses it up and with the tips of its lips
					nibbles away at the bait.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 145; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 524 ff.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The sea-bass is braver than your elephant<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 974 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>: it is
					not from another, but from himself without assistance,
					that he extracts the barb when he is caught by the
					hook ; he swings his head from side to side to widen
					the wound, enduring the pain of tearing his flesh until
					he can throw off the hook.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 40, of the tunny; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> 39 f. and Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 128 ff., of the bass.</note> The fox-shark<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch seems here to have confused this fish with the so-called <hi rend="italics">scolopendra</hi> (of which he writes correctly in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 567 b; see also Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 424). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (621 a 11); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 12; <hi rend="italics">Varia Hist.</hi> i. 5; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 144; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 145. <q direct="unspecified">There are fish (but not sharks) which can disgorge their stomachs and swallow them again. Note that hasty reading of Aristotle <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi> could easily cause this misstatement</q> (Andrews).</note> does not
					often approach the hook and shuns the lure ; but if
					he is caught, he immediately turns himself inside
					out, for by reason of the elasticity and flexibility of
					his body he can naturally shift and twist it about, so
					that when he is inside out, the hook falls away.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Now the examples I have given indicate intelligence and an ingenious, subtle use of it for opportune
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.427"/>
					
					profit; but there are others that display, in combination with understanding, a social sense and mutual
					affection, as is the case with the barbier<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <hi rend="italics">anthias</hi> of the above passage is probably the Mediterranean barbier, <hi rend="italics">Serranus anthias</hi> C.V., although elsewhere it is sometimes obviously a much larger fish of uncertain identity. On the identification <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> vi. 17 (570 b 19); <hi rend="italics">Glossary of Greek Fishes, s.v.</hi>; Mair, introd. to his ed. of Oppian, pp. liii-lxi; Marx, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, i. 2375-2377; ii. 2415; Schmid, <hi rend="italics">Philologus</hi>, Suppb. xi, 1907-1910, p. 273; Brands, <hi rend="italics">Grieksche Diernamen</hi>, pp. 147 f.; Cotte, <hi rend="italics">Possions et animaux aquatiques au temps de Pline</hi>, pp. 69-73; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">Le Vocabulaire des animaux marins en latin classique</hi>, pp. 5-7. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also 981 e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and the
					parrot-fish. For if one parrot-fish swallows the hook,
					the others present swarm upon the line and nibble it
					away ; and the same fish, when any of their kind
					have fallen into the net, give them their tails from
					outside ; when they eagerly fix their teeth in these,
					the others pull on them and bring them through in
					tow.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On this story <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 4; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xxxii. 11; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> 9 ff.; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iv. 40 ff. Note also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> v. 22, on mice.</note> And barbiers are even more strenuous in
					rescuing their fellows : getting under the line with
					their backs, they erect their sharp spines and try to
					saw the line through and cut if off with the rough
					edge.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 182; xxxii. 13; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> 45 ff.; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 321 ff.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Yet we know of no land animal that has the courage
					to assist another in danger - not bear or boar or
					lioness or panther. True it is that in the arena those
					of the same kind draw close together and huddle in a
					circle ; yet they have neither knowledge nor desire
					to help each other. Instead, each one flees to get
					as far as possible from a wounded or dying fellow.
					That tale of the elephants<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 972 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der griech. Hist.</hi> iii, p. 146, frag. 51 b. On the community spirit of elephants see also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> v. 49; vi. 61; vii. 15; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> carrying brushwood to
					the pits and giving their fallen comrade a ramp to
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.429"/>
					
					mount is monstrous and far-fetched and dictates, as
					it were, that we are to believe it on a king's prescription - that is, on the writs of Juba.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Juba was king of Mauretania (25 b.c. - <hi rend="italics">c.</hi> a.d. 23).</note> Suppose it to
					be true : it merely proves that many sea creatures
					are in no way inferior in community spirit and intelligence to the wisest of the land animals. As for their
					sociability, I shall soon make a special plea on that
					topic.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Now fishermen, observing that most fish evade
					the striking of the hook by such countermoves as
					wrestlers use, resorted, like the Persians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, vi. 31; iii. 149; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi> 698 d; Fraenkel on Aesch. <hi rend="italics">Agam.</hi> 358. On kinds of nets see Mair, L.C.L. <hi rend="italics">Oppian</hi>, pp. xl ff.</note> to force
					and used the dragnet, since for those caught in it
					there could be no escape with the help of reason or
					cleverness. For mullet and rainbow-wrasse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Coris iulis</hi> Gth. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 3 (610 b 7); <hi rend="italics">A Glossary of Greek Fishes</hi>, p. 91; Schmid, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 292; Brands, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 157; Cotte, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 59-60; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 52.</note> are
					caught by casting-nets and round nets, as are also
					the bream<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In particular, probably <hi rend="italics">Pagellus mormyrus</hi> C.V. On the identification <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> vi. 7 (570 b 20); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 161; Cotte, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 105-107; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 65-66.</note> and the sargue<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In particular, probably <hi rend="italics">Sargus culgaris</hi> Geoff. On the identification <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> v. 9 (543 a 7); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 227-228; Cotte, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 105-107; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 99, 107-108; Keller, <hi rend="italics">Die antike Tierwelt</hi>, ii, p. 370; Gossen-Steier, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, Second Series, ii. 365.</note> and the goby<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A term mostly for the black goby, <hi rend="italics">Gobius niger</hi> L., the most common Mediterranean species. On the identification <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 14 (598 a 12); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 137-139; Gossen, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, Second Series, ii. 794-796.</note> and the
					sea-bass. The so-called net fish, that is surmullet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The red or plain surmullet, <hi rend="italics">Mullus barbatus</hi> L., and the striped or common surmullet, <hi rend="italics">Mullus surmuletus</hi> L. On this fish <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cotte, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 98-101; Keller, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> ii, pp. 364 f.; Prechac, <hi rend="italics">Revue d. Et. Lat.</hi> xiv (1936), pp. 102-105; xvii (1939), p. 279; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 68 f.; Schmid, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 310-312; Steier, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, xvi. 496-503; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 264-268; Andrews, <hi rend="italics">Class. Weekly</hi>, xlii (1949), pp. 186-188.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.431"/>
					
					and gilthead<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Chrysophrys aurata</hi> C.V., called gilthead from the golden band that runs from eye to eye. On this fish <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Wellmann, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, iii. 2517-2518; Keller, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> ii, pp. 369 ff.; <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, vii. 1578; Schmid, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 297-298; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 292-294; Cotte, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 73-74; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 80-81.</note> and sculpin,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Scorpaena scrofa</hi>, L. and <hi rend="italics">S. porcus</hi> L. On this fish <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cotte, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 111-113; Saint-Denis, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> pp. 103-104; Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> v. 9 (543 a 7); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 245 f.</note> are caught in seines by
					trawling : accordingly it was quite correct for Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, v. 487; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Platt, <hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> v, p. 255; Fraenkel, Aesch. <hi rend="italics">Agam.</hi> ii, p. 190.</note>
					to call this kind of net a <q direct="unspecified">catch-all.</q> Codfish,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Principally the hake and rockling, <hi rend="italics">Phycis</hi> sp. and <hi rend="italics">Motella</hi> sp. Not to be confused with <foreign lang="greek">galeo/s</foreign>, a general term for sharks and dogfishes. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Andrews, <hi rend="italics">Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences</hi>, xxxix (1949), pp. 1-16.</note> like
					bass,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 121 ff.</note> have devices even against these. For when
					the bass perceives that the trawl is approaching, it
					forces the mud apart and hammers a hollow in the
					bottom. When it has made room enough to allow
					the net to overrun it, it thrusts itself in and waits
					until the danger is past.
				</p>
            <p>
					Now when the dolphin is caught and perceives
					itself to be trapped in the net, it bides its time, not
					at all disturbed but well pleased, for it feasts without
					stint on the fish that have been gathered with no
					trouble to itself. But as soon as it comes near the
					shore, it bites its way through the net and makes its
					escape. Yet if it should not get away in time, on
					the first occasion it suffers no harm : the fishermen
					merely sew rushes to its crest and let it go. But if it
					is taken a second time, they recognize it from the
					seam and punish it with a beating. This, however,
					rarely occurs : most dolphins are grateful for their
					pardon in the first instance and take care to do no
					harm in the future.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the alliance of dolphins and fisherman see Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 8; xi. 12; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 29 ff.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Further, among the many examples of wariness,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.433"/>
					
					precaution, or evasion, we must not pass over that
					of the cuttlefish<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (621 b 28); Athenaeus, 323 d-e; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 84; Horace, <hi rend="italics">Sat.</hi> i. 4. 100; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 34; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 156.</note>: it has the so-called <hi rend="italics">mytis</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> iv. 1 (524 b 15); <hi rend="italics">De Part. Animal.</hi> iv. 5 (679 a 1).</note> beside
					the neck<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Under the mouth,</q> says Aristotle.</note> full of black liquid, which they call <q direct="unspecified">ink.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Tholos</hi>, <q direct="unspecified">mud,</q> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">turbidity.</q>
               </note>
					When it is come upon, it discharges the liquid to the
					purpose that the sea shall be inked out and create
					darkness around it while it slips through and eludes
					the fisherman's gaze. In this it imitates Homer's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For example, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, v. 345.</note>
					gods who often <q direct="unspecified">in a dark cloud</q> snatch up and
					smuggle away those whom they are pleased to save.
					But enough of this.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>As for cleverness in attacking and catching
					prey, we may perceive subtle examples of it in many
					different species. The starfish,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">[Aristotle], <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> v. 15 (548 a 7 f.), an interpolated passage; nor can we be certain that it was known to Plutarch. See also Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 181.</note> for example, knowing that everything with which it comes in contact
					dissolves and liquefies, offers its body and is indifferent
					to the contact of those that overtake or meet it.
					You know, of course, the property of the torpedo<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or <q direct="unspecified">electric ray</q> or <q direct="unspecified">crampfish</q>: for the ancient references see Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ic. 37 (620 b 12-23); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 169-172; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 36; ix. 14; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 143; Mair, L.C.L. <hi rend="italics">Oppian</hi>, p. lxix, and on <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 56; iii. 149; Philo, 30 (p. 115); Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 48; Boulenger, <hi rend="italics">World Natural History</hi>, pp. 189 f.</note>:
					not only does it paralyse all those who touch it, but
					even through the net creates a heavy numbness in
					the hands of the trawlers. And some who have
					experimented further with it report that if it is
					washed ashore alive and you pour water on it from
					above, you may perceive the numbness mounting to
					the hand and dulling your sense of touch by way of
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.435"/>
					
					the water which, so it seems, suffers a change and is
					first infected.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the <q direct="unspecified">upward infection</q> of the basilisk, Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 78.</note> Having, therefore, an innate sense
					of this power, it never makes a frontal attack or endangers itself; rather, it swims in a circle around its
					prey and discharges its shocks as if they were darts,
					thus poisoning first the water, then through the
					water the creature which can neither defend itself
					nor escape, being held fast as if by chains and frozen
					stiff.
				</p>
            <p>
					The so-called fisherman<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The fishing-frog, <hi rend="italics">Lophius piscatorius</hi> L.: Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (620 b 12); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 144; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 86; Str&ouml;mberg, <hi rend="italics">Gr. Fischnamen</hi>, pp. 122 f.</note> is known to many ; he
					gets his name from his actions. Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (622 a 1); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> iv. 1 (524 a 3), iv. 6 (531 b 6); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 83 ff.; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 122.</note> says that
					the cuttlefish also makes use of this stratagem : he
					lets down, like a fishing line, a tentacle from his neck
					which is naturally designed to extend to a great
					length when it is released, or to be drawn to him
					when it is pulled in. So when he espies a little fish,
					he gives it the feeler to bite and then by degrees
					imperceptibly draws it back toward himself until the
					prey attached to the arm is within reach of his
					mouth.
				</p>
            <p>
					As for the octopus' change of colour,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (622 a 8); Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 233. Athenaeus, 316 f, 317 f, 513 d; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 87; Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 25, 50; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Hist.</hi> i. 1; and Wellmann, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, li, p. 40.</note> Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 43 Schroeder, 208 Turyn, 235 Bowra (p. 516, ed. Sandys L.C.L.); <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 916 c and Turyn's references.</note> has
					made it celebrated in the words
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To all the cities to which you resort
					</l>
                  <l>Bring a mind like the changing skin of the seabeast;</l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.437"/>
					
					and Theognis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">215-216; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 96 f, 916 c. There are many textual variants, but none alters the sense.</note> likewise :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Be minded like the octopus' hue:
					</l>
                  <l>The colour of its rock will meet the view.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or <quote rend="blockquote">
                           <quote>Keep a mind as multicoloured as the octopus, </quote>
                        </quote>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                           <quote>With the rock whereon it sits homologous</quote>
                        </quote> (Andrews).</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The chameleon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ii. 11 (503 b 2); Ogle on <hi rend="italics">De Part. Animal.</hi> iv. 11 (692 a 22 ff.). See also Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal</hi>, iv. 33; and <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 122 for the chameleon's exclusive diet of <q direct="unspecified">air</q>; <foreign lang="la">nec alio quam aeris alimento</foreign>.</note> to be sure, is metachromatic, but
					not from any design or desire to conceal itself; it
					changes colour uselessly from fear, being naturally
					timid and cowardly. And this is consistent with the
					abundance of air in it, as Theophrastus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 189 Wimmer (p. 225); Aristotle says merely, <q direct="unspecified">The change takes place when it is inflated by air.</q>
               </note> says ; for
					nearly the whole body of the creature is occupied by
					its lungs,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Which confirms Karsch's emendation of Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ii. 11 (503 b 21); for Theophrastus and Plutarch must have had <q direct="unspecified">lungs</q> and not <q direct="unspecified">membranes</q> in their text of Aristotle.</note> which shows it to be full of air and for
					this reason easily moved to change colour. But this
					same action on the part of the octopus is not an
					emotional response, but a deliberate change, since it
					uses this device to escape what it fears and to capture
					what it feeds on : by this deceit it can both seize the
					latter, which does not try to escape, and avoid the
					former, which proceeds on its way. Now the story
					that it eats its own tentacles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 965 e <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> and the note; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 87; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 1059 e, 1098 e, <hi rend="italics">Comm. in Hes.</hi> fr. 53 (Bernardakis, vol. VII, p. 77).</note> is a lie, but it is true
					that it fears the moray and the conger. It is, in fact,
					maltreated by them; for it cannot do them harm,
					since they slip from its grasp. On the other hand,
					when the crawfish<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <hi rend="italics">langouste</hi> as distinguished from the <hi rend="italics">homard</hi>; see Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 32; ix. 25; x. 38; Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 2 (590 b 16); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 102 ff.; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 185; Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 92.</note> has once got them in its grasp,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.439"/>
					
					it wins the victory easily, for smoothness is no aid
					against roughness ; yet when the octopus has once
					thrust its tentacles inside the crawfish, the latter
					succumbs. And so Nature has created this cycle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The octopus is worsted by the moray and the conger, which in turn are defeated by the crawfish, which (to complete the cycle) becomes the octopus' prey. The whole engagement is graphically portrayed in Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 253-418. For Nature's battle see, <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>, Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 79.</note>
					and succession of mutual pursuit and flight as a field
					for the exercise and competitive practice of adroitness
					and intelligence.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>We have, to be sure, heard Aristotimus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 972 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>. Valentine Rose, curiously enough, emended to Aristotle (see <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6, 612 b 4) and included this passage in Frag. 342. See further Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 226.</note>
					telling us about the hedgehog's foreknowledge of
					the winds ; and our friend also admired the V-shaped
					flight of cranes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 967 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> I can produce no hedgehog of
					Cyzicus or Byzantium,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps he is learnedly confuting Aristotimus (972 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>) by drawing on Aristotle.</note> but instead the whole body
					of sea-hedgehogs,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the sea-urchin, regarded by the ancients as a sort of marine counterpart of the hedgehog because of the similar spines.</note> which, when they perceive that
					storm and surf are coming, ballast themselves with
					little stones<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 967 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, of bees.</note> in order that they may not be capsized
					by reason of their lightness or be swept away by the
					swell, but may remain fixed in position through the
					weight of their little rocks.
				</p>
            <p>
					Again, the cranes' change of flight against the wind<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 967 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					is not merely the action of one species : all fish generally have the same notion and always swim against
					wave and current, taking care that a blast from the
					rear does not fold back their scales and expose and
					roughen their bodies. For this reason they always
					present the prow of their bodies to the waves, for in
					that way head first they cleave the sea, which depresses
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.441"/>
					
					their gills and, flowing smoothly over the
					surface, keeps down, instead of ruffling up, the bristling skin. Now this, as I have said, is common to all
					fish except the sturgeon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably usually the common sturgeon, <hi rend="italics">Acipenser sturio</hi>: see Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 62 f.; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 28, speaks of it as a rare and sacred fish; see 981 d <hi rend="italics">infra. Cf.</hi> Milton's <q direct="unspecified">Ellops drear</q> (<hi rend="italics">P.L.</hi> x. 525).</note> which, they say, swims
					with wind and tide and does not fear the harrowing
					of its scales since the overlaps are not in the direction
					of the tail.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>The tunny<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 42; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 13 (598 b 25 f.).</note> is so sensitive to equinox and
					solstice that it teaches even men themselves without
					the need of astronomical tables ; for wherever it
					may be when the winter solstice overtakes it, in that
					same place it stands and stays until the equinox. As
					for that clever device of the crane,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 967 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> the grasping of
					the stone by night so that if it falls, she may awake
					from sleep - how much cleverer, my friend, is the
					artifice of the dolphin, for whom it is illicit to stand
					still or to cease from motion.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Reiske may have been right in suspecting a trimeter of unknown origin in these words.</note> For its nature is to
					be ever active<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xi. 22. The dolphin even nurses its young while in motion; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 235; and <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ii. 13 (504 b 21 ff.).</note>: the termination of its life and its
					movement is one and the same. When it needs
					sleep, it rises to the surface of the sea and allows
					itself to sink deeper and deeper on its back, lulled
					to rest by the swinging motion of the ground swell<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As it were, the cradle of the deep.</note>
					until it touches the bottom. Thus roused, it goes
					whizzing up, and when it reaches the surface, again
					goes slack, devising for itself a kind of rest combined
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.443"/>
					
					with motion.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But see Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 210, where it is reported that dolphins <q direct="unspecified">are actually heard snoring.</q>
               </note> And they say that tunnies do the
					same thing for the same reason.
				</p>
            <p>
					Having just a moment ago given you an account
					of the tunny's mathematical foreknowledge of the
					reversal of the sun, of which Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 13 (598 b 25).</note> is a witness,
					I beg you to hear the tale of their arithmetical
					learning. But first, I swear, I must mention their
					knowledge of optics, of which Aeschylus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 96, frag. 308; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 42.</note> seems not
					to have been ignorant, for these are his words :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Squinting the left eye like a tunny fish.</quote>
					They seem, indeed, to have poor sight in one eye.
					And it is for this reason that when they enter the
					Black Sea, they hug one bank on the right, and
					the other<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 13 (598 b 19 ff.); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 84; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 50. They follow the opposite shore when returning, thus keeping the same eye towards the land.</note> when they are going out, it being very
					prudent and sagacious of them always to entrust
					the protection of themselves to the better eye. Now
					since they apparently need arithmetic to preserve
					their consociation and affection for each other, they
					have attained such perfection of learning that, since
					they take great pleasure in feeding and schooling
					together,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 2 (610 b 1 f.); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> xv. 3, 5.</note> they always form the school into a cube,
					making it an altogether solid figure with a surface
					of six equal plane sides ; then they swim on their
					way preserving their formation, a square that faces
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.445"/>
					
					both ways. Certainly a hooer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A watcher posted on a tall mast to warn fishermen of the approach of a shoal and to give a count. See Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> iv. 10 (537 a 19); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 87; Gow on Theocritus, iii. 26; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> iii. 638. Accounts of the ancient tunny fishery are given by Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 84-88; Pace, <hi rend="italics">Atti R. Ac. Archeologia Napoli</hi>, N.S. xii (1931/2), pp. 326 ff.; and Rhode, <hi rend="italics">Jahrb. f. class. Phil.</hi>, Suppb. xviii (1900), pp. 1-78. An account of the ancient and the modern tunny fishery is given by Parona, <hi rend="italics">R. Comitato Talasso-grafico Italiano, Memoria</hi>, no. 68, 1919.</note> watching for tunnies
					who counts the exact number on the surface at once
					makes known the total number of the shoal, since he
					knows that the depth is equal one to one with the
					breadth and the length.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Schooling together has also given the bonitos
					their name of <hi rend="italics">amia</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Similarly, Athenaeus (vii. 278 a; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 324 d) quotes Aristotle as defining <hi rend="italics">amia</hi> as <q direct="unspecified">not solitary,</q> 
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> running in schools. Actually the term is probably foreign, perhaps of Egyptian origin (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 13).</note> and I think this is true of year-old tunnies as well.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch takes <hi rend="italics">pelamys</hi> to be compound of <hi rend="italics">pelein</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">to be</q> and <hi rend="italics">hama</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">with,</q> with references to their running in schools. It was also anciently presumed to be a compound of <hi rend="italics">pelos</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">mud</q> and <hi rend="italics">myein</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">be shut in or enclosed,</q> because of its habit of hiding in the mud (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> 599 b 18; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 47). Most scholars now regard it as a loan from the Mediterranean substratum, although Thompson (<hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 198) suggests that it may be of Asiatic origin, since it was used especially of the tunny in the Black Sea.</note> As for the other kinds which
					are observed to live in shoals in mutual society, it
					is impossible to state their number. Let us rather,
					therefore, proceed to examine those that have a
					special partnership, that is, symbiosis. One of these
					is the pinna-guard,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 202.</note> over which Chrysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, p. 208, frag. 729 b (Athenaeus, 89 d). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also fragments 729, 729 a, and 730. On the place of the pinna in Chrysippus' theology see A. S. Pease, <hi rend="italics">Harv. Theol. Rev.</hi> xxxiv (1941), p. 177.</note> spilled
					a very great deal of ink ; indeed it has a reserved
					seat in every single book of his, whether ethical or
					physical.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 1035 b, 1038 b.</note> Chrysippus has obviously not investigated
					the sponge-guard<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A little crab that lives in the hollow chambers of a sponge. See Thompson, <hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>
               </note>; otherwise he could hardly have
					left it out. Now the pinna-guard is a crab-like
					creature, so they say, who lives with the pinna<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On this bivalve shellfish see Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 200; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> ii. 186.</note> and
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.447"/>
					
					sits in front of the shell guarding the entrance. It
					allows the pinna to remain wide open and agape until
					one of the little fish that are their prey gets within ;
					then the guard nips the flesh of the pinna and slips
					inside ; the shell is closed and together they feast
					on the imprisoned prey.
				</p>
            <p>
					The sponge is governed by a little creature not
					resembling a crab, but much like a spider.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nevertheless, it is a crab, <hi rend="italics">Typton spongicola</hi>.</note> Now the
					sponge<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 16; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> v. 16 (548 a 28 ff.); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 148; Antigonus, 83; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 656; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 249-250.</note> is no lifeless, insensitive, bloodless thing ;
					though it clings to the rocks,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> W. Jaeger, <hi rend="italics">Nemesios con Emesa</hi>, p. 116, n. 1.</note> as many other animals
					do, it has a peculiar movement outward and inward
					which needs, as it were, admonition and supervision.
					In any case it is loose in texture and its pores are
					relaxed because of its sloth and dullness ; but when
					anything edible enters, the guard gives the signal,
					and it closes up and consumes the prey. Even more,
					if a man approaches or touches it, informed by the
					scratching of the guard, it shudders, as it were, and
					so closes itself up by stiffening and contracting that
					it is not an easy, but a very difficult, matter for the
					hunters to undercut it.
				</p>
            <p>
					The purplefish<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> v. 15 (546 b 19 ff.) quoted in Athenaeus, 88 d - 89 a; <hi rend="italics">De Gen. Animal.</hi> iii. 11 (761 b 32 ff.); Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 209-218.</note> lives in colonies which build up a
					comb together, like bees. In this the species is said
					to propagate ; they catch at edible bits of oystergreen and seaweed that stick to shells, and furnish
					each other with a sort of periodic rotating banquet,
					as they feed one after another in series.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>And why should anyone be surprised at the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.449"/>
					
					community life of these when the most unsociable
					and brutal of all creatures bred in river, lake, or sea,
					the crocodile, shows himself marvellously proficient
					at partnership and goodwill in his dealings with the
					Egyptian plover?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Herodotus, ii. 68; Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 6 (612 a 20); <hi rend="italics">Glossary of Greek Birds</hi>, p. 287. Some authorities such as Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 90 and Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> iii. 415 ff., state that the ichneumon attacks the crocodile while its mouth is open for the plover's operations. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Boulenger, <hi rend="italics">Animal Mysteries</hi>, p. 104, for a modern factual account (see also his <hi rend="italics">World Natural History</hi>, p. 146).</note> The plover is a bird of the
					swamps and river banks and it guards the crocodile,
					not supplying its own food, but as a boarder making
					a meal of the crocodile's scraps.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 11; xii. 15; [Aristotle], <hi rend="italics">Mir. Ausc.</hi> 7.</note> Now when it
					perceives that, during the crocodile's sleep, the ichneumon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 966 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> is planning to attack it, smearing itself
					with mud like an athlete dusting himself for the
					fray, the bird awakes the crocodile by crying and
					pecking at it. And the crocodile becomes so gentle
					with it that it will open its mouth and let it in and is
					pleased that the bird quietly pecks out, with its bill,
					bits of flesh which are caught in the teeth and cleans
					them up. When it is now satisfied and wants to close
					its mouth, it tilts its snout upward as an indication
					of its desire and does not let it down until the plover,
					at once perceiving the intention, flies out.
				</p>
            <p>
					The so-called <q direct="unspecified">guide</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The name and the activity are appropriate to the pilot-fish (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 62 ff.; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 13), but the description fits rather one of the globe-fishes, such as <hi rend="italics">Diodon hystrix</hi> (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 75). See also Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 186; xi. 165, who calls it the sea mouse. <q direct="unspecified">Actually the . . . pilot is just a &lsquo;sponger&rsquo; and accompanies the shoals . . . with the sole object of picking up such crumbs as may fall from their table.</q> Boulenger, <hi rend="italics">Animal Mysteries</hi>, p. 105.</note> is a small fish, in size and
					shape like a goby ; but by reason of the roughness
					of its scales it is said to resemble a ruffled bird. It
					always accompanies one of the great whales, swimming in front of it and directing its course so that it
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.451"/>
					
					may not go aground in shallows or be cut off in some
					lagoon or strait from which exit may be difficult.
					The whale follows it, as a ship obeys the helm, changing course with great docility. And whatever else,
					creature or boat or stone, it embraces in its gaping
					jaws is at once destroyed and goes to its ruin completely engulfed ; but that little fish it knows and
					receives inside its mouth as in a haven. While the
					fish sleeps within, the whale remains motionless and
					lies by ; but when it comes out again, the beast
					accompanies it and does not depart from it day or
					night; or, if it does, it gets lost and wanders at
					random. Many, indeed, have been cast up on the
					land and perished, being, as it were, without a
					pilot.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the whole passage in Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 70-349 on the destruction of whales.</note> We, in fact, were witnesses of such a mishap
					near Anticyra not long ago ; and they relate that
					some time ago, when a whale came aground not far
					from Boulis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the unknown Bouna or Bounae of the mss. C. O. M&uuml;ller (<hi rend="italics">Orchomenos</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">2</hi>, p. 482) proposed Boulis, a town to the east of Anticyra on the Phocian Gulf.</note> and rotted, a plague ensued.
				</p>
            <p>
					Is it, then, justifiable to compare with these
					associations and companionships those friendships
					which Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 354, ed. V. Rose.</note> says exist between foxes and snakes
					because of their common hostility to the eagle ; or
					those between bustards and horses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 28 and Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Cyn.</hi> ii. 406.</note> because the
					former like to approach and pick over the dung ?
					As for me, I perceive even in ants or bees no such
					concern for each other. It is true that every one of
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.453"/>
					
					them promotes the common task, yet none of them
					has any interest in or regard for his fellow individually.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>And we shall observe this difference even more
					clearly when we turn our attention to the oldest and
					most important of social institutions and duties, those
					concerned with generation and procreation. Now in
					the first place those fish that inhabit a sea that borders
					on lagoons or receives rivers resort to these when
					they are ready to deposit then; eggs, seeking the tranquillity and smoothness of fresh water, since calm is a
					good midwife. Besides, lagoons and rivers are devoid
					of sea monsters,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 981 e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 71.</note> so that the eggs and fry may survive. This is the reason why the Black Sea is most
					favoured for spawning by very many fish. It breeds
					no large sea beasts at all except an infrequent seal
					and a small dolphin<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> viii. 13 (598 b 2); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 49 f.; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iv. 9; ix. 59; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> i. 599; Amm. Marc. xxii. 8. 47; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 54, 281.</note>; besides, the influx of rivers
					 - and those which empty into the Black Sea are
					numerous and very large - creates a gentle blend
					conducive to the production of offspring. The most
					wonderful tale is told about the <hi rend="italics">anthias</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the identity see note on 977 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> which
					Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xvi. 407.</note> calls <q direct="unspecified">Sacred Fish.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Gow on Theocritus, frag. 3. Homer does not call the <hi rend="italics">anthias</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">Sacred Fish,</q> but merely alludes to a sacred fish; and in later times several were so regarded.</note> Yet some think that
					<q direct="unspecified">sacred</q> means <q direct="unspecified">important,</q> just as we call the
					important bone <hi rend="italics">os sacrum</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The last bone of the spine.</note> and epilepsy, an important
					disease, the sacred disease.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> [Hippocrates], <hi rend="italics">De Morbo Sacro</hi> (L.C.L., vol. ii, pp. 138 ff.); Herodotus, iii. 33; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 85 a-b.</note> Others interpret it in
					the ordinary sense as meaning <q direct="unspecified">dedicated</q> or <q direct="unspecified">consecrated.</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.12.p.455"/>
					
					Eratosthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Powell, <hi rend="italics">Collectanea Alexandrina</hi>, p. 60, frag. 12. 3; Hiller, frag. 14 (p. 31).</note> seems to refer to the
					gilthead<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> i. 169.</note> when he says
					<quote rend="blockquote">Swift courser golden-browed, the sacred fish.</quote>
					Many say that this is the sturgeon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 979 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>. They are wrong, for while both the gilthead and the sturgeon were sacred fish, the description points clearly to the gilthead.</note> which is rare and
					hard to catch, though it is often seen off the coast of
					Pamphylia. If any ever do succeed in catching it,
					they put on wreaths themselves and wreathe their
					boats ; and, as they sail past, they are welcomed
					and honoured with shouts and applause. But most
					authorities hold that it is the <hi rend="italics">anthias</hi> that is and
					is called <q direct="unspecified">sacred,</q> for wherever this fish appears
					there are no sea monsters. Sponge-fishers<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 950 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 153; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, p. 15.</note> may dive
					in confidence and fish may spawn without fear, as
					though they had a guarantor of their immunity.
					The reason for this is a puzzle : whether the monsters
					avoid the <hi rend="italics">anthias</hi> as elephants do a pig<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 38; viii. 28; xvi. 36; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>.</note> and lions a
					cock,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> iii. 31; vi. 22; viii. 28; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> or whether there are indications of places free
					from monsters, which the fish comes to know and
					frequents, being an intelligent creature with a good
					memory.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>Then again the care of the young is shared
					by both parents : the males do not eat their own
					young, but stand by the spawn to guard the eggs,
					as Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 37 (621 a 21 ff.); <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 93.</note> relates. Some follow the female and
					sprinkle the eggs gradually with milt, for otherwise
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.457"/>
					
					the spawn will not grow, but remains imperfect and
					undeveloped. In particular the wrasse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <hi rend="italics">phycis</hi> is almost certainly one of the wrasses, probably in particular <hi rend="italics">Crenilabrus pavo</hi> C.V. See Mair, L.C.L. <hi rend="italics">Oppian</hi>, p. liii; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 276-278; Andrews, <hi rend="italics">Journal of The Washington Academy of Sciences</hi>, xxxix (1949), pp. 12-14.</note> makes a
					sort of nest of seaweed, envelops the spawn in it,
					and shelters it from the waves.
				</p>
            <p>
					The affection of the dogfish<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 494 c; 730 e; Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> vi. 10 (565 a 22 ff., b 2 ff.); <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 39-42; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> i. 734.</note> for its young is not
					inferior in warmth and kindliness to that of any of the
					tamest animals ; for they lay the egg, then sustain
					and carry the newlyhatehed young, not without, but
					within themselves, as if from a second birth. When
					the young grow larger, the parents let them out and
					teach them to swim close by ; then again they collect
					them through their mouths and allow their bodies
					to be used as dwelling-places, affording at once room
					and board and sanctuary until the young become
					strong enough to shift for themselves.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> 565 b 24) reports that some dogfish brought forth their young by the mouth and took them therein again. Athenaeus (vii. 294 e) says that the dogfish took the young just hatched into its mouth and emitted them again. Plutarch has a somewhat garbled version of this presumed process, blended with data on the parental care of dolphins (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plin. <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> ix. 21)</q> (Andrews).</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Wonderful also is the care of the tortoise for the
					birth and preservation of her young. To bear them
					she comes out of the sea to the shore near at hand ;
					but since she is unable to incubate the eggs or to
					remain on dry land for long, she deposits them on
					the strand and heaps over them the smoothest and
					softest part of the sand. When she has buried and
					concealed them securely,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 37; contrast the forgetful lizard (x. 187).</note> some say that she scratches
					and scribbles the place with her feet, making it easy
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.459"/>
					
					for her to recognize ; others affirm that it is because
					she has been turned on her back by the male that
					she leaves peculiar marks and impressions about the
					place. But what is more remarkable than this, she
					waits for the fortieth day<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Hist.</hi> i. 6.</note> (for that is the number
					required to develop and hatch out the eggs) and then
					approaches. And each tortoise recognizes her own
					treasure and opens it more joyously and eagerly
					than a man does a deposit of gold.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>The accounts given of the crocodile are similar
					in other respects, but the animal's ability to estimate
					the right place goes beyond man's power to guess
					or calculate the cause. Hence they affirm that this
					creature's foreknowledge is divine and not rational.
					For neither to a greater or a less distance, but just
					so far as the Nile will spread that season and cover
					the land in flood, just so far does she go to deposit
					her eggs, with such accuracy that any farmer finding
					the eggs may know himself and predict to others
					how far the river will advance.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> v. 52; and compare B. Evans, <hi rend="italics">The Natural History of Nonsense</hi>, p. 33.</note> And her purpose in
					being so exact is to prevent either herself or her
					eggs getting wet when she sits on them. When they
					are hatched, the one which, upon emerging, does not
					immediately seize in its mouth anything that comes
					along, fly or midge or worm or straw or plant, the
					mother tears to pieces and bites to death<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 3; contrast Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi>x. 10; Antigonus, 46, of the sea eagle; Lucan, ix. 902 ff., of the eagle. See also Julian, <hi rend="italics">Epistle</hi> 59 (383 c); 78 (418 d) with Wright's note (L.C.L. vol. iii, p. 259, n. 2).</note>; but those
					that are bold and active she loves and tends, thus
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.461"/>
					
					bestowing her affection by judgement, as the wisest
					of men think right, not by emotion.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apparently with reference to Theophrastus, frag. 74 (<hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 482 b).</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Furthermore, seals<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 9; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> i. 686 ff.; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 41.</note> too bear their young on dry
					land and little by little induce their offspring to try
					the sea, then quickly take them out again. This they
					do often at intervals until the young are conditioned
					in this way to feel confidence and enjoy life in the
					sea.
				</p>
            <p>
					Frogs in their coupling use a call, the so-called
					<hi rend="italics">ololygon</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Gow on Theocritus, vii. 139; Boulenger, <hi rend="italics">Animal Mysteries</hi>, pp. 67 f.</note> a cry of wooing and mating. When the
					male has thus attracted the female, they wait for the
					night together, for they cannot consort in the water
					and during the day they are afraid to do so on land;
					but when the darkness falls, they come out and
					embrace with impunity. On other occasions when
					their cry is shrill, it is because they expect rain.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 912 c-d; Aratus, <hi rend="italics">Phaenomena</hi>, 946 ff.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 19; ix. 13.</note>
					And this is among the surest of signs.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>But, dear Poseidon! What an absurd and
					ridiculous error I have almost fallen into : while I am
					spending my time on seals and frogs, I have neglected
					and omitted the wisest of sea creatures, the most
					beloved of the gods!<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As it is to Thetis: Virgil, <hi rend="italics">Georgics</hi>, i. 399.</note> For what nightingales are to
					be compared with the halcyon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary of Greek Birds, s.v.</hi>; Kraak, <hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi> (3rd series), vii. 142; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 89 ff.; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vii. 17; Gow on Theocritus, vii. 57; and the pleasant work <hi rend="italics">Halcyon</hi> found in mss. of Lucian and Plato.</note> for its love of sweet
					sound, or what swallows for its love of offspring, or
					what doves for its love of its mate, or what bees for
					its skill in construction ? What creature's procreation
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.463"/>
					
					and birth pangs has the god<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Poseidon.</note> so honoured ? For
					Leto's parturition,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the birth of Apollo and Artemis.</note> so they say, only one island<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Delos, the wandering island.</note> was
					made firm to receive her; but when the halcyon lays
					her eggs, about the time of the winter solstice, the
					god<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Poseidon.</note> brings the whole sea to rest, without a wave,
					without a swell. And this is the reason why there
					is no other creature that men love more. Thanks
					to her they sail the sea without a fear in the dead of
					winter for seven days and seven nights.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Halcyon Days (Suidas, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi>); Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> v. 8 (542 b 6 ff.); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 36; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xviii. 231; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> For the
					moment, journey by sea is safer for them than by
					land. If it is proper to speak briefly of her several
					virtues, she is so devoted to her mate that she keeps
					him company, not for a single season, but throughout
					the year. Yet it is not through wantonness that she
					admits him to her company, for she never consorts
					at all with any other male ; it is through friendship
					and affection, as with any lawful wife. When by
					reason of old age the male becomes too weak and
					sluggish to keep up with her, she takes the burden on
					herself, carries him and feeds him, never forsaking,
					never abandoning him ; but mounting him on her
					own shoulders, she conveys him everywhere she goes
					and looks after him, abiding with him until the end.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Alcman's famous lines: frag. 26 Edmonds (<hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, i, p. 72, L.C.L.), frag. 94 Diehl (<hi rend="italics">Anth. Lyrica</hi>, ii, p. 34); Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 23; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					As for love of her offspring and care for their preservation, as soon as she perceives herself to be
					pregnant, she applies herself to building the nest,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 494 a-b; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Historia Animal.</hi> ix. 13 (616 a 19 ff.); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ix. 17.</note>
					not making pats of mud or cementing it on walls and
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.465"/>
					
					roofs like the house-martin<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 966 d-e <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; nor does she use the
					activity of many different members of her body, as
					when the bee employs its whole frame to enter and
					open the wax, with all six feet pressing at the same
					time to fashion the whole mass into hexagonal cells,
					But the halcyon, having but one simple instrument,
					one piece of equipment, one tool - her bill and nothing
					else, co-operating with her industry and ingenuity - 
					what she contrives and constructs would be hard to
					believe without ocular evidence, seeing the object
					that she moulds - or rather the ship that she builds.
					Of many possible forms, this alone cannot be capsized<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristotle (<hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>), on the contrary, seems to say (though his text is corrupt; see Thompson <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>): <q direct="unspecified">The opening is small, just enough for a tiny entrance, so that even if the nest is upset, the sea does not enter.</q>
               </note> or even wet its cargo. She collects the spines
					of garfish<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Belone</hi> was usually a term for the garfish and the needlefish, neither of which has spines of any size. Thompson (<hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 31-32) rightly regards the meaning of <hi rend="italics">belone</hi> here as indeterminable. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 494 a, which is almost certainly mistranslated in the L.C.L. edition.</note> and binds and weaves them together,
					some straight, others transverse, as if she were
					thrusting woven threads through the warp, adding
					such bends and knots of one with another that a
					compact, rounded unit is formed, slightly prolate in
					shape, like a fisherman's weel. When it is finished,
					she brings and deposits it beside the surging waves,
					where the sea beats gently upon it and instructs her
					how to mend and strengthen whatever is not yet good
					and tight, as she observes it loosened by the blows.
					She so tautens and secures the joints that it is difficult
					even for stones or iron to break or pierce it. The
					proportions and shape of the hollow interior are as
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.467"/>
					
					admirable as anything about it; for it is so constructed as to admit herself only, while the entrance
					remains wholly hidden and invisible to others - with
					the result that not even a drop of water can get in.
					Now I presume that all of you have seen this nest;
					as for me, since I have often seen and touched it, it
					comes to my mind to chant the words
					<quote rend="blockquote">Once such a thing in Delos near Apollo's shrine<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, vi. 162. <q direct="unspecified">That there was some religious mystery associated with the so-called nest is indicated by the close of Plutarch's description.</q> (Thompson on Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">loc. cit.</hi>)</note>
               </quote>
					I saw, the Altar of Horn, celebrated as one of the
					Seven Wonders of the World<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xiv. 2. 5.</note> because it needs no
					glue or any other binding, but is joined and fastened
					together, made entirely of horns taken from the
					right side of the head.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Curiously enough, the <hi rend="italics">Life of Theseus</hi>, xxi. 2 (9 e) says the <q direct="unspecified">left side.</q>
               </note> Now may the god<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apollo. From this point on the text of the rest of this chapter is very bad and full of lacunae. The restorations adopted here are somewhat less than certain.</note> be propitious to me while I sing of the Sea Siren<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is not fulfilled and so is presumably an indication of another lacuna toward the end of Phaedimus' speech, the location of which we cannot even guess.</note> - and
					indeed, being both a musician and an islander, he
					should laugh good-naturedly at my opponents'
					scoffing questions. Why should he not be called a
					<q direct="unspecified">conger-slayer</q> or Artemis be termed a <q direct="unspecified">surmullet-slayer</q>?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 966 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> Since he well knows that Aphrodite,
					born of the sea, regards practically all sea creatures
					as sacred and related to herself and relishes the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.469"/>
					
					slaughter of none of them. In Leptis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Andrews suspects a confusion here and at <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 730 d with Lepidotonpolis on the Nile, not far below Thebes, apparently a focal point of a taboo on eating the bynni, allegedly due to its consumption of the private parts of Osiris when they were thrown into the river (<hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 358 b).</note> you know, the
					priests of Poseidon refrain entirely from any sea
					food, and those initiated into the mysteries at
					Eleusis hold the surmullet in veneration, while the
					priestess of Hera at Argos abstains from this fish to
					pay it honour. For surmullets are particularly good
					at killing and eating the sea-hare, which is lethal to
					man.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 45; ix. 51; xvi. 19; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 155; Philostratus, <hi rend="italics">Vita Apoll.</hi> vi. 32.</note> It is for this reason that surmullets possess
					this immunity, as being friendly and life-saving
					creatures.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>Furthermore, many of the Greeks have temples
					and altars to Artemis Dictynna<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As though <q direct="unspecified">Artemis of the Net</q>; see Callimachus, <hi rend="italics">Hymn</hi> iii. 198.</note> and Apollo Delphinios ; and that place which the god had chosen
					for himself the poet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Hymn to Apollo</hi>, iii. 393 ff. (as restored by van Herwerden). For Delphinian Apollo see lines 495 f.</note> says was settled by Cretans
					under the guidance of a dolphin. It was not, however,
					the god who changed his shape and swam in front of
					the expedition, as tellers of tales relate ; instead,
					he sent a dolphin to guide the men and bring them
					to Cirrha.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The port of Delphi.</note> They also relate that Soteles and Dionysius, the men sent by Ptolemy Soter<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 361 f; Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Histories</hi>, iv. 83-84.</note> to Sinope to
					bring back Serapis, were driven against their will by
					a violent wind out of their course beyond Malea,
					with the Peloponnesus on their right. When they
					were lost and discouraged, a dolphin appeared by the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.471"/>
					
					prow and, as it were, invited them to follow and led
					them into such parts as had safe roadsteads with but
					a gentle swell until, by conducting and escorting the
					vessel in this manner, it brought them to Cirrha.
					Whence it carne about that when they had offered
					thanksgiving for their safe landing, they carne to see
					that of the two statues they should take away the
					one of Pluto, but should merely take an impress of
					that of Persephone and leave it behind.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, in Sinope.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Well might the god be fond of the music-loving
					character of the dolphin,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 162 f; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xi. 137.</note> to which Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Page 597, ed. Sandys (L.C.L.); frag. 125, line 69-71 ed. Bowra (O.C.T.); frag. 222. 14-17, ed. Turyn. The quotation is found also in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 704 f - 705 a. The lines were partially recovered in <hi rend="italics">Oxyrhynchus Papyri</hi>, iii. 408 b (1903); for the critical difficulties see Turyn's edition.</note> likens
					himself, saying that he is roused
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Like a dolphin of the sea
					</l>
                  <l>Who on the waveless deep of ocean
					</l>
                  <l>Is moved by the lovely sound of flutes.</l>
               </quote>
					Yet it is even more likely that its affection for men<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> x. 24. For Dionysus and the pirate-dolphins see the seventh <hi rend="italics">Homeric Hymn</hi> and Frazer on Apollodorus, iii. 5. 3 (L.C.L., vol. i, p. 332).</note>
					renders it dear to the gods; for it is the only creature
					who loves man for his own sake.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">The hunting of dolphins is immoral</q>: Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 416 (see the whole passage).</note> Of the land animals,
					some avoid man altogether, others, the tamest kind,
					pay court for utilitarian reasons only to those who
					feed them, as do dogs and horses and elephants to
					their familiars. Martins take to houses to get what
					they need, darkness and a minimum of security, but
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.473"/>
					
					avoid and fear man as a dangerous wild beast.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 728 a; but see Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> i. 52; Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, i. 25. 8.</note> To
					the dolphin alone, beyond all others, nature has
					granted what the best philosophers seek : friendship
					for no advantage. Though it has no need at all of
					any man, yet it is a genial friend to all and has helped
					many. The story of Arion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herodotus, i. 24; Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 448. In <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 161 a ff. the story is told by an eye-witness at the banquet of the Seven Wise Men.</note> is familiar to everyone
					and widely known ; and you, my friend, opportunely
					put us in mind of the tale of Hesiod,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 969 e <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">But you failed to reach the end of the tale.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, ix. 56.</note>
               </quote>
					When you told of the dog, you should not have left
					out the dolphins, for the information of the dog that
					barked and rushed with a snarl on the murderers
					would have been meaningless if the dolphins had not
					taken up the corpse as it was floating on the sea near
					the Nemeon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The shrine of Zeus at Oeneon in Locris.</note> and zealously passed it from group
					to group until they put it ashore at Rhium and so
					made it clear that the man had been stabbed.
				</p>
            <p>
					Myrsilus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iv, p. 459; Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. griech. Hist.</hi> ii, frag. 12; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 163 b-d; Athenaeus, 466 c gives as his authority Anticleides.</note> of Lesbos tells the tale of Enalus the
					Aeolian who was in love with that daughter of
					Smintheus who, in accordance with the oracle of
					Amphitrite, was cast into the sea by the Penthilidae,
					whereupon Enalus himself leaped into the sea and
					was brought out safe on Lesbos by a dolphin.
				</p>
            <p>
					And the goodwill and friendship of the dolphin for
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.475"/>
					
					the lad of Iasus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 15 (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> viii. 11), tells the story in great detail and with several differences; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also the younger Pliny's famous letter (ix. 33) on the dolphin of Hippo and the vaguer accounts in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> ii. 6; Antigonus, 55; Philo, 67 (p. 132). Gulick on Athenaeus, 606 c-d collects the authorities; see also the dolphin stories in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 25 ff. and Mair on Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 458; Thompson, <hi rend="italics">Glossary</hi>, pp. 54 f. Iasus is a city in Ionian Caris on the gulf of the same name.</note> was thought by reason of its greatness to be true love. For it used to swim and play
					with him during the day, allowing itself to be touched;
					and when the boy mounted upon its back, it was not
					reluctant, but used to carry him with pleasure wherever he directed it to go, while all the inhabitants of
					Iasus flocked to the shore each time this happened.
					Once a violent storm of rain and hail occurred and the
					boy slipped off and was drowned. The dolphin took
					the body and threw both it and itself together on the
					land and would not leave until it too had died, thinking it right to share a death for which it imagined that
					it shared the responsibility. And in memory of this
					calamity the inhabitants of Iasus have minted their
					coins with the figure of a boy riding a dolphin.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story has a happier ending in one version found in Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 27: the dolphin dies, but Alexander the Great makes the boy head of the priesthood of Poseidon in Babylon.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					From this the wild tales about Coeranus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> viii. 3; Athenaeus, 606 e-f cites from Phylarchus, Book XII (Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. griech. Hist.</hi> i, p. 340). There are many other examples of dolphins rescuing people, such as the fragment of Euphorion in Page, <hi rend="italics">Greek Literary Papyri</hi>, i, p. 497 (L.C.L.).</note> gained
					credence. He was a Parian by birth who, at Byzantium, bought a draught of dolphins which had
					been caught in a net and were in danger of slaughter,
					and set them all free. A little later he was on a sea
					voyage in a penteconter, so they say, with fifty
					pirates aboard ; in the strait between Naxos and
					Paros the ship capsized and all the others were lost,
					while Coeranus, they relate, because a dolphin sped
					beneath him and buoyed him up, was put ashore at
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.477"/>
					
					Sicinus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An island south of Paros.</note> near a cave which is pointed out to this day
					and bears the name of Coeraneum.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi>, ii, p. 321 (L.C.L.).</note> It is on this
					man that Archilochus is said to have written the line
					<quote rend="blockquote">Out of fifty, kindly Poseidon left only Coeranus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> ii, p. 164; Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anth. Lyrica</hi>, i, p. 243. frag. 117.</note>
               </quote>
					When later he died, his relatives were burning the
					body near the sea when a large shoal of dolphins
					appeared off shore as though they were making it
					plain that they had come for the funeral, and they
					waited until it was completed.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the grief of dolphins see Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ix. 25, 33.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					That the shield of Odysseus had a dolphin emblazoned on it, Stesichorus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, ii, p. 66, frag. 71.</note> also has related ; and
					the Zacynthians perpetuate the reason for it, as
					Critheus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nothing whatever is known about this author, whose name may be given incorrectly in our mss.</note> testifies. For when Telemachus was a
					small boy, so they say, he fell into the deep inshore
					water and was saved by dolphins who came to his aid
					and swam with him to the beach ; and that was the
					reason why his father had a dolphin engraved on
					his ring and emblazoned on his shield, making this
					requital to the animal.
				</p>
            <p>
					Yet since I began by saying that I would not tell
					you any tall tales and since, without observing what
					I was up to, I have now, besides the dolphins, run
					aground on both Odysseus and Coeranus to a point
					beyond belief, I lay this penalty upon myself : to
					conclude here and now.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Aristotimus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps rather Heracleon (975 c) or Optatus (965 d).</note> So, gentlemen of the jury, you
					may now cast your votes.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.479"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Soclarus. As for us, we have for some time held
					the view of Sophocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 314, frag. 783; Pearson, iii, p. 69, frag. 867.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>It is a marvel how of rival sides
					</l>
                  <l>The strife of tongues welds both so close together.</l>
               </quote>
					For by combining what you have said against each
					other, you will together put up a good fight against
					those<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Stoics, as always in this essay.</note> who would deprive animals of reason and
					understanding.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">To some critics the ending is suspicious because of its brevity and vagueness; they regard it as added by an ancient editor who could not find the original termination. But the sudden turn at the end may merely indicate that the whole debate is in reality a single argument to prove the thesis that animals do have some degree of rationality (see also the Introduction to this dialogue).</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.12.p.481"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="appendix">
            <head>APPENDIX: CLASSIFIED ZOOLOGICAL INDEX</head>
            <p>
					A word of caution is needed : Plutarch emphatically was
					no naturalist. The zoological material is a hodge-podge of
					misinformation dredged up from various zoological sources,
					seasoned here and there with personal contributions, which
					are not necessarily correct. In the original sources, terms
					for specific types of animals were probably used with considerable precision. It is my impression that Plutarch often
					had only a vague idea of the meaning of such terms. For
					example, he consistently uses the specific term for a rock
					dove, but probably had in mind any type of domestic dove.
					Similarly, dorcas was used in Greece commonly as a term
					for the roedeer, but in Asia Minor for the common gazelle.
					In the original sources the word probably denoted specifically
					one or the other, depending on where the man lived ; but
					Plutarch may well have used the term vaguely for any type
					of small deer, including gazelles and antelopes.
					Alfred C. Andrews
				</p>
            <pb id="v.12.p.482"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">1. Mammals</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ai)/louros</foreign>: wild cat of Egypt (<foreign lang="la">Felis ocreata</foreign> Gm.) and of Europe (<foreign lang="la">F. silvestris</foreign> Schreb.) and domestic form (<foreign lang="la">F. domestica</foreign> Briss.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ai)/c</foreign>: domestic goat, <foreign lang="la">Capra hircus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)alw/phc</foreign>: fox, esp. <foreign lang="la">Vulpes vulgaris</foreign> Flem.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/arktos</foreign>: bear, more esp. the European brown bear, <foreign lang="la">Ursus arctos</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*bou=s</foreign>: domestic ox, <foreign lang="la">Bos taurus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*gale/h</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">galh=</foreign>): the weasel (<foreign lang="la">Putorius vulgaris</foreign> Cuv.), and such similar animals as the marten (<foreign lang="la">Martes</foreign> sp.) and the polecat or foumart (<foreign lang="la">Mustela putorius</foreign> L.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*dasu/pous</foreign>: hare (see <foreign lang="greek">*lagwo/s</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*delfi/s</foreign>: dolphin, esp. <foreign lang="la">Delphinus delphis</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*dorka/s</foreign>: in Greece, usually a term for the roedeer, <foreign lang="la">Capreolus capreolus</foreign> L.; in Asia Minor, usually a term for the common gazelle, <foreign lang="la">Gazella dorcas</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>*<foreign lang="greek">*)/elafos</foreign>: in Greece, usually a term for the red-deer, <foreign lang="la">Cervus elaphus</foreign> L.; in Ionia, usually a term for the fallow-deer, <foreign lang="la">C. dama</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)ele/fas</foreign>: elephant, <foreign lang="la">Elephas indicus</foreign> L. and . <foreign lang="la">africanus</foreign> Blumenb.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/erifos</foreign>: usually a kid (see <foreign lang="greek">*)ai)/c</foreign>); sometimes a very young lamb (see <foreign lang="greek">*)/oi+s</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)exi=nos</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">xersai=os</foreign>): common hedgehog, <foreign lang="la">Erinaceus europaeus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(hmi/onos</foreign>: mule, usually by mare and he-ass, sometimes by stallion and she-ass; in Syria, a term for the wild ass (<foreign lang="la">Asinus onager</foreign> Sm.) or the dschigetai (<foreign lang="la">A. hemionus</foreign> Sm.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(/ippos</foreign>: horse, <foreign lang="la">Caballus caballus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(/ippos pota/mios</foreign>: hippopotamus, <foreign lang="la">Hippopotamus amphibius</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)ixneu/mwn</foreign>: ichneumon, <foreign lang="la">Herpestes ichneumon</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ka/mhlos</foreign>: the Bactrian camel, <foreign lang="la">Camelus bactrianus</foreign> L., and the Arabian camel or dromedary, C. dromedarius L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ka/pros</foreign>: wild boar, mostly <foreign lang="la">Sus scrofa ferus</foreign> R&uuml;timeyer.</p>
            <pb id="v.12.p.483"/>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*kh=tos</foreign>: in Plutarch usually whale, as in 980 F. See also <foreign lang="greek">*kh=tos</foreign> under FISHES.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*krio/s</foreign>: ram (see <foreign lang="greek">*)/oi+s</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ku/wn</foreign>: dog, <foreign lang="la">Canis familiaris</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*lagwo/s</foreign>: hare, esp. the common European hare (<foreign lang="la">Lepus europaeus</foreign> Pall.), to a lesser degree the variable hare (<foreign lang="la">L. timidus</foreign> L.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*le/wn:</foreign> lion, <foreign lang="la">Felis leo</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*lu/gc</foreign>: lynx, <foreign lang="la">Lynx lynx</foreign> L.; caracal, <foreign lang="la">Lynx caracal</foreign> G&uuml;ld.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*lu/kos</foreign>: wolf, <foreign lang="la">Canis lupus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/oi+s</foreign>: domestic sheep, <foreign lang="la">Ovis aries</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/onos</foreign>: domestic ass, <foreign lang="la">Asinus domesticus</foreign> Sm.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)oreu/s</foreign>: mule (see <foreign lang="greek">*(hmi/onos</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/oruc</foreign>: chiefly the scimitar-horned oryx (<foreign lang="la">Oryx leucoryx</foreign> Pall.) and the straight-horned oryx (<foreign lang="la">O. beisa</foreign> R&uuml;ppel).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pa/rdalis</foreign>: panther or leopard, <foreign lang="la">Felis pardus antiquorum</foreign> Smith.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pro/baton</foreign>: sheep (see <foreign lang="greek">*)/oi+s</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*su/s</foreign>: pig, <foreign lang="la">Sus scrofa domesticus</foreign> R&uuml;timeyer.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*tau=ros</foreign>: bull (see <foreign lang="greek">*bou=s</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ti/gris</foreign>: tiger, <foreign lang="la">Felis tigris</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*fw/hn</foreign>: seal, including the common seal (<foreign lang="la">Phoca vitulina</foreign> L.) and the monk seal (<foreign lang="la">P. monachus</foreign> Herm.).</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">2. Birds</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)aeto/s</foreign>: eagle, esp. <foreign lang="la">Aquila</foreign> sp.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)ahdw/n</foreign>: nightingale, chiefly <foreign lang="la">Luscinia megarhyncha</foreign> Brehm.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)alektruw/n</foreign>: domestic cock, <foreign lang="la">Gallus domesticus</foreign> Briss.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)alkuw/n</foreign>: kingfisher, <foreign lang="la">Alcedo ispida</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ge/ranos</foreign>: common crane, <foreign lang="la">Grus grus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)erwdio/s</foreign>: heron, including the common heron (<foreign lang="la">Ardea cinerea</foreign> L.), the greater European egret (<foreign lang="la">Herodias alba</foreign> Gray), the lesser European egret (<foreign lang="la">Garzetta garzetta</foreign> L.), and the bittern (<foreign lang="la">Botaurus stellaris</foreign> L.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)=ibis</foreign>: ibis, including the sacred white ibis (<foreign lang="la">Ibis aethiopica</foreign> Ill.) and the black ibis (<foreign lang="la">Plegades falcinellus</foreign> Kaup.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(ierac</foreign>: smaller hawks and falcons generically.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)ikti=nos</foreign>: kite, including the common kite (<foreign lang="la">Milvus ictinus</foreign> Sav.) and the black kite (<foreign lang="la">. ater</foreign> Gm.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ki/tta</foreign>: jay, <foreign lang="la">Garrulus glandarius</foreign> L.; sometimes the magpie, <foreign lang="la">Pica caudata</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*koloio/s</foreign>: jackdaw, <foreign lang="la">Corvus monedula</foreign> L.</p>
            <pb id="v.12.p.484"/>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ko/rac</foreign>: raven, <foreign lang="la">Corvus corax</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*korw/nh</foreign>: crow (<foreign lang="la">Corvus corone</foreign> L.) and hooded crow (<foreign lang="la">C. cornix</foreign> L.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ku/knos</foreign>: swan, <foreign lang="la">Cygnus olor</foreign> Gra. and <foreign lang="la">C. musicus</foreign> Bkst.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*me/roy</foreign>: bee-eater, <foreign lang="la">Merops apiaster</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pelargo/s</foreign>: stork, esp. <foreign lang="la">Ciconia alba</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pe/rdic</foreign>: partridge, esp. the Greek partridge, <foreign lang="la">Alectoris graeca</foreign> Kaup; in Italy also the red-legged partridge, <foreign lang="la">A. rufa</foreign> Kaup.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*peristera/</foreign>: rock-dove, <foreign lang="la">Columba livia</foreign> L.; domestic rock-dove, <foreign lang="la">C. livia domestica</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*troxi/los</foreign>: Egyptian plover, <foreign lang="la">Pluvianus aegyptius</foreign> Viell.; elsewhere also the common European wren, <foreign lang="la">Troglodytes troglodytes</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*xelidw/n</foreign>: swallow, including the chimney swallow (<foreign lang="la">Chelidon rustica</foreign> L.) and the house-martin (<foreign lang="la">Chelidon urbica</foreign> Boie).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*xh'n</foreign>: as a wild type, the gray or graylag goose (<foreign lang="la">Anser cinereus</foreign> Meyer) and the bean goose (<foreign lang="la">Anser segetum</foreign> Bonn.), often the domestic type of the gray goose.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ya/r</foreign>: starling, <foreign lang="la">Sturnus vulgaris</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*yittako/s</foreign>: parrot, perhaps esp. <foreign lang="la">Psittacus alexandri</foreign> L. and <foreign lang="la">P. torquatus</foreign> Gm.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)wti/s</foreign>: bustard, <foreign lang="la">Otis tarda</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)=wtos</foreign>: a horned or eared owl, not more specifically identifiable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">3. REPTILES AND AMPHIBIA</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ba/traxos</foreign>: frog, <foreign lang="la">Rana</foreign> sp. and allied genera.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*kroko/deilos</foreign>: Nile crocodile, <foreign lang="la">Crocodilus niloticus</foreign> Laur.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/ofis</foreign>: serpent generically.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*xamaile/wn</foreign>: the African chameleon, <foreign lang="la">Chameleo vulgaris</foreign> Latr.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*xelw/nh</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">xersai/a</foreign>): tortoise, <foreign lang="la">Testudo graeca</foreign> L. and . <foreign lang="la">marginata</foreign> Schoepff.; (<foreign lang="greek">qalatti/a</foreign>): sea-turtle, <foreign lang="la">Thalassochelys corticata</foreign> Rondel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">4. FISHES</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(alieu/s</foreign>: fishing-frog, <foreign lang="la">Lophius piscatorius</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)alw/phc</foreign>: fox-shark, <foreign lang="la">Alopecias vulpes</foreign> Bp.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)ami/a</foreign>: bonito, more esp. the pelamid or belted bonito, <foreign lang="la">Sarda sarda</foreign> Cuv., to a lesser degree the bonito or striped-bellied tunny, <foreign lang="la">Katsuwonus pelamis</foreign> Kish.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)anqi/as</foreign>: in 977 c probably the Mediterranean barbier, <foreign lang="la">Serranus anthias</foreign> C. V.; sometimes spoken of as a much larger fish, then of uncertain identity.</p>
            <pb id="v.12.p.485"/>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*belo/nh</foreign>: usually the pipefish (<foreign lang="la">Syngnathus rubescens</foreign> Risso and <foreign lang="la">S. acus</foreign> L.) and the garfish (<foreign lang="la">Belone imperialis</foreign> Vincig. and <foreign lang="la">Strongylura acus</foreign> Lac&eacute;p.); in 983 C indeterminable.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*galeo/s</foreign>: generic term for sharks and dogfishes, more esp. <foreign lang="la">Scyllium canicula</foreign> Cuv., <foreign lang="la">S. catulus</foreign> Cuv., and <foreign lang="la">Mustelus vulgaris</foreign> M&uuml;ll.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*galh=</foreign>: principally the hake and rockling, <foreign lang="la">Phycis</foreign> sp. and <foreign lang="la">Motella</foreign> sp.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*go/ggros</foreign>: conger-eel, <foreign lang="la">Conger vulgaris</foreign> Cuv.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/elloy</foreign>: probably mostly the common sturgeon, <foreign lang="la">Acipenser sturio</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(hgemw/n</foreign>: usually the pilot-fish, <foreign lang="la">Naucrates ductor</foreign> Cuv.; in 980 F apparently also one of the globe-fishes, such as <foreign lang="la">Diodon hystrix</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*qri/ssa</foreign>: probably the shad, <foreign lang="la">Alosa vulgaris</foreign> C. V., or the sardinelle, <foreign lang="la">Sardinella aurita</foreign> C. V.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*qu/nnos</foreign>: tunny, mostly the common tunny, <foreign lang="la">Thunnus thynnus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*(iero/s</foreign>: &ldquo;sacred,&rdquo; an epithet applied to several fish, more especially the <foreign lang="greek">a)nqi/as</foreign>, the gilthead, the sturgeon, the dolphin, and the pilotfish.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)iouli/s</foreign>: rainbow-wrasse, <foreign lang="la">Coris iulis</foreign> Gth.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*kestreu/s</foreign>: the gray mullet in general, sometimes the common gray mullet, <foreign lang="la">Mugil capito</foreign> Cuv., in particular.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*kh=tos</foreign>: sometimes a large sea monster (as in 981 D), in other authors sometimes a huge fish (such as a large tunny), but more commonly, and usually in Plutarch, a whale.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*koli/as</foreign>: coly-mackerel, <foreign lang="la">Pneumatophorus colias</foreign> Gm.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*kwbio/s</foreign>: goby, chiefly the black goby, <foreign lang="la">Gobius niger</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*la/brac</foreign>: sea-bass, <foreign lang="la">Labrax lupus</foreign> Cuv.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*mormu/ros</foreign>: type of sea bream, the mormyrus, <foreign lang="la">Pagellus mormyrus</foreign> C. V.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*mu/raina</foreign>: moray or murry, <foreign lang="la">Muraena helena</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*na/rkh</foreign>: torpedo or electric ray, esp. <foreign lang="la">Torpedo marmorata</foreign> Risso, less commonly <foreign lang="la">. narce</foreign> Nardo and <foreign lang="la">. hebetans</foreign> L&ouml;we.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*perai/as</foreign>: a type of gray mullet (<foreign lang="la">Mugil</foreign> sp.).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*phlamu/s</foreign>: year-old tunny (see <foreign lang="greek">*qu/nnos</foreign>).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*sargo/s</foreign>: sargue, esp. <foreign lang="la">Sargus vulgaris</foreign> Geoff.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ska/ros</foreign>: parrot-fish, <foreign lang="la">Scarus cretensis</foreign> C. V.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*skorpi/os</foreign>: sculpin, <foreign lang="la">Scorpaena scrofa</foreign> L. and S. <foreign lang="la">porcus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*tri/gla</foreign>: the red or plain surmullet, <foreign lang="la">Mullus barbatus</foreign> L., and the striped or common surmullet, <foreign lang="la">. surmuletus</foreign> L.</p>
            <pb id="v.12.p.486"/>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*fuki/s</foreign>: a wrasse, probably specifically <foreign lang="la">Crenilabrus pavo</foreign> C. V.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*xruswpo/s</foreign>: gilthead, <foreign lang="la">Chrysophrys aurata</foreign> C. V.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">5. MOLLUSCS</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ko/gxh</foreign>: mussels in general, including oysters.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*lagwo/s</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">qala/ttios</foreign>): sea-hare, <foreign lang="la">Aplysia depilans</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)/ostreon</foreign>: sometimes a generic term for mussels; more commonly a specific term for the common European oyster, <foreign lang="la">Ostrea edulis</foreign> L.; occasionally a term for other species of oyster, such as <foreign lang="la">O. lamellosa</foreign> Brocchi and <foreign lang="la">O. cristata</foreign> Lam.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pi/nnh</foreign>: pinna, especially <foreign lang="la">Pinna nobilis</foreign> L.; but also <foreign lang="la">P. rudis</foreign> L., <foreign lang="la">P. rotundata</foreign> L., and <foreign lang="la">P. pectinata</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*polu/pous</foreign>: octopus, <foreign lang="la">Octopus vulgaris</foreign> Lam.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*porfu/ra</foreign>: purplefish, <foreign lang="la">Murex trunculus</foreign> L., <foreign lang="la">. brandaris</foreign> L., and <foreign lang="la">Thais haemastoma</foreign> Lam.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*shpi/a</foreign>: cuttlefish, <foreign lang="la">Sepia officinalis</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">6. CRUSTACEA</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*ka/rabos</foreign>: rock lobster, <foreign lang="la">Palinurus vulgaris</foreign> Latr.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*karki/nos</foreign>: crab, Decapoda brachyura Lam.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pa/gouros</foreign>: probably the common edible crab, <foreign lang="la">Cancer pagurus</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*pinnothrhs</foreign>: pinna-guard, <foreign lang="la">Pinnoteres veterum</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*spoggoth/rhs</foreign>: sponge-guard, <foreign lang="la">Typton spongicola</foreign> Costa.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">7. INSECTS AND SPIDERS</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)ara/xnhs</foreign>: spider (class Arachnoidea, order Araneida).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*me/litta</foreign>: bee generically, but mostly domestic honeybee, <foreign lang="la">Apis mellifera</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*mu/rmhc</foreign>: ant generically (family Formicidae).</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*te/ttic</foreign>: cicada, esp. <foreign lang="la">Cicada plebeia</foreign> Scop, and <foreign lang="la">C. orni</foreign> L.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">8. ECHINODERMS</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)asth/r</foreign>: starfish generically, <foreign lang="la">Asterias</foreign> sp.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*)exi=nos</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">qala/ttios</foreign>): sea-urchin, especially <foreign lang="la">Echinus esculentus</foreign> Lam. and <foreign lang="la">Strongylocentrotus lividus</foreign> Brdt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">9. PORIFERA</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="greek">*spo/ggos</foreign>: sponge, chiefly <foreign lang="la">Euspongia officinalis</foreign> Bronn. and <foreign lang="la">Hippospongia equina</foreign> Schmidt.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>