<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De faciae quae in orbe lunae apparet</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.126">
      <body>
         <head>Of the face appearing within the orb of the moon.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The beginning of this discourse is lost.</note>
				        <lb/> Lamprias, Apollonides, Lucius, Pharnaces, Sylla, Aristoteles, Theon, Menelaus.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.234"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>These things then, said Sylla, agree with my story,
				and are taken thence. But I should first willingly ask,
				what need there is of making such a preamble against
				these opinions, which are at hand and in every man's
				mouth, concerning the face that is seen within the orb of
				the moon. Why should we not, said I, being, by the difficulty there is in these discourses, forced upon those? For,
				as they who have long lain lingering under chronical diseases, after they have been worn out and tired with experimenting all ordinary remedies and the usual rules of
				living and diet, have at last recourse to lustrations and
				purifications, to charms and amulets fastened about the
				neck, and to the interpretation of dreams; so in such obscure and abstruse questions and speculations, when the
				common, apparent, and ordinary reasons are not satisfactory, there is a necessity of trying such as are more extravagant, and of not contemning but enchanting ourselves
				(as one may say) with the discourses of the ancients, and
				endeavoring always to find out the truth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>For you see at the very first blush, how impertinent
				his opinion is who said, that the form appearing in the
				moon is an accident of our sight, by its weakness giving
				way to her brightness, which we call the dazzling of our
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.235"/>
				
				eyes; for he perceives not that this should rather befall
				our looking against the sun, whose lustre is more resplendent, and whose rays are more quick and piercing; as
				Empedocles also in a certain passage of his has not
				unpleasantly noted the difference of these two planets,
				saying,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sharp-rayed sun, and gently shining moon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For thus does he call her alluring, favorable, and harmless
					light. No less absurd appears the reason he afterwards
					gives why dull and weak eyes discern no difference of
					form in the moon, her orb appearing to them plain and
					smooth, whereas those whose sight is more acute and penetrating better descry the lineaments and more perfectly
					observe the impressions of a face, and more evidently distinguish its different parts. For it should, in my opinion,
					be quite contrary, if this were a fancy caused by the weakness of the vanquished sight; so that where the patient's eye
					is weaker, the appearance would be more express and evident. Moreover, the inequality every way confutes this
					reason; for this face is not seen in a continuance and confused shadow, but the poet Agesianax not unelegantly
					describes it, saying,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With shining fire it circled does appear,
						</l>
                     <l>And in the midst is seen the visage clear
						</l>
                     <l>Of a young maid, whose eyes more gray than blue,
						</l>
                     <l>Her brow and cheeks a blushing red do show.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For indeed dark and shady things, encompassed with
					others that are bright and shining, sink underneath and
					reciprocally rise again, being repelled by them; and in a
					word, they are so interlaced one within another, that they
					represent the figure of a face painted to the life; and there
					seems to have been great probability in that which was
					spoken against your Clearchus, my dear Aristotle. For
					he appears not inconveniently to be called yours, for he
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.236"/>
					
					was intimately acquainted with the ancient Aristotle, although he perverted many of the Peripatetic doctrines.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Then Apollonides taking up the discourse, and asking
				what that opinion of Clearchus was; It would more, said
				I, beseem any man than you to be ignorant of this discourse, as being grounded on the very fundamental principles of geometry. For he affirms, that what we call a face,
				is the image and figure of the great ocean, represented in
				the moon as in a mirror. For the circumference of a
				circle, when it is reflected back,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the account of various ancient doctrines of vision and the reflection of light
					in the treatise on the Opinions of Philosophers, Book IV. Chapters 13 and 14. The
					idea that vision was caused by something proceeding from the eye to the object is
					especially to be noticed. (G.)</note> is wont in many places
				to touch objects which are not seen in a direct line. And
				the full moon is for evenness and lustre the most beautiful
				and purest of all mirrors. As then you hold, that the
				heavenly bow appears, when the ray of light is reflected
				back towards the sun, in a cloud which has got a little
				liquid smoothness and consistence; so, said he, there is
				seen in the moon the surface of the sea, not in the place
				where it is situated, but from whence the reflection gives a
				sight of it by its reverberated and reflexed light, as Agesianax again says in another passage,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This flaming mirror offers to your eyes
					</l>
                     <l>The vast sea's figure, as beneath it lies
					</l>
                     <l>Foaming with raging billows.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Apollonides therefore, being delighted with this, said.
				A singular opinion indeed is this of his, and (to speak in a
				word) strangely and newly invented by a man sufficiently
				presumptuous, but not void of learning and wit. But how,
				I pray, was it refuted?</p>
            <p>First, said I, the superficies of the sea is all of a nature,
					the current of it being uniform and continuous; but the
					appearance of those black and dark spots which are seen
					in the face of the moon is not continued, but has certain
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.237"/>
					
					isthmuses or partitions clear and bright, which divide and
					separate what is dark and shady. Whence every place
					being distinguished and having its own limits apart, the
					conjunctions of the clear with the obscure, taking a resemblance of high and low, express and represent the
					similitude of a figure seeming to have eyes and lips; so
					that we must of necessity suppose, either that there are
					main oceans and main seas, distinguished by isthmuses and
					continents of firm land, which is evidently absurd and
					false; or that if there is but one, it is not credible its
					image should appear so distracted and dissipated into
					pieces. And as for this, there is less danger in asking than
					in affirming in your presence, whether, since the habitable
					earth has both length and breadth, it is possible that the
					sight of all men, when it is reflected by the moon, should
					equally touch the ocean, even of those that sail and
					dwell in it, as do the Britons; especially since the earth,
					as you have maintained, has but the proportion of a point,
					if compared to the sphere of the moon. This therefore,
					said I, it is your business to observe, but the reflection of
					the sight against the moon belongs neither to you nor Hipparchus. And yet, my friend Lamprias, there are many
					naturalists, who approve not this doctrine of his touching
					the driving back of the sight, but affirm it to be more
					probable that it has a certain obedient and agreeing temperature and compactness of structure, than such beatings
					and repercussions as Epicurus feigned for his atoms.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text in this passage is defective, and the sense chiefly conjectural. (G.)</note> Nor
					am I of opinion that Clearchus would have us suppose the
					moon to be a massy and weighty body, but a celestial and
					light-giving star, as you say it is, which must have the
					property of breaking and turning aside the sight; so that
					all this reflection would come to nothing. But if we are
					desired to receive and admit it, we shall ask why this face
					or image of the sea is to be seen only in the body of the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.238"/>
					
					moon; and not in any of the other stars? For the laws
					of probability require that the sight should suffer this
					equally in all, or else in none.</p>
            <p>But pray, sir, said I, casting mine eyes upon Lucius, call
					a little to mind what was said at first by those of our party.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Nay rather, answered he,&mdash;lest we should seem too
				injurious to Pharnaces, in thus passing by the opinion of
				the Stoics, without opposing any thing against it,&mdash;let us
				make some reply to this man, who supposes the moon to
				be wholly a mixture of air and mild fire, and then says
				that, as in a calm there sometimes arises on a sudden a
				breeze of wind which curls and ruffles the superficies of
				the sea, so, the air being darkened and rendered black,
				there is an appearance and form of a face.</p>
            <p>You do courteously, Lucius, said I, thus to veil and cover
					with specious expressions so absurd and false an opinion.
					But so did not our friend; but he said, as the truth is, that
					the Stoics disfigured and mortified the moon's face, filling
					it with stains and black spots, one while invocating her by
					the name of Diana and Minerva, and another while making
					her a lump and mixture of dark air and charcoal-fire, not
					kindling of itself or having any light of its own, but a
					body hard to be judged and known, always smoking and
					ever burning, like to those thunders which by the poets
					are styled lightless and sooty. Now that a fire of coals,
					such as they would have that of the moon to be, cannot
					have any continuance nor yet so much as the least subsistence, unless it meets with some solid matter fit to maintain it, keep it in, and feed it, has, I think, far better than
					it is by these philosophers, been understood by those poets
					who in merriment affirm that Vulcan was therefore said to
					be lame because fire can no more go forward without wood
					or fuel than a cripple without a crutch. If then the moon
					is fire, whence has it so much air? For that region above,
					which is with a continual motion carried round, consists
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.239"/>
					
					not of air, but some more excellent substance, whose nature it is to subtilize and set on fire all other things. And
					if it has been since engendered there, how comes it that it
					does not perish, being changed and transmuted by the fire
					into an ethereal and heavenly substance? And how can it
					maintain and preserve itself, cohabiting so long with the
					fire, as a nail always fixed and fastened in one and the
					same place? For being rare and diffused, as by Nature it
					is, it is not fitted for permanency and continuance, but for
					change and dissipation. Neither is it possible that it
					should condense and grow compact, being mixed with fire,
					and utterly void of water and earth, the only two elements
					by which the nature of the air suffers itself to be brought
					to a consistency and thickness. And since the swiftness
					and violence of motion is wont to inflame the air which is
					in stones, and even in lead itself, as cold as it is; much
					more will it that which, being in fire, is with so great an
					impetuosity whirled about. For they are displeased with
					Empedocles for making the moon a mass of air congealed
					after the manner of hail, included within a sphere of fire.
					And yet they themselves say, that the moon, being a globe
					of fire, contains in it much air dispersed here and there,&mdash;
					and this, though it has neither ruptures, concavities, nor
					depths (which they who affirm it to be earthly admit),
					but the air lies superficially on its convexity. Now this is
					both against the nature of permanency, and impossible to
					be accorded with what we see in full moons; for it should
					not appear separately black and dark, but either be wholly
					obscured and concealed or else co-illuminated, when the
					moon is overspread by the sun. For with us the air which
					is in the pits and hollows of the earth, whither the rays of
					the sun cannot penetrate, remains dark and lightless; but
					that which is spread over its exterior parts has clearness
					and a lightsome color. For it is by reason of its rarity
					easily transformed into every quality and faculty, but principally
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.240"/>
					
					 that of light and brightness, by which, being never
					so little touched, it incontinently changes and is illuminated. This reason therefore, as it seems greatly to help
					and maintain the opinion of those who thrust the air into
					certain deep valleys and caves in the moon, so confutes
					you, who mix and compose her sphere, I know not how,
					of air and fire. For it is not possible that there should remain any shadow or darkness in the superficies of the
					moon, when the sun with his brightness clears and enlightens whatsoever we can discern of her and ken with
					our sight.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Whilst I was yet speaking, Pharnaces interrupting
				my discourse said: See here again the usual stratagem of
				the Academy brought into play against us, which is to busy
				themselves at every turn in speaking against others, but
				never to afford an opportunity for reproving what they say
				themselves; so that those with whom they confer and dispute must always be respondents and defendants, and never
				plaintiffs or opponents. You shall not therefore bring me
				this day to give you an account of those things you charge
				upon the Stoics, till you have first rendered me a reason
				for your turning the world upside down.</p>
            <p>Then Lucius smiling said: This, good sir, I am well
					contented to do, provided only that you will not accuse us
					of impiety, as Cleanthes thought that the Greeks ought
					to have called Aristarchus the Samian into question and
					condemned him of blasphemy against the Gods, as shaking
					the very foundations of the world, because this man, endeavoring to save the appearances, supposed that the
					heavens remained immovable, and that the earth moved
					through an oblique circle, at the same time turning about
					its own axis. As for us therefore, we say nothing that we
					take from them. But how do they, my good friend, who
					suppose the moon to be earth, turn the world upside down
					more than you, who say that the earth remains here hanging
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.241"/>
					
					 in the air, being much greater than the moon, as the
					mathematicians measure their magnitude by the accidents
					of eclipses, and by the passages of the moon through the
					shadow of the earth, gathering thence how great a space
					it takes up? For the shadow of the earth is less than itself, by reason it is cast by a greater light. And that the
					end of this shadow upwards is slender and pointed, they
					say that Homer himself was not ignorant, but plainly expressed it when he called the night <foreign lang="greek">qoh/</foreign> (that is, <hi rend="italics">acute</hi>) from
					the sharp-pointedness of the earth's shadow. And yet
					the moon in her eclipses, being caught within this point
					of the shadow, can scarce get out of it by going forward
					thrice her own bigness in length. Consider then, how
					many times the earth must needs be greater than the
					moon, if it casts a shadow, the narrowest point of which
					is thrice as broad as the moon. But you are perhaps
					afraid lest the moon should fall, if it were acknowledged
					to be earth; but as for the earth, Aeschylus has secured
					you, when he says that Atlas
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Stands shouldering the pillar of the heaven and earth,
						</l>
                     <l>A burden onerous.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aesch. Prom. 349.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>If then there runs under the moon only a light air, not firm
					enough to bear a solid burthen, whereas under the earth
					there are, as Pindar says, columns and pillars of adamant
					for its support, therefore Pharnaces himself is out of all
					dread of the earth's falling, but he pities the Ethiopians
					and those of Taprobane, who lie directly under the course
					of the moon, fearing lest so ponderous a mass should tumble upon their heads. And yet the moon has, for an help
					to preserve her from falling, her motion and the impetuosity of her revolution; as stones, pebbles, and other
					weights, put into slings, are kept from dropping out,
					whilst they are swung round, by the swiftness of their motion. For every body is carried according to its natural
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.242"/>
					
					motion, unless it be diverted by some other intervening
					cause. Wherefore the moon does not move according to
					the motion of her weight, her inclination being stopped
					and hindered by the violence of a circular revolution. And
					perhaps there would be more reason to wonder, if the
					moon continued always immovable in the same place, as
					does the earth. But now the moon has a great cause to
					keep herself from tending hither downwards; but for the
					earth, which has no other motion, it is probable that it has
					also no other cause of its settlement but its own weight.
					For the earth is heavier than the moon, not only because it
					is greater, but also because the moon is rendered lighter
					by the heat and inflammation that is in it. In brief, it appears by what you say, if it is true that the moon is fire,
					that it stands in need of earth or some other matter, which
					it may rest on and cleave to, for the maintaining and nourishing of its power. For it is not possible to imagine how
					a fire can be preserved without some combustible matter.
					And you yourselves say that the earth continues firm without any basis or pedestal to support it.</p>
            <p>Yes surely, said Pharnaces, being in its proper and natural place, the very middle and centre of the universe. For
					this it is to which all heavy and ponderous things do from
					every side naturally tend, incline, and aspire, and about
					which they cling and are counterpoised. But every superior region, though it may perhaps receive some earthly
					and weighty thing sent by violence up into it, immediately
					repels and casts it down again by force, or (to speak better) lets it follow its own proper inclination, by which it
					naturally tends downwards.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>For the refutation of which, being willing to give
				Lucius time for the calling to mind his arguments, I addressed myself to Theon, and asked him which of the
				tragic poets it was who said that physicians
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With bitter med'cines bitter choler purge.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.243"/>
            <p>And Theon having answered me that it was Sophocles;
					This, said I to him, we must of necessity permit them to
					do; but we are not to give ear to those philosophers who
					would overthrow paradoxes by assertions no less strange
					and paradoxical, and for the oppugning strange and extravagant opinions, devise others yet more wonderful and
					absurd; as these men do, who broach and introduce this
					doctrine of a motion tending towards the middle, in which
					what sort of absurdity is there not to be found? Does it
					not thence follow, that the earth is spherical, though we
					nevertheless see it to have so many lofty hills, so many
					deep valleys, and so great a number of inequalities? Does
					it not follow that there are antipodes dwelling opposite to
					another, sticking on every side to the earth, with their
					heads downwards and their heels upwards, as if they were
					woodworms or lizards? That we ourselves go not on the
					earth straight upright, but obliquely and bending aside
					like drunken men? That if bars and weights of a thousand talents apiece should be let fall into the hollow of
					the earth, they would, when they were come to the centre,
					stop and rest there, though nothing came against them or
					sustained them; and that, if peradventure they should by
					force pass the middle, they would of themselves return
					and rebound back thither again? That if one should saw
					off the two trunks or ends of a beam on either side of the
					earth, they would not be always carried downwards, but
					falling both from without into the earth, they would equally
					meet, and hide themselves together in the middle? That
					if a violent stream of water should run downwards into
					the ground, it would, when it came to the centre of the
					earth, which they hold to be an incorporeal point, there
					gather together, and turn round like a whirlpool, with a
					perpetual and endless suspension? Some of which positions are so absurd, that none can so much as force his
					imagination, though falsely, to conceive them possible.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.244"/>
					
					For this is indeed to make that which is above to be
					below; and to turn all things upside down, by making all
					that is as far as the middle to be <hi rend="italics">downwards,</hi> and all that
					is beyond the middle to be <hi rend="italics">upwards;</hi> so that if a man
					should, by the sufferance and consent of the earth, stand
					with his navel just against her centre, he would by this
					means have his feet and head both upwards; and if one,
					having digged through that place which is beyond the
					middle, should come to pull him out from thence, that part
					which is below would at one and the same time be drawn
					upwards, and that which is above, downwards. And if
					another should be imagined to stand the contrary way,
					their feet, though the one's were opposite to the other's,
					would both be and be said to be upwards.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Bearing then upon their shoulders, and drawing after
				them. I do not say a little bag or box, but a whole pack of
				juggler's boxes, full of so many absurdities, with which
				they play the hocus-pocus in philosophy, they nevertheless
				accuse others of error for placing the moon, which they
				hold to be earth, on high, and not in the middle or centre of the world. And yet, if every heavy body inclines
				towards the same place, and does from all sides and with
				every one of its parts tend to its own centre, the earth
				certainly will appropriate and challenge to itself these
				ponderous masses&mdash;which are its parts&mdash;not because it
				is the centre of the universe, but rather because it is the
				whole; and this gathering together of heavy bodies round
				about it will not be a sign showing it to be the middle of
				the world, but an argument to prove and testify that these
				bodies which had been plucked from it and again return
				to it have a communication and conformity of nature with
				the earth. For as the sun draws into himself the parts
				of which he is composed, so the earth receives a stone as
				a part belonging to it, in such manner that every one of
				such things is in time united and incorporated with it.
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.245"/>
				
				And if peradventure there is some other body which was
				not from the beginning allotted to the earth nor has been
				separated from it, but had its own proper and peculiar
				consistence and nature apart, as these men may say of the
				moon, what hinders but it may continue separated by itself, being kept close, compacted, and bound together by
				its own parts? For they do not demonstrate that the earth
				is the middle of the universe; and this conglomeration of
				heavy bodies which are here, and their coalition with the
				earth, show us the manner how it is probable that the
				parts which are assembled in the body of the moon continue also there. But as for him who drives and ranges
				together in one place all earthly and ponderous things,
				making them parts of one and the same body, I wonder
				that he does not attribute also the same necessity and constraint to light substances, but leaves so many conglomerations of fire separated one from another; nor can I see
				why he should not amass together all the stars, and think
				that there ought to be but one body of all those substances
				which fly upwards.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>But you mathematicians, friend Apollonides, say that
				the sun is distant from our upper sphere infinite thousands
				of miles, and after him the day-star or Venus, Mercury,
				and other planets, which being situated under the fixed
				stars, and separated from one another by great intervals,
				make their revolutions; and in the mean time you think
				that the world affords not to heavy and terrestrial bodies
				any great and large place or distance one from another.
				You plainly see, it would be ridiculous, if we should deny
				the moon to be earth because it is not seated in the lowest
				region of the world, and yet affirm it to be a star, though
				so many thousands of miles remote from the upper firmanent, as if it were plunged into some deep gulf. For she
				is so low before all other stars, that the measure of the
				distances cannot be expressed, and you mathematicians
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.246"/>
				
				want numbers to compute and reckon it; but she in a
				manner touches the earth, making her revolution so near
				the tops of the mountains, that she seems, as Empedocles
				has it, to leave even the very tracks of her chariot-wheels
				behind her. For oftentimes she surpasses not the shadow
				of the earth, which is very short through the excessive
				greatness of the sun that shines upon it, but seems to turn
				so near the superficies, and (as one may say) between the
				arms and in the bosom of the earth, that it withholds from
				her the light of the sun, because she mounts that shady,
				earthly, and nocturnal region which is the lot and inheritance of the earth. And therefore I am of opinion, we
				may boldly say that the moon is within the limits and confines of the earth, seeing she is even darkened by the
				summits of its mountains.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But leaving the stars, as well erring as fixed, see
				what Aristarchus proves and demonstrates in his treatise
				of magnitudes and distances; that the distance of the sun
				is above eighteen times and under twenty times greater
				than that of the moon from us. And yet they who place
				the moon lowest say that her distance from us contains six
				and fifty of the earth's semidiameters, that is, that she is
				six and fifty times as far from us as we are from the centre
				of the earth; which is forty thousand stadia, according to
				those that make their computation moderately. Therefore
				the sun is above forty millions and three hundred thousand
				stadia distant from the moon; so far is she from the sun
				by reason of her gravity, and so near does she approach
				to the earth. So that if substances are to be distinguished
				by places, the portion and, region of the earth challenges
				to itself the moon, which, by reason of neighborhood and
				proximity, has a right to be reputed and reckoned amongst
				the terrestrial natures and bodies. Nor shall we, in my
				opinion, do amiss if, having given so vast an interval and
				distance to these bodies which are said to be above, we
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.247"/>
				
				leave also to those which are below some space and room
				to turn them in, such as is that between the earth and the
				moon. For neither is he who calls only the utmost superficies of the heaven <hi rend="italics">above</hi> and all the rest <hi rend="italics">beneath</hi> moderate or tolerable; nor is he to be endured who confines
				<hi rend="italics">beneath</hi> only to the earth, or rather to its centre; seeing
				the vast greatness of the world may afford means for the
				assigning farther to this lower part some such space as is
				necessary for motion. Now against him who holds that
				whatever is above the earth is immediately high and sublime, there is presently another opposition to encounter
				and contradict it, that whatever is beneath the sphere of
				the fixed stars ought to be called low and inferior.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>In a word, how is the earth said to be the middle,
				and of what is it the middle? For the universe is infinite;
				and infiniteness having neither beginning nor end, it is
				convenient also that it should not have any middle; for the
				middle is a certain end or limit, but infiniteness is a privation of all sorts of limits. Now he that affirms the earth
				to be the middle, not of the universe but of the world, is
				certainly a pleasant man, if he does not think that the
				world itself is subject to the same doubts and difficulties.
				For the universe has not left a middle even to the very
				world, but this being without any certain seat or foundation, it is carried in an infinite voidness to no proper end;
				or if perhaps it has stopped, it has met with some other
				cause or stay, not according to the nature of the place.
				As much may be conjectured of the moon, that by the
				means of another soul and another Nature, or (to say
				better) of another difference, the earth continues firm here
				below, and the moon moves. Besides this, see whether
				they are not ignorant of a great inconvenience and error.
				For if it is true that all which is without the centre of the
				earth, however it be, is above, there will then be no part
				of the world below; but the earth and all that is upon it
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.248"/>
				
				will be above; and in brief, every body that shall be placed
				about the centre will be above, and there will be nothing below or underneath, but one only point which has no
				body, which will of necessity make head against and oppose all the rest of the world's nature, if <hi rend="italics">above</hi> and <hi rend="italics">beneath</hi>
				are naturally opposite to one another. Nor is this the only
				absurdity that will follow; but all heavy and ponderous
				bodies will also lose the cause for which they move and
				tend downwards hither, for there will be no body below to
				which they should move; and as for that which is incorporeal, it is not probable, neither will they themselves
				allow, that it should be so forcible as to draw and retain
				all things about itself. But if it is unreasonable and contrary to Nature that the whole world should be above, and
				that there should be nothing below but an incorporeal and
				indivisible term or limit, then is this, as we say, yet more
				reasonable, that the region above and that below being
				divided the one from the other, have nevertheless each of
				them a large and spacious room.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Nevertheless, supposing, if you please, that it is
				against Nature for earthly bodies to have any motions in
				heaven, let us consider leisurely and mildly-and not
				violently, as is done in tragedies&mdash;that this is no proof of
				the moon's not being earth, but only that earth is in a
				place where by nature it should not be; for the fire of
				Mount Aetna is indeed against nature under ground, nevertheless it ceases not to be fire. And the wind contained
				within bottles is indeed of its own nature light and inclined
				to ascend, but is yet by force constrained to be there where
				naturally it should not be. And is not our very soul, I
				beseech you in the name of Jupiter, which, as yourselves
				say, is light, of a fiery substance, and imperceptible to
				sense, included within the body, which is heavy, cold, and
				palpable? Yet do we therefore say that the soul does not
				belong to the body; or that it is not a divine substance
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.249"/>
				
				under a gross and heavy mass, or that it does not in a
				moment pass through heaven, earth, and sea, pierce into
				the flesh, nerves, and marrow, and into the humors which
				are the cause of a thousand passions? And even your
				Jupiter, such as you imagine him and depaint him to be,
				is he not of his own nature a great and perpetual fire?
				Yet now he submits, is pliable, and transformed into all
				things by several mutations. Take heed therefore, good
				sir, lest, by transferring and reducing every thing to the
				place assigned it by Nature, you so philosophize as to bring
				in a dissolution of the whole world, and put all things
				again into that state of enmity mentioned by Empedocles,
				or (to speak more properly) lest you raise up again those
				ancient Titans and Giants to put on arms against Nature,
				and endeavor to introduce again that fabulous disorder and
				confusion, where all that is heavy goes one way apart, and
				all that is light another;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where neither sun's bright face is seen,
					</l>
                     <l>Nor earth beheld, spread o'er with green,
					</l>
                     <l>Nor the salt sea,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Empedocles has it. Then the earth felt no heat, nor
					the sea any wind; no heavy thing moved upwards, nor any
					light thing downwards; but the principles of all things
					were solitary, without any mutual love or dilection one to
					another, not admitting any society or mixture together;
					but shunning and avoiding all communication, moving
					separately by particular motions, as being disdainful,
					proud, and altogether carrying themselves in such manner as every thing does from which (as Plato says) God is
					absent; that is, as those bodies do in which there is neither
					soul nor understanding; till such time as, by Divine Providence, desire coming into Nature engendered mutual amity,
					Venus, and Love,&mdash;as Empedocles, Parmenides, and
					Hesiod have it,&mdash;to the end that changing their natural
					places, and reciprocally communicating their faculties,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.250"/>
					
					some being by necessity bound to motion, others to quiet
					and rest, and all tending to the better, every thing remitting
					a little of its power and yielding a little from its place,
					. . .they might make at length a harmony, accord, and
					society together.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>For if there had not been any other part of the
				world against Nature, but every thing had been in the
				same place and quality it naturally ought to be, without
				standing in need of any change or transposition or having
				had any occasion for it from the beginning, I know not
				what the work of Divine Providence is or in what it consists, or of what Jupiter has been the father, creator, or
				worker. For there would not in a camp be any need of
				the art of ranging and ordering of battles, if every soldier
				of himself knew and understood his rank, place, and
				station, and the opportunity he ought to take and keep;
				nor would there be any want of gardeners or builders, if
				water were of itself framed to flow where it is necessary,
				and irrigate such plants as stand in need of watering, or if
				bricks, timber, and stones would of their own inclinations
				and natural motion range and settle themselves in due and
				fitting places and orders. Now if this discourse manifestly
				takes away Providence, and if the ordering and distinction
				of things that are in the world belongs to God, why should
				we wonder at Nature's having been so disposed and ordained by him, that the fire should be here, and the stars
				there, and again the earth should be situated here below,
				and the moon above, lodged in a prison found out by
				reason, more sure and straight than that which was first
				ordained by Nature? For if it were of absolute necessity
				that all things should follow their natural instinct and
				move according to the motion given them by Nature,
				neither the Sun, Venus, nor any other planet would any
				more run a circular course; for light and fiery substances
				have by Nature their motion directly upwards. And if
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.251"/>
				
				perhaps Nature itself receives this permutation and change
				by reason of the place, so that fire should here in a direct
				line tend upwards, but being once arrived at heaven, should
				turn round with the revolution of the heavens; what wonder would it be, if heavy and terrestrial bodies, being in
				like manner out of their natural place, were vanquished
				by the ambient air, and forced to take another sort of motion? For it cannot with any reason be said that heaven
				has by Nature the power to take away from light things
				the property of mounting directly upwards, and cannot
				likewise have the force to overcome heavy things and such
				as tend downwards; but that sometimes making use of
				this power, and sometimes of the proper nature of the
				things, it still orders every thing for the best.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>But if, laying aside those servile habits and opinions
				to which we have enslaved ourselves, we must frankly and
				fearlessly deliver our judgment, it seems clear to me, that
				there is not any part of the universe which has a peculiar
				and separate rank, situation, or motion, that can simply be
				said to be natural to it. But when every thing exhibits
				and yields up itself to be moved, as is most profitable and
				fit for that for whose sake it was made and to which it is
				by Nature appointed,&mdash;suffering, doing, or being disposed,
				as is most expedient and meet for the safety, beauty, and
				power of the same,&mdash;then it appears to have its place,
				motion, and disposition according to Nature. As a proof
				of this, we may observe that man, who, if any thing in
				the world be so, is made and disposed according to Nature; has upwards, especially about his head, heavy and
				terrestrial things, and about the middle of his body such
				as are hot and participate of fire; of his teeth also some
				grow upwards and some downwards, and yet neither the
				one nor the other are contrary to Nature; neither is the
				fire which shines in his eyes according to Nature, and that
				which is in his heart and stomach against it; but it is in
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.252"/>
				
				each place properly and beneficially seated. Moreover,
				consider the nature of all shell-fishes; and, that I may use
				the words of Empedocles,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Look on the crabs, the oysters of the sea,
					</l>
                     <l>And shell-fish all, which heavy coats enfold,
					</l>
                     <l>The tortoise too with arched back, whom we
					</l>
                     <l>Covered with crust, as hard as stone, behold.
					</l>
                     <l>View them but well, and plain it will appear,
					</l>
                     <l>They hardened earth above their bodies bear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this crust, stone-like, hard, and heavy, as it is thus
					placed over their bodies, does not press and crush their
					natural habit, nor on the contrary does their heat fly upwards by reason of its lightness, and vanish away, but they
					are mingled and composed one with another, according to
					the nature of each one.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Wherefore it is also probable that the world, if it is
				an animal, has in many parts of its body earth, and in as
				many fire and water and air, not thrust and driven into it
				by force, but ordered and disposed by reason. For neither
				was the eye by its lightness forced into that part of the body
				where it is, nor the heart by its gravity pressed down into
				the breast; but both the one and the other were thus
				placed because it was better and more expedient. In like
				manner we ought not to think of the parts of the world,
				either that the earth settled where it is, being beaten down
				thither by its ponderosity; or that the sun was carried
				upwards by its levity, like a bottle or bladder full of wind
				(which, being plunged into the bottom of the water, immediately rises up again), as Metrodorus of Chios was persuaded; or that the other stars, as if they had been put
				into a balance, were swayed this way or that way, according to their weight or lightness, and so mounted higher or
				lower to the places they now possess. But reason having
				prevailed in the constitution of the world, the stars have,
				like to glittering eyes, been fixed in the firmament, as it
				were in the face of the universe, there to turn continually
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.253"/>
				
				about; and the sun, having the force and vigor of the
				heart, sends and distributes its heat and light, like blood
				and spirits, throughout all; the earth and sea are in the
				world, as the paunch and bladder in the body of a living
				creature; and the moon placed between the sun and the
				earth, as the liver, or some other soft entrail between the
				heart and the belly, transmits down thither the heat of
				the superior bodies, and draws round about her the vapors
				which arise from hence, subtilizing them by way of concoction and purification. And whether its solid and terrestrial quality has any other property serving for some
				profitable use, is indeed unknown to us; but everywhere
				that which is better prevails over what is by necessity.
				For what probability can we draw from that which they
				Affirm? They say, that the most subtile and luminous
				part of the air, by reason of its rarity, became heaven;
				but what was thickened and closely driven together was
				made into stars, of which the moon being the heaviest is
				compacted of the grossest and muddiest matter. And yet
				it is plainly to be seen, that the moon is not separated or
				divided from the air, but moves and makes her revolution through that which is about her, to wit, the region
				of the winds, and where the comets are engendered
				and keep their course. These bodies then were not
				by a natural inclination thus placed and situated as they
				are, but have by some other reason been so ordered and
				disposed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>These things being said, as I was giving Lucius his
				turn to follow and continue the discourse,&mdash;there being
				nothing left to be added but the demonstrations of this
				doctrine,&mdash;Aristotle smiling said: I am a witness, that
				you have directed all your contradictions and all your refutations against those who, supposing the moon to be half
				fire, affirm in general that all bodies do of their own accord tend either upwards or downwards; but if there is
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.254"/>
				
				any one who holds that the stars have of their own nature
				a circular motion, and that they are of a substance wholly
				different from the four elements, you have not thought of
				saying any thing, so much as accidentally or by the way,
				against him; and therefore I am wholly unconcerned in
				your discourse.</p>
            <p>Indeed, good sir, said Lucius, if you should suppose the
					other stars, and the whole heaven apart, to be of a pure
					and sincere nature, free from all change and alteration of
					passion, and should bring in also a circle, in which they
					make their motion by a perpetual revolution, you would
					not perhaps find any one now to contradict you, though
					there are in this infinite doubts and difficulties. But when
					the discourse descends so far as to touch the moon, it cannot maintain in her that perfection of being exempt from
					all passion and alteration, nor that heavenly beauty of her
					body. But to let pass all other inequalities and differences,
					the very face which appears in the body of the moon necessarily proceeds from some passion of her own substance
					or the mixture of another; for what is mixed suffers, because it loses its first purity, being filled by force with that
					which is worse. Besides, as for the slowness and dulness
					of her course, her feeble and inefficacious heat, by which,
					as Ion says,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The black grape comes not to maturity,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>to what shall we attribute them but to her weakness and
					passion, if an eternal and celestial body can be subject to
					passion?</p>
            <p>In brief, my friend Aristotle, if the moon is earth, she is
					a most fair and admirable thing, and excellently well
					adorned; but if you regard her as a star or light or a certain divine and heavenly body, I am afraid she will prove
					deformed and foul, and disgrace that beautiful appellation,
					if of all bodies, which are in heaven so numerous, she
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.255"/>
					
					alone stands in need of light borrowed of another, and, as
					Parmenides has it,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Looks always backwards on the sun's bright rays.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Our friend therefore indeed, having in a lecture of his
					demonstrated this proposition of Anaxagoras, that the sun
					communicates to the moon what brightness she has, was
					well esteemed for it. As for me, I will not say what I
					have learned of you or with you, but having taken it for
					granted, will pass on to the rest. It is then probable that the
					moon is illuminated, not like a glass or crystal, by the
					brightness of the sun's rays shining through her, nor yet
					again, by a certain collustration and conjunction of light
					and brightness, as when many torches set together augment the light of one another. For so she would be no
					less full in her conjunction or first quarter than in her opposition, if she did not obstruct or repel the rays of the
					sun, but let them pass through her by reason of her rarity, or if he did by a contemperature shine upon her and
					kindle the light within her. For we cannot allege her
					declinations and aversions in the conjunction or new moon,
					as when it is half-moon or when she appears crescent or
					in the wane; but being then perpendicularly (as Democritus says) under him that illuminates her, she receives and
					admits the sun; so that then it is probable she should appear, and he shine through her. But this she is so far
					from doing, that she is not only then unseen, but also often
					hides the sun, as Empedocles has it:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sun's bright beams from us she turns aside,
						</l>
                     <l>And of the earth itself as much doth hide,
						</l>
                     <l>As her orb's breadth can cover;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if the light of the sun fell not upon another star, but
					upon night and darkness. And as for what Posidonius
					says, that the depth of the moon's body is the cause why
					the light of the sun cannot pierce through her to us, this
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.256"/>
					
					is evidently refuted; for the air, which is infinite and of a
					far greater depth than the body of the moon, is nevertheless all over illustrated and enlightened by the rays of the
					sun.</p>
            <p>It remains then that, according to the opinion of Empedocles, the light of the moon which appears to us comes
					from the repercussion and reflection of the sun's beams.
					And for this reason it comes not to us hot and bright, as in
					all probability it would, if her shining proceeded either
					from inflammation or the commixtion of two lights. But as
					voices reverberated cause an echo more obscure and less
					express than the speech that was pronounced, and as the
					blows of darts and arrows, rebounding from some wall
					against which they are shot, are more mild and gentle;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>So Titan's lustre, smiting the moon's orb,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>yields but a faint and feeble reflection and repercussion of
					brightness upon us, its force being abated and weakened
					by the refraction.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Sylla then, taking up the discourse, said: There is
				indeed a great deal of probability in all that you have
				spoken. But as to the strongest objection that is brought
				against it, has it, think you, been any way weakened by
				this discourse? Or has our friend quite passed it over in
				silence?</p>
            <p>What opposition do you mean, said Lucius? Is it the
					difficulty about the moon, when one half of her appears
					enlightened?</p>
            <p>The very same, answered Sylla. For there is some
					reason, seeing that all reflection is made by equal angles,
					that when the half-moon is in the midst of heaven, the
					light proceeding from her should not be carried upon the
					earth, but glance and fall beyond and on one side of it.
					For the sun, being placed in the horizon, touches the moon
					with its beams; which, being equally reflected, will therefore
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.257"/>
					
					 necessarily fall on the other bound of the horizon, and
					not send their light down hither; or else there will be a great
					distortion and difference of the angle, which is impossible.</p>
            <p>And yet, by Jupiter, replied Lucius, this has not been
					forgotten or overpassed, but already spoken to. And casting his eye, as he was discoursing, upon the mathematician
					Menelaus; I am ashamed, said he, in your presence, dear
					Menelaus, to attempt the subverting and overthrowing of a
					mathematical position, which is supposed as a basis and
					foundation to the doctrine of the catoptrics concerning the
					causes and reasons of mirrors. And yet of necessity I
					must. For it neither appears of itself nor is confessed as
					true, that all reflections are at equal angles; but this
					position is first checked and contradicted in concave mirrors, when they represent the images of things, appearing
					at one point of sight, greater than the things themselves.
					And it is also disproved by double mirrors, which being
					inclined or turned one towards the other, so that an angle
					is made within, each of the glasses or plain superficies
					yields a double resemblance; so that there are four images
					from the same face, two answerable to the object without
					on the left side, and two others obscure and not so evident
					on the right side in the bottom of the mirror. Of which
					Plato renders the efficient cause; for he says, that a mirror
					being raised on the one and the other side, the sight varies
					the reflection, falling from one side to the other. And
					therefore, since of the views or visions some immediately
					have recourse to us, and others, sliding to opposite parts
					of the mirror, do again return upon us from thence, it is
					not possible that all reflections should be made at equal
					angles. Though those who closely impugn our opinion
					contend that, by these reflections of light from the moon
					upon the earth, the equality of angles is taken away,
					thinking this to be much more probable than the other.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, if we must of necessity yield and grant
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.258"/>
					
					thus much to our dearly beloved geometry, first, this should
					in all likelihood befall those mirrors which are perfectly
					smooth and exquisitely polished; whereas the moon has
					many inequalities and roughnesses, so that the rays proceeding from a vast body, and carried to mighty altitudes,
					receive one from another and intercommunicate their lights,
					which, being sent to and fro and reciprocally distributed,
					are refracted and interlaced all manner of ways, and the
					counter-lights meet one another, as if they came to us from
					several mirrors. And then, though we should suppose
					these reflections on the superficies of the moon to be made
					at equal angles, yet it is not impossible that the rays, coming down unto us by so long an interval, may have their
					flexions, fractions, and delapsions, that the light being
					compounded may shine the more. Some also there are
					who prove by lineary demonstration, that many lights send
					a ray down by a line drawn below the line of reflection;
					but to make the description and delineation of it publicly,
					especially where there were many auditors, would not be
					very easy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>But in brief, said he, I wonder how they come thus
				to allege against us the half-moon, there being the same
				reason when she is gibbous and crescent. For if the sun
				enlightened the moon, as a mass of ethereal or fiery matter,
				he would never surely leave one hemisphere, or half of
				her globe always appearing dark and shadowy to sense, as
				it is seen to be; but how little soever he touched her superficies, it would be agreeable to reason that it should be
				wholly replenished and totally changed by that light of his,
				which by reason of its agility and swiftness so easily spreads
				and passes through all. For, since wine touching water
				only in one point, or one drop of blood falling into any
				liquor, dyes and colors it all with a red or purple color;
				and since they say, that the very air is altered and changed
				with light, not by any defluxions or beams intermingled,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.259"/>
				
				but by a sudden conversion and change made in one only
				point; how can they imagine that one star touching another star, and one light another light, should not be immediately mingled, nor make any thorough confusion or
				change, but only exteriorly illuminate that whose superficies it touches? For that circle which the sun makes by
				fetching a compass and turning towards the moon,&mdash;sometimes falling upon the very line that distinguishes her visible part from her invisible, and sometimes rising up directly,
				so that it cuts her in two and is reciprocally cut by her,
				causing in her, by several inclinations and habitudes of the
				luminous to the dark, those various forms by which she
				appears gibbous and crescent,&mdash;that more than any thing
				else demonstrates, that all this illumination of the moon is
				not a mixture, but only a touching; nor a conflux or
				gathering together of sundry lights, but only an illustration round about.</p>
            <p>But forasmuch as she is not only enlightened herself,
					but also sends back hither the image of her illumination,
					this confirms us yet further in what we say touching her
					substance. For reflections and reverberations are not made
					upon any thing which is rare, and of thin and subtile parts;
					nor is it easily to be imagined how light can rebound from
					light, or one fire from another. But that which is to make
					the reverberation or reflection must be solid and firm, that
					a blow may be given against it and a rebounding made
					from it. As a proof of this, we see that the air transmits
					the sun, and gives him a way to pierce quite through it, not
					obstructing or driving back his rays; but on the contrary
					from wood, stones, or clothes put in the sun, there are made
					many reflections of light and many illuminations round
					about. So we see that the earth is illuminated by him, not
					to the very bottom, as the water, nor thoroughly and all
					over, as the air, through which the beams of the sun have
					a clear passage; but just such a circle as surrounds the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.260"/>
					
					moon surrounds also the earth; and as much of the earth
					as this circle includes, so much does the sun enlighten, the
					rest being left without light; for what is illuminated both
					in the one and in the other is little more than an hemisphere. Permit me therefore now to conclude after the
					manner of geometricians by proportions. If there are
					three things which the light of the sun approaches, the
					air, the moon, and the earth, and if we see that the moon
					is enlightened by him, not as the air, but as the earth, it
					is of necessity that those two things must have one and
					the same nature, which of one and the same cause suffer
					the same effects.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Now when all the company began highly to commend Lucius's harangue; This is excellently well done
				of you, Lucius (said I to him), that you have to so fine a
				discourse added as fine a proportion, for you must not be
				defrauded of that which is your due.</p>
            <p>Then Lucius, smiling, thus went on: I have yet a
					second proportion to be added to the former, by which we
					will clearly demonstrate that the moon altogether resembles the earth, not only because they suffer and receive the
					same accidents from the same cause, but because they
					work the same effect on the same object. For you will
					without difficulty, I suppose, grant me that, of all the
					accidents which befall the sun, there is none so like to his
					setting as his eclipse, especially if you but call to mind that
					recent conjunction which, beginning at noonday, showed
					us many stars in many places of the heavens, and wrought
					a temperature in the air like that of the twilight. But if
					you will not grant me this, our friend Theon here will
					bring us a Mimnermus, a Cydias, an Archilochus, and besides these, a Stesichorus and a Pindar, lamenting that in
					eclipses the world is robbed of its brightest light, and saying that night comes on in the midst of the day, and that
					the rays of the sun wander in the path of darkness; but
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.261"/>
					
					above all he will produce Homer, saying that the faces of
					men are in eclipses seized upon by night and darkness,
					and the sun is quite lost out of heaven by the conjunction
					of the moon. And . . . it is natural that this should
					happen,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When one moon's going, and another comes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the rest of the demonstration is, in my opinion, as certain and exactly concluding, as are the acute arguments of
					the mathematics. As night is the shadow of the earth, so
					the eclipse of the sun is the shadow of the moon, when it
					stands in the way of our sight. For the sun is at his setting kept from our sight by the interposition of the earth,
					and at his eclipse by that of the moon. Now both of
					these are obscurations; but that of his setting is from the
					earth, and that of his being eclipsed from the moon, their
					shadows intercepting our sight. Now the consequences
					of these things are easily understood. For if the effect is
					alike, the efficient causes are also alike; because it is of
					necessity that the same effects, happening in the same
					subjects, proceed from the same efficients. Now if the
					darkness in eclipses is not so profound, nor does so forcibly and entirely seize the air, as does the night, we are not
					to wonder at it; for the substance of the body which
					makes the night, and of that which causes the eclipse,
					is indeed the same, though their greatness is not equal.
					For the Egyptians, if I am not mistaken, hold that the
					moon is in bigness the two and seventieth part of the earth;
					and Anaxagoras says, she is as big as Peloponnesus. And
					Aristarchus shows the overthwart line or diameter of the
					moon to have a proportion to that of the earth which is
					less than if sixty were compared to nineteen, and somewhat greater than an hundred and eight compared to forty
					and three. Whence it happens that the earth, by reason
					of its greatness, wholly withdraws the sun from our sight;
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.262"/>
					
					for it is a great obstacle and opposition, and lasts all the
					night. But although the moon sometimes hides all the
					sun, yet that eclipse continues not so long nor is so far extended, but there always appears about the circumference
					a certain brightness, which permits not the darkness to be
					black, deep, and perfectly obscure.</p>
            <p>And Aristotle (I mean the ancient philosopher of that
					name) rendering the reason why there are oftener seen to
					happen eclipses of the moon than of the sun, among other
					causes alleges this, that the sun is eclipsed by the interposition of the moon, and the moon by that of the earth,
					which is much greater and consequently oftener opposes
					itself. And Posidonius thus defines this accident: The
					eclipse of the sun is the conjunction of the sun and moon,
					the shadow of which darkens our sight.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Here again the text is defective, and the sense conjectural. (G.)</note> For there is no
					eclipse except to those whose sight the shadow of the moon
					intercepting hinders them from seeing the sun. Now in
					confessing that the shadow of the moon descends down to
					us, I know not what he has left himself to say. It is certainly impossible for a star to cast a shadow; for that
					which is not enlightened is called a shadow, and light
					makes no shadow, but on the contrary drives it away.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>But what arguments, said he, were alleged after
				this?</p>
            <p>The moon, answered I then, suffered the same eclipse.</p>
            <p>You have done well, replied he, to put me in mind of it.
					But would you have me go on and prosecute the rest of
					the discourse, as if you had already supposed and granted
					that the moon is eclipsed, being intercepted within the
					shadow of the earth? Or shall I take for the subject of a
					declamation the making a demonstration of it, by rehearsing to you all the arguments, one after another?</p>
            <p>Nay, by Jove, said Theon, let this be the argument of
					your discourse. For I indeed stand in need of some persuasion,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.263"/>
					
					 having only heard that when these three bodies,
					the earth, the moon, and the sun, are in a direct line, then
					eclipses happen; for that either the earth takes the sun
					from the moon, or the moon takes him from the earth. For
					the sun suffers an eclipse when the moon, and the moon
					when the earth, is in the midst of the three; of which
					the one happens in the conjunction or new moon, and the
					other in the opposition or when the moon is full.</p>
            <p>Then said Lucius: These are the principal points, and
					the summary of what is said. But in the first place, if
					you please, take the argument drawn from the form and
					figure of the shadow. For this is a cone, as it must be
					when a great fire or light that is spherical encompasses a
					mass that is also globular but less; whence it comes that,
					in the eclipses of the moon, the circumscriptions of the
					black and dark from the clear and luminous have their
					sections always round. For the sections given or received
					by one round body applied to another, which way soever
					they go, do by reason of the similitude always keep a circular form. Now as for the second argument, I suppose
					you understand that the first part which is eclipsed in the
					moon is always that which looks towards the east, and in
					the sun that which regards the west. Now the shadow of
					the earth moves from the east to the west, but the sun and
					moon from the west eastward. The experience of the appearances gives us a visible knowledge of this, nor is there
					need of many words to make us fully understand it; and
					from these suppositions the cause of the eclipse is confirmed. For, inasmuch as the sun is eclipsed by being
					overtaken, and the moon by meeting that which makes
					the eclipse, it probably or rather necessarily follows that
					the one is surprised behind, and the other before.
					For the obstruction begins on that side whence that
					which causes it first approaches. Now the moon comes
					upon the sun from the west, as striving in course with
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.264"/>
					
					him and hastening after him; but the shadow of the earth
					comes from the east, as that which has a contrary motion.</p>
            <p>The third argument is taken from the time and greatness of the eclipses. For the moon, if she is eclipsed
					when she is on high in her apogee (or at her farthest distance from the earth), continues but a little while in her
					defect or want of light; but when she suffers the same
					accident being low and in her perigee (or near the earth),
					she is very much oppressed, and slowly gets out of the
					shadow; and yet, when she is low, she moves swifter, and
					when high, slower. But the cause of the difference is in
					the shadow, which is, like pyramids, broadest at the bottom or basis; and, growing still narrower by little and
					little, terminates in a sharp point at the top. Whence it
					comes, that when she is low, she is embarrassed within
					greater circles, traversing the bottom of the shadow and
					what is most obscure and dark; but when she is high, being through the narrowness of the shadow (as it were) but
					in a shallow puddle, by which she is sullied, she immediately gets out again. I omit what was said particularly
					about the bases and disposition of parts, for these admit
					of a rational explanation, so far as this is possible; but I
					return to the subject properly before us, which has its
					foundation in our senses. For we see that fire shines
					forth and appears brighter out of a dark and shady place,
					through the thickness of the caliginous air, which admits
					no effluxions or diffusions of the fire's virtue, but keeps in
					and contains its substance within itself. Or rather,&mdash;if
					this is a passion of the senses,&mdash;as hot things, when near
					to cold ones, are felt to be hotter, and pleasures immediately after pains are found more vehement, so things
					that are bright appear better when they are near to such
					as are obscure, the imagination being more strained and
					extended by means of different passions. But there seems
					to be a greater appearance of probability in the first reason.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.265"/>
					
					 For in the sun, all the nature of fire not only loses
					its faculty of illuminating, but is also rendered duller and
					more unapt to burn, because the heat of the sun dissipates
					and scatters all its force.</p>
            <p>If it were then true that the moon, being, as the Stoics
					say, a muddy and troubled star, has a weak and duskish
					fire, it would be meet that she should suffer none of these
					accidents which she is now seen to suffer, but altogether
					the contrary; to wit, that she should be seen when she is
					hidden, and absconded when she appears; that is, she
					should be concealed all the rest of the time, being obscured
					by the environing air, and again shine forth and become
					apparent and manifest for six months together, and afterwards disappear again five months, entering into the shadow
					of the earth. For of four hundred and sixty-five revolutions of ecliptic full moons, four hundred and four are of
					six months' duration, and the rest of five. The moon
					then should all this time appear shining in the shadow;
					but on the contrary we see, that in the shadow she is
					eclipsed and loses her light, and recovers it again after
					she is escaped and got forth of the shadow. Nay, she appears often in the daytime, so that she is rather any thing
					else than a fiery and starry body.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>As soon as Lucius had said these things, Pharnaces
				and Apollonides ran both together upon him, to oppugn
				and refute his discourse; and then Apollonides giving him
				way, Pharnaces said: This it is that principally shows the
				moon to be a star and of a fiery nature, that in her eclipses she is not wholly obscured and disappearing, but
				shows herself with a certain coal-resembling color, terrible to the sight, yet such as is proper to her.</p>
            <p>As for Apollonides, he insisted much in opposition to
					the word shadow, saying, that the mathematicians always
					give that name to the place which is not enlightened, and
					that heaven admits no shadow.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.266"/>
            <p>To this I thus answered: This instance is rather alleged
					obstinately against the name, than naturally or mathematically against the thing. For if one will not call the
					place obfuscated by the opposition of the earth a shadow,
					but a place deprived of light, yet be it what it will, you
					must of necessity confess that the moon being there becomes obscure; and every way, said I, it is a folly to deny
					that the shadow of the earth reaches thither from whence
					the shadow of the moon, falling upon our sight here on
					earth, causes the eclipse of the sun. And therefore I now
					address myself to you, Pharnaces; for this coal-like and
					burnt color of the moon, which you affirm to be proper to
					her, belongs to a body that has thickness and depth. For
					there is not wont to remain any relic, mark, or print of
					flame in a body that is rare, nor can a coal be made where
					there is not a solid body which may receive into it the
					heat of the fire; as Homer himself shows in a certain passage, where he says,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then, when the languid flames at length subside,
						</l>
                     <l>He strows a bed of glowing embers wide.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 212.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the coal seems not properly a fire, but a body enkindled and altered by the fire, which stays and remains
					in a solid firmly rooted mass; and whereas flames are the
					setting on fire and fluxions of a nutriment and matter,
					which is of a rare substance, and by reason of its weakness
					quickly dissolved and consumed; so that there could not
					be any more evident and plain argument to demonstrate
					that the moon is solid and earthly, than if 'her proper
					color were that of a coal. But it is not so, my friend
					Pharnaces; but in her eclipses she diversely changes her
					colors, which the mathematicians, determining with respect
					to the time and hour, thus distinguish. If she is eclipsed
					in the evening, she appears horribly black until the middle
					of the fourth hour of the night; if about midnight, she
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.267"/>
					
					sends forth this reddish and fire-resembling color, and after
					the middle of the eighth hour, the redness disappears;
					and finally, if about the dawning of the morning, she takes
					a blue or grayish color; which is the cause why she
					is by the poets, and particularly by Empedocles, called
					Glaucopis.</p>
            <p>Since then they clearly see that the moon changes into
					so many colors in the shadow, they do ill to attribute to
					her only that of a burning coal, which may be said to be
					less proper to her than any other, being only a small
					remnant and semblance of light, appearing and shining
					through a shadow, her own proper color being black and
					earthy. And since that here below, red and purple garments, and rivers and lakes, which receive the rays of the
					sun, cause neighboring shady places to take the same
					appearances of colors and to be illuminated by them, casting and sending back by reason of reflections several rebated splendors; what wonder is it if a copious flux of
					shadow, falling as it were into an immense celestial sea of
					light, not steady and quiet, but agitated by innumerable
					stars, and besides admitting several mixtures and mutations
					in itself, takes from the moon the impression sometimes
					of one color, sometimes of another, and sends them hither
					to us? For it is not to be denied but that a star of fire
					cannot appear in a shadow black, gray, or violet; but
					there are seen upon hills, plains, and seas, several various
					resemblances of colors, caused by the reflection of the sun,
					which are the very tinctures that brightness mixed with
					shadows and mists, as if it were with painters' colors,
					brings upon them. And as for the tincture or colors of the
					sea, Homer has indeed in some sort endeavored to name
					and express them, when he sometimes terms the sea violet-colored or red as wine, at other times the waves purple,
					and again the sea blue, and the calm white. As for the
					diversities of tinctures and colors appearing upon the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.268"/>
					
					earth, he has, I suppose, omitted them, because they are
					in number infinite. Now it is not probable that the moon
					has but one superficies all plain and even, as the sea; but
					rather that of its nature it principally resembles the earth,
					of which old Socrates in Plato seemed to mythologize at
					his pleasure; whether it were, that under covert and enigmatical speeches he meant it of the moon, or whether he
					spake it of some other. For it is neither incredible nor
					wonderful, if the moon, having in herself nothing corrupt
					or muddy, but enjoying a pure and clear light from heaven,
					and being full of heat, not of a burning and furious fire,
					but of such as is mild and harmless, has in her places
					admirably fair and pleasant, resplendent mountains, purple-colored cinctures or zones, and store of gold and silver,
					not dispersed here and there within her bowels, but flourishing in great abundance on the superficies of her plains,
					or spread all over her smooth hills and mountains.</p>
            <p>And if the sight of all these things comes to us through
					a shadow, sometimes in one manner and sometimes in another, by reason of the diversity and different change of
					the ambient air, the moon does not therefore lose the
					venerable persuasion that is had of her, or the reputation
					of divinity; being esteemed by men a heavenly earth, or
					rather (as the Stoics say) a troubled, thick, and dreggish
					fire. For even the fire itself is honored with barbarian
					honors among the Assyrians and Medes, who through fear
					serve and adore such things as are hurtful, hallowing them
					even above such things as are of themselves indeed holy
					and honorable. But the very name of the earth is truly
					dear and venerable to every Greek, and there is through
					all Greece a custom received of adoring and revering it,
					as much as any of the Gods. And we are very far from
					thinking that the moon, which we hold to be a heavenly
					earth, is a body without soul and spirit, exempt and deprived of all that is to be offered to the Gods. For both
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.269"/>
					
					by law we yield her recompenses and thanksgivings, for
					that we receive of her and by nature we adore what we
					acknowledge to be of a more excellent virtue and a more
					honorable power; and therefore we do not think that we
					offend in supposing the moon to be earth.</p>
            <p>Now as to the face which appears in her, as this earth
					on which we are has in it many great sinuosities and valleys, so it is probable that the moon also lies open, and is
					cleft with many deep caves and ruptures, in which there is
					water or very obscure air, to the bottom of which the sun
					cannot reach or penetrate, but failing there, sends back a
					dissipated reflection to us here below.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Here Apollonides, taking up the discourse, said:
				Tell me then, I beseech you, good sir, even by the moon
				herself, do you think it possible that there should be there
				shadows of caves and chinks, and that the sight of them
				should come even to our eyes? Or do you not regard
				what will come of it? And must I tell you what it is?
				But hearken to me, although you are not ignorant of it.
				The diameter of the moon, according to that bigness which
				appears to us when she is in her mean and ordinary distances, is twelve digits, and every one of these black and
				shady spots is above half a digit, that is above the four
				and twentieth part of the diameter. Now if we suppose
				the circumference of the moon to be only thirty thousand
				stadia; and the diameter according to that supposition to
				be ten thousand, every one of these shadowy marks within
				her will not be less than five hundred stadia. Consider
				then, first, whether there can possibly be in the moon such
				great gaps and such inequalities as may make such a
				shadow? And then how is it possible that, being so great,
				they are not seen by us?</p>
            <p>At this I, smiling upon him, said: You have done me a
					pleasure, dear Apollonides, in having found out such a
					demonstration by which you will prove that you and I
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.270"/>
					
					shall be bigger than those giant sons of Aloeus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Otus and Ephialtes.</note>&mdash;not
					indeed every hour of the day, but principally morning and
					evening,&mdash;if indeed you think that, when the sun makes
					our shadows so long, he suggests to our minds this goodly
					argument; if that which is shadowed is great, that which
					shadows must of necessity be yet excessively greater. I
					know well that neither you nor I have ever been in Lemnos; yet we have often heard that Iambic verse, so frequent
					in every one's mouth:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mount Athos' shade shall hide the Lemnian cow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For the shadow of that mountain falls, as it seems, on
					the image of a brazen heifer which is in Lemnos, extending itself in length over the sea not less than seven hundred stadia. . . . The mountain which makes the shadow
					causes it, because the distance of the light renders the
					shadow of bodies manifoldly greater than the bodies themselves. Consider then here, that when the moon is in the
					full, and shows us the form of a visage most expressly, by
					reason of the profundity of the shadow, it is then that she
					is most remote from the sun; for it is the distance of the
					light that makes the shadow bigger, and not the greatness
					of the inequalities which are on the superficies of the
					moon. And you moreover see, that the brightness of the
					sun's beams suffers not the tops of the mountains to be discerned in open day; but on the contrary, the deep hollow
					and shadowy parts appear from afar. It is not therefore
					any way absurd or strange, if we cannot so exactly see
					how the illumination of the moon and her reception of
					the sunbeams take place, while yet the conjunction of
					things that are obscure and dark to such as are clear and
					shining is by reason of this diversity apparent to our
					sight.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But this, said I, seems rather to refute and check
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.271"/>
				
				the reflection and reverberation which is said to rebound
				from the moon; because those who are within retorted
				rays do not only see that which is enlightened, but also
				that which enlightens. For when, at the resulting of
				light from water upon a wall, the sight falls upon the
				place which is thus illuminated by the reflection, the eye
				there beholds three things, to wit, the ray or light that is
				driven back, the water which makes the reflection, and the
				sun himself, whose light, falling on the superficies of the
				water, is repulsed and sent back. This being confessed,
				as what is evidently seen, it is required of those who say
				that the earth is enlightened from the moon by the reflections of the sun's rays upon it, that they show us by night
				the sun appearing upon the superficies of the moon, in the
				same manner as he may be seen by day appearing in the
				water on which he shines when there is the said reflection
				of his beams. But since the sun does not so appear, they
				thence infer that the moon receives her illumination by
				some other means, and not by reflection; and if there is
				no reflection, the moon then is not earth.</p>
            <p>What answer then is to be made them, said Apollonides? For the argument of this objection against reflection is common also to us.</p>
            <p>It is indeed, answered I, in some sort common, and in
					some sort not. But first consider the comparison, how
					perversely and against the stream they take it. For the
					water is here below on the earth, and the moon there
					above in heaven. So that the reflected and reverberated
					rays make the form of their angles quite opposite one to
					the other, the one having their point upwards towards the
					superficies of the moon, and the other downwards toward
					the earth. Let them not then require that from every
					form of mirror, nor that from every distance and remoteness, there should be a like and semblable reflection; for
					so doing, they would repugn notorious and apparent evidence.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.272"/>
					
					 And as for those who hold the moon to be a body
					not smooth, even, and subtile as the water, but solid, massy,
					and terrestrial, I cannot conceive why they should require
					to see the image of the sun in her as in a glass. For
					neither does mill itself render such peculiar images, nor
					cause reflection of the sight, by reason of the inequality
					and ruggedness of its parts. How then is it possible that
					the moon should send back the sight from her superficies,
					as mirrors do that are more polished? And if in these
					also there is any scratch, filth, or dulness on their superficies whence the reflected sight is wont to receive a form,
					they are dimmed, and although the mirrors may be seen,
					they yield no counterlight. He then who requires that
					either the sun should appear in the moon, or else the moon
					should not reflect the sun's light to us, might as well require
					that the eye be the sun, the sight light, and man heaven.
					For it is probable, that the reflection of the sun's beams
					which is made upon the moon does, by reason of their
					vehemence and great brightness, rebound with a stroke
					upon us. But our sight being weak and slender, what
					wonder is it, if it neither give such a stroke as may rebound, or if it rebounds, that it does not maintain its
					continuity, but is broken and fails, as not having such
					abundance of light that it should not disgregate and be
					dissipated within those inequalities and asperities? For
					it is not impossible, that the reflection upon water or other
					sorts of mirrors, being yet strong, powerful, and near its
					origin, should from thence return upon the eye; but though
					there may perhaps from the moon be some glimmerings,
					yet they still will be weak and obscure, and will fail in the
					way, by reason of so long a distance. For otherwise hollow and concave mirrors send back the reverberated and
					reflected rays stronger than they came, so that they frequently burn and set on fire; and those that are convex
					and embossed like a bowl, because they beat them not back
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.273"/>
					
					on all sides, render them dark and feeble. You see for
					certain, when two rainbows appear together in the heaven,
					one cloud comprehending another, that the rainbow which
					outwardly environs the other yields dim colors, and such
					as are not sufficiently distinguished and expressed, because
					the exterior cloud, being more remote, makes not a strong
					and forcible reflection. And what needs there any more
					to be said, seeing that the very light of the sun, reverberated and sent back by the moon, loses all its heat; and of
					his brightness, there comes to us with much ado but a
					small remainder, and that very languishing and weak? Is
					it then possible, that our sight, turning the same course,
					should bring back any part of the solar image from the
					moon? I for my part think it is not. But consider, I
					said, yourselves, that if our sight were in one and the
					same manner affected and disposed towards the water and
					towards the moon, the full moon would of necessity represent to us the images of the earth, plants, men, and stars,
					as is done by the water and all other sorts of mirrors.
					And if there is no such reflection of our sight as to bring
					us back these images, either by reason of our said sight's
					weakness, or through the rugged inequality of the moon's
					superficies, let us no longer require that it should rebound
					against the sun.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>We have then, said I, related, as far as our memory
				would carry it away, whatever was there said. It is now
				time to desire Sylla, or rather to exact of him, that he
				would make us his narration, as being on such condition
				admitted to hear all this discourse. If you think good
				therefore, let us give over walking, and sitting down on
				these seats, make him a quiet and settled audience.</p>
            <p>Every one approved this motion. And therefore, when
					we had seated ourselves, Theon thus began: I am indeed,
					O Lamprias, as desirous as any of you can be to hear
					what shall be said; but I would gladly first understand
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.274"/>
					
					something concerning those who are said to dwell in the
					moon; not whether there are any persons inhabiting it,
					but whether it is impossible there should be any; for if it
					is not possible for the moon to be inhabited, it is also unreasonable to say that she is earth; otherwise she would
					have been created in vain and to no end, not bearing any
					fruits, not affording a place for the birth or education of
					any men, for which causes and ends this earth wherein we
					live was made and created, being (as Plato says) our nurse
					and true guardian, producing and distinguishing the day
					from the night. Now you know, that of this matter many
					things have been said, as well merrily and in jest as
					seriously and in earnest. For of those who dwell under
					the moon, it is said that she hangs over their heads, as if
					they were so many Tantaluses; and on the contrary, of
					those who inhabit her, that being tied and bound to her,
					like a sort of Ixious, they are with violence turned and
					whirled about. Nor is the moon indeed moved by one
					only motion, but is, as they were wont to call her, Trivia,
					or Three-wayed; performing her course together according
					to length, breadth, and depth in the Zodiac; the first of
					which motions mathematicians call a direct revolution, the
					second volutation, or an oblique winding and wheeling in
					and out; and the third (I know not why) an inequality;
					although they see that she has no motion uniform, settled,
					and certain, in all her circuits and reversions. Wherefore
					it is not greatly to be admired, if through violence of her
					motion there sometime fell a lion from her into Peloponnesus, but it is rather to be wondered, that we do not daily
					see ten thousand falls of men and women and shocks of
					other animals tumbling down thence with their heels upwards on our heads; for it would be a mockery to dispute
					about their habitation there, if they can have there neither
					birth nor existence. For seeing the Egyptians and the
					Troglodytes, over whose heads the sun directly stands only
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.275"/>
					
					one moment of one day in the solstice, and then presently
					retires, can hardly escape being burnt, by reason of the
					air's excessive dryness; is it credible that those who are
					in the moon can bear every year twelve solstices, the sun
					being once a month just in their zenith, when the moon is
					full? As for winds, clouds, and showers, without which
					the plants can neither come up nor, when they are come
					up, be preserved, it cannot be so much as imagined there
					should be any, where the ambient air is so hot, dry, and
					subtile; since even here below, the tops of mountains
					never feel those hard and bitter winters, but the air, being
					there pure and clear, without any agitation, by reason of
					its lightness, avoids all that thickness and concretion which
					is amongst us; unless, by Jupiter, we will say that, as
					Minerva instilled nectar and ambrosia into the mouth of
					Achilles, when he received no other food, so the moon,
					which both is called and indeed is Minerva, nourishes men,
					producing for them and sending them every day ambrosia,
					with which, as old Pherecydes was wont to say, the Gods
					themselves are fed. For as touching that Indian root,
					which, as Megasthenes says, some people in those parts,
					who neither eat nor drink, but have pure mouths, burn
					and smoke, living on the smell of its perfume; whence
					should they have any of it there, the moon not being
					watered or refreshed with rain?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>When Theon had spoken these things; You have
				very dexterously and gently, said I to him, by this facetiousness of yours smoothed as it were the brow, and taken off
				the chagrin and sourness of this discourse; which encourages and emboldens us to return an answer, since, however
				we may chance to fail, we expect not any severe or rigorous
				chastisement. For, to speak the truth, they who are extremely offended with these things and wholly discredit
				them, not being willing mildly to consider what probability
				and possibility there may be in them, are not much less in
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.276"/>
				
				fault than those that are too excessively persuaded of them.
				First then, I say, it is not necessary that the moon must
				have been made in vain and to no end or purpose, if there
				are not men who dwell in it; for we see that this very
				earth here is not all cultivated or inhabited, but that only
				a small part of it, like so many promontories or demi-islands arising out of the deep, engenders, brings forth,
				and breeds plants and animals; the rest being through
				excessive cold or heat wholly desert and barren, or (which
				is indeed the greatest share of it) covered and plunged
				under the vast ocean. But you, who are always so great a
				lover and admirer of Aristarchus, give no ear to Crates
				when he reads in Homer,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The sea, which gave to Gods and men their birth,
					</l>
                     <l>Covers with waves the most part of the earth.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. XIV. 246. The second of these verses is not found in the present text
						of the Iliad, but was probably defended by Crates against Aristarchus. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet those parts are far from having been made in vain.
					For the sea exhales and breathes out mild vapors; and the
					snow, leisurely melting from the cold and uninhabited
					regions, sends forth and spreads over all our countries
					those gentle breezes which qualify the scorching heat of
					summer; and in the midst, as Plato says, is placed the
					faithful guardian and operator of night and day. There is
					then nothing to hinder but that the moon may be without
					living creatures, and yet give reflections to the light that is
					diffused about her, and afford a receptacle to the rays of
					the stars, which have their confluence and temperature in
					her, for to digest the evaporation rising from the earth and
					moderate the over-violent and fiery heat of the sun. And
					attributing much to ancient fame, we will say that she is
					styled Diana, as being a virgin and fruitless, but otherwise
					greatly salutary, helpful, and profitable to the world.
					Moreover, of all that has been said, my friend Theon, there
					is nothing which shows it impossible for the moon to be
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.277"/>
					
					inhabited. For her turning about, being gentle, mild, and
					calm, dulcifies and polishes the ambient air, and distributes
					it in so good order about her, that there is no occasion to
					fear the falling or slipping out of those who live in her.
					And as to the diversity and multiplicity of her motion, it
					proceeds not from any inequality, error, or uncertainty, but
					the astrologers show in this an admirable order and course,
					enclosing her within circles, which are turned by other
					circles; some supposing that she herself stirs not, others
					making her always move equally, smoothly, and with the
					same swiftness. For it is these ascensions of divers circles,
					with their turnings and habitudes, one towards another and
					with respect to us, which most exactly make those heights,
					depths, and depressions, that appear to us in her motion,
					and her digressions in latitude, all joined with the ordinary
					revolution she makes in longitude. As to the great heat
					and continual inflammation of the sun, you will cease to
					fear it, if first to the eleven estival conjunctions you oppose
					the full moons, and then to the excesses the continuity of
					change which permits them not to last long, reducing them
					to a proper and peculiar temperature, and taking from
					them both what is over much; for the middle, or what is
					between them, it is probable, has a season most like to the
					spring. And, moreover, the sun sends his beams to us
					through a gross and troubled air, and casts on us an heat
					fed by exhalation; whereas the air, being there subtile and
					transparent, dissipates and disperses his lustre, which has
					no nourishment nor body on which it may settle. Trees
					and fruits are here nourished by showers; but elsewhere, as
					in the higher countries with you about Thebes and Syene,
					the earth drinking in not aerial but earth-bred water, and
					being assisted with refreshing winds and dew, will not
					(such is the virtue and temperature of the soil) yield the
					first place for fertility to the best watered land in the
					world. And the same sorts of trees which in our country,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.278"/>
					
					having suffered a long and sharp winter, bring forth abundance of good fruit, are in Africa and with you in Egypt
					soon offended with cold and very fearful of the winter.
					And the provinces of Gedrosia and Troglodytis, which lie
					near the ocean sea, being by reason of drought barren and
					without any trees, there grow nevertheless in the adjacent
					sea trees of a wonderful height and bigness, and green
					even to the very bottom; some of which they call olive-trees, others laurels, and others the hair of Isis. And
					those plants which are named anacampserotes, being
					hanged up after they are plucked out of the ground, not
					only live, but&mdash;which is more&mdash;bud and put forth green
					leaves. Some seeds are sown in winter; and others in the
					heat of summer, like sesame and millet. And thyme or
					centaury, if it is sown in a rich and fat earth, and there
					well drenched and watered, degenerates from its natural
					quality and all its virtue, because it loves dryness and
					thrives in its own proper natural soil. Others cannot bear
					so much as the least dew, of which kind are the most part
					of the Arabian plants, and if they are but once wet, they
					wither, fade, and die. What wonder is it then, if there
					grow in the moon roots, seeds, and plants which have no
					need of rains or winter colds, and are appropriated to a
					dry and subtile air, such as is that of summer? And why
					may it not be probable that the moon sends forth warm
					winds, and that her shaking and agitation, as she moves, is
					accompanied by comfortable breezes, fine dews, and gentle
					moistures, which are everywhere dispersed to furnish
					nutriment for the verdant plants?&mdash;seeing she is not of
					her temperature ardent or parched with drought, but rather
					soft, moist, and engendering all humidity. For there come
					not from her to us any effects of dryness, but many of a
					feminine moisture and softness, such as are the growing of
					plants, the putrefaction of flesh, the changing and flatness
					of wines, the tenderness and rotting of wood, and the easy
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.279"/>
					
					deliveries of child-bearing women. But because I am
					afraid of irritating again and provoking Pharnaces&mdash;who
					all this while speaks not a word&mdash;if I should allege the
					flowing and ebbing of the great ocean (as they themselves
					say), and the increasing of the friths and straits, which
					swell and rise by the moon augmenting the moisture;
					therefore I will rather turn myself to you, my friend
					Theon. For you, interpreting this verse of the poet
					Alcman,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such things as dew, Jove's daughter and the moon's,
						</l>
                     <l>Does nourish,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>tell us, that in this place he calls the air Jupiter, which,
					being moistened by the moon, is by Nature changed into
					dew. For she seems, my good friend, to be of a nature
					almost wholly contrary to the sun, not only in that she is
					wonted to moisten, dissolve, and soften what he thickens,
					dries, and hardens; but moreover, in that she allays and
					cools his heat, when it lights upon her and is mingled with
					her.</p>
            <p>Those then who think the moon to be a fiery and burning body are in an error; and in like manner those who
					would have all such things to be necessary for the generation, life, food, and entertainment of the animals dwelling
					there as are requisite to those that are here below, consider not the vast diversity and inequality there is in Nature; in which there are found greater varieties and differences between animals and animals, than there are between
					animals and other subjects that are not animated. There
					are surely not in the world any men of such pure mouths
					that they feed only on smells. . . . But that power of Nature which Ammonius himself has shown us, and which
					Hesiod has obscurely signified in these words,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor how great virtue is in asphodels and mallows,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 41.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Epimenides has made plain to us in effect, teaching us that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.280"/>
					
					Nature sustains a living creature with very little food, and
					that, provided it has but the quantity of an olive, it stands
					in need of no other nourishment. Now, if any, those
					surely who dwell within the moon should be active, light,
					and easy to be nourished with any thing whatsoever; since
					they affirm that the moon herself, as also the sun, which is
					a fiery animal, and manifoldly greater than the earth, is
					nourished and maintained by the moistures that come from
					the earth, as are also all the other stars, whose number is in
					a manner infinite; such light and slender animals do they
					assign to the upper region, and with so small necessaries
					do they think them contented and satisfied. But we
					neither see these things, nor consider that a quite different
					region, nature, and temperature is accommodated to those
					lunar men.</p>
            <p>As therefore, if we were unable to come near and touch
					the sea, but could only see it at a distance, and had heard
					that its water is brackish, salt, and undrinkable, any one
					who should tell us that there are in its depths many and
					great animals of various forms and shapes, and that it is
					full of great and monstrous beasts who make the same
					use of the water as we do of the air, would be thought
					only to relate a parcel of strange and uncreditable stories,
					newly found out and invented for delight and amusement;
					in the same manner we seem to be affected and disposed
					towards the moon, not believing that there are any who
					inhabit it. And I am of opinion, that they themselves do
					much more wonder, when they behold the earth,&mdash;which
					is, as it were, the dregs and mud of the universe, appearing to them through moist and foggy clouds and mists, a
					little place, a low, abject, and immovable thing without any
					brightness or light whatever,&mdash;how this pitiful inconsiderable thing should be able to produce, nourish, and maintain
					animals that have motion, respiration, and heat. And if
					peradventure they had ever heard these verses of Homer,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.281"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A filthy squalid place, abhorred even by
						</l>
                     <l>The Gods themselves;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XX. 65.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hell is as far beneath, as heaven above
						</l>
                     <l>The earth;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VIII. 16.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they would certainly think them to have been written of
					this place where we live, and that here is hell and Tartarus, and that the earth which is equally distant from
					heaven and hell is only the moon.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>I had not well ended my discourse, when Sylla interrupting me said: Forbear Lamprias, and put a stop to
				your discourse, lest running (as they say) the vessel of
				your story on ground, you confound and spoil all the play,
				which has at present another scene and disposition. I myself therefore shall be the actor, but shall, before I enter
				upon my part, make known to you the poet or author;
				beginning, if there is nothing to hinder, with that of
				Homer,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>An isle Ogygia lies in Ocean's arms,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VII. 244.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>distant about five days' sail westward from Britain; and
					before it there are three others, of an equal distance from
					one another and also from that, bearing north-west, where
					the sun sets in summer. In one of these the barbarians
					feign that Saturn is detained prisoner by Jupiter, who, as
					his son, having the guard or keeping of those islands and
					the adjacent sea, named the Saturnian, has his seat a little
					below; and that the continent, by which the great sea is
					circularly environed, is distant from Ogygia about five
					thousand stadia, but from the others not so far, men using
					to row thither in galleys, the sea being there low and ebb.
					and difficult to be passed by great vessels because of the
					mud brought thither by a multitude of rivers, which, coming from the mainland, discharge themselves into it, and
					raise there great bars and shelves that choke up the river
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.282"/>
					
					and render it hardly navigable; whence anciently there
					arose an opinion of its being frozen. Moreover, the
					coasts of this continent lying on the sea are inhabited by
					the Greeks about a bay not much smaller than the Maeotic, the mouth of which lies in a direct line over against
					that of the Caspian Sea. These name and esteem themselves the inhabitants of the firm land, calling all us others
					islanders, as dwelling in a land encompassed round about
					and washed by the sea. And they think that those who
					heretofore came thither with Hercules and were left there
					by him, mixing themselves with the people of Saturn,
					raised up again the Greek nation, which was well near extinguished, brought under and supplanted by the language,
					laws, and manners of the barbarians, and made it again
					flourish and recover its pristine vigor. And therefore in
					that place they give the first honor to Hercules, and the
					second to Saturn. Now when the star of Saturn, by us
					called Phaenon and by them Nycturus, comes to the sign
					of Taurus, as it does once in the time of thirty years, they,
					having been a long time preparing what is necessary for a
					solemn sacrifice and a long voyage or navigation, send forth
					those on whom the lots fall to row in that vast sea, and
					make their abode for a great while in foreign countries.
					These men then, being embarked and departed, meet with
					different adventures, some in one manner, others in another. Now such as have in safety passed the danger of
					the sea go first ashore in those opposite islands, which are
					inhabited by the Greeks, where they see that the sun is
					scarce hidden one full hour during the space of thirty
					days, and that this is their night, of which the darkness is
					but small, as having a twilight from the going down of the
					sun not unlike the dawning of the day; that having continued there ninety days, during which they are highly
					caressed and honored, as being reputed and termed holy
					men, they are afterwards conducted by the winds, and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.283"/>
					
					transported into the isle of Saturn, where there are no
					other inhabitants but themselves and such as have been
					sent thither before them. For though it is lawful for
					them, after they have served Saturn thirty years, to return
					home to their own countries and houses, yet most of them
					choose rather to remain quietly there; some, because they
					are already accustomed to the place; others, because
					without any labor and trouble they have abundance of all
					things, as well for the offering of sacrifices and holding
					festival solemnities, as to support the ordinary expenses
					of those who are perpetually conversant in the study of
					learning and philosophy. For they affirm the nature of
					the island and the mildness of the air which environs
					it to be admirable; and that there have been some
					persons who, intending to depart thence, have been hindered by the Divinity or Genius of the place showing
					himself to them, as to his familiar friends and acquaintance, not only in dreams and exterior signs, but also visibly
					appearing to them by the means of familiar spirits discoursing and conversing with them. For they say, that
					Saturn himself is personally there, lying asleep in the
					deep cave of an hollow rock, shining like fine gold, Jupiter having prepared sleep instead of fetters and shackles
					to keep him from stirring; but that there are on the top
					of this rock certain birds, which fly down and carry him
					ambrosia; that the whole island is filled with an admirable fragrancy and perfume, which is spread all over it,
					arising from this cave, as from an odoriferous fountain;
					that these Daemons serve and minister to Saturn, having
					been his courtiers and nearest attendants when he held the
					empire and exercised regal authority over men and Gods;
					and that having the science of divining future occurrences,
					they of themselves foretell many things; but the greatest
					and of the highest importance, when they return from assisting Saturn, and reveal his dreams; for whatever Jupiter
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.284"/>
					
					 premeditates, Saturn dreams; but his awakenings are
					Titanical passions or perturbations of the soul in him,
					which sleep altogether controls, in order that the royal
					and divine nature may be pure and incontaminate in itself.</p>
            <p>This stranger then, having been brought thither, and
					there serving the God in repose and at his ease, attained
					to as great skill in astrology as it is possible for any one to
					do that has made the greatest progress in geometry; as for
					the rest of philosophy, having given himself to that which
					is called natural, he was seized with an extraordinary desire and longing to visit and see the great island; for so
					they call the continent inhabited by us. After therefore
					his thirty years were passed and his successors arrived,
					having taken leave of all his relations and friends, he put
					to sea, in other respects soberly and moderately equipped,
					but having good store of voyage-provision in vessels of
					gold. Now one day would not suffice to relate unto you
					in particular what adventures befell him, how many nations he visited, through how many countries he passed,
					how he searched into sacred writings, and was initiated in
					all holy confraternities and religious societies, as he himself recounted it to us, exactly particularizing every thing.
					But give ear, I pray you, to what concerns the present
					dispute. For he continued no small time at Carthage, a
					city not a little also esteemed by us, where he found certain sacred skins of parchment, which had been secretly
					conveyed thither when the old town was sacked, and had
					there long lain hidden under ground. Now he told me
					that, of all the Gods which appear to us in heaven, we
					ought chiefly to honor the Moon, and earnestly exhorted
					me to be diligent in venerating of her, as having the principal influence and dominion over our life.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>At these things when I was amazed, and entreated
				him to declare and explain them a little more fully to me,
				he said: The Greeks, O Sylla, deliver many things concerning
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.285"/>
				
				 the Gods, but they are not always in the right,
				For first, when they tell us that there is a Ceres and a
				Proserpine, they say well; but not so well, when they put
				them both in one and the same place. For one, to wit
				Ceres, is on the earth, and the lady and mistress of all
				earthly things. The other, to wit Proserpine, is in the
				moon, and the mistress of all lunar things; and she is
				called both Cora and Persephone; Persephone, as being a
				bringer of light and brightness, and Cora, because the
				apple of the eye, in which the image of him who looks
				into it is represented, as the brightness of the sun appears
				in the moon, is by the Greeks called <foreign lang="greek">ko/rh</foreign>. And as to what
				they say concerning the wandering about of Ceres and
				Proserpine, and their mutual seeking of one another, there
				is in it somewhat of truth, for they long after each other,
				being separated, and often embrace in shadow. And that
				Cora is sometimes in heaven and light, and sometimes in
				darkness and night, is not untrue; only there is some error
				in the computation of the time. For we see her not six
				whole months, but every sixth month, caught in the shadow
				by the earth, as by her mother; and this rarely happens
				within five months, because it is impossible she should forsake Pluto (Hades), being herself the bound or limit of
				Hades; which Homer also covertly but not unelegantly
				signified, when he said,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Into th' Elysian fields, earth's utmost bounds,
					</l>
                     <l>The Gods will bring thee;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IV. 563.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for he has there placed the end and boundary of the earth,
					where the shadow ceases and goes no farther. Now into
					that place no wicked or impure person can have access.
					But good folks, being after their decease carried thither,
					lead there indeed an easy and quiet, but yet not a blessed
					and divine life, till the second death.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>But what is that, O Sylla? said I. Ask me not, he
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.286"/>
				
				replied, for I am of myself going to declare it to you.
				The common opinion, which most persons hold, is that
				man is a compound subject, and this they have reason to
				believe. But they are mistaken in thinking him to be
				compounded of two parts only. For they imagine that the
				understanding is a part of the soul, but they err in this no
				less than those who make the soul to be a part of the
				body; for the understanding as far exceeds the soul, as the
				soul is better and diviner than the body. Now this composition of the soul with the understanding makes reason;
				and with the body, passion; of which the one is the beginning or principle of pleasure and pain, and the other
				of virtue and vice. Of those three parts conjoined and
				compacted together, the earth has given the body, the moon
				the soul, and the sun the understanding to the generation
				of man, . . . as therefore brightness to the moon. Now
				of the deaths we die, the one makes man two of three.
				and the other one of two. And the former indeed is in
				the region and jurisdiction of Ceres, whence the name
				given to her mysteries (<foreign lang="greek">telei=n</foreign>) resembles that given to death
				(<foreign lang="greek">teleuta=n</foreign>). The Athenians also heretofore called the deceased sacred to Ceres. As for the other death, it is in the
				moon, or region of Proserpine. And as with the one the
				terrestrial, so with the other the celestial Mercury doth
				dwell. This suddenly and with force and violence plucks
				the soul from the body; but Proserpine mildly and in a
				long time disjoins the understanding from the soul. And
				for this reason is she called <foreign lang="greek">*monogenh/s,</foreign> that is, <hi rend="italics">only begotten,</hi>
				or rather, <hi rend="italics">begetting one alone;</hi> for the better part of man
				becomes alone when it is separated by her. Now both
				the one and the other happens thus according to Nature.
				It is ordained by Fate that every soul, whether with or
				without understanding, when gone out of the body, should
				wander for a time, though not all for the same, in the
				region lying between the earth and the moon. For those
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.287"/>
				
				that have been unjust and dissolute suffer there the punishments due to their offences; but the good and virtuous
				are there detained till they are purified, and have by expiation purged out of them all the infections they might
				have contracted from the contagion of the body, as if from.
				foul breath, living in the mildest part of the air, called
				the meadows of Pluto, where they must remain for a certain perfixed and appointed time. And then, as if they
				were returning from a wandering pilgrimage or long exile
				into their country, they have a taste of joy, such as they
				principally receive who are initiated in sacred mysteries,
				mixed with trouble, admiration, and each one's proper and
				peculiar hope. For the moon drives and chases out many
				souls which already long after it. And some who are
				already come thither, and yet take pleasure in things below, are seen descending down as it were into an abyss.
				But those that are got on high, and are there securely
				seated, first go about as victors, crowned with garlands
				called the wings of constancy, because in their lives they
				restrained the unreasonable and passible part of their soul,
				rendering it subject and obedient to the curb of reason.
				Secondly, they are like to the rays of the sun in appearance, and like to fire in their soul, which is borne aloft by
				the clear air which is about the moon,&mdash;like fire here on
				the earth,&mdash;from which they gather strength and solidity,
				as iron and steel do by their being tempered and plunged
				in water. For that which was hitherto rare and loose is
				compacted and made firm, and becomes bright and transparent; so that it is nourished with the least exhalation in
				the world. And this is what Heraclitus meant, when he
				said that the souls in Pluto's region have their smell exceeding quick.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Now they first see the moon's greatness, beauty, and
				nature, which is not simple nor unmixed, but a composition as it were of earth and star. For as the earth mixed
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.288"/>
				
				with wind and moisture becomes soft, and as the blood
				tempered with the flesh gives it sense; so they say that the
				moon, being mingled with an ethereal quintessence even to
				the very bottom, is animated, becomes fruitful, and generative, and is equally counterpoised with ponderosity and
				lightness. For even the world itself, being composed of
				some things naturally moving upwards and others by nature tending downwards, is exempt from all local motion
				or change of place. These things also Xenocrates seems
				by a certain divine reasoning to have understood, having
				taken his first light from Plato. For Plato it was who first
				affirmed that every star is compounded of fire and earth,
				by the means of certain intermediate natures given in proportion; forasmuch as nothing can be an object of human
				sense which has not in some proportion a mixture of earth
				and light. Now Xenocrates says that the stars and the
				sun are composed of fire and the first or primitive solid;
				the moon of the second solid and its own peculiar air;
				and the earth, of water, fire, and the third solid. For
				neither is the solid alone by itself, nor the rare alone by
				itself, capable or susceptible of a soul. And let thus much
				suffice for the substance of the moon.</p>
            <p>Now as to her breadth and magnitude, it is not such as
					the geometricians deliver, but manifoldly greater. And
					she seldom measures the shadow of the earth by her
					greatness, not because she is small, but because she adds
					to her motion by heat, that she may quickly pass the shady
					place, carrying with her the souls of the blessed, which
					make haste and cry. For when they are in the shadow,
					they can no longer hear the harmony of the heavenly
					bodies. And withal, the souls of the damned are from
					below presented to them, lamenting and wailing through
					this shadow. Wherefore also in eclipses, many are wont
					to ring vessels of brass, and to make a noise and clattering to be heard by these souls. Moreover, that which
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.289"/>
					
					is called the face of the moon affrights them when they
					draw near it, seeming to them a dreadful and terrible
					sight; whereas indeed it is not so. But as our earth has
					deep and great bays, one here running between Hercules's
					pillars into the land to us, and others without, as the
					Caspian, and those about the Red Sea; so in the moon
					also there are hollows and great depths. Now of these,
					the greatest they call the gulf of Hecate, where the souls
					punish or are punished according to the evils they suffered
					or did whilst they were Daemons. The two others are
					long passages, through which the soul must go sometimes
					to that part of the moon which is towards heaven, and
					sometimes to that which is towards earth. Now that part
					of the moon which is towards heaven is called the Elysian
					fields; and that which is towards the earth, the fields of
					Proserpine that is opposite to the earth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>The Daemons do not always stay in the moon, but
				sometimes descend down here below, to have the care and
				superintendency of oracles. They are assistant also, and
				join in celebrating the sublimest ceremonies, having their
				eye upon misdeeds, which they punish, and preserving the
				good as well in perils of war as of the sea. And if in the
				performance of this charge they commit any fault, either
				through anger, envy, or any unjust grace or favor, they
				smart for it; for they are again thrust down to the earth,
				and tied to human bodies. Now those who were about
				Saturn said, that themselves were some of the better of
				these Daemons; as were formerly those that were heretofore in Crete called Dactyli Idaei, the Corybantes in
				Phrygia, and the Trophoniades in Lebadea, a city of
				Boeotia, and infinite others in several places of the habitable earth, whose names, temples, and honors continue to
				this day. But the powers of some fail, being by a most
				happy change translated to another place; which translations some obtain sooner, others later, when the understanding
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.290"/>
				
				 comes to be separated from the soul; which
				separation is made by the love and desire to enjoy the
				image of the sun, in which and by which shines that
				divine, desirable, and happy beauty, which every other
				nature differently longs after and seeks, one after one
				manner, another after another. For the moon herself
				continually turns, through the desire she has to be joined
				with him. But the nature of the soul remains in the
				moon, retaining only some prints and dreams of life. And
				of this I think it to have been well and truly said,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The soul, like to a dream, flies quick away;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 221.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>which it does not immediately, as soon as it is separated
					from the body, but afterwards, when it is alone and divided
					from the understanding. And of all that Homer ever
					writ, there is not any passage more divine than that in
					which, speaking of those who are departed this life, he
					says,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Next these, I saw Alcides' image move;
						</l>
                     <l>Himself is with th' immortal Gods above.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 601.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For every one of us is neither courage, nor fear, nor desire,
					&mdash;no more than flesh or humors,&mdash;but the part by which
					we think and understand. And the soul being moulded
					and formed by the understanding, and itself moulding and
					forming the body, by embracing it on every side, receives
					from it an impression and form; so that although it be
					separated both from the understanding and the body, it
					nevertheless so retains still its figure and semblance for a
					long time, that it may with good right be called its image.</p>
            <p>And of these souls (as I have already said) the moon is
					the element, because souls resolve into her, as the bodies
					of the deceased do into earth. Those indeed who have
					been virtuous and honest, living a quiet and philosophical
					life without embroiling themselves in troublesome affairs,
					are quickly resolved; because being left by the understanding,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.291"/>
					
					 and no longer using corporeal passions, they incontinently vanish away. But the souls of the ambitious and
					such as have been busied in negotiations, of the amorous
					and such as have been addicted to corporeal pleasures, as
					also of the angry and revengeful, calling to mind the things
					they did in their lives, as dreams in their sleep, walk wandering about here and there, like that of Endymion; because their inconstancy and their being over-subject to
					passions transports them, and draws them out of the moon
					to another generation, not letting them rest, but alluring
					them and calling them away. For there is nothing small,
					staid, constant, and accordant, after that being forsaken by
					the understanding, they come to be seized by corporeal
					passions. And of such souls, destitute of reason and suffering themselves to be carried away by the proud violence
					of passion, were bred the Tityi and Typhons; and particularly that Typhon who, having by force and violence seized
					the city of Delphi, overturned the sanctuary of the oracle
					there. Nevertheless, after a long tract of time the moon
					receives those souls and recomposes them; and the sun
					inspiring again and sowing understanding in them, the
					moon receives them by its vital power, and makes them
					new souls; and the earth in the third place gives them a
					body. For she gives nothing . . . after death of all that
					she takes to generation. And the sun takes nothing, but
					reassembles and receives again the understanding which
					he gave. But the moon gives and receives, joins and disjoins, unites and separates, according to divers faculties
					and powers; of which the one is named Ilithyia or Lucina
					(to wit, that which joins), and the other Artemis or Diana
					(to wit, that which separates and divides). And of the
					three fatal Goddesses or Parcae, she which is called Atropos
					is placed in the sun, and gives the principle of generation;
					and Clotho, being lodged in the moon, is she who joins,
					mingles, and unites; and the last, named Lachesis, is on
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.292"/>
					
					the earth, where she adds her helping hand, and with her
					does Fortune very much participate. For that which is
					without a soul is weak in itself and liable to be affected by
					others. The understanding is sovereign over all the rest,
					and cannot be made to suffer by any. Now the soul is a
					certain middle thing mixed of them both; as the moon
					was by God made and created a composition and mixture
					of things high and low, having the same proportion to the
					sun as the earth has to her.</p>
            <p>This (said Sylla) is what I understood from this guest
					of mine, who was a stranger and a traveller; and this he
					said he learned from the Daemons who served and ministered to Saturn. And you, O Lamprias, may take my
					relation in such part as you please.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>