<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Vitae decem oratorum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.121">
      <body>
         <head>Lives of the ten orators.</head>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>I. ANTIPHON.</head>
            <pb id="v.5.p.17"/>
            <p>Antiphon, the son of Sophilus, by descent a Rhamnusian, was his father's scholar; for Sophilus kept a rhetoric
					school, to which it is reported that Alcibiades himself had
					recourse in his youth. Having attained to competent
					measure of knowledge and eloquence,&mdash;and that, as some
					believe, from his own natural ingenuity,&mdash;he dedicated his
					study chiefly to affairs of state. And yet he was for some
					time conversant in the schools, and had a controversy with
					Socrates the philosopher about the art of disputing,&mdash;not
					so much for the sake of contention as for the profit of
					arguing, as Xenophon tells us in his Commentaries of Socrates. At the request of some citizens, he wrote orations
					by which they defended their suits at law. Some say that
					he was the first that ever did any thing of this nature.
					For it is certain there is not one juridical oration extant
					written by any orator that lived before him, nor by his contemporaries either, as Themistocles, Aristides, and Pericles;
					though the times gave them opportunity, and there was
					need enough of their labor in such business. Not that we
					are to impute it to their want of parts that they did nothing in this way, for we may inform ourselves of the contrary
					from what historians relate of each of them. Besides, if
					we inspect the most ancient of those known in history who
					had the same form and method in their pleadings, such as
					Alcibiades, Critias, Lysias, and Archinous, we shall find
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.18"/>
					
					that they all followed Antiphon when he was old. For
					being a man of incomparable sagacity, he was the first
					that published institutions of oratory; and by reason of
					his profound learning, he was surnamed Nestor. Caecilius,
					in a tract which he wrote of him, supposes him to have
					been Thucydides's pupil, from what Antiphon delivered in
					praise of him. He is most accurate in his orations, in invention subtle; and he would frequently baffle his adversary at unawares, by a covert sort of pleading; in troublesome and intricate matters he was very judicious and sharp;
					and as he was a great admirer of ornamental speaking, he
					would always adapt his orations to both law and reason.</p>
            <p>He lived about the time of the Persian war and of
					Gorgias the rhetorician, being somewhat younger than he.
					And he lived to see the subversion of the popular government in the commonwealth which was wrought by the
					four hundred conspirators, in which he himself is thought
					to have had the chiefest hand, being sometimes commander
					of two galleys, and sometimes general, and having by the
					many and great victories he obtained gained them many
					allies, he armed the young men, manned out sixty galleys,
					and on all their occasions went ambassador to Lacedaemon
					at the time when Eetionia was fortified. But when those
					Four Hundred were overcome and taken down, he with
					Archeptolemus, who was likewise one of the same number,
					was accused of the conspiracy, condemned, and sentenced
					to the punishment due to traitors, his body cast out unburied, and all his posterity infamous on record. But
					there are some who tell us, that he was put to death by the
					Thirty Tyrants; and among the rest, Lysias, in his oration
					for Antiphon's daughter, says the same; for he left a little
					daughter, whom Callaeschrus claimed for his wife by the
					law of propinquity. And Theopompus likewise, in his
					Fifteenth Book of Philippics, tells us the same thing. But
					this must have been another Antiphon, son of Lysidonides,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.19"/>
					
					whom Cratinus mentions in his Pytine as a rascal. But
					how could he be executed in the time of the Four Hundred,
					and afterward live to be put to death by the Thirty Tyrants?
					There is likewise another story of the manner of his death:
					that when he was old, he sailed to Syracuse, when the
					tyranny of Dionysius the First was most famous; and
					being at table, a question was put, what sort of brass was
					best. When others had answered as they thought most
					proper, he replied, That is the best brass, of which the
					statues of Harmodius and Aristogiton were made. The
					tyrant hearing this, and taking it as a tacit exhortation to
					his subjects to contrive his ruin, he commanded Antiphon
					to be put to death; and some say that he put him to death
					for deriding his tragedies.</p>
            <p>This orator is reported to have written sixty orations;
					but Caecilius supposes twenty-five of them to be spurious
					and none of his. Plato, in his comedy called Pisander,
					traduces him as a covetous man. He is reported to have
					composed some of his tragedies alone, and others with
					Dionysius the tyrant. While he was poetically inclined,
					he invented an art of curing the distemper of the mind, as
					physicians are wont to provide cure of bodily diseases.
					And having at Corinth built him a little house, in or near
					the market, he set a postscript over the gate, to this effect:
					that he had a way to cure the distemper of men's minds by
					words; and let him but know the cause of their malady,
					he would immediately prescribe the remedy, to their comfort. But after some time, thinking that art not worth his
					while, he betook himself to the study and teaching of
					oratory. There are some who ascribe the book of Glaucus
					of Rhegium concerning Poets to him as author. His orations concerning Herodes, against Erasistratus concerning
					Peacocks,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Concerning Ideas, according to the MSS. (G.)</note> are very much commended, and also that which,
					when he was accused, he penned for himself against a
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.20"/>
					
					public indictment, and that against Demosthenes the
					general for moving an illegal measure. He likewise had
					another against Hippocrates the general; who did not
					appear on the day appointed for his trial, and was condemned in his absence.</p>
            <p>Caecilius has recorded the decree of the senate for the
					judicial trial of Antiphon, passed in the year<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theopompus was Archon in B.C. 411. (G.)</note> in which
					Theopompus was chief magistrate of Athens, the same in
					which the Four Hundred were overthrown,&mdash;in these
					words:</p>
            <p>&ldquo;Enacted by the senate on the twenty-first day of the
					prytany. Demonicus of Alopece was clerk; Philostratus
					of Pallene was president.</p>
            <p>&ldquo;Andron moved in regard to those men,&mdash;viz. Archeptolemus, Onomacles, and Antiphon, whom the generals had
					declared against, for that they went in an embassage to
					Lacedaemon, to the great damage of the city of Athens,
					and departed from the camp in an enemies' ship, and
					went through Decelea by land,&mdash;that they should be
					apprehended and brought before the court for a legal
					trial.</p>
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Therefore let the generals, with others of the senate,
					to the number of ten, whom it shall please the generals to
					name and choose, look after these men to present them
					before the court, that they may be present during the proceedings. Then let the Thesmothetes summon the defendants to appear on the morrow, and let them open the
					proceedings in court at the time at which the summonses
					shall be returnable. Then let the chosen advocates, with
					the generals and any others who may have any thing to say,
					accuse the defendants of treason; and if any one of them
					shall be found guilty, let sentence be passed upon him as a
					traitor, according to the law in such case made and provided.</q>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.21"/>
            <p>At the bottom of this decree was subscribed the sentence:&mdash;</p>
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Archeptolemus son of Hippodamus, the Agrylian, and
					Antiphon son of Sophilus, the Ramnusian, being both
					present in court, are condemned of treason. And this
					was to be their punishment: that they should be delivered
					to the eleven executioners, their goods confiscated, the
					tenth part of them being first consecrated to Minerva;
					their houses to be levelled with the ground, and in the
					places where they stood this subscription to be engraven
					on brass, '[The houses] of Archeptolemus and Antiphon,
					traitors.' . . .<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The corrupt clause indicated by . . . probably means, that the Demarchs were
						to make inventories (<foreign lang="greek">a)pofh=nai</foreign>) of the traitors' estates. (G.)</note> That Archeptolemus and Antiphon should
					neither of them be buried in Athens, nor anywhere else
					under that government. And besides all this, that their
					posterity should be accounted infamous, bastards as well
					as their lawful progeny; and he too should be held infamous who should adopt any one of their progeny for his
					son. And that all this should be engrossed and engraven
					on a brass column, and that column should be placed
					where that stands on which is engraven the decree concerning Phrynichus.</q>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>II. ANDOCIDES.</head>
            <p>ANDOCIDES, the son of Leogoras, [and grandson of that
					Andocides] who once made a peace between the Athenians
					and the Lacedaemonians, by descent a Cydathenian or
					Thorian, of a noble family, and, as Hellanicus tells us, the
					offspring of Mercury himself, for the race of Heralds
					belongs to him. On this account he was chosen by the
					people to go with Glaucon, with twenty sail of ships, to
					aid the Corcyraeans against the Corinthians. But in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.22"/>
					
					process of time he was accused of some notorious acts
					of impiety, as that he was of the number of those who
					defaced the statues of Mercury and divulged the sacred
					mysteries of Ceres. And withal, he had been before this
					time wild and intemperate, and had once been seen in the
					night in masquerade to break one of the statues of Mercury; and when on his trial he refused to bring his servant
					to examination whom his accusers named, he not only
					remained under this reproach, but was also on this account
					very much suspected to be guilty of the second crime too.
					This later action was laid to his charge soon after the expedition of the navy sent by the Athenians into Sicily.
					For, as Cratippus informs us, when the Corinthians sent the
					Leontines and Egestians to the Athenians, who hesitated
					to lend them assistance, they in the night defaced and
					brake all the statues of Mercury which were erected in the
					market. To which offence Andocides added another, that
					of divulging the mysteries of Ceres. He was brought to
					his trial, but was acquitted on condition he would discover
					who were companions with him in the crime. In which
					affair being very diligent, he found out who they were that
					had been guilty, and among the rest he discovered his own
					father. He proved all guilty, and caused them all to be
					put to death except his father, whom he saved, though in
					prison, by a promise of some eminent service he would do
					to the commonwealth. Nor did he fail of what he promised; for Leogoras accused many who had acted in several
					matters against the interest of the commonwealth, and
					for this was acquitted of his own crime.</p>
            <p>Now, though Andocides was very much esteemed of for
					his skill in the management of the affairs of the commonwealth, yet his inclinations led him rather to traffic by
					sea; and by this means he contracted friendship with the
					kings of Cyprus and other great princes. At which time
					he privily stole a damsel of the city, the daughter of Aristides,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.23"/>
					
					 and his own niece, and sent her as a present to the
					king of Cyprus. But suspecting he should be called in
					question for it, he again stole her from Cyprus, for which
					the king of Cyprus took him and clapped him up in
					prison; whence he brake loose, and returned to Athens,
					just at that time when the four hundred conspirators had
					usurped the government. By whom being confined, he
					again escaped when the oligarchical government was
					broken up .... But when the Thirty Tyrants were
					uppermost, he withdrew to Elis, and there lived till Thrasybulus and his faction returned into the city, and then he
					also repaired thither. And after some time, being sent
					to Lacedaemon to conciliate a peace, he was again suspected to be faulty, and on that suspicion banished.</p>
            <p>He himself has given an account of all these transactions, in his orations, which he has left behind him. For
					some of them contain his defence of himself in regard to
					the mysteries; others his petition for restoration from exile; there is one extant on <hi rend="italics">Endeixis</hi> (or information laid
					against a criminal); also a defence against Phaeax, and
					one on the peace. He flourished at the same time with
					Socrates the philosopher. He was born in the seventy-eighth Olympiad, when Theogenides was chief magistrate
					of Athens, so that he should seem to be about ten years
					before Lysias. There is an image of Mercury, called from
					his name, being given by the tribe Aegeis; and it stood
					near the house where Andocides dwelt, and was therefore
					called by his name. This Andocides himself was at the
					charge of a cyclic chorus for the tribe Aegeis, at the performance of a dithyrambus. And having gained a victory,
					he erected a tripod on an ascent opposite to the tuffstone
					statue of Silenus. His style in his orations is plain and
					easy, without the least affectation or any thing of a figurative ornament.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.24"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>III. LYSIAS.</head>
            <p>LYSIAS was the son of Cephalus, grandson of Lysanias,
					and great-grandson of Cephalus. His father was by birth
					a Syracusan; but partly for the love he had to the city,
					and partly in condescension to the persuasions of Pericles
					the son of Xanthippus, who entertained him as his friend
					and guest, he went to live at Athens, being a man of great
					wealth. Some say that he was banished Syracuse when
					the city was under the tyranny of Gelo. Lysias was born
					at Athens when Philocles, the successor of Phrasicles, was
					chief magistrate, in the second year of the eightieth Olympiad.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 459.</note> At his first coming, he was educated among the
					most noble of the Athenians. But when the city sent
					a colony to Sybaris, which was afterwards called Thurii, he
					went thither with his other brother Polemarchus, his father
					being now dead (for he had two other brothers, Euthydemus and Brachyllus), that he might receive his portion
					of his father's estate. This was done in the fifteenth year
					of his age, when Praxiteles was chief magistrate.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 444.</note> There
					then he stayed, and was brought up under Nicias and Tisias,
					both Syracusans. And having purchased a house and received his estate, he lived as a citizen for thirty-three years,
					till the year of Cleocritus.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 413.</note> In the year following, in the
					time of Callias, viz. in the ninety-second Olympiad, when the
					Athenians had met with their disasters in Sicily, and when
					other of their allies revolted, and especially the Italians,
					he, being accused of favoring the Athenians, was banished with three other of his association; when coming to
					Athens, in the year wherein Callias succeeded Cleocritus,
					the city then laboring under the tyranny of the four hundred
					conspirators, he there sat down. But after the fight at
					Aegospotami, when the Thirty Tyrants had usurped the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.25"/>
					
					government, he was banished thence, after he had remained
					in Athens seven years. His goods were confiscated; and
					having likewise lost his brother Polemarchus, he himself
					escaped by a back door of the house in which he was kept
					for execution, fled to Megara and there lived. But when
					the citizens endeavored to return from Phyle, he also behaved himself very well, and appeared very active in the
					affair, having, to forward this great enterprise, deposited
					two thousand drachms of silver and two hundred targets,
					and being commissioned with Hermas, he maintained three
					hundred men in arms, and prevailed with Thrasylaeus the
					Elean, his old friend and host, to contribute two talents.
					Upon entering the city, Thrasybulus proposed that, for a
					consideration of his good service to the public, he should
					receive the rights of citizenship: this was during the so called time of anarchy before Euclides. Which proposal
					being ratified by the people, Archinus objected that it was
					against the laws, and a decree without authority of the
					senate. The decree was thereupon declared void, and
					Lysias lost his citizenship. He led the remainder of his
					life in the rank of an <hi rend="italics">Isoteles</hi> (or citizen who had no right
					to vote or hold office), and died at last at Athens, being
					fourscore and three years old, or as some would have it,
					seventy-six; and others again say, that he lived above fourscore years, till after the birth of Demosthenes. It is supposed he was born in the year of Philocles.</p>
            <p>There are four hundred and twenty-five orations which
					bear his name, of which Dionysius and Caecilius affirm
					only two hundred and thirty to be genuine, and he is said
					to have been overcome but twice in all. There is extant
					also the oration which he made in defence of the fore-mentioned decree against Archinus, who indicted it and
					thereby prevented Lysias from receiving the citizenship, as
					also another against the Thirty Tyrants. He was very cogent in his persuasions, and was always very brief in what
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.26"/>
					
					he delivered. He would commonly give orations to private
					persons. There are likewise his institutions of oratory,
					his public harangues, his epistles, his eulogies, funeral
					orations, discourses of love, and his defence of Socrates,
					accommodated to the minds of the judges. His style
					seems plain and easy, though hardly imitable. Demosthenes, in his oration against Neaera, says that he was in love
					with one Metanira, Neaera's serving-maid, but afterwards
					married his brother Brachyllus's daughter. Plato in his
					Phaedrus makes mention of him, as a most eloquent orator and ancienter than Isocrates. Philiscus, his companion,
					and Isocrates's votary, composed an epigram concerning
					him, whence the same that we have urged from Plato is
					deducible; and it sings to this effect:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Calliope's witty daughter, Phrontis, show
						</l>
                     <l>If aught of wit or eloquence thou hast;
						</l>
                     <l>For 'tis decreed that thou shalt bear a son,
						</l>
                     <l>Lysias by name, to spread the name of him
						</l>
                     <l>Whose great and generous acts do fill the world,
						</l>
                     <l>And are received for glorious above.
						</l>
                     <l>Let him who sings those praises of the dead,
						</l>
                     <l>Let him, my friend, too, praise our amity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>He likewise wrote two orations for Iphicrates,&mdash;one
					against Harmodius, and another accusing Timotheus of
					treason,&mdash;in both which he overcame. But when Iphicrates made himself responsible for Timotheus's actions,
					and would purge himself of the allegation of treason
					made also against him, Lysias wrote an oration for him to
					deliver in his defence; upon which he was acquitted, but
					Timotheus was fined in a considerable sum of money.
					He likewise delivered an oration at the Olympic games,
					in which he endeavored to convince the Greeks of how
					great advantage it would be to them, if they could but
					unanimously join to pull down the tyrant Dionysius.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.27"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>IV. ISOCRATES.</head>
            <p>ISOCRATES was the son of Theodorus, of Erchia, reckoned among the middle class of citizens, and a man who
					kept servants under him to make flutes, by which he got
					so much money as enabled him not only to bring up his
					children after the most genteel manner, but likewise to
					maintain a choir. For besides Isocrates, he had other
					sons, Telesippus and Diomnestus, and one daughter. And
					hence, we may suppose, those two comical poets, Aristophanes and Stratis, took occasion to bring him on the
					stage. He was born in the eighty-sixth Olympiad,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 436.</note> Lysimachus being archon, about two and twenty years after
					Lysias, and seven before Plato. When he was a boy, he
					was as well educated as any of the Athenian children,
					being under the tuition of Prodicus the Cean, Gorgias the
					Leontine, Tisias the Syracusan, and Theramenes the rhetorician. And when Theramenes was to be apprehended
					by the order of the Thirty Tyrants, and flying for succor
					to the altar of the senate, only Isocrates stood his friend,
					when all others were struck with terror. For a long time
					he stood silent; but after some time Theramenes advised
					him to desist, because, he told him, it would be an aggravation of his grief, if any of his friends should come
					into trouble through him. And it is said that he made
					use of certain institutions of rhetoric composed by Theramenes, when he was slandered in court; which institutions
					have since borne Boton's name.</p>
            <p>When Isocrates was come to man's estate, he meddled
					with nothing of state affairs, both because he had a very
					weak voice and because he was something timorous; and
					besides these two impediments, his estate was much impaired by the loss of a great part of his patrimony in the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.28"/>
					
					war with the Lacedaemonians. It is evident that he
					composed orations for others to use, but delivered only one,
					that concerning Exchange of Property. Having set up a
					school, he gave himself much to writing and the study of
					philosophy, and then he wrote his Panegyrical oration,
					and others which were used for advice, some of which he
					delivered himself, and others he gave to others to pronounce for him; aiming thereby to persuade the Greeks
					to the study and practice of such things as were of most
					immediate concern to them. But his endeavors in that way
					proving to no purpose, he gave those things over, and
					opened a school in Chios first, as some will have it, having
					for a beginning nine scholars; and when they came to him
					to pay him for their schooling, he weeping said, <q direct="unspecified">Now I
						see plainly that I am sold to my scholars.</q> He admitted
					all into his acquaintance who desired it. He was the first
					that made a separation between wrangling pleas and political arguments, to which latter he rather addicted himself.
					He instituted a form of magistracy in Chios, much the
					same with that at Athens. No schoolmaster ever got so
					much; so that he maintained a galley at his own charge.
					He had more than a hundred scholars, and among others
					Timotheus the son of Conon was one, with whom he
					visited many cities, and composed the epistles which Timotheus sent to the Athenians; who for his pains gave him
					a talent out of that which he got at Samos. Theopompus likewise the Chian, Ephorus the Cumaean, Asclepiades
					who composed arguments for tragedies, and Theodectes of
					Phaselis, who afterwards wrote tragedies, were all Isocrates's scholars. The last of these had a monument in
					the way to the shrine of Cyamites, as we go to Eleusis by
					the Sacred Way, of which now remains only rubbish.
					There also he set up with his own the statues of other
					famous poets, of all which only Homer's is to be seen.
					Leodamas also the Athenian, and Lacritus who gave laws
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.29"/>
					
					to the Athenians, were both his scholars; and some say,
					Hyperides and Isaeus too. They add likewise, that Demosthenes also was very desirous to learn of him, and
					because he could not give the full rate, which was a thousand drachms, he offered him two hundred, the fifth part,
					if he would teach him but the fifth part of his art proportionable: to whom Isocrates answered, We do not use,
					Demosthenes, to impart our skill by halves, but as men
					sell good fish whole, or altogether, so if thou hast a desire
					to learn, we will teach thee our full art, and not a piece
					of it. He died in the year when Charondas was chief
					magistrate,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 338.</note> when, being at Hippocrates's public exercise,
					he received the news of the slaughter at Chaeronea; for
					he was the cause of his own death by a four days' fast,
					which he then made, pronouncing just at his departure
					the three verses which begin three tragedies of Euripides
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Danaus, father of the fifty sisters,&mdash;
						</l>
                     <l>Pelops, son of Tantalus, in quest of Pisa,&mdash;
						</l>
                     <l>Cadmus, in time past, going from Sidon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>He lived ninety-eight years, or, as some say, a hundred,
					not being able to behold Greece the fourth time brought
					into slavery. The year (or, as some say, four years) before
					he died, he wrote his Panathenaic oration. He labored
					upon his Panegyric oration ten years, or, as some tell us,
					fifteen, which he is supposed to have borrowed out of
					Gorgias the Leontine and Lysias. His oration concerning
					Exchange of Property he wrote when he was eighty-two
					years old, and those to Philip a little before his death.
					When he was old, he adopted Aphareus, the youngest of
					the three sons of Plathane, the daughter of Hippias the
					orator. He was very rich, both in respect of the great
					sums of money he exacted of his scholars, and besides
					that, having at one time twenty talents of Nicocles, king
					of Cyprus, for an oration which he dedicated to him. By
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.30"/>
					
					reason of his riches he became obnoxious to the envy of
					others, and was three times named to maintain a galley;
					which he evaded twice by the assistance of his son and a
					counterfeit sickness, but the third time he undertook it,
					though the charge proved very great. A father telling him
					that he had allowed his son no other companion than one
					slave, Isocrates replied, Go thy way then, for one slave
					thou shalt have two. He strove for the prize which Aretemisia dedicated to the honor and memory of her husband
					Mausolus; but that oration is lost. He wrote also another
					oration in praise of Helen, and one called Areopagiticus.
					Some say that he died when he had fasted nine days,
					&mdash;some again, at four days' end,&mdash;and his death took its
					date from the funeral solemnities of those that lost their
					lives at Chaeronea. His son Aphareus likewise wrote
					several orations.</p>
            <p>He lies buried with all his family near Cynosarges, on
					the left hand of the hill. There are interred Isocrates
					and his father Theodorus, his mother and her sister Anaco,
					his adoptive son Aphareus, Socrates the son of Anaco,
					Theodorus his brother, bearing his father's name, his
					grandsons, the sons of his adopted Aphareus, and his
					wife Plathane, the mother of Aphareus. On these tombs
					were erected six tables, which are now demolished. And
					upon the tomb of Isocrates himself was placed a column
					thirty cubits high, and on that a mermaid of seven cubits,
					which was an emblem of his eloquence; there is nothing
					now extant. There was also near it a table, having poets
					and his schoolmasters on it; and among the rest, Gorgias
					inspecting a celestial globe, and Isocrates standing by him.
					There is likewise a statue of his of bronze in Eleusis,
					dedicated by Timothy the son of Conon, before the entry
					of the porch, with this inscription:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To the fame and honor of Isocrates,
						</l>
                     <l>This statue's sacred to the Goddesses;
						</l>
                     <l>The gift of Timothy.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.31"/>
            <p>This statue was made by Leochares. There are threescore orations which bear his name; of which, if we credit
					Dionysius, only five and twenty are genuine; but according to Caecilius, twenty-eight; and the rest are accounted
					spurious. He was an utter stranger to ostentation, insomuch that, when there came at one time three persons to
					hear him declaim, he admitted but two of them, desiring
					the third to come the next day, for that two at once were
					to him as a full theatre. He used to tell his scholars that
					he taught his art for ten minas; but he would give any
					man ten thousand, that could teach him to be bold and
					give him a good utterance. And being once asked how
					he, who was not very eloquent himself, could make others
					so, he answered, Just as a whetstone cannot cut, yet it will
					sharpen knives for that purpose. Some say that he wrote
					institutions to the art of oratory; others are of opinion
					that he had no method of teaching, but only exercise.
					He would never ask any thing of a free-born citizen. He
					used to enjoin his scholars being present at public assemblies to repeat to him what was there delivered. He conceived no little sorrow for the death of Socrates, insomuch
					that the next day he put himself in mourning. Being
					asked what was the use and force of rhetoric, he answered, To make great matters small, and small great.
					At a feast with Nicoceon, the tyrant of Cyprus, being
					desired by some of the company to declaim upon some
					theme, he made answer, that that was not a season for
					him to speak what he knew, and he knew nothing that
					was then seasonable. Happening once to see Sophocles
					the tragedian amorously eying a comely boy, he said to
					him, It will become thee, Sophocles, to restrain not only
					thy hands, but thine eyes. When Ephorus of Cumae left
					his school before he had arrived at any good proficiency,
					his father Demophilus sent him again with a second sum
					of money in his hand; at which Isocrates jocosely called
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.32"/>
					
					him Diphorus, that is, <hi rend="italics">twice bringing</hi> his fee. However,
					he took a great deal of pains and care with him, and went
					so far as to put him in the way of writing history.</p>
            <p>He was wantonly given; and used to lie upon a . .
					mat for his bed, and his bolster was commonly made moist
					with saffron. He never married while he was young; but
					in his old age he kept a miss, whose name was Lagisce,
					and by her he had a daughter, who died in the twelfth
					year of her age, before she was married. He afterwards
					married Plathane, the wife of Hippias the rhetorician, who
					had three sons, the youngest of which, Aphareus by name,
					he adopted for his own, as we said before. This Aphareus
					erected a bronze statue to him near the temple of Jupiter,
					as may be seen from the inscription:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In veneration of the mighty Jove,
						</l>
                     <l>His noble parents, and the Gods above,
						</l>
                     <l>Aphareus this statue here has set,
						</l>
                     <l>The statue of Isocrates his father.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>He is said to have run a race on a swift horse, when he
					was but a boy; for he is to be seen in this posture in the
					Citadel, in the tennis court of the priestesses of Minerva,
					in a statue. There were but two suits commenced against
					him in his whole life. One whereof was with Megaclides,
					who provoked him to exchange of property; at the trial of
					which he could not be personally present, by reason of
					sickness; but sending Aphareus, he nevertheless overcame.
					The other suit was commenced against him by Lysimachus,
					who would have him come to an exchange or be at the
					charge of maintaining a galley for the commonwealth. In
					this case he was overthrown, and forced to perform the
					service. There was likewise a painting of him in the
					Pompeum.</p>
            <p>Aphareus also wrote a few orations, both judicial and
					deliberative; as also tragedies to the number of thirty-seven, of which two are contested. He began to make
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.33"/>
					
					his works public in the year of Lysistratus, and continued
					it to the year of Sosigenes, that is, eight and twenty years.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 369-342.</note>
					In these years he exhibited dramas six times at the city
					Dionysiac festivals, and twice went away with the prize
					through the actor Dionysius; he also gained two other
					victories at the Lenaean festival through other actors.</p>
            <p>There were to be seen in the Citadel the statues of the
					mother of Isocrates, of Theodorus, and of Anaco his
					mother's sister. That of the mother is placed just by the
					image of Health, the inscription being changed; that of
					Anaco is no longer there. [Anaco] had two sons, Alexander by Coenes, and Lysicles by Lysias.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>V. ISAEUS.</head>
            <p>ISAEUS was born in Chalcis. When he came to Athens,
					he read Lysias's works, whom he imitated so well, both in
					his style and in his skill in managing causes, that he who
					was not very well acquainted with their manner of writing
					could not tell which of the two was author of many of
					their orations. He flourished after the Peloponnesian war,
					as we may conjecture from his orations, and was in repute
					till the reign of Philip. He taught Demosthenes&mdash;not at
					his school, but privately&mdash;who gave him ten thousand
					drachms, by which business he became very famous. Some
					say that he composed orations for Demosthenes, which he
					pronounced in opposition to his guardians. He left behind
					him sixty-four orations, of which fifty are his own; as likewise some peculiar institutions of rhetoric. He was the
					first that used to speak or write figuratively, and that addicted himself to civil matters; which Demosthenes chiefly
					followed. Theopompus the comedian makes mention of
					him in his Theseus.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.34"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>VI. AESCHINES.</head>
            <p>HE was the son of Atrometus&mdash;who, being banished by
					the Thirty Tyrants, was thereby a means of reducing the
					commonwealth to the government of the people&mdash;and of
					his wife Glaucothea; by birth a Cothocidian. He was
					neither nobly born nor rich; but in his youth, being strong
					and well set, he addicted himself to all sorts of bodily exercises; and afterwards, having a very clear voice, he took
					to playing of tragedies, and if we may credit Demosthenes,
					he was a petty clerk, and also served Aristodemus as a
					player of third parts at the Bacchanalian festivals, in his
					times of leisure rehearsing the ancient tragedies. When
					he was but a boy, he was assisting to his father in teaching
					little children their letters, and when he was grown up, he
					listed himself a private soldier. Some think he was
					brought up under Socrates and Plato; but Caecilius will
					have it that Leodamas was his master. Being concerned
					in the affairs of the commonwealth, he openly acted in
					opposition to Demosthenes and his faction; and was employed in several embassies, and especially in one to Philip,
					to treat about articles of peace. For which Demosthenes
					accused him for being the cause of the overthrow and ruin
					of the Phocians, and the inflamer of war; which part he
					would have him thought to have acted when the Amphictyons chose him one of their deputies to the Amphissians
					who were building up the harbor [of Crissa]. On which
					the Amphictyons put themselves under Philip's protection,
					who, being assisted by Aeschines, took the affair in hand,
					and soon conquered all Phocis.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greek text is corrupt; but it is evident that the author confounds the
						Phocian war, which ended in 346 B.C., with the Amphissian war of 339 B.C. The
						next sentence shows the same mistake. (G.)</note> But Aeschines, notwithstanding all that Demosthenes could do, being favored by
					Eubulus the son of Spintharus, a Probalisian, who pleaded
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.35"/>
					
					 in his behalf, carried his cause by thirty voices, and
					so was cleared. Though some tell us, that there were
					orations prepared by the orators, but the news of the conquest of Chaeronea put a stop to the present proceedings,
					and so the suit fell.</p>
            <p>Some time after this, Philip being dead, and his son
					Alexander marching into Asia, Aeschines impeached Ctesiphon for acting against the laws, in passing a decree in
					favor of Demosthenes. But he having not the fifth part
					of the voices of the judges on his side, was forced to
					go in exile to Rhodes, because he would not pay his
					mulct of a thousand drachms. Others say, that he incurred disfranchisement also, because he would not depart
					the city, and that he went to Alexander at Ephesus. But
					upon the death of Alexander, when a tumult had been
					excited, he went to Rhodes, and there opened a school and
					taught. And on a time pronouncing the oration which he
					had formerly made against Ctesiphon, to pleasure the Rhodians, he did it with that grace, that they wondered how
					he could fail of carrying his cause if he pleaded so well
					for himself. But ye would not wonder, said he, that I was
					overthrown, if ye had heard Demosthenes pleading against
					me. He left a school behind him at Rhodes, which was
					afterwards called the Rhodian school. Thence he sailed
					to Samos, and there in a short time died. He had a very
					good voice, as both Demosthenes and Demochares testified
					of him.</p>
            <p>Four orations bear his name, one of which was against
					Timarchus, another concerning false embassage, and a
					third against Ctesiphon, which three are really his own;
					but the fourth called Deliaca, is none of his; for though
					he was named to plead the cause of the temple at Delos,
					yet Demosthenes tells us that Hyperides was chosen in
					his stead.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Demosthenes on the Crown, p. 271, 27.</note> He says himself, that he had two brothers,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.36"/>
					
					Aphobetus and Philochares. He was the first that brought
					the Athenians the news of the victory obtained at Tamynae,
					for which he was crowned for the second time. Some
					report that Aeschines was never any man's scholar, but
					having passed his time chiefly in courts of justice, he raised
					himself from the office of clerk to that of orator. His first
					public appearance was in a speech against Philip; with
					which the people being pleased, he was immediately chosen
					to go ambassador to the Arcadians; and being come
					thither, he excited the Ten Thousand against Philip.
					He indicted Timarchus for profligacy; who, fearing the
					issue, deserted his cause and hanged himself, as Demosthenes somewhere informs us. Being employed with
					Ctesiphon and Demosthenes in an embassage to Philip to
					treat of peace, he appeared the most accomplished of the
					three. Another time also he was one of ten men sent in
					embassage to conclude a peace; and being afterwards
					called to answer for it, he was acquitted, as we said.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>VII. LYCURGUS.</head>
            <p>LYCURGUS was the son of Lycophron, and grandson of
					that Lycurgus whom the Thirty Tyrants put to death, by
					the procurement of Aristodemus the Batesian, who, also
					being treasurer of the Greeks, was banished in the time
					of the popular government. He was a Butadian by birth,
					and of the line or family of the Eteobutades. He received
					his first institutions of philosophy from Plato the philosopher. But afterward entering himself a scholar to Isocrates the orator, he employed his study about affairs of
					the commonwealth. And to his care was committed the
					disposal and management of the city stock, and so he executed the office of treasurer-general for the space of twelve
					years; in which time there went through his hands fourteen
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.37"/>
					
					 thousand talents, or (as some will have it) eighteen
					thousand six hundred and fifty. It was the orator Stratocles that procured him this preferment. At first he was
					chosen in his own name; but afterwards he nominated one
					of his friends to the office, while he himself performed the
					duties; for there was a law just passed, that no man should
					be chosen treasurer for above the term of four years. But
					Lycurgus plied his business closely, both summer and winter, in the administration of public affairs. And being
					entrusted to make provision of all necessaries for the wars,
					he reformed many abuses that were crept into the commonwealth. He built four hundred galleys for the use of
					the public, and prepared and fitted a place for public exercises in Lyceum, and planted trees before it; he likewise
					built a wrestling-court, and being made surveyor of the
					theatre of Bacchus, he finished this building. He was
					likewise of so great repute among all sorts, that he was
					entrusted with two hundred and fifty talents of private
					citizens. He adorned and beautified the city with gold
					and silver vessels of state, and golden images of victory.
					He likewise finished many things that were as yet imperfect, as the dockyards and the arsenal. He built a wall also
					about the spacious Panathenaic race-course, and made
					level a piece of uneven ground, given by one Dinias to Lycurgus for the use of the city. The keeping of the city
					was committed wholly to his care, and power to apprehend
					malefactors, of whom he cleared the city utterly; so that
					some sophisters were wont to say, that Lycurgus did not
					dip his pen in ink, but in blood. And therefore it was,
					that when Alexander demanded him of the people, they
					would not deliver him up. When Philip made the second
					war upon the Athenians, he was employed with Demosthenes and Polyeuctus in an embassy to Peloponnesus and
					other cities. He was always in great repute and esteem
					with the Athenians, and looked upon as a man of that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.38"/>
					
					justice and integrity, that in the courts of judicature his
					good word was at all times prevalent on the behalf of
					those persons for whom he undertook to speak. He was
					the author of several laws; one of which was, that there
					should be certain comedies played at the Chytrian solemnities, and whoever of the poets or players should come off
					victor, he should thereby be invested with the freedom of
					the city, which before was not lawful; and so he revived
					a solemnity which for want of encouragement had for
					some time before been out of request. Another of his
					laws was, that the city should erect statues to the memory
					of Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides; and that their
					tragedies, being fairly engrossed, should be preserved in
					the public consistory, and that the public clerks should
					read these copies as the plays were acted, that nothing
					might be changed by the players; and that otherwise it
					should be unlawful to act them. A third law proposed by
					him was, that no Athenian, nor any person inhabiting in
					Athens, should be permitted to buy a captive, who was
					once free, to be a slave, without the consent of his former master. Further, that in the Piraeus there should be
					at least three circular dances played to Neptune; and that
					to the victor in the first should be given not less than ten
					minas; in the second, eight; in the third, six. Also, that
					no woman should go to Eleusis in a coach, lest the poor
					should appear more despicable than the rich, and so be
					dejected and cast down; and that whoever should ride in
					a coach contrary to this law should be fined six thousand
					drachms. And when even his own wife was taken in the
					violation of it, he paid to the discoverers of it a whole
					talent; for which being afterwards called in question by
					the people: See therefore, said he, I am called to answer
					for giving, and not for receiving money.</p>
            <p>As he was walking one day in the streets, he saw an
					officer lay hand on Xenocrates the philosopher; and when
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.39"/>
					
					nothing would serve his turn but the philosopher must to
					prison, because he had not deposited the tribute due from
					strangers, he with his staff struck the officer on the head
					for his unmannerly roughness toward a person of that
					character, and freeing Xenocrates, cast the other into prison in his stead. And not many days after, Xenocrates
					meeting with the children of Lycurgus said: I have returned thanks unto your father right speedily, my good
					children, for his friendship towards me, for I hear his
					kindness commended by all people where I go. He made
					likewise several decrees, in which he made use of the
					help of an Olynthian named Euclides, one very expert in
					such matters. Though he was rich enough, yet he was
					used to wear the same coat every day, both summer and
					winter; but he wore shoes only when he was compelled to
					do it. Because he was not ready to speak extempore,
					he used to practise and study day and night. And to the
					end he might not at any time oversleep himself and so
					lose time from his study, he used to cover himself on his
					bed only with a sheepskin with the wool on, and to lay a
					hard bolster under his head. When one reproached him
					for being in fee with rhetoricians when he studied his orations, he answered, that, if a man would promise to restore
					his sons better, he would give him not only a thousand
					drachms, but half what he was worth. He took the liberty of speaking boldly upon all occasions, by reason of his
					greatness; as when once the Athenians interrupted him in
					his speaking, he cried out, O thou Corcyraean whip, how
					many talents art thou worth? And another time, when
					some would rank Alexander among the Gods, What manner of God, said he, must he be, when all that go out of
					his temple had need to be dipped in water to purify themselves?</p>
            <p>After his death Menesaechmus accusing and indicting
					them by virtue of an instrument drawn by Thracycles, his
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.40"/>
					
					sons were delivered to the eleven executioners of Justice.
					But Demosthenes, being in exile, wrote to the Athenians,
					to let them know that they were wrongfully accused, and
					that therefore they did not well to hear their accusers;
					upon which they recanted what they had done, and set
					them at liberty again,&mdash;Democles, who was Theophrastus's
					scholar, likewise pleading in their defence. Lycurgus and
					some of his posterity were buried publicly, at or near the
					temple of Minerva Paeonia, where their monuments stand
					in the garden of Melanthius the philosopher, on which
					are inscriptions to Lycurgus and his children, which are
					yet extant. The greatest thing he did while he lived was
					his raising the revenue of the commons totally from sixty
					talents, as he found it, to twelve hundred. When he
					found he must die, he was by his own appointment carried
					into the temple of the Mother of the Gods, and into the
					senate-house, being willing before his death to give an account of his administration. And no man daring to accuse
					him of any thing except Menesaechmus, having purged
					himself from those calumnies which he cast upon him,
					he was carried home again, where in a short time he
					ended his life. He was always accounted honest; his
					orations were commended for the eloquence they carried
					in them; and though he was often accused, yet he never
					was overthrown in any suit.</p>
            <p>He had three children by Callisto, the daughter of
					Abron, and sister of Callias, Abron's son, by descent a
					Batesian,&mdash;I mean, of him who, when Chaerondas was
					magistrate, was paymaster to the army. Of this affinity
					Dinarchus speaks in his oration against Pastius. He left
					behind him three sons, Abron, Lycurgus, and Lycophron;
					of which, Abron and Lycurgus died without issue, though
					the first, Abron, did for some time act very acceptably and
					worthily in affairs of the commonwealth. Lycophron marrying Callistomacha, the daughter of Philip of Aexone,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.41"/>
					
					begat Callisto, who married Cleombrotus the son of Dinocrates the Acharnian, to whom she bare Lycophron, who,
					being adopted by his grandfather, died without issue. He
					being dead, Socrates married Callisto, of whom he had his
					son Symmachus. To him was born Aristonymus; to Aristonymus, Charmides, who was the father of Philippe. Of
					her and Lysander came Medeius, who also was an interpreter, one of the Eumolpids. He begat two children of
					Timothea, the daughter of Glaucus, viz. Laodamia and
					Medius, who were priests of Neptune Erechtheus; also
					Philippe a daughter, who was afterward priestess of Minerva; for before, she was married to Diocles of Melite, to
					whom she bare a son named Diocles, who was a colonel
					of a regiment of foot. He married Hediste, the daughter
					of Abron, and of her begat Philippides and Nicostrata,
					whom Themistocles the torch-bearer, son of Theophrastus,
					married, and by her had Theophrastus and Diodes; and
					he likewise constituted the priesthood of Neptune Erechtheus.</p>
            <p>It is said that he penned fifteen orations. He was often
					crowned by the people, and had statues dedicated to him.
					His image in brass was set up in Ceramicus by order of
					the public, in the year of Anaxicrates; in whose time also
					it was ordered that he and his eldest son should be provided
					for with diet in the Prytaneum; but he being dead, Lycophron his eldest son was forced to sue for that donation.
					This Lycurgus also was used frequently to plead on the
					account of sacred things; and accused Autolycus the Areopagite, Lysicles the general, Demades the son of Demeas,
					Menesaechmus, and many others, all whom he caused to
					be condemned as guilty. Diphilus also was called in question by him, for impairing and diminishing the props
					of the metal mines, and unjustly making himself rich
					therefrom; and he caused him to be condemned to die,
					according to the provision made by the laws in that case.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.42"/>
					
					He gave out of his own stock fifty drachms to every citizen, the sum total of which donation amounted to one
					hundred and sixty talents;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is one of the statements which seem to fix the number of Athenian citizens in the age of the Orators at about 20,000. See Boeckh's Public Economy of
						the Athenians, I. Book 1, chap. 7. (G.)</note> but some say he gave a mina
					of silver to each. He likewise accused Aristogiton, Leocrates, and Autolycus for cowardice. He was called the
					Ibis: . . .
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ibis to Lycurgus, to Chaerephon the bat.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristoph. Birds, 1296.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>His ancestors derived their pedigree from Erechtheus, the
					son of the Earth and of Vulcan; but he was nearest to
					Lycomedes and Lycurgus, whom the people honored with
					public solemnities. There is a succession of those of the
					race who were priests of Neptune, in a complete table
					placed in the Erechtheum, painted by Ismenias the Chalcidian; in the same place stood wooden images of Lycurgus,
					and of his sons, Abron, Lycurgus, and Lycophron; made by
					Timarchus and Cephisodotus, the sons of Praxiteles. His
					son Abron dedicated the table; and coming to the priesthood by right of succession, he resigned to his brother
					Lycophron, and hence he is painted as giving a trident.
					But Lycurgus had made a draught of all his actions, and
					hung it on a column before the wrestling-court built by
					himself, that all might read that would; and no man could
					accuse him of any peculation. He likewise proposed to
					the people to crown Neoptolemus, the son of Anticles, and
					to dedicate statues to him, because he had promised and
					undertaken to cover the altar of Apollo in the market with
					gold, according to the order of the oracle. He decreed
					honors likewise to Diotimus, the son of Diopithes of
					Euonymus, in the year when Ctesicles was magistrate.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.43"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>VIII. DEMOSTHENES.</head>
            <p>DEMOSTHENES, the son of Demosthenes by Cleobule, the
					daughter of Gylon, was a Paeanian by descent. He was
					left an orphan by his father, when he was but seven years
					old, together with a sister of the age of five. Being kept
					by his mother during his nonage, he went to school to Isocrates, say some; but the generality are of opinion that he
					was pupil to Isaeus the Chalcidian, who lived in Athens
					and was Isocrates's scholar. He imitated Thucydides and
					Plato, and some affirm that he more especially attended the
					school of Plato. Hegesias the Magnesian writes, that he
					entreated his master's leave to go to hear Callistratus the
					son of Empaedus, an Amphidnean, a noble orator, and
					sometime commander of a troop of horse, who had dedicated an altar to Mercury Agoraeos, and was to make an
					oration to the people. And when he heard him, he
					became a lover of oratory, and so long as he continued
					at Athens, remained his disciple.</p>
            <p>But Callistratus being soon banished to Thrace, and
					Demosthenes arrived at some years of maturity, he joined
					with Isocrates and Plato. After this, he took Isaeus into
					his house, and for the space of four years labored very
					hard in imitation of his orations. Though Ctesibius in
					his book of philosophy affirms that, by the help of Callias
					the Syracusan, he got the orations of Zoilus the Amphipolite, and by the assistance of Charicles the Carystian
					those also of Alcidamas, and devoted himself to the imitation of them. When he came to age, in the year of Timocrates<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 364.</note> he called his tutors and guardians to account for
					their maladministration, in not allowing him what was
					fitting and requisite out of his estate. And these tutors or
					guardians were three, Aphobus, Therippides, and Demophbn (or Demeas), the last of whom, being his uncle, he
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.44"/>
					
					charged more severely than the other two. He arrested
					each of them in an action of ten talents, and cast them,
					but did not exact of them what the law had given him,
					releasing some for money and others for favor.</p>
            <p>When Aristophon, by reason of his age, could not hold
					the office any longer, he was chosen choregus, or overseer
					of the dances. During the execution of which office,
					Midias the Anagyrasian striking him as he was ordering
					the dances in the theatre, he sued him upon it, but let
					fall his suit upon Midias's paying him three thousand
					drachms.</p>
            <p>It is reported of him that, while he was a youth, he
					confined himself to a den or cave, and there studied his
					orations, and shaved half of his head that he might not be
					allured to divert himself from it; and that he lay upon a
					very narrow bed, that he might awake and rise the sooner.
					And for that he could not very well pronounce the letter
					R, he accustomed himself very much to that, that he might
					master it if possible; and using likewise an unseemly
					motion of his shoulder when he spake at any time, he
					remedied that by a spit (or, as some say, a sword) stuck in
					the ceiling just over his shoulder, that the fear of being
					pricked with it might break him of that indecent gesture. They report of him further that, when he could
					declaim pretty well, he had a sort of mirror made as big
					as himself, and used always in declaiming to look in that,
					to the end that he might see and correct what was amiss.
					He used likewise at some certain times to go down to the
					Phalerian shore, to the end that, being accustomed to the
					surges and noise of the waves, he might not be daunted
					by the clamors of the people, when he should at any time
					declaim in public. And being naturally short-winded, he
					gave Neoptolemus a player ten thousand drachms to teach
					him to pronounce long sentences in one breath.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, betaking himself to the affairs of the commonwealth,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.45"/>
					
					 and finding the people divided into two different factions, one in favor of Philip, and the other standing
					for the liberty and properties of the people, he took part
					with them that opposed Philip, and always persuaded the
					citizens to help those who were in danger and trouble by
					Philip's oppression; taking for his companions in council
					Hyperides, Nausicles, Polyeuctus, and Diotimus; and then
					he drew the Thebans, Euboeans, Corcyraeans, Corinthians,
					Boeotians, and many more into a league with the Athenians. Being in the assembly one day and his memory
					failing him, his oration was hissed; which made him return
					home very heavy and melancholy; and being met by Eunomus the Thriasian, an old man, by him he was comforted
					and encouraged. But he was chiefly animated by Andronicus the player, who told him that his orations were
					excellent, but that he wanted something of action, thereupon rehearsing certain places out of his oration which
					he had delivered in that same assembly. Unto which
					Demosthenes gave good ear and credit, and he then betook himself to Andronicus. And therefore, when he was
					afterwards asked what was the first part of oratory, he
					answered, <q direct="unspecified">Action;</q> and which was the second, he replied, <q direct="unspecified">Action;</q> and which was the third, he still answered, <q direct="unspecified">Action.</q> Another time, declaiming publicly, and
					using expressions too youthful for one of his years and
					gravity, he was laughed at, and ridiculed by the comedians,
					Antiphanes and Timocles, who in derision used to repeat
					such phrases as these, as uttered by him:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>By the earth, by the fountains, by the rivers, by the floods!</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For having sworn thus in presence of the people, he raised
					a tumult about him. He likewise used to swear by
					Asclepius, and accented the second syllable (<foreign lang="greek">)*asklh/pios</foreign>)<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This name was properly pronounced with the accent on the last syllable, <foreign lang="greek">)*asklhpio/s</foreign> (G.)</note>
					through some mistake, and yet afterwards defended it; for
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.46"/>
					
					this Asclepius, he said, was called <foreign lang="greek">h)/pios,</foreign> that is a <hi rend="italics">mild</hi> God.
					This also often caused him to be interrupted. But all
					these things he reformed in time, being sometime conversant with Eubulides, the Milesian philosopher. Being on a time present at the Olympic games, and hearing
					Lamachus the Myrrhinaean sound the praises of Philip and
					of Alexander the Great, his son, and decry the cowardice
					of the Thebans and Olynthians, he stood up in their defence against him, and from the ancient poets he proclaimed the great and noble achievements of the Thebans
					and Olynthians; and so elegantly he behaved himself in
					this affair, that he at once silenced Lamachus, and made
					him convey himself immediately out of the assembly. And
					even Philip himself, when he had heard what harangues
					he made against him, replied, that if he had heard him, he
					should have chosen him general in the war against himself.
					He was used to compare Demosthenes's orations to soldiers,
					for the force they carried along with them; but the orations of Isocrates to fencers, because of the theatrical
					delight that accompanied them.</p>
            <p>Being about the age of seven and thirty, reckoning from
					Dexitheus to Callimachus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B. C. 385-384 to 349-348.</note>&mdash;in whose time the Olynthians
					sent to beg aid of the Athenians against Philip, who then
					made war upon them,&mdash;he persuaded them to answer the
					Olynthians' request; but in the following year, in which
					Plato died,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 348-347.</note> Philip overthrew and destroyed the Olynthians. Xenophon also, the scholar of Socrates, had some
					knowledge of Demosthenes, either at his first rise, or at
					least when he was most famous and flourishing; for he
					wrote the Acts of the Greeks, as touching what passed at
					the battle of Mantinea, in the year of Chariclides;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 363-362.</note> our
					Demosthenes having sometime before overthrown his guardians in a suit he had commenced against them, in the
					year of Timocrates. When Aeschines, being condemned,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.47"/>
					
					fled from Athens, Demosthenes hearing of it took horse
					and rode after him; which Aeschines understanding, and
					fearing to be apprehended again, he came out to meet Demosthenes, and fell at his feet, covered his face, and begged
					his mercy; upon which Demosthenes bid him stand up,
					be assured of his favor, and as a pledge of it, gave him a
					talent of silver. He advised the people to maintain a
					company of mercenary soldiers in Thasos, and thither
					sailed himself as captain of the galleys. Another time,
					being entrusted to buy corn, he was accused of defrauding
					the city, but cleared himself of the accusation and was
					acquitted. When Philip had seized upon Elatea, Demosthenes with others went to the war of Chaeronea, where he
					is said to have deserted his colors; and flying away, a bramble caught hold of his vest behind, when turning about in
					haste, thinking an enemy had overtaken him, he cried out,
					Save my life, and say what shall be my ransom. On his
					buckler he had engraven for his motto, To Good Fortune.
					And it was he that made the oration at the funerals of
					such as died in that battle.</p>
            <p>After these things, he bent his whole care and study for
					the reparation of the city and wall; and being chosen
					commissary for repairing the walls, besides what money
					he expended out the city stock, he laid out of his own at
					least a hundred minas. And besides this, he gave ten
					thousand drachms to the festival fund; and taking ship,
					he sailed from coast to coast to collect money of the allies;
					for which he was often by Demotelus, Aristonicus, and
					Hyperides crowned with golden crowns, and afterwards
					by Ctesiphon. Which last decree had like to have been
					retracted, Diodotus and Aeschines endeavoring to prove it
					to be contrary to the laws; but he defended himself so
					well against their allegations, that he overcame all difficulties, his enemies not having the fifth part of the votes of
					the judges.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.48"/>
            <p>After this, when Alexander the Great made his expedition into Asia, and Harpalus fled to Athens with a great
					sum of money, at first he would not let him be entertained,
					but afterwards, Harpalus being landed and having given
					him a thousand darics he was of another mind; and when
					the Athenians determined to deliver Harpalus up to Antipater, he opposed it, proposing to deposit the money in
					the Citadel, still without declaring the amount to the people.
					Thereupon Harpalus declared that he had brought with
					him from Asia seven hundred talents, and that this sum had
					been deposited in the Citadel; but only three hundred and
					fifty or a little more could be found, as Philochorus relates.
					But when Harpalus broke out of the prison wherein he
					was kept till some person should come from Alexander,
					and was escaped into Crete,&mdash;or, as some will have it,
					into Taenarum in Laconia,&mdash;Demosthenes was accused
					that he had received from him a sum of money, and that
					therefore he had not given a true account of the sum delivered to him, nor had impeached the negligence of the
					keepers. So he was judicially cited by Hyperides, Pytheus, Menesaechmus, Himeraeus, and Patrocles, who
					prosecuted him so severely as to cause him to be condemned in the court of Areopagus; and being condemned,
					he went into exile, not being able to pay fivefold; for he
					was accused of receiving thirty talents. Others say, that
					he would not run the risk of a trial, but went into banishment before the day came. After this tempest was over,
					when the Athenians sent Polyeuctus to the republic of
					Arcadia to draw them off from the alliance with the Macedonians, he not succeeding, Demosthenes appeared to
					second him, where he reasoned so effectually that he easily
					prevailed. Which procured him so much credit and esteem,
					that after some time a galley was dispatched to call him
					home again. And the Athenians decreed that, whereas he
					owed the state thirty talents, as a fine laid on him for the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.49"/>
					
					misdemeanor he was accused of, he should be excused for
					only building an altar to Jupiter Servator in the Piraeus;
					which decree was first proposed by Demon his near kinsman. This being agreed on, he returned to the administration of affairs in the commonwealth again.</p>
            <p>But when Antipater was blocked up in Lamia, and the
					Athenians offered sacrifices for the happy news, he happened, being talking with Agesistratus, one of his intimate
					friends, to say, that his judgment concerning the state of
					affairs did not jump with other men's, for that he knew
					the Greeks were brisk and ready enough to run a short
					course but not to hold on a long race. When Antipater
					had taken Pharsalus, and threatened to besiege Athens itself if they refused to deliver up such orators as had declaimed against him, Demosthenes, suspecting himself to
					be one of the number, left the city, and fled first into
					Aegina, that he might take sanctuary in the temple of
					Aeacus; but being afraid to trust himself long there, he
					went over to Calauria; and when the Athenians had decreed to deliver up those orators, and him especially as one
					of them, he continued a suppliant in the temple of Neptune. When Archias came thither,&mdash;who, from his office
					of pursuing fugitives, was called Phygadotheres and was
					the scholar of Anaximines the orator,&mdash;when he, I say,
					came to him, and persuaded him to go with him, telling
					him that no doubt he should be received by Antipater as a
					friend, he replied: When you played a part in a tragedy,
					you could not persuade me to believe you the person you
					represented; no more shall you now persuade me by your
					counsel. And when Archias endeavored to force him
					thence, the townsmen would not suffer it. And Demosthenes told them, that he did not flee to Calauria to save
					his life, but that he might convince the Macedonians of
					their violence committed even against the Gods themselves.
					And with that he called for a writing-table; and if we may
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.50"/>
					
					credit Demetrius the Magnesian, on that he wrote a distich,
					which afterwards the Athenians caused to be affixed to his
					statue; and it was to this purpose:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hadst thou, Demosthenes, an outward force
						</l>
                     <l>Great as thy inward magnanimity,
						</l>
                     <l>Greece should not wear the Macedonian yoke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This statue, made by Polyeuctus, is placed near the
					cloister where the altar of the twelve Gods is erected.
					Some say this writing was found: <q direct="unspecified">Demosthenes to Antipater, Greeting.</q> Philochorus tells us that he died by
					drinking of poison; and Satyrus the historiographer will
					have it, that the pen was poisoned with which he wrote his
					epistle, and putting it into his mouth, soon after he tasted
					it he died. Eratosthenes is of another opinion, that being
					in continual fear of the Macedonians, he wore a poisoned
					bracelet on his arms. Others say again, that he died with
					holding his breath; and others, lastly, say that he carried
					strong poison in his signet. He lived to the age of seventy,
					according to those who give the highest number,&mdash;of
					sixty-seven, according to other statements. And he was in
					public life two and twenty years.</p>
            <p>When King Philip was dead, he appeared publicly in a
					glorious robe or mantle, as rejoicing for his death, though
					he but just before mourned for his daughter. He assisted
					the Thebans likewise against Alexander, and animated all
					the other Greeks. So that when Alexander had conquered
					Thebes, he demanded Demosthenes of the Athenians,
					threatening them if they refused to deliver him. When he
					went against Persia, demanding ships of the Athenians, Demosthenes opposed it, saying, who can assure us that he will
					not use those ships we should send him against ourselves?</p>
            <p>He left behind him two sons by one wife, the daughter
					of one Heliodorus, a principal citizen. He had but one
					daughter, who died unmarried, being but a child. A sister
					too he had, who married with Laches of Leuconoe, his
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.51"/>
					
					kinsman, and to him bore Demochares, who proved inferior
					to none in his time for eloquence, conduct, and courage.
					His statue is still standing in the Prytaneum, the first on
					the right as you approach the altar, clothed with a mantle
					and girt with a sword, because in this habit he delivered
					an oration to the people, when Antipater demanded of
					them their orators.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, in process of time, the Athenians decreed
					nourishment to be given to the kindred of Demosthenes in
					the Prytaneum, and likewise set up a statue to his memory,
					when he was dead, in the market, in the year of Gorgias,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C 280.</note>
					which honors were paid him at the request of Demochares
					his sister's son. And ten years after, Laches, the son of
					Demochares of Leuconoe, in the year of Pytharatus, required the same honor for himself, that his statue should
					be set up in the market, and that both he and the eldest
					of his line for the future should have their allowance in
					the Prytaneum, and the highest room at all public shows.
					These decrees concerning both of them are engrossed, and
					to be found among the statute laws. The statue of Demochares, of which we have spoken before, was afterwards
					removed out of the market into the Prytaneum.</p>
            <p>There are extant sixty-five orations which are truly his.
					Some report of him, that he lived a very dissolute and
					vicious life, appearing often in women's apparel, and being
					frequently conversant at masks and revellings, whence he
					was surnamed Batalus; though others say, that this was a
					pet name given him by his nurse, and that from this he was
					called Batalus in derision. Diogenes the Cynic espying
					him one day in a victualling-house, he was very much
					ashamed, and to shun him, went to withdraw; but Diogenes called after him, and told him, The more you shrink
					inward, the more you will be in the tavern. The same
					Diogenes once upon the banter said of him, that in his
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.52"/>
					
					orations he was a Scythian, but in war a delicate nice
					citizen. He was one of them who received gold of Ephialtes, one of the popular orators, who, being sent in an
					embassy to the king of Persia, took money privily, and
					distributed it among the orators of Athens, that they might
					use their utmost endeavors to kindle and inflame the war
					against Philip; and it is said of Demosthenes, that he for
					his part had at once three thousand darics of the king.
					He apprehended one Anaxilas of Oreus, who had been
					his friend, and caused him to be tortured for a spy; and
					when he would confess nothing, he procured a decree that
					he should be delivered to the eleven executioners.</p>
            <p>When once at a meeting of the Athenians they would
					not suffer him to speak, he told them he had but a short
					story to tell them. Upon which all being silent, thus he
					began: A certain youth, said he, hired an ass in summer
					time, to go from hence to Megara. About noon, when the
					sun was very hot, and both he that hired the ass and the
					owner were desirous of sitting in the shade of the ass,
					they each thrust the other away,&mdash;the owner arguing that
					he let him only his ass and not the shadow, and the other
					replying that, since he had hired the ass, all that belonged
					to him was at his dispose. Having said thus, he seemed
					to go his way. But the Athenians willing now to hear his
					story out, called him back, and desired him to proceed.
					To whom he replied: How comes it to pass that ye are so
					desirous of hearing a story of the shadow of an ass, and
					refuse to give ear to matters of greater moment? Polus
					the player boasting to him that he had gotten a whole
					talent by playing but two days, he answered, and I have
					gotten five talents by being silent but one day. One day
					his voice failing him when he was declaiming publicly,
					being hissed, he cried out to the people, saying, Ye are to
					judge of players, indeed, by their voice, but of orators by
					the gravity of their sentences.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.53"/>
            <p>Epicles upbraiding him for his premeditating what he
					was to say, he replied, I should be ashamed to speak what
					comes uppermost to so great an assembly. They say of
					him that he never put out his lamp&mdash;that is, never ceased
					polishing his orations&mdash;until he was fifty years old. He
					says of himself, that he drank always fair water. Lysias
					the orator was acquainted with him; and Isocrates knew
					him concerned in the management of public affairs till the
					battle of Chaeronea; as also some of the Socratical sect.
					[He delivered most of his orations extempore, Nature having well qualified him for it.]<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is supposed to have been added by some other hand, because a contrary
						sentence is given of him before.</note> The first that proposed
					the crowning him with a coronet of gold was Aristonicus,
					the son of Nicophanes, the Anagyrasian; though Diondas
					interposed with an indictment.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>IX. HYPERIDES.</head>
            <p>HYPERIDES was son of Glaucippus, and grandson of
					Dionysius, of the borough of Colyttus. He had a son,
					who bare the same name with his father Glaucippus, an
					orator, who wrote many orations, and begat a son named
					Alphinous. At the same time with Lycurgus, he had been
					a scholar of the philosopher Plato and of the orator Isocrates. In Athens his concern in the commonwealth was
					at that time when Alexander accosted Greece, whom he
					vigorously opposed in his demands made of the Athenians
					for the generals as well as for galleys. He advised the
					people not to discharge the garrison of Taenarum, and this
					he did for the sake of a friend of his, Chares, who was
					commander of it. At first he used to plead causes for a
					fee. He was suspected to have received part of the money
					which Ephialtes brought out of Persia, and was chosen
					to maintain a galley, and was sent to assist the Byzantines,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.54"/>
					
					when Philip was besieging their city. Nevertheless, in
					the same year he took the charge of defraying the expense
					of the solemn dances, whereas the rest of the captains
					were exempt from all such public burdens for that year.
					He obtained a decree for some honors to be paid to Demosthenes; and when that decree was indicted at the instance of Diondas, as being contrary to the laws, he, being
					called in question upon it, cleared himself. He did not
					continue his friendship with Demosthenes, Lysicles, and
					Lycurgus to the last; for, Lysicles and Lycurgus being
					dead, and Demosthenes being accused of having received
					money of Harpalus, he, among all the rest, was pitched
					upon, as the only person who was not corrupted with
					bribery, to draw up his indictment, which he accordingly did.
					Being once accused at the instance of Aristogiton of publishing acts contrary to the laws after the battle of Chaeronea,&mdash;that all foreign inhabitants of Athens should be
					accounted citizens, that slaves should be made free, that
					all sacred things, children, and women should be confined
					to the Piraeus,&mdash;he cleared himself of all and was acquitted. And being blamed by some, who wondered how
					he could be ignorant of the many laws that were directly
					repugnant to those decrees, he answered, that the arms of
					the Macedonians darkened his sight, and it was not he but
					the battle of Chaeronea that made that decree. But Philip,
					being affrighted at somewhat, gave leave to carry away
					their dead out of the field, which before he had denied to
					the heralds from Lebadea.</p>
            <p>After this, at the overthrow at Crannon, being demanded
					by Antipater, and the people being resolved to deliver
					him up, he fled out of the city with others who were under
					the same condemnation to Aegina; where meeting with
					Demosthenes, he excused himself for the breach of friendship between them. Going from thence, he was apprehended by Archias, surnamed Phygadotheres, by country a
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.55"/>
					
					Thurian, formerly a player, but at that time in the service
					of Antipater; by this man, I say, he was apprehended,
					even in the very temple of Neptune, though he grasped
					the image of that God in his arms. He was brought before Antipater, who was then at Corinth; where being
					put upon the rack, he bit out his tongue, because he would
					not divulge the secrets of his country, and so died, on the
					ninth day of October. Hermippus tells us that, as he went
					into Macedonia, his tongue was cut out and his body cast
					forth unburied; but Alphinous his cousin-german (or, according to the opinion of others, his grandson, by his son
					Glaucippus) obtained leave, by means of one Philopithes
					a physician, to take up his body, which he burnt, and carried the ashes to Athens to his kinsfolk there, contrary to
					the edicts both of the Athenians and Macedonians, which
					not only banished them, but likewise forbade the burial of
					them anywhere in their own country. Others say, that
					he was carried to Cleonae with others, and there died,
					having his tongue cut out, as above; however, his relations
					and friends took his bones, when his body was burned, and
					buried them among his ancestors before the gate Hippades,
					as Heliodorus gives us the relation in his Third Book of
					Monuments. His monument is now altogether unknown
					and lost, being thrown down with age and long standing.</p>
            <p>He is said to have excelled all others in his way of delivering himself in his orations to the people. And there
					are some who prefer him even to Demosthenes himself.
					There are seventy-seven orations which bear his name, of
					which only two and fifty are genuine and truly his. He
					was much given to venery, insomuch that he turned his
					son out of doors, to entertain that famous courtesan Myrrhina. In Piraeus he had another, whose name was Aristagora; and at Eleusis, where part of his estate lay, he
					kept another, one Philte a Theban, whom he ransomed
					for twenty minas. His usual walk was in the fish-market.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.56"/>
					
					It is thought that he was accused of impiety with one
					Phryne, a courtesan likewise, and so was sought after to be
					apprehended, as he himself seems to intimate in the beginning of an oration; and it is said, that when sentence
					was just ready to be passed upon her, he produced her in
					court, opened her clothes before, and discovered her naked
					breasts, which were so very white, that for her beauty's
					sake the judges acquitted her. He at leisure times drew
					up several declamations against Demosthenes, which were
					thus discovered: Hyperides being sick, Demosthenes came
					one day to visit him, and caught him with a book in his
					hand written against him; at which seeming somewhat
					displeased, Hyperides told him: This book shall hurt no
					man that is my friend; but as a curb, it may serve to restrain my enemy from offering me any injury. He obtained
					a decree of some honors to be paid to Iolas, who gave the
					poisoned cup to Alexander. He joined with Leosthenes
					in the Lamian war, and made an admirable oration at the
					funerals of those who lost their lives therein.</p>
            <p>When Philip was prepared to embark for Euboea, and
					the Athenians heard the news of it with no little consternation, Hyperides in a very short time, by the voluntary
					contributions of the citizens, fitted out forty sail, and was
					the first that set an example, by sending out two galleys,
					one for himself and another for his son, at his own
					charge.</p>
            <p>When there was a controversy between the Delians and
					the Athenians, who should have the pre-eminence in the
					temple at Delos; Aeschines being chosen on the behalf of
					the Athenians for their advocate, the Areopagites refused
					to ratify the choice and elected Hyperides; and his oration is yet extant, and bears the name of the Deliac oration.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Demosthenes on the Crown, p. 221, 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He likewise went ambassador to Rhodes; where meeting
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.57"/>
					
					 other ambassadors from Antipater, who commended
					their master very highly for his goodness and virtue, We
					know, replied he, that Antipater is good, but we have no
					need of a good master at present.</p>
            <p>It is said of him, that he never affected much action in
					his orations to the people, his chief aim being to lay down
					the matter plainly, and make the case as obvious to the
					judges as he could.</p>
            <p>He was sent likewise to the Eleans, to plead the cause of
					Callippus the fencer, who was accused of carrying away
					the prize at the public games unfairly; in which cause he
					got the better. But when he opposed the sentence of paying honors to Phocion, obtained by Midias the son of Midias the Anagyrasian, he was in that cause overthrown.
					This cause was pleaded on the twenty-fourth day of May,
					in the year when Xenius was magistrate.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>X. DINARCHUS.</head>
            <p>DINARCHUS, the son of Socrates or Sostratus,&mdash;born, as
					some think, at Athens, but according to others, at Corinth,
					&mdash;came to Athens very young, and there took up his
					dwelling, at that time when Alexander made his expedition
					into Asia. He used to hear Theophrastus, who succeeded
					Aristotle in his school. He was frequently conversant with
					Demetrius the Phalerian too. He betook himself more
					especially to the affairs of the commonwealth after the
					death of Antipater, when some of the orators were killed
					and others banished. Having contracted friendship with
					Cassander, he became in a short time vastly rich, by exacting great rates for his orations of those for whom he wrote
					them. He opposed himself to the greatest and most noble
					orators of his time, not by being overforward to declaim
					publicly,&mdash;for his faculty did not lie that way,&mdash;but by
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.58"/>
					
					composing orations for their adversaries. And when Harpalus had broken out of prison, he wrote several orations,
					which he gave to their accusers to pronounce against those
					that were suspected to have taken bribes of him.</p>
            <p>Some time after, being accused of a conspiracy with
					Antipater and Cassander about the matter of Munychia,
					when it was surprised by Antigonus and Demetrius, who
					put a garrison into it, in the year of Anaxicrates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 307.</note> he turned
					the greatest part of his estate into money, and fled to Chalcis, where he lived in exile about fifteen years, and increased his stock; but afterwards, by the mediation of
					Theophrastus, he and some other banished persons returned
					to Athens. Then he took up his abode .in the house of
					one Proxenus, his intimate friend; where, being very aged
					and withal dim-sighted, he lost his gold. And because
					Proxenus refused to make inquiry after the thief, he apprehended him; and this was the first time that ever he appeared in court. That oration against Proxenus is extant;
					and there are sixty-four that bear his name, whereof some
					are believed to be Aristogiton's. He imitated Hyperides;
					or, as some incline to judge, rather Demosthenes, because
					of that vigor and force to move the affections, and the
					rhetorical ornaments that are evident in his style.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>Decrees proposed to the Athenians. I.</head>
            <p>Demochares, the son of Laches of Leuconoe, requires
					that a statue of brass be set up for Demosthenes, the son
					of Demosthenes the Paeanian, in the market-place, as
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.59"/>
					
					likewise that provision of diet be made in the Prytaneum
					for himself and the eldest of his progeny successively, and
					the chief seat in all public shows; for that he had done
					many good offices for the Athenians, had on most occasions
					been a good counsellor, and had spent his patrimony in the
					commonwealth; had expended eight talents for the fitting
					out and maintenance of one galley, when they delivered
					Euboea, another, when Cephisodorus sailed into the Hellespont, and a third, when Chares and Phocion were commissioned by the people to go captains to Byzantium; that he
					at his own charge had redeemed many who had been taken
					prisoners by Philip at Pydna, Methone, and Olynthus; that
					himself had maintained a choir of men, when no provision
					had been made therefor through the neglect of the tribe
					Pandionis; that he had furnished many indigent citizens
					with arms; that being chosen by the people to oversee the
					city works, he had laid out three talents of his own stock
					towards the repairing of the walls, besides all that he
					gave for making two trenches about the Piraeus; that
					after the battle of Chaeronea he deposited one talent for
					the use of the public, and after that, another to buy corn
					in time of scarcity and want; that by his beneficence,
					wholesome counsels and effectual persuasions, he allured
					the Thebans, Euboeans, Corinthians, Megarians, Achaeans,
					Locrians, Byzantines, and Messenians to a league with the
					Athenians; that he raised an army of ten thousand foot
					and a thousand horse, and contracted plenty to the people
					and their allies; that being ambassador, he had persuaded
					the allies to the contribution of above five hundred talents;
					that in the same quality, by his influence and the free gift
					of money, he obtained of the Peloponnesians that they
					should not send aid to Alexander against the Thebans;
					and in consideration of many other good offices performed
					by him, either as to his counsels, or his personal administration
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.60"/>
					
					 of affairs in the commonwealth, in which, and in
					defending the lights and liberties of the people, no man in
					his time had done more or deserved better; and in regard
					of his sufferings when the commonwealth was ruined,
					being banished by the insolence of the oligarchy, and at
					last dying at Calauria for his good-will to the public, there
					being soldiers sent from Antipater to apprehend him; and
					that notwithstanding his being in the hands of his enemies,
					in so great and imminent danger, his hearty affection to his
					countrymen was still the same, insomuch that he never to
					the last offered any unworthy thing to the injury of his
					people.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>Decrees proposed to the Athenians. II.</head>
            <p>IN the magistracy of Pytharatus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 269.</note> Laches, the son of
					Demochares of Leuconoe requires of the Athenian senate
					that a statue of brass be set up for Demochares, the son
					of Laches of Leuconoe, in the market-place, and table and
					diet in the Prytaneum for himself and the eldest of his
					progeny successively, and the first seat at all public shows;
					for that he had always been a benefactor and good counsellor to the people, and had done these and the like good
					offices to the public: he had gone in embassies in his own
					person; had proposed and carried in bills relating to his
					embassage; had been chief manager of public matters;
					had repaired the walls, prepared arms and machines;
					had fortified the city in the time of the four years' war, and
					composed a peace, truce, and alliance with the Boeotians;
					for which things he was banished by those who overturned
					and usurped the government;&mdash;and being called home
					again by a decree of the people, in the year of Diocles,
					he had contracted the administration, sparing the public
					funds; and going in embassage to Lysimachus, he had at
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.61"/>
					
					one time gained thirty, and at another time a hundred
					talents of silver, for the use of the public; he had moved
					the people to send an embassage to Ptolemy, by which
					means the people got fifty talents; he went ambassador
					to Antipater, and by that got twenty talents, and brought
					it to Eleusis to the people,&mdash;all which measures he persuaded the people to adopt while he himself carried them
					out; furthermore, he was banished for his love for the
					commonwealth, and would never take part with usurpers
					against the popular government; neither did he, after the
					overthrow of that government, bear any public office in
					the state; he was the only man, of all that had to do in
					the public administration of affairs in his time, who never
					promoted or consented to any other form of government
					but the popular; by his prudence and conduct, all the
					judgments and decrees, the laws, courts, and all things
					else belonging to the Athenians, were preserved safe and
					inviolate; and, in a word, he never said or did any thing
					to the prejudice of the popular government.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <head>Decrees proposed to the Athenians. III.</head>
            <p>LYCOPHRON, the son of Lycurgus of Butadae, requires
					that he may have diet in the Prytaneum, according to a
					donation of the people to Lycurgus. In the year of
					Anaxicrates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">B.C. 307.</note> in the sixth prytany,&mdash;which was that
					of the tribe Antiochis,&mdash;Stratocles, the son of Euthydemus of Diomea, proposed; that,&mdash;since Lycurgus, the
					son of Lycophron of Butadae, had (as it were) an ingenerated good-will in him towards the people of Athens;
					and since his ancestors Diomedes and Lycurgus lived in
					honor and esteem of all people, and when they died were
					honored for their virtue so far as to be buried at the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.62"/>
					
					public charge in the Ceramicus; and since Lycurgus
					himself, while he had the management of public affairs,
					was the author of many good and wholesome laws, and
					was the city treasurer for twelve years together, during
					which time there passed through his own hands eighteen
					thousand and nine hundred talents, besides other great
					sums of money that he was entrusted with by private citizens for the public good, to the sum of six hundred and
					fifty talents; in all which concerns he behaved himself so
					justly, that he was often crowned by the city for his
					fidelity; besides, being chosen by the people to that
					purpose, he brought much money into the Citadel, and
					provided ornaments, golden images of victory, and vessels
					of gold and silver for the Goddess Minerva, and gold ornaments for a hundred Canephoroe;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Persons who carried baskets, or panniers, on their heads, of sacred things.</note> since, being commissary-general, he brought into the stores a great number
					of arms and at least fifty thousand shot of darts, and set
					out four hundred galleys, some new built, and others
					only repaired; since, finding many buildings half finished,
					as the dock-yards, the arsenal, and the theatre of Bacchus,
					he completed them; and finished the Panathenaic race,
					and the court for public exercises at the Lyceum, and
					adorned the city with many fair new buildings; since,
					when Alexander, having conquered Asia, and assuming
					the empire of all Greece, demanded Lycurgus as the principal man that confronted and opposed him in his affairs,
					the people refused to deliver him up, notwithstanding the
					terror inspired by Alexander; and since, being often called
					to account for his management of affairs in so free a city,
					which was wholly governed by the people, he never was
					found faulty or corrupt in any particular;&mdash;that all people, therefore, may know, not only that the people do
					highly esteem all such as act in defence of their liberties
					and rights while they live, but likewise that they pay them
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.63"/>
					
					honors after death, in the name of Good Fortune it is decreed by the people, that such honors be paid to Lycurgus,
					the son of Lycophron of Butadae, for his justice and magnanimity, as that a statue of brass be erected in memory
					of him in any part of the market which the laws do not
					prohibit; as likewise that there be provision for diet in
					the Prytaneum for every eldest son of his progeny, successively for ever. Also, that all his decrees be ratified,
					and engrossed by the public notary, and engraven on
					pillars of stone, and set up in the Citadel just by the
					gifts consecrated to Minerva; and that the city treasurer
					shall deposit fifty drachms for the engraving of them, out
					of the money set apart for such uses.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>