<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De curiositate</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.102">
      <body>
         <head>Of curiosity, or an over-busy inquisitiveness into things impertinent.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.424"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>IF a dwelling-house, by reason of its ill situation or
				contrivance, be not commodiously light and airy, or too much
				exposed to ill weather and unhealthy, it is most advisable
				entirely to quit such a habitation, unless perhaps, through
				continuance of time, neighborhood of friends, or any other
				endearing circumstance, a man should become much wedded to the place; in which case it may be possible, by the
				alteration of windows and new placing of doors and staircases, either to remove or to lessen these inconveniences.
				By such like remedies, even whole cities have been much
				amended and improved both as to health and pleasantness;
				and it is said of the place of my nativity particularly, that,
				while it once lay open to the western winds, and to the
				beams of the declining sun streaming over the top of Parnassus, it was by Chaeron turned toward the east; but it
				is thought that Empedocles the naturalist secured that
				whole region round about from the pestilence, by closing
				up the rift of a certain mountain, from whence a contagious
				southerly damp breathed forth upon the flat of that country. And now, since there are several noxious qualities
				and distempered passions that lurk within the body too,
				which is the more immediate habitation of the soul,&mdash;and
				which, like the dark and tempestuous weather that is with
				out, do cloud and disturb it,&mdash;therefore the like method
				which has been observed in curing the defects and annoyances
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.425"/>
				
				 of an ill-contrived and unhealthy dwelling may be
				followed here, in rendering the body a more commodious,
				serviceable, and delightful mansion for the soul. Wherein
				that it may enjoy its desired calmness and serenity, it will
				conduce beyond all other expedients whatsoever, that those
				blind, tumultuous, and extravagant passions should be expelled or extinguished utterly; or, if that cannot be, yet
				that they be so far reduced and moderated, and so prudently applied and accommodated to their proper objects,
				that the mischief and disorder of them (at least) may be
				removed.</p>
            <p>Among these may deservedly be accounted that sort of
					curiosity, which, by its studious prying into the evils of mankind, seems to be a distemper of envy and ill-nature.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why envious wretch, with such a piercing ray,
					</l>
                     <l>Blind to thine own, dost others' faults survey?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>If the knowledge of ill can reward the industrious search
					with so much delight and pleasure, turn the point of thy
					curiosity upon thyself and thine own affairs, and thou shalt
					within doors find matter enough for the most laborious
					enquiries, plentiful as
					<quote rend="blockquote">Water in Aliso's stream, or leaves about the oak.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>So vast a heap of offences shalt thou find in thy own conversation, such variety of perturbations in thy soul, and
					manifold failures in thy duty. To take a distinct and orderly survey of all which, that of Xenophon will be good
					direction, who said, that it was the manner of discreet
					housekeepers to place their weapons of war, utensils for
					the kitchen, instruments of husbandry, and furniture for
					religious and sacred services, each in several and proper repositories. So every man that would make an exact enquiry
					into and take a just account of himself, should first make
					a particular search into the several mischiefs that proceed
					from each passion within him, whether it be envy or
					jealousy, covetousness or cowardice, or any other vicious
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.426"/>
					
					inclination; and then distribute and range them all (as it
					were) into distinct apartments.</p>
            <p>This done, make thy reviews upon them with the most
					accurate inspection, so that nothing may divert thee from
					the severest scrutiny; obstruct every prospect that looks
					towards thy neighbors' quarters, and close up all those
					avenues which may lead thee to any foreign curiosity;
					become an eavesdropper to thine own house, listen to the
					whispers of thine own walls, and observe those secret arts
					of the female closet, the close intrigues of the parlor, and
					the treacherous practices of thy servants, which thy own
					windows will discover to thee. Here this inquisitive and
					busy disposition may find an employment that will be of
					use and advantage, and is neither ill-natured nor impertinent; while every man shall call himself to this strict
					examination:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where have I err'd? What have I said, or done?
					</l>
                     <l>What duty, when, and how have I foregone?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>But now, as the poets feign concerning Lamia, that
				upon her going to bed she lays aside her eyes among the
				attirements of her dressing-box, and is at home for the
				most part blind and drowsy too, and puts on her eyes only
				when she goes abroad a gadding; so it is with most men,
				who, through a kind of an affected ignorance and artificial
				blindness, commonly blunder and stumble at their own
				threshold, are the greatest strangers to their own personal
				defects, and of all others least familiarly acquainted with
				their own domestic ills and follies. But when they look
				abroad, their sight is sharpened with all the watchful and
				laborious curiosity imaginable, which serves as deforming
				spectacles to an evil eye, that is already envenomed by the
				malignity of a worse nature.</p>
            <p>And hence it is, that a person of this busy meddlesome
					disposition is a greater friend to them he hates than to
					himself; for overlooking his own concerns, through his
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.427"/>
					
					being so heedfully intent on those of other men, he reproves and exposes their miscarriages, admonishes them
					of the errors and follies they ought to correct, and affrights
					them into greater caution for the future; so that not only
					the careless and unwary, but even the more sober and prudent persons, may gain no small advantage from the im
					pertinence and ill-nature of inquisitive people.</p>
            <p>It was a remarkable instance of the prudence of Ulysses,
					that, going into the regions of departed souls, he would
					not exchange so much as one word with his mother there
					till he had first obtained an answer from the oracle and
					despatched the business he came about; and then, turning
					to her, he afforded some small time for a few impertinent
					questions about the other women upon the place, asking
					which was Tyro, and which the fair Chloris, and concerning the unfortunate Epicasta, why,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Noosed to a lofty beam, she would suspended die.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 278.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But we through extreme sloth and ignorance, being stupidly careless of our own affairs, must be idly spending
					our time and talk either about our neighbor's pedigree,
					how that such a one had a tapster for his grandfather, and
					that his grandmother was a laundress; or that another
					owes three or four talents, and is not able to pay the
					interest. Nay, and such trivial stuff as this we busy ourselves about,&mdash;where such a man's wife has been all this
					while; and what it was, that this and the other fellow
					have been talking of in a corner. But the wise Socrates
					employed his curiosity to better purpose, when he went
					about enquiring by what excellent precepts Pythagoras
					obtained so great authority among his followers; and Aristippus, meeting Ischomachus at the Olympic games, asked
					him what those notions were with which Socrates had so
					powerfully charmed the minds of his young scholars;
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.428"/>
					
					upon the slight information whereof, he was so passionately inflamed with a desire of going to Athens, that he
					grew pale and lean, and almost languished till he came to
					drink of the fountain itself, and had been acquainted with
					the person of Socrates, and more fully learned that philosophy of his, the design of which was to teach men how
					to discover their own ills and apply proper remedies to
					them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>But to some sort of men their own life and actions
				would appear the most unpleasant spectacle in the world,
				and therefore they fly from the light of their conscience,
				and cannot bear the torture of one reflecting thought upon
				themselves; for when the soul, being once defiled with all
				manner of wickedness, is scared at its own hideous deformity, it endeavors to run from itself, and ranging here and
				there, it pampers its own malignity with malicious speculations on the ills of others.</p>
            <p>It is observed of the lien that, loathing the plenty of
					meat that is cast before her on a clean floor, she will be
					scratching in a hole or spurning the dunghill, in search
					of one single musty grain. So these over-busy people,
					neglecting such obvious and common things into which
					any man may enquire and talk of without offence, cannot
					be satisfied unless they rake into the private and concealed evils of every family in the neighborhood. It was
					smartly said by the Egyptian, who, being asked what it
					was he carried so closely, replied, it was therefore covered that it might be secret. Which answer will serve to
					check the curiosity of those impertinent men who will be
					always peeping into the privacies of others; for assuredly
					there is nothing usually more concealed than what is too
					foul to be seen; nor would it be kept so close, were it
					either fit or safe it should be known. Without knocking
					at the door, it is great rudeness to enter another's house,
					and therefore in former times were rappers fitted to the
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.429"/>
					
					gates, that by the noise thereof notice might be given to
					the family; for the same purpose are porters appointed
					now, lest, a stranger coming in unawares, the mistress or
					daughter of the family might be surprised busy or undressed, or a servant be seen under correction, or the
					maids be overheard in the heat of their scolding. But a
					person of this prying busy temper, who would disdain the
					being invited to a sober and well-governed house, will yet
					even forcibly intrude himself as a spy into the indecencies
					of private families; and he pries into those very things
					which locks, bolts, and doors were intended to secure from
					common view, for no other end but to discover them to all
					the world. Aristo said that those winds were the most
					troublesome which blew up one's garments and exposed
					one's nakedness; but these inquisitive people deprive us
					of all the shelter or security of walls and doors, and like
					the wanton air, which pervades the veil and steals through
					the closest guards of virgin modesty, they insinuate into
					those divertisements which are hidden in the retirements
					of the night, and strip men even to their very skin.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>So that&mdash;as it is merrily said by the comedian concerning Cleon, that <q direct="unspecified">his hands were in Aetolia, and his soul
				in Thieftown</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, Knights, 79.</note>&mdash;the hands and feet, eyes and thoughts
				of inquisitive persons are straggling about in many places
				at once. Neither the mansions of the great, nor the cottages of the poor, nor the privy chambers of princes, nor
				the recesses of the nuptial alcove, can escape the search
				of their curiosity; they are familiar to the affairs of
				strangers, and will be prying into the darkest mysteries
				of state, although it be to the manifest peril of their being
				ruined by it. For as to him that will be curiously examining the virtues of medicinal herbs, the unwary taste
				of a venomous plant conveys a deleterious impression
				upon the brain, before its noxious quality can be discerned
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.430"/>
				
				 by the palate; so they that boldly pry into the
				ills of great persons usually meet with their own destruction, sooner than they can discover the dangerous secret
				they enquire after. And so it happens that, when the
				rashly curious eye, not contented to expatiate in the free
				and boundless region of reflected light, will be gazing at
				the imperial seat of brightness, it becomes a sacrifice to the
				burning rays, and straight sinks down in penal darkness.</p>
            <p>It was therefore well said by Philippides the comedian,
					who, being asked by King Lysimachus what he desired
					might be imparted to him, replied, Any thing but a secret.
					And indeed, those things in the courts of princes that are
					most pleasant in themselves and most delightful to be
					known,&mdash;such as balls, magnificent entertainments, and
					all the shows of pomp and greatness,&mdash;are exposed to
					common view, nor do they ever hide those divertisements
					and enjoyments which are the attendants of a prosperous
					estate; but in what cases soever they seem reserved,&mdash;as
					when they are conceiving some high displeasure, or contriving the methods of a revenge, or raging under a fit of
					jealousy, or suspicious of the disloyal practices of their
					children, or dubious concerning the treachery of a favorite,&mdash;come not near nor intermeddle, for every thing is
					of a dreadful aspect and of very dangerous access that is
					thus concealed. Fly from so black a cloud, whose darkness condenses into a tempest; and it will be time enough,
					when its fury breaks forth with flash and thunder, for thee
					to observe upon whose head the mischief falls.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But to avoid the danger of this curiosity, divert thy
				thoughts to more safe and delightful enquiries; survey the
				wonders of nature in the heavens, earth, the sea, and air;
				in which thou hast a copious choice of materials for the
				more sublime, as well as the more easy and obvious contemplations. If thy more piercing wit aspires to the
				noblest enquiries, consider the greater luminary in its
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.431"/>
				
				diurnal motion, in what part of heaven its morning beams
				are kindled, and where those chambers of the night are
				placed which entertain its declining lustre. View the
				moon in all her changes, the just representation of human
				vicissitudes, and learn the causes that destroy and then
				restore her brightness:&mdash;
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>How from an infant-spark sprung out of night,
				</l>
                     <l>She swells into a perfect globe of light;
				</l>
                     <l>And soon her beauties thus repaired die,
				</l>
                     <l>Wasting into their first obscurity.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Sophocles, Frag. 786.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These are indeed the great secrets of Nature, whose
					depth may perhaps amaze and discourage thy enquiries.
					Search therefore into things more obvious,&mdash;why the fruits
					of plants are shaped into such variety of figures; why
					some are clothed with the verdure of a perennial spring,
					and others, which sometime were no less fresh and fair,
					like hasty spendthrifts, lavish away the bounty of Heaven
					in one summer's gayety, and stand naked to the succeeding frosts. But such harmless speculations will perchance
					affect thee little, and it may be thou hast that malignity in
					thy temper which, like venomous beasts that cannot live
					out of stink and putrefaction, must be ever preying upon
					the follies and miseries of mankind. Peruse therefore the
					histories of the world, wherein thou shalt find such vast
					heaps of wickedness and mischiefs, made up of the downfalls and sudden deaths of great men,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aeschylus, Suppliants, 937.</note> the rapes and
					defilements of women, the treacheries of servants, the
					falseness of friends, the arts of poisoning, the fatal effects
					of envy and jealousy, the ruin of families, dethroning of
					princes, with many other such direful occurrences as may
					not only delight and satisfy, but even cloy and nauseate
					thy ill-natured curiosity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But neither (as it appears) are such antiquated evils
				any agreeable entertainment to people of this perverse
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.432"/>
				
				disposition; they hearken most to modern tragedies, and
				such doleful accidents as may be grateful as well for the
				novelty as the horror of the relation. All pleasant and
				cheerful converse is irksome to them; so that if they happen into a company that are talking of weddings, the
				solemnities of sacred rites, or pompous processions, they
				make as though they heard not, or, to divert and shorten
				the discourse, will pretend they knew as much before.
				Yet, if any one should relate how such a wench had a
				child before the time, or that a fellow was caught with
				another man's wife, or that certain people were at law
				with each other, or that there was an unhappy difference
				between near relations, he no longer sits unconcerned or
				minds other things, but
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With ears pricked up, he listens. What, and when,
				</l>
                     <l>And how, he asks; pray say, let's hear't again!</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, that proverbial saying, <q direct="unspecified">Ill news goes quick
					and far,</q> was occasioned chiefly by these busy ill-natured
					men, who very unwillingly hear or talk of any ting else.
					For their ears, like cupping-glasses that attract the most
					noxious humors in the body, are ever sucking in the most
					spiteful and malicious reports; and, as in some cities there
					are certain ominous gates through which nothing passes
					but scavenger's carts or the sledges of malefactors, so
					nothing goes in at their ears or out of their mouths but
					obscene, tragical, and horrid relations.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Howling and woe, as in a jail or hell,
					</l>
                     <l>Always infest the places where they dwell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This noise is to them like the Sirens' song and the sweetest melody, the most pleasant hearing in the world.</p>
            <p>Now this curiosity, being an affectation of knowledge in
					things concealed, must needs proceed from a great degree
					of spite and envy. For men do not usually hide, but ambitiously proclaim whatever is for their honor or interest to
					be known; and therefore to pry into what is industriously
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.433"/>
					
					covered can be for no other purpose than that secret delight curious persons enjoy in the discovery of other men's
					ills,&mdash;which is spite,&mdash;and the relief they gather thence,
					to ease themselves under their tormenting resentment at
					another's prosperity,&mdash;which is envy;&mdash;both which spring
					from that savage and brutal disposition which we call
					ill-nature.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>But how ungrateful it is to mankind to have their
				evils enquired into appears from hence; that some have
				chosen rather to die than disclose a secret disease to their
				physician. Suppose then that Herophilus or Erasistratus,
				or Aesculapius himself when he was upon earth, should
				have gone about from house to house, enquiring whether
				any there had a fistula in ano or cancer in utero to be
				cured. Although such a curiosity as this might in them
				seem much more tolerable, from the charity of their design and the benefit intended by their art; yet who would
				not rebuke the saucy officiousness of that quack who should,
				unsent for, thus impudently pry into those privy distempers
				which the modesty or perhaps the guilt of the patient would
				blush or abhor to discover, though it were for the sake of
				a cure? But those that are of this curious and busy humor cannot forbear searching into these, and other ills too
				that are of a more secret nature; and&mdash;what makes the
				practice the more exceedingly odious and detestable&mdash;the
				intent is not to remedy, but expose them to the world. It
				is not ill taken, if the searchers and officers of the customs
				do inspect goods openly imported, but only when, with a
				design of being vexatious and troublesome, they rip up the
				unsuspected packets of private passengers; and yet even
				this they are by law authorized to do, and it is sometimes
				to their loss, if they do not. But curious and meddlesome
				people will be ever enquiring into other men's affairs, without leave or commission, though it be to the great neglect
				and damage of their own.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.434"/>
            <p>It is farther observable concerning this sort of men, how
					averse they are to living long in the country, as being not
					able to endure the quiet and calm of a retired solitude.
					But if by chance they take a short ramble to their country-house, the main of their business there is more to enquire
					into their neighbors' concerns than their own; that they
					may know how other men's fruit-trees are blasted, the
					number of cattle they have lost, and what a scanty harvest
					they are like to have, and how well their wine keeps; with
					which impertinent remarks having filled their giddy brains,
					the worm wags, and away they must to the town again.
					Now a true bred rustic, if he by chance meet with any
					news from the city, presently turns his head another way,
					and in his blunt language thus reflects upon the impertinence of it:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>One can't at quiet eat, nor plough one's lond;
					</l>
                     <l>Zo much us country-voke they bear in hond
					</l>
                     <l>With tales, which idle rascals blow about,
					</l>
                     <l>How kings (and well, vhat then ?) vall in and out.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But the busy cit hates the country, as a dull unfashionable thing, and void of mischief; and therefore keeps
				himself to the town, that he may be among the crowds that
				throng the courts, exchange, and wharfs, and pick up all
				the idle stories. Here he goes about pumping, What news
				d'ye hear? Were not you upon the exchange to-day, sir
				The city's in a very ticklish posture, what d'ye think on't?
				In two or three hours' time we may be altogether by the
				ears. If he's riding post, he will light off his horse, and even
				hug and kiss a fellow that has a story to tell him; and stay
				never so long, till he hears it out. But if any one upon
				demand shall answer, No news! he replies, as in a passion,
				What, have you been neither at the exchange or market
				to-day? Have you not been towards the court lately
				Have you not heard any thing from those gentlemen that
				newly came out of Italy? It was (methinks) a good piece
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.435"/>
				
				of policy among the Locrians, that if any person coning
				from abroad but once asked concerning news, he was presently confined for his curiosity; for as cooks and fishmongers wish for plenty in the commodities they trade
				with, so inquisitive people that deal much in news are
				ever longing for innovations, alterations, variety of action,
				or any thing that is mischievous and unlucky, that they
				may find store of game for their restless ill-nature to hunt
				and prey upon. Charondas also did well in prohibiting
				comedians by law from exposing any citizen upon the stage,
				unless it were for adultery or this malignant sort of curiosity. And indeed there is a near affinity between these
				two vices, for adultery is nothing else but the curiosity of
				discovering another man's secret pleasures, and the itch of
				knowing what is hidden; and curiosity is (as it were) a
				rape and violence committed upon other people's privacies.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>And now as the accumulation of notions in the head
				usually begets multiplicity of words,&mdash;for which reason
				Pythagoras thought fit to check the too early loquacity of
				his scholars, by imposing on them five years' silence from
				their first admission,&mdash;so the same curiosity that is thus
				inquisitive to know is no less intemperate in talking too,
				and must needs be as ill-spoken as it is ill-natured. And
				hence it is that curiosity does not only become a restraint
				to the vices and follies of others, but is a disappointment
				also to itself. For all mankind are exceeding shy of inquisitive persons: no serious business is consulted of where
				they are; and if they chance to surprise men in the negotiation of any affair, it is presently laid aside as carefully
				as the housewife locks up her fish from the cat; nor (if it
				be possible to avoid it) is any thing of moment said or done
				in their company. But whatever is freely permitted to any
				other people to see, hear, or talk of, is kept as a great
				secret from persons of this busy impertinent disposition;
				and there is no man but would commit his letters, papers,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.436"/>
				
				and writings to the care of a servant or a stranger, rather
				than to an acquaintance or relation of this busy and blabbing humor.</p>
            <p>By the great command which Bellerophon had over his
					curiosity, he resisted the solicitations of a lustful woman,
					and (though it were to the hazard of his life) abstained
					from opening the letters wherein he was designed to be the
					messenger of his own destruction. For curiosity and adultery (as was intimated before) are both vices of incontinence; only they are aggravated by a peculiar degree of
					madness and folly, beyond what is found in most other vices
					of this nature. And can there any thing be more sottish,
					than for a man to pass by the doors of so many common
					prostitutes that are ready to seize him in the streets, and to
					beleaguer the lodgings of some coy and recluse female that
					is far more costly, and perhaps far less comely too, than a
					hackney three-penny strumpet? But such is plainly the
					frensy of curious persons, who, despising all those
					things that are of easy access and unenvied enjoyment,&mdash;
					such as are the divertisements of the theatre, the conversation of the ingenious, and the discourses of the learned,&mdash;
					must be breaking open other men's letters, listening at their
					neighbors' doors, peeping in at their windows, or whispering with their servants; a practice which (as it deserves)
					is commonly dangerous, but ever extremely base and ignominious.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Now to dissuade inquisitive persons (as much as
				possible) from this sneaking and most despicable humor,
				it would contribute much, if they would but recollect and
				review all their past observations. For as Simonides,
				using at certain times to open two chests he kept by him,
				found that wherein he put rewards ever full, and the other
				appointed for thanks always empty; so, if inquisitive people did but now and then look into their bag of news,
				they would certainly be ashamed of that vain and foolish
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.437"/>
				
				curiosity which, with so much hazard and trouble to themselves, had been gathering together such a confused heap
				of worthless and loathsome trash. If a man, in reading
				over the writings of the ancients, should rake together all
				the dross he could meet with, and collect into one volume
				all the unfinished scraps of verse in Homer, the incongruous expressions in the tragedians, or those obscenities of
				smutty Archilochus for which he was scorned and pointed
				at, would not such a filthy scavenger of books well deserve
				that curse of the tragedian,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pox on your taste ! Must you, like lice and fleas,
				</l>
                     <l>Be always fed with scabs and nastiness?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But without this imprecation, the practice itself becomes
					its own punishment, in the dishonest and unprofitable
					drudgery of amassing together such a noisome heap of
					other men's vices and follies; a treasure much resembling
					the city Poneropolis (or <hi rend="italics">Rogue-town</hi>), so called by King
					Philip after he had peopled it with a crew of rogues and
					vagabonds. For curious people do so load their dirty brains
					with the ribaldry and solecisms of other men's writings,
					as well as the defects and blemishes of their lives, that
					there is not the least room left in their heads for one witty,
					graceful, or ingenious thought.</p>
            <p>There is a sort of people at Rome who, being unaffected
					with any thing that is beautiful and pretty, either in the
					works of art or nature, despise the most curious pieces in
					painting or sculpture, and the fairest boys and girls that
					are there exposed to sale, as not worth their money; therefore they much frequent the monster-market, looking after
					people of distorted limbs and preternatural shapes, of
					three eyes and pointed heads, and mongrels
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where kinds of unlike form oft blended be
					</l>
                     <l>Into one hideous deformity.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Theseus of Euripides, Frag. 383.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>All which are sights so loathsome, that they themselves
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.438"/>
					
					would abhor them were they compelled often to behold
					them. And if they who curiously enquire into those vicious
					deformities and unlucky accidents that may be observed
					in the lives of other men would only bind themselves to
					a frequent recollection of what they had seen and heard,
					there would be found very little delight or advantage in
					such ungrateful and melancholy reflections.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Now since it is from the use and custom of intermeddling in the affairs of other men that this perverse
				practice grows up into such a vicious habit, therefore the
				best remedy thereof is, that beginning (as it were) at a
				distance, and with such things as do less excite the itch
				of our curiosity, we gradually bring ourselves to an utter
				desuetude of enquiring into or being concerned at any of
				those things that do not pertain unto us. Therefore let
				men first make trial of themselves in smaller and less considerable matters. As for the purpose, why should it be
				thought such a severe piece of self-denial for any man, as
				he passes by, to forbear reading the inscriptions that are
				upon a monument or gravestone, or the letters that are
				drawn on walls and sign-posts, if it were but considered
				that there is nothing more, either for delight or benefit, to
				be learned thereby, but that certain people had a desire
				to preserve the memory of their friends and relations by
				engraving their names on brass or marble, or that some
				impudent quack or rooking tradesman wants money, and
				knows no other way to draw men to their shop or lodgings, but by decoying billets and the invitation of a show-board? The taking notice of which and such like things
				may seem for the present harmless; yet there is really a
				secret mischief wrought by it, while men, suffering their
				minds to rove so inconsiderately at every thing they see,
				are inured to a foolish curiosity in busying themselves
				about things impertinent. For as skilful huntsmen do not
				permit their beagles to fling or change, but lead them forth
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.439"/>
				
				in couples, that their noses may be kept sharp for their
				proper game,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>With scent most quick of nostrils after kind,
				</l>
                     <l>The tracks of beast so wild in chase to find;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so ought persons of an inquisitive temper to restrain the
					wanton excursions of their curiosity, and confine it to observations of prudence and sobriety. Thus the lion and
					eagle, which walk with their claws sheathed to keep them
					always pointed for their prey, are an example of that discretion which curious persons should imitate, by carefully
					preserving those noble faculties of wit and understanding,
					which were made for useful and excellent enquiries, from
					being dulled and debauched with low and sottish speculations.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>The second remedy of this curiosity is that we accustom ourselves in passing by not to peep in at other
				men's doors or windows, for in this case the hand and eye
				are much alike guilty; and Xenocrates said, <q direct="unspecified">One may
					as well go as look into another man's house,</q> because the
				eye may reach what the hand cannot, and wander where
				the foot does not come. And besides, it is neither genteel
				nor civil thus to gaze about. A well-bred person will commonly discover very little that is either meet or delightful
				to look on; but foul dishes perhaps lying about the floor,
				or wenches in lazy or immodest postures, and nothing that
				is decent or in good order; but as one said upon this occasion,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ought that's here worth seeing, friend, you may
				</l>
                     <l>Ev'n turn your prying look another way.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet laying aside this consideration of uncomely sights,
					this very staring and glancing of the eyes to and fro implies such a levity of mind and so great a defect in good
					manners, as must needs render the practice in itself very
					clownish and contemptible. When Diogenes observed Dioxippus, a victor in the Olympic games, twisting his neck
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.440"/>
					
					as he sat in his chariot, that he might take the better view
					of a fair damsel that came to see the sport, Look (says
					he) what a worthy gamester goes there, that even a woman
					can turn him which way she lists. But these busy-brained
					people do so twist and turn themselves to every frivolous
					show, as if they had acquired a verticity in their heads
					by their custom of gazing at all things round about them.
					Now (methinks) it is by no means seemly, that the sense
					which ought to behave itself as a handmaid to the soul
					(in doing its errands faithfully, returning speedily, and
					keeping at home with submissive and reserved modesty)
					should be suffered, like a wanton and ungovernable servant, to be gadding abroad from her mistress, and straying
					about at her pleasure. But this happens according to that
					of Sophocles,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And then the Aenianian's colts disdain
					</l>
                     <l>Bridle and bit, nor will abide the rein.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Electra, 724.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For so the senses, not exercised and well managed, will
					at every turn break loose into wild excursions, and hurry
					reason along with them into the same extravagance.</p>
            <p>It is said of Democritus, that he voluntarily put out his
					eyes by the reflection of a burning-glass, that (as by the
					darkening of windows, sometimes done for the same purpose) he might not by the allurements of sense be called
					off from attending to his purely intellectual contemplations. Although the story be false, yet this at least is
					true, that those men who are most addicted to profound
					speculations do least of all converse with impressions of
					sense. And therefore, to prevent that interruption and disturbance which either noise or impertinent visits might
					be to their philosophical enquiries, they placed their
					studies at some distance from cities, and called the night
					<hi rend="italics">Euphrone</hi> (from <foreign lang="greek">eu)/frwn</foreign>, of <hi rend="italics">good understanding</hi>), thinking
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.441"/>
					
					that its quiet and stillness from all disturbances made it
					the fittest season for meditation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Farther, to forbear mixing with a crowd of fellows
				that are quarrelling in the market-place, or to sit still
				while the mad rabble are rioting in the streets, or at least
				to get out of hearing of it, will not be very difficult to any
				man that considers how little there is to be gained by intermeddling with busy and unquiet people, and how great
				the certain advantage is of bridling our curiosity, and
				bringing it under subjection to the commands of reason.
				And thus, when by this more easy discipline a man hath
				acquired some power over himself, exercises of greater
				difficulty are to be attempted; as, for instance, to forbear
				the theatre upon the tempting fame of some new and
				much applauded play; to resist the importunity of a friend
				that invites thee to a ball, an entertainment at the tavern,
				or a concert of music; and not to be transported if thou
				chance at a distance to hear the din at a race-course,
				or the noise at the circus. For as Socrates advises
				well, that men should abstain from tasting those meats
				and drinks which, by their exquisite pleasantness, tempt
				the palate to exceed the sober measures of thirst and
				hunger, so are all those oblectations of the ear and eye
				to be avoided which are apt to entice men into impertinence or extravagance. When Araspes had commended
				the fair Panthea to Cyrus, as a beauty worth his admiration, he replied: For that very reason I will not see her,
				lest, if by thy persuasion I should see her but once, she
				herself might persuade me to see her often, and spend
				more time with her than would be for the advantage of
				my own affairs. So Alexander, upon like consideration,
				would not trust his eyes in the presence of the beautiful
				queen of Persia, but kept himself out of the reach of her
				charms, and treated only with her aged mother. But
				we, alas! (that no opportunity may be lost of doing ourselves
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.442"/>
				
				 all the mischief we can by our curiosity) cannot
				forbear prying into sedans and coaches, or gazing at the
				windows or peeping under the balconies, where women
				are; nay, we must be staring about from the house-top, to
				spy out all occasions of our ruin, and are all the while so
				sottishly inconsiderate as to apprehend no danger from
				giving such a boundless license to our wandering eyes.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Now as, in point of justice and honesty, it conduces much to prevent our defrauding and overreaching other men if we now and then in smaller matters
				voluntarily abate somewhat of our strict dues, and as it
				is a means to keep men chaste and continent to all other
				women if they sometimes forbear the lawful enjoyment
				of their own wives, so will these excesses of curiosity be
				cured by the same restraints, if, instead of enquiring into
				what concerns other men, we can prevail with ourselves
				so far as not to hear or see all that is done in our own
				houses, nor to listen to every thing that may be told us
				concerning ourselves or our private affairs. Oedipus by
				his curiosity fell into great mischief; for, being of a parentage to himself unknown and now at Corinth where he
				was a stranger, he went about asking questions concerning himself, and lighting on Laius he slew him; and then
				by the marriage of the queen, who was his own mother,
				he obtained the government. Not contented with the
				thoughts of being thus happy, he must needs once more
				(against all the persuasions of his wife) be enquiring concerning himself; when, meeting with an old man that
				was privy to the whole contrivance, he pressed him earnestly to reveal the secret. And when he now began to
				suspect the worst, the old man cried out,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Alas! So sad a tale to tell I dread;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>but he, burning with impatience of knowing all, replied,
					<quote rend="blockquote">And I to hear 't: but yet it must be said.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Oed. Tyr. 1169 and 1170.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.443"/>
            <p>Thus oddly mixed with pain and pleasure is this restless
					itch of curiosity, that, like a healing wound, will hazard
					the loss of blood rather than want the seeming ease of
					being rubbed and scratched. But such as either by good
					nature or good discipline are free from this disease, and
					have experienced the invaluable felicity of a calm and
					undisturbed spirit, will rather rejoice in being ignorant
					than desire to be informed of the wickedness and the miseries that are in the world, and will sit down well satisfied
					in this opinion,
					<quote rend="blockquote">How sage and wise art thou, oblivion!<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orestes, 213.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Wherefore, as a farther help to check the impatience
				of our curiosity, it will contribute much to practise such
				acts of abstinence as these. If a letter be brought thee,
				lay it aside for some time before thou read it; and do not
				(as many do) eagerly fall upon the seal with tooth and nail,
				as soon as ever it comes to thy hands, as if it were scarce
				possible to open it with sufficient speed; when a messenger returns, do not hastily rise up and run towards him,
				as if thou couldst not hear what he had to say time enough;
				and if any one makes an offer to tell thee something that
				is new, say that thou hadst rather it were good and useful.</p>
            <p>When, at a public dissertation I sometime made at Rome,
					Rusticus (who afterwards perished by the mere envy of
					Domitian) was one of my auditors, a messenger comes suddenly in with an express from Caesar; upon which, when
					I offered to be silent till he had perused the paper, he desired me to proceed, nor would so much as look into it till
					the discourse was ended and the audience dismissed; all
					that were present much admiring the gravity of the man
					In great persons, whose power encourages them to greater
					licentiousness, this vicious curiosity is hardly curable; for
					when it is arrived in them to the consistence of an invetcrate
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.444"/>
					
					 habit, they will never undergo those previous restraints
					upon their outward actions which are necessary to destroy
					the evil habit within them. For such as are thus inured
					will be breaking up other men's letters, intruding upon the
					privacies of their friends, making bold enquiries into the
					unfathomable mysteries of religion, profaning sacred places
					and holy offices by their coming where and doing what
					they ought not, and even prying into the most secret acts
					and discourses of princes; all or any of which odious practices it will be hard for any one after long custom to forbear, but especially for great persons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>And indeed princes themselves&mdash;who are concerned to have as particular knowledge of all things as
				they can, and to whom it is in some sort necessary for the
				ends of government to maintain spies and intelligencers
				about them&mdash;are yet usually hated for nothing more than
				their retaining this lewd sort of people in quality of eavesdroppers of state and public informers. The first that employed this kind of officers was Darius in his younger years,
				when he could not confide in himself nor durst trust any one
				else. The Sicilian tyrants afterwards planted them in Syracuse; but upon a revolution that happened there, the people first fell upon these informers, and destroyed them without
				mercy. Of near affinity with these are common accusers,
				which, from a particular occasion imported in the word, were
				called sycophants, fig-blabbers; because, upon the prohibited exportation of that fruit, they became informers against
				those that broke this order. Much the like sort of people
				were those at Athens, where a dearth of grain happened
				and the corn-sellers were commanded to bring out their
				stores for public sale; and those that went about listening
				at the mills and prying into granaries, that they might
				find matter of information against offenders, were thence
				called aliterians or (if you please) mill-clackers. Which
				consideration, superadded to the rest that has been said, is
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.445"/>
				
				enough to render this sort of malignant curiosity extremely
				execrable, and to be highly abhorred and most carefully
				avoided by every man who would desire, for mere reputation's sake, not to be ranked among that profligate crew of
				villains which are looked upon as the most detestable of
				all mankind.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>