<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vitae decem oratorum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold North Fowler</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.10.p.342"/>
            <head>LIVES OF THE TEN ORATORS (VITAE DECEM ORATORUM) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					At some time in the second century before Christ
					ten Attic orators were selected, probably by Apollodorus of Pergamum, as the orators whose speeches
					were most worthy of preservation and study, and
					this <q direct="unspecified">Canon</q> of the Ten Attic Orators was generally
					accepted. The <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi> of these orators which are
					contained in manuscripts of Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi> were
					certainly not written by Plutarch. They are altogether lacking in the charm which characterizes
					Plutarch's careful and elaborate style. Facts are
					stated one after another with little variety and with
					little or no distinction between mere anecdotes and
					matters of real importance ; but the <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi> are of
					interest on account of their subject matter.
				</p>
            <p>
					The <q direct="unspecified">decrees</q> appended to the <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi> are, except
					in some details, fairly accurate copies of official
					documents (see F. Ladek, <hi rend="italics">Wiener Studien</hi>, xiii., 1891,
					pp. Ill ff.). The two which are concerned with
					Demosthenes and his family are not really decrees,
					but petitions addressed to the Senate, copies of
					which were undoubtedly kept among the official
					records at Athens, whereas the third - that in honour
					of Lycurgus - is a decree of the people. A large part
					of the inscription recording this decree has been
					found and is published in the <hi rend="italics">Inscriptiones Graecae</hi>, ii.
					No. 240 (editio minor, ii. No. 457), Dittenberger,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.343"/>
					
					          <hi rend="italics">Sylloge Inscriptionum Graecarum</hi>, third edition, No. 326.
					The text which has been handed down in the manuscripts of Plutarch varies somewhat from that of the
					inscription, but hardly more than is to be expected.
					It may well be that whoever appended the <q direct="unspecified">decrees</q>
					to the <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi> of the orators derived them, not directly
					from inscriptions or other official documents, but (as
					suggested by B. Keil in <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xxx. pp. 210 ff.) from
					the work of Heliodorus <hi rend="italics">On Monuments</hi>.
				</p>
            <p>
					The <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi>, with the <q direct="unspecified">decrees,</q> are published by
					Anton Westermann in his <hi rend="italics">Biographi Graeci</hi> (1833 and
					1845).
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.345"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>I. ANTIPHON</head>
            <p>
					Antiphon was the son of Sophilus, and his deme
					was Rhamnus. He was a pupil of his father (for his
					father was a sophist, and it is said that Alcibiades
					as a boy attended his school), and having acquired
					power in speaking - as some think, through his own
					natural ability - he entered upon a public career.
					And he set up a school and had his disagreement with
					Socrates on the subject of words, not in a contentious
					spirit, but for the sake of argument, as Xenophon
					has narrated in his <hi rend="italics">Memoirs</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Memorabilia</hi>, i. 6.</note> And he wrote some
					speeches for citizens who wanted them for their
					suits in the law-courts, being the first who practised
					this profession, as some say. At any rate no legal
					oration is extant of any of those who lived before
					his time, nor of his contemporaries either, because
					the custom of speech-writing had not yet arisen ;
					there is none by Themistocles, Aristeides, or Pericles,
					although the times afforded them many opportunities
					and also occasions when such speeches were needed.
					And it was not for lack of ability that they refrained
					from such speech-writing, as is evident from what
					is said by the historians about each of the abovementioned orators. Yet all those whom we are able
					to record as having practised this kind of speeches,
					going back to the earliest occurrence, will be found
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.347"/>
					
					
					to have followed Antiphon when he was already old;
					I mean such as Alcibiades, Critias, Lysias, and
					Archinus. He was also the first to publish rules of
					the art of oratory, being of sharp intellect, and for
					this reason he was nicknamed Nestor.
				</p>
            <p>
					And Caecilius, in the treatise he compiled about
					him, conjectures from the terms in which Antiphon
					is praised in the work of the historian Thucydides
					that he was the latter's teacher.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, viii. 68 <foreign lang="greek">a)nh\r *)aqhnai/wn tw=n kaq' e(auto\n a)reth=| te ou)deno\s deu/teros kai\ kra/tistos e)nqumhqh=nai geno/menos kai\ a(\ gnoi/h ei)pei=n</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">a man inferior to none of the Athenians of his own day in force of character, and one who had proved himself most able both to formulate a plan and to set forth his conclusions in speech</q> (Smith's translation, L.C.L.).</note> In his speeches
					he is accurate and persuasive, clever in invention,
					ingenious in handling perplexing cases; he attacks
					unexpectedly, and he addresses his arguments to
					both the laws and the emotions, aiming especially at
					propriety. He was born at the time of the Persian
					wars and of the sophist Gorgias, who was somewhat
					older than he ; and his life extended until the destruction of the democracy by the Four Hundred,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 411 b.c. when for some four months an oligarchy ruled Athens.</note>
					in causing which he seems himself to have had a
					part, at one time by being trierarch<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The duty of fitting out ships for the navy devolved upon wealthy citizens, who were then called trierarchs.</note> of two ships, at
					another by being general<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Antiphon was a common name at Athens in the fifth century. Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed. i. pp. 93 ff., distinguishes, in addition to the orator: (1) a patriotic and worthy citizen (Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hell.</hi> ii. 3. 40) in defence of whose daughter Lysias wrote a speech, and to whom the military activities belong which are here ascribed to the orator; (2) the tragic poet who was put to death by Dionysius of Syracuse (Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi> ii. 6. p. 1385 a 9); (3) Antiphon the sophist (Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Mem.</hi> i. 6. 5; Diog. Laert. ii. 5. 25), who is probably the one who practised mental healing at Corinth; (4) the son of Pyrilampus (Plato, <hi rend="italics">Parmenides</hi>, 127 a); (5) the son of Lysonides (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 833 a); and (6) an Antiphon derided by Aristophanes (<hi rend="italics">Wasps</hi>, 1270), as a starveling. The Pseudo-Plutarch has evidently fused several of these personalities with that of the orator.</note> and gaining many victories
					in battle and winning important alliances for the
					Four Hundred, by arming the men of military age,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.349"/>
					
					
					by manning sixty triremes, and by being on every
					occasion their envoy to Lacedaemon at the time
					when E&euml;tioneia had been fortified.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">E&euml;tioneia, the mole which formed the northern side of the great Harbour of Peiraeus, was fortified by the Four Hundred in order to command the entrance.</note> And after the
					overthrow of the Four Hundred he was indicted along
					with Archeptolemus, one of the Four Hundred, was
					found guilty, subjected to the punishments prescribed for traitors, thrown out unburied, and inscribed along with his descendants in the list of the
					disfranchised. But some tell us that he was put to
					death by the Thirty,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 404 b.c., when Athens was occupied by the Lacedaemonians, a body of Thirty men was appointed to revise the constitution. They seized all power and ruled ruthlessly until overthrown in May 403 b.c.</note> as Lysias says in his speech
					in defence of Antiphon's daughter ; for he had a
					daughter whom Callaeschrus claimed in marriage by
					legal process. And that he was put to death by the
					Thirty is told also by Theopompus in the fifteenth
					book of his <hi rend="italics">Philippics</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> i. p. 300.</note>; but that must have been
					another Antiphon, the son of Lysidonides, whom
					Cratinus also, in his play <hi rend="italics">The Flask</hi>, mentions as a
					rascal; for how could a man who had died previously
					and had been put to death by the Four Hundred be
					living again in the time of the Thirty ? But there is
					also another story of his death : that he sailed as
					envoy to Syracuse when the tyranny of Dionysius
					the First was at its height, and at a convivial gathering the question arose what bronze was the best ;
					then when most of the guests disagreed, he said
					that bronze was the best from which the statues of
					Harmodius and Aristogeiton were made ; and when
					Dionysius heard this, suspecting that the remark
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.351"/>
					
					
					was intended to encourage an attack upon himself,
					he ordered that Antiphon be put to death. But
					others say that he was angry because Antiphon made
					fun of his tragedies.
				</p>
            <p>
					There are current sixty orations ascribed to this
					orator, twenty-five of which Caecilius says are
					spurious. He is ridiculed as a lover of money by
					Plato in his <hi rend="italics">Peisander</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. p. 629, no. 103.</note> And he is said to have
					written tragedies both by himself and in collaboration
					with the tyrant Dionysius. But while he was still
					busy with poetry he invented a method of curing
					distress, just as physicians have a treatment for those
					who are ill; and at Corinth, fitting up a room near
					the market-place, he wrote on the door that he
					could cure by words those who were in distress ; and
					by asking questions and finding out the causes of
					their condition he consoled those in trouble. But
					thinking this art was unworthy of him he turned to
					oratory. There are some who ascribe also to Antiphon the book <hi rend="italics">On Poets</hi> by Glaucus of Rhegium.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 23.</note>
					His most admired orations are the one concerning
					Herodes, that against Erasistratus about the peacocks, that on the Indictment, which he wrote in his
					own defence, and that against the general Demosthenes for moving an illegal measure. He wrote
					also a speech against the general Hippocrates and
					caused him to be convicted by default.
				</p>
            <p>
					Caecilius has appended a decree passed in the
					archonship of Theopompus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">411-410 b.c. Caecilius derived his text of the decree from Craterus's collection of decrees. See Harpocration, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi> 
                  <foreign lang="greek">*)/andrwn</foreign> and Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., i. p. 99.</note> the year in which the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.353"/>
					
					
					Four Hundred were overthrown, according to which
					the senate voted the trial of Antiphon :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Voted by the senate on the twenty-first day of the
					prytany. Demonicus of Alopec&ecirc; was secretary, Philostratus
					of Pallen&ecirc; was president. Andron moved in regard to
					the men whom the generals denounce for acting to the
					detriment of the State of the Athenians while serving as
					envoys to Lacedaemon and for sailing from the camp
					in a ship of the enemy and for having passed by land
					through Deceleia, namely Archeptolemus, Onomacles, and
					Antiphon, that they be arrested and brought before the
					court for trial. And the generals, with those members of
					the senate whom they shall co-opt to the number of ten, are
					directed to produce them in court, that they may be present
					at the trial. And the Thesmothetae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Six of the annually elected archons; their duties were to administer the courts of justice.</note> shall summon them
					to-morrow, and when the summonses have been returned
					to the court, they shall propose that the chosen prosecutors
					and the generals and others, if anyone so desire, shall accuse
					them of treason; and whomsoever the court may convict, he
					shall be treated in accordance with the law which has been
					passed relating to traitors.</quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Under this enactment the judgement is written :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Archeptolemus, son of Hippodamus, of Agryle, and
					Antiphon, son of Sophilus, of Rhamnus, both being present,
					were found guilty of treason. The sentence passed upon
					them was that they be handed over to the Eleven for execution,
					that their belongings be confiscated and ten per cent thereof
					be given to the Goddess, that their houses be torn down and
					boundary-stones be set up on their sites with the inscription
					&amp;ldquo;Land of Archeptolemus and Antiphon the two traitors&amp;rdquo;;
					and that the two demarchs make a declaration of their
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.355"/>
					
					
					property; and that it be forbidden to bury Archeptolemus
					and Antiphon at Athens or in any place ruled by the
					Athenians; and that Archeptolemus and Antiphon be
					attainted, and also their descendants legitimate and illegitimate ; and that if anyone shall adopt any descendant of
					Archeptolemus or Antiphon, he who so adopts shall be
					attainted ; and that this be inscribed on a bronze tablet,
					which shall be set up where the decrees relating to Phrynichus
					are placed.</quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>II. ANDOCIDES</head>
            <p>
					Andocides was the son of Leogoras, son of that
					Andocides who once made peace between the
					Lacedaemonians and the Athenians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Thirty Years' Peace, by the terms of which Athens gave up Megara and its ports in 446-445 b.c.</note>; he was as
					regards his deme a Cydathenian or a Thorian<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note <hi rend="italics">d</hi> below for the source of this error.</note> and
					was descended from nobles, and even, according to
					Hellanicus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> i. p. 55, no. 78.</note> from Hermes ; for the race of heralds
					traces its origin to him. On this account, too, he
					was once chosen along with Glaucon to go with
					twenty ships to aid the Corcyraeans who were embroiled with the Corinthians.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, i. 51, who seems to have been the source of this error. The colleague of Glaucon on this expedition was Dracontides, son of Leogoras of Thurae, and not Andocides, who at the time, 433 b.c., was too young. See <hi rend="italics">I. G.</hi> i. 295 (ed. min.), and Kirchner, <hi rend="italics">Prosopographia Attica</hi>, 828 and 4551.</note> And after this he
					was accused of impiety as being one of those who
					mutilated the Hermae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Hermae, square pillars surmounted by the head of the god Hermes, stood before the doors of Athenian houses. In 415 b.c., just as the great expedition against Sicily was about to sail, these Hermae were systematically mutilated in the night by unknown persons.</note> and as profaning the mysteries of Demeter [because at an earlier time he was
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.357"/>
					
					
					dissipated and in a nocturnal revel had broken one
					of the images of the god, and when he was indicted
					refused to surrender the slave whom his accusers
					were looking for, so that he gained a bad name and
					was suspected and accused in the second suit also,
					which was brought shortly after the expedition went
					to Sicily, when the Corinthians sent in men from
					Leontini and Egesta and, as the Athenians hesitated
					about aiding them privately, they mutilated the
					Hermae about the market-place, as Cratippus says,
					and profaned the mysteries besides]. At his trial
					on these charges he was acquitted on condition that
					he should inform against the wrongdoers. He
					exerted himself greatly and discovered those who
					were guilty of the sacrilege, among whom he informed against his own father. And he brought
					about the conviction and death of all the others, but
					saved his father, although he had already been put
					in prison, by promising that he would be of great
					service to the city. And he kept his promise ; for
					Leogoras caused the conviction of many men who
					were embezzling public funds and committing other
					misdeeds. And for these reasons he was acquitted
					of the charge.
				</p>
            <p>
					But Andocides, since his reputation in public life
					was not good, took to merchandising and became a
					friend of the Cypriote kings and many other men of
					note, at which time he abducted a girl of Athenian
					birth, daughter of Aristeides and his own niece,
					without the knowledge of her family, and sent her as
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.359"/>
					
					
					a gift to the King of Cyprus. Then, when he was to be
					brought to trial for this, he stole her back again from
					Cyprus and was caught and put in prison by the king ;
					but he ran away and came back to Athens at the
					time when the Four Hundred were in control of
					affairs. He was put in prison by them, but escaped,
					and again, when the oligarchy was overthrown, he
					. . . was banished from the city after the Thirty had
					taken over the government. He spent the period
					of his exile in Elis, but when Thrasybulus and his
					band returned,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the summer of 404 b.c. thirty men had been appointed to draw up laws and manage the state temporarily. Thrasybulus seized the hill-fortress of Phyl&ecirc; in December and maintained his position against two attacks by the Thirty. In May 403 Thrasybulus and his followers seized Peiraeus. In September the Thirty were overthrown and the democracy re-established.</note> he also returned to the city. He
					was sent to Lacedaemon to negotiate a peace, but
					was suspected of wrongdoing<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The nature of the accusation cannot be determined. See Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., pp. 293 ff. The oration <hi rend="italics">On the Peace</hi>, delivered between 393 and 390 b.c., deals with the terms proposed by the mission in which Andocides participated.</note> and banished. He
					gives information about all this in the speeches
					which he wrote ; for some of them he composed in
					his defence in the matter of the mysteries, and others
					when he was asking to be allowed to return home.
					There is also extant his speech <hi rend="italics">On the Indictment</hi>,
					also the Defence against Phaeax and the speech <hi rend="italics">On
					the Peace</hi>. He flourished at the same time as
					Socrates the philosopher ; the date of his birth was
					the seventy-eighth Olympiad, when Theogenides
					was archon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">468-467 b.c. This date, however, is based upon a false reckoning, and from the orator's own statements he could not have been born much before 440. See Blass, <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> i. p. 283, and Kirchner, <hi rend="italics">Prosop. Att.</hi> 828.</note> at Athens, so that he was about ten
					years older<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The numeral is an emendation.</note> than Lysias. The Hermes called the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.361"/>
					
					
					Hermes of Andocides is named after him. It is a
					dedication of the tribe Aegeis and is called Hermes
					of Andocides because Andocides lived near it. He
					himself supplied the chorus for his tribe<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A decree of the tribe Pandionis in which the orator is named among the victorious choregi is extant, <hi rend="italics">I. G.</hi> ii. 1138 (ed. min.); it was with a chorus of boys at the Dionysia.</note> when it was
					competing in a dithyrambic contest, and he gained
					the victory, for which he set up a tripod on a high
					spot opposite the limestone Silenus. He is simple
					and free from artifice in his orations, plain and employing no figures of speech.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>III. LYSIAS</head>
            <p>
					Lysias was the son of Cephalus, grandson of
					Lysanias, and great-grandson of Cephalus. His
					father was by birth a Syracusan but moved to Athens
					because he wished to live in that city and also because
					Pericles, son of Xanthippus, persuaded him to do so,
					as he was a personal friend of Pericles and they were
					connected by ties of hospitality, and he was a man of
					great wealth. But some say that he moved because
					he was banished from Syracuse when Gelo was
					tyrant. Lysias was born at Athens in the archonship
					of the Philocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">459-458 b.c.</note> who succeeded Phrasicles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The archon in 460-459 b.c. was Phrasicleides, not Phrasicles.</note> in the
					second year of the eightieth Olympiad, and at first he
					was a schoolmate of the most prominent Athenians ;
					but when the city sent the colony to Sybaris, which
					was afterwards renamed Thurii, he went out with his
					eldest brother Polemarchus (for he had two others,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.363"/>
					
					
					Euthydemus and Brachyllus), their father being
					already dead, to share in the allotment of land.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The scene of Plato's <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi> is laid at the house of Cephalus. The dialogue is not historical, and its imagined date cannot be fixed, but it seems to show that Plato knew Cephalus and his sons, see Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., i. p. 341.</note> This
					was in the archonship of Praxiteles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">444-443 b.c.</note> and he was then
					fifteen years old. He remained there, was instructed
					by the Syracusans Teisias and Nicias, acquired a
					house, had a share of the allotment, and was a citizen
					for thirty-three years, until Cleocritus was archon
					at Athens.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">413-412 b.c. The ninety-second Olympiad is the date of the archonship of another Callias, 406-405 b.c.</note> But in the next year, when Callias was
					archon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The dates given by our author for events in the life of Lysias are consistent (see also 835 a above, and 836 f below, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Dion. Hal. <hi rend="italics">Isocrates</hi>, i.), on the assumption that he went to Thurii when the colony was founded, in 444 b.c. But if that is correct, his activity as a writer of speeches to be delivered in the Athenian courts would not begin until his fifty-seventh year. Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., i. p. 345, after stating the evidence, comes to the conclusion that Lysias was born at Athens probably about 446 b.c., the only certain date being his age (fifteen years), when he went to Thurii, and his treutn to Athens in 413-412 b.c. or the year following. It is quite possible that he did not go to Thurii until some years after the foundation of the colony. The latest of his extant speeches may be dated about 380 b.c., so that we may believe that he died not long after that date.</note> in the ninety-second Olympiad, when the
					misfortunes in Sicily<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The great expedition which the Athenians had sent out in 415 b.c. expecting to conquer Sicily was utterly annihilated in the autumn of 413 b.c.</note> had happened to the Athenians
					and unrest had arisen among the allies in general and
					especially those who dwelt in Italy, he was accused of
					favouring Athens and, with three hundred others, was
					banished. Arriving at Athens in the archonship of
					the Callias<note resp="ed" place="unspeciifed" anchored="yes">412-411 b.c.</note> who succeeded Cleocritus, when the Four
					Hundred already had possession of the city,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Summer of 411 b.c.</note> he remained
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.365"/>
					
					
					there. But when the battle of Aegospotami<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">405 b.c. The Athenian fleet was destroyed by the Lacedaemonians, which virtually ended the Peloponnesian War.</note>
					had taken place and the Thirty had taken possession
					of the city,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">404 b.c.</note> he was banished after having been there
					seven years. He was deprived of his property and
					lost his brother Polemarchus, but he himself escaped
					from the house in which he was kept to be executed
					(for it had two doors)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Lysias, xii. (<hi rend="italics">Against Eratosthenes</hi>) 15.</note> and lived at Megara. But
					when the men at Phyle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Thrasybulus and his followers, May 303 b.c. After these exiles seized Periaeus, there was a period of confusion until the democracy was re-established and Eucleides made archon for the year 403-402 b.c.</note> set about their return to
					Athens, he was seen to be more helpful than anyone
					else, since he supplied two thousand drachmas and
					two hundred shields and, when sent with Hermas,
					hired three hundred mercenaries and persuaded
					Thrasydaeus of Elis, who had become his guest-friend,
					to give two talents. For these services Thrasybulus,
					after the restoration of the exiles to the city and
					in the period of anarchy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Athenians termed any period an <q direct="unspecified">anarchy</q> in which no archon could be elected because of party strife.</note> before Eucleides, proposed a grant of citizenship for him, and the popular assembly ratified the grant, but when Archinus
					had him up for illegality because it had not been
					previously voted by the senate,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Senate or Council of Five Hundred prepared the business for the Popular Assembly, which could not legally vote upon any measure not previously adopted by the Senate.</note> the enactment was
					declared void. And after losing his citizenship in
					this way, he lived the rest of his life at Athens with all
					the rights of citizenship except the vote and eligibility to office, and died there at the age of eightythree years or, as some say, seventy-six or, as others
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.367"/>
					
					
					say, over eighty ; and he lived to see Demosthenes
					as a youth. They say he was born in the archonship
					of Philocles.
				</p>
            <p>
					Four hundred and twenty-five orations attributed
					to him are current. Of these Dionysius and Caecilius
					and their school say that two hundred and thirtythree are genuine, and he is said to have lost his case
					with only two of them. There is also his speech in
					support of the enactment against which Archinus
					brought suit and deprived him of citizenship, and
					another against the Thirty. He was very persuasive
					and concise and produced most of his speeches for
					private clients. There are also Textbooks of Rhetoric
					prepared by him, and Public Addresses, Letters and
					Eulogies, Funeral Speeches, Love Speeches, and a
					Defence of Socrates addressed to the judges.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Oratore</hi>, i. 231, and Diogenes Laertius, ii. 20, 40, say that Lysias composed an oration in defence of Socrates, and offered it to him, but Socrates refused it. A speech in defence of Socrates (<foreign lang="greek">u(pe\r *swkra/tous pro\s *polukra/thn</foreign>) is mentioned several times by the scholiast on Aristeides. It was composed probably some years after the death of Socrates, as an epideictic oration in reply to a similar speech against Socrates by the sophist Polycrates. This is doubtless the speech which Cicero and Diogenes wrongly believed to have been composed for use in the actual trial of Socrates. See Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., i. p. 351.</note> In
					the matter of his diction he appears to be easy,
					although in fact he is hard to imitate.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Dionysius of Halicarnassus, <foreign lang="greek">*)arxai/wn kri/sis</foreign>, v. 1 <foreign lang="greek">a)nagignwsko/menon me\n eu)/kolon nomi/zesqai xalepo\n de\ eu(ri/skesqai zhlou=n peirwme/nois</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">when read he is considered easy, but is found to be difficult by any who try to imitate him.</q>
               </note> Demosthenes
					in his speech against Neaera<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, Or. lix. 21.</note> says that he was
					in love with Metaneira, a fellow-slave with Neaera;
					but later he married the daughter of his brother
					Brachyllus. Plato also mentions him in the <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 279 a.</note>
					as an able speaker and older than Isocrates. Moreover Philiscus, a pupil of Isocrates and comrade of
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.369"/>
					
					
					Lysias, composed an elegiac poem to him, from
					which it is plain that he was earlier in years, which
					is indicated also by what Plato said. The verses
					are as follows :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Now, O Calliope's daughter endowed with great eloquence,
					Phrontis,
					</l>
                  <l>Show if thy wisdom is aught, if thou hast anything new.
					</l>
                  <l>Him who is altered and changed to another form, him who
					in other
					</l>
                  <l>Orders and manners of life hath a new body assumed,
					</l>
                  <l>Thou must bring forth some herald of virtue to celebrate:
					Lysis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lysis, because the word Lysias is inadmissible in the Greek metre. Wyttenbach suggests that the verses were really written in honour of Lysis the Pythagorean.</note>
					             </l>
                  <l>Gone to the dead and the gloom, there an immortal to
					dwell;
					</l>
                  <l>One who will show unto all the love of my soul for my
					comrade,
					</l>
                  <l>Show, too, the worth of the dead unto the whole of
					mankind.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr Graec.</hi> ii. p. 640. Bergk rightly says that this is only part of a longer poem. The fragment does not indicate that Lysias was older than Isocrates, but some such statement may have been contained in a later part of the poem.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					He also wrote two speeches for Iphicrates, one against
					Harmodius, the other for use in accusing Timothe&uuml;s
					of treason, with both of which he won his case ; but
					when Iphicrates accepted the responsibility for the
					actions of Timothe&uuml;s,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 355 b.c. Iphicrates and Timothe&uuml;s, Athenian generals who had been unsuccessful, were accused by their colleague, Chares, of treason. Although Iphicrates accepted full responsibility, he was acquitted, but Timothe&uuml;s was fined one hundred talents, which he could not pay. He left Athens and soon died.</note> assuming at the rendering of
					accounts the accusation for treason, he defended himself with the speech by Lysias ; and he himself was
					acquitted, but Timothe&uuml;s was very heavily fined.
					And at the Olympic festival also he read a very great
					oration urging that the Greeks make peace with one
					another and overthrow Dionysius.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Only a fragment (Or. xxxiii.) of this is extant.</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.371"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>IV. ISOCRATES</head>
            <p>
					Isocrates was the son of Theodorus of Erchia, a
					citizen of the middle class, an owner of slaves who
					made flutes, through whom he gained a competence,
					so that he paid for a public chorus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wealthy Athenians performed in turn special services to the state called <q direct="unspecified">liturgies.</q> The most expensive of these was the choregy, which involved the payment, training, and equipment of a chorus for a lyrical or dramatic performance.</note> and gave his
					children an education<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Isocrates, <hi rend="italics">On the Exchange of Property</hi> (Or. xv.), 161.</note> (for he had other sons, Telesippus and Diomnestus, and also a daughter), and
					hence he is ridiculed on account of the flutes by
					Aristophanes and Strattis. Isocrates was born in
					the eighty-sixth Olympiad, in the archonship of
					Lysimachus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">436-435 b.c.</note> of Myrrhinus, being twenty-two years
					younger than Lysias and seven years older than
					Plato.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato was born in 428-427 b.c. Lysias, according to this statement, in 459-458. But see note on 835 d above.</note> In his boyhood he was as well educated as
					any Athenian, for he attended the lectures of Prodicus of Ceos, Gorgias of Leontini, Teisias of Syracuse,
					and the orator Theramenes ; and when the lastnamed was in danger of being arrested by the Thirty
					and had fled for safety to the altar of Hestia Boulaea,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The sanctuary of this Goddess of the Senate's Hearth was in or near the Prytaneum, which was somewhere on the northern slope of the Acropolis.</note>
					everyone else was terrified, but Isocrates alone arose
					to speak in his aid; and at first he was silent for a long
					time, then afterwards he was urged to be silent by
					Theramenes himself, who said that his misfortune
					would be more painful if any of his friends should
					share it. And it is said that certain rhetorical teachings of Theramenes - those which go under the name
					of Boton - were of use to Isocrates when he was
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.373"/>
					
					
					falsely accused in the courts. But when he became
					a man he kept away from political affairs, since he had
					a weak voice and a timid disposition<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Isocrates, <hi rend="italics">Philip</hi> (Or. v.), 81; <hi rend="italics">Panathenaic</hi> (Or. xii.), 9.</note> and had lost his
					inherited property in the war against the Lacedaemonians. It is evident that he composed speeches
					for others, but he delivered only one, that on the
					Exchange of Property. He set up a school and turned
					to philosophy and to writing out the results of his
					thinking, and he composed his Festival Oration<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Panegyric</hi>, delivered at Olympia.</note> and
					some others of an advisory nature, some of which he
					delivered himself and some of which he prepared for
					others to deliver, hoping that in this way he might
					lead the Greeks to think as they ought. But when
					he failed of his purpose he gave up that sort of thing
					and became the head of a school, at first, as some say,
					at Chios, where he had nine pupils. That was the
					time when, as he saw the tuition fees counted out,
					he burst into tears and said, <q direct="unspecified">Now I recognize that I
						have sold myself to these people.</q> He would carry
					on conversation with all who desired it and was the
					first to make a distinction between contentious
					speeches and those of a political character, to which
					latter he devoted himself. And he also instituted at
					Chios public offices and the same constitution which
					existed in his native city. He made more money
					than any other sophist, so that he was even a trierarch.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The trierarchy was one of the <q direct="unspecified">liturgies</q> which wealthy citizens were obliged to perform. Being trierarch thus showed wealth.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					His pupils numbered about one hundred, including
					among many others Timothe&uuml;s, son of Conon, with
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.375"/>
					
					
					whom he visited many cities ; and he composed the
					letters which Timothe&uuml;s sent to the Athenians, on
					account of which Timothe&uuml;s presented him with a
					talent out of the sum remaining after the relief
					of Samos.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">365 b.c.</note> Pupils of his were also Theopompus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text of Photius reads Xenophon the son of Gryllus and Theopompus.</note> of
					Chios, Ephorus of Cumae, Asclepiades who compiled the arguments of tragedies, and Theodectas of
					Phaselis, who afterwards wrote tragedies and whose
					monument stood as you go to the Bean-market along
					the Sacred Way which leads to Eleusis ; it is now in
					ruins. There, too, were set up statues of the famous
					poets along with his ; of these only the poet Homer
					exists now. And Leodamas the Athenian and
					Lacritus the Athenian law-maker and, as some say,
					Hypereides and Isaeus were his pupils. And they
					say that while he was still teaching oratory Demosthenes came to him eager to learn and said that he
					could not pay the thousand drachmas which he asked
					as tuition fee, but would give two hundred for one
					fifth of the instruction ; whereupon Isocrates replied :
					<q direct="unspecified">We do not cut our instruction into bits, Demosthenes, but just as people sell fine fish whole, so, if
						you wish to be my pupil, I will sell you my course
						whole.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					He died in the archonship of Chaerondas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">338-337 b.c.</note> after
					hearing in the palaestra of Hippocrates the news of
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.377"/>
					
					
					the battle of Chaeroneia;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This popular sotry of Isocrates' death is given also by Lucian (?), <hi rend="italics">Macrobioi</hi> 23, Pausanias, i. 18. 8, and Plutarch, 838 below. It is made famous by Milton in his tenth sonnet: <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>. . . as that dishonest victory </l>
                     <l>At Chaeronea, fatal to liberty, </l>
                     <l>Killed by report that old man eloquent</l>
                  </quote>
                  <p/>But Isocrates himself, at the end of his third letter, writes to Philip: <q direct="unspecified">But I am grateful to old age for this thing only, that it has continued my life to this point, so that of the things which I meditated in my youth and undertook to write in my <hi rend="italics">Panegyric Oration</hi> and in that which I sent to you, I now see some being accomplished through your deeds and hope that others will be accomplished.</q> Apparently he was well pleased with Philip's success. See Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., ii. p. 97.</note> and he removed himself
					from life by abstaining from food for four days. Just
					before the end he declaimed the opening lines of
					three dramas of Euripides :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Dana&uuml;s of fifty daughters fair the sire,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Archela&uuml;s</hi>; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 427, no. 228.</note>
					             </l>
                  <l>Pelops the Tantalid to Pisa came,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Iphigeneia in Tauris</hi>, 1.</note>
					             </l>
                  <l>Once Sidon's city Cadmus having left.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Phrixus</hi>; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 627, no. 819. Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., ii. p. 97, thinks these lines enumerate three intrusions of foreigners into Greece. The fourth - not mentioned - would then be that of the Macedonians under Philip.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					He died at the age of ninety-eight or, as some say,
					one hundred years, for he could not endure the sight
					of Greece enslaved four times.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Under the Athenian empire in the fifth century, by the Spartans after the Peloponnesian War, by the Thebans under Epameinondas, and by the Macedonians. All these Isocrates himself had seen. But see note <hi rend="italics">d</hi> above.</note> A year (or, as some
					say, four years) before his end he wrote the Panathenaic Oration;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In L.C.L. Isocrates, vol. ii. pp. 368 ff.</note> and for the composition of the
					Festival Oration he took ten (but some say fifteen)
					years. This, they say, he derived from the speeches
					of Gorgias of Leontini and Lysias. The speech on the
					Exchange of Property<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> pp. 181 ff. If anyone proposed that a certain man be obliged to perform one of the <q direct="unspecified">liturgies</q> which were required of wealthy Athenians, the man of whom this was required could challenge the proposer to an exchange of properties, which might transfer the obligation.</note> he wrote at the age of eighty-two years, and those against Philip shortly before
					his death. When he was an old man he adopted
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.379"/>
					
					
					Aphareus, the youngest of the three sons of Plathan&ecirc;,
					daughter of the orator Hippias. He acquired ample
					wealth, for he not only collected money from his
					pupils, but he also received from Nicocles, king of
					Cyprus, who was the son of Evagoras, twenty talents
					for the oration written in his honour. On account
					of his wealth he was envied and was proposed three
					times as trierarch. Twice he alleged illness and was
					exempted by petitions presented by his son, but the
					third time he undertook the duty and spent no small
					sum. To a father who said that he gave his son only
					a slave as companion he said, <q direct="unspecified">Go your ways, then,
						for you will have two slaves instead of one.</q> He
					took part also in the competition offered by Artemisia
					in honour of Maussolus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mausolus, ruler of Halicarnassus, died in 353 b.c. His widow, Artemisia, caused eulogies to be written in competition by Greek orators and completed the magnificent tomb which he had, apparently, begun. This magnificent building - the Mausoleum - was designed by Greek architects and decorated by famous Greek sculptors. The remains of the sculpture include portrait statues of Maussolus and Artemisia and are among the most highly prized possessions of the British Museum.</note> but his Eulogy is not extant.
					He wrote also a Eulogy of Helen and a speech called
					the Areopagitic. He departed this life some say on
					the ninth day of his abstention from food, others
					on the fourth day at the time of the funeral of those
					who fell at Chaeroneia. His son Aphareus also wrote
					speeches. Isocrates was buried with his family near
					Cynosarges<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Cynosarges was a region in Athens in which was a great gymnasium.</note> on the left side of the hill-he himself, his father Theodorus, and his mother ; and her
					sister Anaco, the orator's aunt, and his adopted son
					Aphareus, and his cousin Socrates, son of Anaco
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.381"/>
					
					
					Isocrates' mother's sister, and his brother Theodorus
					who had the same name as his father, and his grandsons, the sons of his adopted son Aphareus, Aphareus
					and his father Theodorus, and the latter's wife
					Plathan&ecirc;, mother of the adopted son Aphareus.
					And over them there were six tablets which do not
					now exist. On the monument of Isocrates himself
					was a column thirty cubits high, on which was a siren
					seven cubits high as a symbol; but this exists no
					longer. There was also a tablet near by with poets
					and his instructors on it, among whom was Gorgias
					gazing into an astrological sphere and Isocrates
					standing beside him. There is also a bronze statue
					of him, dedicated by Timothe&uuml;s, son of Conon, at
					Eleusis in front of the vestibule. It bears this
					inscription :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Here to the goddesses twain Timothe&uuml;s giveth this statue
					</l>
                  <l>Tribute to friend and to sage, image of Isocrates.</l>
               </quote>
					It is a work of Leochares.
				</p>
            <p>
					Sixty orations are current under his name, of which
					twenty-five are genuine according to Dionysius,
					twenty-eight according to Caecilius, and the rest are
					spurious. He was averse to public declamation, so
					much so that once, when three persons came to hear
					him, he retained two but let the third go, telling him
					to come the next day, since now the lecture-room had
					a full audience. And he used to say to his pupils that
					he himself gave instruction for ten minas, but would
					give ten thousand to anyone who would teach him
					self-confidence and a pleasant voice. And when he
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.383"/>
					
					
					was asked how he, not being a good speaker himself,
					could make others so, he replied that whetstones
					cannot themselves cut, but make iron fit to do so.
					Some say that he also wrote textbooks of oratory,
					others that in his teaching he made use of practice,
					not of method. He never demanded a fee from a
					fellow-citizen. When his pupils went to meetings of
					the assembly, he told them to report to him what was
					said there. He was greatly grieved by the death of
					Socrates, and the next day he appeared in black
					clothing. And again, when someone asked him
					<q direct="unspecified">What is oratory?</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">the art of making
						small things great and great things small.</q> And
					once when he was a guest at a banquet in the house
					of Nicocreon, despot of Cyprus, and some of those
					present urged him to discourse, he said, <q direct="unspecified">for subjects
						in which I am competent this is not the time ; in the
						subjects for which this is the time I am not competent.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 613 a.</note> When he saw the tragic poet Sophocles
					amorously following a boy, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Sophocles, we
						must not only keep our hands to ourselves, but our
						eyes as well.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Attributed to Pericles by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pericles</hi>, chap. viii., and Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Officiis</hi>, i. 40. 144.</note> And when Ephorus of Cumae had
					left his school without learning anything and had been
					sent back by his father with a second tuition-fee, he
					called him in fun Diphorus (Twice-bringer) ; he took,
					however, great pains with him and even suggested to
					him the subject of his work.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The great work of Ephorus was a history of the world (primarily of Greece) from the return of the Heracleidae to the siege of Perinthus in 340 b.c. From this work Plutarch and others derived much of their information. Ephorus was born early in the fourth century and died about 320 b.c.</note> He showred himself
					also prone to sexual indulgence ; he used an additional mattress beside him on his bed and kept his
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.385"/>
					
					
					pillow wet with saffron. And when he was young he
					did not marry, but in his old age he kept a mistress
					named Lagisc&ecirc;, by whom he had a daughter who died
					unmarried at twelve years of age. Then he married
					the daughter of the orator Hippias, Plathan&ecirc;, who
					had three sons, one of whom, Aphareus, as has been
					said above, he adopted. This Aphareus dedicated a
					bronze statue of him near the Olympieium on a
					column with the inscription :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Aphareus set up this statue his father Isocrates' image,
					</l>
                  <l>Sacred to Zeus, to exalt gods and his ancestors' worth.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 329. The column and statue existed in the time of Pausanias (Paus. i. 18. 8). A bust in the Villa Albani in Rome may be a late copy of the head of this statue or, more probably, since Leochares was a famous sculptor, of the statue at Eleusis mentioned above.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And it is said that he rode a horse in a race when he
					was still a boy ; for a bronze figure of him as a boy
					riding a horse is set up on the Acropolis in the ballground of the Arrhephoroi,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This seems to have been situated near the north-west wall of the Acropolis, west of the Erechtheum: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Judeich, <hi rend="italics">Topographie von Athen</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">2</hi>, p. 283. Two maidens were chosen each year to carry the peplos at the Panathenaic festival and were called Arrephoroi.</note> as some have said. In all
					his life but two lawsuits were brought against him :
					first when Megacleides challenged him to an exchange
					of property.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See note on 837 f.</note> He did not appear in court in this suit,
					because he was ill, but sent his son Aphareus and won
					his case. The second suit was when Lysimachus
					challenged him to exchange property in connexion
					with the trierarchy ; and this case he lost and performed the trierarchy. There was also a painted
					portrait of him in the Pompeium.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Pompeium was just inside the Dipylon gate, at which point the processions began. It was the storehouse for objects used in processions.</note> Aphareus wrote
					speeches, both juridical and deliberative, but not
					many. He also composed about thirty-seven tragedies, but the authorship of tw o of them is contested.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.387"/>
					
					
					Beginning in the archonship of Lysistratus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">369-368 b.c.</note> he presented in the twenty-eight years to the archonship of
					Sosigenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">342-341 b.c.</note> six series of dramas at the City Dionysia
					and won the prize twice, Dionysius as his manager,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">When a poet (<foreign lang="greek">dida/skalos</foreign>) wished to avoid the labour of presenting a play he could delegate the management to a hypodidascalus, another poet experienced in such matters. We have many instances of this practice in the didascalic notices, notably in the case of Aristophanes.</note>
					and, other poets managing, he presented two other
					series at the Lenaean festival.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The City or Greater Dionysia were celebrated in March, the Rural or Lesser Dionysia in the various demes of Attica in December, and the Lenaean festival in December. At all of these dramas were performed, but new tragedies were not produced at the Rural Dionysia, and for a time the same was true of the Lenaean festival. A series of dramas comprised three tragedies and a satyr drama. The two prizes of Aphareus are recorded in an inscription, <hi rend="italics">I.G.</hi> ii.<hi rend="super">2</hi> 2325 <hi rend="italics">b</hi> (ed. min.).</note> There were statues
					of the mother of Isocrates and Theodorus and of her
					sister Anaco set up on the Acropolis ; of these the
					statue of the mother is now placed, with a changed
					inscription,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Statues erected to honour one person were not infrequently transferred to another by changing the inscriptions. Dio Chrysostom in his <hi rend="italics">Oration to the Rhodians</hi> condemns this practice.</note> near that of Hygieia, but the statue of
					Anaco is gone. She had two sons, Alexander by
					Coenus, and Sosicles by Lysias.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>V. ISAEUS</head>
            <p>
					Isaeus was a Chalcidian by birth, but came to
					Athens and went to school [to Isocrates. He resembled] Lysias<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Dion. Hal. <hi rend="italics">De Isaeo Iudicium</hi>, 2 <foreign lang="greek">xarakth=ra de\ *lusi/ou kata\ to\ plei=ston e)zh/lwse</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">he emulated in the highest degree the character of Lysias.</q>
               </note> in his melodious diction and in his
					skilful arrangement and treatment of the subject
					matter in his speeches, so that unless a person were
					thoroughly familiar with their particular styles,
					he could not easily tell to which of the two orators
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.389"/>
					
					
					many of the speeches belong. He was in his prime
					after the Peloponnesian War, as may be inferred
					from his speeches, and lived until the reign of
					Philip. He taught Demosthenes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See below, Demosthenes, 844 b.</note> not at his school,
					but privately, for ten thousand drachmas, whereby
					he acquired great distinction. And he himself composed for Demosthenes the speeches against his
					guardians, as some said. He has left behind him
					sixty-four speeches, fifty of which are genuine, and
					some rules of rhetoric of his own. He was also the
					first to give artistic form to his speech<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., ii. p. 499, interprets this as referring to figures of thought (construing <foreign lang="greek">th\n dia/noian</foreign> with <foreign lang="greek">sxhmati/zein</foreign>). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 835 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> 
                  <foreign lang="greek">a)sxhma/tistos</foreign> of Andocides.</note> and to turn
					his attention to the urbane style of the orator ; in
					which Demosthenes has closely imitated him. Theopompus the comic playwright mentions him<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. p. 737, no. 18.</note> in the
					<hi rend="italics">Theseus</hi>.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>VI. AESCHINES</head>
            <p>
					Aeschines was the son of Atrometus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A catalogue of the tribe Oeneis, <hi rend="italics">I.G.</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">2</hi> 2408, gives his full name: <foreign lang="greek">*)atro/mhtos *ai)sxi/nou *koqoki/dhs</foreign>. It gives also the name of Aeschines' son <foreign lang="greek">*)atro/mhtos</foreign>.</note> who was
					exiled in the time of the Thirty and helped to restore
					the democracy, and of Glaucothea. He belonged to
					the deme of the Cothocidae and was not of distinguished family or great wealth. When he was young
					and physically strong he worked hard in the gymnasia ; and afterwards, since he had a clear voice, he
					practised tragedy; and according to Demosthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, xviii. 261; xix. 246. The festivals in question are those held in the small towns of Attica. Aristodemus was one of the most noted tragic actors of his time. Born at Metapontum, he was granted Athenian citizenship and was one of the envoys (among whom were Aeschines, Demosthenes, and Philocrates) who made the peace of Philocrates with Philip in 346 b.c.</note>
					he was for a long time under-secretary and regularly
					played as a third-rate actor with Aristodemus at the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.391"/>
					
					
					Dionysiac festivals,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">More accurately in Photius, the dramatic festivals held in the small towns of Attica. For the ancient accounts of Aeschines' career as an actor see O'Connor, <hi rend="italics">Actors and Acting in Ancient Greece</hi>, pp. 74 ff. Kelly Rees, <hi rend="italics">The Rule of Three Actors in the Classical Greek Drama</hi>, pp. 31 ff., has shown that the term <q direct="unspecified">tritagonist</q> was invented by Demosthenes as an opprobrious epithet and it is applied in antiquity to not other actor than Aeschines; also that it meant, not <q direct="unspecified">actor of third-rate roles,</q> but <q direct="unspecified">third-rate actor</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Bekker, <hi rend="italics">Anecdota</hi>, p. 309. 31 <foreign lang="greek">a)dokimw/tatos tw=n u(pokritw=n, e)n th=| trith| ta/cei katariqmou/menos</foreign>.</note> repeating the old tragedies<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Old tragedies</q> are those which had been performed in Athens before.</note> in
					his spare time. And while still a child he helped his
					father to teach letters, and as a young man he served
					in the patrol of the frontiers. After studying with
					Isocrates and Plato, as some say, but with Leodamas
					according to Caecilius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But see below, 840 e, where the more probable statement is made that he had no teacher. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the anonymous <hi rend="italics">Life of Aeschines</hi>, 13, Quintilian, ii. 17. 12, and Blass, <hi rend="italics">Die attische Beredsamkeit</hi>, 2nd ed., iii. p. 157.</note> he was prominent in public
					life in the party opposed to that of Demosthenes, and
					was sent on many embassies, among them the one
					to Philip concerning the peace.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschines was sent in 347 and 346 b.c. on two embassies to Philip concerning peace. The second is probably the one especially referred to here. In his orations <hi rend="italics">On the Peace</hi> (346 b.c.) and <hi rend="italics">On the False Legation</hi> (343 b.c.) Demosthenes attacks Aeschines and his colleagues.</note> For this he was
					accused by Demosthenes of having destroyed the
					Phocian nation and moreover of having stirred up
					war between the Amphissians, who were building
					the harbour when he was chosen as delegate to the
					Amphictyonic Council, and the Amphictyons ; as a
					result of which the Amphictyons turned to Philip
					for protection, and he, assisted by Aeschines, took
					matters in hand and conquered Phocis. But through
					the aid of Eubulus, son of Spintharus, of the deme of
					Probalinthus, who had influence with the people, he
					was acquitted by thirty votes ; but some say that
					though the orators composed their speeches, yet
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.393"/>
					
					
					the suit never came to trial because the battle of
					Chaeroneia intervened.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The author's extreme brevity reduces to two sentences the events of about eight years. The acquittal of Aeschines took place in 343 b.c.</note> At a later time, when Philip
					was dead and Alexander was crossing over to Asia, he
					brought a suit against Ctesiphon for illegal conduct in
					proposing the honours for Demosthenes; and when he
					did not receive one-fifth of the votes cast, he went into
					exile at Rhodes, not being willing to pay a fine of a
					thousand drachmas for his defeat.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Anyone who brought a suit against another for proposing a measure forbidden by law was subject to a fine and was debarred from bringing any similar suit if he received less than one-fifth of the votes cast by the dicasts.</note> But some say that
					he was further punished by disfranchisement and did
					not leave the city of his own accord, and that he went
					to Alexander at Ephesus. During the confusion following Alexander's death he sailed to Rhodes, set up a
					school there, and taught. He read to the Rhodians
					his oration against Ctesiphon as an exhibition of his
					powers, and when they all wondered that after
					delivering that speech he had lost his case, <q direct="unspecified">You
						would not wonder, Rhodians,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">if you had
							heard Demosthenes speak in reply to it.</q> And he
					left a school behind him there, called the Rhodian
					school. Then he sailed to Samos and not long after,
					while lingering on that island, died. He had an
					excellent voice, as is clear from what Demosthenes
					says<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, xviii. (<hi rend="italics">On the Crown</hi>) 259, 308.</note> and from the oration of Demochares.
				</p>
            <p>
					Four orations are current under his name : that
					<hi rend="italics">Against Timarchus</hi>, that <hi rend="italics">On the False Legation</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In L.C.L. Aeschines, pp. 15 ff.</note> and
					that <hi rend="italics">Against Ctesiphon</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> pp. 303 ff.</note> and these alone are genuine,
					since the one entitled the <hi rend="italics">Delian Oration</hi> is not
					by Aeschines ; for he was, to be sure, appointed
					associate advocate in the trial relating to the sanctuary
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.395"/>
					
					
					at Delos, but he did not deliver the speech ; for
					Hypereides was elected in his place, as Demosthenes
					says.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, xviii. (<hi rend="italics">On the Crown</hi>) p. 271, 134.</note> He had, as he himself says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschines, <hi rend="italics">On the False Legation</hi>, 149.</note> two brothers,
					Aphobetus and Philochares. He was the first to
					bring to the Athenians the news of the victory at
					Tamynae, for which he was crowned a second time.
				</p>
            <p>
					Some have said that Aeschines did not study under
					any teachers, but rose from the under-clerkship in the
					courts, which he held at that time. And they say
					that his first speech before the people was against
					Philip, by which he gained such reputation as to be
					chosen envoy to the Arcadians ; and when he came
					to them he raised the ten thousand troops with which
					to oppose Philip. He also prosecuted for unchastity
					Timarchus, who gave up the defence and hanged
					himself, as Demosthenes says somewhere.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes xix. (<hi rend="italics">On the False Legation</hi>) 2 and 285.</note> He was
					elected envoy to Philip with Ctesiphon and Demosthenes to treat for peace, on which occasion he was
					more successful than Demosthenes ; and the second
					time, when he was one of ten,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschines, <hi rend="italics">On the False Legation</hi>, 178.</note> he confirmed the peace
					with oaths, was tried for it, and was acquitted, as has
					been said above.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>VII. LYCURGUS</head>
            <p>
					Lycurgus was the son of Lycophron and grandson of the Lycurgus whom the Thirty Tyrants put to
					death, his execution being brought about by Aristodemus
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.397"/>
					
					
					of Bat&ecirc;, who also, after having been one of the
					Hellenotamiae,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Hellenotamiae were a board of ten members who collected and administered the tribute paid to Athens by the members of the Delian Confederacy.</note> was banished under the democracy.
					Lycurgus was of the deme of the Butadae and the
					family of the Eteobutadae. He attended the
					lectures of Plato the philosopher and at first devoted
					himself to philosophy ; then, after being a pupil of
					the orator Isocrates, he had a notable public career
					both as a speaker and as a man of action, and he was
					also entrusted with the management of the finances
					of the State ; for he was made treasurer for three
					periods of four years<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">338-326 b.c. The title of his office is not known. No regular office so extensive as this is mentioned in Aristotle's <hi rend="italics">Constitution of Athens</hi>. He may have been in charge of the theoric fund or the military fund, or both, by virtue of a special commission, which in the next generation became a regular office; see Ferguson, <hi rend="italics">Hellenistic Athens</hi>, p. 10, Tarn, <hi rend="italics">Cambridge Ancient History</hi>, vi. p. 441. The period meant may be the quinquennium.</note> in charge of fourteen thousand
					talents, or, as some say (and among them the man
					who proposed the vote of honours for him,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Decree III, below, 852.</note> Stratocles
					the orator), eighteen thousand, six hundred and
					fifty.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Roughly equivalent to 3,026,000 or $15,130,000, or more at present values.</note> He was elected in his own person the first
					time, but afterwards he entered the name of one of
					his friends, though he himself administered the office,
					because a law had previously been introduced forbidding anyone elected treasurer of the public funds
					to hold the office more than four years ; and he was
					always intent upon the public business summer and
					winter. When he was elected to provide munitions
					of war he restored many edifices in the city, he
					provided four hundred triremes for the people, he constructed the gymnasium in the Lyceum and planted
					trees in it, he built the palaestra and finished the
					Dionysiac theatre when he was the commissioner
					in charge of that work.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably while he was in control of the finances. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> D&ouml;rpfeld and Reisch, <hi rend="italics">Das griechische Theater</hi>, pp. 39 f.</note> He took care of two hundred
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.399"/>
					
					
					and fifty talents entrusted to him on deposit by
					private persons, he provided for the city objects of
					gold and silver for use in processions and golden
					Victories, and many buildings which came into his
					hands half-finished he completed, among them the
					ship-sheds and the arsenal. And he put the foundation-walls round the Panathenaic stadium. This he
					accomplished, and also the levelling of the ravine,
					because a certain Deinias who owned this plot of
					land gave it to the city when Lycurgus suggested to
					him that he make the gift.
				</p>
            <p>
					He was charged also with guarding the city and
					arresting malefactors, whom he drove out entirely,
					so that some of the sophists said that Lycurgus
					signed warrants against evil-doers with a pen dipped,
					not in ink, but in death. And therefore, when King
					Alexander demanded his surrender, the people did
					not give him up. When Philip was carrying on the
					second war with the Athenians, Lycurgus went as
					envoy with Polyeuctus and Demosthenes to the
					Peloponnesus and to some other States. Throughout
					his life he was always highly esteemed among the
					Athenians and considered a just man, so that in the
					courts of law the word of Lycurgus was regarded as
					a help to anyone requiring an advocate.
				</p>
            <p>
					He also introduced laws : the law relating to
					comic actors, that a competitive performance be held
					on the festival of Pots<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The third day of the Anthesteria, the thirteenth day of the month Anthesterium.</note> and that the victor's name
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.401"/>
					
					
					be inscribed as eligible for the City Dionysia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The <foreign lang="greek">tragw|doi/</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">kwmw|doi/</foreign> alone were eligible to be chosen by lot as protagonists for the tragedies and comedies to be presented at the City Dionysia, the subordinate roles being assigned to plain <foreign lang="greek">u(pokritai/</foreign>. Prior to the passage of the law of Lycurgus those only were eligible who had previously won a victory at the City Dionysia. The effect of the law of Lycurgus was, therefore, to increase the number of thos efrom whom the archon could choose a <foreign lang="greek">kwmw|do/s</foreign> for each of the five comedies to be presented. See Rohde, <hi rend="italics">Rheinisches Museum</hi>, xxxviii. p. 276, and J. B. O'Connor, <hi rend="italics">Chapters in the History of Actors and Acting</hi>, pp. 57 ff.</note>
					which had not been permitted before, and thus he
					revived a contest which had fallen out of use ; the
					law that bronze statues of the poets Aeschylus,
					Sophocles, and Euripides be erected, that their
					tragedies be written out and kept in a public depository, and that the clerk of the State read them to the
					actors who were to perform their plays for comparison of the texts and that it be unlawful to depart
					from the authorized text in acting ; a third law that
					no Athenian or foreign resident of Athens should be
					permitted to buy from among captives a person of free
					birth to be a slave without the consent of his former
					master<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Prisoners of war were usually auctioned off into slavery regardless of their previous condition. If such a captive could prove his free birth through the testimony of the man who owned him when taken captive, he could not under this new law be purchased by any Athenian for slavery, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> M. H. E., Meier, <hi rend="italics">Comment. de vita Lycurgi</hi>, xxxix. ff.</note>; furthermore, that a festival of Poseidon
					should be held in Peiraeus, consisting of no fewer than
					three cyclic choruses, that not less than ten minas be
					given to the victors, eight to those ranked second by
					the judges, and six to those ranked third; furthermore, that no woman should go to Eleusis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This refers to the great annual procession to Eleusis in the celebration of the mysteries of Demeter and Persephon&ecirc;.</note> in a carriage, lest the women of the people appear inferior to
					the rich, and if any woman should be caught doing
					this, she should pay a fine of six thousand drachmas.
					His own wife disobeyed, the informers caught her
					in the act, and he gave them a talent; and at a later
					time, wrhen accused of this in the popular assembly,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.403"/>
					
					
					he said, <q direct="unspecified">At any rate I am found to have been the
						giver, not the receiver.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The story may well be apocryphal. The saying of Lycurgus, repeated by Plutarch in his <hi rend="italics">Comp. of Nicias and Crassus</hi>, 3, is not there connected with the Eleusis incident; and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Var. Hist.</hi> xiii. 24, expressly states that the statesman's wife paid a fine after legal condemnation, not a bribe to the informer.</note> And once when a taxcollector laid hands on Xenocrates the philosopher
					and Lycurgus met him as he was leading him away
					to enforce payment of his tax as a resident alien,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The tax was twelve drachmas.</note>
					he brought his walking-stick down on the tax-collector's head, set Xenocrates free, and shut the
					other man up in prison for improper conduct. As he
					was generally commended for his act, Xenocrates,
					happening to meet Lycurgus's children some days
					later, said <q direct="unspecified">I have repaid your father quickly for the
						favour he did me, boys ; for he is widely commended
						for coming to my assistance.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					He also proposed decrees,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Several decrees moved by him are extant, <hi rend="italics">e.g. I.G.</hi> ii.<hi rend="super">2</hi> 337, 338.</note> making use of a certain
					Olynthian named Eucleides, who was an expert in
					decrees. And although he was well-to-do, he wore
					one and the same cloak winter and summer and put
					on sandals only on days when they wTere necessary.
					He studied night and day, since he had no natural
					gift for extemporaneous speaking, and he lay on a
					cot with only a sheepskin and a pillow on it, so that
					he might wake up easily and study. When someone
					found fault with him for paying money to sophists
					although he made words his profession, he replied
					that if anyone would promise to make his sons better,
					he would pay him, not thousands only, but half his
					property. He was an outspoken speaker on account
					of his good birth. Once, indeed, when the Athenians
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.405"/>
					
					
					were showing dissent as he was speaking, he burst
					out with : <q direct="unspecified">O Corcyraean whip, how ma ly talents
						you are worth!</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Corcyraean whip was especially stinging, and the orator's outbreak means: <q direct="unspecified">I would give a great deal to use a cat-o'-nine-tails on you people.</q>
               </note> And when they were proclaiming
					Alexander a god, <q direct="unspecified">What sort of god,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">is
						he when those who <hi rend="italics">come out</hi> of his temple have to
						sprinkle themselves with holy water?</q> After his
					death his sons were handed over to the eleven executioners on the accusation of Menesaechmus, the
					indictment being written by Thrasycles; but when
					Demosthenes, who was at that time in exile, wrote
					a letter to the Athenians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Demosthenes, <hi rend="italics">Epistle</hi> iii., and Aeschines, <hi rend="italics">Epistle</hi> xii. 14.</note> saying that their reputation was suffering because of Lycurgus's sons, they
					changed their mind and released them, Democles,
					a pupil of Theophrastus, speaking in their defence.
					He himself and some of his descendants were buried
					at public expense ; and their monuments are opposite
					the Paeonian Athena in the garden of the philosopher
					Melanthius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Judeich, <hi rend="italics">Topogr. v. Athen</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">2</hi>, p. 409, conjectures that the garden of Melanthius was in the neighbourhood of the Academy.</note>; they are in the form of tables, and
					those of Lycurgus and his children have inscriptions
					and are still preserved in our day. His greatest
					achievement was the raising of the State revenue to
					twelve hundred talents when it had previously been
					sixty. When he was at the point of death he gave
					orders that he be carried to the temple of the Great
					Mother and into the Bouleuterion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Bouleuterion was the meeting-place of the Boul&ecirc; or Senate; the foundations of this and of the temple of the Great Mother have recently been found on the west side of the Agora. See T. L. Shear, <hi rend="italics">Hesperia</hi>, iv. pp. 349 ff.</note> as he wished
					to give an accounting for his public acts ; and when
					no one had the face to accuse him except Menesaechmus, he freed himself from his false accusations,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.407"/>
					
					
					was carried to his house, and died,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">His death occurred about 324 b.c.</note> having been considered a honourable man throughout his whole life,
					and highly praised for his speeches. He never was
					convicted, though many brought accusations against
					him.
				</p>
            <p>
					He had three children by Callisto, the daughter of
					Habron and sister of Callias the son of Habron of the
					deme Bat&ecirc;, the one who was treasurer of military
					funds in the archonship of Charondas.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">338-337 b.c.</note> Deinarchus,
					in his speech against Pistius, tells about this connexion
					by marriage. He left three sons, Habron, Lycurgus,
					and Lycophron, of whom Habron and Lycurgus died
					without issue. However, Habron at any rate had
					a distinguished public career before he died ; but
					Lycophron married Callistomach&ecirc;, daughter of
					Philippus of Aexon&ecirc;, and had a daughter Callisto.
					She was married to Cleombrotus of Acharnae, son
					of Deinocrates, to whom she bore a son Lycophron,
					who was adopted by his grandfather Lycophron and
					died without issue. After Lycophron's death Socrates
					married Callisto and had a son Symmachus. Symmachus had a son Aristonymus, he a son Charmides,
					and Charmides a daughter Philippa. Her son by
					Lysander was Medeius, who became an expounder
					of rites,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At Eleusis in connexion with the Eleusinian Mysteries.</note> being of the family of the Eumolpidae. He
					and Timothea, daughter of Glaucus, had three
					children, Laodameia and Medeius, who held the
					priestship of Poseidon-Erechtheus, and Philippa, who
					afterwards became priestess of Athena ; but before
					that Diocles of Melit&ecirc; married her, and their son was
					the Diocles who was general in command of the
					heavy-armed force. He married Hedist&ecirc;, daughter
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.409"/>
					
					
					of Habron, and bad two children, Philippides and
					Nicostrata. Themistocles, the Torch-bearer,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Torch-bearer was an important functionary in the Eleusinian Mysteries. The office was hereditary.</note> son of
					Theophrastus, married Nicostrata and had two sons,
					Theophrastus and Diocles. He also organized the
					priesthood of Poseidon-Erechtheus.
				</p>
            <p>
					Fifteen speeches of the orator are current.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Of these only the speech against Leocrates has come down to us.</note> He
					was crowned by the people many times and was
					honoured with statues. A bronze statue<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The inscription on the base of this statue is probably preserved in <hi rend="italics">I.G.</hi> ii.<hi rend="super">2</hi> 3776. Another statue stood not far from the Prytaneium; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Pausanius, i. 8. 2.</note> of him
					stands in the Cerameicus, set up in accordance with
					a decree passed in the archonship of Anaxicrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">307-306 b.c. See the Decree below, 851 ff.</note>
					in which year Lycurgus and his eldest descendant
					were granted maintenance in the Prytaneum by the
					same decree. After Lycurgus died his eldest son,
					Lycophron, brought a suit for the grant. Lycurgus
					spoke also many times on religious matters, bringing
					suit against Autolycus the Areopagite, Lysicles the
					general, Demades the son of Demeas, Menesaechmus,
					and many others, and he caused them all to be
					convicted. He also brought Diphilus to trial, who
					removed from the silver mines the rock props which
					supported the weight above and made himself rich
					from them contrary to the law ; and though the
					penalty for this was death, Lycurgus brought about
					his conviction, and from the confiscated estate distributed fifty drachmas to every citizen, since the
					total sum collected was one hundred and sixty
					talents or, as some say, he distributed a mina to each
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.411"/>
					
					
					citizen.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The drachma was worth, in silver, about 9d. or 18 cents, the mina 100 drachmas, the talent 60 minas. The sums mentioned are therefore roughly equivalent to 1 : 16s. ($9), 40,960 ($172,800), and 3 : 12 s. ($18), but the fluctuations in the value of modern currencies render such calculations very inexact. See Decree III. below, 851 f-852 e.</note> He it was who called Aristogeiton, Leocrates, and Autolycus to account for cowardice.
					Lycurgus was nicknamed <q direct="unspecified">Ibis,</q>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">An ibis for Lycurgus, for Chaerephon a bat.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophanes, <hi rend="italics">Birds</hi>, 1296 and scholium. But it was the grandfather of the orator and statesman to whom Aristophanes referred.</note>
               </quote>
					His family was derived ultimately from Erechtheus,
					the son of Gaea and Poseidon, but in the nearest
					generations from Lycomedes and Lycurgus, whom the
					people honoured with funerals at the public expense ;
					and this succession from father to son of those of the
					family who have been priests of Poseidon exists on a
					complete tablet which has been set up in the Erechtheum, painted by Ismenias the Chalcidian ; and
					there are wooden statues of Lycurgus and his sons
					Habron, Lycurgus, and Lycophron, made by Timarchus and Cephisodotus, the sons of Praxiteles. But
					the tablet was put up by his son Habron, who received the priesthood by inheritance and handed it
					over to his brother Lycophron ; and that is why
					Habron is represented as handing Lycophron the
					trident. And Lycurgus had a record made of all his
					acts as a public official and set it up on a tablet, for
					all men to see who wished, in front of the palaestra
					that he had built; no one, however, could convict
					him of embezzlement. He made the motion to crown
					Neoptolemus the son of Anticles and to set up a
					statue of him because he had promised to gild the
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.413"/>
					
					
					altar of Apollo<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This altar may have stood in front of the temple of Apollo Patro&uuml;s; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Judeich, <hi rend="italics">Topographie von Athen</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">2</hi>, p. 345, n. 4.</note> in the Market-place in accordance
					with the God's prophecy. He also moved a decree
					granting honours to Diotimus, son of Diopeithes, of
					the deme Euonymus, in the archonship of Ctesicles.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">334-333 b.c.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>VIII. DEMOSTHENES</head>
            <p>
					Demosthenes, son of Demosthenes and Cleobul&ecirc;
					daughter of Gylon, was of the deme Paeania. He
					was left an orphan at the age of seven years<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">He was born in 384 b.c.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Orations xxx. 15 and xxi. 154.</note> by his
					father, along with his five-year-old sister, and lived
					during his minority with his mother. Some say that
					he went to school to Isocrates, but most authorities
					say that he went to Isaeus of Chalcis, who was a
					pupil of Isocrates living in Athens. He imitated
					Thucydides and also the philosopher Plato, whose
					instruction, some say, he followed with especial zeal.
					But Hegesias of Magnesia says that he asked his
					attendant to let him hear Callistratus of Aphidna,
					son of Empedus, a noted orator who had been a commander of cavalry and had set up the altar to Hermes-of-the-Market<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The bronze Hermes Agoraios was <foreign lang="greek">e)n me/sh| th=| a(gora=|</foreign> (schol. Aristoph. <hi rend="italics">Eq.</hi> 297; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Paus. i. 15. 1) and <foreign lang="greek">para\ th\n poiki/lhn</foreign> (Lucian, <hi rend="italics">Iup. Trag.</hi> 33).</note> and was about to address the popular
					assembly; and Demosthenes, when he had heard
					him speak, fell in love with oratory. Demosthenes
					heard him, it is true, for only a short time, as long
					as Callistratus remained in Athens ; but when he
					had been banished to Thrace and Demosthenes had
					finished his service as ephebe,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> at the age of twenty. This service, designed to be a training for citizenship, lasted two years.</note> he went over to Isocrates
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.415"/>
					
					
					and Plato ; then he took Isaeus into his house
					and for four years exerted himself to imitate his
					speeches. But Ctesibius says in his work <hi rend="italics">On Philosophy</hi> that through Callias of Syracuse he obtained
					the speeches of Zethus of Amphipolis and through
					Charicles of Carystus those of Alcidamas and that he
					studied them thoroughly.
				</p>
            <p>
					When he attained his majority, because he received from his guardians less than was right, he
					brought them to trial for their administration, in the
					archonship of Timocrates.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">364-363 b.c.</note> There were three of
					them : Aphobus, Therippides, and Demophon or
					Demeas, and he accused the last-named especially,
					since he was his mother's brother.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This is incorrect. The author seems to have confused Demophon and his father Demeas. Demosthenes accused Aphobus chiefly, and Aphobus was his cousin, not his uncle. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Demosthenes, xxix. (<hi rend="italics">Against Aphobus for False Witness</hi>) 59, also 6 and 20; xxviii. (<hi rend="italics">Against Aphobus</hi> II.) 15; xxvii. (<hi rend="italics">Against Aphobus</hi> I.) 4.</note> He fixed the
					penalty in each suit at ten talents, and he obtained
					conviction of all three defendants ; but he exacted no
					part of the penalty, for he let them off, some for money
					and some as an act of grace. When Aristophon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aristophon, a second-rate but influential politician, was especially active in the decade preceding the choregia of Demosthenes, but no connexion can be perceived between his retirement and Demosthenes' choregia. He lived to be nearly 100 years old (<foreign lang="greek">h)/dh</foreign>).</note> at
					last on account of age resigned political leadership,
					Demosthenes was even made choregus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An indication of Demosthenes' restored fortune. The choregus was a wealthy man who equipped the chorus for dramas and superintended its training.</note> And wThen
					Meidias of the deme of Anagyros struck him as he
					was performing his duties in the theatre as choregus,
					he sued him for the act, but on receipt of three
					thousand drachmas he dropped the suit. They say
					that when he was still a young man he withdrew into
					a cave and studied there, shaving half of his head to
					keep himself from going out; also that he slept on a
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.417"/>
					
					
					narrow bed in order to get up quickly, and that since
					he could not pronounce the sound of R he learned
					to do so by hard work, and since in declaiming for
					practice he made an awkward movement with his
					shoulder, he put an end to the habit by fastening a
					spit or, as some say, a dagger from the ceiling to
					make him through fear keep his shoulder motionless.
					They say, too, that as he progressed in his ability to
					speak he had a mirror made as large as himself and
					kept his eyes on it while practising, that he might
					correct his faults ; and that he used to go down to
					the shore at Phalerum and address his remarks to
					the roar of the waves, that he might not be disconcerted if the people should ever make a disturbance ; and that because he was short of breath
					he paid Neoptolemus the actor ten thousand drachmas
					to teach him to speak whole paragraphs without
					taking breath.
				</p>
            <p>
					And when he entered upon political life, finding that
					the public men of the city were divided into two
					parties, one favouring Philip and the other addressing
					the populace in defence of liberty, he enrolled himself
					among those opposed to Philip and always constantly
					advised the people to support the cause of those
					peoples which were in danger of being subjected by
					Philip, in which policy he was associated with
					Hypereides, Nausicles, Polyeuctus, and Diotimus ;
					and thus he also brought the Thebans, Euboeans,
					Corcyraeans, Corinthians, Boeotians, and many others
					into alliance with the Athenians. Once he was hissed
					out of the assembly and was walking home feeling
					discouraged ; but Eunomus of the deme Thria, who
					was already an old man, happened to meet him and
					encouraged him, and more than anyone else the actor
					
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.419"/>
					
					
					Andronicus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A tragic actor of the first part of the fourth century b.c. See O'Connor, <hi rend="italics">Chapters in the History of Actors and Acting in Ancient Greece</hi>, p. 78. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, chap. vii. assigns to Satyrus about the same relation to the orator's training as is here assigned to Andronicus.</note> by telling him that his words were
					excellent but that his delivery was deficient, and
					then Andronicus declaimed from memory the speech
					which Demosthenes had delivered in the assembly ;
					whereupon Demosthenes was convinced and put himself in the hands of Andronicus. Therefore when
					someone asked him what was the first thing in oratory,
					he replied <q direct="unspecified">Delivery,</q> and what the second,
					<q direct="unspecified">Delivery,</q> and the third, <q direct="unspecified">Delivery.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the meaning, broader than that of our <q direct="unspecified">delivery,</q> in Greek rhetoric see Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, iii., <hi rend="italics">ad init.</hi>
               </note> And when
					he spoke again in the assemblies he was hissed for
					some new-fangled expressions, so that Antiphanes
					and Timocles made fun of him in their comedies,
					<quote rend="blockquote">By earth, by founts, by rivers, and by floods,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 128, no. 296. For Demosthenes' metrical oath here parodied see <hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, chap. vii.</note>
               </quote>
					for it was by swearing in this way that he had caused
					an uproar in the assembly. He used also to swear by
					Asclepius, putting the accent on the third syllable
					from the end, though it is properly on the final
					syllable ; and he offered, a proof that he was right, for
					he said that the god was <q direct="unspecified">mild</q> (<hi rend="italics">epios</hi>). For this
					also he often provoked a clamour from the audience.
					But by going to school to Eubulides the Milesian
					philosopher he corrected all his faults. Once when
					he was at the Olympic festival and heard Lamachus
					of Tereina reading a eulogy of Philip and Alexander
					fand decrying the Thebans and Olynthians, he stood
					up and quoted the words of the ancient poets testifying to the glorious deeds of the Thebans and Olynthians,
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.421"/>
					
					
					with the result that Lamachus was silenced
					and fled from the festival. And Philip said to those
					who reported to him the public speeches of Demosthenes against him, <q direct="unspecified">I myself, if I had heard
						Demosthenes speak, would have elected the man
						general to carry on the war against me.</q> And Philip
					used to say that Demosthenes' speeches were like
					soldiers because of their warlike power, but those of
					Isocrates were like athletes, because they afforded
					pleasure like that of a show.
				</p>
            <p>
					When he was thirty-seven years old, reckoning
					from the archonship of Dexitheus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">385-384 b.c.</note> to that of Callimachus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">349-348 b.c.</note> who was in office when an embassy came from
					the Olynthians asking for help because they were
					being hard pressed by Philip in the war, he persuaded
					the Athenians to send the help ; but in the following
					year, in which Plato died,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">348-347 b.c.</note> Philip overthrew the
					Olynthians. Xenophon, the follower of Socrates,
					knew him either in his youth or in his prime ; for
					Xenophon's <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi> ended with the battle of
					Mantineia and the archonship of Charicles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">363-362 b.c.</note> and
					Demosthenes had already before that time, in the
					archonship of Timocrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">324-323 b.c.</note> caused the conviction of
					his guardians. When Aeschines fled after his condemnation,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschines brought a suit on grounds of illegality against Ctesiphon, who proposed in 336 b.c. that Demosthenes be honoured by the city with a golden crown. The case was tried in 330 b.c., when Aeschines delivered his oration <hi rend="italics">Against Ctesiphon</hi> and Demosthenes his oration <hi rend="italics">On the Crown</hi>. Aeschines received less than one-fifth of the votes of the dicasts, and was therefore condemned to pay a fine of 1000 drachmas and to forfeit the right to bring any similar suit.</note> he followed him on horseback, and
					Aeschines, thinking he was arresting him, fell at his
					feet and covered his head, but Demosthenes raised
					him up, encouraged him, and gave him a talent of
					silver. And he advised the people to support a force
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.423"/>
					
					
					of mercenaries at Thasos, and sailed out as commander
					of a trireme on that occasion. After he had been in
					charge of the food supply he was accused of embezzlement but was acquitted. When Philip had taken
					Elateia Demosthenes himself went out with those
					who fought at Chaeroneia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 338 b.c., when Philip destroyed the independence of Greece.</note> on which occasion it
					appears that he deserted his post, and that, as he was
					running away, a bramble-bush caught his cloak,
					whereupon he turned and said, <q direct="unspecified">Take me alive.</q>
					And he had as a device on his shield the words <q direct="unspecified">With
						good fortune.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apparently a jest in connexion with the story of his cowardice.</note> However, he delivered the funeral
					address for those who fell.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This indicates that he had not disgraced himself.</note> And after that, directing
					his efforts to the improvement of the city and being
					elected commissioner in charge of the fortifications,
					he contributed out of his own pocket the funds expended, amounting to one hundred minae ; he also
					presented ten thousand drachmas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On these contributions <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aeschines, iii. (<hi rend="italics">Against Ctesiphon</hi>) 17, and Demosthenes, xviii. (<hi rend="italics">On the Crown</hi>) 118.</note> for sacred envoys,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Delegations sent to sacred places to attend festivals and the like.</note>
					and he made a cruise in a trireme to the allied cities
					collecting money. For these activities he was
					crowned many times, on earlier occasions on motions
					offered by Demomeles, Aristonicus, and Hypereides
					with golden crowns, and the last time on the motion
					of Ctesiphon ; and when the decree granting this
					honour was attacked as illegal by Diodotus and
					Aeschines, he was so successful in his defence that the
					accuser did not receive one-fifth of the votes.
				</p>
            <p>
					And at a later time, when Alexander was campaigning in Asia and Harpalus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Harpalus, treasurer of Alexander, embezzled a large sum and fled first to Tarsus, then, in 324 b.c., to Greece.</note> came fleeing to Athens
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.425"/>
					
					
					with money, at first Demosthenes kept him from
					being admitted, but after he had entered the harbour,
					Demosthenes accepted one thousand darics and
					changed his attitude, and when the Athenians wished
					to surrender the man to Antipater, he spoke against
					it and made a motion that Harpalus deposit the money
					on the Acropolis without even stating the amount to
					the people ; and although Harpalus stated that he
					had brought with him seven hundred talents, that
					which was taken up to the Acropolis was found to
					amount to only three hundred and fifty or a little
					more, as Philochorus says. And after this, when
					Harpalus escaped from the prison in which he was
					being kept until a representative of Alexander should
					arrive, and had gone to Crete or, as some say, to
					Taenarum in Laconia, Demosthenes was accused of
					bribe-taking and of having this reason for not mentioning the amount of the money taken up or the
					carelessness of the guard. He was brought to trial
					by Hypereides, Pytheas, Menesaechmus, Himeraeus,
					and Patrocles, and they obtained his conviction by
					the Senate of the Areopagus ; and after his conviction he went into exile, not being able to pay back
					five times the amount (he was accused of having
					accepted thirty talents), or, as some say, he did not
					wait for the trial. After this time the Athenians
					sent Polyeuctus as envoy to the commonwealth of the
					Arcadians in order to detach them from their alliance
					with the Macedonians, and when Polyeuctus was
					unable to persuade them, Demosthenes appeared to
					help him and did persuade them. For this he was
					admired, and after some time he was permitted to
					return, a decree in his favour having been passed
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.427"/>
					
					
					and a trireme dispatched to bring him. When the
					Athenians passed a decree proposed by his cousin
					Demon of Paeania that he should use the thirty
					talents which he owed in adorning the altar of Zeus
					the Saviour at Peiraeus and should then be absolved,
					he returned on those conditions to public life.
				</p>
            <p>
					When Antipater was shut up in Lamia by the
					Greeks, and the Athenians were making thankofferings for the good news, he said to his friend
					Agesistratus that he did not agree with the rest about
					these matters, <q direct="unspecified">for,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">I know that the
						Greeks have both the knowledge and the strength
						for a stadium dash<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A stadium was about equal to a furlong and was the usual short-distance run. The <hi rend="italics">dolichos</hi> was twenty stadia.</note> in warfare, but cannot hold out
						for a long-distance run.</q> When Antipater had taken
					Pharsalus and threatened to besiege the Athenians
					unless they surrendered the orators, Demosthenes
					left the city and fled first to Aegina to sit as suppliant
					in the sanctuary of Aeacus, but was frightened and
					changed over to Calauria; and when the Athenians
					voted to surrender the orators including himself, he
					took his seat as a suppliant there in the temple of
					Poseidon. And when Archias,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This Archias was a tragic actor recorded as victor at the Lenaea <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 330 b.c. in <hi rend="italics">I.G.</hi> ii.<hi rend="super">2</hi> 2325 n. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, chap. xxviii. names several other prominent Athenians <q direct="unspecified">hunted down</q> by him, among them Hypereides. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> p. 441 below. Another version of Demosthenes' retort to Archias is given <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> 29.</note> nicknamed <q direct="unspecified">ExileHunter,</q> who had been a pupil of the orator Anaximenes, came to fetch him and urged him to leave his
					sanctuary, indicating that Antipater would receive
					him as a friend, he said, <q direct="unspecified">Your acting in tragedy was
						not convincing to me, nor will your advice be convincing now</q> ; and when Archias tried to use force,
					the authorities of the city prevented him, and Demosthenes
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.429"/>
					
					
					said, <q direct="unspecified">I took refuge in Calauria, not to save
						my life, but to convict the Macedonians of using force
						even against the sanctuaries of the gods,</q> and asking
					for writing materials he wrote - so Demetrius of
					Magnesia says - the distich which was later inscribed
					by the Athenians upon his statue :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Had you possessed but the strength, Demosthenes, like to
					your spirit;
					</l>
                  <l>Never would Macedon's war Greece to submission have
					brought.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 331.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					The statue, a work of Polyeuctus, is placed near the
					Roped-off Enclosure<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This was a large area in the Market Place which was enclosed at ostracisms, and perhaps at other times, within a barrier of rope for the better control of the popular assembly. Since the contiguous altar of the Twelve Gods has recently (<hi rend="italics">vide</hi> Shear in <hi rend="italics">Hesperia</hi>, iv. pp. 355 ff.) been uncovered in the northern part of the Agora, this enclosure can no longer, with Judeich (<hi rend="italics">Topographie von Athen</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">2</hi>, p. 250), be placed in the south-west area, on the slopes of the Areopagus.</note> and the altar of the Twelve
					Gods. But according to some authorities he was
					found to have written <q direct="unspecified">Demosthenes to Antipater,
						greeting.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These were the words usually employed at the beginning of letters.</note> Philochorus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> i. p. 407.</note> says that he died by
					drinking poison, but Satyrus the historian says that
					the pen with which he began to write the letter was
					poisoned, and he died by sucking it; and Eratosthenes says that for a long time he wore a poisoned
					bracelet on his arm through fear of the Macedonians.
					There are those who say that he died by holding his
					breath, but others assert that it was by sucking poison
					from his seal ring. He lived, according to those who
					give the higher number, seventy years, according to
					those who giye the lower, sixty-seven. He was active
					in politics twenty-two years.
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.431"/>
					
				        </p>
            <p>
					When Philip died,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">336 b.c.</note> Demosthenes came out from
					his house dressed in a white garment, in spite of the
					fact that his daughter had lately died, thus showing his joy at the death of the Macedonian.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See <hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, chap. xxii.</note> He
					also assisted the Thebans when they were at war
					with Alexander, and he always encouraged the rest
					of the Greeks ; for which reason Alexander after
					razing Thebes demanded him of the Athenians and
					threatened them if they should refuse to surrender
					him. And when Alexander was making war on the
					Persians and called upon the Athenians for a naval
					force, he spoke against it, saying that it was not clear
					whether Alexander would not employ the force
					against those who furnished it.
				</p>
            <p>
					He left two sons by one wife of noble family,
					daughter of a certain Heliodorus ; and he had one
					daughter who died unmarried while still a child. He
					had also a sister to whom and her husband Laches of
					Leucono&euml; his nephew Demochares was born, a man
					both brave in war and inferior to none in political
					speeches. There is a statue of him in the Prytaneum,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Prytaneum was the building in which the Prytanes who formed the executive committee of the Senate held their meetings. Maintenance in the Prytaneum was often voted in recognition of service to the state.</note>
					the first on the right as you go in towards the hearth,
					wearing both a cloak and a sword ; for he is said to
					have worn this costume in addressing the people when
					Antipater was demanding the surrender of the
					orators. At a later time the Athenians voted maintenance in the Prytaneum to the relatives of Demosthenes and erected to him after his death the statue
					in the Market-place,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See above, 847 a.</note> in the archonship of Gorgias.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">280-279 b.c.</note>
					The grants to him were requested by his nephew
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.433"/>
					
					
					Demochares, for whom in turn his son Laches, son
					of Demochares, of Leucono&ecirc;, asked in the archonship
					of Pytharatus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">271-270 b.c.</note> the tenth year after, for grants
					extending to the erection of the statue in the Market-place, maintenance in the Prytaneum for Demochares
					and his eldest descendant in perpetuity, and front
					seats at all competitive spectacles. And the decrees
					in favour of both are inscribed, but the statue of
					Demochares mentioned above was transferred to the
					Prytaneum.
				</p>
            <p>
					Sixty-five genuine speeches of Demosthenes are
					current. Some say that he lived a dissolute life,
					wearing women's clothes and indulging in revels on
					every occasion, on which account he was nicknamed
					Batalus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschines, i. (<hi rend="italics">Against Timarchus</hi>) 131. The nickname is also said to refer to his stammering.</note>; but others say that this was a diminutive
					derived from the name of his nurse and was given to
					him in reproach. And Diogenes the Cynic, seeing
					him once in a tavern looking ashamed and trying to
					withdraw from sight, said, <q direct="unspecified">The more you withdraw,
						the more you will be in the tavern.</q> And he jeered
					at him, saying that in his speeches he was a Scythian,
					but in battle a city man. He received money from
					Ephialtes also, one of the politicians, who had been
					on an embassy to the King of Persia and came
					secretly bringing funds for distribution among the
					politicians for the purpose of stirring up the war
					against Philip ; and they say that he received a
					private bribe of three thousand darics from the King.
					He arrested a certain Anaxilas of Oreus, who had been
					a guest-friend of his, subjected him to torture as a
					spy, and when he confessed nothing proposed a decree
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.435"/>
					
					
					that he be handed over to the executioners. And
					once when he was being prevented by the Athenians
					from speaking in the assembly, he said that he only
					wished to speak briefly to them, and when they became silent he said, <q direct="unspecified">A young man in the summer
						time hired an ass to go from the city to Megara.
						When noon came and the sun was blazing fiercely,
						both he and the owner of the ass wished to lie down
						in its shadow. Each tried to prevent the other from
						so doing, the owner maintaining that he had rented
						him the ass, not its shadow, and the one who had hired
						the ass that he had complete rights in him.</q> When
					he had said this, he began to go away ; and when the
					Athenians stopped him and asked him to tell the rest
					of the tale, he said, <q direct="unspecified">You are willing to listen when
						I speak about the shadow of an ass,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">An ass's shadow</q> was proverbial for things utterly trivial.</note> but when I speak
						of serious matters, you refuse.</q> Once when Polus
					the actor told him that he received a talent as pay
					for acting two days, he replied, <q direct="unspecified">And I five talents
						for being silent one day.</q> And when his voice failed
					in the assembly and the people jeered at him, he said
					<q direct="unspecified">It is actors who should be judged by their voices,
						but statesmen by their opinions.</q> And when Epicles
					rebuked him for always preparing his speeches, he
					said, <q direct="unspecified">I should be ashamed to speak off-hand to such
						a great people.</q> They say that he never put out his
					lamp until he was fifty years old - polishing his
					speeches. And he says himself that he was a waterdrinker.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Demosthenes, vi. (<hi rend="italics">Second Philippic</hi>) 30; xix. (<hi rend="italics">False Legation</hi>) 46.</note> Lysias the orator was acquainted with
					him, and Isocrates saw him engaged in public affairs
					until the battle of Chaeroneia, as did some of the
					Socratic philosophers. He delivered most of his
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.437"/>
					
					
					speeches extemporaneously, as he was well endowed
					for that by nature.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This does not agree with what has been said above about his preparing all his speeches.</note> The first who moved that he be
					crowned with a crown of gold was Aristonicus of
					Anagyrus, son of Nicophanes, but Diondas prevented
					it by an affidavit.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>IX. HYPEREIDES</head>
            <p>
					Hypereides was the son of Glaucippus and grandson of Dionysius, of the deme of Collyt&ecirc;. He had a
					son, Glaucippus, named after his grandfather, who
					was an orator and writer of speeches.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the Athenian courts of law the parties to a suit were obliged to speak in person, therefore those who were not sure of their own ability hired others to write their speeches, which they learned by heart and delivered.</note> He in turn
					had a son Alphinous. After being a pupil of the
					philosopher Plato, along with Lycurgus, and of the
					orator Isocrates, Hypereides entered upon public life
					at Athens at the time when Alexander was interfering in the affairs of Greece. And he spoke in
					opposition to him concerning the generals whose
					surrender he demanded of the Athenians and concerning the triremes. He also advised against
					disbanding the mercenary force at Taenarum under
					the command of Chares, since he was well disposed
					towards that general. At first he pleaded in suits at
					law in return for a fee. And since he was believed to
					have shared the Persian funds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The comic poets of the time were very free with such insinuations, <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Timocles in his <hi rend="italics">Delos</hi> (Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 432) mentions both Demosthenes and Hypereides.</note> with Ephialtes, and
					was elected trierarch when Philip was besieging
					Byzantium, he was sent out to aid the Byzantines ;
					and in that year he bore the expense of a chorus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Such offices or <q direct="unspecified">liturgies</q> were imposed upon wealthy men only, and the fact that he undertook one may have led to the belief that he partook of the Persian funds, or that belief may have led to the imposition of the offices.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.10.p.439"/>
					
					
					when others were released from all contributions to the
					public service. He also proposed honours for Demosthenes, and when suit was brought by Diondas on the
					ground that the decree was contrary to law, he was
					acquitted. Although he was a friend of Demosthenes, Lysicles, Lycurgus, and their associates, he
					did not remain so to the end ; but when Lysicles and
					Lycurgus were dead and Demosthenes was being
					tried for receiving bribes from Harpalus, he was
					chosen from all the orators (for he alone was unbribed)
					and brought the accusation against him. And when
					he was brought to trial by Aristogeiton for illegal
					conduct in proposing a decree after the battle of
					Chaeroneia to grant citizenship to the resident aliens,
					to set the slaves free, and to put the sacred objects,
					the children, and the women in Peiraeus for safekeeping, he was acquitted. And when certain
					persons blame d him for having disregarded many laws
					in his decree, he said, <q direct="unspecified">The shields of the Macedonians cast a shadow<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The shadow of the shields made him fail to see the laws (taking <foreign lang="greek">parido/nta</foreign> literally).</note> over my eyes,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">It was
						not I, but the battle of Chaeroneia, that proposed the
						decree.</q> After this, however, Philip was frightened
					and granted permission to remove the bodies of the
					slain, though before that he had refused it to the
					heralds who came from Lebadeia. Later, however,
					after the battle of Crannon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">After the death of Alexander the Great the Greeks revolted, but they lacked leadership, and when they were defeated in an engagement at Crannon, Thessaly, in August 322 b.c., the Greek states came to terms separately with Antipater.</note> when his surrender was
					demanded by Antipater and the people was on the
					point of surrendering him, he fled from the city to
					Aegina along with those against whom decrees had
					been passed. Here he met Demosthenes and excused
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.441"/>
					
					
					himself for his disagreement with him. After leaving
					Aegina he was seized forcibly by Archias,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See above, p. 427, note <hi rend="italics">b</hi>.</note> nicknamed
					<q direct="unspecified">The Exile-Hunter</q> (a Thurian by birth, at first an
					actor, but at that time an assistant of Antipater), in
					the temple of Poseidon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At Hermion&ecirc;.</note> while clinging to the statue
					of the god. He was brought to Antipater at Corinth,
					and when put to the torture he bit off his tongue that
					he might not be able to utter any secrets of his native
					city. And in this way he died, on the ninth day of the
					month of Pyanepsion. But Hermippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> i. p. 50.</note> says that he
					went to Macedonia, where his tongue was cut out and
					he was thrown out unburied, and that Alphinous, who
					was his cousin (or, as some say, the son of his son
					Glaucippus), obtained possession of the body by the
					aid of a physician named Philopeithes, burned it and
					brought the bones to Athens to his relatives contrary
					to the decrees of the Athenians and the Macedonians;
					for they had ordered, not only that he be exiled, but
					that he be not even buried in his own country. And
					others say that he died at Cleonae after being brought
					there with the rest, where his tongue was cut out and
					he perished in the manner related above ; and that
					his relatives obtained the bones and buried them with
					his ancestors before the gates of the Hippades,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At Athens, probably south-east from the Acropolis.</note> as
					Heliodorus says in the third book of his work <hi rend="italics">On
					Monuments</hi>. But now the monument has fallen in
					ruins and cannot be identified.
				</p>
            <p>
					He is said to have excelled all in addressing the
					people ; and by some critics he is ranked above
					Demosthenes. Seventy-seven speeches are current
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.443"/>
					
					
					under his name, fifty-two of which are genuine.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Only small fragments of these were preserved until, at various times in the nineteenth century, six more or less complete orations were discovered in Egyptian papyrus manuscripts.</note> He
					was also very prone to sexual indulgence, so that he
					turned his son out of the house and brought in
					Myrrhina, the most expensive prostitute, kept Aristagora in Peiraeus, and at his own estate in Eleusis kept
					the Theban girl Phila, whom he had ransomed for
					twenty minas. He used to walk in the Fish-market
					every day.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Another comic gibe against a public man supposed to be a gourmand. Athenaeus viii. 341 ff. quotes from the <hi rend="italics">Delos</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Icarians</hi> of Timocles gossip of this kind against Hypereides.</note> And, as it is indeed reasonable to
					suppose, it was because he had been intimate also
					with Phryn&ecirc;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The traditional text is certainly corrupt; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> critical notes. The inference seems to have been drawn from the orator's amatory record that his advocacy of Phryn&ecirc; at her famous trial was due to an intimacy with her. An advocate was never <q direct="unspecified">examined with</q> the defendant.</note> the courtesan that when she was on
					trial for impiety he became her advocate ; for he
					makes this plain himself at the beginning of his
					speech.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Explained by Athenaeus xiii. 590 d <foreign lang="greek">e)n tw=| u(pe\r *fru/nhs lo/gw| *(uperei/dhs o(mologw=n e)ra=n th=s gunaiko/s</foreign>. Hypereides' speech was translated into Latin by Messala Corvinus (Quintilian x. 5. 2).</note> And when she was likely to be found
					guilty, he led the woman out into the middle of the
					court and, tearing off her clothes, displayed her
					breasts. When the judges saw her beauty, she was
					acquitted.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This version is foudn also in Athenaeus xiii. 590 e, but the comic poet Poseidippus in his <hi rend="italics">Ephesian Lady</hi> (<hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> 591 e; Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 339) attributes Phryn&ecirc;'s acquittal to her own arts.</note> He quietly compiled accusations against
					Demosthenes and the fact became known ; for once,
					when he was ill, Demosthenes came to his house to
					visit him and found him with the document against
					himself in his hand ; and when Demosthenes was
					angry, Hypereides said, <q direct="unspecified">It will do you no harm
						while you are my friend, but if you become my
						enemy, it will prevent your doing anything against
						
						<pb id="v.10.p.445"/>
						
						me.</q> He also proposed a decree conferring honours
					upon Iolas, who was supposed to have given Alexander
					the poison.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The belief that Alexander died of poison was apparently unfounded.</note> He took part with Leosthenes in the
					Lamian War<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In 323-322 b.c. after Alexander's death, when the Greeks under Leosthenes besieged the Macedonian Antipater in Lamia near Thermopylae. A large part of Hypereides' funeral oration is preserved.</note> and delivered the funeral oration for
					the fallen in marvellous fashion. When Philip was
					preparing to sail against Euboea, and the Athenians
					were afraid, he assembled forty triremes by private
					contributions, and in his own name and his son's he
					gave two triremes, the first contribution made. And
					when a dispute arose with the Delians as to which
					people should have control of the sanctuary, although
					Aeschines was chosen Athenian advocate, the senate
					of the Areopagus elected Hypereides ; and his speech
					is the one entitled <hi rend="italics">The Delian</hi>. He was also an envoy
					to the Rhodians. And when envoys came from
					Antipater and praised their sender as a good man, in
					replying to them he said, <q direct="unspecified">We know that he is good,
						but we do not want a good master.</q> It is said that
					in addressing the public he did not employ the
					actor's art, that he merely related the facts of the case
					and did not bore the jurors even with these. He was
					sent also to the Eleans to defend the athlete Callippus against the charge of having used corruption in
					the contest, and he won his case; but when he
					brought a suit against the grant of a gift for Phocion,
					which Meidias, son of Meidias, of the deme Anagyros,
					proposed in the archonship of Xenias,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An archon Xenias is unknown. Euxenippus, suggested by Schafer, was archon in 305-304 b.c., but Hypereides was then dead. Possibly the archon Archias, 346-345 b.c., is intended, in which case the gift for Phocion may have had some connexion with the battle of Tamynae.</note> on the twentyfourth day of Gamelion, he was defeated.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.447"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>X. DEINARCHUS</head>
            <p>
					Deinarchus, son of Socrates or Sostratus, an
					Athenian according to some, but, as others think, a
					Corinthian, came to Athens while still young at the
					time when Alexander was invading Asia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">334-323 b.c.</note> settled
					there, and became a pupil of Theophrastus, who had
					succeeded Aristotle as head of his School<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Lyceum, <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Peripatetic School.</note>; but he
					also attended the lectures of Demetrius of Phalerum.
					He took part most actively in public affairs after the
					death of Antipater,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">318 b.c.</note> since some of the public men
					had been put to death and the rest were in exile.
					Since he became a friend of Cassander he prospered
					exceedingly through the fees he charged for the
					speeches which he wrote for those who requested his
					services ; and he had as his opponents the most
					distinguished public men, although he did not speak
					before the popular assembly (for he was unable to
					do so<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">If he was a Corinthian by birth, he would be debarred from such speaking.</note>); but he merely wrote speeches for their
					opponents. And when Harpalus absconded he composed many speeches against those who were accused
					of having accepted bribes from him, and these he
					furnished to their accusers. But at a later time he
					was accused of having dealings with Antipater and
					Cassander in connexion with their occupation of
					Munichia when it was garrisoned by Antigonus and
					Demetrius in the archonship of Anaxicrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">307-306 b.c.</note> whereupon he turned most of his property into cash and
					went into exile at Chalcis. And after living in exile
					about fifteen years and amassing considerable wealth,
					he returned, his restoration, and at the same time
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.449"/>
					
					
					that of the other exiles, having been effected by
					Theophrastus and his friends. He lodged at the
					house of a friend of his named Proxenus and lost his
					money, when he was already an old man and his
					eyes were weak, and when Proxenus refused to investigate the matter<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Evidently Deinarchus suspected theft or fraud.</note> he brought a suit against him,
					and then for the first time he spoke in a court of law.
					His speech is extant, too.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Only a fragment of this speech is extant.</note> There are sixty-four
					speeches of his extant which are regarded as genuine ;
					of these some are handed down as by Aristogeiton.
					He was a zealous follower of Hypereides or, as
					some say on account of his emotional and vehement
					qualities, of Demosthenes. He certainly is an imitator
					of the latter's figures of speech.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>DECREES<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the following documents, called in the manuscripts <q direct="unspecified">Decrees,</q> see the Introduction to these <hi rend="italics">Lives</hi>, p. 342 above.</note> I</head>
            <p>
					Demochares<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Apparently the son of the Laches, son of Demochares, mentioned above, 847 d, that is, the orator's nephew.</note> of Leucono&ecirc;, son of Laches, asks for
					Demosthenes of Paeania, son of Demosthenes, the grant of
					a bronze statue in the Market-place and maintenance in
					the Prytaneum and the privilege of front seats at the public
					spectacles for him and for the eldest of his descendants in
					perpetuity, because he has shown himself as a public benefactor and counsellor, and has brought about many benefits
					for the people of the Athenians, not only having relinquished
					his property for the common weal but also having contributed
					eight talents and a trireme when the people freed Euboea,
					and another trireme when Cephisodorus sailed to the Hellespont, and another when Chares and Phocion were sent as
					generals to Byzantium by the vote of the popular assembly,
					and having ransomed many of those who were taken prisoners
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.451"/>
					
					
					by Philip at Pydna, Methon&ecirc;, and Olynthus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">356, 353, and 348 b.c.</note> and having
					contributed the expense of a chorus of men because when
					the members of the tribe of Pandionis failed to furnish this
					chorus, he contributed the money and, besides, furnished
					arms to the citizens who lacked them ; and when elected
					Commissioner of the Fortifications by the popular assembly
					he supplied the money for the work, himself contributing
					three talents in addition to the cost of two trenches about
					the Peiraeus, which he dug as his contribution. And after
					the battle of Chaeroneia he contributed a talent, and in the
					scarcity of food he contributed a talent for the food-supply.
					And because, through persuasion, benefactions, and the
					advice by which he moved them, he brought into alliance with
					the people the Thebans, Euboeans, Corinthians, Megarians,
					Achaeans, Locrians, Byzantines, and Messenians and gained
					troops for the people and its allies, namely ten thousand
					foot, one thousand horse, and a contribution of money which
					he as envoy persuaded the allies to give for the war - more
					than five hundred talents - and because he prevented the
					Peloponnesians from going to the aid of the Boeotians, giving
					money and going in person as envoy. And he advised the
					people to adopt many other excellent measures, and of all his
					contemporaries he performed the best public actions in the
					cause of liberty and democracy. And having been exiled by
					the oligarchy when the democracy had been destroyed, and
					having died at Calauria on account of his devotion to the
					democracy, when soldiers were sent against him by Antipater,
					persisting in his loyalty and devotion to the democracy and
					neither surrendering to its enemies nor doing anything in his
					time of danger that was unworthy of the democracy.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>DECREES II</head>
            <p>
					Archon Pytharatus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">271-270 b.c. See above, pp. 431 f., where the same facts are given.</note> Laches, son of Demochares, of
					Leucono&ecirc;, asks from the senate and people of the Athenians
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.453"/>
					
					
					for Demochares, son of Laches, of Leucono&ecirc;, a grant of a
					bronze statue in the Market-place, and maintenance in the
					Prytaneum for him and the eldest of his descendants in
					perpetuity, and the privilege of a front seat at all public
					spectacles, because he proved himself a benefactor and a good
					counsellor to the people of the Athenians and benefited the
					people as follows: He was a good ambassador, proposer
					of legislation, and statesman [. . . , and he superintended]
					the building of the walls and the preparation of armour,
					missiles, and engines of war, he fortified the city at the time
					of the four years' war<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">294-290 b.c. The war ended with the surrender of Athens to Demetrius Poliorcetes.</note> and made peace, truce, and alliance
					with the Boeotians, in return for which he was banished by
					those who overthrew the democracy. When he was recalled
					by the people in the archonship of Diocles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">288-287 b.c.</note> he first reduced
					the expenses of the administration and was sparing of the
					public resources; he went as envoy to Lysimachus and
					secured for the people thirty talents of silver and again one
					hundred more ; he proposed the sending of an embassy to
					Ptolemy in Egypt, and those who took part in it brought
					back for the people fifty talents of silver; he was envoy to
					Antipater and secured twenty talents of silver which he
					brought to Eleusis for the people. He won the assent of the
					people to all these measures and accomplished them ; he was
					exiled for the sake of the democracy, he took no part in any
					oligarchy, he held no office after the democracy had been
					overthrown, and he was the only Athenian of those who were
					engaged in public life in his time who never plotted to alter
					the government of the country by changing it to a form other
					than democracy; he made the decisions of the courts, the
					laws, the courts, and property, safe for all Athenians by
					the policy he pursued, and he never did anything adverse to
					the democracy by word or deed.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.10.p.455"/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>DECREES III</head>
            <p>
					Lycophron, son of Lycurgus, of the deme Butadae, presented in writing a claim for maintenance in the Prytaneum
					for himself in accordance with the gift presented by the
					people to Lycurgus of the deme Butadae. In the archonship
					of Anaxicrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">307-306 b.c. Much of the substance of this document is contained in the <hi rend="italics">Life</hi> of Lycurgus, see pp. 395 ff. above.</note> in the sixth prytany, that of the tribe
					Antiochis, Stratocles, son of Euthydemus, of the deme
					Diomeia, made the following motion: Whereas Lycurgus,
					son of Lycophron, of the deme Butadae, having inherited
					from early times from his ancestors that loyalty to the
					democracy which has been peculiar to his family, and the
					progenitors of Lycurgus, Lycomedes and Lycurgus, were
					not only honoured by the people during their lives, but also
					after their death the people granted them for their courage
					and virtue public burials in the Cerameicus ; and whereas
					Lycurgus himself during his public career made many
					excellent laws for his country, and when he was treasurer of
					the public revenues of the city for three periods of four years
					distributed from the public revenue eighteen thousand nine
					hundred talents ; and having received in trust large funds
					from private citizens, from which he made loans previously
					agreed upon in order to meet the exigencies of the city
					and the people, in all six hundred and fifty talents ; and,
					because he was believed to have administered all these funds
					justly, was often crowned by the State ; and whereas when
					chosen by the people he brought together large sums of
					money upon the Acropolis, providing adornment for the
					Goddess, solid gold Victories, gold and silver vessels for the
					processions, and ornaments of gold for one hundred basket-carriers,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Maidens of good birth who carried baskets of offerings in the processions.</note> and when chosen to be in charge of the equipment for
					the war he brought to the Acropolis many pieces of armour
					and fifty thousand missiles and fitted out four hundred
					triremes ready to set sail, providing the equipment for some
					of them and causing some to be built from the beginning;
					
					<pb id="v.10.p.457"/>
					
					
					and besides all this he finished the ship-sheds and the arsenal,
					which were half done when they came into his hands, and
					completed the Panathenaic stadium and erected the gymnasium at the Lyceum, and adorned the city with many
					other edifices. And when King Alexander, after overthrowing all Asia, assumed to give orders to all the Greeks in
					common and demanded that Lycurgus be surrendered because
					he was acting in opposition to him, the city did not surrender
					him in spite of fear of Alexander. And although he had
					many times submitted his accounts while the city was free
					and had a democratic form of government, he never was
					convicted of wrongdoing or of taking bribes through all his
					career. Therefore, that all may know that those who choose
					to act justly in public life in behalf of democracy and freedom
					are held in the highest esteem while living and receive after
					death enduring gratitude: With good Fortune: Be it resolved
					by the people to commend Lycurgus, son of Lycophron, of
					the deme Butadae, for his virtue and justice, and to set up
					a bronze statue of him in the Market-place, only not in
					any place where the law forbids its erection, and to grant
					maintenance in the Prytaneum to the eldest descendant of
					Lycurgus for all time, and that all his decrees be valid, and
					that the secretary of the people inscribe them on stone
					tablets arid place them on the Acropolis near the dedicatory
					offerings; and that the treasurer of the people give for
					inscribing the tablets fifty drachmas from the funds expended
					by the people for decrees.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>