<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De esu carnium I</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1957</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v.12.p.537"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>ON THE EATING OF FLESH (DE ESU CARNIUM) I <lb/> INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					These two badly mutilated discourses, urging the
					necessity for vegetarianism, are merely extracts
					from a series (see 996 a) which Plutarch delivered in
					his youth, perhaps to a Boeotian audience (995 e).<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This was Hirzel's opinion (<hi rend="italics">Der Dialog</hi>, ii, p. 126, n. 2), which Ziegler (<hi rend="italics">RE, s.v.</hi> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">Plutarchos,</q> col. 734) combats.</note>
					In spite of the exaggerated and calculated rhetoric<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">F. Krauss, <hi rend="italics">Die rhetorischen Schriften Plutarchs</hi>, pp. 77 ff.</note>
					these fragments probably depict faithfully a foible
					of Plutarch's early manhood, the Pythagorean or
					Orphic<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 782 c. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 159 c, makes Solon say, <q direct="unspecified">To refrain entirely from eating meat, as they record of Orpheus long ago, is rather a quibble than a way of avoiding wrong diet.</q>
               </note> abstention from animal food. There is
					little trace of this in his later life as known to us,
					though a corrupt passage in the <hi rend="italics">Symposiacs</hi> (635 e)
					seems to say that because of a dream our author
					abstained from eggs for a long time. In the <hi rend="italics">De
					Sanitate Tuenda</hi> also (132 a) Plutarch excuses flesh-eating on the ground that habit <q direct="unspecified">has become a sort
						of unnatural second nature.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The work appears, on the whole, rather immature
					beside the <hi rend="italics">Gryllus</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">De Sollertia Animalium</hi>,
					but the text is so poor that this may not be the
					author's fault. In fact the excerptor responsible for
					our jumbled text, introducing both stupid interpolations (see especially 998 a) and even an extract from
					an entirely different work (994 b-d), may well have
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.538"/>
					
					altered Plutarch's wording in many other places
					where we have not the means to detect him.
				</p>
            <p>
					Porphyry<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is, of course, possible that Porphyry used some portion of the missing parts of our work; but this cannot be proved and may even be thought unlikely in view of the fact that he makes no use of any extant portion.</note> (<hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 24) says that Plutarch attacked the Stoics and Peripatetics in many
					books; in this one the anti-Stoic polemic has only
					just begun (999 a) when the work breaks off. For a
					more complete assault the reader must turn back to
					the two preceding dialogues.
				</p>
            <p>
					It is interesting to learn that Shelley found these
					fragments inspiring. In the eighth book of <hi rend="italics">Queen
					Mab</hi> (verses 211 ff.) we read :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>No longer now
					</l>
                  <l>He slays the lamb that looks him in the face,
					</l>
                  <l>And horribly devours his mangled flesh,
					</l>
                  <l>Which, still avenging Nature's broken law,
					</l>
                  <l>Kindled all putrid humours in his frame,
					</l>
                  <l>All evil passions, and all vain belief, ...
					</l>
                  <l>The germs of misery, death, disease, and crime.</l>
               </quote>
					To this passage the poet appended, <hi rend="italics">more suo</hi>, a long
					note which ended with four quotations from our essay
					in Greek, untranslated (a compliment to the public
					of his day, one may suppose). This note he subsequently republished as <hi rend="italics">A Vindication of Natural Diet</hi>
					(1813), omitting the Greek ; and in the same year he
					wrote to Thomas Hogg that he had <q direct="unspecified">translated the
						two Essays of Plutarch, <foreign lang="greek">*peri\ sarkofagi/as</foreign>.</q> But this
					has been lost; it has not, at least, been found among
					the unpublished Shelley material in the Bodleian.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These facts I owe to the kindness of Professors J. A. Notopoulos of Trinity College and J. E. Jordan of the University of California; see also K. N. Cameron, <hi rend="italics">The Young Shelley</hi>, pp. 224 f.</note>
					
				        </p>
            <pb id="v.12.p.539"/>
            <p>
					This is one of the eighteen works of the received
					Corpus of Plutarch that do not appear in the Lamprias
					Catalogue. Such a fact is not, however, to be adduced against its genuineness, since the <hi rend="italics">Symposiacs</hi>
					themselves are not to be found there.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is important to observe that H. Fuchs, <hi rend="italics">Der geistige Widerstand gegen Rom</hi>, p. 49, n. 60, athetizes this work. A further discussion by this great critic would be warmly welcomed, especially since Wilamowitz recognized here also <q direct="unspecified">den unverkennbaren Stempel der plutarchischen Art.</q>
               </note>
					
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.12.p.541"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Can you really ask what reason Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 964 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					had for abstaining from flesh ? For my part I rather
					wonder both by what accident and in what state of
					soul or mind the first man<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 959 e <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> who did so, touched his
					mouth to gore and brought his lips to the flesh of a
					dead creature, he who set forth tables of dead, stale<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 991 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 995 c <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					bodies and ventured to call food and nourishment
					the parts that had a little before bellowed and cried,
					moved and lived. How could his eyes endure the
					slaughter when throats were slit and hides flayed and
					limbs torn from limb ? How could his nose endure
					the stench ? How was it that the pollution did not
					turn away his taste, which made contact with the sores
					of others and sucked juices and serums from mortal
					wounds ?
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The skins shivered ; and upon the spits the flesh bellowed,
					</l>
                  <l>Both cooked and raw ; the voice of kine was heard.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, xii. 395-396.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					Though this is an invention and a myth, yet that sort
					of dinner is really portentous - when a man craves the
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.543"/>
					
					meat that is still bellowing, giving instructions which
					tell us on what animals we are to feed while they are
					still alive uttering their cries, and organizing various
					methods of seasoning and roasting and serving. It
					is the man<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Hyperbius . . . first killed an animal, Prometheus an ox.</q> (Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> vii. 209.) See also the amusing analysis of Prometheus and the vulture (= disease) in Shelley's <hi rend="italics">A Vindication of Natural Diet</hi>.</note> who first began these practices that one
					should seek out, not him who all too late desisted.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pythagoras.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Or would everyone declare that the reason for
					those who first instituted flesh-eating was the necessity of their poverty ? It was not while they passed
					their time in unlawful desires nor when they had
					necessaries in abundance that after indulgence in
					unnatural and antisocial pleasures they resorted to
					such a practice. If, at this moment, they could recover feelings and voice, they might, indeed, remark : <q direct="unspecified">Oh blessed and beloved of the gods, you
						who live now, what an age has fallen to your lot
						wherein you enjoy and assimilate a heritage abounding in good things ! How many plants grow for you !
						What vintages you gather ! What wealth you may
						draw from the plains and what pleasant sustenance
						from trees ! Why, you may even live luxuriously
						without the stain of blood. But as for us, it was a
						most dismal and fearful portion of the world's history<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Empedocles, frag. B 2. 3 (Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 309); the whole passage is received as a doubtful fragment (B 154; i, pp. 371 f.).</note>
						that confronted us, falling as we did into great and
						unbearable poverty brought on by our first appearance among the living. As yet the heavens and the
						stars were concealed by dense air that was contaminated with turbid moisture, not easily to be
						penetrated, and fire and furious wind. Not yet was
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.545"/>
						
						the sun established undeviating
						<quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>In his firm course,
						</l>
                     <l>Dividing day and night; he brought them back
						</l>
                     <l>Again and crowned them with the fruitful hours
						</l>
                     <l>All wreathed with bloom, while violence</l>
                  </quote>
						had been done to earth by rivers pouring forth their
						floods at random and most parts were deformed by
						pools.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">You could not tell land from water, because invading water made pools that dried up later.</note> Earth was made a wilderness by deep quagmires and the unfruitful growth of thickets and
						forests ; nor was there as yet any agricultural production or professional tool or any resource of skill.
						Our hunger gave us no respite nor was there any
						seed at that time awaiting the annual season of
						sowing. What wonder if, contrary to nature, we
						made use of the flesh of beasts when even mud was
						eaten and the bark of trees devoured, and to light on
						sprouting grass or the root of a rush was a piece of
						luck ? When we had tasted and eaten acorns we
						danced for joy around some oak,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <q direct="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Drys</hi> was a term used especially for <hi rend="italics">Quercus robur</hi> L. <hi rend="italics">phegos</hi> for <hi rend="italics">Q. aegilops</hi> L. Actually the early Greeks ate the acorns mostly of <hi rend="italics">Q. aegilops</hi>.</q> (Andrews.)</note> calling it <q direct="unspecified">life-giving</q>
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The epithet properly meant <q direct="unspecified">wheat-giving</q> (as in Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, ii. 548), but was early misinterpreted.</note> and <q direct="unspecified">mother</q> and <q direct="unspecified">nurse.</q> This was the
						only festival that those times had discovered ; all
						else was a medley of anguish and gloom. But you
						who live now, what madness, what frenzy drives
						you to the pollution of shedding blood, you who
						have such a superfluity of necessities ? Why slander
						the earth by implying that she cannot support you ?
						Why impiously offend law-giving Demeter<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 1119 e.</note> and
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.547"/>
						
						bring shame upon Dionysus, lord of the cultivated
						vine,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 451 c (where the epithet is otherwise interpreted), 663 d, 692 e.</note> the gracious one, as if you did not receive
						enough from their hands ? Are you not ashamed to
						mingle domestic crops with blood and gore ? You
						call serpents and panthers and lions savage, but you
						yourselves, by your own foul slaughters, leave them
						no room to outdo you in cruelty ; for their slaughter
						is their living, yours is a mere appetizer.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As above in 991 d. See the interesting observations in G. Murray, <hi rend="italics">Rise of the Greek Epic</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">3</hi>, p. 64 and the note.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>It is certainly not lions and wolves that we eat
					out of self-defence ; on the contrary, we ignore these
					and slaughter harmless, tame creatures without
					stings or teeth to harm us, creatures that, I swear,
					Nature appears to have produced for the sake of
					their beauty and grace. . . . <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The rest of this chapter, though possibly by Plutarch, is probably from another quite different work. Chapter 4 follows quite naturally upon this sentence.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					[It is as though one, seeing the Nile overflow
					its banks, filling the landscape with its fertile and
					productive stream, should not marvel at this, its
					nourishing of plants and its fruitfulness in such crops
					as are most to be cultivated and contribute most
					to the support of life, but should espy a crocodile
					swimming there somewhere or an asp being swept
					along or a thousand other savage creatures and should
					cite them as the reasons for his censure and his
					compulsion to do as he does.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These words, plainly out of context as the passage stands, are too vague to be rendered with any certainty.</note> Or, I swear, it is as
					though one fixed ones gaze on this land and its soil
					covered with cultivated crops and heavy with ears
					of wheat, and then, looking beneath these rich
					harvests, one were to catch sight somewhere of a
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.549"/>
					
					growth of darnel or broom-rape and, without more
					ado, ceasing to reap the benefit and claim the booty
					of the good crops, burst into a tirade about the weeds.
					Another example : if one should see an orator
					making a speech at some trial where he was advocate,
					a speech in which his eloquence in full flood was advancing to the succour of someone in jeopardy or
					(so help me) to the conviction or denunciation of rash
					acts or defaults - a flood of eloquence not simple or
					jejune, but charged with many (or rather all kinds
					of) emotional appeals for the simultaneous influencing of the many different kinds of minds in the
					audience or jury, which must either be roused and
					won over or (by heaven !) soothed and made gentle
					and calm - then if one neglected to observe and take
					into account this main point and issue of the matter,
					but merely picked out flaws of style that the flood of
					oratory, as it moved to its goal, had swept along by
					the momentum of its current, flaws that came rushing
					out and slipped by with the rest - and seeing . . . of
					some popular leader. . . . <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The rest of this perplexing fragment has been lost, so that we do not know what the object of these three comparisons is.</note>]
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>But nothing abashed us, not the flower-like
					tinting of the flesh, not the persuasiveness of the
					harmonious voice, not the cleanliness of their habits
					or the unusual intelligence that may be found in the
					poor wretches. No, for the sake of a little flesh we
					deprive them of sun, of light, of the duration of life
					to which they are entitled by birth and being. Then
					we go on to assume that when they utter cries and
					squeaks their speech is inarticulate, that they do
					not, begging for mercy, entreating, seeking justice,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.551"/>
					
					each one of them say, <q direct="unspecified">I do not ask to be spared in
						ease of necessity; only spare me your arrogance!
						Kill me to eat, but not to please your palate!</q> Oh,
					the cruelty of it! What a terrible thing it is to look
					on when the tables of the rich are spread, men who
					employ cooks and spicers to groom the dead ! And
					it is even more terrible to look on when they are
					taken away, for more is left than has been eaten.
					So the beasts died for nothing! There are others who
					refuse when the dishes are already set before them
					and will not have them cut into or sliced. Though
					they bid spare the dead, they did not spare the
					living.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Post believes that there is another lacuna after this chapter; and Stephanus posited another one after the first sentence of chapter 5, rightly, if Bernardakis' emendation is not accepted.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>We declare, then, that it is absurd for them to
					say that the practice of flesh-eating is based on
					Nature. For that man is not naturally carnivorous
					is, in the first place, obvious from the structure of his
					body.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 988 e <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> and the note.</note> A man's frame is in no way similar to those
					creatures who were made for flesh-eating : he has
					no hooked beak or sharp nails or jagged teeth, no
					strong stomach or warmth of vital fluids able to
					digest and assimilate a heavy diet of flesh.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 87 b, 642 c.</note> It is
					from this very fact, the evenness of our teeth, the
					smallness of our mouths, the softness of our tongues,
					our possession of vital fluids too inert to digest meat
					that Nature disavows our eating of flesh. If you
					declare that you are naturally designed for such a
					diet, then first kill for yourself what you want to eat.
					Do it, however, only through your own resources,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.553"/>
					
					unaided by cleaver or cudgel of any kind or axe.
					Rather, just as wolves and bears and lions themselves
					slay what they eat, so you are to fell an ox with your
					fangs or a boar with your jaws, or tear a lamb or
					hare in bits. Fall upon it and eat it still living, as
					animals do.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Let the advocate of animal food force himself to a decisive experiment on its fitness, and, as Plutarch recommends, tear a living lamb with his teeth, and, plunging his head into its vitals, slake his thirst with the steaming blood</q> (Shelley, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi>).</note> But if you wait for what you eat to be
					dead, if you have qualms about enjoying the flesh
					while life is still present, why do you continue,
					contrary to nature, to eat what possesses life ? Even
					when it is lifeless and dead, however, no one eats the
					flesh just as it is ; men boil it and roast it, altering
					it by fire and drugs, recasting and diverting and
					smothering with countless condiments the taste of
					gore so that the palate may be deceived and accept
					what is foreign to it.
				</p>
            <p>
					It was, indeed, a witty remark of the Spartan<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 234 e-f, where it is meat, not fish, that is bought; see also 128 c.</note>
					who bought a little fish in an inn and gave it to the
					innkeeper to prepare. When the latter asked for
					cheese and vinegar and oil,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">To make a sauce for the fish. The innkeeper's action was natural enough, in view of Hegesander's comment (Athenaeus, 564 a) that apparently everyone liked the seasonings, not the fish, since no one wanted fish plain and unseasoned.</note> the Spartan said, <q direct="unspecified">If I
						had those, I should not have bought a fish.</q> But we
					are so refined in our blood-letting that we term flesh
					a supplementary food<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 991 d (and the note), 993 b, 994 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; and then we need <q direct="unspecified">supplements</q> for the flesh itself, mixing oil, wine, honey,
					fish paste, vinegar, with Syrian and Arabian spices,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 990 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					as though we were really embalming a corpse for
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.555"/>
					
					burial. The fact is that meat is so softened and
					dissolved and, in a way, predigested that it is hard
					for digestion to cope with it; and if digestion loses
					the battle, the meats affect us with dreadful pains
					and malignant forms of indigestion.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 956 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> where the context is quite different. See also Athenaeus, 341 e; Lucian, <hi rend="italics">Vit. Auctio</hi> 10; Julian, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi>, vi. 181 a, 191 c ff.; Diogenes Laertius, vi. 76; <hi rend="italics">al.</hi>
               </note> ventured to eat a raw octopus in
					order to put an end to the inconvenience of preparing
					cooked food. In the midst of a large throng he
					veiled his head and, as he brought the flesh to his
					mouth, said, <q direct="unspecified">It is for you that I am risking my life.</q>
					Good heavens, a wondrous fine risk! Just like
					Pelopidas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Pelopidas</hi>, chapters 7-11.</note> for the liberty of the Thebans or Harmodius and Aristogiton<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Thucydides, vi. 54-59.</note> for that of the Athenians,
					this philosopher risked his life struggling with a raw
					octopus - in order to brutalize our lives !
				</p>
            <p>
					Note that the eating of flesh is not only physically
					against nature, but it also makes us spiritually coarse
					and gross by reason of satiety and surfeit. <q direct="unspecified">For wine
						and indulgence in meat make the body strong and
						vigorous, but the soul weak.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A quotation from the medical writer Androcydes; see <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 472 b and the note.</note> And in order that I
					may not offend athletes, I shall take my own people as
					examples. It is a fact that the Athenians used to call
					us Boeotians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Rhys Roberts, <hi rend="italics">The Ancient Boeotians</hi>, pp. 1-5.</note> beef-witted and insensitive and foolish,
					precisely because we stuffed ourselves.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The passage that follows is badly mutilated: it probably contained other quotations and fuller ones than the mss. indicate.</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">These
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.557"/>
						
						men are swine</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the proverbial <q direct="unspecified">sow and Athena</q> (<hi rend="italics">Life of Demosthenes</hi>, xi. 5, 851 b and <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 803 d) and the Introduction to the <hi rend="italics">Gryllus</hi>.</note>; . . . and Menander<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii, p. 238 (frag. 748 Koerte); the words probably mean <q direct="unspecified">Who are greedy fellows.</q>
               </note> says, <q direct="unspecified">Who
							have jaws</q>; and Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Olympians</hi>, vi. 89, which continues <q direct="unspecified">whether we are truly arraigned by that ancient gibe, &lsquo;Boeotian swine.&rsquo;</q> (For this interpretation see G. Norwood, <hi rend="italics">Pindar</hi>, pp. 82 and 237.)</note> 
               <q direct="unspecified">And then to learn . . .</q>;
					<q direct="unspecified">A dry soul is wisest</q> according to Heraclitus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi> i, p. 100, frag. B 118; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the note on <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 432 f.</note>
					Empty jars make a noise when struck, but full
					ones do not resound to blows.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 721 b-d.</note> Thin bronze objects
					will pass the sounds from one to another in a circle
					until you dampen and deaden the noise with your
					hand as the beat goes round.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 721 c-d suggests that Plutarch is talking about a single cauldron with a wave going around it rather than about a circular arrangement of tuning forks. <q direct="unspecified">Sounding brass</q>: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> L. Parmentier, <hi rend="italics">Recherches sur l'Isis et Osiris</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Mem. Acad. Roy. Belg.</hi> ii, vol. II, 1912/13), pp. 31 ff.</note> The eye<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 714 d.</note> when it is
					flooded by an excess of moisture grows dim and
					weakened for its proper task. When we examine the
					sun through dank atmosphere and a fog of gross
					vapours, we do not see it clear and bright, but submerged and misty, with elusive rays. In just the
					same way, then, when the body is turbulent and surfeited and burdened with improper food, the lustre
					and light of the soul inevitably come through it
					blurred and confused, aberrant and inconstant, since
					the soul lacks the brilliance and intensity to penetrate to the minute and obscure issues of active life.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>But apart from these considerations, do you not
					find here a wonderful means of training in social
					responsibility ? Who could wrong a human being
					when he found himself so gently and humanely disposed
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.559"/>
					
					toward other non-human creatures ? Two days
					ago in a discussion I quoted the remark of Xenocrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Heinze, <hi rend="italics">Xenokrates</hi>, p. 151, frag. 99.</note> that the Athenians punished the man who
					had flayed a ram while it was still alive ; yet, as
					I think, he who tortures a living creature is no worse
					than he who slaughters it outright. But it seems
					that we are more observant of acts contrary to convention than of those that are contrary to nature. In
					that place, then, I made my remarks in a popular
					vein. I still hesitate, however, to attempt a discussion of the principle underlying my opinion, great as
					it is, and mysterious and incredible, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 245 c.</note> says,
					with merely clever men of mortal opinions, just as a
					steersman hesitates to shift his course<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greek is both difficult and ambiguous; perhaps <q direct="unspecified">hesitates to set his ship in motion while a storm is raging.</q>
               </note> in the midst
					of a storm, or a playwright to raise his god from the
					machine in the midst of a play. Yet perhaps it is
					not unsuitable to set the pitch and announce the
					theme by quoting some verses of Empedocles.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The verses have fallen out, but may be, in part, those quoted <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, 998 c, or a similar passage.</note> . . .
					By these lines he means, though he does not say so
					directly, that human souls are imprisoned in mortal
					bodies as a punishment for murder, the eating of
					animal flesh, and cannibalism. This doctrine, however, seems to be even older, for the stories told about
					the sufferings and dismemberment of Dionysus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See I. M. Linforth, <hi rend="italics">The Arts of Orpheus</hi>, chapter 5, <q direct="unspecified">The Dismemberment of Dionysus,</q> and especially pp. 334 ff., on this passage. A good illustration is the fragment of Dionysius in D. L. Page, <hi rend="italics">Greek Literary Papyri</hi>, i (L.C.L.), pp. 538-541.</note> and
					the outrageous assaults of the Titans upon him, and
					their punishment and blasting by thunderbolt after
					they had tasted his blood - all this is a myth which
					in its inner meaning has to do with rebirth. For to
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.561"/>
					
					that faculty in us which is unreasonable and disordered and violent, and does not come from the
					gods, but from evil spirits, the ancients gave the
					name Titans,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Hesiod's etymology, <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 209 f. For this <q direct="unspecified">Greek equivalent of original sin</q> see Shorey on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 701 c (<hi rend="italics">What Plato Said</hi>, p. 629), <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 975 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; and Dodds, <hi rend="italics">The Greeks and the Irrational</hi>, pp. 155 and 177.</note> that is to say, those that are punished
					and subjected to correction. . . . <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The first discourse breaks off at this point.</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>