<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Consolatio ad uxorem</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.111">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.5.p.386"/>
         <head>Plutarch's consolatory letter to his wife.
				<lb/> Plutarch to his wife: all health.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>As for the messenger you despatched to tell me of
				the death of my little daughter, it seems he missed his
				way as he was going to Athens. But when I came to
				Tanagra, I heard of it by my niece. I suppose by this
				time the funeral is over. I wish that whatever has been
				done may create you no dissatisfaction, as well now as
				hereafter. But if you have designedly let any thing alone,
				depending upon my judgment, thinking better to determine the point if I were with you, I pray let it be without
				ceremony and timorous superstition, which I know are far
				from you.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Only, dear wife, let you and me bear our affliction
				with patience. I know very well and do comprehend what
				loss we have had; but if I should find you grieve beyond
				measure, this would trouble me more than the thing itself.
				For I had my birth neither from a stock nor a stone;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. XXII. 126.</note> and
				you know it full well, I having been assistant to you in the
				education of so many children, which we brought up at
				home under our own care. This daughter was born after
				four sons, when you were longing to bear a daughter;
				which made me call her by your own name. Therefore I
				know she was particularly dear to you. And grief must
				have a peculiar pungency in a mind tenderly affectionate
				to children, when you call to mind how naturally witty and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.387"/>
				
				innocent she was, void of anger, and not querulous. She
				was naturally mild, and compassionate to a miracle. And
				her gratitude and kindness not only gave us delight, but
				also manifested her generous nature; for she would pray
				her nurse to give suck, not only to other children, but to
				her very playthings, as it were courteously inviting them
				to her table, and making the best cheer for them she
				could.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Now, my dear wife, I see no reason why these and
				the like things, which delighted us so much when she
				was alive, should upon remembrance of them afflict us
				when she is dead. But I also fear lest, while we cease
				from sorrowing, we should forget her; as Clymene said,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I hate the handy horned bow,
					</l>
                     <l>And banish youthful pastimes now;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>because she would not be put in mind of her son by the
					exercises he had been used to. For Nature always shuns
					such things as are troublesome. But since our little
					daughter afforded all our senses the sweetest and most
					charming pleasure; so ought we to cherish her memory,
					which will conduce many ways&mdash;or rather many fold&mdash;
					more to our joy than our grief. And it is but just, that
					the same arguments which we have oft-times used to others
					should prevail upon ourselves at this so seasonable a time,
					and that we should not supinely sit down and overwhelm
					the joys which we have tasted with a multiplicity of new
					griefs.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Moreover, they who were present at the funeral report this with admiration, that you neither put on mourning, nor disfigured yourself or any of your maids; neither
				were there any costly preparations nor magnificent pomp;
				but all things were managed with silence and moderation in the presence of our relatives alone. And it
				seemed not strange to me that you, who never used richly
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.388"/>
				
				to dress yourself for the theatre or other public solemnities, esteeming such magnificence vain and useless even
				in matters of delight, have now practised frugality on
				this sad occasion. For a virtuous woman ought not only
				to preserve her purity in riotous feasts, but also to think
				thus with herself, that the tempest of the mind in violent
				grief must be calmed by patience, which does not intrench
				on the natural love of parents towards their children, as
				many think, but only struggles against the disorderly and
				irregular passions of the mind. For we allow this love
				of children to discover itself in lamenting, wishing for,
				and longing after them when they are dead. But the excessive inclination to grief, which carries people on to
				unseemly exclamations and furious behavior, is no less
				culpable than luxurious intemperance. Yet reason seems
				to plead in its excuse; because, instead of pleasure, grief
				and sorrow are ingredients of the crime. What can be
				more irrational, I pray, than to check excessive laughter
				and joy, and yet to give a free course to rivers of tears
				and sighs, which flow from the same fountain? Or, as
				some do, quarrel with their wives for using artificial helps
				to beauty, and in the mean time suffer them to shave their
				heads, wear the mournful black, sit disconsolate, and lie in
				pain? And, which is worst of all, if their wives at any
				time chastise their servants or maids immoderately, they
				will interpose and hinder them, but at the same time suffering them to torment and punish themselves most
				cruelly, in a case which peculiarly requires their greatest tenderness and humanity?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But between us, dear wife, there never was any
				occasion for such contests, nor, I think, will there ever
				be. For there is no philosopher of our acquaintance
				who is not in love with your frugality, both in apparel and
				diet; nor a citizen, to whom the simplicity and plainness
				of your dress is not conspicuous, both at religious sacrifices
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.389"/>
				
				and public shows in the theatre. Formerly also you discovered on the like occasion a great constancy of mind,
				when you lost your eldest son; and again, when the
				lovely Chaeron left us. For I remember, when the news
				was brought me of my son's death, as I was returning
				home with some friends and guests who accompanied me
				to my house, when they beheld all things in order, and
				observed a profound silence everywhere,&mdash;as they afterwards declared to others,&mdash;they thought no such calamity
				had happened, but that the report was false. So discreetly
				had you settled the affairs of the house at that time, when
				no small confusion and disorder might have been expected.
				And yet you gave this son suck yourself, and endured the
				lancing of your breast, to prevent the ill effects of a contusion. These are things worthy of a generous woman, and
				one that loves her children.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Whereas, we see most other women receive their
				children in their hands as playthings with a feminine
				mirth and jollity; and afterwards, if they chance to die,
				they will drench themselves in the most vain and excessive sorrow. Not that this is any effect of their love, for
				that gentle passion acts regularly and discreetly; but it
				rather proceeds from a desire of vain-glory, mixed with
				a little natural affection, which renders their mourning barbarous, brutish, and extravagant. Which thing Aesop
				knew very well, when he told the story of Jupiter's giving
				honors to the Gods; for, it seems, Grief also made her demands, and it was granted that she should be honored, but
				only by those who were willing of their own accord to do
				it. And indeed, this is the beginning of sorrow. Everybody first gives her free access; and after she is once rooted
				and settled and become familiar, she will not be forced
				thence with their best endeavors. Therefore she must be
				resisted at her first approach; nor must we surrender the
				fort to her by any exterior signs, whether of apparel, or
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.390"/>
				
				shaving the hair, or any other such like symptoms of
				mournful weakness; which happening daily, and wounding us by degrees with a kind of foolish bashfulness, at
				length do so enervate the mind, and reduce her to such
				straits, that quite dejected and besieged with grief, the
				poor timorous wretch dare not be merry, or see the light,
				or eat and drink in company. This inconvenience is accompanied by a neglect of the body, carelessness of anointing and bathing, with whatsoever else relates to the
				elegancy of human life. Whereas, on the contrary, the
				soul, when it is disordered, ought to receive aid from
				the vigor of a healthful body. For the sharpest edge of the
				soul's grief is rebated and slacked, when the body is in
				tranquillity and ease, like the sea in a calm. But where,
				from an ill course of diet, the body becomes dry and hot,
				so that it cannot supply the soul with commodious and
				serene spirits, but only breathes forth melancholy vapors
				and exhalations, which perpetually annoy her with grief
				and sadness; there it is difficult for a man (though never so
				willing and desirous) to recover the tranquillity of his
				mind, after it has been disturbed with so many evil
				affections.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>But that which is most to be dreaded in this case does
				not at all affrighten me, to wit, the visits of foolish women,
				and their accompanying you in your tears and lamentations; by which they sharpen your grief, not suffering it
				either of itself or by the help of others to fade and vanish
				away. For I am not ignorant how great a combat you
				lately entered, when you assisted the sister of Theon, and
				opposed the women who came running in with horrid cries
				and lamentations, bringing fuel as it were to her passion.
				Assuredly, when men see their neighbor's house on fire,
				every one contributes his utmost to quench it; but when
				they see the mind inflamed with furious passion, they bring
				fuel to nourish and increase the flame. When a man's
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.391"/>
				
				eye is in pain, he is not suffered to touch it, though the
				inflammation provoke him to it, nor will they that are near
				him meddle with it. But he who is galled with grief sits
				and exposes his distemper to every one, like waters that
				all may poach in; and so that which at first seemed a light
				itching or trivial smart, by much fretting and provoking,
				becomes a great and almost incurable disease. But I
				know very well that you will arm yourself against these
				inconveniences.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Moreover, I would have you endeavor to call often to
				mind that time when our daughter was not as yet born to
				us, and when we had no cause to complain of Fortune.
				Then, joining that time with this, argue thus with yourself, that we are now in the same condition as then.
				Otherwise, dear wife, we shall seem discontented at the
				birth of our little daughter, if we own that our circumstances were better before her birth. But the two years
				of her life are by no means to be forgotten by us, but to
				be numbered amongst our blessings, in that they afforded
				us an agreeable pleasure. Nor must we esteem a small
				good for a great evil; nor ungratefully complain against
				Fortune for what she has actually given us, because she
				has not added what we wished for. Certainly, to speak
				reverently of the Gods, and to bear our lot with an even
				mind without accusing Fortune, always brings with it a
				fair reward. But he who in such a case calls prosperous
				things to mind, and turning his thoughts from dark and
				melancholy objects, fixes them on bright and cheerful ones,
				will either quite extinguish his grief, or by allaying it with
				contrary sentiments, will render it weak and feeble. For,
				as perfumes bring delight to the nose, and arm it against
				ill scents, so the remembrance of happiness gives necessary
				assistance in adversity to those who avoid not the recollection of their past prosperity nor complain at all against
				Fortune. For certainly it would little become us to accuse
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.392"/>
				
				our life, if like a book it hath but one little blot in it,
				though all the rest be fair and clean.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>For you have oftentimes heard, that true happiness
				consists in the right discourses and counsels of the mind,
				tending to its own constant establishment, and that the
				changes of Fortune are of no great importance to the felicity of our life. But even if we must also be governed by
				exterior things, and with the common sort of people have
				a regard to casualties, and suffer any kind of men to be
				judges of our happiness, however, do not you take notice
				of the tears and moans of such as visit you at present,
				condoling your misfortunes; for their tears and sighs are
				but of course. But rather, do you consider how happy
				every one of them esteems you for the children you have,
				the house you keep, and the life you lead. For it would
				be an ill thing, while others covet your fortune, though
				sullied with this affliction, that you should exclaim against
				what you enjoy, and not be sensible, from the taste of
				affliction, how grateful you ought to be for the happiness
				which remains untouched. Or, like some who, collecting
				all the defective verses of Homer, pass over at the same
				time so many excellent parts of his poems, so shall we
				peevishly complain of and reckon up the inconveniences
				of our life, neglecting at the same time promiscuously the
				benefits thereof? Or, shall we imitate covetous and sordid
				misers, who, having heaped together much riches, never
				enjoy what they have in possession, but bewail it if it
				chance to be lost?</p>
            <p>But if you lament the poor girl because she died unmarried and without offspring, you have wherewithal to comfort yourself, in that you are defective in none of these
					things, having had your share. And these are not to be
					esteemed at once great evils where they are wanted, and
					small benefits where they are enjoyed. But so long as she
					is gone to a place where she feels no pain, what need is
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.393"/>
					
					there of our grief? For what harm can befall us from
					her, when she is free from all hurt? And surely the loss
					of even great things abates the grief, when it is come to
					this, that we have no need or use of them. But thy
					Timoxena was deprived but of small matter; for she had
					no knowledge but of such, neither took she delight but in
					such small things. But for that which she never was sensible of, and which did not so much as once enter into her
					thoughts, how can you say it is taken from her?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>As for what you hear others say, who persuade the
				vulgar that the soul, when once freed from the body, suffers no inconvenience or evil nor is sensible at all, I know
				that you are better grounded in the doctrines delivered
				down to us from our ancestors, as also in the sacred mysteries of Bacchus, than to believe such stories; for the
				religious symbols are well known to us who are of the
				fraternity. Therefore be assured, that the soul, being incapable of death, is affected in the same manner as birds
				that are kept in a cage. For if she has been a long time
				educated and cherished in the body, and by long custom
				has been made familiar with most things of this life, she
				will (though separable) return again, and at length enter
				the body; nor ceaseth it by new births now and then to be
				entangled in the chances and events of this life. For do
				not think that old age is therefore evil spoken of and
				blamed, because it is accompanied with wrinkles, gray
				hairs, and weakness of body. But this is the most troublesome thing in old age, that it maketh the soul weak in its
				remembrance of divine things, and too earnest for things
				relating to the body; thus it bendeth and boweth, retaining that form which it took of the body. But that which
				is taken away in youth, being more soft and tractable, soon
				returns to its native vigor and beauty. Just as fire that is
				quenched, if it be forthwith kindled again, sparkles and
				burns out immediately. . . . So most speedily
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.394"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Twere good to pass the gates of death,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. V. 646; XXIII. 71.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>before too great a love of bodily and earthly things be engendered in the soul, and it become soft and tender by
					being used to the body, and (as it were) by charms and
					potions incorporated with it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But the truth of this will appear in the laws and
				traditions received from our ancestors. For when children
				die, no libations nor sacrifices are made for them, nor any
				other of those ceremonies which are wont to be performed
				for the dead. For infants have no part of earth or earthly
				affections. Nor do we hover or tarry about their sepulchres
				or monuments, or sit by when their dead bodies are exposed. The laws of our country forbid this, and teach us
				that it is an impious thing to lament for those whose souls
				pass immediately into a better and more divine state.
				Wherefore, since it is safer to give credit to our traditions than to call them in question, let us comply with the
				custom in outward and public behavior, and let our interior be more unpolluted, pure, and holy....</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>