<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De Iside et Osiride</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.5.p.3"/>
            <head>ISIS AND OSIRIS
					(DE ISIDE ET OSIRIDE)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					Plutarch's knowledge of Egyptology was not profound. It is true that he once visited Egypt,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 678 c.</note> but how
					long he stayed and how much he learned we have no
					means of knowing. It is most likely that his treatise
					represents the knowledge current in his day, derived,
					no doubt, from two sources : books and priests. The
					gods of Egypt had early found a welcome in other
					lands, in Syria and Asia Minor, and later in Greece
					and Rome. That the worship of Isis had been introduced into Greece before 330 b.c. is certain from an
					inscription found in the Peiraeus (<hi rend="italics">I.G.</hi> II.<hi rend="super">1</hi> 168, or
					II.<hi rend="super">2</hi> 337 ; Dittenberger, <hi rend="italics">Sylloge</hi>
               <hi rend="super">3</hi>, 280, or 551<hi rend="super">2</hi>), in
					which the merchants from Citium ask permission to
					found a shrine of Aphrodite on the same terms as
					those on which the Egyptians had founded a shrine of
					Isis. In Delos there was a shrine of the Egyptian
					gods, and in Plutarch's own town they must have
					been honoured, for there have been found two dedications to Serapis, Isis, and Anubis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Collitz, <hi rend="italics">Sammlung der griechischen Dialektinschriften</hi>, vol. i. pp. 149-155.</note> as well as numerous
					inscriptions recording the manumission of slaves,
					which in Greece was commonly accomplished by
					dedicating them to a god, who, in these inscriptions,
					is Serapis (Sarapis). An idea of the widespread
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.4"/>
					
					worship of Egyptian gods in Greek lands may be
					obtained from Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Ausf&uuml;hrliches Lexikon der griechischen und romischen Mythologie</hi>, vol. ii. pp. 379-392,
					where the cults of Isis are listed.
				</p>
            <p>
					Another source of information available to Plutarch
					was books. Herodotus in the fifth century b.c. had
					visited Egypt, and he devoted a large part of the
					second book of his History to the manners and
					customs of the Egyptians. Plutarch, however, draws
					but little from him. Some of the information that
					Plutarch gives us may be found also in Diodorus
					Siculus, principally in the first book, but a little also
					in the second. Aelian and, to a less extent, other
					writers mentioned in the notes on the text, have
					isolated fragments of information which usually agree
					with Plutarch and Diodorus. All this points to the
					existence of one or more books, now lost, which contained this information, possibly in a systematic form.
					As a result, Plutarch has many things right and some
					wrong. Those who are interested in these matters
					may consult Erman-Grapow, <hi rend="italics">W&ouml;rterbuch der &auml;gyptischen Sprache</hi> (Leipzig, 1925-1929), and G. Parthey's
					edition of the <hi rend="italics">Isis and Osiris</hi> (Berlin, 1850).
				</p>
            <p>
					One matter which will seem very unscientific to the
					modern reader is Plutarch's attempts to explain the
					derivation of various words, especially his attempt to
					derive Egyptian words from Greek roots ; but in this
					respect he sins no more than Plato, who has given
					us some most atrocious derivations of Greek words,
					especially in the <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>; nor is it more disastrous
					than Herodotus's industrious attempts (in Book II)
					to derive all manner of Greek customs, ritual, and
					theology from Egypt.
				</p>
            <p>
					In spite of minor errors contained in the <hi rend="italics">Isis and</hi>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.5"/>
					
					          <hi rend="italics">Osiris</hi>, no other work by a Greek writer is more
					frequently referred to by Egyptologists except,
					possibly, Herodotus. Connected information may,
					of course, be found in histories of Egypt, such as
					those of Breasted and Baikie.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">All the Greek and Roman sources for the religion of the Egyptians will be found conveniently collected in Hopfner, <hi rend="italics">Fontes Historiae Religionis Aegyptiacae</hi>, Parts I. and II. (Bonn, 1922-1923).</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The work is dedicated to Clea, a cultured and
					intelligent woman, priestess at Delphi, to whom
					Plutarch dedicated also his book on the <hi rend="italics">Bravery of
					Women</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 242 e - 263 c, contained in vol. iii. of
					L.C.L. pp. 473-581). It is, no doubt, owing to this
					that the author, after he has unburdened himself of
					his information on Egyptology, goes on to make some
					very sane remarks on the subject of religion and the
					proper attitude in which to approach it. This part
					of the essay ranks with the best of Plutarch's writing.
					The Ms. tradition of the essay is bad, as may be
					seen from the variations found in the few passages
					quoted by later writers such as Eusebius and Stobaeus;
					yet much has been done by acute scholars to make
					the text more intelligible. It may not be invidious
					to mention among those who have made special contributions to the study of this work W. Baxter, who
					translated it (1684), and S. Squire, who edited it
					(1744). Many other names will be found in the
					critical notes.
				</p>
            <p>
					The essay is No. 118 in Lamprias's list of Plutarch's
					works, where the title is given as an account of Isis
					and Serapis.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.5.p.7"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>All good things, my dear Clea,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The priestess for whom Plutarch composed his collection of stories about the <hi rend="italics">Bravery of Women</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 242 e ff.).</note> sensible men
					must ask from the gods ; and especially do we pray
					that from those mighty gods we may, in our quest,
					gain a knowledge of themselves, so far as such a thing
					is attainable by men.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 780 f - 781 a and 355 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> For we believe that there is
					nothing more important for man to receive, or more
					ennobling for God of His grace to grant, than the
					truth. God gives to men the other things for which
					they express a desire, but of sense and intelligence
					He grants them only a share, inasmuch as these are
					His especial possessions and His sphere of activity.
					For the Deity is not blessed by reason of his possession
					of gold and silver,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Themistius, <hi rend="italics">Oration</hi> xxxiii. p. 365 b-d.</note> nor strong because of thunder and
					lightning, but through knowledge and intelligence.
					Of all the things that Homer said about the gods, he
					has expressed most beautifully this thought:<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xiii. 354; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 32 a, and <hi rend="italics">Life and Writings of Homer</hi>, ii. 114.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Both, indeed, were in lineage one, and of the same country,
					</l>
                  <l>Yet was Zeus the earlier born and his knowledge was
					greater.</l>
               </quote>
					Thereby the poet plainly declares that the primacy
					of Zeus is nobler since it is elder in knowledge and in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.9"/>
					
					wisdom. I think also that a source of happiness in
					the eternal life, which is the lot of God, is that events
					which come to pass do not escape His prescience. But
					if His knowledge and meditation on the nature of
					Existence should be taken away, then, to my mind,
					His immortality is not living, but a mere lapse of
					time.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 781 a.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Therefore the effort to arrive at the Truth, and
					especially the truth about the gods, is a longing for
					the divine. For the search for truth requires for its
					study and investigation the consideration of sacred
					subjects, and it is a work more hallowed than any
					form of holy living or temple service ; and, not least
					of all, it is well-pleasing to that goddess whom you
					worship, a goddess exceptionally wise and a lover of
					wisdom, to whom, as her name at least seems to
					indicate, knowledge and understanding are in the
					highest degree appropriate. For Isis is a Greek
					word,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch is attempting to connect <q direct="unspecified">Isis</q> with <foreign lang="greek">oi)=da</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">know</hi>, and <q direct="unspecified">Typhon</q> with <foreign lang="greek">*tufw=</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">puff up</hi>. See, however, 375 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and so also is Typhon, her enemy, who is
					conceited, as his name implies,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch is attempting to connect <q direct="unspecified">Isis</q> with <foreign lang="greek">oi)=da</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">know</hi>, and <q direct="unspecified">Typhon</q> with <foreign lang="greek">*tufw=</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">puff up</hi>. See, however, 375 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> because of his ignorance and self-deception. He tears to pieces and
					scatters to the winds the sacred writings, which the
					goddess collects and puts together and gives into
					the keeping of those that are initiated into the holy
					rites, since this consecration, by a strict regimen and
					by abstinence from many kinds of food and from
					the lusts of the flesh, curtails licentiousness and the
					love of pleasure, and induces a habit of patient submission to the stem and rigorous services in shrines,
					the end and aim of which is the knowledge of Him
					who is the First, the Lord of All, the Ideal One.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 355 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> Him
					does the goddess urge us to seek, since He is near
					her and with her and in close communion. The name
					of her shrine also clearly promises knowledge and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.11"/>
					
					comprehension of reality ; for it is named Iseion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As if derived from <foreign lang="greek">oi(=da</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">know</hi>, and <foreign lang="greek">o)/n</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">being</hi>.</note>
					to indicate that we shall comprehend reality if in a
					reasonable and devout frame of mind we pass within
					the portals of her shrines.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Moreover, many writers have held her to be the
					daughter of Hermes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 355 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and many others the daughter
					of Prometheus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 365 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, i. 106. 1, 21 (p. 382, Potter).</note> because of the belief that Prometheus
					is the discoverer of wisdom and forethought, and
					Hermes the inventor of grammar and music. For
					this reason they call the first of the Muses at Hermopolis Isis as well as Justice : for she is wise, as
					I have said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi>, 351 f.</note> and discloses the divine mysteries to
					those who truly and justly have the name of
					<q direct="unspecified">bearers of the sacred vessels</q> and <q direct="unspecified">wearers of the
						sacred robes.</q> These are they who within their own
					soul, as though within a casket, bear the sacred
					writings about the gods clear of all superstition and
					pedantry ; and they cloak them with secrecy, thus
					giving intimations, some dark and shadowy, some
					clear and bright, of their concepts about the gods,
					intimations of the same sort as are clearly evidenced in the wearing of the sacred garb.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Dittenberger, <hi rend="italics">Sylloge Inscriptionum Graecarum</hi>, No. 754 (not included in the third edition), or <hi rend="italics">Altert&uuml;mer von Pergamon</hi>, viii. 2, p. 248, no. 326; also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 382 c.</note> For this
					reason, too, the fact that the deceased votaries of
					Isis are decked with these garments is a sign that
					these sacred writings accompany them, and that they
					pass to the other world possessed of these and of
					naught else. It is a fact, dea, that having a beard
					and wearing a coarse cloak does not make philosophers, nor does dressing in linen and shaving the
					hair make votaries of Isis ; but the true votary of Isis
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.13"/>
					
					is he who, when he has legitimately received what is
					set forth in the ceremonies connected with these gods,
					uses reason in investigating and in studying the truth
					contained therein.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>It is true that most people are unaware of this
					very ordinary and minor matter : the reason why the
					priests remove their hair and wear linen garments.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 37 and 81.</note>
					Some persons do not care at all to have any knowledge
					about such things, while others say that the priests,
					because they revere the sheep,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In Sa&iuml;s and Theba&iuml;s according to Strabo, xvii. 40 (p. 812).</note> abstain from using its
					wool, as well as its flesh ; and that they shave their
					heads as a sign of mourning, and that they wear their
					linen garments because of the colour which the flax
					displays when in bloom, and which is like to the
					heavenly azure which enfolds the universe. But for
					all this there is only one true reason, which is to be
					found in the words of Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 67 b; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 108 d.</note>; <q direct="unspecified">for the Impure to
						touch the Pure is contrary to divine ordinance.</q> No
					surplus left over from food and no excrementitious
					matter is pure and clean ; and it is from forms of
					surplus that wool, fur, hair, and nails originate and
					grow.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Apuleius, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, chap. 26.</note> So it would be ridiculous that these persons
					in their holy living should remove their own hair by
					shaving and making their bodies smooth all over,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 37.</note>
					and then should put on and wear the hair of domestic
					animals. We should believe that when Hesiod<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 742-743. The meaning of these somewhat cryptic lines is, of course, that one should not pare one's nails at table; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, ed. Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 90.</note> said,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.15"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Cut not the sere from the green when you honour the gods
					with full feasting,
					</l>
                  <l>Paring with glittering steel the member that hath the five
					branches,</l>
               </quote>
					he was teaching that men should be clean of such
					things when they keep high festival, and they should
					not amid the actual ceremonies engage in clearing
					away and removing any sort of surplus matter. But
					the flax springs from the earth which is immortal; it
					yields edible seeds, and supplies a plain and cleanly
					clothing, which does not oppress by the weight
					required for warmth. It is suitable for every season
					and, as they say, is least apt to breed lice ; but this
					topic is treated elsewhere.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch touches briefly on this subject in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 642 c.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>The priests feel such repugnance for things that
					are of a superfluous nature that they not only eschew
					most legumes, as well as mutton and pork,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 37, and <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 286 e.</note> which
					leave a large residuum, but they also use no salt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. infra</hi>, 363 e; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 684 f, 729 a; and Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, iii. 4. 4.</note> with
					their food during their periods of holy living. For
					this they have various other reasons, but in particular
					the fact that salt, by sharpening the appetite, makes
					them more inclined to drinking and eating. To
					consider salt impure, because, as Aristagoras has said,
					when it is crystallizing many minute creatures are
					caught in it and die there, is certainly silly.
				</p>
            <p>
					It is said also that they water the Apis from a
					well of his own, and keep him away from the Nile
					altogether, not that they think the water unclean
					because of the crocodile, as some believe ; for there
					is nothing which the Egyptians hold in such honour
					as the Nile. But the drinking of the Nile water is
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.17"/>
					
					reputed to be fattening and to cause obesity.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, xi. 10.</note> They
					do not want Apis to be in this condition, nor themselves either ; but rather they desire that their bodies,
					the encasement of their souls, shall be well adjusted
					and light, and shall not oppress and straiten the divine
					element by the predominance and preponderance of
					the mortal.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>As for wine, those who serve the god in Heliopolis bring none at all into the shrine, since they feel
					that it is not seemly to drink in the day-time while
					their Loi'd and King is looking upon them.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Iamblichus, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pythagoras</hi>, 97 and 98, who says that the Pythagoreans would have nothing to do with wine in the day-time. See also the critical note on the opposite page.</note> The
					others use wine, but in great moderation. They
					have many periods of holy living when wine is prohibited, and in these they spend their time exclusively
					in studying, learning, and teaching religious matters.
					Their kings also were wont to drink a limited quantity<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 70. 11.</note>
					prescribed by the sacred writings, as Hecataeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, ii. p. 153, Hecataeus no. B 11.</note> has
					recorded ; and the kings are priests. The beginning
					of their drinking dates from the reign of Psammetichus ; before that they did not drink wine nor
					use it in libation as something dear to the gods,
					thinking it to be the blood of those who had once
					battled against the gods, and from whom, when they
					had fallen and had become commingled with the earth,
					they believed vines to have sprung. This is the reason
					why drunkenness drives men out of their senses and
					crazes them, inasmuch as they are then filled with the
					blood of their forbears. These tales Eudoxus says in
					the second book of his <hi rend="italics">World Travels</hi> are thus related
					by the priests.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.19"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>As for sea-fish, all Egyptians do not abstain
					from all of them,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 37.</note> but from some kinds only ; as, for
					example, the inhabitants of Oxyrhynchus abstain
					from those that are caught with a hook<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xvii. 1. 40 (p. 812); Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 46; Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Protrepticus</hi>, ii. 39. 5 (p. 34 Potter); also 358 b and 380 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; for,
					inasmuch as they revere the fish called oxyrhynchus
					(the pike), they are afraid that the hook may be
					unclean, since an oxyrhynchus may have been caught
					with it. The people of Syen&ecirc; abstain from the
					phagrus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 19.</note> (the sea-bream) ; for this fish is reputed to
					appear with the oncoming of the Nile, and to be a self-sent messenger, which, when it is seen, declares to a
					glad people the rise of the river. The priests, however, abstain from all fish ; and on the ninth day of
					the first month, when every one of the other Egyptians
					eats a broiled fish in front of the outer door of his
					house, the priests do not even taste the fish, but burn
					them up in front of their doors.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 729 a.</note> For this practice
					they have two reasons, one of which is religious and
					curious, and I shall discuss it at another time,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch does not explain this elsewhere (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 363 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>), but the reason may be that given by Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, vii. 6. 34. 1 (p. 850 Potter), that fish do not breathe the same air as other living creatures.</note> since
					it harmonizes with the sacred studies touching Osiris
					and Typhon ; the other is obvious and commonplace,
					in that it declares that fish is an unnecessary and
					superfluous food, and confirms the words of Homer,
					who, in his poetry, represents neither the Phaeacians,
					who lived amid a refined luxury, nor the Ithacans,
					who dwelt on an island, as making any use of fish, nor
					did even the companions of Odysseus, while on such
					a long voyage and in the midst of the sea, until they
					had come to the extremity of want.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv. 369 and xii. 332. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 730 c, d. The facts are as stated, but the deduction that fishing was despised in Homeric times is not warranted.</note> In fine, these
					people hold the sea to be derived from purulent
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.21"/>
					
					matter, and to lie outside the confines of the world
					and not to be a part of it or an element, but a corrupt
					and pestilential residuum of a foreign nature.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 729 b.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Nothing that is irrational or fabulous or prompted
					by superstition, as some believe, has ever been given
					a place in their rites, but in them are some things that
					have moral and practical values, and others that are
					not without their share in the refinements of history
					or natural science, as, for example, that which has
					to do with the onion. For the tale that Dictys, the
					nurseling of Isis, in reaching for a clump of onions,
					fell into the river and was drowned is extremely incredible. But the priests keep themselves clear of
					the onion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aulus Gellius, xx. 8.</note> and detest it and are careful to avoid it,
					because it is the only plant that naturally thrives and
					flourishes in the waning of the moon. It is suitable
					for neither fasting nor festival, because in the one
					case it causes thirst and in the other tears for those
					who partake of it.
				</p>
            <p>
					In like manner they hold the pig to be an unclean
					animal,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 47.</note> because it is reputed to be most inclined
					to mate in the waning of the moon, and because the
					bodies of those who drink its milk break out with
					leprosy and scabrous itching.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 670 f; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 16; Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Histories</hi>, v. 4.</note> The story which they
					relate at their only sacrifice and eating of a pig at the
					time of the full moon, how Typhon, while he was
					pursuing a boar by the light of the full moon, found
					the wooden coffin in which lay the body of Osiris,
					which he rent to pieces and scattered,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> they do not
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.23"/>
					
					all accept, believing it to be a misrepresentation, even
					as many other things are.
				</p>
            <p>
					Moreover, they relate that the ancient Egyptians
					put from them luxury, lavishness, and self-indulgence,
					to such a degree that they used to say that there was
					a pillar standing in the temple at Thebes which had
					inscribed upon it curses against Meinis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Usually known as Menes. The name is variously written by Greek authors as Min, Minaeus, Meneus, Menas. According to tradition he was the first king of Egypt. His reign is put <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 3500 or 3400 b.c. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 4. In Diodorus, i. 45, is found this same story.</note> their king,
					who was the first to lead the Egyptians to quit their
					frugal, thrifty, and simple manner of living. It is
					said also that Technactis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Tefnakhte (also spelled Tnephachthos or Tnephachtho by Greek writers), after much fighting, made himself king of Lower Egypt <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 725 b.c.</note> the father of Bocchoris,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bekneranef, king of Egypt <hi rend="italics">circa</hi> 718-712 b.c., was, according to Greek tradition, a wise and just ruler. An apocryphal story about him may be found in Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, xii. 3.</note>
					when he was leading his army against the Arabians,
					because his baggage was slow in arriving, found
					pleasure in eating such common food as was available,
					and afterwards slept soundly on a bedding of straw,
					and thus became fond of frugal living ; as the result,
					he invoked a curse on Meinis, and, with the approval
					of the priests, had a pillar set up with the curse
					inscribed upon it.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>The kings were appointed from the priests or
					from the military class, since the military class had
					eminence and honour because of valour, and the
					priests because of wisdom. But he who was appointed
					from the military class was at once made one of the
					priests and a participant in their philosophy, which,
					for the most part, is veiled in myths and in words
					containing dim reflexions and adumbrations of the
					truth, as they themselves intimate beyond question
					by appropriately placing sphinxes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, v. 5. 31, chap. 5 (p. 664 Potter).</note> before their
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.25"/>
					
					shrines to indicate that their religious teaching has in
					it an enigmatical sort of wisdom. In Sa&iuml;s the statue
					of Athena, whom they believe to be Isis, bore the
					inscription : <q direct="unspecified">I am all that has been, and is, and shall
						be, and my robe no mortal has yet uncovered.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Moreover, most people believe that Amoun is the
					name given to Zeus in the land of the Egyptians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 42.</note> a
					name which we, with a slight alteration, pronounce
					Ammon. But Manetho of Sebennytus thinks that
					the meaning <q direct="unspecified">concealed</q> or <q direct="unspecified">concealment</q> lies in
					this word. Hecataeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, Hecataeus (60), No. B, 8.</note> of Abdera, however, says
					that the Egyptians use this expression one to another
					whenever they call to anyone, for the word is a form
					of address. When they, therefore, address the
					supreme god, whom they believe to be the same as
					the Universe, as if he were invisible and concealed,
					and implore him to make himself visible and manifest
					to them, they use the word <q direct="unspecified">Amoun</q>; so great, then,
					was the circumspection of the Egyptians in their
					wisdom touching all that had to do wTith the gods.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Witness to this also are the wisest of the
					Greeks : Solon, Thales, Plato, Eudoxus, Pythagoras,
					who came to Egypt and consorted with the priests<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 96 and 98; Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, i. 69. 1, chap. 15 (p. 356 Potter); <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 578 f, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, chap. xxvi. (92 e).</note>;
					and in this number some would include Lycurgus
					also. Eudoxus, they say, received instruction from
					Chonuphis of Memphis, Solon from Sonchis of Sa&iuml;s,
					and Pythagoras from Oenuphis of Heliopolis. Pythagoras, as it seems, was greatly admired, and he also
					greatly admired the Egyptian priests, and, copying
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.27"/>
					
					their symbolism and occult teachings, incorporated
					his doctrines in enigmas. As a matter of fact most
					of the Pythagorean precepts<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For these precepts <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 12 e-f, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Numa</hi>, chap. xiv. (69 c); Athenaeus, x. 77 (452 d); Iamblichus, <hi rend="italics">Protrepticus</hi>, chap. xxi. (pp. 131-160); Diogenes Laeritus, viii. 17-18.</note> do not at all fall short
					of the writings that are called hieroglyphs; such, for
					example, as these : <q direct="unspecified">Do not eat upon a stool</q>;
					<q direct="unspecified">Do not sit upon a peck measure</q>; <q direct="unspecified">Do not lop
						off the shoots of a palm-tree<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 365 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi>, ii. 3. 16.</note>
               </q>; <q direct="unspecified">Do not poke a fire
							with a sword within the house.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					For my part, I think also that their naming unity
					Apollo, duality Artemis, the hebdomad Athena, and
					the first cube Poseidon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example, 381 f and 393 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Iamblichus, <hi rend="italics">Comment. in Nichomachi Arithmetica</hi>, 14.</note> bears a resemblance to the
					statues and even to the sculptures and paintings with
					which their shrines are embellished. For their King
					and Lord Osiris they portray by means of an eye
					and a sceptre<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Occasionally found on the monuments; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 371 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; there are even some who explain
					the meaning of the name as <q direct="unspecified">many-eyed</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 11.</note> on
					the theory that <hi rend="italics">os</hi> in the Egyptian language means
					<q direct="unspecified">many</q> and <hi rend="italics">iri</hi> 
               <q direct="unspecified">eye</q> ; and the heavens, since
					they are ageless because of their eternity, they portray by a heart with a censer beneath.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Horapollo, <hi rend="italics">Hieroglyphics</hi>, i. 22.</note> In Thebes
					there were set up statues of judges without hands,
					and the statue of the chief justice had its eyes closed,
					to indicate that justice is not influenced by gifts or by
					intercession.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 48. 6.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The military class had their seals engraved with
					the form of a beetle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Egyptian scarab, or sacred beetle. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> xxx. 13 (30).</note>; for there is no such thing as a
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.29"/>
					
					female beetle, but all beetles are male.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 381 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. The idea that all beetles are male was very common in antiquity; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>, for example, Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 15; Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iv. 9.</note> They eject
					their sperm into a round mass which they construct,
					since they are no less occupied in arranging for a
					supply of food<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">They are <foreign lang="greek">skatofa/goi</foreign>.</note> than in preparing a place to rear their
					young.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Therefore, Clea, whenever you hear the traditional tales which the Egyptians tell about the gods,
					their wanderings, dismemberments, and many experiences of this sort, you must remember what has been
					already said, and you must not think that any of
					these tales actually happened in the manner in which
					they are related. The facts are that they do not call
					the dog by the name Hermes as his proper name,
					but they bring into association with the most astute
					of their gods that animal's watchfulness and wakefulness and wisdom, since he distinguishes between
					what is friendly and what is hostile by his knowledge
					of the one and his ignorance of the other, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato's <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 375 e, and the note in Adam's edition (Cambridge, 1902).</note>
					remarks. Nor, again, do they believe that the sun
					rises as a new-born babe from the lotus, but they
					portray the rising of the sun in this manner to indicate allegorically the enkindling of the sun from the
					waters.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 368 f and 400 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> So also Ochus, the most cruel and terrible
					of the Persian kings, who put many to death and
					finally slaughtered the Apis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The sacred bull.</note> and ate him for dinner
					in the company of his friends, the Egyptians called
					the <q direct="unspecified">Sword</q> ; and they call him by that name even
					to this day in their list of kings.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Both Cambyses and Ochus are said to have killed the sacred bull Apis; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 368 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iv. 8. In <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 28, Aelian says that both Cambyses and Ochus were guilty of this offence.</note> But manifestly they
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.31"/>
					
					do not mean to apply this name to his actual being ;
					they but liken the stubbornness and wickedness in
					his character to an instrument of murder. If, then,
					you listen to the stories about the gods in this way,
					accepting them from those who interpret the story
					reverently and philosophically, and if you always perform and observe the established rites of worship,
					and believe that no sacrifice that you can offer, no
					deed that you may do will be more likely to find
					favour with the gods than your belief in their true
					nature, you may avoid superstition which is no less
					an evil than atheism.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 164 f, 165 c, 378 a, 379 e.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Here follows the story related in the briefest
					possible words with the omission of everything that
					is merely unprofitable or superfluous :
				</p>
            <p>
					They say that the Sun, when lie became aware of
					Rhea's intercourse with Cronus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 429 f; Diodorus, i. 13. 4; Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praeparatio Evang.</hi> ii. 1. 1-32.</note> invoked a curse upon
					her that she should not give birth to a child in any
					month or any year ; but Hermes, being enamoured
					of the goddess, consorted with her. Later, playing
					at draughts with the moon, he won from her the
					seventieth part of each of her periods of illumination,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch evidently does not reckon the <foreign lang="greek">e(/nh kai\ ne/a</foreign> (the day when the old moon changed to the new) as a period of illumination, since the light given by the moon at that time is practically negligible. An intimation of this is given in his <hi rend="italics">Life of Solon</hi>, chap. xxv. (92 c). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 409 b, and the scholium on Aristophanes' <hi rend="italics">Clouds</hi>, 1186. One seventieth of 12 lunar months of 29 days each (348 days) is very nearly five days.</note>
					and from all the winnings he composed five days, and
					intercalated them as an addition to the three hundred
					and sixty days. The Egyptians even now call these
					five days intercalated<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 4.</note> and celebrate them as the
					birthdays of the gods. They relate that on the first
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.33"/>
					
					of these days Osiris was born, and at the hour of his
					birth a voice issued forth saying, <q direct="unspecified">The Lord of All
						advances to the light.</q> But some relate that a certain
					Pamyles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">What is known about Pamyles (or Paamyles or Pammyles), a Priapean god of the Egyptians, may be found in Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 289. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also 365 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> while he was drawing water in Thebes,
					heard a voice issuing from the shrine of Zeus, which
					bade him proclaim with a loud voice that a mighty
					and beneficent king, Osiris, had been born ; and for
					this Cronus entrusted to him the child Osiris, which
					he brought up. It is in his honour that the festival
					of Pamylia is celebrated, a festival which resembles
					the phallic processions. On the second of these days
					Ar ueris was born whom they call Apollo, and some call
					him also the elder Horus. On the third day Typhon
					was born, but not in due season or manner, but with
					a blow he broke through his mother s side and leapt
					forth. On the fourth day Isis was born in the regions
					that are ever moist<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The meaning is doubtful, but Isis as the goddess of vegetation, of the Nile, and of the sea, might very naturally be associated with moisture.</note>; and on the fifth Nephthys, to
					whom they give the name of Finality<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 366 b and 375 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and the name
					of Aphrodit&ecirc;, and some also the name of Victory.
					There is also a tradition that Osiris and Arueris were
					sprung from the Sun, Isis from Hermes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 352 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and Typhon
					and Nephthys from Cronus. For this reason the kings
					considered the third of the intercalated days as inauspicious, and transacted no business on that day,
					nor did they give any attention to their bodies until
					nightfall. They relate, moreover, that Nephthys
					became the wife of Typhon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 375 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; but Isis and Osiris were
					enamoured of each other<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 373 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and consorted together in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.35"/>
					
					the darkness of the womb before their birth. Some
					say that Arueris came from this union and was called
					the elder Horus by the Egyptians, but Apollo by the
					Greeks.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>One of the first acts related of Osiris in his
					reign was to deliver the Egyptians from their destitute and brutish manner of living.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 13-16.</note> This he did by
					showing them the fruits of cultivation, by giving them
					laws, and by teaching them to honour the gods.
					Later he travelled over the whole earth civilizing it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 17. 1-3; 18. 5-6; 20. 3-4.</note>
					without the slightest need of arms, but most of the
					peoples he won over to his way by the charm of his
					persuasive discourse combined with song and all
					manner of music. Hence the Greeks came to identify
					him with Dionysus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 362 b, 364 d-f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Herodotus, ii. 42 and 144.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					During his absence the tradition is that Typhon
					attempted nothing revolutionary because Isis, who
					was in control, was vigilant and alert; but when he
					returned home Typhon contrived a treacherous plot
					against him and formed a group of conspirators
					seventy-two in number. He had also the co-operation
					of a queen from Ethiopia<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 366 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> who was there at the time
					and whose name they report as Aso. Typhon, having
					secretly measured Osiris's body and having made ready
					a beautiful chest of corresponding size artistically
					ornamented, caused it to be brought into the room
					where the festivity was in progress. The company was
					much pleased at the sight of it and admired it greatly,
					whereupon Typhon jestingly promised to present it
					to the man who should find the chest to be exactly his
					length when he lay down in it. They all tried it in
					turn, but no one fitted it; then Osiris got into it and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.37"/>
					
					lay down, and those who were in the plot ran to it and
					slammed down the lid, which they fastened by nails
					from the outside and also by using molten lead. Then
					they carried the chest to the river and sent it on its
					way to the sea through the Tanitic Mouth. Wherefore the Egyptians even to this day name this mouth
					the hateful and execrable. Such is the tradition.
					They say also that the date on which this deed was
					done was the seventeenth day of Athyr,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">November 13. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also 366 d and 367 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> when the
					sun passes through Scorpion, and in the twenty-eighth
					year of the reign of Osiris ; but some say that these
					are the years of his life and not of his reign.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 367 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>The first to learn of the deed and to bring to
					men's knowledge an account of what had been done
					were the Pans and Satyrs who lived in the region
					around Chemmis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 91 and 156, and Diodorus, i. 18. 2.</note> and so, even to this day, the sudden
					confusion and consternation of a crowd is called a
					panic.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> E. Harrison, <hi rend="italics">Classical Review</hi>, vol. xl. pp. 6 ff.</note> Isis, when the tidings reached her, at once
					cut off one of her tresses and put on a garment of
					mourning in a place where the city still bears the
					name of Kopto.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 23.</note> Others think that the name means
					deprivation, for they also express <q direct="unspecified">deprive</q> by
					means of <q direct="unspecified">koptein.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The word <hi rend="italics">kopto</hi>, <q direct="unspecified">strike,</q> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">cut,</q> is used in the middle voice in the derived meaning <q direct="unspecified">mourn</q> (<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> to beat oneself as a sign of mourning). Occasionally the active voice also means <q direct="unspecified">cut off,</q> and from this use Plutarch derives the meaning <q direct="unspecified">deprive.</q>
               </note> But Isis wandered everywhere
					at her wits' end ; no one whom she approached did
					she fail to address, and even when she met some little
					children she asked them about the chest. As it
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.39"/>
					
					happened, they had seen it, and they told her the
					mouth of the river through which the friends of
					Typhon had launched the coffin into the sea. Wherefore the Egyptians think that little children possess
					the power of prophecy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Dio Chrysostom, <hi rend="italics">Oratio</hi> xxxii. p. 364 d (660 Reiske), and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, xi. 10, <hi rend="italics">ad fin</hi>.</note> and they try to divine the
					future from the portents which they find in children's
					words, especially when children are playing about in
					holy places and crying out whatever chances to come
					into their minds.
				</p>
            <p>
					They relate also that Isis, learning that Osiris in his
					love had consorted with her sister<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nephthys; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 366 b, 368 e, and 375 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> through ignorance,
					in the belief that she was Isis, and seeing the proof of
					this in the garland of melilote which he had left with
					Nephthys, sought to find the child ; for the mother,
					immediately after its birth, had exposed it because of
					her fear of Typhon. And when the child had been
					found, after great toil and trouble, with the help of
					dogs which led Isis to it, it was brought up and became
					her guardian and attendant, receiving the name of
					Anubis, and it is said to protect the gods just as dogs
					protect men.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 87. 2.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Thereafter Isis, as they relate, learned that the
					chest had been cast up by the sea near the land of
					Byblus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi>, ii. 1. 3.</note> and that the waves had gently set it down
					in the midst of a clump of heather. The heather in a
					short time ran up into a very beautiful and massive
					stock, and enfolded and embraced the chest with its
					growth and concealed it within its trunk. The king
					of the country admired the great size of the plant,
					and cut off the portion that enfolded the chest (which
					was now hidden from sight), and used it as a pillar to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.41"/>
					
					support the roof of his house. These facts, they say,
					Isis ascertained by the divine inspiration of Rumour,
					and came to Byblus and sat down by a spring, all
					dejection and tears<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the similar account of Demeter in the Homeric <hi rend="italics">Hymn to Demeter</hi> (ii.), 98 ff.</note>; she exchanged no word with
					anybody, save only that she welcomed the queen's
					maidservants and treated them with great amiability,
					plaiting their hair for them and imparting to their
					persons a wondrous fragrance from her own body.
					But when the queen observed her maidservants, a
					longing came upon her for the unknown woman and
					for such hairdressing and for a body fragrant with
					ambrosia. Thus it happened that Isis was sent for and
					became so intimate with the queen that the queen
					made her the nurse of her baby. They say that
					the king's name was Malcander ; the queens name
					some say was Astart&ecirc;, others Saosis, and still others
					Neman&ucirc;s, which the Greeks would call Athena&iuml;s.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>They relate that Isis nursed the child by giving
					it her finger to suck instead of her breast, and in the
					night she would burn away the mortal portions of its
					body. She herself wrould turn into a swallow and
					flit about the pillar with a wailing lament, until the
					queen who had been watching, when she saw her
					babe on fire, gave forth a loud cry and thus deprived
					it of immortality. Then the goddess disclosed herself
					and asked for the pillar which served to support the
					roof. She removed it with the greatest ease and cut
					away the wood of the heather which surrounded the
					chest; then, when she had wrapped up the wood in
					a linen cloth and had poured perfume upon it, she
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.43"/>
					
					entrusted it to the care of the kings ; and even to
					this day the people of Byblus venerate this wood
					which is preserved in the shrine of Isis. Then the
					goddess threw herself down upon the coffin with such
					a dreadful wailing that the younger of the king's sons
					expired on the spot. The elder son she kept with her,
					and, having placed the coffin on board a boat, she
					put out from land. Since the Phaedrus river toward
					the early morning fostered a rather boisterous wind,
					the goddess grew angry and dried up its stream.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>In the first place where she found seclusion,
					when she was quite by herself, they relate that she
					opened the chest and laid her face upon the face
					within and caressed it and wept. The child came
					quietly up behind her and saw what was there, and
					when the goddess became aware of his presence, she
					turned about and gave him one awful look of anger.
					The child could not endure the fright, and died.
					Others will not have it so, but assert that he fell overboard into the sea from the boat that was mentioned
					above.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">At the end of the preceding chapter.</note> He also is the recipient of honours because
					of the goddess ; for they say that the Maneros of
					whom the Egyptians sing at their convivial gatherings is this very child.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 79; Pausanias, ix. 29. 3; Athenaeus, 620 a.</note> Some say, however, that his
					name was Palaestinus or Pelusius, and that the city
					founded by the goddess was named in his honour.
					They also recount that this Maneros who is the theme
					of their songs was the first to invent music. But
					some say that the word is not the name of any person,
					but an expression belonging to the vocabulary of
					drinking and feasting : <q direct="unspecified">Good luck be ours in things
						like this!</q>, and that this is really the idea expressed
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.45"/>
					
					by the exclamation <q direct="unspecified">maneros</q> whenever the
					Egyptians use it. In the same way we may be
					sure that the likeness of a corpse which, as it is
					exhibited to them, is carried around in a chest, is
					not a reminder of what happened to Osiris, as some
					assume ; but it is to urge them, as they contemplate
					it, to use and to enjoy the present, since all very
					soon must be what it is now and this is their purpose
					in introducing it into the midst of merry-making.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 148 a; Herodotus, ii. 78; Lucian, <hi rend="italics">De Luctu</hi>, 21.</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>As they relate, Isis proceeded to her son Horus,
					who was being reared in Buto,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 366 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and bestowed the
					chest in a place well out of the way ; but Typhon,
					who was hunting by night in the light of the moon,
					happened upon it. Recognizing the body he divided
					it into fourteen parts<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 368 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. Diodorus, i. 21, says sixteen parts.</note> and scattered them, each in
					a different place. Isis learned of this and sought
					for them again, sailing through the swamps in a boat
					of papyrus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praepar. Evang.</hi> v. p. 198 b.</note> This is the reason why people sailing
					in such boats are not harmed by the crocodiles, since
					these creatures in their own way show either their
					fear or their reverence for the goddess.
				</p>
            <p>
					The traditional result of Osiris's dismemberment is
					that there are many so-called tombs of Osiris in
					Egypt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 a, 365 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Diodorus, i. 21.</note>; for Isis held a funeral for each part when
					she had found it. Others deny this and assert that
					she caused effigies of him to be made and these she
					distributed among the several cities, pretending that
					she was giving them his body, in order that he might
					receive divine honours in a greater number of
					cities, and also that, if Typhon should succeed in
					overpowering Horus, he might despair of ever finding
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.47"/>
					
					the true tomb when so many were pointed out to
					him, all of them called the tomb of Osiris.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 21.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Of the parts of Osiris's body the only one which Isis
					did not find was the male member,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 365 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> for the reason
					that this had been at once tossed into the river, and the
					lepidotus, the sea-bream. and the pike had fed upon
					it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xvii. 1. 40 (p. 812).</note>; and it is from these very fishes the Egyptians
					are most scrupulous in abstaining. But Isis made a
					replica of the member to take its place, and consecrated the phallus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 22. 6.</note> in honour of which the Egyptians
					even at the present day celebrate a festival.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Later, as they relate, Osiris carne to Hor us
					from the other world and exercised and trained him
					for the battle. After a time Osiris asked Hor us
					what he held to be the most noble of all things.
					When Florus replied, <q direct="unspecified">To avenge one's father and
						mother for evil done to them,</q> Osiris then asked him
					what animal he considered the most useful for them
					who go forth to battle; and when Horus said, <q direct="unspecified">A
						horse,</q> Osiris was surprised and raised the question
					why it was that he had not rather said a lion than a
					horse. Horus answered that a lion was a useful thing
					for a man in need of assistance, but that a horse
					served best for cutting off the flight of an enemy and
					annihilating him. When Osiris heard this he was
					much pleased, since he felt that Horus had now an
					adequate preparation. It is said that, as many were
					continually transferring their allegiance to Horus,
					Typhon's concubine, Thueris, also came over to him ;
					and a serpent which pursued her was cut to pieces
					by Horus's men, and now, in memory of this, the people
					throw down a rope in their midst and chop it up.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.49"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Now the battle, as they relate, lasted many days
					and Horus prevailed. Isis, however,to whom Typhon
					was delivered in chains, did not cause him to be put
					to death, but released him and let him go. Horus
					could not endure this with equanimity, but laid hands
					upon his mother and wrested the royal diadem from
					her head ; but Hermes put upon her a helmet like
					unto the head of a cow.
				</p>
            <p>
					Typhon formally accused Horus of being an illegitimate child, but with the help of Hermes to plead
					his cause it was decided by the gods that he also was
					legitimate. Typhon was then overcome in two other
					battles. Osiris consorted with Isis after his death,
					and she became the mother of Harpocrates, untimely
					born and weak in his lower limbs.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 377 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>These are nearly all the important points of the
					legend, with the omission of the most infamous of
					the tales, such as that about the dismemberment of
					Horus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1026 c, and <hi rend="italics">De Anima</hi>, i. 6 (in Bernardakis's ed. vol. vii. p. 7).</note> and the decapitation of Isis. There is one
					thing that I have no need to mention to you : if they
					hold such opinions and relate such tales about the
					nature of the blessed and imperishable (in accordance
					with which our concept of the divine must be framed)
					as if such deeds and occurrences actually took place,
					then
					<quote rend="blockquote">Much need there is to spit and cleanse the mouth,</quote>
					as Aeschylus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Aeschylus, no. 354.</note> has it. But the fact is that you yourself detest those persons who hold such abnormal
					and outlandish opinions about the gods. That these
					accounts do not, in the least, resemble the sort of
					loose fictions and frivolous fabrications which poets
					and writers of prose evolve from themselves, after
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.51"/>
					
					the manner of spiders, interweaving and extending their unestablished first thoughts, but that
					these contain narrations of certain puzzling events
					and experiences, you will of yourself understand. Just
					as the rainbow, according to the account of the
					mathematicians, is a reflection of the sun, and owes its
					many hues to the withdrawal of our gaze from the
					sun and our fixing it on the cloud, so the somewhat
					fanciful accounts here set down are but reflections of
					some true tale which turns back our thoughts to
					other matters ; their sacrifices plainly suggest this,
					in that they have mourning and melancholy reflected
					in them ; and so also does the structure of their
					temples,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xvii. 1. 28 (p. 804).</note> which in one portion are expanded into
					wrings and into uncovered and unobstructed corridors,
					and in another portion have secret vesting-rooms in
					the darkness under ground, like cells or chapels ; and
					not the least important suggestion is the opinion held
					regarding the shrines of Osiris, whose body is said to
					have been laid in many different places.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 365 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> For they
					say that Diochites<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The introduction of Diochites here is based upon an emendation of a reading found in one ms. only. The emendation is drawn from Stephanus Byzantinus, a late writer on a geographical topics.</note> is the name given to a small town,
					on the ground that it alone contains the true tomb ;
					and that the prosperous and influential men among
					the Egyptians are mostly buried in Abydos, since it
					is the object of their ambition to be buried in the
					same ground with the body of Osiris. In Memphis,
					however, they say, the Apis is kept, being the image
					of the soul of Osiris,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 362 c and 368 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> whose body also lies there. The
					name of this city some interpret as <q direct="unspecified">the haven of
						the good</q> and others as meaning properly the <q direct="unspecified">tomb
							
							<pb id="v.5.p.53"/>
							
							of Osiris.</q> They also say that the sacred island by
					Philae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 22, and Strabo, xvii. p. 803, which seem to support the emendation <q direct="unspecified">Philae.</q> Others think that the gates (the ms. reading) of Memphis are meant.</note> at all other times is untrodden by man and
					quite unapproachable, and even birds do not alight
					on it nor fishes approach it; yet, at one special time,
					the priests cross over to it, and perform the sacrificial
					rites for the dead, and lay wreaths upon the tomb,
					which lies in the encompassing shade of a persea-<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The persea-tree was sacred to Osiris.</note>
					tree, which surpasses in height any olive.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Eudoxus says that, while many tombs of Osiris
					are spoken of in Egypt, his body lies in Busiris; for
					this was the place of his birth; moreover, Taphosiris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Strabo, xvii. 1. 14 (pp. 799 and 800). Tradition varies between Taphosiris and Taposiris, and there may be no <q direct="unspecified">tomb</q> in the word at all.</note>
					requires no comment, for the name itself means <q direct="unspecified">the
						tomb of Osiris.</q> I pass over the cutting of wood,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 368 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> the
					rending of linen, and the libations that are offered,
					for the reason that many of their secret rites are
					involved therein. In regard not only to these gods,
					but in regard to the other gods, save only those
					whose existence had no beginning and shall have no
					end, the priests say that their bodies, after they have
					done with their labours, have been placed in the
					keeping of the priests and are cherished there, but
					that their souls shine as the stars in the firmament,
					and the soul of Isis is called by the Greeks the Dog-star, but by the Egyptians Sothis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 974 f.</note> and the soul of
					Horus is called Orion, and the soul of Typhon the
					Bear. Also they say that all the other Egyptians pay
					the agreed assessment for the entombment of the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.55"/>
					
					animals held in honour,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 84, <hi rend="italics">ad fin.</hi>, for the great expense often involved.</note> but that the inhabitants of
					the Theban territory only do not contribute because
					they believe in no mortal god, but only in the god
					whom they call Kneph, whose existence had no
					beginning and shall have no end.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Many things like these are narrated and
					pointed out, and if there be some wrho think that
					in these are commemorated the dire and momentous
					acts and experiences of kings and despots who, by
					reason of their pre-eminent virtue or might, laid claim
					to the glory of being styled gods, and later had to
					submit to the vagaries of fortune,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, to die, and thus to lose their claim to divinity; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 360 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. This is common Euhemeristic doctrine.</note> then these persons
					employ the easiest means of escape from the narrative,
					and not ineptly do they transfer the disrepute from
					the gods to men; and in this they have the support of
					the common traditions. The Egyptians, in fact, have
					a tradition that Hermes had thin arms and big elbows,
					that Typhon was red in complexion, Horus white, and
					Osiris dark,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 363 a and 364 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> as if they had been in their nature but
					mortal men. Moreover, they give to Osiris the title
					of general, and the title of pilot to Canopus, from
					whom they say that the star derives its name ; also
					that the vessel which the Greeks call Argo, in form
					like the ship of Osiris, has been set among the constellations in his honour, and its course lies not far
					from that of Orion and the Dog-star ; of these the
					Egyptians believe that one is sacred to Horus and
					the other to Isis.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>I hesitate, lest this be the moving of things
					immovable<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Proverbial; <hi rend="italics">cf. e.g.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 684 d.</note> and not only <q direct="unspecified">warring against the long
						years of time,</q> as Simonides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi> iii., Simonides, no. 193, and Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, ii. p. 340 in L.C.L.</note> has it, but warring, too,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.57"/>
					
					against <q direct="unspecified">many a nation and race of men</q> who are
					possessed by a feeling of piety towards these gods,
					and thus we should not stop short of transplanting
					such names from the heavens to the earth, and
					eliminating and dissipating the reverence and faith
					implanted in nearly all mankind at birth, opening wide
					the great doors to the godless throng, degrading
					things divine to the human level, and giving a splendid
					licence to the deceitful utterances of Euhemerus of
					Messene,who of himself drew up copies of an incredible
					and non-existent mythology,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Doubtless <foreign lang="greek">h( i(era\ a)nagrafh/</foreign> (<hi rend="italics">sacra scriptio</hi>); see Diodorus, v. 41-46, and vi. 1.</note> and spread atheism over
					the whole inhabited earth by obliterating the gods of
					our belief and converting them all alike into names of
					generals, admirals, and kings, who, forsooth, lived in
					very ancient times and are recorded in inscriptions
					written in golden letters at Panchon, which no
					foreigner and no Greek had ever happened to meet
					with, save only Euhemerus. He, it seems, made a
					voyage to the Panchoans and Triphyllians, who never
					existed anywhere on earth and do not exist!
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>However, mighty deeds of Semiramis are celebrated among the Assyrians, and mighty deeds of
					Sesostris in Egypt, and the Phrygians, even to this
					day, call brilliant and marvellous exploits <q direct="unspecified">manic</q>
					because Manes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, i. 94, iv. 45, and W. M. Ramsay, <hi rend="italics">Mitteilungen des deutsch. arch. Institutes in Athen</hi>, viii. 71.</note> one of their very early kings, proved
					himself a good man and exercised a vast influence
					among them. Some give his name as Masdes.
					Cyrus led the Persians, and Alexander the Macedonians,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.59"/>
					
					in victory after victory, almost to the ends of
					the earth ; yet these have only the name and fame of
					noble kings. <q direct="unspecified">But if some, elated by a great self-conceit,</q> as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 716 a.</note> says, <q direct="unspecified">with souls enkindled with
						the fire of youth and folly accompanied by arrogance,</q>
					have assumed to be called gods and to have temples
					dedicated in their honour, yet has their repute
					flourished but a brief time, and then, convicted of
					vain-glory and imposture,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Swift in their fate, Jike to smoke in the air, rising upward
					they flitted,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Empedocles: <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> H. Diels, <hi rend="italics">Poetarum Philosophorum Fragmenta</hi>, p. 106, Empedocles, no. 2. 4.</note>
               </quote>
					and now, like fugitive slaves without claim to protection, they have been dragged from their shrines and
					altars, and have nothing left to them save only
					their monuments and their tombs. Hence the elder
					Antigonus, when a certain Hermodotus in a poem proclaimed him to be <q direct="unspecified">the Offspring of the Sun and a
						god,</q> said, <q direct="unspecified">the slave who attends to my chamberpot is not conscious of any such thing !</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch tells the same story with slight variations in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 182 c.</note> Moreover,
					Lysippus the sculptor was quite right in his disapproval of the painter Apelles, because Apelles in
					his portrait of Alexander had represented him with
					a thunderbolt in his hand, whereas he himself had
					represented Alexander holding a spear, the glory of
					which no length of years could ever dim, since it was
					truthful and was his by right.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In connexion with chapters 25 and 26 one may well compare 418 d - 419 a and 421 c-e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praepar. Evang.</hi> iv. 21 - v. 5.</note>Better, therefore, is the judgement of those
					who hold that the stories about Typhon, Osiris, and
					Isis, are records of experiences of neither gods nor
					men, but of demigods, whom Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 361 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, viii. 32.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.61"/>
					
					and Xenocrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Eclogae</hi>, i. 2. 29.</note> and Chrysippus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 277 a, 419 a, and 1051 c-d; and von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 1103 (p. 320).</note> following the lead of
					early writers on sacred subjects, allege to have been
					stronger than men and, in their might, greatly surpassing our nature, yet not possessing the divine
					quality unmixed and uncontaminated, but with a
					share also in the nature of the soul and in the perceptive faculties of the body, and with a susceptibility to
					pleasure and pain and to whatsoever other experience
					is incident to these mutations, and is the source of
					much disquiet in some and of less in others. For in
					demigods, as in men, there are divers degrees of
					virtue and of vice. The exploits of the Giants and
					Titans celebrated among the Greeks, the lawless
					deeds of a Cronus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The vengeance which he wreaked on his father Uranus.</note> the stubborn resistance of Python
					against Apollo, the flights of Dionysus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 135 ff. If <foreign lang="greek">fqo/roi</foreign> is read (<q direct="unspecified">destructions wrought by Dionysus</q>) there would be also a reference to the death of Pentheus as portrayed in the <hi rend="italics">Bacchae</hi> of Euripides. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 996 c.</note> and the
					wanderings of Demeter, do not fall at all short of
					the exploits of Osiris and Typhon and other exploits
					which anyone may hear freely repeated in traditional
					story. So, too, all the things which are kept always
					away from the ears and eyes of the multitude by
					being concealed behind mystic rites and ceremonies
					have a similar explanation.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>As we read Homer, we notice that in many
					different places he distinctively calls the good <q direct="unspecified">godlike</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The word is found forty-four times in Homer.</note> and <q direct="unspecified">peers of the gods</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer employs this expression sixty-two times.</note> and &ldquo;having prudence
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.63"/>
					
					gained from the gods,&rsquo;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> vi. 12.</note> but that the epithet derived
					from the demigods (or daemons) he uses of the worthy
					and worthless alike<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 415 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; for example :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Daemon-possessed, come on ! Why seek you to frighten the
					Argives
					</l>
                  <l>Thus ?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xiii. 810.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					and again
					<quote rend="blockquote">When for the fourth time onward he came with a rush, like
					a daemon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> v. 438, xiv. 705, xx. 447.</note>;</quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Daemon-possessed, in what do Priam and children of Priam
					</l>
                  <l>Work you such ill that your soul is ever relentlessly eager
					</l>
                  <l>Ilium, fair-built city, to bring to complete desolation ?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv. 31.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					The assumption, then, is that the demigods (or
					daemons) have a complex and inconsistent nature
					and purpose ; wherefore Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 717 a, assigns the Even and the Left to the chthonic deities, and Plutarch quite correctly derives his statement from this.</note> assigns to the
					Olympian gods right-hand qualities and odd numbers,
					and to the demigods the opposite of these. Xenocrates also is of the opinion that such days as are days
					of ill omen, and such festivals as have associated with
					them either beatings or lamentations or fastings or
					scurrilous language or ribald jests have no relation to
					the honours paid to the gods or to worthy demigods,
					but he believes that there exist in the space about us
					certain great and powerful natures, obdurate, however, and morose, which take pleasure in such things
					as these, and, if they succeed in obtaining them,
					resort to nothing worse.
				</p>
            <p>
					Then again, Hesiod calls the worthy and good
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.65"/>
					
					demigods <q direct="unspecified">holy deities</q> and <q direct="unspecified">guardians of mortals</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 123 and 253. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 431 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Givers of wealth, and having therein a reward that is kingly.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 126, repeated in 417 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
               </quote>
					Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 202 e. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 415 a and 416 c-f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Dionysius of Halicarnassus, <hi rend="italics">Roman Antiq.</hi> i. 77.</note> calls this class of beings an interpretative
					and ministering class, midway between gods and
					men, in that they convey thither the prayers and
					petitions of men, and thence they bring hither the
					oracles and the gifts of good things.
				</p>
            <p>
					Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Part of a longer passage from Empedocles; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> H. Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 267, Empedocles, no. 115, 9-12. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 830 f.</note> says also that the demigods must pay
					the penalty for the sins that they commit and the
					duties that they neglect :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Might of the Heavens chases them forth to the realm of
					the Ocean ;
					</l>
                  <l>Ocean spews them out on the soil of the Earth, and
					Earth drives them
					</l>
                  <l>Straight to the rays of the tireless Sun, who consigns
					them to Heaven's
					</l>
                  <l>Whirlings ; thus one from another receives them, but
					ever with loathing ;</l>
               </quote>
					until, when they have thus been chastened and
					purified, they recover the place and position to which
					they belong in accord with Nature.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Stories akin to these and to others like them
					they say are related about Typhon ; how that,
					prompted by jealousy and hostility, he wrought
					terrible deeds and, by bringing utter confusion upon
					all things, filled the whole Earth, and the ocean as
					well, with ills, and later paid the penalty therefor.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.67"/>
					
					But the avenger, the sister and wife of Osiris, after
					she had quenched and suppressed the madness and
					fury of Typhon, was not indifferent to the contests
					and struggles which she had endured, nor to her own
					wanderings nor to her manifold deeds of wisdom and
					many feats of bravery, nor would she accept oblivion
					and silence for them, but she intermingled in the
					most holy rites portrayals and suggestions and representations of her experiences at that time, and
					sanctified them, both as a lesson in godliness and an
					encouragement for men and women who find themselves in the clutch of like calamities. She herself
					and Osiris, translated for their virtues from good
					demigods into gods,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 363 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> as were Heracles and Dionysus
					later,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 857 d.</note> not incongruously enjoy double honours, both
					those of gods and those of demigods, and their powers
					extend everywhere, but are greatest in the regions
					above the earth and beneath the earth. In fact,
					men assert that Pluto is none other than Serapis and
					that Persephon&ecirc; is Isis, even as Archemachus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iv. p. 315, no. 7.</note> of
					Euboea has said, and also Heracleides Ponticus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ii. 198 or Frag. 103, ed. Voss.</note> who
					holds the oracle in Canopus to be an oracle of Pluto.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Ptolemy Soter saw in a dream the colossal
					statue of Pluto in Sinope, not knowing nor having
					ever seen how it looked, and in his dream the statue
					bade him convey it with all speed to Alexandria. He
					had no information and no means of knowing where
					the statue was situated, but as he related the vision
					to his friends there was discovered for him a much
					travelled man by the name of Sosibius, who said that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.69"/>
					
					he had seen in Sinop&ecirc; just such a great statue as
					the king thought he saw. Ptolemy, therefore, sent
					Soteles and Dionysius, who, after a considerable time
					and with great difficulty, and not without the help of
					divine providence, succeeded in stealing the statue and
					bringing it away.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 984 a; Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Histories</hi>, iv. 83-84, who tells the story more dramatically and with more detail; Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Protrepticus</hi>, iv. 48 (p. 42 Potter); Origen, <hi rend="italics">Against Celsus</hi>, v. 38.</note> When it had been conveyed to
					Egypt and exposed to view, Timotheus, the expositor
					of sacred law, and Manetho of Sebennytus, and their
					associates, conjectured that it was the statue of
					Pluto, basing their conjecture on the Cerberus and
					the serpent with it, and they convinced Ptolemy that
					it was the statue of none other of the gods but Serapis.
					It certainly did not bear this name when it came from
					Sinope, but, after it had been conveyed to Alexandria,
					it took to itself the name which Pluto bears among
					the Egyptians, that of Serapis. Moreover, since
					Heracleitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. 81, Heracleitus no. 14.</note> the physical philosopher says, <q direct="unspecified">The
						same are Hades and Dionysus, to honour whom they
						rage and rave,</q> people are inclined to come to this
					opinion. In fact, those who insist that the body is
					called Hades, since the soul is, as it were, deranged
					and inebriate when it is in the body, are too frivolous
					in their use of allegory. It is better to identify
					Osiris with Dionysus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 364 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and Serapis with Osiris,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 376 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Pauly-Wissowa, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi> Sarapis (vol. i. a, col. 2394).</note> who
					received this appellation at the time when he changed
					his nature. For this reason Serapis is a god of all
					peoples in common, even as Osiris is ; and this they
					who have participated in the holy rites well know.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.71"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>It is not worth while to pay any attention to
					the Phrygian writings,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Deorum</hi>, iii. 16 (42).</note> in which it is said that Serapis
					was the son of Heracles, and Isis was his daughter,
					and Typhon was the son of Alcaeus, who also was
					a son of Heracles ; nor must we fail to contemn
					Phylarchus, who writes that Dionysus was the first to
					bring from India into Egypt two bulls, and that the
					name of one was Apis and of the other Osiris. But
					Serapis is the name of him who sets the universe in
					order, and it is derived from <q direct="unspecified">sweep</q> (<hi rend="italics">sairein</hi>), which
					some say means <q direct="unspecified">to beautify</q> and <q direct="unspecified">to put in order.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pauly-Wissowa, <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi>, col. 2396-2397, for other etymologies. The derivation from <hi rend="italics">sairein</hi> (sweep) is wholly fanciful.</note>
					As a matter of fact, these statements of Phylarchus
					are absurd, but even more absurd are those put forth
					by those who say that Serapis is no god at all, but
					the name of the coffin of Apis ; and that there are
					in Memphis certain bronze gates called the Gates of
					Oblivion and Lamentation,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 96, and Pausanias, i. 18. 4, with Frazer's note.</note> which are opened when
					the burial of Apis takes place, and they give out a
					deep and harsh sound ; and it is because of this that
					we lay hand upon anything of bronze that gives out
					a sound.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 995 e-f; Aristotle, Frag. 196 (ed. Rose); or Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">Life of Pythagoras</hi>, 41.</note> More moderate is the statement of those
					who say that the derivation<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This derivation (from <hi rend="italics">seuesthai</hi> or <hi rend="italics">sousthai</hi>) is also fanciful.</note> is from <q direct="unspecified">shoot</q>
					(<hi rend="italics">seuesthai</hi>) or <q direct="unspecified">scoot</q> (<hi rend="italics">sousthai</hi>), meaning the general
					movement of the universe. Most of the priests say
					that Osiris and Apis are conjoined into one, thus
					explaining to us and informing us that we must regard
					Apis as the bodily image of the soul of Osiris.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 368 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and Diodorus, i. 85.</note> But
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.73"/>
					
					it is my opinion that, if the name Serapis is Egyptian,
					it denotes cheerfulness and rejoicing, and I base this
					opinion on the fact that the Egyptians call their
					festival of rejoicing <hi rend="italics">sairei</hi>. In fact, Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 403 a-404 a, suggests various derivations of the name Hades.</note> says
					that Hades is so named because he is a beneficent and
					gentle god towards those who have come to abide
					with him. Moreover, among the Egyptians many
					others of the proper names are real words ; for
					example, that place beneath the earth, to which they
					believe that souls depart after the end of this life,
					they call Amenthes, the name signifying <q direct="unspecified">the one
						who receives and gives.</q> Whether this is one of
					those words which came from Greece in very ancient
					times and were brought back again<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 375 e-f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> we will consider
					later,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 375 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> but for the present let us go on to discuss the
					remainder of the views now before us.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Now Osiris and Isis changed from good minor
					deities into gods.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 361 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> But the power of Typhon,
					weakened and crushed, but still fighting and strugglingagainst extinction, they try to console and mollify
					by certain sacrifices ; but again there are times when,
					at certain festivals, they humiliate and insult him by
					assailing red-headed men with jeering, and by throwing
					an ass over the edge of a precipice, as the people of
					Kopto do, because Typhon had red hair and in colour
					resembled an ass.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 364 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; for Kopto <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 356 d.</note> The people of Busiris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 150 e-f.</note> and
					Lycopolis do not use trumpets at all, because these
					make a sound like an ass<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 28.</note>; and altogether they
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.75"/>
					
					regard the ass as an unclean animal dominated by
					some higher power because of its resemblance to
					Typhon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 150 f.</note> and when they make cakes at their sacrifices in the month of Pa&yuml;ni and of Phaophi they
					imprint upon them the device of an ass tied by a
					rope.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 371 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> Moreover, in the sacrifice to the Sun they
					enjoin upon the worshippers not to wear any golden
					ornaments nor to give fodder to an ass. It is plain
					that the adherents of Pythagoras hold Typhon to be
					a daemonic power ; for they say that he was born in
					an even factor of fifty-six ; and the dominion of the
					triangle belongs to Hades, Dionysus, and Ares, that
					of the quadrilateral to Rhea, Aphrodit&ecirc;, Demeter,
					Hestia, and Hera, that of the dodecagon to Zeus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As the chief of the twelve gods presumably; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 4.</note> and
					that of a polygon of fifty-six sides to Typhon, as
					Eudoxus has recorded.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>The Egyptians, because of their belief that
					Typhon was of a red complexion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 364 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> also dedicate to
					sacrifice such of their neat cattle as are of a red
					colour,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 88.</note> but they conduct the examination of these so
					scrupulously that, if an animal has but one hair black
					or white, they think it wrong to sacrifice it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 38, and Diodorus, i. 88.</note>; for they
					regard as suitable for sacrifice not what is dear to the
					gods but the reverse, namely, such animals as have
					incarnate in them souls of unholy and unrighteous
					men who have been transformed into other bodies.
					For this reason they invoke curses on the head of the
					victim and cut it off, and in earlier times they used to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.77"/>
					
					throw it into the river, but now they sell it to aliens.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">To Greeks,</q> says Herodotus, ii. 39. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Deuteronomy xiv. 21, <q direct="unspecified">Thou shalt give it (<hi rend="italics">sc.</hi> anything that dieth of itself) unto the stranger that is in thy gates . . . or thou mayest sell it unto an alien.</q>
               </note>
					Upon the neat animal intended for sacrifice those of
					the priests who were called <q direct="unspecified">Sealers</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 38, and Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iv. 7.</note> used to put
					a mark; and their seal, as Castor records, bore an
					engraving of a man with his knee on the ground and
					his hands tied behind his back, and with a sword at
					his throat.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 88. 4-5.</note> They think, as has been said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">362 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that the
					ass reaps the consequences of his resemblance
					because of his stupidity and his lascivious behaviour
					no less than because of his colour. This is also
					the reason why, since they hated Ochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 355 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iv. 8.</note> most of
					all the Persian kings because he was a detested
					and abominable ruler, they nicknamed him <q direct="unspecified">the
						Ass</q>; and he remarked, <q direct="unspecified">But this Ass will feast
							upon your Bull,</q> and slaughtered Apis, as Deinon has
					recorded. But those who relate that Typhon's flight
					from the battle was made on the back of an ass and
					lasted for seven days, and that after he had made his
					escape, he became the father of sons, Hierosolymus
					and Judaeus, are manifestly, as the very names show,
					attempting to drag Jewish traditions<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Histories</hi>, v. 2.</note> into the legend.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Such, then, are the possible interpretations
					which these facts suggest. But now let us begin over
					again, and consider first the most perspicuous of those
					who have a reputation for expounding matters more
					philosophically. These men are like the Greeks who
					say that Cronus is but a figurative name for Chronus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Deorum</hi>, ii. 25 (64).</note>
					(Time), Hera for Air, and that the birth of Hephaestus
					symbolizes the change of Air into Fire.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 392 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> And thus
					among the Egyptians such men say that Osiris is the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.79"/>
					
					Nile consorting with the Earth, which is Isis, and that
					the sea is Typhon into which the Nile discharges its
					waters and is lost to view and dissipated, save for that
					part which the earth takes up and absorbs and thereby
					becomes fertilized.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 366 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					There is also a religious lament sung over Cronus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For Cronus as representing rivers and water see Pauly-Wissowa, xi. 1987-1988.</note>
					The lament is for him that is born in the regions on
					the left, and suffers dissolution in the regions on the
					right; for the Egyptians believe that the eastern
					regions are the face of the world, the northern the
					right, and the southern the left.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 282 d-e and 729 b.</note> The Nile, therefore,
					which runs from the south and is swallowed up by the
					sea in the north, is naturally said to have its birth on
					the left and its dissolution on the right. For this
					reason the priests religiously keep themselves aloof
					from the sea, and call salt the <q direct="unspecified">spume of Typhon</q> ;
					and one of the things forbidden them is to set salt upon
					a table<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 685 a and 729 a.</note>; also they do not speak to pilots,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 729 c.</note> because
					these men make use of the sea, and gain their livelihood from the sea. This is also not the least of the
					reasons why they eschew fish,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 353 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and they portray hatred
					by drawing the picture of a fish. At Sa&iuml;s in the vestibule of the temple of Athena was carved a babe and
					an aged man, and after this a hawk, and next a fish,
					and finally an hippopotamus. The symbolic meaning
					of this was<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There is a lacuna in one ms. (E) at this point (God hateth . . . of departing from it). The supplement is from Clement of Alexandria; see the critical note.</note>: <q direct="unspecified">O ye that are coming into the world
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.81"/>
						
						and departing from it, God hateth shamelessness.</q>
					The babe is the symbol of coming into the world and
					the aged man the symbol of departing from it, and by
					a hawk they indicate God,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 371 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> by the fish hatred, as has
					already been said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 353 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> because of the sea, and by the
					hippopotamus shamelessness ; for it is said that he
					kills his sire<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iii. 23.</note> and forces his mother to mate with him.
					That saying of the adherents of Pythagoras, that the
					sea is a tear of Cronus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, v. 50. 1 (p. 676 Potter), and Aristotle, Frag. 196 (ed. Rose).</note> may seem to hint at its impure
					and extraneous nature.
				</p>
            <p>
					Let this, then, be stated incidentally, as a matter
					of record that is common knowledge. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>But the
					wiser of the priests call not only the Nile Osiris and the
					sea Typhon, but they simply give the name of Osiris
					to the whole source and faculty creative of moisture,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 365 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					believing this to be the cause of generation and the
					substance of life-producing seed ; and the name of
					Typhon they give to all that is dry, fiery, and arid,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 369 a and 376 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					in general, and antagonistic to moisture. Therefore,
					because they believe that he was personally of a
					reddish sallow colour,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 e and 363 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> they are not eager to meet
					men of such complexion, nor do they like to associate
					with them.
				</p>
            <p>
					Osiris, on the other hand, according to their legendary tradition, was dark,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> because water darkens
					everything, earth and clothes and clouds, when it
					comes into contact with them.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 950 a.</note> In young people the
					presence of moisture renders their hair black, while
					greyness, like a paleness as it were, is induced by
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.83"/>
					
					dryness in those who are passing their prime.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Generatione Animalium</hi>, v. 1 (780 b 6).</note> Also
					the spring-time is vigorous, prolific, and agreeable ;
					but the autumn, since it lacks moisture, is inimical to
					plants and unhealthful for living creatures.
				</p>
            <p>
					The bull kept at Heliopolis which they call Mneuis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 21; Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praepar. Evang.</hi> iii. 13. 1-3; Strabo, xvii. 1. 22; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, xi. 11.</note>
					and which is sacred to Osiris (some hold it to be the
					sire of Apis), is black and has honours second only to
					Apis. Egypt, moreover, which has the blackest of
					soils,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 12.</note> they call by the same name as the black portion
					of the eye, <q direct="unspecified">Chemia,</q> and compare it to a heart<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Horapollo, <hi rend="italics">Hieroglyphica</hi>, i. 22.</note>; for
					it is warm and moist and is enclosed by the southern
					portions of the inhabited world and adjoins them, like
					the heart in a man's left side.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>They say that the sun and moon do not use
					chariots, but boats<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, v. 41. 2 (p. 566 Potter); Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praepar. Evang.</hi> iii. 11. 48.</note> in which to sail round in their
					courses ; and by this they intimate that the nourishment and origin of these heavenly bodies is from
					moisture. They think also that Homer,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiv. 201.</note> like Thales,
					had gained his knowledge from the Egyptians, when he
					postulated water as the source and origin of all things;
					for, according to them, Oceanus is Osiris, and Tethys
					is Isis, since she is the kindly nurse and provider for all
					things. In fact, the Greeks call emission <hi rend="italics">apousia</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Artemidorus, <hi rend="italics">Oneirocritica</hi>, i. 78.</note>
					and coition <hi rend="italics">synousia</hi>, and the son (<hi rend="italics">hyios</hi>) from water
					(<hi rend="italics">hydor</hi>) and rain (<hi rend="italics">hysai</hi>) ; Dionysus also they call
					Hyes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the name <hi rend="italics">Hyades</hi> of the constellation.</note> since he is lord of the nature of moisture ; and
					he is no other than Osiris.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 b, 362 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 365 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> In fact, Hellanicus seems
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.85"/>
					
					to have heard Osiris pronounced Hysiris by the
					priests, for he regularly spells the name in this way,
					deriving it, in all probability, from the nature of
					Osiris and the ceremony of finding him.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 366 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>That Osiris is identical with Dionysus who could
					more fittingly know than yourself, Clea ? For you are
					ii t the head of the inspired maidens of Delphi, and
					have been consecrated by your father and mother in
					the holy rites of Osiris. If, however, for the benefit
					of others it is needful to adduce proofs of this identity,
					let us leave undisturbed what may not be told, but the
					public ceremonies which the priests perform in the
					burial of the Apis, when they convey his body on an
					improvised bier, do not in any way come short of a
					Bacchic procession ; for they fasten skins of fawns
					about themselves, and carry Bacchic wands and
					indulge in shoutings and movements exactly as do
					those who are under the spell of the Dionysiac
					ecstasies.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 11.</note> For the same reason many of the Greeks
					make statues of Dionysus in the form of a bull<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A partial list in Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Lexikon d. gr. u. r&ouml;m. Mythologie</hi>, i. 1149.</note>; and
					the women of Elis invoke him, praying that the god
					may come with the hoof of a bull<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 299 a, where the invocation is given at greater length; also Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, iii. p. 510 (L.C.L.).</note>; and the epithet
					applied to Dionysus among the Argives is <q direct="unspecified">Son of the
						Bull.</q> They call him up out of the water by the sound
					of trumpets,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 671 e.</note> at the same time casting into the depths
					a lamb as an offering to the Keeper of the Gate. The
					trumpets they conceal in Bacchic wands, as Socrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iv. p. 498, Socrates, no. 5.</note>
					has stated in his treatise on The Holy Ones. Furthermore,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.87"/>
					
					the tales regarding the Titans and the rites
					celebrated by night agree with the accounts of the
					dismemberment of Osiris and his revivification and
					regenesis. Similar agreement is found too in the
					tales about their sepulchres. The Egyptians, as has
					already been stated,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">358 a and 359 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> point out tombs of Osiris in
					many places, and the people of Delphi believe that
					the remains of Dionysus rest with them close beside
					the oracle ; and the Holy Ones offer a secret sacrifice
					in the shrine of Apollo whenever the devotees of
					Dionysus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, the inspired maidens, mentioned at the beginning of the chapter.</note> wake the God of the Mystic Basket.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Callimachus, <hi rend="italics">Hymn to Demeter</hi> (vi.), 127; <hi rend="italics">Anth. Pal.</hi> vi. 165; Virgil, <hi rend="italics">Georg.</hi> i. 166.</note> To
					show that the Greeks regard Dionysus as the lord and
					master not only of wine, but of the nature of every
					sort of moisture, it is enough that Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 153 (Christ). Plutarch quotes the line also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 745 a and 757 f.</note> be our
					witness, when he says
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>May gladsome Dionysus swell the fruit upon the trees,
					</l>
                  <l>The hallowed splendour of harvest-time.</l>
               </quote>
					For this reason all who reverence Osiris are prohibited
					from destroying a cultivated tree or blocking up a
					spring of water.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>Not only the Nile, but every form of moisture<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 366 a, 371 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and 729 b.</note>
					they call simply the effusion of Osiris ; and in their
					holy rites the water jar in honour of the god heads
					the procession.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Stromateis</hi>, vi. 31. 1 (p. 758 Potter).</note> And by the picture of a rush they
					represent a king and the southern region of the world,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Such a symbol exists on Egyptian monuments.</note>
					and the rush is interpreted to mean the watering and
					fructifying of all things, and in its nature it seems to
					bear some resemblance to the generative member.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.89"/>
					
					Moreover, when they celebrate the festival of the
					Pamylia which, as has been said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">355 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> is of a phallic
					nature, they expose and carry about a statue of which
					the male member is triple<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 371 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, Herodotus, ii. 48, and Egyptian monuments.</note>; for the god is the Source,
					and every source, by its fecundity, multiplies what
					proceeds from it; and for <q direct="unspecified">many times</q> we have a
					habit of saying <q direct="unspecified">thrice,</q> as, for example, <q direct="unspecified">thrice
						happy,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> v. 306, and vi. 154. It is interesting that G. H. Palmer translates this <q direct="unspecified">most happy.</q>
               </note> and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Bonds, even thrice as many, unnumbered,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> viii. 340.</note>
               </quote>
					unless, indeed, the word <q direct="unspecified">triple</q> is used by the early
					writers in its strict meaning ; for the nature of
					moisture, being the source and origin of all things,
					created out of itself three primal material substances,
					Earth, Air, and Fire. In fact, the tale that is annexed
					to the legend to the effect that Typhon cast the male
					member of Osiris into the river, and Isis could not find
					it, but constructed and shaped a replica of it, and
					ordained that it should be honoured and borne in
					processions,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> plainly comes round to this doctrine,
					that the creative and germinal power of the god, at
					the very first, acquired moisture as its substance, and
					through moisture combined with whatever was by
					nature capable of participating in generation.
				</p>
            <p>
					There is another tale current among the Egyptians,
					that Apopis, brother of the Sun, made Avar upon
					Zeus, and that because Osiris espoused Zeus's cause
					and helped him to overthrow his enemy, Zeus adopted
					Osiris as his son and gave him the name of Dionysus.
					It may be demonstrated that the legend contained in
					this tale has some approximation to truth so far as
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.91"/>
					
					Nature is concerned ; for the Egyptians apply the
					name <q direct="unspecified">Zeus</q> to the wind,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 12. 2.</note> and whatever is dry or
					fiery is antagonistic to this. This is not the Sun, but it
					has some kinship with the Sun ; and the moisture,
					by doing away with the excess of dryness, increases
					and strengthens the exhalations by which the wind is
					fostered and made vigorous.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Moreover, the Greeks are wont to consecrate
					the ivy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diodorus, i. 17. 4.</note> to Dionysus, and it is said that among the
					Egyptians the name for ivy is <hi rend="italics">chenosiris</hi>, the meaning
					of the name being, as they say, <q direct="unspecified">the plant of Osiris.</q>
					Now, Ariston,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> iii. p. 324.</note> the author of <hi rend="italics">Athenian Colonization</hi>,
					happened upon a letter of Alexarchus, in which it is
					recorded that Dionysus was the son of Zeus and Isis,
					and is called not Osiris, but Arsaphes, spelled with an
					<q direct="unspecified">a,</q> the name denoting virility. Hermaeus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv. p. 427.</note> too,
					makes this statement in the first volume of his book
					<hi rend="italics">The Egyptians</hi> ; for he says that Osiris, properly interpreted, means <q direct="unspecified">sturdy.</q> I leave out of account
					Mnaseas's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iii. p. 155.</note> annexation of Dionysus, Osiris, andSerapis
					to Epaphus, as well as Anticleides'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Gr. Hist.</hi> 140, no. 13.</note> statement that
					Isis was the daughter of Prometheus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 352 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and was wedded
					to Dionysus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 156.</note> The fact is that the peculiarities
					already mentioned regarding the festival and sacrifices carry a conviction more manifest than any
					testimony of authorities.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>Of the stars the Egyptians think that the Dog-star is the star of Isis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 376 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> because it is the bringer of
					water.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the Nile.</note> They also hold the Lion in honour, and they
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.93"/>
					
					adorn the doorways of their shrines with gaping lions'
					heads,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 670 c; Horapollo, <hi rend="italics">Hieroglyphica</hi>, i. 21.</note> because the Nile overflows
					<quote rend="blockquote">When for the first time the Sun comes into conjunction
					with Leo.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aratus, <hi rend="italics">Phaenomena</hi>, 151. The Dog-star rises at about the same time.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					As they regard the Nile as the effusion of Osiris,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 365 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> so
					they hold and believe the earth to be the body of Isis,
					not all of it, but so much of it as the Nile covers,
					fertilizing it and uniting with it.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 363 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> From this union
					they make Horus to be born. The all-conserving and
					fostering Hora, that is the seasonable tempering of
					the surrounding air, is Horus, who they say was
					brought up by Leto in the marshes round about
					Buto<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 357 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; for the watery and saturated land best
					nurtures those exhalations which quench and abate
					aridity and dryness.
				</p>
            <p>
					The outmost parts of the land beside the mountains
					and bordering on the sea the Egyptians call Nephthys.
					This is why they give to Nephthys the name of
					<q direct="unspecified">Finality,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 355 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 375 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and say that she is the wife of Typhon.
					Whenever, then, the Nile overflows and with abounding waters spreads far away to those who dwell in the
					outermost regions, they call this the union of Osiris
					with Nephthys,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 356 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> which is proved by the upspringing
					of the plants. Among these is the melilotus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> by the
					wilting and failing of which, as the story goes, Typhon
					gained knowledge of the wrong done to his bed. So
					Isis gave birth to Horus in lawful wedlock, but
					Nephthys bore Anubis clandestinely. However, in
					the chronological lists of the kings they record that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.95"/>
					
					Nephthys, after her marriage to Typhon, was at first
					barren. If they say this, not about a woman, but
					about the goddess, they must mean by it the utter
					barrenness and unproduetivity of the earth resulting
					from a hard-baked soil.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>The insidious scheming and usurpation of
					Typhon, then, is the power of drought, which gains
					control and dissipates the moisture which is the source
					of the Nile and of its rising ; and his coadjutor, the
					Queen of the Ethiopians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> signifies allegorically the
					south winds from Ethiopia ; for whenever these gain
					the upper hand over the northerly or Etesian winds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 898 a, and Diodorus, i. 39.</note>
					which drive the clouds towards Ethiopia, and when
					they prevent the falling of the rains which cause the
					rising of the Nile, then Typhon, being in possession,
					blazes with scorching heat ; and having gained complete mastery, he forces the Nile in retreat to draw
					back its waters for weakness, and, flowing at the
					bottom of its almost empty channel, to proceed to the
					sea. The story told of the shutting up of Osiris in the
					chest seems to mean nothing else than the vanishing
					and disappearance of water. Consequently they say
					that the disappearance of Osiris occurred in the month
					of Athyr,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The month of November.</note> at the time when, owing to the complete
					cessation of the Etesian winds, the Nile recedes to its
					low level and the land becomes denuded. As the nights
					grow longer, the darkness increases, and the potency
					of the light is abated and subdued. Then among the
					gloomy rites which the priests perform, they shroud
					the gilded image of a cow with a black linen vestment,
					and display her as a sign of mourning for the goddess,
					inasmuch as they regard both the cow and the earth<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 366 a <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.97"/>
					
					as the image of Isis ; and this is kept up for four days
					consecutively, beginning with the seventeenth of the
					month. The things mourned for are four in number :
					first, the departure and recession of the Nile ; second,
					the complete extinction of the north winds, as the
					south winds gain the upper hand ; third, the day's
					growing shorter than the night; and, to crown all,
					the denudation of the earth together with the defoliation of the trees and shrubs at this time. On the
					nineteenth day they go down to the sea at nighttime ; and the keepers of the robes and the priests
					bring forth the sacred chest containing a small golden
					coffer, into which they pour some potable water
					which they have taken up, and a great shout arises
					from the company for joy that Osiris is found. Then
					they knead some fertile soil with the water and mix
					in spices and incense of a very costly sort, and fashion
					therefrom a crescent-shaped figure, which they clothe
					and adorn, thus indicating that they regard these
					gods as the substance of Earth and Water.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>When Isis recovered Osiris and was watching
					Horus grow up<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 357 c-f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> as he was being made strong by the
					exhalations and mists and clouds, Typhon was vanquished but not annihilated<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; for the goddess who
					holds sway over the Earth would not permit the
					complete annihilation of the nature opposed to moisture, but relaxed and moderated it, being desirous
					that its tempering potency should persist, because it
					w as not possible for a complete world to exist, if the
					fiery element left it and disappeared. Even if this
					story were not current among them, one would hardly
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.99"/>
					
					be justified in rejecting that other account, to the
					effect that Typhon, many ages ago, held sway over
					Osiris's domain ; for Egypt used to be all a sea,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 5; Diodorus, iii. 3, and i. 39. 11.</note> and,
					for that reason, even to-day it is found to have shells
					in its mines and mountains.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 12.</note> Moreover, all the
					springs and wells, of which there are many, have a
					saline and brackish water, as if some stale dregs of
					the ancient sea had collected there.
				</p>
            <p>
					But, in time, Horas overpowered Typhon ; that is
					to say, there carne on a timely abundance of rain, and
					the Nile forced out the sea and revealed the fertile
					land, which it filled out with its alluvial deposits. This
					has support in the testimony of our own observation ;
					for we see, even to-day, as the river brings down new
					silt and advances the land, that the deep waters
					gradually recede and, as the bottom gains in height
					by reason of the alluvial deposits, the water of the
					sea runs off from these. We also note that Pharos,
					which Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv. 356. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Strabo, xii. 2. 4 (p. 536), and xvii. 1. 6 (p. 791).</note> knew as distant a day's sail from
					Egypt, is now a part of it ; not that the island has
					extended its area by rising, or has come nearer to the
					land, but the sea that separated them was obliged to
					retire before the river, as the river reshaped the land
					and made it to increase.
				</p>
            <p>
					The fact is that all this is somewhat like the doctrines promulgated by the Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 1093 (p. 319).</note> about the gods ;
					for they say that the creative and fostering spirit is
					Dionysus, the truculent and destructive is Heracles,
					the receptive is Ammon, that which pervades the
					Earth and its products is Demeter and the Daughter,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.101"/>
					
					and that which pervades the Sea is Poseidon.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Deorum</hi>, i. 15 (40), ii. 28 (71); and Diogenes Laertius, vii. 147.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>But the Egyptians, by combining with these
					physical explanations some of the scientific results
					derived from astronomy, think that by Typhon is
					meant the solar world, and by Osiris the lunar world ;
					they reason that the moon, because it has a light that
					is generative and productive of moisture,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 658 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> is kindly
					towards the young of animals and the burgeoning
					plants, whereas the sun, by its untempered and pitiless heat, makes all growing and flourishing vegetation hot and parched, and, through its blazing light,
					renders a large part of the earth uninhabitable, and
					in many a region overpowers the moon. For this
					reason the Egyptians regularly call Typhon <q direct="unspecified">Seth,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 371 b and 376 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					which, being interpreted, means <q direct="unspecified">overmastering and
						compelling.</q> They have a legend that Heracles,
					making his dwelling in the sun, is a companion for it
					in its revolutions, as is the case also with Hermes and
					the moon. In fact, the actions of the moon are like
					actions of reason and perfect wisdom, whereas those
					of the sun are like beatings administered through
					violence and brute strength. The Stoics<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. 663. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Diogenes Laertius, vii. 145; and Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Antro Nympharum</hi>, 11.</note> assert that
					the sun is kindled and fed from the sea, but that for
					the moon the moving waters from the springs and
					lakes send up a sweet and mild exhalation.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>The Egyptians have a legend that the end of
					Osiris s life came on the seventeenth of the month, on
					which day it is quite evident to the eye that the
					period of the full moon is over.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Fourteen days, or one half of a lunar month, before the <foreign lang="greek">e(/nh kai\ ne/a</foreign>, if the lunar month could ever be made to square with any system of chronology!</note> Because of this the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.103"/>
					
					Pythagoreans call this day <q direct="unspecified">the Barrier,</q> and utterly
					abominate this number. For the number seventeen,
					coming in between the square sixteen and the oblong
					rectangle eighteen, which, as it happens, are the only
					plane figures that have their perimeters equal to their
					areas,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is: 4 x 4 = 16 and 4 + 4 + 4 + 4 = 16: so also 3 x 6 = 18 and 3 + 6 + 3 + 6 = 18.</note> bars them off from each other and disjoins
					them, and breaks up the ratio of eight to eight and an
					eighth<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, 1/8 of a number added to itself: thus 16 + 16/8 = 18. Eighteen, therefore, bears the epogdoon relation to sixteen, which is broken up by the intervention of seventeen, an odd number.</note> by its division into unequal intervals.
				</p>
            <p>
					Some say that the years of Osiris's life, others that
					the years of his reign, were twenty-eight<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; for that is
					the number of the moon's illuminations, and in that
					number of days does she complete her cycle. The
					wood which they cut on the occasions called the
					<q direct="unspecified">burials of Osiris</q> they fashion into a crescent-shaped
					coffer because of the fact that the moon, when it
					comes near the sun, becomes crescent-shaped and
					disappears from our sight. The dismemberment of
					Osiris into fourteen parts they refer allegorically to
					the days of the waning of that satellite from the time
					of the full moon to the new moon. And the day on
					which she becomes visible after escaping the solar rays
					and passing by the sun they style <q direct="unspecified">Incomplete Good</q>;
					for Osiris is beneficent, and his name means many
					things, but, not least of all, an active and beneficent
					power, as they put it. The other name of the god,
					Omphis, Hermaeus says means <q direct="unspecified">benefactor</q> when
					interpreted.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>They think that the risings of the Nile have
					some relation to the illuminations of the moon ; for
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.105"/>
					
					the greatest rising,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Besides the famous ancient Nilometer at Elephantin&ecirc;, others have been found at Philae, Edfu, and Esna.</note> in the neighbourhood of Elephantin&ecirc;, is twenty-eight cubits, which is the number of its
					illuminations that form the measure of each of its
					monthly cycles ; the rising in the neighbourhood of
					Mendes and Xo&iuml;s, which is the least, is six cubits,
					corresponding to the first quarter. The mean rising,
					in the neighbourhood of Memphis, when it is normal,
					is fourteen cubits, corresponding to the full moon.
				</p>
            <p>
					The Apis, they say, is the animate image of Osiris,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 b and 362 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					and he comes into being when a fructifying light
					thrusts forth from the moon and falls upon a cow in her
					breeding-season.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 718 b, and Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, xi. 10.</note> Wherefore there are many things
					in the Apis that resemble features of the moon, his
					bright parts being darkened by the shadowy. Moreover, at the time of the new moon in the month of
					Pharnenoth they celebrate a festival to which they
					give the name of <q direct="unspecified">Osiris's coming to the Moon,</q> and
					this marks the beginning of the spring. Thus they
					make the power of Osiris to be fixed in the Moon, and
					say that Isis, since she is generation, is associated
					with him. For this reason they also call the Moon the
					mother of the world, and they think that she has a
					nature both male and female, as she is receptive and
					made pregnant by the Sun, but she herself in turn emits
					and disseminates into the air generative principles.
					For, as they believe, the destructive activity of
					Typhon does not always prevail, but oftentimes is
					overpowered by such generation and put in bonds, and
					then at a later time is again released and contends
					against Horus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> who is the terrestrial universe ; and
					this is never completely exempt either from dissolution or from generation.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.107"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>There are some who would make the legend an
					allegorical reference to matters touching eclipses ; for
					the Moon suffers eclipse only when she is full, with
					the Sun directly opposite to her, and she falls into the
					shadow of the Earth, as they say Osiris fell into his
					coffin. Then again, the Moon herself obscures the
					Sun and causes solar eclipses, always on the thirtieth
					of the month ; however, she does not completely
					annihilate the Sun, and likewise Isis did not annihilate
					Typhon.
				</p>
            <p>
					When Nephthys gave birth to Anubis, Isis treated
					the child as if it were her own<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; for Nephthys is
					that which is beneath the Earth and invisible, Isis
					that which is above the earth and visible ; and the
					circle which touches these, called the horizon, being
					common to both,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 375 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> has received the name Anubis, and
					is represented in form like a dog ; for the dog can see
					with his eyes both by night and by day alike. And
					among the Egyptians Anubis is thought to possess
					this faculty, which is similar to that which Hecat&ecirc; is
					thought to possess among the Greeks, for Anubis is a
					deity of the lower world as well as a god of Olympus.
					Some are of the opinion that Anubis is Cronus. For
					this reason, inasmuch as he generates all things out
					of himself and conceives all things within himself, he
					has gained the appellation of <q direct="unspecified">Dog.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch would connect <foreign lang="greek">ku/wn</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">dog,</q> with the participle of <foreign lang="greek">kuw=</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">be pregnant.</q> If the animal were a bear, we might say, <q direct="unspecified">bears all things . . . the appellation of Bear,</q> which would be a very close parallel.</note> There is,
					therefore, a certain mystery observed by those who
					revere Anubis; in ancient times the dog obtained the
					highest honours in Egypt; but, when Cambyses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 355 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> had
					slain the Apis and cast him forth, nothing came near
					the body or ate of it save only the dog ; and thereby
					the dog lost his primacy and his place of honour above
					that of all the other animals.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.109"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					There are some who give the name of Typhon to the
					Earth's shadow, into which they believe the moon
					slips when it suffers eclipse.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 373 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>Hence it is not
					unreasonable to say that the statement of each person
					individually is not right, but that the statement of all
					collectively is right; for it is not drought nor wind nor
					sea nor darkness,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 364 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 376 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> but everything harmful and destructive that Nature contains, which is to be set down
					as a part of Typhon. The origins of the universe are
					not to be placed in inanimate bodies, according to
					the doctrine of Democritus and Epicurus, nor yet is
					the Artificer of undifferentiated matter, according to
					the Stoic doctrine,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta</hi>, ii. p. 1108, and Diogenes Laertius, vii. 134.</note> one Reason, and one Providence
					which gains the upper hand and prevails over all
					things. The fact is that it is impossible for anything
					bad whatsoever to be engendered where God is the
					Author of all, or anything good where God is the
					Author of nothing ; for the concord of the universe,
					like that of a lyre or bow, according to Heracleitus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 87, no. b 51. Plutarch quotes this again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 473 f and 1026 b.</note>
					is resilient if disturbed ; and according to Euripides,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Euripides, no. 21, from the <hi rend="italics">Aeolus</hi>; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 25 c and 474 a.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The good and bad cannot be kept apart,
					</l>
                  <l>But there is some commingling, which is well.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Wherefore this very ancient opinion comes dowTn
					from writers on religion and from lawgivers to poets
					and philosophers ; it can be traced to no source, but
					it carried a strong and almost indelible conviction, and
					is in circulation in many places among barbarians and
					Greeks alike, not only in story and tradition but also
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.111"/>
					
					in rites and sacrifices, to the effect that the Universe
					is not of itself suspended aloft without sense or reason
					or guidance, nor is there one Reason which rules and
					guides it by rudders, as it were, or by controlling
					reins,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The language is reminiscent of a fragment of Sophocles quoted by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 767 e, and <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. vii. (668 b). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>, Sophocles, no. 785. <q direct="unspecified">A task for many reins and rudders too</q> (<foreign lang="greek">pollw=n xalinw=n e)/rgon oi)a/kwn q' a(/ma</foreign>).</note> but, inasmuch as Nature brings, in this life of
					ours, many experiences in which both evil and good
					are commingled, or better, to put it very simply,
					Nature brings nothing which is not combined with
					something else, we may assert that it is not one
					keeper of two great vases<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The reference is to Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 527-528, as misquoted in Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 379 d. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 24 a (and the note), 105 c (and the ntoe), and 473 b. <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 600 c, is helpful in understanding the present passage.</note> who, after the manner of
					a barmaid, deals out to us our failures and successes
					in mixture, but it has come about, as the result of two
					opposed principles and two antagonistic forces, one of
					which guides us along a straight course to the right,
					while the other turns us aside and backward, that
					our life is complex, and so also is the universe ; and
					if this is not true of the whole of it, yet it is true that
					this terrestrial universe, including its moon as well, is
					irregular and variable and subject to all manner of
					changes. For if it is the law of Nature that nothing
					comes into being without a cause, and if the good
					cannot provide a cause for evil, then it follows that
					Nature must have in herself the source and origin of
					evil, just as she contains the source and origin of good.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>The great majority and the wisest of men hold
					this opinion : they believe that there are two gods,
					rivals as it were, the one the Artificer of good and the
					other of evil. There are also those who call the better
					one a god and the other a daemon, as, for example,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.113"/>
					
					Zoroaster<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The casual reader will gain a better understanding of chapters 46 and 47 if he will consult some brief book or article on Zoroaster (Zarathustra) and the Persian religion.</note> the sage,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, one of the Persian Magi or Wise Men.</note> who, they record, lived five
					thousand years before the time of the Trojan War. He
					called the one Oromazes and the other Areimanius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1026 b, and Diogenes Laertius, <hi rend="italics">Prologue</hi>, 2.</note>;
					and he further declared that among all the things perceptible to the senses, Oromazes may best be compared
					to light, and Areimanius, conversely, to darkness and
					ignorance, and midway between the two is Mithras ;
					for this reason the Persians give to Mithras the name,
					of <q direct="unspecified">Mediator.</q> Zoroaster has also taught that men
					should make votive offerings and thank-offerings to
					Oromazes, and averting and mourning offerings to
					Areimanius. They pound up in a mortar a certain
					plant called omomi, at the same time invoking Hades<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, <hi rend="italics">Prologue</hi>, 8.</note>
					and Darkness ; then they mix it with the blood of a
					wolf that has been sacrificed, and carry it out and
					cast it into a place where the sun never shines. In
					fact, they believe that some of the plants belong to
					the good god and others to the evil daemon ; so also
					of the animals they think that dogs, fowls, and hedgehogs, for example, belong to the good god, but that
					water-rats<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 537 a and 670 d.</note> belong to the evil one ; therefore the
					man who has killed the most of these they hold to
					be fortunate.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>However, they also tell many fabulous stories
					about their gods, such, for example, as the following :
					Oromazes, born from the purest light,and Areimanius.
					born from the darkness, are constantly at Avar with
					each other ; and Oromazes created six gods, the first
					of Good Thought, the second of Truth, the third of
					Order, and, of the rest, one of Wisdom, one of Wealth,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.115"/>
					
					and one the Artificer of Pleasure in what is Honourable. But Areimanius created rivals, as it were, equal
					to these in number. Then Oromazes enlarged himself to thrice his former size, and removed himself as
					far distant from the Sun as the Sun is distant from
					the Earth, and adorned the heavens with stars. One
					star he set there before all others as a guardian and
					watchman, the Dog-star. Twenty-four other gods
					he created and placed in an egg. But those created
					by Areimanius, who were equal in number to the
					others, pierced through the egg and made their way
					inside<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">It is plain that the two sets of gods became intermingled, but whether the bad gods got in or the good gods got out is not clear from the text.</note>; hence evils are now combined with good.
					But a destined time shall come when it is decreed that
					Areimanius, engaged in bringing on pestilence and
					famine, shall by these be utterly annihilated and shall
					disappear ; and then shall the earth become a level
					plain, and there shall be one manner of life and one
					form of government for a blessed people who shall all
					speak o ne tongue. Theopompus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Jacoby, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Gr. Hist.</hi>, Theopompus, no. 65.</note> says that, according
					to the sages, one god is to overpower, and the other
					to be overpowered, each in turn for the space of three
					thousand years, and afterward for another three
					thousand years they shall fight and war, and the one
					shall undo the works of the other, and finally Hades
					shall pass away ; then shall the people be happy, and
					neither shall they need to have food nor shall they
					cast any shadow. And the god, who has contrived to
					bring about all these things, shall then have quiet and
					shall repose for a time,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The meaning of the text is clear enough, but the wording of it is uncertain.</note> no long time indeed, but for
					the god as much as would be a moderate time for a
					man to sleep.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.117"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Such, then, is the character of the mythology of
					the sages. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>The Chaldeans declare that of the
					planets, which they call tutelary gods,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The translation is based on an emendation of Wyttenbach's, which makes the words refer to Chaldean astrology (<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the planet under which one is born). <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Adversus Mathematicos</hi>, v. 29.</note> two are
					beneficent, two maleficent, and the other three are
					median and partake of both qualities. The beliefs
					of the Greeks are well known to all; they make
					the good part to belong to Olympian Zeus and the
					abominated part to Hades, and they rehearse a
					legend that Concord is sprung from Aphrodit&ecirc; and
					Ares,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, from Love and War.</note> the one of whom is harsh and contentious,
					and the other mild and tutelary.
					Observe also that the philosophers are in agreement with these ; for Heracleitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 88, no. b 53.</note> without reservation styles War <q direct="unspecified">the Father and King and Lord of
						All,</q> and he says that when Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xviii. 107, but Plutarch modifies the line to suit his context.</note> prays that
					<quote rend="blockquote">Strife may vanish away from the ranks of the gods and of
					mortals,</quote>
					lie fails to note that he is invoking a curse on the
					origin of all things, since all things originate from
					strife and antagonism; also Heracleitus says that
					the Sun will not transgress his appropriate bounds,
					otherwise the stern-eyed maidens, ministers of
					Justice, will find him out.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 604 a; Origen, <hi rend="italics">Against Celsus</hi>, vi. 42; Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 96, no. b 94.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Empedocles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> p. 232, Empedocles, no. 18; p. 239, no. 17, 1. 19; and p. 269, no. 122 (=<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 474 b).</note> calls the beneficent principle <q direct="unspecified">friendship</q> or <q direct="unspecified">friendliness,</q> and oftentimes he calls Concord
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.119"/>
					
					          <q direct="unspecified">sedate of countenance</q>; the worse principle
					he calls <q direct="unspecified">accursed quarrelling</q> and <q direct="unspecified">blood-stained
						strife.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The adherents of Pythagoras<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 881 e, and Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Metaphysics</hi>, i. 5 (986 a 22).</note> include a variety of
					terms under these categories : under the good they
					set Unity, the Determinate, the Permanent, the
					Straight, the Odd, the Square, the Equal, the Righthanded, the Bright; under the bad they set Duality,
					the Indeterminate, the Moving, the Curved, the
					Even, the Oblong, the Unequal, the Left-handed, the
					Dark, on the supposition that these are the underlying principles of creation. For these, however,
					Anaxagoras postulates Mind and Infinitude, Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Metaphysics</hi>, i. 9 (990 b).</note> Form and Privation, and Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 35 a; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 441 f.</note> in many
					passages, as though obscuring and veiling his
					opinion, names the one of the opposing principles
					<q direct="unspecified">Identity</q> and the other <q direct="unspecified">Difference</q> ; but in his
					Laws,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 896 d ff.</note> when he had grown considerably older, he
					asserts, not in circumlocution or symbolically, but. in
					specific words, that the movement of the Universe
					is actuated not by one soul, but perhaps by several,
					and certainly by not less than two, and of these the
					one is beneficent, and the other is opposed to it
					and the artificer of things opposed. Between these
					he leaves a certain third nature, not inanimate
					nor irrational nor without the power to move
					of itself,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 374 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> as some think, but with dependence on
					both those others, and desiring the better always
					and yearning after it and pursuing it, as the succeeding portion of the treatise will make clear, in the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.121"/>
					
					endeavour to reconcile the religious beliefs of the
					Egyptians with this philosophy.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 372 e and 377 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>The fact is that the creation and constitution
					of this world is complex, resulting, as it does, from
					opposing influences, which, however, are not of equal
					strength, but the predominance rests with the better.
					Yet it is impossible for the bad to be completely
					eradicated, since it is innate, in large amount, in the
					body and likewise in the soul of the Universe, and is
					always fighting a hard fight against the better. So
					in the soul Intelligence and Reason, the Ruler and
					Lord of all that is good, is Osiris, and in earth and
					wind and water and the heavens and stars that which
					is ordered, established, and healthy, as evidenced by
					seasons, temperatures, and cycles of revolution, is the
					efflux of Osiris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on 365 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and his reflected image. But Typhon
					is that part of the soul which is impressionable, impulsive, irrational and truculent, and of the bodily part
					the destructible, diseased and disorderly as evidenced
					by abnormal seasons and temperatures, and by obscurations of the sun and disappearances of the moon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 368 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					outbursts, as it were, and unruly actions on the part
					of Typhon. And the name <q direct="unspecified">Seth,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 367 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and 376 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> by which they
					call Typhon, denotes this ; it means <q direct="unspecified">the overmastering</q> and <q direct="unspecified">overpowering,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">So also in the Egyptian papyri.</note> and it means in very many
					instances <q direct="unspecified">turning back,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 376 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and again <q direct="unspecified">overpassing.</q>
					Some say that one of the companions of Typhon was
					Bebon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 376 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> but Manetho says that Bebon was still
					another name by which Typhon was called. The
					name signifies <q direct="unspecified">restraint</q> or <q direct="unspecified">hindrance,</q> as much as
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.123"/>
					
					to say that, when things are going along in a proper
					way and making rapid progress towards the right
					end, the power of Typhon obstructs them. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>For
					this reason they assign to him the most stupid of the
					domesticated animals, the ass, and of the wild animals,
					the most savage, the crocodile and the hippopotamus.
				</p>
            <p>
					In regard to the ass we have already<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi>, 362 f.</note> offered some
					explanation. At Hermopolis they point out a statue
					of Typhon in the form of an hippopotamus, on whose
					back is poised a hawk fighting with a serpent. By the
					hippopotamus they mean to indicate Typhon, and by
					the hawk a power and rule, which Typhon strives to
					win by force, oftentimes without success, being confused by his wickedness and creating confusion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text and significance of this passage are none too clear.</note> For
					this reason, when they offer sacrifice on the seventh
					day of the month Tybi, which they call the <q direct="unspecified">Coming
						of Isis from Phoenicia,</q> they imprint on their sacred
					cakes the image of an hippopotamus tied fast. In
					the town of Apollonopolis it is an established custom
					for every person without exception to eat, of a crocodile<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 69; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, x. 21; Strabo, xvii. 1. 47 (p. 817).</note>; and on one day they hunt as many as they
					can and, after killing them, cast them down directly
					opposite the temple. And they relate that Typhon
					escaped Horus by turning into a crocodile, and they
					would make out that all animals and plants and incidents that are bad and harmful are the deeds and
					parts and movements of Typhon.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="51">
            <p>Then again, they depict Osiris by means of an
					eye and a sceptre,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 354 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> the one of which indicates forethought and the other power, much as Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, viii. 22.</note> in
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.125"/>
					
					calling the Lord and King of all <q direct="unspecified">Zeus supreme and
						counsellor</q> appears by <q direct="unspecified">supreme</q> to signify his prowess
					and by <q direct="unspecified">counsellor</q> his careful planning and thoughtfulness. They also often depict this god by means of
					a hawk ; for this bird is surpassing in the keenness of
					its vision and the swiftness of its flight, and is wont
					to support itself with the minimum amount of food.
					It is said also in flying over the earth to cast dust
					upon the eyes of unburied dead<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, ii. 42, and Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iv. 9.</note>; and whenever it
					settles down beside the river to drink it raises its
					feather upright, and after it has drunk it lets this
					sink down again, by which it is plain that the bird
					is safe and has escaped the crocodile,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> x. 24.</note> for if it be
					seized, the feather remains fixed upright as it was
					at the beginning.
				</p>
            <p>
					Everywhere they point out statues of Osiris in
					human form of the ithyphallic type, on account of
					his creative and fostering power<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 365 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; and they clothe
					his statues in a flame-coloured garment, since they
					regard the body of the Sun as a visible manifestation
					of the perceptible substance of the power for good.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 393 d and 477 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
					Therefore it is only right and fair to contemn those
					who assign the orb of the Sun to Typhon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 372 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> to whom
					there attaches nothing bright or of a conserving nature,
					no order nor generation nor movement possessed
					of moderation or reason, but everything the reverse ; moreover, the drought,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 367 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> by which he destroys
					many of the living creatures and growing plants, is
					not to be set down as the work of the Sun, but rather
					as due to the fact that the winds and waters in the
					earth and the air are not seasonably tempered when
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.127"/>
					
					the principle of the disorderly and unlimited power
					gets out of hand and quenches the exhalations.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 369 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="52">
            <p>In the sacred hymns of Osiris they call upon
					him who is hidden in the arms of the Sun ; and on
					the thirtieth of the month Epiphi they celebrate the
					birthday of the Eyes of Horus, at the time when the
					Moon and the Sun are in a perfectly straight line,
					since they regard not only the Moon but also the Sun
					as the eye and light of Horus.
				</p>
            <p>
					On the 8th of the waning of the month Phaophi
					they conduct the birthday of the Staff of the Sun
					following upon the autumnal equinox, and by this
					they declare, as it were, that he is in need of support
					and strength, since he becomes lacking in warmth and
					light, and undergoes decline, and is carried away from
					us to one side.
				</p>
            <p>
					Moreover, at the time of the winter solstice they
					lead the cow seven times around the temple of the
					Sun and this circumambulation is called the Seeking
					for Osiris, since the Goddess in the winter-time yearns
					for water ; so many times do they go around, because
					in the seventh month the Sun completes the transition
					from the winter solstice to the summer solstice. It is
					said also that Horus, the son of Isis, offered sacrifice to
					the Sun first of all on the fourth day of the month, as
					is written in the records entitled the Birthdays of
					Horus.
				</p>
            <p>
					Every day they make a triple offering of incense to
					the Sun, an offering of resin at sunrise, of myrrh at
					midday, and of the so-called <hi rend="italics">cyphi</hi> at sunset; the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.129"/>
					
					reason which underlies each one of these offerings I
					will describe later.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 383 a-end, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> They think that by means of all
					these they supplicate and serve the Sun. Yet, what
					need is there to collect many such things ? There are
					some who without reservation assert that Osiris is the
					Sun and is called the Dog-star (Sirius) by the Greeks<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An attempt to connect <foreign lang="greek">*)/osiris</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">o( *si/rios</foreign>? <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 11. 3-4.</note>
					even if among the Egyptians the addition of the
					article has created some ambiguity in regard to the
					name ; and there are those who declare that Isis is
					none other than the  ; for this reason it is said
					that the statues of Isis that bear horns are imitations
					of the crescent moon, and in her dark garments are
					shown the concealments and the obscurations in which
					she in her yearning pursues the Sun. For this reason
					also they call upon the Moon in love affairs, and
					Eudoxus asserts that Isis is a deity who presides over
					love affairs. These people may lay claim to a certain
					plausibility, but no one should listen for a moment to
					those who make Typhon to be the Sun.
				</p>
            <p>
					But let us now take up again the proper subject
					of our discussion. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="53">
            <p>Isis is, in fact, the female
					principle of Nature, and is receptive of every form
					of generation, in accord with which she is called by
					Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 49 a and 51 a; also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1014 d, 1015 d, and 1023 a.</note> the gentle nurse and the all-receptive, and
					by most people has been called by countless names,
					since, because of the force of Reason, she turns
					herself to this thing or that and is receptive of all
					manner of shapes and forms. She has an innate
					love for the first and most dominant of all things,
					which is identical with the good, and this she yearns
					for and pursues ; but the portion which comes from
					evil she tries to avoid and to reject, for she serves
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.131"/>
					
					them both as a place and means of growth, but inclines always towards the better and offers to it
					opportunity to create from her and to impregnate her
					with effluxes and likenesses in which she rejoices and
					is glad that she is made pregnant and teeming with
					these creations. For creation is the image of being in
					matter, and the thing created is a picture of reality.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="54">
            <p>It is not, therefore, out of keeping that they
					have a legend that the soul of Osiris is everlasting and
					imperishable, but that his body Typhon oftentimes
					dismembers and causes to disappear, and that Isis
					wanders hither and yon in her search for it, and fits
					it together again<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; for that which really is and is
					perceptible and good is superior to destruction and
					change. The images from it with which the sensible
					and corporeal is impressed, and the relations, forms,
					and likenesses which this takes upon itself, like impressions of seals in wax, are not permanently lasting,
					but disorder and disturbance overtakes them, being
					driven hither from the upper reaches, and fighting
					against Horus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> whom Isis brings forth, beholden of
					all, as the image of the perceptible world. Therefore
					it is said that he is brought to trial by Typhon on
					the charge of illegitimacy, as not being pure nor uncontaminated like his father, reason unalloyed and
					unaffected of itself, but contaminated in his substance
					because of the corporeal element. He prevails,
					however, and wins the case when Hermes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> that is to
					say Reason, testifies and points out that Nature, by
					undergoing changes of form with reference to the
					perceptible, duly brings about the creation of the world.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.133"/>
					
					The birth of Apollo from Isis and Osiris, while these
					gods were still in the womb of Rhea, has the allegorical meaning that before this world was made vis ible and its rough material was completely formed by
					Reason, it was put to the test by Nature and brought
					forth of itself the first creation imperfect. This is the
					reason why they say that this god was born in the
					darkness a cripple, and they call him the elder Horus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>;
					for there was then no world, but only an image and
					outline of a world to be.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="55">
            <p>But this Horus is himself perfected and complete ; but he has not done away completely with
					Typhon, but has taken away his activity and strength.
					Hence they say that at Kopto the statue of Horus
					holds in one hand the privy members of Typhon, and
					they relate a legend that Hermes cut out the sinews
					of Typhon, and used them as strings for his lyre,
					thereby instructing us that Reason adjusts the
					Universe and creates concord out of discordant
					elements, and that it does not destroy but only
					cripples the destructive force. Hence this is weak
					and inactive here, and combines with the susceptible
					and changeable elements and attaches itself to them,
					becoming the artificer of quakes and tremblings in
					the earth, and of droughts and tempestuous winds
					in the air, and of lightning-flashes and thunderbolts.
					Moreover, it taints waters and winds with pestilence,
					and it runs forth wanton even as far as the moon,
					oftentimes confounding and darkening the moon's
					brightness ; according to the belief and account of
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.135"/>
					
					the Egyptians, Typhon at one time smites the eye
					of Horus, and at another time snatches it out and
					swallows it, and then later gives it back again to the
					Sun. By the smiting, they refer allegorically to the
					monthly waning of the moon, and by the crippling, to
					its eclipse,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 368 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> which the Sun heals by shining straight
					upon it as soon as it has escaped the shadow of the
					earth.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="56">
            <p>The better and more divine nature consists of
					three parts : the conceptual, the material, and that
					which is formed from these, which the Greeks call the
					world. Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 50 c-d.</note> is wont to give to the conceptual the
					name of idea, example, or father, and to the material
					the name of mother or nurse, or seat and place of
					generation, and to that which results from both the
					name of offspring or generation.
				</p>
            <p>
					One might conjecture that the Egyptians hold in
					high honour the most beautiful of the triangles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 393 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> since
					they liken the nature of the Universe most closely to
					it, as Plato in the <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 546 b-c.</note> seems to have made use of
					it in formulating his figure of marriage. This triangle
					has its upright of three units, its base of four, and its
					hypotenuse of five, whose power is equal to that of
					the other two sides.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 429 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> The upright, therefore, may be
					likened to the male, the base to the female, and the
					hypotenuse to the child of both, and so Osiris may be
					regarded as the origin, Isis as the recipient, and Horus
					as perfected result. Three is the first perfect odd
					number : four is a square whose side is the even
					number two ; but five is in some ways like to its
					father, and in some wrays like to its mother, being
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.137"/>
					
					made up of three and two.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 264 a, and Rose, <hi rend="italics">Plutarch's Roman Questions</hi>, p. 170.</note> And panta (all) is a
					derivative of <hi rend="italics">pente</hi> (five), and they speak of counting
					as <q direct="unspecified">numbering by fives.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 387 e and 429 d-f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> Five makes a square of
					itself, as many as the letters of the Egyptian alphabet,
					and as many as the years of the life of the Apis.
				</p>
            <p>
					Horus they are wont to call also Min, which means
					<q direct="unspecified">seen</q> ; for the world is something perceptible and
					visible, and Isis is sometimes called Muth, and again
					Athyri or Methyer. By the first of these names they
					signify <q direct="unspecified">mother,</q> by the second the mundane house
					of Horus, the place and receptacle of generation, as
					Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 52 d-53 a. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 882 c and 1023 a.</note> has it, and the third is compounded of <q direct="unspecified">full</q>
					and <q direct="unspecified">cause</q> ; for the material of the world is full,
					and is associated with the good and pure and orderly.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="57">
            <p>It might appear that Hesiod,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 116-122.</note> in making the
					very first things of all to be Chaos and Earth and
					Tartarus and Love, did not accept any other origins
					but only these, if we transfer the names somewhat
					and assign to Isis the name of Earth and to Osiris the
					name of Love and to Typhon the name of Tartarus ;
					for the poet seems to place Chaos at the bottom as
					a sort of region that serves as a resting-place for the
					Universe.
				</p>
            <p>
					This subject seems in some wise to call up the myth
					of Plato, which Socrates in the <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 203 b.</note> gives at
					some length in regard to the birth of Love, saying
					that Poverty, wishing for children, insinuated herself
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.139"/>
					
					beside Plenty while he was asleep, and having become
					pregnant by him, gave birth to Love, who is of a mixed
					and utterly variable nature, inasmuch as he is the son
					of a father who is good and wise and self-sufficient in
					all things, but of a mother who is helpless and without
					means and because of want always clinging close to
					another and always importunate over another. For
					Plenty is none other than the first beloved and desired, the perfect and self-sufficient ; and Plato calls
					raw material Poverty, utterly lacking of herself in
					the Good, but being filled from him and always
					yearning for him and sharing with him. The World,
					or Horus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 373 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> which is born of these, is not eternal nor
					unaffected nor imperishable, but, being ever reborn,
					contrives to remain always young and never subject
					to destruction in the changes and cycles of events.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="58">
            <p>We must not treat legend as if it were history
					at all, but we should adopt that which is appropriate
					in each legend in accordance with its verisimilitude.
					Whenever, therefore, we speak of material we must
					not be swept away to the opinions of some philosophers,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 370 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, and Diogenes Laertius, vii. 134.</note> and conceive of an inanimate and indifferentiated body, which is of itself inert and inactive.
					The fact is that we call oil the material of perfume
					and gold the material of a statue, and these are not
					destitute of all differentiation. We provide the very
					soul and thought of Man as the basic material of
					understanding and virtue for Reason to adorn and to
					harmonize, and some have declared the Mind to be
					a place for the assembling of forms and for the impression of concepts, as it were.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Anima</hi>, iii. 4 (429 a 27).</note>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.141"/>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Some think the seed of Woman is not a power or
					origin, but only material and nurture of generation.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 651 c, and 905 c.</note>
					To this thought we should eling fast and conceive that
					this Goddess also who participates always with the
					first God and is associated with him in the love<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 372 e, and 383 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> of
					the fair and lovely things about him is not opposed
					to him, but, just as we say that an honourable and
					just man is in love if his relations are just, and a good
					woman who has a husband and consorts with him we
					say yearns for him ; thus we may conceive of her as
					always clinging close to him and being importunate
					over him and constantly filled with the most dominant and purest principles. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="59">
            <p>But where Typhon
					forces his way in and seizes upon the outermost areas,
					there we may conceive of her as seeming sad, and
					spoken of as mourning, and that she seeks for the
					remains and scattered members of Osiris and arrays
					them, receiving and hiding away the things perishable, from which she brings to light again the things
					that are created and sends them forth from herself.
				</p>
            <p>
					The relations and forms and effluxes of the God
					abide in the heavens and in the stars ; but those things
					that are distributed in susceptible elements, earth
					and sea and plants and animals, suffer dissolution and
					destruction and burial, and oftentimes again shine
					forth and appear again in their generations. For this
					reason the fable has it that Typhon cohabits with
					Nephthys<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and that Osiris has secret relations with
					her<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 356 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; for the destructive power exercises special
					dominion over the outermost part of matter which
					they call Nephthys or Finality.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 355 f and 366 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> But the creating
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.143"/>
					
					and conserving power distributes to this only a weak
					and feeble seed, which is destroyed by Typhon,
					except so much as Isis takes up and preserves and
					fosters and makes firm and strong.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 356 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="60">
            <p>In general this god is the better, as both Plato
					and Aristotle conceive. The creative and conserving
					element of Nature moves toward him and toward
					existence while the annihilating and destructive
					moves away from him towards non-existence. For
					this reason they call Isis by a name derived from
					<q direct="unspecified">hastening</q> (<hi rend="italics">hiemai</hi>) with understanding,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 351 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> or being
					borne onward (<hi rend="italics">pheromai</hi>), since she is an animate and
					intelligent movement; for the name is not a foreign
					name, but, just as all the gods have a name in
					common<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 397 d.</note> derived from two words, <q direct="unspecified">visible</q> (<hi rend="italics">theaton</hi>)
					and <q direct="unspecified">rushing</q> (<hi rend="italics">theon</hi>), in the same way this goddess,
					from her understanding<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 351 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and her movement, we call
					Isis and the Egyptians call her Isis. So also Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 401 c.</note>
					says that the men of ancient times made clear the
					meaning of <q direct="unspecified">essence</q> (<hi rend="italics">ousia</hi>) by calling it <q direct="unspecified">sense</q>
					(<hi rend="italics">ista</hi>). So also he speaks of the intelligence and
					understanding as being a carrying and movement
					of mind hasting and being carried onward; and also
					comprehension and good and virtue they attribute
					to those things which are ever flowing and in rapid
					motion, just as again, on the other hand, by means of
					antithetical names they vilified evil: for example, that
					which hinders and binds fast and holds and checks
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.145"/>
					
					Nature from hasting and going they called baseness,
					or <q direct="unspecified">ill-going</q> (<hi rend="italics">kak-ia</hi>), and helplessness or <q direct="unspecified">difficulty of going</q> (<hi rend="italics">apor-ia</hi>), and cowardice or <q direct="unspecified">fear of
						going</q> (<hi rend="italics">deil-ia</hi>), and distress or <q direct="unspecified">not going</q> (<hi rend="italics">an-ia</hi>).<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 376 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>. It is impossible to reproduce these fanciful derivations in an English translation. Most of them may be found in Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 401 c-415 e. Note that Plutarch would connect the abstract suffix -<foreign lang="greek">i/a</foreign> with the shorter stem of <foreign lang="greek">ei)=mi</foreign> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">go.</q>
               </note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="61">
            <p>Osiris has a name made up from <q direct="unspecified">holy</q> (<hi rend="italics">hosion</hi>)
					and <q direct="unspecified">sacred</q> (<hi rend="italics">kieron</hi>)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 382 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; for he is the combined relation of the things in the heavens and in the lower
					world, the former of which it was customary for
					people of olden time to call sacred and the latter to
					call holy. But the relation which discloses the things
					in the heavens and belongs to the things which tend
					upward is sometimes named Anubis and sometimes
					Hermanubis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Porphyry in Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praepar. Evang.</hi> iii. 11. 2.</note> as belonging in part to the things above
					and in part to the things below.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 368 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> For this reason
					they sacrifice to him on the one hand a white cock
					and on the other hand one of saffron colour, regarding
					the former things as simple and clear, and the others
					as combined and variable.
				</p>
            <p>
					There is no occasion to be surprised at the revamping of these words into Greek.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 362 d-e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> The fact is that
					countless other words went forth in company with
					those who migrated from Greece, and persist even to
					this day as strangers in strange lands; and, when the
					poetic art would recall some of these into use, those
					who speak of such words as strange or unusual falsely
					accuse it of using barbarisms. Moreover, they record
					that in the so-called books of Hermes it is written in
					regard to the sacred names that they call the power
					which is assigned to direct the revolution of the Sun
					Horus, but the Greeks call it Apollo ; and the power
					assigned to the wind some call Osiris and others
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.147"/>
					
					Serapis, and Sothis in Egyptian signifies <q direct="unspecified">pregnancy</q> (<hi rend="italics">caesis</hi>) or <q direct="unspecified">to be pregnant</q> (<hi rend="italics">cyein</hi>) : therefore in Greek, with a change of accent,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch attempts to connect <foreign lang="greek">ku/wn</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">dog,</q> with <foreign lang="greek">kuw=n</foreign>, the present participle of <foreign lang="greek">kuw=</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">to be pregnant.</q>
               </note> the star is
					called the Dog-star (<hi rend="italics">Cyon</hi>), which they regard as the
					special star of Isis.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 c-e and 365 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> Least of all is there any need
					of being very eager in learning about these names.
					However, I would rather make a concession to the
					Egyptians in regard to Serapis than in regard to
					Osiris ; for I regard Serapis as foreign, but Osiris as
					Greek, and both as belonging to one god and one
					power.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="62">
            <p>Like these also are the Egyptian beliefs ; for
					they oftentimes call Isis by the name of Athena,
					expressive of some such idea as this, <q direct="unspecified">I came of
						myself,</q> which is indicative of self-impelled motion.
					Typhon, as has been said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">367 d and 371 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> is named Seth and Bebon
					and Smu, and these names would indicate some forcible
					and preventive check or opposition or reversal.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 371 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					Moreover, they call the loadstone the bone of Horus,
					and iron the bone of Typhon, as Manetho<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 77.</note> records.
					For, as the iron oftentimes acts as if it were being
					attracted and drawn toward the stone, and oftentimes is rejected and repelled in the opposite direction,
					in the same way the salutary and good and rational
					movement of the world at one time, by persuasion,
					attracts and draws toward itself and renders more
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.149"/>
					
					gentle that harsh and Typhonian movement, and then
					again it gathers itself together and reverses it and
					plunges it into difficulties.
				</p>
            <p>
					Moreover, Eudoxus says that the Egyptians have
					a mythical tradition in regard to Zeus that, because
					his legs were grown together, he was not able to
					walk, and so, for shame, tarried in the wilderness ;
					but Isis, by severing and separating those parts of his
					body, provided him with means of rapid progress.
					This fable teaches by its legend that the mind and
					reason of the god, fixed amid the unseen and invisible, advanced to generation by reason of motion.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="63">
            <p>The sistrum (rattle) also makes it clear that
					all things in existence need to be shaken, or rattled
					about, and never to cease from motion but, as it were,
					to be waked up and agitated when they grow drowsy
					and torpid. They say that they avert and repel
					Typhon by means of the sistrums, indicating thereby
					that when destruction constricts and checks Nature,
					generation releases and arouses it by means of motion.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 375 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The upper part of the sistrum is circular and its
					circumference contains the four things that are
					shaken ; for that part of the world which undergoes
					reproduction and destruction is contained underneath
					the orb of the moon, and all things in it are subjected
					to motion and to change through the four elements :
					fire, earth, water, and air. At the top of the circumference of the sistrum they construct the figure of a
					cat with a human face, and at the bottom, below the
					things that are shaken, the face of Isis on one side,
					and on the other the face of Nephthys. By these
					faces they symbolize birth and death, for these are
					the changes and movements of the elements ; and by
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.151"/>
					
					the cat they symbolize the moon because of the varied
					colouring, nocturnal activity, and fecundity of the
					animal. For the cat is said to bring forth first one,
					then two and three and four and five, thus increasing
					the number by one until she reaches seven,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Photius, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi>, 242 (p. 343 a 5 ed. Bekker).</note> so that
					she brings forth in all twenty-eight, the number also
					of the moon's illuminations. Perhaps, however, this
					may seem somewhat mythical. But the pupils in the
					eye of the cat appear to growr large and round at the
					time of full moon, and to become thin and narrow at
					the time of the wanings of that heavenly body. By
					the human features of the cat is indicated the intelligence and the reason that guides the changes of the
					moon.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 367 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="64">
            <p>To put the matter briefly, it is not right to
					believe that water or the sun or the earth or the sky
					is Osiris or Isis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 363 d and 364 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; or again that fire or drought or the
					sea is Typhon, but simply if we attribute to Typhon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 364 a and 369 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>
					whatever there is in these that is immoderate and
					disordered by reason of excesses or defects ; and if
					we revere and honour what is orderly and good and
					beneficial as the work of Isis and as the image and
					reflection and reason of Osiris, we shall not be wrrong.
					Moreover, we shall put a stop to the incredulity of
					Eudoxus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 63.</note> and his questionings how it is that Demeter
					has no share in the supervision of love affairs, but
					Isis has ; and the fact that Dionysus cannot cause
					the Nile to rise, nor rule over the dead. For by
					one general process of reasoning do we come to
					the conclusion that these gods have been assigned
					to preside over every portion of what is good ;
					and whatever there is in nature that is fair and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.153"/>
					
					good exists entirely because of them, inasmuch as
					Osiris contributes the origins, and Isis receives them
					and distributes them.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="65">
            <p>In this way we shall undertake to deal with the
					numerous and tiresome people, whether they be such
					as take pleasure in associating theological problems
					with the seasonal changes in the surrounding atmosphere, or with the growth of the crops and seedtimes and ploughing ; and also those who say that
					Osiris is being buried at the time when the grain is
					sown and covered in the earth and that he comes to
					life and reappears when plants begin to sprout. For
					this reason also it is said that Isis, when she perceived
					that she was pregnant, put upon herself an amulet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 378 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> on
					the sixth day of the month Phaophi ; and about the
					time of the winter solstice she gave birth to Harpocrates, imperfect and premature,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 358 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> amid the early
					flowers and shoots. For this reason they bring to him
					as an offering the first-fruits of growing lentils, and
					the days of his birth they celebrate after the spring
					equinox. When the people hear these things, they
					are satisfied with them and believe them, deducing
					the plausible explanation directly from what is
					obvious and familiar.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="66">
            <p>And there is nothing to fear if, in the first place,
					they preserve for us our gods that are common to both
					peoples and do not make them to belong to the
					Egyptians only, and do not include under these names
					the Nile alone and the land wrhich the Nile waters,
					and do not assert that the marshes and the lotus are
					the only work of God's hand, and if they do not deny
					the great gods to the rest of mankind that possess no
					Nile nor Buto nor Memphis. But as for Isis, and the
					gods associated with her, all peoples own them and are
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.155"/>
					
					familiar with them, although they have learned not
					so very long ago to call some of them by the names
					which come from the Egyptians ; yet they have from
					the beginning understood and honoured the power
					which belongs to each one of them.
				</p>
            <p>
					In the second place, and this is a matter of greater
					importance, they should exercise especial heed and
					caution lest they unwittingly erase and dissipate
					things divine<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 757 b-c.</note> into winds and streams and sowings
					and ploughings, developments of the earth and
					changes of the seasons, as do those who regard
					wine as Dionysus and flame as Hephaestus. And
					Cleanthes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 547.</note> says somewhere that the breath of air
					which is carried (<hi rend="italics">pheromenon</hi>) through the crops and
					then suffers dissolution (<hi rend="italics">phoneuomenon</hi>) is Phersephon&ecirc; ; and a certain poet has written with reference
					to the reapers,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. The Life and Poetry of Homer</hi>, chap. xxiii. in Bernardakis, vol. vii.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Then when the sturdy youth come to sever the limbs of
					Demeter.</quote>
					The fact is that these persons do not differ at all from
					those who regard sails and ropes and anchor as a
					pilot, warp and woof as a weaver, a cup or an honey
					mixture or barley gruel as a physician. But they
					create in men fearful atheistic opinions by conferring the names of gods upon natural objects which
					are senseless and inanimate, and are of necessity destroyed by men when they need to use them.
				</p>
            <p>
					It is impossible to conceive of these things as being
					gods in themselves ; 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="67">
            <p>for God is not senseless nor
					inanimate nor subject to human control. As a result
					of this we have come to regard as gods those who
					make use of these things and present them to us and
					provide us with things everlasting and constant. Nor
					do we think of the gods as different gods among
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.157"/>
					
					different peoples, nor as barbarian gods and Greek
					gods, nor as southern and northern gods ; but, just as
					the sun and the moon and the heavens and the earth
					and the sea are common to all, but are called by
					different names by different peoples, so for that one
					rationality which keeps all these things in order and
					the one Providence which watches over them and
					the ancillary powers that are set over all, there have
					arisen among different peoples, in accordance with
					their customs, different honours and appellations.
					Thus men make use of consecrated symbols, some
					employing symbols that are obscure, but others those
					that are clearer, in guiding the intelligence toward
					things divine, though not without a certain hazard.
					For some go completely astray and become engulfed
					in superstition; and others, while they fly from
					superstition<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note at the end of chapter 11 (355 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>).</note> as from a quagmire, on the other hand
					unwittingly fall, as it were, over a precipice into
					atheism.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="68">
            <p>Wherefore in the study of these matters it is
					especially necessary that we adopt, as our guide in
					these mysteries, the reasoning that comes from
					philosophy, and consider reverently each one of the
					things that are said and done, so that, to quote
					Theodorus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 467 b.</note> who said that while he offered the good
					word with his right hand some of his auditors received
					it in their left, we may not thus err by accepting in a
					different spirit the things that the laws have dictated
					admirably concerning the sacrifices and festivals.
					The fact that everything is to be referred to reason
					we may gather from the Egyptians themselves ; for
					on the nineteenth day of the first month, when they
					are holding festival in honour of Hermes, they eat
					honey and a fig; and as they eat they say, <q direct="unspecified">A sweet
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.159"/>
						
						thing is Truth.</q> The amulet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 377 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> of Isis, which they
					traditionally assert that she hung about her neck, is
					interpreted <q direct="unspecified">a true voice.</q> And Harpocrates is not
					to be regarded as an imperfect and an infant god,
					nor some deity or other that protects legumes, but
					as the representative and corrector of unseasoned,
					imperfect, and inarticulate reasoning about the gods
					among mankind. For this reason he keeps his finger
					on his lips in token of restrained speech or silence.
					In the month of Mesor&ecirc; they bring to him an offering
					of legumes and say, <q direct="unspecified">The tongue is luck, the tongue
						is god.</q> Of the plants in Egypt they say that the
					persea is especially consecrated to the goddess
					because its fruit resembles a heart and its leaf a
					tongue. The fact is that nothing of mans usual
					possessions is more divine than reasoning, especially
					reasoning about the gods ; and nothing has a greater
					influence toward happiness. For this reason we give
					instructions to anyone who comes down to the oracle
					here to think holy thoughts and to speak words of
					good omen. But the mass of mankind act ridiculously
					in their processions and festivals in that they proclaim
					at the outset the use of words of good omen,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The regular proclamation (<foreign lang="greek">eu)fhmei=te</foreign>) used by the Greeks at the beginning of any ceremony.</note> but later
					they both say and think the most unhallowed thoughts
					about the very gods.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="69">
            <p>How, then, are we to deal with their gloomy,
					solemn, and mournful sacrifices, if it be not proper
					either to omit the customary ceremonials or to confound and confuse our opinions about the gods by unwarranted suspicions ? Among the Greeks also many
					things are done which are similar to the Egyptian
					ceremonies in the shrines of Isis, and they do them at
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.161"/>
					
					about the same time. At Athens the women fast at
					the Thesmophoria sitting upon the ground ; and the
					Boeotians move the halls of the Goddess of Sorrow
					and name that festival the Festival of Sorrow,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Pausanias, ix. 8. 1, and Preller, <hi rend="italics">Griechische Mythologie</hi>
                  <hi rend="super">4</hi>, i. 752, note 3; but the matter is very uncertain.</note> since
					Demeter is in sorrow because of her Daughter's
					descent to Pluto's realm. This month, in the season
					of the Pleiades, is the month of seeding which the
					Egyptians call Athyr, the Athenians Pyanepsion, and
					the Boeotians Damatrius.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The month sacred to Demeter.</note> Theopompus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 335.</note> records
					that the people who live toward the west believe that
					the winter is Cronus, the summer Aphrodite, and the
					spring Persephon&ecirc;, and that they call them by these
					names and believe that from Cronus and Aphrodit&ecirc;
					all things have their origin. The Phrygians, believing that the god is asleep in the winter and awake
					in the summer, sing lullabies for him in the winter and
					in the summer chants to arouse him, after the manner
					of bacchic worshippers. The Paphlagonians assert
					that in the winter he is bound fast and imprisoned,
					but that in the spring he bestirs himself and sets
					himself free again.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="70">
            <p>The season of the year also gives us a suspicion
					that this gloominess is brought about because of the
					disappearance from our sight of the crops and fruits
					that people in days of old did not regard as gods, but
					as necessary and important contributions of the gods
					toward the avoidance of a savage and a bestial life.
					At the time of year when they saw some of the fruits
					vanishing and disappearing completely from the
					trees, while they themselves were sowing others in
					a mean and poverty-stricken fashion still, scraping
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.163"/>
					
					away the earth with their hands and again replacing
					it, committing the seeds to the ground with uncertain
					expectation of their ever appearing again or coming
					to fruition, they did many things like persons at a
					funeral in mourning for their dead. Then again,
					even as we speak of the man who buys the books of
					Plato as <q direct="unspecified">buying Plato,</q> and of the man who represents the poems of Menander as <q direct="unspecified">acting Menander,</q>
					even so those men of old did not refrain from calling
					by the names of the gods the gifts and creations of
					the gods, honouring and venerating them because of
					the need which they had for them. The men of later
					times accepted this blindly, and in their ignorance
					referred to the gods the behaviour of the crops and
					the presence and disappearance of necessities, not
					only calling them the births and deaths of the gods,
					but even believing that they are so ; and thus they
					filled their minds with absurd, unwarranted, and
					confused opinions although they had before their
					eyes the absurdity of such illogical reasoning.
					Rightly did Xenophanes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. 44, Xenophanes, no. a 13; also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 171 d, 228 e, and 763 d; and Heracleitus, no. b 127 (Diels, i. 103).</note> of Colophon insist that the
					Egyptians, if they believed these to be gods, should
					not lament them ; but if they lamented them, they
					should not believe them to be gods. Is it anything
					but ridiculous amid their lamentations to pray that
					the powers may cause their crops to sprout again and
					bring them to perfection in order that they again be
					consumed and lamented ? 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="71">
            <p>This is not quite the
					case : but they do lament for their crops and they do
					pray to the gods, who are the authors and givers, that
					they produce and cause to grow afresh other new
					crops to take the place of those that are undergoing
					destruction. Hence it is an excellent saying current
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.165"/>
					
					among philosophers that they that have not learned
					to interpret rightly the sense of words are wont to
					bungle their actions.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 707 f.</note> For example, there are some
					among the Greeks who have not learned nor habituated themselves to speak of the bronze, the painted,
					and the stone effigies as statues of the gods and
					dedications in their honour, but they call them gods ;
					and then they have the effrontery to say that Lachares
					stripped Athena,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The gold was removed by him from the chryselephantine statue of Athena in the Parthenon; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> W. B. Dinsmoor, <hi rend="italics">Amer. Journ. Arch.</hi> xxxviii. (1934) p. 97.</note> that Dionysius sheared Apollo of
					the golden locks, and that Jupiter Capitolinus was
					burned and destroyed in the Civil War,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">July 6, 83 b.c., according to <hi rend="italics">Life of Sulla</hi>, chap. xxvii. (469 b). The numerous references may be found in Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Lexikon der gr. und r&ouml;m. Mythologie</hi>, ii. 714.</note> and thus
					they unwittingly take over and accept the vicious
					opinions that are the concomitants of these names.
				</p>
            <p>
					This has been to no small degree the experience of
					the Egyptians in regard to those animals that are held
					in honour. In these matters the Greeks are correct in
					saying and believing that the dove is the sacred bird of
					Aphrodit&ecirc;, that the serpent is sacred to Athena, the
					raven to Apollo, and the dog to Artemis - as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Frag. Graec.</hi>, Euripides, no. 968.</note> says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Dog you shall be, pet of bright Hecat&ecirc;.</quote>
					But the great majority of the Egyptians, in doing
					service to the animals themselves and in treating them
					as gods, have not only filled their sacred offices with
					ridicule and derision, but this is the least of the evils
					connected with their silly practices. There is engendered a dangerous belief, which plunges the weak and
					innocent into sheer superstition, and in the case of the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.167"/>
					
					more cynical and bold, goes off into atheistic and
					brutish reasoning.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the note on 355 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> Wherefore it is not inappropriate
					to rehearse in some detail what seem to be the facts
					in these matters.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="72">
            <p>The notion that the gods, in fear of Typhon,
					changed themselves into these animals,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 86. 3.</note> concealing
					themselves, as it were, in the bodies of ibises, dogs,
					and hawks, is a play of fancy surpassing all the wealth
					of monstrous fable. The further notion that as many
					of the souls of the dead as continue to exist are reborn
					into these animals only is likewise incredible. Of
					those who desire to assign to this some political reason
					some relate that Osiris, on his great expedition,
					divided his forces into many parts, which the Greeks
					call squads and companies, and to them all he gave
					standards in the form of animals, each of which came
					to be regarded as sacred and precious by the descendants of them who had shared in the assignment.
					Others relate that the later kings, to strike their
					enemies with terror, appeared in battle after putting
					on gold and silver masks of wild beasts' heads.
					Others record that one of these crafty and unscrupulous kings,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> i. 89. 5 and 90.</note> having observed that the Egyptians
					were by nature light-minded and readily inclined to
					change and novelty, but that, because of their
					numbers, they had a strength that was invincible and
					very difficult to check when they were in their sober
					senses and acted in concert, communicated to them
					and planted among them an everlasting superstition,
					a ground for unceasing quarrelling. For he enjoined
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.169"/>
					
					on different peoples to honour and revere different
					animals ; and inasmuch as these animals conducted
					themselves with enmity and hostility toward one
					another, one by its nature desiring one kind of food
					and another another, the several peoples were ever
					defending their own animals, and were much offended
					if these animals suffered injury, and thus they were
					drawn on unwittingly by the enmities of the animals
					until they were brought into open hostility with one
					another. Even to-day the inhabitants of Lycopolis
					are the only people among the Egyptians that eat
					a sheep ; for the wolf, whom they hold to be a god,
					also eats it. And in my day the people of Oxyrhynchus
					caught a dog and sacrificed it and ate it up as if
					it had been sacrificial meat,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 353 c and 358 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, xi. 27, and Juvenal, xv. 35.</note> because the people of
					Cynopolis were eating the fish known as the oxyrhynchus or pike. As a result of this they became
					involved in war and inflicted much harm upon each
					other ; and later they were both brought to order
					through chastisement by the Romans.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="73">
            <p>Many relate that the soul of Typhon himself
					was divided among these animals. The legend would
					seem to intimate that all irrational and brutish nature
					belongs to the portion of the evil deity, and in trying
					to soothe and appease him they lavish attention and
					care upon these animals. If there befall a great
					and severe drought that brings on in excess either
					fatal diseases or other unwonted and extraordinary
					calamities, the priests, under cover of darkness, in
					silence and stealth, lead away some of the animals
					that are held in honour ; and at first they but threaten
					and terrify the animals,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Mitteis und Wilcken, <hi rend="italics">Grundz*uuml;ge und Chrestomathie der Papyruskunde</hi>, i. p. 125.</note> but if the drought still persists,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.171"/>
					
					they consecrate and sacrifice them, as if,
					forsooth, this were a means of punishing the deity,
					or at least a mighty rite of purification in matters
					of the highest importance ! The fact is that in the
					city of Eileithyia they used to burn men alive,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 88. 5.</note> as
					Manetho has recorded ; they called them Typhonians,
					and by means of winnowing fans they dissipated and
					scattered their ashes. But this was performed publicly
					and at a special time in the dog-days. The consecrations of the animals held in honour, however, were
					secret, and took place at indeterminate times with
					reference to the circumstances ; and thus they are
					unknown to the multitude, except when they hold
					the animals' burials,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 359 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Diodorus, i. 21. 5; 83. 1 and 5; 84. 7.</note> and then they display some of
					the other sacred animals and, in the presence of all,
					cast them into the grave together, thinking thus to
					hurt and to curtail Typhon's satisfaction. The Apis,
					together with a few other animals, seems to be sacred
					to Osiris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 362 c-d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; but to Typhon they assign the largest
					number of animals. If this account is true, I think it
					indicates that the object of our inquiry concerns those
					which are commonly accepted and whose honours are
					universal: for example, the ibis, the hawk, the
					eynocephalus, and the Apis himself, as well as the
					Mendes, for thus they call the goat in Mendes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 46; Diodorus, i. 84. 4; Strabo, xvii. 1. 19.</note>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="74">
            <p>There remain, then, their usefulness and their
					symbolism ; of these two, some of the animals share
					in the one, and many share in both. It is clear that
					the Egyptians have honoured the cow, the sheep, and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.173"/>
					
					the ichneumon because of their need for these animals
					and their usefulness. Even so the people of Lemnos
					hold larks in honour because they seek out the eggs
					of the locust and destroy them ; and so the people of
					Thessaly honour storks,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Mirabilibus Ausc.</hi> 23 (832 a 14); Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, x. 31. 62; Stephanus Byzant. <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi> 
                  <foreign lang="greek">*qessali/a</foreign>.</note> because, when their land
					produced many snakes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Clement of Alexandria, <hi rend="italics">Protrepticus</hi>, ii. 39. 6; Plutarch's source may have been Theophrastus, Frag. 174. 6 (Wimmer, vol. iii. p. 220).</note> the storks appeared and
					destroyed them all. For this reason they passed a
					law that whoever killed a stork should be banished
					from the country. The Egyptians also honoured the
					asp, the weasel, and the beetle, since they observed
					in them certain dim likenesses of the power of the
					gods, like images of the sun in drops of water. There
					are still many people who believe and declare that
					the weasel conceives through its ear and brings forth
					its young by way of the mouth, and that this is a
					parallel of the generation of speech. The race of
					beetles has no female,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 355 a, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> but all the males eject their
					sperm into a round pellet of material which they roll
					up by pushing it from the opposite side, just as
					the sun seems to turn the heavens in the direction
					opposite to its own course, which is from west to east.
					They compare the asp to lightning, since it does not
					grow old and manages to move with ease and suppleness without the use of limbs.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="75">
            <p>The crocodile,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, ii. 69.</note> certainly, has acquired honour
					which is not devoid of a plausible reason, but he is
					declared to be a living representation of God, since he
					is the only creature without a tongue ; for the Divine
					Word has no need of a voice, and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.175"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>through noiseless ways advancing, guides
					</l>
                  <l>By Justice all affairs of mortal men.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Troades</hi>, 887-888; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1007 c.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					They say that the crocodile is the only animal living
					in the water which has a thin and transparent membrane extending down from his forehead to cover up his
					eyes, so that he can see without being seen ; and this
					prerogative belongs also unto the First God. In
					whatever part of the land the female crocodile lays
					her eggs, well she knows that this is destined to mark
					the limit of the rise of the Nile<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 982 c; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Animalium</hi>, v. 33 (558 a 17).</note>; for the females,
					being unable to lay their eggs in the water and afraid
					to lay them far from it, have such an accurate perception of the future that they make use of the oncoming
					river as a guide in laying their eggs and in keeping
					them warm; and thus they preserve them dry and
					untouched by the water. They lay sixty eggs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, ii. 33, v. 52.</note> and
					hatch them in the same number of days, and those
					crocodiles that live longest live that number of years :
					the number sixty is the first of measures for such
					persons as concern themselves with the heavenly
					bodies.
				</p>
            <p>
					Of the animals that are held in honour for both
					reasons, mention has already been made of the dog.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Supra</hi>, 355 b and 368 f.</note>
					The ibis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diodorus, i. 87. 6.</note> which kills the deadly creeping things, was
					the first to teach men the use of medicinal purgations
					when they observed her employing clysters and being
					purged by herself.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, ii. 35; Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Natural History</hi>, x. 40 (75).</note> The most strict of the priests
					take their lustral water for purification from a place
					where the ibis has drunk<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 974 c; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animalium</hi>, vii. 45.</note>: for she does not drink
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.177"/>
					
					water if it is unwholesome or tainted, nor will she
					approach it. By the spreading of her feet, in their
					relation to each other and to her bill, she makes
					an equilateral triangle.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 670 c.</note> Moreover the variety and
					combination of her black feathers with her white
					picture the moon in its first quarter.
				</p>
            <p>
					There is no occasion for surprise that the Egyptians
					were so taken with such slight resemblances ; for the
					Greeks in their painted and sculptured portrayals of
					the gods made use of many such. Tor example, in
					Crete there was a statue of Zeus having no ears ; for
					it is not fitting for the Ruler and Lord of all to listen
					to anyone. Beside the statue of Athena Pheidias
					placed the serpent and in Elis beside the statue of
					Aphrodit&ecirc; the tortoise,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 142 d; Pausanias, vi. 25. 2.</note> to indicate that maidens
					need watching, and that for married women staying
					at home and silence is becoming. The trident of
					Poseidon is a symbol of the Third Region where the
					sea holds sway, for it. has been assigned to a demesne
					of less importance than the heavens and the air. For
					this reason they thus named Amphitrit&ecirc; and the
					Tritons.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">An effort to derive these names from <foreign lang="greek">tri/tos</foreign>, <q direct="unspecified">third.</q>
               </note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The Pythagoreans embellished also numbers and
					figures with the appellations of the gods. The equilateral triangle they called Athena, born from the
					head and third-born, because it is divided by three
					perpendiculars drawn from its three angles. The
					number one they called Apollo<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the note on 354 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> because of its rejection of plurality<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 393 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> and because of the singleness of
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.179"/>
					
					unity. The number two they called <q direct="unspecified">Strife,</q> and
					<q direct="unspecified">Daring,</q> and three they called <q direct="unspecified">Justice,</q> for,
					although the doing of injustice and suffering from injustice are caused by deficiency and excess, Justice,
					by reason of its equality, intervenes between the two.
					The so-called sacred quaternion, the number thirtysix, was, so it is famed, the mightiest of oaths, and it
					has been given the name of <q direct="unspecified">World</q> since it is made
					up of the first four even numbers and the first four
					odd numbers added together.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="76">
            <p>If, then, the most noted of the philosophers,
					observing the riddle of the Divine in inanimate and incorporeal objects, have not thought it proper to treat
					any thing with carelessness or disrespect, even more do
					I think that, in all likelihood, we should welcome those
					peculiar properties existent in natures which possess
					the power of perception and have a soul and feeling
					and character. It is not that we should honour these,
					but that through these we should honour the Divine,
					since they are the clearer mirrors of the Divine by
					their nature also, so that we should regard them as
					the instrument or device of the God who orders all
					things. And in general we must hold it true that
					nothing inanimate is superior to what is animate, ana
					nothing without the power of perception is superior
					to that which has that power - no, not even if one
					should heap together all the gold and emeralds in the
					world. The Divine is not engendered in colours or in
					forms or in polished surfaces, but whatsoever things
					have no share in life, things whose nature does not
					allow them to share therein, have a portion of less
					honour than that of the dead. But the nature that
					lives and sees and has within itself the source of
					movement and a knowledge of what belongs to it and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.181"/>
					
					what belongs to others, has drawn to itself an efflux
					and portion of beauty from the Intelligence <q direct="unspecified">by
						which the Universe is guided,</q> as Heracleitus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. 86, Heracleitus, no. b 41.</note> has it.
					Wherefore the Divine is no worse represented in
					these animals than in works of bronze and stone which
					are alike subject to destruction and disfiguration, and
					by their nature are void of all perception and comprehension. This, then, is what I most approve in
					the accounts that are given regarding the animals
					held in honour.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="77">
            <p>As for the robes, those of Isis<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 352 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> are variegated in
					their colours ; for her power is concerned with matter
					which becomes everything and receives everything,
					light and darkness, day and night, fire and water, life
					and death, beginning and end. But the robe of
					Osiris has no shading or variety in its colour, but only
					one single colour like to light. For the beginning
					is combined with nothing else, and that which is
					primary and conceptual is without admixture ; wherefore, when they have once taken off the robe of Osiris,
					they lay it away and guard it, unseen and untouched.
					But the robes of Isis they use many times over; for in
					use those things that are perceptible and ready at hand
					afford many disclosures of themselves and opportunities to view them as they are changed about in
					various ways. But the apperception of the conceptual, the pure, and the simple, shining through the
					soul like a flash of lightning, affords an opportunity to
					touch and see it but once.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Letters</hi>, vii. 344 b.</note> For this reason Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Symposium</hi>, 210 a.</note> and
					Aristotle call this part of philosophy the epoptic<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, chap. vii. (668 a).</note> or
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.183"/>
					
					mystic part, inasmuch as those who have passed
					beyond these conjectural and confused matters of all
					sorts by means of Reason proceed by leaps and bounds
					to that primary, simple, and immaterial principle ;
					and when they have somehow attained contact with
					the pure truth abiding about it, they think that they
					have the whole of philosophy completely, as it were,
					within their grasp.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="78">
            <p>This idea at the present time the priests
					intimate with great circumspection in acquitting
					themselves of this religious secret and in trying to
					conceal it : that this god Osiris is the ruler and king
					of the dead, nor is he any other than the god that
					among the Greeks is called Hades and Pluto. But
					since it is not understood in what manner this is true,
					it greatly disturbs the majority of people who suspect
					that the holy and sacred Osiris truly dwells in the
					earth and beneath the earth,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 375 d, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> where are hidden away
					the bodies of those that are believed to have reached
					their end. But he himself is far removed from the
					earth, uncontaminated and unpolluted and pure from
					all matter that is subject to destruction and death ;
					but for the souls of men here, which are compassed
					about by bodies and emotions, there is no association
					with this god except in so far as they may attain to a
					dim vision of his presence by means of the apperception which philosophy affords. But when these souls
					are set free and migrate into the realm of the invisible
					and the unseen, the dispassionate and the pure, then
					this god becomes their leader and king, since it is
					on him that they are bound to be dependent in their
					insatiate contemplation and yearning for that beauty
					which is for men unutterable and indescribable.
					With this beauty Isis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 372 e and 374 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> as the ancient story declares,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.185"/>
					
					Is for ever enamoured and pursues it and consorts
					with it and filis our earth here with all things fair
					and good that partake of generation.
				</p>
            <p>
					This which I have thus far set forth comprises that
					account which is most befitting the gods. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="79">
            <p>If,
					as I have promised,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">372 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> I must now speak of the offerings
					of incense which are made each day, one should first
					consider that this people always lays the very greatest
					stress upon those practices which are conducive to
					health. Especially in their sacred services and holy
					living and strict regimen the element of health is no
					less important than that of piety. For they did not
					deem it proper to serve that which is pure and in all
					ways unblemished and unpolluted with either bodies
					or souls that were unhealthy and diseased.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the Roman taboo in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 281 c.</note> Since,
					then, the air, of which we make the greatest use and
					in which we exist, has not always the same consistency
					and composition, but in the night-time becomes dense
					and oppresses the body and brings the soul into
					depression and solicitude, as if it had become befogged
					and heavy, therefore, immediately upon arising, they
					burn resin on their altars, revivifying and purifying
					the air by its dissemination, and fanning into fresh
					life the languished spirit innate in the body, inasmuch
					as the odour of resin contains something forceful
					and stimulating.
				</p>
            <p>
					Again at midday, when they perceive that the sun
					is forcibly attracting a copious and heavy exhalation
					from the earth and is combining this with the air, they
					burn myrrh on the altars ; for the heat dissolves and
					scatters the murky and turgid concretions in the
					surrounding atmosphere. In fact, physicians seem to
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.187"/>
					
					bring relief to pestilential affections by making a large
					blazing fire, for this rarefies the air. But the rarefication is more effective if they burn fragrant woods, such
					as that of the cypress, the juniper, and the pine. At
					any rate, they say that Acron, the physician in Athens
					at the time of the great plague, won great repute by
					prescribing the lighting of a fire beside the sick, and
					thereby he helped not a few. Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Rose, <hi rend="italics">Aristoteles Pseudepigraphus</hi>, p. 233.</note> says that
					fragrant exhalations from perfumes and flowers and
					meadows are no less conducive to health than to
					pleasure, inasmuch as by their warmth and lightness
					they gently relax the brain, which is by nature cold
					and frigid. If it is true that among the Egyptians
					they call myrrh <q direct="unspecified">bal,</q> and that this being interpreted
					has the particular meaning <q direct="unspecified">the dissipation of
						repletion,</q> then this adds some testimony to our
					account of the reason for its use.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="80">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Cyphi</hi>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> M&uuml;ller, <hi rend="italics">Frag. Hist. Graec.</hi> ii. p. 616 (Manetho, frag. 84). An interesting note in Parthey's edition (pp. 277-280) describes the different kinds of cyphi mentioned in ancient writers, and gives in modern terms recipes for three.</note> is a compound composed of sixteen
					ingredients : honey, wine, raisins, cyperus, resin,
					myrrh, aspalathus, seselis, mastich, bitumen, rush,
					sorrel, and in addition to these both the junipers, of
					which they call one the larger and one the smaller,
					cardamum, and calamus. These are compounded, not
					at random, but while the sacred writings are being
					read to the perfumers as they mix the ingredients.
					As for this number, even if it appears quite clear that
					it is the square of a square and is the only one of the
					numbers forming a square that has its perimeter equal
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.189"/>
					
					to its area,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 367 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> and deserves to be admired for this reason,
					yet it must be said that its contribution to the topic
					under discussion is very slight. Most of the materials
					that are taken into this compound, inasmuch as they
					have aromatic properties, give forth a sweet emanation
					and a beneficent exhalation, by which the air is
					changed, and the body, being moved gently and
					softly<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1087 e.</note> by the current, acquires a temperament conducive to sleep; and the distress and strain of our daily
					carking cares, as if they were knots, these exhalations relax and loosen without the aid of wine. The
					imaginative faculty that is susceptible to dreams it
					brightens like a mirror, and makes it clearer no less
					effectively than did the notes of the lyre which the
					Pythagoreans<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 45 d, and Quintilian, ix. 4. 12.</note> used to employ before sleeping as a
					charm and a cure for the emotional and irrational in
					the soul. It is a fact that stimulating odours often
					recall the failing powers of sensation, and often again
					lull and quiet them when their emanations are diffused
					in the body by virtue of their ethereal qualities ;
					even as some physicians state that sleep supervenes
					when the volatile portion of our food, gently permeating the digestive tract and coming into close contact
					with it, produces a species of titillation.
				</p>
            <p>
					They use <hi rend="italics">cyphi</hi> as both a potion and a salve ;
					for taken internally it seems to cleanse properly the
					internal organs, since it is an emollient. Apart from
					this, resin and myrrh result from the action of the
					sun when the trees exude them in response to the
					heat. Of the ingredients which compose <hi rend="italics">cyphi</hi>,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.191"/>
					
					there are some which delight more in the night, that
					is, those which are wont to thrive in cold winds and
					shadows and dews and dampness. For the light of
					day is single and simple, and Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Olympian Odes</hi>, i. 6.</note> says that the
					sun is seen <q direct="unspecified">through the deserted aether.</q> But the
					air at night is a composite mixture made up of many
					lights and forces, even as though seeds from every
					star were showered down into one place. Very
					appropriately, therefore, they burn resin and myrrh
					in the daytime, for these are simple substances
					and have their origin from the sun ; but the <hi rend="italics">cyphi</hi>,
					since it is compounded of ingredients of all sorts of
					qualities, they offer at nightfall.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Some think the essay ends too abruptly; others think it is quite complete; each reader may properly have his own opinion.</note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>