<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An vitiositas ad infelicitatem sufficia</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">W. C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>W. C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1939</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.6.p.361"/>
            <head>WHETHER VICE BE SUFFICIENT
					TO CAUSE UNHAPPINESS
					(AN VITIOSITAS AD FELICITATEM
					SUFFICIAT)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					Again we have a fragment, mutilated at the beginning
					and the end.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There may, in addition, be a lacuna between chapters 1 and 2.</note> The attribution to Plutarch has been
					questioned by D&uuml;bner, Hense,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Teletea</hi>, p. lxxxix., note.</note> Naber, and Hartman,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, pp. 249-253.</note> but on insufficient grounds, which have, in the
					main, been explained away by Siefert,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Commentationes Ienenses</hi>, 1896, pp. 110-119.</note> who has also
					analysed the structure of the work and the Plutarchean parallels. Wilamowitz,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, xl. 161-165.</note> on the other hand,
					believed this and the following fragment to be scraps
					of the same dialogue : I follow Pohlenz in rejecting
					this view.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Similarly Usener, <hi rend="italics">Fleckeisens Jahrb.</hi>, cxxxix. 381, believed this treatise to be a fragment of the work mentioned in the Lamprias catalogue as No. 84: <foreign lang="greek">*)ammw/nios h)\ peri\ tou= mh\ h(de/ws th=| kaki/a| sunei=nai</foreign>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The text is not good, and the work is not mentioned
					in the Lamprias catalogue.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.6.p.363"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>...<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This passage is tantalizing, not only because so much is lost of the text, and because the text is so corrupt, but chiefly because since the discovery of the Claremont fragments of Euripides' <hi rend="italics">Pha&euml;thon</hi> we may perceive that this play, of whose ingenious plot we now know a good deal, colours the whole of the opening passage. In the play Pha&euml;thon, declining to accept marriage with the goddess to whom his mother Clymene wished to marry him, speaks the first verse quoted; and there are probably further quotations from the play in the second sentence (<foreign lang="greek">pollh=s dia\ te/fras, a)lla\ purkai+a=s tinos</foreign>). It is quite possible that Pha&euml;thon himself swears that he will go through <q direct="unspecified">heaps of cinders</q> rather than marry the goddess; and in the play there is in fact a <q direct="unspecified">royal conflagration</q> when the Sun's treasure-house burns (see Nauck, p. 601). But it cannot be too strongly insisted that the text is very corrupt and that the restorations here adopted can claim only an approximation to the truth.</note> He will not submit to (such a marriage)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Conjecturally supplied.</note>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">His body bartered for the dower's sake,</quote>
					as Euripides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 606, Frag. 775, from the <hi rend="italics">Pha&euml;thon</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 13 f; Plautus, <hi rend="italics">Asinaria</hi>, 87.</note> says ; but he has only a slight and
					precarious reason for being envied. For this man (it
					were better)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Conjecturally supplied.</note> to make his journey, not <q direct="unspecified">through
						heaps of hot cinders,</q> but <q direct="unspecified">through a royal conflagration,</q> as it were, and surrounded by flames,
					panting and full of terror and drenched with sweat,
					and so to perish, though (his mother)<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Conjecturally supplied.</note> had offered to
					him such a wealth as Tantalus had, which he was
					too busy to enjoy. For while that Sicyonian horsebreeder was a wise man, who gave to the king
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.365"/>
					
					of the Achaeans, Agamemnon, a swift mare as a
					gift,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>That he might not follow him to wind-swept Troy,
						</l>
                  <l>But stay at home and take his pleasure,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xxiii. 297-298; Echepolus is the Sicyonian referred to. <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 32 f.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					surrendering himself to the enjoyment of deep riches
					and to unmolested ease ; yet modern courtiers who
					are looked upon as men of affairs, though no one
					summons them, of their own accord push their way
					headlong into courts and official escorts and toilsome
					bivouacs that they may get a horse or a brooch or
					some such piece of good fortune.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>His wife, rending both cheeks, was left behind
						</l>
                  <l>In Phylace, and his half-finished home,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, ii. 700-701.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					while he himself is swept about and wanders afar,
					worn out by one hope after another and constantly
					insulted ; and even if he obtains any of his desires,
					yet, whirled about and made giddy by Fortune's ropedance, he seeks to make his descent and considers
					happy those who live in obscurity and safety, whereas
					they so regard him as they look up at him soaring
					above their heads.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Vice makes all men completely miserable, since
					as a creator of unhappiness it is clothed with absolute
					power, for it has no need of either instruments or
					ministers. But whereas despots, when they desire
					to make miserable those whom they punish, maintain
					executioners and torturers, or devise branding-irons
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.367"/>
					
					and wedges<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Prometheus</hi>, 64-65: <foreign lang="greek"><quote rend="blockquote"><l>
                     a)damanti/nou nu=n sfhno\s au)q/dh gna/qon </l><l>ste/rnwn diampa\c passa/leu' e)rrwme/nws.</l></quote></foreign>
               </note>; vice, without any apparatus, when it
					has joined itself to the soul, crushes and overthrows it,
					and filis the man with grief and lamentation, dejection and remorse. And this is the proof : many are
					silent under mutilation and endure scourging and
					being tortured by the wedge at the hands of masters
					or tyrants without uttering a cry, whenever by the
					application of reason the soul abates the pain and by
					main force, as it were, checks and represses it<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusc. Disp.</hi>, ii. 22. 53 ff.</note>; but
					you cannot order anger to be quiet nor grief to be
					silent, nor can you persuade a man possessed by fear
					to stand his ground, nor one suffering from remorse
					not to cry out or tear his hair or smite his thigh. So
					much more violent is vice than either fire or sword.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Cities, as we know, when they give public notice
					of intent to let contracts for the building of temples
					or colossal statues, listen to the proposals of artists
					competing for the commission and bringing in their
					estimates and models,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>, for example, Richter, <hi rend="italics">Greek Sculptors</hi>, p. 230: <q direct="unspecified">A model of the pediment figures must have preceded the beginning of their execution.</q>
               </note> and then choose the man who
					will do the same work with the least expense and
					better than the others and more quickly. Come,
					then, let us suppose that we also give public proclamation of intent to contract for making a life
					wretched, and that Fortune and Vice come to get
					the commission in a rival spirit. Fortune is provided
					with all manner of instruments and costly apparatus
					to render a life miserable and wretched ; she brings in
					her train frightful robberies and wars, the foul bloodthirstiness
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.369"/>
					
					of tyrants, and storms at sea and thunder
					from the sky ; she compounds hemlock, she carries
					swords, she levies informers, she kindles fevers, she
					claps on fetters, and builds prison-enclosures (and yet
					the greater part of these belong to Vice rather than
					to Fortune, but let us suppose them all Fortune's).
					And let Vice stand by quite unarmed, needing no
					external aid against the man, and let her ask Fortune
					how she intends to make man wretched and dejected:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>Fortune,
						</l>
                     <l>Do you threaten poverty? Metrocles laughs at you,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">H. Richards has seen that this is probably a verse from comedy.</note>
                     </l>
                  </quote>
						Metrocles, who in winter slept among the sheep and
						in summer in the gateways of sacred precincts, yet
						challenged to vie with him in happiness the king of
						the Persians who winters in Babylon and summers in
						Media.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 604 c; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, viii. 6. 22.</note> Do you bring on slavery and chains and the
						auction block? Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, vi. 29. 74; Epictetus, iv. 1. 116.</note> despises you, for when
						he was being sold by pirates, he cried out with the
						voice of an auctioneer, &amp;ldquo;Who wants to buy a master?&amp;rdquo;
						Do you mix a cup of poison? Did you not present
						this to Socrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 117 b-c.</note> also? And cheerfully and calmly,
						without trembling or changing either colour or posture, he drained it with great cheerfulness ; and as
						he died the living esteemed him happy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 607 f.</note> believing
						that &amp;ldquo;not even in Hades would he be without some
							god-given portion.&amp;rdquo;
                  <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 58 e; Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, 32.</note> And as for your fire, Decius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 310 a-b.</note> 
						the Roman general anticipated it, when he built a
						
						<pb id="v.6.p.371"/>
						
						funeral pyre between the camps and, to fulfil a vow,
						sacrificed himself to Saturn on behalf of Rome's
						supremacy. And among the Indians, loving and
						chaste wives strive and contend with one another for
						the fire, and the wife who wins the honour of being
						consumed together with her dead husband is hymned
						as happy by the others.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This reference to Suttee is of great interest. It is probably derived ultimately from Megasthenes' account of the Maurya Empire of the 3rd centure b.c. See, for example, Rawlinson, <hi rend="italics">India and the Western World</hi> (Cambridge University Press, 1916), p. 59.</note> And of the wise men in that
						part of the world, not one is considered enviable or
						happy, if, while he yet lives and is sane and healthy,
						he does not separate by fire his soul from his body
						and emerge pure from the flesh, with the mortal part
						washed away. Or will you reduce a man from
						splendid wealth and house and table and lavish living
						to a threadbare cloak and wallet and begging of his
						daily bread? These things were the beginning of
						happiness for Diogenes, of freedom and repute for
						Crates. But will you nail him to a cross or impale
						him on a stake? And what does Theodorus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Cyrenaic, called <q direct="unspecified">The Atheist,</q>, philosopher of the late 4th century b.c.; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 606 b; Teles ed. Hense, p. 31; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusc. Disp.</hi>, i. 43. 102; Valerius Maximus, vi. 2, Ext. 3; Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Tranquillitate</hi>, xiv. 3; <hi rend="italics">Wien. Stud.</hi>, ix. 204.</note> care
						whether he rots above ground or beneath? Among
						the Scythians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Herodotus, iv. 71-72.</note> such is the manner of happy burial;
						and among the Hyrcanians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Porphyry, <hi rend="italics">De Abstinentia</hi>, iv. 21; Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Hypotyposes</hi>, iii. 227; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusc. Disp.</hi>, i. 45. 108.</note> dogs, among the Bactrians birds, devour, in accordance with the laws,
						the bodies of men, when these have met a happy end.</quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Whom, then, do these things make wretched?
					The unmanly and irrational, the unpracticed and untrained, those who retain from childhood their notions
					unchanged. Therefore Fortune is not a producer of
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.373"/>
					
					perfect unhappiness if she does not have Vice to
					co-operate with her. For as a thread saws through
					the bone that has been soaked in ashes and vinegar,
					and as men bend and fashion ivory when it has been
					made soft and pliable by beer, but cannot do so
					otherwise, so Fortune, falling upon that which is of
					itself ill-affected and soft as the result of Vice, gouges
					it out and inj ures it. And just as the Parthian poison,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nothing is known about either a Parthian juice (<foreign lang="greek">o)po/s</foreign>), or a Parthian poison (<foreign lang="greek">i)o/s</foreign>).</note>
					though harmful to no one else nor injurious to those
					who touch it and carry it about, if it is merely brought
					into the presence of wounded men, it straightway
					destroys them, since they receive its effluence because
					of their previous susceptibility ; so he who is liable to
					have his soul crushed by Fortune must have within
					himself some festering wound of his own in order that
					it may make whatever befalls him from without
					pitiful and lamentable.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Is, then, Vice such a thing that it needs Fortune's
					help to produce unhappiness? How can that be?
					Vice does not raise up a rough and stormy sea, she
					does not gird the skirts of lonely mountains with
					ambushes of robbers along the way, she does not
					make clouds of hail to burst on fruitful plains, she
					does not bring in a Meletus or an Anytus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 475 e, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> or a
					Callixenus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Hellenica</hi>, i. 7. 8. ff.</note> as accusers, she does not take away
					wealth, she does not debar from the praetorship, in
					order to make men unhappy. Yet she dismays men
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.375"/>
					
					who are rich, prosperous, and heirs to fortunes ; on
					land and on sea she insinuates herself into them and
					clings to them, sinking deep into them through evil
					lusts, firing them with anger, crushing them with
					superstitious fears, shattering them with the eyes...<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The interpretation of this last phrase is quite uncertain: perhaps <q direct="unspecified">tearing them to pieces with envy,</q> or <q direct="unspecified">making them ridiculous with envy.</q>
               </note>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>