<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Animine an corporis affectiones sint peiores</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.100">
      <body>
         <head>Whether the passions of the soul or diseases
				of the body are worse.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.504"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>HOMER, having contemplated the various kinds of
				mortal animals, and compared them one with another in
				respect to their lives and habits, cried out:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What wretched creature of what wretched kind,
				</l>
                     <l>Than man more weak, calamitous, and blind!</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVII. 446.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>attributing to man that unhappy primacy of having the
					superiority in miseries. But we, considering man as having already gained the victory for infelicity, and being
					publicly declared the most miserable of all animals, will
					compare him with himself in a contention about his own
					calamities, not unprofitably but even altogether necessarily
					dividing his soul from his body; that we may thence learn,
					whether we live more miserably on account of Fortune or
					of ourselves. For sickness is indeed, engendered in the
					body by Nature; but vice and malice in the soul are first
					its own work, afterward its passion. Now it is of no small
					advantage towards content of mind, if that which is the
					worse is curable, and lighter and less violent in its attacks
					than we feared.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>The fox in Aesop, disputing with the panther for
				the superiority in beautiful variety,&mdash;when this latter had
				shown his body, and its superficies curiously stained and
				spotted, whereas the fox's tawny skin was ill-favored and
				unpleasant to the sight,&mdash;said thus: <q direct="unspecified">But if you, sir
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.505"/>
					
					judge, will look within me, you will find me much fuller
					of variety than this leopard;</q> manifesting the nimble subtlety of his natural disposition, frequently changing as
				occasions require. Let us then say also to ourselves: Thy
				body, O man, naturally of itself breeds many diseases and
				passions, and many it receives befalling it from without;
				but if thou shalt open thy interior, thou wilt find a certain
				various and abundantly furnished storehouse and (as Democritus says) treasury of evils, not flowing into it from
				abroad, but having as it were their inbred and original
				springs, which vice, exceedingly affluent and rich in passions, causes to break forth. Now, whereas the diseases
				in the flesh are discerned by the pulses, and the flushings
				in the color of the skin, and discovered by unusual heats
				and sudden pains, and these maladies of the soul lie hid
				from many who are affected with them; these are therefore worse, as removing from them the sense of the patient.
				For if the reason is sound, it is sensible of the body's
				diseases; but being itself diseased with those of the soul,
				it has no judgment in what it suffers; for it suffers by
				what it judges. We ought therefore to account, that the
				first and greatest of the soul's diseases is folly, by which
				vice being rendered incurable cohabits, lives, and dies together with most men. For the beginning of the cure is
				the sense of the disease, leading the patient to the use of
				what is helpful; but he who, through his not believing
				himself sick, is ignorant of his own necessities, though a
				remedy is presented him, refuses it. For also amongst the
				diseases of the body, those are indeed the worst which are
				accompanied with a stupefaction of the senses,&mdash;as lethargies, headaches, epilepsies, apoplexies, and those burning
				fevers which, carrying on the inflammation even to the loss
				of the wits, and disturbing the senses, as it were in a
				musical instrument, <q direct="unspecified">move the heart-strings till then untouched.</q>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.506"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Wherefore the physicians do in the first place indeed
				desire that a man should not be sick, and next, that being
				sick he should not be ignorant that he is so; which nevertheless befalls all the diseases of the soul. For neither
				those who are mad, those that are lascivious, nor those who
				act unjustly, think that they sin; nay, some of them are
				on the contrary persuaded even that they do well. Never
				yet did any man call a fever health, a consumption a good
				constitution of body, the gout swift-footedness, or the wanness of the face a fresh color; but many there are who
				term anger courage, unchaste love amity, envy emulation,
				and cowardice cautiousness. Moreover, those who are
				troubled with corporeal sickness send for physicians, for
				they are sensible what they stand in need of for the cure
				of their diseases; but these who are sick in mind shun
				philosophers, because they think themselves to act excellently in those very things in which they most offend.
				For making use of this reasoning, we affirm that the blearness or soreness of the eyes is a less malady than madness,
				and the gout in the feet than a frenzy in the brain; for
				in the one a man is sensible of his distemper, and crying
				out calls for the physician, to whom, when he is come, he
				shows his eye to be anointed, stretches out his vein to be
				opened, and gives up his head to be cured; but on the
				contrary, you hear Agave, when seized with madness,
				through the violence of her passion not knowing the dearest pledges of her womb, to cry out:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>From the hill's top into the plain,
				</l>
                     <l>Bring me this young fawn, newly slain,
				</l>
                     <l>Which happily's become our prey.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Bacch. 1170.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For he who is sick in body, presently yielding and betaking himself to his bed, lies there quiet, till he is cured;
					and if the accession of some violent hot fit makes him a little
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.507"/>
					
					tumble and toss his body, any one of those who are by
					saying to him,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lie still at ease, poor wretch, keep in thy bed,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orest. 258.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>easily stays and retains him; but those, on the other side,
					who are surprised with the passions of the soul are then
					most active, then least at quiet; for the impulses of the
					mind are the principal causes of actions, and passions are
					the violent fits of such impulses. Wherefore, they suffer
					not the soul to be at rest; but when a man has most need
					of patience, silence, and retirement, then is he drawn
					forth into the light, then is he chiefly discovered by his
					choleric humors, his eagerness in contending, his dishonest
					loves, and his heart-breaking sorrows, which force him to
					commit many irregular actions, and speak many words unfitting for the times.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>As therefore that storm which hinders a ship from
				entering into the port is more dangerous than that which
				suffers it not to sail; so the tempests of the soul are more
				difficult, which permit not a man to restrain himself, nor to
				settle his disturbed reason, so that, being without pilot or
				cables, he is through tumult and deceit hurried headlong
				by rash and pernicious courses, till he falls into some terrible shipwreck, where he casts away his life. So that also
				for these reasons it is worse to be sick in the soul than
				body; for to the one it happens only to suffer, but to the
				other both to suffer and do amiss. And what need is there to
				reckon up the greater number of our passions? This very
				nick of time is a sufficient remembrance. Do you see
				this vast and promiscuous multitude, here crowding and
				thrusting each other about the tribunal and forum? They
				are not assembled to sacrifice to their country Gods, nor to
				participate together in the sacred ceremonies. They are
				not come to offer up to Jupiter Ascraeus the first of the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.508"/>
				
				Lydian fruits, nor to celebrate the solemnities of Bacchus
				by the observance of festival nights and common revellings;
				but a mighty pestilence, as it were by yearly revolutions
				irritating Asia, drives them hither to manage their processes and suits at law; and a multitude of affairs, as it
				were of impetuous torrents, fall into one market-place,
				where they grow hot and are eagerly prosecuted both by
				those that destroy and by those that are destroyed. Of
				what fevers, of what agues, are these the effects? What
				lodgements, what irruptions, what distemperature of heat,
				what superfusion of humors produces them? Should you
				ask every suit at law as if it were a man, whence it had its
				original, whence it proceeded; you would find, that audacious anger generated one, furious obstinacy another, and
				unjust covetousness a third ...</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>