<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De vitando aere alieno</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.120">
      <body>
         <head>Against running in debt, or taking up money
				upon usury.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.412"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Plato in his Laws<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Laws, VIII. p. 844 B.</note>permits not any one to go and
				draw water from his neighbor's well, who has not first
				digged and sunk a pit in his own ground till he is come to
				a vein of clay, and has by his sounding experimented that
				the place will not yield a spring. For the clay or potter's
				earth, being of its own nature fatty, solid, and strong,
				retains the moisture it receives, and will not let it soak or
				pierce through. But it must be lawful for them to take
				water from another's ground, when there is no way or
				means for them to find any in their own; for the law ought
				to provide for men's necessity, but not favor their laziness.
				Should there not be the like ordinance also concerning
				money; that none should be allowed to borrow upon
				usury, nor to go and dive into other men's purses,&mdash;as
				it were into their wells and fountains,&mdash;before they have
				first searched at home and sounded every means for the
				obtaining it; having collected (as it were) and gathered
				together all the gutters and springs, to try if they can
				draw from them what may suffice to supply their most
				necessary occasions? But on the contrary, many there
				are who, to defray their idle expenses and to satisfy their
				extravagant and superfluous delights, make not use of
				their own, but have recourse to others, running themselves
				deeply into debt without any necessity. Now this may
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.413"/>
				
				easily be judged, if one does but consider that usurers do
				not ordinarily lend to those which are in distress, but only
				to such as desire to obtain somewhat that is superfluous
				and of which they stand not in need. So that the credit
				given by the lender is a testimony sufficiently proving
				that the borrower has of his own; whereas on the contrary, since he has of his own, he ought to keep himself
				from borrowing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Why shouldst thou go and make thy court to a
				banker or a merchant? Borrow from thine own table.
				Thou hast tankards, dishes, and basins of silver. Make
				use of them for thy necessity, and when they are gone to sup
				ply thy wants, the pleasant town of Aulis or isle of Tenedos
				will again refurnish thy board with fair vessels of earth, far
				more cleanly and neat than those of silver. For they are
				not scented with the strong and unpleasant smell of usury,
				which, like rust, daily more and more sullies and tarnishes
				the lustre of thy sumptuous magnificence. They will not be
				every day putting thee in mind of the Kalends and
				new moons, which, being of themselves the most holy
				and sacred days of the months, are by reason of usuries
				rendered the most odious and accursed. For as to those
				who choose rather to carry their goods to the brokers and
				there lay them in pawn for money taken upon usury than
				to sell them outright, I do not believe that Jupiter Ctesius
				himself can preserve them from beggary. They are
				ashamed forsooth to receive the full price and value of
				their goods; but they are not ashamed to pay use for
				the money they have borrowed on them. And yet the
				great and wise Pericles caused that costly ornament of
				fine gold, weighing about forty talents, with which Minerva's statue was adorned, to be made in such a manner
				that he could take it off and on at his pleasure; to the
				end (said he) that when we shall stand in need of money
				to support the charges of war, we may take it and make
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.414"/>
				
				use of it, putting afterwards in its place another of no less
				value. Thus we ought in our affairs, as in a besieged
				town, never to admit or receive the hostile garrison of a
				usurer, nor to endure before our eyes the delivering up
				of our goods into perpetual servitude; but rather to cut
				off from our table what is neither necessary nor profitable,
				and in like manner from our beds, our couches, and our
				ordinary expenses, and so to keep ourselves free and at liberty, in hopes to restore again what we shall have retrenched, if Fortune shall hereafter smile upon us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>The Roman ladies heretofore willingly parted with
				their jewels and ornaments of gold, for the making a cup
				to be sent as an offering to the temple of Apollo Pythius
				in the city of Delphi. And the Carthaginian matrons did
				with their own hands cut the hair from their heads, to
				make cords for the managing of their warlike engines and
				instruments, in defence of their besieged city. But we, as
				if we were ashamed of being able to stand on our own
				legs without being supported by the assistance of others,
				go and enslave ourselves by engagements and obligations;
				whereas it were much better that, restraining our ambition
				and confining it to what is profitable for us, we should of
				our useless and superfluous plate, which we should either
				melt or sell, build a temple of Liberty for ourselves, our
				wives, and our children. The Goddess Diana in the city
				of Ephesus gives to such debtors as can fly into her temple
				freedom and protection against their creditors; but the
				sanctuary of parsimony and moderation in expenses, into which no usurer can enter to pluck thence and carry
				away any debtor prisoner, is always open for the prudent,
				and affords them a long and large space of joyful and
				honorable repose. For as the prophetess which gave
				oracles in the temple of the Pythian Apollo, about the
				time of the Persian wars, answered the Athenians, that
				God had for their safety given them a wall of wood, upon
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.415"/>
				
				which, forsaking their lands, their city, their houses, and
				all their goods, they had recourse to their ships for the
				preservation of their liberty; so God gives us a table of
				wood, vessels of earth, and garments of coarse cloth, if
				we desire to live and continue in freedom.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aim not at gilded coaches, steeds of price,
					</l>
                     <l>And harness, richly wrought with quaint device;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for how swiftly soever they may run, yet will usuries overtake them and outrun them.
					Take rather the first ass thou shalt meet or the first packhorse that shall come in thy way, and fly from that cruel and
					tyrannical enemy the usurer, who asks thee not earth and
					water, as heretofore did the barbarous king of Persia, but
					&mdash;which is worse&mdash;touches thy liberty, and wounds thy
					honor by proscriptions. If thou payest him not, he troubles
					thee; if thou hast wherewithal to satisfy him, he will not
					receive it, unless it be his pleasure. If thou sellest, he will
					have thy goods for nothing, or at a very under rate; and
					if thou wilt not sell, he will force thee to it; if thou suest
					him, he speaks to thee of an accommodation; if thou
					swearest to give him content, he will domineer over thee;
					if thou goest to his house to discourse with him, he shuts
					his door against thee; if thou stayest at home, he is always
					knocking at thy door and will never stir from thee.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Of what use to the Athenians was the decree of
				Solon, by which he ordained that the body should not be
				obliged for any public debt? For they who owe are in
				bondage to all bankers, and not to them alone (for then
				there would be no great hurt), but to their very slaves,
				who are proud, insolent, barbarous, and outrageous, and in
				a word exactly such as Plato describes the devils and
				fiery executioners to be, who in hell torment the souls
				of the wicked. For thus do these wretched usurers make
				the court where justice is administered a hell to the poor
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.416"/>
				
				debtors, preying on some and gnawing them, vulture-like,
				to the very bones, and
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Piercing into their entrails with sharp beaks;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XI. 578.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and standing over others, who are, like so many Tantaluses,
					prohibited by them from tasting the corn and fruits of their
					own ground and drinking the wine of their own vintage.
					And as King Darius sent to the city of Athens his lieutenants Datis and Artaphernes with chains and cords, to
					bind the prisoners they should take; so these usurers, bringing into Greece boxes full of schedules, bills, and obligatory contracts, as so many irons and fetters for the
					shackling of poor criminals, go through the cities, sowing in them, as they pass, not good and profitable seed,&mdash;
					as did heretofore Triptolemus, when he went through all
					places teaching the people to sow corn,&mdash;but roots and
					grains of debts, that produce infinite labors and intolerable usuries, of which the end can never be found, and
					which, eating their way and spreading their sprouts round
					about, do in fine make cities bend under the burden, till
					they come to be suffocated. They say that hares at the
					same time suckle one young leveret, are ready to kindle
					and bring forth another, and conceive a third; but the
					usuries of these barbarous and wicked usurers bring forth
					before they conceive. For at the very delivery of their
					money, they immediately ask it back, taking it up at the
					same moment they lay it down; and they let out that
					again to interest which they take for the use of what they
					have before lent.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>It is a saying among the Messenians,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pylos before Pylos, and Pylos still you'll find;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but it may much better be said against the usurers,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Use before use, and use still more you'll find.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>So that they laugh at those natural philosophers who hold
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.417"/>
					
					that nothing can be made of nothing and of that which
					has no existence; but with them usury is made and engendered of that which neither is nor ever was. They
					think the taking to farm the customs and other public
					tributes, which the laws nevertheless permit, to be a
					shame and reproach; and yet themselves on the contrary,
					in opposition to all the laws in the world, make men pay
					tribute for what they lend upon interest; or rather, if
					truth may be spoken, do in the very letting out their
					money to use, basely deceive their debtor. For the poor
					debtor, who receives less than he acknowledges in his
					obligation, is falsely and dishonestly cheated. And the
					Persians indeed repute lying to be a sin only in a second
					degree, but to be in debt they repute to be in the first;
					forasmuch as lying frequently attends those that owe. Now
					there are not in the whole world any people who are
					oftener guilty of lying than usurers, nor that practise more
					unfaithfulness in their day-books, in which they set down
					that they have delivered such a sum of money to such a
					person, to whom they have not given nigh so much. And
					the moving cause of their lying is pure avarice, not want
					or poverty, but an insatiable desire of always having more,
					the end of which is neither pleasurable nor profitable to
					themselves, but ruinous and destructive to those whom
					they injure. For they neither cultivate the lands of which
					they deprive their debtors, nor inhabit the houses out of
					which they eject them, nor eat at the tables which they
					take away from them, nor wear the clothes of which they
					strip them. But first one is destroyed, and then a second
					soon follows, being drawn on and allured by the former.
					For the mischief spreads like wildfire, still consuming,
					and yet still increasing by the destruction and ruin of those
					that fall into it, whom it devours one after another. And
					the usurer who maintains this fire, blowing and kindling it
					to the undoing of so many people, reaps no other advantage
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.418"/>
					
					 from it but only that he now and then takes his book
					of accounts, and reads in it how many poor debtors he has
					caused to sell what they had, how many he has dispossessed of their lands and livings, whence his money came
					which he is always turning, winding, and increasing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Think not that I speak this for any ill-will or enmity
				that I have borne against usurers;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For never did they drive away
					</l>
                     <l>My horses or my kine.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 154.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But my only aim is to show those who are so ready to take
					up money upon use, how much shame and slavery there is
					in it, and how it proceeds only from extreme folly, sloth,
					and effeminacy of heart. For if thou hast of thy own,
					borrow not, since thou hast no need of it; and if thou
					hast nothing, borrow not, because thou wilt not have any
					means to pay. But let us consider the one and the other
					apart. The elder Cato said to a certain old man, who
					behaved himself ill: My friend, seeing old age has of
					itself so many evils, why dost thou go about to add to
					them the reproach and shame of wickedness? In like
					manner may we say to a man oppressed with poverty:
					Since poverty has of itself so many and so great miseries,
					do not heap upon them the anguishes of borrowing and
					being in debt. Take not from poverty the only good thing
					in which it is superior to riches, to wit, freedom from pensive care. Otherwise thou wilt subject thyself to the derision of the common proverb, which says,
					A goat I cannot bear away,
					Therefore an ox upon me lay.
					Thou canst not bear poverty, and yet thou art going to load
					on thyself a usurer, which is a burden even to a rich man
					insupportable.
					But you will say perhaps, how then would you have
					me to live Is this a question fit for thee to ask, who hast
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.419"/>
					
					hands, feet, and a voice, who in brief art a man, whose
					property it is to love and be beloved, to do and receive a
					courtesy? Canst thou not teach, bring up young children,
					be a porter or doorkeeper, travel by sea, serve in a ship?
					There is in all these nothing more shameful or odious, than
					to be dunned with the importunate clamors of such as are
					always saying, Pay me, give me my money.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Rutilius that rich Roman, coming one day to Musonius the philosopher, whispered him thus in his ear:
				Musonius, Jupiter the Savior, whom you philosophers
				profess to imitate and follow, takes not up money at interest. Musonius smiling presently answered him: Nor
				yet does he lend for use. For this Rutilius, who was himself an usurer, upbraided the other with borrowing upon
				use. Now what a foolish stoical arrogance was this. For
				what need was there of bringing here Jupiter the Savior,
				when he might have given him the same admonition by
				things that were familiar and before his eyes? Swallows
				run not themselves into debt, ants borrow not upon interest; and yet Nature has given them neither reason, hands,
				nor art. But she has endued men with such abundance of
				understanding, that they maintain not only themselves, but
				also horses, dogs, partridges, hares, and jays. Why then
				dost thou condemn thyself, as if thou wert less able to
				persuade than a jay, more dumb than a partridge, and
				more ungenerous than a dog, in that thou couldst not
				oblige any man to be assistant to thee, either by serving
				him, charming him, guarding him, or fighting in his defence? Dost thou not see how many occasions the land,
				and how many the sea affords thee for thy maintenance?
				Hear also what Crates says:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here I saw Miccylus the wool to card,
					</l>
                     <l>Whilst his wife spun, that they by labor hard
					</l>
                     <l>In these hard times might 'scape the hungry jaws
					</l>
                     <l>Of famine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>King Antigonus, when he had not for a long time seen
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.420"/>
					
					Cleanthes the philosopher, said to him, Dost thou yet, O
					Cleanthes, continue to grind Yes, sir, replied Cleanthes,
					I still grind, and that I do to gain my living and not to
					depart from philosophy. How great and generous was the
					courage of this man, who; coming from the mill and the
					kneading-trough, did with the same hand which had been
					employed in turning the stone and moulding the dough,
					write of the nature of the Gods, moon, stars, and sun!
					And yet we think these to be servile works.</p>
            <p>Therefore, forsooth, that we may be free, we take up
					money at interest, and to this purpose flatter base and servile persons, wait on them, treat them, make them presents,
					and pay them pensions; and this we do, not being compelled by poverty (for no usurer will lend a poor man
					money) but to gratify our prodigality. For if we would
					be content with such things as are necessary for human
					life, usurers would be no less rare in the world than Centaurs and Gorgons. But luxury and excess, as it produced
					goldsmiths, silversmiths, perfumers, and dyers of curious
					colors, so has it also brought forth usurers. For we run
					not into debt for bread and wine, but for the purchasing
					of stately seats, numerous slaves, fine mules, costly banqueting halls, rich tables, and for all those foolish and
					superfluous expenses to which we frequently put ourselves
					for the exhibiting of plays to the people, or some such vain
					ambition, from which we frequently reap no other fruit
					but ingratitude. Now he that is once entangled in usury
					remains a debtor all his life, not unlike in this to the
					horse, who, having once taken the bridle into his mouth
					and the saddle on his back, receives one rider after another. Nor is there any means for these debtors to make
					their escape into those fair pastures and meadows which
					once they enjoyed, but they wander about, like those Daemons mentioned by Empedocles to have been driven out
					of heaven by the offended Gods:
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.421"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>By the sky's force they're thrust into the main,
						</l>
                     <l>Which to the earth soon spews them back again.
						</l>
                     <l>Thence to bright Titan's orb they're forced to fly,
						</l>
                     <l>And Titan soon remits them to the sky.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner do such men fall from the hand of one
					usurer or banker to another, sometimes of a Corinthian,
					sometimes of a Patrian, sometimes of an Athenian, till,
					having been deceived and cheated by all, they finally find
					themselves dissipated and torn in pieces by usury. For as
					he who is fallen into the dirt must either rise up and get
					out of it, or else lie still in the place into which he first
					fell, for that by tumbling, turning, and rolling about, he
					does but still more and more bemire himself; so also those
					who do but change their creditor, and cause their names to
					be transcribed from one usurer's book to another's, do by
					loading and embroiling themselves with new usuries become more and more oppressed. Now in this they properly resemble persons distempered with cholera, who cannot
					receive any medicine sufficient to work a perfect cure, but
					continually vomit up all that is given them, and so make
					way for the choleric humor to gather more and more. For
					in the same manner these men are not willing to be cleansed
					at once, but do with grievous anguish and sorrow pay their
					use at every season of the year, and no sooner have they
					discharged one, but another drops and stills immediately
					after, which causes them both aching hearts and heads;
					whereas they should have taken care to get wholly clear,
					that they might remain free and at liberty.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>For I now turn my speech to those who are more
				wealthy, and withal more nice and effeminate, and whose
				discourse is commonly in this manner: How shall I remain then without servants, without fire, and without
				a house or place to which I may repair? Now this
				is the same thing as if one who is sick of a dropsy
				and puffed up as a barrel should say to a physician:
				How? Would you have me become slender, lean, and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.422"/>
				
				empty? And why not, provided you thereby get your
				health? Thus it is better you should be without servants,
				than that you should yourself become a slave; and that
				you should remain without possessions, than that you
				should be made the possession of another. Give ear a
				little to the discourse of the two vultures, as it is reported
				in the fable. One of them was taken with so strong a fit
				of vomiting, that he said: I believe I shall cast up my very
				bowels. Now to this his companion answered: What hurt
				will there be in it? For thou wilt not indeed throw up
				thine own entrails, but those of the dead man which we
				devoured the other day. So he who is indebted sells not
				his own inheritance nor his own house, but that of the
				usurer who lent him the money, to whom by the law he
				has given the right and possession of them. Nay, by Jupiter (will he say to me); but my father left me this estate.
				I believe it well, but he left thee also liberty and a good
				repute, of which thou oughtest to make more account and
				be more careful. He who begat thee made thy foot and
				thy hand, and nevertheless, if they happen to be mortified,
				thou wilt give money to the chirurgeon to cut them off.
				Calypso presented Ulysses with a robe breathing forth the
				sweet-scented odor of an immortal body, which she put on
				him, as a token and memorial of the love she had borne
				him. But when his ship was cast away and himself ready
				to sink to the bottom, not being able to keep above the
				water by reason of his wet robe, which weighed him downwards, he put it off and threw it away, and having girt
				his naked breast with a broad swaddling band,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Swam, gazing on the distant shore.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. V. 439.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And afterwards, when the danger was over and he seen to
					be landed, he wanted neither food nor raiment. And is
					it not a true tempest, when the usurer after some time
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.423"/>
					
					comes to assault the miserable debtors with this word Pay?
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This having said, the clouds grow thick, the sea
						</l>
                     <l>Is troubled, and its raging waves beat high,
						</l>
                     <l>Whilst east, south, west winds through the welkin fly.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. V. 291, 295.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These winds are use, and use upon use, which roll one
					after another; and he that is overwhelmed by them and
					kept down by their weight cannot serve himself nor make
					his escape by swimming, but at last sinks down to the
					bottom, where he perishes, carrying with him his friends
					who were pledges and sureties for him.</p>
            <p>Crates, the Theban philosopher, acted far otherwise;
					for owing nothing, and consequently not being pressed for
					payment by any creditor, but only tired with the cares and
					troubles of housekeeping and the solicitude requisite to
					the management of his estate, he left a patrimony of eight
					talents' value, and taking only his cloak and wallet, retired to philosophy and poverty. Anaxagoras also forsook
					his plentiful and well-stocked pastures. But what need
					is there of alleging these examples, seeing that the lyric
					poet Philoxenus, being one of those who were sent to people a new city and new land in Sicily, where there fell to
					his share a good house and great wealth with which he
					might have lived well at his ease, yet seeing that delights,
					pleasure, and idleness, without any exercise of good letters,
					reigned in those quarters, said: These goods, by all the
					Gods, shall not destroy me, but I will rather lose them.
					And immediately leaving to others the portion that was
					allotted to himself, he again took shipping, and returned to
					Athens. Whereas those who are in debt bear and suffer
					themselves to be sued, taxed, made slaves of, and cheated
					with false money, feeding like King Phineus certain winged
					harpies. For these usurers fly to them, and ravish out of
					their hands their very food. Neither yet have they patience to stay and expect the season; for they buy their
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.424"/>
					
					debtors' corn before it is ready for harvest, bargain for the
					oil before the olives are ripe, and in like manner for their
					wines. I will have it, says the usurer, at such a price;
					and immediately he gets the writing signed; and yet the
					grapes are still hanging on the vine, expecting the rising
					of Arcturus.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>