<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Aquane an ignis sit utilior</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.128">
      <body>
         <head>Whether water or fire be most
				useful.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.331"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>
               <q direct="unspecified">Water is the best of things, but gold is like burning
				fire,</q> says Pindar.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Olymp. I. 1.</note> Therefore he positively assigns the
				second place to fire; with whom Hesiod agrees, where he
				says,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>First of all Chaos being had.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Theog. 116.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For most believe that by the word chaos he meant water,
					from <foreign lang="greek">xu/sis,</foreign> signifying <hi rend="italics">diffusion.</hi> But the balance of argument as to this point seems to be equal. For there are
					some who will have it that fire is the principle of all
					things, and that like sperm it begets all things out of itself,
					and resolves all things again by conflagration. Therefore,
					not to mention the persons, let us consider the arguments
					on both sides, which are to us the most convincing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Now then, is not that the most useful to us, which in
				all places and always and most of all we stand in need of,
				&mdash;like a piece of household-stuff or a tool, nay, like a
				friend that is ready at all hours and seasons? But fire is
				not always useful; for sometimes it is a prejudice to us
				and we avoid it if we can. But water is useful, winter
				and summer, to the healthy and sick, night and day;
				neither indeed is there any time but that a man has need
				of it. Therefore it is that the dead are called <hi rend="italics">alibantes,</hi>
				as being without moisture (<foreign lang="greek">liba/s</foreign>) and by that means deprived of life; and man may be without fire, but never
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.332"/>
				
				was any man without water. Besides, that which was
				existent from the beginning and with the first creation of
				man must be thought more useful than what was afterwards
				invented. From whence it is apparent, that Nature bestowed the one upon us as a thing absolutely necessary,
				the other fortune and art found out for superfluity of uses.
				Nor was the time ever known when man lived without
				water, nor was it an invention of any of the Gods or
				heroes; for it was present almost at their generation, and
				it made their creation possible. But the use of fire was a
				late invention of Prometheus, at what time life was without
				fire, but not without water. And that this is no poetical
				fiction is demonstrable from this, that there are many sorts
				of people that live without fire, without houses, and without hearths, in the open air. And Diogenes the Cynic
				made no use of fire; so that after he had swallowed a raw
				fish, <q direct="unspecified">This hazard,</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">do I run for your sakes.</q>
				But without water no man ever thought it convenient or
				possible to live.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>But why do I so meanly confine my discourse to the
				nature of men, seeing there are many, nay, infinite sorts of
				creatures? The race of man is almost the only one that
				knows the use of fire; the others live and feed without
				fire. Indeed, beasts, birds, and creeping things live upon
				roots, fruits, and raw flesh, without fire; but without water
				neither fish nor fowl nor land animals can subsist. For
				all beasts that feed upon flesh, of which there are some
				(as Aristotle reports) that never drink, nevertheless support life and being merely by moisture. So that of necessity that must be most profitable without which no sort of
				life can subsist or endure.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Let us therefore make a step from animals that eat
				to things that we ourselves make use of, such are plants
				and fruits; of which some are altogether void of heat,
				others enjoy it but imperfectly and obscurely. But moisture
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.333"/>
				
				 causes all things to germinate, increase, and bring
				forth. Why should I stand to reckon up wine and oil,
				milk and honey, and whatever else we reap and bring forth
				and see before our eyes, when wheat itself, which is looked
				upon as a dry nourishment, grows by alteration, putrefaction, and corruption of the moist matter?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Then again, that is most useful which is no way
				detrimental. Now fire easily becomes most pernicious,
				but the nature of water is never prejudicial. In the next
				place, that is most useful which affords the benefit which
				it brings with least expense, and without any preparation.
				But the benefit of fire requires cost and materials, and
				therefore the rich make more use of it than the poor, and
				princes than private persons; but water has that kindness
				for mankind, that it freely offers itself to all alike, a benefit
				perfect in itself, indigent of nothing, and wanting neither
				tools nor implements.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Moreover, that which by augmentation loses its benefit is of least use. Such is fire, which like a devouring
				beast ravages all before it, useful rather by art and skilful
				moderation, than of its own nature. But from water there
				is nothing to be feared. Furthermore, that is most useful
				which may be joined with another. But fire will not
				admit of water, neither is it any way profitable by conjunction with it. But water becomes profitable by joining
				with fire; and therefore hot waters are wholesome, and
				sensibly cure several diseases. Neither shall you ever find
				moist fire; but water both cold and hot is profitable for
				the body of man.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Then again, there being four elements, water produces a fifth out of itself, which is the sea, no less beneficial than the rest, as well for commerce as for many other
				things. So that it may be said, this element united and
				perfected our manner of living, which before was wild
				and unsociable, correcting it by mutual assistance, and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.334"/>
				
				creating community of friendship by reciprocal exchanges
				of one good turn for another. And as Heraclitus said, If
				there were no sun, it would be perpetual night; so may
				we say, If there were no sea, man would be the most
				savage and shameless of all creature. But the sea brought
				the vine from India into Greece, and out of Greece transmitted the use of corn to foreign parts; from Phoenicia translated
				the knowledge of letters, the memorials that prevent oblivion; furnished the world with wine and fruit, and prevented the greatest part of mankind from being illiterate
				and void of education. How is it possible then but that
				water should be the most useful, when it thus furnishes us
				with an entirely new element?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Or can any man speak as follows in defence of the
				contrary? We say then that God, as a master workman,
				had before him the four elements, to complete the fabric
				of the universe; and these again were different one from
				another. But earth and water were placed at the foundation, like matter, to be formed and fashioned, participating
				of form and order and of power to procreate and bring
				forth, so far as they are assisted by air and fire,&mdash;the great
				artificers that mould them into various shapes,&mdash;and&gt;
				lying dead till roused by them to act and generate. Of
				these two latter, fire is the ruling agent. This is manifest
				by induction. For earth without warmth and heat is altogether barren and unfruitful; but fire, by virtue of its
				rousing and inflaming quality, renders it diffusive, and
				swells it into generation. Nor can any man find out any
				other cause why rocks and the dry tops of mountains are
				not productive, but because they participate either nothing
				at all or very little of fire.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Then generally for water, it is so far from being sufficient of itself for the generation and preservation of other
				things, that it is itself destroyed for want of fire. But fire is
				that which upholds every thing in its proper being, and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.335"/>
				
				preserves it in its proper substance, as well water itself as
				all other things; so that when fire leaves it, water will
				stink, and it may be said that the want of fire is the death
				and destruction of water. And thus we find in regard to
				pools and all manner of standing waters, and such as are
				settled in pits and holes without issue, what an offensive
				and dead stench they send forth, and all for want of motion; for this kindles and preserves heat in all things, and
				more especially in running waters and swift streams, which
				being thus agitated and enlivened by heat, we commonly
				say such waters <q direct="unspecified">live.</q> Why then should not that be accounted the most useful of the two, that affords to the
				other the cause of its being, as fire does to water? Moreover, that is the most useful, of which if an animal be
				wholly deprived, it must perish; for it is evident, that anything without which an animal cannot live affords the
				reason and cause why it exists. There is moisture also
				in things after they are dead, nor are they altogether
				dried up; for otherwise moist bodies would never putrefy;
				since putrefaction is the alteration of dry into moist, or
				rather the corruption of moisture in flesh. Neither is death
				any other than an absolute defect and want of heat, and
				therefore dead carcasses are the coldest of all; so that if
				you do but touch them with a razor, they will blunt the
				edge of it through excess of coldness. Also in living
				creatures, those parts that least partake of heat are most
				insensible, as the bones and hair, and those parts which
				are most distant from the heart. Nay, to some of the
				most important things the absence of fire and the presence
				of water are destructive. For plants and fruits are not
				produced by moisture, but by the warmth of the moisture;
				and cold waters are most certainly either less productive,
				or altogether barren. For if water were fruitful in itself,
				it would always, and that spontaneously too, bear fruit.
				But the contrary is apparent, and it is rather baneful to
				generation.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.336"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Let us begin anew. As to the use of fire, considered as fire, we have no need of water. Rather the
				contrary is to be made out; for water extinguishes fire.
				And as for water, there is no use to be made of it in most
				things without fire. For water heated becomes more usefill, whereas otherwise it is prejudicial. So that, of the
				two, that is to be accounted best which is profitable of itself without the assistance of another. Besides, water is
				beneficial only to the feeling, when you either wash with
				it or touch it; but fire is profitable to all the senses, being
				not only felt, but also seen at a distance; so that you may
				add this to the rest of the virtues of it, that its uses are
				manifold.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Then to say that man did once subsist without fire
				is a mistake, it being impossible that man should be without it. But we must acknowledge there are differences in
				this kind, as well as in other things. Thus heat has rendered the sea more beneficial, as having a greater portion
				of heat in it than other waters, from which it otherwise
				differs not at all. And as for those that have no need of
				outward fire, they do not avoid it because they db not want
				it, but because they abound in heat within themselves. So
				that the use of fire seems to be more excellent in this, that
				water is never in such a condition as not to want external
				aids, but fire, endued with manifold virtues, contents itself
				with its own sufficiency. Therefore, as he is the best
				commander who so manages the affairs of his city as not
				to have any need of foreign assistance, so that element
				excels that supplies us in such a manner as to want the
				least of other helps from without. And this is to be said
				of other creatures that have no need of external heat.</p>
            <p>Now, to argue on the other side, a man may say thus,
					that whatever we singly and alone make use of is more
					profitable, since we are by our reason best fitted to choose
					what is best. For what is more useful and beneficial to us
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.337"/>
					
					than reason? ... And yet brute animals want fire. What
					then? Is it the less profitable, because found out by foresight of a higher power?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And since our discourse has brought us to it, what
				is more beneficial to life than art? Yet fire invented and
				preserves all manner of arts. And therefore Vulcan is
				feigned to be the prince of all artificers. Man has allowed
				him but a little time to live; and as Aristo said, sleep, like
				a toll-gatherer, deprives him of the one-half of that too.
				I would rather say that the darkness does this; for a man
				may watch all night. But he would have no benefit of his
				watchfulness unless fire afforded him all the benefit of the
				light of day, and removed the difference between night and
				day. Since then there is nothing more beneficial to man
				than life, and this is prolonged by fire, why should not fire
				be accounted the most beneficial of all things?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Lastly, that is to be thought most profitable, of
				which the temperament of the senses participates most.
				Now do you find that there is any of the senses, which of
				itself makes use of moisture without an intermixture of air
				and fire? But every sense partakes of fire, as being that
				which quickens the vital faculty; more especially the sight,
				which is the most acute of all the senses in the body, being
				a certain fiery efflux, that gave us our first light into the
				belief of a Deity, and by virtue of which we are able, as
				Plato says, to conform our souls to the motions of the
				celestial bodies.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>