<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De Herodoti malignitate</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.123">
      <body>
         <head>Of Herodotus's malice.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.331"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>The style, O Alexander, of Herodotus, as being simple, free, and easily suiting itself to its subject, has deceived many; but more, a persuasion of his dispositions
				being equally sincere. For it is not only (as Plato says)
				an extreme injustice, to make a show of being just when
				one is not so; but it is also the highest malignity, to pretend to simplicity and mildness and be in the mean time
				really most malicious. Now since he principally exerts
				his malice against the Boeotians and Corinthians, though
				without sparing any other, I think myself obliged to defend our ancestors and the truth against this part of his
				writings, since those who would detect all his other lies
				and fictions would have need of many books. But, as
				Sophocles has it, the face of persuasion is prevalent, especially when delivered in good language, and such as has
				power to conceal both the other absurdities and the ill-nature of the writer. King Philip told the Greeks who
				revolted from him to Titus Quinctius, that they had got a
				more polished, but a longer-lasting yoke. So the malice
				of Herodotus is indeed more polite and delicate than that
				of Theopompus, yet it pinches closer, and makes a more
				severe impression,&mdash;not unlike to those winds which,
				blowing secretly through narrow chinks, are sharper than
				those that are more diffused. Now it seems to me very
				convenient to delineate, as it were, in a rough draught,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.332"/>
				
				those signs and marks that distinguish a malicious narration from a candid and unbiassed one, applying afterwards
				every point we shall examine to such as appertain to them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>First then, whoever in relating a story shall use the
				most odious terms when gentler expressions might do as
				well, is not to be esteemed impartial, but an enjoyer of his
				own fancy, in putting the worst construction on things; as
				if any one, instead of saying Nicias is too much given to
				superstition, should call him fanatic, or should accuse
				Cleon of presumption and madness rather than of inconsiderateness in speech.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Secondly, when a writer, catching hold of a fault
				which has no reference to his story, shall draw it into the
				relation of such affairs as need it not, extending his narrative with circumlocutions, only that he may insert a man's
				misfortune, offence, or discommendable action, it is manifest that he delights in speaking evil. Therefore Thucydides would not clearly relate the faults of Cleon, which
				were very numerous; and as for Hyperbolus the orator,
				having touched at him in a word and called him an ill
				man, he let him go. Philistus also passed over all those
				outrages committed by Dionysius on the barbarians which
				had no connection with the Grecian affairs. For the excursions and digressions of history are principally allowed
				for fables and antiquities, and sometimes also for encomiums. But he who makes reproaches and detractions an
				addition to his discourse seems to incur the tragedian's
				curse on the <q direct="unspecified">collector of men's calamities.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Now the opposite to this is known to every one, as
				the omitting to relate some good and laudable action,
				which, though it may seem not to be reprehensible, yet is
				then done maliciously when the omission happens in a
				place that is pertinent to the history. For to praise unwillingly is
				so far from being more civil than to dispraise
				willingly, that it is perhaps rather more uncivil.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.333"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>The fourth sign of a partial disposition in writing of
				history I take to be this: When a matter is related in two
				or more several manners, and the historian shall embrace
				the worst. Sophisters indeed are permitted, for the obtaining either of profit or reputation, to undertake the defence
				of the worst cause; for they neither create any firm belief
				of the matter, nor yet do they deny that they are often
				pleased in maintaining paradoxes and making incredible
				things appear probable. But an historian is then just,
				when he asserts such things as he knows to be true, and
				of those that are uncertain reports rather the better than
				the worse. Nay, there are many writers who wholly omit
				the worse. Thus Ephorus writes of Themistocles, that he
				was acquainted with the treason of Pausanias and his
				negotiations with the King's lieutenants, but that he neither
				consented to it, nor hearkened to Pausanias's proffers of
				making him partaker of his hopes; and Thucydides left
				the whole matter out of his story, as judging it to be
				false.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Moreover, in things confessed to have been done, but
				for doing which the cause and intention is unknown, he
				who casts his conjectures on the worst side is partial and
				malicious. Thus do the comedians. who affirm the Peloponnesian war to have been kindled by Pericles for the
				love of Aspasia or the sake of Phidias, and not through
				any desire of honor, or ambition of pulling down the
				Peloponnesian pride and giving place in nothing to the
				Lacedaemonians. For those who suppose a bad cause for
				laudable works and commendable actions, endeavoring by
				calumnies to insinuate sinister suspicions of the actor when
				they cannot openly discommend the act,&mdash;as they that
				impute the killing of Alexander the tyrant by Theba not
				to any magnanimity or hatred of vice, but to a certain
				feminine jealousy and passion, and those that say Cato
				slew himself for fear Caesar should put him to a more
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.334"/>
				
				shameful death,&mdash;such as these are manifestly in the
				highest degree envious and malicious.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>An historical narration is also more or less guilty of
				malice, according as it relates the manner of the action;
				as if one should be said to have performed an exploit
				rather by money than valor, as some affirm of Philip; or
				else easily and without any labor, as it is said of Alexander;
				or else not by prudence, but by Fortune, as the enemies of
				Timotheus painted cities falling into his nets as he lay
				sleeping. For they undoubtedly diminish the greatness
				and beauty of the actions, who deny the performers of
				them to have done them generously, industriously, virtuously, and by themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Moreover, those who will directly speak ill of any
				one incur the reproach of moroseness, rashness, and madness, unless they keep within measure. But they who
				send forth calumnies obliquely, as if they were shooting
				arrows out of corners, and then stepping back think to
				conceal themselves by saying they do not believe what they
				most earnestly desire to have believed, whilst they disclaim
				all malice, condemn themselves also of farther disingenuity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Next to these are they who with their reproaches
				intermix some praises, as did Aristoxenus, who, having
				termed Socrates unlearned, ignorant, and libidinous, added,
				Yet was he free from injustice. For, as they who flatter
				artificially and craftily sometimes mingle light reprehensions with their many and great praises, joining this liberty
				of speech as a sauce to their flattery; so malice, that it
				may gain belief to its accusations, adds also praise.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>We might here also reckon up more notes; but
				these are sufficient to let us understand the nature and
				manners of Herodotus.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>First therefore,&mdash;beginning, as the proverb is, with
				Vesta,&mdash;whereas all the Grecians affirm Io, daughter to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.335"/>
				
				Inachus, to have been worshipped with divine honor by
				the barbarians, and by her glory to have left her name to
				many seas and principal passages, and to have given a
				source and original to most noble and royal families; this
				famous author says of her, that she gave herself to certain
				Phoenician merchants, having been not unwillingly deflowered by a mariner, and fearing lest she should be found by
				her friends to be with child.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 5.</note> And he belies the Phoenicians as having delivered these things of her, and says
				that the Persian stories testify of her being carried away
				by the Phoenicians with other women.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 1.</note> Presently after,
				he gives sentence on the bravest and greatest exploits of
				Greece, saying that the Trojan war was foolishly undertaken for an ill woman. For it is manifest, says he, that
				had they not been willing they had never been ravished.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 4.</note>
				Let us then say, that the Gods also acted foolishly, in
				inflicting their indignation on the Spartans for abusing the
				daughters of Scedasus the Leuctrian, and in punishing
				Ajax for the violation of Cassandra. For it is manifest, if
				we believe Herodotus, that if they had not been willing
				they had never been defiled. And yet he himself said that
				Aristomenes was taken alive by the Spartans; and the
				same afterwards happened to Philopoemen, commander of
				the Achaeans; and the Carthaginians took Regulus, the
				consul of the Romans; than whom there are not easily to
				be found more valiant and warlike men. Nor is it to be
				wondered, since even leopards and tigers are taken alive
				by men. But Herodotus blames the poor women that
				have been abused by violence, and patronizes their ravishers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Nay, he is so favorable to the barbarians, that,
				acquitting Busiris of those human sacrifices and that
				slaughter of his guests for which he is accused, and attributing by his testimony to the Egyptians much religion and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.336"/>
				
				justice, he endeavors to cast that abominable wickedness
				and those impious murders on the Grecians. For in his
				Second Book he says, that Menelaus, having received
				Helen from Proteus and having been honored by him with
				many presents, showed himself a most unjust and wicked
				man; for wanting a fair wind to set sail, he found out an
				impious device, and having taken two of the inhabitants'
				boys, consulted their entrails; for which villany being
				hated and persecuted, he fled with his ships directly into
				Libya.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Herod. II. 45.</note> From what Egyptian this story proceeds, I know
				not. For, on the contrary, many honors are even at this
				day given by the Egyptians both to Helen and Menelaus.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>The same Herodotus, that he may still be like himself, says that the Persians learned the defiling of the male
				sex from the Greeks.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 135.</note> And yet how could the Greeks
				have taught this impurity to the Persians, amongst whom,
				as is confessed by almost all, boys had been castrated before
				ever they arrived in the Grecian seas? He writes also,
				that the Greeks were instructed by the Egyptians in their
				pomps, solemn festivals, and worship of the twelve Gods;
				that Melampus also learned of the Egyptians the name of
				Dionysus (or Bacchus) and taught it the other Greeks;
				that the mysteries likewise and rites of Ceres were brought
				out of Egypt by the daughters of Danaus; and that the
				Egyptians were wont to beat themselves and make great
				lamentation, but yet he himself would not tell the names
				of their Deities, but concealed them in silence. As
				to Hercules and Bacchus, whom the Egyptians named
				Gods, and the Greeks very aged men, he nowhere feels
				such scruples and hesitation; although he places also the
				Egyptian Hercules amongst the Gods of the second rank,
				and Bacchus amongst those of the third, as having had
				some beginning of their being and not being eternal, and
				yet he pronounces those to be Gods; but to the Greek
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.337"/>
				
				Bacchus and Hercules, as having been mortal and being
				now demi gods, he thinks we ought to perform anniversary solemnities, but not to sacrifice to them as to Gods.
				The same also he said of Pan, overthrowing the most venerable and purest sacrifices of the Greeks by the proud
				vanities and mythologies of the Egyptians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the passages referred to in this chapter, see Herod. II. 48-51, 145, 146, 171.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Nor is this impious enough; but moreover, deriving
				the pedigree of Hercules from Perseus, he says that Perseus
				was an Assyrian, as the Persians affirm. <q direct="unspecified">But the leaders,</q>
				says he, <q direct="unspecified">of the Dorians may appear to be descended in a
					right line from the Egyptians, reckoning their ancestors
					from before Danae and Acrisius.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VI. 53, 54.</note> Here he has wholly
				passed by Epaphus, Io, Iasus, and Argus, being ambitious
				not only to make the other Herculeses Egyptians and
				Phoenicians, but to carry this also, whom himself affirms
				to have been the third, out of Greece to the barbarians.
				But of the ancient learned writers, neither Homer, nor
				Hesiod, or Archilochus, nor Pisander, nor Stesichorus, nor
				Alcman, nor Pindar, makes any mention of the Egyptian
				or the Phoenician Hercules, but all acknowledge this our
				own Boeotian and Argive Hercules.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Now of the seven sages, whom he calls Sophisters,
				he affirms Thales to have been a barbarian, descended of
				the Phoenicians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 170.</note> Speaking ill also of the Gods under
				the person of Solon, he has these words: <q direct="unspecified">Thou, O
					Croesus, askest me concerning human affairs, who know
					that every one of the Deities is envious and tumultuous.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 32.</note>
				Thus attributing to Solon what himself thinks of the Gods,
				he joins malice to blasphemy. Having made use also of
				Pittacus in some trivial matters, not worth the mentioning,
				he has passed over the greatest and gallantest action that
				was ever done by him. For when the Athenians and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.338"/>
				
				Mitylenaeans were at war about Sigaeum, Phrynon, the
				Athenian general, challenging whoever would come forth
				to a single combat, Pittacus advanced to meet him, and
				catching him in a net, slew that stout and giant-like man;
				for which when the Mitylenaeans offered him great presents,
				darting his javelin as far as he could out of his hand, he
				desired only so much ground as he should reach with that
				throw; and the place is to this day called Pittacium. Now
				what does Herodotus, when he comes to this? Instead
				of Pittacus's valiant act, he tells us the fight of Alcaeus
				the poet, who throwing away his arms ran out of the
				battle; by thus not writing of honorable deeds and not
				passing over such as are dishonorable, he gives his
				testimony to those who say, that from one and the same
				malice proceed both envy and a rejoicing at other men's
				harms.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. V. 95.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>After this, he accuses of treason the Alcmaeonidae,
				who showed themselves generous men, and delivered their
				country from tyranny.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 61.</note> He says, that they received Pisistratus after his banishment and got him called home, on
				condition he should marry the daughter of Megacles; but
				the damsel saying to her mother, Do you see, mother, how
				I am not known by Pisistratus according to nature? the
				Alcmaeonidae were so offended at this villany, that they
				expelled the tyrant.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>Now that the Lacedaemonians might have no less
				share of his malice than the Athenians, behold how he
				bespatters Othryadas, the man most admired and honored
				by them. <q direct="unspecified">He only,</q> says Herodotus, <q direct="unspecified">remaining alive
					of the three hundred, and ashamed to return to Sparta,
					his companions being lost, slew himself on the spot at
					Thyreae.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 82</note> For having before said the victory was doubtful on both sides, he here, by making Othryadas ashamed,
				witnesses that the Lacedaemonians were vanquished. For
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.339"/>
				
				it was shameful for him to survive, if conquered; but glorious, if conqueror.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>I pass by now, that having represented Croesus as
				foolish, vain-glorious, and ridiculous in all things, he makes
				him, when a prisoner, to have taught and instructed Cyrus,
				who seems to have excelled all other kings in prudence,
				virtue, and magnanimity.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 155, 156, 207, 208.</note> Having testified of the same
				Croesus nothing else that was commendable, but his honoring the Gods with many and great oblations, he shows
				that very act of his to have been the most impious of all.
				For he says, that he and his brother Pantoleon contended
				for the kingdom while their father was yet alive; and that
				Croesus, having obtained the crown, caused a companion
				and familiar friend of Pantoleon's to be torn in pieces in a
				fulling-mill, and sent presents to the Gods from his estate.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 92.</note>
				Of De&iuml;oces also, the Median, who by virtue and justice
				obtained the government, he says that he got it not by
				real but pretended justice.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 96.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>But I let pass the barbarian examples, since he has
				offered us plenty enough in the Grecian affairs. He says,
				that the Athenians and most other Ionians were so ashamed
				of that name that they wholly refused to be called Ionians;
				and that those who esteemed themselves the noblest among
				them, and who had set forth from the very Prytaneum of
				Athens, begat children on barbarian wives whose parents,
				husbands, and former children they had slain; that the
				women had therefore made a law among themselves, confirmed it by oath, and delivered it to be kept by their
				daughters, never to eat with their husbands, nor to call
				any of them by his name; and that the present Milesians
				are descended from these women. Having afterwards
				added that those are true Ionians who celebrate the feast
				called Apaturia; they all, says he, keep it except the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.340"/>
				
				Ephesians and Colophonians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. I. 143-148.</note> In this manner does he
				deprive these two states of their nobility.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>He says moreover, that the Cumaeans and Mitylenaeans agreed with Cyrus to deliver up to him for a
				price Pactyas, who had revolted from him. I know not
				indeed, says he, for how much; since it is not certain what
				it was. Well done!&mdash;not to know what it was, and yet to
				cast such an infamy on a Grecian city, as if he had an
				assured knowledge! He says farther, that the Chians
				took Pactyas, who was brought to them out of the temple
				of Minerva Poliuchus (or Guardianess of the city), and
				delivered him up, having received the city Atarneus for
				their recompense. And yet Charon the Lampsacenian, a
				mote ancient writer, relating this matter concerning Pactyas, charges neither the Mitylenaeans nor the Chians with
				any such impious action. These are his very words: <q direct="unspecified">Pactyas, hearing that the Persian army drew near, fled first
					to Mitylene, then to Chios, and there fell into the hands
					of Cyrus.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Herod. I. 157, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>Our author in his Third Book, relating the expedition of the Lacedaemonians against the tyrant Polycrates,
				affirms, that the Samians think and say that the Spartans,
				to recompense them for their former assistance against the
				Messenians, both brought back the Samians that were banished, and made war on the tyrant; but that the Lacedaemonians deny this, and say, they undertook this design not
				to help or deliver the Samians, but to punish them for
				having taken away a cup sent by them to Croesus, and besides, a breastplate sent them by Amasis.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. III. 47, 48.</note> And yet we
				know that there was not at that time any city so desirous
				of honor, or such an enemy to tyrants, as Sparta. For
				what breastplate or cup was the cause of their driving the
				Cypselidae out of Corinth and Ambracia, Lygdamis out of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.341"/>
				
				Naxos, the children of Pisistratus out of Athens, Aeschines
				out of Sicyon, Symmachus out of Thasus, Aulis out of
				Phocis, and Aristogenes out of Miletus; and of their overturning the domineering powers of Thessaly, pulling down
				Aristomedes and Angelus by the help of King Leotychides?
				&mdash;which facts are elsewhere more largely described. Now,
				if Herodotus says true, they were in the highest degree
				guilty both of malice and folly, when, denying a most honorable and most just cause of their expedition, they confessed that in remembrance of a former injury, and too
				highly valuing an inconsiderable matter, they invaded a
				miserable and afflicted people.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Now perhaps he gave the Lacedaemonians this
				stroke, as directly falling under his pen; but the city of
				Corinth, which was wholly out of the course of his story,
				he has dragged in&mdash;going out of his way (as they say) to
				seize upon it&mdash;and has bespattered it with a most filthy
				crime and most shameful calumny. <q direct="unspecified">The Corinthians,</q>
				says he, &ldquo;studiously forwarded this expedition of the Lacedaemonians to Samos, as having themselves also been formerly affronted by the Samians. The matter was this.
				Periander tyrant of Corinth sent three hundred boys, sons
				to the principal men of Corcyra, to King Alyattes, to be
				gelt. These, going ashore in the island of Samos, were
				by the Samians taught to sit as suppliants in the temple of
				Diana, where they preserved them, setting before them for
				their food sesame mixed with honey. This our author
				calls an affront put by the Samians on the Corinthians, who
				therefore instigated the Lacedaemonians against them, to
				wit, because the Samians had saved three hundred children
				of the Greeks from being unmanned. By attributing this
				villany to the Corinthians, he makes the city more wicked
				than the tyrant. He indeed was revenging himself on
				those of Corcyra who had slain his son; but what had the
				Corinthians suffered, that they should punish the Samians
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.342"/>
				
				for putting an obstacle to so great a cruelty and wickedness?&mdash;and this, after three generations, reviving the
				memory of an old quarrel for the sake of that tyranny,
				which they found so grievous and intolerable that they are
				still endlessly abolishing all the monuments and marks of
				it, though long since extinct. Such then was the injury
				done by the Samians to the Corinthians. Now what a
				kind of punishment was it the Corinthians would have inflicted on them? Had they been indeed angry with the
				Samians, they should not have incited the Lacedaemonians,
				but rather diverted them from their war against Polycrates,
				that the Samians might not by the tyrant's overthrow recover liberty, and be feed from their slavery. But (what
				is most to be observed) why were the Corinthians so offended with the Samians, that desired indeed but were not
				able to save the Corcyraeans' children, and yet were not
				displeased with the Cnidians, who both preserved them and
				restored them to their friends? Nor indeed have the
				Corcyraeans any great esteem for the Samians on this account; but of the Cnidians they preserve a grateful memory, having granted them several honors and privileges, and
				made decrees in their favor. For these, sailing to Samos,
				drove away Periander's guards from the temple, and taking the children aboard their ships, carried them safe to
				Corcyra; as it is recorded by Antenor the Cretan, and by
				Dionysius the Chalcidian in his foundations. Now that
				the Spartans undertook not this war on any design of punishing the Samians, but to save them by delivering them
				from the tyrant, we have the testimony of the Samians
				themselves. For they affirm that there is in Samos a
				monument erected at the public charge, and honors there
				done to Archias a Spartan, who fell fighting valiantly in
				that quarrel; for which cause also his posterity still keep a
				familiar and friendly correspondence with the Samians, as
				Herodotus himself witnesses.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.343"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>In his Fifth Book, he says, that Clisthenes, one of
				the best and noblest men in Athens, persuaded the priestess
				Pythia to be a false prophetess, and always to exhort the
				Lacedaemonians to free Athens from the tyrants; calumniating this most excellent and just action by the imputation
				of so great a wickedness and imposture, and taking from
				Apollo the credit of that true and good prophecy, beseeming even Themis herself, who is also said to have joined
				with him. He says farther, that Isagoras prostituted his
				wife to Cleomenes, who came to her.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. V. 63, 70.</note> Then, as his manner is, to gain credit by mixing some praises with his reproaches, he says: Isagoras the son of Tisander was of a
				noble family, but I cannot tell the original of it; his kinsmen, however, sacrifice to the Carian Jupiter.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. V. 66.</note> O this
				pleasant and cunning scoffer of a writer, who thus disgracefully sends Isagoras to the Carians, as it were to the ravens.
				As for Aristogiton, he puts him not forth at the back door,
				but thrusts him directly out of the gate into Phoenicia,
				saying that he had his original from the Gephyraeans, and
				that the Gephyraeans were not, as some think, Euboeans
				or Eretrians, but Phoenicians, as himself has learned by
				report.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. V. 58.</note> And since he cannot altogether take from the
				Lacedaemonians the glory of having delivered the Athenians from the tyrants, he endeavors to cloud and disgrace
				that most honorable act by as foul a passion. For he says,
				they presently repented of it, as not having done well, in
				that they had been induced by spurious and deceitful oracles to drive the tyrants, who were their allies and had
				promised to put Athens into their hands, out of their country, and had restored the city to an ungrateful people. He
				adds, that they were about to send for Hippias from Sigeum, and bring him back to Athens; but that they were
				opposed by the Corinthians, Sosicles telling them how
				much the city of Corinth had suffered under the tyranny
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.344"/>
				
				of Cypselus and Periander.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. V. 90, 91.</note> And yet there was no outrage of Periander's more abominable and cruel than his
				sending the three hundred children to be emasculated, for
				the delivering and saving of whom from that contumely,
				the Corinthians, he says, were angry and bore a grudge
				against the Samians, as having put an affront upon them.
				With so much repugnance and contradiction is that malice
				of his discourse filled, which on every occasion insinuates
				itself into his narrations.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>After this, relating the action of Sardis, he, as much
				as in him lies, diminishes and discredits the matter; being
				so audacious as to call the ships which the Athenians sent
				to the assistance of the Ionians, who had revolted from the
				King, the beginning of evils, because they endeavored to
				deliver so many and so great Grecian cities from the barbarians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. V. 97.</note> As to the Eretrians, making mention of them
				only by the way, he passes over in silence a great, gallant,
				and memorable action of theirs. For when all Ionia was
				in a confusion and uproar, and the King's fleet drew nigh,
				they, going forth to meet him, overcame in a sea-fight the
				Cyprians in the Pamphylian Sea. Then turning back and
				leaving their ships at Ephesus, they invaded Sardis and
				besieged Artaphernes, who was fled into the castle, that so
				they might raise the siege of Miletus. And this indeed
				they effected, causing the enemies to break up their camp
				and remove thence in a wonderful fright, and then seeing
				themselves in danger to be oppressed by a multitude, retired. This not only others, but Lysanias of Mallus also
				in his history of Eretria relates, thinking it convenient, if
				for no other reason, yet after the taking and destruction of
				the city, to add this valiant and heroic act. But this writer
				of ours says, they were defeated, and pursued even to their
				ships by the barbarians; though Charon the Lampsacenian
				has no such thing, but writes thus, word for word: <q direct="unspecified">The
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.345"/>
					
					Athenians set forth with twenty galleys to the assistance
					of the Ionians, and going to Sardis, took all thereabouts,
					except the King's wall; which having done, they returned
					to Miletus.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>In his Sixth Book, our author, discoursing of the
				Plataeans,&mdash;how they gave themselves to the Lacedaemonians, who exhorted them rather to have recourse to the
				Athenians, who were nearer to them and no bad defenders,
				&mdash;adds, not as a matter of suspicion or opinion, but as a
				thing certainly known by him, that the Lacedaemonians
				gave the Plataeans this advice, not so much for any good
				will, as through a desire to find work for the Athenians by
				engaging them with the Boeotians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VI. 108.</note> If then Herodotus is
				not malicious, the Lacedaemonians must have been both
				fraudulent and spiteful; and the Athenians fools, in suffering themselves to be thus imposed on; and the Plataeans
				were brought into play, not for any good-will or respect,
				but as an occasion of war.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>He is farther manifestly convinced of belying the
				Lacedaemonians, when he says that, whilst they expected
				the full moon, they failed of giving their assistance to the
				Athenians at Marathon. For they not only made a thousand other excursions and fights at the beginning of the
				month, without staying for the full moon; but wanted so
				little of being present at this very battle, which was fought
				the sixth day of the month Boedromion, that at their coming they found the dead still lying in the field. And yet
				he has written thus of the full moon: <q direct="unspecified">It was impossible
					for them to do these things at that present, being unwilling
					to break the law; for it was the ninth day of the month,
					and they said, they could not go forth on the ninth day, the
					orb of the moon being not yet full. And therefore they
					stayed for the full moon.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VI. 106.</note> But thou, O Herodotus, transferest the full moon from the middle to the beginning of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.346"/>
				
				the month, and at the same time confoundest the heavens,
				days, and all things; and yet thou dost pretend to be the
				historian of Greece!</p>
            <p>And professing to write more particularly and carefully
					of the affairs of Athens, thou dost not so much as say a
					word of that solemn procession which the Athenians even
					at this day send to Agrae, celebrating a feast of thanks-giving to Hecate for their victory. But this helps Herodotus to refel the crime with which he is charged, of having
					flattered the Athenians for a great sum of money he received of them. For if he had rehearsed these things to
					them, they would not have omitted or neglected to notice
					that Philippides, when on the ninth he called the Lacedaemonians to the fight, must have come from it himself, since
					(as Herodotus says) he went in two days from Athens to
					Sparta; unless the Athenians sent for their allies to the
					fight after their enemies were overcome. Indeed Diyllus
					the Athenian, none of the most contemptible as an historian, says, that he received from Athens a present of ten
					talents, Anytus proposing the decree. Moreover Herodotus, as many say, has in relating the fight at Marathon
					derogated from the credit of it, by the number he sets down
					of the slain. For it is said that the Athenians made a vow
					to sacrifice so many kids to Diana Agrotera, as they should
					kill barbarians; but that after the fight, the number of the
					dead appearing infinite, they appeased the Goddess by
					making a decree to immolate five hundred to her every
					year.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>But letting this pass, let us see what was done after
				the fight. <q direct="unspecified">The barbarians,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">retiring back with
					the rest of their ships, and taking the Eretrian slaves out
					of the island, where they had left them, doubled the point
					of Sunium, desiring to prevent the Athenians before they
					could gain the city. The Athenians suspected this to have
					been done by a plot of the Alcmaeonidae, who by agreement
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.347"/>
					
					 showed a shield to the Persians when they were got
					into their ships. They therefore doubled the cape of Sunium.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VI. 115, 121-124.</note> Let us in this place take no notice of his calling
				the Eretrians slaves, who showed as much courage and
				gallantry in this war as any other of the Grecians, and
				suffered things unworthy their virtue. Nor let us insist
				much on the calumny with which he defames the Alcmaeonidae, some of whom were both the greatest families and
				noblest men of the city. But the greatness of the victory
				itself is overthrown, and the end of that so celebrated
				action comes to nothing, nor does it seem to have been a
				fight or any great exploit, but only a light skirmish with
				the barbarians, as the envious and ill-willers affirm, if they
				did not after the battle fly away, cutting their cables and
				giving themselves to the wind, to carry them as far as
				might be from the Attic coast, but having a shield lifted
				up to them as a signal of treason, made straight with their
				fleet for Athens, in hope to surprise it, and having at
				leisure doubled the point of Sunium, were discovered
				above the port Phalerum, so that the chief and most illustrious men, despairing to save the city, would have betrayed it. For a little after, acquitting the Alcmaeonidae,
				he charges others with the treason. <q direct="unspecified">For the shield indeed was shown, nor can it be denied,</q> says he, as if he
				had seen it himself. But this could no way be, since the
				Athenians obtained a solid victory; and if it had been
				done, it could not have been seen by the barbarians, flying
				in a hurry amidst wounds and arrows into their ships,
				and leaving every one the place with all possible speed.
				But when he again pretends to excuse the Alcmaeonidae
				of those crimes which he first of all men objected against
				them, and speaks thus: <q direct="unspecified">I cannot believe that the Alcmaeonidae by agreement would ever have lifted up a shield
					to the Persians, and have brought the Athenians under the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.348"/>
					
					power of the barbarians and Hippias;</q> I am reminded
				of a certain proverbial saying,&mdash;Stop and be caught, crab,
				and I'll let you go. For why art thou so eager to catch
				him, if thou wilt let him go when he is caught? Thus
				you first accuse, then apologize; and you write calumnies
				against illustrious men, which again you refute. And you
				discredit yourself; for you heard no one but yourself say
				that the Alcmaeonidae lifted up a shield to the vanquished
				and flying barbarians. And in those very things which
				you allege for the Alcmaeonidae, you show yourself a sycophant. For if, as here you write, the Alcmaeonidae were
				more or no less enemies to tyrants than Callias, the son of
				Phaenippus and father of Hipponicus, where will you
				place their conspiracy, of which you write in your First
				Book, that assisting Pisistratus they brought him back
				from exile to the tyranny and would not have driven
				him away till he was accused of unnaturally abusing his
				wife? Such then are the repugnances of these things;
				and by his intermixing the praises of Callias, the son of
				Phaenippus, amidst the crimes and suspicions of the Alcmaeonidae, and joining to him his son Hipponicus, who
				was (as Herodotus himself says) one of the richest men in
				Athens, he confesses that he brought in Callias not for any
				necessity of the story, but to ingratiate himself and gain
				favor with Hipponicus.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>Now, whereas all know that the Argives denied not
				to enter into the common league of the Grecians, though
				they thought not fit to follow and be under the command
				of the Lacedaemonians, who were their mortal enemies,
				and that this was no otherways, our author subjoins a most
				malicious cause for it, writing thus: <q direct="unspecified">When they saw
					they were comprised by the Greeks, knowing that the
					Lacedaemonians would not admit them into a share of the
					command, they requested it, that they might have a pretence to lie still.</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">And of this,</q> he says, <q direct="unspecified">the Argive
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.349"/>
						
						ambassadors afterwards put Artaxerxes in mind, when
						they attended him at Susa, and the King said, he esteemed
						no city more his friend than Argos.</q> Then adding, as his
				manner is, to cover the matter, he says: <q direct="unspecified">Of these things
					I know nothing certainly; but this I know, that all men
					have faults, and that the worst things were not done by
					the Argives; but I must tell such things as are reported,
					though I am not bound to believe them all; and let this
					be understood of all my narrations. For it is farther said
					that the Argives, when they were not able to sustain the
					war against the Lacedaemonians, called the Persians into
					Greece, willing to suffer any thing rather than the present
					trouble.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 148-152.</note> Therefore, as himself reports the Ethiopian to
				have said of the ointment and purple, <q direct="unspecified">Deceitful are the
					beauties, deceitful the garments of the Persians,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. III. 22.</note> may not
				any one say also of him, Deceitful are the phrases, deceitful the figures of Herodotus's speeches; as being perplexed, unsound, and full of ambiguities? For as painters
				set off and render more eminent the luminous part of their
				pictures by adding shadows, so he by his denials extends
				his calumnies, and by his dubious speeches makes his suspicions take deeper impression. If the Argives joined not
				with the other Greeks, but stood out through an emulation of the Lacedaemonians' command and valor, it cannot
				be denied but that they acted in a manner not beseeming
				their nobility and descent from Hercules. For it had been
				more honorable for the Argives under the rule of Siphnians
				and Cythnians to have defended the Grecian liberty, than
				contending with the Spartans for superiority to have
				avoided so many and such signal combats. And if it was
				they who brought the Persians into Greece, because their
				war against the Lacedaemonians succeeded ill, how came
				it to pass, that they did not at the coming of Xerxes openly
				join themselves to the Persians? Or if they would not
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.350"/>
				
				fight under the King, why did they not, being left at home,
				make incursions into Laconia, or again attempt Thyreae,
				or by some other way disturb and infest the Lacedaemonians? For they might have greatly damaged the Grecians, by hindering the Spartans from going with so great
				an army to Plataea.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>But in this place indeed he has highly magnified the
				Athenians and pronounced them the saviors of Greece,
				doing herein rightly and justly, if he had not intermixed
				many reproaches with their praises. But now, when he
				says<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 139.</note> that (had it not been for the Athenians) the Lacedaemonians would have been betrayed by the other Greeks,
				and then, being left alone and having performed great
				exploits, they would have died generously; or else, having
				before seen that the Greeks were favoring the Medes,
				they would have made terms with Xerxes; it is manifest,
				he speaks not these things to the commendation of the
				Athenians, but he praises the Athenians that he may speak
				ill of all the rest. For how can any one now be angry
				with him for so bitterly and intemperately upbraiding the
				Thebans and Phocians at every turn, when he charges even
				those who exposed themselves to all perils for Greece with
				a treason which was never acted, but which (as he suspects)
				might have been acted. Nay, of the Lacedaemonians themselves, he makes it doubtful whether they would have fallen
				in the battle or have yielded to the enemy, distrusting the
				proofs of their valor which were shown at Thermopylae;&mdash;and these indeed were slight!</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>After this, when he declares the shipwreck that befell the King's fleet, and how, an infinite mass of wealth
				being cast away, Aminocles the Magnesian, son of Cresines,
				was greatly enriched by it, having gotten an immense
				quantity of gold and silver; he could not so much as let
				this pass without snarling at it. <q direct="unspecified">For this man,</q> says he,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.351"/>
				
				           <q direct="unspecified">who had till then been none of the most fortunate, by
					wrecks became exceeding rich; for the misfortune he had
					in killing his son much afflicted his mind.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 190. Most scholars interpret this passage of Herodotus to mean that some accident destroyed one or more of the children of Aminocles. (G.)</note> This indeed
				is manifest to every one, that he brought this golden treasure and this wealth cast up by the sea into his history, that
				he might make way for the inserting Aminocles's killing
				his son.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>Now Aristophanes the Boeotian wrote, that Herodotus demanded money of the Thebans but received
				none, and that going about to discourse and reason with
				the young men, he was prohibited by the magistrates
				through their clownishness and hatred of learning; of
				which there is no other argument. But Herodotus bears
				witness to Aristophanes, whilst he charges the Thebans
				with some things falsely, with others ignorantly, and with
				others as hating them and having a quarrel with them.
				For he affirms that the Thessalians at first upon necessity
				inclined to the Persians,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 172</note> in which he says the truth; and
				prophesying of the other Grecians that they would betray
				the Lacedaemonians, he added, that they would not do it
				willingly, but upon necessity, one city being taken after
				another. But he does not allow the Thebans the same
				plea of necessity, although they sent to Tempe five hundred men under the command of Mnamias, and to Thermopylae as many as Leonidas desired, who also alone with
				the Thespians stood by him, the rest leaving him after he
				was surrounded. But when the barbarian, having possessed himself of the avenues, was got into their confines,
				and Demaratus the Spartan, favoring in right of hospitality Attaginus, the chief of the oligarchy, had so wrought
				that he became the King's friend and familiar, whilst the
				other Greeks were in their ships, and none came on by
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.352"/>
				
				land; then at last being forsaken did they accept conditions
				of peace, to which they were compelled by great necessity.
				For they had neither the sea and ships at hand, as had the
				Athenians; nor did they dwell far off, as the Spartans, who
				inhabited the most remote parts of Greece; but were not
				above a day and half's journey from the Persian army, whom
				they had already with the Spartans and Thespians alone
				resisted at the entrance of the straits, and were defeated.</p>
            <p>But this writer is so equitable, that having said, <q direct="unspecified">The
					Lacedaemonians, being alone and deserted by their allies,
					would perhaps have made a composition with Xerxes,</q>
					he yet abuses the Thebans, who were driven to the same
					act by the same necessity. But when he could not wholly
					obliterate this most great and glorious act of the Thebans,
					yet went he about to deface it with a most vile imputation
					and suspicion, writing thus: <q direct="unspecified">The confederates who had
						been sent returned back, obeying the commands of Leonidas; there remained only with the Lacedaemonians the
						Thespians and the Thebans: of these, the Thebans stayed
						against their wills, for Leonidas retained them as hostages;
						but the Thespians most willingly, as they said they would
						never depart from Leonidas and those that were with
						him.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 222.</note> Does he not here manifestly discover himself to
					have a peculiar pique and hatred against the Thebans, by
					the impulse of which he not only falsely and unjustly
					calumniated the city, but did not so much as take care to
					render his contradiction probable, or to conceal, at least
					from a few men, his being conscious of having knowingly
					contradicted himself? For having before said that Leonidas,
					perceiving his confederates not to be in good heart nor prepared to undergo danger, wished them to depart, he a little
					after adds that the Thebans were against their wills detained by him; whereas, if he had believed them inclined
					to the Persians, he should have driven them away though
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.353"/>
					
					they had been willing to tarry. For if he thought that
					those who were not brisk would be useless, to what purpose was it to mix among his soldiers those that were suspected? Nor was the king of the Spartans and general of
					all Greece so senseless as to think that four hundred armed
					Thebans could be detained as hostages by his three hundred, especially the enemy being both in his front and rear.
					For though at first he might have taken them along with
					him as hostages; it is certainly probable that at last, having
					no regard for him, they would have gone away from him,
					and that Leonidas would have more feared his being encompassed by them than by the enemy. Furthermore,
					would not Leonidas have been ridiculous, to have sent
					away the other Greeks, as if by staying they should soon
					after have died, and to have detained the Thebans, that
					being himself about to die, he might keep them for the
					Greeks? For if he had indeed carried them along with
					him for hostages, or rather for slaves, he should not have
					kept them with those that were at the point of perishing,
					but have delivered them to the Greeks that went away.
					There remained but one cause that might be alleged for
					Leonidas's unwillingness to let them go, to wit, that they
					might die with him; and this our historian himself has
					taken away, writing thus of Leonidas's ambition: <q direct="unspecified">Leonidas considering these things, and desirous that this glory
						might redound to the Spartans alone, sent away his confederates rather for this than because they differed in their
						opinions.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 220.</note> For it had certainly been the height of folly
					to keep his enemies against their wills, to be partakers of
					that glory from which he drove away his confederates.
					But it is manifest from the effects, that Leonidas suspected
					not the Thebans of insincerity, but esteemed them to be
					his steadfast friends. For he marched with his army into
					Thebes, and at his request obtained that which was never
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.354"/>
					
					granted to any other, to sleep within the temple of Hercules; and the next morning he related to the Thebans the
					vision that had appeared to him. For he imagined that he
					saw the most illustrious and greatest cities of Greece irregularly tost and floating up and down on a very stormy and
					tempestuous sea; that Thebes, being carried above all
					the rest, was lifted up on high to heaven, and suddenly
					after disappeared. And this indeed had a resemblance of
					those things which long after befell that city.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Now Herodotus, in his narration of that fight, hath
				obscured also the bravest act of Leonidas, saying that they
				all fell in the straits near the hill.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 225.</note> But the affair was
				otherwise managed. For when they perceived by night
				that they were encompassed by the barbarians, they
				marched straight to the enemies' camp, and got very near
				the King's pavilion, with a resolution to kill him and leave
				their lives about him. They came then to his tent, killing
				or putting to flight all they met; but when Xerxes was
				not found there, seeking him in that vast camp and wandering about, they were at last with much difficulty slain
				by the barbarians, who surrounded them on every side.
				What other acts and sayings of the Spartans Herodotus
				has omitted, we will write in the Life of Leonidas; yet that
				hinders not but we may here set down also some few.
				Before Leonidas went forth to that war, the Spartans exhibited to him funeral games, at which the fathers and
				mothers of those that went along with him were spectators. Leonidas himself, when one said to him, You lead
				very few with you to the battle, answered, There are many
				to die there. When his wife, at his departure, asked him
				what commands he had for her; he, turning to her, said,
				I command you to marry good men, and bring them good
				children. After he was enclosed by the enemy at Thermopylae, desiring to save two that were related to him, he
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.355"/>
				
				gave one of them a letter and sent him away; but he rejected it, saying angrily, I followed you as a soldier, not
				as a post. The other he commanded on a message to the
				magistrates of Sparta; but he, answering by his act, took
				his shield, and stood up in his rank. Who would not
				have blamed another that should have omitted these things?
				But he who has collected and recorded the fart of Amasis,
				the coming of the thiefs asses, and the giving of bottles,
				and many such like things, cannot seem to have omitted
				these gallant acts and these remarkable sayings by negligence and oversight, but as bearing ill-will and being unjust to some.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>He says that the Thebans, being at the first with
				the Greeks, fought compelled by necessity.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 233.</note> For belike
				not only Xerxes, but Leonidas also, had whipsters following his camp, by whom the Thebans were scourged and
				forced against their wills to fight. And what more savage libeller could be found than Herodotus, when he says
				that they fought upon necessity, who might have gone
				away and fled, and that they inclined to the Persians,
				whereas not one came in to help them. After this, he
				writes that, the rest making to the hill, the Thebans separated themselves from them, lifted up their hands to the
				barbarian, and coming near, cried with a most true voice,
				that they had favored the Persians, had given earth and
				water to the King, that now being forced by necessity they
				were come to Thermopylae, and that they were innocent
				of the King's wound. Having said these things, they obtained quarter; for they had the Thessalians for witnesses of all they said. Behold, how amidst the barbarians'
				exclamations, tumults of all sorts, flights and pursuits, their
				apology was heard, the witnesses examined; and the Thessalians, in the midst of those that were slain and trodden
				under foot, all being done in a very narrow passage, patronized
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.356"/>
				
				 the Thebans, to wit, because the Thebans had but
				a little before driven away them, who were possessed of
				all Greece as far as Thespiae, having conquered them in
				a battle, and slain their leader Lattamyas! For thus at
				that time stood matters between the Boeotians and the
				Thessalians, without any friendship or good-will. But yet
				how did the Thebans escape, the Thessalians helping them
				with their testimonies? Some of them, says he, were
				slain by the barbarians; many of them were by command
				of Xerxes marked with the royal mark, beginning with
				their leader Leontiades. Now the captain of the Thebans
				at Thermopylae was not Leontiades, but Anaxander, as
				both Aristophanes, out of the Commentaries of the Magistrates, and Nicander the Colophonian have taught us. Nor
				did any man before Herodotus know that the Thebans
				were stigmatized by Xerxes; for otherwise this would
				have been an excellent plea for them against his calumny,
				and this city might well have gloried in these marks, that
				Xerxes had punished Leonidas and Leontiades as his
				greatest enemies, having outraged the body of the one
				when he was dead, and caused the other to be tormented
				whilst living. But as to a man who makes the barbarian's
				cruelty against Leonidas when dead a sign that he hated
				him most of all men when living,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 238.</note> and yet says that the
				Thebans, though favoring the Persians, were stigmatized
				by them at Thermopylae, and having been thus stigmatized, again cheerfully took their parts at Plataea, it seems
				to me that such a man&mdash;like that Hippoclides<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Herod. VI. 126-130.</note> who stood
				on his head upon a table and gesticulated with his legs&mdash;would dance away the truth and exclaim, Herodotus
				cares not for that.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>In the Eighth Book our author says, that the
				Greeks being frighted designed to fly from Artemisium
				into Greece, and that, being requested by the Euboeans to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.357"/>
				
				stay a little till they could dispose of their wives and families, they regarded them not, till such time as Themistocles, having taken money of them, divided it between
				Eurybiades and Adimantus, the captain of the Corinthians,
				and that then they stayed and had a sea-fight with the barbarians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 4</note> Yet Pindar, who was not a citizen of any of
				the confederate cities, but of one that was suspected to
				take part with the Medians, having made mention of Artemisium, brake forth into this exclamation: <q direct="unspecified">This is the
					place where the sons of the Athenians laid the glorious
					foundation of liberty.</q> But Herodotus, by whom, as some
				will have it, Greece is honored, makes that victory a work
				of bribery and theft, saying that the Greeks, deceived by
				their captains, who had to that end taken money, fought
				against their wills. Nor does he here put an end to his
				malice. All men in a manner confess that, although the
				Greeks got the better at sea, they nevertheless abandoned
				Artemisium to the barbarians after they had received the
				news of the overthrow at Thermopylae. For it was to no
				purpose for them to stay there and keep the sea, the war
				being already within Thermopylae, and Xerxes having
				possessed himself of the avenues. But Herodotus makes
				the Greeks contriving to fly before they heard any thing of
				Leonidas's death. For thus he says: <q direct="unspecified">But they having
					been ill-treated, and especially the Athenians, half of
					whose ships were sorely shattered, consulted to take their
					flight into Greece.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 18.</note> But let him be permitted so to name
				(or rather reproach) this retreat of theirs before the fight;
				but having before called it a flight, he both now styles it a
				flight, and will again a little after term it a flight; so bitterly does he adhere to this word <q direct="unspecified">flight.</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Presently
					after this,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">there came to the barbarians in the
						pinnace a man of Hestiaea, who acquainted them with the
						flight of the Grecians from Artemisium. They, because
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.358"/>
						
						the thing seemed incredible, kept the messenger in custody, and sent forth some light galleys to discover the
						truth.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 23.</note> But what is this you say? That they fled as
				conquered, whom the enemies after the fight could not believe to have fled, as having got much the better? Is then
				this a fellow fit to be believed when he writes of any man
				or city, who in one word deprives Greece of the victory,
				throws down the trophy, and pronounces the inscriptions
				they had set up to Diana Proseoa (<hi rend="italics">Eastward-looking</hi>) to be
				nothing but pride and vain boasting? The tenor of the
				inscription was as follows:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Athens youth had in a naval fight
				</l>
                     <l>All Asia's forces on this sea overthrown,
				</l>
                     <l>And all the Persian army put to flight,
				</l>
                     <l>Than which a greater scarce was ever known,
				</l>
                     <l>To show how much Diana they respected,
				</l>
                     <l>This trophy to her honor they erected.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, not having described any order of the Greeks,
					nor told us what place every city of theirs held during the
					sea-fight, he says that in this retreat, which he calls their
					flight, the Corinthians sailed first and the Athenians last.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 21.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>He indeed ought not to have too much insulted over
				the Greeks that took part with the Persians, who, being
				by others thought a Thurian, reckons himself among the
				Halicarnassians, who, being Dorians by descent, went with
				their wives and children to the war against the Greeks.
				But he is so far from giving first an account of the straits
				they were in who revolted to the Persians, that, having related how the Thessalians sent to the Phocians, who
				were their mortal enemies, and promised to preserve their
				country free from all damage if they might receive from
				them a reward of fifty talents, he writ thus of the Phocians:
				<q direct="unspecified">For the Phocians were the only people in these quarters
					who inclined not to the Persians, and that, as far as I upon
					due consideration can find, for no other reason but because
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.359"/>
					
					they hated the Thessalians; for if the Thessalians had
					been affected to the Grecian affairs, I suppose the Phocians
					would have joined themselves to the Persians.</q> And yet
				a little after he will say, that thirteen cities of the Phocians
				were burned by the barbarians, their country laid waste,
				and the temple which was in Abae set on fire, and all of
				both sexes put to the sword, except those that by flight
				escaped to Parnassus.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 30-33. Compare IX. 17.</note> Nevertheless, he puts those who
				suffered all extremities rather than lose their honesty in
				the same rank with those who most affectionately sided
				with the Persians. And when he could not blame the
				Phocians' actions, he sat at his desk devising false causes
				and framing suspicions against them, and bidding us judge
				them not by what they did, but by what they would have
				done if the Thessalians had not taken the same side, as if
				they had been shut out from treason because they found
				the place already occupied by others! Now if any one,
				going about to excuse the revolt of the Thessalians to the
				Persians, should say that they would not have done it but
				for the hatred they bare the Phocians,&mdash;whom when they
				saw joined to the Greeks, they against their inclinations
				followed the party of the Persians,&mdash;would not such a one
				be thought most shamefully to flatter, and for the sake of
				others to pervert the truth, by feigning good causes for
				evil actions? Indeed, I think, he would. Why then
				would not he be thought openly to calumniate, who says
				that the Phocians chose the best, not for the love of virtue,
				but because they saw the Thessalians on the contrary side?
				For neither does he refer this device to other authors, as
				he is elsewhere wont to do, but says that himself found it
				out by conjecture. He should therefore have produced
				certain arguments, by which he was persuaded that they,
				who did things like the best, followed the same counsels
				with the worst. For what he alleges of their enmities is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.360"/>
				
				ridiculous. For neither did the difference between the
				Aeginetans and the Athenians, nor that between the Chalcidians and the Eretrians, nor yet that between the Corinthians and the Megarians, hinder them from fighting
				together for Greece. Nor did the Macedonians, their most
				bitter enemies, divert the Thessalians from their friendship
				with the barbarians, by joining the Persian party themselves. For the common danger did so bury their private
				grudges, that banishing their other passions, they applied
				their minds either to honesty for the sake of virtue, or to
				profit through the impulse of necessity. And indeed, after
				that necessity which compelled them to obey the Persians
				was over, they returned again to the Greeks, as Lacrates
				the Spartan has openly testified of them. And Herodotus,
				as constrained to it, in his relation of the affairs at Plataea,
				confessed that the Phocians took part with the Greeks.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 31.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>Neither ought it to seem strange to any, if he thus
				bitterly inveighs against the unfortunate; since he reckons
				amongst enemies and traitors those who were present at
				the engagement, and together with the other Greeks hazarded their safety. For the Naxians, says he, sent three
				ships to the assistance of the barbarians; but Democritus,
				one of their captains, persuaded the others to take the
				party of the Greeks.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 46.</note> So unable he is to praise without
				dispraising, that if he commends one man he must condemn a whole city or people. But in this there give testimony against him, of the more ancient writers Hellanicus,
				and of the later Ephorus, one of which says that the
				Naxians came with six ships to aid the Greeks, and the
				other with five. And Herodotus convinces himself of
				having feigned these things. For the writers of the
				Naxian annals say, that they had before beaten back
				Megabates, who came to their island with two hundred
				ships, and after that had put to flight the general Datis,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.361"/>
				
				who had set their city on fire. Now if, as Herodotus has
				elsewhere said, the barbarians burned their city so that
				the men were glad to save themselves by flying into the
				mountains, most surely had they just cause rather to send
				aid to the destroyers of their country than to help the
				protectors of the common liberty. But that he framed
				this lie not so much to honor Democritus, as to cast infamy
				on the Naxians, is manifest from his omitting and wholly
				passing over in silence the valiant acts then performed by
				Democritus, of which Simonides gives us an account in
				this epigram:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When as the Greeks at sea the Medes did meet,
				</l>
                     <l>And had near Salamis a naval fight,
				</l>
                     <l>Democritus as third led up the fleet,
				</l>
                     <l>Charging the enemy with all his might;
				</l>
                     <l>He took five of their ships, and did another,
				</l>
                     <l>Which they had taken from the Greeks, recover.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>But why should any one be angry with him about
				the Naxians? If we have, as some say, antipodes inhabiting the other hemisphere, I believe that they also have
				heard of Themistocles and his counsel, which he gave to
				the Greeks, to fight a naval battle before Salamis, after
				which, the barbarian being overcome, he built in Melite a
				temple to Diana the Counsellor. This gentle writer, endeavoring, as much as in him lies, to deprive Themistocles
				of the glory of this, and transfer it to another, writes thus
				word for word: <q direct="unspecified">Whilst things were thus, Mnesiphilus,
					an Athenian, asked Themistocles, as he was going aboard
					his ship, what had been resolved on in council. And being
					answered, that it was decreed the ships should be brought
					back to Isthmus, and a battle fought at sea before Peloponnesus; he said, If then they remove the navy from Salamis,
					you will no longer be fighting for one country; for they
					will return every one to his own city. Wherefore, if there
					be any way left, go and endeavor to break this resolution;
					and, if it be possible, persuade Eurybiades to change his
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.362"/>
					
					mind and stay here.</q> Then adding that this advice pleased
				Themistocles, who, without making any reply, went straight
				to Eurybiades, he has these very expressions: <q direct="unspecified">And sitting
					by him he related what he had heard from Mnesiphilus,
					feigning as if it came from himself, and adding other
					things.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 57, 58.</note> You see how he accuses Themistocles of disingenuity in arrogating to himself the counsel of Mnesiphilus.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>And deriding the Greeks still further, he says, that
				Themistocles, who was called another Ulysses for his wisdom, was so blind that he could not foresee what was fit
				to be done; but that Artemisia, who was of the same city
				with Herodotus, without being taught by any one, but by
				her own consideration, said thus to Xerxes: <q direct="unspecified">The Greeks
					will not long be able to hold out against you, but you will
					scatter them, and they will flee to their own cities; nor is
					it probable, if you march your army by land to Peloponnesus, that they will sit still, or take care to fight at sea
					for the Athenians. But if you make haste to give them a
					naval battle, I fear lest your fleets receiving damage may
					prove also very prejudicial to your land-forces.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 68.</note> Certainly Herodotus wanted nothing but verses to make Artemisia another Sibyl, so exactly prophesying of things to
				come. Therefore Xerxes also delivered his sons to her to
				be carried to Ephesus; for he had (it seems) forgot
				to bring women with him from Susa, if indeed the boys
				wanted a train of female attendants.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>But it is not our design to search into the lies of
				Herodotus; we only make enquiry into those which he
				invented to detract from the glory of others. He says: <q direct="unspecified">It
					is reported by the Athenians that Adimantus, captain of the
					Corinthians, when the enemies were now ready to join
					battle, was struck with such fear and astonishment that he
					fled; not thrusting his ship backward by the stern, or leisurely
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.363"/>
					
					 retreating through those that were engaged, but
					openly hoisting up his sails, and turning the heads of all
					his vessels. And about the farther part of the Salaminian
					coast, he was met by a pinnace, out of which one spake
					thus to him: Thou indeed, Adimantus, fliest, having betrayed the Grecians; yet they overcome, and according to
					their desires have the better of their enemies.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 94.</note> This
				pinnace was certainly let down from heaven. For what
				should hinder him from erecting a tragical machine, who
				by his boasting excelled the tragedians in all other things?
				Adimantus then crediting him (he adds) <q direct="unspecified">returned to the
					fleet, when the business was already done.</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">This report,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">is believed by the Athenians; but the Corinthians deny it, and say, they were the first at the sea-fight,
						for which they have the testimony of all the other Greeks.</q>
				Such is this man in many other places. He spreads different calumnies and accusations of different men, that he
				may not fail of making some one appear altogether wicked.
				And it has succeeded well with him in this place; for if
				the calumny is believed, the Corinthians&mdash;if it is not, the
				Athenians&mdash;are rendered infamous. But in truth the Athenians did not belie the Corinthians, but he hath belied them
				both. Certainly Thucydides, bringing in an Athenian ambassador contesting with a Corinthian at Sparta, and gloriously boasting of many things about the Persian war and
				the sea-fight at Salamis, charges not the Corinthians with
				any crime of treachery or leaving their station. Nor was
				it likely the Athenians should object any such thing against
				Corinth, when they saw her engraven in the third place
				after the Lacedaemonians and themselves on those spoils
				which, being taken from the barbarians, were consecrated
				to the Gods. And in Salamis they had permitted them to
				bury the dead near the city, as being men who had behaved
				themselves gallantly, and to write over them this elegy:
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.364"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Well-watered Corinth, stranger, was our home;
				</l>
                     <l>Salamis, Ajax's isle, is now our grave;
				</l>
                     <l>Here Medes and Persians and Phoenician ships
				</l>
                     <l>We fought and routed, sacred Greece to save.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And their honorary sepulchre at the Isthmus has on it this
					epitaph:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Greece upon the point of danger stood,
					</l>
                     <l>We fell, defending her with our life-blood.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The versions of this epigram and of the last two in this chapter are taken from Burges's Greek Anthology. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, on the offerings of Diodorus, one of the Corinthian sea-captains, reserved in the temple of Latona, there
					is this inscription:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Diodorus's seamen to Latona sent
					</l>
                     <l>These arms, of hostile Medes the monument.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And as for Adimantus himself, against whom Herodotus
					frequently inveighs,&mdash;saying, that he was the only captain
					who went about to fly from Artemisium, and would not
					stay the fight,&mdash;behold in how great honor he is:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here Adimantus rests: the same was he,
					</l>
                     <l>Whose counsels won for Greece the crown of liberty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For neither is it probable, that such honor would have been
					shown to a coward and a traitor after his decease; nor
					would he have dared to give his daughters the names of
					Nausinica, Acrothinius, and Alexibia, and his son that of
					Aristeas, if he had not performed some illustrious and
					memorable action in that fight. Nor is it credible that
					Herodotus was ignorant of that which could not be unknown even to the meanest Carian, that the Corinthian
					women alone made that glorious and divine prayer, by
					which they besought the Goddess Venus to inspire their
					husbands with a love of fighting against the barbarians.
					For it was a thing divulged abroad, concerning which Simonides made an epigram to be inscribed on the brazen
					image set up in that temple of Venus which is said to have
					been founded by Medea, when she desired the Goddess, as
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.365"/>
					
					some affirm, to deliver her from loving her husband Jason,
					or, as others say, to free him from loving Thetis. The
					tenor of the epigram follows:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For those who, fighting on their country's side,
					</l>
                     <l>Opposed th' imperial Mede's advancing tide,
					</l>
                     <l>We, votaresses, to Cythera pray'd;
					</l>
                     <l>Th' indulgent power vouchsafed her timely aid,
					</l>
                     <l>And kept the citadel of Hellas free
					</l>
                     <l>From rude assaults of Persia's archery.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These things he should rather have written and recorded,
					than have inserted Aminocles's killing of his son.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>After he had abundantly satisfied himself with the
				accusations brought against Themistocles,&mdash;of whom he
				says that, unknown to the other captains, he incessantly
				robbed and spoiled the islands,&mdash;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 112.</note> he at length openly
				takes away the crown of victory from the Athenians, and
				sets it on the head of the Aeginetans, writing thus: <q direct="unspecified">The
					Greeks having sent the first-fruits of their spoils to Delphi,
					asked in general of the God, whether he had a sufficient
					part of the booty and were contented with it. He answered,
					that he had enough of all the other Greeks, but not of the
					Aeginetans; for he expected a donary of them, as having
					won the greatest honor in the battle at Salamis.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 122.</note> See
				here how he attributes not his fictions to the Scythians, to
				the Persians, or to the Egyptians, as Aesop did his to the
				ravens and apes; but using the very person of the Pythian Apollo, he takes from Athens the chief honor of the
				battle at Salamis. And the second place in honor being
				given to Themistocles at the Isthmus by all the other captains,&mdash;every one of which attributed to himself the first
				degree of valor, but gave the next to Themistocles,&mdash;and
				the judgment not coming to a determination, when he
				should have reprehended the ambition of the captains, he
				said, that all the Greeks weighed anchor from thence
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.366"/>
				
				through envy, not being willing to give the chief honor of
				the victory to Themistocles.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VIII. 123, 124.</note>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>In his ninth and last book, having nothing left to
				vent his malice on but the Lacedaemonians and their glorious action against the barbarians at Plataea, he writes,
				that the Spartans at first feared lest the Athenians should
				suffer themselves to be persuaded by Mardonius to forsake
				the other Greeks; but that now, the Isthmus being fortified,
				they, supposing all to be safe at Peloponnesus, neglected
				and slighted the rest, feasting and making merry at home,
				and deluding and delaying the Athenian ambassadors.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 8. See also VIII. 141.</note>
				How then did there go forth from Sparta to Plataea a thousand and five men, having every one of them with him
				seven Helots? Or how came it that, exposing themselves
				to so many dangers, they vanquished and overthrew so
				many thousand barbarians? Hear now his probable cause
				of it. <q direct="unspecified">It happened,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">that there was then at
					Sparta a certain stranger of Tegea, named Chileus, who
					had some friends amongst the Ephori, between whom and
					him there was mutual hospitality. He then persuaded
					them to send forth the army, telling them that the fortification on the Isthmus, by which they had fenced in Peloponnesus, would be of no avail if the Athenians joined
					themselves with Mardonius.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 9.</note> This counsel then drew
				Pausanias with his army to Plataea; but if any private
				business had kept that Chileus at Tegea, Greece had never
				been victorious.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>Again, not knowing what to do with the Athenians,
				he tosses to and fro that city, sometimes extolling it, and
				sometimes debasing it. He says that, contending for the
				second place with the Tegeatans they made mention of the
				Heraclidae, alleged their acts against the Amazons, and
				the sepulchres of the Peloponnesians that died under the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.367"/>
				
				walls of Cadmea, and at last ambitiously brought down
				their discourse to the battle of Marathon, saying, however,
				that they would be contented with the command of the left
				wing.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 26, 27.</note> A little after, he says, Pausanias and the Spartans
				yielded them the first place, desiring them to fight in the
				right wing against the Persians and give them the left, who
				excused themselves as not skilled in fighting against the
				barbarians.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 46.</note> Now it is a ridiculous thing, to be unwilling
				to fight against an enemy unless one has been used to him.
				But he says farther, that the other Greeks being led by
				their captains to encamp in another place, as soon as they
				were moved, the horse fled with joy towards Plataea, and
				in their flight came as far as Juno's temple.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 52.</note> In which
				place indeed he charges them all in general with disobedience, cowardice, and treason. At last he says, that only
				the Lacedaemonians and the Tegeates fought with the
				barbarians, and the Athenians with the Thebans; equally
				defrauding all the other cities of their part in the honor of
				the victory, whilst he affirms that none of them joined in
				the fight, but that all of them, sitting still hard by in their
				arms, betrayed and forsook those who fought for them;
				that the Phliasians and Megarians indeed, when they heard
				Pausanias had got the better, came in late, and falling on
				the Theban horse, were all cut off; that the Corinthians
				were not at the battle, and that after the victory, by pressing on over the hills, they escaped the Theban cavalry.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the account of the battle of Plataea, Herod. IX. 59-70.</note>
				For the Thebans, after the barbarians were overthrown,
				going before with their horse, affectionately assisted them
				in their flight; to return them thanks (forsooth) for the
				marks they had stigmatized them with at Thermopylae!
				Now what rank the Corinthians had in the fight at Plataea
				against the barbarians, and how they performed their duty,
				you may hear from Simonides in these verses:
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.368"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I' th' midst were men, in warlike feats excelling
				</l>
                     <l>Who Ephyre, full of springs, inhabited,
				</l>
                     <l>And who in Corinth, Glaucus' city, dwelling,
				</l>
                     <l>Great praise by their great valor merited;
				</l>
                     <l>Of which they to perpetuate the fame,
				</l>
                     <l>To th' Gods of well-wrought gold did offerings frame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For he wrote not these things, as one that taught at
					Corinth or that made verses in honor of the city, but
					only as recording these actions in elegiac verses. But
					Herodotus, whilst he desires to prevent that objection by
					which those might convince him of lying who should ask,
					Whence then are so many mounts, tombs, and monuments
					of the dead, at which the Plataeans, even to this day, celebrate funeral solemnities in the presence of the Greeks?&mdash;has charged, unless I am mistaken, a fouler crime than
					that of treason on their posterity. For these are his
					words: <q direct="unspecified">As for the other sepulchres that are seen in
						Plataea, I have heard that their successors, being ashamed
						of their progenitors' absence from this battle, erected
						every man a monument for posterity's sake.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. IX. 85.</note> Of this
					treacherous deserting the battle Herodotus was the only
					man that ever heard. For if any Greeks withdrew them
					selves from the battle, they must have deceived Pausanias,
					Aristides, the Lacedaemonians, and the Athenians. Neither
					yet did the Athenians exclude the Aeginetans who were
					their adversaries from the inscription, nor convince the
					Corinthians of having fled from Salamis before the victory,
					Greece bearing witness to the contrary. Indeed Cleadas, a
					Plataean, ten years after the Persian war, to gratify, as
					Herodotus says, the Aeginetans, erected a mount bearing
					their name. How came it then to pass that the Athenians
					and Lacedaemonians, who were so jealous of each other
					that they were presently after the war ready to go together by the ears about the setting up a trophy, did not
					yet repel those Greeks who fled in a fear from the battle
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.369"/>
					
					from having a share in the honor of those that behaved
					themselves valiantly, but inscribed their names on the
					trophies and colossuses, and granted them part of the
					spoils? Lastly they set up an altar, on which was engraven this epigram:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Greeks, by valor having put to flight
					</l>
                     <l>The Persians and preserved their country's right,
					</l>
                     <l>Erected here this altar which you see,
					</l>
                     <l>To Jove, preserver of their liberty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Did Cleadas, 0 Herodotus, or some other, write this also,
					to oblige the cities by flattery? What need had they then
					to employ fruitless labor in digging up the earth, to make
					tombs and erect monuments for posterity's sake, when they
					saw their glory consecrated in the most illustrious and
					greatest donaries? Pausanias indeed, when he was aspiring
					to the tyranny, set up this inscription in Delphi:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pausanias, of Greeks the general,
					</l>
                     <l>When he the Medes in fight had overthrown,
					</l>
                     <l>Offered to Phoebus a memorial
					</l>
                     <l>Of victory, this monumental stone.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In which he gave the glory to the Greeks, whose general
					he professed himself to be. Yet the Greeks not enduring
					but utterly misliking it, the Lacedaemonians, sending to
					Delphi, caused this to be cut out, and the names of the
					cities, as it was fit, to be engraven instead of it. Now how
					is it possible that the Greeks should have been offended
					that there was no mention made of them in the inscription,
					if they had been conscious to themselves of deserting the
					fight? or that the Lacedaemonians would have erased the
					name of their leader and general, to insert deserters and
					such as withdrew themselves from the common danger?
					For it would have been a great indignity, that Sophanes,
					Aeimnestus, and all the rest who showed their valor in that
					fight, should calmly suffer even the Cythnians and Melians
					to be inscribed on the trophies; and that Herodotus, attributing that fight only to three cities, should raze all
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.370"/>
					
					the rest out of those and other sacred monuments and
					donaries.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>There having been then four fights with the barbarians; he says, that the Greeks fled from Artemisium;
				that, whilst their king and general exposed himself to
				danger at Thermopylae, the Lacedaemonians sat negligent
				at home, celebrating the Olympian and Carnean feasts;
				and discoursing of the action at Salamis, he uses more
				words about Artemisia than he does in his whole narrative
				of the naval battle. Lastly, he says, that the Greeks sat
				still at Plataea, knowing no more of the fight, till it was
				over, than if it had been a skirmish between mice and
				frogs (like that which Pigres, Artemisia's fellow-countryman, merrily and scoffingly described in his poem), and it
				had been agreed to fight silently, lest they should be heard
				by others; and that the Lacedaemonians excelled not the
				barbarians in valor, but only got the better, as fighting
				against naked and unarmed men. To wit, when Xerxes
				himself was present, the barbarians were with much difficulty compelled by scourges to fight with the Greeks; but
				at Plataea, having taken other resolutions, as Herodotus
				says, <q direct="unspecified">they were no way inferior in courage and strength;
					but their garments being without armor was prejudicial to
					them, since being naked they fought against a completely
					armed enemy.</q> What then is there left great and memorable to the Grecians of those fights, if the Lacedaemonians
				fought with unarmed men, and the other Greeks, though
				present, were ignorant of the battle; if empty monuments
				are set up everywhere, and tripods and altars full of lying
				inscriptions are placed before the Gods; if, lastly, Herodotus only knows the truth, and all others that give any account of the Greeks have been deceived by the fame of
				those glorious actions, as the effect of an admirable prowess? But he is an acute writer, his style is pleasant, there
				is a certain grace, force, and elegancy in his narrations;
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.371"/>
				
				and he has, like a musician, pronounced his discourse,
				though not knowingly, still clearly and elegantly. These
				things delight, please, and affect all men. But as in roses
				we must beware of the venomous flies called cantharides;
				so must we take heed of the calumnies and envy lying hid
				under smooth and well-couched phrases and expressions,
				lest we imprudently entertain absurd and false opinions
				of the most excellent and greatest cities and men of
				Greece.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>