<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De Stoicorum repugnantiis</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.136">
      <body>
         <head>The contradictions of the Stoics.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.428"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>I first lay this down for an axiom, that there ought
				to be seen in men's lives an agreement with their doctrines.
				For it is not so necessary that the pleader (as Aeschines
				has it) and the law speak one and the same thing, as that
				the life of a philosopher be consonant to his speech. For
				the speech of a philosopher is a law of his own and voluntarily imposed on himself, unless they esteem philosophy
				to be a game, or an acuteness in disputing invented for the
				gaining of applause, and not&mdash;what it really is&mdash;a thing
				deserving our greatest study.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Since then there are in their discourses many things
				written by Zeno himself, many by Cleanthes, and most of
				all by Chrysippus, concerning policy, governing, and being
				governed, concerning judging and pleading, and yet there
				is not to be found in any of their lives either leading of
				armies, making of laws, going to parliament, pleading before the judges, fighting for their country, travelling on
				embassies, or bestowing of public gifts, but they have all,
				feeding (if I may so say) on rest as on the lotus, led their
				whole lives, and those not short but very long ones, in
				foreign countries, amongst disputations, books, and walkings; it is manifest that they have lived rather according
				to the writings and sayings of others than their own professions, having spent all their days in that repose which
				Epicurus and Hieronymus so much commend.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.429"/>
            <p>Chrysippus indeed himself, in his Fourth Book of Lives,
					thinks there is no difference between a scholastic life and
					a voluptuous one. I will set down here his very words:
					<q direct="unspecified">They who are of opinion that a scholastic life is from
						the very beginning most suitable to philosophers seem to
						me to be in an error, thinking that men ought to follow
						this for the sake of some recreation or some other thing
						like to it, and in that manner to spin out the whole course
						of their life; that is, if it may be explained, to live at
						ease. For this opinion of theirs is not to be concealed,
						many of them delivering it clearly, and not a few more
						obscurely.</q> Who therefore did more grow old in this
					scholastic life than Chrysippus, Cleanthes, Diogenes, Zeno,
					and Antipater, who left their countries not out of any discontent, but that they might quietly enjoy their delight,
					studying, and disputing at their leisure. To verify which,
					Aristocreon, the disciple and intimate friend of Chrysippus,
					having erected his statue of brass upon a pillar, engraved
					on it these verses:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This brazen statue Aristocreon
					</l>
                     <l>To's friend Chrysippus newly here has put,
					</l>
                     <l>Whose sharp-edged wit, like sword of champion,
					</l>
                     <l>Did Academic knots in sunder cut.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Such a one then was Chrysippus, an old man, a philosopher, one who praised the regal and civil life, and thought
					there was no difference between a scholastic and voluptuous one.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>But those others of them who intermeddle in state
				affairs act yet more contradictorily to their own doctrines.
				For they govern, judge, consult, make laws, punish, and
				honor, as if those were indeed cities in the government of
				which they concern themselves, those truly counsellors and
				judges who are at any time allotted to such offices, those
				generals who are chosen by suffrages, and those laws which
				were made by Clisthenes, Lycurgus, and Solon, whom they
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.430"/>
				
				affirm to have been vicious men and fools. Thus even in
				the management of state affairs are they at war with themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Indeed Antipater, in his writings concerning the
				difference between Cleanthes and Chrysippus, has related
				that Zeno and Cleanthes would not be made citizens of
				Athens, lest they might seem to injure their own countries.
				I shall not much insist upon it, that, if they did well,
				Chrysippus acted amiss in suffering himself to be enrolled
				as a member of that city. But this is very contradictory
				and absurd, that, removing their persons and their lives so
				far off amongst strangers, they reserved their names for
				their countries; which is the same thing as if a man,
				leaving his wife, and cohabiting and bedding with another,
				and getting children on her, should yet refuse to contract
				marriage with the second, lest he might seem to wrong the
				former.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Again, Chrysippus, writing in his treatise of Rhetoric,
				that a wise man will so plead and so act in the management
				of a commonwealth, as if riches, glory, and health were
				really good, confesses that his speeches are inextricable
				and impolitic, and his doctrines unsuitable for the uses and
				actions of human life.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>It is moreover a doctrine of Zeno's, that temples are
				not to be built to the Gods; for that a temple is neither a
				thing of much value nor holy; since no work of carpenters
				and handicrafts-men can be of much value. And yet they
				who praise these things as well and wisely said are initiated
				in the sacred mysteries, go up to the Citadel (where Minerva's temple stands), adore the shrines, and adorn with
				garlands the sacraries, being the works of carpenters and
				mechanical persons. Again, they think that the Epicureans, who sacrifice to the Gods and yet deny them to
				meddle with the government of the world, do thereby refute themselves; whereas they themselves are more contrary
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.431"/>
				
				 to themselves, sacrificing on altars and in temples,
				which they affirm ought not to stand nor to have been
				built.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Moreover, Zeno admits (as Plato does) several virtues
				with various distinctions&mdash;to wit, prudence, fortitude,
				temperance and justice&mdash;as being indeed inseparable,
				but yet divers and different from one another. But again,
				defining every one of them, he says that fortitude is prudence in executing, justice prudence in distributing, as
				being one and the same virtue, but seeming to differ in its
				relation to various affairs when it comes to action. Nor
				does Zeno alone seem to contradict himself in these matters; but Chrysippus also, who blames Ariston for saying
				that the other virtues are different habits of one and the
				same virtue, and yet defends Zeno, who in this manner
				defines every one of the virtues. And Cleanthes, having
				in his Commentaries concerning Nature said, that vigor is
				the striking of fire, which, if it is sufficient in the soul to
				perform the duties presented to it, is called force and
				strength; subjoins these very words: <q direct="unspecified">Now this force and
					strength, when it is in things apparent and to be persisted
					in, is continence; when in things to be endured, it is fortitude; when about worthiness, it is justice; and when
					about choosing or refusing, it is temperance.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Against him, who said,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Give not thy judgment till both sides are heard,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">In the Pseudo-Phocylidea, vs. 87 (Bergk).</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Zeno on the contrary made use of such an argument as
					this: <q direct="unspecified">If he who spake first has plainly proved his cause,
						the second is not to be heard, for the question is at an end;
						and if he has not proved it, it is the same case as if being
						cited he did not appear, or appearing did nothing but
						wrangle; so that, whether he has proved or not proved his
						cause, the second is not to be heard.</q> And yet he who
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.432"/>
					
					made this dilemma has written against Plato's Commonweal, dissolved sophisms, and exhorted his scholars to
					learn logic, as enabling them to do the same. Now Plato
					has either proved or not proved those things which he writ
					in his Commonweal; but in neither case was it necessary
					to write against him, but wholly superfluous and vain.
					The same may be said concerning sophisms.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Chrysippus is of opinion, that young students should
				first learn logic, secondly, ethics, and after these, physics,
				and likewise in this to meddle last of all with the disputes
				concerning the Gods. Now these things having been often
				said by him, it will suffice to set down what is found in his
				Fourth Book of Lives, being thus word for word: <q direct="unspecified">First
					then, it seems to me, according as it has been rightly said
					by the ancients, that there are three kinds of philosophical
					speculations, logical, ethical, and physical, and that of these,
					the logical ought to be placed first, the ethical second, and
					the physical third, and that of the physical, the discourse
					concerning the Gods ought to be the last; wherefore also
					the traditions concerning this have been styled <foreign lang="greek">*teletai/</foreign>, or the
					<hi rend="italics">Endings.</hi>
               </q> But that very discourse concerning the Gods,
				which he says ought to be placed the last, he usually places
				first and sets before every moral question. For he is seen
				not to say any thing either concerning the ends, or concerning justice, or concerning good and evil, or concerning
				marriage and the education of children, or concerning the
				law and the commonwealth; but, as those who propose
				decrees to states set before them the words To Good
				Fortune, so he also premises something of Jupiter, Fate,
				Providence, and of the world's being one and finite and
				maintained by one power. None of which any one can
				be persuaded to believe, who has not penetrated deeply
				into the discourses of natural philosophy. Hear what he
				says of this in his Third Book of the Gods: <q direct="unspecified">For there is
					not to be found any other beginning or any other generation
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.433"/>
					
					 of Justice, but what is from Jupiter and common
					Nature. From thence must every such thing have its beginning, if we will say any thing concerning good and evil.</q>
				And again, in his Natural Positions he says: <q direct="unspecified">For one
					cannot otherwise or more properly come to the discourse
					of good and evil, to the virtues, or to felicity, than from
					common Nature and the administration of the world.</q> And
				going farther on, he adds: <q direct="unspecified">For to these we must annex
					the discourse concerning good and evil, there being no
					other better beginning or relation thereof, and the speculation of Nature being learned for nothing else, but to understand the difference between good and evil.</q> According
				to Chrysippus, therefore, the natural science is both before
				and after the moral; or rather, it is an inversion of order
				altogether absurd, if this must be put after those things
				none of which can be comprehended without this; and his
				contradicting himself is manifest, when he asserts the discourse of Nature to be the beginning of that concerning
				good and evil, and yet commands it to be delivered, not
				before, but after it.</p>
            <p>Now, if any one shall say that Chrysippus in his book
					concerning the Use of Speech has written, that he who
					applies himself to logic first needs not absolutely to abstain
					from the rest, but should take as much of them as shall
					fall in his way, he will indeed say the truth, but will withal
					confirm the fault. For he oppugns himself, one while
					commanding that the science concerning God should be
					taken last and for a conclusion, as being therefore also
					called <foreign lang="greek">*teleth/</foreign>, and again, another while saying that this is to
					be learned together with the very first. For order is at an
					end, if all things must be used at all times. But this is
					more, that having made the science concerning the Gods
					the beginning of that concerning good and evil, he bids not
					those who apply themselves to the ethics to begin with
					that; but learning these, to take of that also as it shall
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.434"/>
					
					come in their way, and then to go from these to that, without which, he says, there is no beginning or entrance upon
					these.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>As for disputing on both sides, he says, that he does
				not universally reject it, but exhorts us to use it with caution, as is done in pleadings, not with a design really to
				disprove, but to dissolve their probability. <q direct="unspecified">For to those,</q>
				says he, <q direct="unspecified">who endeavor a suspension of assent concerning
					all things, it is convenient to do this, and it co-operates to
					what they desire; but as for those who would work and
					establish in us a certain science according to which we
					shall professedly live, they ought, on the contrary, to state
					the first principles, and to direct their novices who are entered from the beginning to the end; and where there is
					occasion to make mention of contrary discourses, to dissolve
					their probability, as is done in pleadings.</q> For this he
				hath said in express words. Now that it is absurd for philosophers to think that they ought to set down the contrary
				opinion, not with all its reasons, but like pleaders, disabling
				it, as if they contended not for truth but victory, we have
				elsewhere spoken against him. But that he himself has,
				not here and there in his disputations, but frequently, confirmed the discourses which are contrary to his own opinions,&mdash;and that stoutly, and with so much earnestness and
				contention that it was not for every one to understand what
				he liked,&mdash;the Stoics themselves affirm, who admire the
				man's acuteness, and think that Carneades said nothing of
				his own, but that catching hold of those arguments which
				Chrysippus alleged for the contrary opinion, he assaulted
				with them his positions, and often cried out,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Wretch, thy own strength will thee undo,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VI. 407.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if Chrysippus had given great advantages against himself to those who would disturb and calumniate his doctrines.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.435"/>
            <p>But of those things which he has written against custom
					they are so proud and boasting, that they fear not to affirm,
					that all the sayings of all the Academics together, if they
					were collected into one body, are not comparable to what
					Chrysippus has writ in disparagement of the senses. Which
					is an evident sign of the ignorance or self-love of the
					speakers; but this indeed is true, that being afterwards
					desirous to defend custom and the senses, he was inferior
					to himself, and the latter treatise was much weaker than
					the former. So that he contradicts himself; for having
					always directed the proposing of an adversary's opinions
					not with approbation, but with a demonstration of their
					falsity, he has showed himself more acute in opposing than
					defending his own doctrines; and having admonished others
					to take heed of contrary arguments, as withdrawing comprehension, he has been more sedulous in framing such
					proofs as take away comprehension, than such as confirm
					it. And yet he plainly shows that he himself feared this,
					writing thus in his Fourth Book of Lives: <q direct="unspecified">Repugnant
						arguments and probabilities on the contrary side are not
						rashly to be proposed, but with caution, lest the hearers
						distracted by them should let go their conceptions, not being able sufficiently to apprehend the solutions, but. so
						weakly that their comprehensions may easily be shaken.
						For even those who have, according to custom, preconceived
						both sensible objects and other things depending on the
						senses quickly forego them, being distracted by Megarian
						interrogatories and by others more numerous and forcible.</q>
					I would willingly therefore ask the Stoics, whether they
					think these Megarian interrogatories to be more forcible
					than those which Chrysippus has written in six books
					against custom; or rather this should be asked of Chrysippus himself. For observe what he has written about
					the Megarian reason, in his book concerning the Use of
					Speech, thus: <q direct="unspecified">Some such things fell out in the discourse
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.436"/>
						
						of Stilpo and Menedemus; for, whereas they were renowned
						for wisdom, their disputing has turned to their reproach,
						their arguments being part clumsy, and the rest violently
						sophistical.</q> And yet, good sir, you fear lest those arguments which you deride and term the disgrace of their
					proposers, as having a manifest faultiness, should divert
					some from comprehension. And did not you yourself,
					writing so many books against custom, in which you have
					added whatever you could invent, ambitiously striving to
					exceed Arcesilaus, expect that you should perplex some of
					your readers? For neither does he use slender arguments
					against custom; but as if he were pleading, he with some
					passion in himself stirs up the affections of others, telling
					his opponent that he talks foolishly and labors in vain.
					And that he may leave no room to deny his speaking of
					contradictions, he has in his Natural Positions written thus:
					<q direct="unspecified">It may be lawful for those who comprehend a thing to
						argue on the contrary side, applying to it that defence
						which the matter itself affords; and sometimes, when they
						comprehend neither, to discourse what is alleged for either.</q>
					And having said in his book concerning the Use of Speech,
					that we ought no more to use the force of reason than of
					arms for such things as are not fitting, he subjoins this:
					<q direct="unspecified">For they are to be employed for the finding out of truths
						and for the alliance of them, and not for the contrary,
						though many men do it.</q> By <q direct="unspecified">many</q> perhaps he means
					those who withhold their assent. But these philosophers,
					comprehending neither, argue on both sides, believing that,
					if any thing is comprehensible, thus only or chiefly does
					truth afford a comprehension of itself. But you, who accuse them, and do yourself write contrary to those things
					which you comprehend concerning custom, and exhort
					others with assurance to do the same, confess that you
					wantonly use the faculty of disputing, out of vain ambition,
					even on unprofitable and hurtful things.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.437"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>They say, that a good deed is the command, and sin
				the prohibition of the law; and therefore that the law
				forbids the wicked many things, but commands them nothing, because they cannot do a good deed. But who is
				ignorant that he who cannot do a good deed cannot also
				sin? Therefore they make the law to contradict itself,
				commanding men those things which they cannot perform,
				and forbidding them those things from which they cannot
				abstain. For a man who cannot be temperate cannot but
				act intemperately; and he who cannot be wise cannot but
				act foolishly. And they themselves affirm, that those who
				forbid say one thing, forbid another, and command another.
				For he who says <q direct="unspecified">Thou shalt not steal</q> at the same time
				that he says these words, <q direct="unspecified">Thou shalt not steal,</q> forbids also
				to steal, and commands not to steal. The law therefore
				forbids the wicked nothing, unless it also commands them
				something. And they say, that the physician bids his disciple to cut and cauterize, omitting to add these words,
				<q direct="unspecified">seasonably and moderately;</q> and the musician commands
				his scholar to play on the harp and sing, omitting <q direct="unspecified">tunably</q> and <q direct="unspecified">keeping time.</q> Wherefore also they punish
				those who do these things unskilfully and faultily; for
				that they were commanded to do them well, and they have
				done them ill. If therefore a wise man commands his
				servant to say or do something, and punishes him for doing
				it unseasonably or not as he ought, is it not manifest that
				he commanded him to do a good action and not an indifferent one? But if wise men command wicked ones indifferent things, what hinders but the commands of the
				law may be also such? Moreover, the impulse (called
				<foreign lang="greek">o(rmh/</foreign>) is according to him, the reason of a man commanding him to do something, as he has written in his book of
				the law. Is not therefore also the aversion (called <foreign lang="greek">'aformh/</foreign>)
				a prohibiting reason, and a disinclination a disinclination
				agreeable to reason? Caution therefore is also reason
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.438"/>
				
				prohibiting a wise man; for to be cautious is proper only
				to the wise, and not to the wicked. If then the reason of
				a wise man is one thing and the law another, wise men
				have caution contrary to the law; but if the law is nothing
				else but the reason of a wise man, the law is found to forbid wise men the doing of those things of which they are
				cautious.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Chrysippus says, that nothing is profitable to the
				wicked, that the wicked have neither use nor need of any
				thing. Having said this in his First Book of Good Deeds,
				he says again, that both commodiousness and grace pertain
				to mean or indifferent things, none of which, according to
				them, is profitable. In the same place he affirms, that
				there is nothing proper, nothing convenient for a vicious
				man, in these words: <q direct="unspecified">On the same principle we declare
					that there is nothing foreign or strange to the good man,
					and nothing proper or rightfully belonging to the bad
					man, since the one is good and the other bad.</q> Why
				then does he break our heads, writing particularly in every
				one of his books, as well natural as moral, that as soon as
				we are born, we are appropriated to ourselves, our parts,
				and our offspring? And why in his First Book of Justice
				does he say that the very brutes, proportionably to the
				necessity of their young, are appropriated to them, except
				fishes, whose young are nourished by themselves? For
				neither have they sense who have nothing sensible, nor
				they appropriation who have nothing proper; for appropriation seems to be the sense and perception of what is
				proper.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>And this opinion is consequent to their principal
				ones. It is moreover manifest that Chrysippus, though he
				has also written many things to the contrary, lays this for
				a position, that there is not any vice greater or any sin
				more grievous than another, nor any virtue more excellent
				or any good deed better than another; so that he says in
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.439"/>
				
				his Third Book of Nature: <q direct="unspecified">As it well beseems Jupiter to
					glory in himself and his life, to magnify himself, and (if
					we may so say) to bear up his head, have an high conceit
					of himself, and speak big, for that he leads a life worthy
					of lofty speech; so the same things do not misbeseem all
					good men, since they are in nothing exceeded by Jupiter.</q>
				And yet himself, in his Third Book of Justice, says, that
				they who make pleasure the end destroy justice, but they
				who say it is only a good do not destroy it. These are his
				very words: <q direct="unspecified">For perhaps, if we leave this to pleasure,
					that it is a good but not the end, and that honesty is one
					of those things which are eligible for themselves, we may
					preserve justice, making the honest and the just a greater
					good than pleasure.</q> But if that only is good which is
				honest, he who affirms pleasure to be a good is in an error,
				but he errs less than he who makes it also the end; for
				the one destroys justice, the other preserves it; and by
				the one human society is overthrown, but the other leaves
				a place to goodness and humanity. Now I let pass his
				saying farther in his book concerning Jupiter, that the
				virtues increase and go on, lest I may seem to catch at
				words; though Chrysippus is indeed in this kind very
				sharp upon Plato and others. But when he forbids the
				praising of every thing that is done according to virtue, he
				shows that there is some difference between good deeds.
				Now he says thus in his book concerning Jupiter: <q direct="unspecified">For
					since each virtue has its own proper works, there are some
					of these that are more to be praised than others; for he
					would show himself to be very frigid, that should undertake to praise and extol any man for holding out the finger
					stoutly, for abstaining chastely from an old woman ready
					to drop into the grave, and patiently hearing it said that
					three are not exactly four.</q> What he says in his Third
				Book of the Gods is not unlike to this: <q direct="unspecified">For I moreover
					think that the praises of such things as to abstain from an
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.440"/>
					
					old woman who has one foot in the grave, and to endure
					the bite of a fly, though proceeding from virtue, would be
					very impertinent.</q> What other reprehender of his doctrines does this man then expect? For if he who praises
				such things is frigid, he who asserts every one of them to
				be a great&mdash;nay, a very great good deed&mdash;is much more
				frigid. For if to bear the bite of a fly is equal to the
				being valiant, and to abstain from an old trot now at the
				pit's brink is equal to the being temperate, there is, I
				think, no difference whether a virtuous man is prized for
				these or for those. Moreover, in his Second Book of
				Friendship, teaching that friendships are not for every
				fault to be dissolved, he has these very expressions: <q direct="unspecified">For
					it is meet that some faults should be wholly passed by,
					others lightly reprehended, others more severely, and others
					deemed worthy a total dissolution of friendship.</q> And
				which is more, he says in the same book, that we will
				converse with some more and some less, so that some shall
				be more and some less friends; and this diversity extending very far, some are worthy of such an amity, others of
				a greater; and these will deserve to be so far trusted,
				those not so far, and the like. For what else has he done
				in these places, but shown the great diversity there is between these things? Moreover, in his book concerning
				Honesty, to demonstrate that only to be good which is
				honest, he uses these words: <q direct="unspecified">What is good is eligible;
					what is eligible is acceptable; what is acceptable is laudable; and what is laudable is honest.</q> And again: <q direct="unspecified">What
						is good is joyous; what is joyous is venerable; what is
						venerable is honest.</q> But these speeches are repugnant
				to himself; for either all good is commendable, and then
				the abstaining chastely from an old woman is also commendable; or all good is neither venerable nor joyous,
				and his reason falls to the ground. For how can it
				possibly be frigid in others to praise any for such
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.441"/>
				
				things, and not ridiculous for him to rejoice and glory
				in them?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Such indeed he frequently is; but in his disputations
				against others he takes not the least care of speaking
				things contrary and dissonant to himself. For in his books
				of Exhorting, reprehending Plato, who said, that to him
				who has neither learned nor knows how to live it is profitable not to live, he speaks in this manner: <q direct="unspecified">For this
					speech is both repugnant to itself, and not at all persuasive.
					For first insinuating that it is best for us not to live, and in
					a sort counselling us to die, he will excite us rather to any
					thing else than to be philosophers; for neither can he who
					does not live philosophize, nor he who shall live long
					wickedly and ignorantly become wise.</q> And going on, he
				says that it is convenient for the wicked also to continue
				in life. And afterwards thus, word for word: <q direct="unspecified">First, as
					virtue, barely taken, has nothing towards our living, so
					neither has vice any thing to oblige us to depart.</q> Nor is
				it necessary to turn over other books, that we may show
				Chrysippus's contradictoriness to himself; but in these
				same, he sometimes with commendation brings forth this
				saying of Antisthenes, that either understanding or a
				halter is to be provided, as also that of Tyrtaeus,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Come nigh the bounds of virtue or of death.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now what else will this show, but that to wicked men
					and fools not to live is more profitable than to live? And
					sometimes correcting Theognis, he says, that the poet should
					not have written,
					<quote rend="blockquote">From poverty to fly;&mdash;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>but rather thus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>From wickedness to fly, into the deep
					</l>
                     <l>Throw thyself, Cyrnus, or from rocks so steep.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Theognis, vs. 175.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>What therefore else does he seem to do, but to set down
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.442"/>
					
					himself those things and doctrines which, when others
					<hi rend="italics">write</hi> them, he expunges; condemning, indeed, Plato for
					showing that not to live is better than to live viciously and
					ignorantly; and yet counselling Theognis to let a man
					break his neck or throw himself into the sea, that he may
					avoid vice? For having praised Antisthenes for directing
					fools to an halter, he again blames him, saying that vice
					has nothing that should oblige us to depart out of life.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Moreover, in his books against the same Plato, concerning Justice, he immediately at the very beginning leaps
				into a discourse touching the Gods, and says, that Cephalus
				did not rightly avert men from injustice by the fear of the
				Gods, and that his doctrine is easily misrepresented, and
				that it affords to the contrary many arguments and probabilities impugning the discourse concerning divine punishments, as nothing differing from the tales of Acco and
				Alphito (or Raw-Head and Bloody-Bones), with which
				women are wont to frighten little children from their unlucky pranks. Having thus traduced Plato, he in other
				places again praises him, and often alleges this saying of
				Euripides:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Howe'er you may deride it, there's a Jove,
				</l>
                     <l>With other Gods, who sees men's woes above.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And likewise, in his First Book of Justice citing these
					verses of Hesiod,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then Jove from heaven punishments did send,
					</l>
                     <l>And plague and famine brought them to their end,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Works and Days, 242.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he says, the Gods do these things, that the wicked being
					punished, others admonished by these examples may less
					dare to attempt the doing of such things.</p>
            <p>Again, in his book of Justice, subjoining, that it is possible for those who make pleasure a good but not the end
					to preserve also justice, he said in express terms: <q direct="unspecified">For
						perhaps if we leave this to pleasure, that it is a good but
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.443"/>
						
						not the end, and that honesty is one of those things which
						are eligible for themselves, we may preserve justice, making
						the honest and the just a greater good than pleasure.</q> So
					much he says in this place concerning pleasure. But in
					his book against Plato, accusing him for seeming to make
					health a good, he says, that not only justice, but also magnanimity, temperance, and all the other virtues will be
					taken away, if we make pleasure, health, or any thing else
					which is not honest, to be a good. What therefore is to be
					said for Plato, we have elsewhere written against him.
					But here his contradicting himself is manifest, when he
					says in one place, that if a man supposes that with honesty
					pleasure also is a good, justice is preserved, and in another, accuses those who make any thing besides honesty
					to be a good of taking away all the virtues. But that he
					may not leave any means of making an apology for his
					contradictions, writing against Aristotle concerning justice,
					he affirms him not to have spoken rightly when he said,
					that pleasure being made the end, justice is taken away,
					and together with justice, every one also of the other
					virtues. For justice (he says) will indeed be taken away;
					but there is nothing to hinder the other virtues from remaining and being, though not eligible for themselves, yet
					good and virtues. Then he reckons up every one of them
					by name. But it will be better to set down his own words.
					<q direct="unspecified">For pleasure,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">appearing according to this discourse to be made the end, yet all this seems not to me to
						be contained in it. Wherefore we must say, that neither
						any of the virtues is eligible nor any of the vices to be
						avoided for itself, but that all these things are to be referred to the proposed scope. Yet nothing, according to
						their opinion, will hinder but that fortitude, prudence, continence, and patience may be good, and their contraries to
						be avoided.</q> Has there ever then been any man more
					peevish in his disputes than he, who has blamed two of
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.444"/>
					
					the principal philosophers, the one for taking away all
					virtue, by not making that only to be good which is honest,
					and the other for not thinking all the virtues except justice
					to be preserved, though pleasure is made the end? For it
					is a wonderful licentiousness that, discoursing of the same
					matters, he should when accusing Plato take away again
					those very things which himself sets down when reprehending Aristotle. Moreover, in his demonstrations concerning justice, he says expressly, that every good deed is
					both a lawful action and a just operation; but that every
					thing which is done according to continence, patience, prudence, or fortitude is a good deed, and therefore also a just
					operation. Why then does he not also leave justice to
					them to whom he leaves prudence, fortitude, and continence; since whatever they do well according to the said
					virtue, they do also justly?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>Moreover, Plato having said, that injustice, as being
				the corruption and sedition of the soul, loses not its power
				even in those who have it within them, but sets the wicked
				man against himself, and molests and disturbs him; Chrysippus, blaming this, affirms that it is absurdly said, <q direct="unspecified">A
					man injures himself;</q> for that injustice is to another, and
				not to one's self. But forgetting this, he again says, in
				his demonstrations concerning justice, that the unjust man
				is injured by himself and injures himself when he injures
				another, becoming to himself the cause of transgressing,
				and undeservedly hurting himself. In his books indeed
				against Plato, contending that we cannot speak of injustice against one's self, but against another, he has these
				words: <q direct="unspecified">For men cannot be unjust by themselves; injustice requires several on opposite sides, speaking contrary
					one unto another. But no such thing extends to one
					alone, except inasmuch as he is affected towards his neighbor.</q> But in his demonstrations he has such discourses as
				these, concerning the unjust man's being injurious also to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.445"/>
				
				himself: <q direct="unspecified">The law forbids the being any way the author
					of transgression, and to act unjustly will be transgression.
					He therefore who is to himself the author of acting unjustly transgresses against himself. Now he that transgresses against any one also injures him; therefore he who
					is injurious to any one whomsoever is injurious also to
					himself.</q> Again: <q direct="unspecified">Sin is a hurt, and every one who
						sins sins against himself; every one therefore who sins
						hurts himself undeservedly, and if so, is also unjust to
						himself.</q> And farther thus: <q direct="unspecified">He who is hurt by another hurts himself, and that undeservedly. Now that is to
							be unjust. Every one therefore that is injured, by whomsoever it is, is unjust also to himself.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>He says, that the doctrine concerning good and
				evil which himself introduces and approves is most agreeable to life, and does most of all reach the inbred prenotions; for this he has affirmed in his Third Book of
				Exhortations. But in his First Book he says, that this
				doctrine takes a man off from all other things, as being
				nothing to us, nor co-operating any thing towards felicity.
				See now, how consonant he is to himself, when he asserts
				a doctrine which takes us off from life, health, indolence,
				and integrity of the senses, and says that those things we
				beg of the Gods are nothing to us, though most agreeable
				to life and to the common presumptions. But that there
				may be no denial of his speaking contradictions, in his
				Third Book of Justice he has said thus: <q direct="unspecified">Wherefore also,
					from the excellence of their greatness and beauty, we
					seem to speak things like to fictions, and not according to
					man or human nature.</q> Is it then possible that any one
				can more plainly confess his speaking things contrary to
				himself than this man does, who affirms those things which
				(he says) for their excellency seem to be fictions and to be
				spoken above man and human nature, to be agreeable to
				life, and most of all to reach the inbred prenotions?</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.446"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>In every one of his natural and ethical books, he
				asserts vice to be the very essence of unhappiness; writing and contending that to live viciously is the same thing
				as to live unhappily. But in his Third Book of Nature,
				having said that it is profitable for a fool to live rather
				than to die, though he is never to become wise, he subjoins: <q direct="unspecified">For such is the nature of good things among
					men, that evil things are in some sort preferred before indifferent ones.</q> I let pass therefore, that having elsewhere said that nothing is profitable to fools, he here says
				that to live foolishly is profitable to them. Now those
				things being by them called indifferent which are neither
				bad nor good, when he says that bad things precede them,
				he says nothing else but that evil things precede those
				that are not evil, and that to be unhappy is more profitable than not to be unhappy; and if so, he esteems not
				to be unhappy to be more unprofitable&mdash;and if more
				unprofitable, more hurtful&mdash;than to be unhappy. Desiring therefore to mitigate this absurdity, he adds concerning evils: <q direct="unspecified">But it is not these evils that are preferred,
					but reason; with which it is more convenient to live,
					though we shall be fools.</q> First therefore he says that
				vice and things participating of vice are evil, and that
				nothing else is so. Now vice is something reasonable, or
				rather depraved reason. For those therefore who are
				fools to live with reason, is nothing else but to live with
				vice. Thence to live being fools is to live being unhappy.
				In what then is this preferred to indifferent things? For
				he surely will not say that with regard to happiness unhappiness is to be preferred. But neither, say they, does
				Chrysippus altogether think that the remaining in life is
				to be reckoned amongst good things, or the going out of
				it amongst bad; but both of them amongst indifferent
				ones, according to Nature. Wherefore also it sometimes
				becomes meet for the happy to make themselves away,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.447"/>
				
				and again for the unhappy to continue in life. Now what
				greater repugnance can there be than this in the choice
				and avoiding of things, if it is convenient for those who
				are in the highest degree happy to forsake those good
				things that are present, for the want of some one indifferent thing? And yet they esteem none of the indifferent
				things either desirable or to be avoided; but only good desirable, and only evil to be avoided. So that it comes to
				pass, according to them, that the reasoning about actions
				regards neither things desirable nor things refusable; but
				that aiming at other things, which they neither shun nor
				choose, they make life and death dependent on these.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Chrysippus confesses that good things are totally
				different from bad; and it must of necessity be so, if these
				make them with whom they are present miserable to the
				very utmost point, and those render their possessors in the
				highest degree happy. Now he says, that good and evil
				things are sensible, writing thus in his First Book of the
				End: <q direct="unspecified">That good and evil things are perceptible by sense,
					we are by these reasons forced to say; for not only the
					passions, with their species, as sorrow, fear, and such
					others, are sensible; but we may also have a sense of
					theft, adultery, and the like, and generally, of folly, cowardice, and other vices not a few; and again, not only of
					joy, beneficence, and many other dependences on good
					deeds, but also of prudence, fortitude, and the other virtues.</q> Let us pass by the other absurdities of these things;
				but that they are repugnant to those things which are delivered by him concerning <q direct="unspecified">the wise man that knows
					nothing of his being so,</q> who does not confess? For good,
				when present, being sensible and having a great difference
				from evil, is it not most absurd, that he who is of bad become good should be ignorant of it, and not perceive virtue when present, but think that vice is still within him?
				For either none who has all virtues can be ignorant and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.448"/>
				
				doubt of his having them; or the difference of virtue from
				vice, of happiness from misery, and of a most honest life
				from a most shameful one, is little and altogether difficult
				to be discerned, if he who has exchanged the one for the
				other does not perceive it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>He has written one volume of lives divided into
				four books; in the fourth of these he says, that a wise
				man meddles with no business but his own, and is employed about his own affairs. His words are these:
				<q direct="unspecified">For I am of opinion, that a prudent man shuns affairs,
					meddles little, and at the same time minds his own occasions; civil persons being both minders of their own
					affairs and meddlers with little else.</q> He has said almost
				the same in his book of Things eligible for Themselves, in
				these very words: <q direct="unspecified">For indeed a quiet life seems to have
					in it a certain security and freedom from danger, though
					there are not very many who can comprehend it.</q> It is
				manifest that he does not much dissent from Epicurus,
				who takes away Providence that he may leave God in
				repose. But the same Chrysippus in his First Book of
				Lives says, that a wise man willingly takes upon him a
				kingdom, making his profit by it; and if he cannot reign
				himself, will dwell with a king, and go to the wars with
				such a king as was Hydanthyrsus the Scythian or Leucon
				the Pontic. But I will here also set down his very discourse, that we may see whether, as from the treble and the
				base strings there arises a symphony in music, so the life
				of a man who chooses quietness and meddling with little
				accords with him who, upon any necessity, rides along
				with the Scythians and manages the affairs of the tyrants
				in the Bosphorus: <q direct="unspecified">For that a wise man will both go to the
					wars and live with potentates, we will again consider this
					hereafter; some indeed upon the like arguments not so
					much as suspecting this, and we for semblable reasons admitting it.</q> And a little after: <q direct="unspecified">Not only with those who
						
						<pb id="v.4.p.449"/>
						
						have proceeded well, and are become proficients in discipline and good manners, as with Leucon and Hydanthyrsus.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Some there are who blame Callisthenes for sailing to
					Alexander in hopes to obtain the rebuilding of Olynthus,
					as Aristotle had procured that of Stagira; and commend
					Ephorus, Xenocrates, and Menedemus, who rejected Alexander's invitation. But Chrysippus thrusts his wise man
					headforwards for the sake of gain, as far as Panticapaeum
					and the desert of the Scythians. And that he does this
					for the sake of profit and gain, he has showed before,
					supposing three ways of gaining most suitable for a
					wise man,&mdash;the first by a kingdom, the second by his
					friends, and the third, besides these, by teaching of philosophy. And yet he frequently even tires us with his
					praises of this saying:
					<quote rend="blockquote">What need have men of more than these two things?</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in his books of Nature he says, that a wise man, if he
					has lost the greatest wealth imaginable, seems to have lost
					but a single groat. But having there thus elevated and
					puffed him up, he again here throws him down to mercenariness and sophistry; nay, to asking pay and even to
					receiving it beforehand, sometimes at the very entrance of
					his scholar, and otherwhiles after some time past. The
					latter, he says indeed, is the more civil, but to receive
					beforehand the more sure; delay being subject to sustain
					injuries. Now he says thus: <q direct="unspecified">All who are well advised
						do not require their salary in the same manner, but differently; a multitude of them, as opportunity offers, not
						promising to make their scholars good men, and that
						within a year, but to do this, as far as in them lies, within
						a time agreed on.</q> And again going on, he says: <q direct="unspecified">But
							he will know his opportunity, whether he ought to receive
							his recompense presently at the very entrance (as many
							
							<pb id="v.4.p.450"/>
							
							have done), or to give them time, this manner being more
							liable to injuries, but withal, seeming the more courteous.</q>
					And how is the wise man a contemner of wealth, who
					upon a contract delivers virtue for money, and if he has
					not delivered it, yet requires his reward, as having done
					what is in him? Or how is he above being endamaged,
					when he is so cautious lest he be wronged of his recompense? For no man is wronged who is not endamaged.
					Therefore, though he has elsewhere asserted that a wise
					man cannot be injured, he here says, that this manner of
					dealing is liable to injury.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>In his book of a Commonweal he says, that his citizens will neither act nor prepare any thing for the sake of
				pleasure, and praises Euripides for having uttered this
				sentence:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What need have men of more than these two things,
				</l>
                     <l>The fruits of Ceres, and thirst-quenching springs?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet a little after this, going on, he commends Diogenes,
					who forced his nature to pass from himself in public, and
					said to those that were present: I wish I could in the
					same manner drive hunger also out of my belly. What
					reason then is there to praise in the same books him who
					rejects all pleasure, and withal, him who for the sake of
					pleasure does such things, and proceeds to such a degree
					of filthiness? Moreover, having in his book of Nature
					written, that Nature has produced many creatures for the
					sake of beauty, delighting in pulchritude and pleasing herself with variety, and having added a most absurd expression, that the peacock was made for the sake of his tail
					and for the beauty of it; he has, in his treatise of a Commonweal, sharply reprehended those who bred peacocks
					and nightingales, as if he were making laws contrary to
					the lawgiver of the world, and deriding Nature for pleasing herself in the beauty of animals to which a wise man
					would not give a place in his city. For how can it but be
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.451"/>
					
					absurd to blame those who nourish these creatures, if he
					commends Providence which created them? In his Fifth
					Book of Nature, having said, that bugs profitably awaken
					us out of our sleep, that mice make us cautious not to lay
					up every thing negligently, and that it is probable that
					Nature, rejoicing in variety, takes delight in the production
					of fair creatures, he adds these words: <q direct="unspecified">The evidence
						of this is chiefly shown in the peacock's tail; for here she
						manifests that this animal was made for the sake of his
						tail, and not the contrary; so, the male being made, the
						female follows.</q> In his book of a Commonweal, having
					said that we are ready to paint even dunghills, a little after
					he adds, that some beautify their cornfields with vines
					climbing up trees, and myrtles set in rows, and keep peacocks, doves, and partridges, that they may hear them
					cackle and coo, and nightingales. Now I would gladly
					ask him, what he thinks of bees and honey? For it was
					of consequence, that he who said bugs were created profitably should also say that bees were created unprofitably.
					But if he allows these a place in his city, why does he
					drive away his citizens from things that are pleasing and
					delight the ear? To be brief,&mdash;as he would be very absurd who should blame the guests for eating sweetmeats
					and other delicacies and drinking of wine, and at the same
					time commend him who invited them and prepared such
					things for them; so he that praises Providence, which has
					afforded fishes, birds, honey, and wine, and at the same
					time finds fault with those who reject not these things, nor
					content themselves with
					<quote rend="blockquote">The fruits of Ceres and thirst-quenching springs,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>which are present and sufficient to nourish us, seems to
					make no scruple of speaking things contradictory to himself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Moreover, having said in his book of Exhortations,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.452"/>
				
				that the having carnal commerce with our mothers, daughters, or sisters, the eating forbidden food, and the going
				from a woman's bed or a dead carcass to the temple, have
				been without reason blamed, he affirms, that we ought for
				these things to have a regard to the brute beasts, and from
				what is done by them conclude that none of these is absurd or contrary to Nature; for that the comparisons of
				other animals are fitly made for this purpose, to show that
				neither their coupling, bringing-forth, nor dying in the
				temples pollutes the Divinity. Yet he again in his Fifth
				Book of Nature says, that Hesiod rightly forbids the making
				water into rivers and fountains, and that we should rather
				abstain from doing this against any altar. or statue of the
				Gods; and that it is not to be admitted for an argument,
				that dogs, asses, and young children do it, who have no
				discretion or consideration of such things. It is therefore
				absurd to say in one place, that the savage example of
				irrational animals is fit to be considered, and in another,
				that it is unreasonable to allege it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>To give a solution to the inclinations, when a man
				seems to be necessitated by exterior causes, some philosophers place in the principal faculty of the soul a certain
				adventitious motion, which is chiefly manifested in things
				differing not at all from one another. For when, with two
				things altogether alike and of equal importance, there is a
				necessity to choose the one, there being no cause inclining
				to either, for that neither of them differs from the other,
				this adventitious power of the soul, seizing on its inclination, determines the doubt. Chrysippus, discoursing against
				these men, as offering violence to Nature by devising an
				effect without a cause, in many places alleges the die and
				the balance, and several other things, which cannot fall or
				incline either one way or the other without some cause or
				difference, either wholly within them or coming to them
				from without; for that what is causeless (he says) is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.453"/>
				
				wholly insubsistent, as also what is fortuitous; and in
				those motions devised by some and called adventitious,
				there occur certain obscure causes, which, being concealed from us, move our inclinations to one side or other.
				These are some of those things which are most evidently
				known to have been frequently said by him; but what he
				has said contrary to this, not lying so exposed to every
				one's sight, I will set down in his own words. For in his
				book of Judging, having supposed two running for a
				wager to have exactly finished their race together, he
				examines what is fit for the judge in this case to do.
				<q direct="unspecified">Whether,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">may the judge give the palm to
					which of them he will, because they both happen to be
					so familiar to him, that he would in some sort seem to
					bestow on them somewhat of his own? Or rather, since
					the palm is common to both, may it be, as if lots had been
					cast, given to either, according to the inclination he chances to have? I say the inclination he chances to have, as
					when two groats, every way else alike, being presented to
					us, we incline to one of them and take it.</q> And in his
				Sixth Book of Duties, having said that there are some
				things not worthy of much study or attention, he thinks
				we ought, as if we had cast lots, to commit the choice of
				those things to the casual inclination of the mind: <q direct="unspecified">As
					if,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">of those who try the same two groats in a
						certain time, some should say this and others that to be
						good, and there being no more cause for the taking of one
						than the other, we should leave off making any farther
						enquiry into their value, and take that which chances to
						come first to hand; thus casting the lot (as it were) according to some hidden principle, and being in danger of
						choosing the worse of them.</q> For in these passages, the
				casting of lots and the casual inclining of the mind, which
				is without any cause, introduce the choice of indifferent
				things.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.454"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>In his Third Book of Dialectics, having said that
				Plato, Aristotle, and those who came after them, even to
				Polemon and Straton, but especially Socrates, diligently
				studied dialectics, and having cried out that one would
				even choose to err with such and so great men as these,
				he brings in these words: <q direct="unspecified">For if they had spoken of
					these things cursorily, one might perhaps have cavilled at
					this place; but having treated of dialectic skill as one of
					the greatest and most necessary faculties, it is not probable
					they should have been so much mistaken, having been
					such in all the parts of philosophy as we esteem them.</q>
				Why then (might some one say to him) do you never
				cease to oppose and argue against such and so great men,
				as if you thought them to err in the principal and greatest
				matters? For it is not probable that they writ seriously
				of dialectics, and only transitorily and in sport of the
				beginning, end, Gods, and justice, in which you affirm
				their discourse to be blind and contradictory to itself, and
				to have a thousand other faults.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>In one place he says, that the vice called <foreign lang="greek">'*epixairekaki/a</foreign>,
				or the rejoicing at other men's harms, has no being; since
				no good man ever rejoiced at another's evils. But in his
				Second Book of Good, having declared envy to be a sorrow
				at other men's good,&mdash;to wit, in such as desire the depression of their neighbors that themselves may excel,&mdash;
				he joins to it this rejoicing at other men's harms, saying thus:
				<q direct="unspecified">To this is contiguous the rejoicing at other men's harms, in
					such as for like causes desire to have their neighbors low;
					but in those that are turned according to other natural motions, is engendered mercy.</q> For he manifestly admits
				the joy at other men's harms to be subsistent, as well as
				envy and mercy; though in other places he affirms it to
				have no subsistence; as he does also the hatred of wickedness, and the desire of dishonest gain.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>Having in many places said, that those who have a
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.455"/>
				
				long time been happy are nothing more so, but equally
				and in like manner with those who have but a moment
				been partakers of felicity, he has again in many other
				places affirmed, that it is not fit to stretch out so much as
				a finger for the obtaining momentary prudence, which flies
				away like a flash of lightning. It will be sufficient to set
				down what is to this purpose written by him in his Sixth
				Book of Moral Questions. For having said, that neither
				does every good thing equally cause joy, nor every good
				deed the like glorying, he subjoins these words: <q direct="unspecified">For if
					a man should have wisdom only for a moment of time or
					the last minute of life, he ought not so much as to stretch
					out his finger for such a short-lived prudence.</q> And yet
				men are neither more happy for being longer so, nor is
				eternal felicity more eligible than that which lasts but a
				moment. If he had indeed held prudence to be a good,
				producing felicity, as Epicurus thought, one should have
				blamed only the absurdity and the paradoxicalness of this
				opinion; but since prudence of itself is not another thing
				differing from felicity, but felicity itself, how is it not a
				contradiction to say, that momentary happiness is equally
				desirable with eternal, and yet that momentary happiness
				is nothing worth?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Chrysippus also says, that the virtues follow one
				another, and that not only he who has one has all, but also
				that he who acts according to any one of them acts according to them all; and he affirms, that there is not any
				man perfect who is not possessed of all the virtues, nor
				any action perfect to the doing of which all the virtues do
				not concur. But yet in his Sixth Book of Moral Questions
				he says, that a good man does not always act valiantly, nor
				a vicious man always fearfully; for certain objects being
				presented to the fancies, the one must persist in his judgments, and the other depart from them; and he says that
				it is not probable a wicked man should be always indulging
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.456"/>
				
				 his lust. If then to act valiantly is the same thing as
				to use fortitude; and to act timorously as to yield to fear,
				they cannot but speak contradictions who say, that he who
				is possessed of either virtue or vice acts at the same time
				according to all the virtues or all the vices, and yet that a
				valiant man does not always act valiantly nor a vicious man
				timorously.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>He defines Rhetoric to be an art concerning the
				ornament and the ordering of a discourse that is pronounced. And farther in his First Book he has written
				thus: <q direct="unspecified">And I am not only of opinion that a regard ought
					to be had to a liberal and simple adorning of words, but
					also that care is. to be taken for proper delivery, as
					regards the right elevation of the voice and the compositions of the countenance and hands.</q> Yet he, who is in
				this place so curious and exact, again in the same book,
				speaking of the collision of the vowels, says: <q direct="unspecified">We ought
					not only to let these things pass, minding somewhat that
					is better, but also to neglect certain obscurities and defects,
					nay, solecisms also, of which others, and those not a few,
					would be ashamed.</q> Certainly, in one place to allow those
				who would speak eloquently so carefully to dispose their
				speech as even to observe a decorum in the very composition of their mouth and hands, and in another place to
				forbid the taking care of defects and obscurities, and the
				being ashamed even of committing solecisms, is the property of a man who little cares what he says, but rashly
				utters whatever comes first into his mouth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Moreover, in his Natural Positions having warned
				us not to trouble ourselves but to be at quiet about such
				things as require experience and investigation, he says:
				<q direct="unspecified">Let us not think after the same manner with Plato, that
					liquid nourishment is conveyed to the lungs, and dry to the
					stomach; nor let us embrace other errors like to these.</q>
				Now it is my opinion, that to reprehend others, and then
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.457"/>
				
				not to keep one's self from falling into those things which
				one has reprehended, is the greatest of contradictions and
				shamefullest of errors. But he says, that the connections
				made by ten axioms amount to above a million in number,
				having neither searched diligently into it by himself nor
				attained to the truth by men experienced in it. Yet Plato
				had to testify for him the most renowned of the physicians,
				Hippocrates, Philistion, and Dioxippus the disciple of Hippocrates; and of the poets, Euripides, Alcaeus, Eupolis,
				and Eratosthenes, who all say that the drink passes through
				the lungs. But all the arithmeticians refel Chrysippus,
				amongst whom also is Hipparchus, demonstrating that the
				error of his computation is very great; since the affirmative makes of the ten axioms one hundred and three.
				thousand forty and nine connections, and the negative
				three hundred and ten thousand nine hundred fifty and
				two.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Some of the ancients have said, that the same befell
				Zeno which befalls him who has sour wine which he can
				sell neither for vinegar nor wine; for his <q direct="unspecified">things preferred,</q> as he called them, cannot be disposed of, either as
				good or as indifferent. But Chrysippus has made the
				matter yet far more intricate; for he sometimes says, that
				they are mad who make no account of riches, health,
				freedom from pain, and integrity of the body, nor take
				any care to attain them; and having cited that sentence of
				Hesiod,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Work hard, O God-born Perses,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Works and Days, 299.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>he cries out, that it would be a madness to advise the
					contrary and say,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Work not, O God-born Perses.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in his book of Lives he affirms, that a wise man
					will for the sake of gain live with kings, and teach for
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.458"/>
					
					money, receiving from some of his scholars his reward
					beforehand, and making contract with others of them;
					and in his Seventh Book of Duties he says, that he will
					not scruple to turn his heels thrice over his head, if for
					so doing he may have a talent. In his First Book of Good
					Things, he yields and grants to those that desire it to call
					these preferred things good and their contraries evil, in
					these very words: <q direct="unspecified">Any one who will, according to these
						permutations, may call one thing good and another evil,
						having a regard to the things themselves, and not wandering elsewhere, not failing in the understanding of the
						things signified, and in the rest accommodating himself to
						custom in the denomination.</q> Having thus in this place
					set his preferred things so near to good, and mixed them
					therewith, he again says, that none of these things belongs
					at all to us, but that reason withdraws and averts us from
					all such things; for he has written thus in his First Book
					of Exhortations. And in his Third Book of Nature he
					says, that some esteem those happy who reign and are
					rich, which is all one as if those should be reputed happy
					who make water in golden chamber-pots and wear golden
					fringes; but to a good man the losing of his whole estate
					is but as the losing of one groat, and the being sick no
					more than if he had stumbled. Wherefore he has not
					filled virtue only, but Providence also, with these contradictions. For virtue would seem to the utmost degree sordid
					and foolish, if it should busy itself about such matters,
					and enjoin a wise man for their sake to sail to Bosphorus
					or tumble with his heels over his head. And Jupiter would
					be very ridiculous to be styled Ctesius, Epicarpius, and
					Charitodotes, because forsooth he gives the wicked golden
					chamber-pots and golden fringes, and the good such
					things as are hardly worth a groat, when through Jupiter's
					providence they become rich. And yet much more ridiculous is Apollo, if he sits to give oracles concerning
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.459"/>
					
					golden fringes and chamber-pots and the recovering of a
					stumble.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>But they make this repugnancy yet more evident by
				their demonstration. For they say, that what may be used
				both well and ill, the same is neither good nor bad; but
				fools make an ill use of riches, health, and strength of
				body; therefore none of these is good. If therefore God
				gives not virtue to men,&mdash;but honesty is eligible of itself,
				&mdash;and yet bestows on them riches and health without
				virtue, he confers them on those who will use them not
				well but ill, that is hurtfully, shamefully, and perniciously.
				Now, if the Gods can bestow virtue and do not, they are
				not good; but if they cannot make men good, neither can
				they help them, for except virtue nothing is good and helpful. Now to judge those who are otherwise made good
				according to virtue and strength . . . is nothing to the
				purpose, for good men also judge the Gods according to
				virtue and strength; so that they do no more aid men than
				they are aided by them.</p>
            <p>Now Chrysippus neither professes himself nor any one
					of his disciples and teachers to be virtuous. What then
					do they think of others, but those things which they say,
					&mdash;that they are all mad, fools, impious, transgressors of
					the laws, and in the utmost degree of misery and unhappiness? And yet they say that our affairs, though we act
					thus miserably, are governed by the providence of the
					Gods. Now if the Gods, changing their minds, should
					desire to hurt, afflict, overthrow, and quite crush us, they
					could not put us in a worse condition than we already
					are; as Chrysippus demonstrates that life can admit no
					greater degree either of misery or of unhappiness; so
					that if it had a voice, it would pronounce these words of
					Hercules:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am so full of miseries, there is
					</l>
                     <l>No place to stow them in.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Here. Fur. 1245.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.460"/>
            <p>Now who can imagine any assertions more repugnant to
					one another than that of Chrysippus concerning the Gods
					and that concerning men; when he says, that the Gods do
					in the best manner possible provide for men, and yet men
					are in the worst condition imaginable?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>Some of the Pythagoreans blame him for having in
				his book of Justice written concerning cocks, that they
				are usefully procreated, because they awaken us from our
				sleep, hunt out scorpions, and animate us to battle, breeding in us a certain emulation to show courage; and yet
				that we must eat them, lest the number of chickens should
				be greater than were expedient. But he so derides those
				who blame him for this, that he has written thus concerning Jupiter the Savior and Creator, the father of justice,
				equity, and peace, in his Third Book of the Gods: <q direct="unspecified">As
					cities overcharged with too great a number of citizens send
					forth colonies into other places and make war upon some,
					so does God give the beginnings of corruption.</q> And he
				brings in Euripides for a witness, with others who say,
				that the Trojan war was caused by the Gods, to exhaust
				the multitude of men.</p>
            <p>But letting pass their other absurdities (for our design is
					not to enquire what they have said amiss, but only what
					they have said dissonantly to themselves), consider how
					he always attributes to the Gods specious and kind appellations, but at the same time cruel, barbarous, and Galatian deeds. For those so great slaughters and carnages,
					as were the productions of the Trojan war and again of
					the Persian and Peloponnesian, were no way like to colonies unless these men know of some cities built in hell
					and under the earth. But Chrysippus makes God like to
					De&iuml;otarus, the Galatian king, who having many sons, and
					being desirous to leave his kingdom and house to one of
					them, killed all the rest; as he that cuts and prunes away
					all the other branches from the vine, that one which he
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.461"/>
					
					leaves remaining may grow strong and great. And yet the
					vine-dresser does this, the sprigs being slender and weak;
					and we, to favor a bitch, take from her many of her new
					born puppies, whilst they are yet blind. But Jupiter,
					having not only suffered and seen men to grow up, but
					having also both created and increased them, plagues them
					afterwards, devising occasions of their destruction and corruption; whereas he should rather not have given them
					any causes and beginnings of generation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>However this is but a small matter; but that which
				follows is greater. For there is no war amongst men without vice. But sometimes the love of pleasure, sometimes
				the love of money, and sometimes the love of glory and
				rule is the cause of it. If therefore God is the author
				of wars, he must be also of sins, provoking and perverting
				men. And yet himself says in his treatise of Judgment
				and his Second Book of the Gods, that it is no way rational to say that the Divinity is in any respect the cause
				of dishonesty. For as the law can in no way be the cause
				of transgression, so neither can the Gods of being impious;
				therefore neither is it rational that they should be the
				causes of any thing that is filthy. What therefore can be
				more filthy to men than the mutual killing of one another?
				&mdash;to which Chrysippus says that God gives beginnings.
				But some one perhaps will say, that he elsewhere praises
				Euripides for saying,
				<quote rend="blockquote">If Gods do aught dishonest, they're no Gods;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					<quote rend="blockquote">'Tis a most easy thing t' accuse the Gods;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Bellerophontes of Euripides, Frag. 294; and the Archelaus, Frag.
						256.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if we were now doing any thing else than setting down
					such words and sentences of his as are repugnant to one
					another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>Yet that very thing which is now praised may be
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.462"/>
				
				objected, not once or twice or thrice, but even ten thousand
				times, against Chrysippus:
				<quote rend="blockquote">'Tis a most easy thing t' accuse the Gods.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For first having in his book of Nature compared the eternity of motion to a drink made of divers species confusedly
					mixed together, turning and jumbling the things that are
					made, some this way, others that way, he goes on thus:
					<q direct="unspecified">Now the administration of the universe proceeding in
						this manner, it is of necessity we should be in the condition we are, whether contrary to our own nature we are
						sick or maimed, or whether we are grammarians or musicians.</q> And again a little after, <q direct="unspecified">According to this reason we shall say the like of our virtue and vice, and
							generally of arts or the ignorance of arts, as I have said.</q>
					And a little after, taking away all ambiguity, he says:
					<q direct="unspecified">For no particular thing, not even the least, can be otherwise than according to common Nature and its reason.</q>
					But that common Nature and the common reason of Nature are with him Fate and Providence and Jupiter, is not
					unknown even to the antipodes. For these things are
					everywhere inculcated by the Stoics; and Chrysippus affirms that Homer said very well,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Jove's purposes were ripening,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 5.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>having respect to Fate and the Nature of the universe, according to which every thing is governed. How then do
					these agree, both that God is no way the cause of any dishonest thing, and again, that not even the least thing imaginable can be otherwise done than according to common
					Nature and its reason? For amongst all things that are
					done, there must of necessity be also dishonest things attributed to the Gods. And though Epicurus indeed turns
					himself every way, and studies artifices, devising how to
					deliver and set loose our voluntary free will from this
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.463"/>
					
					eternal motion, that he may not leave vice irreprehensible;
					yet Chrysippus gives vice a most absolute liberty, as being
					done not only of necessity or according to Fate, but also
					according to the reason of God and best Nature. And
					these things are yet farther seen in what he says afterwards, being thus word for word: <q direct="unspecified">For common Nature
						extending to all things, it will be of necessity that every
						thing, howsoever done in the whole or in any one soever
						of its parts, must be done according to this common Nature
						and its reason, proceeding on regularly without any impediment. For there is nothing without that can hinder
						the administration, nor is there any of the parts that can
						be moved or habituated otherwise than according to common Nature.</q> What then are these habits and motions of
					the parts? It is manifest, that the habits are vices and
					diseases, covetousness, luxury, ambition, cowardice, injustice; and that the motions are adulteries, thefts, treasons,
					murders, parricides. Of these Chrysippus thinks, that
					no one, either little or great, is contrary to the reason of
					Jupiter, or to his law, justice, and providence; so neither
					is the transgressing of the law done against the law, nor
					the acting unjustly against justice, nor the committing of
					sin against Providence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>And yet he says, that God punishes vice, and does
				many things for the chastising of the wicked. And in
				his Second Book of the Gods he says, that many adversities sometimes befall the good, not as they do the wicked,
				for punishment, but according to another dispensation, as
				it is in cities. And again in these words: <q direct="unspecified">First we are
					to understand of evils in like manner as has been said
					before: then, that these things are distributed according
					to the reason of Jupiter, whether for punishment, or according to some other dispensation, having in some sort
					respect to the universe.</q> This therefore is indeed severe,
				that wickedness is both done and punished according to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.464"/>
				
				the reason of Jupiter. But he aggravates this contradiction in his Second Book of Nature, writing thus: <q direct="unspecified">Vice,
					in reference to grievous accidents, has a certain reason of
					its own. For it is also in some sort according to the reason of Nature, and, as I may so say, is not wholly useless
					in respect of the universe. For otherwise also there would
					not be any good.</q> Thus does he reprehend those that
				dispute indifferently on both sides, who, out of a desire to
				say something wholly singular and more exquisite concerning every thing, affirms, that men do not unprofitably cut
				purses, calumniate, and play madmen, and that it is not
				unprofitable there should be unprofitable, hurtful, and unhappy persons. What manner of God then is Jupiter,&mdash;
				I mean Chrysippus's Jupiter,&mdash;who punishes an act done
				neither willingly nor unprofitably? For vice is indeed,
				according to Chrysippus's discourse, wholly reprehensible;
				but Jupiter is to be blamed, whether he has made vice
				which is an unprofitable thing, or, having made it not un
				profitable, punishes it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>Again, in his First Book of Justice, having spoken
				of the Gods as resisting the injustices of some, he says
				<q direct="unspecified">But wholly to take away vice is neither possible nor expedient.</q> Whether it were not better that law-breaking,
				injustice, and folly should be taken away, is not the design
				of this present discourse to enquire. But he himself, as
				much as in him lies, by his philosophy taking away vice,
				which it is not expedient to take away, does something repugnant both to reason and God. Besides this, saying
				that God resists some injustices, he again declares plainly
				the impiety of sins.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>Having often written that there is nothing reprehensible, nothing to be complained of in the world, all
				things being finished according to a most excellent nature,
				he again elsewhere leaves certain negligences to be reprehended, and those not concerning small or base matters.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.465"/>
				
				For having in his Third Book of Substance related that
				some such things befall honest and good men, he says:
				<q direct="unspecified">Is it because some things are not regarded, as in great
					families some bran&mdash;yea, and some grains of corn also&mdash;are scattered, the generality being nevertheless well ordered;
					or is it that there are evil Genii set over those things in
					which there are real and faulty negligence</q> And he
				also affirms that there is much necessity intermixed, I let
				pass, how inconsiderate it is to compare such accidents befalling honest and good men, as were the condemnation of
				Socrates, the burning of Pythagoras, whilst he was yet
				living, by the Cyloneans, the putting to death&mdash;and that
				with torture&mdash;of Zeno by the tyrant Demylus, and of
				Antiphon by Dionysius, with the letting of bran fall. But
				that there should be evil Genii placed by Providence over
				such charges,&mdash;how can it but be a reproach to God, as
				it would be to a king, to commit the administration of his
				provinces to evil and rash governors and captains, and
				suffer the best of his subjects to be despised and ill-treated
				by them? And furthermore, if there is much necessity
				mixed amongst affairs, then God has not power over them
				all, nor are they all administered according to his reason.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>He contends much against Epicurus and those that
				take away providence from the conceptions we have of the
				Gods, whom we esteem beneficial and gracious to men.
				And these things being frequently said by them, there is
				no necessity of setting down the words. Yet all do not
				conceive the Gods to be good and favorable to us. For
				see what the Jews and Syrians think of the Gods; see
				also with how much superstition the poets are filled. But
				there is not any one, in a manner to speak of, that imagines God to be corruptible or to have been born. And to
				omit all others, Antipater the Tarsian, in his book of the
				Gods writes thus, word for word: <q direct="unspecified">At the beginning of
					our discourse we will briefly repeat the opinion we have
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.466"/>
					
					concerning God. We understand therefore God to be an
					animal, blessed and incorruptible, and beneficial to men.</q>
				And then expounding every one of these terms he says:
				<q direct="unspecified">And indeed all men esteem the Gods to be incorruptible.</q> Chrysippus therefore is, according to Antipater,
				not one of <q direct="unspecified">all men ;</q> for he thinks none of the Gods, except Fire, to be incorruptible, but that they all equally were
				born and will die. These things are, in a manner, everywhere said by him. But I will set down his words out of
				his Third Book of the Gods: <q direct="unspecified">It is otherwise with the
					Gods. For some of them are born and corruptible, but
					others not born. And to demonstrate these things from
					the beginning will be more fit for a treatise of Nature.
					For the Sun, the Moon, and other Gods who are of a like
					nature, were begotten; but Jupiter is eternal.</q> And
				again going on: <q direct="unspecified">But the like will be said concerning dying and being born, both concerning the other Gods and
					Jupiter. For they indeed are corruptible, but his parts
					incorruptible.</q> With these I compare a few of the things
				said by Antipater: <q direct="unspecified">Whosoever they are that take away
					from the Gods beneficence, they attack in some part our
					preconception of them; and according to the same reason
					they also do this, who think they participate of generation
					and corruption.</q> If then he who esteems the Gods corruptible is equally absurd with him who thinks them not
				to be provident and gracious to men, Chrysippus is no less
				in an error than Epicurus. For one of them deprives the
				Gods of beneficence, the other of incorruptibility.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>And moreover, Chrysippus, in his Third Book of
				the Gods treating of the other Gods being nourished, says
				thus: <q direct="unspecified">The other Gods indeed use nourishment, being
					equally sustained by it; but Jupiter and the World are sustained after another manner from those who are consumed
					and were engendered by fire.</q> Here indeed he declares,
				that all the other Gods are nourished except the World and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.467"/>
				
				Jupiter; but in his First Book of Providence he says.
				<q direct="unspecified">Jupiter increases till he has consumed all things into himself. For since death is the separation of the soul from
					the body, and the soul of the World is not indeed separated,
					but increases continually till it has consumed all matter into
					itself, it is not to be said that the World dies.</q> Who can
				therefore appear to speak things more contradictory to himself than he who says that the same God is now nourished
				and again not nourished? Nor is there any need of gathering this by argument; for himself has plainly written in
				the same place: <q direct="unspecified">But the World alone is said to be self-sufficient, because it alone has in itself all things it stands
					in need of, and is nourished and augmented of itself, the
					other parts being mutually changed into one another.</q> He
				is then repugnant to himself, not only by declaring in one
				place that all the Gods are nourished except the World and
				Jupiter, and saying in another, that the World also is
				nourished; but much more, when he affirms that the World
				increases by nourishing itself. Now the contrary had been
				much more probable, to wit, that the World alone does not
				increase, having its own destruction for its food; but that
				addition and increase are incident to the other Gods, who
				are nourished from without, and the World is rather consumed into them, if so it is that the World feeds on itself,
				and they always receive something and are nourished from
				that.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>Secondly, the conception of the Gods contains in
				it felicity, blessedness, and self-perfection. Wherefore also
				Euripides is commended for saying:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For God, if truly God, does nothing want,
				</l>
                     <l>And all these speeches are but poets' cant.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hercules Furens, 1345</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But Chrysippus in the places I have alleged says, that the
					World only is self-sufficient, because this alone has in itself
					all things it needs. What then follows from this, that the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.468"/>
					
					World alone is self-sufficient? That neither the Sun, Moon,
					nor any other of the Gods is self-sufficient, and not being
					self-sufficient, they cannot be happy or blessed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>He says, that the infant in the womb is nourished by
				Nature, like a plant; but when it is brought forth, being
				cooled and hardened by the air, it changes its spirit and
				becomes an animal; whence the soul is not unfitly named
				Psyche because of this refrigeration (<foreign lang="greek">yu/xein</foreign>). But again he
				esteems the soul the more subtile and fine spirit of Nature,
				therein contradicting himself; for how can a subtile thing
				be made of a gross one, and be rarefied by refrigeration
				and condensation? And what is more, how does he, declaring an animal to be made by refrigeration, think the sun
				to be animated, which is of fire and made of an exhalation
				changed into fire? For he says in his Third Book of Nature: <q direct="unspecified">Now the change of fire is such, that it is turned
					by the air into water; and the earth subsiding from this,
					the air exhales; the air being subtilized, the ether is produced round about it; and the stars are, with the sun,
					kindled from the sea.</q> Now what is more contrary to
				kindling than refrigeration, or to rarefaction than condensation? For the one makes water and earth of fire and air,
				and the other changes that which is moist and earthy into
				fire and air. But yet in one place he makes kindling, in
				another cooling, to be the beginning of animation. And
				he moreover says, that when the inflammation is throughout, it lives and is an animal, but being again extinct and
				thickened, it is turned into water and earth and corporeity.
				Now in his First Book of Providence he says: <q direct="unspecified">For the
					world, indeed, being wholly set on fire, is presently also
					the soul and guide of itself; but when it is changed into
					moisture, and has changed the soul remaining within it in
					some sort into a body and soul, so as to consist of these
					two, it is then after another manner.</q> Here, forsooth, he
				plainly says, that the inanimate parts of the world are by
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.469"/>
				
				inflammation turned into an animated thing, and that again
				by extinction the soul is relaxed and moistened, being
				changed into corporeity. He seems therefore very absurd,
				one while by refrigeration making animals of senseless
				things, and again, by the same changing the greatest part
				of the world's soul into senseless and inanimate things.</p>
            <p>But besides this, his discourse concerning the generation
					of the soul has a demonstration contrary to his own
					opinion; for he says, that the soul is generated when the
					infant is already brought forth, the spirit being changed by
					refrigeration, as by hardening. Now for the soul's being
					engendered, and that after the birth, he chiefly uses this
					demonstration, that the children are for the most part in
					manners and inclinations like to their parents. Now the
					repugnancy of these things is evident. For it is not possible that the soul, which is not generated till after the
					birth, should have its inclination before the birth; or it
					will fall out that the soul is like before it is generated;
					that is, it will be in likeness, and yet not be, because it is
					not yet generated. But if any one says that, the likeness
					being bred in the tempers of the bodies, the souls are
					changed when they are generated, he destroys the argument of the soul's being generated. For thus it may come
					to pass, that the soul, though not generated, may at its
					entrance into the body be changed by the mixture of likeness.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>He says sometimes, that the air is light and mounts
				upwards, and sometimes, that it is neither heavy nor light.
				For in his Second Book of Motion he says, that the fire,
				being without gravity, ascends upwards, and the air like to
				that; the water approaching more to the earth, and the air
				to the fire. But in his Physical Arts he inclines to the
				other opinion, that the air of itself has neither gravity nor
				levity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>He says that the air is by nature dark, and uses this
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.470"/>
				
				as an argument of its being also the first cold; for that its
				darkness is opposite to the brightness, and its coldness to
				the heat of fire. Moving this in his First Book of Natural
				Questions, he again in his treatise of Habits says, that
				habits are nothing else but airs; for bodies are contained
				by these, and the cause that every one of the bodies contained in any habit is such as it is, is the containing air,
				which they call in iron hardness, in stone solidness, in
				silver whiteness. These words have in them much absurdity and contradiction. For if the air remains such as it is
				of its own nature, how comes black, in that which is not
				white, to be made whiteness; and soft, in that which is not
				hard, to be made hardness; and rare, in that which is
				not thick, to be made thickness? But if, being mixed with
				these, it is altered and made like to them, how is it a habit
				or power or cause of these things by which it is subdued?
				For such a change, by which it loses its own qualities, is
				the property of a patient, not of an agent, and not of a
				thing containing, but of a thing languishing. Yet they
				everywhere affirm, that matter, being of its own nature idle
				and motionless, is subjected to qualities, and that the qualities are spirits, which, being also aerial tensions, give a
				form and figure to every part of matter to which they adhere. These things they cannot rationally say, supposing
				the air to be such as they affirm it. For if it is a habit
				and tension, it will assimilate every body to itself, so that it
				shall be black and soft. But if by the mixture with these
				things it receives forms contrary to those it has, it will be
				in some sort the matter, and not the cause or power of
				matter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>It is often said by Chrysippus, that there is without
				the world an infinite vacuum, and that this infinity has
				neither beginning, middle, nor end. And by this the Stoics
				chiefly refute that spontaneous motion of the atoms downward, which is taught by Epicurus; there not being in
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.471"/>
				
				infinity any difference according to which one thing is
				thought to be above, another below. But in his Fourth
				Book of Things Possible, having supposed a certain middle
				place and middle region, he says that the world is situated
				there. The words are these: <q direct="unspecified">Wherefore, if it is to be
					said of the world that it is corruptible, this seems to want
					proof; yet nevertheless it rather appears to me to be so.
					However, its occupation of the place wherein it stands cooperates very much towards its seeming to be incorruptible,
					because it is in the midst; since if it were thought to be
					anywhere else, corruption would absolutely take hold of
					it.</q> And again, a little after: <q direct="unspecified">For so also in a manner
						has essence happened eternally to possess the middle place,
						being immediately from the beginning such as it is; so that
						both by another manner and through this chance it admits
						not any corruption, and is therefore eternal.</q> These words
				have one apparent and visible contradiction, to wit, his
				admitting a certain middle place and middle region in
				infinity. They have also a second, more obscure indeed,
				but withal more absurd than this. For thinking that the
				world would not have remained incorruptible if its situation
				had happened to have been in any other part of the vacuum, he manifestly appears to have feared lest, the parts of
				essence moving towards the middle, there should be a dissolution and corruption of the world. Now this he would
				not have feared, had he not thought that bodies do by nature tend from every place towards the middle, not of
				essence, but of the region containing essence; of which
				also he has frequently spoken, as of a thing impossible
				and contrary to Nature; for that (as he says) there is not
				in the vacuum any difference by which bodies are drawn
				rather this way than that way, but the construction of the
				world is the cause of motion, bodies inclining and being
				carried from every side to the centre and middle of it. It
				is sufficient to this purpose, to set down the text out of his
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.472"/>
				
				Second Book of Motion; for having discoursed, that the
				world indeed is a perfect body, but that the parts of the
				world are not perfect, because they have in some sort
				respect to the whole and are not of themselves; and going
				forward concerning its motion, as having been framed by
				Nature to be moved by all its parts towards compaction
				and cohesion, and not towards dissolution and breaking, he
				says thus: <q direct="unspecified">But the universe thus tending and being
					moved to the same point, and the parts having the same
					motion from the nature of the body, it is probable that all
					bodies have this first motion according to Nature towards
					the centre of the world,&mdash;the world being thus moved as
					regards itself, and the parts being thus moved as being its
					parts.</q> What then ailed you, good sir (might some one
				say to him), that you have so far forgotten those words, as
				to affirm that the world, if it had not casually possessed
				the middle place, would have been dissoluble and corruptible? For if it is by Nature so framed as always to incline
				towards the middle, and its parts from every side tend to the
				same, into what place soever of the vacuum it should have
				been transposed,&mdash;thus containing and (as it were) embracing itself,&mdash;it would have remained incorruptible and without
				danger of breaking. For things that are broken and dissipated suffer this by the separation and dissolution of their
				parts, every one of them hasting to its own place from that
				which it had contrary to Nature. But you, being of opinion that, if the world should have been seated in any other
				place of the vacuum, it would have been wholly liable to
				corruption, and affirming the same, and therefore asserting
				a middle in that which naturally can have no middle,&mdash;
				to wit, in that which is infinite,&mdash;have indeed dismissed
				these tensions, coherences, and inclinations, as having
				nothing available to its preservation, and attributed all the
				cause of its permanency to the possession of place. And,
				as if you were ambitious to confute yourself, to the things
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.473"/>
				
				you have said before you join this also: <q direct="unspecified">In whatsoever
					manner every one of the parts moves, being coherent to
					the rest, it is agreeable to reason that in the same also the
					whole should move by itself; yea, though we should, for
					argument's sake, imagine and suppose it to be in some
					vacuity of this world; for as, being kept in on every side,
					it would move towards the middle, so it would continue in
					the same motion, though by way of disputation we should
					admit that there were on a sudden a vacuum round about
					it.</q> No part then whatsoever, though encompassed by a
				vacuum, loses its inclination moving it towards the middle
				of the world; but the world itself, if chance had not prepared it a place in the middle, would have lost its containing vigor, the parts of its essence being carried some one
				way, some another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>And these things indeed contain great contradictions
				to natural reason; but this is also repugnant to the doctrine concerning God and Providence, that assigning to
				them the least causes, he takes from them the most principal and greatest. For what is more principal than the
				permanency of the world, or that its essence, united in its
				parts, is contained in itself? But this, as Chrysippus
				says, fell out casually. For if the possession of place
				is the cause of incorruptibility, and this was the production of chance, it is manifest that the preservation of
				the universe is a work of chance, and not of Fate and
				Providence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>Now, as for his doctrine of possibles, how can it but
				be repugnant to his doctrine of Fate? For if that is not
				possible which either is true or shall be true, as Diodorus
				has it, but every thing which is capable of being, though
				it never shall be, is possible, there will be many things
				possible which will never be according to invincible, inviolable, and all-conquering Fate. And thus either Fate
				will lose its power; or if that, as Chrysippus thinks, has
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.474"/>
				
				existence, that which is susceptible of being will often fall
				out to be impossible. And every thing indeed which is
				true will be necessary, being comprehended by the principal of all necessities; and every thing that is false will
				be impossible, having the greatest cause to oppose its ever
				being true. For how is it possible that he should be susceptible of dying on the land, who is destined to die at
				sea? And how is it possible for him who is at Megara to
				come to Athens, if he is prohibited by Fate?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>But moreover, the things that are boldly asserted by
				him concerning fantasies or imaginations are very opposite
				to Fate. For desiring to show that fantasy is not of itself
				a perfect cause of consent, he says, that the Sages will
				prejudice us by imprinting false imaginations in our minds,
				if fantasies do of themselves absolutely cause consent; for
				wise men often make use of falsity against the wicked,
				representing a probable imagination,&mdash;which is yet not
				the cause of consent, for then it would be also a cause of
				false apprehension and error. Any one therefore, transferring these things from the wise man to Fate, may say,
				that consents are not caused by Fate; for if they were,
				false consents and opinions and deceptions would also be
				by Fate, and men would be endamaged by Fate. Thus the
				reason which exempts the wise man from doing hurt also
				demonstrates at the same time that Fate is not the cause of
				all things. For if men neither opine nor are prejudiced
				by Fate, it is manifest also that they neither act rightly nor
				are wise nor remain firm in their sentiments nor have utility by Fate, but that there is an end of Fate's being the
				cause of all things. Now if any one shall say that Chrysippus makes not Fate the absolute cause of all things, but
				only a <hi rend="italics">procatarctical</hi> (or antecedent) one, he will again
				show that he is contradictory to himself, since he excessively praises Homer for saying of Jupiter,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.475"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Receive whatever ill or good
				</l>
                     <l>He sends to each of you;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XV. 109. The words <q direct="unspecified">or good</q> are not found in Homer. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as also Euripides for these words,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Jove, how can I say that wretched we,
					</l>
                     <l>Poor mortals, aught do understand? On thee
					</l>
                     <l>We all depend, and nothing can transact,
					</l>
                     <l>But as thy sacred wisdom shall enact.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Suppliants, 734.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And himself writes many things agreeable to these. In
					fine, he says that nothing, be it never so little, either rests
					or is moved otherwise than according to the reason of Jupiter, which is the same thing with Fate. Moreover, the
					antecedent cause is weaker than the absolute one, and
					attains not to its effect when it is subdued by others that
					rise up against it. But he himself, declaring Fate to be an
					invincible, unimpeachable, and inflexible cause, calls it
					Atropos,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, Unchangeable.</note> Adrasteia,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, Unavoidable.</note> Necessity, and Pepromene (as putting a limit to all things). Whether then shall we say, that
					neither consents nor virtues nor vices nor doing well nor
					doing ill is in our power? Or shall we affirm, that Fate is
					deficient, that terminating destiny is unable to determine,
					and that the motions and habits of Jupiter cannot accomplish? For the one of these two consequences will follow
					from Fate's being an absolute, the other from its being only
					antecedent cause. For if it is an absolute cause, it takes
					away our free will and leaves nothing in our power; and
					if it is only antecedent, it loses its being unimpeachable
					and effectual. For not once or ten times, but everywhere,
					especially in his Physics, he has written, that there are
					many obstacles and impediments to particular natures and
					motions, but none to that of the universe. And how can
					the motion of the universe, extending as it does to particular ones, be undisturbed and unimpeached, if these are
					stopped and hindered? For neither can the nature of man
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.476"/>
					
					be free from impediment, if that of the foot or hand is not
					so; nor can the motion of a ship but be hindered, if there
					are any obstacles about the sails or the operation of the
					oars.</p>
            <p>Besides all this, if the fantasies are not according to Fate,
					neither are they causes of consents; but if, because it imprints fantasies leading to consent, the consents are said to
					be according to Fate, how is it not contrary to itself, imprinting in the greatest matters different imaginations and
					such as draw the understanding contrary ways? For (they
					say) those who adhere to one of them, and withhold not
					their consent, do amiss: if they yield to obscure things,
					they stumble; if to false, they are deceived; if to such as
					are not commonly comprehended, they opine. And yet one
					of these three is of necessity,&mdash;either that every fantasy
					is not the work of Fate, or that every receipt and consent
					of fantasy is faultless, or that Fate itself is not irreprehensible. For I do not know how it can be blameless, pro
					posing to us such fantasies that not the resisting or going
					against them, but the following and yielding to them, is
					blamable. Moreover, both Chrysippus and Antipater, in
					their disputes against the Academics, take not a little pains
					to prove that we neither act nor are incited without consent, saying, that they build on fictions and false suppositions who think that, a proper fantasy being presented, we
					are presently incited, without having either yielded or consented. Again, Chrysippus says, that God imprints in us
					false imaginations, as does also the wise man; not that
					they would have us consent or yield to them, but only that
					we should act and be incited with regard to that which appears; but we, being evil, do through infirmity consent to
					such fantasies. Now the perplexity and discrepancy of
					these discourses among themselves are not very difficult to
					be discerned. For he that would not have men consent
					but only act according to the fantasies which he presents
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.477"/>
					
					unto them&mdash;whether he be God or a wise man knows
					that the fantasies are sufficient for acting, and that consents
					are superfluous. For if, knowing that the imagination
					gives us not an instinct to work without consent, he ministers to us false and probable fantasies, he is the voluntary
					cause of our falling and erring by assenting to incomprehensible things.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>