<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De exilio</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.110">
      <body>
         <head>Of banishment, or flying one's country.</head>
         <pb id="v.3.p.15"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>ONE may say of discourses what they use to say of
				friends, that they are the best and firmest that afford their
				useful presence and help in calamities. Many indeed present themselves and discourse with those that are fallen
				into misfortunes, who yet do them more harm than good.
				Like men that attempt to succor drowning persons and
				have themselves no skill in diving under water, they entangle one another, and sink together to the bottom. The
				discourses of friends, such as would help an afflicted person,
				ought to be directed to the consolation, and not to the patronage of his sorrows. For we have no need in our distresses of such as may bear us company in weeping and
				howling, like a chorus in a tragedy, but of such as will
				deal freely with us, and will convince us that,&mdash;as it is in
				all cases vain and foolish and to no purpose to grieve and
				cast down one's self,&mdash;so, when the things themselves that
				afflict us, after a rational examination and discovery of what
				they are, give a man leave to say to himself thus,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou feel'st but little pain and smart,
				</l>
                     <l>Unless thou'lt feign and act a part,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>it would be extremely ridiculous for him not to put the
					question to his body, and ask it what it has suffered, nor to
					his soul, and ask how much worse it is become by this
					accident, but only to make use of those teachers of grief
					from abroad, who come to bear a part with him in his sorrow, or to express indignation at what has happened.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.16"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Let us therefore, when we are alone, question with
				ourselves concerning the things that have befallen us, considering them as heavy loads. The body, we know, is
				under pressure by a burden lying upon it; but the soul
				oft-times adds a further weight of her own to things. A
				stone is hard and ice is cold by nature, not by any thing
				from without happening to make such qualities and impressions upon them. But as for banishment and disgraces and
				loss of honors (and so for their contraries, crowns, chief
				rule, and precedency of place), our opinion prescribing the
				measure of our joys or sorrows and not the nature of the
				things themselves, every man makes them to himself light
				or heavy, easy to be borne or grievous. You may hear
				Polynices's answer to this question,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>JOCAST. But say, is't so deplorable a case
				</l>
                     <l>To live in exile from one's native place?
				</l>
                     <l>POLYN. It's sad indeed; and whatsoe'er you guess,
				</l>
                     <l>'Tis worse to endure than any can express.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 388 and 389.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But you may hear Alcman in quite another strain, as
					the epigrammatist has brought him in saying:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sardis, my ancient fatherland,
					</l>
                     <l>Hadst thou, by Fate's supreme command,
					</l>
                     <l>My helpless childhood nourished,
					</l>
                     <l>I must have begg'd my daily bread,
					</l>
                     <l>Or else, a beardless priest become,
					</l>
                     <l>Have toss'd Cybele frantic down.
					</l>
                     <l>Now Alcman I am call'd&mdash;a name
					</l>
                     <l>Inscribed in Sparta's lists of fame,
					</l>
                     <l>Whose many tripods record bear
					</l>
                     <l>Of solemn wreaths and tripods rare,
					</l>
                     <l>Achieved in worship at the shrine
					</l>
                     <l>Of Heliconian maids divine,
					</l>
                     <l>By whose great aid I'm mounted higher
					</l>
                     <l>Than Gyges or his wealthy sire.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This translation is taken from Burges's Greek Anthology, p. 470. It is there signed J. H. M. (G.)</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Thus one man's opinion makes the same thing commodious, like current money, and another man's unserviceable
					and hurtful.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.17"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>But let us grant (as many say and sing) that it is a
				grievous thing to be banished. So there are also many
				things that we eat, of a bitter, sharp, and biting taste, which
				yet by a mixture of other things more mild and sweet have
				all their unpleasantness taken off. There are also some
				colors troublesome to look upon, which bear so hard and
				strike so piercingly upon the sight, that they confound and
				dazzle it; if now by mixing shadows with them, or by turning our eyes upon some green and pleasant color, we remedy this inconvenience, thou mayst also do the same to the
				afflictions that befall thee, considering them with a mixture
				of those advantages and benefits thou still enjoyest, as wealth,
				friends, vacancy from business, and a supply of all things
				necessary to human life. For I think there are few Sardians but would desire to be in your condition, though banished, and would choose to live as you may do, though in a
				strange country, rather than&mdash;like snails that grow to their
				shells&mdash;enjoy no other good, saving only what they have
				at home without trouble.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>As he therefore in the comedy that advised his unfortunate friend to take heart and to revenge himself of Fortune, being asked which way, answered, By the help of
				philosophy; so we also may be revenged of her, by acting
				worthily like philosophers. For what course do we take
				when it is rainy weather, or a cold north wind blows? We
				creep to the fireside, or go into a bath, put on more clothes,
				or go into a dry house; and do not sit still in a shower and
				cry. It is in thy power above most men's to revive and
				cherish that part of thy life which seems to be chill and
				benumbed, not needing any other helps, but only according
				to thy best judgment and prudence making use of the
				things that thou possessest. The cupping-glasses physicians use, by drawing the worst humors out of the body,
				alleviate and preserve the rest; but they that are prone to
				grieve and make sad complaints, by mustering together
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.18"/>
				
				alway the worst of their afflictive circumstances, by debating these things over and over, being fastened (as it
				were) to their troubles, make the most advantageous things
				to be wholly useless to themselves, and especially when
				their case requires most help and assistance. As for those
				two hogsheads, my friend, which Homer says lie in heaven,
				full, the one of the good, the other of the ill fates of men,&mdash;
				it is not Jupiter that sits to draw out and transmit to some
				a moderate share of evils mixed with good, but to others
				only unqualified streams of evil; but it is we ourselves who
				do it. Those of us that are wise, drawing out of the good
				to temper with our evils, make our lives pleasant and potable; but the greater part (which are fools) are like sieves,
				which let the best pass through, but the worst and the very
				dregs of misfortune stick to them and remain behind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Wherefore, if we fall into any real evil or calamity,
				we must bring in what is pleasant and delightful of the
				remaining good things in our possession, and thus, by what
				we enjoy at home, mitigate the sense of those evils that
				befall us from abroad. But where there is no evil in the
				nature of the things, but the whole of that which afflicts
				us is framed by imagination and false opinion, in this case
				we must do just as we deal with children that are apt to
				be frighted with false faces and vizards; by bringing them
				nearer, and making them handle and turn then on every
				side, they are brought at last to despise them; so we, by
				a nearer touching and fixing our consideration upon our
				feigned evils, may be able to detect and discover the weakness and vanity of what we fear and so tragically deplore.</p>
            <p>Such is your present condition of being banished out of
					that which you account your country; for nature has given
					us no country, as it has given us no house or field, no smith's
					or apothecary's shop, as Ariston said; but every one of
					them is always made or rather called such a man's by his
					dwelling in it or making use of it. For man (as Plato says)
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.19"/>
					
					is not an earthly and unmovable, but a heavenly plant, the
					head raising the body erect as from a root, and directed
					upwards toward heaven.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Timaeus, p. 90 A.</note> Hence is that saying of Hercules:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Am I of Thebes or Argos? Whether
					</l>
                     <l>You please, for I'm content with either;
					</l>
                     <l>But to determine one, 'tis pity,
					</l>
                     <l>In Greece my country's every city.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But Socrates expressed it better, when he said, he was
					not an Athenian or a Greek, but a citizen of the world
					(just as a man calls himself a citizen of Rhodes or Corinth), because he did not enclose himself within the limits
					of Sunium, Taenarum, or the Ceraunian mountains.
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Behold how yonder azure sky,
					</l>
                     <l>Extending vastly wide and high
					</l>
                     <l>To infinitely distant spaces,
					</l>
                     <l>In her soft arms our earth embraces.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Frag. 935.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These are the boundaries of our country, and no man is
					an exile or a stranger or foreigner in these, where there is
					the same fire, water, air, the same rulers, administrators,
					and presidents, the same sun, moon, and daystar; where
					there are the same laws to all, and where, under one orderly disposition and government, are the summer and
					winter solstices, the equinoxes, Pleiades, Arcturus, times
					of sowing and planting; where there is one king and supreme ruler, which is God, who comprehends the beginning,
					the middle, and end of the universe; who passes through
					all things in a straight course, compassing all things according to nature: justice follows him to take vengeance on
					those that transgress the divine law, which justice we
					naturally all make use of towards all men, as being citizens
					of the same community.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But for thee to complain that thou dost not dwell at
				Sardis is no objection; for all the Athenians do not inhabit
				Collytus, nor do all the men of Corinth live in the Cranium, nor all of Lacedaemon in Pitane.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.20"/>
            <p>Do you look upon those Athenians as strangers and banished persons who removed from Melite to Diomea,&mdash;whence they called the month Metageitnion, and the sacrifices they offered in memory of their removal Metageitnia,
					being pleased with and cheerfully accepting this new
					neighborhood to another people? Surely you will not say
					so. What parts of the inhabited earth or of the whole
					earth can be said to be far distant one from another, when
					mathematicians demonstrate that the whole earth is to be
					accounted as an indivisible point, compared with the heavens? But we, like pismires or bees, when we are cast out
					of one ant-hill or hive, are in great anxiety, and take on as
					if we were strangers and undone, not knowing how to
					make and account all things our own, as indeed they are.
					We shall certainly laugh at his folly who shall affirm there
					was a better moon at Athens than at Corinth; and yet we
					in a sort commit the same error, when being in a strange
					country we look upon the earth, the sea, the air, the heavens doubtfully, as if they were not the same, but quite
					different from those we have been accustomed to. Nature
					in our first production sent us out free and loose; we bind
					and straiten and pin up ourselves in houses, and reduce
					ourselves into a scant and little room.</p>
            <p>Moreover, we laugh at the kings of Persia, who (if the
					story be true) will drink only the water of the River Choaspes, by this means making the rest of the habitable world
					to be without water, as to themselves; but we, when we
					remove to other countries, and retain our longings after
					Cephissus and Eurotas, and are pleased with nothing so
					much as the hills Taygetus and Parnassus, we make the
					whole earth unhabitable to ourselves, and are without a
					house or city where we can dwell.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>When certain Egyptians, not enduring the anger and
				hard usage of their king, went to dwell in Ethiopia, and
				some earnestly entreated them to return to their wives
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.21"/>
				
				and children they had left behind them, they very impudently showed them their privy parts, saying they should
				never want wives or children whilst they carried those
				about them. But it is more grave and becoming to say
				that whosoever happens to be provided with a competency
				of the necessaries to life, wheresoever he is, is not without
				a city or a dwelling, nor need reckon himself a stranger
				there; only he ought to have besides these prudence and
				consideration, like a governing anchor, that he may be able
				to make advantage of any port at which he arrives. It is
				not easy indeed for him that has lost his wealth quickly to
				gather it up again; but every city becomes presently that
				man's country who has the skill to use it, and who has
				those roots which can live and thrive, cling and grow to
				every place. Such had Themistocles, and such had Demetrius Phalareus; for this last named, after his banishment,
				being the prime friend of King Ptolemy in Alexandria, not
				only was abundantly provided for himself, but also sent
				presents to the Athenians. As for Themistocles, he was
				maintained by an allowance suitable to his quality at the
				King's charge, and is reported to have said to his wife and
				children, We had been undone, if we had not been undone.
				Diogenes the Cynic also, when one told him, The Sinopians
				have condemned thee to fly from Pontus, replied, And I
				have condemned them to stay in Pontus,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Close prisoners there to be,
				</l>
                     <l>At th' utmost shore of the fierce Euxine Sea.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Iph. Taur. 253.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Stratonicus enquiring of his host in the isle of Seriphus
					what crime among them was punished with banishment,
					and being told forgery was so punished, he asked him why
					he did not commit that crime that he might be removed
					out of that strait place; and yet there, as the comedian
					expresses it, they reap down their figs with slings, and
					that island is provided with all things that it wants.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.22"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>For if you consider the truth of things, setting aside
				vain fancy and opinion, he that has got an agreeable city
				to dwell in is a stranger and foreigner to all the rest, for it
				seems not reasonable and just, that leaving his own he
				should go to dwell in another city. As the proverb is,
				<q direct="unspecified">Sparta is the province fallen to your lot, adorn it,</q> though
				it should be in no credit or prove unhealthful, though disturbed with seditions, and its affairs in distemper and out
				of order. But as for him whom Fortune has deprived of
				his own habitation, it gives him leave to go and dwell
				where he pleases. That goad precept of the Pythagoreans, <q direct="unspecified">Make choice of the best life you can, and custom
					will make it pleasant,</q> is here also wise and useful. Choose
				the best and pleasantest place to live in, and time will
				make it thy country, and such a country as will not encumber and distract thee, not laying on thee such commands as these,&mdash;Bring in so much money; Go on such
				an embassy to Rome; Entertain such a governor; Bear
				such a public office. If a prudent person and no way
				conceited, calls these things to mind, he will choose to live
				in exile in such a sorry island as Gyarus, or in Cynarus
				that is <q direct="unspecified">so hard and barren and unfit for plantation,</q> and
				do this without reluctancy, not making such sorrowful complaints as the women do in the poet Simonides:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The troubled sea's dark waves surround me,
				</l>
                     <l>And with their horrid noise confound me;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but will rather remind himself of that saying of King
					Philip, who receiving a fall in a place of wrestling, when
					he turned himself in rising and saw the print of his body
					in the dust, exclaimed, Good God! what a small portion
					of earth has Nature assigned us, and yet we covet the
					whole world.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>I presume you have seen the island of Naxos, or at
				least the town of Hyria here hard by; in the former of
				which Ephialtes and Otus made their abode, and in the
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.23"/>
				
				latter Orion dwelt. Alcmaeon's seat was on the newly
				hardened mud which the river Achelous had cast up,&mdash;when he fled from the Furies, as the poets tell us,&mdash;but I
				guess it was when he fled from the rulers of the state and
				from seditions, and to avoid those furies, the sycophants
				and informers, that he chose that little spot of ground to
				dwell on, where he was free from business and lived in ease
				and quiet. Tiberius Caesar passed the last seven years of
				his life in the island of Capreae; and that sacred governing
				spirit that swayed the whole world, and was enclosed as it
				were in his breast, yet for so long time never removed nor
				changed place. And yet the thoughts and cares of the
				empire, that were poured in upon him and invaded him on
				every side, made that island's repose and retirement to be
				less pure and undisturbed to him. But he that by retreating to a small island can free himself from great evils
				is a miserable man, if he does not often say and sing those
				verses of Pindar to himself,&mdash;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where slender cypress grows I'd have a seat,
				</l>
                     <l>But care not for the shady woods of Crete!
				</l>
                     <l>I've little land and so not many trees,
				</l>
                     <l>But free from sorrow I enjoy much ease,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>not being disquieted with seditions or the edicts of princes,
					nor with administering affairs when the public is in straits,
					nor undergoing officers that are hard to be put by and
					denied.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>For if that be a good saying of Callimachus, that
				we ought not to measure wisdom by a Persian cord, much
				less should we measure happiness by cords of furlongs,
				or, if we chance to inhabit an island of two hundred furlongs and not (like Sicily) of four days' sail in compass,
				think that we ought to disquiet ourselves and lament as if
				we were very miserable and unfortunate. For what does a
				place of large extent contribute to the tranquillity of one's
				life? Do you not hear Tantalus saying in the tragedy:
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.24"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I sow the Berecyntian ground,
				</l>
                     <l>A field of twelve days' journey round?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But he says a little after:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>My mind, that used to mount the skies,
					</l>
                     <l>Fallen to the earth dejected lies,
					</l>
                     <l>And now this friendly counsel brings,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>Less to admire all earthly things.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Niobe of Aeschylus, Frag. 153 and 154.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nausithous, forsaking the spacious country of Hyperia
					because the Cyclops bordered upon it, and removing to an
					island far distant from all other people, chose there,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Remote from all commerce t' abide,
					</l>
                     <l>By sea's surrounding waves denied;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VI. 204.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and yet he procured a very pleasant way of living to his
					own citizens.</p>
            <p>The Cyclades islands were formerly inhabited by the
					children of Minos, and afterwards by the children of Codrus
					and Neleus; in which now fools that are banished thither
					think they are punished. And indeed, what island is there
					to which men are wont to be banished that is not larger
					than the land that lies about Scillus, in which Xenophon
					after his military expedition passed delicately his old age?
					The Academy near Athens, that was purchased for three
					thousand drachmas, was the place where Plato, Xenocrates, and Polemo dwelt; there they held their schools,
					and there they lived all their lifetime, except one day every
					year, when Xenocrates came into the city at the time of
					the Bacchanals and the new tragedies, to grace the feast,
					as they say. Theocritus of Chios reproached Aristotle,
					who affected a court-life with Philip and Alexander, that
					he chose instead of the Academy rather to dwell at the
					mouth of Borborus. For there is a river by Pella, which
					the Macedonians call by that name.</p>
            <p>But as for islands, Homer sets himself as it were studiously to commend them in these verses:
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.25"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He comes to the isle of Lemnos, and the town
					</l>
                     <l>Where divine Thoas dwelt, of great renown;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As much as fruitful Lesbos does contain,
					</l>
                     <l>A seat which Gods above do not disdain;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When he to th' lofty hills of Scyros came,
					</l>
                     <l>And took the town that boasts Enyeus's name;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>These from Dulichium and th' Echinades,
					</l>
                     <l>Blest isles, that lie 'gainst Elis, o'er the seas.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIV. 230; XXIV. 544; IX. 668; II. 625.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And among the famous men that dwelt in islands they
					reckon Aeolus, a great favorite of the Gods, the most prudent Ulysses, the most valiant Ajax, and Alcinous, the most
					courteous entertainer of strangers.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>When Zeno was told that the only ship he had
				remaining was cast away at sea with all her lading, he
				replied: Well done Fortune, that hast reduced me to the
				habit and life of a philosopher. And, indeed, a man that
				is not puffed up with conceit nor madly in love with a
				crowd will not, I suppose, have any reason to accuse
				Fortune for constraining him to live in an island, but will
				rather commend her for removing so much anxiety and
				agitation of his mind, for putting a stop to his rambles in
				foreign countries, to his dangers at sea, and the noise and
				tumult of the exchange, and for giving him a fixed, vacant,
				undisturbed life, such a life as he may truly call his own,
				describing as it were a circle about him, in which is contained the use of all things necessary. For what island is
				there that has not a horse, a walk, and a bath in it; that
				has not fishes and hares for such as delight in hunting and
				angling and such like sports? But the chiefest of all is,
				that the quiet which others thirst so much after thou commonly mayst have here without seeking. For those that
				are gamesters at dice, shutting up themselves at home,
				there are sycophants and busy spies that hunt them out,
				and prosecute them from their houses of pleasure and
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.26"/>
				
				gardens in the suburbs, and hale them by violence before
				the judges or the court. But none sails to an island to
				give a man any disturbance, no petitioner, no borrower, no
				urger to suretyship, no one that comes to beg his voice
				when he stands candidate for an office; only the best
				friends and familiars, out of good-will and desire to see
				him, may come over thither; and the rest of his life is
				safe and inviolable to him, if he has the will and the skill
				to live at case. But he that cries up the happiness of
				those that run about in other countries, or spend the most
				of their life in inns and passage-boats, is no wiser than he
				is that thinks the planets in a better estate than the fixed
				stars. And yet every planet rolling about in its proper
				sphere, as in an island, keeps its order. For the sun never
				transgresses its limited measures, as Heraclitus says; if it
				did do so, the Furies, which are the attendants of Justice,
				would find it out and punish it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>These things, my friend, and such like we say and
				sing to those who, by being banished into an island, have
				no correspondence or commerce with other people,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hindered by waves of the surrounding deep,
				</l>
                     <l>Which many 'gainst their mind close prisoners keep.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXI. 59.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But as for thee, who art not assigned to one place only,
					but forbidden only to live in one, the prohibiting thee one
					is the giving thee leave to dwell anywhere else besides.
					If on one hand it is urged thus against you: You are in
					no office, you are not of the senate, nor preside as moderator at the public games, you may oppose on the other
					hand thus: We head no factions, we make no expensive
					treats, nor give long attendance at the governor's gates;
					we care not at all who is chosen into our province, though
					he be choleric or unsufferably vexatious.</p>
            <p>But just as Archilochus disparaged the island of Thasos
					because of its asperity and inequality in some places,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.27"/>
					
					overlooking its fruitful fields and vineyards, saying thus
					of it,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Like ridge of ass's back it stood,
					</l>
                     <l>Full of wild plants, for nothing good;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so we, whilst we pore upon one part of banishment which
					is ignominious, overlook its vacancy from business, and
					that leisure and freedom it affords us.</p>
            <p>Men admired the happiness of the Persian kings, that
					passed their winter in Babylon, their summer in Media,
					and the pleasant spring-time at Susa. And he that is an
					exile may, if he pleases, when the mysteries of Ceres are
					celebrated, go and live at Eleusis; and he may keep the
					feasts of Bacchus at Argos; at the time of the Pythian
					games, he may pass over to Delphi, and of the Isthmian,
					to Corinth, if public spectacles and shows are the things
					he admires; if not, then he may be idle, or walk, or read,
					or sleep quietly; and you may add that privilege Diogenes
					bragged of when he said, <q direct="unspecified">Aristotle dines when it seems
						good to King Philip, but Diogenes when he himself pleases,</q>
					having no business, no magistrate, no prefect to interrupt
					and disturb his customary way of living.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>For this reason, you will find that very few of the
				most prudent and wise men were buried in their own
				country, but the most of them, when none forced them
				to it, weighed anchor and steered their course to live
				in another port, removing some to Athens, and others
				from it.</p>
            <p>Who ever gave a greater encomium of his own country
					than Euripides in the following verses?
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>We are all of this country's native race,
					</l>
                     <l>Not brought-in strangers from another place,
					</l>
                     <l>As some, like dice hither and thither thrown,
					</l>
                     <l>Remove in haste from this to t'other town.
					</l>
                     <l>And, if a woman may have leave to boast,
					</l>
                     <l>A temperate air breathes here in every coast;
					</l>
                     <l>We neither curse summer's immoderate heat,
					</l>
                     <l>Nor yet complain the winter's cold's too great.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.28"/>
            <p>
               <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>If aught there be that noble Greece doth yield,
				</l>
                     <l>Or Asia rich, by river or by field,
				</l>
                     <l>We seek it out and bring it to our doors.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet he that wrote all this went himself into Macedonia, and passed the rest of his days in the court of
					Archelaus. I suppose you have also heard of this short
					epigram:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here lieth buried Aeschylus, the son
					</l>
                     <l>Of the Athenian Euphorion;
					</l>
                     <l>In Sicily his latest breath did yield,
					</l>
                     <l>And buried lies by Gela's fruitful field.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For both he and Simonides before him went into Sicily.
					And whereas we meet with this title, <q direct="unspecified">This publication
						of the History of Herodotus of Halicarnassus,</q> many have
					changed it into Herodotus of Thurii, for he dwelt at
					Thurii, and was a member of that colony. And that
					sacred and divine poet Homer, that adorned the Trojan
					war,&mdash;why was he a controversy to so many cities (every
					one pleading he was theirs) but because he did not cry up
					any one of them to the disparagement of the rest? Many
					also and great are the honors that are paid to Jupiter
					Hospitalis.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>If any one object, that these men hunted ambitiously after glory and honor, let him go to the philosophers and the schools and nurseries of wisdom at Athens,
				those in the Lyceum, the Academy, the Stoa, the Palladium, the Odeum. If he admires and prefers the Peripatetic philosophy before the rest, Aristotle was a native
				of Stagira, Theophrastus of Ephesus, Straton of Lampsacus, Glycon of Troas, Ariston of Ceus, Critolaus of
				Phaselis. If thou art for the Stoic philosophy, Zeno was
				of Citium, Cleanthes of Assus, Chrysippus of Soli, Diogenes
				of Babylon, Antipater of Tarsus, and Archedemus who was
				of Athens went over to the Parthians, and left a succession of Stoic philosophers in Babylon. And who, I pray,
				persecuted and chased these men out of their country?
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.29"/>
				
				Nobody at all; but they pursued their own quiet, which
				men cannot easily enjoy at home that are in any reputation or have any power; other things they taught us by
				what they said, but this by what they (lid. For even now
				the most approved and excellent persons live abroad out
				of their own country, not being transported, but departing
				voluntarily, not being driven thence, but flying from business and from the disquiets and molestations which they
				are sure to meet with at home.</p>
            <p>It seems to me that the Muses helped the ancient
					writers to finish their choicest and most approved compositions, by calling in, as it were, banishment to their assistance. Thucydides the Athenian wrote the Peloponnesian and Athenian War in Thrace, hard by the forest of
					Scapte; Xenophon wrote his history in Scillus belonging
					to Elis; Philistus in Epirus, Timaeus of Tauromenum at
					Athens, Androtion the Athenian in Megara, Bacchylides
					the poet in Peloponnesus. These and many more, after
					they had lost their country, did not lose all hope nor were
					dejected in their minds, but took occasion thereupon to
					express the vivacity of their spirit and the dexterity of
					their wit, receiving their banishment at the hands of Fortune as a viaticum that she had sent them; whereby they
					became renowned everywhere after death, whereas there
					is no remaining mention of those factious persons that
					expelled them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>He therefore is ridiculous that looks upon it as an
				ignominious thing to be banished. For what is it that thou
				sayest? Was Diogenes ignominious, when Alexander,
				who saw him sitting and sunning himself, came and asked
				him whether he wanted any thing, and he answered him,
				that he lacked nothing but that he would go a little aside
				and not stand in his light? The king, admiring the presence of his mind, turned to his followers and said: If I
				were not Alexander, I would be Diogenes. Was Camillus
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.30"/>
				
				inglorious because he was expelled Rome, considering
				he has got the reputation of being its second founder?
				Neither did Themistocles by his banishment lose any of
				the renown he had gained in Greece, but added to it that
				which he had acquired among the barbarians; neither is
				there any so without all sense of honor, or of such an abject mind, that had not rather be Themistocles the banished, than Leobates that indicted him; or be Cicero that
				had the same fate, than Clodius that expelled him Rome;
				or be Timotheus that abandoned his country, than Aristophon that was his accuser.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>But because the words of Euripides move many, who
				seems to frame a heavy charge against banishment and to
				urge it home, let us see what he says more particularly in
				his questions and answers about it.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>JOCASTA. But is't so sad one's country to forego,
				</l>
                     <l>And live in exile? Pray, son, let me know.
				</l>
                     <l>POL. Some ills when told are great, when tried are less;
				</l>
                     <l>But this is saddest felt, though sad t' express.
				</l>
                     <l>JOC. What is't, I pray, afflicts the banished most?
				</l>
                     <l>POL. That liberty to speak one's mind is lost.
				</l>
                     <l>JOC. He is indeed a slave that dares not utter
				</l>
                     <l>His thoughts, nor 'gainst his cruel masters mutter.
				</l>
                     <l>POL. But all their insolencies must o'erpass,
				</l>
                     <l>And bear their follies tamely like an ass.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 388.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These assertions of his are neither good nor true. For
					first, not to speak what one thinks is not a piece of slavery;
					but it is the part of a prudent man to hold one's peace and
					be silent when time and the circumstances of affairs require it; as he himself says better elsewhere, that a wise
					man knows
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Both when it's best no tongue to find,
					</l>
                     <l>And when it's safe to speak his mind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Again, as for the rudeness and insolency of such as have
					power in their hands, they that stay in their country are
					no less forced to bear and endure it than those that are
					driven out of it; nay, commonly the former stand more in
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.31"/>
					
					fear of false informations and the violence of unjust rulers
					in cities than the latter. But his greatest mistake and
					absurdity is his taking away all freedom of speech from
					exiles. It is wonderful indeed if Theodorus had no freedom of this kind, who,&mdash;when King Lysimachus said to
					him: Thou being such a criminal, the country cast thee
					forth, did it not?&mdash;replied: Yes, not being able to bear
					me; just as Semele cast out Bacchus, when she could bear
					him no longer. And when the king showed him Telesphorus in an iron cage, with his eyes digged out of their
					holes, his nose and ears and tongue cut off, and said: So I
					deal with those that injure me, he was not abashed.
					What! did not Diogenes retain his wonted freedom of
					speaking, who coming into King Philip's camp, when he
					was going to give the Grecians battle, was brought before
					him for a spy; and confessed that he was so, but that he
					came to take a view of his unsatiable greediness of empire and of his madness and folly who was going in the
					short time of a fight to throw a die for his crown and
					life?</p>
            <p>And what say you to Hannibal the Carthaginian? Did
					not he use a convenient freedom towards Antiochus (he at
					that time an exile, and the other a king), when upon an
					advantageous occasion he advised him to give his enemies
					battle? He, when he had sacrificed, told him the entrails
					forbade it. Hannibal sharply rebuked him thus: You are
					for doing what the flesh of a beast, not what the reason of
					a wise man, adviseth.</p>
            <p>Neither does banishment deprive geometricians or mathematicians
					of the liberty of discoursing freely concerning
					matters they know and have skill in; and why should any
					worthy or good man be denied it? But meanness of
					thought obstructs and hinders the voice, strangles the
					power of speech, and makes a man a mute. But let us
					see what follows from Euripides:
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.32"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>JOC. Upon good hopes exiles can thrive, they say.
					</l>
                     <l>POL. Hopes have fine looks, but kill one with delay.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Phoeniss. 396.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>This is also an accusation of men's folly rather than of
					banishment; for it is not the well instructed and those that
					know how to use what they have aright, but such as depend upon what is to come and desire what they have not,
					that are carried and tossed up and down by hopes, as in a
					floating vessel, though they have scarce ever stirred beyond
					the gates of their own city. But to go on:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>JOC. Did not your father's friends aid your distress?
					</l>
                     <l>POL. Take care to thrive; for if you once are poor,
					</l>
                     <l>Those you call friends will know you then no more.
					</l>
                     <l>JOC. Did not your high birth stand you in some stead?
					</l>
                     <l>POL. It's sad to want, for honor buys no bread.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These also are ungrateful speeches of Polynices, who
					accuses banishment as casting disparagement upon noble
					birth and leaving a man without friends, who yet because
					of his high birth was thought worthy, though an exile, to
					have a king's daughter given him in marriage, and also by
					the powerful assistance of his friends gathered such an
					army as to make war against his own country, as he confesses himself a little after:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Many a famous Grecian peer
					</l>
                     <l>And captain from Mycenae here
					</l>
                     <l>'In readiness t' assist me tarry;
					</l>
                     <l>Sad service 'tis, but necessary.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Ibid.,</hi> 430 and 344</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Neither are the words of his lamenting mother any wiser:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No nuptial torch at all I lighted have
					</l>
                     <l>To thee, as doth a wedding-feast beseem;
					</l>
                     <l>No marriage-song was sung; nor thee to lave
					</l>
                     <l>Was water brought from fair Ismenus' stream.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>She ought to have been well pleased and rejoiced when
					she heard that her son dwelt in such kingly palaces; but,
					whilst she laments that the nuptial torch was not lighted,
					and the want of waters from Ismenus's river for him to
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.33"/>
					
					have bathed in (as if people at Argos were destitute both
					of fire and water at their weddings), she makes those evils,
					which her own conceit and folly produced, to be the effects
					of banishment.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>But is it not then an ignominious thing to be an exile? Yes, it is among fools, with whom it is a reproach to
				be poor, to be bald, or of low stature, and (with as much
				reason) to be a stranger or a pilgrim. But they that do not
				fall into these mistakes admire good men, though they happen to be poor or strangers or in exile. Do not we see the
				temple of Theseus venerated by all men, as well as the
				Parthenon and Eleusinium? And yet Theseus was banished from Athens, by whose means it is at this time
				inhabited; and lost his abode in that city, which he did
				not hold as a tenant, but himself built. And what remarkable thing is there remaining in Eleusis, if we are
				ashamed of Eumolpus, who coming thither from Thrace
				initiated the Greeks, and still does so, in the mysteries of
				religion? And whose son was Codrus, that reigned at
				Athens, but of that Melanthus who was banished from
				Messene? Will you not commend that speech of Antisthenes, who, when one said to him, Phrygia is thy mother,
				replied, She was also the mother of the Gods? And if
				any one reproach thee with thy banishment, why canst not
				thou answer, that the father of the great conqueror Hercules was an exile? And so was Cadmus the grandfather
				of Bacchus, who, being sent abroad in search for Europa,
				did return no more:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sprung from Phoenicia, to Thebes he came;
				</l>
                     <l>Thebes to his grandson Bacchus lays a claim,
				</l>
                     <l>Who there inspires with rage the female rout,
				</l>
                     <l>That worship him by running mad about.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Phryxus of Euripides, Frag. 816.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>As for those things which Aeschylus obscurely insinuates
					in that expression of his,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.34"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">And of Apollo, chaste God, banished heaven,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>I'll favor my tongue, as Herodotus phrases it, and say
					nothing.</p>
            <p>Empedocles, when he prefaces to his philosophy thus,&mdash;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This old decree of fate unchanged stands,&mdash;
					</l>
                     <l>Whoso with horrid crimes defiles his hands,
					</l>
                     <l>To long-lived Daemons this commission's given
					</l>
                     <l>To chase him many ages out of heaven.
					</l>
                     <l>Into this sad condition I am hurled,
					</l>
                     <l>Banished from God to wander through the world,&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>does not here only point at himself; but in what he
					says of himself he shows the condition of us all, that we
					are pilgrims and strangers and exiles here in this world.
					For know, says he, O men, that it is not blood nor a spirit
					tempered with it that gave being and beginning to the soul,
					but it is your terrestrial and mortal body that is made up
					of these. And by the soft name of pilgrimage, he insinuates the origin of the soul, that comes hither from another
					place. And the truth is, she flies and wanders up and down,
					being driven by the divine decrees and laws; and afterwards, as in an island surrounded with a great sea, as
					Plato speaks, she is tied and linked to the body, just like
					an oyster to its shell, and because she is not able to remember nor relate,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>From what a vast and high degree
					</l>
                     <l>Of honor and felicity</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>she has removed,&mdash;not from Sardis to Athens, not from
					Corinth to Lemnos or Scyros, but having changed heaven
					and the moon for earth and an earthly life,&mdash;if she is
					forced to make little removes here from place to place, the
					soul hereupon is ill at ease and troubled at her new and
					strange state, and hangs her head like a decaying plant.
					And indeed some one country is found to be more agreeable to a plant than another, in which it thrives and flourishes better; but no place can deprive a man of his happiness, unless he pleases, no more than of his virtue and
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.35"/>
					
					prudence. For Anaxagoras wrote his book of the Squaring of a Circle in prison; and Socrates, just when he was
					going to drink the poison that killed him, discoursed of
					philosophy, and exhorted his friends to the study of it;
					who then admired him as a happy man. But Pha&euml;ton
					and Tantalus, though they mounted up to heaven, yet,
					the poets tell us, through their folly fell into the extremest
					calamities.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>