<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Non posse suaviter vivi secundum Epicurum</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.139">
      <body>
         <head>That it is not possible to live pleasurably according to the doctrine of Epicurus. <lb/> Plutarch, Zeuxippus, Theon, Aristodemus.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.157"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>EPICURUS'S great confidant and familiar, Colotes, set
				forth a book with this title to it, that according to the tenets
				of the other philosophers it is impossible to live. Now
				what occurred to me then to say against him, in the defence of those philosophers, hath been already put into
				writing by me. But since upon breaking up of our lecture several things have happened to be spoken afterwards
				in the walks in further opposition to his party, I thought
				it not amiss to recollect them also, if for no other reason,
				yet for this one, that those who will needs be contradicting
				other men may see that they ought not to run cursorily
				over the discourses and writings of those they would disprove, nor by tearing out one word here and another there,
				or by falling foul upon particular passages without the
				books, to impose upon the ignorant and unlearned.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Now as we were leaving the school to take a walk
				(as our manner is) in the place of exercise, Zeuxippus
				began to us: In my opinion, said he, the debate was managed on our side with more softness and less freedom than
				was fitting. I am sure, Heraclides sufficiently signified
				his disgust at us at parting, for handling Epicurus and
				Metrodorus more roughly than they deserved. Yet you
				may remember, replied Theon, how you told them that
				Colotes himself, compared with the rhetoric of those two
				gentlemen, would appear the complaisantest man alive;
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.158"/>
				
				for when they have raked together the lewdest terms of
				ignominy the tongue of man ever used, as buffooneries,
				trollings, arrogancies, whorings, assassinations, whining
				counterfeits, vile seducers, and blockheads, they faintly
				throw them in the faces of Aristotle, Socrates, Pythagoras, Protagoras, Theophrastus, Heraclides, Hipparchus, and
				which not, even of the best and most celebrated authorities.
				So that, should they pass for very knowing men upon all
				other accounts, yet their very calumnies and reviling language would bespeak them at the greatest distance from
				philosophy imaginable. For emulation can never enter
				that God-like consort, nor such fretfulness as wants resolution to conceal its own resentments. Aristodemus then
				subjoined: Heraclides, you know, is a great philologist;
				and that may be the reason why he made Epicurus those
				amends for the poetic din (so that party style poetry) and
				for the fooleries of Homer; or else, it may be, it was because Metrodorus had libelled that poet in so many books.
				But let us let these gentlemen pass at present, Zeuxippus, and
				rather return to what was charged upon the philosophers
				in the beginning of our discourse, that it is impossible to
				live according to their tenets. And I see not why we two
				may not despatch this affair betwixt us, with the good assistance of Theon; for I find this gentleman (meaning me) is
				already tired. Then Theon said to him,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Our fellows have that garland from us won;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>therefore, if you please,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Let's fix another goal, and at that run.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XXII. 6.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>We will even prosecute them at the suit of the philosophers, in the following form: We'll prove, if we can, that
					it is impossible to live a pleasurable life according to their
					tenets. Bless me ! said I to him, smiling, you seem to me
					to level your foot at the very bellies of the men, and to
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.159"/>
					
					design to enter the list with them for their lives, whilst you
					go about to rob them thus of their pleasure, and they cry
					out to you,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Forbear, we're no good boxers, sir;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>no, nor good pleaders, nor good senators, nor good magistrates either;
					<quote rend="blockquote">Our proper talent is to eat and drink,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VIII. 246, 248.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and to excite such tender and delicate motions in our
					bodies as may chafe our imaginations to some jolly delight
					or gayety.&rdquo; And therefore you seem to me not so much to
					take off (as I may say) the pleasurable part, as to deprive
					the men of their very lives, while you will not leave them
					to live pleasurably. Nay then, said Theon, if you think
					so well of this subject-matter, why do you not set in hand
					to it? By all means, said I, I am for this, and shall not
					only hear but answer you too, if you shall require it. But
					I must leave it to you to take the lead.</p>
            <p>Then, after Theon had spoken something to excuse
					himself, Aristodemus said: When we had so short and
					fair a cut to our design, how have you blocked up the way
					before us, by preventing us from joining issue with the
					faction at the very first upon the single point of honesty!
					For you must grant, it can be no easy matter to drive men
					already possessed that pleasure is their utmost good yet to
					believe a life of pleasure impossible to be attained. But
					now the truth is, that just when they failed of living honestly they failed also of living pleasurably; for to live
					pleasurably without living honestly is even by themselves
					allowed inconsistent.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Theon then said: We may probably resume the consideration of that in the process of our discourse; in the
				interim we will make use of their concessions. Now they
				suppose their last good to lie about the belly and such
				other conveyances of the body as let in pleasure and not
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.160"/>
				
				pain; and are of opinion, that all the brave and ingenious
				inventions that ever have been were contrived at first for
				the pleasure of the belly, or the good hope of compassing
				such pleasure,&mdash;as the sage Metrodorus informs us. By
				which, my good friend, it is very plain, they found their
				pleasure in a poor, rotten, and unsure thing, and one that
				is equally perforated for pains, by the very passages they
				receive their pleasures by; or rather indeed, that admits
				pleasure but by a few, but pain by all its parts. For the
				whole of pleasure is in a manner in the joints, nerves, feet,
				and hands; and these are oft the seats of very grievous
				and lamentable distempers, as gouts, corroding rheums,
				gangrenes, and putrid ulcers. And if you apply to yourself the exquisitest of perfumes or gusts, you will find but
				some one small part of your body is finely and delicately
				touched, while the rest are many times filled with anguish
				and complaints. Besides, there is no part of us proof
				against fire, sword, teeth, or scourges, or insensible of
				dolors and aches; yea, heats, colds, and fevers sink into
				all our parts alike. But pleasures, like gales of soft wind,
				move simpering, one towards one extreme of the body and
				another towards another, and then go off in a vapor. Nor
				are they of any long durance, but, as so many glancing
				meteors, they are no sooner kindled in the body than they
				are quenched by it. As to pain, Aeschylus's Philoctetes
				affords us a sufficient testimony:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The cruel viper ne'er will quit my foot;
				</l>
                     <l>Her dire envenomed teeth have there ta'en root.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For pain will not troll off as pleasure doth, nor imitate it
					in its pleasing and tickling touches. But as the clover
					twists its perplexed and winding roots into the earth, and
					through its coarseness abides there a long time; so pain
					disperses and entangles its hooks and roots in the body,
					and continues there, not for a day or a night, but for several seasons of years, if not for some revolutions of Olympiads,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.161"/>
					
					 nor scarce ever departs unless struck out by other
					pains, as by stronger nails. For who ever drank so long as
					those that are in a fever are adry? Or who was ever so
					long eating as those that are besieged suffer hunger? Or
					where are there any that are so long solaced with the conversation of friends as tyrants are racking and tormenting?
					Now all this is owing to the baseness of the body and its
					natural incapacity for a pleasurable life; for it bears pains
					better than it doth pleasures, and with respect to those is
					firm and hardy, but with respect to these is feeble and soon
					palled. To which add, that if we are minded to discourse
					on a life of pleasure, these men won't give us leave to go
					on, but will presently confess themselves that the pleasures
					of the body are but short, or rather indeed but of a moment's continuance; if they do not design to banter us or
					else speak out of vanity, when Metrodorus tells us, We
					many times spit at the pleasures of the body, and Epicurus
					saith, A wise man, when he is sick, many times laughs at
					the very extremity of his distemper.</p>
            <p>With what consistence then can those that account the
					pains of the body so light and easy think so highly of its
					pleasures? For should we allow them not to come behind
					its pains either in duration or magnitude, they would not
					yet have their being without them. For Epicurus hath
					made the removal of all that pains the common definition
					of all pleasure; as if Nature had intended to advance the
					pleasurable part only to the destruction of the painful, but
					would not have it improved any further in magnitude,
					and as if she only diverted herself with certain useless diversifications after she hath once arrived to an abolition
					of pain. But now the passage to this, conjoined with an
					appetence which is the measure of pleasure, is extremely
					short and soon over. And therefore the sense of their
					narrow entertainment here hath obliged them to transplant
					their last end from the body, as from a poor and lean soil,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.162"/>
					
					to the mind, in hopes of enjoying there, as it were, large
					pastures and fair meadows of delights and satisfactions.
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For Ithaca is no fit place
					</l>
                     <l>For mettled steeds to run a race.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. IV. 605.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Neither can the joys of our poor bodies be smooth and
					equal; but on the contrary they must be coarse and harsh,
					and immixed with much that is displeasing and inflamed.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Zeuxippus then said: And do you not think then
				they take the right course to begin at the body, where
				they observe pleasure to have its first rise, and thence to
				pass to the mind as the more stable and sure part, there to
				complete and crown the whole?</p>
            <p>They do, by Jove, I said; and if, after removing thither,
					they have indeed found something more consummate than
					before, they take a course too as well agreeing with nature
					as becoming men adorned with both contemplative and
					civil knowledge. But if after all this you still hear them
					cry out, and protest that the mind of man can receive no
					satisfaction or tranquillity from any thing under Heaven
					but the pleasures of the body either in possession or expectance, and that these are its proper and only good, can
					you forbear thinking they make use of the soul but as a
					funnel for the body, while they mellow their pleasure by
					shifting it from one vessel to another, as they rack wine
					out of an old and leaky vessel into a new one and there
					let it grow old, and then imagine they have performed
					some extraordinary and very fine thing? True indeed,
					time may both keep and recover wine that hath thus been
					drawn off; but the mind, receiving but the remembrance
					only of past pleasure, like a kind of scent, retains that
					and no more. For as soon as it hath given one hiss in
					the body, it immediately expires, and that little of it that
					stays behind in the memory is but flat and like a queasy
					fume; as if a man should lay up and treasure in his fancy
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.163"/>
					
					what he either ate or drank yesterday, that he may have
					recourse to that when he wants fresh fare. See now how
					much more temperate the Cyrenaics are, who, though they
					have drunk out of the same bottle with Epicurus, yet will
					not allow men so much as to practise their amours by
					candle-light, but only under the covert of the dark, for
					fear seeing should fasten too quick an impression of the
					images of such actions upon the fancy and thereby too
					frequently inflame the desire. But these gentlemen account it the highest accomplishment of a philosopher to
					have a clear and retentive memory of all the various
					figures, passions, and touches of past pleasure. We will
					not now say, they present us with nothing worthy the
					name of philosophy, while they leave the refuse of pleasure in their wise man's mind, as if it could be a lodging
					for bodies; but that it is impossible such things as these
					should make a man live pleasurably, I think is abundantly manifest from hence.</p>
            <p>For it will not perhaps seem strange if I assert, that the
					memory of pleasure past brings no pleasure with it if it
					seemed but little in the very enjoyment, or to men of such abstinence as to account it for their benefit to retire from its
					first approaches; when even the most amazed and sensual
					admirers of corporeal delights remain no longer in their
					gaudy and pleasant humor than their pleasure lasts them.
					What remains is but an empty shadow and dream of that
					pleasure that hath now taken wing and is fled from them,
					and that serves but for fuel to foment their untamed desires.
					Like as in those that dream they are adry or in love, their
					unaccomplished pleasures and enjoyments do but excite the
					inclination to a greater keenness. Nor indeed can the
					remembrance of past enjoyments afford them any real contentment at all, but must serve only, with the help of a
					quick desire, to raise up very much of outrage and stinging
					pain out of the remains of a feeble and befooling pleasure.
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.164"/>
					
					Neither doth it befit men of continence and sobriety to exercise their thoughts about such poor things, or to do what
					one twitted Carneades with, to reckon, as out of a diurnal,
					how oft they have lain with Hedia or Leontion, or where
					they last drank Thasian wine, or at what twentieth-day
					feast they had a costly supper. For such transport and
					captivatedness of the mind to its own remembrances as
					this is would show a deplorable and bestial restlessness and
					raving towards the present and hoped-for acts of pleasure.
					And therefore I cannot but look upon the sense of these
					inconveniences as the true cause of their retiring at last to
					a freedom from pain and a firm state of body; as if living
					pleasurably could lie in bare imagining this either past or
					future to some persons. True indeed it is, <q direct="unspecified">that a sound
						state of body and a good assurance of its continuing must
						needs afford a most transcending and solid satisfaction to
						all men capable of reasoning.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But yet look first what work they make, while they
				course this same thing&mdash;whether it be pleasure, exemption from pain, or good health&mdash;up and down, first from
				the body to the mind, and then back again from the mind
				to the body, being compelled to return it to its first origin,
				lest it should run out and so give them the slip. Thus
				they pitch the pleasure of the body (as Epicurus says)
				upon the complacent joy in the mind, and yet conclude
				again with the good hopes that complacent joy hath in
				bodily pleasure. Indeed what wonder is it if, when the
				foundation shakes, the superstructure totter? Or that there
				should be no sure hope nor unshaken joy in a matter that
				suffers so great concussion and changes as continually attend a body exposed to so many violences and strokes from
				without, and having within it the origins of such evils as
				human reason cannot avert? For if it could, no understanding man would ever fall under stranguries, gripes,
				consumptions, or dropsies; with some of which Epicurus
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.165"/>
				
				himself did conflict and Polyaenus with others, while
				others of them were the deaths of Neocles and Agathobulus. And this we mention not to disparage them, knowing
				very well that Pherecydes and Heraclitus, both very excellent persons, labored under very uncouth and calamitous
				distempers. We only beg of them, if they will own their
				own diseases and not by noisy rants and popular harangues
				incur the imputation of false bravery, either not to take the
				health of the whole body for the ground of their content,
				or else not to say that men under the extremities of dolors
				and diseases can yet rally and be pleasant. For a sound
				and hale constitution of body is indeed a thing that often
				happens, but a firm and steadfast assurance of its continuance can never befall any intelligent mind. But as at sea
				(according to Aeschylus)
				<quote rend="blockquote">Night to the ablest pilot trouble brings,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus, Suppliants, 770.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and so will a calm too, for no man knows what will be,&mdash;
					so likewise is it impossible for a soul that dwells in a healthful body, and that places her good in the hopes she hath of
					that body, to perfect her voyage here without flights or
					waves. For man's mind hath not, like the sea, its tempests
					and storms only from without it, but it also raises up from
					within far more and greater disturbances. And a man may
					with more reason look for constant fair weather in the midst
					of winter than for perpetual exemption from afflictions in
					his body. For what else hath given the poets occasion to
					term us creatures of a day, uncertain and unfixed, and
					to liken our lives to leaves that both spring and fall in the
					compass of a summer, but the unhappy, calamitous, and
					sickly condition of the body, whose very utmost good we
					are warned to dread and prevent For an exquisite habit,
					Hippocrates saith, is slippery and hazardous. And
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>He that but now looked jolly, plump, and stout,
					</l>
                     <l>Like a star shot by Jove, is now gone out;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.166"/>
            <p>as it is in Euripides. And it is a vulgar persuasion, that
					very handsome persons, when looked upon, oft suffer damage by envy and an evil eye; for (it is said) a body at its
					utmost vigor will through delicacy very soon admit of
					changes.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But now that these men are miserably unprovided for
				an undisturbed life, you may discern even from what they
				themselves advance against others. For they say that those
				who commit wickedness and incur the displeasure of the
				laws live in constant misery and fear, for, though they may
				perhaps attain to privacy, yet it is impossible they should
				ever be well assured of that privacy; whence the ever-impending fear of the future will not permit them to have
				either complacency or assurance in their present circumstances. But they consider not how they speak all this
				against themselves. For a sound and healthy state of body
				they may indeed oftentimes possess, but that they should
				ever be well assured of its continuance is impossible; and
				they must of necessity be in constant disquiet and pain for
				the body with respect to futurity, never succeeding in at
				taining to that firm and steadfast assurance from it which
				they expect. But to do no wickedness will contribute nothing to our assurance; for it is not suffering justly but
				suffering in itself that is dismaying. Nor can it be a matter of trouble to be engaged in villanies one's self, and not
				afflictive to suffer by the villanies of others. Neither can
				it be said that the tyranny of Lachares was less, if it was
				not more, calamitous to the Athenians, and that of Dionysius to the Syracusans, than they were to the tyrants themselves; for it was disturbing that made them be disturbed;
				and their first oppressing and pestering of others gave them
				occasion to expect to suffer ill themselves. Why should a
				man recount the outrages of rabbles, the barbarities of
				thieves, or the villanies of inheritors, or yet the contagions
				of airs and the concursions of seas, by which Epicurus (as
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.167"/>
				
				himself writeth) was in his voyage to Lampsacus within
				very little of drowning? The very composition of the
				body&mdash;it containing in it the matter of all diseases, and
				(to use a pleasantry of the vulgar) cutting thongs for the
				beast out of its own hide, I mean pains out of the body&mdash;is sufficient to render life perilous and uneasy, and that to
				the good as well as to the bad, if they have learned to place
				their complacence and assurance in the body and the hopes
				they have of it, and in nothing else; as Epicurus hath
				written, as well in many other of his discourses as in that
				of Man's End.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>They therefore assign not only a treacherous and unsure ground of their pleasurable living, but also one in all
				respects despicable and little, if the escaping of evils be
				the matter of their complacence and last good. But now
				they tell us, nothing else can be so much as imagined, and
				nature hath no other place to bestow her good in but only
				that out of which her evil hath been driven; as Metrodorus
				speaks in his book against the Sophists. So that this single
				thing, to escape evil, he says, is the supreme good; for
				there is no room to lodge this good in where nothing of
				what is painful and afflicting goes out. Like unto this is
				that of Epicurus, where he saith: The very essence of
				good arises from the escaping of bad, and a man's recollecting, considering, and rejoicing within himself that this hath
				befallen him. For what occasions transcending joy (he
				saith) is some great impending evil escaped; and in this
				lies the very nature and essence of good, if a man attain
				unto it aright, and contain himself when he hath done, and
				not ramble and prate idly about it. Oh the rare satisfaction
				and felicity these men enjoy, that can thus rejoice for having undergone no evil and endured neither sorrow nor pain!
				Have they not reason, think you, to value themselves for
				such things as these, and to talk as they are wont when
				they style themselves immortals and equals to Gods?&mdash;and
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.168"/>
				
				when, through the excessiveness and transcendency of the
				blessed things they enjoy, they rave even to the degree of
				whooping and hollowing for very satisfaction that, to the
				shame of all mortals, they have been the only men that could
				find out this celestial and divine good that lies in an exemption from all evil So that their beatitude differs little
				from that of swine and sheep, while they place it in a mere
				tolerable and contented state, either of the body, or of the
				mind upon the body's account. For even the wiser and
				more ingenious sort of brutes do not esteem escaping of
				evil their last end; but when they have taken their repast,
				they are disposed next by fulness to singing, and they divert themselves with swimming and flying; and their gayety
				and sprightliness prompt them to entertain themselves with
				attempting to counterfeit all sorts of voices and notes; and
				then they make their caresses to one another, by skipping
				and dancing one towards another; nature inciting them,
				after they have escaped evil, to look after some good, or
				rather to shake off what they find uneasy and disagreeing,
				as an impediment to their pursuit of something better and
				more congenial.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>For what we cannot be without deserves not the name
				of good; but that which claims our desire and preference
				must be something beyond a bare escape from evil. And
				so, by Jove, must that be too that is either agreeing or congenial to us, according to Plato, who will not allow us to
				give the name of pleasures to the bare departures of sorrows
				and pains, but would have us look upon them rather as
				obscure draughts and mixtures of agreeing and disagreeing,
				as of black and white, while the extremes would advance
				themselves to a middle temperament. But oftentimes unskilfulness and ignorance of the true nature of the extreme
				occasions some to mistake the middle temperament for the
				extreme and outmost part. Thus do Epicurus and Metrodorus, while they make avoiding of evil to be the very
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.169"/>
				
				essence and consummation of good, and so receive but as
				it were the satisfaction of slaves or of rogues newly discharged the gaol, who are well enough contented if they
				may but wash and supple their sores and the stripes they
				received by whipping, but never in their lives had one taste
				or sight of a generous, clean, unmixed, and unulcerated
				joy. For it follows not that, if it be vexatious to have
				one's body itch or one's eyes to run, it must be therefore a
				blessing to scratch one's self, and to wipe one's eye with a
				rag; nor that, if it be bad to be dejected or dismayed at
				divine matters or to be discomposed with the relations
				of hell, therefore the bare avoiding of all this must be
				some happy and amiable thing. The truth is, these men's
				opinion, though it pretends so far to outgo that of the vulgar, allows their joy but a straight and narrow compass to
				toss and tumble in, while it extends it but to an exemption
				from the fear of hell, and so makes that the top of acquired
				wisdom which is doubtless natural to the brutes. For if
				freedom from bodily pain be still the same, whether it come
				by endeavor or by nature, neither then is an undisturbed
				state of mind the greater for being attained to by industry
				than if it came by nature. Though a man may with good
				reason maintain that to be the more confirmed habit of the
				mind which naturally admits of no disorder, than that which
				by application and judgment eschews it.</p>
            <p>But let us suppose them both equal; they will yet appear not one jot superior to the beasts for being unconcerned at the stories of hell and the legends of the Gods,
					and for not expecting endless sorrows and everlasting torments hereafter. For it is Epicurus himself that tells us that,
					had our surmises about celestial things and our foolish apprehensions of death and the pains that ensue it given us no
					disquiet, we had not then needed to contemplate nature for
					our relief. For neither have the brutes any weak surmises of
					the Gods or fond opinions about things after death to disorder
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.170"/>
					
					 themselves with; nor have they as much as imagination or notion that there is any thing in these to be
					dreaded. I confess, had they left us the benign providence of God as a presumption, wise men might then
					seem, by reason of their good hopes from thence, to have
					something towards a pleasurable life that beasts have not.
					But now, since they have made it the scope of all their
					discourses of God that they may not fear him, but may be
					eased of all concern about him, I much question whether
					those that never thought at all of him have not this in a
					more confirmed degree than they that have learned to think
					he can do no harm. For if they were never freed from
					superstition, they never fell into it; and if they never laid
					aside a disturbing conceit of God, they never took one up.
					The like may be said as to hell and the future state. For
					though neither the Epicurean nor the brute can hope for
					any good thence; yet such as have no forethought of death
					at all cannot but be less amused and scared with what
					comes after it than they that betake themselves to the principle that death is nothing to us. But something to them
					it must be, at least so far as they concern themselves to
					reason about it and contemplate it; but the beasts are
					wholly exempted from thinking of what appertains not to
					them; and if they fly from blows, wounds, and slaughters,
					they fear no more in death than is dismaying to the Epicurean himself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Such then are the things they boast to have attained by their philosophy. Let us now see what those
				are they deprive themselves of and chase away from them.
				For those diffusions of the mind that arise from the body,
				and the pleasing condition of the body, if they be but
				moderate, appear to have nothing in them that is either
				great or considerable; but if they be excessive, besides
				their being vain and uncertain, they are also importune
				and petulant; nor should a man term them either mental
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.171"/>
				
				satisfactions or gayeties, but rather corporeal gratifications,
				they being at best but the simperings and effeminacies
				of the mind. But now such as justly deserve the names of
				complacencies and joys are wholly refined from their contraries, and are immixed with neither vexation, remorse,
				nor repentance; and their good is congenial to the mind
				and truly mental and genuine, and not superinduced. Nor
				is it devoid of reason, but most rational, as springing either
				from that in the mind that is contemplative and enquiring,
				or else from that part of it that is active and heroic. How
				many and how great satisfactions either of these affords
				us, he that would can never relate. But to hint briefly at
				some of them. We have the historians before us, which,
				though they find us many and delightful exercises, still
				leave our desire after truth insatiate and uncloyed with
				pleasure, through which even lies are not without their
				grace. Yea, tales and poetic fictions, while they cannot
				gain upon our belief, have something in them that is
				charming to us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>For do but think with yourself, with what a sting
				we read Plato's Atlantic and the conclusion of the Iliad,
				and how we hanker and gape after the rest of the tale, as
				when some beautiful temple or theatre is shut up. But
				now the informing of ourselves with the truth herself is
				a thing so delectable and lovely as if our very life and
				being were for the sake of knowing. And the darkest and
				grimmest things in death are its oblivion, ignorance, and
				obscurity. Whence, by Jove, it is that almost all mankind
				encounter with those that would destroy the sense of the
				departed, as placing the very whole of their life, being,
				and satisfaction solely in the sensible and knowing part of
				the mind. For even the things that grieve and afflict us
				yet afford us a sort of pleasure in the hearing. And it is
				often seen that those that are disordered by what is told
				them, even to the degree of weeping, notwithstanding
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.172"/>
				
				require the telling of it. So he in the tragedy who is
				told,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Alas! I now the very worst must tell,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>replies,
					<quote rend="blockquote">I dread to hear it too, but I must hear.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Oed. Tyr. 1169, 1170.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But this may seem perhaps a sort of intemperateness of
					delight in knowing every thing, and as it were a stream
					violently bearing down the reasoning faculty. But now,
					when a story that hath in it nothing that is troubling and
					afflictive treats of great and heroic enterprises with a potency and grace of style such as we find in Herodotus's
					Grecian and in Xenophon's Persian history, or in what,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Inspired by heavenly Gods, sage Homer sung,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>or in the Travels of Eudoxus, the Foundations and Republics of Aristotle, and the Lives of Famous Men compiled
					by Aristoxenus;&mdash;these will not only bring us exceeding
					much and great contentment, but such also as is clean and
					secure from repentance. And who could take greater satisfaction either in eating when a-hungry or drinking when
					a-dry amongst the Phaeacians, than in going over Ulysses's
					relation of his own voyage and rambles? And what man
					could be better pleased with the embraces of the most
					exquisite beauty, than with sitting up all night to read
					over what Xenophon hath written of Panthea, or Aristobulus of Timoclea, or Theopompus of Thebe?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>But now these appertain all solely to the mind. But
				they chase away from them the delights that accrue from
				the mathematics also. Though the satisfactions we receive
				from history have in them something simple and equal,
				but those that come from geometry, astronomy, and music
				inveigle and allure us with a sort of nimbleness and variety,
				and want nothing that is tempting and engaging; their
				figures attracting us as so many charms, whereof whoever
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.173"/>
				
				hath once tasted, if he be but competently skilled, will
				run about singing that in Sophocles,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'm mad; the Muses with new rage inspire me.
				</l>
                     <l>I'll mount the hill; my lyre, my numbers fire me.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Thamyras of Sophocles, Frag. 225.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nor doth Thamyras break out into poetic raptures upon
					any other score; nor, by Jove, Eudoxus, Aristarchus, or
					Archimedes. And when the lovers of the art of painting
					are so enamored with the charmingness of their own performances, that Nicias, as he was drawing the Evocation
					of Ghosts in Homer, often asked his servants whether he
					had dined or no, and when King Ptolemy had sent him
					threescore talents for his piece, after it was finished, he
					neither would accept the money nor part with his work;
					what and how great satisfactions may we then suppose to
					have been reaped from geometry and astronomy by Euclid
					when he wrote his Dioptrics, by Philippus when he had
					perfected his demonstration of the figure of the moon, by
					Archimedes when with the help of a certain angle he had
					found the sun's diameter to make the same part of the
					largest circle that that angle made of four right angles,
					and by Apollonius and Aristarchus who were the inventors
					of some other things of the like nature? The bare contemplating and comprehending of these now engender in
					the learners both unspeakable delights and a marvellous
					height of spirit. And it doth in no wise beseem me, by
					comparing with these the fulsome debauchees of victualling-houses and stews, to contaminate Helicon and the
					Muses,&mdash;
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where swain his flock ne'er fed,
					</l>
                     <l>Nor tree by hatchet bled.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 75.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But these are the verdant and untrampled pastures of ingenious bees; but those are more like the mange of lecherous boars and he-goats. And though a voluptuous
					temper of mind be naturally fantastic and precipitate, yet
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.174"/>
					
					never any yet sacrificed an ox for joy that he had gained
					his will of his mistress; nor did any ever wish to die immediately, might he but once satiate himself with the
					costly dishes and comfits at the table of his prince. But
					now Eudoxus wished he might stand by the sun, and inform himself of the figure, magnitude, and beauty of that
					luminary, though he were, like Phaethon, consumed by it.
					And Pythagoras offered an ox in sacrifice for having completed the lines of a certain geometric diagram; as Apollodotus tells us,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When the famed lines Pythagoras devised,
					</l>
                     <l>For which a splendid ox he sacrificed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it was that by which he showed that the [square of
					the] line that regards the right angle in a triangle is equivalent to the [squares of the] two lines that contain that angle,
					or the problem about the area of the parabolic section of a
					cone. And Archimedes's servants were forced to hale him
					away from his draughts, to be anointed in the bath; but
					he notwithstanding drew the lines upon his belly with his
					strigil. And when, as he was washing (as the story goes
					of him), he thought of a manner of computing the proportion of gold in King Hiero's crown by seeing the water
					flowing over the bathing-stool, he leaped up as one possessed or inspired, crying, <q direct="unspecified">I have found it</q> (<foreign lang="greek">eu(/rhka</foreign>); which
					after he had several times repeated, he went his way. But
					we never yet heard of a glutton that exclaimed with such
					vehemence, <q direct="unspecified">I have eaten,</q> or of an amorous gallant that
					ever cried, <q direct="unspecified">I have kissed,</q> among the many millions of dissolute debauchees that both this and preceding ages have
					produced. Yea, we abominate those that make mention
					of their great suppers with too luscious a gust, as men
					overmuch taken with mean and abject delights. But we
					find ourselves in one and the same ecstasy with Eudoxus,
					Archimedes, and Hipparchus; and we readily give assent
					to Plato when he saith of the mathematics, that while ignorance
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.175"/>
					
					 and unskilledness make men despise them, they
					still thrive notwithstanding by reason of their charming
					ness, in despite of contempt.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>These then so great and so many pleasures, that
				run like perpetual springs and rills, these men decline and
				avoid; nor will they permit those that put in among them
				so much as to take a taste of them, but bid them hoist up
				the little sails of their paltry cock-boats and fly from them.
				Nay, they all, both he and she philosophers, beg and entreat Pythocles, for dear Epicurus's sake, not to affect or
				make such account of the sciences called liberal. And
				when they cry up and defend one Apelles, they write of
				him that he kept himself clean by refraining himself all
				along from the mathematics. But as to history&mdash;to pass
				over their aversedness to other kinds of compositions&mdash;I
				shall only present you with the words of Metrodorus, who
				in his treatise of the Poets writes thus: Wherefore let it
				never disturb you, if you know not either what side Hector
				was of, or the first verses in Homer's Poem, or again what
				is in its middle. But that the pleasures of the body
				spend themselves like the winds called Etesian or Anniversary, and utterly determine when once age is past its
				vigor, Epicurus himself was not insensible; and there
				fore he makes it a problematic question, whether a sage
				philosopher, when he is an old man and disabled for enjoyment, may not still be recreated with having handsome
				girls to feel and grope him, being not, it seems, of the
				mind of old Sophocles, who thanked God he had at length
				escaped from this kind of pleasure, as from an untame and
				furious master. But, in my opinion, it would be more advisable for these sensual lechers, when they see that age
				will dry up so many of their pleasures, and that, as Euripides saith,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Dame Venus is to ancient men a foe,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Aeolus, Frag. 23.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.176"/>
            <p>in the first place to collect and lay up in store, as against a
					siege, these other pleasures, as a sort of provision that will
					not impair and decay; that then, after they have celebrated
					the venereal festivals of life, they may spend a cleanly after
					feast in reading over the historians and poets, or else in
					problems of music and geometry. For it would never have
					come into their minds so much as to think of these purblind and toothless gropings and spurtings of lechery, had
					they but learned, if nothing more, to write comments upon
					Homer or Euripides, as Aristotle, Heraclides, and Dicaearchus did. But I verily persuade myself that their neglecting to take care for such provisions as these, and finding
					all the other things they employed themselves in (as they
					use to say of virtue) but insipid and dry, and being wholly
					set upon pleasure, and the body no longer supplying them
					with it, give them occasion to stoop to do things both mean
					and shameful in themselves and unbecoming their age; as
					well when they refresh their memories with their former
					pleasures and serve themselves of old ones (as it were)
					long since dead and laid up in pickle for the purpose,
					when they cannot have fresh ones, as when again they
					offer violence to nature by suscitating and kindling in their
					decayed bodies, as in cold embers, other new ones equally
					senseless, they having not, it seems, their minds stored
					with any congenial pleasure that is worth the rejoicing at.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>As to the other delights of the mind, we have already
				treated of them, as they occurred to us. But their aversedness and dislike to music, that affords us so great delights and such charming satisfactions, a man could not
				forget if he would, by reason of the inconsistency of what
				Epicurus saith, when he pronounceth in his book called
				his Doubts that his wise man ought to be a lover of public spectacles and to delight above any other man in the
				music and shows of the Bacchanals; and yet he will not
				admit of music problems or of the critical enquiries of
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.177"/>
				
				philologists, no, not so much as at a compotation. Yea,
				he advises such princes as are lovers of the Muses rather
				to entertain themselves at their feasts either with some
				narration of military adventures or with the importune
				scurrilities of drolls and buffoons, than to engage in disputes about music or in questions of poetry. For this
				very thing he had the face to write in his treatise of
				Monarchy, as if he were writing to Sardanapalus, or to
				Nanarus satrap of Babylon. For neither would a Hiero
				nor an Attalus nor an Archelaus be persuaded to make a
				Euripides, a Simonides, a Melanippides, a Crates, or a
				Diodotus rise up from their tables, and to place such
				scaramuchios in their rooms as a Cardax, an Agrias, or
				a Callias, or fellows like Thrasonides and Thrasyleon, to
				make people disorder the house with hollowing and clapping. Had the great Ptolemy, who was the first that
				formed a consort of musicians, but met with these excellent and royal admonitions, would he not, think you, have
				thus addressed himself to the Samians:
				<quote rend="blockquote">O Muse, whence art thou thus maligned?</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For certainly it can never belong to any Athenian to be
					in such enmity and hostility with the Muses. But
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No animal accurst by Jove
					</l>
                     <l>Music's sweet charms can ever love.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, Pyth. I. 25.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>What sayest thou now, Epicurus? Wilt thou get thee up
					betimes in the morning, and go to the theatre to hear the
					harpers and flutists play? But if a Theophrastus discourse at the table of Concords, or an Aristoxenus of
					Varieties, or if an Aristophanes play the critic upon Homer, wilt thou presently, for very dislike and abhorrence,
					clap both thy hands upon thy ears? And do they not
					hereby make the Scythian king Ateas more musical than
					this comes to, who, when he heard that admirable flutist
					Ismenias, detained then by him as a prisoner of war, playing
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.178"/>
					
					 upon the flute at a compotation, swore he had rather
					hear his own horse neigh? And do they not also profess
					themselves to stand at an implacable and irreconcilable
					defiance with whatever is generous and becoming ? And
					indeed what do they ever embrace or affect that is either
					genteel or regardable, when it hath nothing of pleasure
					to accompany it? And would it not far less affect a pleasurable way of living, to be disgusted with perfumes and
					odors, like beetles and vultures, than to shun and abhor
					the conversation of learned critics and musicians? For
					what flute or harp ready tuned for a lesson, or
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What sweetest consort e'er with artful noise,
					</l>
                     <l>Warbled by softest tongue and best tuned voice,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>ever gave Epicurus and Metrodorus such content as the
					disputes and precepts about consorts gave Aristotle, Theophrastus, Hieronymus, and Dicaearchus? And also the
					problems about flutes, rhythms, and harmonies; as, for
					instance, why the slenderer of two flutes of the same
					longitude should speak flatter?&mdash;why, if you raise the
					pipe, will all its notes be sharp; and flat again, if you
					lower it?&mdash;and why, when clapped to another, will it
					sound flatter; and sharper again, when taken from it?&mdash;
					why also, if you scatter chaff or dust about the orchestra
					of a theatre, will the sound be softened?&mdash;and why,
					when one would have set up a bronze Alexander for a
					frontispiece to a stage at Pella, did the architect advise to
					the contrary, because it would spoil the actors' voices ?&mdash;
					and why, of the several kinds of music, will the chromatic
					diffuse and the harmonic compose the mind ? But now
					the several humors of poets, their differing turns and
					forms of style, and the solutions of their difficult places,
					have conjoined with a sort of dignity and politeness somewhat also that is extremely agreeable and charming; insomuch that to me they seem to do what was once said
					by Xenophon, to make a man even forget the joys of
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.179"/>
					
					love, so powerful and overcoming is the pleasure they
					bring us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Of all this these gentlemen have not the least
				share, nor do they so much as pretend or desire to have
				any. But while they are sinking and depressing their
				contemplative part into the body, and dragging it down
				by their sensual and intemperate appetites, as by so many
				weights of lead, they make themselves appear little better
				than hostlers or graziers that still ply their cattle with
				hay, straw, or grass, looking upon such provender as the
				properest and meetest food for them. And is it not even
				thus they would swill the mind with the pleasures of the
				body, as hogherds do their swine, while they will not
				allow it can be gay any longer than it is hoping, feeling,
				or remembering something that refers to the body; but
				will not have it either to receive or seek for any congenial joy or satisfaction from within itself? Though what
				can be more absurd and unreasonable than&mdash;when there
				are two things that go to make up the man, a body and
				a soul, and the soul besides hath the prerogative of governing&mdash;that the body should have its peculiar, natural,
				and proper good, and the soul none at all, but must sit
				gazing at the body and simper at its passions, as if she
				were pleased and affected with them, though indeed she
				be all the while wholly untouched and unconcerned, as
				having nothing of her own to choose, desire, or take delight in? For they should either pull off the vizor quite,
				and say plainly that man is all body (as some of them do,
				that take away all mental being), or, if they will allow us
				to have two distinct natures, they should then leave to
				each its proper good and evil, agreeable and disagreeable;
				as we find it to be with our senses, each of which is peculiarly adapted to its own sensible, though they all very
				strangely intercommune one with another. Now the intellect is the proper sense of the mind; and therefore
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.180"/>
				
				that it should have no congenial speculation, movement,
				or affection of its own, the attaining to which should be
				matter of complacency to it, is the most irrational thing
				in the world, if I have not, by Jove, unwittingly done the
				men wrong, and been myself imposed upon by some that
				may perhaps have calumniated them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Then I said to him: If we may be your judges, you
				have not; yea, we must acquit you of having offered them
				the least indignity; and therefore pray despatch the rest
				of your discourse with assurance. How! said he, and
				shall not Aristodemus then succeed me, if you are tired
				out yourself? Aristodemus said: With all my heart,
				when you are as much tired as he is; but since you are
				yet in your vigor, pray make use of yourself, my noble
				friend, and don't think to pretend weariness. Theon then
				replied: What is yet behind, I must confess, is very easy;
				it being but to go over the several pleasures contained in
				that part of life that consists in action. Now themselves
				somewhere say that there is far more satisfaction in doing
				than in receiving good; and good may be done many times,
				it is true, by words, but the most and greatest part of
				good consists in action, as the very name of beneficence
				tells us and they themselves also attest. For you may
				remember, continued he, we heard this gentleman tell us
				but now what words Epicurus uttered, and what letters
				he sent to his friends, applauding and magnifying Metrodorus,&mdash;how bravely and like a spark he quitted the
				city and went down to the port to relieve Mithrus the
				Syrian,&mdash;and this, though Metrodorus did not then do
				any thing at all. What and how great then may we presume the pleasures of Plato to have been, when Dion by
				the measures he gave him deposed the tyrant Dionysius
				and set Sicily at liberty? And what the pleasures of
				Aristotle, when he rebuilt his native city Stagira, then
				levelled with the ground, and brought back its exiled inhabitants?
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.181"/>
				
				 And what the pleasures of Theophrastus and
				of Phidias, when they cut off the tyrants of their respective countries For what need a man recount to you,
				who so well know it, how many particular persons they
				relieved, not by sending them a little wheat or a measure
				of meal (as Epicurus did to some of his friends), but by
				procuring restoration to the banished, liberty to the imprisoned, and restitution of wives and children to those
				that had been bereft of them? But a man could not, if
				he would, pass by the sottish stupidity of the man who,
				though he tramples under foot and vilifies the great and
				generous actions of Themistocles and Miltiades, yet writes
				these very words to his friends about himself: <q direct="unspecified">You have
					given a very gallant and noble testimony of your care of
					me in the provision of corn you have made for me, and
					have declared your affection to me by signs that mount
					to the very skies.</q> So that, should a man but take that
				poor parcel of corn out of the great philosopher's epistle,
				it might seem to be the recital of some letter of thanks
				for the delivery or preservation of all Greece or of the
				commons of Athens.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>We will now forbear to mention that Nature requires
				very large and chargeable provisions to be made for accomplishing the pleasures of the body; nor can the height
				of delicacy be had in barley bread and lentil pottage. But
				voluptuous and sensual appetites expect costly dishes, Thasian wines, perfumed unguents, and varieties of pastry
				works,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And cakes by female hands wrought artfully,
				</l>
                     <l>Well steep'd in th' liquor of the gold-wing'd bee;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Cressae of Euripides, Frag. 470.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and besides all this. handsome young lassies too, such as
					Leontion, Boidion, Hedia, and Nicedion, that were wont
					to roam about in Epicurus's philosophic garden. But now
					such joys as suit the mind must undoubtedly be grounded
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.182"/>
					
					upon a grandeur of actions and a splendor of worthy deeds,
					if men would not seem little, ungenerous, and puerile, but
					on the contrary, bulky, firm, and brave. But for a man to
					be elated with pleasures, as Epicurus is, like tarpaulins
					upon the festivals of Venus, and to vaunt himself that,
					when he was sick of an ascites, he notwithstanding called
					his friends together to certain collations and grudged not
					his dropsy the satisfaction of good liquors, and that, when
					he called to remembrance the last words of Neocles, he
					was melted with a peculiar sort of joy intermixed with
					tears,&mdash;no man in his right senses would call these true
					joys or satisfactions. Nay, I will be bold to say that, if
					such a thing as that they call a sardonic or grinning laughter can happen to the mind, it is to be found in these forcings and crying laughters. But if any will needs have them
					still called by the name of joys and satisfactions, let him
					but yet think how far they are exceeded by the pleasures
					that here ensue:
					<quote rend="blockquote">Our counsels have proud Sparta's glory clipt;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Stranger, this is his country Rome's great star;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again this,
					<quote rend="blockquote">I know not which to guess thee, man or God.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Now when I set before my eyes the brave achievements of
					Thrasybulus and Pelopidas, of Aristides engaged at Plataea
					and Miltiades at Marathon, I am here constrained with
					Herodotus to declare it my opinion, that in an active state
					of life the pleasure far exceeds the glory. And Epaminondas herein bears me witness also, when he saith (as is
					reported of him), that the greatest satisfaction he ever received in his life was that his father and mother had lived
					to see the trophy set up at Leuctra when himself was general. Let us then compare with Epaminondas's Epicurus's
					mother, rejoicing that she had lived to see her son cooping
					himself up in a little garden, and getting children in common
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.183"/>
					
					 with Polyaenus upon the strumpet of Cyzicus. As
					for Metrodorus's mother and sister, how extravagantly rejoiced they were at his nuptials appears by the letters he
					wrote to his brother in answer to his; that is, out of his own
					books. Nay, they tell us bellowing that they have not
					only lived a life of pleasure, but also exult and sing hymns
					in the praise of their own living. Now, when our servants
					celebrate the festivals of Saturn or go in procession at the
					time of the rural bacchanals, you would scarcely brook the
					hollowing and din they make, should the intemperateness
					of their joy and their insensibleness of decorum make them
					act and speak such things as these:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lean down, boy ! why dost sit! let's tope like mad !
					</l>
                     <l>Here's belly-timber store; ne'er spare it, lad.
					</l>
                     <l>Straight these huzza like wild. One fills up drink;
					</l>
                     <l>Another plaits a wreath, and crowns the brink
					</l>
                     <l>O' th' teeming bowl. Then to the verdant bays
					</l>
                     <l>All chant rude carols in Apollo's praise;
					</l>
                     <l>While one his door with drunken fury smites,
					</l>
                     <l>Till he from bed his pretty consort frights.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And are not Metrodorus's words something like to these
					when he writes to his brother thus: It is none of our business to preserve the Greeks, or to get them to bestow garlands upon us for our wit, but to eat well and drink good
					wine, Timocrates, so as not to offend but pleasure our
					stomachs. And he saith again, in some other place in the
					same epistles: How gay and how assured was I, when I
					had once learned of Epicurus the true way of gratifying
					my stomach; for, believe me, philosopher Timocrates, our
					prime good lies at the stomach.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>In brief, these men draw out the dimensions of their
				pleasures like a circle, about the stomach as a centre.
				And the truth is, it is impossible for those men ever to
				participate of generous and princely joy, such as enkindles
				a height of spirit in us and sends forth to all mankind an
				unmade hilarity and calm serenity, that have taken up a
				sort of life that is confined, unsocial, inhuman, and uninspired
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.184"/>
				
				 towards the esteem of the world and the love of
				mankind. For the soul of man is not an abject, little, and
				ungenerous thing, nor doth it extend its desires (as polyps
				do their claws) unto eatables only,&mdash;yea, these are in
				an instant of time taken off by the least plenitude,&mdash;
				but when its efforts towards what is brave and generous and the honors and caresses that accrue therefrom are now in their consummate vigor, this life's duration cannot limit them, but the desire of glory and
				the love of mankind grasp at whole eternity, and wrestle
				with such actions and charms as bring with then an
				ineffable pleasure, and such as good men, though never so
				fain, cannot decline, they meeting and accosting them on
				all sides and surrounding them about, while their being
				beneficial to many occasions joy to themselves.
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As he passes through the throngs in the city,
				</l>
                     <l>All gaze upon him as some Deity.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VIII. 173.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For he that can so affect and move other men as to fill
					them with joy and rapture, and to make them long to
					touch him and salute him, cannot but appear even to a
					blind man to possess and enjoy very extraordinary satisfactions in himself. And hence it comes that such men are
					both indefatigable and undaunted in serving the public,
					and we still hear some such words from them:
					<quote rend="blockquote">Thy father got thee for the common good;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and
					<quote rend="blockquote">Let's not give off to benefit mankind.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>But what need I instance in those that are consummately
					good? For if to one of the middling rank of bad men,
					when he is just a dying, he that hath the power over him
					(whether his God or prince) should but allow one hour
					more, upon condition that, after he hath spent that either
					in some generous action or in sensual enjoyment, he should
					then presently die, who would in this time choose rather to
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.185"/>
					
					accompany with Lais or drink Ariusian wine, than to despatch Archias and restore the Thebans to their liberties?
					For my part I believe none would. For I see that even
					common sword-players, if they are not utter brutes and savages, but Greek born, when they are to enter the list,
					though there be many and very costly dishes set before
					them, yet take more content in employing their time in
					commending their poor wives to some of their friends, yea,
					and in conferring freedom on their slaves, than in gratifying their stomachs. But should the pleasures of the body be
					allowed to have some extraordinary matter in them, this
					would yet be common to men of action and business.
					<quote rend="blockquote">For they can eat good meat, and red wine drink,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Il. V. 341.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>aye, and entertain themselves with their friends, and perhaps with a greater relish too, after their engagements and
					hard services,&mdash;as did Alexander and Agesilaus, and (by
					Jove) Phocion and Epaminondas too,&mdash;than these gentlemen who anoint themselves by the fireside, and are gingerly rocked about the streets in sedans. Yea, those make
					but small account of such pleasures as these, as being
					comprised in those greater ones. For why should a man
					mention Epaminondas's denying to sup with one, when he
					saw the preparations made were above the man's estate,
					but frankly telling his friend, <q direct="unspecified">I thought you had intended
						a sacrifice and not a debauch,</q> when Alexander himself
					refused Queen Ada's cooks, telling her he had better ones
					of his own, to wit, travelling by night for his dinner, and
					a light dinner for his supper, and when Philoxenus writing to him about some handsome boys, and desiring to
					know of him whether he would have him buy them for
					him, was within a small matter of being discharged his
					office for it? And yet who might better have them than
					he? But as Hippocrates saith that of two pains the lesser
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.186"/>
					
					is obscured by the greater, so the pleasures that accrue
					from action and the love of glory, while they cheer and refresh the mind, do by their transcendency and grandeur obliterate and extinguish the inferior satisfactions of the body.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>If then the remembering of former good things (as
				they affirm) be that which most contributes to a pleasurable living, not one of us will then credit Epicurus when
				he tells us that, while he was dying away in the midst of
				the strongest agonies and distempers, he yet bore himself
				up with the memory of the pleasures he formerly enjoyed.
				For a man may better see the resemblance of his own face
				in a troubled deep or a storm, than a smooth and smiling
				remembrance of past pleasure in a body tortured with
				such lancing and rending pains. But now the memories
				of past actions no man can put from him that would.
				For did Alexander, think you, (or indeed could he possibly) forget the fight at Arbela ? Or Pelopidas the tyrant
				Leontiadas ? Or Themistocles the engagement at Salamis?
				For the Athenians to this very day keep an annual festival
				for the battle at Marathon, and the Thebans for that at
				Leuctra; and so, by Jove, do we ourselves (as you very
				well know) for that which Daiphantus gained at Hyampolis, and all Phocis is filled with sacrifices and public
				honors. Nor is there any of us that is better satisfied
				with what himself hath either eaten or drunk than he
				is with what they have achieved. It is very easy then to
				imagine what great content, satisfaction, and joy accompanied the authors of these actions in their lifetime, when
				the very memory of them hath not yet after five hundred
				years and more lost its rejoicing power. The truth is,
				Epicurus himself allows there are some pleasures derived
				from fame. And indeed why should he not, when he himself had such a furious lechery and wriggling after glory
				as made him not only to disown his masters and scuffle
				about syllables and accents with his fellow-pedant Democritus
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.187"/>
				
				 (whose doctrines he stole verbatim), and to tell his
				disciples there never was a wise man in the world besides
				himself, but also to put it in writing how Colotes performed adoration to him, as he was one day philosophizing,
				by touching his knees, and that his own brother Neocles
				was used from a child to say, <q direct="unspecified">There neither is, nor ever
					was in the world, a wiser man than Epicurus,</q> and that
				his mother had just so many atoms within her as, when
				they came together, must have produced a complete wise
				man? May not a man then&mdash;as Callicratidas once said
				of the Athenian admiral Conon, that he whored the sea&mdash;
				as well say of Epicurus that he basely and covertly forces
				and ravishes Fame, by not enjoying her publicly but ruffling and debauching her in a corner? For as men's bodies
				are oft necessitated by famine, for want of other food, to
				prey against nature upon themselves, a like mischief to this
				does vain-glory create in men's minds, forcing them, when
				they hunger after praise and cannot obtain it from other
				men, at last to commend themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>And do not they then that stand so well affected
				towards applause and fame themselves own they cast away
				very extraordinary pleasures, when they decline magistrature, public offices, and the favor and confidences of princes,
				from whom Democritus once said the grandest blessings of
				human life are derived? For he will never induce any mortal
				to believe, that he that could so highly value and please
				himself with the attestation of his brother Neocles and the
				adoration of his friend Colotes would not, were he clapped
				by all the Greeks at the Olympiads, go quite out of his
				wits and even hollow for joy, or rather indeed be elated
				in the manner spoken of by Sophocles,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Puffed like the down of a gray-headed thistle.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>If it be a pleasing thing then to be of a good fame, it is on
					the contrary afflictive to be of an ill one; and it is most
					certain that nothing in the world can be more infamous
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.188"/>
					
					than want of friendship, idleness, atheism, debauchery,
					and negligence. Now these are looked upon by all men
					except themselves as inseparable companions of their
					party. But unjustly, some one may say. Be it so then;
					for we consider not now the truth of the charge, but what
					fame and reputation they are of in the world. And we
					shall forbear at present to mention the many books that
					have been written to defame them, and the blackening
					decrees made against them by several republics; for that
					would look like bitterness. But if the answers of oracles,
					the providence of the Gods, and the tenderness and affection of parents to their issue,&mdash;if civil policy, military
					order, and the office of magistracy be things to be looked
					upon as deservedly esteemed and celebrated, it must of
					necessity then be allowed also, that they that tell us it is
					none of their business to preserve the Greeks, but they
					must eat and drink so as not to offend but pleasure their
					stomachs, are base and ignominious persons, and that their
					being reputed such must needs extremely humble them
					and make their lives untoward to them, if they take honor
					and a good name for any part of their satisfaction.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>When Theon had thus spoken, we thought good to
				break up our walk to rest us awhile (as we were wont
				to do) upon the benches. Nor did we continue any long
				space in our silence at what was spoken; for Zeuxippus,
				taking his hint from what had been said, spake to us:
				Who will make up that of the discourse which is yet behind? For it hath not yet received its due conclusion;
				and this gentleman, by mentioning divination and providence, did in my opinion suggest as much to us; for these
				people boast that these very things contribute in no small
				degree to the providing of their lives with pleasure, serenity, and assurance; so that there must be something said
				to these too. Aristodemus subjoined then and said: As to
				pleasure, I think there hath been enough said already
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.189"/>
				
				to evince that, supposing their doctrine to be successful
				and to attain its own design, it yet doth but ease us of fear
				and a certain superstitious persuasion, but helps us not to
				any comfort or joy from the Gods at all; nay, while it
				brings us to such a state as to be neither disquieted nor
				pleased with them, it doth but render us in the same
				manner affected towards them as we are towards the
				Scythians or Hyrcanians, from whom we expect neither
				good nor harm. But if something more must yet be
				added to what hath been already spoken, I think I may
				very well take it from themselves. And in the first place,
				they quarrel extremely with those that would take away
				all sorrowing, weeping, and sighing for the death of
				friends, and tell them that such unconcernedness as arrives
				to an insensibility proceeds from some other worse cause,
				to wit, inhumanity, excessive vain-glory, or prodigious
				fierceness, and that therefore it would be better to be a
				little concerned and affected, yea, and to liquor one's eyes
				and be melted, with other pretty things of the like kind,
				which they use foppishly to affect and counterfeit, that
				they may be thought tender and loving-hearted people.
				For just in this manner Epicurus expressed himself upon
				the occasion of the death of Hegesianax, when he wrote
				to Dositheus the father and to Pyrson the brother of the
				deceased person; for I fortuned very lately to run over his
				epistles. And I say, in imitation of them, that atheism is
				no less an evil than inhumanity and vain-glory, and into
				this they would lead us who take away with God's anger
				the comfort we might derive from him. For it would be
				much better for us to have something of the unsuiting
				passion of dauntedness and fear conjoined and intermixed
				with our sentiments of a Deity, than while we fly from it,
				to leave ourselves neither hope, comfort, nor assurance in
				the enjoyment of our good things, nor any recourse to
				God in our adversity and misfortunes.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.190"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>We ought, it is true, to remove superstition from the
				persuasion we have of the Gods, as we would the gum
				from our eyes; but if that be impossible, we must not
				root out and extinguish with it the belief which the most
				have of the Gods; nor is that a dismaying and sour one
				either, as these gentlemen feign, while they libel and
				abuse the blessed Providence, representing her as a hobgoblin or as some fell and tragic fury. Yea, I must tell
				you, there are some in the world that fear God in an excess, for whom yet it would not be better not so to fear
				him. For, while they dread him as a governor that is
				gentle to the good and severe to the bad, and are by this
				one fear, which makes them not to need many others,
				freed from doing ill and brought to keep their wickedness with them in quiet and (as it were) in an enfeebled
				languor, they come hereby to have less disquiet than those
				that indulge the practice of it and are rash and daring in
				it, and then presently after fear and repent of it. Now
				that disposition of mind which the greater and ignorant
				part of mankind, that are not utterly bad, are of towards
				God, hath, it is very true, conjoined with the regard and
				honor they pay him, a kind of anguish and astonished
				dread, which is also called superstition; but ten thousand
				times more and greater than this are the good hope and
				true joy that attend it, which both implore and receive
				the whole benefit of prosperity and good success from
				the Gods only. And this is manifest by the greatest
				tokens that can be; for neither do the discourses of those
				that wait at the temples, nor the good times of our
				solemn festivals, nor any other actions or sights more
				recreate and delight us than what we see and do about the
				Gods ourselves, while we assist at the public ceremonies,
				and join in the sacred balls, and attend at the sacrifices
				and initiations. For the mind is not then sorrowful, demiss, and heavy, as she would be if she were addressing
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.191"/>
				
				to certain tyrants or cruel torturers; but on the contrary,
				where she is most apprehensive and fullest persuaded the
				Divinity is present, there she most of all throws off sorrows, tears, and pensiveness, and lets herself loose to
				what is pleasing and agreeable, to the very degree of tipsiness, frolic, and laughter. In amorous concerns, as the
				poet said once,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When old man and old wife think of love's fires,
				</l>
                     <l>Their frozen breasts will swell with new desires;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>but now in the public processions and sacrifices not only
					the old man and the old wife, nor yet the poor and mean
					man only, but also
					<quote rend="blockquote">The dusty thick-legged drab that turns the mill,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and household-slaves and day-laborers, are strangely elevated and transported with mirth and jovialty. Rich men
					as well as princes are used at certain times to make public entertainments and to keep open houses; but the
					feasts they make at the solemnities and sacrifices, when
					they now apprehend their minds to approach nearest the
					Divinity, have conjoined with the honor and veneration
					which they pay him a much more transcending pleasure
					and satisfaction. Of this, he that hath renounced God's
					providence hath not the least share; for what recreates
					and cheers us at the festivals is not the store of good
					wine and roast meat, but the good hope and persuasion
					that God is there present and propitious to us, and kindly
					accepts of what we do. From some of our festivals we
					exclude the flute and garland; but if God be not present
					at the sacrifice, as the solemnity of the banquet, the rest
					is but unhallowed, unfeast-like, and uninspired. Indeed
					the whole is but ungrateful and irksome to such a man;
					for he asks for nothing at all, but only acts his prayers
					and adorations for fear of the public, and utters expressions contradictory to his philosophy. And when he sacrifices, he stands by and looks upon the priest as he kills
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.192"/>
					
					the offering but as he doth upon a butcher; and when
					he hath done, he goes his way, saying with Menander,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To bribe the Gods I sacrificed my best,
					</l>
                     <l>But they ne'er minded me nor my request.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For such a mien Epicurus would have us to put on, and
					neither to envy nor to incur the hatred of the common
					sort by doing ourselves with displeasure what others do
					with delight. For, as Evenus saith,
					<quote rend="blockquote">No man can love what he is made to do.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>For which very reason they think the superstitious are
					not pleased in their minds but in fear while they attend
					at the sacrifices and mysteries; though they themselves are
					in no better condition, if they do the same things out of
					fear, and partake not either of as great good hope as the
					others do, but are only fearful and uneasy lest they should
					come to be discovered cheating and abusing the public,
					upon whose account it is that they compose the books
					they write about the Gods and the Divine Nature,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Involved, with nothing truly said,
					</l>
                     <l>But all around enveloped;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>hiding out of fear the real opinions they contain.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>And now, after the two former ranks of ill and
				common men, we will in the third place consider the best
				sort and most beloved of the Gods, and what great satisfactions they receive from their clean and generous sentiments of the Deity, to wit, that he is the Prince of all
				good things and the Parent of all things brave, and can
				no more do an unworthy thing than he can be made to
				suffer it. For he is good, and he that is good can upon
				no account fall into envy, fear, anger, or hatred; for it is
				not proper to a hot thing to cool, but to heat; nor to a
				good thing to do harm. Now anger is by nature at the
				farthest distance imaginable from complacency, and spleenishness from placidness, and animosity and turbulence from
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.193"/>
				
				humanity and kindness. For the latter of these proceed
				from generosity and fortitude, but the former from impotency and baseness. The Deity is not therefore constrained by either anger or kindnesses; but that is because it is natural to it to be kind and aiding, and
				unnatural to be angry and hurtful. But the great Jove,
				whose mansion is in heaven and who drives his winged
				chariot, is the first that descends downwards and orders
				all things and takes the care of them. But of the other
				Gods one is surnamed the Distributer, and another the
				Mild, and a third the Averter of Evil. And according to
				Pindar,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Apollo was by mighty Jove designed
				</l>
                     <l>Of all the Gods to be to man most kind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And Diogenes saith, that all things are the Gods', and
					friends have all things common, and good men are the
					Gods' friends; and therefore it is impossible either that a
					man beloved of the Gods should not be happy, or that a
					wise and a just man should not be beloved of the Gods.
					Can you think then that they that take away Providence
					need any other chastisement, or that they have not a sufficient one already, when they root out of themselves such
					vast satisfaction and joy as we that stand thus affected
					towards the Deity have? Metrodorus, Polyaenus, and
					Aristobulus were the confidence and rejoicing of Epicurus; the better part of whom he all his lifetime either
					attended upon in their sicknesses or lamented at their
					deaths. So did Lycurgus, when he was saluted by the
					Delphic prophetess,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Dear friend to heavenly Jove and all the Gods.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And did Socrates when he believed that a certain Divinity
					was used out of kindness to discourse him, and Pindar
					when he heard Pan sing one of the sonnets he had composed, but a little rejoice, think you? Or Phormio, when
					he thought he had treated Castor and Pollux at his
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.194"/>
					
					house ? Or Sophocles, when he entertained Aesculapius,
					as both he himself believed, and others too, that thought
					the same with him by reason of the apparition that then
					happened? What opinion Hermogenes had of the Gods
					is well worth the recounting in his very own words.
					<q direct="unspecified">For these Gods,</q> saith he, <q direct="unspecified">who know all things and
						can do all things, are so friendly and loving to me that,
						because they take care of me, I never escape them either
						by night or by day, wherever I go or whatever I am
						about. And because they know beforehand what issue
						every thing will have, they signify it to me by sending
						angels, voices, dreams, and presages.</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>Very amiable things must those be that come to us
				from the Gods; but when these very things come by the
				Gods too, this is what occasions vast satisfaction and unspeakable assurance, a sublimity of mind and a joy that,
				like a smiling brightness, doth as it were gild over our
				good things with a glory. But now those that are persuaded otherwise obstruct the very sweetest part of their
				prosperity, and leave themselves nothing to turn to in their
				adversity; but when they are in distress, look only to this
				one refuge and port, dissolution and insensibility; just as
				if in a storm or tempest at sea, some one should, to hearten
				the rest, stand up and say to them: Gentlemen, the ship
				hath never a pilot in it, nor will Castor and Pollux come
				themselves to assuage the violence of the beating waves or
				to lay the swift careers of the winds; yet I can assure you
				there is nothing at all to be dreaded in all this, for the
				vessel will be immediately swallowed up by the sea, or else
				will very quickly fall off and be dashed in pieces against
				the rocks. For this is Epicurus's way of discourse to persons under grievous distempers and excessive pains. Dost
				thou hope for any good from the Gods for thy piety ? It
				is thy vanity; for the blessed and incorruptible Being is
				not constrained by either angers or kindnesses. Dost thou
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.195"/>
				
				fancy something better after this life than what thou hast
				here? Thou dost but deceive thyself; for what is dissolved
				hath no sense, and that which hath no sense is nothing to
				us. Aye; but how comes it then, my good friend, that
				you bid me eat and be merry ? Why, by Jove, because he
				that is in a great storm cannot be far off a shipwreck ; and
				your extreme peril will soon land you upon Death's strand.
				Though yet a passenger at sea, when he is got off from a
				shattered ship, will still buoy himself up with some little
				hope that he may drive his body to some shore and get out
				by swimming; but now the poor soul, according to these
				men's philosophy,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Has no escape beyond the hoary main.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. V. 410.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, she presently evaporates, disperses, and perishes, even
					before the body itself; so that it seems her great and excessive rejoicing must be only for having learned this one
					sage and divine maxim, that all her misfortunes will at
					last determine in her own destruction, dissolution, and annihilation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>But (said he, looking upon me) I should be impertinent, should I say any thing upon this subject, when we have
				heard you but now discourse so fully against those that
				would persuade us that Epicurus's doctrine about the soul
				renders men more disposed and better pleased to die than
				Plato's doth. Zeuxippus therefore subjoined and said:
				And must our present debate be left then unfinished because of that? Or shall we be afraid to oppose that
				divine oracle to Epicurus? No, by no means, I said;
				and Empedocles tells us that
				<quote rend="blockquote">What's very good claims to be heard twice.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore we must apply ourselves again to Theon; for I
					think he was present at our former discourse; and moreover,
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.196"/>
					
					 he is a young man, and needs not fear being charged
					by these young gentlemen with having a bad memory.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Then Theon, like one constrained, said: Well then,
				if you will needs have me to go on with the discourse, I
				will not do as you did, Aristodemus. For you were shy
				of repeating what this gentleman spoke, but I shall not
				scruple to make use of what you have said; for I think
				indeed you did very well divide mankind into three ranks;
				the first of wicked and very bad men, the second of the
				vulgar and common sort, and the third of good and wise
				men. The wicked and bad sort then, while they dread
				any kind of divine vengeance and punishment at all,
				and are by this deterred front doing mischief, and thereby
				enjoy the greater quiet, will live both in more pleasure
				and in less disturbance for it. And Epicurus is of
				opinion that the only proper means to keep men from
				doing ill is the fear of punishments. So that we should
				cram them with more and more superstition still, and
				raise up against them terrors, chasms, frights, and surmises, both from heaven and earth, if their being amazed
				with such things as these will make them become the more
				tame and gentle. For it is more for their benefit to be restrained from criminal actions by the fear of what comes
				after death, than to commit them and then to live in perpetual danger and fear.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>As to the vulgar sort, besides their fear of what is
				in hell, the hope they have conceived of an eternity from
				the tales and fictions of the ancients, and their great desire
				of being, which is both the earliest and the strongest of
				all, exceed in pleasure and sweet content of mind that
				childish dread. And therefore, when they lose their children, wives or friends, they would rather have them be
				somewhere and still remain, though in misery, than that
				they should be quite destroyed, dissolved, and reduced to
				nothing. And they are pleased when they hear it said of
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.197"/>
				
				a dying person, that he goes away or departs, and such
				other words as intimate death to be the soul's remove and
				not destruction. And they sometimes speak thus:
				<quote rend="blockquote">But I'll even there think on my dearest friend;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XXII. 390.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and thus:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What's your command to Hector ? Let me know;
					</l>
                     <l>Or to your dear old Priam shall I go?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hecuba, 422.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And (there arising hereupon an erroneous deviation) they
					are the better pleased when they bury with their departed
					friends such arms, implements, or clothes as were most
					familiar to them in their lifetime; as Minos did the Cretan
					flutes with Glaucus,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Made of the shanks of a dead brindled fawn.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>And if they do but imagine they either ask or desire any
					thing of them, they are glad when they give it them. Thus
					Periander burnt his queen's attire with her, because he
					thought she had asked for it and complained she was acold. Nor doth an Aeacus, an Ascalaphus, or an Acheron
					much disorder them whom they have often gratified with
					balls, shows, and music of every sort. But now all men
					shrink from that face of death which carries with it insensibility, oblivion, and extinction of knowledge, as being dismal, grim, and dark. And they are discomposed when
					they hear it said of any one, he is perished, or he is gone, or
					he is no more; and they show great uneasiness when
					they hear such words as these:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Go to the wood-clad earth he must,
					</l>
                     <l>And there lie shrivelled into dust,
					</l>
                     <l>And ne'er more laugh or drink, or hear
					</l>
                     <l>The charming sounds of flute or lyre;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and these:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>But from our lips the vital spirit fled
					</l>
                     <l>Returns no more to wake the silent dead.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. IX. 408.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.198"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Wherefore they must needs cut the very throats of
				them that shall with Epicurus tell them, We men were
				born once for all, and we cannot be born twice, but our not
				being must last for ever. For this will bring them to slight
				their present good as little, or rather indeed as nothing at
				all compared with everlastingness, and therefore to let it
				pass unenjoyed and to become wholly negligent of virtue
				and action, as men disheartened and brought to a contempt
				of themselves, as being but as it were of one day's continuance and uncertain, and born for no considerable purpose. For insensibility, dissolution, and the conceit that
				what hath no sense is nothing to us, do not at all abate the
				fear of death, but rather help to confirm it; for this very
				thing is it that nature most dreads,&mdash;
				<quote rend="blockquote">But may you all return to mould and wet,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 99.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>to wit, the dissolution of the soul into what is without
					knowledge or sense. Now, while Epicurus would have
					this to be a separation into atoms and void, he doth but
					further cut off all hope of immortality; to compass which
					(I can scarce refrain from saying) all men and women
					would be well contented to be worried by Cerberus, and to
					carry water into the tub full of holes, so they might but
					continue in being and not be exterminated. Though (as I
					said before) there are not very many that stand in fear of
					these things, they being but the tenets of old women and the
					fabulous stories of mothers and nurses,&mdash;and even they
					that do fear them yet believe that certain rites of initiation
					and purgation will relieve them, by which being cleansed
					they shall play and dance in hell for ever, in company with
					those that have the privilege of a bright light, clear air,
					and the use of speech,&mdash;still to be deprived of living disturbs all both young and old. For it seems that we
					<quote rend="blockquote">Impatient love the light that shines on earth,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 193.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.199"/>
            <p>as Euripides saith. Nor are we easy or without regret
					when we hear this:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Him speaking thus th' eternal brightness leaves,
					</l>
                     <l>Where night the wearied steeds of day receives.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>And therefore it is very plain that with the belief
				of immortality they take away the sweetest and greatest
				hopes the vulgar sort have. And what shall we then
				think they take away from the good and those that have
				led pious and just lives, who expect no ill after death, but
				on the contrary most glorious and divine things For,
				in the first place, champions are not used to receive the
				garland before they have performed their exercises, but
				after they have contested and proved victorious; in like
				manner is it with those that are persuaded that good men
				have the prize of their conquests after this life is ended;
				it is marvellous to think to what a pitch of grandeur their
				virtue raises their spirits upon the contemplation of those
				hopes, among the which this is one, that they shall one
				day see those men that are now insolent by reason of their
				wealth and power, and that foolishly flout at their betters,
				undergo just punishment. In the next place, none of the
				lovers of truth and the contemplation of being have here
				their fill of them; they having but a watery and puddled
				reason to speculate with, as it were, through the fog and
				mist of the body; and yet they still look upwards like
				birds, as ready to take their flight to the spacious and
				bright region, and endeavor to make their souls expedite
				and light from things mortal, using philosophy as a study
				and preparation for death. Thus I account death a truly
				great and accomplished good thing; the soul being to live
				there a real life, which here lives not a waking life, but
				suffers things most resembling dreams. If then (as Epicurus saith) the remembrance of a dead friend be a thing
				every way complacent; we may easily from thence imagine how great a joy they deprive themselves of who
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.200"/>
				
				think they do but embrace and pursue the phantoms and
				shades of their deceased familiars, that have in them
				neither knowledge nor sense, but who never expect to be
				with them again, or to see their dear father and dear
				mother and sweet wife, nor have any hopes of that familiarity and dear converse they have that think of the soul
				with Pythagoras, Plato, and Homer. Now what their
				sort of passion is like to was hinted at by Homer,
				when he threw into the midst of the soldiers, as they
				were engaged, the shade of Aeneas, as if he had been
				dead, and afterwards again presented his friends with him
				himself,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Coming alive and well, as brisk as ever;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>at which, he saith,
					<quote rend="blockquote">They all were overjoyed.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. V. 514 and 515.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And should not we then,&mdash;when reason shows us that a
					real converse with persons departed this life may be had,
					and that he that loves may both feel and be with the
					party that affects and loves him,&mdash;relinquish these men
					that cannot so much as cast off all those airy shades and
					outside barks for which they are all their time in lamentation and fresh afflictions?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Moreover, they that look upon death as the commencement of
				another and better life, if they enjoy good things, are the better
				pleased with them, as expecting much greater hereafter; but if they
				have not things here to their minds, they do not much grumble at it,
				but the hopes of those good and excellent things that are after death
				contain in them such ineffable pleasures and expectances, that they
				wipe off and wholly obliterate every defect and every offence from
				the mind, which, as on a road or rather indeed in a short deviation
				out of the road, bears whatever befalls it with great ease and
				moderation.
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.201"/>
				
				But now, as to those to whom life ends in insensibility
				and dissolution,&mdash;since death brings to them no removal
				of evils, though it is afflicting in both conditions, yet is it
				more so to those that live prosperously than to such as
				undergo adversity. For it cuts the latter but from an
				uncertain hope of doing better hereafter; but it deprives
				the former of a certain good, to wit, their pleasurable
				living. And as those medicinal potions that are not grateful to the palate but yet necessary give sick men ease, but
				rake and hurt the well; just so, in my opinion, doth the
				philosophy of Epicurus, which promises to those that live
				miserably no happiness in death, and to those that do well
				an utter extinction and dissolution of the mind, while it
				quite obstructs the comfort and solace of the grave and
				wise and those that abound with good things, by throwing
				them down from a happy living into a deprivation of both
				life and being. From hence then it is manifest, that the
				contemplation of the loss of good things will afflict us in
				as great a measure as either the firm hope or present
				enjoyment of them delights us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Yea, themselves tell us, that the contemplation of
				future dissolution leaves them one most assured and complacent good, to wit, freedom from anxious surmises of
				incessant and endless evils, and that Epicurus's doctrine
				effects this by stopping the fear of death by the belief in
				the soul's dissolution. If then deliverance from the expectation of infinite evils be a matter of greatest complacence, how comes it not to be afflictive to be bereft of
				eternal good things and to miss of the highest and most
				consummate felicity? For not to be can be good for
				neither condition, but is on the contrary both against
				nature and ungrateful to all that have a being. But those
				it eases of the evils of life through the evils of death
				have, it is very true, the want of sense to comfort them,
				while they, as it were, make their escape from life. But,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.202"/>
				
				on the other hand, they that change from good things to
				nothing seem to me to have the most dismaying end of
				all, it putting a period to their happiness. For Nature
				doth not fear insensibility as the entrance upon some new
				thing, but because it is the privation of our present good
				things. For to say that the destruction of all that we call
				ours toucheth us not is absurd, for it toucheth us already
				by the very apprehension. And insensibility afflicts not
				those that are not, but those that are, when they think
				what damage they shall sustain by it in the loss of their
				beings and in being suffered never to emerge from annihilation. Wherefore it is neither the dog Cerberus nor
				the river Cocytus that has made our fear of death boundless; but the threatened danger of not being, representing it as impossible for such as are once extinct to shift
				back again into being. For we cannot be born twice, and
				our not being must last for ever; as Epicurus speaks.
				For if our end be in not being, and that be infinite and
				unalterable, then hath privation of good found out an
				eternal evil, to wit, a never ending insensibleness. Herodotus was much wiser, when he said that God, having
				given men a taste of the sweets of life, seems to be envious in this regard,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Herod. VII. 46.</note> and especially to those that conceit
				themselves happy, to whom pleasure is but a bait for sorrow, they being but permitted to taste of what they must
				be deprived of. For what solace or fruition or exultation
				would not the perpetual injected thought of the soul's
				being dispersed into infinity, as into a certain huge and
				vast ocean, extinguish and quell in those that found their
				amiable good and beatitude in pleasure? But if it be
				true (as Epicurus thinks it is) that most men die in very
				acute pain, then is the fear of death in all respects inconsolable; it bringing us through evils unto a deprivation
				of good.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.203"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>And yet they are never wearied with their brawling
				and dunning of all persons to take the escape of evil for
				a good, and yet not to repute privation of good for an
				evil. But they still confess what we have asserted, that
				death hath in it nothing of either good hope or solace,
				but that all that is complacent and good is then wholly
				extinguished; at which time those men look for many
				amiable, great, and divine things, that conceive the minds
				of men to be unperishable and immortal, or at least to go
				about in certain long revolutions of times, being one
				while upon earth and another while in heaven, until they
				are at last dissolved with the universe and then, together
				with the sun and moon, sublimed into an intellective fire.
				So large a field and one of so great pleasures Epicurus
				wholly cuts off, when he destroys (as hath been said) the
				hopes and graces we should derive from the Gods, and by
				that extinguishes both in our speculative capacity the
				desire of knowledge, and in our active the love of glory,
				and confines and abases our nature to a poor narrow
				thing, and that not cleanly neither, to wit, the content the
				mind receives by the body, as if it were capable of no
				higher good than the escape of evil.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>