<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Amatoriae narrationes</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.114">
      <body>
         <head>Five tragical histories of love.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.312"/>
         <p/>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>Chapter I</head>
            <p>IN Haliartus, which is a city of Boeotia, lived a young
					damsel of surpassing beauty, whose name was Aristoclia,
					the daughter of Theophanes. This lady was courted by
					Straton an Orchomenian, and Callisthenes of Haliartus;
					but Straton was the more wealthy of the two, and more
					enamored of the virgin. For he had seen her bathing
					herself in the fountain of Hercyne, which is in Lebadea,
					against the time that she was to bear the sacred basket in
					honor of Jupiter the King. But the virgin herself had a
					greater affection for Callisthenes, for that he was more
					nearly allied to her. In this case, her father Theophanes,
					not knowing well what to do (for he was afraid of Straton,
					who had the advantage both of noble birth and riches
					above all the rest of the Boeotians), resolved to refer the
					choice to the oracle of Trophonius. On the other side,
					Straton (for he was made believe by some of the virgin's
					familiar acquaintance that his mistress had the greatest
					kindness for him) earnestly desired to refer the matter to the
					election of the virgin herself. But when Theophanes put
					the question to his daughter in a great assembly of all the
					friends of all parties, it fell out that the damsel preferred
					Callisthenes. Thereupon it presently appeared in Straton's
					countenance how much he was disgusted at the indignity
					he had received. However, two days after, he came to
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.313"/>
					
					Theophanes and Callisthenes, requesting the continuance
					of their friendship, notwithstanding that some Daemon
					had envied him the happiness of his intended marriage.
					They so well approved his proposal, that they invited him
					to the wedding and the nuptial feast. But he in the mean
					time having mustered together a great number of his
					friends, together with a numerous troop of his own servants, whom he secretly dispersed and disposed up and
					down in places proper for his purpose, watched his opportunity so well that, as the damsel was going down, according to the custom of the country, to the fountain called
					Cissoessa, there to pay her offerings to the Nymphs before
					her wedding-day, he and his accomplices rushing out of
					their ambuscade seized upon the virgin, whom Straton held
					fast and pulled to himself. On the other side, Callisthenes,
					with those that were about him, as it is easy to be believed,
					flew with all speed to her relief; and in this fatal contest,
					while the one tugged and the other hauled, the unhappy
					damsel perished. As for Callisthenes, he was never seen
					any more; whether he laid violent hands upon himself, or
					whether it were that he left Boeotia as a voluntary exile;
					for no man could give any account of him afterwards.
					And as for Straton, he slew himself before the eyes of all
					upon the dead body of the unfortunate virgin.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>Chapter II</head>
            <p>A certain great person whose name was Phido, designing to make himself lord of the whole Peloponnesus, and
					more especially desirous that Argos, being his native
					country, should be the metropolis of all the rest, resolved
					to reduce the Corinthians under his subjection. To this
					purpose he sent to them to demand a levy of a thousand
					young gentlemen, the most valiant and the chiefest in the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.314"/>
					
					prime of their age in the whole city. Accordingly they
					sent him a thousand young sparks, brisk and gallant, under the leading of Dexander, whom they chose to be their
					captain. But Phido, designing nothing more than the
					massacre of these gentlemen, to the end he might the more
					easily make himself master of Corinth when it should be
					enfeebled by so great a loss (as being by its situation the
					chief bulwark to guard the entrance into Peloponnesus),
					imparted this contrivance of his to several of his confidants,
					in which number was one whose name was Abro; who,
					having been formerly acquainted with Dexander, and familiarly entertained by him, discovered the whole conspiracy
					to his friend in acknowledgment of his kindness. By
					which means the thousand, before they fell into the ambuscade, retreated and got safe to Corinth. Phido thus disappointed made all the inquiry imaginable, to find out who it
					was that had betrayed and discovered his design. Which
					Abro understanding fled to Corinth with his wife and all
					his family, and settled himself in Melissus, a certain village
					in the territory of the Corinthians. There he begat a son,
					whom he named Melissus from the name of the place
					where he was born. The son of this Melissus was
					Actaeon, the loveliest and most modest of all the striplings
					of his age. For which reason there were several that fell
					in love with him, but none with so much ardor as Archias,
					being of the race of the Heraclidae, and for wealth and
					authority the greatest person in all Corinth. This Archias,
					when he found that no fair means and persuasions would
					prevail upon the young lad, resolved to ravish him away
					by force; to which purpose he invited himself to Melissus's
					house, as it were to make merry, accompanied with a great
					number of his friends and servants, and by their assistance
					he made an attempt to carry away the son by violence.
					But the father and his friends opposing the rape, and the
					neighbors coming in to the rescue of the child, poor
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.315"/>
					
					Actaeon, between the one and the other, was pulled and
					hauled to death; and Archias with his company departed.
					Upon this, Melissus carried the murdered body of his son
					into the market-place of Corinth, and there, exposing him
					to public view, demanded justice to be done upon the murderers. But finding that the Corinthians only pitied his
					condition, without taking any farther notice of the matter,
					he returned home, and waited for the grand assembly of
					the Greeks at the Isthmus. At what time, getting up to
					the very top of Neptune's temple, he exclaimed against
					the whole race of the Bacchiadae, and after he had made
					a public relation of the good service which his father Abro
					had done the Corinthians, he invoked the vengeance of
					the Gods, and presently threw himself headlong among the
					rocks. Soon after the Corinthians being plagued with a
					most terrible drought, upon which ensued a violent famine,
					they sent to the oracle, to know by what means they might
					be delivered from their calamity. To whom the Deity
					made answer, that it was Neptune's wrath, which would
					not cease till they had revenged the death of Actaeon.
					Archias, hearing this (for he was one of those that were
					sent to the oracle), never returned again to Corinth, but
					sailing into Sicily, built there the city of Syracuse; where,
					after he was become the father of two daughters, Ortygia
					and Syracusa, he was treacherously slain by Telephus,
					whom he had preternaturally abused in his youth, and
					who, having the command of a ship, sailed along with
					him into Sicily.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>Chapter III</head>
            <p>A certain poor man, Scedasus by name, lived at Leuctra,
					a small village in the territory of the Thespians, and had
					two daughters, Hippo and Miletia, or as others say, Theano
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.316"/>
					
					and Euxippe. This Scedasus was a very good man, and,
					to the extent of his fortune, very hospitable to strangers.
					This was the reason that most readily and gladly he entertained two young gentlemen of Sparta, that came to lodge
					at his house; who, falling in love with the virgins, were
					yet so overawed by the kindness that Scedasus had showed
					them, that they durst not make any rude attempt for that
					time. The next morning therefore they went directly to
					the city of Delphi, whither they were journeying, where
					after they had consulted the oracle touching such questions as they had to put, they returned homeward, and
					travelling through Boeotia, stopped again at Scedasus's
					house, who happened at that time not to be at Leuctra.
					However, his daughters, according to that education to
					which their father had accustomed them, gave the same
					entertainment to the strangers as if their father had been
					at home. But such was the perfidious ingratitude of these
					guests, that finding the virgins alone, they ravished and by
					force deflowered the damsels; and, which was worse, perceiving them lamenting to excess the undeserved injury
					they had received, the ravishers murdered them, and after
					they had thrown their bodies into a well, went their ways.
					Soon after Scedasus, returning home, missed both his
					daughters, but all things else he found safe and in order,
					as he left them; which put him into such a quandary,
					that he knew not what to say or do, till instructed by a
					little bitch, that several times in a day came whining and
					fawning upon him and then returned to the well, he began to suspect what he found to be true; and so he drew up
					the dead bodies of his daughters. Moreover, being then
					informed by his neighbors, that they had seen the two
					Lacedaemonian gentlemen which he had entertained some
					time before go into his house, he guessed them to be the
					persons who had committed the fact, for that they would be
					always praising the virgins when they lodged there before,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.317"/>
					
					and telling their father what happy men they would be that
					should have the good fortune to marry them. Thereupon
					away he went to Lacedaemon, with a resolution to make
					his complaint to the Ephori; but being benighted in the
					territory of Argos, he put into a public house, where he
					found another old man of the city of Oreus, in the province
					of Histiaea; whom when he heard sighing and cursing
					the Lacedaemonians, Scedasus asked him what injury the
					Lacedaemonians had done him. In answer to which, the
					old man gave him this account: I am, said he, a subject to
					the Lacedaemonians, by whom Aristodemus was sent to
					Oreus to be governor of that place, where he committed
					several outrages and savage enormities. Among the rest,
					being fallen in love with my son, when he could by no
					fair means procure his consent, he endeavored to carry him
					away by main force out of the wrestling-place. But the
					president of the exercises opposing him, with the assistance of several of the young men, Aristodemus was constrained to retire; but the next day, having provided a
					galley to be in readiness, he ravished away my son, and
					sailing from Oreus to the opposite continent, endeavored,
					when he had the boy there, to abuse his body; and because the lad refused to submit to his lust, cut the child's
					throat. Upon his return he made a great feast at Oreus,
					to which he invited all his friends. In the mean while,
					I being soon informed of the sad accident, presently went
					and interred the body; and having so done, I made
					haste to Sparta, and preferred my complain to the Ephori,
					but they gave no answer, nor took any notice of the
					matter.</p>
            <p>Scedasus, having heard this relation, remained very
					much dejected, believing he should have no better success. However, in his turn, he gave an account to the
					stranger of his own sad mischance; which when he had
					done, the stranger advised him not to complain to the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.318"/>
					
					Ephori, but to return to his own country, and erect a
					monument for his two daughters. But Scedasus, not
					liking this advice, went to Sparta, made his case known
					to the Ephori, and demanded justice; who taking no notice
					of his complaint, away he went to the Kings; but they as
					little regarding him, he applied himself to every particular
					citizen, and. recommended to them the sadness of his condition. At length, when he saw nothing would do, he ran
					through the city, stretching forth his hands to the sun and
					stamping on the ground with his feet, and called upon the
					Furies to revenge his cause; and when he had done all he
					could, in the last place slew himself. But afterwards the
					Lacedaemonians dearly paid for their injustice. For being at that time lords of all Greece, while all the chiefest
					cities of that spacious region were curbed by their garrisons, Epaminondas the Theban was the first that threw off
					their yoke, and cut the throats of the garrison that lay in
					Thebes. Upon which, the Lacedaemonians making war
					upon the revolters, the Thebans met them at Leuctra, confident of success from the name of the place; for that
					formerly they had been there delivered from slavery, at
					what time Amphictyon, being driven into exile by Sthenelus, came to the city of Thebes, and finding them tributaries to the Chalcidians, after he had slain Chalcodon king
					of the Euboeans, eased them altogether of that burthen.
					In like manner it happened that the Lacedaemonians
					were vanquished not far from the monument of Scedasus's
					daughters. It is reported also, that before the fight, Pelopidas being then one of the Theban generals, and troubled by reason of some certain signs that seemed to portend some ill event in the battle, Scedasus appeared to him
					in a dream and bade him be of good courage, for that the
					Lacedaemonians were come to Leuctra, to receive the just
					vengeance which they deserved from him and his daughters; only the ghost advised him, the day before he encountered
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.319"/>
					
					 the Lacedaemonians, to sacrifice a white colt,
					which he should find ready for him close by his daughters'
					sepulchre. Whereupon Pelopidas, while the Lacedaemonians yet lay encamped at Tegea, sent certain persons to
					examine the truth of the matter; and finding by the inhabitants thereabouts that every thing agreed with his
					dream, he advanced with his army boldly forward, and
					won the field.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>Chapter IV</head>
            <p>Phocus was a Boeotian by birth (for he was born in the
					city of Clisas), the father of Callirrhoe, who was a virgin
					of matchless beauty and modesty, and courted by thirty
					young gentlemen, the prime of the Boeotian nobility.
					Phocus therefore, seeing so many suitors about her, still
					pretended one excuse or other to put off her marriage,
					afraid lest some force or other should be put upon her.
					At length, when he could hold out no longer, the gentlemen
					being offended at his dilatory answers, he desired them to
					refer it to the Pythian Deity to make the choice. But this
					the gentlemen took so heinously, that they fell upon Phocus
					and slew him. In this combustion and tumult, the virgin
					making her escape fled into the country, and was as soon
					pursued by the young sparks; but lighting upon certain
					country people that were piling up their wheat in a barn,
					by their assistance she saved herself. For the countrymen
					hid her in the corn, so that they who were in chase of her
					passed her by. The virgin thus preserved kept herself
					close till the general assembly of all the Boeotians; and
					then coming to Coronea, she there sat as a suppliant before
					the altar of Itonian Minerva, and there gave a full relation
					of the villany and murder committed by her several suitors,
					discovering withal the names of the persons, and places of
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.320"/>
					
					their abode. The Boeotians commiserating the virgin
					were no less incensed against the young gentlemen; who,
					having notice of what had passed, fled to Orchomenus, but
					being shut out by the citizens, made their escape to Hippotae, a village near to Helicon, seated between Thebes and
					Coronea, where they were received and protected. Thither
					the Thebans sent to have the murderers of Phocus delivered up; which the inhabitants refusing to do, they
					marched against the town with a good force of other
					Boeotians under the leading of Phoedus, then the chief
					ruler of Thebes. And laying siege to it (for it was a
					strong place), at last they took it for want of water; and
					in the first place having apprehended all the murderers,
					they stoned them to death; then they condemned the inhabitants to perpetual slavery, broke down the walls,
					ruined the houses, and divided the land between the Thebans and Coroneans. The report goes, that the night before Hippotae was taken, there was a voice heard from
					Helicon several times uttering these words, I am come;
					and that when the thirty rivals heard it, they knew it to be
					the voice of Phocus. It was said, moreover, that the very
					day the rivals were stoned, the monument of the old man
					which was erected in Clisas was covered with drops of
					saffron. And as Phoedus, the governor and general of the
					Thebans, was upon his march homeward from the siege,
					news was brought him that his wife had brought him a
					daughter, which for the good omen's sake he called by the
					name of Nicostrate.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>Chapter V</head>
            <p>Alcippus was a Lacedaemonian by birth, who marrying
					Damocrita became the father of two daughters. This
					Alcippus, being a person that always advised the city for
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.321"/>
					
					the best, and one that was always ready to serve his countrymen upon all occasions, was envied by a contrary faction, that continually accused him to the Ephori as one that
					endeavored to subvert the ancient laws and constitutions
					of the city. At length the Ephori banished the husband,
					who being condemned forsook the city; but when Damocrita and his daughters would fain have followed him, they
					would not permit them to stir. Moreover, they confiscated
					his estate, to deprive his daughters of their portions. Nay,
					more than this, when there were some that courted the
					daughters for the sake of their father's virtue, his enemies
					obtained a decree whereby it was forbid that any man
					should make love to the young ladies, cunningly alleging
					that the mother had often prayed to the Gods to favor her
					daughters with speedy wedlock, to the end they might the
					sooner bring forth children to be revenged of the injury
					done their father. Damocrita thus beset, and in a strait
					on every side, stayed till the general festival, when the
					women, together with their daughters, servants, and little
					children, feast in public together; on which day, the wives
					of the magistrates and persons in dignity feast all night in
					a spacious hall by themselves. But then it was that Damocrita, with a sword girt about her, and taking her daughters with her, went in the night-time to the temple; and
					watching her opportunity, when the women were all busy
					in the great hall performing the mysteries of the solemnity,
					after all the ways and passages were stopped up, she
					fetched the wood that was ready prepared for the sacrifices
					appertaining to the festival, and piled it against the doors
					of the room, and so set fire to it. All was then in a hurry,
					and the men came crowding in vain to help their wives;
					but then it was that Damocrita slew her daughters, and
					upon their dead bodies herself. Thus the Lacedaemonians,
					not knowing upon whom to wreak their anger, were forced
					to be contented with only throwing the dead bodies of the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.322"/>
					
					mother and the daughters without the confines of their
					territories. For which barbarous act of theirs, the Deity
					being highly offended plagued the Lacedaemonians, as
					their histories record, with that most dreadful earthquake
					so remarkable to posterity.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>