<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De virtute morali</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.094">
      <body>
         <head>Of moral virtue.</head>
         <pb id="v.3.p.461"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>MY design in this essay is to treat of that virtue
					which is called and accounted moral, and is chiefly distinguished from the contemplative, in its having for the
					matter thereof the passions of the mind, and for its form,
					right reason; and herein to consider the nature of it and
					how it subsists, and whether that part of the soul wherein
					it resides be endowed with reason of its own, inherent in
					itself, or whether it participates of that which is foreign;
					and if the latter, whether it does this after the manner of
					those things which are mingled with what is better than
					themselves, or whether, as being distinct itself but yet under
					the dominion and superintendency of another, it may be
					said to partake of the power of the predominant faculty.
					For that it is possible for virtue to exist and continue altogether independent of matter, and free from all mixture,
					I take to be most manifest. But in the first place I. conceive it may be very useful briefly to run over the opinions
					of other philosophers, not so much for the vanity of giving
					an historical account thereof, as that, they being premised,
					ours may thence receive the greater light and be more
					firmly established.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>To begin then with Menedemus of Eretria, he took
					away both the number and the differences of virtue, by
					asserting it to be but one, although distinguished by several
					names; holding that, in the same manner as a mortal and
					a man are all one, so what we call temperance, fortitude,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.462"/>
					
					and justice are but one and the same thing. As for Ariston of Chios, he likewise made virtue to be but one in
					substance, and called it sanity, which, as it had respect to
					this or that, was to be variously multiplied and distinguished; just after the same manner as if any one should
					call our sight, when applied to any white object, by the
					name of white-look; when to one that is black, by the
					name of black-look; and so in other matters. For according to him, virtue, when it considers such things as we
					ought to do or not to do, is called prudence; when it moderates our desires, and prescribes the measure and season
					for our pleasures, temperance; and when it governs the
					commerce and mutual contracts of mankind, justice;&mdash;in
					the same manner, for instance, as a knife is one and the
					same knife still, notwithstanding sometimes it cuts one
					thing, sometimes another, and just as fire does operate
					upon different matter, and yet retain the very same nature.
					Unto which opinion it seems also as if Zeno the Citian did
					in some measure incline; he defining prudence, while it
					distributes to every man his own, to be justice; when it
					teaches what we are to choose and what to reject or avoid,
					temperance; and with respect to what is to be borne or
					suffered, fortitude. But it is to be observed, that they who
					take upon them the defence of Zeno's notions do suppose
					him to mean science by what he calls prudence. But then
					Chrysippus, whilst he imagined from every distinct quality
					a several and peculiar virtue to be formed, before he was
					aware, raised (as Plato hath it) a whole swarm of virtues
					never before known or used among the philosophers. For
					as from brave he derived bravery; from mild, mildness;
					and from just, justice; so from pleasant he fetched
					pleasantness; from good, goodness; from grand, grandeur;
					and from honest, honesty; placing these and all kind of
					dexterous application of discourse, all kind of facetiousness
					of conversation, and all witty turns of expression in the
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.463"/>
					
					number of virtues, thereby over-running philosophy, which
					requires nothing less, with a multitude of uncouth, absurd,
					and barbarous terms.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>However, all these do commonly agree in this one
					thing, in supposing virtue to be a certain disposition and
					faculty of the governing and directive part of the soul, of
					which reason is the cause; or rather to be reason itself,
					when it consents to what it ought, and is firm and immutable. And they do likewise think, that that part of the soul
					which is the seat of the passions, and is called brutal or
					irrational, is not at all distinct by any physical difference
					from that which is rational; but that this part of the soul
					(which they call rational and directive), being wholly
					turned about and changed by its affections and by those
					several alterations which are wrought in it with respect
					either to habit or disposition, becometh either vice or virtue, without having any thing in itself that is really brutal
					or irrational, but is then called brutal or irrational, when by
					the over-ruling and prevailing violence of our appetites it
					is hurried on to something absurd and vicious, against the
					judgment of reason. For passion, according to them, is
					nothing else but depraved and intemperate reason, that
					through a perverse and vicious judgment is grown over-vehement and headstrong.</p>
            <p>Now, it seems to me, all these philosophers were perfect
					strangers to the clearness and truth of this point, that we
					every one of us are in reality twofold and compound.
					For, discerning only that composition in us which of the
					two is most evident, namely that of the soul and body, of
					the other they knew nothing at all. And yet that in the
					soul itself also there is a certain composition of two dissimilar and distinct natures, the brutal part whereof, as
					another body, is necessarily and physically compounded
					with and conjoined to reason, was, it should seem, no secret
					to Pythagoras himself,&mdash;as some have guessed from his
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.464"/>
					
					having introduced the study of music amongst his scholars,
					for the more easy calming and assuaging the mind, as well
					knowing that it is not in every part of it obedient and
					subject to precepts and discipline, nor indeed by reason
					only to be recovered and retrieved from vice, but requires some other kind of persuasives to co-operate with
					it, to dispose it to such a temper and gentleness as that it
					may not be utterly intractable and obstinate to the precepts
					of philosophy. And Plato very strongly and plainly, without the least hesitation, maintained that the soul of the
					universe is neither simple, uniform, nor uncompounded;
					but that being mixed, as it were, and made up of that
					which is always the same and of that which is otherwise,
					in some places it is continually governed and carried about
					after a uniform manner in one and the same powerful and
					predominant order, and in other places is divided into motions and circles, one contrary to the other, unsettled and
					fortuitous,&mdash;whence are derived the beginnings and generation of differences in things. And so, in like manner,
					the soul of man, being a part or portion of that of the
					universe, and framed upon reasons and proportions answerable to it, cannot be simple and all of the same nature; but
					must have one part that is intelligent and rational, which
					naturally ought to have dominion over a man, and another
					which, being subject to passion, irrational, extravagant,
					and unbounded, stands in need of direction and restraint.
					And this last is again subdivided into two other parts;
					one whereof, being called corporeal, is called concupiscible, and the other, which sometimes takes part with this
					and sometimes with reason, and gives respectively to either
					of them strength and vigor, is called irascible. And that
					which chiefly discovers the difference between the one and
					the other is the frequent conflict of the intellect and reason with concupiscence and anger, it being the nature
					of things that are different amongst themselves to be
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.465"/>
					
					oftentimes repugnant and disobedient to what is best
					of all.</p>
            <p>These principles at first Aristotle seems most to have
					relied upon, as plainly enough appears from what he has
					written. Though afterwards he confounded the irascible
					and concupiscible together, by joining the one to the other,
					as if anger were nothing but a thirst and desire of revenge.
					However, to the last he constantly maintained that the
					sensual and irrational was wholly distinct from the intellectual and rational part of the soul. Not that it is so absolutely devoid of reason as those faculties of the soul
					which are sensitive, nutritive, and vegetative, and are common to us with brute beasts and plants; for these are always deaf to the voice of reason and incapable of it, and
					may in some sort be said to derive themselves from flesh
					and blood, and to be inseparably attached to the body and
					devoted to the service thereof; but the other sensual part,
					subject to the sudden efforts of the passions and destitute
					of any reason of its own, is yet nevertheless naturally
					adapted to hear and obey the intellect and judgment, to
					have regard to it, and to submit itself to be regulated and
					ordered according the rules and precepts thereof, unless it
					happen to be utterly corrupted and vitiated by pleasure,
					which is deaf to all instruction, and by a luxurious way of
					living.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>As for those who wonder how it should come to pass,
					that that which is irrational in itself should yet become obsequious to the dictates of right reason, they seem to me
					not to have duly considered the force and power of reason,
					how great and extensive it is, and how far it is able to
					carry and extend its authority and command, not so much
					by harsh and arbitrary methods, as by soft and gentle
					means, which persuade more and gain obedience sooner
					than all the severities and violences in the world. For
					even the spirits, the nerves, bones, and other parts of the
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.466"/>
					
					body are destitute of reason; but yet no sooner do they
					feel the least motion of the will, reason shaking (as it
					were), though never so gently, the reins, but all of them
					observe their proper order, agree together, and pay a ready
					obedience. As, for instance, the feet, if the impulse of
					the mind be to run, immediately betake themselves to their
					office; or if the motion of the will be for the throwing or
					lifting up of any thing, the hands in a moment fall to
					their business. And this sympathy or consent of the brutal faculties to right reason, and the ready conformity
					of them thereto, Homer has most admirably expressed in
					these verses:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>In tears dissolved she mourns her consort's fate,
					</l>
                     <l>So great her sorrows, scarce her charms more great.
					</l>
                     <l>Her tears compassion in Ulysses move,
					</l>
                     <l>And fill his breast with pity and with love;
					</l>
                     <l>Yet artful he his passion secret keeps,
					</l>
                     <l>It rages in his heart; and there he inward weeps.
					</l>
                     <l>Like steel or ivory, his fixed eyeballs stand,
					</l>
                     <l>Placed by some statuary's skilful hand;
					</l>
                     <l>And when a gentle tear would force its way,
					</l>
                     <l>He hides it falling, or commands its stay.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XIX. 208.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Under such perfect subjection to his reason and judgment
					had he even his spirits, his blood, and his tears. A most
					evident proof of this matter we have also from hence, that
					our natural desires and motions are as soon repressed and.
					quieted as we know we are either by reason or law forbidden to approach the fair ones we at the first view had
					so great a passion for; a thing which most commonly happens to those who are apt to fall in love at sight with
					beautiful women, without knowing or examining who they
					are; for no sooner do they afterwards find their error, by
					discovering the person with whose charms they were before captivated to be a sister or a daughter, but their flame
					is presently extinguished by the interposition of reason.
					And flesh and blood are immediately brought into order,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.467"/>
					
					and become obedient to the judgment. It often falls out
					likewise that, after we have eaten some kinds of meat or
					fish finely dressed, and by that means artificially disguised,
					with great pleasure and a very good stomach, at the first
					moment we understand they were either unclean, or unlawful and forbidden, our judgment being thereby shocked,
					we feel not only remorse and trouble in our mind, but the
					conceit reaches farther, and our whole frame is disordered
					by the nauseous qualms and vomitings thereby occasioned.
					I fear I should be thought on purpose to hunt after too
					far-fetched and youthful instances to insert in this discourse, if I should take notice of the lute, the harp, the
					pipe and flute, and such like musical instruments invented
					by art, and adapted to the raising or allaying of human
					passions; which, though they are void of life and sense,
					do yet most readily accommodate themselves to the judgment, to our passions and our manners, either indulging
					our melancholy, increasing our mirth, or feeding our wantonness, as we happen at that time to be disposed. And
					therefore it is reported of Zeno himself, that, going one
					day to the theatre to hear Amoebeus sing to the lute, he
					called to his scholars, Come, says he, let us go and learn
					what harmony and music the guts and sinews of beasts,
					nay even wood and bones are capable of, by the help of
					numbers, proportion, and order.</p>
            <p>But to let these things pass, I would gladly know of
					them, whether, when they see domestic animals (as dogs,
					horses, or birds) by use, feeding, and teaching brought to
					so high a degree of perfection as that they shall utter articulately some senseful words, and by their motions, gestures, and all their actions, shall approve themselves
					governable, and become useful to us; and when also they
					find Achilles in Homer encouraging horses, as well as men,
					to battle;&mdash;whether, I say, after all this, they can yet
					make any wonder or doubt, whether those faculties of the
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.468"/>
					
					mind to which we owe our anger, our desires, our joys,
					and our sorrows, be of such a nature that they are capable
					of being obedient to reason, and so affected by it as to
					consent and become entirely subject to it; considering especially that these faculties are not seated without us, or
					separated from us, or formed by any thing which is not in
					us, or hammered out by force and violence, but, as they
					have by nature their entire dependence upon the soul, so
					they are ever conversant and bred up with it, and also receive their final complement and perfection from use, custom, and practice. For this reason the Greeks very
					properly call manners <foreign lang="greek">h)=qos</foreign>, <hi rend="italics">custom;</hi> for they are nothing
					else, in short, but certain qualities of the irrational and
					brutal part of the mind, and hence by them are so named,
					in that this brutal and irrational part of the mind being
					formed and moulded by right reason, by long custom and
					use (which they call <foreign lang="greek">e)/qos</foreign>), has these qualities or differences
					stamped upon it. Not that reason so much as attempts to
					eradicate our passions and affections, which is neither possible nor expedient, but only to keep them within due
					bounds, reduce them into good order, and so direct them
					to a good end; and thus to generate moral virtue, consisting
					not in a kind of insensibility, or total freedom from passions, but in the well-ordering our passions and keeping
					them within measure, which she effects by wisdom and
					prudence, bringing the faculties of that part of the soul
					where our affections and appetite are seated to a good
					habit. For these three things are commonly held to be in
					the soul, namely, a faculty or aptitude, passion, and habit.
					This aptitude or faculty then is the principle or very matter of passions; as for example, the power or aptitude to
					be angry, to be ashamed, to be confident and bold, or the
					like; passion is the actual exercise of that aptitude or
					faculty, as anger, shame, confidence, or boldness; and
					habit is the strength, firmness, and establishment of the
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.469"/>
					
					disposition or faculty in the irrational part of the soul,
					gotten by continual use and custom, and which, according
					as the passions are well or ill governed by reason, becomes
					either virtue or vice.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But, forasmuch as philosophers do not make all virtue
					to consist in a mediocrity nor call it moral, to show the
					difference more clearly, it will be necessary to take our
					rise a little farther off. For of all things then in the universe, some do exist absolutely, simply, and for themselves only; others again relatively, for and with regard to
					us. Among those things which have an absolute and
					simple existence are the earth, the heavens, the stars, and
					the sea; and of such things as have their being relatively,
					with respect to us, are good and evil, things desirable and
					to be avoided, and things pleasant and hurtful. And seeing that both are the proper objects of reason,&mdash;while it
					considers the former, which are absolutely and for themselves, it is scientifical and contemplative; and when the
					other, which have reference to us, it is deliberative and
					practical. And as the proper virtue in the latter case is
					prudence, in the former it is science. And between the one
					and the other, namely, between prudence and science, there
					is this difference. Prudence consists in a certain application and relation of the contemplative faculties of the soul to
					those which are practical, for the government of the sensual and irrational part, according to reason. To which
					purpose prudence has often need of Fortune; whereas
					neither of that nor of deliberation has science any occasion or want to attain its ends, forasmuch as it has nothing
					to consider but such things as remain always the same.
					For as a geometrician never deliberates about a triangle,
					whether all its three angles be equal to two right angles,
					because of that he has a clear and distinct knowledge
					(and men use to deliberate about such things only as are
					sometimes in one state or condition and sometimes in
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.470"/>
					
					another, and not of those which are always firm and immutable), so the mind, when merely contemplative, exercising itself about first principles and things permanent,
					such as retaining the same nature are incapable of mutation, has no room or occasion for deliberation. Whereas
					prudence, descending to actions full of error and confusion,
					is very often under the necessity of encountering with fortuitous accidents, and, in doubtful cases, of making use
					of deliberation, and, to reduce those deliberations into practice, of calling also to its assistance even the irrational
					faculties, which are (as it were) forcibly dragged to go
					along with it, and by that means to give a certain vigor or
					impetus to its determinations. For its determinations do
					indeed want something which may enliven and give them
					such an impetus. And moral virtue it is which gives an
					impetus or vigor to the passions; but at the same time
					reason, which accompanies that impetus, and of which it
					stands in great need, does so set bounds thereunto, that
					nothing but what is moderate appears, and that it neither
					outruns the proper seasons of action, nor yet falls short of
					them.</p>
            <p>For the sensual faculties, where passions are seated, are
					subject to motions, some over-vehement, sudden, and quick,
					and others again too remiss, and more slow and heavy
					than is convenient. So that, though every thing we do can
					be good but in one manner, yet it may be evil in several;
					as there is but one single way of hitting the mark, but to
					miss it a great many, either by shooting over, or under, or
					on one side. The business therefore of practical reason,
					governing our actions according to the order of Nature, is
					to correct the excesses as well as the defects of the passions, by reducing them to a true mediocrity. For as,
					when through infirmity of the mind, effeminacy, fear, or
					laziness, the vehemence and keenness of the appetites are
					so abated that they are ready to sink and fall short of the
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.471"/>
					
					good at which they are aimed and directed, there is then
					this practical reason at hand, exciting and rousing and
					pushing them onward; so, on the other hand, when it
					lashes out too far and is hurried beyond all measure, there
					also is the same reason ready to bring it again within compass and put a stop to its career. And thus, prescribing
					bounds and giving law to the motions of the passions, it
					produces in the irrational part of the soul these moral
					virtues (of which we now treat), which are nothing else
					but the mean between excess and defect. For it cannot
					be said that all virtue consists in mediocrity; since wisdom
					or prudence (one of the intellectual virtues), standing in
					no need of the irrational faculties,&mdash;as being seated in
					that part of the soul which is pure and unmixed and free
					from all passions,&mdash;is of itself absolutely perfect, the
					utmost extremity and power of reason, whereby we attain
					to that perfection of knowledge which is itself most divine
					and renders us most happy. Whereas moral virtue, which
					because of the body is so necessary to us, and, to put
					things in practice, stands in need of the instrumental ministry of the passions (as being so far from promoting the
					destruction and abolition of irrational powers, as to be
					altogether employed in the due regulation thereof), is, with
					respect to its power or quality, the very top and extremity
					of perfection; but, in respect of the proportion and quantity which it determines, it is mediocrity, in that it takes
					away all excess on the one hand, and cures all defects on
					the other.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Now mean and mediocrity may be differently understood. For there is one mean which is compounded and
					made up of the two simple extremes, as in colors, gray,
					of white and black; and another, where that which contains and is contained is the medium between the containing and the contained, as, for instance, the number eight,
					between twelve and four. And a third sort there is also,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.472"/>
					
					which participates of neither extreme, as for example, all
					those things which, as being neither good nor evil in themselves, we call adiaphorous, or indifferent. But in none of
					these ways can virtue be said to be a mean, or mediocrity.
					For neither is it a mixture of vices, nor, comprehending
					that which is defective and short, is it comprehended by
					that which runs out into excess; nor yet is it exempt from
					the impetuosity and sudden efforts of the passions, in which
					excess and defect do properly take place. But moral virtue properly doth consist in a mean or mediocrity (and so
					it is commonly taken), most like to that which there is in
					our Greek music and harmony. For, whereas there are the
					highest and lowest musical notes in the extremities of
					the scale called nete and hypate; so likewise is there in
					the middle thereof, between these two, another musical
					note, and that the sweetest of all, called mese (or mean),
					which does as perfectly avoid the extreme sharpness of the
					one as it doth the over-flatness of the other. And so also
					virtue, being a motion and power which is exercised about
					the brutal and irrational part of the soul, takes away the
					remission and intention&mdash;in a word, the excess and defect&mdash;of the appetites, reducing thereby every one of the
					passions to a due mediocrity and perfect state of rectitude.</p>
            <p>For example, fortitude is said to be the mean between
					cowardice and rashness, whereof the one is a defect, as
					the other is an excess of the irascible faculty; liberality,
					between sordid parsimony on the one hand, and extravagant prodigality on the other; clemency between insensibility of injuries and its opposite, revengeful cruelty;
					and so of justice and temperance; the former being the
					mean between giving and distributing more or less than is
					due in all contracts, affairs, and business between man and
					man, and the latter a just mediocrity between a stupid
					apathy, touched with no sense or relish of pleasure, and
					dissolute softness, abandoned to all manner of sensualities.</p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.473"/>
            <p>And from this instance of temperance it is, that we are
					most clearly given to understand the difference between
					the irrational and the rational faculties of the soul, and
					that it so plainly appears to us that the passions and affections of the mind are quite a distinct thing from reason.
					For otherwise never should we be able to distinguish continence from temperance, nor incontinence from intemperance, in lust and pleasures, if it were one and the same
					faculty of the soul wherewith we reason and judge, and
					whereby we desire and covet. Now temperance is that
					whereby reason governs and manages that part of the soul
					which is subject to the passions (as it were some wild
					creature brought up by hand, and made quite tame and
					gentle), having gained an absolute victory over all its appetites, and brought them entirely under the dominion of it.
					Whereas we call it continence, when reason has indeed
					gained the mastery over the appetites and prevailed against
					them, though not without great pains and trouble, they
					being perverse and continuing to struggle, as not having
					wholly submitted themselves; so that it is not without
					great difficulty able to preserve its government over them,
					being forced to retain and hold them in, and keep them
					within compass, as it were, with stripes, with the bit and
					bridle, while the mind all the time is full of nothing but
					agony, contentions, and confusion. All which Plato endeavors to illustrate by a similitude of the chariot-horses
					of the soul, the one whereof, being more unruly, not only
					kicks and flings at him that is more gentle and tractable,
					but also thereby so troubles and disorders the driver himself, that he is forced sometimes to hold him hard in, and
					sometimes again to give him his head,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lest from his hands the purple reins should slip,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Simonides speaks.</p>
            <p>And from hence we may see why continence is not
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.474"/>
					
					thought worthy to be placed in the number of perfect virtues, but is taken to be a degree under virtue. For there
					is not therein produced a mediocrity arising from a symphony of the worst with the better, nor are the excesses
					of the passions retrenched; nor yet doth the appetite become obedient and subservient to the reasonable faculties,
					but it both makes and feels disorder and disturbance, being
					repressed by violence and constraint, and (as it were) by
					necessity; as in a sedition or faction in a city or state, the
					contending parties, breathing nothing but war and destruction and ruin to one another, do yet cohabit together (it
					may be) within the compass of the same walls; insomuch
					that the soul of the incontinent person, with respect to the
					conflicts and incongruities therein, may very properly be
					compared to the city,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where all the streets are filled with incense smoke,
					</l>
                     <l>And songs of triumph mixed with groans resound.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Oed. Tyr. 4.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And upon the same grounds it is, that incontinence is held
					to be something less than vice also, but intemperance to
					be a complete and perfect vice, for therein not the appetite only but reason likewise is debauched and corrupted;
					and as the former incites and pushes forward the desires
					and affections to that which is evil, so this, by making an
					ill judgment, is easily led to consent and agree to the soft
					whispers and tempting allurements of corrupt lusts and
					passions, and soon loseth all sense of sin and evil.
					Whereas incontinence preserves the judgment, by the
					help of reason, right and sound; but yet, by irresistible
					force and violence of the passions, is even against judgment drawn away. Moreover, in these respects following
					it differeth also from intemperance:&mdash;inasmuch as reason
					in that is overpowered by passion, but in this it never so
					much as struggleth; the incontinent person, after a noble
					resistance, is at last forced to submit to the tyranny of his
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.475"/>
					
					lusts, and follow their guidance, while the intemperate approves them, and gladly goes along with and submits to
					them; one feels remorse for the evil he commits, while the
					other prides in lewdness and vice. Again, the one wilfully
					and of his own accord runs into sin; while the other, even
					against his will, is forced to abandon that which is good.</p>
            <p>And this difference between them is not to be collected
					only from their actions, but may as plainly also be discovered by their words. For at this rate do intemperate
					persons use to talk:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What mirth in life, what pleasure, what delight,
					</l>
                     <l>Without content in sports of Venus bright?
					</l>
                     <l>Were those joys past, and I for them unmeet,
					</l>
                     <l>Ring out my knell, bring forth my winding-sheet.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Mimnermus.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And thus says another:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To eat, to drink, to wench are principal,
					</l>
                     <l>All pleasures else I accessories call;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if from his very soul he were wholly abandoned and
					given up to pleasures and voluptuousness, and even over
					whelmed therein. And much of the same mind was he,
					and his judgment was as totally depraved by his passions,
					who said,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let me, ye dull and formal fops, alone,
					</l>
                     <l>I am resolved, 'tis best to be undone.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But quite another spirit do we find running through the
					sayings of the incontinent:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Blame Nature only for it, blame not me,
					</l>
                     <l>Would she permit, I then should virtuous be,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Chrysippus of Euripides, Frag. 837 and 838.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>says one of them. And again,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ah! 'tis decreed by Fate. We know, 'tis true,
					</l>
                     <l>We know those virtues, which we ne'er pursue.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Chrysippus of Euripides, Frag. 837 and 838.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And another,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What will my swelling passions' force assuage?
					</l>
                     <l>No more can I sustain this tempest's rage,
					</l>
                     <l>Than anchor's fluke, dropt on loose ground, a storm;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.476"/>
            <p>where not improperly he compares the fluke of an anchor
					dropped in loose ground to that ill-grounded, feeble, and
					irresolute reason, which by the vanity, weakness, and luxury
					of the mind is easily brought to forsake the judgment.
					And the like metaphor has the poet made use of happily
					enough in these verses:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To us, in ships moored near the shore who lie,
					</l>
                     <l>Though strong the cables, when the winds rise high
					</l>
                     <l>Cables will prove but small security;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>where by the cables the poet means the judgment opposing itself against all that is evil or dishonest, which is,
					however, oftentimes disturbed and broken by violent and
					sudden gusts of the passions. For, indeed, the intemperate
					are borne away directly and with full sail to their pleasures;
					to them they deliver up themselves entirely, and thither it
					is they bend their whole course. While the incontinent,
					indirectly only, as endeavoring to sustain and repel the
					assaults of the passions and withstand their temptations,
					either is allured and as it were slides into evil, or else is
					plunged violently into it whether he will or no. As
					Timon, in his bitter way of raillery, reproaches Anaxarchus,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When first the dogged Anaxarchus strove
					</l>
                     <l>The power of virtue o'er his mind to prove,
					</l>
                     <l>Firm though he seemed, and obstinately good,
					</l>
                     <l>In vain th' impulse of temper he withstood.
					</l>
                     <l>Nature recoiled, whatever he could do;
					</l>
                     <l>He saw those ills, which yet he did pursue;
					</l>
                     <l>In this not single, other sophists too
					</l>
                     <l>Felt the same force, which they could ne'er subdue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And neither is a wise man continent, but temperate; nor
					a fool incontinent, but intemperate; the one taking true
					pleasure and delight in good, the other having no displeasure against evil. And therefore incontinence is said
					to be found only in a mind which is sophistical (or which
					barely makes a show of being governed and directed by
					prudence), and which has indeed the use of reason, but in
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.477"/>
					
					so weak and faint a manner, that it is not able to persevere
					in that which it knows to be right.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Thus we have seen the diversity between incontinence and intemperance. And as for continence and
					temperance, their differences are analogous, and bear
					proportion to those of the other, but in contrary respects.
					For remorse, grief, and indignation do always accompany
					continence; whereas in the mind of a temperate person
					there is all over such an evenness, calmness, and firmness,
					that, seeing with what wonderful easiness and tranquillity
					the irrational faculties go along with reason and submit
					to its directions, one cannot but call to mind that of the
					poet:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Swift the command ran through the raging deep;
					</l>
                     <l>Th' obedient waves compose themselves to sleep;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XII. 168.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>reason having quite deadened and repressed the vehement
					raging and furious motions of the passions and affections.
					But those whose assistance Nature necessarily requires
					are by reason rendered so agreeable and consenting, so
					submissive, friendly, and co-operative in the execution of
					all good designs and purposes, that they neither outrun it,
					nor recede from it, nor behave themselves disorderly, nor
					ever show the least disobedience; but every appetite willingly and cheerfully pursues its dictates,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">As sucking foal runs by his mother mare.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Which very much confirms what was said by Xenocrates
					of those who are true philosophers, namely, that they
					alone do that voluntarily which all others do against their
					wills for fear of the laws; being diverted and restrained
					from the pursuit of their pleasures, as a dog is frightened
					by a whipping or a cat scared by a noise, having regard to
					nothing else in the matter but their own danger.</p>
            <p>It is manifest then from what has been discoursed, that
					the soul does perceive within itself something that is firm
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.478"/>
					
					and immovable, totally distinct from its passions and appetites, these being what it does always oppose and is ever
					contending with. But some there are, nevertheless, who
					affirm that reason and passion do not materially differ from
					one another, and that there is not in the soul any faction,
					sedition, or dissension of two several and contending faculties, but only a shifting, conversion, or alteration of the
					same reason or rational faculty from one side to the other,
					backward and forward, which, by reason of the suddenness and swiftness of the change, is not perceptible by
					us; and therefore, that we do not consider that the same
					faculty of the soul is by nature so adapted as to be capable of both concupiscence and repentance, of anger and
					of fear, of being drawn to the commission of any lewdness
					or evil by the allurements of pleasure, and afterwards of
					being again retrieved from it. And as for lust, anger,
					fear, and such like passions, they will have them to be
					nothing but perverse opinions and false judgments, not
					arising or formed in any inferior part of the soul, peculiarly belonging to them, but being the advances and
					returns, or the motions forward and backward, the good
					likenings and more vehement efforts, and (in a word) such
					operations and energies of the whole rational and directive
					faculty as are ready to be turned this way or that with the
					greatest ease imaginable; like the sudden motions and
					irruptions in children, the violence and impetuosity whereof, by reason of their imbecility and weakness, are very
					fleeting and inconstant.</p>
            <p>But these opinions are against common sense and experience; for no man ever felt such a sudden change in
					himself, as that whenever he chose any thing he immediately judged it fit to be chosen, or that, on the other
					hand, whenever he judged any thing fit to be chosen he
					immediately made choice of it. Neither does the lover
					who is convinced by reason that his amour is fit to be
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.479"/>
					
					broken off, and that he ought to strive against his passion,
					therefore immediately cease to love; nor on the other side
					doth he desist reasoning, and cease from being able to give
					a right judgment of things, even then, when, being softened and overcome by luxury, he delivers himself up a
					captive to his lusts. But as, while by the assistance of
					reason he makes opposition to the efforts of his passions,
					they yet continue to solicit, and at last overcome him; so
					likewise, when he is overcome and forced to submit to
					them, by the light of reason does he plainly discern and
					know that he has done amiss; so that neither by the passions is reason effaced and destroyed, nor yet by reason is
					he rescued and delivered from them; but, being tossed to
					and fro between the one and the other, he is a kind of
					neuter, and participates in common of them both. And
					those, methinks, who imagine that one while the directive
					and rational part of the soul is changed into concupiscence
					and lust, and that by and by reason opposes itself against
					them, and they are changed into that, are not much unlike
					them who make the sportsman and his game not to be
					two, but one body, which, by a nimble and dexterous
					mutation of itself, one while appears in the shape of the
					huntsman, and at another turn puts on the form of a wild
					beast. For as these in a plain evident matter seem to
					be stalk blind, so they in the other case belie even their
					own senses, seeing they must needs feel in themselves not
					merely a change or mutation of one and the same thing,
					but a downright struggle and quarrel between two several
					and distinct faculties.</p>
            <p>But is not, say they, the deliberative power or faculty
					of a man often divided in itself, and distracted among several opinions contrary to one another, about that which is
					expedient; and yet is but one, simple, uniform thing? All
					this we grant to be true; but it does not reach the case we
					are speaking of. For that part of the soul where reason
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.480"/>
					
					and judgment are seated is not at variance with itself, but
					by one and the same faculty is conversant about different
					reasonings; or rather, there is but one simple power of
					reasoning, which employs itself on several arguments, as
					so many different subject-matters. And therefore it is, that
					no disturbance or uneasiness accompanies those reasonings
					or deliberations, where the passions do not at all interpose.
					Nor are we at any time forced, as it were, to choose any
					thing contrary to the dictates of our own reason, but when,
					as in a balance, some lurking hidden passions lay something in the scale against reason to weigh it down. And
					this often falls out to be the case, where it is not reasoning
					that is opposed to reasoning, but either ambition, or emulation, or favor, or jealousy, or fear, making a show as if
					there were a variance or contest between two differing reasons, according to that of Homer,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Shame in denial, in acceptance fear;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 98.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and of another poet,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hard fate to fall, but yet a glorious fate;
					</l>
                     <l>'Tis cowardly to live, but yet 'tis sweet.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in determining of controversies about contracts between man and man, it is by the interposition of the passions that so many disputes and delays are created. So
					likewise in the consultations and counsels of kings, they
					who design to make their court incline not to one side of
					the question or debate rather than the other, but only accommodate themselves to their own passions, without any
					regard to the interest of the public. Which is the reason
					that in aristocratical governments the magistrates will not
					suffer orators in their pleadings, by declaiming and haranguing, to raise the passions and move the affections. For
					reason, not being disturbed or diverted by passion, tends
					directly to that which is honorable and just; but if the
					passions are once raised, there immediately follows a mighty
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.481"/>
					
					controversy and struggle between pleasure and grief on the
					one hand, and reason and judgment on the other. For otherwise how comes it to pass, that in philosophical disputes
					and disquisitions we so often and with so little trouble are by
					others drawn off from our own opinions and wrought upon
					to change them?&mdash;and that Aristotle himself, Democritus,
					and Chrysippus have without any concern or regret of mind,
					nay even with great satisfaction to themselves, retracted
					some of those points which they formerly so much approved
					of, and were wont so stiffly to maintain? For no passions
					residing in the contemplative and scientifical part of the
					soul make any tumult or disturbance therein, and the irrational and brutal faculties remain quiet and calm, without
					busying themselves to intermeddle in matters of that kind.
					By which means it falls out, that reason no sooner comes
					within view of truth, but rejecting that which is false it
					readily embraces it; forasmuch as there is in the former
					what is not to be found in the other, namely, a willingness
					to assent and disagree as there is occasion; whereas in all
					deliberations had, judgments made, and resolutions taken
					about such things as are to be reduced into practice, and
					are mixed and interwoven with the passions and affections,
					reason meets with much opposition, and is put under great
					difficulties, by being stopped and interrupted in its course
					by the brutal faculties of the mind, throwing in its way
					either pleasure or fear or grief or lust, or some such like
					temptation or discouragement. And then the decision of
					these disputes belongs to sense, which is equally affected
					with both the one and the other; and whichsoever of
					them gets the mastery, the other is not thereby destroyed,
					but (though struggling and resisting all the while) is forced
					only to comply and go along with the conqueror. As an
					amorous person, for example, finding himself engaged in
					an amour he cannot approve of, has immediately recourse
					to his reason, to oppose the force of that against his passion,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.482"/>
					
					 as having them both together actually subsisting in
					his soul, plainly discerning them to be several and distinct,
					and feeling a sensible conflict between the two, while he
					endeavors (as it were) with his hand to repress and keep
					down the part which is inflamed and rages so violently
					within him. But, on the contrary, in those deliberations
					and disquisitions where the passions have nothing to do,
					such I mean as belong properly to the contemplative part
					of the soul, if the reasons are equally balanced, not inclining more to one side than another, then is there no
					determinate judgment formed, but there remains a doubting, as if there were a rest or suspense of the understanding between two contrary opinions. But if there happen
					to be any inclination or determination towards one side,
					that prevailing must needs get the better of the other, but
					without any regret or obstinate opposition from it against
					the opinion which is received. In short, whenever the
					contest seems to be of reason against reason, in that case
					we have no manner of sense of two distinct powers, but
					of one simple, uniform faculty only, under different apprehensions or imaginations; but when the dispute is between
					the irrational part and reason, where nature has so ordered
					it that neither the victory nor the defeat can be had without anxiety and regret, there immediately the two contending powers divide the soul in the quarrel, and thereby
					make the difference and distinction between them to be
					most plain and evident.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>And not only from their contests, but no less also
					from the consequences that follow thereupon, may one
					clearly enough discern the source and original of the passions to be different from that of reason. For since a man
					may set his affection upon an ingenuous and virtuously disposed child, and no less also upon one that is naughty and
					dissolute, and since also one may have unreasonable and
					indecent transports of anger against his children or his
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.483"/>
					
					parents, and on the contrary, may justly and unblamably
					be angry in their defence against their enemies and tyrants;
					as in the one case there is perceived a struggle and dispute
					of the passions against reason, so in the other may be seen
					a ready submission and agreement of them, running to its
					assistance, and lending as it were their helping hand. To
					illustrate this with a familiar example,&mdash;after a good man
					has in obedience to the laws married a convenient wife, he
					then in the first place comes to a resolution of conversing
					and cohabiting with her wisely and honestly, and of making
					at least a civil husband; but in process of time, custom
					and constant familiarity having bred within him a true
					passion for her, he sensibly finds that upon principles of
					reason his affection' and love for her are every day more
					and more improved and grow upon him. So in like manner, young men having met with kind and gentle masters,
					to guide and inform their minds in the study of philosophy
					and sciences, make use of them at first for instruction only
					and information, but afterwards come to have such an affection for them, that from familiar companions and scholars
					they become their lovers and admirers, and are so accounted.
					And the same happens also to most men, with respect to
					good magistrates in the commonwealth, to their neighbors,
					and to their kindred; for, beginning an acquaintance upon
					necessity and interest, for the exchange of the common
					offices of intercourse and commerce with one another, they
					do afterwards by degrees, ere they are aware, grow to have
					a love and friendship for them; reason in such and the
					like cases having over-persuaded and even compelled the
					passions to take delight in and pursue what it before had
					approved of and consented to. As for the poet who said,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of modesty two kinds there be;
					</l>
                     <l>The one we cannot blame,
					</l>
                     <l>The other troubleth many a house,
					</l>
                     <l>And doth decay the same;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Hippol. 384.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.3.p.484"/>
            <p>doth he not plainly hereby intimate, that he had oftentimes found by experience that this affection of the mind,
					by a sheepish, shamefaced backwardness, and by foolishly
					bashful delays against all reason, had lost him the opportunities and seasons of making his fortune, and hindered
					and disappointed many brave actions and noble enterprises?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>But these men, though by the force of these arguments sufficiently convinced, do yet seek for evasions, by
					calling shame by the name of modesty, pleasures by that
					of joy, and fear by that of caution. No man would go
					about to blame them for giving things the softest names
					they can invent, if they would be so just as to bestow these
					good words upon those passions and affections only which
					have put themselves under the conduct and direction of
					reason, and leave those which oppose reason and offer violence to it to be called by their own proper and odious
					names. But, when fully convinced by the tears they shed,
					by the trembling of their joints, and by their sudden changing of color back and forward, if instead of plainly calling
					the passions whereof these are the effects grief and fear, they,
					make use of the fantastic terms of compunctions and conturbations, and to varnish over and disguise the lusts and
					affections, give them the name only of so many forwardnesses of mind, and I know not what else, they seem not
					to act like philosophers, but, relying upon little shifts and
					sophistical artifices, under an amusement of strange words,
					they vainly hope to cover and conceal the nature of
					things.</p>
            <p>And yet even these men themselves sometimes make use
					of very proper terms to express these matters; as, for instance, when they call those joys, volitions, and cautions
					of theirs, not by the name of apathies, as if they were devoid of all manner of passions, but of eupathies. For
					then is there said to be an eupathy, or good disposition of
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.485"/>
					
					the affections, when reason hath not utterly destroyed, but
					composed and adjusted them in the minds of discreet and
					temperate persons. But what then becomes of vicious
					and dissolute persons? Why, if they should judge it reasonable to love their parents, instead of a mistress or a
					gallant, are they unable to perform this; but should they
					judge it fitting to set their hearts upon a strumpet or a
					parasite, the judgment is no sooner made, but they are
					most desperately in love? Now were the passions and
					judgment one, it could not be but that the passions of love
					and hatred would immediately follow upon judgments made
					what to love and hate. But we see the contrary often happen; for the passions, as they submit to some resolutions and
					judgments, so others again they oppose themselves to, and
					refuse to comply with. Whence it is that, compelled thereto by truth and the evidence of things, they do not affirm
					every judgment and determination of reason to be passion,
					but that only which excites too violent and inordinate an
					appetite; acknowledging thereby that the faculty we have
					in us of judging is quite another thing than that which is
					susceptible of the passions, as is that also which moveth
					from that which is moved. Nay, even Chrysippus himself,
					in many places defining patience and continence to be
					habits of submitting to and pursuing the choice and direction of right reason, doth thereby make it apparent that
					by the force of truth he was driven to confess that it is
					one thing in us which is obedient and submissive, but
					another and quite a different thing which it obeys when
					it submits, but resists when it does not submit.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Now, as for those who make all sins and faults to
					be equal, to examine whether in other matters they have
					not also departed from the truth is not at this time and in
					this place seasonable; since they seem not herein only,
					but in most things else, to advance unreasonable paradoxes
					against common sense and experience. For according to
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.486"/>
					
					them, all our passions and affections are so many faults
					and whosoever grieves, fears, or desires, commits sin. But,
					with their leave, nothing is more visible and apparent than
					the mighty difference in those and all other passions, according as we are more or less affected with them. For
					will any man say that the fear of Dolon was no more than
					that of Ajax, who, being forced to give way before the
					enemy,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sometimes retreated back, then faced about,
					</l>
                     <l>And step by step retired at once, and fought?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XI. 547.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Or compare the grief of Plato for the death of Socrates to
					the sorrow and anguish of mind which Alexander felt,
					when, for having murdered Clitus, he attempted to lay
					violent hands upon himself. For our grief is commonly
					increased and augmented above measure by sudden and
					unexpected accidents. And that which surprises us on
					the sudden, contrary to our hope and expectation, is much
					more uneasy and grievous than that which is either foreseen, or not very unlikely to happen; as must needs fall
					out in the case of those who, expecting nothing more than
					to see the happiness, advancement, and glory of a friend
					or a kinsman, should hear of his being put to the most exquisite tortures, as Parmenio did of his son Philotas. And
					who will ever say that the anger of Magas against Philemon can bear any proportion to the rage of Nicocreon
					against Anaxarchus? The occasion given was in both
					cases the same, each of them having severally been bitterly reproached and reviled by the other. For whereas Nicocreon caused Anaxarchus to be broken to pieces and brayed
					in a mortar with iron pestles, Magas only commanded the
					executioner to lay the edge of the naked sword upon the
					neck of Philemon, and so dismissed him. And therefore
					Plato called anger the nerves of the mind; because, as it
					may swell and be made more intense by sourness and ill-nature,
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.487"/>
					
					 so may it be slackened and remitted by gentleness
					and good-nature.</p>
            <p>But to elude these and such like objections, they will
					not allow these intense and vehement efforts of the passions to be according to judgment, or so to proceed from it
					as if that were therein faulty; but they call them cessations, contractions, and extensions or diffusions, which by
					the irrational part are capable of being increased or diminished. But that there are also differences of judgment
					is most plain and evident; for some there are who take
					poverty to be no evil at all, others who look upon it as a
					great evil, and others again who esteem it to be the greatest evil and worst thing in the world, insomuch that rather
					than endure it they would dash themselves in pieces against
					the rocks, or cast themselves headlong into the sea. And
					among those who reckon death to be an evil, some are of
					that opinion, in regard only that it deprives us of the enjoyment of the good things of the world, as others are
					with respect to the eternal torments and horrible punishments under ground in hell. As for bodily health, some
					love it no otherwise than as it is agreeable to Nature, and
					very convenient and useful; while others value it as the
					most sovereign good, in comparison whereof they make
					no reckoning of riches or children, no, nor of sceptres and
					crowns,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Which make men equal to the Gods above.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will they, in fine, allow even virtue itself to signify
					any thing or be of any use, without good health. So that
					hence it sufficiently appears that, in the judgments men
					make of things, they may be mistaken and very faulty with
					respect to both the extremes of too much and too little;
					but I shall pursue this argument no farther in this place.</p>
            <p>Thus much may, however, fairly be assumed from what
					has already been said on this head, that even they themselves do allow a plain difference between the judgment
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.488"/>
					
					and the irrational faculties, by means whereof, they say,
					the passions become greater and more violent; and so,
					while they cavil and contend about names and words, they
					give up the very cause to those who maintain the irrational
					part of the soul, which is the seat of the passions, to be
					several and distinct from that faculty by which we reason
					and make a judgment of things. And indeed Chrysippus,
					in those books which he wrote of Anomology,&mdash;after he
					has told us that anger is blind, not discerning oftentimes
					those things which are plain and conspicuous, and as
					frequently casting a mist upon such things as were before
					clear and evident,&mdash;proceeds a little farther in this manner: For, says he, the passions, being once raised, not
					only reject and drive away reason and those things which
					appear otherwise than they would have them, but violently
					push men forward to actions that are contrary to reason.
					And then he makes use of the testimony of Menander,
					saying,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>What have I done? Where has my soul been strayed?
					</l>
                     <l>Would she not stay to see herself obeyed,
					</l>
                     <l>But let me act what I abhorred but now?</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And again the same Chrysippus a little after says: Every
					rational creature is by Nature so disposed as to use reason
					in all things, and to be governed by it; but yet oftentimes
					it falls out that we dispose and reject it, being carried away
					by another more violent and over-ruling motion. In these
					words he plainly enough acknowledges what uses in such
					a case to happen on acccount of the difference and contest
					between the passions and reason. And upon any other
					ground it would be ridiculous (as Plato says) to suppose a
					man to be sometimes better than himself, and sometimes
					again worse; one while to be his own master, and another
					while his own slave.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>For how could it possibly be, that a man should be
					better and worse than himself, and at once both his own
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.489"/>
					
					master and slave, if every one were not in some sort
					naturally double or twofold, having in himself at the same
					time a better part and a worse? For so may he be reckoned
					to have a power over himself and to be better than himself, who has his worse and inferior faculties in obedience
					and subjection to the superior and more excellent; whereas
					he who suffers his nobler powers to fall under the government and direction of the intemperate and irrational part
					of the soul is less and worse than himself, and has wholly
					lost the command over himself, and is in a state which is
					contrary to Nature. For by the order of Nature, reason,
					which is divine, ought to have the sovereignty and dominion
					over the irrational and brutal faculties, which, deriving
					their original from the body, and being incorporated, as it
					were, and thoroughly mixed therewith, bear a very near
					resemblance to it, are replenished with, and do participate
					in common of the qualities, properties, and passions thereof; as is plain from our more vehement motions and efforts
					towards corporeal objects, which always increase or diminish in vigor according to the several changes and alterations which happen in the body. From whence it is that
					young men are in their lusts and appetites, because of the
					abundance and warmth of their blood, so quick, forward,
					hot, and furious; whereas in old men all natural fire being
					almost extinguished, and the first principles and source of
					the affections and passions, seated about the liver, being
					much lessened and debilitated, reason becomes more vigorous and predominant, while the appetites languish and
					decay together with the body. And after this manner it is
					that the nature of beasts is framed and disposed to divers
					passions. For it is not from any strength or weakness of
					thought, or from any opinions right or wrong which they
					form to themselves, that some of them are so bold and
					venturous, and dare encounter any thing, and others of
					them are fearful and cowardly, shrinking at every danger;
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.490"/>
					
					but from the force and power of the blood, the spirits, and
					the body does this diversity of passions in them arise; for
					that part where the passions are seated, being derived from
					the body, as from its root, retains all the qualities and propensions of that from whence it is extracted.</p>
            <p>Now that in man there is a sympathy and an agreeable
					and correspondent motion of the body with the passions
					and appetites, is proved by the paleness and blushings of
					the face, by the tremblings of the joints, and by the palpitation of the heart; and, on the contrary, by the diffusion
					or dilatation which we feel upon the hope and expectation
					of pleasures. But when the mind or intellect doth move
					of itself alone, without any passion to disorder and ruffle
					it, then is the body at repose and rests quiet, having nothing at all to do with those acts and operations of the mind;
					as, when it takes into consideration a proposition in
					mathematics or some such scientifical thing, it calls not for
					the aid or assistance of the irrational or brutal faculties.
					From whence also it is very apparent that there are in us
					two distinct parts, differing in their powers and faculties
					from one another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>In fine, throughout the whole world, all things (as
					they themselves are forced to confess, and is evident in
					itself) are governed and directed, some by a certain habit,
					some by Nature, others by a brutal or irrational soul, and
					some again by that which has reason and understanding.
					Of all which things man does in some measure participate,
					and is concerned in all the above-mentioned differences.
					For he is contained by habit, and nourished by Nature; he
					makes use of reason and understanding; he wants not his
					share of the irrational soul; he has also in him a native
					source and inbred principle of the passions, not as adventitious, but necessary to him, which ought not therefore
					to be utterly rooted out, but only pruned and cultivated.
					For it is not the method and custom of reason&mdash;in imitation
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.491"/>
					
					 either of the manner of the Thracians or of what
					Lycurgus ordered to be done to the vines&mdash;to destroy and
					tear up all the passions and affections indifferently, good
					and bad, useful and hurtful together; but rather&mdash;like
					some kind and careful Deity who has a tender regard to
					the growth and improvement of fruit-trees and plants&mdash;to
					cut away and clip off that which grows wild and rank, and
					to dress and manage the rest that it may serve for use and
					profit. For as they who are afraid of being drunk pour
					not their wine upon the ground, but dilute it with water;
					so neither do they who fear any violent commotion of their
					passions go about utterly to destroy and eradicate, but
					rather wisely to temper and moderate them. And as they
					who use to break horses and oxen do not go about to take
					away their goings, or to render them unfit for labor and
					service, but only strive to cure them of their unluckiness
					and flinging up their heels, and to bring them to be patient
					of the bit and yoke, so as to become useful; after the
					same manner reason makes very good use of the passions,
					after they are well subdued and made gentle, without
					either tearing in pieces or over-much weakening that part
					of the soul which was made to be obedient to her. In
					Pindar we find it said:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>As 'tis the horse's pride to win the race,
					</l>
                     <l>And to plough up the fruitful soil
					</l>
                     <l>Is the laborious ox's toil,
					</l>
                     <l>So the fierce dog we take the foaming boar to chase.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But much more useful than these in their several kinds
					are the whole brood of passions, when they become attendants to reason, and when, being assistant and obedient to
					virtue, they give life and vigor to it.</p>
            <p>Thus, moderate anger is of admirable use to courage or
					fortitude; hatred and aversion for ill men promotes the
					execution of justice; and a just indignation against those
					who are prosperous beyond what they deserve is then both
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.492"/>
					
					convenient and even necessary, when with pride and insolence their minds are so swollen and elated, that they
					need to be repressed and taken down. Neither by any
					means can a man, though he never so much desire it, be
					able to separate from friendship a natural propension to
					affection; from humanity and good nature, tenderness and
					commiseration; nor from true benevolence, a mutual participation of joy and grief. And if they run into an error
					who would take away all love that they may destroy mad
					and wanton passions, neither can those be in the right
					who, for the sake of covetousness, condemn all other appetites and desires. Which is full as ridiculous as if one
					should always refuse to run, because one time or other he
					may chance to catch a fall; or to shoot, because he may
					sometimes happen to miss the mark; or should forbear all
					singing, because a discord or a jar is offensive to the ear.
					For, as in sounds the music and harmony thereof takes
					away neither the sharpest nor the deepest notes, and in
					our bodies physic procureth health, not by the destruction
					of heat and cold, but by a due and proportionable temperature and mixture of them both together; so in the same
					manner it happeneth in the soul of man, when reason
					becomes victorious and triumphant by reducing the faculties of the mind which belong to the passions, and all
					their motions, to a due moderation and mediocrity. And
					excessive and unmeasurable joy or grief or fear in the
					soul (not, however, either joy, grief, or fear, simply in
					itself) may very properly be resembled to a great swelling
					or inflammation in the body. And therefore Homer, where
					he says,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A valiant man doth never color change;
					</l>
                     <l>Excessive fear to him is very strange,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIII. 284.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>does not take away all fear (but that only which is extreme and unmanly), that bravery and courage may not be
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.493"/>
					
					thought to be fool-hardiness, nor boldness and resolution
					pass for temerity and rashness. And therefore he that in
					pleasures and delights can prescribe bounds to his lusts and
					desires, and in punishing offences can moderate his rage
					and hatred to the offenders, shall in one case get the reputation not of an insensible, but temperate person, and in
					the other be accounted a man of justice without cruelty or
					bitterness. Whereas, if all the passions, if that were possible, were clean rooted out, reason in most men would
					grow sensibly more dull and inactive than the pilot of a
					ship in a calm.</p>
            <p>And to these things (as it should seem) prudent lawgivers having regard have wisely taken care to excite and
					encourage in commonwealths and cities the ambition and
					emulation of their people amongst one another, and with
					trumpets, drums, and flutes to whet their anger and courage against their enemies. For not only in poetry (as
					Plato very well observes), he that is inspired by the Muses,
					and as it were possessed by a poetical fury, will make him
					that is otherwise a master of his trade and an exact critic
					in poetry appear ridiculous; but also in fighting, those who
					are elevated and inspired with a noble rage, and a resolution and courage about the common pitch, become invincible, and are not to be withstood. And this is that warlike
					fury which the Gods, as Homer will have it, infuse into
					men of honor:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">He spoke, and every word new strength inspired;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">This more than human rage is from the Gods;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XV. 262; V. 185.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as if to reason the Gods had joined some or other of passions, as an incitement or, if I may so say, a vehicle to
					push and carry it forward.</p>
            <p>Nay we often see these very men against whom I now
					dispute exciting and encouraging young persons with
					
					<pb id="v.3.p.494"/>
					
					praises, and as often checking and rebuking them with
					severe reprimands; whereupon in the one case there must
					follow pleasure and satisfaction as necessarily as grief and
					trouble are produced in the other. For reprehension and
					admonition certainly strike us with repentance and shame,
					whereof this is comprehended under fear, as the other is
					under grief. And these are the things they chiefly make
					use of for correction and amendment. Which seems to
					be the reason why Diogenes, to some who had magnified
					Plato, made this reply: What can there be in him, said
					he, so much to be valued, who, having been so long a
					philosopher, has never yet been known so much as to
					excite the single passion of grief in the mind of any one?
					And certainly the mathematics cannot so properly be called
					(to use the words of Xenocrates) the handles of philosophy,
					as these passions are of young men, namely, bashfulness,
					desire, repentance, pleasure, pain, ambition; whereon right
					reason and the law discreetly laying their salutary hands
					do thereby effectually and speedily reduce a young man
					into the right way. Agreeably hereunto the Lacedaemonian instructor of youth was in the right, when he professed that he would bring it to pass that youths under
					his care should take a pleasure and satisfaction in good
					and have an abhorrence for evil, than which there cannot
					be a greater or nobler end of the liberal education of
					youth proposed or assigned.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>