<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De genio Socratis</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.109">
      <body>
         <head>A discourse concerning Socrates's daemon. <lb/> Caphisias, Timotheus, Archidamus, children of Archinus,
				Lysithides, other companions.</head>
         <pb id="v.2.p.378"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>I HEARD lately, Caphisias, a neat saying of a painter,
				comprised in a similitude upon those that came to view his
				pictures. For he said, the ignorant and unskilful were like
				those that saluted a whole company together, but the
				curious and knowing like those that complimented each
				single person; for the former take no exact, but only one
				general view of the performance; but those that with
				judgment examine part by part take notice of every stroke
				that is either well or ill done in the whole picture. The
				duller and lazy sort are abundantly satisfied with a short
				account and upshot of any business. But he that is of a
				generous and noble temper, that is fitted to be a spectator
				of virtue, as of a curious piece of art, is more delighted
				with the particulars. For, upon a general view, much of
				fortune is discovered; but when the particulars are examined, then appear the art and contrivance, the boldness
				in conquering intervening accidents, and the reason that
				was mixed with and tempered the heat and fury of the
				undertakers. Suppose us to be of this sort, and give us
				an account of the whole design, how from the very beginning it was carried on, what company you kept, and what
				particular discourse you had that day;&mdash;a thing so much
				desired, that I protest I would willingly go to Thebes to be
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.379"/>
				
				informed, did not the Athenians already suspect me to lean
				too much to the Boeotian interest.</p>
            <p>CAPHISIAS. Indeed Archidamus, your kind eagerness
					after this story is so obliging, that, putting myself above all
					business (as Pindar says), I should have come on purpose
					to give you a relation. But since I am now come upon an
					embassy, and have nothing to do until I receive an answer
					to my memorial, to be uncivil and not to satisfy the request
					of an obliging friend would revive the old reproach that
					hath been cast upon the Boeotians for morose sullenness and
					hating good discourse, a reproach which began to die in
					the time of Socrates. But as for the rest of the company,
					pray sir, are they at leisure to hear such a story?&mdash;for I
					must be very long, since you enjoin me to add the particular discourses that passed between us.</p>
            <p>ARCH. You do not know the men, Caphisias, though
					they are worthy your acquaintance; men of good families,
					and no enemies to you. This is Lysithides, Thrasybulus's
					nephew; this Timotheus, the son of Conon; these
					Archinus's sons; and all the rest my very good acquaintance, so that you need not doubt a favorable and obliging
					audience.</p>
            <p>CAPH. Very well; but where shall I begin the story?
					How much of these affairs are you acquainted with
					already?</p>
            <p>ARCH. We know, Caphisias, how matters stood at
					Thebes before the exiles returned,&mdash;how Archias, Leontidas, and their associates, having persuaded Phoebidas the
					Spartan in the time of peace to surprise that castle, banished some of the citizens, awed others, took the power
					into their own hands, and tyrannized against all equity and
					law. We understood Melon's and Pelopidas's designs,
					having (as you know) entertained them, and having conversed with them ever since they were banished. We
					knew likewise that the Spartans fined Phoebidas for taking
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.380"/>
					
					the Cadmea, and in their expedition to Olynthus cashiered
					him; but sent a stronger garrison, under Lysinoridas and
					two more, to command the castle; and further, that Ismenias presently after his trial was basely murdered. For
					Gorgidas wrote constantly to the exiles, and sent them all
					the news; so that you have nothing to do but only to inform us in the particulars of your friends' return and the
					seizing of the tyrants.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>CAPH. In those days, Archidamus, all that were concerned in the design, as often as our business required,
				used to meet at Simmias's house, who then lay lame of a
				blow upon his shin. This we covered with a pretence of
				meeting for improvement and philosophical discourse, and,
				to take off all suspicion, we many times invited Archias
				and Leontidas, who were not altogether averse to such conversation. Besides, Simmias, having been a long time
				abroad and conversant with different nations, was lately
				returned to Thebes, full of all sorts of stories and strange
				relations. To him Archias, when free from business,
				would resort with the youth of Thebes, and sit and hear
				with a great deal of delight; being better pleased to see
				us mind philosophy and learning than their illegal actions.
				Now the same day in which it was agreed that about night
				the exiles should cone privately to town, a messenger,
				whom none of us all but Charon knew, came from them
				by Pherenicus's order, and told us that twelve of the
				youngest of the exiles were now hunting on the mountain
				Cithaeron, and designed to come at night, and that he was
				sent to deliver this and to know in whose house they should
				be received, that as soon as they entered they might go directly thither. This startling us, Charon put an end to all
				our doubts by offering to receive them in his house. With
				this answer the messenger returned.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>But Theocritus the soothsayer, grasping me by the
				hand, and looking on Charon that went just before us, said:
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.381"/>
				
				That Charon, Caphisias, is no philosopher, nor so general
				nor so acute a scholar as thy brother Epaminondas, and yet
				you see that, Nature leading him, under the direction of
				the law, to noble actions, he willingly ventures on the greatest danger for the benefit of his country; but Epaminondas, who thinks he knows more of virtue than any of
				the Boeotians, is dull and inactive; and though opportunity
				presents, though there cannot be a fairer occasion, and
				though he is fitted to embrace it, yet he refuseth to join,
				and will not make one in this generous attempt. And I
				replied: Courageous Theocritus, we do what upon mature
				deliberation we have approved, but Epaminondas, being of
				a contrary opinion and thinking it better not to take this
				course, rationally complies with his judgment, whilst he
				refuseth to meddle in those matters which his reason upon
				our desire cannot approve, and to which his nature is
				averse. Nor can I think it prudent to force a physician to
				use fire and a lancet, that promiseth to cure the disease
				without them. What, said Theocritus, doth he not approve of our method No, I replied, he would have no
				citizens put to death without a trial at law; but if we
				would endeavor to free our country without slaughter and
				bloodshed, none would more readily comply; but since we
				slight his reasons and follow our own course, he desires to
				be excused, to be guiltless of the blood and slaughter of
				his citizens, and to be permitted to watch an opportunity
				when he may deliver his country according to equity and
				right. For this action may go too far, Pherenicus, it is
				true, and Pelopidas may assault the bad men and the oppressors of the people; but Eumolpidas and Samidas, men
				of extraordinary heat and violence, prevailing in the night,
				will hardly sheathe their swords until they have filled the
				whole city with slaughter and cut in pieces many of the
				chief men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Anaxidorus, overhearing this discourse of mine to
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.382"/>
				
				Theocritus (for he was just by), bade us be cautious, for
				Archias with Lysanoridas the Spartan were coming from
				the castle directly towards us. Upon this advice we left
				off; and Archias, calling Theocritus aside together with
				Lysanoridas, privately discoursed him a long while, so that
				we were very much afraid lest they had some suspicion or
				notice of our design, and examined Theocritus about it.
				In the mean time Phyllidas (you know him, Archidamus)
				who was then secretary to Archias the general, who knew
				of the exiles coming and was one of the associates, taking
				me by the hand, as he used to do, before the company,
				found fault with the late exercises and wrestling he had
				seen; but afterwards leading me aside, he enquired after
				the exiles, and asked whether they were resolved to be
				punctual to the day. And upon my assuring that they
				were, then he replied, I have very luckily provided a feast
				to-day to treat Archias, make him drunk, and then deliver
				him an easy prey to the invaders. Excellently contrived,
				Phyllidas, said I, and prithee endeavor to draw all or most
				of our enemies together. That, said he, is very hard, nay,
				rather impossible; for Archias, being in hopes of the company of some noble women there, will not yield that
				Leontidas should be present, so that it will be necessary to
				divide the associates into two companies, that we may surprise both the houses. For, Archias and Leontidas being
				taken off, I suppose the others will presently fly, or staying
				make no stir, being very well satisfied if they can be permitted to be safe and quiet. So, said I, we will order it;
				but about what, I wonder, are they discoursing with Theocritus? And Phyllidas replied, I cannot certainly tell, but
				I have heard that some omens and oracles portend great
				disasters and calamities to Sparta; and perhaps they consult him about those matters. Theocritus had just left
				them, when Phidolaus the Haliartian meeting us said:
				Simmias would have you stay here a little while, for he is
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.383"/>
				
				interceding with Leontidas for Amphitheus, and begs that
				instead of dying, according to the sentence, he may be
				banished.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>Well, said Theocritus, this happens very opportunely, for I had a mind to ask what was seen and what
				found in Alcmena's tomb lately opened amongst you, for
				perhaps, sir, you were present when Agesilaus sent to
				fetch the relics to Sparta. And Phidolaus replied: Indeed
				I was not present at the opening of the grave, for I was
				not delegated, being extremely concerned and very angry
				with my fellow-citizens for permitting it to be done. There
				were found no relics of a body; but a small brazen bracelet, and two earthen pipkins full of earth, which now by
				length of time was grown very hard and petrified. Upon
				the monument there was a brazen plate full of strange,
				because very ancient, letters; for though, when the plate
				was washed, all the strokes were very easily perceived,
				yet nobody could make any thing of them; for they were
				a particular, barbarous, and very like the Egyptian character. And therefore Agesilaus, as the story goes, sent a
				transcript of them to the king of Egypt, desiring him to
				show them to the priests, and if they understood them, to
				send him the meaning and interpretation. But perhaps
				in this matter Simmias can inform us, for at that time he
				studied their philosophy and frequently conversed with
				the priests upon that account. The Haliartii believe the
				great scarcity and overflowing of the pool that followed
				were not effects of chance, but a particular judgment upon
				them for permitting the grave to be opened. And Theocritus, after a little pause, said: Nay, there seem some
				judgments to hang over the Lacedaemonians themselves,
				as those omens about which Lysanoridas just now discoursed me portend. And now he is gone to Haliartus to
				fill up the grave again, and, as the oracle directs, to make
				some oblations to Alcmena and Aleus; but who this Aleus
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.384"/>
				
				is, he cannot tell. And as soon as he returns, he must
				endeavor to find the sepulchre of Dirce, which not one of
				the Thebans themselves, besides the captains of the horse,
				knows; for he that goes out of his office leads his successor
				to the place alone, and in the dark; there they offer some
				sacrifices, but without fire, and leaving no mark behind
				them, they separate from one another, and come home
				again in the dark. So that I believe, Phidolaus, it will be
				no easy matter for him to discover it. For most of those
				that have been duly elected to that office are now in exile;
				nay, all besides Gorgidas and Plato; and they will never
				ask those, for they are afraid of them. And our present
				officers are invested in the castle with the spear only and
				the seal, but know nothing of the tomb, and cannot direct
				him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Whilst Theocritus was speaking, Leontidas and his
				friends went out; and we going in saluted Simmias, sitting
				upon his couch, very much troubled because his petition
				was denied. He, looking up upon us, cried out: Good
				God! The savage barbarity of these men! And was it
				not an excellent remark of Thales, who, when his friends
				asked him, upon his return from his long travels, what
				strange news he brought home, replied, <q direct="unspecified">I have seen a
					tyrant an old man.</q> For even he that hath received no
				particular injury, yet disliking their stiff pride and haughty
				carriage, becomes an enemy to all lawless and unaccountable powers. But Heaven perhaps will take these things
				into consideration. But, Caphisias, do you know that
				stranger that came lately hither, who he is? And I replied, I do not know whom you mean. Why, said he,
				Leontidas told me that there was a man at night seen to
				rise out of Lysis's tomb, with great pomp and a long train
				of attendants, and that he had lodged there all night upon
				beds made of leaves and boughs; for the next morning
				such were discovered there, with some relics of burnt
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.385"/>
				
				sacrifices and some milk-oblations; and that in the morning he enquired of every one he met, whether he should
				find Polymnis's sons at home. I wonder, said I, who it is,
				for by your description I guess him to be no mean man.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Well, said Phidolaus, when he comes we will entertain him; but at the present, Simmias, if you know any
				thing more of those letters about which we were talking,
				pray let us have it; for it is said that the Egyptian priests
				took into consideration the writing of a certain table which
				Agesilaus had from us when he opened Alcmena's tomb.
				As for the table, replied Simmias, I know nothing of it;
				but Agetoridas the Spartan came to Memphis with letters
				from Agesilaus to Chonouphis the priest, whilst I, Plato,
				and Ellopio the Peparethian, studied together at his house.
				He came by order of the king, who enjoined Chonouphis,
				if he understood the writing, to send him the interpretation with all speed. And he in three days' study, having
				collected all the different sorts of characters that could be
				found in the old books, wrote back to the king and likewise told us, that the writing enjoined the Greeks to
				institute games in honor of the Muses; that the characters were such as were used in the time of Proteus, and
				that Hercules, the son of Amphitryo, then learned them;
				and that the Gods by this admonished the Greeks to live
				peaceably and at quiet, to contend in philosophy to the
				honor of the Muses, and, laying aside their arms, to determine what is right and just by reason and discourse.
				We then thought that Chonouphis spoke right; and that
				opinion was confirmed when, as we were sailing from
				Egypt, about Caria some Delians met us, who desired
				Plato, being well skilled in geometry, to solve an odd
				oracle lately delivered by Apollo. The oracle was this:
				<q direct="unspecified">Then the Delians and all the other Greeks should enjoy
					some respite from their present evils, when they had
					doubled the altar at Delos.</q> They, not comprehending
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.386"/>
				
				the meaning of the words, after many ridiculous endeavors
				(for each of the sides being doubled, they had framed a
				body, instead of twice, eight times as big) made application to Plato to clear the difficulty. He, calling to mind
				what the Egyptian had told him, said that the God was
				merry upon the Greeks, who despised learning; that he
				severely reflected on their ignorance, and admonished them
				to apply themselves to the deepest parts of geometry; for
				this was not to be done by a dull short-sighted intellect,
				but one exactly skilled in the natures and properties of
				lines; it required skill to find the true proportion by
				which alone a body of a cubic figure can be doubled,
				all its dimensions being equally increased. He said that
				Eudoxus the Cnidian or Helico the Cyzicenian might do
				this for them; but that was not the thing desired by the
				God; for by this oracle he enjoined all the Greeks to
				leave off war and contention, and apply themselves to
				study, and, by learning and arts moderating the passions,
				to live peaceably with one another, and profit the community.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Whilst Simmias was speaking, my father Polymnis
				came in, and sitting down by him said: Epaminondas desires you and the rest of the company, unless some urgent
				business requires your attendance, to stay for him here a
				little while, designing to bring you acquainted with this
				stranger, who is a very worthy man; and the design upon
				which he comes is very genteel and honorable. He is a
				Pythagorean of the Italian sect, and comes hither to make
				some offerings to old Lysis at his tomb, according to divers
				dreams and very notable appearances that he hath seen.
				He hath brought a good sum of money with him, and
				thinks himself bound to satisfy Epaminondas for keeping
				Lysis in his old age; and is very eager, though we are
				neither willing nor desire him, to relieve his poverty.
				And Simmias, glad at this news, replied: You tell me, sir,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.387"/>
				
				of a wonderful man and worthy professor of philosophy;
				but why doth he not come directly to us? I think, said my
				father, he lay all night at Lysis's tomb; and therefore
				Epaminondas hath now led him to the Ismenus to wash;
				and when that is done, they will be here. For before he
				came to our house, he lodged at the tomb, intending to
				take up the relics of the body and transport them into
				Italy, if some genius at night should not advise him
				to forbear.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>As soon as my father had ended this discourse, Galaxidorus cried out: Good Gods! how hard a matter is it to
				find a man pure from vanity and superstition! For some
				are betrayed into those fooleries by their ignorance and
				weakness; others, that they may be thought extraordinary
				men and favorites of Heaven, refer all their actions to some
				divine admonition pretending dreams, visions, and the like
				surprising fooleries for every thing they do. This method
				indeed is advantageous to those that intend to settle a commonwealth, or are forced to keep themselves up against a
				rude and ungovernable multitude; for by this bridle of
				superstition they might manage and reform the vulgar;
				but these pretences seem not only unbecoming philosophy,
				but quite opposite to all those fine promises she makes.
				For having promised to teach us by reason what is good
				and profitable, falling back again to the Gods as the principle of all our actions, she seems to despise reason, and disgrace that demonstration which is her peculiar glory; and
				she relies on dreams and visions, in which the worst of
				men are oftentimes as happy as the best. And therefore
				your Socrates, Simmias, in my opinion followed the most
				philosophical and rational method of instructions, choosing
				that plain and easy way as the most genteel and friendly
				unto truth, and scattering to the sophisters of the age all
				those vain pretences which are as it were the smoke of
				philosophy. And Theocritus taking him up said: What,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.388"/>
				
				Galaxidorus, and hath Meletus persuaded you that Socrates
				contemned all divine things?&mdash;for that was part of his
				accusation. Divine things! by no means, replied Galaxidorus; but having received philosophy from Pythagoras
				and Empedocles, full of dreams, fables, superstitions, and
				perfect raving, he endeavored to bring wisdom and things
				together, and make truth consist with sober sense.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Be it so, rejoined Theocritus, but what shall we
				think of his Daemon? Was it a mere juggle? Indeed,
				nothing that is told of Pythagoras regarding divination
				seems to me so great and divine. For, in my mind, as
				Homer makes Minerva to stand by Ulysses in all dangers.
				so the Daemon joined to Socrates even from his cradle
				some vision to guide him in all the actions of his life;
				which going before him, shed a light upon hidden and
				obscure matters and such as could not be discovered by
				unassisted human understanding; of such things the Daemon often discoursed with him, presiding over and by
				divine instinct directing his intentions. More and greater
				things perhaps you may learn from Simmias and other
				companions of Socrates; but once when I was present, as
				I went to Euthyphron the soothsayer's, it happened, Simmias,&mdash;for you remember it,&mdash;that Socrates walked up
				to Symbolum and the house of Andocides, all the way asking questions and jocosely perplexing Euthyphron. When
				standing still upon a sudden and persuading us to do the
				like, he mused a pretty while, and then turning about
				walked through Trunk-makers' Street, calling back his
				friends that walked before him, affirming that it was his
				Daemon's will and admonition. Many turned back, amongst
				whom I, holding Euthyphron, was one; but some of the
				youths keeping on the straight way, on purpose (as it were)
				to confute Socrates's Daemon, took along with them Charillus the piper, who came in my company to Athens to see
				Cebes. Now as they were walking through Gravers' Row,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.389"/>
				
				near the court-houses, a herd of dirty swine met them;
				and being too many for the street and running against one
				another, they overthrew some that could not get out of the
				way, and dirted others; and Charillus came home with his
				legs and clothes very dirty; so that now and then in merriment they would think on Socrates's Daemon, wondering
				that it never forsook the man, and that Heaven took such
				particular care of him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Then Galaxidorus: And do you think, Theocritus,
				that Socrates's Daemon had some peculiar and extraordinary power? And was it not that this man had by experience confirmed some part of the common necessity which
				made him, in all obscure and inevident matters, add some
				weight to the reason that was on one side? For as one
				grain doth not incline the balance by itself, yet added to
				one of two weights that are of equal poise, makes the
				whole incline to that part; thus an omen or the like sign
				may of itself be too light to draw a grave and settled resolution to any action, yet when two equal reasons draw on
				either side, if that is added to one, the doubt together with
				the equality is taken off, so that a motion and inclination
				to that side is presently produced. Then my father continuing the discourse said: You yourself, Galaxidorus, have heard
				a Megarian, who had it from Terpsion, say that Socrates's
				Daemon was nothing else but the sneezing either of himself or others; for if another sneezed, either before, behind
				him, or on his right hand, then he pursued his design and
				went on to action; but if on the left hand, he desisted.
				One sort of sneezing confirmed him whilst deliberating
				and not fully resolved; another stopped him when already upon action. But indeed it seems strange that, if
				sneezing was his only sign, he should not acquaint his familiars with it, but pretend that it was a Daemon that encouraged or forbade him. For that this should proceed
				from vanity or conceit is not agreeable to the veracity and
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.390"/>
				
				simplicity of the man; for in those we knew him to be
				truly great, and far above the generality of mankind. Nor
				is it likely so grave and wise a man should be disturbed at
				a casual sound or sneezing, and upon that account leave
				off what he was about, and give over his premeditated resolutions. Besides all, Socrates's resolution seems to be
				altogether vigorous and steady, as begun upon right principles and mature judgment. Thus he voluntarily lived poor
				all his life, though he had friends that would have been
				very glad and very willing to relieve him; he still kept
				close to philosophy, notwithstanding all the discouragements he met with; and at last, when his friends endeavored and very ingeniously contrived his escape, he would
				not yield to their entreaties, but met death with mirth and
				cheerfulness, and appeared a man of a steady reason in the
				greatest extremity. And sure these are not the actions of
				a man whose designs, when once fixed, could be altered by
				an omen or a sneeze; but of one who, by some more considerable guidance and impulse, is directed to practise
				things good and excellent. Besides, I have heard that to
				some of his friends he foretold the overthrow of the
				Athenians in Sicily. And before that time, Perilampes
				the son of Antiphon, being wounded and taken prisoner by
				us in that pursuit at Delium, as soon as he heard from the
				ambassadors who came from Athens that Socrates with
				Alcibiades and Laches fled by Rhegiste and returned safe,
				blamed himself very much, and blamed also some of his
				friends and captains of the companies&mdash;who together
				with him were overtaken in their flight about Parnes by
				our cavalry and slain there&mdash;for not obeying Socrates's
				Daemon and retreating that way which he led. And this
				I believe Simmias hath heard as well as I. Yes, replied
				Simmias, many times, and from many persons; for upon
				this, Socrates's Daemon was very much talked of at
				Athens.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.391"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Why then, pray, Simmias, said Phidolaus, shall we
				suffer Galaxidorus drollingly to degrade so considerable
				a prophetic spirit into an omen or a sneeze; which the
				vulgar and ignorant, it is true, merrily use about small
				matters; but when any danger appears, then we find that
				of Euripides verified,&mdash;
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">None near the edge of swords will mind such toys.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Autolycus, a lost Satyrdrama of Euripides, Frag. 284, vs. 22. (G.)</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>To this Galaxidorus rejoined: Sir, if Simmias hath
					heard Socrates himself speak any thing about this matter,
					I am very ready to hear and believe it with you; but yet
					what you and Polymnis have delivered I could easily
					demonstrate to be weak and insignificant. For as in
					physic the pulse or a whelk is itself but a small thing,
					yet is a sign of no small things to the physicians; and as
					the murmuring of the waves or of a bird, or the driving
					of a thin cloud, is a sign to the pilot of a stormy heaven
					and troubled sea; thus to a prophetic soul, a sneeze or an
					omen, though no great matter simply considered in itself,
					yet may be the sign and token of considerable impending
					accidents. For every art and science takes care to collect
					many things from few, and great from small. And as if
					one that doth not know the power of letters, when he
					sees a few ill-shapen strokes, should not believe that a
					man skilled in letters could read in them the famous
					battles of the ancients, the rise of cities, the acts and
					calamities of kings, and should assert that some divine
					power told him the particulars, he would by this ignorance of his raise a great deal of mirth and laughter in
					the company; so let us consider whether or no we ourselves, being altogether ignorant of every one's power
					of divination by which he guesseth at what is to come,
					are not foolishly concerned when it is asserted that a wise
					man by that discovers some things obscure and inevident
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.392"/>
					
					in themselves, and moreover himself declares that it is not
					a sneeze or voice, but a Daemon, that leads him on to
					action. This, Polymnis, particularly respects you, who
					cannot but wonder that Socrates, who by his meekness
					and humility hath humanized philosophy, should not call
					this sign a sneeze or a voice, but very pretendingly a
					Daemon; when, on the contrary, I should have wondered
					if a man so critical and exact in discourse, and so good at
					names as Socrates, should have said that it was a sneeze,
					and not a Daemon, that gave him intimation; as much as
					if any one should say that he is wounded by a dart, and
					not with a dart by him that threw it; or as if any one
					should say that a weight was weighed by the balance,
					and not with the balance by the one who holds it. For
					any effect is not the effect of the instrument, but of him
					whose the instrument is, and who useth it to that effect;
					and a sign is an instrument, which he that signifies any
					thing thereby useth to that effect. But, as I said before,
					if Simmias hath any thing about this matter, let us quietly
					attend; for no doubt he must have a more perfect knowledge of the thing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Content, said Theocritus; but let us first see who
				these are that are coming, for I think I see Epaminondas bringing in the stranger. Upon this motion, looking
				toward the door, we saw Epaminondas with his friends
				Ismenidorus and Bacchylidas and Melissus the musician
				leading the way, and the stranger following, a man of no
				mean presence; his meekness and good-nature appeared
				in his looks, and his dress was grave and becoming. He
				being seated next Simmias, my brother next me, and the
				rest as they pleased, and all silent, Simmias speaking to
				my brother said: Well, Epaminondas, by what name and
				title must I salute this stranger?&mdash;for those are commonly
				our first compliments, and the beginning of our better
				acquaintance. And my brother replied: His name, Simmias,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.393"/>
				
				 is Theanor; by birth he is a Crotonian, a philosopher by profession, no disgrace to Pythagoras's fame; for
				he hath taken a long voyage from Italy hither, to evidence by generous actions his eminent proficiency in that
				school.</p>
            <p>The stranger subjoined: But you, Epaminondas, hinder
					the performance of the best action; for if it is commendable to oblige friends, it is not discommendable to be
					obliged; for a benefit requires a receiver as well as a
					giver; by both it is perfected, and becomes a good work.
					For he that refuseth to receive a favor, as a ball that is
					struck fairly to him, disgraceth it by letting it fall short of
					the designed mark; and what mark are we so much
					pleased to hit or vexed to miss, as our kind intentions
					of obliging a person that deserves a favor? It is true,
					when the mark is fixed, he that misseth can blame nobody
					but himself; but he that refuseth or flies a kindness is
					injurious to the favor in not letting it attain the desired
					end. I have told you already what was the occasion of
					my voyage; the same I would discover to all present, and
					make them judges in the case. For after the opposite
					faction had expelled the Pythagoreans, and the Cylonians
					had burned the remains of that society in their school at
					Metapontum, and destroyed all but Philolaus and Lysis,&mdash;
					who being young and nimble escaped the flame,&mdash;Philolaus flying to the Lucanians was there protected by his
					friends, who rose for his defence and overpowered the
					Cylonians; but where Lysis was, for a long time nobody
					could tell; at last Gorgias the Leontine, sailing from
					Greece to Italy, seriously told Arcesus that he met and
					discoursed Lysis at Thebes. Arcesus, being very desirous
					to see the man, as soon as he could get a passage, designed
					to put to sea himself; but age and weakness coming on,
					he took care that Lysis should be brought to Italy alive, if
					possible; but if not, the relics of his body. The intervening
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.394"/>
					
					 wars, usurpations, and seditious hindered his friends
					from doing it whilst he lived; but since his death, Lysis's
					Daemon hath made very frequent and very plain discoveries to us of his death; and many that were very well
					acquainted with the matter have told us how courteously
					you received and civilly entertained him, how in your poor
					family he was allowed a plentiful subsistence for his age,
					counted a father of your sons, and died in peace. I therefore, although a young man and but one single person,
					have been sent by many who are my elders, and who,
					having store of money, offer it gladly to you who need it,
					in return for the gracious friendship bestowed upon Lysis.
					Lysis, it is true, is buried nobly, and your respect, which
					is more honorable than a monument, must be acknowledged and requited by his familiars and his friends.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>When the stranger had said this, my father wept a
				considerable time, in memory of Lysis; but my brother,
				smiling upon me, as he used to. do, said: What do we do,
				Caphisias? Are we to give up our poverty to wealth, and yet
				be silent? By no means, I replied, let us part with our
				old friend and the excellent breeder of our youth; but
				defend her cause, for you are to manage it. My dear
				father, said he, I have never feared that wealth would
				take possession of our house, except on account of Caphisias's body; for that wants fine attire, that he may appear
				gay and gaudy to his numerous company of lovers, and
				great supplies of food, that he may be strong to endure
				wrestling and other exercises of the ring. But since he
				doth not give up poverty, since he holds fast his hereditary
				want, like a color, since he, a youth, prides himself in
				frugality, and is very well content with his present state,
				what need have we, and what shall we do with wealth?
				Shall we gild our arms? Shall we, like Nicias the Athenian, adorn our shield with gold, purple, and other gaudy
				variety of colors, and buy for you, sir, a Milesian cloak,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.395"/>
				
				and for my mother a purple gown? For I suppose we
				shall not consume any upon our belly, or feast more sumptuously than we did before, treating this wealth as a guest
				of quality and honor! Away, away, son, replied my father;
				let me never see such a change in our course of living.
				Well, said my brother, we would not lie lazily at home,
				and watch over our unemployed riches; for then the
				bestower's kindness would be a trouble, and the possession
				infamous. What need then, said my father, have we of
				wealth? Upon this account, said Epaminondas, when
				Jason, the Thessalian general, lately sent me a great
				sum of money and desired me to accept it, I was thought
				rude and unmannerly for telling him that he was a knave
				for endeavoring, whilst he himself loved monarchy, to
				bribe one of democratical principles and a member of
				a free state. Your good will, sir (addressing the stranger),
				which is generous and worthy a philosopher, I accept and
				passionately admire; but you offer physic to your friends
				who are in perfect health! If, upon a report that we
				were distressed and overpowered, you had brought men
				and arms to our assistance, but being arrived had found
				all in quietness and peace, I am certain you would not
				have thought it necessary to leave those supplies which
				we did not then stand in need of. Thus, since now you
				came to assist us against poverty as if we had been distressed by it, and find it very peaceable and our familiar
				inmate, there is no need to leave any money or arms to
				suppress that which gives us no trouble or disturbance.
				But tell your acquaintance that they use riches well, and
				have friends here that use poverty as well. What was
				spent in keeping and burying Lysis, Lysis himself hath
				sufficiently repaid, by many profitable instructions, and by
				teaching us not to think poverty a grievance.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>What then, said Theanor, is it mean to think poverty a grievance? Is it not absurd to fly and be afraid of
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.396"/>
				
				riches, if no reason, but an hypocritical pretence, narrowness of mind, or pride, prompts one to reject the offer?
				And what reason, I wonder, would refuse such advantageous and creditable enjoyments as Epaminondas now
				doth? But, sir,&mdash;for your answer to the Thessalian about
				this matter slows you very ready,&mdash;pray answer me, do
				you think it commendable in some cases to give money,
				but always unlawful to receive it? Or are the givers and
				receivers equally guilty of a fault? By no means, replied
				Epaminondas; but, as of any thing else, so the giving and
				receiving of money is sometimes commendable and sometimes base. Well then, said Theanor, if a man gives
				willingly what he ought to give, is not that action commendable in him? Yes. And when it is commendable
				in one to give, is it not as commendable in another to
				receive? Or can a man more honestly accept a gift from
				any one, than from him that honestly bestows? No. Well
				then, Epaminondas, suppose of two friends, one hath a
				mind to present, the other must accept. It is true, in a
				battle we should avoid that enemy who is skilful in hurling
				his weapon; but in civilities we should neither fly nor
				thrust back that friend that makes a kind and genteel
				offer. And though poverty is not so grievous, yet on the
				other side, wealth is not so mean and despicable a thing.
				Very true, replied Epaminondas; but you must consider
				that sometimes, even when a gift is honestly bestowed, he
				is more commendable who refuses it. For we have many
				lusts and desires, and the objects of those desires are many.
				Some arc called natural; these proceed from the very constitution of our body, and tend to natural pleasures; others
				are acquired, and rise from vain opinions and mistaken
				notions; yet these by the length of time, ill habits, and
				bad education are usually improved, get strength, and
				debase the soul more than the other natural and necessary
				passions. By custom and care any one, with the assistance
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.397"/>
				
				of reason, may free himself from many of his natural
				desires. But, sir, all our arts, all our force of discipline,
				must be employed against the superfluous and acquired
				appetites; and they must be restrained or cut off by the
				guidance or edge of reason. For if the contrary applications of reason can make us forbear meat and drink,
				when hungry or thirsty, how much more easy is it to
				conquer covetousness or ambition, which will be destroyed
				by a bare restraint from their proper objects, and a non-attainment of their desired end? And pray, sir, are you
				not of the same opinion? Yes, replied the stranger. Then,
				sir, continued Epaminondas, do you not perceive a difference between the exercise itself and the work to which
				the exercise relates? For instance, in a wrestler, the
				work is the striving with his adversary for the crown, the
				exercise is the preparation of his body by diet, wrestling,
				or the like. So in virtue, you must confess the work to
				be one thing and the exercise another. Very well, replied
				the stranger. Then, continued Epaminondas, let us first
				examine whether to abstain from the base unlawful pleasures is the exercise of continence, or the work and evidence of that exercise? The work and evidence, replied
				the stranger. But is not the exercise of it such as you
				practise, when after wrestling, where you have raised your
				appetites like ravenous beasts, you stand a long while at a
				table covered with plenty and variety of meats, and then
				give it to your servants to feast on, whilst you offer mean
				and spare diet to your subdued appetites? For abstinence
				from lawful pleasure is exercise against unlawful. Very
				well, replied the stranger. So, continued Epaminondas,
				justice is exercise against covetousness and love of money;
				but so is not a mere cessation from stealing or robbing
				our neighbor. So he that doth not betray his country or
				friends for gold doth not exercise against covetousness,
				for the law perhaps deters, and fear restrains him; but he
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.398"/>
				
				that refuseth just gain and such as the law allows, voluntarily exercises, and secures himself from being bribed or
				receiving any unlawful present. For when great, hurtful,
				and base pleasures are proposed, it is very hard for any
				one to contain himself, who hath not often despised those
				which he had power and opportunity to enjoy. Thus,
				when base bribes and considerable advantages are offered,
				it will be difficult to refuse, unless he hath long ago rooted
				out all thoughts of gain and love of money; for other
				desires will nourish and increase that appetite, and he will
				easily be drawn to any unjust action who can scarce forbear reaching out his' hand to a proffered present. But
				he that will not lay himself open to the favors of friends
				and the gifts of kings, but refuseth even what Fortune proffers, and keeps off his appetite, that is eager after and (as
				it were) leaps forward to an appearing treasure, is never
				disturbed or tempted to unlawful actions, but hath great
				and brave thoughts, and hath command over himself, being
				conscious of none but generous designs. 1 and Caphisias,
				dear Simmias, being passionate admirers of such men, beg
				the stranger to suffer us to be taught and exercised by
				poverty to attain that height of virtue and perfection.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>My brother having finished this discourse, Simmias,
				nodding twice or thrice, said: Epaminondas is a great
				man, but this Polymnis is the cause of his greatness, who
				gave his children the best education, and bred them philosophers. But, sir, you may end this dispute at leisure
				among yourselves. As for Lysis (if it is lawful to discover
				it), pray, sir, do you design to take him out of his tomb
				and transport him into Italy, or leave him here amongst
				his friends and acquaintance, who shall be glad to lie by
				him in the grave? And Theanor with a smile answered:
				Lysis, good Simmias, no doubt is very well pleased with
				the place, for Epaminondas supplied him with all things
				necessary and fitting. But the Pythagoreans have some
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.399"/>
				
				particular funeral ceremonies, which if any one wants,
				we conclude he did not make a proper and happy exit.
				Therefore, as soon as we learned from some dreams that
				Lysis was dead (for we have certain marks to know the
				apparitions of the living from images of the dead), most
				began to think that Lysis, dying in a strange country, was
				not interred with the due ceremonies, and therefore ought
				to be removed to Italy that he might receive them there.
				I coming upon this design, and being by the people of
				the country directed to the tomb, in the evening poured
				out my oblations, and called upon the soul of Lysis to
				come out and direct me in this affair. The night drawing on, I saw nothing indeed, but thought I heard a voice
				saying: Move not those relics that ought not to be moved,
				for Lysis's body was duly and religiously interred; and his
				soul is sent to inform another body, and committed to the
				care of another Daemon. And early this morning, asking
				Epaminondas about the manner of Lysis's burial, I found
				that Lysis had taught him as far as the incommunicable
				mysteries of our sect; and that the same Daemon that
				waited on Lysis presided over him, if I can guess at the
				pilot from the sailing of the ship. The paths of life are
				large, but in few are men directed by the Daemons.
				When Theanor had said this, he looked attentively on
				Epaminondas, as if he designed a fresh search into his
				nature and inclinations.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>At the same instant the chirurgeon coming in unbound Simmias's leg and prepared to dress it; and Phyllidas entering with Hipposthenides, extremely concerned,
				as his very countenance discovered, desired me, Charon,
				and Theocritus to withdraw into a private corner of the
				porch. And I asking, Phyllidas, hath any new thing happened?&mdash;Nothing new to me, he replied, for I knew and
				told you that Hipposthenides was a coward, and therefore begged you not to communicate the matter to him or
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.400"/>
				
				make him an associate. We seeming all surprised, Hipposthenides cried out: For Heaven's sake, Phyllidas, don't
				say so, don't think rashness to be bravery, and blinded by
				that mistake ruin both us and the commonwealth; but, if
				it must be so, let the exiles return again in peace. And
				Phyllidas in a passion replied, How many, Hipposthenides, do you think are privy to this design? Thirty I
				know engaged. And why then, continued Phyllidas,
				would you singly oppose your judgment to them all, and
				ruin those measures they have all taken and agreed to?
				What had you to do to send a messenger to desire them
				to return and not approach to-day, when even chance
				encouraged and all things conspired to promote the
				design?</p>
            <p>These words of Phyllidas troubled every one; and Charon, looking very angrily upon Hipposthenides, said:
					Thou coward! what hast thou done? No harm, replied
					Hipposthenides, as I will make appear if you will moderate your passion and hear what your gray-headed equal
					can allege. If, Phyllidas, we were minded to show our
					citizens a bravery that sought danger, and a heart that
					contemned life, there is day enough before us; why should
					we wait till the evening? Let us take our swords presently, and assault the tyrants. Let us kill, let us be
					killed, and be prodigal of our blood. If this may be
					easily performed or endured, and if it is no easy matter
					by the loss of two or three men to free Thebes from so
					great an armed power as possesses it, and to beat out the
					Spartan garrison,&mdash;for I suppose Phyllidas hath not provided wine enough at his entertainment to make all Archias's guard of fifteen hundred men drunk; or if we
					despatch him, yet Arcesus and Herippidas will be sober,
					and upon the watch,&mdash;why are we so eager to bring our
					friends and families into certain destruction, especially
					since the enemy hath some notice of their return? For
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.401"/>
					
					why else should the Thespians for these three days be
					commanded to be in arms and follow the orders of the
					Spartan general? And I hear that to-day, after examination before Archias when he returns, they design to put
					Amphitheus to death; and are not these strong proofs
					that our conspiracy is discovered? Is it not the best way
					to stay a little, until an atonement is made and the Gods
					reconciled? For the diviners, having sacrificed an ox to
					Ceres, said that the burnt offering portended a great sedition and danger to the commonwealth. And besides,
					Charon, there is another thing which particularly concerns
					you; for yesterday Hypatodorus, the son of Erianthes, a
					very honest man and my good acquaintance, but altogether
					ignorant of our design, coming out of the country in my
					company, accosted me thus: Charon is an acquaintance
					of yours, Hipposthenides, but no great crony of mine;
					yet, if you please, advise him to take heed of some imminent danger, for I had a very odd dream relating to some
					such matter. Last night methought I saw his house in
					travail; and he and his friends, extremely perplexed, fell
					to their prayers round about the house. The house
					groaned, and sent out some inarticulate sounds; at last a
					raging fire broke out of it, and consumed the greatest part
					of the city; and the castle Cadmea was covered all over
					with smoke, but not fired. This was the dream, Charon,
					that he told me. I was startled at the present, and that
					fear increased when I heard that the exiles intended to
					come to-day to your house, and I am very much afraid
					that we shall bring mighty mischiefs on ourselves, yet do
					our enemies no proportionable harm, but only give them
					a little disturbance; for I think the city signifies us, and
					the castle (as it is now in their power) them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Then Theocritus putting in, and enjoining silence
				on Charon, who was eager to reply, said: As for my part,
				Hipposthenides, though all my sacrifices were of good
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.402"/>
				
				omen to the exiles, yet I never found any greater inducement to go on than the dream you mentioned; for you say
				that a great and bright fire, rising out of a friend's house,
				caught the city, and that the habitation of the enemies
				was blackened with smoke, which never brings any thing
				better than tears and disturbance; that inarticulate sounds
				broke out from us shows that none shall make any clear
				and full discovery; only a blind suspicion shall arise, and
				our design shall appear and have its desired effect at the
				same time. And it is very natural that the diviners should
				find the sacrifices ill-omened; for both their office and
				their victims belong not to the public, but to the men in
				power. Whilst Theocritus was speaking, I said to Hip
				posthenides, Whom did you send with this message? for
				if it was not long ago, we will follow him. Indeed, Caphisias, he replied, it is unlikely (for I must tell the truth)
				that you should overtake him, for he is upon the best
				horse in Thebes. You all know the man, he is master of
				the horse to Melon, and Melon from the very beginning
				hath made him privy to the design. And I, observing
				him to be at the door, said: What, Hipposthenides, is
				it Clido, he that last year at Juno's feast won the single
				horse-race? Yes, the very same. Who then, continued
				I, is he that hath stood a pretty while at the court-gate
				and gazed upon us? At this Hipposthenides turning
				about cried out: Clido, by Hercules! I'll lay my life some
				unlucky accident hath happened. Clido, observing that
				we took notice of him, came softly from the gate towards
				us; and Hipposthenides giving him a nod and bidding
				him deliver his message to the company, for they were all
				sure friends and privy to the whole plot, he began: Sir,
				I know the men very well, and not finding you either at
				home or in the market-place, I guessed you were with
				them, and came directly hither to give you a full account
				of the present posture of affairs. You commanded me
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.403"/>
				
				with all possible speed to meet the exiles upon the mountain, and accordingly I went home to take horse, and
				called for my bridle; my wife said it was mislaid, and
				stayed a long time in the hostry, tumbling about the things
				and pretending to look carefully after it; at last, when she
				had tired my patience, she confessed that her neighbor's
				wife had borrowed it last night; this raised my passion
				and I chid her, and she began to curse, and wished me a
				bad journey and as bad a return; all which curses, pray
				God, may fall upon her own head. At last my passion
				grew high, and I began to cudgel her, and presently the
				neighbors and women coming in, there was fine work; I
				am so bruised that it was as much as I could do to come
				hither to desire you to employ another man, for I protest
				I am amazed and in a very bad condition.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Upon this news we were strangely altered. Just
				before we were angry with the man that endeavored to put
				it off; and now the time approaching, the very minute just
				upon us, and it being impossible to defer the matter, we
				found ourselves in great anxiety and perplexity. But I,
				speaking to Hipposthenides and taking him by the hand,
				bade him be of good courage, for the Gods themselves
				seemed to invite us to action. Presently we parted. Phyllidas went home to prepare his entertainment, and to make
				Archias drunk as soon as conveniently he could; Charon
				went to his house to receive the exiles; and I and Theocritus went back to Simmias again, that having now a good
				opportunity, we might discourse with Epaminondas.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>We found them engaged in a notable dispute, which
				Galaxidorus and Phidolaus had touched upon before; the
				subject of the enquiry was this,&mdash;What kind of substance
				or power was the famed Daemon of Socrates? Simmias's
				reply to Galaxidorus's discourse we did not hear; but he
				said that, having once asked Socrates about it and received
				no answer, he never repeated the same question; but he
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.404"/>
				
				had often heard him declare those to be vain pretenders
				who said they had seen any divine apparition, while to
				those who affirmed that they heard a voice he would
				gladly hearken, and would eagerly enquire into the particulars. And this upon consideration gave us probable
				reasons to conjecture that this Daemon of Socrates was not
				an apparition, but rather a sensible perception of a voice,
				or an apprehension of some words, which after an unaccountable manner affected him; as in a dream there is no
				real voice, yet we have fancies and apprehensions of words
				which make us imagine that we hear some speak. This
				perception in dreams is usual, because the body whilst we
				are asleep is quiet and undisturbed; but when we are
				awake, meaner thoughts creep in, and we can hardly bring
				our souls to observe better advertisements. For being in
				a hurry of tumultuous passions and distracting business,
				we cannot compose our mind or make it listen to the discoveries. But Socrates's understanding being pure, free
				from passion, and mixing itself with the body no more than
				necessity required, was easy to be moved and apt to take
				an impression from every thing that was applied to it; now
				that which was applied was not a voice, but more probably a
				declaration of a Daemon, by which the very thing that it
				would declare was immediately and without audible voice
				represented to his mind. Voice is like a stroke given to
				the soul, which receives speech forcibly entering at the
				ears whilst we discourse; but the understanding of a more
				excellent nature affects a capable soul, by applying the very
				thing to be understood to it, so that there is no need of
				another stroke. And the soul obeys, as it stretches or
				slackens her affections, not forcibly, as if it wrought by
				contrary passions, but smoothly and gently, as if it moved
				flexible and loose reins. And sure nobody can wonder at
				this, that hath observed what great ships of burden are
				turned by a small helm, or seen a potter's wheel move
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.405"/>
				
				round by the gentle touch of one finger. These are lifeless things, it is true; but being of a frame fit for motion,
				by reason of their smoothness, they yield to the least impulse. The soul of man, being stretched with a thousand
				inclinations, as with cords, is the most tractable instrument
				that is, and if once rationally excited, easy to be moved to
				the object that is to be conceived; for here the beginnings
				of the passions and appetites spread to the understanding
				mind, and that being once agitated, they are drawn back
				again, and so stretch and raise the whole man. Hence
				you may guess how great is the force of a conception when
				it hath entered the mind; for the bones that are insensible,
				the nerves, the flesh that is full of humors, and the heavy
				mass composed of all these, lying quiet and at rest, as
				soon as the soul gives the impulse and raiseth an appetite
				to move towards any object, are all roused and invigorated,
				and every member seems a wing to carry it forward to
				action. Nor is it impossible or even very difficult to conceive the manner of this motion and stirring, by which the
				soul having conceived any thing draweth after her, by means
				of appetites, the whole mass of the body. But inasmuch
				as language, apprehended without any sensible voice, easily
				excites; so, in my opinion, the understanding of a superior nature and a more divine soul may excite an inferior
				soul, touching it from without, like as one speech may
				touch and rouse another, and as light causes its own reflection. We, it is true, as it were groping in the dark,
				find out one another's conceptions by the voice; but the
				conceptions of the Daemons carry a light with them, and
				shine to those that are able to perceive them, so that there
				is no need of words such as men use as signs to one
				another, seeing thereby only the images of the conceptions, and being unable to see the conceptions themselves
				unless they enjoy a peculiar and (as I said before) a divine
				light. This may be illustrated from the nature and effect
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.406"/>
				
				of voice; for the air being formed into articulate sounds,
				and made all voice, transmits the conception of the soul
				to the hearer; so that it is no wonder if the air, that is
				very apt to take impressions, being fashioned according to
				the object conceived by a more excellent nature, signifies
				that conception to some divine and extraordinary men.
				For as a stroke upon a brazen shield, when the noise
				ariseth out of a hollow, is heard only by those who are in
				a convenient position, and is not perceived by others; so
				the speeches of the Daemon, though indifferently applied
				to all, yet sound only to those who are of a quiet temper
				and sedate mind, and such as we call holy and divine men.
				Most believe that Daemons communicate some illuminations to men asleep, but think it strange and incredible
				that they should communicate the like to them whilst they
				are awake and have their senses and reason vigorous; as
				vise a fancy as it is to imagine that a musician can use his
				harp when the strings are slack, but cannot play when
				they are screwed up and in tune. For they do not consider that the effect is hindered by the unquietness and
				incapacity of their own minds; from which inconveniences
				our friend Socrates was free, as the oracle assured his
				father whilst he was a boy. For that commanded him to
				let young Socrates do what he would, not to force or draw
				him from his inclinations, but let the boy's humor have its
				free course; to beg Jupiter's and the Muses' blessing upon
				him, and take no farther care, intimating that he had a
				good guide to direct him, that was better than ten thousand
				tutors and instructors.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>This, Phidolaus, was my notion of Socrates's Daemon,
				whilst he lived and since his death; and I look upon all
				they mention about omens, sneezings, or the like, to be
				dreams and fooleries. But what I heard Timarchus discourse upon the same subject, lest some should think I
				delight in fables, perhaps it is best to conceal. By no
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.407"/>
				
				means, cried Theocritus, let's have it; for though they do
				not perfectly agree with it, yet I know many fables that
				border upon truth; but pray first tell us who this Timarchus was, for I never was acquainted with the man. Very
				likely, Theocritus, said Simmias; for he died when he was
				very young, and desired Socrates to bury him by Lampocles, the son of Socrates, who was his dear friend, of the
				same age, and died not many days before him. He being
				eager to know (for he was a fine youth, and a beginner in
				philosophy) what Socrates's Daemon was, acquainting none
				but Cebes and me with his design, went down into Trophonius's cave, and performed all the ceremonies that were
				requisite to gain an oracle. There he stayed two nights
				and one day, so that his friends despaired of his return
				and lamented him as lost; but the next morning he came
				out with a very cheerful countenance, and having adored
				the God, and freed himself from the thronging inquisitive
				crowd, he told us many wonderful things that he had seen
				and heard; for this was his relation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>As soon as he entered, a thick darkness surrounded
				him; then, after he had prayed, he lay a long while upon
				the ground, but was not certain whether awake or in a
				dream, only he imagined that a smart stroke fell upon his
				head, and that through the parted sutures of his skull his
				soul fled out; which being now loose, and mixed with a
				purer and more lightsome air, was very jocund and well
				pleased; it seemed to begin to breathe, as if till then it
				had been almost choked, and grew bigger than before, like
				a sail swollen by the wind; then he heard a small noise
				whirling round his head, very sweet and ravishing, and
				looking up he saw no earth, but certain islands shining with
				a gentle fire, which interchanged colors according to the
				different variation of the light, innumerable and very large,
				unequal, but all round. These whirling, it is likely, agitated the ether, and made that sound; for the ravishing softness
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.408"/>
				
				 of it was very agreeable to their even motions. Between these islands there was a large sea or lake which
				shone very gloriously, being adorned with a gay variety of
				colors mixed with blue; some few of the islands swam in
				this sea, and were carried to the other side of the current;
				others, and those the most, were carried up and down,
				tossed, whirled, and almost overwhelmed.</p>
            <p>The sea in some places seemed very deep, especially
					toward the south, in other parts very shallow; it ebbed and
					flowed, but the tides were neither high nor strong; in some
					parts its color was pure and sea-green, in others it looked
					muddy and as troubled as a pool. The current brings
					those islands that were carried over to the other side back
					again; but not to the same point, so that their motions are
					not exactly circular, but winding. About the middle of
					these islands, the ambient sea seemed to bend into a hollow, a little less, as it appeared to him, than eight parts
					of the whole. Into this sea were two entrances, by which
					it received two opposite fiery rivers, running in with so
					strong a current, that it spread a fiery white over a great
					part of the blue sea. This sight pleased him very much;
					but when he looked downward, there appeared a vast
					chasm, round, as if he had looked into a divided sphere,
					very deep and frightful, full of thick darkness, which was
					every now and then troubled and disturbed. Thence a
					thousand howlings and bellowings of beasts, cries of children, groans of men and women, and all sorts of terrible
					noises reached his ears; but faintly, as being far off and
					rising through the vast hollow; and this terrified him exceedingly.</p>
            <p>A little while after, an invisible thing spoke thus to him:
					Timarchus, what dost thou desire to understand? And
					he replied, Every thing; for what is there that is not wonderful and surprising? We have little to do with those
					things above, they belong to other Gods; but as for Proserpina's
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.409"/>
					
					 quarter, which is one of the four (as Styx divides them) that we govern, you may visit it if you please.
					But what is Styx? The way to hell, which reaches to the
					contrary quarter, and with its head divides the light; for,
					as you see, it rises from hell below, and as it rolls on
					touches also the light, and is the limit of the extremest
					part of the universe. There are four divisions of all
					things; the first is of life, the second of motion, the third
					of generation, and the fourth of corruption. The first is
					coupled to the second by a unit, in the substance invisible;
					the second to the third by understanding, in the Sun; and
					the third to the fourth by nature, in the Moon. Over every
					one of these ties a Fate, daughter of Necessity, presides;
					over the first, Atropos; over the second, Clotho; and
					Lachesis over the third, which is in the Moon, and about
					which is the whole whirl of generation. All the other
					islands have Gods in them; but the Moon, belonging to
					earthly Daemons, is raised but a little above Styx. Styx
					seizes on hr once in a hundred and seventy-seven second
					revolutions; and when it approaches, the souls are startled,
					and cry out for fear; for hell swallows up a great many,
					and the Moon receives some swimming up from below
					which have run through their whole course of generation,
					unless they are wicked and impure. For against such she
					throws flashes of lightning, makes horrible noises, and
					frights them away; so that, missing their desired happiness
					and bewailing their condition, they are carried down again
					(as you see) to undergo another generation. But, said
					Timarchus, I see nothing but stars leaping about the hollow, some carried into it, and some darting out of it again.
					These, said the voice, are Daemons; for thus it is. Every
					soul hath some portion of reason; a man cannot be a man
					without it; but as much of each soul as is mixed with flesh
					and appetite is changed, and through pain or pleasure
					becomes irrational. Every soul doth not mix herself after
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.410"/>
					
					one sort; for some plunge themselves into the body, and
					so in this life their whole fame is corrupted by appetite
					and passion; others are mixed as to some part, but the
					purer part still remains without the body,&mdash;it is not drawn
					down into it, but it swims above, and touches the extremest
					part of the man's head; it is like a cord to hold up and
					direct the subsiding part of the soul, as long as it proves
					obedient and is not overcome by the appetites of the flesh.
					That part that is plunged into the body is called the soul,
					but the uncorrupted part is called the mind, and the vulgar
					think it is within them, as likewise they imagine the image
					reflected from a glass to be in that. But the more intelligent, who know it to be without, call it a Daemon. Therefore those stars which you see extinguished imagine to be
					souls whose whole substances are plunged into bodies; and
					those that recover their light and rise from below, that
					shake off the ambient mist and darkness, as if it were
					clay and dirt, to be such as retire from their bodies after
					death; and those that are carried up on high are the
					Daemons of wise men and philosophers. But pray pry
					narrowly, and endeavor to discover the tie by which every
					one is united to a soul. Upon this, Timarchus looked as
					steadfastly as he could, and saw some of the stars very
					much agitated, and some less, as the corks upon a net;
					and some whirled round like a spindle, having a very irregular and uneven motion, and not being able to run in a
					straight line. And thus the voice said: Those that have a
					straight and regular motion belong to souls which are very
					manageable, by reason of their genteel breeding and philosophical education, and which upon earth do not plunge
					themselves into the foul clay and become irrational.
					But those that move irregularly, sometimes upwards, sometimes downwards, as striving to break loose from a vexing
					chain, are yoked to and strive with very untractable conditions, which ignorance and want of learning make headstrong
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.411"/>
					
					 and ungovernable. Sometimes they get the better
					of the passions, and draw them to the right side; sometimes they are drawn away by them, and sink into sin and
					folly, and then again endeavor to get out. For the tie, as
					it were a bridle on the irrational part of the soul, when it
					is pulled back, draws in repentance for past sins, and
					shame for loose and unlawful pleasures, which is a pain
					and stroke inflicted on the soul by a governing and prevailing power; till by this means it becomes gentle and
					manageable, and like a tamed beast, without blows or torment, it understands the minutest direction of the Daemon.
					Such indeed are but very slowly and very hardly brought to a
					right temper; but of that sort which from the very beginning are governable and obedient to the direction of the
					Daemon, are those prophetic souls, those intimates of the
					Gods. Such was the soul of Hermodorus the Clazomenian,
					of which it is reported that for several nights and days it
					would leave his body, travel over many countries, and return after it had viewed things and discoursed with persons
					at a great distance; till at last, by the treachery of his
					wife, his body was delivered to his enemies, and they burnt
					the house while the inhabitant was abroad. It is certain,
					this is a mere fable. The soul never went out of the
					body, but it loosened the tie that held the Daemon, and
					permitted it to wander; so that this, seeing and hearing
					the various external occurrences, brought in the news to
					it; yet those that burnt his body are even till this time
					severely tormented in the deepest pit of hell. But this,
					youth, you shall more clearly perceive three months hence;
					now depart. The voice continuing no longer, Timarchus
					(as he said) turned about to discover who it was that spoke;
					but a violent pain, as if his skull had been pressed together,
					seized his head, so that he lost all sense and understanding;
					but in a little while recovering, he found himself in the
					entrance of the cave, where he at first lay down.</p>
            <pb id="v.2.p.412"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>This was Timarchus's story; and when at Athens,
				in the third month after he had heard the voice, he died.
				We, amazed at the event, told Socrates the whole tale.
				Socrates was angry with us for not discovering it whilst
				Timarchus was alive; for he would very gladly have had
				a more full discovery front his own mouth. I have done,
				Theocritus, with the story and discourse; but pray, shall
				we not entreat the stranger to discuss this point? For it is
				a very proper subject for excellent and divine men. What
				then, said Theanor, shall we not have the opinion of Epaminondas, who is of the same school, and as well learned
				as myself in these matters? But my father with a smile
				said: Sir, that is his humor; he loves to be silent, he is
				very cautious how he proposeth any thing, but will hear
				eternally, and is never weary of an instructive story; so
				that Spintharus the Tarentine, who lived with him a long
				time, would often say that he never met a man that knew
				more, or spake less. Therefore, pray sir, let us have your
				thoughts.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>Then, said Theanor, in my opinion, that story of
				Timarchus should be accounted sacred and inviolable, and
				consecrated to God; and I wonder that any one should
				disbelieve his report, as Simmias has related it. Swans,
				horses, dogs, and dragons we sometimes call sacred; and
				yet we cannot believe that men are sacred and favorites of
				Heaven, though we confess the love of man and not the
				love of birds to be an attribute of the Deity. Now as one
				that loves horses doth not take an equal care of the whole
				kind, but always choosing out some one excellent, rides,
				trains, feeds, and loves him above the rest; so amongst
				men, the superior powers, choosing, as it were, the best out
				of the whole herd, breed them more carefully and nicely;
				not directing them, it is true, by reins and bridles, but by
				reason imparted by certain notices and signs, which the
				vulgar and common sort do not understand. For neither
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.413"/>
				
				do all dogs know the huntsman's, nor all horses the jockey's
				signs; but those that are bred to it are easily directed by a
				whistle or a hollow, and very readily obey. And Homer
				seems to have understood the difference I mention; for
				some of the prophets he calls augurs, some priests, some
				such as understood the voice of the very Gods, were of the
				same mind with them, and could foretell things; thus,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Helenus Priam's son the same decreed,
				</l>
                     <l>On which consulting Gods before agreed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And in another place,
					<quote rend="blockquote">As I heard lately from th' immortal Gods.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 44 and 53.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For as those that are not near the persons of kings or commanders understand their minds by fire-signals, proclamation,
					sound of trumpet, or the like, but their favorites receive it
					from their own mouth; so the Deity converses immediately
					but with very few, and very seldom; but to most he gives
					signs, from which the art of divination is gathered. So
					that the Gods direct the lives of very few, and of such only
					whom they intend to raise to the highest degree of perfection and happiness. Those souls (as Hesiod sings) that
					are not to be put into another body, but are freed from all
					union with flesh, turn guardian Daemons and preside over
					others. For as wrestlers, when old age makes them unfit
					for exercise, have some love for it still left, delight to see
					others wrestle, and encourage them; so souls that have
					passed all the stages of life, and by their virtue are exalted
					into Daemons, do not slight the endeavors of man, but being kind to those that strive for the same attainments, and
					in some sort banding and siding with them, encourage and
					help them on, when they see them near their hope and ready
					to catch the desired prize. For the Daemon doth not go
					along with every one; but as in a shipwreck, those that
					are far from land their friends standing on the shore only
					
					<pb id="v.2.p.414"/>
					
					look upon and pity, but those that are near they encourage
					and wade in to save; so the Daemon deals with mankind.
					Whilst we are immersed in worldly affairs, and are changing
					bodies, as fit vehicles for our conveyance, he lets us alone
					to try our strength, patiently to stem the tide and get into
					the haven by ourselves; but if a soul hath gone through
					the trials of a thousand generations, and now, when her
					course is almost finished, strives bravely, and with a great
					deal of labor endeavors to ascend, the Deity permits her
					proper Genius to aid her, and even gives leave to any other
					that is willing to assist. The Daemon, thus permitted,
					presently sets about the work; and upon his approach, if
					the soul obeys and hearkens to his directions, she is saved;
					if not, the Daemon leaves her, and she lies in a miserable
					condition.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>This discourse was just ended, when Epaminondas
				looking upon me, said: Caphisias, it is time for you to be
				at the ring, your usual company will expect you; we, as
				soon as we break company, will take care of Theanor.
				And I replied: Sir, I'll go presently, but I think Theocritus
				here hath something to say to you and me and Galaxidorus.
				Let's hear it in God's name, said he; and rising up, he led
				us into a corner of the porch. When we had him in the
				midst of us, we all began to desire him to make one in the
				conspiracy. He replied that he knew the day appointed
				for the exiles' return, and that he and Gorgidas had their
				friends ready upon occasion; but that he was not for killing
				any of the citizens without due process of law, unless some
				grave necessity seemed to warrant the execution. Besides,
				it was requisite that there should be some unconcerned in
				the design; for such the multitude would not be jealous
				of, but would think what they advised was for the good of
				the commonwealth, that their counsels proceeded from the
				love they had for their country, and not from any design of
				procuring their own safety. This motion we liked; he
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.415"/>
				
				returned to Simmias and his company, and we went to the
				ring, where we met our friends, and as we wrestled together,
				communicated our thoughts to one another, and put things
				in order for action. There we saw Philip and Archias very
				spruce, anointed and perfumed, going away to the prepared
				feast; for Phyllidas, fearing they would execute Amphitheus before supper, as soon as he had brought Lysanoridas
				going, went to Archias, and putting him in hopes of the
				woman's company he desired, and assuring him she would
				be at the place appointed, soon trepanned him into stupid
				carelessness and sensuality with his fellow-wantons.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>About the night, the wind rising, the sharpness of
				the weather increased, and that forced most to keep within
				doors; we meeting with Damoclides, Pelopidas, and Theopompus received them, and others met other of the exiles;
				for as soon as they were come over Cithaeron, they separated,
				and the stormy weather obliged them to walk with their
				faces covered, so that without any fear or danger they passed
				through the city. Some as they entered had a flash of
				lightning on their right-hand, without a clap of thunder,
				and that portended safety and glory; intimating that their
				actions should be splendid and without danger.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>When we were all together in the house (eight and
				forty in number), and Theocritus in a little room by himself
				offering sacrifice, there was heard on a sudden a loud
				knocking at the gate; and presently one came and told us
				that two of Archias's guard, who had some earnest business with Charon, knocked at the gate, demanding entrance,
				and were very angry that they were not admitted sooner.
				Charon surprised commanded the doors to be opened presently, and going to meet them with a garland on his head,
				as if he had been sacrificing or making merry, asked their
				business. One of them replied, Philip and Archias sent
				us to tell you that you must come before them presently.
				And Charon demanding why they sent for him in such
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.416"/>
				
				haste, and if all was well; We know nothing more, the
				messenger returned, but what answer shall we carry back ?
				That, replied Charon, putting off his garland and putting
				on his cloak, I follow you; for should I go along with you,
				my friends would be concerned, imagining that I am taken
				into custody. Do so, said they, for we must go and carry
				the governor's orders to the city guard. With this they
				departed, but Charon coming in and telling us the story,
				we were all very much surprised, imagining the design had
				been discovered; and most suspected Hipposthenides, and
				thought that he, having endeavored to hinder their coming
				through Chido and failed, now the time for the dangerous
				attempt unavoidably approached, grew faint-hearted and
				made a discovery of the plot. And this seemed probable,
				for he did not appear at Charon's house with the rest, and
				so was looked upon by every one to be a rascal and a turn
				coat; yet we all were of opinion that Charon ought to
				obey the governor's orders and go to them. Then he,
				commanding his son to be brought to him,&mdash;the prettiest
				youth, Archidamus, in all Thebes, skilled in most exercises,
				scarce fifteen years old, but very strong and lusty for his
				age,&mdash;thus said: Friends, this is my only and my beloved
				son, and him I put into your hands, conjuring you by all
				that's good, if you find me treacherous, to kill him and
				have no mercy upon him for my sake; but as for your
				parts, sirs, be provided against the worst that can come; do
				not yield your bodies tamely to be butchered by base fellows, but behave yourselves bravely, and preserve your
				souls invincible for the good and glory of your country.
				When Charon had ended, we admired the honesty and
				bravery of the man, but were angry at his suspicion, and
				bade him take away his son. Charon, said Pelopidas, we
				should have taken it more kindly, if you had removed your
				son into another house, for why should he suffer for being
				in our company ? Nay, let us send him away now, that,
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.417"/>
				
				if we fall, he may live, and grow up to punish the tyrants
				and be a brave revenger of our deaths. By no means, replied Charon, he shall stay here, and run the same danger
				with you all, for it is not best that he should fall into the
				power of his enemies; and you, my boy, be daring above
				thy age, and with these brave citizens venture upon necessary dangers for the defence of liberty and virtue; for we
				have good hopes still left, and perhaps some God will protect us in this just and generous undertaking.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>These words of his, Archidamus, drew tears from
				many; but he not shedding so much as one, and delivering his son to Pelopidas, went out of the door, saluting
				and encouraging every one as he went. But you would
				have been exceedingly surprised at the serene and fearless
				temper of the boy, with a soul as great as that of Achilles's son; for he did not change color or seem concerned,
				but drew out and tried the goodness of Pelopidas's sword.
				In the mean time Diotonus, one of Cephisodorus's friends,
				came to us with his sword girt and breastplate on; and
				understanding that Archias had sent for Charon, he chid
				our delay, and urged us to go and set upon the house
				presently; for so we should be too quick for them, and
				take them unprovided. Or, if we did not like that proposal, he said, it was better to go out and fall upon them
				while they were scattered and in confusion, than to coop
				ourselves up altogether in one room, and like a hive of
				bees be taken off by our enemies. Theocritus likewise
				pressed us to go on, affirming that the sacrifices were
				lucky, and promised safety and success.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Upon this, whilst we were arming and setting ourselves in order, Charon came in, looking very merrily and
				jocund, and with a smile said: Courage, sirs, there is no
				danger, but the design goes on very well; for Archias
				and Philip, as soon as they heard that according to their
				order I was come, being very drunk and weakened in
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.418"/>
				
				body and understanding, with much ado came out to me;
				and Archias said, I hear that the exiles are returned, and
				lurk privately in town. At this I was very much surprised,
				but recovering myself asked, Who are they, sir, and where ?
				We don't know, said Archias, and therefore sent for you,
				to enquire whether you had heard any clear discovery;
				and I, as it were surprised, considering a little with myself, imagined that what they heard was only uncertain
				report, and that none of the associates had made this discovery (for then they would have known the house), but
				that it was a groundless suspicion and rumor about town
				that came to their ears, and therefore said: I remember,
				whilst Androclidas was alive, that a great many idle lying
				stories were spread abroad, to trouble and amuse us;
				but, sir, I have not heard one word of this, yet if you
				please, I will enquire what ground there is for it, and if I
				find any thing considerable, I shall give you notice. Yes,
				pray, said Phyllidas, examine this matter very narrowly;
				slight no particular, be very diligent and careful, foresight
				is very commendable and safe. When he had said this,
				he led back Archias into the room, where they are now
				drinking. But, sirs, let us not delay, but begging the
				God's assistance, put ourselves presently upon action.
				Upon this, we went to prayers, and encouraged one another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>It was now full supper-time, the wind was high,
				and snow and small rain fell, so that the streets and narrow lanes we passed were all empty. They that were to
				assault Leontidas and Hypates, whose houses joined, went
				out in their usual clothes, having no arms besides their
				swords; amongst those were Pelopidas, Democlides, and
				Cephisodorus. Charon, Melon, and the rest that were to
				set upon Archias, put on breastplates, and shady fir or
				pine garlands upon their heads; some dressed themselves in
				women's clothes, so that they looked like a drunken company
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.419"/>
				
				 of mummers. But our enemies' unlucky Fortune,
				Archidamus, resolving to make their folly and carelessness
				as conspicuous as our eagerness and courage, and having,
				as in a play, intermixed a great many dangerous underplots
				into our plan, now, at the very point of its execution,
				presented to us a most unexpected and hazardous adventure. For whilst Charon, as soon as ever he parted from
				Archias and Philip, was come back and was setting us
				forward to execute the design, a letter from Archias, the
				chief-priest of Athens, was sent to Archias our governor,
				which contained a full discovery of the plot, in what
				house the exiles met, and who were the associates. Archias being now dead drunk, and quite beside himself
				with expectation of the desired women, took the letter;
				and the bearer saying, <q direct="unspecified">Sir, it contains matter of concern,</q>
				           <q direct="unspecified">Matters of concern to-morrow,</q> he replied, and clapped it
				under his cushion; and calling for the glass, he bade the
				servant fill a brimmer, and sent Phyllidas often to the
				door to see if the women were coming.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>The hopes of this company made them sit long; and
				we coming opportunely quickly forced our way through
				the servants to the hall, and stood a little at the door, to
				take notice of every one at table; our shady garlands and
				apparel disguising our intentions, all sat silent, in expectation of what would follow. But as soon as Melon, laying
				his hand upon his sword, was making through the midst
				of them, Cabirichus (who was the archon chosen by lot)
				catching him by the arm cried out to Phyllidas, Is not this
				Melon? Melon loosed his hold presently, and drawing
				out his sword, made at staggering Archias, and laid him
				dead on the floor; Charon wounded Philip in the neck,
				and whilst he endeavored to defend himself with the cups
				that were about him, Lysitheus threw him off his seat,
				and ran him through. We persuaded Cabirichus to be
				quiet, not to assist the tyrants, but to join with us to free
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.420"/>
				
				his country, for whose good he was consecrated governor
				and devoted to the Gods. But when being drunk he
				would not harken to reason, but grew high, began to
				bustle, and turned the point of his spear upon us (for
				our governors always carry a spear with them), I catching
				it in the midst, and raising it higher than my head, desired him to let it go and consult his own safety, for else
				he would be killed. But Theopompus, standing on his
				right side and smiting him with his sword, said: Lie
				there, with those whose interest you espoused; thou shalt
				not wear the garland in freed Thebes, nor sacrifice to the
				Gods any more, by whom thou hast so often curst thy
				country, by making prayers so many times for the prosperity of her enemies. Cabirichus falling, Theocritus
				standing by snatched up the sacred spear, and kept it
				from being stained; and some few of the servants that
				dared to resist we presently despatched; the others that
				were quiet we shut up in the hall, being very unwilling
				that they should get abroad and make any discovery, till
				we knew whether the other company had succeeded in
				their attempt.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>They managed their business thus: Pelopidas and
				those with him went softly and knocked at Leontidas's gate;
				and a servant coming to demand their business, they said,
				they came from Athens, and brought a letter from Callistratus to Leontidas. The servant went and acquainted his
				master, and was ordered to open the door; as soon as it
				was unbarred, they all violently rushed in, and overturning the servant ran through the hall directly to Leontidas's
				chamber. He, presently suspecting what was the matter,
				drew his dagger and stood upon his guard; an unjust man,
				it is true, and a tyrant, but courageous and strong of his
				hands; but he forgot to put out the candle and get
				amongst the invaders in the dark, and so appearing in the
				light, as soon as they opened the door, he ran Cephisodorus
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.421"/>
				
				through the belly. Next he engaged Pelopidas, and cried out
				to the servants to come and help; but those Samidas and
				his men secured, nor did they dare to come to handy blows
				with the strongest and most valiant of the citizens. There
				was a smart encounter between Pelopidas and Leontidas,
				for the passage was very narrow, and Cephisodorus falling
				and dying in the midst, nobody else could come to strike
				one blow. At last Pelopidas, receiving a slight wound in
				the head, with repeated thrusts overthrew Leontidas, and
				killed him upon Cephisodorus, who was yet breathing; for
				he saw his enemy fall, and shaking Pelopidas by the hand,
				and saluting all the rest, he died with a smile upon his
				face. This done, they went to the house of Hypates, and
				entering after the same manner, they pursued Hypates,
				flying over the roof into a neighbor's house, and caught
				and killed him.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>From thence they marched directly to us, and
				we met in the piazza; and having saluted and told one
				another our success, we went all to the prison. And
				Phyllidas, calling out the keeper, said: Philip and Archias
				command you to bring Amphitheus presently before them.
				But he, considering the unseasonableness of the time, and
				that Phyllidas, as being yet hot and out of breath, spoke
				with more than ordinary concern, suspected the cheat, and
				replied to Phyllidas: Pray, sir, did ever the governors send
				for a prisoner at such a time before? Or ever by you?
				That warrant do you bring? As he was prating thus,
				Phyllidas ran him through,&mdash;a base fellow, upon whose
				carcass the next day many women spat and trampled. We,
				breaking open the prison door, first called out Amphitheus
				by name, and then others, as every one had a mind; they,
				knowing our voice, jocundly leaped out of their straw in
				which they lay, with their chains upon their legs. The
				others that were in the stocks held out their hands, and
				begged us not to leave them behind. These being set
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.422"/>
				
				free, many of the neighbors came in to us, understanding
				and rejoicing for what was done. The women too, as soon
				as they were acquainted with the flying report, unmindful
				of the Boeotian strictness, ran out to one another, and
				enquired of every one they met how things went. Those
				that found their fathers or their husbands followed them;
				for the tears and prayers of the modest women were a very
				great incitement to all they met.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>Our affairs being in this condition, understanding
				that Epaminondas, Gorgidas, and their friends were drawing into a body about Minerva's temple, I went to them.
				Many honest worthy citizens at first joined, and their number continually increased. When I had informed them
				in the particulars of what was done, and desired them to
				march into the market-place to assist their friends, they
				proclaimed liberty; and the multitude were furnished with
				arms out of the piazzas, that were stuffed with spoil, and
				the neighboring armorers' shops. Then Hipposthenides
				with his friends and servants appeared, having by chance
				joined the trumpeters that were coming to Thebes, against
				the feast of Hercules. Straight some gave the alarm in
				the market-place, others in other parts of the city, distracting their enemies on all sides, as if the whole city was in
				arms. Some, lighting smoky fire, concealed themselves in
				the cloud and fled to the castle, drawing to them the select
				band which used to keep guard about the castle all night.
				The garrison of the castle, when these poured in among
				them scattered and in disorder, though they saw us all in
				confusion, and knew we had no standing compact body,
				yet would not venture to make a descent, though they were
				above five thousand strong. They were really afraid, but
				pretended they dared not move without Lysanoridas's orders, who, contrary to his usual custom, was absent from
				the castle that day. For which neglect, the Spartans (as I
				was told), having got Lysanoridas into their hands, fined
				
				<pb id="v.2.p.423"/>
				
				him heavily; and having taken Hermippidas and Arcesus
				at Corinth, they put them both to death without delay.
				And surrendering the castle to us upon articles, they
				marched out with their garrison.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>