<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De virtute morali</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">W. C. Helmbold</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>W. C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1939</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <pb id="v.6.p.16"/>
            <head>ON MORAL VIRTUE
					(DE VIRTUTE MORALI)
					<lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>
					If the present essay is the work of Plutarch,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The only recent attempt, that of Hartman, to show that it is not, relies on the looseness of the reasoning, the tediousness of the argumentation, and the absence of anything that might be called structure. But all three of these are by no means unusual in admittedly genuine works. The language and phraseology appear to the present editor, at any rate, to be Plutarchean.</note> we
					may, perhaps, be surprised at the diffuseness with
					which the author permits himself to wander at leisure
					over the preserves of Aristotelian psychology, while
					almost completely neglecting the promises made in
					such high-sounding terms in his first sentence. The
					purpose of the essay is apparently to refute certain
					tenets of Stoic psychology, and these are, to be sure,
					attacked with some spirit, but at such length and
					with so little attention to logic or to their intended
					meaning, that complete success is not to be expected. The point which is continually belaboured
					is that there <hi rend="italics">are</hi> two parts of the soul, the Rational
					and the Irrational; for Moral Virtue to arise, the
					Rational must control the Irrational. So much our
					author has gleaned from Aristotle and to this he
					adds very little; nor can he apply his vast reading
					in poetry and philosophy with much effect to the
					demolition of Stoic dogma, which he appears in
					several points to have misunderstood. On the whole,
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.17"/>
					
					whether from the standpoint of popular or from that
					of serious philosophy, this is one of the least successful
					of Plutarch's works.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But Hartman's words are no doubt too harsh: <q direct="unspecified">
                     <foreign lang="la">Multo...Chaeronensi indignior hic libellus, quem, ut ad finem perlegas quantum tibi est taedii devorandum!</foreign>
                  </q>
               </note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					A word on the terminology is necessary : Aristotelian usage is probably intended throughout the
					greater part of the w ork. I have, therefore, followed
					most English Aristotelians in my rendering of many
					terms, with <foreign lang="greek">du/namis</foreign> 
               <q direct="unspecified">capacity</q> or <q direct="unspecified">faculty</q> or
					<q direct="unspecified">power,</q> 
               <foreign lang="greek">fro/nhsis</foreign> 
               <q direct="unspecified">prudence,</q> and the like. <foreign lang="greek">e(/cis</foreign>
					I have rendered <q direct="unspecified">acquired state,</q> but <foreign lang="greek">pa/qos</foreign> and
					its forms and derivatives I have translated <q direct="unspecified">emotions,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">passions,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">experiences,</q> according to my
					interpretation of the context.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Mr. H. Rackham's very just remarks in the preface to his recent (L.C.L., 1935) edition of the <hi rend="italics">Atheniensium Respublica</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					It is interesting to notice that Pope in the <hi rend="italics">Essay
						on Man</hi> (ii. 51 if.) has apparently drawn his philosophy
					from Plutarch's diluted Aristotelianism rather than
					from the fountain head.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> T. Sinko (<hi rend="italics">Eos</hi>, xv. 1909, pp. 119-122), who further holds this essay to be the product of Plutarch's youth, comparing the more mature attitude toward the passions to be found in <hi rend="italics">De Cohibenda Ira</hi> and <hi rend="italics">De Tranquillitate Animi</hi>.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					The ms. tradition is fairly good. The work has been
					well edited by Mr. Pohlenz in the Teubner series ;
					from this edition most of the critical notes and the
					parallel passages have been taken.
				</p>
            <p>
					The work is No. 72 in Lamprias's catalogue of
					Plutarch's writings.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.6.p.19"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>It is my purpose to speak of that virtue which is
					called <q direct="unspecified">moral</q> and reputed to be so, which differs
					from contemplative virtue chiefly in that it has as
					its material the emotions of the soul and as its form
					reason, and to inquire what its essential nature is and
					how, by its nature, it subsists ; whether, also, that
					part of the soul which receives it is equipped with its
					own reason, or does but share in the reason of some
					other part; and if the latter, whether it does this
					after the manner of elements that are mingled with
					what is better than themselves, or rather, whether
					this portion of the soul is guided and governed by
					another part and in this sense may be said to
					share in that governing part's power. For that it is
					possible for virtue also to have come into being and
					to remain entirely independent of matter and free
					from all admixture with it, I think is quite obvious.
					It is better, however, to run summarily through the
					opinions of the philosophers holding opposing views,
					not so much for the sake of inquiring into them as
					that my own opinions may become clearer and more
					firmly established when those of the philosophers in
					question have been presented.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>In the first place, Menedemus of Eretria deprived the virtues of both plurality and differences by
					asserting that virtue is but one, though it goes under
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.21"/>
					
					many names : the same thing is meant by temperance and courage and justice, as is the case with
					<q direct="unspecified">mortal</q> and <q direct="unspecified">man.</q> And Ariston of Chios<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, i. p. 86.</note> himself also made virtue but one in its essential nature
					and called it health ; but in its relative aspect he
					made certain distinctions and multiplied virtues, just
					as though one should wish to call our sight <q direct="unspecified">white-sight</q> when it is applied to white objects, or <q direct="unspecified">black-sight</q>when applied to black objects, or anything else
					of the sort. For instance virtue, when it considers
					what we must do or avoid, is called prudence<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> for example, Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, vi. 6. 1: prudence is <q direct="unspecified">concerned only with things which admit of variation.</q>
               </note>; when
					it controls our desires and lays down for them the
					limitations of moderation and seasonableness in our
					pleasures, it is called temperance ; when it has to do
					with men's relations to one another and their commercial dealings, it is called justice - just as a knife is
					one and the same knife, though it cuts now one thing,
					now another, or as a fire retains its single nature
					though it operates upon different substances. Moreover it appears likely that Zeno<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, i. p. 48; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 97 e and 1034 c.</note> of Citium also
					inclines in some measure to this opinion, for he defines
					prudence as justice when it is concerned with what
					must be rendered to others as their due, as temperance when concerned with what must be chosen or
					avoided, as fortitude when concerned with what must
					be endured ; and those who defend Zeno postulate
					that in these definitions he uses the word prudence in
					the sense of knowledge. Chrysippus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 59.</note> however, by
					his opinion that corresponding to each several quality
					a virtue is formed by its own distinctive attribute of
					quality, unwittingly stirred up a <q direct="unspecified">swarm of virtues,</q>
					
					          <pb id="v.6.p.23"/>
					
					as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Meno</hi>, 72 a; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 93 b.</note> has it, which were not familiar nor even
					known ; for as from the adjective <q direct="unspecified">brave</q> he derived <q direct="unspecified">bravery,</q> from <q direct="unspecified">mild</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">mildness,</q> and
					<q direct="unspecified">justice</q> from <q direct="unspecified">just,</q> so from <q direct="unspecified">charming</q> he
					derived <q direct="unspecified">charmingnesses,</q> from <q direct="unspecified">virtuous</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">virtuousnesses,</q> from <q direct="unspecified">great</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">greatnesses,</q> from
					<q direct="unspecified">honourable</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">honourablenesses,</q> postulating also
					the other qualities of the same sort, dexterousnesses,
					approachablenesses, adroitnesses, as virtues, and
					thus filled philosophy, which needed nothing of the
					sort, with many uncouth names.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Yet all of these men agree<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, i. pp. 49, 50: iii. p. 111.</note> in supposing
					virtue to be a certain disposition of the governing
					portion of the soul and a faculty engendered by
					reason, or rather to be itself reason which is in accord
					with virtue and is firm and unshaken. They also
					think that the passionate and irrational part of the
					soul is not distinguished from the rational by any
					difference or by its nature, but is the same part,
					which, indeed, they term intelligence and the governing part; it is, they say, wholly transformed and
					changes both during its emotional states and in the
					alterations brought about in accordance with an
					acquired disposition or condition and thus becomes
					both vice and virtue ; it contains nothing irrational
					within itself, but is called irrational whenever, by the
					overmastering power of our impulses, which have
					become strong and prevail, it is hurried on to something outrageous which contravenes the convictions
					of reason.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the phrase <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Parmenides</hi>, 141 d: Marcus Aurelius, ii. 5.</note> Passion, in fact, according to them, is a
					vicious and intemperate reason, formed from an evil
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.25"/>
					
					and perverse judgement which has acquired additional violence and strength.
				</p>
            <p>
					But it seems to have eluded all these philosophers
					in what way each of us is truly two-fold and composite.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 943 a and 1083 c.</note> For that other two-fold nature of ours they
					have not discerned, but merely the more obvious one,
					the blend of soul and body. But that there is some
					element of composition, some two-fold nature and
					dissimilarity of the very soul within itself, since the
					irrational, as though it were another substance, is
					mingled and joined with reason by some compulsion
					of Nature-this, it is likely, was not unknown even
					to Pythagoras, if we may judge by the mans
					enthusiasm for the study of music, which he introduced to enchant and assuage the soul,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Euthydemus</hi>, 290 a.</note> perceiving
					that the soul has not every part of itself in subjection to discipline and study, and that not every part
					can be changed from vice by reason, but that the
					several parts have need of some other kind of persuasion to co-operate with them, to mould them, and
					to tame them, if they are not to be utterly intractable and obstinate to the teaching of philosophy.
				</p>
            <p>
					Plato,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 35 a ff.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also the treatise <hi rend="italics">De Animae Procreatione in Timaeo</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1012 b ff.).</note> however, comprehended clearly, firmly, and
					without reservation both that the soul of this universe
					of ours is not simple nor uncompounded nor uniform,
					but that, being compounded of the potentialities of
					sameness and otherness, in one part it is ever governed
					in uniformity and revolves in but one and the same
					order, which maintains control, yet in another part it
					is split into movements and circles which go in contrariety to each other and wander about, thus giving
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.27"/>
					
					rise to the beginnings of differentiation and change
					and dissimilarity in those things which come into being
					and pass away on earth ; and also that the soul of
					man,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Timaeus</hi>, 69 c ff.</note> since it is a portion or a copy of the soul of the
					Universe and is joined together on principles and in
					proportions corresponding to those which govern the
					Universe,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Themistius, <hi rend="italics">Paraphrasis Aristotelis de Anima</hi>, i. 5 (p. 59 ed. Spengel).</note> is not simple nor subj ect to similar emotions,
					but has as one part the intelligent and rational, whose
					natural duty it is to govern and rule the individual,
					and as another part the passionate and irrational, the
					variable and disorderly, which has need of a director.
					This second part is again subdivided into two parts,
					one of which, by nature ever willing to consort with
					the body and to serve the body, is called the appetitive ; the other, which sometimes joins forces with
					this part and sometimes lends strength and vigour to
					reason, is called the spirited part. And Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 435 a ff.</note> shows
					this differentiation chiefly by the opposition of the
					reasoning and intelligent part to the appetitive part
					and the spirited part, since it is by the very fact that
					these last are different that they are frequently disobedient and quarrel with the better part.
				</p>
            <p>
					Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>448 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, and the note.</note> at first made use of these principles to a
					very great extent, as is obvious from his writings.
					But later<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. De Anima</hi>, iii. 9 (432 a 25); <hi rend="italics">Magna Moralia</hi>, i. 1 (1182 a 24); <hi rend="italics">Ethica Eudemia</hi>, ii. 1. 15 (1219 b 28); <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, i. 13. 9 (1102 a 29); Iamblichus, <hi rend="italics">Protrepticus</hi>, 7 (p. 41 ed. Pistelli).</note> he assigned the spirited to the appetitive
					part, on the ground that anger is a sort of appetite
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.29"/>
					
					and desire to cause pain in requital<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">De Anima</hi>, i. 1 (403 a 30); Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De Ira</hi>, i. 3. 3.</note>; to the end,
					however, he continued to treat the passionate and
					irrational part as distinct from the rational, not
					because this part is wholly irrational, as is the perceptive part of the soul, or the nutritive and vegetative
					part (for these parts are completely unsubmissive
					and deaf to reason and, so to speak, mere off-shoots
					of our flesh and wholly attached to the body), but
					though the passionate part is wanting in reason
					and has no reason of its own, yet otherwise it is
					by nature fitted to heed the rational and intelligent
					part, to turn toward it, to yield to it, to conform itself
					thereto, if it is not completely corrupted by foolish
					pleasure and a life of no restraint.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Those who wonder how it is that this part is
					irrational, yet subservient to reason, do not seem to
					me to reflect thoroughly upon the power of reason,
					<quote rend="blockquote">How great it is, how far it penetrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 648, Euripides, Frag. 898.</note>
               </quote>
					through its mastery and guidance, not by harsh and
					inflexible methods, but by flexible ones, which have a
					quality of yielding and submitting to the rein which
					is more effective than any possible constraint or
					violence. For, to be sure, even our breathing, our
					sinews and bones, and the other parts of the body,
					though they are irrational, yet when an impulse
					comes, with reason shaking the reins, as it were, they
					all grow taut and are drawn together in ready
					obedience. So, when a man purposes to run, his feet
					are keyed for action ; if he purposes to throw or to
					grasp, his hands fall to their business. And most
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.31"/>
					
					excellently does the Poet<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xix. 208-212; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 475 a, 506 a=b, and <hi rend="italics">De Vita et Poesi Homeri</hi>, 135 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 409).</note> portray in the following
					words the sympathy and conformity of the irrational
					with reason :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Thus were her fair cheeks wet with tears, as she
						</l>
                  <l>Wept for her lord, though he sat by. In heart
						</l>
                  <l>Odysseus pitied his lamenting wife,
						</l>
                  <l>But kept his eyes firm-fixed within their lids
						</l>
                  <l>Like horn or iron : with guile he hid his tears.
						</l>
                  <l>Under such subjection to his judgement did he keep
						</l>
                  <l>his breathing and his blood and his tears.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					An evident proof of this is also the shrinking and
					withdrawal of the private parts, which hold their
					peace and remain quiet in the presence of such
					beautiful maidens and youths as neither reason nor
					law allows us to touch. This is particularly the case
					with those who first fall in love and then hear that
					they have unwittingly become enamoured of a sister
					or a daughter ; for lust cowers as reason asserts itself
					and, at the same time, the body brings its parts into
					decent conformity with the judgement. Indeed,
					very often with foods and meat, when men have
					partaken of them with gusto, if they then perceive
					or come to know that they have eaten something
					unclean or unlawful, not only is this judgement of
					theirs attended by displeasure and remorse, but the
					body itself, revolted and sharing the mind's disgust,
					falls a prey to the retchings and vomitings of
					nausea.
				</p>
            <p>
					But I fear that I shall be thought to be rounding
					out my discourse with instances which are altogether
					seductive and exotic, if I recount in full how harps and
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.33"/>
					
					lyres, pipes and flutes, and all the other harmonious
					and consonant instruments which musical art has
					devised, void of soul though they be, accord in songs
					of both joy and grief, in stately measures and dissolute tunes, with human experiences, reproducing the
					judgements, the experiences, and the morals of those
					who use them. And yet they say that even Zeno<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, i. p. 67; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1029 e.</note>
					on his way to the theatre when Amoebeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Life of Aratus</hi>, xvii. (1034 e); Athenaeus, xiv. 623 d; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">Varia Historia</hi>, iii. 30.</note> was singing to the lyre, remarked to his pupils, <q direct="unspecified">Come, let us
						observe what harmony and music gut and sinew,
						wood and bone, send forth when they partake of
						reason, proportion, and order.</q>
				        </p>
            <p>
					But, letting these subjects pass, I would gladly
					learn from my opponents whether, when they see
					dogs, horses, and domestic birds, through habituation,
					breeding, and teaching, uttering intelligible sounds
					and moving and assuming postures in subordination
					to reason, and acting in a manner conformable to due
					proportion and our advantage ; and when they hear
					Homer declaring that Achilles
					<quote rend="blockquote">Urged on both horses and men<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Adapted from <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xvi. 167.</note>
               </quote>
					to battle - whether, I say, they still wonder and are
					in doubt that the element in us which is spirited and
					appetitive and experiences pain and pleasure, does,
					by its very nature, harken to the intelligence, and is
					affected and harmoniously disposed by its agency, and
					does not dwell apart from the intelligence, nor is it
					separated therefrom, nor moulded from without the
					body, nor formed by any extraneous violence or
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.35"/>
					
					blows, but that by its nature it is dependent upon the
					intelligence and is always in association with it and
					nurtured together with it and influenced by familiar
					intercourse.
				</p>
            <p>
					Therefore, also, ethical, or moral, virtue (<hi rend="italics">ethos</hi>) is
					well named,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 3 a, 551 e; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, ii. 1. 1 (1103 a 17).</note> for ethical virtue is, to but sketch the
					subject, a quality of the irrational, and it is so named
					because the irrational, being formed by reason, acquires this quality and differentiation by habit (<hi rend="italics">ethos</hi>),
					since reason does not wish to eradicate passion completely (for that would be neither possible<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 452 b, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> nor
					expedient), but puts upon it some limitation and
					order and implants the ethical virtues, which are not
					the absence of passion but a due proportion and
					measure therein ; and reason implants them by using
					prudence to develop the capacity for passion into a
					good acquired disposition. For these three things
					the soul is said to possess<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, ii. 5 (1105 b 19); Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Eclogae</hi>, ii. 7. 20 (vol. ii. p. 139 ed. Wachsmuth).</note>: capacity, passion,
					acquired state. Now capacity<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">The capacities are the faculties in virtue of which we can be said to be liable to the emotions, for example, capable of feeling anger or fear [mss. read pain] or pity.</q> (Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi>, Rackham's translation adapted.)</note> is the starting-point,
					or raw material, of passion, as, for instance, irascibility, bashfulness, temerity. And passion is a kind
					of stirring or movement of the capacity, as anger,
					shame, boldness. And finally, the acquired state is
					a settled force and condition of the capacity of the
					irrational, this settled condition being bred by habit
					and becoming on the one hand vice, if the passion
					has been educated badly, but virtue, if educated
					excellently by reason.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>But inasmuch as philosophers do not make
					virtue as a whole a mean nor apply to it the
					term <q direct="unspecified">moral,</q> we must discuss the difference, starting with first principles. Now in this world things
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.37"/>
					
					are of two sorts, some of them existing absolutely,
					others in some relation to us. Things that exist
					absolutely are earth, heavens, stars, sea ; things that
					exist in relation to us are good and evil, things desirable and to be avoided, things pleasant and painful.
					Now reason<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, vi. 1. 5 (1139 a 7).</note> contemplates both of these, but when
					it is concerned merely with things which exist absolutely, it is called scientific and contemplative ; and
					when it is engaged with those things which exist in
					relation to us, it is called deliberative and practical.
					The virtue of the latter activity is called prudence,
					that of the former wisdom ; and prudence differs from
					wisdom in that when the contemplative faculty is
					occupied in a certain active relationship with the
					practical and passionate, prudence comes to subsist in
					accordance with reason. Therefore prudence<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iii. 3. 4-9 (1112 a 21); vi. 5. 3-6 (1140 a 31); contrast also <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 97 e-f.</note> has
					need of chance, but wisdom has no need of it, nor yet
					of deliberation, to attain its proper end ; for wisdom is
					concerned with things that remain ever the same and
					unchanging. And just as the geometer does not
					deliberate whether the triangle has its internal angles
					equal to two right angles, but knows it to be true (for
					deliberation concerns matters that are now one way,
					now another, not things that are sure and immutable),
					just so the contemplative mind has its activity concerning first principles, things that are permanent
					and have ever one nature incapable of mutation, and
					so has no occasion for deliberation. But prudence
					must often come down among things that are
					material and are full of error and confusion ; it has
					to move in the realm of chance ; to deliberate where
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.39"/>
					
					the case is doubtful; and then at last to reduce
					deliberation to practice in activities in which decisions are both accompanied by and influenced by
					the irrational, whose impulsion they, as a matter of
					fact, need. The impulsion of passion springs from
					moral virtue ; but it needs reason to keep it within
					moderate bounds and to prevent its exceeding or
					falling short of its proper season. For it is indeed
					true that the passionate and irrational moves sometimes too violently and swiftly, at other times
					more weakly and slothfully than the case demands.
					Therefore everything that we ever do can succeed
					but in one way, while it may fail in many ways<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, ii. 6. 14 (1106 b 28).</note>:
					for to hit the mark there is but one single, uncomplicated, way, yet it can be missed in several ways,
					according to whether we exceed the mean, or fall
					short of it. This, then, is the natural task of
					practical reason : to eliminate both the defects and
					the excesses of the passions. For wherever, through
					infirmity and weakness, or fear and hesitation, the
					impulsion yields too soon and prematurely forsakes
					the good,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The good is the mean.</note> there practical reason comes on the
					scene to incite and rekindle the impulsion; and
					where, again, the impulsion is borne beyond proper
					bounds, flowing powerfully and in disorder, there
					practical reason removes its violence and checks
					it. And thus by limiting the movement of the
					passions reason implants in the irrational the moral
					virtues, which are means between deficiency and
					excess. For we must not declare that every virtue
					comes into being by the observance of a mean,
					but, on the one hand, wisdom, being without any
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.41"/>
					
					need of the irrational and arising in the activity
					of the mind, pure and uncontaminated by passion,
					is, as it were, a self-sufficing perfection and power<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Some would render, more naturally, <q direct="unspecified">extreme and potentiality</q>; but, in Plutarch's view, neither <q direct="unspecified">extreme</q> nor <q direct="unspecified">potentiality</q> could be called <q direct="unspecified">self-sufficing.</q>
               </note>
					of reason, by which the most divine and blessed
					element of knowledge becomes possible for us ;
					on the other hand, that virtue which is necessary
					to us because of our physical limitations, and
					needs, by Heaven, for its practical ends the service
					of the passions as its instrument, so to speak,
					and is not a destruction nor abolition of the irrational in the soul, but an ordering and regulation thereof, is an extreme as regards its power
					and quality, but as regards its quantity it is a
					mean, since it does away with what is excessive and
					deficient.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>But since a <q direct="unspecified">mean</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, ii. 6. 4-9 (1106 a 24).</note> is capable of various interpretations (for that which is a compound is a mean
					between the simple uncompounded substances, as
					grey is of white and black ; and that which contains
					and is contained is a mean between the contained and
					the container, as eight of twelve and four ; and that
					which partakes of neither of the extremes is a mean,
					as the indifferent is a mean between good and bad),
					in none of these ways can virtue be called a mean, for
					it is not a mixture of the vices, nor, encompassing
					what falls short of due measure, is it encompassed by
					that which is in excess of it ; nor is it entirely exempt
					from the impulses of the passions, wherein are found
					excess and deficiency. But it is a mean, and is said
					to be so, in a sense very like that which obtains in
					musical sounds and harmonies. For there the mean
					or mese, a properly-pitched note<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 1007 e ff., 1014 c, and 451 f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> like the <hi rend="italics">neti</hi> and
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.43"/>
					
					the <hi rend="italics">hypat&ecirc;</hi>,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The highest and lowest sounds of the heptachord; presumably the <hi rend="italics">mes&ecirc;</hi> is the fourth note of a scale of seven.</note> escapes the sharp highness of the one
					and the heavy deepness of the other ; so virtue,
					being an activity and faculty concerned with the
					irrational, does away with the remissions and overstrainings of the impulse and its excesses and defects
					altogether, and reduces each passion to moderation
					and faultlessness. So, for instance, they declare
					courage<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, ii. 7. 2-4 (1107 a 33); Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Eclogae</hi>, ii. 7. 20 (vol. ii. p. 141 ed. Wachsmuth).</note> to be a mean between cowardice and rashness, of which the former is a defect, the latter an
					excess, of the spirited part of the soul; so, likewise,
					liberality is a mean between parsimony and prodigality, and gentleness between insensibility and
					cruelty ; and temperance itself and justice are means,
					the latter distributing to itself in contracts neither
					more nor less than what is due, the former ever
					regulating the desires to a mean between lack of
					feeling and intemperance.
				</p>
            <p>
					In this last instance, indeed, the irrational seems,
					with particular clearness, to allow us to observe the
					difference between itself and the rational, and to
					show that passion is essentially quite a different thing
					from reason. For self-control<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, vii. 9. 6 (1151 b 33).</note> would not differ from
					temperance, nor incontinence from intemperance, as
					regards the pleasures and desires, if it were the same
					part of the soul that we naturally use for desiring as
					for forming judgements. But the fact is that temperance belongs to the sphere where reason guides and
					manages the passionate element, like a gentle animal
					obedient to the reins, making it yielding in its desires
					and willingly receptive of moderation and propriety;
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.45"/>
					
					but the self-controlled man, while he does indeed
					direct his desire by the strength and mastery of
					reason, yet does so not without pain, nor by persuasion, but as it plunges sideways and resists, as
					though with blow and curb, he forcibly subdues it and
					holds it in, being the while himself full of internal
					struggle and turmoil. Such a conflict Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 253 c ff.</note> portrays
					in his simile of the horses of the soul, where the worse
					horse struggles against his better yoke-fellow and at
					the same time disconcerts the charioteer, who is ever
					forced to hold out against him and with might and
					main to rein him in,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lest he let fall from his hands the crimson thongs,</quote>
					as Simonides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 17 (ed. Bergk and ed. Diehl); Frag. 48 (ed. Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, ii. p. 311).</note> has it. That is the reason why they
					do not account self-control even a virtue<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Ethica Nicomachea</hi>, iv. 9. 8 (1128 b 33): it is rather <q direct="unspecified">a mixture of virtue and vice.</q>
               </note> in the
					absolute sense, but less than virtue. For it is not
					a mean which has been produced by the harmony of
					the worse with the better, nor has the excess of
					passion in it been eliminated, nor has the desiderative
					part of the soul become obedient and compliant to
					the intelligent part, but is vexed and causes vexation
					and is confined by compulsion and, though living with
					reason, lives as in a state of rebellion against it,
					hostile and inimical:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The city reeks with burning incense, rings
						</l>
                  <l>Alike with prayers for health and cries of woe<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Tyrannus</hi>, 4-5; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 95 c, 169 d, 623 c.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					even so is the soul of the self-controlled man because
					of its lack of consistency and its conflict. And on the
					same grounds they hold that incontinence also is
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.47"/>
					
					something less than a vice, but that intemperance is a
					full-fledged vice. For intemperance possesses both an
					evil passion and an evil reason ; under the influence
					of the former, it is incited by desire to shameful
					conduct; under the influence of the latter, which,
					since its judgement is evil, is enlisted with the desires,
					intemperance loses even the perception of its errors.
					But incontinence,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 705 c-e.</note> with the aid of reason, preserves
					its power of judgement intact, yet by its passions,
					which are stronger than its reason, it is swept along
					against its judgement. That is why incontinence
					differs from intemperance, for in it reason is worsted
					by passion, whereas with intemperance reason does
					not even fight; in the case of incontinence reason
					argues against the desires as it follows them, whereas with intemperance reason guides them and is
					their advocate ; it is characteristic of intemperance
					that its reason shares joyfully in the sins committed,
					whereas with incontinence the reason shares in them,
					but with reluctance ; with intemperance, reason is
					willingly swept along into shameful conduct, whereas
					with incontinence, it betrays honour unwillingly.
				</p>
            <p>
					So also the difference between them is not less
					manifest in their words than in their actions. These
					are, for instance, the sayings of intemperate persons :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>What pleasure can there be, what joy, without
						</l>
                  <l>The golden Aphrodite? May I die
						</l>
                  <l>When things like these no longer comfort me.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Mimnermus, Frag. 1, vv. 1-2 (ed. Bergk and ed. Diehl); Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambic</hi>, i. p. 89.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And another says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To eat, to drink, to have one's way in love<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Alexis, Frag. 271 ed. Kock, vv. 4-5; the whole fragment is quoted in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 21 d.</note>:
						</l>
                  <l>All other things I call accessory,</l>
               </quote>
					
					          <pb id="v.6.p.49"/>
					
					as though with all his soul he were acquiescing in
					pleasures and were being subverted thereby. Not
					less than these does he<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 450, ades. 217.</note> who says
					<quote rend="blockquote">Leave me to die, for that is best for me,</quote>
					have his judgement suffering with the same ailment
					as his passions.
				</p>
            <p>
					But the sayings of incontinence are otherwise and
					different:
					<quote rend="blockquote">A mind I have, but Nature forces me<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">2</hi> p. 634, Euripides, Frag. 840 = Aeschylus, Frag. 262 ed. Smyth (L.C.L.).</note>;</quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Alas I from God this evil comes to men
						</l>
                  <l>When, knowing what is good, they do it not<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Frag. 841; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 33 e. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> St. Paul's <hi rend="italics">Epistle to the Romans</hi>, vii. 19, in the King James Version; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Metamorphoses</hi>, vii. 21: <foreign lang="la">video meliora proboque, | deteriora sequor</foreign>.</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The spirit yields and can resist no more,
						</l>
                  <l>Like anchor-hook in sand amid the surge.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 911, ades. 379; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 782 d. Some ascribe this and the following quotation to Euripides.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					Here not inaptly the poet terms <q direct="unspecified">an anchor-hook in
						sand</q> that which is not under the control of reason,
					nor firmly fixed, but surrenders its judgement to
					the loose and soft part of the soul. Very close to
					this imagery are also those famous lines<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 911, ades. 380.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>I, like some ship, am tied by ropes to shore,
						</l>
                  <l>And when winds blow, our cables do not hold.</l>
               </quote>
					For here the poet calls <q direct="unspecified">cables</q> the judgements
					which resist shameful conduct and then are broken
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.51"/>
					
					by passion, as by a great gust of wind. Truly the
					intemperate man is swept along to his pleasures
					by his desires with sails full-spread and delivers
					himself over to them and steers his course directly
					thither; whereas the course of the incontinent
					man zigzags here and there, as he strives to
					emerge from his passion and to stave it off and is
					yet swept down and shipwrecked on the reef of
					shameful conduct. Just as Timon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 9 (ed. Wachsmuth, p. 106); portions are quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 529 a and 705 d; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Diels, <hi rend="italics">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</hi>
                  <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, ii. p. 238.</note> used to lampoon
					Anaxarchus :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>The Cynic might of Anaxarchus seemed
						</l>
                  <l>Steadfast and bold, wherever he wished, to spring;
						</l>
                  <l>Well did he know the truth, they said, and yet
						</l>
                  <l>Was bad : for Nature smote him with desire
						</l>
                  <l>And led him back from truth - 'twas Nature's dart,
						</l>
                  <l>Before whom trembles many a Sophist heart.</l>
               </quote>
					For neither is the wise man continent, though he is
					temperate, nor is the fool incontinent, though he
					is intemperate. For the wise man takes pleasure in
					what is honourable, but the fool is not vexed by
					shamefulness. Incontinence, therefore, is the mark
					of a sophistic soul, which has, indeed, reason, but
					reason which cannot stand firm by its own just
					decisions.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>Such, then, are the differences between incontinence and intemperance ; and again between continence and temperance, these differences being the
					counterpart of the former. For continence is not yet
					free from remorse and pain and indignation ; but in
					the soul of the temperate man there is serenity on all
					occasions, freedom from violent changes, and sanity,
					by which the irrational is harmonized and blended
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.53"/>
					
					with reason, when this is equipped with great persuasion and a wonderful gentleness. And you would
					say, as you looked at the man,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Then, indeed, ceased the gale ; a windless calm
						</l>
                  <l>Arose ; some god had laid the waves to rest,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, xii. 168.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					since by reason the violent, raging, and furious
					movements of the desires had been quenched and
					those movements which Nature absolutely requires
					had been made sympathetic, submissive, friendly,
					and, when the man chose a course of action, willing
					to co-operate, so that they did not outstrip the
					dictates of reason, nor fall short of them, nor misbehave, nor disobey, but so that every impulse was
					easily led
					<quote rend="blockquote">As new-weaned foal beside his mother runs,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Semonides, Frag. 5; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 84 d 136 a, 790 f, 997 d; Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 150 (=Stobaeus, vol. v. p. 1024 ed. Hense).</note>
               </quote>
					and confirmed the remark of Xenocrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 3; <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 1124 e.</note> about
					true philosophers, that they alone do willingly what
					all others do unwillingly because of the law, even as
					dogs by a blow and cats by a noise are turned from
					their pleasures and regard with suspicion the danger
					that threatens them.
				</p>
            <p>
					It is quite obvious, then, that there is in the soul
					a perception of some such distinction and difference
					as regards the desires, as though some force were
					fighting against them and contradicting them. But
					some affirm<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 111.</note> that passion is not essentially different
					from reason, nor is there quarrelling between the
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.55"/>
					
					two and factious strife, but only a conversion of
					one and the same reason to its two aspects ; this
					escapes our notice by reason of the suddenness
					and swiftness of the change, for we do not perceive
					that it is the same part of the soul with which we
					naturally desire and change to aversion, are angry
					and afraid, are swept along by pleasure to shameful
					conduct, and then, when the soul itself is being
					swept away, recover ourselves again. In fact, they
					say, desire and anger and fear and all such things are
					but perverse opinions and judgements, which do not
					arise in one certain part of the soul, but are inclinations and yieldings, assents and impulses of the whole
					directive faculty and, in a word, certain activities
					which may in a moment be changed this way or that,
					just as the sudden assaults of children<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 458 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> have an
					impetuosity and violence that is precarious and
					inconstant because of children's weakness.
				</p>
            <p>
					But this doctrine is, in the first place, contrary to
					the clear evidence of our perceptions. For no one
					ever perceives in himself a change from desiring to
					judging, nor again a change from judging to desiring ;
					nor does the lover cease loving when he reasons that
					he must restrain his love and fight against it, and
					then give up again the process of reasoning and
					judging when he is softened by desire and yields to
					love ; but both while by reason he still continues to
					oppose passion, he continues in the passion, and
					again, when mastered by passion, he plainly sees his
					error by the light of reason : and neither through
					passion has he done away with reason, nor through
					reason is he rid of passion, but being borne back and
					forth from one to the other he lies between them and
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.57"/>
					
					participates in both. For those who assume now
					that desire becomes the controlling faculty, now that
					it is reason which arrays itself against desire, are in
					the same position as those who assume the hunter
					and the beast to be not two,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Emerson, <hi rend="italics">Brahma</hi>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                     <l>If the red slayer think he slays, </l>
                     <l>Or if the slain think he is slain, </l>
                     <l>They know not well the subtle ways </l>
                     <l>I keep, and pass, and turn again.</l>
                  </quote>
               </note> but one and the same
					body which, by a change, is now the beast, and
					now becomes the hunter. For just as those persons
					overlook something quite plain, so these testify
					against the evidence of perception, which tells us
					that we have in these cases, not a changing of some
					one thing, but two things struggling and fighting
					against one another.
				</p>
            <p>
					          <q direct="unspecified">What then?</q> they object. <q direct="unspecified">Is it not true that
						man's deliberative faculty also is often divided and
						distracted toward contrary opinions regarding what is
						expedient, but that it is yet one and the same?</q>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Quite so,</q> we shall say, <q direct="unspecified">but the process is not
						parallel.</q> For the intellectual part of the soul does not
					here oppose itself,but, using one and the same faculty,
					applies itself to different lines of reasoning ; or rather,
					there is but one single reason, which functions on
					things essentially different, as though on different
					matters. Therefore neither is pain present in reasoning where passion is absent, nor are men forced, as it
					were, to choose a course contrary to reason, unless
					indeed some emotion is furtively attached, as it were,
					to one pan of the balances. This, in fact, happens
					often : when it is not reasoning that opposes reasoning, but ambition or contentiousness or the pursuit of
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.59"/>
					
					favour or jealousy or fear that opposes, we think it is
					a difference between two reasons, as in the verse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, vii. 93.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">To refuse they were ashamed, but feared to accept;</quote>
					and this :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>To die is dreadful, yet it brings fair fame ;
						</l>
                  <l>Not to die is craven, yet there's pleasure there.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, p. 638, Euripides, Frag. 854.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					And in the judgement of suits concerning business
					affairs the passions rush in unawares and cause the
					greatest waste of time. So also in the councils of
					kings those who speak to obtain favour are not
					advocating one or the other of two decisions, but are
					submitting to some emotion which is contrary to their
					calculation of what is expedient. Therefore in
					aristocratic states the magistrates do not allow
					political speakers to make passionate harangues, for
					reason, if not influenced by passion, inclines to a just
					balance toward what is right; but if passion intervenes, the part of the soul that feels pleasure and
					pain fights and opposes the part which forms judgements and deliberates. Otherwise, why is it that in
					philosophical speculations no feeling of pain is present
					when, under the influence of those who hold different
					opinions, we change our views again and again, but
					that Aristotle<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> W. Jaeger, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, lxiv. 22 f.; Eusebius, <hi rend="italics">Praepar. Evang.</hi>, xiv. 6. 9, where Cephisodorus attacks the young Aristotle by an onslaught on the Platonic Ideas, <foreign lang="greek">oi)hqei\s kata\ *pla/twna to\n *)aristote/lhn filosofei=n</foreign>. See also 442 b, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> himself and Democritus and Chrysippus have recanted without any dismay or pain, and
					even with pleasure, some of the dogmas they previously held? It is because passion has set up no
					opposition to the contemplative and scientific part
					of the soul and the irrational part remains quiet and
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.61"/>
					
					does not meddle with these matters. Therefore
					reason, as soon as the truth appears, dismisses the
					false and gladly inclines toward the truth ; for it is in
					reason, not in its opposite, that the faculty resides
					which yields to persuasion and, through persuasion,
					changes opinion. But with most people, their deliberations, judgements, and decisions which are to be
					converted into action are in a state of emotion and
					therefore offer obstructions and difficulties to the path
					of reason, for reason is checked and confused by the
					irrational, which, with some emotion of pleasure or
					fear, pain or desire, rises up to oppose it. In such
					cases the senses make the decision, since they have
					contact with both; and if, in fact, one gains the
					mastery, it does not destroy the other, but forces it
					to comply and drags it along resisting. For the
					lover who admonishes himself<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 71 a, and Euripides, Frag. 665 there cited.</note> uses reason against
					his passion, since they both exist at the same time
					in his soul, as it were pressing with his hand the
					other member, which is inflamed, and clearly perceiving that there are two distinct forces and that
					they are at variance. On the other hand, in those
					deliberations and speculations where passion is absent
					(and these are the sort in which the contemplative
					faculty most commonly engages), if they be equally
					balanced, no judgement has taken place, but merely
					a perplexity has arisen, which is a rest or suspension
					of intellectual activity brought about by opposing
					probabilities ; but if the inclination falls to either
					side, the winning opinion has cancelled the other,
					with the result that there is no pain nor any
					opposition left. In general, when it appears that
					reason is opposing reason, there is no perception of
					them as two distinct things, but as a single thing
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.63"/>
					
					which arises in different impressions made upon the
					senses. Yet when there is a struggle against reason
					on the part of the irrational, which, by its very
					nature, can neither conquer nor be conquered without pain, straightway the irrational splits the soul in
					two by its battling and makes the distinction between
					the two perfectly obvious.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>It is not only from their dissension, however, but
					no less from their agreement, that one can perceive
					that the source of passion is essentially different from
					that of reason. For since it is equally possible to love
					a noble youth, well-formed by nature for virtue, and
					to love an evil and profligate one, and since it happens
					that one both becomes angry irrationally against
					one's own children or parents, and angry justly on
					behalf of parents and children against enemies and
					despots ; just as in the one case there is perception of
					struggle and dissension of passion against reason, so
					in the other there is perception of persuasion and
					agreement on the part of passion, which inclines the
					scales, as it were, in favour of reason and increases its
					power. Yet again, when a good man has lawfully
					married a wife, his intention is to treat her respectfully
					and consort with her honourably and soberly ; but as
					time goes on, his intimacy with her has given birth to
					passion, when he perceives that his love and affection
					increases by the exercise of his reason. So again,
					when young men happen upon cultivated teachers,
					they follow them and admire them at first because of
					their usefulness ; but later they come to feel affection
					for them also, and in place of familiar companions and
					pupils they are called lovers and are actually so.
					The same thing happens also in people's relations to
					good magistrates in cities and good neighbours and
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.65"/>
					
					relatives by marriage ; for in the beginning they
					dutifully associate with one another from some consideration of usefulness, but later they are carried
					unconsciously into genuine affection, reason drawing
					along, and aiding in the persuasion of, the passionate
					element. Is it not obvious that he<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Phaedra is the speaker: Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus</hi>, 385-386.</note> who said,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>And modesty. Two kinds there are : the one
						</l>
                  <l>Not bad, the other burdening our homes,</l>
               </quote>
					has perceived in himself that this emotion often
					follows the lead of reason and is arrayed at reason's
					side, but often, contrary to reason, by hesitations and
					delays ruins opportunities and actions?
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>But my opponents, though forced to concede in
					a manner these arguments because of their obvious
					truth, yet persist in calling shame <q direct="unspecified">modesty,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 529 d; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 107.</note> pleasure <q direct="unspecified">joy,</q> and fears <q direct="unspecified">precautions.</q> No one would
					blame them for this euphemism if they would but call
					these same emotions by these soft names when they
					attach themselves to reason, and call them by those
					harsher names when the emotions oppose and offer
					violence to reason. But when, convicted by their
					tears and tremblings and changes of colour, in place
					of grief and fear they call these emotions <q direct="unspecified">compunctions</q> and <q direct="unspecified">perplexities</q> and gloss over the desires
					with the term <q direct="unspecified">eagernesses,</q> they seem to be devising casuistic, not philosophic, shifts and escapes
					from reality through the medium of fancy names.
				</p>
            <p>
					And yet these very men,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iii. pp. 105-108.</note> to cite another instance,
					call those <q direct="unspecified">joys,</q> 
               <q direct="unspecified">volitions,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">precautions</q> of
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.67"/>
					
					theirs <q direct="unspecified">right sensibilities to emotion,</q> not <q direct="unspecified">insensibilities,</q> in this case using the terms correctly. For
					a <q direct="unspecified">right sensibility</q> arises when reason does not
					destroy the emotion, but composes and sets it in
					order in the souls of temperate persons. But what
					it is that happens in the case of evil and incontinent persons when, though their judgement tells
					them to love father and mother in place of a
					favourite or mistress, they cannot do this ; yet when
					their judgement bids them to love courtesan and
					flatterer, they immediately do that very thing?
					For if emotion and judgement were one, love and
					hate would follow upon our judgement of what we
					ought to love and hate ; but as it is, the contrary
					happens : with some judgements the emotion joins
					forces, others it disregards. Therefore even these
					very men<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 93.</note> affirm, since the evidence forces them to
					do so, that not every judgement is an emotion, but
					only that which sets in motion a violent and excessive
					impulse, thereby acknowledging that in us the faculty
					of judging and the faculty of feeling emotion are
					different, in the sense that the one is that which sets
					in motion, the other that which is moved. And
					Chrysippus himself in many places, by defining endurance and continence as states which follow the convictions of reason, is obviously forced by the evidence
					to acknowledge that that within us which follows is
					different from that which it follows when persuaded,
					or, on the other hand, fights against when it is not
					persuaded.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Now if, by positing<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iii. p. 119.</note> that all errors and faults
					are equal, they are in some other way overlooking
					the truth, this present discourse is not the proper
					occasion to confute them ; but in the case of the
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.69"/>
					
					emotions they certainly appear to be in opposition to
					reason and contrary to plain evidence. For, according to them, every emotion is an error, and every one
					who grieves or fears or desires is guilty of error. Yet
					there are seen to be great differences in the emotions
					according to their greater or lesser intensity. For
					who would declare that Dolon's<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, x. 374 ff.; <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 76 a.</note> fear was no greater
					than that of Ajax,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Il.</hi>, xi. 547; <hi rend="italics">De Vita et Poesi Hmeri</hi>, 135 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 409).</note> who <q direct="unspecified">often faced about</q> and
					departed slowly from the midst of his enemies,
					<q direct="unspecified">scarcely changing knee for knee</q>? Or that the
					grief of Alexander,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> for the slaying of Cleitus by Alexander Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Life of Alexander</hi>, li.; and for Alexander's grief <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> lii. (694 d-e).</note> who attempted to kill himself
					because of Cleitus, was equal to Plato's grief for the
					death of Socrates? For griefs are increased immoderately by unpredictable circumstances,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 463 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; 474 e-f, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi> (Carneades).</note> and an
					unexpected occurrence is more painful than one quite
					likely to happen; if, for instance, one should expect
					to see someone in prosperity and honour and then
					should learn that he had been cruelly tortured, as
					Parmenion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Philotas, the son of Alexander's general Parmenion, was suddenly executed on suspicion of conspiracy; <hi rend="italics">cf. Life of Alexander</hi>, xlix. (693 b).</note> did of Philotas. And who would affirm
					that the rage of Nicocreon against Anaxarchus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A friend of Alexander who insulted Nicocreon, tyrant of Cyprus, so markedly that the latter took his revenge after Alexander's death; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, ix. 58-59.</note>
					was equal to that of Magas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 458 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; see Hartman, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, p. 205, for the absurdity of this comparison.</note> against Philemon,
					though they had both been reviled by their opponents? For Nicocreon with iron pestles ground
					Anaxarchus to powder, but Magas merely ordered
					the public executioner to place his naked blade on
					Philemon's neck and then to let him go. That is the
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.71"/>
					
					reason why Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 411 b; contrast <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 457 b-c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> also called anger <q direct="unspecified">sinews of the
						soul</q> on the ground that it is intensified by harshness
					and relaxed by gentleness.
				</p>
            <p>
					So to elude these and similar difficulties my opponents<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Stoics, as generally throughout the essay; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 119.</note> deny that these intensities and violences of
					the emotions come into existence in accordance with
					the judgement, in which lies the liability to error ;
					but maintain that the irritations, contractions, and
					diffusions admit of increase and diminution through
					the operations of the irrational element. Yet there
					obviously are differences in judgements also ; for
					some adjudge poverty not to be an evil, others to be
					a great evil, still others to be the greatest evil, so that
					they even hurl themselves down from precipices<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 165 a, 1039 f, 1069 d; Theognis, 173-178, and the references cited by Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi>, i. p. 249, note 5.</note> or
					throw themselves into the sea. Some think death to
					be an evil merely because it deprives them of the
					good things of life, others because there are eternal
					torments and horrible punishments beneath the earth.
					By some the health of the body is cherished because
					it is in accordance with Nature and useful, to others
					it appears the greatest good in the world ; for neither
					do they value
					<quote rend="blockquote">Joy in wealth or children,</quote>
					nor
					<quote rend="blockquote">In that kingly rule that makes man like to gods<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Ariphron, <hi rend="italics">Paean to Health</hi>, vv. 3-4 (Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</hi>, iii. p. 597, or Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, iii. p. 401); <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 497 a, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>
               </quote>
					in comparison therewith ; and finally they think even
					virtue to be useless and unprofitable if health be not
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.73"/>
					
					present. Hence it plainly appears that some make a
					greater, some a lesser, error in their judgements also.
				</p>
            <p>
					This doctrine, however, need not be confuted at
					present, but that other point maybe assumed from this
					discussion: that my opponents themselves also concede
					that the irrational part is essentially different from
					judgement, the irrational, in accordance with which
					they say that emotion becomes greater and more
					violent ; their contention is concerning the name and
					the expression, but they really surrender the point at
					issue to those who assert that the passionate and
					irrational element is different from the reasoning and
					judging. In his book <hi rend="italics">On the Failure to Lead a Consistent Life</hi> Chrysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 94; the title was interpreted by Xylander as <hi rend="italics">De Dissensione Partium Animi</hi>.</note> has said, <q direct="unspecified">Anger is a blind
						thing : often it prevents our seeing obvious matters,
						and often it obscures matters which are already apprehended</q> ; and, proceeding a little further, he says,
					<q direct="unspecified">For the passions, when once raised, drive out the
						processes of reasoning and all things that appear
						otherwise than they would have them be, and push
						forward with violence to actions contrary to reason.</q>
					He then uses as evidence the words of Menander<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 567, Kock, <hi rend="italics">Comic. Att. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 173 (Allinson, p. 497).</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Ah woe, alas for me! Where ever were
						</l>
                  <l>My wits awandering in my body then
						</l>
                  <l>When I made choice to do not this, but that?</l>
               </quote>
					And again, Chrysippus proceeds to say that every
					rational creature is so disposed by nature as to use
					reason in all things and to be governed by it ; yet
					often reason is rejected when we are under the impulse of some other more violent force. Thus in this
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.75"/>
					
					passage he plainly acknowledges what conclusion is
					to be drawn from the difference which exists between
					passion and reason.
				</p>
            <p>
					Why, it would be ridiculous, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 430 e.</note> says, for
					a man to say that he is now better than himself
					and again worse than himself, and sometimes master
					of himself and sometimes not. 
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>For how is it
					possible for the same man to be both better and
					worse than himself, or to be master of himself and
					at the same time be mastered, if in some way or
					other each man were not by nature double and had
					not both the worse and the better within himself?
					This being the case, he who holds the worse in subjection to the better is Iself-controlled and better than
					himself, but he who permits the better part to follow
					and be in subjection to the intemperate and irrational
					part of his soul is called worse than himself and incontinent and in a state contrary to Nature.
				</p>
            <p>
					For, in accordance with Nature, it is proper that
					reason, which is divine, should lead and rule the
					irrational, which derives its origin directly from the
					body to which Nature has designed that it should bear
					a resemblance and share in the body's passions and
					be contaminated by it, since it has entered into the
					body and has become merged with it; that this is so
					is shown by our impulses,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 86 b.</note> which arise and are set in
					motion toward corporeal objects and become violent
					or relax in keeping with the changes of the body.
					For this reason young men are swift and impetuous
					and fiery in their appetites, and stung by madness, as
					it were, through the abundance and heat of their
					blood ; but in old men the source of desire, which is
					seated about the liver,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 71 a.</note> is in the process of being
					extinguished and becoming small and weak, whereas
					
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.77"/>
					
					reason increases more and more in vigour as the
					passionate element fades away together with the body.
					And this, of course, is what determines the natures
					of wild beasts also as regards the passions. For it
					is not, I presume, by the rightness or wrongness of
					their opinions that some of them oppose apparent
					dangers with valour and impetuousness whereas others
					have helpless flutterings and fears in their souls ; but
					the faculties which control the blood, the breath, and
					the body in general cause the difference in their
					affections, since the emotional part springs up from
					the flesh as from a root and carries with it its quality
					and composition. But that in man his body is
					affected and moved together with the impulses of his
					passions is proved by his paleness<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. De Libidine et Aegritudine</hi>, 6 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 5).</note> and blushing, his
					trembling and palpitations of the heart, and again by
					his cheerful and relaxed expression when in hope and
					expectation of pleasures. But whenever the intellect
					acts, not accompanied by emotion but by itself alone,
					the body remains in repose and at rest, neither sharing
					nor partaking in the activity of the mind, so long as the
					body does not have to deal with the emotional element
					or include the irrational in such activity. Consequently,
					this fact also makes it plain that there are two parts
					within us which differ from each other in their
					faculties.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And in general, both as my opponents<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Stoics; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, ii. p. 150.</note> themselves admit and as is quite obvious, in this world some
					things are governed by an acquired disposition, others
					by a natural one, some by an irrational soul, others
					by a rational and intellectual one ; and in practically
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.79"/>
					
					all these things man participates and he is subject
					to all the differences I have mentioned. For he is
					controlled by his acquired disposition, nurtured by
					his natural disposition, and makes use of reason and
					intellect. He has, therefore, some portion of the
					irrational also and has innate within him the mainspring of emotion, not as an adventitious accessory,
					but as a necessary part of his being, which should
					never be done away with entirely, but must needs
					have careful tending and education. Therefore the
					work of reason is not Thracian, not like that of Lycurgus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 15 d-e. Lycurgus, king of Thrace, angered with Dionysus, cut down the vines; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Apollodorus, <hi rend="italics">Bibliotheca</hi>, iii. 5. 1, with Frazer's notes (L.C.L., vol. i. pp. 327 ff.).</note> - to cut down<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 529 b-c.</note> and destroy the helpful
					elements of emotion together with the harmful, but to
					do as the god<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Poseidon: <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 158 d, 730 d.</note> who watches over crops and the god<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Dionysus: <hi rend="italics">cf. Moralia</hi>, 994 a; both Poseidon and Dionysus are said to be lords of <foreign lang="greek">th=s u(gra=s kai\ goni/mou a)rxh=s</foreign> in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 675 f. Poseidon's functions as a god of vegetation are perhaps to be derived from his position as god of fresh streams and fountains; see Farnell, <hi rend="italics">Cults of the Greek States</hi>, iv. p. 6.</note>
					who guards the vine do - to lop off the wild growth
					and to clip away excessive luxuriance, and then to
					cultivate and to dispose for use the serviceable remainder. For neither do those who fear drunkenness
					pour out their wine upon the ground,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 773 d.</note> nor do those
					who fear passion eradicate the disturbing element,
					but both temper<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Hartman, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, pp. 203 f., for criticism of the ellipsis. Plutarch's meaning is, of course, that wine is tempered by water, and passion by reason.</note> what they fear. It is, in fact, the
					rebellious kicking and plunging of oxen and horses
					that men do away with, not their movements and
					activities ; even so reason makes use of the emotions
					when they have been subdued and are tame, and
					does not hamstring<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 449 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> nor altogether excise that part
					of the soul which should be its servant. For
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.81"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">The horse is meet for the chariot,</quote>
					as Pindar<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 234 ed. Bergk; 258 ed. Boeckh (p. 611 ed. Sandys); the quotation is given more fully in 472 c, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>the ox for the plough ;
						</l>
                  <l>But if you think to slay a boar, you must find a stout-hearted hound.</l>
               </quote>
					Yet much more useful than these beasts are the whole
					brood of passions when they are present in the service
					of reason and help to intensify the virtues : anger,
					if it be moderate, will assist courage, and hatred of evil
					will aid justice, and righteous indignation<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. p. 100, 1. 37.</note> will oppose
					those who are prosperous beyond their deserts when
					their souls are inflamed with folly and insolence<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 716 a.</note> and
					they need to be checked. For who, even if he so
					wished, could separate or sever from friendship a
					natural propensity toward affection, from humaneness pity, and from true benevolence the mutual
					participation in joy and grief? And if those err who
					discard love entirely because love may bring madness,
					neither are they right who blame commerce because
					it may beget covetousness ; on the contrary, what
					they do is somewhat like the action of those who would
					abolish running because one may chance to stumble,
					or shooting<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf. Moralia</hi>, 459 d, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> because one may overshoot the mark, and
					dislike any singing at all because some sing off key.
					For as in the realm of sound musical art produces consonance, not by doing away with the deep low and
					the shrill high notes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 444 e-f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; and in the case of the body, medical art produces health, not by the removal of heat
					and coldness, but by the proportionately quantitative
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.83"/>
					
					admixture of the two ; so in the soul moral virtue is
					produced when equity and moderation are engendered
					by reason in the emotional faculties and activities.
					For a soul possessed of excessive pain or joy or fear is
					like a swollen and feverish body; it is not so, however,
					if the joy or pain or fear be moderate. And Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xiii. 284; <hi rend="italics">cf. De Vita et Poesi Homeri</hi>, 135 (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 408).</note>
					in his admirable words,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>A valiant man will never change his hue,
						</l>
                  <l>Nor will his fear be over-great,</l>
               </quote>
					does not abolish fear, but excessive fear, in order
					that the valiant man may have not foolhardiness but
					courage, not audacity but daring. In his pleasures,
					therefore, a man must rid himself of excessive desire,
					and in punishing wrong, of excessive hatred of evil:
					for in this way he will be, in the former case, not
					insensible but temperate, and in the latter case, just,
					not savage nor cruel. But if the passions could in
					reality be entirely done away with,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 443 c, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> in many persons
					reason would be too inactive and dulled, like a pilot
					when the wind dies down. It is surely this truth
					that the legislators also have perceived when they
					try to put into their constitutions the emotions of
					ambition and emulation as regards the citizens'
					relations to each other, but in relation to the enemy
					try to rouse and increase their spirited and fighting
					qualities with trumpets and pipes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Contrast 458 e, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note> For it is not in
					poetry only that, as Plato<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 245 a; <hi rend="italics">cf. Ion</hi>, 533 a ff.</note> says, he who is inspired
					and possessed by the Muses renders ridiculous the
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.85"/>
					
					man who is an artist equipped with exact knowledge
					of technique, but in battles also the passionate and
					inspired is irresistible and invincible. This quality it
					is that Homer says the gods instil into men :
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>So did he speak and breathed great might
						</l>
                  <l>Into the shepherd of the people<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, xv. 262: Apollo to Hector.</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					and
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>Not without some god does he
						</l>
                  <l>These deeds of madness<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                        <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>, v. 185; of Diomedes.</note>;</l>
               </quote>
					as though the gods were adding passion as an incitement or a vehicle to reason.
				</p>
            <p>
					Indeed we may see these very opponents of mine
					often inciting young men with praise and often chastising them with admonitions; and of these, in the
					first case pleasure is the consequence, in the second
					pain (in fact, admonition and rebuke engender repentance and shame, of which the first is a kind of pain,
					the second a kind of fear<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">Stoic. Vet. Frag.</hi>, iii. pp. 98 f.</note>) ; and of these methods
					they make particular use to improve their charges.
					As Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Archidamus's remark on Charillus, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 55 e, 218 b, 537 d.</note> also remarked, when Plato was being
					praised, <q direct="unspecified">What is there so august about one who has
						spent so much time talking philosophy, yet has never
						caused anyone pain?</q> For surely studies could not
					so properly be called, to use Xenocrates'<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, iv. 10.</note> words, the
					<q direct="unspecified">grips of philosophy,</q> as could the emotions of young
					men : shame, desire, repentance, pleasure, pain,
					ambition. On these if reason and law obtain a suitable and salutary grip, they efficaciously set the young
					man upon the path that he should take. Therefore the
					
					<pb id="v.6.p.87"/>
					
					Spartan<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 439 f, <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>, 653 b-c.</note> tutor was not wide of the mark when he
					said that he intended to make a boy entrusted to him
					delight in honourable and be vexed at dishonourable
					things. Than this saying there can be shown no
					greater nor fairer end of such education as befits a
					free-born child.
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>