<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Compendium Argumenti Stoicos absurdiora poetis dicere</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.137">
      <body>
         <head>A breviate of a discourse, showing that the Stoics speak greater improbabilities than the poets.</head>
         <pb id="v.3.p.194"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Pindar's Caeneus hath been taken to task by several,
				being improbably feigned, impenetrable by steel and impassible in his body, and so
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Descending into hell without a wound,
				</l>
                     <l>And with sound foot parting in two the ground.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But the Stoics' Lapithes, as if they had carved him out
					of the very adamantine matter of impassibility itself, though
					he is not invulnerable, nor exempt from either sickness or
					pain, yet remains fearless, regretless, invincible, and unconstrainable in the midst of wounds, dolors, and torments,
					and in the very subversions of the walls of his native city,
					and other such like great calamities. Again, Pindar's
					Caeneus is not wounded when struck; but the Stoics' wise
					man is not detained when shut up in a prison, suffers no
					compulsion by being thrown down a precipice, is not tortured when on the rack, takes no hurt by being maimed,
					and when he catches a fall in wrestling he is still unconquered; when he is encompassed with a rampire, he is
					not besieged; and when sold by his enemies, he is still
					not made a prisoner. The wonderful man is like to
					those ships that have inscribed upon them A PROSPEROUS
					VOYAGE, or PROTECTING PROVIDENCE, or A PRESERVATIVE
					AGAINST DANGERS, and yet for all that endure storms, and
					are miserably shattered and overturned.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Euripides's Iolaus of a feeble, superannuated old man,
				by means of a certain prayer, became on a sudden youthful
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.195"/>
				
				 and strong for battle; but the Stoics' wise man was
				yesterday most detestable and the worst of villains, but today is changed on a sudden into a state of virtue, and is
				become of a wrinkled, pale fellow, and, as Aeschylus
				speaks,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of an old sickly wretch with stitch in's back,
				</l>
                     <l>Distent with rending pains as on a rack,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>a gallant, god-like, and beauteous person.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>The Goddess Minerva took from Ulysses his wrinkles,
				baldness, and deformity, to make him appear a handsome
				man. But these men's wise man, though old age quits
				not his body, but contrariwise still lays on and heaps more
				upon it, though he remains (for instance) hump-backed,
				toothless, one-eyed, is yet neither deformed, disfigured, nor
				ill-favored. For as beetles are said to relinquish perfumes
				and to pursue after ill scents; so Stoical love, having used
				itself to the most foul and deformed persons, if by means
				of philosophy they change into good form and comeliness,
				becomes presently disgusted.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>He that in the Stoics' account was in the forenoon
				(for example) the worst man in the world is in the afternoon  best of men; and he that falls asleep a very sot,
				dunce, miscreant, and brute, nay, by Jove, a slave and a
				beggar to boot, rises up the same day a prince, a rich and
				a happy man, and (which is yet more) a continent, just,
				determined, and unprepossessed person ;&mdash;not by shooting
				forth out of a young and tender body a downy beard or
				the sprouting tokens of mature youth, but by having in a
				feeble, soft, unmanful, and undetermined mind, a perfect
				intellect, a consummate prudence, a godlike disposition, an
				unprejudiced science, and an unalterable habit. All this
				time his viciousness gives not the least ground in order to
				it, but he becomes in an instant, I had almost said, of the
				vilest brute, a sort of hero, genius, or God. For he that
				receives his virtue from the Stoics' portico may say,
				
				<pb id="v.3.p.196"/>
				
				           <quote rend="blockquote">Ask what thou wilt, it shall be granted thee.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Menander.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>It brings wealth along with it, it contains kingship in it,
					it confers fortune; it renders men prosperous, and makes
					them to want nothing and to have a sufficiency of every
					thing. though they have not one drachm of silver in the
					house.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>The fabular relations of the poets are so careful of
				decorum, that they never leave a Hercules destitute of
				necessaries; but those still spring, as out of some fountain,
				as well for him as for his companions. But he that hath
				received of the Stoics Amalthaea becomes indeed a rich
				man, but he begs his victuals of other men ; he is a king,
				but resolves syllogisms for hire; he is the only man that
				hath all things, but yet he pays rent for the house he lives
				in, and oftentimes buys bread with borrowed money, or
				else begs it of those that have nothing themselves.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>The king of Ithaca begs with a design that none may
				know who he is, and makes himself
				<quote rend="blockquote">As like a dirty sorry beggar<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. XVI. 273.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as he can. But he that is of the Portico, while he bawls
					and cries out, It is I only that am a king, It is I only that
					am a rich man, is yet many times seen at other people's
					doors saying:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>On poor Hipponax, pray, some pity take,
					</l>
                     <l>Bestow an old cast coat for heaven's sake;
					</l>
                     <l>I'm well nigh dead with cold, and all o'er quake.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>