<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quomodo adolescens poetas audire debeat</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent/>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic/>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1927</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>5/10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>RS</name>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>tagged and parsed</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb id="v1.p.72"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="intro">
            <head>HOW THE YOUNG SHOULD STUDY POETRY (QUOMODO ADOLESCENS POETAS AUDIRE DEBEAT) <lb/>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>Plutarch's essay on the study of poetry is not a discussion of the essentials
					of poetry, nor an analysis of its various kinds after the manner of
					Aristotle's Poetics, but it is concerned with poetry only as a means of
					training the young in preparation for the study of philosophy later. Some
					experience with the adumbrations of philosophic doctrines which are to be
					found in poetry will, in the opinion of the author, make such doctrines seem
					less strange when they are met later in the actual study of philosophy.</p>
            <p>This training is to be imparted, not by confining the reading to selected
					passages, but by teaching the young to recognize and ignore the false and
					fabulous in poetry, to choose always the better interpretation, and, in
					immoral passages where art is employed for art's sake, not to be deluded
					into approving vicious sentiments because of their artistic presentation.
					Such passages may be offset by other passages from the same author or from
					another author, and, as a last resort, one may try his hand at emending
					unsavoury lines to make them conform to a higher ethical standard. This last
					proposal seems to the modern reader a weak subterfuge, but it was a practice
					not unknown even before Plutarch's time.</p>
            <p>Philology, in the narrower sense, Plutarch says, is a science in itself, and
					a knowledge of it is not <pb id="v1.p.73"/> essential to an understanding of
					literature (a fact enunciated from time to time by modern educators as a new
					discovery). But, on the other hand, Plutarch strongly insists that an exact
					appreciation of words and of their meanings in different contexts is
					indispensable to the understanding of any work of poetry.</p>
            <p>The various points in the essay are illustrated by plentiful quotations drawn
					in the main from Homer, Hesiod, Archilochus, Pindar, Simonides, Theognis,
					Aeschylus, Sophocles, Euripides, and Menander. These are accompanied by many
					keen and intelligent observations (such, for example, as that regarding
					Paris), which attest Plutarch's wide and careful reading in the classical
					authors.</p>
            <p>The fact that Plutarch does not use the methods of historical criticism will
					not escape the reader, and, although this seems to us a great defect in the
					essay, it is wholly in keeping with the spirit of Plutarch's age. On the
					other hand there is well shown the genial and kindly Plutarch, who wishes to
					believe only good of all men, including the poets, however much they may
					fall short of the standards set by the divine Homer.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v1.p.75"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>If, my dear Marcus Sedatus, it is true, as the poet Philoxenus used to say,
					that of meats those that are not meat, and of fish those that are not fish,
					have the best flavour, let us leave the expounding of this matter to those
					persons of whom Cato said that their palates are more sensitive than their
					minds. And so of philosophical discourses it is clear to us that those
					seemingly not at all philosophical, or even serious, are found more
					enjoyable by the very young, who present themselves at such lectures as
					willing and submissive hearers. For in perusing not only Aesop's Fables, and
					Tales from the Poets, but even the Abaris of Heracleides, the Lycon of
					Ariston, and philosophic doctrines about the soul when these are combined
					with tales from mythology,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch probably has Plato in mind, and is
						thinking of passages like <q direct="unspecified">The Last Judgement</q> (<hi rend="italics">Gorgias</hi>, 523 ff.).</note> they get inspiration as well as
					pleasure. Wherefore we ought not only to keep the young decorous in the
					pleasures of eating and drinking, but, even more, in connexion with what
					they hear and read, by using in moderation, as a relish, that which gives
					pleasure, we should accustom them to seek what is useful and salutary
					therein. For close-shut gates do not <pb id="v1.p.77"/> preserve a city from
					capture if it admit the enemy through one; nor does continence in the other
					pleasures of sense save a young man, if he unwittingly abandon himself to
					that which comes through hearing. On the contrary, inasmuch as this form of
					pleasure engages more closely the man that is naturally given to thought and
					reason, so much the more, if neglected, does it injure and corrupt him that
					receives it. Since, then, it is neither possible, perhaps, nor profitable to
					debar from poetry a boy as old as my Soclarus and your Cleander now are, let
					us keep a very close watch over them, in the firm belief that they require
					oversight in their reading even more than in the streets. Accordingly, I
					have made up my mind to commit to writing and to send to you some thoughts
					on poetry which it occurred to me recently to express. I beg that you will
					take them and peruse them, and if they seem to you to be no worse than the
					things called amethysts <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <q direct="unspecified">Preventitives of intoxication</q>; herbs or
						seeds (Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Symp.</hi> 647 B, Athenaeus, 24 C),
						or nuts (Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Symp.</hi> 624 C) which were
						eaten, or stones (Pliny, <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> xxxvii. 9. 124)
						which were hung about the neck, in the belief that they would resist
						drunkenness.</note> which some persons on convivial occasions hang upon
					their persons or take beforehand, then impart them to Cleander, and thus
					forestall his natural disposition, which, because it is slow in nothing, but
					impetuous and lively in everything, is more subject to such influences.
					<quote rend="blockquote">Bad may be found in the head of the
						cuttle-fish; good there is also,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
							Leutsch and Schneidewin, <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi
								Graeci</hi>, i. p. 299; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 734 E.</note>
               </quote> because it is very pleasant
					to eat but it makes one's sleep full of bad dreams and subject to strange
					and disturbing fancies, as they say. Similarly also in the art of poetry
					there is much that is pleasant and nourishing for the mind of a youth, but
					quite as much <pb id="v1.p.79"/> that is disturbing and misleading, unless
					in the hearing of it he have proper oversight. For it may be said, as it
					seems, not only of the land of the Egyptians but also of poetry, that it
					yields <quote rend="blockquote">Drugs, and some are good when mixed and
						others baneful<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv.
							230.</note>
               </quote> to those who cultivate it. <quote rend="blockquote">Hidden therein are love and desire and winning converse, Suasion that
								steals away the mind of the very wisest.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xiv. 216.</note>
               </quote> For the element of deception
					in it does not gain any hold on utterly witless and foolish persons. This is
					the ground of Simonides' answer to the man who said to him, <q direct="unspecified">Why are
						the Thessalians the only people whom you do not deceive ?</q> His
					answer was, <q direct="unspecified">Oh, they are too ignorant to be deceived by me</q>
					; and Gorgias called tragedy a deception wherein he who deceives is more
					honest than he who does not deceive, and he who is deceived is wiser than he
					who is not deceived. Shall we then stop the ears of the young, as those of
					the Ithacans were stopped, with a hard and unyielding wax, and force them to
					put to sea in the Epicurean boat, and avoid poetry and steer their course
					clear of it; or rather shall we set them against some upright standard of
					reason and there bind them fast, guiding and guarding their judgement, that
					it may not be carried away from the course by pleasure towards that which
					will do them hurt ? <quote rend="blockquote">No, not even Lycurgus, the
						mighty son of Dryas<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi.
							130.</note>
               </quote> had sound sense, because, when many became drunk
					and violent, he went about uprooting the grapevines instead of bringing the
					springs of water nearer, <pb id="v1.p.81"/> and thus chastening the <q direct="unspecified">
						frenzied god,</q> as Plato says, <q direct="unspecified">through correction by
							another, a sober, god.</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Laws</hi>,
								773 D.</note> For the tempering of wine with water removes its
					harmfulness without depriving it at the same time of its usefulness. So let
					us not root up or destroy the Muses' vine of poetry, but where the mythical
					and dramatic part grows all riotous <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
						Theophrastus, <hi rend="italics">De causis plantarum</hi>, iii. 1.
						5.</note> and luxuriant, through pleasure unalloyed, which gives it
					boldness and obstinacy in seeking acclaim, let us take it in hand and prune
					it and pinch it back. But where with its grace it approaches a true kind of
					culture, and the sweet allurement of its language is not fruitless or
					vacuous, there let us introduce philosophy and blend it with poetry. For as
					the mandragora, when it grows beside the vine and imparts its influence to
					the wine, makes this weigh less heavily on those who drink it, so poetry, by
					taking up its themes from philosophy and blending them with fable, renders
					the task of learning light and agreeable for the young. Wherefore poetry
					should not be avoided by those who are intending to pursue philosophy, but
					they should use poetry as an introductory exercise in philosophy, by
					training themselves habitually to seek the profitable in what gives
					pleasure, and to find satisfaction therein ; and if there be nothing
					profitable, to combat such poetry and be dissatisfied with it. For this is
					the beginning of education, <quote rend="blockquote">If one begin each task
						in proper way So is it likely will the ending be,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi>, No.
							747.</note>
               </quote> as Sophocles says. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>First of all, then, the young man should be introduced into poetry with
					nothing in his mind so <pb id="v1.p.83"/> well imprinted, or so ready at
					hand, as the saying, <q direct="unspecified">Many the lies the poets
						tell,</q>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Proverbial; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Aristotle,
							<hi rend="italics">Metaphysics</hi>, i. 2.</note> some intentionally
					and some unintentionally; intentionally, because for the purpose of giving
					pleasure and gratification to the ear (and this is what most people look for
					in poetry) they feel that the truth is too stern in comparison with fiction.
					For the truth, because it is what actually happens, does not deviate from
					its course, even though the end be unpleasant; whereas fiction, being a
					verbal fabrication, very readily follows a roundabout route, and turns aside
					from the painful to what is more pleasant. For not metre nor figure of
					speech nor loftiness of diction nor aptness of metaphor nor unity of
					composition has so much allurement and charm, as a clever interweaving of
					fabulous narrative. But, just as in pictures, colour is more stimulating
					than line-drawing because it is life-like, and creates an illusion, so in
					poetry falsehood combined with plausibility is more striking, and gives more
					satisfaction, than the work which is elaborate in metre and diction, but
					devoid of myth and fiction. This explains why Socrates, being induced by
					some dreams to take up poetry, since he was not himself a plausible or
					naturally clever workman in falsehood, inasmuch as he had been the champion
					of truth all his life, put into verse the fables of Aesop,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 60
						A.</note> assuming that there can be no poetic composition which has no
					addition of falsehood. It is true that we know of sacrifices without dancing
					or flute, but we do not know of any poetic composition without fable or
					without falsehood. The verses of Empedocles and of Parmenides, the Antidotes
					against Poisons of Nicander, and the maxims of Theognis, are merely
					compositions which have borrowed from poetic <pb id="v1.p.85"/> art its
					metre and lofty style as a vehicle in order to avoid plodding along in
					prose. Whenever, therefore, in the poems of a man of note and repute some
					strange and disconcerting statement either about gods or lesser deities or
					about virtue is made by the author, he who accepts the statement as true is
					carried off his feet, and has his opinions perverted; whereas he who always
					remembers and keeps clearly in mind the sorcery of the poetic art in dealing
					with falsehood, who is able on every such occasion to say to it, <quote rend="blockquote">
						            &amp;ldquo;Device more subtly cunning than the lynx,a why knit your brows
							when jesting, why pretend to instruct when practising deception
							?&amp;rdquo;
						            <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., adesp.</hi> No.
							349.</note>
					          </quote>will not suffer any dire effects or even acquire any base beliefs,
					but he will check himself when he feels afraid of Poseidon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xx. 60.</note> and is in terror lest the
					god rend the earth asunder and lay bare the nether world; he will check
					himself when he is feeling wroth at Apollo in behalf of the foremost of the
					Achaeans, <quote rend="blockquote">Whose praises he himself did sing,
						himself Was present at the feast, these words he spoke Himself, and yet
						himself brought death to him;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Spoken by Thetis of the death of her
							son Achilles, as we are told by Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, ii. p. 383 B, who quotes the passage more fully.
							<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
								Graec. Frag., Aeschylus</hi>, No. 350.</note>
               </quote> he will
					cease to shed tears over the dead Achilles and over Agamemnon <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer,
						<hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xi. 470 and 360.</note> in the nether
					world, as they stretch out their impotent and feeble arms in their desire to
					be alive ; and if, perchance, he is beginning to be disturbed by their
					suffering and overcome by the enchantment, he will not hesitate to say to
					himself, <pb id="v1.p.87"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Hasten eager to the light, and all you saw here Lay
						to heart that you may tell your wife hereafter.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xi. 223.</note>
               </quote> Certainly Homer
					has put this gracefully in reference to the visit to the shades, indicating
					that it is fit stuff for a woman's ear because of the element of fable in
					it. </p>
            <p> Such things as this are what the poets fabricate intentionally, but more
					numerous are the things which they do not fabricate, but think and believe
					in their own hearts, and then impart to us in their false colouring. Take
					for example what Homer has said relating to Zeus: <quote rend="blockquote">In the scales he placed two fates of Death so grievous, One of Achilles
						and the other of horse-taming Hector; Grasping the middle he poised it,
						and Hector's fated day descended. Down to Hades he went, and Phoebus
						Apollo forsook him.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxii.
							210.</note>
               </quote> Now Aeschylus has fitted a whole tragedy to this
					story, giving it the title of The Weighing of Souls, and has placed beside
					the scales of Zeus on the one side Thetis, and on the other Dawn, entreating
					for their sons who are fighting. But it is patent to everybody that this is
					a mythical fabrication which has been created to please or astound the
					hearer. But in the lines <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Zeus, appointed to decide the
						outcome of men's fighting<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv.
							84.</note>
               </q> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">A fault doth God create
								in men Whene'er he wills to crush a house in woe,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Niobe</hi>, of Aeschylus; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Aeschylus</hi>, No.
									156.</note>
               </q> we have at last statements in accord with their
					opinion and belief, as they thus publish to us and try to make us share
					their delusion and ignorance <pb id="v1.p.89"/> regarding the gods. Then
					again the monstrous tales of visits to the shades, and the descriptions,
					which in awful language create spectres and pictures of blazing rivers and
					hideous places and grim punishments, do not blind very many people to the
					fact that fable and falsehood in plenty have been mingled with them like
					poison in nourishing food. And not Homer nor Pindar nor Sophocles really
					believed that these things are so when they wrote : <quote rend="blockquote">From there the slow-moving rivers of dusky night Belch forth a darkness
						immeasurable,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 130
							Christ.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">On past Ocean's
								streams they went and the headland of Leucas,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xxiv. 11.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">The narrow throat of Hades and the refluent
									depths.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi>, No.
										748.</note>
               </quote> However, take the case of those who, bewailing
					and fearing death as something piteous, or want of burial as something
					terrible, have given utterance to sentiments like these : <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Go not hence and leave me behind unwept,
						unburied,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xi.
							72.</note>
               </q> and <quote rend="blockquote">Forth from his body went
								his soul on wing to Hades, Mourning its fate and leaving its vigour and
								manhood,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 856 and xxii.
									362.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Destroy me not
										untimely ; for 'tis sweet To see the light. Compel me not to gaze Upon
										the regions underneath the earth.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Iphigenia at Aulis</hi>, 1218.</note>
               </quote> These are the
					voices of persons affected by emotion <pb id="v1.p.91"/> and prepossessed by
					opinions and delusions. For this reason such sentiments take a more powerful
					hold on us and disturb us the more, inasmuch as we become infected by their
					emotions and by the weakness from whence they proceed. Against these
					influences, then, once more let us equip the young from the very outset to
					keep ever sounding in their ears the maxim, that the art of poetry is not
					greatly concerned with the truth, and that the truth about these matters,
					even for those who have made it their sole business to search out and
					understand the verities, is exceedingly hard to track down and hard to get
					hold of, as they themselves admit; and let these words of Empedocles be
					constantly in mind: <quote rend="blockquote">Thus no eye of man hath seen
						nor ear hath heard this, Nor can it be comprehended by the
						mind,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The passage is quoted more fully by Sextus Empiricus, <hi rend="italics">Adv. math.</hi> vii. 122-4; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Poetarum Philosophorum
							Fragmenta, Empedocles</hi>, No. 2</note>
               </quote> and the words
					of Xenophanes: <quote rend="blockquote">Never yet was born a man nor ever
						shall be Knowing the truth about the gods and what I say of all
						things,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Quoted with two additional lines by Sextus Empiricus,
							<hi rend="italics">Adv. math.</hi> vii. 49; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Philos. Frag.,
								Xenophanes</hi>, No. 34.</note>
               </quote> and by all means the
					words of Socrates, in Plato,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 69
						D.</note> when he solemnly disavows all acquaintance with these
					subjects. For young people then will give less heed to the poets, as having
					some knowledge of these matters, when they see that such questions stagger
					the philosophers. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>We shall steady the young man still more if, at his first entrance into
					poetry, we give a general description of the poetic art as an imitative art
					and faculty analogous to painting. And let him not <pb id="v1.p.93"/> merely
					be acquainted with the oft-repeated saying that <q direct="unspecified">poetry is articulate
						painting, and painting is inarticulate poetry,</q> but let us teach
					him in addition that when we see a lizard or an ape or the face of Thersites
					in a picture, we are pleased with it and admire it, not as a beautiful
					thing, but as a likeness. For by its essential nature the ugly cannot become
					beautiful ; but the imitation, be it concerned with what is base or with
					what is good, if only it attain to the likeness, is commended. If, on the
					other hand, it produces a beautiful picture of an ugly body, it fails to
					give what propriety and probability require. Some painters even depict
					unnatural acts, as Timomachus painted a picture of Medea slaying her
					children, and Theon of Orestes slaying his mother, and Parrhasius of the
					feigned madness of Odysseus, and Chaerephanes of the lewd commerce of women
					with men. In these matters it is especially necessary that the young man
					should be trained by being taught that what we commend is not the action
					which is the subject of the imitation, but the art, in case the subject in
					hand has been properly imitated. Since, then, poetry also often gives an
					imitative recital of base deeds, or of wicked experiences and characters,
					the young man must not accept as true what is admired and successful
					therein, nor approve it as beautiful, but should simply commend it as
					fitting and proper to the character in hand. For just as when we hear the
					squealing of a pig, the creaking of a windlass, the whistling of the winds,
					and the booming of the sea, we are uneasy and annoyed ; but if anybody gives
					a plausible imitation of these, as Parmeno imitated a pig, and Theodorus a
					windlass, we are pleased ; and just as we avoid a diseased and ulcerous
					person <pb id="v1.p.95"/> as an unpleasant sight, but take delight in seeing
					Aristophon's Philoctetes and Silanion's Jocasta, who are represented on the
					stage as pining away or dying ; so too the young man, as he reads what
					Thersites the buffoon, or Sisyphus the seducer of women, or Batrachus the
					bawd, is represented as saying or doing, must be taught to commend the
					faculty and art which imitates these things, but to repudiate and condemn
					the disposition and the actions which it imitates. For it is not the same
					thing at all to imitate something beautiful and something beautifully, since
					<q direct="unspecified">beautifully</q> means <q direct="unspecified">fittingly and properly
					</q> and ugly things are <q direct="unspecified">fitting and proper</q> for the
					ugly. Witness the boots made for the crippled feet of Damonidas, who prayed
					once, when he had lost them, that the man who had stolen them might have
					feet which they would fit; they were sorry boots, it is true, but they
					fitted their owner. Consider the following lines : <quote rend="blockquote">If one must needs do wrong, far best it were To do it for a kingdom's
						sake,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>,
							324.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Achieve the just
								man's good repute, but deeds That fit the knave ; therein shall be your
								gain,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From lines spoken by Ixion in an unknown play; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec.
									Frag., adesp.</hi> No. 4.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">A talent dowry ! Shall I not accept ? Can I still live
										if I should overlook A talent ? Shall I ever sleep again If I should
										give it up ? In Hell shall I Not suffer for impiety to gold ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From
											an unknown poet of the new comedy; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock,
											<hi rend="italics">Comicorum Atticorum Fragmenta</hi>, iii.
											430.</note>
               </quote> These, it is true, are wicked and fallacious
					sentiments, <pb id="v1.p.97"/> but fitting respectively for Eteocles, Ixion,
					and an old usurer. If then we remind our sons that authors write them, not
					because they commend or approve them, but with the idea of investing mean
					and unnatural characters and persons with unnatural and mean sentiments,
					they could not be harmed by the opinions of poets ; nay, on the contrary,
					the suspicion felt against the person in question discredits both his
					actions and words, as being mean because spoken or done by a mean man. Of
					such sort is the account of Paris in his wife's arms after his cowardly
					escape from battle.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iii. 369 ff. and
						441 ff.</note> For since the poet represents no other save this
					licentious and adulterous man as dallying with a woman in the daytime, it is
					clear that he classes such sensuality as a shame and reproach. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>In these passages, close attention must be given to see whether the poet
					himself gives any hints against the sentiments expressed to indicate that
					they are distasteful to himself; just as Menander in the prologue of his
					Thais has written : <quote rend="blockquote">Oh, sing to me, my muse, of
						such a girl, One bold and fair, and of persuasive tongue, Unjust,
						exclusive, and demanding much, In love with none, but always feigning
						love.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag., Menander</hi>,
							No. 217, and Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi>, in L.C.L.,
							p. 356.</note>
               </quote> But Homer has best employed this method ; for
					he in advance discredits the mean and calls our attention to the good in
					what is said. His favourable introductions are after this manner : <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Then at once he spoke ; his words were gentle and
						winning<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> vi.
							148.</note>
               </q> and <pb id="v1.p.99"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">He would stand by his side, and speak soft words to
						restrain him.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii.
							189.</note>
               </quote> But in discrediting in advance, he all but protests
					and proclaims that we are not to follow or heed the sentiments expressed, as
					being unjustifiable and mean. For example, when he is on the point of
					narrating Agamemnon's harsh treatment of the priest, he says in advance,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Yet Agamemnon, Atreus' son, at heart did not
						like it; Harshly he sent him away ;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi>
							i. 24.</note>
               </quote> that is to say, savagely and wilfully and
					contrary to what he should have done ; and in Achilles' mouth he puts the
					bold words, <quote rend="blockquote">Drunken sot, with eyes of a dog and the
						wild deer's courage,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> i.
							225.</note>
               </quote> but he intimates his own judgement in saying, <quote rend="blockquote">Then once more with vehement words did the son of
								Peleus Speak to the son of Atreus, nor ceased as yet from his anger;
								<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> i. 223.</note>
               </quote> hence
					it is likely that nothing spoken with anger and severity can be good. In
					like manner also, he comments upon actions : <quote rend="blockquote">Thus
						he spoke, and Hector divine he treated unseemly, Stretching him prone in
						the dust by the bier of the son of Menoetius.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi>, xxiii. 24.</note>
               </quote> He also employs his
					closing lines to good purpose, as though adding a sort of verdict of his own
					to what is done or said. Of the adultery of Ares, he represents the gods as
					saying, <quote rend="blockquote">Evil deeds do not succeed: the swift by the
						slow is taken,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>, viii.
							329.</note>
               </quote> and on the occasion of Hector's great arrogance
					and boasting he says, <pb id="v1.p.101"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Thus he spoke in boast; queen Hera's wrath was
						kindled<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> viii.
							198.</note>
               </quote> and regarding Pandarus's archery, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Thus Athena spoke, and the mind of the fool she
								persuaded.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv.
									104.</note>
               </q> Now these declarations and opinions contained in the
					words of the text may be discovered by anybody who will pay attention, but
					from the actions themselves the poets supply other lessons : as, for
					example, Euripides is reported to have said to those who railed at his Ixion
					as an impious and detestable character, <q direct="unspecified">But I did not remove him
						from the stage until I had him fastened to the wheel.</q> In Homer
					this form of instruction is given silently, but it leaves room for a
					reconsideration, which is helpful in the case of those stories which have
					been most discredited. By forcibly distorting these stories through what
					used to be termed <q direct="unspecified">deeper meanings,</q> but are nowadays called
					<q direct="unspecified">allegorical interpretations,</q> some persons say that the
					Sun is represented as giving information about Aphrodite in the arms of
					Ares, because the conjunction of the planet Mars with Venus portends births
					conceived in adultery, and when the sun returns in his course and discovers
					these, they cannot be kept secret. And Hera's beautifying of herself for
					Zeus's eyes,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xiv. 166 ff.</note> and the
					charms connected with the girdle, such persons will have it, are a sort of
					purification of the air as it draws near the fiery element;—as though the
					poet himself did not afford the right solutions. For, in the account of
					Aphrodite, he teaches those who will pay attention that vulgar music, coarse
					songs, and stories treating of vile themes, create licentious characters,
					unmanly lives, and men that love luxury, soft living, intimacy with women,
					and <pb id="v1.p.103"/>
					          <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Changes of clothes, warm baths, and the genial bed of
						enjoyment.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> viii.
							239.</note>
               </q> This too is the reason why he has represented
					Odysseus as bidding the harper <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Come now, change the
						theme and sing how the horse was builded,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> viii. 492.</note>
               </q> thus admirably indicating
					the duty of musicians and poets to take the subjects of their compositions
					from the lives of those who are discreet and sensible. And in his account of
					Hera, he has shown excellently well how the favour that women win by
					philters and enchantments and the attendant deceit in their relations with
					their husbands, not only is transitory and soon sated and unsure, but
					changes also to anger and enmity, so soon as the pleasurable excitement has
					faded away. Such, in fact, are Zeus's angry threats as he speaks to Hera in
					this wise : <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">So you may see if aught you gain from the
						love and caresses Won by your coming afar from the gods to deceive
						me.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xv. 32.</note>
               </q>
					For the description and portrayal of mean actions, if it also represent as
					it should the disgrace and injury resulting to the doers thereof, benefits
					instead of injuring the hearer. Philosophers, at any rate, for admonition
					and instruction, use examples taken from known facts; but the poets
					accomplish the same result by inventing actions of their own imagination,
					and by recounting mythical tales. Thus it was Melanthius who said, whether
					in jest or in earnest, that the Athenian State was perpetually preserved by
					the quarrelling and disorder among its public speakers ; for they were not
					all inclined to crowd to the same side of the boat, and so, in the
					disagreement <pb id="v1.p.105"/> of the politicians, there was ever some
					counterpoise to the harmful. And so the mutual contrarieties of the poets,
					restoring our belief to its proper balance, forbid any strong turning of the
					scale toward the harmful. When therefore a comparison of passages makes
					their contradictions evident, we must advocate the better side, as in the
					following examples : <quote rend="blockquote">Oft do the gods, my child,
						cause men to fail,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Archelaus</hi>, Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,
							Euripides</hi>, No. 254. The second line is again quoted by
							Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1049 F.</note>
               </quote> as
					compared with <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">You've named the simplest way; just
						blame the gods; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Archelaus</hi>,
							Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No.
							254. The second line is again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1049 F.</note>
               </q> and again <quote rend="blockquote">You may rejoice in wealth, but these may
								not,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,
									Euripides</hi>, No. 1069.</note>
               </quote> as compared with <quote rend="blockquote">'Tis loutish to be rich, and know naught
										else;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,
											Euripides</hi>, No. 1069.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">What need to sacrifice when you must die ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid., Adesp.</hi>, No. 350.</note>
               </quote> as
					compared with <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">'Tis better thus ; God's worship is not
						toil.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid., Adesp.</hi>, No.
							350.</note>
               </q> For such passages as these admit of solutions
					which are obvious, if, as has been said, we direct the young, by the use of
					criticism, toward the better side. But whenever anything said by such
					authors sounds preposterous, and no solution is found close at hand, we must
					nullify its effect by something said by them elsewhere to the opposite
					effect, and we should not be offended or angry at the poet, but with the
					words, which are spoken in character and with humorous intent. As an obvious
					illustration, if you wish, over against Homer's accounts of the gods <pb id="v1.p.107"/> being cast forth by one another, their being wounded by
					men, their disagreements, and their displays of ill-temper, you may set the
					line : <quote rend="blockquote">Surely you know how to think of a saying
						better than this one,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 358
							and xii. 232.</note>
               </quote> and indeed elsewhere you do think of
					better things and say more seemly things, such as these : <quote rend="blockquote">Gods at their ease ever living,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vi. 138; <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>
						iv. 805 and v. 122.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">There the blessed gods pass all their days in enjoyment,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer,
							<hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> vi. 46.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Thus the gods have spun the fate of unhappy mortals
								Ever to live in distress, but themselves are free from all
								trouble.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 525 (again
									quoted, <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, 22 B).</note>
               </quote> These,
					then, are sound opinions about gods, and true, but those other accounts have
					been fabricated to excite men's astonishment. Again, when Euripides says,
					<quote rend="blockquote">By many forms of artifice the gods Defeat our
						plans, for they are stronger far,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag.
							Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 972.</note>
               </quote> it is not
					bad to subjoin, <quote rend="blockquote">If gods do aught that's base, they
						are no gods,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Bellerophon</hi>,
							according to Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, c. 3,
							who quotes also six preceding lines; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>
							Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No.
							292. 7.</note>
               </quote> which is a better saying of his. And when
					Pindar very bitterly and exasperatingly has said, <quote rend="blockquote">Do what you will, so you vanquish your foe,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Isthmian Odes</hi>, iv. 48.</note>
               </quote>
					          <q direct="unspecified">Yet,</q> we may reply, <q direct="unspecified">you yourself say that <pb id="v1.p.109"/>
						            <quote rend="blockquote">Most bitter the end Must surely await Sweet
							joys that are gained By a means unfair.</quote>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Isthmian Odes</hi>, vii. 47.</note>
               </q> a=
					And when Sophocles has said, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Sweet is the pelf though
						gained by falsity.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,
							Sophocles</hi>, No. 749.</note>
               </q>
               <q direct="unspecified">Indeed,</q>
					we may say, <q direct="unspecified">but we have heard from you that <quote rend="blockquote">False words unfruitful prove when harvested.</quote>
                  <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi>, No. 750.</note>
               </q> And over
					against those statements about wealth : <quote rend="blockquote">Clever is
						wealth at finding ways to reach Both hallowed and unhallowed ground, and
						where A poor man, though he even gain access, Could not withal attain
						his heart's desire. An ugly body, hapless with its tongue, Wealth makes
						both wise and comely to behold,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Sophocles, <hi rend="italics">Aleadae</hi>; quoted with additional lines by Stobaeus, <hi rend="italics">Florilegium</hi>, xci. 27; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,
							Sophocles</hi>, No 85.</note>
               </quote> he will set many of
					Sophocles' words, among which are the following : <quote rend="blockquote">E'en without wealth a man may be esteemed,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi>, No.
						761.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">To beg doth not
							degrade a noble mind,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi>, No.
								752.</note>
               </quote> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">In the blessings of
									plenty What enjoyment is there, If blest wealth owe its increase To
									base-brooding care ?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps from the <hi rend="italics">Tereus</hi> of Sophocles; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck,
										<hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi>, No.
										534.</note>
               </q> And Menander certainly exalted the love of
					pleasure, <pb id="v1.p.111"/> with a suggestion of boastfulness too, in
					these glowing lines that refer to love : <quote rend="blockquote">All things
						that live and see the self-same sun That we behold, to pleasure are
						enslaved.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii.
							<hi rend="italics">Menander</hi>, No. 611, and Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi>, in L.C.L. p. 506.</note>
               </quote>
					But at another time he turns us about and draws us towards the good, and
					uproots the boldness of licentiousness, by saying: <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">A
						shameful life, though pleasant, is disgrace.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii., <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi>, No. 756.</note>
               </q> The latter sentiment is
					quite opposed to the former, and it is better and more useful. Such
					comparison and consideration of opposing sentiments will result in one of
					two ways : it will either guide the youth over toward the better side, or
					else cause his belief to revolt from the worse. </p>
            <p> In case the authors themselves do not offer solutions of their unjustifiable
					sayings, it is not a bad idea to put on the other side declarations of other
					writers of repute, and, as in a balance, make the scales incline toward the
					better side. For example, if Alexis stirs some people when he says, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">The man of sense must gather pleasure's fruits, And three
						there are which have the potency Truly to be of import for this life— To
						eat and drink and have one's way in love, All else must be declared
						accessory,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ii., <hi rend="italics">Alexis</hi>, No. 271.</note>
               </q> we must
					recall to their minds that Socrates used to say just the opposite—that
					<q direct="unspecified">base men live to eat <pb id="v1.p.113"/> and drink, and good men
						eat and drink to live.</q> And he who wrote <quote rend="blockquote">Not useless 'gainst the knave is knavery,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Source unknown; quoted
							again by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 534
							A.</note>
               </quote> thus bidding us, in a way, to make ourselves like
					knaves, may be confronted with the saying of Diogenes ; for, being asked how
					one might defend himself against his adversary, he said, <q direct="unspecified">By proving
						honourable and upright himself.</q> We should use Diogenes against
					Sophocles, too; for Sophocles has filled hosts of men with despondency by
					writing these lines about the mysteries : <quote rend="blockquote">Thrice
						blest are they Who having seen these mystic rites shall pass To Hades'
						house ; for them alone is life Beyond ; for others all is evil
						there.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.,
							Sophocles</hi>, No. 753.</note>
               </quote> But Diogenes, hearing
					some such sentiment as this, said, <q direct="unspecified">What! Do you mean to say that
						Pataecion, the robber, will have a better portion after death than
						Epaminondas, just because he is initiate ?</q> And when Timotheus,
					in a song in the theatre, spoke of Artemis as <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Ecstatic
						Bacchic frantic fanatic,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr.
							Gr.</hi> iii. p. 620; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 170 A.</note>
               </q> Cinesias at
					once shouted back, <q direct="unspecified">May you have a daughter like that I</q> Neat
					too is Bion s retort to Theognis, who said: <pb id="v1.p.115"/>
					          <quote rend="blockquote">Any man that is subject to poverty never is able
						Either to speak or to act; nay, but his tongue is tied.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Theognis,
							177.</note>
               </quote>
					          <q direct="unspecified">How is it, then,</q> said Bion, <q direct="unspecified">that you, who are poor,
						can talk much nonsense, and weary us with this rubbish ?</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>We must not neglect, either, the means for rectifying a statement which are
					afforded by the words that lie near, or by the context; but just as
					physicians, in spite of the fact that the blister-fly is deadly, think that
					its feet and wings are helpful to counteract its potent effect, so in poetry
					if a noun or adjective or a verb by its position next to another word blunts
					the point which the passage, in its worse interpretation, would have, we
					should seize upon it and add explanation, as some do in the case of the
					following: <quote rend="blockquote">Thus, at the last, can honour be paid by
						miserable mortals Cutting the hair from their heads while the tears
						stream down their faces,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iv.
							197.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Thus, then, the
								gods have spun the fate of unhappy mortals Ever to live in
								distress.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 525 (quoted
									<hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 20 F).</note>
               </quote> For he did
					not say that absolutely and to all mankind a grievous life has been allotted
					by the gods, but to the silly and foolish, whom, since they are wretched and
					pitiable on account of wickedness, he is wont to call by the name of <q direct="unspecified">
						unhappy</q> and <q direct="unspecified">miserable.</q>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Another method, again, which transfers from the worse to the better sense
					suspicious passages in poetry, is that which works through the normal usage
					of words, in which it were better to have the <pb id="v1.p.117"/> young man
					trained than in what are called <q direct="unspecified">glosses.</q>
					          <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Strange of obsolete words.</note> It is indeed learned, and not
					unpleasing, to know that <q direct="unspecified">rhigedanos</q>
					          <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xix. 325.</note> means <q direct="unspecified">
						dying miserably</q> (for the Macedonians call death <q direct="unspecified">danos
						</q>), that the Aeolians call a victory won by patience and perseverance
					an <q direct="unspecified">outlasting,</q>
					          <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xxii. 257 and xxiii. 661.</note> that
					the Dryopians call the divinities <q direct="unspecified">popoi.</q>
					          <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There was a tradition, preserved in the scholia, that <foreign lang="greek">w)= po/poi</foreign>, often found in Homer, was the
						equivalent of <foreign lang="greek">w)= qeoi/</foreign> 
                  <q direct="unspecified">gods.</q>
               </note>
					But it is necessary and useful, if we are to be helped and not harmed by
					poetry, to know how the poets employ the names of the gods, and again the
					names of bad and of good things, and what they mean when they speak of
					Fortune or of Fate, and whether these belong to the class of words which in
					their writings are used in one sense only or in several senses, as the case
					is with many other words. For, to illustrate, they apply the term <q direct="unspecified">
						house</q> sometimes to a dwelling house, as <quote rend="blockquote">Into the lofty house,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> v. 42, vii. 77, and perhaps x. 474.</note>
               </quote> and
					sometimes to property, as <quote rend="blockquote">My house is being
						devoured; <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv. 318.</note>
               </quote>
					and the term <q direct="unspecified">living</q> they apply sometimes to life, as <quote rend="blockquote">But dark-haired Poseidon Thwarted his spear, nor would
						let him end his foeman's living,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>
							xiii. 562.</note>
               </quote> and sometimes to possessions, as <quote rend="blockquote">And others are eating my living;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xiii. 419.</note>
							        </quote> and the expression <q direct="unspecified">be distraught</q> is used sometimes
					instead of <q direct="unspecified">be chagrined</q> and <q direct="unspecified">be at one's wits' end
					</q>: <pb id="v1.p.119"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Thus he spoke, and she departed distraught and
						sore troubled<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> v. 352.</note>
               </quote> and at other times, instead of <q direct="unspecified">to be arrogant
						</q> and <q direct="unspecified">be delighted,</q> as <quote rend="blockquote">Are you now distraught since
							you vanquished Irus, the vagrant ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xviii. 332, 392.</note>
               </quote> and by <q direct="unspecified">huddle</q> they
					mean either <q direct="unspecified">be in motion,</q> as Euripides says :<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Andromeda</hi> of Euripides, Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 145.</note> A monster
					huddling from th' Atlantic's surge, or <q direct="unspecified">sit down</q> and <q direct="unspecified">
						be seated,</q> as Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Oedipus Tyrannus</hi>, 2.</note> says : What means your huddling in
					these places here With suppliant garlands on the boughs ye bear ? It is a
					graceful accomplishment also to adapt the usage of the words to fit the
					matter in hand, as the grammarians teach us to do, taking a word for one
					signification at one time, and at another time for another, as for example,
					<q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Better commend a small ship, but put your goods on a big one.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 643.</note>
               </q> For by
					<q direct="unspecified">commend</q> is meant <q direct="unspecified">recommend,</q> and the
					very expression of <q direct="unspecified">recommend</q> to another is used nowadays
					instead of deprecating for one's self, as in everyday speech we say, <q direct="unspecified">
						It's very kind,</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Very welcome,</q> when we do not
					want a thing and do not accept it. In this way also some persons will have
					it that it must be <q direct="unspecified">commendable Persephone</q> because she is
					deprecated. </p>
            <p> Let us then observe closely this distinction and discrimination of words in
					greater and more serious matters, and let us begin with the gods, in
					teaching 
					<pb id="v1.p.121"/> the young that when the poets employ the names of the
					gods, sometimes they apprehend in their conception the gods themselves, and
					at other times they give the same appellation to certain faculties of which
					gods are the givers and authors. To take an obvious example, it is clear
					that Archilochus, when he says in his prayer, <quote rend="blockquote">Hear my praver, O Lord
						Hephaestus, and propitious Lend thy aid, and bestow what thy mercy bestows,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> ii. p. 703.</note>
               </quote>
					is calling on the god himself; but when, lamenting his sister's husband who
					was lost at sea and received no formal burial, he says that he could have
					borne the calamity with greater moderation, <quote rend="blockquote">If upon his head and his body so
						fair, All in garments clean, Hephaestus had done his office,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> p. 687.</note>
               </quote> it is fire
					that he called by this name and not the god. And again when Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 1006.</note> said
					in an oath, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">By Zeus amidst the stars and Ares murderous,</q> he named the gods
					themselves ; but when Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi>, No. 574; again cited by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 757 B.</note> says, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Blind and unseeing Ares, worthy
						dames, With snout like that of swine upturns all ills,</q> the name is to be
					understood as meaning war ; just as again it suggests weapons of bronze in
					the passage where Homer <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 329.</note> says, <quote rend="blockquote">Dark red blood of these men by the
						fair-flowing river Scamander Keen-edged Ares has shed.</quote> Since, then, many
					words are used in this way, it is 
					<pb id="v1.p.123"/> necessary to know and to remember that under the name
					Zeus also (or Zen) the poets address sometimes the god, sometimes Fortune,
					and oftentimes Fate. For when they say, <quote rend="blockquote">Father Zeus, enthroned on Ida, most
						glorious and mighty, Grant to Ajax victory,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iii. 276, vii. 202, xxiv. 308.</note>
               </quote> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">O Zeus ! who boasts to be
							more wise than thou ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 351.</note>
               </q> they mean the god himself; but when they apply the
					name of Zeus to the causes of all that happens, and say, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Many valiant souls
						it sent to the realm of Hades, Goodly men, and their bodies gave to the dogs
						as ravin And to birds a feast—the design of Zeus in fulfilment,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 3. </note>
               </q> they mean
					Fate. For the poet does not imagine that it is the god who contrives evils
					for mankind, but by the name he rightly implies the compelling force of
					circumstances, that States and armies and leaders, if they show
					self-control, are destined to succeed and to prevail over their enemies, but
					if they fall into passions and errors, if they disagree and quarrel among
					themselves, as these heroes did, then are they destined to act discreditably
					and to become disorganized and to come to a bad end, as Sophocles says <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 352.</note>:
					<quote rend="blockquote">For fated is it that from evil plans An evil recompense shall mortals reap ;</quote>
					and certainly Hesiod <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 86.</note> in representing Prometheus as exhorting Epimetheus
					
					<pb id="v1.p.125"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Never to welcome Any gifts from Zeus of Olympus, but
						always return them,</quote> employs the name of Zeus as a synonym for the power of
					Fortune. For he has given the name of <q direct="unspecified">gifts of Zeus</q> to the
					blessings of Fortune, such as wealth, marriage, office, and, in a word, all
					outward things, the possession of which is unprofitable to those who cannot
					make good use of them. Wherefore he thinks that Epimetheus, who is a
					worthless man and a fool, ought to be on his guard against any piece of good
					fortune, and be fearful of it, as he is likely to be injured and corrupted
					by it. And again when the poet says, <quote rend="blockquote">Never dare to reproach any man for
						accursed and woeful Poverty, gift of the blessed gods whose life is for
						ever,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 717.</note>
               </quote> he now speaks of what happens by chance as godgiven, with the
					suggestion that it is not meet to impugn those who are poor through
					misfortune, but to reproach the penury that is accompanied by laziness, soft
					living, and extravagance, since then it is disgraceful and reprehensible.
					For at a time when men did not as yet use the name <q direct="unspecified">Fortune,</q>
					but knew the force of causation as it traverses its irregular and
					indeterminate course, so strong, so impossible for human reason to guard
					against, they tried to express this by the names of the gods, exactly as we
					are wont to call deeds and characters, and in fact even words and men,
					<q direct="unspecified">divine</q> and <q direct="unspecified">godlike.</q> In this manner, then,
					a corrective is to be found for most of the seemingly unjustifiable
					statements regarding Zeus, among which are the following : <quote rend="blockquote">Fixed on Zeus'
						floor two massive urns stand ever, Filled with happy lives the one, the
						other with sorrows,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The quotation follows Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, 379 D, and not Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 528. The original, however, is quoted in the <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 105 C.</note>
               </quote> and <pb id="v1.p.127"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Cronos' son, enthroned on high,
							hath made naught of our pledges, But for both our hosts with evil thought is
							planning,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 69.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Then rolled forth the beginning of trouble Both on Trojans
								and Greeks through designs of Zeus the almighty.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> viii. 81.</note>
               </quote> These are to be
					interpreted as referring to Fortune or Fate, in which guise are denoted
					those phases of causation which baffle our logic, and are, in a word, beyond
					us. But wherever there is appropriateness, reason, and probability in the
					use of the name, let us believe that there the god himself is meant, as in
					the following : <quote rend="blockquote">But he ranged to and fro 'gainst the lines of the rest of
						the fighters; Only with Ajax, Telamon's son, he avoided a conflict, Seeing
						that Zeus was wroth if he fight with a man far better,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 540, 542. The third line is not found in the MSS. of Homer, but on the authority of this passage and 36 A and Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>, ii. 9, and the life of Homer ascribed to Plutarch, it has commonly been printed as line 542 in the editions of Homer.</note>
               </quote> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">For Zeus takes
							thought for mortals' greatest weal; The little things he leaves to other
							gods.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 353.</note>
               </q> 
            </p>
            <p> Particular attention must be paid to the other words also, when their
					signification is shifted about and changed by the poets according to various
					circumstances. An example is the word <q direct="unspecified">virtue.</q> For inasmuch
					as virtue not only renders men sensible, honest, and upright in actions and
					words, but also often enough secures for them repute and influence, 
					<pb id="v1.p.129"/> the poets, following this notion, make good repute and
					influence to be virtue, giving them this name in exactly the same way that
					the products of the olive and the chestnut are called <q direct="unspecified">olives
					</q> and <q direct="unspecified">chestnuts,</q> the same names as the trees that
					bear them. So then when poets say, <quote rend="blockquote">Sweat the gods have set before the
						attainment of virtue,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 289.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Then the Greeks by their virtue broke the line of
							their foemen,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 90.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">If to die be our fate, Thus to die is our right Merging
								our lives into virtue,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 994. Again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Pelopidas</hi>, 317 E.</note>
               </quote> let our young man at once feel that these sayings
					relate to the best and godliest estate to which we can attain, which we
					think of as correctness of reasoning, the height of good sense, and a
					disposition of soul in full agreement therewith. But when at another time,
					in his reading, he finds this line, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Zeus makes virtue in men both to
						increase and diminish,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xx. 242.</note>
               </q> or this, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Virtue and glory are attendant on riches,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 313.</note>
               </q>
					let him not <q direct="unspecified">sit</q> astounded and <q direct="unspecified">amazed</q> at
					the rich, as though they were able to purchase virtue without ado for money,
					nor let him believe either that the increase or diminution of his own wisdom
					rests with Fortune, but let him consider that the poet has employed <q direct="unspecified">
						virtue</q> instead of repute, or influence, or good fortune, or the
					like. For assuredly 
					<pb id="v1.p.131"/> by <q direct="unspecified">evil</q> the poets sometimes signify
					badness in its strict sense, and wickedness of soul, as when Hesiod <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 287.</note> says,
					Evil may always be had by all mankind in abundance, and sometimes some other
					affliction or misfortune, as when Homer <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xix. 360.</note> says, Since full soon do mortals
					who live in evil grow aged. And so too anybody would be sadly deceived,
					should he imagine that the poets give to <q direct="unspecified">happiness</q> the
					sense which the philosophers give to it, namely, that of complete possession
					or attainment of good, or the perfection of a life gliding smoothly along in
					accord with nature, and that the poets do not oftentimes by a perversion of
					the word call the rich man happy and blessed, and call influence or repute
					happiness. Now Homer <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv. 93.</note> has used the words correctly : <quote rend="blockquote">No delight <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Logically, we should expect here a word meaning <q direct="unspecified">happy.</q> See the critical note on the opposite page.</note> have I in
						ruling these possessions,</quote> and so has Menander :<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 184, and Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi> in L.C.L. p. 506.</note> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">A great estate have I, and
							rich am called By all, but I am called by no man blest.</quote> But Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Medea</hi>, 603.</note> works
					much disturbance and confusion when he says, <quote rend="blockquote">May I ne'er have a painful
						happy life,</quote> and 
					<pb id="v1.p.133"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Why do you honour show to tyranny, Happy iniquity ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Phoenissae</hi>, 549.</note>
               </quote>
					unless, as has been said, one follows the figurative and perverted use of
					the words. This, then, is enough on this subject. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>There is a fact, however, which we must recall to the minds of the young not
					once merely, but over and over again, by pointing out to them that while
					poetry, inasmuch as it has an imitative basis, employs embellishment and
					glitter in dealing with the actions and characters that form its groundwork,
					yet it does not forsake the semblance of truth, since imitation depends upon
					plausibility for its allurement. This is the reason why the imitation that
					does not show an utter disregard of the truth brings out, along with the
					actions, indications of both vice and virtue commingled ; as is the case
					with that of Homer, which emphatically says good-bye to the Stoics, who will
					have it that nothing base can attach to virtue, and nothing good to vice,
					but that the ignorant man is quite wrong in all things, while, on the other
					hand, the man of culture is right in everything. These are the doctrines
					that we hear in the schools ; but in the actions and in the life of most
					men, according to Euripides, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Aeolus</hi> of Euripides; quoted again <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 369 B and 474 A. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 21.</note> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">The good and bad cannot be kept apart But
						there is some commingling.</quote> But when poetic art is divorced from the truth,
					then chiefly it employs variety and diversity. For it is the sudden changes
					that give to its stories the elements of the emotional, the surprising, and
					the unexpected, and these are attended by very great astonishment and
					enjoyment; but sameness is unemotional <pb id="v1.p.135"/> and prosaic.
					Therefore poets do not represent the same people as always victorious or
					prosperous or successful in everything ; no, not even the gods, when they
					project themselves into human activities, are represented in the poets'
					usage as free from emotion or fault, that the perturbing and exciting
					element in the poetry shall nowhere become idle and dull, for want of danger
					and struggle. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>Now since this is so, let the young man, when we set him to reading poems,
					not be prepossessed with any such opinions about those good and great names,
					as, for instance, that the men were wise and honest, consummate kings, and
					standards of all virtue and uprightness. For he will be greatly injured if
					he approves everything, and is in a state of wonderment over it, but resents
					nothing, refusing even to listen or accept the opinion of him who, on the
					contrary, censures persons that do and say such things as these: <quote rend="blockquote">This I
						would, O Zeus, Athena, and Apollo, That not one escape death of all the
						Trojans living And of the Greeks; but that you and I elude destruction, So
						that we alone may raze Troy's sacred bulwarks,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 97.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Saddest of all the sad
							sounds that I heard was the cry of Cassandra Priam's daughter, whom
							Clytemnestra craftily planning Slew o'er my body,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xi. 421.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">That I seduce the
								girl and ensure her hate for my father. So I obeyed her and did it,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 452.</note>
               </quote> and
					
					<pb id="v1.p.137"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Father Zeus, none other of the gods is more baleful.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iii. 365.</note>
               </quote>
					Let the young man, then, not get into the habit of commending anything like
					this, nor let him be plausible and adroit in making excuses or in contriving
					some specious quibbles to explain base actions, but rather let him cherish
					the belief that poetry is an imitation of character and lives, and of men
					who are not perfect or spotless or unassailable in all respects, but
					pervaded by emotions, false opinions, and sundry forms of ignorance, who yet
					through inborn goodness frequently change their ways for the better. For if
					the young man is so trained, and his understanding so framed, that he feels
					elation and a sympathetic enthusiasm over noble words and deeds, and an
					aversion and repugnance for the mean, such training will render his perusal
					of poetry harmless. But the man who admires everything, and accommodates
					himself to everything, whose judgement, because of his preconceived opinion,
					is enthralled by the heroic names, will, like those who copy Plato's stoop
					or Aristotle's lisp, unwittingly become inclined to conform to much that is
					base. One ought not timorously, or as though under the spell of religious
					dread in a holy place, to shiver with awe at everything, and fall prostrate,
					but should rather acquire the habit of exclaiming with confidence <q direct="unspecified">
						wrong</q> and <q direct="unspecified">improper</q> no less than <q direct="unspecified">right
						</q> and <q direct="unspecified">proper.</q> For example, Achilles summons an
					assembly of the soldiers, who are suffering from an illness, since he is
					most impatient of all over the slow progress of the war because of his
					conspicuous position and reputation on the field; moreover, because he has
					some knowledge of medicine, and perceives now after the ninth day, on <pb id="v1.p.139"/> which these maladies naturally reach their crisis, that
					the disease is out of the ordinary and not the result of familiar causes, he
					does not harangue the multitude when he rises to speak, but makes himself an
					adviser to the king : <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Son of Atreus, now, as I think, are we destined to
						wander Back to seek our homes again.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 59.</note>
               </q> Rightly, moderately, and properly is
					this put. But after the seer has said that he fears the wrath of the most
					powerful of the Greeks, Achilles no longer speaks rightly and moderately,
					when he swears that nobody shall lay hands on the seer while he himself is
					alive, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">No, not though you name Agamemnon,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 90.</note>
               </q> thus making plain his slight
					regard and his contempt for the leader. A moment later his irritation
					becomes more acute, and his impulse is to draw his sword with intent to do
					murder ; not rightly, either for honour or for expediency. Again, later,
					repenting, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Back he thrust his massive blade once more to its scabbard, Nor
						ignored Athena's words,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 220.</note>
               </q> this time rightly and honourably, because, although
					he could not altogether eradicate his anger, yet before doing anything
					irreparable he put it aside and checked it by making it obedient to his
					reason. Then again, although Agamemnon is ridiculous in his actions and
					words at the Assembly, yet in the incidents touching Chryseis he is more
					dignified and kingly. For whereas Achilles, as Briseis was being led away,
					
					<pb id="v1.p.141"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Burst into tears and withdrawing apart sat aloof from
						his comrades,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 349.</note>
               </quote> Agamemnon, as he in person put aboard the ship, and gave up
					and sent away, the woman of whom, a moment before, he has said that he cared
					more for her than for his wedded wife, committed no amorous or disgraceful
					act. Then again, Phoenix, cursed by his father on account of the concubine,
					says : <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">True in my heart I had purposed to slay him with keenpointed dagger,
						Save that one of the deathless gods put an end to my anger, Bringing to mind
						the people's talk and men's many reproaches, Lest I be known among the
						Greeks as my father's slayer.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">These lines are not found in any MS. of Homer, but on the authority of this quotation they have been printed in practically all editions since that of Barnes (1711) as lines 458-61 of Book IX. of the <hi rend="italics">Iliad.</hi> Plutarch cites the second and part of the third line in the <hi rend="italics">Life of Coriolanus</hi>, chap. 32 (229 B), and the last line in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 72 B.</note>
               </q> Now Aristarchus removed these lines from the
					text through fear, but they are right in view of the occasion, since Phoenix
					is trying to teach Achilles what sort of a thing anger is, and how many wild
					deeds men are ready to do from temper, if they do not use reason or hearken
					to those who try to soothe them. So also the poet introduces Meleager angry
					at his fellow-citizens, and later mollified, and he rightly finds fault with
					his emotions, but, on the other hand, his refusal to yield, his resistance,
					his mastery over them, and his change of heart the poet commends as good and
					expedient. Now in these cases the difference is manifest; but in cases where
					Homer's judgement is not made clear, a distinction is to be drawn by
					directing the young man's attention in some such manner as the following :
					If, on the one hand, Nausicaa, after merely looking at a strange man,
					Odysseus, and experiencing Calypso's emotions toward him, being, as she was,
					
					<pb id="v1.p.143"/> a wanton child and at the age for marriage, utters such
					foolish words as these to her maid-servants, <quote rend="blockquote">How I wish that a man like this
						might be called my husband, Living here with us, and be contented to tarry,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> vi. 244.</note>
               </quote>
					then are her boldness and lack of restraint to be blamed. But if, on the
					other hand, she sees into the character of the man from his words, and
					marvels at his conversation, so full of good sense, and then prays that she
					may be the consort of such a person rather than of some sailor man or
					dancing man of her own townsmen, then it is quite right to admire her. And
					again, when Penelope enters into conversation with the suitors, not holding
					herself aloof, and they favour her with gifts of garments and other apparel,
					Odysseus is pleased <quote rend="blockquote">Since she had coaxed all these gifts from them, and had
						cozened their senses.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xviii. 282.</note>
               </quote> If, on the one hand, he rejoices at the receipt of
					the presents and the profit, then in his prostitution of his wife he outdoes
					Poliager, who is satirized in the comedy as <quote rend="blockquote">Poliager blest Who keeps a
						Cyprian goat to yield him wealth.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. 299. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Alciphro, <hi rend="italics">Epist.</hi> iii. 62. The reference is probably to the goat Amalthea, the fabled nurse of the infant Zeus, but Pantazides thinks that Uranium (<foreign lang="greek">*ou)ra/nion</foreign>) may have been the woman's name.</note>
               </quote> But if, on the other hand, he thinks that
					he shall have them more in his power, while they are confident because of
					their hopes and blind to the future, then his pleasure and confidence has a
					reasonable justification. Similarly, in the enumeration of his possessions
					which the Phaeacians had put ashore with him before they sailed away, if on
					the one hand, upon finding himself in such solitude and in such uncertainty
					and ambiguity regarding his surroundings, he really fears about his
					possessions, <pb id="v1.p.145"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Lest the men on the ship had sailed away
						with something,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xiii. 216.</note>
               </quote> then it is quite right to pity or indeed even to loathe his
					avarice. But if, on the other hand, he, as some say, being of two minds
					whether he were in Ithaca, thinks that the safety of his possessions is a
					demonstration of the rectitude of the Phaeacians (for otherwise they would
					not have carried him for nothing, put him ashore in a strange land, and left
					him there, at the same time keeping their hands off his possessions), then
					he makes use of no mean proof, and it is quite right to praise his
					forethought. But some critics find fault also with the very act of putting
					him ashore, if this really was done while he was asleep, and assert that the
					Etruscans still preserve a tradition that Odysseus was naturally sleepy, and
					that for this reason most people found him difficult to converse with. Yet
					if his sleep was not real, but if, being ashamed to send away the Phaeacians
					without gifts and entertainment, and at the same time unable to elude his
					enemies if the Phaeacians were in company with him, he provided himself with
					a cloak for his embarrassment in feigning himself asleep, then they find
					this acceptable. By indicating these things to the young, we shall not allow
					them to acquire any leaning toward such characters as are mean, but rather
					an emulation of the better, and a preference for them, if we unhesitatingly
					award censure to the one class and commendation to the other. It is
					particularly necessary to do this with tragedies in which plausible and
					artful words are framed to accompany disreputable and knavish actions. For
					the statement of Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi> No. 755.</note> is not altogether true when he says : <pb id="v1.p.147"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">From unfair deed fair word cannot proceed.</quote> For, as a
					fact, he is wont to provide for mean characters and unnatural actions
					alluring words and humane reasons. And you observe also that his
					companion-at-arms in the dramatic art has represented Phaedra <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably in the <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus Veiled; cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Eurip.</hi>, 491.</note> as preferring
					the charge against Theseus that it was because of his derelictions that she
					fell in love with Hippolytus. Of such sort, too, are the frank lines, aimed
					against Hecuba, which in the Trojan Women <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">The Trojan Women</hi>, 919.</note> he gives to Helen, who there
					expresses her feeling that Hecuba ought rather to be the one to suffer
					punishment because she brought into the world the man who was the cause of
					Helen's infidelity. Let the young man not form the habit of regarding any
					one of these things as witty and adroit, and let him not smile indulgently,
					either, at such displays of verbal ingenuity, but let him loathe the words
					of licentiousness even more than its deeds. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Now in all cases it is useful also to seek after the cause of each thing that
					is said. Cato, for example, used, even as a child, to do whatever the
					attendant in charge of him ordered, yet he also demanded to know the ground
					and reason for the order. And so the poets are not to be obeyed as though
					they were our keepers or law-givers, unless their subject matter be
					reasonable ; and this it will be if it be good, but if it be vile, it will
					be seen to be vacuous and vain. But most people are sharp in demanding the
					reasons for trivial things like the following, and insist on knowing in what
					sense they are intended : <quote rend="blockquote">Never ought the ladle atop of the bowl to be
						rested While the bout is on, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 744.</note>
               </quote> 
               <pb id="v1.p.149"/> and <quote rend="blockquote">Whoso from his car can
							reach the car of another Let him thrust with his spear.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iv. 306.</note>
               </quote> But in far
					weightier matters they take things on faith without testing them at all,
					such, for example, as these : <quote rend="blockquote">A man, though bold, is made a slave whene'er
						He learns his mother's or his sire's disgrace,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Hippolytus</hi>, 424; cited also by Plutarch in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1 C.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Who prospers not must be
							of humble mind.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 957.</note>
               </quote> And yet these sentiments affect our characters and disorder
					our lives, by engendering in us mean judgements and ignoble opinions, unless
					from habit we can say in answer to each of them, <q direct="unspecified">Why must the man
						who has ' not prospered be of humble mind,' and why must he not rather
						rise up against Fortune, and make himself exalted and not humbled ? And
						why, though I be the son of a bad and foolish father, yet if I myself am
						good and sensible, is it unbecoming for me to take pride in my good
						qualities, and why should I be dejected and humble on account of my
						father's crassness ?</q> For he who thus meets and resists, and
					refuses to entrust himself broadside on to every breath of doctrine, as to a
					wind, but believes in the correctness of the saying that <q direct="unspecified">a fool is
						wont to be agog at every word that's said</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A dictum of Heracleitus. It is again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 41 A; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diels, <hi rend="italics">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</hi>, i. p. 95.</note> will thrust aside a
					good deal of what is not true or profitable therein. This, then, will take
					away all danger of harm from the perusal of poetry. 
					<pb id="v1.p.151"/>
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But, just as amid the luxuriant foliage and branches of a vine the fruit is
					often hidden and unnoticed from being in the shadow, so also amid the poetic
					diction and the tales that hang clustered about, much that is helpful and
					profitable escapes a young man. This, however, ought not to happen to him,
					nor should he allow his attention to be diverted from the facts, but he
					should cling especially close to those that lead toward virtue and have the
					power to mould character. In which regard it may not be a bad thing to treat
					this topic briefly, touching summarily the principal points, but leaving any
					extended and constructive treatment, and long list of examples, to those who
					write more for display. In the first place, then, as the young man takes
					note of good and bad characters and personages, let him pay attention to the
					lines and the actions which the poet assigns to them as respectively
					befitting. For example, Achilles says to Agamemnon, although he speaks with
					anger : <quote rend="blockquote">Never a prize like yours is mine whene'er the Achaeans Capture and
						sack some goodly and populous town of the Trojans.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> i. 163.</note>
               </quote> But Thersites in
					reviling the same man says : <quote rend="blockquote">Full of bronze are your quarters, and many,
						too, are the women, Chosen from all the captives for you, and these we
						Achaeans Give to you first of all whenever we capture a city.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ii. 226.</note>
               </quote> And on
					another occasion Achilles says, <quote rend="blockquote">If perchance Zeus ever Grants to us that we
						plunder Troy, the well-walled city,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> i. 128.</note>
               </quote> but Thersites, <pb id="v1.p.153"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">One
							that I or another Achaean may bring in as captive.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 231.</note>
               </quote> At another time, in the
					Inspection, when Agamemnon upbraided Diomede, the latter made no answer,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Showing respect for the stern rebuke of a king so respected.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv. 402.</note>
               </quote> But Sthenelus,
					a man of no account, says : <quote rend="blockquote">Son of Atreus, speak not to deceive, knowing how
						to speak clearly; We can avow ourselves to be better far than our fathers.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 404.</note>
               </quote>
					A difference of this sort then, if not overlooked, will teach the young man
					to regard modesty and moderation as a mark of refinement, but to be on his
					guard against boasting and self-assertion as a mark of meanness. It is
					useful to note also the behaviour of Agamemnon in this case ; for Sthenelus
					he passed by without a word, but Odysseus he did not disregard, but made
					answer and addressed him, <quote rend="blockquote">When he saw he was wroth, and tried to retract his
						saying.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 357.</note>
               </quote> For to defend one's actions to everybody smacks of servility, not
					of dignity, while to despise everybody is arrogant and foolish. And most
					excellently does Diomede in the battle hold his peace, although upbraided by
					the king, but after the battle he uses plain speech to him : <quote rend="blockquote">First let me
						say that you 'mid the Danaans slighted my prowess<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ix. 34.</note>
               </quote> 
            </p>
            <p> It is well, too, not to miss a difference that exists between a man of sense
					and a seer who courts popularity. For example, Calchas <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> i. 94-5.</note> had no regard to the
					occasion, and made nothing of accusing the king before the multitude,
					alleging that he had 
					<pb id="v1.p.155"/> brought the pestilence upon them; but Nestor, though
					anxious to put in a word for the reconciliation with Achilles, yet, in order
					that he may not seem to discredit Agamemnon with the multitude as having
					made a mistake and indulged in anger, says, <quote rend="blockquote">Give a feast for the elders;
						'tis fitting and not unbefitting; Then, when many are gathered, whoever
						shall offer best counsel Him you will follow,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ix. 70, and 74-5.</note>
               </quote> and after the dinner he sends
					forth the envoys. For this was the way to amend an error; the other was
					arraignment and foul abuse. </p>
            <p> Moreover, the difference between the two peoples should be observed, their
					behaviour being as follows : the Trojans advance with shouting and
					confidence, but the Achaeans <quote rend="blockquote">Silently, fearing their captains.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> iv. 431.</note>
               </quote> For to fear
					one's commanders when at close quarters with the enemy is a sign of bravery
					and of obedience to authority as well. Wherefore Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Platp, <hi rend="italics">Apology</hi>, 28 F and E.</note> tries to establish
					the habit of fearing blame and disgrace more than toils and dangers, and
					Cato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Life of Cato</hi>, chap. 9 (341 C).</note> used to say that he liked people that blushed better than those that
					blanched. There is also in the promises of the heroes a special character.
					For Dolon promises : <quote rend="blockquote">Straight to the midst of their host shall I go till I
						come to the vessel Which Agamemnon commands.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> x. 325.</note>
               </quote> Diomede, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 222.</note> however, promises
					nothing, but says that he should be less frightened if he were sent in
					company with another man. Prudence, then, is 
					<pb id="v1.p.157"/> characteristic of a Greek and of a man of refinement,
					while presumption is barbaric and cheap : the one should be emulated and the
					other detested. And it is not unprofitable to consider how the Trojans and
					Hector were affected, at the time when Ajax was about to engage with him i
					single combat. Once when a boxer at the Isthmian games was struck in the
					face, and a clamour arose, Aeschylus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 79 D.</note> said, <q direct="unspecified">What a thing is
						training. The onlookers cry out; it is the man who is struck who says
						nothing.</q> In like manner, when the poet says <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 214.</note> that when Ajax
					appeared resplendent in his armour, the Greeks rejoiced at seeing him,
					whereas <quote rend="blockquote">Dreadful trembling seized on the limbs of every Trojan ; Even Hector
						himself felt his heart beat quick in his bosom,</quote> who could fail to admire the
					difference ? For the heart of the man who is facing the danger only throbs,
					as though indeed he were simply going to wrestle or run a race, while the
					onlookers tremble and shiver in their whole bodies through loyalty and fear
					for their king. Here, too, one should carefully consider the difference
					between the very valiant man and the craven. For Thersites <quote rend="blockquote">Hateful was most
						of all to Achilles as well as Odysseus,<hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> ii. 220.</quote> while Ajax was always friendly to
					Achilles, and says to Hector regarding him— <quote rend="blockquote">Now alone from one man alone
						shall you learn quite clearly What sort of men with us are the Danaans'
						chieftains Even after the smiter of men, lion-hearted Achilles.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vii. 226.</note>
               </quote> This is the
					compliment paid to Achilles, but these succeeding lines in behalf of all are
					put in such a way as to be useful: 
					<pb id="v1.p.159"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Yet are we of such sort as are ready to face you, Yea,
						and many of us,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vii. 231.</note>
               </quote> thereby declaring himself not the only man or the best, but
					only one among many equally capable of offering defence. This is enough on
					the subject of differences, unless perhaps we desire to add, that of the
					Trojans many were taken alive, but none of the Achaeans ; and that of the
					Trojans some fell down at the feet of the enemy, as did Adrastus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vi. 37.</note> the sons <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xi. 122.</note>
					of Antimachus, Lycaon,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xxi. 64.</note> and Hector <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xxii. 337.</note> himself begging Achilles for burial, but
					of the Achaeans none, because of their conviction that it is a trait of
					barbarian peoples to make supplication and to fall at the enemy's feet in
					combat, but of Greeks to conquer or to die fighting. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>Now just as in pasturage the bee seeks the flower, the goat the tender shoot,
					the swine the root, and other animals the seed and the fruit, so in the
					reading of poetry one person culls the flowers of the story, another rivets
					his attention upon the beauty of the diction and the arrangement of the
					words, as Aristophanes <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> i. p. 513.</note> says of Euripides, <quote rend="blockquote">I use the rounded neatness of his
						speech ;</quote> but as for those who are concerned with what is said as being
					useful for character (and it is to these that our present discourse is
					directed), let us remind them how strange it is if the lover of fables does
					not fail to observe the novel and unusual points in the story, and the
					student of language does not allow faultless and elegant forms of expression
					to escape him, whereas he that affects what is honourable and good, 
					<pb id="v1.p.161"/> who takes up poetry not for amusement but for education,
					should give but a slack and careless hearing to utterances that look toward
					manliness or sobriety or uprightness, such, for example, as the following :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Son of Tydeus, what has made us forget our swift prowess ? Hither, stand, my
						friend, by me. Disgrace will befall us If yon Hector, gleaming-helmed, shall
						capture our vessels.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xi. 313; the first line is quoted <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>, 71 F.</note>
               </quote> For to observe that the most wise and prudent man,
					when he is in danger of being destroyed and lost, together with the whole
					host, fears shame and disapprobation, but not death, will make the young man
					keenly alive to the moral virtues. And by the line, <quote rend="blockquote">Glad was Athena because
						of the man that was prudent and honest,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iii. 52.</note>
               </quote> the poet permits us to draw a
					similar conclusion in that he represents the goddess as taking delight, not
					in some rich man or in one who is physically handsome or strong, but in one
					who is wise and honest. And again when she says that she does not overlook
					Odysseus, much less desert him, <quote rend="blockquote">Since he is courteous and clever of mind and
						prudent,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xiii. 332.</note>
               </quote> her words indicate that the only one of our attributes that is
					dear to the gods and divine is a virtuous mind, if it be true that it is the
					nature of like to delight in like. </p>
            <p> Since it seems to be, and really is, a great thing to master one's anger,
					and since a greater thing is the exercise of precaution and forethought so
					as not to become involved in anger or to be made captive by 
					<pb id="v1.p.163"/> it, we must make a point of indicating to our young
					readers such matters as this : that Achilles, being not tolerant or mild in
					temper, bids Priam in these words to be quiet and not to exasperate him :
					<quote rend="blockquote">Anger me now no more, old man (to ransom your Hector I myself am disposed;
						from Zeus has come such a message), Lest, old man, even here 'neath my roof
						I leave you not scatheless Suppliant though you are, and sin against Zeus's
						commandments,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 560-1, 569-70.</note>
               </quote> and having washed and shrouded the body of Hector, he places
					it with his own hands on the wagon before its disfigurement was seen by the
					father, <quote rend="blockquote">Lest with heart so distressed he fail to master his anger, Seeing
						his son, and Achilles' heart be stirred with resentment, So that he slay him
						there, and sin against Zeus's commandments.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 584.</note>
               </quote> For it is mark of a wondrous
					foresight for a man whose hold on his temper is uncertain, who is naturally
					rough and quick-tempered, not to be blind to his own weakness, but to
					exercise caution, and to be on his guard against possible grounds for anger,
					and to forestall them by reason long beforehand, so that he may not even
					inadvertently become involved in such emotions. After the same manner should
					he that is fond of wine be on his guard against drunkenness, and he that is
					amorous against love. So did Agesilaus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Agesilaus</hi>, v. 4.</note> who would not submit to being
					kissed by the handsome boy who approached him, so did Cyrus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia</hi>, v. 1. 4.</note> who durst not
					even to look at Pantheia ; but the uneducated, on the contrary, gather fuel
					to kindle their passions, casting themselves headlong into those wherein
					they are weakest and least sure of themselves. Yet Odysseus not only
					restrains himself when enraged, <pb id="v1.p.165"/> but perceiving from some
					words of Telemachus that he too is angry and filled with hatred of the
					wicked, labours to mitigate his feelings and prepares him well beforehand to
					keep quiet and restrain himself, bidding him, <quote rend="blockquote">Even if they within my own
						house shall dishonour me sorely, Let your heart within you endure all the
						wrongs that I suffer: Though through the house they should drag me out by
						the feet to the open, Yea, or with missiles smite me, still you must patient
						behold it.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> xvi. 274.</note>
               </quote> For just as drivers do not curb their horses during the race,
					but before the race, so with those persons who are quick-tempered and hard
					to hold back when dangers threaten, we first gain control over them by
					reasoning, and make them ready beforehand, and then lead them into the
					strife. While it is also necessary not to pass over the words carelessly,
					yet one should eschew the puerility of Cleanthes ; for there are times when
					he uses a mock seriousness in pretending to interpret the words, <quote rend="blockquote">Father
						Zeus, enthroned on Ida,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iii. 320; vii. 202; xxiv. 208</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Zeus, lord of Dodona,</quote> bidding us in the latter
					case to read the last two words as one <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xvi. 233. It is of inerest that this reading is attested also in scholia on the passage.</note> (taking the word <q direct="unspecified">lord
					</q> as the preposition <q direct="unspecified">up</q>) as though the vapour
					exhaled from the earth were <q direct="unspecified">updonative</q> because of its being
					rendered up! And Chrysippus also is often quite petty, although he does not
					indulge in jesting, but wrests the words ingeniously, yet without carrying
					conviction, as when he would force the phrase <q direct="unspecified">wide-seeing</q>
					son of Cronos <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> i. 498.</note> to signify <q direct="unspecified">clever in conversation,</q> that is to
					say, with a widespread power of speech. <pb id="v1.p.167"/>
				        </p>
            <p> It is better, however, to turn these matters over to the grammarians, and to
					hold fast rather to those in which is to be found both usefulness and
					probability, such as <quote rend="blockquote">Nor does my heart so bid me, for I have learned to be
						valiant,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> vi. 444.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">For towards all he understood the way to be gentle.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xvii. 671.</note>
               </quote> For by
					declaring that bravery is a thing to be learned, and by expressing the
					belief that friendly and gracious intercourse with others proceeds from
					understanding, and is in keeping with reason, the poet urges us not to
					neglect our own selves, but to learn what is good, and to give heed to our
					teachers, intimating that both boorishness and cowardice are but ignorance
					and defects of learning. With this agrees very well what he says regarding
					Zeus and Poseidon : <quote rend="blockquote">Both, indeed, were of one descent and of the same
						birthplace, Yet was Zeus the earlier born and his knowledge was wider.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xiii. 354.</note>
               </quote> For
					he declares understanding to be a most divine and kingly thing, to which he
					ascribes the very great superiority of Zeus, inasmuch as he believes that
					all the other virtues follow upon this one. </p>
            <p> At the same time, the young man must get the habit of perusing with a mind
					wide awake such sayings as these : <quote rend="blockquote">Falsehood he will not utter because he is
						very prudent,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iii. 20 and 328.</note> and <pb id="v1.p.169"/> What an act Is this, Antilochus,
						prudent aforetime! You have put my skill to disgrace and hindered my
						horses,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiii. 570.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Glaucus, what cause has a man like you for words so disdainful
							? Truly I thought, my friend, that in sense you excelled all the others,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xvii. 170.</note>
               </quote>
					the implication being that men of sense do not lie or contend unfairly in
					games, or make unwarranted accusations against other people. And from the
					poet's saying <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vi. 104.</note> that Pandarus was persuaded because of his want of sense to
					bring to naught the sworn agreement, he clearly shows his opinion that the
					man of sense would not do wrong. It is also possible to give similar
					intimations in regard to self-control, by directing the young man's
					attention to statements like these : <quote rend="blockquote">Mad for him was Proetus' royal wife
						Anteia Lusting to make him her lover in secret, but could not persuade him,
						Since the wise Bellerophon thought more of virtue,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> vi. 160.</note>
               </quote> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">She at the first
							would not consent to a deed so unseemly, Royal Clytemnestra, since her
							thoughts were for virtue.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi> iii. 265.</note>
               </q> In these lines the poet attributes to
					understanding the cause of self-control; and in his exhortations to battle
					he says on the several occasions : <quote rend="blockquote">Shame, men of Lycia, whither now flee ye
						? Now be ye valiant,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xvi. 422.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">But let all your minds be imbued with Shame and
							resentment, for now, as you see, great strife has arisen,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xiii. 121.</note>
               </quote> 
               <pb id="v1.p.171"/> and thereby he appears to represent the men of self-control as brave
					because of their being ashamed of disgrace, and as able to overcome
					pleasures and to undergo dangerous adventures. Timotheus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> iii. 622; Timotheus, <hi rend="italics">Frag.</hi> 14 ed. Wilamowitz.</note> also adopted this
					point of view, when in his Persians he urged the Greeks, not infelicitously,
					to have <quote rend="blockquote">Respect for shame that helps the brave in war ;</quote> and Aeschylus <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Seven Against Thebes</hi>, 599; the lines are quoted also, in whole or in part, by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 8 B, 186 B, and the <hi rend="italics">Life of Aristeides</hi>, chap. iii. (320 B).</note> sets
					it down as a point of good sense not to be puffed up with fame, nor to be
					excited and elated by popular praise, when he writes of Amphiaraus, <quote rend="blockquote">His wish
						is not to seem, but be, the best, Reaping the deep-sown furrow of his mind
						In which all goodly counsels have their root.</quote> For to take pride in oneself
					and in one's state of mind when it is altogether good, marks the man of good
					sense; and since everything may be referred to understanding, it follows
					that every form of virtue is added unto him from reason and instruction.
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>Now the bee, in accordance with nature's laws, discovers amid the most
					pungent flowers and the roughest thorns the smoothest and most palatable
					honey ; so children, if they be rightly nurtured amid poetry, will in some
					way or other learn to draw some wholesome and profitable doctrine even from
					passages that are suspect of what is base and improper. For example,
					Agamemnon is suspected of having, for a bribe, released from service in the
					army the rich man who made him a present of the mare Aetha,
					<pb id="v1.p.173"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Gift so he fare not with him to Troy where the wind
						never ceaseth, But enjoy himself at home; for wealth in abundance Zeus had
						bestowed upon him.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiii. 297.</note>
               </quote> But, as Aristotle <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably in his <hi rend="italics">Homeric Questions.</hi>
               </note> observes, he did quite right in
					preferring a good mare to a man of that type. For a coward, and a weakling,
					made dissolute by wealth and soft living, is not, I swear, worth a dog or
					even an ass. Again, it appears most shameful in Thetis <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxiv. 130.</note> when she incites her
					son to pleasures and reminds him of love. But even there we must contrast
					Achilles' mastery of himself, that although he is in love with Briseis, who
					has come back to him, and although he knows that the end of his life is
					near, yet he does not make haste to enjoy love's pleasures, nor, like most
					men, mourn for his friend by inactivity and omission of his duties, but as
					he refrains from such pleasures because of his grief, so he bestirs himself
					in the business of his command. Again, Archilochus cannot be commended,
					because while grieving over his sister's husband, who was lost at sea, he is
					minded to fight against his grief by means of wine and amusement; he has,
					however, alleged a cause that has some appearance of reason, <quote rend="blockquote">By my tears I
						shall not cure it, nor worse make it By pursuing joys, yea, and
						festivities.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bergk, <hi rend="italics">Poet. Lyr. Gr.</hi> ii. p. 687.</note>
               </quote> For if he thought that he should not make matters <q direct="unspecified">worse
							by pursuing joys, yea, and festivities,</q> how shall our present
					condition be any the worse if we engage in the study of philosophy or take
					part in public life, if we go out to the market-place or down to the
					Academy, or if we pursue our farming ? Wherefore the corrected versions
					which Cleanthes 
					<pb id="v1.p.175"/> and Antisthenes employed are themselves not without
					value. Antisthenes, observing that the Athenians had raised an uproar in the
					theatre at the line, <quote rend="blockquote">What's shameful if its doer think not so ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Aeolus</hi> of Euripides, Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 17.</note>
               </quote> at once
					interpolated, <quote rend="blockquote">A shame's a shame, though one think so or no</quote> and Cleanthes,
					taking the lines about riches, <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Give to your friends, and when your body's
						ill, Save it by spending,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Electra</hi>, 428.</note>
               </q> rewrote them in this manner, <quote rend="blockquote">To harlots give, and
							when your body's ill Waste it by spending.</quote> And Zeno in amending the lines of
					Sophocles, <quote rend="blockquote">Whoever comes to traffic with a king To him is slave however free
						he come,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Sophocles</hi>, No. 789; quoted by Plutarch also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 204 D and the <hi rend="italics">Life of Pompey</hi> chap. lxxviii. (661 A).</note>
               </quote> rewrote it thus : <quote rend="blockquote">Is not a slave if only free he come,</quote> by the word
					<q direct="unspecified">free</q> as he now uses it designating the man who is
					fearless, high-minded, and unhumbled. What, then, is to hinder us also from
					encouraging the young to take the better course by means of similar
					rejoinders, dealing with the citations something like this : <quote rend="blockquote">Most enviable
						is the lot of him The shaft of whose desire hits what he would.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 354.</note>
               </quote> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Not
							so,</q> will be our retort, <q direct="unspecified">but  <pb id="v1.p.177"/> 
                  <quote rend="blockquote">The shaft of whose desire hits what is
								good.</quote>
               </q> For to gain and achieve one's wish, if what one wishes is
					not right, is pitiable and unenviable. Again, <quote rend="blockquote">Not for good and no ill came
						thy life from thy sire, Agamemnon, but joy Thou shalt find interwoven with
						grief.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Iphigenia at Aulis</hi>, 29; quoted also in <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 103 B.</note>
               </quote> 
               <q direct="unspecified">No, indeed,</q> we shall say, <q direct="unspecified">but you must find
							joy and not grief if your lot be but moderate, since <quote rend="blockquote">Not for good and no
								ill came thy life from thy sire, Agamemnon;</quote>
               </q> and : <quote rend="blockquote">Alas, from God
									this evil comes to men, When, knowing what is good, one does it not.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Chrysippus</hi> of Euripides; Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 841; again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 446 A.</note>
               </quote>
					          <q direct="unspecified">No, rather is it bestial,</q> we reply, <q direct="unspecified">and
						irrational and pitiable that a man who knows the better should be led
						astray by the worse as a result of a weak will and soft living.</q>
					And again : <quote rend="blockquote">'Tis character persuades, and not the speech.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. p. 135; again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 801 C.</note>
               </quote>
               <q direct="unspecified">No,
						rather it is both character and speech, or character by means of speech,
						just as a horseman uses a bridle, or a helmsman uses a rudder, since
						virtue has no instrument so humane or so akin to itself as
						speech.</q> And: 
					<pb id="v1.p.179"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">To women more than men is he inclined ? Where there is
						beauty, either suits him best.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No, 355; again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 766 F.</note>
               </quote> But it were better to say <q direct="unspecified">
                  <quote rend="blockquote">Where
							there is virtue, either suits him best,</quote> of a truth, and there is no
							difference in his inclination ; but the man who is influenced by
							pleasure or outward beauty to shift his course hither and thither is
							incompetent and inconstant.</q> Again : <quote rend="blockquote">God's doings make the wise
								to feel afraid.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 356.</note>
               </quote> 
               <q direct="unspecified">Not so by any means, but <quote rend="blockquote">God's doings make the wise
									to feel assured,</quote> but they do make the silly and foolish and ungrateful
									to feel afraid, because such persons suspect and fear the power which is
									the cause and beginning of every good thing, as though it did
									harm.</q> Such then is the system of amendment. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>Chrysippus has rightly indicated how the poet's statements can be given a
					wider application, saying that what is serviceable should be taken over and
					made to apply to like situations. For when Hesiod <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 348.</note> says, <quote rend="blockquote">Nor would even an
						ox disappear were there not a bad neighbour,</quote> he says the same thing also
					about a dog and about an ass and about all things which in a similar way can
					<q direct="unspecified">disappear.</q> And again when Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 958; again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 106 D. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> CIcero, <hi rend="italics">Ad Atticum</hi>, ix. 2a, 2.</note> says, <quote rend="blockquote">What man who
						recks not death can be a slave ?</quote> we must understand that he makes the same
					statement 
					<pb id="v1.p.181"/> also about trouble and disease. For, as physicians who
					have learnt the efficacy of a drug adapted to one malady take it over and
					use it for every similar malady, so also when a statement has a general and
					universal value, we ought not to suffer it to be fixed upon one matter
					alone, but we ought to apply it to all the like, and inure the young men to
					see its general value, and quickly to carry over what is appropriate, and by
					many examples to give themselves training and practice in keen appreciation
					; so that when Menander says, <quote rend="blockquote">Blest is the man who has both wealth and
						sense,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Bridal Manager</hi> of Menander, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> iii. <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi>, No. 114, and Allinson, <hi rend="italics">Menander</hi> in L.C.L. p. 342.</note>
               </quote> they may think of the statement as holding good also about repute
					and leadership and facility in speaking ; and so also that when they hear
					the rebuke which was administered by Odysseus to Achilles as he sat among
					the maidens in Scyrus, <quote rend="blockquote">Dost thou, to dim the glory of thy race, Card wool,
						son of the noblest man in Greece ? <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 9; again quoted by Plutarch with variant reading, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 72 E.</note>
               </quote> they may imagine it to be addressed
					also to the profligate and the avaricious and the heedless and the ill-bred,
					as, for example, <quote rend="blockquote">Dost drink, son of the noblest man in Greece,</quote> or gamble, or
					follow quail-fighting, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Greeks were very fond, not only of cock-fights, but also of quail-fights. Another form of the latter sport known as <foreign lang="greek">o)rtugokopi/a</foreign> is often referred to by Greek writers and is perhaps best described by Pollus ix. 102 and 107. The quails were put into an enclosed ring, and their courage was tested by tapping them on the head with the finger or by pulling the feathers on op of their heads. If a bird showed fight, its owner won. Plutarch in the present passage, without doubt, uses <foreign lang="greek">o)rtugokopi/a</foreign> to cover all forms of the sport.</note> or petty trading, or the exacting of usury, without
					a thought of what is magnanimous or worthy of your noble parentage ?
					
					<pb id="v1.p.183"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Speak not of Wealth. I can't admire a god Whose ready
						favour basest men secure.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Aeolus of Euripides</hi>. Nauck, <hi rend="italics">TGF., Euripides</hi>, No. 20; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusculan Disputations</hi>, v. 16.</note>
               </quote> Therefore speak not of repute, either, or of
					personal beauty, or the general's cloak, or the priestly crown, to all which
					we see the worst of men attaining. <quote rend="blockquote">For ugly is the brood of cowardice,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">TGF., Adesp.</hi> No. 357.</note>
               </quote> and
					the same we may also aver of licentiousness, superstition, envy, and all the
					other pestilent disorders. Most excellently has Homer said <quote rend="blockquote">Paris, poor
						wretch, excelling in looks,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> iii. 39.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Hector, excelling in looks <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> xvii. 142.</note>
               </quote> (for he
					declares the man deserving of censure and reproach who is endowed with no
					good quality better than personal comeliness), and this we must make to
					apply to similar cases, thereby curtailing the pride of those who plume
					themselves on things of no worth, and teaching the young to regard as a
					disgrace and reproach such phrases as <q direct="unspecified">excelling in wealth</q>
					and <q direct="unspecified">excelling in dinners</q> and <q direct="unspecified">excelling in children
					</q> or <q direct="unspecified">oxen,</q> and in fact even the use of the word
					<q direct="unspecified">excelling</q> in such a connexion. For we ought to aim at
					the pre-eminence which comes from noble qualities, and we should strive to
					be first in matters of first importance, and to be great in the greatest:
					but the repute which comes from small and petty things is disreputable and
					paltry. </p>
            <p> This illustration at once reminds us to consider carefully instances of
					censure and commendation, particularly in Homer's poems. For he gives us
					expressly to understand that bodily and adventitious 
					<pb id="v1.p.185"/> characteristics are unworthy of serious attention. For,
					to begin with, in their greetings and salutations, they do not call one
					another handsome or rich or strong, but they employ such fair words as
					these— <quote rend="blockquote">Heaven-sprung son of Laertes, Odysseus of many devices,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> ii. 173.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Hector,
						son of Priam, peer of Zeus in counsel,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> vii. 47.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Son of Peleus, Achilles, great
							glory to the Achaeans,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> xix. 216.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Noble son of Menoetius, in whom my soul finds
								pleasure.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> xi. 608.</note>
               </quote> In the second place they reproach without touching at all upon
					bodily characteristics, but they direct their censure to faults : <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Drunken
						sot, with eyes of a dog and the wild deer's courage,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> i. 225.</note>
               </q> and <quote rend="blockquote">Ajax, excelling at
							wrangling, ill advised,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> xxiii. 483.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Why, Idomeneus do you brag so soon ? Unfitting
								Is it for you to be braggart,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> xxiii. 474, 478.</note>
               </quote> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">Ajax, blundering boaster,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> xiii. 824.</note>
               </q> and finally
					Thersites is reproached <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                  <hi rend="italics">Ib.</hi> ii. 246.</note> by Odysseus, not as lame or bald or hunchbacked,
					but as indiscreet in his language, while on the other hand the mother of
					Hephaestus affectionately drew an epithet from his lameness when she
					addressed him thus : 
					<pb id="v1.p.187"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Up with you, club-foot, my child !<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> xxi. 331.</note>
               </quote> Thus Homer ridicules
					those who feel ashamed of lameness or blindness, in that he does not regard
					as blameworthy that which is not shameful, or as shameful that which is
					brought about, not through our own acts, but by fortune. Plainly, then, two
					great advantages accrue to those who accustom themselves carefully to peruse
					works of poetry : the first is conducive to moderation, that we do not
					odiously and foolishly reproach anybody with his fortune ; while the second
					is conducive to magnanimity, that when we ourselves have met with chances
					and changes we be not humiliated or even disturbed, but bear gently with
					scoffings and revilings and ridicule, having especially before us the words
					of Philemon : <quote rend="blockquote">There's naught more pleasing or in better taste Than having
						strength to bear when men revile.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the <hi rend="italics">Epidicazomenus</hi> of Philemon; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Kock, <hi rend="italics">Com. Att. Frag.</hi> ii. p. 484.</note>
               </quote> But if anybody is plainly in need of
					reprehension, we should reprehend his faults and his giving way to emotion,
					after the fashion in which Adrastus of the tragedy, when Alcmaeon said to
					him, <quote rend="blockquote">You are the kin of her who slew her spouse,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Adesp.</hi> No. 358; again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 88 F.</note>
               </quote> replied <quote rend="blockquote">And you have
						murdered her who gave you birth.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note>
               </quote> For just as those who scourge the clothes
					do not 
					<pb id="v1.p.189"/> touch the body,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch says (<hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 173 D) that Artaxerxes (Longhand) ordained that nobles who had offended should lay off their clothes, and their clothes should be scourged instead of their bodies. Considerable corroborative evidence is cited by Wyttenbach in his note on <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 565 A.</note> so those who scoff at misfortune or low
					birth, do but vainly and foolishly assail externals, never touching the soul
					or even such matters as really need correction and stinging reproof. </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Moreover, just as in what we have said above we felt that by setting against
					cheap and harmful poems the sayings and maxims of statesmen and men of
					repute, we were inducing a revolt and revulsion of faith from such poetry,
					so whenever we find any edifying sentiment neatly expressed in the poets we
					ought to foster and amplify it by means of proofs and testimonies from the
					philosophers, at the same time crediting these with the discovery. For this
					is right and useful, and our faith gains an added strength and dignity
					whenever the doctrines of Pythagoras and of Plato are in agreement with what
					is spoken on the stage or sung to the lyre or studied at school, and when
					the precepts of Chilon and of Bias lead to the same conclusions as our
					children's readings in poetry. Hence it is a duty to make a point of
					indicating that the lines <quote rend="blockquote">You, my child, have not the gift of arms in
						battle, Your concern must be for loving arms in wedlock,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi> v. 428.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Seeing
							that Zeus is wroth if you fight with a man far better,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Not found in the MSS. of Homer but often printed as <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xi. 543. See note on 24 C <hi rend="italics">supra.</hi>
                  </note>
               </quote> do not differ
					from <q direct="unspecified">Know thyself,</q> but have the same purport as this ;
					and the lines, 
					<pb id="v1.p.191"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Fools ! They know not how much more than all a half is,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 40.</note>
               </quote>
					and <quote rend="blockquote">Evil counsel is the worst for him who gives it<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid.</hi> 265.</note>
               </quote> are identical with the
					doctrines of Plato in the Gorgias <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Gorgias</hi>, 473 A ff.</note> and the Republic <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, end of Book I. and Book IV.; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also 335 B.</note> upon the principle that
					<q direct="unspecified">to do wrong is worse than to be wronged</q> and <q direct="unspecified">to
						do evil is more injurious than to suffer evil.</q> And on the words
					of Aeschylus, <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Aeschylus</hi>, No. 352.</note> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">Fear not; great stress of pain is not for long,</quote> we ought to
					remark that this is the oft repeated and much admired statement originating
					with Epicurus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One of the <q direct="unspecified">leading principles</q> of Epicurus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diogenes Laertius, x. 140.</note> namely <q direct="unspecified">that great pains shortly spend their force,
						and long continued pains have no magnitude.</q> Of these two ideas
					Aeschylus has perspicuously stated the one and the other is a corollary
					thereto ; for if great and intense pain is not lasting, then that which does
					not last is not great or hard to endure. Take these lines of Thespis <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nothing by Thespis has been preserved, although a few lines attributed to him were current. See Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> p. 833.</note>: <quote rend="blockquote">You
						see that Zeus is first of gods in this, Not using lies or boast or silly
						laugh ; With pleasure he alone is unconcerned.</quote> What difference is there
					between this and the statement, <q direct="unspecified">for the Divine Being sits throned
						afar from pleasure and pain,</q> as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, <hi rend="italics">Letters</hi>, iii. 315 C.</note> has put it ? Consider
					what is said by Bacchylides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Bacchylides, i. 21.</note>: 
					<pb id="v1.p.193"/> 
               <quote rend="blockquote">I shall assert that virtue hath the highest fame, But
						wealth with even wretched men is intimate,</quote> and again by Euripides <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 959.</note> to much
					the same effect: <quote rend="blockquote">There's naught that I hold In a higher esteem Than a
						virtuous life ; 'Twill ever be joined With those that are good.</quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">Why seek
							vain possessions ? Do ye think Virtue by wealth to compass ? Wretched amid
							your comforts shall ye sit.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch, as was often his practice (<hi rend="italics">e.g. Moralia</hi>, 25 C or 646 C), seems to have condensed this quotation. The original of the first portion appears to have been given by Satyrus in his Life of Euripides (<hi rend="italics">Oxyrhynchus Papyri</hi>, ix. 142), <q direct="unspecified">Why have you mortals acquired in vain many possessions, and think that by wealth you shall compass virtue? What boots it, should you have in your ancestral halls some fragment of Aetna's cliff or Parian stone, gold-wrought, which you have secured?</q> 
                     <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag., Euripides</hi>, No. 960.</note>
               </quote> Is not this a proof of what the philosophers
					say regarding wealth and external advantages, that without virtue they are
					useless and unprofitable for their owners ? </p>
            <p> This method of conjoining and reconciling such sentiments with the doctrines
					of philosophers brings the poet's work out of the realm of myth and
					impersonation, and, moreover, invests with seriousness its helpful sayings.
					Besides, it opens and stimulates in advance the mind of the youth by the
					sayings in philosophy. For he comes to it thus not altogether without a
					foretaste of it, nor without having heard of it, nor indiscriminately
					stuffed with what he has heard always from his mother and nurse, and, I
					
					<pb id="v1.p.195"/> dare say, from his father and his tutor as well, who all
					beatify and worship the rich, who shudder at death and pain, who regard
					virtue without money and repute as quite undesirable and a thing of naught.
					But when they hear the precepts of the philosophers, which go counter to
					such opinions, at first astonishment and confusion and amazement take hold
					of them, since they cannot accept or tolerate any such teaching, unless,
					just as if they were now to look upon the sun after having been in utter
					darkness, they have been made accustomed, in a reflected light, as it were,
					in which the dazzling rays of truth are softened by combining truth with
					fable, to face facts of this sort without being distressed, and not to try
					to get away from them.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The whole passage is a reminiscence of Plato, <hi rend="italics">Republic</hi>, vii. chap. 2 (515 E).</note> For if they have previously heard or read in poetry
					such thoughts as these : <quote rend="blockquote">To mourn the babe for th' ills to which he comes;
						But him that's dead, and from his labours rests, To bear from home with joy
						and cheering words,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Celebrated lines from the <hi rend="italics">Cresphontes</hi> of Euripides. Nauck, <hi rend="italics">TGF., Eurip.</hi> No. 449; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Tusc. Disp.</hi> i. 48. 115.</note>
               </quote> and <q rend="italics" direct="unspecified">What needs have mortals save two things alone,
							Demeter's grain and draught from water-jar ?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">ibid., Eurip.</hi> No. 892 (again quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Moralia</hi>, 1043 E, 1044 B and F).</note>
               </q> and <quote rend="blockquote">O Tyranny, beloved of
								barbarous folk,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid., Adesp.</hi> o 359.</note>
               </quote> and <quote rend="blockquote">And mortal men's felicity Is gained by such of them as
									feel least grief,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
                     <hi rend="italics">Ibid., Adesp.</hi> No. 360.</note>
               </quote> they are less confused and disquieted upon hearing at the
					lectures of the philosophers that <q direct="unspecified">Death is nothing to us,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">One of Epicurus's <q direct="unspecified">leading principles,</q> Diogenes Laertius, x. 139.</note>
					and <q direct="unspecified">The wealth allowed by Nature 
						<pb id="v1.p.197"/> is definitely limited,</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Another of Epicurus's <q direct="unspecified">leading principles,</q> Diogenes Laertius, x. 144.</note> and <q direct="unspecified">
							Happiness and blessedness do not consist in vast possessions or exalted
							occupations or offices or authority, but on impassivity, calmness, and a
							disposition of the soul that sets its limitations to accord with
							Nature.</q> 
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Also from Epicurus, without much doubt, but not to be found in just this form; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>, however, Diogenes Laertius, x. 139, 141, 144.</note> 
            </p>
            <p> Wherefore, both because of these considerations and because of those already
					adduced, the young man has need of good pilotage in the matter of reading,
					to the end that, forestalled with schooling rather than prejudice, in a
					spirit of friendship and goodwill and familiarity, he may be convoyed by
					poetry into the realm of philosophy. 
				</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>