<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De communibus notitiis adversus Stoicos</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.138">
      <body>
         <head>Of common conceptions, against the Stoics.</head>
         <pb id="v.4.p.372"/>
         <head>LAMPRIAS, DIADUMENUS.</head>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>LAMPRIAS. You, O Diadumenus, seem not much to
				care, if any one thinks that you philosophize against the
				common notions; since you confess that you contemn also
				the senses, from whence the most part of these notions in
				a manner proceed, having for their seat and foundation the
				belief of such things as appear to us. But I beseech you,
				with what speed you can, either by reasons, incantations,
				or some other manner of discourse, to cure me, who come
				to you full, as I seem to myself, of great and strange perturbations; so much have I been shaken, and into such a
				perplexity of mind have I been brought, by certain Stoics,
				in other things indeed very good men and my familiar
				friends, but most bitterly and hostilely bent against the
				Academy. These, for some few words modestly spoken by
				me, have (for I will tell you no lie) rudely and unkindly
				reprehended me; angrily reputing and branding the ancient
				philosophers as sophisters and corrupters of students of
				philosophy, and subverters of regular doctrines; and saying things yet more absurd than these, they fell at last
				upon the conceptions, into which (they maintained) the
				Academics had brought a certain confusion and disturbance. At length one of them said, that he thought it was
				not by fortune, but by the providence of the Gods, that
				Chrysippus came into the world after Arcesilaus and before
				Carneades; of which the one was the author of the contumelies
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.373"/>
				
				 and injuries done to custom, and the other flourished most of all the Academics. Chrysippus then, coming
				between them, by his writings against Arcesilaus, stopped
				also the way against the eloquence of Carneades, leaving
				indeed many things to the senses, as provisions against a
				siege, but wholly taking away the trouble about anticipations and conceptions, directing every one of them and
				putting it in its proper place; so that they who will again
				embroil and disquiet matters should accomplish nothing,
				but be convinced of being malicious and deceitful sophisters. I, having been this morning set on fire by these discourses, want some cooling remedies to extinguish and
				take away this doubting, as an inflammation, out of my
				mind.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>DIADUMENUS. You perhaps have suffered the same
				things with some of the vulgar. But if you believe the
				poets, who say that the ancient city Sipylus was overthrown
				by the providence of the Gods when they punished Tantalus, believe also the companions of the Stoa saying that
				Nature, not by chance but by divine providence, brought
				forth Chrysippus, when she had a mind to turn things upside down and alter the course of life; for which purpose
				never any man was fitter than he. But as Cato said of
				Caesar, that never any but he came to the management of
				public affairs sober and considerately resolved on the ruin
				of the state; so does this man seem to me with the greatest
				diligence and eloquence to overturn and demolish custom,
				as they who magnify the man testify, when they dispute
				against him concerning the sophism called Pseudomenos
				(or the Liar). For to say, my best friend, that a conclusion drawn from contrary positions is not manifestly false,
				and again to say that some arguments having true premises
				and true inductions may yet moreover have the contrary to
				their conclusions true, what conception of demonstration
				or what presumption of faith does it not overthrow? They
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.374"/>
				
				say, that the polypus in the winter gnaws his own claws;
				but the logic of Chrysippus, taking away and cutting off
				its own chiefest parts and principles,&mdash;what other notion
				has it left unsuspected of falsehood? For the superstructures cannot be steady and sure, if the foundations remain
				not firm but are shaken with so many doubts and troubles.
				But as those who have dust or dirt upon their bodies, if
				they touch or rub the filth that is upon them, seem rather
				to increase than remove it; so some men blame the Academics, and think them guilty of the faults with which they
				show themselves to be burdened. For who do more pervert the common conceptions than the Stoics? But if you
				please, let us leave accusing them, and defend ourselves
				from the things with which they charge us.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>LAMPRIAS. Methinks, Diadumenus, I am this day become a various and unconstant man. For erewhile I came
				dejected and trembling, as one that wanted an apology;
				and now I am changed to an accuser, and desire to enjoy
				the pleasure of revenge, in seeing them all convicted of
				philosophizing against the common conceptions and presumptions, from which they think chiefly their doctrine is
				derived, whence they say that it alone agrees with Nature.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. Shall we then first attack those common
					and celebrated doctrines of theirs which themselves, gently admitting their absurdity, style paradoxes; as that only
					wise men are kings, that they only are rich and fair, they
					only citizens and judges? Or shall we send all this to the
					brokers, as old decayed frippery, and make our enquiry
					into such things as are most practical and with the greatest earnestness delivered by them?</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. I indeed like this best. For who is there
					that is not already full of the arguments brought against
					those paradoxes?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>DIADUMENUS. First then consider this, whether, according to the common conceptions, they can be said to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.375"/>
				
				agree with Nature, who think all natural things indifferent,
				and esteem neither health, vigorousness of body, beauty,
				nor strength as desirable, commodious, profitable, or any
				way contributary to the completing of natural perfection;
				nor believe that their contraries, as maims, pains, disgraces,
				and diseases, are hurtful or to be shunned? To the latter
				of these they themselves say that Nature gives us an abhorrence, and an inclination to the former. Which very
				thing is not a little repugnant to common understanding,
				that Nature should incline us to such things as are neither
				good nor available, and avert us from such as are neither
				ill nor hurtful, and which is more, that she should render
				this inclination and this aversion so violent, that they who
				either possess not the one or fall into the other detest their
				life with good reason, and withdraw themselves out of it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>I think also that this is said by them against common
				sense, that Nature herself is indifferent, and yet that it is
				good to agree with Nature. For it is not our duty either to
				follow the law or be persuaded by argument, unless the
				law and argument be good and honest. And this indeed
				is the least of their errors. But if, as Chrysippus has
				written in his First Book concerning Exhortation, a happy
				life consists only in living according to virtue, other things
				(as he says) being nothing to us, nor co-operating any ways
				towards it, Nature is not only indifferent, but foolish also
				and stupid, in inclining us to such things as belong nothing
				to us; and we also are fools in thinking felicity to be an
				agreeing with Nature, which draws us after such things as
				contribute nothing to happiness. For what can be more
				agreeable to common sense, than that, as desirable things
				are requisite to live commodiously, so natural things are
				necessary that we may live according to Nature? Now
				these men say not so; but having settled the living according to Nature for their end, do nevertheless hold those
				things which are according to Nature to be indifferent.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.376"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>Nor is this less repugnant to common sense, that an
				intelligent and prudent man should not be equally affected
				to equal good things, but should put no value on some,
				and be ready to undergo and suffer any thing for others,
				though the things themselves are neither greater nor less
				one than another. For they say, It is the same thing to
				abstain from the enjoyment of an old woman that has one
				foot in the grave, and...since in both cases we do what
				duty requires. And yet for this, as a great and glorious
				thing, they should be ready to die; when as to boast of the
				other would be shameful and ridiculous. And even Chrysippus himself in his commentary concerning Jupiter, and
				in the Third Book of the Gods, says, that it were a poor,
				absurd, and impertinent thing to glory in such acts, as proceeding from virtue, as bearing valiantly the stinging of a
				wasp, or abstaining chastely from an old woman that lies
				a dying. Do not they then philosophize against the common conception, who profess nothing to be more commendable than those things which yet themselves are ashamed
				to praise? For how can that be desirable or to be approved, which is worthy neither of praise nor admiration,
				but the praisers and admirers of which they esteem absurd
				and ridiculous?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>And yet this will (I suppose) appear to you more
				against common sense, that a wise man should take no
				care whether he enjoys or not enjoys the greatest good
				things, but should carry himself after the same manner in
				these things, as in those that are indifferent and in their
				management and administration. For all of us, <q direct="unspecified">whoever
					we are that eat the fruit of the spacious earth,</q> judge that
				desirable, good, and profitable, which being present we
				use, and absent we want and desire. But that which no
				man thinks worth his concern, either for his profit or delight, is indifferent. For we by no other means distinguish a
				laborious man from a trifler, who is for the most part also
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.377"/>
				
				employed in action, but that the one busies himself in useless matters and indifferently, and the other in things commodious and profitable. But these men act quite contrary;
				for with them, a wise and prudent man, being conversant
				in many comprehensions and memories of comprehension,
				esteems few of them to belong to him; and not caring
				for the rest, he thinks he has neither more or less by remembering that he lately had the comprehension of Dion
				sneezing or Theon playing at ball. And yet every comprehension in a wise man, and every memory having assurance and firmness, is a great, yea, a very great good.
				When therefore his health fails, when some organ of his
				senses is disordered, or when his wealth is lost, is a wise
				man so careless as to think that none of these things concern him? Or does he, <q direct="unspecified">when sick, give fees to the physicians: for the gaining of riches sail to Leucon, governor
					in the Bosphorus, or travel to Idanthyrsus, king of the
					Scythians,</q> as Chrysippus says? And being deprived of
				some of his senses, does he not grow weary even of life?
				How then do they not acknowledge that they philosophize
				against the common notions, employing so much care and
				diligence on things indifferent, and recking not whether
				they have or have not great good things?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But this is also yet against the common conceptions,
				that he who is a man should not rejoice when coming from
				the greatest evils to the greatest goods. Now their wise
				men suffer this. Being changed from extreme viciousness
				to the highest virtue, and at the same time escaping a
				most miserable life and attaining to a most happy one, he
				shows no sign of joy, nor does this so great change lift
				him up or yet move him, being delivered from all infelicity and vice, and coming to a certain sure and firm perfection of virtue. This also is repugnant to common sense,
				to maintain that the being immutable in one's judgments
				and resolutions is the greatest of goods, and yet that he
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.378"/>
				
				who has attained to the height wants not this, nor cares
				for it when he has it, nay, many times will not so much as
				stretch forth a finger for this security and constancy, which
				nevertheless themselves esteem the sovereign and perfect
				good. Nor do the Stoics say only these things, but they
				add also this to them,&mdash;that the continuance of time increases not any good thing; but if a man shall be wise but
				a minute of an hour, he will not be any way inferior in
				happiness to him who has all his time practised virtue and
				led his life happily in it. Yet, whilst they thus boldly
				affirm these things, they on the contrary also say, that a
				short-lived virtue is nothing worth; <q direct="unspecified">For what advantage
					would the attainment of wisdom be to him who is immediately to be swallowed up by the waves or tumbled down
					headlong from a precipice? What would it have benefited Lichas, if being thrown by Hercules, as from a sling
					into the sea, he had been on a sudden changed from vice
					to virtue?</q> These therefore are the positions of men
				who not only philosophize against the common conceptions but also confound their own, if the having been but
				a little while endued with virtue is no way short of the
				highest felicity, and at the same time nothing worth.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>Nor is this the strangest thing you will find in their
				doctrine; but their being of opinion that virtue and happiness, when present, are frequently not perceived by him
				who enjoys them, nor does he discern that, having but a
				little before been most miserable and foolish, he is of a
				sudden become wise and happy. For it is not only childish to say that he who is possessed of wisdom is ignorant
				of this thing alone, that he is wise, and knows not that
				he is delivered from folly; but, to speak in general, they
				make goodness to have very little weight or strength, if it
				does not give so much as a feeling of it when it is present.
				For according even to them, it is not by nature imperceptible; nay, even Chrysippus in his books of the End
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.379"/>
				
				expressly says that good is sensible, and demonstrates it
				also, as he thinks. It remains then, that by its weakness
				and littleness it flies the sense, when being present it is unknown and concealed from the possessors. It were moreover absurd to imagine that the sight, perceiving those
				things which are but a little whitish or inclining to white,
				should not discern such as are white in perfection; or that
				the touch, feeling those things which are but warm or
				moderately hot, should be insensible of those that are hot
				in the highest degree. And yet more absurd it is, that a
				man who perceives what is commonly according to Nature
				&mdash;as are health and good constitution of body&mdash;should
				yet be ignorant of virtue when it is present, which themselves hold to be most of all and in the highest degree
				according to Nature. For how can it but be against sense,
				to conceive the difference between health and sickness, and
				yet so little to comprehend that between wisdom and folly
				as to think the one to be present when it is gone, and
				possessing the other to be ignorant that one has it? Now
				because there is from the highest progress a change made
				to felicity and virtue, one of these two things must of
				necessity follow; either that this progress is not vice and
				infelicity, or that virtue is not far distant from vice, nor
				happiness from misery, but that the difference between
				good and evil is very small and not to be perceived by
				sense; for otherwise they who have the one for the other
				could not be ignorant of it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>Since then they will not depart from any of these
				contrarieties, but confess and hold them all,&mdash;that those
				who are proceeding towards virtue are fools and vicious,
				that those who are become good and wise perceive not this
				change in themselves, and that there is a great difference
				between folly and wisdom,&mdash;they must surely seem to you
				wonderfully to preserve an agreement in their doctrines,
				and yet more so in their actions, when affirming all men
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.380"/>
				
				who are not wise to be equally wicked, unjust, faithless,
				and fools, they on the other side abhor and detest some of
				them,&mdash;nay, sometimes to such a degree that they refuse
				even to speak to them when they meet them,&mdash;while
				others of them they trust with their money, choose to
				offices, and take for husbands to their daughters. Now if
				they say these things in jest, let them smooth their brows;
				but if in earnest and as philosophers, it is against the common notions to reprove and blame all men alike in words,
				and yet to deal with some of them as moderate persons
				and with others as very wicked; and exceedingly to admire Chrysippus, to deride Alexinus, and yet to think
				neither of them more or less mad than the other. <q direct="unspecified">'Tis
					so,</q> say they; <q direct="unspecified">but as he who is not above a cubit under
						the superficies of the sea is no less drowned than he who is
						five hundred fathom deep, so they that are coming towards
						virtue are no less in vice than those that are farther
						off. And as blind men are still blind, though they shall
						perhaps a little after recover their sight; so these that
						have proceeded towards virtue, till such time as they have
						attained to it, continue foolish and wicked.</q> But that they
				who are in the way towards virtue resemble not the blind,
				but such as see less clearly, nor are like to those who are
				drowned, but&mdash;those which swim, and that near the harbor,&mdash;they themselves testify by their actions. For they would
				not use counsellors and generals and lawgivers as blind
				guides, nor would they imitate the works and actions and
				words and lives of some, if they saw them all equally
				drowned in folly and wickedness. But leaving this, wonder at the men in this behalf, that they are not taught by
				their own examples to give up the doctrine that these men
				are wise being ignorant of it themselves, and neither knowing nor being sensible that they are recovered from being
				drowned and see the light, and that being gotten above
				vice, they fetch breath again.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.381"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>This also is against common sense, that it should be
				convenient for a man who has all good things, and wants
				nothing requisite to felicity and happiness, to make away
				himself; and much more this, that for him who neither
				has nor ever shall have any good thing, but who is and
				ever shall be accompanied with all adversities, difficulties,
				and mishaps, it should not be fitting to quit this life unless
				some of the indifferent things befall him. These laws are
				enacted in the Stoa; and by these they incite many wise
				men to kill themselves, as if they would be thereby more
				happy; and they restrain many foolish men, as if it were
				fitting for them to live on in wretchedness. Although the
				wise man is fortunate, blessed, every way happy, secure,
				and free from danger; but the vicious and foolish man is
				<q direct="unspecified">full, as I may say, of evils, so that there is not room to
					put them in;</q> and yet they think that continuing in life
				is fit for the latter, and departing out of it for the former.
				And not without cause, says Chrysippus, for we are not to
				measure life by good things or evil, but by those that are
				according to Nature. In this manner do they maintain
				custom, and philosophize according to the common conceptions. What do you say?&mdash;that he who enters upon
				a deliberation of life and death has no right to consider
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">What good or ill in his own house there is;</quote>
            </p>
            <p>or to weigh, as in a balance, what things have the greatest
					sign of serving to felicity or infelicity; but must argue
					whether he should live or die from those things which are
					neither profitable nor prejudicial, and follow such principles and sentences as command the choosing of a life
					full of all things to be avoided, and the shunning of one
					which wants nothing of all those things that are desirable?
					For though it is an absurd thing, friend Lamprias, to shun
					a life in which there is no evil, it is yet more absurd, if
					any one should leave what is good because he is not possessed
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.382"/>
					
					 of what is indifferent, as these men do who leave
					present felicity and virtue for want of riches and health
					which they have not.
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Saturnian Jove from Glaucus took his wits,</quote>
            </p>
            <p>when he went about to change his suit of golden armor
					for a brazen one, and to give what was worth a hundred
					oxen for that which was worth but nine. And yet the
					brazen armor was no less useful for fight than the golden;
					whereas beauty and health of body, as the Stoics say, contribute not the least advantage as regards happiness. And
					yet they seek health in exchange for wisdom. For they
					say, it would well enough have become Heraclitus and
					Pherecydes to have parted with their virtue and wisdom,
					if the one of them could have thereby been freed from his
					lousy disease, and the other from his dropsy; and if Circe
					had used two sorts of magical drinks, one to make wise
					men fools, and the other to make fools wise, Ulysses would
					rather have drunk that of folly, than have changed his
					shape for the form of a beast, though having with it wisdom, and consequently also happiness. And, they say,
					wisdom itself dictates to them these things, exhorting them
					thus: Let me go, and value not my being lost, if I must
					be carried about in the shape of an ass. But this, some
					will say, is an ass-like wisdom which teacheth thus; if
					indeed to be wise and enjoy felicity is good, and to wear
					the shape of an ass is indifferent. They say, there is a
					nation of the Ethiopians where a dog reigns, is called king,
					and has all regal honors and services done to him; but
					men execute the offices of magistrates and governors of
					cities. Do not the Stoics act in the very same manner?
					They give the name and appearance of good to virtue,
					saying that it alone is desirable, profitable, and available;
					but in the mean time they act these things, they philosophize, they live and die, as at the command of things indifferent.
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.383"/>
					
					 And yet none of the Ethiopians kill that dog;
					but he sits in state, and is revered by all. But these men
					destroy and corrupt their virtue, that they may obtain
					health and riches.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>But the corollary which Chrysippus himself has
				given for a conclusion to his doctrines seems to free us
				from the trouble of saying any thing more about it. For
				there being, says he, in Nature some things good, some
				things bad, and some things between them both, which we
				call indifferent; there is no man but would rather have
				the good than the indifferent, and the indifferent than the
				bad. And of this we call the Gods to witness, begging of
				them by our prayers principally the possession of good
				things, and if that may not be, deliverance from evil; not
				desiring that which is neither good nor bad instead of
				good, but willing to have it instead of evil. But this man,
				changing Nature and inverting its order, removes the
				middle out of its own place into the last, and brings back
				the last into the middle,&mdash;not unlike to those tyrants who
				give the first place to the wicked,&mdash;and he gives us a law,
				first to seek the good, and secondly the evil, and lastly to
				judge that worst which is neither good nor evil; as if any
				one should place infernal things next to celestial, thrusting
				the earth and earthly things into Tartarus,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where very far from hence, deep under ground,
				</l>
                     <l>Lies a vast gulf.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VIII. 14.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore said in his Third Book of Nature,
					that it is more expedient for a fool to live than not, though
					he should never attain to wisdom, he adds these words:
					<q direct="unspecified">For such are the good things of men, that even evil
						things do in a manner precede other things that are in
						the middle place; not that these things themselves
						really precede, but reason, with which we should choose
						rather to live, though we were to be fools.</q> Therefore also,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.384"/>
					
					though we were to be unjust, wicked, hated of the Gods,
					and unhappy; for none of these things are absent from those
					that live foolishly. Is it then convenient rather to live miserably than not to live miserably, and better to be hurt than
					not hurt, to be unjust than not unjust, to break the laws
					than not to break them? That is, is it convenient to do
					things that are not convenient, and a duty to live even
					against duty? Yes indeed, for it is worse to want sense
					and reason than to be a fool. What then ails them, that
					they will not confess that to be evil which is worse than
					evil? Why do they say that folly alone is to be avoided, if
					it is not less but rather more convenient to shun that disposition which is not capable of folly?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>But who can complain of this, that shall remember
				what he has written in his Second Book of Nature, declaring that vice was not unprofitably made for the universe? But it is meet I should set down his doctrine in his
				own words, that you may understand in what place those
				rank vice, and what discourses they hold of it, who accuse
				Xenocrates and Speusippus for not reckoning health indifferent and riches useless. <q direct="unspecified">Vice,</q> saith he, <q direct="unspecified">has its
					limit in reference to other accidents. For it is also in
					some sort according to the reason of Nature, and (as I may
					so say) is not wholly useless in respect of the universe;
					for otherwise there would not be any good.</q> Is there then
				no good among the Gods, because there is no evil? And
				when Jupiter, having resolved all matter into himself, shall
				be alone, other differences being taken away, will there
				then be no good, because there will be no evil? But is
				there melody in a choir though none in it sings faultily,
				and health in the body though no member is sick: and
				yet cannot virtue have its existence without vice? But as
				the poison of a serpent or the gall of an hyena is to be
				mixed with some medicines, was it also of necessity that
				there must have been some conjunction of the wickedness
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.385"/>
				
				of Meletus with the justice of Socrates, and the dissolute
				demeanor of Cleon with the probity of Pericles? And
				could not Jupiter have found a means to bring into the
				world Hercules and Lycurgus, if he had not also made for
				us Sardanapalus and Phalaris? It is now time for them to
				say that the consumption was made for the sound constitution of men's bodies, and the gout for the swiftness of
				their feet; and that Achilles would not have had a good
				head of hair if Thersites had not been bald. For what
				difference is there between such triflers and ravers, and
				those who say that intemperance was not brought forth
				unprofitably for continence, nor injustice for justice, so
				that we must pray to the Gods, there may be always
				wickedness,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">Lies, fawning speeches, and deceitful manners,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, Works and Days, 78.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>if, when these are taken away, virtue will also vanish and
					be lost?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Or do you desire to understand the greatest sweetness of his eloquence and persuasion? <q direct="unspecified">For,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">as
				comedies have in them sometimes ridiculous epigrams,
				which, though bad in themselves, give nevertheless a certain grace to the whole poem; so, though you may blame
				vice in itself, yet is it not useless to other things.</q> First
				then to say that vice was made by the providence of God,
				as a wanton epigram by the will of the poet, transcends in
				absurdity all imagination. For this being granted, how
				will the Gods be rather givers of good than evil? How
				will wickedness be displeasing to them, and hated by
				them? And what shall we have to oppose against these
				ill-sounding sentences of the poets:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A cause to men God sends,
				</l>
                     <l>When to chastise some house his wrath intends;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Niobe of Aeschylus, Frag. 151</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.386"/>
            <p>and again,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">What God those seeds of strife 'twixt them did sow?<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. I. 8.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, a lewd epigram adorns the comedy and contributes to its end, which is to delight the spectators and
					make them laugh. But Jupiter, who is surnamed fatherly,
					supreme, just, and (as Pindar has it) the most perfect artist,
					framing the world, not as a great interlude, full of variety
					and great learning, but as a common city of Gods and
					men, living together in concord and happiness with justice
					and virtue,&mdash;what need had he, for the attaining to this
					excellent end, of thieves, murderers, parricides, and tyrants? For vice entered not as a morris-dance, pleasing
					and delightful to the Divinity; nor was injustice brought
					in amongst the affairs of men, to cause mirth and laughter
					by its raillery and facetiousness, since there is not to be
					seen in it so much as a dream of that celebrated agreement
					with Nature. Besides, that foolish epigram is a very small
					part of the poem, and takes up but a very little place in
					the comedy; neither do such things abound in it, nor do
					they corrupt any of those things which seem to have been
					well done, or spoil their grace. But all human affairs are
					replete with vice, and the whole life, from the very prologue
					and beginning to the end, being disordered, depraved, and
					disturbed, and having no part of it pure or irreprehensible
					(as these men say), is the most filthy and most unpleasant
					of all farces.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Wherefore I would willingly ask, in what vice is
				profitable to the universe. Not surely in respect of heavenly
				things, and such as are divine by nature. For it would
				be ridiculous to say, that if there had not arisen, or were
				not amongst men, malice and covetousness and lying, or
				that if we did not rob, plunder, slander, and murder one
				another, the sun would not run his appointed course, the
				world enjoy its seasons and periods of time, or the earth,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.387"/>
				
				which is seated in the midst of the universe, afford the
				principles of the wind and rain. It remains then, that the
				existence of vice must be profitable for us and our affairs;
				and that perhaps these men mean. Are we more healthy
				for being vicious, or do we more abound with necessaries?
				Or does vice contribute any thing to our beauty and
				strength? They say, no. But where on earth is virtue to
				be found? Is it then only a name, and a visionary opinion
				of night-walking sophisters, and not a reality lying conspicuous to all, like vice, so that we cannot partake of any
				thing as unprofitable,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text of this passage seems to be hopelessly corrupt. (G.)</note> ... but least, 0 ye Gods! of virtue,
				for which we were created? Is it not then absurd, that
				the utensils of the husbandman, mariner, and charioteer
				should be serviceable and aiding towards his intended end,
				whilst that which was by God made for virtue destroys and
				corrupts virtue? But perhaps it is time now to leave this
				point, and pass to another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>LAMPRIAS. Not for my sake, my dear friend, I beseech you; for I desire to understand, in what manner
				these men bring in evil things before the good, and vice
				before virtue.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENAS. It is indeed, sir, a thing worth knowing.
					They babble indeed much; but in conclusion they say that
					prudence, being the knowledge of good and evil, would
					be wholly taken away if there were no evil. For as, if
					there are truths, it is impossible but there must be some
					lies also near to them; so it stands with reason, that if
					there are good things, there must also be evil things.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. One of these things is not said amiss; and
					I think also that the other is not unapprehended by me.
					For I see a difference here: that which is not true must
					immediately be false; but that is not of necessity evil
					which is not good; because that between true and false
					there is no medium, but between good and evil there is the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.388"/>
					
					indifferent. Nor is it of necessity that the one must subsist with the other. For Nature may have good without
					having any need of evil, but only having that which is
					neither good nor evil. But if there is any thing to be said
					by you to the former reason, let us hear it.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>DIADUMENUS. Many things indeed are said; but at
				present we shall make use only of what is most necessary.
				In the first place, it is a folly to imagine that good and evil
				have their existence for the sake of prudence. For good
				and evil being already extant, prudence came afterwards;
				as the art of physic was invented, there being already
				things wholesome and unwholesome. For good and evil
				are not therefore extant that there may be prudence; but
				the faculty by which we judge good and evil that are
				already in being is named prudence. As sight is a sense
				distinguishing white from black; which colors were not
				therefore made that we might have sight, but we rather
				wanted sight to discern these things. Secondly, when the
				world shall be set on fire (as the Stoics will have it),
				there will then no evil be left, but all will then be prudent
				and wise. There is therefore prudence, though there is
				no evil; nor is it of necessity for evil to exist that prudence
				may have a being. But supposing that prudence must
				always be a knowledge of good and evil, what inconvenience would it be if, evil being taken away, prudence
				should no longer subsist; but instead of this we should
				have another virtue, not being the knowledge of good and
				evil, but of good only? So, if black should be wholly
				lost from among the colors, and any one should therefore
				contend that sight is also lost, for that there is no longer
				the sense of discerning black and white, what should hinder us from answering him: It is no prejudice to us, if we
				have not what you call sight, but in lieu of that have
				another sense and faculty, by which we apprehend colors
				that are white and not white. For I indeed think that
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.389"/>
				
				neither our taste would be lost, if bitter things were wanting, nor our feeling, if pain were taken away, nor prudence,
				if evil had no being; but that these senses would remain,
				to apprehend things sweet and grateful and those that are
				not so, and prudence to be the science of things good and
				not good. But let those who think otherwise take the
				name to themselves, leaving us the thing.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>Besides all this, what should hinder but there may
				be an understanding of evil, and an existence of good?
				As the Gods, I believe, enjoy health, but understand the
				fever and pleurisy. Since even we, who, as they say, have
				abundance of evils but no good, are not yet destitute of
				the knowledge what prudence, what goodness, and what
				happiness is. And this also would be wonderful, that if
				virtue were absent, there should be those who could teach
				us what it is and give us a comprehension of it, while if
				vice were not extant, it should be impossible to have any
				understanding of it. For see what these men persuade us
				who philosophize against the conceptions,&mdash;that by folly
				indeed we comprehend prudence, but prudence without
				folly cannot so much as comprehend folly itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>And if Nature had absolutely stood in need of the
				generation of evil, yet might one or two examples of vice
				have been sufficient; or if you will, it might have been
				requisite that ten, a thousand, or ten thousand vicious men
				should be brought forth, and not that the multitude of
				vices should be so great as <q direct="unspecified">to exceed in number the
					sands of the sea, the dust of the earth, and the feathers
					of all the various kinds of birds in the world,</q> and yet
				that there should not be so much all this while as a dream
				of virtue. Those who in Sparta had the charge of the
				public halls or eating places called Phiditia, were wont to
				bring forth two or three Helots drunken and full of wine,
				that the young men, seeing what drunkenness was, might
				learn to keep sobriety. But in human life there are many
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.390"/>
				
				such examples of vice. For there is not any one sober to
				virtue; but we all stagger up and down, acting shamefully
				and living miserably. Thus does reason inebriate us, and
				with so much trouble and madness does it fill us, that we
				fall in nothing short of those dogs of whom Aesop says,
				that seeing certain skins swimming on the water, they endeavored to drink the sea up, but burst before they could
				get at them. For reason also, by which we hope to gain
				reputation and attain to virtue, does, ere we can reach to
				it, corrupt and destroy us, being before filled with abundance of heady and bitter vice;&mdash;if indeed, as these men
				say, they who are got even to the uppermost step have no
				ease, cessation, or breathing from folly and infelicity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>But let us see what manner of thing he shows vice
				to be who says that it was not brought forth unprofitably,
				and of what use and what a possession he makes it to be
				to those who have it, writing in his book of right actions,
				that a wicked man wants nothing, has need of nothing,
				nothing is useful to him, nothing proper, nothing fit for
				him. How then is vice useful, with which neither health
				nor abundance of riches nor advancement in virtue is
				profitable? Who then does not want these things, of
				which some are <q direct="unspecified">preferable</q> and <q direct="unspecified">acceptable,</q> and
				therefore highly useful, and others are <q direct="unspecified">according to
					Nature,</q> as themselves term them? But (they say) no one
				has need of them, unless he become wise. Therefore the
				vicious man does not even stand in need of being made
				wise. Nor are men hungry and thirsty before they become
				wise. When thirsty, therefore, they have no need of
				water, nor when hungry, of bread.
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be like to courteous guests, and him
				</l>
                     <l>Who only fire and shelter asks:</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>does this man now not need entertainment? Nor had he
					need of a cloak, who said,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">Give Hipponax a cloak, for I'm stiff with cold.</quote>
            </p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.391"/>
            <p>But will you speak a paradox indeed, both extravagant
					and singular? Say then that a wise man has need of
					nothing, that he wants nothing, he is fortunate, he is free
					from want, he is self-sufficient, blessed, perfect. Now
					what madness is this, that he to whom nothing is wanting
					has need of the goods he has, but that the vicious indeed
					wants many things, and stands in need of nothing. For
					thus indeed says Chrysippus, that the vicious wants but
					stands not in need; removing the common notions, like
					chessmen, backwards and forwards. For all men think
					that having need precedes wanting, esteeming him who
					stands in need of things that are not at hand or easy to
					be got, to want them. For no man wants horns or wings,
					because no man has need of them. But we say that those
					want arms and money and clothes who are destitute of
					them, when they have occasion for them. But these men
					are so desirous of seeming always to say something against
					the common notions, that for the love of novelty they often
					depart from their own opinions, as they do here.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>But recall yourself to the consideration of what has
				been said a little above. This is one of their assertions
				against the common conception, that no vicious man receives any utility. And yet many being instructed profit;
				many being slaves are made free; many being besieged
				are delivered, being lame are led by the hand, and being
				sick are cured. <q direct="unspecified">But possessing all these things, they are
					never the better, neither do receive benefits, nor have they
					any benefactors, nor do they slight their benefactors.</q>
				Vicious men then are not ungrateful, no more than are
				wise men. Ingratitude therefore has no being; because
				the good receiving a benefit fail not to acknowledge it, and
				the bad are not capable of receiving any. Behold now.
				what they say to this,&mdash;that benefit is ranked among mean
				or middle things, and that to give and receive utility belongs only to the wise, but the bad also receive a benefit.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.392"/>
				
				Then they who partake of the benefit partake not also of
				its use; and whither a benefit extends, there is nothing
				useful or commodious. Now what else is there that makes
				a kind office a benefit, but that the bestower of it is, in
				some respect, useful to the needy receiver?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>LAMPRIAS. But let these things pass. What, I beseech you, is this so highly venerated utility, which preserving as some great and excellent thing for the wise,
				they permit not so much as the name of it to the vicious?</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. If (say they) one wise man does but any
					way prudently stretch out his finger, all the wise men all
					the world over receive utility by it. This is the work of
					their amity; in this do the virtues of the wise man terminate by their common utilities. Aristotle then and Xenocrates doted, saying that men receive utility from the
					Gods, from their parents, from their masters, being ignorant of that wonderful utility which wise men receive
					from one another, being moved according to virtue, though
					they neither are together nor yet know it. Yet all men
					esteem, that laying up, keeping, and bestowing are then
					useful and profitable, when some benefit or profit is recovered by it. The thriving man buys keys, and diligently
					keeps his stores,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">With's hand unlocking wealth's sweet treasury.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From the Bellerophontes of Euripides, Frag. 287, vs. 8.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But to store up and to keep with diligence and labor
					such things as are for no use is not seemly or honorable,
					but ridiculous. If Ulysses indeed had tied up with the
					knot which Circe taught him, not the gifts he had received
					from Alcinous,&mdash;tripods, caldrons, cloths, and gold,&mdash;but
					heaping up trash, stones, and such like trumpery, should
					have thought his employment about such things, and the
					possession and keeping of them, a happy and blessed
					work, would any one have imitated this foolish providence
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.393"/>
					
					and empty care? Yet this is the beauty, gravity, and happiness of the Stoical consent, being nothing else but a
					gathering together and keeping of useless and indifferent
					things. For such are things according to Nature, and still
					more exterior things; if indeed they compare the greatest
					riches to fringes and golden chamber-pots, and sometimes
					also, as it happens, to oil-cruets. Then, as those who seem
					proudly to have affronted and railed at some Gods or
					demi-gods presently changing their note, fall prostrate
					and sit humbly on the ground, praising and magnifying the
					Divinity; so these men, having met with punishment of this
					arrogancy and vanity, again exercise themselves in these
					indifferent things and such as pertain nothing to them, crying out with a loud voice that there is but one thing good,
					specious, and honorable, the storing up of these things
					and the communication of them, and that it is not meet
					for those to live who have them not, but to dispatch out
					of the way and famish themselves, bidding a long farewell
					to virtue.</p>
            <p>They esteem indeed Theognis to have been a man altogether of a base and abject spirit, for saying, as one over-fearful in regard to poverty, which is an indifferent thing:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>From poverty to fly, into the deep
					</l>
                     <l>Throw thyself, Cyrnus, or from rocks so steep.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Yet they themselves exhort the same thing in prose, and
					affirm that a man, to free himself from some great disease
					or exceedingly acute pain, if he have not at hand sword or
					hemlock, ought to leap into the sea or throw himself headlong from a precipice; neither of which is hurtful, or
					evil, or incommodious, or makes them who fall into it miserable.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>With what then, says he, shall I begin? And what
				shall I take for the principle of duty and matter of virtue,
				leaving Nature and that which is according to Nature?
				With what, O good sir, do Aristotle and Theophrastus begin?
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.394"/>
				
				 What beginnings do Xenocrates and Polemo take?
				Does not also Zeno follow these, who suppose Nature and
				that which is according to Nature to be the elements of
				happiness? But they indeed persisted in these things, as
				desirable, good, and profitable; and joining to them virtue, which employs them and uses every one of them
				according to its property, thought to complete and consummate a perfect life and one every way absolute, producing
				that concord which is truly suitable and consonant to Nature. For these men did not fall into confusion, like those
				who leap up from the ground and presently fall down
				again upon it, terming the same things acceptable and not
				desirable, proper and not good, unprofitable and yet useful, nothing to us and yet the principles of duties. But
				their life was such as their speech, and they exhibited actions suitable and consonant to their sayings. But they
				who are of the Stoic sect&mdash;not unlike to that woman in
				Archilochus, who deceitfully carried in one hand water, in
				the other fire&mdash;by some doctrines draw nature to them,
				and by others drive her from them. Or rather, by their
				deeds and actions they embrace those things which are
				according to Nature, as good and desirable, but in words
				and speeches they reject and contemn them, as indifferent
				and of no use to virtue for the acquiring felicity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>Now, forasmuch as all men esteem the sovereign
				good to be joyous, desirable, happy, of the greatest dignity, self-sufficient, and wanting nothing; compare their
				good, and see how it agrees with this common conception.
				Does the stretching out a finger prudently produce this
				joy? Is a prudent torture a thing desirable? Is he happy, who with reason breaks his neck? Is that of the
				greatest dignity, which reason often chooses to let go for
				that which is not good? Is that perfect and self-sufficient,
				by enjoying which, if they have not also indifferent things,
				they neither can nor will endure to live? There is also
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.395"/>
				
				another principle of the Stoics, by which custom is still
				more injured, taking and plucking from her genuine notions, which are as her legitimate children, and supposing
				other bastardly, wild, and illegitimate ones in their room,
				and necessitating her to nourish and cherish the one instead of the other; and that too in those doctrines which
				concern things good and bad, desirable and avoidable,
				proper and strange, the energy of which ought to be more
				clearly distinguished than that of hot and cold, black and
				white. For the imaginations of these things are brought
				in by the senses from without; but those have their original bred from the good things which we have within us.
				But these men entering with their logic upon the topic of
				felicity, as on the sophism called Pseudomenos, or that
				named Kyrieuon, have removed no ambiguities, but brought
				in very many.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>Indeed, of two good things, of which the one is the
				end and the other belongs to the end, none is ignorant that
				the end is the greater and perfecter good. Chrysippus
				also acknowledges this difference, as is manifest from his
				Third Book of Good Things. For he dissents from those
				who make science the end, and sets it down.... In his
				Treatise of Justice, however, he does not think that
				justice can be safe, if any one supposes pleasure to be
				the end; but grants it may, if pleasure is not said to be the
				end, but simply a good. Nor do I think that you need now
				to hear me repeat his words, since his Third Book of
				Justice is everywhere to be had. When therefore, O my
				friend, they elsewhere say that no one good is greater or
				less than another, and that what is not the end is equal to
				the end, they contradict not only the common conceptions,
				but even their own words. Again, if of two evils, the one
				when it is present renders us worse, and the other hurts us
				but renders us not worse, it is against common sense not to
				say that the evil which by its presence renders us worse is
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.396"/>
				
				greater than that which hurts us but renders us not worse.
				Now Chrysippus indeed confesses, that there are some fears
				and sorrows and errors which hurt us, but render us not
				worse. Read his First Book of Justice against Plato; for
				in respect of other things, it is worth the while to note the
				babbling of the man in that place, delivering indifferently
				all matters and doctrines, as well proper to his own sect as
				foreign.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>It is likewise against common sense when he says
				that there may be two ends or scopes proposed of life, and
				that all the things we do are not to be referred to one; and
				yet this is more against common sense, to say that there is
				an end, and yet that every action is to be referred to another. Nevertheless they must of necessity endure one of
				these. For if those things which are first according to
				Nature are not eligible for themselves, but the choice and
				taking of them agreeably to reason is so, and if every one
				therefore does all his actions for the acquiring the first
				things according to Nature, it follows that all things which
				are done must have their reference to this, that the principal things according to Nature may be obtained. But they
				think that they who aim and aspire to get these things do
				not have the things themselves for the end, but that to
				which they must refer, namely, the choice and not the
				things. For the end indeed is to choose and receive these
				things prudently. But the things themselves and the enjoying of them are not the end, but the material object,
				having its worth only from the choice. For it is my opinion
				that they both use and write this very expression, to show
				the difference.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. You have exactly related both what they say
					and in what manner they deliver it.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. But observe how it fares with them, as
					with those that endeavor to leap over their own shadow;
					for they do not leave behind, but always carry along with
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.397"/>
					
					them in their speech some absurdity most remote from
					common sense. For as, if any one should say that he who
					shoots does all he can, not that he may hit the mark, but
					that he may do all he can, such a one would rightly be
					esteemed to speak enigmatically and prodigiously; so these
					doting dreamers, who contend that the obtaining of natural things is not the end of aiming after natural things, but
					the taking and choosing them is, and that the desire and
					endeavor after health is not in every one terminated in the
					enjoyment of health, but on the contrary, the enjoyment of
					health is referred to the desire and endeavor after it, and
					that certain walkings and contentions of speech and suffering incisions and taking of medicines, so they are done by
					reason, are the end of health, and not health of them,&mdash;they, I say, trifle like to those who say, Let us sup, that we
					may sacrifice, that we may bathe. But this rather changes
					order and custom, and all things which these men say carry
					with them the total subversion and confusion of affairs.
					Thus, we do not desire to take a walk in fit time that we
					may digest our meat; but we digest our meat that we may
					take a walk in fit time. Has Nature also made health for
					the sake of hellebore, instead of producing hellebore for
					the sake of health? For what is wanting to bring them
					to the highest degree of speaking paradoxes, but the saying of such things? What difference is there between
					him who says that health was made for the sake of medicines and not medicines for the sake of health, and him
					who makes the choice of medicines and their composition
					and use more desirable than health itself?&mdash;or rather who
					esteems health not at all desirable, but placing the end in
					the negotiation about these things, prefers desire to enjoyment, and not enjoyment to desire? For to desire, forsooth
					(they say), is joined the proceeding wisely and discreetly.
					It is true indeed, we will say, if respect be had to the end,
					that is, the enjoyment and possession of the things it pursues;
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.398"/>
					
					 but otherwise, it is wholly void of reason, if it does
					all things for the obtaining of that the enjoyment of which
					is neither honorable nor happy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>Now, since we are fallen upon this discourse, any
				thing may rather be said to agree with common sense, than
				that those who have neither received nor have any conception of good do nevertheless desire and pursue it. For
				you see how Chrysippus drives Ariston into this difficulty,
				that he should understand an indifference in things inclining neither to good nor to bad, before either good or bad
				is itself understood; for so indifference will appear to have
				subsisted even before itself, if the understanding of it cannot be perceived unless good be first understood, while the
				good is nothing else than this very indifference. Understand now and consider this indifference which the Stoa
				denies and calls consent, whence and in what manner it
				gives us the knowledge of good. For if without good the
				indifference to that which is not good cannot be understood,
				much less does the knowledge of good things give any intelligence of itself to those who had not before some notion
				of the good. But as there can be no knowledge of the art
				of things wholesome and unwholesome in those who have
				not first some knowledge of the things themselves; so they
				cannot conceive any notion of the science of good and evil
				who have not some fore-knowledge of good and evil.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. What then is good?</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. Nothing but prudence.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. And what is prudence?</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. Nothing but the science of good.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. There is much then of Jupiter's Corinth
					(that is, much reasoning in a circle) admitted into their
					arguments. For I would have you let alone the saying
					about the turning of the pestle, lest you should seem to
					mock them; although an accident like to that has insinuated itself into their discourse. For it seems that, to the
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.399"/>
					
					understanding of good, one has need to understand prudence, and to seek for prudence in the understanding of
					good, being forced always to pursue the one by the other,
					and thus failing of both; since to the understanding of
					each we have need of that which cannot be known without
					the other be first understood.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. But there is yet another way, by which
					you may perceive not only the perversion but the eversion
					of their discourse, and the reduction of it entirely to nothing. They hold the essence of good to be the reasonable
					election of things according to Nature. Now the election
					is not reasonable which is not directed to some end, as has
					been said before. What then is this end? Nothing else,
					say they, but to reason rightly in the election of things according to Nature. First then, the conception of good is
					lost and gone. For to reason rightly in election is an
					operation proceeding from an habit of right reasoning;
					and therefore being constrained to learn this from the end,
					and the end not without this, we fail of understanding
					either of them. Besides, which is more, this reasonable
					election ought in strict justice to be a choice of things
					good and useful, and co-operating to the end; for how can
					it be reasonable to choose things which are neither convenient nor honorable nor at all eligible? For be it, as they
					say, a reasonable election of things having a fitness for the
					causing felicity; see then to what a beautiful and grave
					conclusion their discourse brings them. For the end is (it
					seems), according to them, to reason rightly in the choice
					of things which are of worth in causing us to reason
					rightly.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. When I hear these words, my friend, what
					is said seems to me strangely extravagant; and I farther
					want to know how this happens.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. You must then be more attentive; for it
					is not for every one to understand this riddle. Hear therefore
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.400"/>
					
					 and answer. Is not the end, according to them, to
					reason rightly in the election of things according to Nature.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. So they say.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. And are these things according to Nature chosen as good, or as having some fitness or preferences...either for this end or for something else?</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. I think not for any thing else but for this
					end.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. Now then, having discovered the matter,
					see what befalls them. They hold that the end is to
					reason rightly in the choice of things which are of worth
					in causing us to reason rightly, for they say that we neither
					have nor understand any other essence either of good or
					of felicity but this precious rectitude of reasoning in the
					election of things that are of worth. But there are some
					who think that this is spoken against Antipater, and not
					against the whole sect; for that he, being pressed by Carneades, fell into these fooleries.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>But as for those things that are against the common
				conceptions taught in the Stoa concerning love, they are
				all of them concerned in the absurdity. They say, that
				those youths are deformed who are vicious and foolish,
				and that the wise are fair; and yet that none of these
				beautiful ones is either beloved or worthy of being beloved.
				Nor yet is this the worst; but they add, that those who
				love the deformed ones cease to do so when they are become fair. Now whoever knew such a love as is kindled
				and has its being at the sight of the body's deformity
				joined with that of the soul, and is quenched and decays
				at the accession of beauty joined with prudence, justice,
				and temperance? These men are not unlike to those
				gnats which love to settle on the dregs of wine, or on
				vinegar, but shun and fly away from potable and pleasant
				wine. As for that which they call and term an appearance
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.401"/>
				
				 of beauty, saying that it is the inducement of love,
				&mdash;first, it has no probability, for in those who are very
				foul and highly wicked there cannot be an appearance of
				beauty, if indeed (as is said) the wickedness of the disposition fills the face with deformity. And secondly, it is
				absolutely against all common conceptions that the deformed should be worthy of love because he one day will
				be fair and expects to have beauty, but that when he has
				obtained it and is become fair and good, he should be
				beloved of none.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. Love, they say, is a certain hunting after a
					young person who is as yet indeed imperfect, but naturally
					well-disposed towards virtue.</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. And what do we now else, O my best
					friend, but demonstrate that their sect perverts and destroys
					all our common conceptions with improbable things and
					unusual expressions? For none would hinder the solicitude of these wise men towards young persons, if it were
					free from all passionate affection, from being called hunting or love of instruction; but they ought to call love that
					which all men and women understand and call by this
					name, like that which Penelope's suitors in Homer seem
					to acknowledge,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Who all desired to lie with her;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. I. 366.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>or as Jupiter in another place says to Juno,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For neither Goddess yet nor mortal dame
					</l>
                     <l>E'er kindled in my heart so great a flame.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XIV. 315.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>Thus casting moral philosophy into these matters,
				in which all is
				<quote rend="blockquote">A mazy whirl, with nothing sound, and all perplexed,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Andromache, 448.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they contemn and deride all about them, as if themselves
					were the only men who regulated nature and custom as it
					ought to be, and who at the same time adapted reason to
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.402"/>
					
					each man's peculiar state by means of aversions, desires,
					appetites, pursuits, and impulses. But custom has received
					no good from their logic, but, like the ear diseased by
					vain sounds, is filled with difficulty and obscurity,&mdash;of
					which, if you think good, we will elsewhere begin a
					new discourse. But now we will run through the chief
					and principal heads of their natural philosophy, which no
					less confounds the common conceptions than that other
					concerning ends.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>First, this is altogether absurd and against sense, to
				say that is which is not, and things which are not are.
				But above all, that is most absurd which they say of the
				universe. For, putting round about the circumference of
				the world an infinite vacuum, they say that the universe
				is neither a body nor bodiless. It follows then from this
				that the universe has no being, since with them body only
				has a being. Since therefore it is the part of that which
				has a being both to do and suffer, and the universe has no
				being, it follows that the universe will neither do nor
				suffer. Neither will it be in a place; for that which takes
				up place is a body, and the universe is not a body, therefore the universe is nowhere. And since that only rests
				which continues in one and the same place, the universe
				rests not, because it takes not up place. Neither yet is it
				moved, for what is moved must have a place and space to
				move in. Moreover, what is moved either moves itself, or
				suffers motion from another. Now, that which is moved
				by itself has some bents and inclinations proceeding from
				its gravity or levity; and gravity and levity are either
				certain habits or faculties or differences of bodies. But the
				universe is not a body. It follows then of necessity, that the
				universe is neither heavy nor light, and consequently, that
				it has not in itself any principle of motion. Nor yet will
				the universe be moved by any other; for there is nothing
				else besides the universe. Thus are they necessitated to
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.403"/>
				
				say as they do, that the universe neither rests nor is moved.
				Lastly, since according to their opinion it must not be said
				that the universe is a body, and yet the heaven, the earth,
				animals, plants, men, and stones are bodies, it follows that
				that which is no body will have bodies for its parts, and
				things which have existence will be parts of that which
				has no existence, and that which is not heavy will have
				parts that are heavy, and what is not light will have parts
				that are light;&mdash;than which there cannot be any dreams
				imagined more repugnant to the common conceptions.</p>
            <p>Moreover, there is nothing so evident or so agreeing to
					common sense as this, that what is not animate is inanimate, and what is not inanimate is animate. And yet they
					overthrow also this evidence, confessing the universe to be
					neither animate nor inanimate. Besides this, none thinks
					the universe, of which there is no part wanting, to be imperfect; but they deny the universe to be perfect, saying
					that what is perfect may be defined, but the universe because of its infiniteness cannot be defined. Therefore,
					according to them, there is something which is neither
					perfect nor imperfect. Moreover, the universe is neither a
					part, since there is nothing greater than it; nor the whole,
					for the whole (they say) is predicated only of that which
					is digested into order; but the universe is, through its
					infiniteness, undetermined and unordered. Moreover, there
					is no other thing which can be the cause of the universe,
					there being nothing besides the universe; nor is the universe the cause of other things or even of itself; for its
					nature suffers it not to act, and a cause is understood by
					its acting.' Suppose now, one should ask all men what
					they imagine <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> to be, and what notion they have of
					it. Would they not answer, that it neither is a cause nor
					has a cause, that it is neither the whole nor a part, that it
					is neither perfect nor imperfect, that it is neither animate
					nor inanimate, that it neither is moved nor rests nor subsists,
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.404"/>
					
					 that it is neither corporeal nor incorporeal; and that
					this and no other thing is meant by <hi rend="italics">nothing?</hi> Since then
					they alone predicate that of the universe which all others
					do of <hi rend="italics">nothing,</hi> it seems plain that they make the <hi rend="italics">universe</hi>
					and <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi> to be the same. Time must then be said to
					be nothing; the same also must be said of predicate,
					axiom, connection, combination, which terms they use
					more than any of the other philosophers, yet they say
					that they have no being. But farther, to say that what is
					true has no being or subsistence but is comprehended, and
					that that is comprehensible and credible which no way
					partakes of the essence of being,&mdash;does not this exceed
					all absurdity?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>But lest these things should seem to have too much
				of logical difficulty, let us proceed to such as pertain more
				to natural philosophy. Since then, as themselves say,
				<quote rend="blockquote">Jove is of all beginning, midst, and end,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Orphic Fragments, VI. 10 (Herm.).</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>they ought chiefly to have applied themselves to remedy,
					redress, and reduce to the best order the conceptions concerning the Gods, if there were in them any thing confused
					or erroneous; or if not, to have left every one in those sentiments which they had from the laws and custom concerning the Divinity:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For neither now nor yesterday
					</l>
                     <l>These deep conceits of God began;
					</l>
                     <l>Time out of mind they have been aye,
					</l>
                     <l>But no man knows where, how, or when.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Soph. Antigone, 456.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But these men, having begun (as it were) <q direct="unspecified">from Vesta</q> to
					disturb the opinions settled and received in every country
					concerning the Gods, have not (to speak sincerely) left
					any thing entire and uncorrupted. For what man is there
					or ever was, except these, who does not believe the Divinity
					to be immortal and eternal? Or what in the common anticipations
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.405"/>
					
					 is more unanimously chanted forth concerning
					the Gods than such things as these:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>There the blest Gods eternally enjoy
					</l>
                     <l>Their sweet delights;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Odyss. VI. 46.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Both Gods immortal, and earth-dwelling men;<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. V. 442.</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Exempt from sickness and old age are they,
					</l>
                     <l>And free from toil, and have escaped the flood
					</l>
                     <l>Of roaring Acheron?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">From Pindar.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>One may perhaps light upon some nations so barbarous
					and savage as not to think there is a God; but there was
					never found any man who, believing a God, did not at the
					same time believe him immortal and eternal. Certainly,
					those who were called Atheists, like Theodorus, Diagoras,
					and Hippo, durst not say that the Divinity is corruptible,
					but they did not believe that there is any thing incorruptible; not indeed admitting the subsistence of an incorruptibility, but keeping the idea of a God. But Chrysippus
					and Cleanthes, having filled (as one may say) heaven, earth,
					air, and sea with Gods, have not yet made any one of all
					these Gods immortal or eternal, except Jupiter alone, in
					whom they consume all the rest; so that it is no more
					proper for him to consume others than to be consumed
					himself. For it is alike an infirmity to perish by being
					resolved into another, and to be saved by being nourished
					by the resolution of others into himself. Now these are
					not like other of their absurdities, gathered by argument
					from their suppositions or drawn by consequence from their
					doctrines; but they themselves proclaim it aloud in their
					writings concerning the Gods, Providence, Fate, and Nature, expressly saying that all the other Gods were born,
					and shall die by the fire, melting away, in their opinion, as
					if they were of wax or tin. It is indeed as much against
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.406"/>
					
					common sense that God should be mortal as that man
					should be immortal; nay, indeed, I do not see what the
					difference between God and man will be, if God also is a
					reasonable and corruptible animal. For if they oppose us
					with this subtle distinction, that man is mortal, and God not
					mortal but corruptible, see what they get by it. For they
					will say either that God is at the same time both immortal
					and corruptible, or else that he neither is mortal nor immortal; the absurdity of which even those cannot exceed
					who set themselves industriously to devise positions repugnant to common sense. I speak of others; for these men
					have left no one of the absurdest things unspoken or unattempted.</p>
            <p>To these things Cleanthes, contending for the conflagration of the world, says, that the sun will make the moon
					and all the other stars like to himself, and will change
					them into himself. Indeed, if the stars, being Gods,
					should contribute any thing to the sun towards their own
					destruction by contributing to its conflagration, it would be
					very ridiculous for us to make prayers to them for our salvation, and to think them the saviors of men, whose
					nature it is to accelerate their own corruption and dissolution.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>And yet these men leave nothing unsaid against
				Epicurus, crying out, Fie, fie upon him, as confounding
				their presumption concerning God by taking away Providence; for God (they say) is presumed and understood to
				be not only immortal and happy, but also a lover of men
				and careful of them and beneficial to them; and herein
				they say true. Now if they who abolish Providence take
				away the pre-conception concerning God, what do they
				who say that the Gods indeed have care of us, but deny
				them to be helpful to us, and make them not bestowers of
				good things but of indifferent ones, giving, to wit, not
				virtue, but wealth, health, children, and such like things,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.407"/>
				
				none of which is helpful, profitable, desirable, or available?
				Or shall we not rather think, that the Epicureans do not
				take away the conceptions concerning the Gods; but that
				these Stoics scoff at the Gods and deride them, saying one
				is a God of fruits, another of marriage, another a physician, and another a diviner, while yet health, issue, and
				plenty of fruits are not good things, but indifferent things
				and unprofitable to those who have them?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>The third point of the conception concerning the
				Gods is, that the Gods do in nothing so much differ from
				men as in happiness and virtue. But according to Chrysippus, they have not so much as this difference. For he
				says that Jupiter does not exceed Dion in virtue, but that
				Jupiter and Dion, being both wise, are equally aided by
				one another, when one falls into the motion of the other.
				For this and none else is the good which the Gods do to
				men, and likewise men to the Gods when they are wise.
				For they say, that a man who falls not short in virtue
				comes not behind them in felicity, and that he who, being
				tormented with diseases and being maimed in the body,
				makes himself away, is equally happy with Jupiter the
				Savior, provided he be but wise. But this man neither
				is nor ever was upon the earth; but there are infinite millions of men unhappy to the highest degree in the state
				and government of Jupiter, which is most excellently administered. Now what can be more against sense than
				that, when Jupiter governs exceedingly well, we should be
				exceedingly miserable? But if (which it is unlawful even
				to say) he would wish no longer to be a savior, nor a deliverer, nor a protector, but the contrary to all these glorious
				appellations, there can no goodness be added to the things
				that are, either as to their multitude or magnitude, since,
				as these men say, all men live to the height miserably and
				wickedly, neither vice receiving addition, nor unhappiness
				increase.</p>
            <pb id="v.4.p.408"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>Nor is this the worst; but they are angry with Menander for saying upon the stage,
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The chief beginning of men's miseries
				</l>
                     <l>Are things exceeding good;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>for that this is against sense. And yet they make God, who
					is good, the beginning of evils. <q direct="unspecified">For matter,</q> they say,
					<q direct="unspecified">produced not any evil of itself; for it is without quality,
						and whatever differences it has, it has received them all from
						that which moves and forms it.</q> But that which moves and
					forms it is the reason dwelling in it, since it is not made to
					move and form itself. So that of necessity evil, if it come by
					nothing, must have been produced from that which has no
					being; but if by some moving principle, from God. But
					if they think that Jupiter has not the command of his
					parts nor uses every one of them according to his reason,
					they speak against common sense, and imagine an animal,
					many of whose parts are not subservient to his will but
					use their own operations and actions, to which the whole
					gives no incitation nor begins their motion. For there is
					nothing which has life so ill compacted as that, against its
					will, its feet shall go, its tongue speak, its horns push, or
					its teeth bite. The most of which things God must of
					necessity suffer, if the wicked, being parts of him, do
					against his will lie, cheat, rob, and murder one another.
					But if, as Chrysippus says, the very least part cannot possibly behave itself otherwise than according to Jupiter's
					pleasure, and if every living thing is so framed by Nature
					as to rest and move according as he inclines it and as he
					turns, stays, and disposes it,
					<quote rend="blockquote">This saying is more impious than the first.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Nauck's Tragic Fragments, p. 704 (No. 345).</note>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For it were more tolerable to say that many parts of
					Jupiter are, through his weakness and want of power,
					hurried on to do many absurd things against his nature
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.409"/>
					
					and will, than that there is not any intemperance or wickedness of which Jupiter is not the cause. Moreover, since
					they affirm the world to be a city and the stars citizens, if
					this be so, there must be also tribes-men and magistrates, the sun must be some consul, and the evening star
					a praetor or mayor of a city. Now I know not whether
					any one that shall go about to confute such things will
					not show himself more absurd than those who assert and
					affirm them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="35">
            <p>Is it not therefore against sense to say that the seed
				is more and greater than that which is produced of it?
				For we see that Nature in all animals and plants, even
				those that are wild, has taken small, slender, and scarce
				visible things for principles of generation to the greatest.
				For it does not only from a grain of wheat produce an ear-bearing stalk, or a vine from the stone of a grape; but
				from a small berry or acorn which has escaped being eaten
				by the bird, kindling and setting generation on fire (as it
				were) from a little spark, it sends forth the stock of
				a bush, or the tall body of an oak, palm, or pine tree.
				Whence also they say that seed is in Greek called
				<foreign lang="greek">spe/rma</foreign>, as it were, the <foreign lang="greek">spei/rasis</foreign> or the <hi rend="italics">coiling up</hi> of a great
				mass in a little compass; and that Nature has the name
				of <foreign lang="greek">fu/sis</foreign>, as if it were the <hi rend="italics">inflation</hi> (<foreign lang="greek">e)mfu/shsis</foreign>) and diffusion
				of reason and numbers opened and loosened by it. But
				now, in opposition to this, they maintain that fire is the
				seed of the world, which shall after the conflagration
				change into seed the world, which will then have a copious nature from a smaller body and bulk, and possess
				an infinite space of vacuum filled by its increase; and the
				world being made, the size again recedes and settles, the
				matter being after the generation gathered and contracted
				into itself.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="36">
            <p>You may hear them and read many of their writings,
				in which they jangle with the Academics, and cry out
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.410"/>
				
				against them as confounding all things with their doctrine
				of indistinguishable identity, and as vehemently contending
				that there is but one quality in two substances. And yet
				there is no man who understands not this, and would not
				on the contrary think it wonderful and extremely strange
				if there should not in all time be found a dove exactly and
				in all respects like to another dove, a bee to a bee, a grain
				of wheat to a grain of wheat, or (as the proverb has it)
				one fig to another. But these things are plainly against
				common sense which the Stoics say and feign,&mdash;that there
				are in one substance two particular qualities, and that the
				same substance, which has particularly one quality, when
				another quality is added, receives and equally conserves
				them both. For if there may be two, there may be also
				three, four, and five, and even more than you can name,
				in one and the same substance; I say not in its different
				parts, but all alike in the whole, though ever infinite in
				number. For Chrysippus says, that Jupiter and the world
				are like to man, as is also Providence to the soul; when
				therefore the conflagration shall be, Jupiter, who alone of
				all the Gods is incorruptible, will retire into Providence,
				and they being together, will both perpetually remain in
				the one substance of the ether.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="37">
            <p>But leaving now the Gods, and beseeching them to
				give these Stoics common sense and a common understanding, let us look into their doctrines concerning the elements. It is against the common conceptions that one
				body should be the place of another, or that a body should
				penetrate through a body, neither of them containing any
				vacuity, but the full passing into the full, and that which
				has no vacuity&mdash;but is full and has no place by reason of
				its continuity&mdash;receiving the mixture. But these men, not
				thrusting one thing into one, nor yet two or three or ten
				together, but jumbling all the parts of the world, being
				cut piecemeal, into any one thing which they shall first
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.411"/>
				
				light on, and saying that the very least which is perceived
				by sense will contain the greatest that shall come unto it,
				boldly frame a new doctrine, convicting themselves here,
				as in many other things, of taking for their suppositions
				things repugnant to common sense. And presently upon
				this they are forced to admit into their discourse many
				monstrous and strange positions, mixing whole bodies with
				whole; of which this also is one, that three are four. For
				this others put as an example of those things which cannot be conceived even in thought. But to the Stoics it is
				a matter of truth, that when one cup of wine is mixed with
				two of water, if it is not to be lost but the mixture is to
				be equalized, it must be extended through the whole and
				be confounded therewith, so as to make that which was
				one two by the equalization of the mixture. For the one
				remains, but is extended as much as two, and thus is equal
				to the double of itself. Now if it happens in the mixture
				with two to take the measure of two in the diffusion, this
				is together the measure both of three and four,&mdash;of three
				because one is mixed with two, and of four because, being
				mixed with two, it has an equal quantity with those with
				which it is mixed. Now this fine subtilty is a consequence
				of their putting bodies into a body, and so likewise is the
				unintelligibleness of the manner how one is contained in
				the other. For it is of necessity that, of bodies passing
				one into another by mixture, the one should not contain
				and the other be contained, nor the one receive and the
				other be received within; for this would not be a mixture,
				but a contiguity and touching of the superficies, the one
				entering in, and the other enclosing it without, and the
				rest of the parts remaining unmixed and pure, and so it
				would be merely many different things. But there being
				a necessity, according to their axiom of mixture, that the
				things which are mixed should be mingled one within the
				other, and that the same things should together be contained
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.412"/>
				
				 by being within, and by receiving contain the other,
				and that neither of them could possibly exist again as it
				was before, it comes to pass that both the subjects of the
				mixture mutually penetrate each other, and that there is
				not any part of either remaining separate, but that they
				are necessarily all filled with each other.</p>
            <p>Here now that famous leg of Arcesilaus comes in, with
					much laughter insulting over their absurdities; for if these
					mixtures are through the whole, what should hinder but
					that, a leg being cut off and putrefied and cast into the sea
					and diffused, not only Antigonus's fleet (as Arcesilaus said)
					might sail through it, but also Xerxes's twelve hundred
					ships, together with the Grecians' three hundred galleys,
					might fight in it? For the progress will not henceforth
					fail, nor the lesser cease to be in the greater; or else the
					mixture will be at an end, and the extremity of it, touching where it shall end, will not pass through the whole,
					but will give over being mingled. But if the mixture is
					through the whole, the leg will not indeed of itself afford
					the Greeks room for the sea-fight, for to this there is need
					of putrefaction and change; but if one glass or but one
					drop of wine shall fall from hence into the Aegean or
					Cretan Sea, it will pass into the Ocean or main Atlantic
					Sea, not lightly touching its superficies, but being spread
					quite through it in depth, breadth, and length. And this
					Chrysippus admits, saying immediately in his First Book
					of Natural Questions, that there is nothing to hinder one
					drop of wine from being mixed with the whole sea. And
					that we may not wonder at this, he says that this one drop
					will by mixtion extend through the whole world; than
					which I know not any thing that can appear more absurd.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="38">
            <p>And this also is against sense, that there is not in
				the nature of bodies any thing either supreme or first or
				last, in which the magnitude of the body may terminate;
				but that there is always some phenomenon beyond the
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.413"/>
				
				assumed body, and that this still going on carries the subject to infinity and undeterminateness. For one body
				cannot be imagined greater or less than another, if both
				of them may by their parts proceed <hi rend="italics">in infinitum;</hi> but the
				nature of inequality is taken away. For of things that are
				esteemed unequal, the one falls short in its last parts, and
				the other goes on and exceeds. Now if there is no inequality, it follows that there is no unevenness nor roughness of bodies; for unevenness is the inequality of the
				same superficies with itself, and roughness is an unevenness joined with hardness; neither of which is left us by
				those who terminate no body in its last part, but extend
				them all by the multitude of their parts unto an infinity.
				And yet is it not evident that a man consists of more parts
				than a finger, and the world of more than a man? This
				indeed all men know and understand, unless they become
				Stoics; but if they are once Stoics, they on the contrary
				say and think that a man has no more parts than a finger,
				nor the world than a man. For division reduces bodies to
				an infinity; and of infinites neither is more or less or exceeds in multitude, or the parts of the remainder will
				cease to be divided and to afford a multitude of themselves.</p>
            <p>LAMPRIAS. How then do they extricate themselves out
					of these difficulties?</p>
            <p>DIADUMENUS. Surely with very great cunning and courage. For Chrysippus says: <q direct="unspecified">If we are asked, if we have
					any parts, and how many, and of what and how many
					parts they consist, we are to use a distinction, making it a
					position that the whole body is compacted of the head,
					trunk, and legs, as if that were all which is enquired and
					doubted of. But if they extend their interrogation to the
					last parts, no such thing is to be undertaken, but we are
					to say that they consist not of any certain parts, nor yet
					of so many, nor of infinite, nor of finite.</q> And I seem to
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.414"/>
					
					myself to have used his very words, that you may perceive
					how he maintains the common notions, forbidding us to
					think of what or how many parts every body is compacted,
					and whether of infinite or finite. For if there were any
					medium between finite and infinite, as the indifferent is
					between good and evil, he should, by telling us what that
					is, have solved the difficulty. But if&mdash;as that which is
					not equal is presently understood to be unequal, and that
					which is not mortal to be immortal&mdash;we also understand
					that which is not finite to be immediately infinite, to say
					that a body consists of parts neither finite nor infinite is,
					in my opinion, the same thing as to affirm that an argument is compacted of positions neither true nor false....</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="39">
            <p>To this he with a certain youthful rashness adds,
				that in a pyramid consisting of triangles, the sides inclining to the juncture are unequal, and yet do not exceed
				one another in that they are greater. Thus does he keep
				the common notions. For if there is any thing greater
				and not exceeding, there will be also something less and
				not deficient, and so also something unequal which neither
				exceeds nor is deficient; that is, there will be an unequal
				thing equal, a greater not greater, and a less not less. See
				it yet farther, in what manner he answered Democritus,
				enquiring philosophically and properly, if a cone is divided
				by a plane parallel with its base, what is to be thought of
				the superficies of its segments, whether they are equal or
				unequal; for if they are unequal, they will render the
				cone uneven, receiving many step-like incisions and roughnesses; but if they are equal, the sections will be equal,
				and the cone will seem to have the same qualities as the
				cylinder, to wit, to be composed not of unequal but of
				equal circles; which is most absurd. Here, that he may
				convince Democritus of ignorance, he says, that the superficies are neither equal or unequal, but that the bodies are
				unequal, because the superficies are neither equal nor unequal.
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.415"/>
				
				 Indeed to assert this for a law, that bodies are
				unequal while the superficies are not unequal, is the part
				of a man who takes to himself a wonderful liberty of
				writing whatever comes into his head. For reason and
				manifest evidence, on the contrary, give us to understand,
				that the superficies of unequal bodies are unequal, and that
				the bigger the body is, the greater also is the superficies,
				unless the excess, by which it is the greater, is void of a
				superficies. For if the superficies of the greater bodies
				do not exceed those of the less, but sooner fail, a part of
				that body which has an end will be without an end and
				infinite. For if he says that he is compelled to this, . . .
				For those rabbeted incisions, which he suspects in a cone,
				are made by the inequality of the body, and not of the
				superficies. It is ridiculous therefore to take the superficies
				out of the account, and after all to leave the inequality in
				the bodies themselves. But to persist still in this matter,
				what is more repugnant to sense than the imagining of
				such things? For if we admit that one superficies is
				neither equal nor unequal to another, we may say also of
				magnitude and of number, that one is neither equal nor
				unequal to another; and this, not having any thing that
				we can call or think to be a neuter or medium between
				equal and unequal. Besides, if there are superficies neither
				equal nor unequal, what hinders but there may be also
				circles neither equal nor unequal? For indeed these superficies of conic sections are circles. And if circles,
				why may not also their diameters be neither equal nor
				unequal? And if so, why not also angles, triangles, parallelograms, parallelepipeds, and bodies? For if the longitudes are neither equal nor unequal to one another, so
				will the weight, percussion, and bodies be neither equal
				nor unequal. How then dare these men inveigh against
				those who introduce vacuities, and suppose that there are
				some indivisible atoms, and who say that motion and rest
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.416"/>
				
				are not inconsistent with each other, when themselves
				affirm such axioms as these to be false: If any things
				are not equal to one another, they are unequal to one
				another; and the same things are not equal and unequal
				to one another? But when he says that there is something greater and yet not exceeding, it were worth the
				while to ask, whether these things quadrate with one
				another. For if they quadrate, how is either the greater?
				And if they do not quadrate, how can it be but the one
				must exceed and the other fall short? For if neither of
				these be, the other both will and will not quadrate with
				the greater. For those who keep not the common conceptions must of necessity fall into such perplexities.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="40">
            <p>It is moreover against sense to say that nothing
				touches another; nor is this less absurd, that bodies touch
				one another, but touch by nothing. For they are necessitated to admit these things, who allow not the least parts
				of a body, but assume something which is before that
				which seems to touch, and never cease to proceed still
				farther. What, therefore, these men principally object to
				the patrons of those indivisible bodies called atoms is this,
				that there is neither a touching of the whole by the whole,
				nor of the parts by the parts; for that the one makes not
				a touching but a mixture, and that the other is not possible, these individuals having no parts. How then do not
				they themselves fall into the same inconvenience, leaving
				no first or last part, whilst they say, that whole bodies
				mutually touch one another by a term or extremity and not
				by a part? But this term is not a body; therefore one
				body shall touch one another by that which is incorporeal,
				and again shall not touch, that which is incorporeal coming between them. And if it shall touch, the body shall
				both do and suffer something by that which is incorporeal.
				For it is the nature of bodies mutually to do and suffer,
				and to touch. But if the body has a touching by that
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.417"/>
				
				which is incorporeal, it will have also a contact, and a mixture, and a coalition. Again, in these contacts and mixtures the extremities of the bodies must either remain,
				or not remain but be corrupted. Now both of these are
				against sense. For neither do they themselves admit corruptions and generations of incorporeal things; nor can
				there be a mixture and coalition of bodies retaining their
				own extremities. For the extremity determines and constitutes the nature of the body; and mixtions, unless the
				mutual laying of parts by parts are thereby understood,
				wholly confound all those that are mixed. And, as these
				men say, we must admit the corruption of extremities in
				mixtures, and their generation again in the separation of
				them. But this none can easily understand. Now by
				what bodies mutually touch each other, by the same they
				press, thrust, and crush each other. Now that this should
				be done or suffered by things that are incorporeal, is impossible and not so much as to be imagined. But yet this
				they would constrain us to conceive. For if a sphere
				touch a plane by a point, it is manifest that it may be also
				drawn over the plane upon a point; and if the superficies
				of it is painted with vermilion, it will imprint a red line
				on the plane; and if it is fiery hot, it will burn the plane.
				Now for an incorporeal thing to color, or a body to be
				burned by that which is incorporeal, is against sense. But
				if we should imagine an earthen or glassy sphere to fall
				from on high upon a plane of stone, it were against reason
				to think it would not be broken, being struck against that
				which is hard and solid; but it would be more absurd that
				it should be broken, falling upon an extremity or point
				that is incorporeal. So that the presumptions concerning
				things incorporeal and corporeal are wholly disturbed, or
				rather taken away, by their joining to them many impossibilities.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="41">
            <p>It is also against common sense, that there should
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.418"/>
				
				be a time future and past, but no time present; and that
				<hi rend="italics">erewhile</hi> and <hi rend="italics">lately</hi> subsist, but <hi rend="italics">now</hi> is nothing at all. Yet
				this often befalls the Stoics, who admit not the least time
				between, nor will allow the present to be indivisible; but
				whatsoever any one thinks to take and understand as present, one part of that they say to be future, and the other
				part past; so that there is no part remaining or left of the
				present time: but of that which is said to be present, one
				part is distributed to the future, the other to the past.
				Therefore one of these two things follows: either that;
				holding there was a time and there will be a time, we must
				deny there is a time; or we must hold that there is a time
				present, part of which has already been and part will be, and
				say that of that which now is, one part is future and the
				other past; and that of <hi rend="italics">now,</hi> one part is before and the
				other behind; and that <hi rend="italics">now</hi> is that which is neither yet
				now nor any longer now; for that which is past is no
				longer <hi rend="italics">now,</hi> and that which is to come is not yet <hi rend="italics">now.</hi>
				And dividing thus the present, they must needs say of the
				year and of the day, that part of it was of the year or day
				past, and part will be of the year or day to come; and
				that of what is together, there is a part before and a part
				after. For no less are they perplexed, confounding together these terms, <hi rend="italics">not yet</hi> and <hi rend="italics">already</hi> and <hi rend="italics">no longer</hi>
				and <hi rend="italics">now</hi> and <hi rend="italics">not now.</hi> But all other men suppose, esteem, and think <hi rend="italics">erewhile</hi> and <hi rend="italics">awhile hence</hi> to be different
				parts of time from <hi rend="italics">now,</hi> which is followed by the one and
				preceded by the other. But Archedemus, saying that <hi rend="italics">now</hi>
				is the beginning and juncture of that which is past and
				that which is near at hand, has (as it seems) without perceiving it thereby taken away all time. For if <hi rend="italics">now</hi> is no
				time, but only a term or extremity of time, and if every
				part of time is such as <hi rend="italics">now,</hi> all time seems to have no
				parts, but to be wholly dissolved into terms, joints, and beginnings. But Chrysippus, desiring to show more artifice
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.419"/>
				
				in his division, in his book of Vacuity and some others,
				says, that the past and future time are not, but have subsisted (or will subsist), and that the present only is ; but
				in his third, fourth, and fifth books concerning Parts, he
				asserts, that of the present time one part is past, the other
				to come. Thus it comes to pass, that he divides subsisting time into non-subsisting parts of a subsisting total, or
				rather leaves nothing at all of time subsisting, if the
				present has no part but what is either future or past.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="42">
            <p>These men's conception therefore of time is not
				unlike the grasping of water, which, the harder it is held,
				all the more slides and runs away. As to actions and motions, all evidence is utterly confounded. For if <hi rend="italics">now</hi> is
				divided into past and future, it is of necessity that what is
				now moved partly has been moved and partly shall be
				moved, that the end and beginning of motion have been
				taken away, that nothing of any work has been done first,
				nor shall any thing be last, the actions being distributed
				with time. For as they say that of present time, part is
				past and part to come; so of that which is doing, it will
				be said that part is done and part shall be done. When
				therefore had <hi rend="italics">to dine, to write, to walk,</hi> a beginning,
				and when shall they have an end, if every one who is dining has dined and shall dine, and every one who is walking has walked and shall walk? But this is, as it is said,
				of all absurdities the most absurd, that if he who now
				lives has already lived and shall live, then to live neither
				had beginning nor shall have end; but every one of us, as
				it seems, was born without beginning to live, and shall die
				without ceasing to live. For if there is no last part, but
				he who lives has something of the present still remaining
				for the future, to say <q direct="unspecified">Socrates shall live</q> will never be
				false so long as it shall be true to say <q direct="unspecified">Socrates lives;</q>
				and so long also will be false to say <q direct="unspecified">Socrates is dead.</q>
				So that, if <q direct="unspecified">Socrates shall live</q> is true in infinite parts of
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.420"/>
				
				time, it will in no part of time be true to say <q direct="unspecified">Socrates
					is dead.</q> And verily what end will there be of a work,
				and where will you terminate an action, if, as often as it is
				true to say <q direct="unspecified">This is doing,</q> it is likewise true to say <q direct="unspecified">This
					shall be doing</q>? For he will lie who shall say, there
				will be an end of Plato's writing and disputing; since
				Plato will never give over writing and disputing, if it is
				never false to say of him who disputes that he shall dispute, and of him who writes that he shall write. Moreover, there will be no part of that which now is, but either
				has been or is to be, and is either past or future; but of
				what has been and is to be, of past and future, there is no
				sense; wherefore there is absolutely no sense of any thing.
				For we neither see what is past and future, nor do we hear
				or have any other sense of what has been or is to be.
				Nothing then, even what is present, is to be perceived by
				sense, if of the present, part is always future and part
				past,&mdash;if part has been and part is to be.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="43">
            <p>Now they indeed say, that Epicurus does intolerable
				things and violates the conceptions, in moving all bodies
				with equal celerity, and admitting none of them to be
				swifter than another. And yet it is much more intolerable
				and farther remote from sense, that nothing can be overtaken by another:
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not though Adrastus's swift-footed steed
				</l>
                     <l>Should chase the tortoise slow,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as the proverb has it. Now this must of necessity fall out,
					if things move according to <hi rend="italics">prius and posterius,</hi> and the
					intervals through which they pass are (as these men's tenet
					is) divisible <hi rend="italics">in infinitum;</hi> for if the tortoise is but a furlong before the horse, they who divide this furlong <hi rend="italics">in
						infinitum,</hi> and move them both according to <hi rend="italics">prius</hi> and
					<hi rend="italics">posterius,</hi> will never bring the swiftest to the slowest;
					the slower always adding some interval divisible into infinite spaces. Now to affirm that, water being poured from
					
					<pb id="v.4.p.421"/>
					
					a bowl or cup, it will never be all poured out, is it not
					both against common sense, and a consequence of what
					these men say? For no man can understand the motion
					according to <hi rend="italics">prius</hi> of things infinitely divisible to be consummated; but leaving always somewhat divisible, it will
					make all the effusion, all the running and flux of a liquid,
					motion of a solid, and fall of an heavy thing imperfect.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="44">
            <p>I pass by many absurdities of theirs, touching only
				such as are against sense. The dispute concerning increase is indeed ancient; for the question, as Chrysippus
				says, was put by Epicharmus. Now, whereas those of
				the Academy think that the doubt is not very easy and
				ready all of a sudden to be cleared, these men have mightily exclaimed against them, and accused them of taking
				away the presumptions, and yet themselves are so far from
				preserving the common notions, that they pervert even
				sense itself. For the discourse is simple, and these men
				grant the suppositions,&mdash;that all particular substances
				flow and are carried, some of them emitting forth somewhat from themselves, and others receiving things coming
				from elsewhere; and that the things to which there is
				made an accession or from which there is a decession by
				numbers and multitudes, do not remain the same, but become others by the said accessions, the substance receiving
				a change; and that these changes are not rightly called
				by custom increasings or diminutions, but it is fitter they
				should be styled generations and corruptions, because they
				drive by force from one state to another, whereas to increase and be diminished are passions of a body that is
				subject and permanent. These things being thus in a manner said and delivered, what would these defenders of
				evidence and canonical regulators of common conceptions
				have? Every one of us (they say) is double, twin-like,
				and composed of a double nature; not as the poets feigned
				of the Molionidae, that they in some parts grow together
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.422"/>
				
				and in some parts are separated,&mdash;but every one of us
				has two bodies, having the same color, the same figure, the
				same weight and place. ... These things were never
				before seen by any man; but these men alone have discerned this composition, doubleness, and ambiguity, how
				every one of us is two subjects, the one substance, the
				other quality; and the one is in perpetual flux and motion, neither increasing nor being diminished nor remaining
				altogether; the other remains and increases and is diminished, and suffers all things contrary to the former, with
				which it is so concorporated, conjoined, and confounded,
				that it exhibits not any difference to be perceived by sense.
				Indeed, Lynceus is said to have penetrated stones and oaks
				with his sight; and a certain man sitting on a watch-tower
				in Sicily beheld the ships of the Carthaginians setting
				forth from their harbor, which was a day and a night's
				sail from thence. Callicrates and Myrmecides are said to
				have made chariots that might be covered with the wings
				of a fly, and to have engraved verses of Homer on a sesame seed. But none ever discerned or discovered this
				diversity in us; nor have we perceived ourselves to be
				double, in one part always flowing, and in the other remaining the same from our birth even to our death. But
				I make the discourse more simple, since they make four
				subjects in every one, or rather every one of us to be four.
				But two are sufficient to show their absurdity. For if,
				when we hear Pentheus in the tragedy affirm that he
				sees two suns and two cities of Thebes,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Bacch. 918.</note> we say that
				he does not see, but that his sight is dazzled, he being
				transported and troubled in his mind; why do we not
				bid those farewell, who assert not one city alone, but
				all men and animals, and all trees, vessels, instruments,
				and clothes, to be double and composed of two, as men
				who constrain us to dote rather than to understand? But
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.423"/>
				
				this feigning other natures of subjects must perhaps be
				pardoned them; for there appears no other invention by
				which they can maintain and uphold the augmentations of
				which they are so fond.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="45">
            <p>But by what cause moved, or for the adorning of
				what other suppositions, they frame in a manner innumerable differences and forms of bodies in the soul, there is
				none can say, unless it be that they remove, or rather
				wholly abdicate and destroy, the common and usual notions, to introduce other foreign and strange ones. For
				it is very absurd that, making all virtues and vices&mdash;and
				with them all arts, memories, fancies, passions, impulses,
				and assents&mdash;to be bodies, they should affirm that they
				neither lie nor subsist in any subject, leaving them for a
				place one only hole, like a prick in the heart, where they
				crowd the principal part of the soul, enclosed with so many
				bodies, that a very great number of them lie hid even
				from those who think they can spare and distinguish them
				one from another. Nay, that they should not only make
				them bodies, but also rational creatures, and even a swarm
				of such creatures, not friendly or gentle, but a multitude
				maliciously rebellious and revengeful, and should so make
				of each one of us a park or menagerie or Trojan horse, or
				whatever else we may call their fancies,&mdash;this is the very
				height of contempt and rebellion against evidence and
				custom. But they say, that not only the virtues and vices,
				not only the passions, as anger, envy, grief, and maliciousness, not only comprehensions, fancies, and ignorances, not
				only arts, as shoemaking and working in brass, are animals; but besides these, also they make even the operations
				bodies and animals, saying that walking is an animal, as
				also dancing, supposing, saluting, and railing. The consequence of this is that laughing and weeping are also
				animals; and if so, then also are coughing, sneezing,
				groaning, spitting, blowing the nose, and other such like
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.424"/>
				
				things sufficiently known. Neither have they any cause to
				take it ill that they are by reason, proceeding leisurely, reduced to this, if they shall call to mind how Chrysippus,
				in his First Book of Natural Questions, argues thus:
				<q direct="unspecified">Is not night a body? And are not then the evening,
					dawning, and midnight bodies? Or is not a day a body?
					Is not then the first day of the month a body? And the
					tenth, the fifteenth, and the thirtieth, are they not bodies?
					Is not a month a body? Summer, autumn, and the year, are
					they not bodies?</q>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="46">
            <p>These things they hold against the common conceptions; but those which follow they hold also against their
				own, engendering that which is most hot by refrigeration,
				and that which is most subtile by condensation. For the
				soul, to wit, is a substance most hot and most subtile. But
				this they make by the refrigeration and condensation of the
				body, changing, as it were, by induration the spirit, which
				of vegetative is made animal. Moreover, they say that the
				sun became animated, his moisture changing into intellectual fire. Behold how the sun is imagined to be engendered by refrigeration! Xenophanes indeed, when one
				told him that he had seen eels living in hot water, answered,
				We will boil them then in cold. But if these men engender heat by refrigeration and lightness by condensation, it
				follows, they must also generate cold things by heat, thick
				things by dissolution, and heavy things by rarefaction, that
				so they may keep some proportion in their absurdity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="47">
            <p>And do they not also determine the substance and
				generation of conception itself, even against the common
				conceptions? For conception is a certain imagination, and
				imagination an impression in the soul. Now the nature
				of the soul is an exhalation, in which it is difficult for an
				impression to be made because of its tenuity, and for which
				it is impossible to keep an impression it may have received.
				For its nutriment and generation, consisting of moist things,
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.425"/>
				
				have continual accession and consumption. And the mixture of respiration with the air always makes some new
				exhalation, which is altered and changed by the flux of the
				air coming from abroad and again going out. For one may
				more easily imagine that a stream of running water can
				retain figures, impressions, and images, than that a spirit can
				be carried in vapors and humors, and continually mingled
				with another idle and strange breath from without. But
				these men so far forget themselves, that, having defined the
				conceptions to be certain stored-up intelligences, and memoirs to be constant and habitual impressions, and having
				wholly fixed the sciences, as having stability and firmness,
				they presently place under them a basis and seat of a slippery substance, easy to be dissipated and in perpetual flux
				and motion.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="48">
            <p>Now the common conception of an element and
				principle, naturally imprinted in almost all men, is this,
				that it is simple, unmixed, and uncompounded. For that
				is not an element or principle which is mixed; but those
				things are so of which it is mixed. But these men,
				making God, who is the principle of all things, to be an
				intellectual body and a mind seated in matter, pronounce
				him to be neither simple nor uncompounded, but to be
				composed of and by another; matter being of itself indeed
				without reason and void of quality, and yet having simplicity and the property of a principle. If then God is
				not incorporeal and immaterial, he participates of matter as
				a principle. For if matter and reason are one and the same
				thing, they have not rightly defined matter to be reasonless;
				but if they are different things, then is God constituted of
				them both, and is not a simple, but compound thing, having to the intellectual taken the corporeal from matter.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="49">
            <p>Moreover, calling these four bodies, earth, water, air,
				and fire, the first elements, they do (I know not how) make
				some of them simple and pure, and others compound and
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.426"/>
				
				mixed. For they hold that earth and water keep together
				neither themselves nor other things, but preserve their
				unity by the participation of air and force of fire; but that
				air and fire do both fortify themselves by their own strength,
				or being mixed with the other two, give them force,
				permanence, and subsistence. How then is either earth
				or water an element, if neither of them is either simple,
				or first, or self-sufficient, but if each wants somewhat from
				without to contain and keep it in its being? For they
				have not left so much as a thought of their substance; but
				this discourse concerning the earth has much confusion and
				uncertainty, when they say that it subsists of itself; for if
				the earth is of itself, how has it need of the air to fix and
				contain it? But neither the earth nor water can any more
				be said to be of itself; but the air, drawing together and
				thickening the matter, has made the earth, and again dissolving and mollifying it, has produced the water. Neither
				of these then is an element, since something else has contributed being and generation to them both.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="50">
            <p>Moreover, they say that subsistence and matter are
				subject to qualities, and do so in a manner define them;
				and again, they make the qualities to be also bodies. But
				these things have much perplexity. For if qualities have
				a peculiar substance, for which they both are and are called
				bodies, they need no other substance; for they have one
				of their own. But if they have under them in common
				only that which the Stoics call essence and matter, it is
				manifest they do but participate of the body; for they are
				not bodies. But the subject and recipient must of necessity differ from those things which it receives and to which
				it is subject. But these men see by halves; for they say
				indeed that matter is void of quality, but they will not call
				qualities immaterial. Now how can they make a body
				without quality, who understand no quality without a
				body? For the reason which joins a body to all quality
				
				<pb id="v.4.p.427"/>
				
				suffers not the understanding to comprehend any body without some quality. Either, therefore, he who oppugns incorporeal quality seems also to oppugn unqualified matter;
				or separating the one from the other, he mutually parts
				them both. As for the reason which some pretend, that
				matter is called unqualified not because it is void of all
				quality, but because it has all qualities, it is most of all
				against sense. For no man calls that unqualified which is
				capable of every quality, nor that impassible which is by
				nature always apt to suffer all things, nor that immovable
				which is moved every way. And this doubt is not solved,
				that, however matter is always understood with quality, yet
				it is understood to be another thing and differing from
				quality.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>