<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">De fluviis</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Pseudo-Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="chapter" delim="."/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0094.001">
      <body>
         <head>Of the names of rivers and mountains, and of
				such things as are to be found therein.<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">A very slight inspection of this strange treatise will convince the reader that it
					is justly placed among the Pseudoplutarchea. It is reprinted here merely because
					it was included in the original translation. (G.)</note>
         </head>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>I. HYDASPES.</head>
            <pb id="v.5.p.477"/>
            <p>THIS is a river of India, which falls with an extraordinary swift stream into the Saronitic Syrtis. Chrysippe,
					by the impulse of Venus, whom she had offended, fell in
					love with her father Hydaspes, and not being able to curb
					her preternatural desires, by the help of her nurse, in the
					dead of the night got to his bed and received his caresses;
					after which, the king proving unfortunate in his affairs, he
					buried alive the old bawd that had betrayed him, and crucified his daughter. Nevertheless such was the excess of
					his grief for the loss of Chrysippe, that he threw himself
					into the river Indus, which was afterwards called by his
					name Hydaspes.</p>
            <p>Moreover in this river there grows a stone, which is
					called lychnis, which resembles the color of oil, and is
					very bright in appearance. And when they are searching
					after it, which they do when the moon increases, the pipers
					play all the while. Nor is it to be worn by any but the
					richer sort. Also near that part of the river which is called
					Pylae, there grows an herb which is very like a heliotrope,
					with the juice of which the people anoint their skins to
					prevent sunburning, and to secure them against the scorching of the excessive heat.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.478"/>
            <p>The natives whenever they take their virgins tardy, nail
					them to a wooden cross, and fling them into this river,
					singing at the same time in their own language a hymn
					to Venus. Every year also they bury a condemned old
					woman near the top of the hill called Therogonos; at
					which time an infinite multitude of creeping creatures
					come down from the top of the hill, and devour the
					insects that hover about the buried carcass. This Chrysermus relates in his History of India, though Archelaus
					gives a more exact account of these things in his Treatise
					of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Elephas, so called
					upon this occasion. When Alexander the Macedonian
					advanced with his army into India, and the natives were
					resolved to withstand him with all their force, the elephant
					upon which Porus, king of that region, was wont to ride,
					being of a sudden stung with a gad-bee, ran up to the top
					of the mountain of the sun, and there uttered these words
					distinctly in human speech: <q direct="unspecified">O king, my lord, descended
						from the race of Gegasius, forbear to attempt any thing
						against Alexander, for he is descended from Jupiter.</q> And
					having so said, he presently died. Which when Porus
					understood, afraid of Alexander, he fell at his feet and
					sued for peace. Which when he had obtained, he called
					the mountain Elephas;&mdash;as Dercyllus testifies in his Third
					Book of Mountains.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>II. ISMENUS.</head>
            <p>ISMENUS is a river of Boeotia, that washes the walls of
					Thebes. It was formerly called the foot of Cadmus, upon
					this occasion. When Cadmus had slain the dragon which
					kept the fountain of Mars, he was afraid to taste of the
					water, believing it was poisoned; which forced him to
					wander about in search of another fountain to allay his
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.479"/>
					
					thirst. At length, by the help of Minerva, he came to
					the Corycian den, where his right leg stuck deep in the
					mire. And from that hole it was that, after he had pulled
					his leg out again, sprung a fair river, which the hero, after
					the solemnity of his sacrifices performed, called by the
					name of Cadmus's foot.</p>
            <p>Some time after, Ismenus, the son of Amphion and Niobe,
					being wounded by Apollo and in great pain, threw himself into the said river, which was then from his name
					called Ismenus;&mdash;as Sostratus relates in his Second Book
					of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Cithaeron, formerly
					called Asterion for this reason. Boeotus the son of Neptune was desirous, of two noble ladies, to marry her that
					should be most beneficial to him; and while he tarried for
					both in the night-time upon the top of a certain nameless mountain, of a sudden a star fell from heaven upon
					the shoulders of Eurythemiste, and immediately vanished.
					Upon which Boeotus, understanding the meaning of the
					prodigy, married the virgin, and called the mountain Asterion from the accident that befell him. Afterwards it was
					called Cithaeron upon this occasion. Tisiphone, one of
					the Furies, falling in love with a most beautiful youth
					whose name was Cithaeron, and not being able to curb the
					impatience of her desires, declared her affection to him in
					a letter, to which he would not return any answer. Whereupon the Fury, missing her design, pulled one of the serpents from her locks, and flung it upon the young lad as he
					was keeping his sheep on the top of the mountain Asterion; where the serpent twining about his neck choked
					him to death. And thereupon by the will of the Gods
					the mountain was called Cithaeron;&mdash;as Leo of Byzantium writes in his History of Boeotia.
					But Hermesianax of Cyprus tells the story quite otherwise. For he says, that Helicon and Cithaeron were two
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.480"/>
					
					brothers, quite different in their dispositions. For Helicon
					was affable and mild, and cherished his aged parents.
					But Cithaeron, being covetous and greedily gaping after
					the estate, first killed his father, and then treacherously
					threw his brother down from a steep precipice, but in
					striving together, fell himself along with him. Whence,
					by the providence of the Gods, the names of both the
					mountains were changed. Cithaeron, by reason of his impiety, became the haunt of the Furies. Helicon, for the
					young man's love to his parents, became the habitation of
					the Muses.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>III. HEBRUS.</head>
            <p>HEBRUS is a river of Thrace, deriving its former name
					of Rhombus from the many gulfs and whirlpools in the
					water.</p>
            <p>Cassander, king of that region, having married Crotonice, had by her a son whom he named Hebrus. But then
					being divorced from his first wife, he married Damasippe,
					the daughter of Atrax, and brought her home over his
					son's head; with whom the mother-in-law falling in love,
					invited him by letters to her embraces. But he, avoiding
					his mother-in-law as a Fury, gave himself over to the sport
					of hunting. On the other side the impious woman, missing
					her purpose, belied the chaste youth, and accused him of
					attempting to ravish her. Upon this Cassander, raging
					with jealousy, flew to the wood in a wild fury, and with
					his sword drawn pursued his son, as one that treacherously
					sought to defile his father's bed. Upon which the son,
					finding he could no way escape his father's wrath, threw
					himself into the river Rhombus, which was afterwards
					called Hebrus from the name of the young man;&mdash;as
					Timotheus testifies in his Eleventh Book of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Pangaeus, so called
					upon this occasion. Pangaeus, the son of Mars and Critobule,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.481"/>
					
					 by a mistake lay with his own daughter; which perplexed him to that degree that he fled to the Carmanian
					mountain, where, overwhelmed with a sorrow that he could
					not master, he drew his sword and slew himself. Whence,
					by the providence of the Gods, the place was called Pangaeus.</p>
            <p>In the river before mentioned, grows an herb not much
					unlike to origanumn; the tops of which the Thracians cropping off burn upon a fire, and after they are filled with the
					fruits of Ceres, they hold their heads over the smoke, and
					snuff it up into their nostrils, letting it go down their
					throats, till at last they fall into a profound sleep.</p>
            <p>Also upon the mountain Pangaeus grows an herb, which
					is called the harp upon this occasion. The women that
					tore Orpheus in pieces cast his limbs into the river Hebrus;
					and his head being changed, the whole body was turned
					into the shape of a dragon. But as for his harp, such was
					the will of Apollo, it remained in the same form. And
					from the streaming blood grew up the herb which was
					called the harp; which, during the solemnity of the sacrifices to Bacchus, sends forth a sound like that of an harp
					when played upon. At which time the natives, being
					covered with the skins of young hinds and waving their
					thyrsuses in their hands, sing a hymn, of which these are
					part of the words,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When wisdom all in vain must be,
						</l>
                     <l>Then be not wise at all;&mdash;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as Clitonymus reports, in his Third Book of Thracian
					Relations.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>IV. GANGES.</head>
            <p>GANGES is a river in India, so called for this reason. A
					certain Calaurian nymph had by Indus a son called Ganges,
					conspicuous for his beauty. Who growing up to manhood,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.482"/>
					
					being once desperately overcome with wine, in the heat of
					his intoxication lay with his mother. The next day he
					was informed by the nurse of what he had done; and such
					was the excess of his sorrow, that he threw himself into a
					river called Chliarus, afterwards called Ganges from his
					own name.</p>
            <p>In this river grows an herb resembling bugloss, which
					the natives bruise, and keep the juice very charily. With
					this juice in the dead of the night they go and besprinkle
					the tigers' dens; the virtue of which is such, that the
					tigers, not being able to stir forth by reason of the strong
					scent of the juice, are starved to death;&mdash;as Callisthenes
					reports in his Third Book of Hunting.</p>
            <p>Upon the banks of this river lies the mountain called
					the Anatole for this reason. The Sun, beholding the
					nymph Anaxibia innocently spending her time in dancing,
					fell passionately in love with her, and not able to curb his
					loose amours, pursued her with a purpose to ravish her.
					She therefore, finding no other way to escape him, fled to
					the temple of Orthian Diana, which was seated upon the
					mountain called Coryphe, and there immediately vanished
					away. Upon which the Sun, that followed her close at
					the heels, not knowing what was become of his beloved,
					overwhelmed with grief, rose in that very place. And
					from this accident it was that the natives called the top of
					that mountain Anatole, or the rising of the Sun;&mdash;as Caemaron reports in his Tenth Book of the Affairs of India.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="5">
            <head>V. PHASIS.</head>
            <p>PHASIS is a river of Scythia, running by a city of the
					same name. It was formerly called Arcturus, deriving its
					name from the situation of the cold regions through which
					it runs. But the name of it was altered upon this occasion.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.483"/>
            <p>Phasis, the child of the Sun and Ocyrrhoe daughter of
					Oceanus, slew his mother, whom he took in the very act
					of adultery. For which being tormented by the Furies appearing to him, he threw himself into the river Arcturus,
					which was afterwards called by his own name Phasis.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a reed, which is called leucophyllus,
					or the reed with the white leaf. This reed is found at
					the dawning of the morning light, at what time the sacrifices are offered to Hecate, at the time when the divinely
					inspired paean is chanted, at the beginning of the spring;
					when they who are troubled with jealous heads gather this
					reed, and strew it in their wives' chambers to keep them
					chaste. And the nature of the reed is such, that if any
					wild extravagant person happens to come rashly in drink
					into the room where it lies, he presently becomes deprived
					of his rational thoughts, and immediately confesses whatever he has wickedly done and intended to do. At what
					time they that are present to hear him lay hold of him,
					sew him up in a sack, and throw him into a hole called the
					Mouth of the Wicked, which is round like the mouth of a
					well. This after thirty days empties the body into the
					Lake Maeotis, that is full of worms; where of a sudden
					the body is seized and torn to pieces by several vultures
					unseen before, nor is it known from whence they come;&mdash;
					as Ctesippus relates in his Second Book of Scythian Relations.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Caucasus, which was
					before called Boreas's Bed, upon this occasion. Boreas in
					the heat of his amorous passion ravished away by force
					Chione, the daughter of Arcturus, and carried her to a
					certain hill which was called Niphantes, and upon her
					begot a son whom he called Hyrpax, who succeeded Heniochus in his kingdom. For which reason the mountain
					was first called Boreas's Bed; but afterwards Caucasus
					upon this occasion. After the fight of the Giants, Saturn,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.484"/>
					
					to avoid the menaces of Jupiter, fled to the top of Boreas's
					Bed, and there being turned into a crocodile [lay concealed.
					But Prometheus] slew Caucasus one of the shepherds inhabiting that place; and cutting him up and observing the
					disposition of his entrails, he foresaw that his enemies
					were not far off. Presently Jupiter appearing, and binding his father with a woollen list, threw him down to hell.
					Then changing the name of the mountain in honor of the
					shepherd Caucasus, he chained Prometheus to it, and
					caused him to be tormented by an eagle that fed upon his
					entrails, because he was the first that found out the inspection of bowels, which Jupiter deemed a great cruelty;&mdash;
					as Cleanthes relates in his Third Book of the Wars of the
					Gods.</p>
            <p>Upon this mountain grows an herb which is called Prometheus, which Medea gathering and bruising made use
					of to protect Jason against her father's obstinacy.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="6">
            <head>VI. ARAR.</head>
            <p>ARAR is a river in Gallia Celtica, deriving the name from
					its being mixed with the river Rhone. For it falls into the
					Rhone within the country of the Allobroges. It was
					formerly called Brigulus, but afterwards changed its name
					upon this occasion. Arar, as he was a hunting, entering
					into the wood, and there finding his brother Celtiber torn
					in pieces by the wild beasts, mortally wounded himself for
					grief, and fell into the river Brigulus; which from that
					accident was afterwards called by his own name Arar.</p>
            <p>In this river there breeds a certain large fish, which by
					the natives is called Clupaea. This fish during the increase
					of the moon is white; but all the while the moon is in the
					wane, it is altogether black; and when it grows over
					bulky, it is (as it were) stabbed by its own fins. In the
					head of it is found a stone like a corn of salt, which, being
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.485"/>
					
					applied to the left parts of the body when the moon is in
					the wane, cures quartan agues;&mdash;as Callisthenes the
					Sybarite tells us in the Thirteenth Book of Gallic Relations, from whom Timagenes the Syrian borrowed his
					argument.</p>
            <p>Near to this river stands a mountain called Lugdunum,
					which changed its name upon this occasion. When Momorus and Atepomarus were dethroned by Seseroneus, in
					pursuance of the oracle's command they designed to build
					a city upon the top of the hill. But when they had laid
					the foundations, great numbers of crows with their wings
					expanded covered all the neighboring trees. Upon which
					Momorus, being a person well skilled in augury, called the
					city Lugdunum. For <hi rend="italics">lugdon</hi> in their language signifies a
					crow, and <hi rend="italics">dunum</hi>
               <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Whence probably our English word <hi rend="italics">down.</hi>
               </note> any spacious hill.&mdash;This Clitophon
					reports, in his Thirteenth Book of the Building of Cities.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="7">
            <head>VII. PACTOLUS.</head>
            <p>PACTOLUS is a river of Lydia, that washes the walls of
					Sardis, formerly called Chrysorrhoas. For Chrysorrhoas,
					the son of Apollo and Agathippe, being a mechanic artist,
					and one that only lived from hand to mouth upon his
					trade, one time in the middle of the night made bold to
					break open the treasury of Croesus; and conveying thence
					a good quantity of gold, he made a distribution of it to his
					family. But being pursued by the king's officers, when he
					saw he must be taken, he threw himself into the river
					which was afterwards from his name called Chrysorrhoas,
					and afterwards changed into that of Pactolus upon this
					occasion.</p>
            <p>Pactolus, the son of. . . and Leucothea, during the
					performance of the mysteries sacred to Venus, ravished
					Demodice his own sister, not knowing who she was; for
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.486"/>
					
					which being overwhelmed with grief, he threw himself
					into the river Chrysorrhoas, which from that time forward
					was called Pactolus, from his own name. In this river is
					found a most pure gold sand, which the force of the stream
					carries into the bosom of the Happy Gulf.</p>
            <p>Also in this river is to be found a stone which is called
					the preserver of the fields, resembling the color of silver,
					very hard to be found, in regard of its being mixed with
					the gold sand. The virtue of which is such, that the more
					wealthy Lydians buy it and lay it at the doors of their
					treasuries, by which means they preserve their treasure,
					whatever it be, safe from the seizure of pilfering hands.
					For upon the approach of thieves or robbers, the stone
					sends forth a sound like that of a trumpet. Upon which
					the thieves surprised, and believing themselves apprehended by officers, throw themselves headlong and break
					their necks; insomuch that the place where the thieves
					thus frighted come by their violent deaths is called Pactolus's prison.</p>
            <p>In this river also there grows an herb that bears a purple flower, and is called chrysopolis; by which the inhabitants of the neighboring cities try their purest gold. For
					just before they put their gold into the melting-pot, they
					touch it with this herb; at what time, if it be pure and
					unmixed, the leaves of the herb will be tinctured with the
					gold and preserve the substance of the matter; but if it
					be adulterated, they will not admit the discoloring moisture;&mdash;as Chrysermus relates in his Third Book of
					Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Tmolus, full of all
					manner of wild beasts, formerly called Carmanorion, from
					Carmanor the son of Bacchus and Alexirrhoea, who was
					killed by a wild boar as he was hunting; but afterward
					Tmolus upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Tmolus, the son of Mars and Theogone, king of Lydia,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.487"/>
					
					while he was a hunting upon Carmanorion, chanced to see
					the fair virgin Arrhippe that attended upon Diana, and fell
					passionately in love with her. And such was the heat of
					his love, that not being able to gain her by fair means, he
					resolved to vitiate her by force. She, seeing she could by
					no means escape his fury otherwise, fled to the temple of
					Diana, where the tyrant, contemning all religion, ravished
					her,&mdash;an infamy which the nymph not being able to survive immediately hanged herself. But Diana would not
					pass by so great a crime; and therefore, to be revenged
					upon the king for his irreligious insolence, she set a mad
					bull upon him, by which the king being tossed up in the
					air, and falling down upon stakes and stones, ended his
					days in torment. But Theoclymenus his son, so soon as
					he had buried his father, altered the name of the mountain, and called it Tmolus after his father's name.</p>
            <p>Upon this mountain grows a stone not unlike a pumice-stone, which is very rare to be found. This stone changes
					its color four times a day; and is to be seen only by- virgins that are not arrived at the years of understanding.
					But if marriageable virgins happen to see it, they can
					never receive any injury from those that attempt their
					chastity;&mdash;as Clitophon reports.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="8">
            <head>VIII. LYCORMAS.</head>
            <p>LYCORMAS is a river of Aetolia, formerly called Evenus
					for this reason. Idas the son of Aphareus, after he had
					ravished away by violence Marpessa, with whom he was
					passionately in love, carried her away to Pleuron, a city of
					Aetolia. This rape of his daughter Evenus could by no
					means endure, and therefore pursued after the treacherous
					ravisher, till he came to the river Lycormas. But then
					despairing to overtake the fugitive, he threw himself for
					madness into the river, which from his own name was
					called Evenus.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.488"/>
            <p>In this river grows an herb which is called sarissa, because it resembles a spear, of excellent use for those that
					are troubled with dim sight;&mdash;as Archelaus relates in his
					First Book of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies Myenus, from Myenus the son of
					Telestor and Alphesiboea; who, being beloved by his
					mother-in-law and unwilling to defile his father's bed, retired himself to the mountain Alphius. But Telestor,
					being made jealous of his wife, pursued his son into the
					wilderness; and followed him so close, that Myenus, not
					being able to escape, flung himself headlong from the top
					of the mountain, which for that reason was afterwards
					called Myenus.</p>
            <p>Upon this mountain grows a flower called the white violet, which, if you do but name the word step-dame, presently
					dies away;&mdash;as Dercyllus reports in his Third Book of
					Mountains.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="9">
            <head>IX. MAEANDER.</head>
            <p>MAEANDER is a river of Asia, formerly called the Returner. For of all rivers in the world it is the only stream
					which, taking its rise from its own fountain, seems to run
					back to its own head.</p>
            <p>It is called Maeander from Maeander, the son of Cercaphus and Anaxibia, who, waging war with the Pessinuntines, made a vow to the Mother of the Gods, that if he
					obtained the victory, he would sacrifice the first that came
					to congratulate him for his good success. Now it happened that the first that met him were his son Archelaus,
					his mother, and his sister. All which, though so nearly
					related to him, he offered in sacrifice to the satisfaction of
					his vow. But then no less grieved for what he had done,
					he cast himself into the river, which from this accident
					was afterwards called by his own name Maeander;&mdash;as
					Timolaus tells us in his First Book of Phrygian Relations.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.489"/>
					
					Agathocles the Samian also makes mention of this story,
					in his Commonwealth of Pessinus.</p>
            <p>But Demostratus of Apamea relates the story thus:
					Maeander being a second time elected general against the
					Pessinuntines, and obtaining the victory quite contrary to
					his expectation, gave to his soldiers the offerings due to
					the Mother of the Gods. At which the Goddess being
					offended, she deprived him of his reason to that degree,
					that in the height of his madness he slew both his wife
					and his son. But coming somewhat to himself and repenting of what he had done, he threw himself into the
					river, which by his name was called Maeander.</p>
            <p>In this river there is a certain stone, which by Antiphrasis is called sophron, or the sober-stone; which if you
					drop into the bosom of any man, it presently makes him
					mad to that degree as to murder his nearest relations, but
					having once atoned the Mother of the Gods, he is presently restored to his wits;&mdash;as Damaratus testifies in his
					Third Book of Rivers. And Archelaus makes mention of
					the same in his First Book of Stones.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Sipylus, so called
					from Sipylus the son of Agenor and Dioxippe. For he
					having killed his mother by mistake, and being haunted
					by the Furies, retired to the Ceraunian mountain, and
					there hanged himself for grief. After which, by the
					providence of the Gods, the mountain was called Sipylus.</p>
            <p>In this mountain grows a stone that resembles a cylinder, which when children that are obedient to their
					parents find, they lay it up in the temple of the Mother
					of the Gods. Nor do they ever transgress out of impiety;
					but reverence their parents, and are obedient to their
					superior relations;&mdash;as Agatharchides the Samian relates
					in his Fourth Book of Stones, and Demaratus in his
					Fourth Book of Phrygia.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.490"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="10">
            <head>X. MARSYAS.</head>
            <p>MARSYAS is a river of Phrygia, flowing by the city
					Celaenae, and formerly called the fountain of Midas for
					this reason. Midas, king of Phrygia, travelling in the
					remoter parts of the country, and wanting water, stamped
					upon the ground; and there presently appeared a golden
					fountain. But the water proving gold, and both he and
					his soldiers being ready to perish for thirst, he invoked the
					compassion of Bacchus, who listening to his prayers supplied him with water. The Phrygians having by this
					means quenched their thirst, Midas named the river that
					issued from the spring the Fountain of Midas. Afterwards
					it was called Marsyas, upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Marsyas being overcome and flayed by Apollo, certain
					Satyrs are said to have sprung from the stream of his
					blood; as also a river bearing the name of Marsyas;&mdash;as
					Alexander Cornelius recites in his Third Book of Phrygian
					Relations.</p>
            <p>But Euemeridas the Cnidian tells the story after this
					manner. It happened that the wine-bag which was made
					of Marsyas's skin, being corroded by time and carried
					away negligently by the wind, fell at last from the land
					into Midas's well; and driving along with the stream, was
					taken up by a fisherman. At what time Pisistratus the
					Lacedaemonian, being commanded by the oracle to build
					near the place where the relics of the Satyr were found,
					reflected upon the accident, and in obedience to the oracle
					having built a fair city, called it Noricum, which in the
					Phrygian language signifies a wine-bag.</p>
            <p>In this river grows an herb called the pipe, which being
					moved in the wind yields a melodious sound;&mdash;as Dercyllus reports in his First Book of Satyrics.</p>
            <p>Near to this river also lies the mountain Berecyntus,
					deriving its name from Berecyntus, the first priest to the
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.491"/>
					
					Mother of the Gods. Upon this mountain is found a
					stone which is called machaera, very much resembling
					iron; which if any one happens to light upon while the
					solemnities of the Mother of the Gods are performing, he
					presently runs mad;&mdash;as Agatharchides reports in his
					Phrygian Relations.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="11">
            <head>XI. STRYMON.</head>
            <p>STRYMON is a river of Thrace, that flows along by the
					city Edonis. It was formerly called Palaestinus, from
					Palaestinus the son of Neptune. For he being at war
					with his neighbors, and seized with a violent sickness,
					sent his son Haliacmon to be general of his army; who,
					rashly giving battle to his enemies, was slain in the fight.
					The tidings of which misfortune being brought to Palaestinus, he privately withdrew himself from his guards, and
					in the desperation of his grief flung himself into the
					River Conozus, which from that accident was afterwards
					called Palaestinus. But as for Strymon, he was the son of
					Mars and Helice; and hearing that his son Rhesus was
					slain, he flung himself into the river Palaestinus, which
					was after that called Strymon, by his own name.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a stone which is called pausilypus,
					or the grief-easing stone. This stone if any one find who
					is oppressed with grief, he shall presently be eased of his
					sorrow;&mdash;as Jason of Byzantium relates in his Thracian
					Histories.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lie the mountains Rhodope and Haemus. These being brother and sister, and both falling in
					love with each other, the one was so presumptuous as to
					call his sister his Juno, the other to call her brother her
					Jupiter; which so offended the Deities, that they changed
					them into mountains bearing their own names.</p>
            <p>In these two mountains grow certain stones, which are
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.492"/>
					
					called philadelphi, or the loving brethren. These stones
					are of a crow-color, and resembling human shape, and if
					they chance to be named when they are separated one
					from another, they presently and separately, as they lie,
					dissolve and waste away;&mdash;as Thrasyllus the Mendesian
					testifies in his Third Book of Stones, but more accurately
					in his Thracian Histories.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="12">
            <head>XII. SAGARIS.</head>
            <p>SAGARIS is a river of Phrygia, formerly called Xerobates
					because in the summer time it was generally dry. But it
					was called Sagaris for this reason: Sagaris, the son of
					Myndon and Alexirrhoe, contemning and slighting the
					mysteries of the Mother of the Gods, frequently affronted and
					derided her priests the Galli. At which the Goddess heinously offended, struck him with madness to that degree,
					that in one of his raging fits he flung himself into the
					river Xerobates, which from that time forward was called
					Sagaris.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a stone, which is called autoglyphus,
					that is, naturally engraved; for it is found with the Mother
					of the Gods by nature engraved upon it. This stone,
					which is rarely to be found, if any of the Galli or gelded
					priests happen to light upon, he makes no wonder at it,
					but undauntedly brooks the sight of a preternatural action;&mdash;as Aretazes reports in his Phrygian Relations.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Ballenaeus, which
					in the Phrygian language signifies <hi rend="italics">royal;</hi> so called from
					Ballenaeus, the son of Ganymede and Medesigiste, who
					perceiving his father almost wasted with a consumption,
					instituted the Ballenaean festival, observed among the natives to this day.</p>
            <p>In this river is to be found a stone called aster, which
					from the latter end of autumn shines at midnight like fire.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.493"/>
					
					It is called in the language of the natives <hi rend="italics">ballen,</hi> which
					being interpreted signifies a king;&mdash;as Hermesianax the
					Cyprian affirms in his Second Book of his Phrygian Relations.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="13">
            <head>XIII. SCAMANDER.</head>
            <p>SCAMANDER is a river of Troas, which was formerly called
					Xanthus, but changed its name upon this occasion. Scamander, the son of Corybas and Demodice, having suddenly beheld the ceremonies while the mysteries of Rhea were
					solemnizing, immediately ran mad, and being hurried away
					by his own fury to the River Xanthus, flung himself into
					the stream, which from thence was called Scamander.</p>
            <p>In this river grows an herb like a vetch, that bears a
					cod with berries rattling in it when they are ripe; whence
					it derived the name of <hi rend="italics">sistrum,</hi> or the <hi rend="italics">rattle;</hi> whoever
					has this herb in possession fears no apparition nor the
					sight of any God;&mdash;as Demostratus writes in his. Second
					Book of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Ida, formerly Gargarus; on the top of which stand the altars of Jupiter
					and of the Mother of the Gods. But it was called Ida
					upon this occasion. Aegesthius, who descended from Jupiter, falling passionately in love with the nymph Ida, obtained her good-will, and begat the Idaean Dactyli, or
					priests of the Mother of the Gods. After which, Ida
					running mad in the temple of Rhea, Aegesthius, in remembrance of the love which he bare her, called the mountain by her name.</p>
            <p>In this mountain grows a stone called cryphius, as being never to be found but when the mysteries of the Gods
					are solemnizing;&mdash;as Heraclitus the Sicyonian writes in
					his Second Book of Stones.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.494"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="14">
            <head>XIV. TANAIS.</head>
            <p>TANAIS is a river of Scythia, formerly called the Amazonian river, because the Amazons bathed themselves
					therein; but it altered its name upon this occasion. Tanais, the son of Berossus and Lysippe, one of the Amazons, became a vehement hater of the female sex, and
					looking upon marriage as ignominious and dishonorable,
					applied himself wholly to martial affairs. This so offended
					Venus, that she caused him to fall passionately in love
					with his own mother. True it is, at first he withstood the
					force of his passion; but finding he could not vanquish the
					fatal necessity of yielding to divine impulse, and yet desirous to preserve his respect and piety towards his mother,
					he flung himself into the Amazonian river, which was afterwards called Tanais, from the name of the young man.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a plant which is called halinda, resembling a colewort; which the inhabitants bruising, and
					anointing their bodies with the juice of it, find themselves
					in a condition better able to endure the extremity of the
					cold; and for that reason, in their own language they call
					it Berossus's oil.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a stone not unlike to crystal, resembling the shape of a man with a crown upon his head.
					Whoever finds the stone when the king dies, and has it
					ready against the time that the people meet upon the
					banks of the river to choose a new sovereign, is presently
					elected king, and receives the sceptre of the deceased
					prince;&mdash;as Ctesiphon relates in his Third Book of
					Plants; and Aristobulus gives us the same account in his
					First Book of Stones.</p>
            <p>Near to this river also lies a mountain, in the language
					of the natives called Brixaba, which signifies the <hi rend="italics">forehead
						of a ram.</hi> And it was so called upon this occasion.
					Phryxus having lost his sister Helle near the Euxine Sea,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.495"/>
					
					and; as Nature in justice required, being extremely troubled for his loss, retired to the top of a certain hill to disburden himself of his sorrow. At which time certain
					barbarians espying him, and mounting up the hill with
					their arms in their hands, a gold-fleeced ram leaping out
					of a thicket, and seeing the multitude coming, with articulate language and the voice of a man, awakened Phryxus,
					who was fast asleep, and taking him upon his back, carried him to Colchis. From this accident it was that the
					mountainous promontory was called the ram's forehead.</p>
            <p>In this mountain grows an herb, by the barbarians called
					phryxa (which being interpreted signifies <hi rend="italics">hating the
						wicked</hi>), not unlike our common rue. If the son of a former mother have it in his possession, he can never be injured by his step-dame. It chiefly grows near the place
					which is called Boreas's Den, and being gathered, is colder
					than snow. But if any step-dame be forming a design
					against her son-in-law, it sets itself on fire and sends forth
					a bright flame. By which means they who are thus warned
					avoid the danger they are in;&mdash;as Agatho the Samian
					testifies in his Second Book of Scythian Relations.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="15">
            <head>XV. THERMODON.</head>
            <p>THERMODON is a river of Scythia, deriving its name from
					this accident. It was formerly called Crystallus, as being
					often frozen in the summer, the situation of the place producing this effect. But that name was altered upon this
					occasion. . . .
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="16">
            <head>XVI. NILE.</head>
            <p>THE Nile is a river in Egypt, that runs by the city of
					Alexandria. It was formerly called Melas, from Melas the
					son of Neptune; but afterwards it was called Aegyptus
					upon this occasion. Aegyptus, the son of Vulcan and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.496"/>
					
					Leucippe, was formerly king of the country, between
					whom and his own subjects happened a civil war; on
					which account the river Nile not increasing, the Egyptians
					were oppressed with famine. Upon which the oracle made
					answer, that the land should be again blessed with plenty,
					if the king would sacrifice his daughter to atone the
					anger of the Gods. Upon which the king, though greatly
					afflicted in his mind, gave way to the public good, and suffered his daughter to be led to the altar. But so soon as
					she was sacrificed, the king, not able to support the burden
					of his grief, threw himself into the river Melas, which
					after that was called Aegyptus. But then it was called
					Nilus upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Garmathone, queen of Egypt, having lost her son Chrysochoas while he was yet very young, with all her servants
					and friends most bitterly bemoaned her loss. At what
					time Isis appearing to her, she surceased her sorrow for a
					while, and putting on the countenance of a feigned gratitude, kindly entertained the goddess. She, willing to make
					a suitable return to the queen for the piety which she
					expressed in her reception, persuaded Osiris to bring back
					her son from the subterranean regions. When Osiris undertook to do this, at the importunity of his wife, Cerberus
					&mdash;whom some call the Terrible&mdash;barked so loud, that
					Nilus, Garmathone's husband, struck with a sudden frenzy,
					threw himself into the river Aegyptus, which from thence
					was afterwards called Nilus.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a stone, not unlike to a bean, which
					so soon as any dog happens to see, he ceases to bark. It
					also expels the evil spirit out of those that are possessed,
					if held to the nostrils of the party afflicted.</p>
            <p>There are other stones which are found in this river,
					called kollotes, which the swallows picking up against the
					time that Nilus overflows, build up the wall which is called
					the Chelidonian wall, which restrains the inundation of
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.497"/>
					
					the water and will not suffer the country to be injured
					by the fury of the flood;&mdash;as Thrasyllus tells us in his
					Relation of Egypt.</p>
            <p>Upon this river lies the mountain Argyllus, so called for
					this reason.</p>
            <p>Jupiter in the heat of his amorous desires ravished away
					the Nymph Arge from Lyctus, a city of Crete, and then
					carried her to a mountain of Egypt called Argillus, and
					there begat a son, whom he named Dionysus (or Bacchus);
					who, growing up to years of manhood, in honor of his
					mother called the hill Argillus; and then mustering together an army of Pans and Satyrs, first conquered the
					Indian's, and then subduing Spain, left Pan behind him
					there, the chief commander and governor of those places.
					Pan by his own name called that country Pania, which was
					afterward by his posterity called Spania;&mdash;as Sosthenes
					relates in the Thirteenth Book of Iberian Relations.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="17">
            <head>XVII. EUROTAS.</head>
            <p>HIMERUS, the son of the Nymph Taygete and Lacedaemon, through the anger of offended Venus, at a revelling
					that lasted all night, deflowered his sister Cleodice, not
					knowing what he did. But the next day being informed
					of the truth of the matter, he laid it so to heart, that
					through excess of grief he flung himself into the river
					Marathon, which from thence was called Himeros; but
					after that Eurotas, upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>The Lacedaemonians being at war with the Athenians,
					and staying for the full moon, Eurotas their captain-general, despising all religion, would needs fight his enemies,.
					though at the same time he was warned by thunder and'
					lightning. However, having lost his army, the ignominy
					of his loss so incessantly perplexed him, that he flung himself into the river Himerus, which from that accident was
					afterwards called Eurotas.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.498"/>
            <p>In this river grows a stone which is shaped like a helmet, called thrasydeilos, or <hi rend="italics">rash and timorous.</hi> For if it
					hears a trumpet sound, it leaps toward the bank of the
					river; but if you do but name the Athenians, it presently
					sinks to the bottom of the water. Of these stones there
					are not a few which are consecrated and laid up in the
					temple of Minerva of the Brazen House;&mdash;as Nicanor
					the Samian relates in his Second Book of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Taygetus, deriving
					its name from the nymph Taygete; who, after Jupiter had
					deflowered her, being overcome by grief, ended her days
					by hanging at the summit of the mountain Amyclaeus,
					which from thence was called Taygetus.</p>
            <p>Upon this mountain grows a plant called Charisia, which
					the women at the beginning of the spring tied about their
					necks, to make themselves more passionately beloved by
					men;&mdash;as Cleanthes reports in his First Book of Mountains. But Sosthenes the Cnidian is more accurate in the
					relation of these things, from whom Hermogenes borrowed
					the subject of his writing.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>XVIII. INACHUS.</head>
            <p>INACHUS is a river in the territories of Argos, formerly
					called Carmanor. Afterwards Haliacmon, for this reason.</p>
            <p>Haliacmon, a Tirynthian by birth, while he kept sheep
					upon the mountain Coccygium, happened against his will
					to see Jupiter and Rhea sporting together; for which
					being struck mad, and hurried by the violence of the frenzy, he flung himself into the river Carmanor, which after
					that was called Haliacmon. Afterwards it was called Inachus upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Inachus, the son of Oceanus, after that Jupiter had deflowered his daughter Io, pursued the Deity close at the
					heels, abusing and cursing him all the way as he went.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.499"/>
					
					Which so offended Jupiter, that he sent Tisiphone, one of
					the Furies, who haunted and plagued him to that degree,
					that he flung himself into the river Haliacmon, afterwards
					called by his own name Inachus.</p>
            <p>In this river grows an herb called cynura, not unlike
					our common rue, which the women that desire to miscarry without any danger lay upon their navels, being first
					steeped in wine.</p>
            <p>There is also found in this river a certain stone, not
					unlike a beryl, which in the hands of those who intend to
					bear false witness will grow black. Of these stones there
					are many laid up in the temple of Juno Prosymnaea;&mdash;as
					Timotheus relates in his Argolica, and Agatho the Samian
					in his Second Book of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Agathocles the Milesian, in his History of Rivers, also
					adds, that Inachus for his impiety was thunderstruck by
					Jupiter, and so the river dried up.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lie the mountains Mycenae, Apesantus, Coccygium, and Athenaeum; so called for these
					reasons. Apesantus was first called Selenaeus. For Juno,
					resolving to be revenged upon Hercules, called the moon
					(Selene) to her assistance, who by the help of her magical
					charms filled a large chest full of foam and froth, out of
					which sprang an immense lion; which Iris binding with
					her own girdle carried to the mountain Opheltium, where
					the lion killed and tore in pieces Apesantus, one of the
					shepherds belonging to that place. And from that accident, by the will of the Gods, the hill was called Apesantus;&mdash;as Demodocus writes in his First Book of the History of Hercules.</p>
            <p>In this river grows an herb called selene, with the froth
					of which, being gathered in the spring, the shepherds
					anoint their feet, and keep them from being bit or stung
					by any creeping vermin.</p>
            <p>Mycenae was formerly called Argion, from the many-eyed
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.500"/>
					
					Argos; but afterwards the name was changed upon this
					occasion.
					When Perseus had slain Medusa, Stheno and Euryale,
					sisters to her that was killed, pursued him as a murderer.
					But coming to this hill and despairing to overtake him, out
					of that extreme love which they had for their sister they
					made such a bellowing (<foreign lang="greek">mukhqmo/s</foreign>), that the natives from
					thence called the top of the mountain Mycenae;&mdash;as Ctesias
					the Ephesian relates in his First Book of the Acts of Perseus. But Chrysermus the Corinthian relates the story
					thus in the First Book of his Peloponnesiacs. For he says
					that, when Perseus was carried aloft in the air and lit upon
					this mountain, he lost the chape of his scabbard. At what
					time this same Gorgophonos (or Gorgon-slayer), king of
					the Epidaurians, being expelled his kingdom, received this
					answer upon his consulting the oracle, that he should visit
					all the cities of the Argolic territory, and that where he
					found the chape of a scabbard (called in Greek <foreign lang="greek">mukh/s</foreign>), he
					should build a city. Thereupon coming to the mountain
					Argium, and finding there an ivory scabbard, he built a
					city, and from the accident called it Mycenae.</p>
            <p>In this mountain there is found a stone, which is called
					corybas, of a crow-color, which he that finds and wears
					about him shall never be afraid of any monstrous apparitions. As for the mountain Apesantus, this may be added,
					that Apesantus, the son of Acrisius, as he was a hunting
					in that place, chanced to tread upon a venomous serpent,
					which occasioned his death. Whom when his father had
					buried, in memory of his son he named the hill Apesantus,
					which before was called Selinuntius.</p>
            <p>The mountain Coccygium derived its name from this
					accident. Jupiter falling desperately in love with his sister Juno, and having vanquished her by his importunity,
					begat a male child. From whence the mountain, before
					called Lyrceum, was named Coccygium;&mdash;as Agathonymus
					relates in his Persis.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.501"/>
            <p>In this mountain grows a tree, which is called paliurus;
					upon the boughs of which whatever fowl happens to perch,
					it is presently entangled as it were with bird-lime, and cannot stir; only the cuckoo it lets go free, without any harm;
					&mdash;as Ctesiphon testifies in his First Book of Trees.</p>
            <p>As for the mountain Athenaeum, it derives its name
					from Minerva. For after the destruction of Troy, Diomede returning to Argos, ascended the mountain Ceraunius,
					and there erecting a temple to Minerva, called the mountain Athenaeum from her name Athena.</p>
            <p>Upon the top of this mountain grows a root like to that
					of rue, which if any woman unwarily taste of, she presently
					runs mad. This root is called Adrastea;&mdash;as Plesimachus
					writes in his Second Book of the Returns of the Heroes.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>XIX. ALPHEUS.</head>
            <p>APHEUS is a river of Arcadia, running by the walls of
					Pisa, a city of Olympia. It was formerly called Stymphelus,
					from Stymphelus the son of Mars and Dormothea; who,
					having lost his brother Alcmaeon, threw himself for grief
					into the river Nyctimus, for that reason called Stymphelus.
					Afterwards it was called Alpheus upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Alpheus, one of those that derive their descent from the
					Sun, contending with his brother Cercaphus about the
					kingdom, slew him. For which being chased away and
					pursued by the Furies, he flung himself into the river
					Nyctimus, which after that was called Alpheus.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a plant which is called cenchritis,
					resembling a honey-comb, the decoction of which, being
					given by the physicians to those that are mad, cures them
					of their frenzy;&ndash;as Ctesias relates in his First Book of
					Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Cronium, so called
					upon this occasion. After the Giants' war, Saturn, to avoid
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.502"/>
					
					the threats of Jupiter, fled to the mountain Cturus, and
					called it Cronium from his own name. Where after he
					had absconded for some time, he took his opportunity, and
					retired to Caucasus in Scythia.</p>
            <p>In this mountain is found a stone, which is called the
					cylinder, upon this occasion. For as oft as Jupiter either
					thunders or lightens, so often this stone through fear rolls
					down from the top of the mountain;&mdash;as Dercyllus writes
					in his First Book of Stones.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="20">
            <head>XX. EUPHRATES.</head>
            <p>EUPHRATES is a river of Parthia, washing the walls of
					Babylon, formerly called Medus from Medus the son of
					Artaxeres. He, in the heat of his lust, having ravished
					away and deflowered Roxane, and finding he was sought
					after by the king, in order to be brought to punishment,
					threw himself into the river Xaranda, which from thenceforward was called by his name Medus. Afterwards it
					was called Euphrates upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Euphrates the son of Arandacus, finding his son Axurta
					abed with his mother, and thinking him to be some one of
					the citizens, provoked by his jealousy, drew his sword and
					nailed him to the bed. But perceiving himself the author
					of what could not be recalled, he flung himself for grief
					into the river Medus, which from that time forward was
					called by his name Euphrates.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a stone called aetites, which midwives applying to the navels of women that are in hard
					labor, it causes them to bring forth with little pain.</p>
            <p>In the same river also there grows an herb which is
					called axalla, which signifies heat. This herb they that
					are troubled with quartan-agues apply to their breasts,
					and are presently delivered from the fit;&mdash;as Chrysermus
					writes in his Thirteenth Book of Rivers.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.503"/>
            <p>Near this river lies the mountain Drimylus, where grows
					a stone not unlike a sardonyx, worn by kings and princes
					upon their diadems, and greatly available against dimness
					of sight;&ndash;as Nicias Mallotes writes in his Book of
					Stones.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="21">
            <head>XXI. CAICUS.</head>
            <p>CAICUS is a river of Mysia, formerly called Astraeus,
					from Astraeus the son of Neptune. For he, in the height
					of Minerva's nocturnal solemnities having deflowered his
					sister by a mistake, took a ring at the same time from her
					finger; by which when he understood the next day the
					error which he had committed, for grief he threw himself
					headlong into the river Adurus, which from thence was
					called Astraeus. Afterwards it came to be called Caicus
					upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Caicus, the son of Hermes and Ocyrrhoe the Nymph,
					having slain Timander one of the noblemen of the country,
					and fearing the revenge of his relations, flung himself into
					the river Astraeus, which from that accident was called
					Caicus.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a sort of poppy, which instead of
					fruit bears stones. Of these there are some which are
					black and shaped like harps, which the Mysians throw
					upon their ploughed lands; and if the stones lie still in
					the place where they are thrown, it is a sign of a barren
					year; but if they fly away like so many locusts, they prognosticate a plentiful harvest.</p>
            <p>In the same river also grows an herb which is called
					elipharmacus, which the physicians apply to such as are
					troubled with immoderate fluxes of blood, as having a
					peculiar virtue to stop the orifices of the veins;&mdash;according to the relation of Timagoras in his First Book of
					Rivers.</p>
            <p>Adjoining to the banks of this river lies the mountain
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.504"/>
					
					Teuthras, so called from Teuthras king of the Mysians;
					who in pursuance of his sport, as he was a hunting, ascending the hill Thrasyllus and seeing a monstrous wild boar,
					followed him close with the rest of his train. On the other
					side, the boar, to prevent the hunters, like a suppliant fled
					to the temple of Orthosian Diana, into which when the
					hunters were about to force their entrance, the boar in
					articulate words cried out, Spare, O king, the nursling of
					the Goddess. However, Teuthras, exalted with his good
					success, killed the poor boar. At which Diana was so
					highly offended, that she restored the boar to life, but
					struck the offender with scurf and madness. Which affliction the king not enduring betook himself to the tops
					of the mountains. But his mother Leucippe, understanding what had befallen her son, ran to the forest, taking
					along with her the soothsayer Polyidus, the son of Coeranus; by whom being informed of all the several circumstances of the matter, by many sacrifices she at last atoned
					the anger of the Goddess, and having quite recovered and
					cured her son, erected an altar to Orthosian Diana, and
					caused a golden boar to be made with a man's face.
					Which to this day, if pursued by the hunters, enters the
					temple, and speaks with the voice of a man the word
					<q direct="unspecified">spare.</q> Thus Teuthras, being restored to his former
					health, called the mountain by his own name Teuthras.</p>
            <p>In this mountain grows a stone called antipathes (or the
					resister), which is of excellent virtue to cure scabs and
					leprosies, being powdered and mixed with wine;&mdash;as
					Ctesias the Cnidian tells us in his Second Book of Mountains.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="22">
            <head>XXII. ACHELOUS.</head>
            <p>ACHELOUS is a river of Aetolia, formerly called Thestius.
					This Thestius was the son of Mars and Pisidice, who upon
					some domestic discontent travelled as far as Sicyon, where
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.505"/>
					
					after he had resided for some time, he returned to his
					native home. But finding there his son Calydon and his
					mother both upon the bed together, believing him to be an
					adulterer, he slew his own child by a mistake. But when
					he beheld the unfortunate and unexpected fact he had
					committed, he threw himself into the river Axenos, which
					from thence was afterwards called Thestius. And after
					that, it was called Achelous upon this occasion.</p>
            <p>Achelous, the son of Oceanus and the Nymph Nais,
					having deflowered his daughter Cletoria by mistake, flung
					himself for grief into the river Thestius, which then by
					his own name was called Achelous.</p>
            <p>In this river grows an herb, which they call zaclon, very
					much resembling wool; this if you bruise and cast into
					wine, it becomes water, and preserves the smell but not
					the virtues of the wine.</p>
            <p>In the same river also is found a certain stone of a
					mixed black and lead color, called linurgus from the
					effect; for if you throw it upon a linen cloth, by a certain
					affectionate union it assumes the form of the linen, and
					turns white;&mdash;as Antisthenes relates in the Third Book
					of his Meleagris, though Diocles the Rhodian more accurately tells us the same thing in his Aetolics.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Calydon, so called
					from Calydon, the son of Mars and Astynome; for that
					he, by an accident having seen Diana bathing herself, was
					transformed into a rock; and the mountain which before
					was named Gyrus was afterwards by the providence of the
					Gods called Calydon.</p>
            <p>Upon this mountain grows an herb called myops. This
					if any one steep in water and wash his face with it, he
					shall lose his sight, but upon his atoning Diana, he shall
					recover it again;&mdash;as Dercyllus writes in his Third Book
					of Aetolics.
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.506"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="23">
            <head>XXIII. ARAXES.</head>
            <p>ARAXES is a river in Armenia, so called from Araxus the
					son of Pylus. For he, contending with his grandfather Arbelus for the empire, shot him with an arrow. For which
					being haunted by the Furies, he threw himself into the
					river Bactros, for that reason called Araxes;&mdash;as Ctesiphon testifies in his First Book of the Persian Affairs.
					Araxes, king of the Armenians, being at war with his
					neighbors the Persians, before they came to a battle, was
					told by the oracle that he should win the victory if he
					sacrificed to the Gods two of the most noble virgins in his
					kingdom. Now he, out of his paternal affection to his
					children, spared his own daughters, and caused two lovely
					virgins, the daughters of one of his nobility, to be laid
					upon the altar. Which Mnesalces, the father of the victims, laying to heart, for a time concealed his indignation;
					but afterwards, observing his opportunity, he killed both
					the king's daughters, and then leaving his native soil fled
					into Scythia. Which when Araxes understood, for grief
					he threw himself into the river Halmus, which then was
					altered and called Araxes.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a plant which is called araxa, which
					in the language of the natives signifies a virgin-hater.
					For that if it happen to be found by any virgin, it falls a
					bleeding and dies away.</p>
            <p>In the same river there is also found a stone of a black
					color, called sicyonus. This stone, when the oracle advises
					the sacrificing of a human victim, is laid upon the altar of
					the mischief-diverting Gods. And then, no sooner does
					the priest touch it with his knife, but it sends forth a
					stream of blood; at what time the superstitious sacrificers
					retire, and with howlings and loud ohoning carry the stone
					to the temple;&mdash;as Dorotheus the Chaldaean relates in
					his Second Book of Stones.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.507"/>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Diorphus, so called
					from Diorphus the son of the Earth, of whom this story is
					reported. Mithras desirous to have a son, yet hating
					woman-kind, lay with a stone, till he had heated it to that
					degree that the stone grew big, and at the prefixed time
					was delivered of a son, called Diorphus; who, growing up
					and contending with Mars for courage and stoutness, was
					by him slain, and by the providence of the Gods was
					transformed into the mountain which was called Diorphus
					by his name.</p>
            <p>In this mountain grows a tree, not unlike a pomegranate-tree, which yields plenty of apples, in taste like grapes.
					Now if any one gather the ripest of this fruit, and do but
					name Mars while he holds it in his hand, it will presently
					grow green again;&mdash;as Ctesiphon witnesses in his Thirteenth Book of Trees.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="24">
            <head>XXIV. TIGRIS.</head>
            <p>TIGRIS is a river of Armenia flowing into Araxes and the
					lake of Arsacis, formerly called Sollax, which signifies
					running and carried downward. It was called Tigris upon
					this occasion.</p>
            <p>Bacchus, through the design of Juno running mad, wandered over sea and land, desirous to be quit of his distemper. At length coming into Armenia, and not being able
					to pass the river before-mentioned, he called upon Jupiter;
					who, listening to his prayers, sent him a tiger that carried
					him safely over the water. In remembrance of which
					accident, he called the river Tigris;&mdash;as Theophilus relates in his First Book of Stones. But Hermesianax the
					Cyprian tells the story thus:&mdash;</p>
            <p>Bacchus falling in love with the Nymph Alphesiboea,
					and being able to vanquish her neither with presents nor
					entreaties, turned himself into the shape of the river Tigris,
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.508"/>
					
					 and overcoming his beloved by fear, took her away,
					and carrying her over the river, begat a son whom he called
					Medus; who growing up in years, in remembrance of the
					accident he called the river by the name of Tigris;&mdash;as
					Aristonymus relates in his Third Book . . .</p>
            <p>In this river a stone is to be found, called myndan, very
					white; which whoever possesses shall never be hurt by
					wild beasts;&mdash;as Leo of Byzantium relates in his Third
					Book of Rivers.</p>
            <p>Near to this river lies the mountain Gauran; so called
					from Gauran the son of the satrap Roxanes; who, being
					extremely religious and devout towards the Gods, received this reward of his piety, that of all the Persians he
					only lived three hundred years; and dying at last without
					being ever afflicted with any disease, was buried upon the
					top of the mountain Gauran, where he had a sumptuous
					monument erected to his memory. Afterwards, by the
					providence of the Gods, the name of the mountain was
					changed to that of Mausorus.</p>
            <p>In this mountain grows an herb, which is like to wild
					barley. This herb the natives heat over the fire, and
					anointing themselves with the oil of it, are never sick, till
					the necessity of dying overtakes them;&mdash;as Sostratus
					writes in his First Collection of Fabulous History.
					
				</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="chapter" n="25">
            <head>XXV. INDUS.</head>
            <p>INDUS is a liver in India, flowing with a rapid violence
					into the country of the fish-devourers. It was first called
					Mausolus, from Mausolus the son of the Sun, but changed
					its name for this reason.</p>
            <p>At the time when the mysteries of Bacchus were solemnized and the people were earnest at their devotion, Indus,
					one of the chief of the young nobility, by force deflowered
					Damasalcidas, the daughter of Oxyalcus the king of the
					country, as she was carrying the sacred basket; for which
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.509"/>
					
					being sought for by the tyrant, in order to bring him to
					condign punishment, for fear he threw himself into the
					river Mausolus, which from that accident was afterwards
					called Indus.</p>
            <p>In this river grows a certain stone called . . . which if
					a virgin carry about her, she need never be afraid of being
					deflowered.</p>
            <p>In the same river also grows an herb, not unlike to
					bugloss. Which is an excellent remedy against the king's evil, being administered to the patient in warm water;&mdash;
					as Clitophon the Rhodian reports in his First Book of Indian Relations.</p>
            <p>Near to this mountain lies the mountain Lilaeus, so
					called from Lilaeus a shepherd; who, being very superstitious and a worshipper of the Moon alone, always performed her mysteries in the dead time of the night. Which
					the rest of the Gods taking for a great dishonor, sent two
					monstrous lions that tore him in pieces. Upon which
					the Moon turned her adorer into a mountain of the same
					name.</p>
            <p>In this mountain a stone is found which is called clitoris,
					of a very black color, which the natives wear for ornament's sake in their ears;&mdash;as Aristotle witnesses in his
					Fourth Book of Rivers.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>