<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="work">Adversus Colotem</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="editor">Goodwin</editor>&responsibility;&fund.NEH;</titleStmt>
         <extent>About 100Kb</extent>&Perseus.publish;<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title>Plutarch's Morals.</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Translated from the Greek by several hands. Corrected and revised	by</resp>
                     <name>William W. Goodwin, PH. D.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
                     <date>1874</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>--></encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="en">English</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>GRC</name>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item/>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="tlg-0007.140">
      <body>
         <head>Against Colotes, the disciple and favorite of Epicurus.</head>
         <pb id="v.5.p.338"/>
         <div1 type="section" n="1">
            <p>Colotes, whom Epicurus was wont diminutively and
				by way of familiarity or fondness, to call Colotaras and
				Colotarion, composed, O Saturninus, and published a little
				book which he entitled, <q direct="unspecified">That according to the opinions
					of the other philosophers one cannot so much as live.</q>
				This he dedicated to King Ptolemy. Now I suppose that
				it will not be unpleasant for you to read, when set down in
				writing, what came into my mind to speak against this
				Colotes, since I know you to be a lover of all elegant and
				honest treatises, and particularly of such as regard the
				science of antiquity, and to esteem the bearing in memory
				and having (as much as possible may be) in hand the discourses of the ancient sages to be the most royal of all
				studies and exercises.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="2">
            <p>Not long since therefore, as this book was reading,
				Aristodemus of Aegium, a familiar friend of ours (whom
				you well know to be one of the Academy, and not a mere
				thyrsus-bearer, but one of the most frantic celebrators of
				Plato's orgies),<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Plato, Phaed. p. 69 C, and Stallbaum's note. Here the proverb occurs,&mdash;
					<foreign lang="greek">*narqhkofo/roi me\n polloi\, *ba/kxoi de/ te pau=roi,</foreign> 
                  <hi rend="italics">the thrysus-bearers are many, but the true
						priests of Bacchus are few.</hi> (G.)</note> did, I know not how, keep himself contrary to his custom very still all the while, and patiently
				gave ear to it even to the end. But the reading was scarce
				well over, when he said: Well then, whom shall we cause
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.339"/>
				
				to rise up and fight against this man, in defence of the
				philosophers For I am not of Nestor's opinion, who,
				when the most valiant of those nine warriors that presented themselves to enter into combat was to be chosen,
				committed the election to the fortune of a lot.</p>
            <p>Yet, answered I, you see he so disposed himself in
					reference to the lot, that the choice might pass according
					to the arbitrament of the wisest man;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>And th' lot drawn from the helmet, as they wished,
						</l>
                     <l>On Ajax fell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>But yet since you command me to make the election,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>How can I think a better choice to make
						</l>
                     <l>Than the divine Ulysses?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. VII. 182; X. 243.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Consider therefore, and be well advised, in what manner
					you will chastise this man.</p>
            <p>But you know, replied Aristodemus, that Plato, when
					highly offended with his boy that waited on him, would
					not himself beat him, but requested Speusippus to do it
					for him, saying that he himself was angry. As much
					therefore may I say to you; Take this fellow to you, and
					treat him as you please; for I am in a fit of choler.</p>
            <p>When therefore all the rest of the company desired me
					to undertake this office; I must then, said I, speak, since
					it is your pleasure. But I am afraid that I also shall
					seem more vehemently transported than is fitting against
					this book, in the defending and maintaining Socrates
					against the rudeness, scurrility, and insolence of this man;
					who, because Socrates affirmed himself to know nothing
					certainly, instead of bread (as one would say) presents
					him hay, as if he were a beast, and asks him why he puts
					meat into his mouth and not into his ear. And yet perhaps some would make but a laughing matter of this, considering the mildness and gentleness of Socrates; <q direct="unspecified">but
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.340"/>
						
						for the whole host of the Greeks,</q> that is, of the other
					philosophers, amongst which are Democritus, Plato, Stilpo,
					Empedocles, Parmenides, and Melissus, who have been
					basely traduced and reviled by him, it were not only a
					shame to be silent, but even a sacrilege in the least point
					to forbear or recede from freedom of speech in their
					behalf, who have advanced philosophy to that honor and
					reputation it has gotten.</p>
            <p>And our parents indeed have, with the assistance of the
					Gods, given us our life; but to live well comes to us from
					reason, which we have learned from the philosophers, which
					favors law and justice, and restrains our concupiscence.
					Now to live well is to live sociably, friendly, temperately,
					and justly; of all which conditions they leave us not one,
					who cry out that man's sovereign good lies in his belly,
					and that they would not purchase all the virtues together
					at the expense of a cracked farthing, if pleasure were
					totally and on every side removed from them. And in
					their discourses concerning the soul and the Gods, they
					hold that the soul perishes when it is separated from the
					body, and that the Gods concern not themselves in our
					affairs. Thus the Epicureans reproach the other philosophers, that by their wisdom they bereave man of his life;
					whilst the others on the contrary accuse them of teaching
					men to live degenerately and like beasts.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="3">
            <p>Now these things are scattered here and there in the
				writings of Epicurus, and dispersed through all his philosophy. But this Colotes, by having extracted from them
				certain pieces and fragments of discourses, destitute of any
				arguments whatever to render them credible and intelligible, has composed his book, being like a shop or cabinet
				of monsters and prodigies; as you better know than any one
				else, because you have always in your hands the works of
				the ancients. But he seems to me, like the Lydian, to
				open not only one gate against himself, but to involve
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.341"/>
				
				Epicurus also in many and those the greatest doubts and
				difficulties. For he begins with Democritus, who receives
				of him an excellent and worthy reward for his instruction;
				it being certain that Epicurus for a long time called himself a Democritean, which as well others affirm, as Leonteus, a principal disciple of Epicurus, who in a letter
				which he writ to Lycophron says, that Epicurus honored
				Democritus, because he first attained, though a little at a
				distance, the right and sound understanding of the truth,
				and that in general all the treatise concerning natural
				things was called Democritean, because Democritus was
				the first who happened upon the principles and met with
				the primitive foundations of Nature. And Metrodorus
				says openly of philosophy, If Democritus had not gone
				before and taught the way, Epicurus had never attained
				to wisdom. Now if it be true, as Colotes holds, that to
				live according to the opinions of Democritus is not to
				live, Epicurus was then a fool in following Democritus,
				who led him to a doctrine which taught him not to live.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="4">
            <p>Now the first thing he lays to his charge is, that, by
				supposing every thing to be no more of one nature than another, he wholly confounds human life. But Democritus
				was so far from having been of this opinion, that he opposed Protagoras the philosopher who asserted it, and
				writ many excellent arguments concluding against him,
				which this fine fellow Colotes never saw nor read, nor yet
				so much as dreamed of; but deceived himself by misunderstanding a passage which is in his works, where he determines that <foreign lang="greek">to\ de/n</foreign> is no more than <foreign lang="greek">to\ mhde/n,</foreign> naming in that
				place the body by <foreign lang="greek">de/n,</foreign> and the void by <foreign lang="greek">mhde/n,</foreign> and meaning
				that the void has its own proper nature and subsistence,
				as well as the body.</p>
            <p>But he who is of opinion that nothing is more of one
					nature than another makes use of a sentence of Epicurus,
					in which he says that all the apprehensions and imaginations
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.342"/>
					
					 given us by the senses are true. For if of two saying, the one, that the wine is sour, and the other, that it
					is sweet, neither of them shall be deceived by his sense,
					how shall the wine be more sour than sweet? And we
					may often see that some men using one and the same
					bath find it to be hot, and others find it to be cold;
					because those order cold water to be put into it, as these
					do hot. It is said that, a certain lady going to visit Berenice, wife to King Deiotarus, as soon as ever they approached each other, they both immediately turned their
					backs, the one, as it seemed, not being able to bear the
					smell of perfume, nor the other of butter. If then the
					sense of one is no truer than the sense of another, it is
					also probable, that water is no more cold than hot, nor
					sweet ointment or butter better or worse scented one than
					the other. For if any one shall say that it seems the one
					to one, and the other to another, he will, before he is
					aware, affirm that they are both the one and the other.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="5">
            <p>And as for these symmetries and proportions of the
				pores, or little passages in the organs of the senses, about
				which they talk so much, and those different mixtures
				of seeds, which, they say, being dispersed through all savors, odors, and colors, move the senses of different persons to perceive different qualities, do they not manifestly
				drive them to this, that things are no more of one quality
				than another? For to pacify those who think the sense is
				deceived and lies because they see contrary events and
				passions in such as use the same objects, and to solve this
				objection, they teach,&mdash;that all things being mixed and
				confounded together, and yet one nevertheless being more
				suitable and fitting to one, and another to another, it is not
				possible that there should in all cases be a contact and
				comprehension of one and the same quality, nor does the
				object equally affect all with all its parts, every one meeting only those to which it has its sense commensurate and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.343"/>
				
				proportioned; so that they are to blame so obstinately to
				insist that a thing is either good or bad, white or not white,
				thinking to establish their own senses by destroying those
				of others; whereas they ought neither to combat the
				senses,&mdash;because they all touch some quality, each one
				drawing from this confused mixture, as from a living and
				large fountain, what is suitable and convenient,&mdash;nor to
				pronounce of the whole, by touching only the parts, nor
				to think that all ought to be affected after one and the
				same manner by the same thing, seeing that one is affected
				by one quality and faculty of it, and another by another.
				Let us then seek who those men are which bring in this
				opinion that things are not more of one quality than another, if they are not those who hold that every sensible
				thing is a mixture, composed of all sorts of qualities, like
				a mixture of new wine fermenting, and who confess that
				all their rules are lost and their faculty of judging quite
				gone, if they admit any sensible object that is pure and
				simple, and do not make each one thing to be many?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="6">
            <p>See now to this purpose, what discourse and debate
				Epicurus makes Polyaenus to have with him in his Banquet concerning the heat of wine. For when he asked,
				<q direct="unspecified">Do you, Epicurus, say, that wine does not heat?</q> some
				one answered, <q direct="unspecified">It is not universally to be affirmed that
					wine heats.</q> And a little after: <q direct="unspecified">For wine seems not to
						be universally a heater; but such a quantity may be said
						to heat such a person.</q> And again subjoining the cause,
				to wit, the compressions and disseminations of the atoms,
				and having alleged their commixtures and conjunctions
				with others when the wine comes to be mingled in the
				body, he adds this conclusion: <q direct="unspecified">It is not universally to be
					said that wine is endued with a faculty of heating; but
					that such a quantity may heat such a nature and one so
					disposed, while such a quantity to such a nature is cooling.
					For in such a mass there are such natures and complexions
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.344"/>
					
					 of which cold might be composed, and which, joined
					with others in proper measure, would yield a refrigerative
					virtue. Wherefore some are deceived, who say that wine
					is universally a heater; and others, who say that it is universally a cooler.</q> He then who says that most men are
				deceived and err, in holding that which is hot to be heating and that which is cold to be cooling, is himself in an
				error, unless he should believe that his assertion leads to
				the doctrine that one thing is not more of one nature than
				another. He farther adds afterwards, that oftentimes
				wine entering into a body brings with it thither neither a
				calefying nor refrigerating virtue, but, the mass of the
				body being agitated and disturbed, and a transposition
				made of the parts, the heat-effecting atoms being assembled together do by their multitude cause a heat and inflammation in the body, and sometimes on the contrary
				disassembling themselves cause a refrigeration.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="7">
            <p>But it is moreover wholly evident, that we may apply this argument to all those things which are called and
				esteemed bitter, sweet, purging, dormitive, and luminous,
				not any one of them having an entire and perfect quality
				to produce such effects, nor to do rather than to suffer
				when they are in the bodies, but being there susceptible of
				various temperatures and differences. For Epicurus himself, in his Second Book against Theophrastus, affirming
				that colors are not connatural to bodies, but are engendered there according to certain situations and positions
				with respect to the sight of man, says: <q direct="unspecified">For this reason a
					body is no more colored than destitute of color.</q> And a
				little above he writes thus, word for word: <q direct="unspecified">But apart
					from this, I know not how a man may say that those bodies
					which are in the dark have color; although very often, an
					air equally dark being spread about them, some distinguish
					diversities of colors, others perceive them not through the
					weakness of their sight. And moreover, going into a
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.345"/>
					
					dark house or room, we at our first entrance see no color,
					but after we have stayed there awhile, we do. Wherefore we are to say that every body is not more colored than
					not colored. Now, if color is relative and has its being
					in regard to something else, so also then is white, and so
					likewise blue; and if colors are so, so also are sweet and
					bitter. So that it may truly be affirmed of every quality,
					that it cannot more properly be said to be than not to be.
					For to those who are in a certain manner disposed, they
					will be; but to those who are not so disposed, they will
					not be.</q> Colotes therefore has bedashed and bespattered
				himself and his master with that dirt, in which he says
				those lie who maintain that things are not more of one
				quality than another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="8">
            <p>But is it in this alone, that this excellent man shows
				himself
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>To others a physician, whilst himself
					</l>
                     <l>Is full of ulcers?</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Euripides, Frag. 1071.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>No indeed; but yet much farther in his second reprehension, without any way minding it, he drives Epicurus and
					Democritus out of this life. For he affirms that the saying of Democritus&mdash;that the atoms are to the senses
					color by a certain law or ordinance, that they are by the
					same law sweetness, and by the same law concretion<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The text is corrupt here. (G.)</note>&mdash;is
					at war with our senses, and that he who uses this reason
					and persists in this opinion cannot himself imagine whether
					he is living or dead. I know not how to contradict this
					discourse; but this I can boldly affirm, that this is as inseparable from the sentences and doctrines of Epicurus
					as they say figure and weight are from atoms. For what
					is it that Democritus says? <q direct="unspecified">There are substances, in
						number infinite, called atoms (because they cannot be
						divided), without difference, without quality, and impassible, which move, being dispersed here and there, in the
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.346"/>
						
						infinite voidness; and that when they approach one
						another, or meet and are conjoined, of such masses thus
						heaped together, one appears water, another fire, another
						a plant, another a man; and that all things are thus really
						atoms (as he called them), and that there is nothing else;
						for there can be no generation from what is not; and of
						those things which are nothing can be generated, because
						these atoms are so firm, that they can neither change, alter,
						nor suffer; wherefore there cannot be made color of those
						things which are without color, nor nature or soul of
						those things which are without quality and impassible.</q>
					Democritus then is to be blamed, not for confessing those
					things that happen upon his principles, but for supposing
					principles upon which such things happen. For he should
					not have supposed immutable principles; or having supposed them, he ought to have seen that the generation of
					all quality is taken away; but having seen the absurdity,
					to deny it is most impudent. But Epicurus says, that he
					supposes the same principles with Democritus, but that he
					says not that color, sweet, white, and other qualities, are
					by law and ordinance. If therefore <hi rend="italics">not to say</hi> is merely
					<hi rend="italics">not to confess,</hi> he does merely what he is wont to do. For
					it is as when, taking away divine Providence, he nevertheless says that he leaves piety and devotion towards the
					Gods; and when, choosing friendship for the sake of
					pleasure, that he suffers most grievous pains for his friends;
					and supposing the universe to be infinite, that he nevertheless takes not away high and low.... Indeed having
					taken the cup, one may drink what he pleases, and return
					the rest. But in reasoning one ought chiefly to remember
					this wise apophthegm, that where the principles are not
					necessary, the ends and consequences are necessary. It
					was not then necessary for him to suppose or (to say better) to steal from Democritus, that atoms are the principles
					of the universe; but having supposed this doctrine, and
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.347"/>
					
					having pleased and glorified himself in the first probable
					and specious appearances of it, he must afterwards also
					swallow that which is troublesome in it, or must show how
					bodies which have not any quality can bring all sorts of
					qualities to others only by their meetings and joining
					together. As&mdash;to take that which comes next to hand&mdash;whence does that which we call heat proceed, and how is
					it engendered in the atoms, if they neither had heat when
					they came, nor are become hot after their being joined
					together? For the one presupposes that they had some
					quality, and the other that they were fit to receive it. And
					you affirm, that neither the one nor the other must be said
					to belong to atoms, because they are incorruptible.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="9">
            <p>How then? Do not Plato, Aristotle, and Xenocrates
				produce gold from that which is not gold, and stone from
				that which is not stone, and many other things from the
				four simple first bodies? Yes indeed; but with those
				bodies immediately concur also the principles for the generation of every thing, bringing with them great contributions, that is, the first qualities which are in them; then,
				when they come to assemble and join in one the dry with
				the moist, the cold with the hot, and the solid with the
				soft,&mdash;that is active bodies with such as are fit to suffer
				and receive every alteration and change,&mdash;then is generation wrought by passing from one temperature to another.
				Whereas the atom, being alone, is deprived and destitute
				of all quality and generative faculty, and when it comes to
				meet with the others, it can make only a noise and sound
				because of its hardness and firmness, but nothing else.
				For they always strike and are stricken, not being able by
				this means to compose or make an animal, a soul, or a
				nature, nay, not so much as a mass or heap of themselves;
				for that as they beat upon one another, so they fly back
				again asunder.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="10">
            <p>But Colotes, as if he were speaking to some ignorant
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.348"/>
				
				 and unlettered king, again attacks Empedocles for
				breathing forth the same thought:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>I've one thing more to say. 'Mongst mortals there
					</l>
                     <l>No Nature is; nor that grim thing men fear
					</l>
                     <l>So much, called death. There only happens first
					</l>
                     <l>A mixture, and mixt things asunder burst
					</l>
                     <l>Again, when them disunion does befall.
					</l>
                     <l>And this is that which men do Nature call.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For my part, I do not see how this is repugnant and contrary to life or living, especially amongst those who hold
					that there is no generation of that which is not, nor corruption of that which is, but that the assembling and
					union of the things which are is called generation, and
					their dissolution and disunion named corruption and death.
					For that he took Nature for generation, and that this is
					his meaning, he has himself declared, when he opposed
					Nature to death. And if they neither live nor can live
					who place generation in union and death in disunion,
					what else do these Epicureans? Yet Empedocles, gluing,
					(as it were) and conjoining the elements together by heats,
					softnesses, and humidities, gives them in some sort a mixtion and unitive composition; but these men who hunt
					and drive together the atoms, which they affirm to be immutable and impassible, compose nothing proceeding from
					them, but indeed make many and continual percussions
					of them.</p>
            <p>For the interlacement, hindering the dissolution, more
					and more augments the collision and concussion; so that
					there is neither mixtion nor adhesion and conglutination,
					but only a confusion and combat, which according to them
					is called generation. And if the atoms do now recoil for
					a moment by reason of the shock they have given, and
					then return again after the blow is past, they are above
					double the time absent from one another, without either
					touching or approaching, so as nothing can be made of
					them, not even so much as a body without a soul. But as
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.349"/>
					
					for sense, soul, understanding, and prudence, there is not
					any man who can in the least conceive or imagine how it
					is possible they should be made in a voidness, and of atoms
					which neither when separate and apart have any quality,
					nor any passion or alteration when they are assembled and
					joined together, especially seeing this their meeting together is not an incorporation or congress, making a mixture or coalition, but rather percussions and repercussions.
					So that, according to the doctrine of these people, life is
					taken away, and the being of an animal denied, since they
					suppose principles void, impassible, godless, and soulless,
					and such as cannot admit or receive any mixture or incorporation whatever.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="11">
            <p>How then is it, that they admit and allow Nature,
				soul, and living creature? Even in the same manner as
				they do an oath, prayer, and sacrifice, and the adoration
				of the Gods. Thus they adore by word and mouth, only
				naming and feigning that which by their principles they
				totally take away and abolish. If now they call that which
				is born Nature, and that which is engendered generation,
				&mdash;as those who ordinarily call the wood itself wood-work
				and the voices that accord and sound together symphony,
				&mdash;whence came it into his mind to object these words
				against Empedocles? <q direct="unspecified">Why,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">do we tire ourselves in taking such care of ourselves, in desiring and
					longing after certain things, and shunning and avoiding
					others? For we neither are ourselves, nor do we live by
					making use of others.</q> But be of good cheer, my dear
				little Colotes, may one perhaps say to him: there is none
				who hinders you from taking care of yourself by teaching
				that the nature of Colotes is nothing else but Colotes himself, or who forbids you to make use of things (now things
				with you are pleasures) by showing that there is no nature
				of tarts and marchpanes, of sweet odors, or of venereal
				delights, but that there are tarts, marchpanes, perfumes,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.350"/>
				
				and women. For neither does the grammarian who says
				that <q direct="unspecified">the strength of Hercules</q> is Hercules himself deny
				the being of Hercules; nor do those who say that symphonies and roofings are but bare derivations affirm that
				there are neither sounds nor timbers; since also there are
				some who, taking away the soul and prudence, do not yet
				seem to take away either living or being prudent.</p>
            <p>And when Epicurus says that the nature of things consists in bodies and their place, do we so comprehend him
					as if he meant that Nature were something else than the
					things which are, or as if he insinuated that it is simply
					the things which are, and nothing else?&mdash;as, to wit, he
					is wont to call voidness itself the nature of voidness, and
					the universe, by Jupiter, the nature of the universe. And
					if any one should thus question him; What sayst thou,
					Epicurus, that this is voidness, and that the nature of
					voidness? No, by Jupiter, would he answer; but this
					community of names is in use by law and custom. I
					grant it is. Now what has Empedocles done else, but
					taught that Nature is nothing else save that which is born,
					and death no other thing but that which dies? But as the
					poets very often, forming as it were an image, say thus in
					figurative language,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Strife, tumult, noise, placed by some angry God,
						</l>
                     <l>Mischief, and malice there had their abode;</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XVIII. 635.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>so do most men attribute generation and corruption to
					things that are contracted together and dissolved. But so
					far has he been from stirring and taking away that which
					is, or contradicting that which evidently appears, that he
					casts not so much as one single word out of the accustomed
					use; but taking away all figurative fraud that might hurt
					or endamage things, he again restored the ordinary and
					useful signification to words in these verses:
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.351"/>
					
					          <quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>When from mixed elements we sometimes see
						</l>
                     <l>A man produced, sometimes a beast, a tree,
						</l>
                     <l>Or bird, this birth and geniture we name;
						</l>
                     <l>But death, when this so well compacted frame
						</l>
                     <l>And juncture is dissolved. This use I do approve.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I myself say that Colotes, though he alleged these
					verses, did not understand that Empedocles took not away
					men, beasts, trees, or birds, which he affirmed to be composed of the elements mixed together; and that, by teaching how much they are deceived who call this composition
					Nature and life, and this dissolution unhappy destruction
					and miserable death, he did not abrogate the using of the
					customary expressions in this respect.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="12">
            <p>And it seems to me, indeed, that Empedocles did not
				aim in this place at the disturbing the common form of
				expression, but that he really, as it has been said, had
				a controversy about generation from things that have no
				being, which some call Nature. Which he manifestly
				shows by these verses:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fools, and of little thought, we well may deem
					</l>
                     <l>Those, who so silly are as to esteem
					</l>
                     <l>That what ne'er was may now engendered be,
					</l>
                     <l>And that what is may perish utterly.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For these are the words of one who cries loud enough to
					those which have ears, that he takes not away generation,
					but procreation from nothing; nor corruption, but total
					destruction, that is, reduction to nothing. For to him
					who would not so savagely and foolishly but more gently
					calumniate, the following verses might give a colorable
					occasion of charging Empedocles with the contrary, when
					he says:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No prudent man can e'er into his mind
						</l>
                     <l>Admit that, whilst men living here on earth
						</l>
                     <l>(Which only life they call) both fortunes find,
						</l>
                     <l>They being have, but that before the birth
						</l>
                     <l>They nothing were, nor shall be when once dead.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For these are not the expressions of a man who denies
					those that are born to be, but rather of him who holds
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.352"/>
					
					those to be that are not yet born or that are already dead.
					And Colotes also does not altogether accuse him of this,
					but says that according to his opinion we shall never be
					sick, never wounded. But how is it possible, that he who
					affirms men to have being both before their life and after
					their death, and during their life to find both fortunes (or
					to be accompanied both by good and evil), should not leave
					them the power to suffer? Who then are they, O Colotes,
					that are endued with this privilege never to be wounded,
					never to be sick? Even you yourselves, who are composed
					of atoms and voidness, neither of which, you say, has any
					sense. Now there is no great hurt in this; but the worst
					is, you have nothing left that can cause you pleasure, seeing an atom is not capable to receive those things which
					are to effect it, and voidness cannot be affected by them.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="13">
            <p>But because Colotes would, immediately after Democritus, seem to inter and bury Parmenides, and I have
				passed over and a little postponed his defence, to bring in
				between them that of Empedocles, as seeming to be more
				coherent and consequent to the first reprehensions, let us
				now return to Parmenides. Him then does Colotes accuse
				of having broached and set abroad certain shameful and
				villanous sophistries; and yet by these his sophisms he
				has neither rendered friendship less honorable, nor voluptuousness or the desire of pleasures more audacious and
				unbridled. He has not taken from honesty its attractive
				property or its being venerable or recommendable of itself,
				nor has he disturbed the opinions we ought to have of the
				Gods. And I do not see how, by saying that the All (or
				the universe) is one, he hinders or obstructs our living.
				For when Epicurus himself says that the All is infinite, that
				it is neither engendered nor perishable, that it can neither
				increase nor be diminished, he speaks of the universe as
				of one only thing. And having in the beginning of his
				treatise concerning this matter said, that the nature of those
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.353"/>
				
				things which have being consists of bodies and of voidness, he makes a division (as it were) of one thing into
				two parts, one of which has in reality no subsistence,
				being, as you yourselves term it, impalpable, void, and
				incorporeal; so that by this means, even with you also, all
				comes to be one; unless you desire, in speaking of voidness, to use words void of sense, and to combat the ancients, as if you were fighting against a shadow.
				But these atomical bodies, you will say, are, according
				to the opinion of Epicurus, infinite in number, and every
				thing which appears to us is composed of them. See
				now, therefore, what principles of generation you suppose,
				infinity and voidness; one of which, to wit, voidness, is
				inactive, impassible, and incorporeal; the other, to wit,
				infinity, is disorderly, unreasonable, and incomprehensible,
				dissolving and confounding itself, because it cannot for its
				multitude be contained, circumscribed, or limited. But
				Parmenides has neither taken away fire, nor water, nor
				rocks and precipices, nor yet cities (as Colotes says) which
				are built and inhabited as well in Europe as in Asia; since
				he has both made an order of the world, and mixing the
				elements, to wit, light and dark, does of them and by them
				compose and finish all things that are to be seen in the
				world. For he has written very largely of the earth,
				heaven, sun, moon, and stars, and has spoken of the generation of man; and being, as he was, an ancient author in
				physiology, and one who in writing sought to deliver his
				own and not to destroy another's doctrine, he has passed
				over none of the principal things in Nature. Moreover,
				Plato, and before him Socrates himself, understood that in
				Nature there is one part subject to opinion, and another
				subject to intelligence. As for that which is subject to
				opinion, it is always unconstant, wandering, and carried
				away with several passions and changes, liable to diminution and increase, and to be variously disposed to various
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.354"/>
				
				men, and not always appearing after one manner even to
				the same person. But as to the intelligible part, it is quite
				of another kind,
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Constant, entire, and still engenerable,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as himself says, always like to itself, and perdurable in its
					being.</p>
            <p>Here Colotes, sycophant-like, catching at his expressions and drawing the discourse from things to words,
					flatly affirms that Parmenides in one word takes away the
					existence of all things by supposing <hi rend="italics">ens</hi> (or that which is)
					to be one. But, on the contrary, he takes away neither
					the one nor the other part of Nature; but rendering to
					each of them what belongs to it and is convenient for it,
					he places the intelligible in the idea of one and of <q direct="unspecified">that
						which is,</q> calling it <hi rend="italics">ens</hi> because it is eternal and incorruptible, and one because it is always like itself and admits no
					diversity. And as for that part which is sensible, he places
					it in the rank of uncertain, disorderly, and always moving. Of which two parts, we may see the distinct judgment:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>One certain truth and sincere knowledge is,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>as regarding that which is intelligible, and always alike
					and of the same sort;
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>The other does on men's opinions rest,
						</l>
                     <l>Which breed no true belief within our breast,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>because it is conversant in things which receive all sorts
					of changes, passions, and inequalities. Now how he could
					have left sense and opinion, if he had not also left any
					thing sensible and opinable, it is impossible for any man to
					say. But because to that which truly <hi rend="italics">is</hi> it appertains to
					continue in its being, and because sensible things sometimes are, sometimes are not, continually passing from one
					being to another and perpetually changing their state, he
					thought they required some other name than that of <hi rend="italics">entia,</hi>
					
					          <pb id="v.5.p.355"/>
					
					or things which always are. This speech therefore concerning <hi rend="italics">ens</hi> (or that which is), that it should be but one,
					is not to take away the plurality of sensible things, but
					to show how they differ from that which is intelligible.
					Which difference Plato in his discourse of Ideas more fully
					declaring, has thereby afforded Colotes an opportunity of
					cavilling.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="14">
            <p>Therefore it seems not unreasonable to me to take
				next into our consideration, as it were all in a train, what
				he has also said against him. But first let us contemplate
				a little the diligence&ndash;together with the manifold and
				profound knowledge&mdash;of this our philosopher, who says,
				that Aristotle, Xenocrates, Theophrastus, and all the
				Peripatetics have followed these doctrines of Plato. For
				in what corner of the uninhabitable world have you, O
				Colotes, written your book, that, composing all these accusations against such personages, you never have lighted upon
				their works, nor have taken into your hands the books of
				Aristotle concerning Heaven and the Soul, nor those of
				Theophrastus against the Naturalists, nor the Zoroaster
				of Heraclides, nor his books of Hell, nor that of Natural
				Doubts and Difficulties, nor the book of Dicaearchus concerning the Soul; in all which books they are in the highest degree contradictory and repugnant to Plato about the
				principal and greatest points of natural philosophy? Nay,
				Strato himself, the very head and prince of the other Peripatetics, agrees not in many things with Aristotle, and
				holds opinions altogether contrary to Plato, concerning
				motion, the understanding, the soul, and generation. In
				fine, he says that the world is not an animal, and that
				what is according to Nature follows what is according to
				Fortune; for that Chance gave the beginning, and so every
				one of the natural effects was afterwards finished.</p>
            <p>Now as to the ideas,&mdash;for which he quarrels with Plato,
					&mdash;Aristotle, by moving this matter at every turn, and alleging
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.356"/>
					
					 all manner of doubts concerning them, in his Ethics,
					in his Physics, and in his Exoterical Dialogues seems to
					some rather obstinately than philosophically to have disputed against these doctrines, as having proposed to himself the debasing and undervaluing of Plato's philosophy;
					so far he was from following it. What an impudent rashness then is this, that having neither seen nor understood
					what these persons have written and what were their opinions, he should go and devise such things as they never
					imagined; and persuading himself that he reprehends and
					refutes others, he should produce a proof, written with his
					own hand, arguing and convincing himself of ignorance,
					licentiousness, and shameful impudence, in saying that
					those who contradict Plato agree with him, and that those
					who oppose him follow him?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="15">
            <p>Plato, says he, writes that horses are in vain by us
				esteemed horses, and men men. And in which of Plato's
				commentaries has he found this hidden? For as to us,
				we read in all his books, that horses are horses, that men
				are men, and that fire is by him esteemed fire, because he
				holds that every one of these things is sensible and subject to opinion. But this fine fellow Colotes, as if he were
				not a hair's breadth removed from perfect wisdom, apprehends it to be one and the same thing to say, <q direct="unspecified">Man is
					not</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Man is a <hi rend="italics">non ens.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now to Plato there seems to be a wonderful great difference between not being at all and being a <hi rend="italics">non ens;</hi> because the first imports an annihilation and abolishment of
					all substance, and the other shows the diversity there is
					between that which is participated and that which participates. Which diversity those who came after distinguished
					only into the difference of genus and species, and certain
					common and proper qualities or accidents, as they are
					called, but ascended no higher, falling into more logical
					doubts and difficulties. Now there is the same proportion
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.357"/>
					
					between that which is participated and that which participates, as there is between the cause and the matter, the
					original and the image, the faculty and the effect. Wherein that which is by itself and always the same principally
					differs from that which is by another and never abides in
					one and the same manner; because the one never was
					nor ever shall be non-existent, and is therefore totally and
					essentially an <hi rend="italics">ens;</hi> but to the other that very being, which
					it has not of itself but happens to take by participation
					from another, does not remain firm and constant, but it
					goes out of it by its imbecility,&mdash;the matter always gliding and sliding about the form, and receiving several affections and changes in the image of the substance, so that it
					is continually moving and shaking. As therefore he who
					says that the image of Plato is not Plato takes not away
					the sense and substance of the image, but shows the difference of that which exists of itself from that which exists only in regard to some other; so neither do they take
					away the nature, use, or sense of men, who affirm that
					every one of us, by participating in a certain common substance, that is, by the idea, is become the image of that
					which afforded the likeness for our generation. For
					neither does he who says that a red-hot iron is not fire, or
					that the moon is not the sun, but, as Parmenides has it,
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>A torch which round the earth by night
						</l>
                     <l>Does bear about a borrowed light,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>take away therefore the use of iron, or the nature of the
					moon. But if he should deny it to be a body, or affirm
					that it is not illuminated, he would then contradict the
					senses, as one who admitted neither body, animal, generation, nor sense. But he who by his opinion imagines that
					these things subsist only by participation, and considers
					how far remote and distant they are from that which always is and which communicates to them their being, does
					not reject the sensible, but affirms that the intelligible is;
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.358"/>
					
					nor does he take away and abolish the effects which are
					wrought and appear in us; but he shows to those who
					follow him that there are other things, firmer and more
					stable than these in respect of their essence, because they
					are neither engendered, nor perish, nor suffer any thing;
					and he teaches them, more purely touching the difference,
					to express it by names, calling these <foreign lang="greek">o)/nta</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">entia (things
						that have being),</hi> and those <foreign lang="greek">gigno/mena</foreign> or <hi rend="italics">fientia (things engendered</hi>). And the same also usually befalls the moderns;
					for they deprive many&mdash;and those great things&mdash;of the
					appellation of <hi rend="italics">ens</hi> or <hi rend="italics">being;</hi> such as are voidness, time,
					place, and simply the entire genus of things spoken, in
					which are comprised all things true. For these things,
					they say, are not <hi rend="italics">entia</hi> but <hi rend="italics">some things;</hi> and they perpetually make use of them in their lives and in their
					philosophy, as of things having subsistence and existence.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="16">
            <p>But I would willingly ask this our fault-finder,
				whether themselves do not in their affairs perceive this
				difference, by which some things are permanent and immutable in their substances,&mdash;as they say of their atoms,
				that they are at all times and continually after one and the
				same manner, because of their impassibility and hardness,
				&mdash;but that all compounded things are fluxible, changeable,
				generated, and perishing; forasmuch as infinite images
				are always departing and going from them, and infinite
				others, as it is probable, repair to them from the ambient
				air, filling up what was diminished from the mass, which is
				much diversified and transvasated, as it were, by this
				change, since those atoms which are in the very bottom of
				the said mass can never cease stirring and reciprocally
				beating upon one another; as they themselves affirm.
				There is then in things such a diversity of substance
				But Epicurus is in this wiser and more learned than Plato.
				that he calls them all equally <hi rend="italics">entia,</hi>&mdash;to wit, the impalpable voidness, the solid and resisting body, the principles,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.359"/>
				
				and the things composed of them,&mdash;and thinks that the
				eternal participates of the common substance with that
				which is generated, the immortal with the corruptible, and
				the natures that are impassible, perdurable, unchangeable,
				and that can never fall from their being, with those which
				have their essence in suffering and changing, and can
				never continue in one and the same state. But though
				Plato had with all the justness imaginable deserved to be
				condemned for having offended in this, yet should he have
				been sentenced by these gentlemen, who speak Greek
				more elegantly and discourse more correctly than he, only
				as having confounded the terms, and not as having taken
				away the things and driven life from us, because he named
				them <hi rend="italics">fientia</hi> (or things engendered), and not <hi rend="italics">entia</hi> (things
				that have being), as these men do.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="17">
            <p>But because we have passed over Socrates, who
				should have come next after Parmenides, we must now
				turn back our discourse to him. Him therefore has Colotes begun at the very first to remove, as the common proverb has it, from the sacred line; and having mentioned
				how Chaerephon brought from Delphi an oracle, well
				known to us all, concerning Socrates, he says thus: <q direct="unspecified">Now
					as to this narration of Chaerephon's, because it is odious
					and absolutely sophistical, we will overpass it.</q> Plato then,
				that we may say nothing of others, is also odious, who has
				committed it to writing; and the Lacedaemonians are yet
				more odious, who reserve the oracle of Lycurgus amongst
				their most ancient and most authentic inscriptions. The
				oracle also of Themistocles, by which he persuaded the
				Athenians to quit their town, and in a naval fight defeated
				the barbarous Xerxes, was a sophistical fiction. Odious
				also were all the ancient legislators and founders of Greece,
				who established the most part of their temples, sacrifices,
				and solemn festivals by the answer of the Pythian Oracle.
				But if the oracle brought from Delphi concerning Socrates,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.360"/>
				
				a man ravished with a divine zeal to virtue, by which he is
				styled and declared wise, is odious, fictitious, and sophistical, by what name shall we call your cries, noises, and
				shouts, your applauses, adorations and canonizations, with
				which you extol and celebrate him who incites and exhorts
				you to frequent and continual pleasures? For thus has he
				written in his epistle to Anaxarchus: <q direct="unspecified">I for my part in
					cite and call you to continual pleasures, and not to vain and
					empty virtues, which have nothing but turbulent hopes of
					uncertain fruits.</q> And yet Metrodorus, writing to Timarchus, says: <q direct="unspecified">Let us do some extraordinarily excellent
						thing, not suffering ourselves to be plunged in reciprocal
						affections, but retiring from this low and terrestrial life, and
						elevating ourselves to the truly holy and divinely revealed
						ceremonies and mysteries of Epicurus.</q> And even Colotes
				himself, hearing one day Epicurus discoursing of natural
				things, fell suddenly at his feet and embraced his knees, as
				Epicurus himself, glorying in it, thus writes: <q direct="unspecified">For as if
					you had adored what we were then saying, you were suddenly taken with a desire, proceeding not from any natural
					cause, to come to us, prostrate yourself on the ground, embrace our knees, and use all those gestures to us which are
					ordinarily practised by those who adore and pray to the
					Gods. So that you made us also,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">reciprocally
						sanctify and adore you.</q> Those, by Jupiter, well deserve
				to be pardoned, who say, they would willingly give any
				money for a picture in which should be presented to the
				life this fine story of one lying prostrate at the knees and
				embracing the legs of another, who mutually again adores
				him and makes his devout prayers to him. Nevertheless
				this devout service, how well soever it was ordered and
				composed by Colotes, received not the condign fruit he expected; for he was not declared wise; but it was only said
				to him: Go thy ways, and walk immortal; and understand
				that we also are in like manner immortal.</p>
            <pb id="v.5.p.361"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="18">
            <p>These men, knowing well in their consciences that
				they have used such foolish speeches, have had such
				motions, and such passions, dare nevertheless call others
				odious. And Colotes, having shown us these fine first-fruits and wise positions touching the natural senses,&mdash;that
				we eat meat, and not hay or forage; and that when rivers
				are deep and great, we pass them in boats, but when shallow and easily fordable, on foot,&mdash;cries out, <q direct="unspecified">You use
					vain and arrogant speeches, O Socrates; you say one thing
					to those who come to discourse with you, and practise another.</q> Now I would fain know what these vain and
				arrogant speeches of Socrates were, since he ordinarily
				said that he knew nothing, that he was always learning,
				and that he went enquiring and searching after the truth.
				But if, O Colotes, you had happened on such expressions
				of Socrates as are those which Epicurus writ to Idomeneus,
				<q direct="unspecified">Send me then the first-fruits for the entertainment of our
					sacred body, for ourself and for our children: for so it
					comes upon me to speak;</q> what more arrogant and insolent words could you have used? And yet that Socrates
				spake otherwise than he lived, you have wonderful proofs
				in his gests at Delium, at Potidaea, in his behavior during
				the time of the Thirty Tyrants, towards Archelaus, towards
				the people of Athens, in his poverty, and in his death.
				For are not these things beseeming and answerable to the
				doctrine of Socrates? They would indeed, good sir, have
				been indubitable testimonies to show that he acted otherwise than he taught, if, having proposed pleasure for the
				end of life, he had led such a life as this.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="19">
            <p>Thus much for the calumnies he has uttered against
				Socrates. Colotes besides perceives not that he is himself
				found guilty of the same offences in regard to proofs which
				he objects against Socrates. For this is one of the sentences and propositions of Epicurus, that none but the wise
				man ought irrevocably and unchangeably to be persuaded
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.362"/>
				
				of any thing. Since then Colotes, even after those adorations he performed to Epicurus, became not one of the
				sages, let him first make these questions and interrogatories
				his own: How is it that being hungry he eats meat and
				not hay, and that he puts a robe about his body and not
				about a pillar, since he is not indubitably persuaded either
				that a robe is a robe or that meat is meat? But if he not
				only does these things, but also passes not over rivers,
				when they are great and high, on foot, and flies from
				wolves and serpents, not being irrevocably persuaded that
				any of these things is such as it appears, but yet doing
				every thing according to what appears to him; so likewise
				the opinion of Socrates concerning the senses was no obstacle to him, but that he might in like manner make use of
				things as they appeared to him. For it is not likely that
				bread appeared bread and hay hay to Colotes, because he
				had read those holy rules of Epicurus which came down
				from heaven, while Socrates through his vanity took a
				fancy that hay was bread and bread hay. For these wise
				men use better opinions and reasons than we; but to have
				sense, and to receive an impression from things as they appear, is common as well to the ignorant as to the wise, as
				proceeding from causes where there needs not the discourse of reason. And the proposition which affirms that
				the natural senses are not perfect, nor certain enough to
				cause an entire belief, hinders not that every thing may appear to us; but leaving us to make use of our senses in
				our actions according to that which appears, it permits us
				not so to give credit to them as if they were exactly true
				and without error. For it is sufficient that in what is
				necessary and commodious for use there is nothing better.
				But as for the science and knowledge which the soul of a
				philosopher desires to have concerning every thing, the
				senses have it not.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="20">
            <p>But as to this, Colotes will farther give us occasion
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.363"/>
				
				to speak of it hereafter, for he brings this objection against
				several others. Furthermore, whereas he profusely derides
				and despises Socrates for asking what man is, and in a
				youthful bravery (as he terms it) affirming that he was
				ignorant of it, it is manifest that he himself, who scoffs at
				it, never so much as thought of this matter; but Heraclitus
				on the contrary, as having done some great and worthy
				thing, said, I have been seeking myself. And of the
				sentences that were written in Apollo's temple at Delphi,
				the most excellent and most divine seems to have been this,
				Know thyself. And this it was which gave Socrates an
				occasion and beginning of doubting and enquiring into it,
				as Aristotle says in his Platonics. And yet this appears to
				Colotes ridiculous and fit to be scoffed at. And I wonder
				that he derides not also his master himself, who does as
				much whenever he writes concerning the substance of the
				soul and the origin of man. For if that which is compounded of both, as they themselves hold,&mdash;of the body,
				to wit, and the soul,&mdash;is man, he who searches into the
				nature of the soul consequently also searches into the nature of man, beginning from his chiefest principle. Now
				that the soul is very difficult to be comprehended by reason, and altogether incomprehensible by the exterior senses,
				let us not learn from Socrates, who is a vain-glorious and
				sophistical disputer, but let us take it from these wise men,
				who, having forged and framed the substance of the soul
				of somewhat hot, spiritual, and aerial, as far as to her
				faculties about the flesh, by which she gives heat, softness
				and strength to the body, proceed not to that which is the
				principal, but give over faint and tired by the way. For
				that by which she judges, remembers, loves, hates,&mdash;in
				a word, that which is prudent and rational, is,&mdash;say they,
				made afterwards of I know not what nameless quality.
				Now we well know, that this nameless thing is a confession
				of their shameful ignorance, whilst they pretend they cannot
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.364"/>
				
				 name what they are not able to understand or comprehend. But let this, as they say, be pardoned them. For
				it seems not to be a light and easy matter, which every one
				can at the first attempt find out and attain to, but has retired itself to the bottom of some very remote place, and
				there lies obscurely concealed. So that there is not,
				amongst so many words and terms as are in use, any one
				that can explain or show it. Socrates therefore was not a
				fool or blockhead for seeking and searching what himself
				was; but they are rather to be thought shallow coxcombs,
				who enquire after any other thing before this, the knowledge of which is so necessary and so hard to find. For
				how could he hope to gain the knowledge of other things,
				who has not been able to comprehend the principal part
				even of himself?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="21">
            <p>But granting a little to Colotes, that there is nothing
				so vain, useless, and odious as the seeking into one's self,
				let us ask him, what confusion of human life is in this,
				and how it is that a man cannot continue to live, when he
				comes once thus to reason and discourse in himself: <q direct="unspecified">Go
					to now, what am I? Am I a composition, made up of
					soul and body; or rather a soul, serving itself and making
					use of the body, as an horseman using his horse is not a
					subject composed of horse and man? Or is every one of
					us the principal part of the soul, by which we understand,
					reason, and act; and are all the other parts, both of soul
					and body, only organs and utensils of this power? Or, to
					conclude, is there no proper substance of the soul at all
					apart, but is only the temperature and complexion of the
					body so disposed, that it has force and power to understand
					and live?</q> But Socrates does not by these questions overthrow human life, since all natural philosophers treat of
				the same matter. But those perhaps are the monstrous
				questions and enquiries that turn every thing upside down,
				which are in Phaedrus,<note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plato, Phaedrus, p. 230 A.</note> where he says, that every one
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.365"/>
				
				ought to examine and consider himself, whether he is a
				savage beast, more cautelous, outrageous, and furious than
				ever was the monster Typhon; or on the contrary, an
				animal more mild and gentle, partaking by Nature of a
				certain divine portion, and such as is free from pride.
				Now by these discourses and reasonings he overturns not
				the life of man, but drives from it presumption and arrogance, and those haughty and extravagant opinions and
				conceits he has of himself. For this is that monster
				Typhon, which your teacher and master has made to be
				so great in you by his warring against the Gods and divine
				men.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="22">
            <p>Having done with Socrates and Plato, he next attacks Stilpo. Now as for those his true doctrines and good
				discourses, by which he managed and governed himself,
				his country, his friends, and such kings and princes as
				loved him and esteemed him, he has not written a word;
				nor yet what prudence and magnanimity was in his heart,
				accompanied with meekness, moderation, and modesty.
				But having made mention of one of those little sentences
				he was wont in mirth and raillery to object against the
				sophisters, he does, without alleging any reason against it
				or solving the subtlety of the objection, stir up a terrible
				tragedy against Stilpo, saying that the life of man is subverted by him, inasmuch as he affirms that one thing cannot be predicated of another. <q direct="unspecified">For how,</q> says he, <q direct="unspecified">shall
					we live, if we cannot style a man good, nor a man a captain, but must separately name a man a man, good good,
					and a captain a captain; nor can say ten thousand horsemen, or a fortified town, but only call horsemen horsemen,
					and ten thousand ten thousand, and so of the rest?</q> Now
				what man ever was there that lived the worse for this?
				Or who is there that, hearing this discourse, does not immediately perceive and understand it to be the speech of a
				man who rallies gallantly, and proposes to others this
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.366"/>
				
				logical question for the exercise of their wits? It is not,
				O Colotes, a great and dangerous scandal not to call man
				good, or not to say ten thousand horsemen; but not to call
				God God, and not to believe him to be God,&mdash;as you and
				the rest do, who will not confess that there is a Jupiter
				presiding over generation, or a Ceres giving laws, or a
				Neptune fostering the plants,&mdash;it is this separation of
				names that is pernicious, and fills our life with audaciousness and an atheistical contempt of the Gods. When you
				pluck from the Gods the names and appellations that are
				tied to them, you abolish also the sacrifices, mysteries,
				processions, and feasts. For to whom shall we offer the
				sacrifices preceding the tilling of the ground? To whom
				those for the obtaining of preservation? How shall we
				celebrate the Phosphoria, or torch-festivals, the Bacchanals,
				and the ceremonies that go before marriage, if we admit
				neither Bacchantes, Gods of light, Gods who protect the
				sown field, nor preservers of the state? For this it is that
				touches the principal and greatest points, being an error
				in things,&mdash;not in words, in the structure of propositions, or use of terms.</p>
            <p>Now if these are the things that disturb and subvert
					human life, who are there that more offend and fail in
					language than you? For you take utterly away the whole
					class of namable things, which constitute the essence of
					language; and leave only words and their accidental objects, while you take away in the mean time the things
					particularly signified by them, by which are wrought disciplines, doctrines, preconceptions, intelligences, inclination, and assent, which you hold to be nothing at all.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="23">
            <p>But as for Stilpo, thus his argument stands. <q direct="unspecified">If
				of a man we predicate good, and of an horse running, the
				predicate or thing predicated is not the same with the subject or that of which it is predicated, but the essential
				definition of man is one, and of good another. And again,
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.367"/>
				
				to be a horse differs from to be running. For being asked
				the definition of the one and of the other, we do not give
				the same for them both; and therefore those err who
				predicate the one of the other. For if good is the same
				with man, and to run the same with a horse, how is good
				affirmed also of food and medicine, and again (by Jupiter)
				to run of a lion and a dog? But if the predicate is different, then we do not rightly say that a man is good, and
				a horse runs.</q> Now if Stilpo is in this exorbitant and
				grossly mistaken, not admitting any copulation of such
				things as are in the subject, or affirmed of the subject,
				with the subject itself; but holding that every one of them,
				if it is not absolutely one and the same thing with that to
				which it happens or of which it is spoken, ought not to be
				spoken or affirmed of it,&mdash;no, not even as an accident; it
				is nevertheless manifest, that he was only offended with
				some words, and opposed the usual and accustomed manner
				of speaking, and not that he overthrew man's life, and
				turned his affairs upside down.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="24">
            <p>Colotes then, having got rid of the old philosophers,
				turns to those of his own time, but without naming any
				of them; though he would have done better either to have
				reproved by name these moderns, as he did the ancients,
				or else to have named neither of them. But he who has
				so often employed his pen against Socrates, Plato, and
				Parmenides, evidently demonstrates that it is through
				cowardice he dares not attack the living, and not for any
				modesty or reverence, of which he showed not the least
				sign to those who were far more excellent than these.
				But his meaning is, as I suspect, to assault the Cyrenaics
				first, and afterwards the Academics, who are followers of
				Arcesilaus. For it was these who doubted of all things;
				but those, placing the passions and imaginations in themselves, were of opinion that the belief proceeding from
				them is not sufficient for the assuring and affirming of
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.368"/>
				
				things; but, as if it were in the siege of a town, abandoning what is without, they have shut themselves up in the
				passions, using only <hi rend="italics">it seems,</hi> and not asserting <hi rend="italics">it is,</hi> of
				things without. And therefore they cannot, as Colotes
				says of them, live or have the use of things. And then
				speaking comically of them, he adds: <q direct="unspecified">These deny that
					there is a man, a horse, a wall; but say that they themselves (as it were) become walls, horses, men,</q> or <q direct="unspecified">are impressed with the images of walls, horses, or men.</q> In
				which he first maliciously abuses the terms, as calumniators
				are usually wont to do. For though these things follow
				from the sayings of the Cyrenaics, yet he ought to have
				declared the fact as they themselves teach it. For they
				affirm that things then become sweet, bitter, lightsome, or
				dark, when each thing has in itself the natural unhindered
				efficacy of one of these impressions. But if honey is said
				to be sweet, an olive-branch bitter, hail cold, wine hot, and
				the nocturnal air dark, there are many beasts, things, and
				men that testify the contrary. For some have an aversion
				for honey, others feed on the branches of the olive-tree;
				some are scorched by hail, others cooled with wine; and
				there are some whose sight is dim in the sun but who see
				well by night. Wherefore opinion, containing itself within these impressions, remains safe and free from error;
				but when it goes forth and attempts to be curious in judging and pronouncing concerning exterior things, it often
				deceives itself, and opposes others, who from the same
				objects receive contrary impressions and different imaginations.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="25">
            <p>And Colotes seems properly to resemble those young
				children who are but beginning to learn their letters. For,
				being accustomed to learn them where they see them in
				their own horn-books and primers, when they see them written anywhere else, they doubt and are troubled; so those
				very discourses, which he praises and approves in the writings
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.369"/>
				
				 of Epicurus, he neither understands nor knows again,
				when they are spoken by others. For those who say that
				the sense is truly informed and moulded when there is
				presented one image round and another broken, but nevertheless permit us not to pronounce that the tower is
				round and the oar broken, confirm their own passions and
				imaginations, but they will not acknowledge and confess
				that the things without are so affected. But as the Cyrenaics must say that they are imprinted with the figure of a
				horse or of a wall, but do not speak of the horse or the
				wall; so also it is necessary to say that the sight is imprinted with a figure round or with three unequal sides,
				and not that the tower is in that manner triangular or
				round. For the image by which the sight is affected is
				broken; but the oar whence that image proceeds is not
				broken. Since then there is a difference between the impression and the external subject, the belief must either
				remain in the impression, or else&mdash;if it maintains the
				being in addition to the appearing&mdash;be reproved and convinced of untruth. And whereas they cry out and are
				offended in behalf of the sense, because the Cyrenaics say
				not that the thing without is hot, but that the impression
				made on the sense is such; is it not the same with what is
				said touching the taste, when they say that the thing without is not sweet, but that some impression and motion
				about the sense is such? And for him who says that he
				has received the apprehension of an human form, but perceives not whether it is a man, whence has he taken occasion so to say? Is it not from those who affirm that they
				receive an apprehension of a bowed figure and form, but
				that the sight pronounces not that the thing which was
				seen is bowed or round, but that a certain effigies of it is
				such? Yes, by Jupiter, will some one say; but I, going
				near the tower or touching the oar, will pronounce and
				affirm that the one is straight and the other has many angles
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.370"/>
				
				 and faces; but he, when he comes near it, will confess that it seems and appears so to him, and no more.
				Yes certainly, good sir, and more than this, when he sees
				and observes the consequence, that every imagination is
				equally worthy of belief for itself, and none for another; but
				that they are all in like condition. But this your opinion
				is quite lost, that all the imaginations are true and none
				false or to be disbelieved, if you think that these ought to
				pronounce positively of that which is without, but those
				you credit no farther than that they are so affected. For
				if they are in equal condition as to their being believed,
				when they are near or when they are far off, it is just that
				either upon all of them, or else not upon these, should follow the judgment pronouncing that a thing is. But if
				there is a difference in the being affected between those
				that are near and those that are far off, it is then false
				that one sense and imagination is not more express and
				evident than another. Therefore those which they call testimonies and counter-testimonies are nothing to the sense,
				but are concerned only with opinion. So, if they would
				have us following these to pronounce concerning exterior
				things, making being a judgment of opinion, and what appears an affection of sense, they transfer the judicature
				from that which is totally true to that which often fails.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="26">
            <p>But how full of trouble and contradiction in respect
				of one another these things are, what need is there to say
				at present? But the reputation of Arcesilaus, who was
				the best beloved and most esteemed of all the philosophers
				in his time, seems to have been no small eyesore to Epicurus;
				 who says of him that, delivering nothing peculiar
				to himself or of his own invention, he imprinted in illiterate men an opinion and esteem of his being very knowing
				and learned. Now Arcesilaus was so far from desiring
				any glory by being a bringer-in of new opinions, and from
				arrogating to himself those of the ancients, that the sophisters
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.371"/>
				
				 of that time blamed him for attributing to Socrates, Plato, Parmenides, and Heraclitus the doctrines
				concerning the retention of assent, and the incomprehensibility of things; having no need so to do, but only that
				he might strengthen them and render them recommendable
				by ascribing them to such illustrious personages. For this
				therefore thanks to Colotes, and to every one who declares
				that the Academic doctrine was from higher times derived
				to Arcesilaus. Now as for the retention of assent and the
				doubting of all things, not even those who have much labored in the matter, and strained themselves to compose
				great books and large treatises concerning it, were ever able
				to stir it; but bringing at last out of the Stoa itself the
				cessation from all actions, as the Gorgon to frighten away
				the objections that came against them, they were at last
				quite tired and gave over. For they could not, what attempts and stirs soever they made, obtain so much from
				the instinct by which the appetite is moved to act, as to
				suffer itself to be called an assent, or to acknowledge sense
				for the origin and principle of its propension, but it appeared of its own accord to present itself to act, as having no need to be joined with any thing else. For against
				such adversaries the combat and dispute is lawful and
				just. And
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such words as you have spoke, the like you may
					</l>
                     <l>Expect to hear.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Il. XX. 250.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>For to speak to Colotes of instinct and consent is, I suppose, all one as to play on the harp before an ass. But to
					those who can give ear and conceive, it is said that there
					are in the soul three sorts of motions,&mdash;the imaginative,
					the appetitive, and the consenting. As to the imaginative or the apprehension, it cannot be taken away, though
					one would. For one cannot, when things approach, avoid
					being informed and (as it were) moulded by them, and receiving
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.372"/>
					
					 an impression from them. The appetite, being
					stirred up by the imaginative, effectually moves man to
					that which is proper and agreeable to his nature, just as
					when there is made a propension and inclination in the
					principal and reasonable part. Now those who withhold
					their assent and doubt of all things take not away this,
					but make use of the appetition or instinct naturally conducting every man to that which seems convenient for
					him. What then is the only thing that they shun? That
					in which is bred falsehood and deceit,&mdash;that is, opining,
					and precipitation in giving consent,&mdash;which is a yielding
					through weakness to that which appears, and has not any
					true utility. For action stands in need of two things, to
					wit, the apprehension or imagination of what is agreeable
					to Nature, and the instinct or appetition driving to that
					which is so imagined; of which, neither the one nor the
					other is repugnant to the retention of assent. For reason
					withdraws us from opinion, and not from appetition or
					imagination. When therefore that which is delectable
					seems to us to be proper for us, there is no need of opinion
					to move and carry us to it, but appetition immediately exerts itself, which is nothing else but the motion and inclination of the soul.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="27">
            <p>It is their own saying, that a man must only have
				sense and be flesh and blood, and pleasure will appear
				to be good. Wherefore also it will seem good to him who
				withholds his assent. For he also participates of sense,
				and is made of flesh and blood, and as soon as he has conceived an imagination of good, desires it and does all
				things that it may not escape from him; but as much as
				possibly he can, he will keep himself with that which is
				agreeable to his nature, being drawn by natural and not by
				geometrical constraints. For these goodly, gentle, and
				tickling motions of the flesh are, without any teacher,
				attractive enough of themselves&mdash;even as these men forget
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.373"/>
				
				 not to say&mdash;to draw even him who will not in the
				least acknowledge and confess that he is softened and rendered pliable by them. <q direct="unspecified">But how comes it to pass,</q> perhaps you will say, <q direct="unspecified">that he who is thus doubtful and
					withholds his assent hastens not away to the mountain,
					instead of going to the bath? Or that, rising up to go
					forth into the market-place, he runs not his head against
					the wall, but takes his way directly to the door?</q> Do you
				ask this, who hold all the senses to be infallible, and the
				apprehensions of the imagination certain and true? It is
				because the bath appears to him not a mountain, but a
				bath; and the door seems not a wall, but a door; and the
				same is to be said of every other thing. For the doctrine
				of retention does not pervert the sense, nor by absurd
				passions and motions work in it an alteration disturbing
				the imaginative faculty; but it only takes away opinions,
				and for the rest, makes use of other things according to
				their nature.</p>
            <p>But it is impossible, you will say, not to consent to
					things that are evident; for to deny such things as are
					believed is more absurd than neither to deny nor affirm.
					Who then are they that call in question things believed,
					and contend against things that are evident? They who
					overthrow and take away divination, who say that there is
					not any government of Divine Providence, who deny the
					sun and the moon&mdash;to whom all men offer sacrifices and
					whom they honor and adore&mdash;to be animated. And do
					not you take away that which is apparent to all the world,
					that the young are contained in the nature of their parents?
					Do you not, contrary to the sense of all men, affirm that
					there is no medium between pleasure and pain, saying that
					not to be in pain is to be in the fruition of pleasure,
					that not to do is to suffer, and that not to rejoice is to be
					grieved?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="28">
            <p>But to let pass all the rest, what is more evident
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.374"/>
				
				and more generally believed by all men, than that those
				who are seized with melancholy distempers, and whose
				brain is troubled and whose wits are distracted, do, when
				the fit is on them and their understanding altered and
				transported, imagine that they see and hear things which
				they neither see nor hear? Whence they frequently cry
				out:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Women in black arrayed bear in their hands,
					</l>
                     <l>To burn mine eyes, torches and fiery brands.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>And again:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>See, in her arms she holds my mother dear.</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Iph. Taur. 289.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>These, and many other illusions more strange and tragical
					than these,&mdash;resembling those mormos and bugbears
					which they themselves laugh at and deride, as they are
					described by Empedocles to be, <q direct="unspecified">with winding feet and
						undivided hands, bodied like ox and faced like man,</q>&mdash;
					with certain other prodigious and unnatural phantoms,
					these men have gathered together out of dreams and the
					alienations of distracted minds, and affirm that none of
					them is a deception of the sight, a falsity, or inconsistence;
					but that all these imaginations are true, being bodies and
					figures that come from the ambient air. What thing then
					is there so impossible in Nature as to be doubted of, if it
					is possible to believe such reveries as these? For these
					men, supposing that such things as never any mask-maker,
					potter, carver of wonderful images, or skilful and all-daring
					painter durst join together, to deceive or make sport for
					the beholders, are seriously and in good earnest existent,&mdash;
					nay, which is more, affirming that, if they are not really
					so, all firmness of belief, all certainty of judgment and
					truth, is for ever gone,&mdash;do by these their suppositions
					and affirmations cast all things into obscurity, and bring
					fears into our judgments, and suspicions into our actions,
					&mdash;if the things which we apprehend, do, are familiarly
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.375"/>
					
					acquainted with, and have at hand are grounded on the
					same imagination and belief with these furious, absurd,
					and extravagant fancies. For the equality which they
					suppose to be in all apprehensions rather derogates from
					the credit of such as are usual and rational, than adds any
					belief to those that are unusual and repugnant to reason.
					Wherefore we know many philosophers who would rather
					and more willingly grant that no imagination is true than
					that all are so, and that would rather simply disbelieve all
					the men they never had conversed with, all the things they
					had not experimented, and all the speeches they had not
					heard with their own ears, than persuade themselves that
					any one of these imaginations, conceived by these frantic,
					fanatical, and dreaming persons, is true. Since then there
					are some imaginations which may, and others which may
					not be rejected, it is lawful for us to retain our assent concerning them, though there were no other cause but this
					discordance, which is sufficient to work in us a suspicion
					of things, as having nothing certain and assured, but being
					altogether full of obscurity and perturbation. For in the
					dissensions about the infinity of worlds and the nature of
					atoms and individuums and their inclinations, although
					they trouble and disturb very many, there is yet this comfort, that none of all these things that are in question is
					near us, but rather every one of them is far remote from
					sense. But as to this diffidence, perplexity, and ignorance
					concerning sensible things and imaginations (whether these
					be true or false), found even in our eyes, our ears, and our
					hands, what opinion does it not shock? What consent
					does it not turn upside down? For if men neither drunk,
					intoxicated, nor otherwise disturbed in their senses, but
					sober, sound in mind, and professedly writing of the truth
					and of the canons and rules by which to judge it, do in
					the most evident passions and motions of the senses set
					down either that which has no existence for true, or that
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.376"/>
					
					which is existent for false, it is not to be wondered that a
					man should be silent about all things, but rather that he
					should give his assent to any thing; nor is it incredible
					that he should have no judgment about things which appear, but rather that he should have contrary judgments.
					For it is less to be wondered, that a man should neither
					affirm the one nor the other but keep himself in a mean
					between two opposite things, than that he should set down
					things repugnant and contrary to one another. For he
					that neither affirms nor denies, but keeps himself quiet, is
					less repugnant to him who affirms an opinion than he who
					denies it, and to him who denies an opinion than he who
					affirms it. Now if it is possible to withhold one's assent
					concerning these things, it is not impossible also concerning others, at least according to your opinion, who say that
					one sense does not exceed another, nor one imagination
					another.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="29">
            <p>The doctrine then of retaining the assent is not, as
				Colotes thinks, a fable or an invention of rash and lightheaded young men who please themselves in babbling
				and prating; but a certain habit and disposition of men
				who desire to keep themselves from falling into error, not
				leaving the judgment at a venture to such suspected and
				inconstant senses, nor suffering themselves to be deceived
				by those who hold that in uncertain matters things which
				do not appear are credible and ought to be believed, when
				they see so great obscurity and uncertainty in things which
				appear. But the infinity you assert is a fable, and so indeed
				are the images you dream of; and he breeds in young men
				rashness and self-conceitedness, who writ of Pythocles, not
				yet eighteen years of age, that there was not in all Greece
				a better or more excellent nature, that he admirably well
				expressed his conceptions, and that he was in other respects like a woman,&mdash;praying that all these extraordinary
				endowments of the young man might not work him hatred
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.377"/>
				
				and envy. But these are sophisters and arrogant, who
				write so impudently and proudly against great and excellent personages. I confess indeed, that Plato, Aristotle,
				Theophrastus, and Democritus contradicted those who
				went before them; but never durst any man besides
				Colotes set forth with such an insolent title as this against
				all at once.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="30">
            <p>Whence it comes to pass that, like to such as have
				offended some Divinity, confessing his fault, he says thus
				towards the end of his book: <q direct="unspecified">Those who have established laws and ordinances and instituted monarchies and
					other governments in towns and cities, have placed human
					life in great repose and security and delivered it from
					many troubles; and if any one should go about to take
					this away, we should lead the life of savage beasts, and
					should be every one ready to eat up one another as we
					meet.</q> For these are the very words of Colotes, though
				neither justly nor truly spoken. For if any one, taking
				away the laws, should leave us nevertheless the doctrines
				of Parmenides, Socrates, Plato, and Heraclitus, we should
				be far from mutually devouring one another and leading
				the life of beasts. For we should fear dishonest things,
				and should for honesty alone venerate justice, the Gods,
				our superiors, and magistrates, believing that we have
				spirits and Daemons who are the guardians and superintendents of human life, esteeming all the gold that is upon
				and within the earth not to be equivalent to virtue; and
				doing that willingly by reason, as Xenocrates says, which
				we now do by force and through fear of the law. When
				then will our life become savage, unsocial, and bestial
				When, the laws being taken away, there shall be left doctrines inciting men to pleasure; when the world shall be
				thought not to be ruled and governed by Divine Providence; when those men shall be esteemed wise who spit
				at honesty if it is not joined with pleasure; and when such
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.378"/>
				
				discourses and sentences as these shall be scoffed at and
				derided:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>For Justice has an eye which all things sees;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and again:
					
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>God near us stands, and views whate'er we do;</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and once more: <q direct="unspecified">God, as antiquity has delivered to us,
					holding the beginning, middle, and end of the universe,
					makes a direct line, walking according to Nature. After
					him follows Justice, a punisher of those who have been
					deficient in their duties by transgressing the divine law.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For they who contemn these things as if they were
					fables, and think that the sovereign good of man consists
					about the belly, and in those other avenues by which
					pleasure is admitted, are such as stand in need of the law,
					and fear, and stripes, and some king, prince, or magistrate,
					having in his hand the sword of justice; to .the end that
					they may not devour their neighbors through their gluttony, rendered confident by their atheistical impiety. For
					this is the life of brutes, because brute beasts know nothing
					better nor more honest than pleasure, understand not the
					justice of the Gods, nor revere the beauty of virtue; but
					if Nature has bestowed on them any point of courage,
					subtlety, or activity, they make use of it for the satisfaction
					of their fleshly pleasure and the accomplishment of their
					lusts. And the wise Metrodorus believes that this should
					be so, for he says: <q direct="unspecified">All the fine, subtle, and ingenious inventions of the soul have been found out for the pleasure
						and delight of the flesh, or for the hopes of attaining to it
						and enjoying it, and every act which tends not to this end is
						vain and unprofitable.</q> The laws being by such discourses
					and philosophical reasons as these taken away, there wants
					nothing to a beast-like life but lions' paws, wolves' teeth,
					oxen's paunches, and camels' necks; and these passions
					and doctrines do the beasts themselves, for want of speech
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.379"/>
					
					and letters, express by their bellowings, neighings, and brayings, all their voice being for their belly and the pleasure
					of their flesh, which they embrace and rejoice in either
					present or future; unless it be perhaps some animal which
					naturally takes delight in chattering and garrulity.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="31">
            <p>No sufficient praise therefore or equivalent to their
				deserts can be given those who, for the restraining of such
				bestial passions, have set down laws, established policy and
				government of state, instituted magistrates and ordained
				good and wholesome laws. But who are they that utterly
				confound and abolish this? Are they not those who withdraw
				themselves and their followers from all part in the government? Are they not those who say that the garland of tranquillity and a reposed life are far more valuable than all the
				kingdoms and principalities in the world? Are they not those
				who declare that reigning and being a king is a mistaking
				the path and straying from the right way of felicity? And
				they write in express terms: <q direct="unspecified">We are to treat how a man
					may best keep and preserve the end of Nature, and how
					he may from the very beginning avoid entering of his own
					free will and voluntarily upon offices of magistracy, and
					government over the people.</q> And yet again, these other
				words are theirs: <q direct="unspecified">There is no need at all that a man
					should tire out his mind and body to preserve the Greeks,
					and to obtain from them a crown of wisdom; but to eat
					and drink well, O Timocrates, without prejudicing, but
					rather pleasing the flesh.</q> And yet in the constitution of
				laws and policy, which Colotes so much praises, the first
				and most important article is the belief and persuasion of
				the Gods. Wherefore also Lycurgus heretofore sanctified the Lacedaemonians, Numa the Romans, the ancient
				Ion the Athenians, and Deucalion universally all the
				Greeks, through prayers, oaths, oracles, and omens, rendering them devout and affectionate to the Gods by means
				of hopes and fears at once. And if you will take the
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.380"/>
				
				pains to travel through the world, you may find towns and
				cities without walls, without letters, without kings, without
				houses, without wealth, without money, without theatres
				and places of exercise; but there was never seen nor shall
				be seen by man any city without temples and Gods, or
				without making use of prayers, oaths, divinations, and sacrifices for the obtaining of blessings and benefits, and the
				averting of curses and calamities. Nay, I am of opinion,
				that a city might sooner be built without any ground to fix
				it on, than a commonweal be constituted altogether void
				of any religion and opinion of the Gods,&mdash;or being constituted, be preserved. But this, which is the foundation
				and ground of all laws, do these men, not going circularly
				about, nor secretly and by enigmatical speeches, but attacking it with the first of their most principal opinions, directly subvert and overthrow; and then afterwards, as if
				they were haunted by the Furies, they come and confess
				that they have grievously offended in thus taking away the
				laws, and confounding the ordinances of justice and policy,
				that they may not be capable of pardon. For to err in
				opinion, though it be not the part of wise men, is at least
				human; but to impute to others the errors and offences
				they commit themselves, how can any one declare what it
				is, if he forbears to give it the name it deserves?</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="32">
            <p>For if, in writing against Antidorus or Bion the
				sophister, he had made mention of laws, policy, order, and
				justice, might not either of them have said to him, as
				Electra did to her mad brother Orestes:
				
				<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lie still at ease, poor wretch; keep in thy bed,</l>
                     <note place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Eurip. Orest. 258.</note>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>and there cherish thy bit of flesh, leaving those to expostulate and find fault with me who have themselves lived a
					civil and domestic life? Now such are all those whom
					Colotes has reviled and railed at in his book. Amongst
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.381"/>
					
					whom, Democritus in his writings advises and exhorts to
					the learning of political science, as being the greatest of
					all, and to the accustoming one's self to bear fatigues, by
					which men attain to great wealth and honor. And as for
					Parmenides, he beautified and adorned his native country
					with most excellent laws which he there established, so
					that even to this day the officers every year, when they
					enter first on the exercise of their charges, are obliged to
					swear that they will observe the laws and ordinances of
					Parmenides. Empedocles brought to justice some of the
					principal of his city, and caused them to be condemned for
					their insolent behavior and embezzling of the public treasure, and also delivered his country from sterility and the
					plague&mdash;to which calamities it was before subject&mdash;by
					immuring and stopping up the holes of certain mountains,
					whence there issued an hot south wind, which overspread
					all the plain country and blasted it. And Socrates, after
					he was condemned, when his friends offered him, if he
					pleased, an opportunity of making his escape, absolutely
					refused to make use of it, that he might maintain the authority of the laws, choosing rather to die unjustly than to
					save himself by disobeying the laws of his country. Melissus, being captain general of his country, vanquished the
					Athenians in a battle at sea. Plato left in his writings excellent discourses concerning the laws, government, and
					policy of a commonweal; and yet he imprinted much better in the hearts and minds of his disciples and familiars,
					which caused Sicily to be delivered by Dion, and Thrace
					to be set at liberty by Pytho and Heraclides, who slew
					Cotys. Chabrias also and Phocion, those two great generals of the Athenians, came out of the Academy. As for
					Epicurus, he indeed sent certain persons into Asia to chide
					Timocrates, and had him removed out of the king's palace,
					because he had offended his brother Metrodorus; and this
					is written in their own books. But Plato sent of his disciples
					
					<pb id="v.5.p.382"/>
					
					 and friends, Aristonymus to the Arcadians, to set in
					order their commonweal, Phormio to the Eleans, and
					Menedemus to the Pyrrhaeans. Eudoxus gave laws to the
					Cnidians, and Aristotle to the Stagirites, who were both of
					them the intimates of Plato. And Alexander the Great
					demanded of Xenocrates rules and precepts for reigning
					well. And he who was sent to the same Alexander by the
					Grecians dwelling in Asia, and who most of all inflamed
					and stimulated him to embrace and undertake the war
					against the barbarian king of Persia, was Delius the
					Ephesian, one of Plato's familiars. Zeno, the disciple of
					Parmenides, having attempted to kill the tyrant Demylus,
					and failing in his design, maintained the doctrine of Parmenides, like pure and fine gold tried in the fire, that there
					is nothing which a magnanimous man ought to dread but
					dishonor, and that there are none but children and women,
					or effeminate and women-hearted men, who fear pain.
					For, having with his own teeth bitten off his tongue, he
					spit it in the tyrant's face.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="33">
            <p>But out of the school of Epicurus, and from among
				those who follow his doctrine, I will not ask what tyrant-killer has proceeded, nor yet what man valiant and victorious in feats of arms, what lawgiver, what prince, what
				counsellor, or what governor of the people; neither will I
				demand, who of them has been tormented or has died for
				supporting right and justice. But which of all these sages
				has for the benefit and service of his country undertaken
				so much as one voyage at sea, gone of an embassy, or expended a sum of money? What record is there extant of
				one civil action in matter of government, performed by any
				of you? And yet, because Metrodorus went down one day
				from the city as far as the haven of Piraeus, taking a
				journey of forty stadia to assist Mithres a Syrian, one of
				the king of Persia's court who had been arrested and
				taken prisoner, he writ of it to every one and in all his
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.383"/>
				
				letters, Epicurus also highly magnifying and extolling this
				wonderful voyage. What value then, think you, would
				they have put upon it, if they had done such an act as
				Aristotle did, who procured the restoration and rebuilding
				of Stagira, the town of his nativity, after it had been destroyed by King Philip? Or as Theophrastus, who twice
				delivered his city, when possessed and held by tyrants?
				Would not the river Nile sooner have given over to bear
				the paper-reed, than they have been weary of writing their
				brave exploits?</p>
            <p>And it is not the greatest indignity, that, of so many
					sects of philosophers as have been extant, they alone
					should enjoy the benefits that are in cities, without having
					ever contributed to them any thing of their own; but far
					worse is it that, while there are not even any tragical or
					comical poets who do not always endeavor to do or say
					some good thing or other in defence of the laws and policy,
					these men, if peradventure they write, write of policy, that
					we may not concern ourselves in the government of the
					commonweal,&mdash;of rhetoric, that we may not perform an
					act of eloquence,&mdash;and of royalty, that we may shun the
					living and conversing with kings. Nor do they ever name
					any of those great personages who have intermeddled in
					civil affairs, but only to scoff at them and abolish their
					glory. Thus they say that Epaminondas had something of
					good, but that very little, or <foreign lang="greek">mikko/n,</foreign> for that is the very word
					they use. They moreover call him iron-hearted, and ask
					what ailed him that he went marching his army through
					all Peloponnesus, and why he did not rather keep himself
					quiet at home with a night-cap on his head, employed only
					in cherishing and making much of his belly. But methinks
					I ought not in this place to omit what Metrodorus writ in
					his book of Philosophy, when, utterly abjuring all meddling
					in the management of the state, he said thus: <q direct="unspecified">Some,
						through an abundance of vanity and arrogance, have so
						
						<pb id="v.5.p.384"/>
						
						deep an insight into the business of it, that in treating
						about the precepts of good life and virtue, they suffer themselves to be carried away with the very same desires as
						were Lycurgus and Solon.</q> What is this? Was it then
					vanity and abundance of vanity, to set free the city of
					Athens, to render Sparta well-policied and governed by
					wholesome laws, that young men might do nothing licentiously, nor get children upon common courtesans and
					whores, and that riches, delights, intemperance, and dissolution might no longer bear sway and have command in
					cities, but law and justice? For these were the desires of
					Solon. To this Metrodorus, by way of scorn and contumely, adds this conclusion: <q direct="unspecified">It is then very well beseeming a free-born gentleman to laugh heartily, as at other
						men, so especially at these Solons and Lycurguses.</q> But
					such a one, O Metrodorus, is not a gentleman, but a servile
					and dissolute person, and deserves to be scourged, not with
					that whip which is for free-born persons, but with that
					scourge strung with ankle-bones, with which those gelded
					sacrificers called Galli were wont to be chastised, when
					they failed of performing their duty in the ceremonies and
					sacrifices of the Goddess Cybele, the great Mother of the
					Gods.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="section" n="34">
            <p>But that they made war not against the lawgivers
				but against the laws themselves, one may hear and understand from Epicurus. For in his questions, he asks himself, whether a wise man, being assured that it will not be
				known, will do any thing that the laws forbid. To which
				he answers: <q direct="unspecified">That is not so easy to determine simply,</q>&mdash;
				that is, <q direct="unspecified">I will do it indeed, but I am not willing to confess it.</q> And again, I suppose, writing to Idomeneus, he
				exhorts him not to make his life a slave to the laws or to
				the opinions of men, unless it be to avoid the trouble they
				prepare, by the scourge and chastisement, so near at hand.
				If then those who abolish the laws, governments, and
				
				<pb id="v.5.p.385"/>
				
				policies of men subvert and destroy human life, and if
				Metrodorus and Epicurus do this, by dehorting and withdrawing their friends from concerning themselves in public
				affairs, by hating those who intermeddle in them, by reviling the first most wise lawgivers, and by advising contempt of the laws provided there is no fear and danger of
				the whip and punishment, I do not see that Colotes has
				brought so many false accusations against the other philosophers as he has alleged and advanced true ones against
				the writings and doctrines of Epicurus.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>