<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>

<TEI.2>

    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Dinarchus</author> &responsibility; &fund.AnnCPB; </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 485Kb</extent> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Dinarchus</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                <state unit="speech"/>
                <state unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="en">English </language>
                <language id="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>April and May 1992</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>SGML markup</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 n="1" type="speech">
                <head>Against Demosthenes</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This popular
                    leader of yours, Athenians, who has imposed on himself a sentence of death
                    should he be proved to have taken even the smallest sum from Harpalus, has been
                    clearly convicted of taking bribes from those very men whom he formerly
                    professed to oppose. Much has already been said by Stratocles<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Stratocles the orator, who proposed that special honors
                        should be paid to Lycurgus after his death &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Plut. Lyc. 852a">Plut. Vit. Lyc. 852 A</bibl>&rpar;, may possibly
                        be the same man as the general of that name who served at <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.</note> and most of the charges
                    have now been made; as regards the report itself the Areopagus has expressed
                    opinions which are both just and true, while with events succeeding this
                    Stratocles has already dealt and read the decrees relating to them. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/>It remains for us, Athenians, especially when
                    contesting a case never paralleled in the experience of the city, to make a
                    general exhortation to you all. May we ask you first to pardon those of us who
                    have still to speak if there are certain points which we raise again; our aim is
                    not to weary you by alluding twice to the same matters but to arouse your anger
                    all the more. Secondly, may we ask you not to surrender the rights enjoyed by
                    the whole city or to barter away our common security in exchange for the
                    arguments of the defendant. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>You are aware,
                    Athenians, that whereas this man Demosthenes is here for judgement before you,
                    you are on trial before your fellows. For they are waiting to see what kind of
                    conclusion you will reach about your country's interests: are you going to
                    welcome into your midst the private venality and corruption of these people, or
                    will you make it universally known that you hate men who accept bribes against
                    their city and that, in ordering the Areopagus to make its inquiry, your
                    intention was not to acquit the culprits but rather, when the councillors had
                    made their report, to exact punishment in a manner appropriate to the crimes?
                    This decision then rests with you now. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>For when
                    the people passed a lawful decree and every citizen wished to discover which of
                    the politicians had dared to accept money from Harpalus to the discredit and
                    danger of the city; when, moreover, you, Demosthenes, and many others had
                    proposed in a decree that the Areopagus, according to its traditional right,
                    should hold an inquiry to discover if any of them had received gold from
                    Harpalus, the Areopagus began its investigation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    />In reaching a just decision it paid no heed to your challenges, Demosthenes,
                    nor did it wish to pervert the truth or destroy its own reputation on your
                    account. On the contrary, gentlemen, although, as the Areopagites themselves
                    said, the council realized beforehand the strength of these men and their
                    influence as orators and statesmen, it did not consider that if incrimination or
                    danger was threatening its country it ought to be influenced by any
                    misrepresentation likely to be published about itself. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>Though this investigation has been conducted, in the
                    people's opinion, both fairly and profitably, accusations, challenges, and
                    calumnies are proceeding from Demosthenes, since he has been listed as the
                    holder of twenty talents of gold. Will that council then which, in cases of
                    willful] murder, is trustworthy enough to arrive at truth and justice and is
                    empowered to pass judgement in matters of life and death on each of the
                    citizens, to take up the cause of those who have met a violent end and banish or
                    execute any in the city who have broken the law,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                        >After the restoration of the democracy in <date value="-403">403</date>
                        B.C. the Areopagus played a more important part in public affairs than in
                        the preceding half-century. It dealt with all cases of voluntary homicide
                        and sometimes with political cases also, when it could act either on its own
                        initiative &lpar;cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.63">Din. 1.63</bibl> and <bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.133">Dem. 18.133</bibl>&rpar; or in response to the
                        people's request, as in the present instance. See <bibl n="Din. 1.50">Din.
                            1.50</bibl>.</note> be powerless now to administer justice over the
                    money credited to Demosthenes? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone
                        ed="P" unit="para"/>It will; for the council has told lies against
                    Demosthenes. This is the crowning argument in his case. It has told lies, has
                    it, against you and Demades: men against whom it is evidently not even safe to
                    speak the truth; though you previously instructed the Areopagus to investigate
                    many public matters and expressed approval of it for the inquiries which it had
                    held? Are the indictments which the council has made against these men false
                    when the whole city cannot compel them to do right? Great Heavens! <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/>Then why, Demosthenes, did you agree in the Assembly
                    to a penalty of death for yourself, if the report of the council should turn out
                    against you? And why have you yourself ruined many others by insisting on the
                    findings of the council? To what authority should the people now refer, or to
                    whom should it entrust the inquiry in the event of mysterious or momentous
                    crimes, if it is to discover the truth? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>For the
                    council which formerly commanded confidence is being discredited by you, who
                    claim to be the people's man, though it is a body to which the people gave in
                    trust the protection of their lives, to whose charge they have often committed
                    their constitution and democracy, a council which, destined though you were to
                    malign it, has safeguarded your life, according to your own account so often
                    threatened, and which keeps the mystic deposits<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                        >The exact nature of these mystic deposits, on which the welfare of the
                        community was thought to depend, is not known; they were probably
                        oracles.</note> whereby the safety of the city is preserved. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now in one
                    respect&mdash;for I shall speak my mind&mdash;the Areopagus fully
                    deserves this treatment. It was faced with two alternatives. One would have
                    been, in accordance with the people's instructions, to conduct the previous
                    investigation over the three hundred talents which came from the Persian
                        king<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">After Alexander's accession Darius
                        subsidized several Greek states to oppose him. Three hundred talents offered
                        by him to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and officially
                        refused were said to have been accepted by Demosthenes to be used in the
                        king's interest. Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.18">Din. 1.18</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Aeschin. 3.239">Aeschin. 3.239</bibl> &lpar;who gives the sum
                        which Demosthenes appropriated as seventy talents&rpar;; <bibl
                            n="Diod. 17.4">Dio. Sic. 17.4</bibl>.</note>; in which case this monster
                    would have been convicted and the names of those who shared the money published;
                    the betrayal of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, for which
                    Demosthenes was responsible,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In <date
                            value="-335">335</date> B.C., owing to a report that Alexander, who was
                        fighting the Triballi, had been killed, <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> revolted against Macedonian domination encouraged by
                        Demosthenes and others who assisted them to procure arms. When they applied
                        for assistance to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>
                        and <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, the Peloponnesians
                        sent an army as far as the Isthmus, while <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> voted help but awaited the turn of events. Meanwhile
                            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> was taken by
                        Alexander and destroyed. Dinarchus, who goes into greater detail later
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 1.18">Din. 1.18-22</bibl>&rpar;, maintains
                        that for ten talents of the Persian money Demosthenes could have secured the
                        help of the Peloponnesian army but was too miserly to do so. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Diod. 17.8">Dio. Sic. 17.8</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.239">Aeschin.
                            3.239-240</bibl>.</note> would have been exposed, and we, exacting from
                    this demagogue the punishment he deserved, would have been rid of him.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Alternatively, if it was your wish to
                    forgive Demosthenes for these offences and to have in the city a large number of
                    people who would take bribes against you, the council ought, having tested your
                    wishes in the previous cases, to have refused to undertake an investigation over
                    the payments of money recently reported. For despite the excellence and the
                    justice of this recent report, which incriminates Demosthenes and the rest of
                    them, and despite the fact that the Areopagus has not deferred to the power of
                    Demosthenes or Demades but has regarded justice and truth as more important,
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>Demosthenes goes round none the less
                    maligning the council and telling the same stories about himself with which he
                    will probably try to mislead you presently. &ldquo;I made the Thebans your
                        allies.&rdquo;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">In making this claim
                        Demosthenes was referring to events just before the battle of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> when he won <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> over to <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by offering her more liberal
                        terms than Philip. For his defence of this policy see <bibl n="Dem. 18.153"
                            >Dem. 18.153</bibl> sq.</note> No, Demosthenes, you impaired the common
                    interest of both our states. &ldquo;I brought everyone into line at
                        <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.&rdquo; On the
                    contrary you yourself were the only one to leave the line at <placeName
                        key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The
                        charge of cowardice in battle is often brought against Demosthenes by
                        Aeschines &lpar;e.g. <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.175">Aeschin.
                        3.175</bibl>&rpar;; it is mentioned by Plutarch &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Plut. Dem. 20.2">Plut. Dem. 855 A</bibl>&rpar; and in the
                            <title>Lives of the Ten Orators</title> &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Plut. Dec. Orat. 845f">Plut. Vit. 845 F</bibl>&rpar;.</note>
                    &ldquo;I served on many embassies on your behalf.&rdquo; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/>One wonders what he would have done or what he would
                    have said if the course that he had recommended on these missions had proved
                    successful, when, after touring the whole Greek world to negotiate such
                    disasters and mistakes, he still claims to have been granted the greatest
                    privileges, namely those of accepting bribes against his country and saying and
                    doing whatever he wishes against the public interest. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/>You made no allowance for Timotheus,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">The following passage is repeated almost word for word in the
                        speech against Philocles &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 3.17">Din.
                        3.17</bibl>&rpar;. Timotheus, an Athenian general and a friend of
                        Isocrates, who recounts his exploits &lpar;<bibl n="Isoc. 15.107">Isoc.
                            15.107-113</bibl>&rpar;, sailed round the <placeName
                            key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and gained a victory at
                            <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName> in <date value="-375"
                            >375</date> B.C. In 365 he took <placeName key="tgn,7002673"
                            >Samos</placeName>, which was occupied by a Persian garrison, after a
                        ten months' siege &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 15.9">Dem. 15.9</bibl>&rpar;.
                        Thence he moved to <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> and
                        mastered several Chalcidian cities, of which Dinarchus here mentions three.
                        In 356 he was sent out with two others to reinforce the fleet of Chares who
                        was trying to crush an allied revolt; but in a sea battle near <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName> he failed to help Chares, owing to
                        stormy weather, and was therefore prosecuted by him for bribery. Timotheus
                        was not popular owing to his haughty behavior; and being fined the
                        unprecedented amount of a hundred talents, which he could not pay, he went
                        into exile in <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>. Cf.
                            <bibl n="Isoc. 15.131">Isoc. 15.131</bibl>.</note> Athenians, although
                    he sailed round the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and
                    defeated the Lacedaemonians in a naval battle at <placeName key="tgn,7010886"
                        >Corcyra</placeName>, and was the son of <placeName key="tgn,1123029"
                            >Conon</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, a general in the Peloponnesian war
                        who fought at <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>, was
                        later joint commander of the Persian fleet. In this capacity he rendered a
                        service to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by defeating
                        the Spartan Pisander in a naval battle off <placeName key="tgn,5003757"
                            >Cnidus</placeName> in <date value="-394">394</date> B.C.</note> too who
                    liberated <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. Though he captured
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Pydna"
                        >Pydna</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>, and
                    twenty other cities besides, you did not permit such services to outweigh the
                    trial which you were then conducting or the oaths that governed your vote;
                    instead you fined him a hundred talents because Aristophon said that he had
                    accepted money from the Chians and Rhodians. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                    />Will you then absolve this abominable wretch, this Scythian,&mdash;really
                    I cannot contain myself,&mdash;whom no mere individual but the whole
                    Areopagus has shown, after inquiry, to be in possession of money to your
                    detriment, whose bribery and corruption against the city have been revealed and
                    established beyond doubt? Will you not punish him and make him an example to
                    others? He is known not only to have taken gold from the royal treasuries<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See note on <bibl n="Din. 1.10">Din.
                        1.10</bibl></note> but also to have enriched himself at the city's own
                    expense, since he did not even withhold his hand from the money lately brought
                    to her by Harpalus. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>Yet the embassies to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> which Demosthenes
                    undertook are equivalent to a mere fraction of Timotheus' services; and which of
                    you, contrasting with the exploits on which Demosthenes prides himself those
                    which Timotheus and <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> performed on
                    your behalf, would not laugh to scorn all who consented to listen to this man?
                    But then there should be no comparison made between this outcast and the men who
                    in your interests acted worthily of the city and your ancestors. I will
                    therefore cite the decree which was passed concerning Timotheus and then return
                    to my review of the defendant. Read.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This citizen,
                    Demosthenes, of such a character, who might well have gained the pardon and
                    gratitude of his colleagues in the public life of those days, since he had
                    rendered great services to the city, not in word only but in deed, and had
                    always remained true to the same policy rather than changing to and fro as you
                    have done, met his death without begging the people for such extensive favors as
                    would set him above the laws or thinking that men who had sworn to vote in
                    accordance with the law should consider anything more important than their word;
                    he was ready even for condemnation, if the jury decided upon it, and did not
                    plead the inclemency of circumstance or express in public opinions which he did
                    not hold. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Will
                    you not execute this accursed wretch, Athenians, who, in addition to many other
                    crucial blunders, stood by while the Thebans' city was destroyed, though he had
                    accepted three hundred talents from the Persian King for their protection though
                    the Arcadians,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See note on <bibl n="Din. 1.10"
                            >Din. 1.10</bibl></note> arriving at the Isthmus, had dismissed with a
                    rebuff the envoys of Antipater and welcomed those from the unhappy Thebans who
                    had reached them with difficulty by sea, bearing a suppliant's staff and
                    heralds' wands, plaited, they said, from olive shoots? <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/>They came to assure the Arcadians that no wish to break
                    their friendship with the Greeks had led the Thebans to a revolution, nor did
                    they intend to do anything to the detriment of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>; but they were no longer able to countenance at home the
                    behavior of the Macedonians in the city, to endure slavery, or to witness the
                    outrages perpetrated against the persons of free men. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/>The Arcadians were ready to help them and, sympathizing with
                    their misfortunes, explained that, though they were compelled through force of
                    circumstance to serve Alexander with their persons, in spirit they sided always
                    with the Thebans and the cause of Greek liberty. Since their leader, Astylus,
                    was open to bribery, as Stratocles said, and wanted ten talents as the price of
                    helping the Thebans, the envoys approached Demosthenes who, as they knew, held
                    the King's gold and earnestly begged him to spend the money to save their city.
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>But this hard-hearted and impious miser
                    could not bring himself to expend, from his great resources, ten paltry talents,
                    though he saw such high hopes dawning for the salvation of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. Instead, as Stratocles said, he
                    allowed others to provide this sum to induce those of the Arcadians who had
                    marched out to return home and deny their help to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. <milestone n="22" unit="section"
                    />Do you consider that the evils for which Demosthenes and his avarice have been
                    responsible are trivial or of little import for the whole of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>? Do you think that he deserves any pity
                    at your hands after committing such offences? Should he not rather suffer the
                    extreme penalty to atone for his crimes, both past and present? The verdict
                    given by you today, Athenians, will be heard by all mankind, who will observe
                    how you, the judges, treat the man with such a record. <milestone n="23"
                        unit="section"/>You are the people who, for crimes far smaller than those
                    Demosthenes has committed, have inflicted on men severe and irrevocable
                    penalties. It was you who killed Menon the miller, because he kept a free boy
                    from <placeName key="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName> in his mill. You
                    punished with death Themistius of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna"
                        >Aphidna</placeName>, because he assaulted the Rhodian lyre-player at the
                    Eleusinian festival, and Euthymachus, because he put the Olynthian girl in a
                    brothel. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>But through this traitor children and
                    women, the wives of the Thebans, were distributed among the tents of the
                    barbarians, a neighboring and allied city has been torn up from the midst of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and the site of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> is being ploughed and sown, the city
                    of men who shared with you the war against Philip. Yes, it is being ploughed and
                    sown. And this unfeeling wretch showed no compassion for a city thus lamentably
                    destroyed, though he visited it as an envoy representing you and has often
                    shared the meat and drink of its citizens, claiming himself that he made it our
                    ally. But those to whom he often resorted in their prosperity he has betrayed in
                    their misfortune. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>The Thebans, so our elders
                    tell us, when the democracy in our city had been overthrown and Thrasybulus was
                    assembling the exiles in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
                    ready for the seizure of <placeName key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName>,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Thrasybulus and Anytus, exiled by the Thirty,
                        were received in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. After
                        seizing and holding the fortress of <placeName key="perseus,Phyle"
                            >Phyle</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> in
                            <date value="-404">404</date> B.C., they subsequently occupied the
                            <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> and, with the
                        intervention of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, brought
                        about the restoration of democracy in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName>.</note> although the Spartans were strong and
                    forbade them to admit or let out any Athenian, helped the democrats to return
                    and passed that decree which has so often been read before you, stating that
                    they would turn a blind eye if any Athenian marched through their territory
                    bearing arms. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>This man who fraternizes, as he
                    will presently tell you, with our allies, behaved very differently; he would not
                    part with any of the money which he had received for their protection. Remember
                    these things, gentlemen; consider the disasters caused by traitors in the
                    downfall of <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> and of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>; decide wisely now in
                    your interest; destroy those who are ready to take bribes against their country
                    and so rest your hopes of safety on yourselves and on the gods. <milestone
                        n="27" unit="section"/>For there is only one way, Athenians, in which you
                    will reform the rest of mankind, only one way: to expose those criminals who are
                    notable men and punish them as their crimes deserve. In the case of the average
                    defendant no one knows or troubles to inquire, when he is convicted, what has
                    been his sentence. But with men of note everyone hears the news and praises the
                    jury, when they have not sacrificed the interests of justice in deference to the
                    reputation of the defendants. Read the Theban decree. Cite the evidence. Read
                    the letters.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Evidence">
                        <title>Evidence</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Letters">
                        <title>Letters</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This man is a
                    hireling, Athenians, a hireling of long standing. It was he who summoned from
                        <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> the embassy coming to us
                    from Philip and was responsible for finishing the first war.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">The first war with <placeName key="tgn,7002715"
                            >Macedon</placeName> &lpar;<dateRange from="-349" to="-346"
                            >349</dateRange>-346 B.C.&rpar; was undertaken by <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName
                            key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> against Philip. Even before
                            <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> was taken the
                        king made overtures of peace, and it was Philocrates who proposed in
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> that these
                        negotiations should begin. However, after the fall of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> in 348, the Athenians tried
                        to unite other Greek states against Philip, and it was not until this
                        attempt had failed that Demosthenes acquiesced in peace proposals. In 347 he
                        defended Philocrates, who was accused of illegality in making his first
                        peace proposals, and himself served on an embassy to <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>. The final peace was signed in
                        346, when Antipater and Parmenio came to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> as Philip's envoys. Philocrates was prosecuted by
                        Hyperides in 343 for being bribed by Philip and went into exile. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Hyp. Fr. 16">Hyp. frag. 16</bibl></note> He helped to defend
                    Philocrates who proposed the peace with Philip and was exiled by you in
                    consequence, he hired a carriage for the envoys who came here with Antipater,
                    and by attaching them to himself, first introduced into the city the custom of
                    flattering <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>. <milestone n="29"
                        unit="section"/>Do not acquit him, Athenians. Do not let go unpunished this
                    man who has endorsed the misfortunes of his country and the rest of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, when he has been caught with bribes
                    against the city in his very hands. Now that good fortune is improving your lot
                    and, after expelling from the city one of the two who have defiled their
                    country, has surrendered this other to you for execution, do not oppose all our
                    interests yourselves but rather bring happier omens to our state affairs and
                    divert our misfortunes on to the heads of these leaders. <milestone n="30"
                        unit="section"/>Against what occasion will you reserve Demosthenes in the
                    belief that he will prove useful to you? Could any one of you, or of the
                    bystanders, say what public or private affairs he has not ruined by his contact
                    with them? After gaining access to the home of Aristarchus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">This story is told more fully by Aeschines &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Aeschin. 1.171">Aeschin. 1.171</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.148"
                            >Aeschin. 2.148</bibl> and <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.166">Aeschin.
                            2.166</bibl>&rpar;, who says that Aristarchus son of Moschus was a
                        wealthy orphan, half mad, from whom Demosthenes, pretending to have taken a
                        fancy to him personally, extracted three talents. He asserts that together
                        they contrived to murder, with great brutality, Nicodemus of Aphidna who had
                        once prosecuted Demosthenes for desertion; as the result of which crime
                        Aristarchus went into exile. Demosthenes himself mentions the murder in his
                        speech against Midias, where he claims that Midias went about casting
                        suspicion on him and persuaded the relatives of Nicodemus to do likewise
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 21.104">Dem. 21.104</bibl>&rpar;. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Ath. 23.592">Athen. 23.592 f</bibl>.</note> and planning with him the
                    death of Nicodemus which they contrived, an affair of which you all know the
                    details, did he not banish Aristarchus on the most shameful charges? And did not
                    Aristarchus find in Demosthenes such a friend as to make him think that this was
                    some evil spirit which had visited him and the originator of all his
                    misfortunes? <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>Is it not true that once this man
                    began to advise the city, and would he had never done so,&mdash;I shall pass
                    over his private affairs, for time does not permit me to speak at
                    length,&mdash;absolutely no good has befallen it; indeed not only the city
                    but the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> has been
                    involved in dangers, misfortunes, and dishonor? Is it not true that he has had
                    many opportunities while speaking to you and yet let slip every opportunity to
                    help you? On those occasions when a patriot with any regard for the city would
                    have chosen to make some move, this demagogue, who will presently say that he
                    has been of service to you, was so far from showing signs of action that he even
                    infected with his own ill-luck the men who were doing something to further your
                    interests. <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>Charidemus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Charidemus of <placeName key="perseus,Oreos"
                            >Oreos</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>
                        was made an Athenian citizen for his services as a soldier &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Dem. 23.151">Dem. 23.151</bibl>&rpar;. He went to <placeName
                            key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> in <date value="-335">335</date>
                        B.C., having been banished from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> on the orders of Alexander &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Arr. An. 1.10.6">Arr. 1.10.6</bibl>&rpar;, and after being well
                        received at first by Darius, fell under suspicion two years later and was
                        executed &lpar;<bibl n="Diod. 17.30">Dio. Sic.
                        17.30</bibl>&rpar;.</note> set out to visit the Persian King, wishing to
                    do you some practical service apart from mere talking, and anxious at his own
                    peril to win safety for you and every Greek. Demosthenes went round the market
                    making speeches and associating himself with the project. So completely did
                    fortune wreck this plan that it turned out in just the opposite way to what was
                    expected. <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>Ephialtes put to sea. Admittedly he
                    hated Demosthenes but he was compelled to have a partner in public affairs.
                    Fortune robbed the city of this man too.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The
                        facts are here distorted. Ephialtes, one of the orators whose surrender was
                        demanded by Alexander in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C. &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Arr. An. 1.104">Arr. 1.104</bibl>&rpar;, was a supporter of
                        Demosthenes and, according to the Pseudo-Plutarch, brought back money for
                        the demagogues from the Persian court &lpar;<bibl n="Plut. Dem. 847f"
                            >Plut. Vit. Dem. 847 F</bibl> and 848 E&rpar;. He was killed while
                        helping the Persians to defend <placeName key="tgn,7016142"
                            >Halicarnassus</placeName> against Alexander &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Diod. 17.27">Dio. Sic. 17.27</bibl>&rpar;.</note> Euthydicus<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">No details are known of Euthydicus. He seems to
                        be mentioned as an Athenian patriot together with Ephialtes and Lycurgus in
                        the third letter of Demosthenes &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. L. 3.31">Dem. L
                            3.31</bibl>&rpar;, where however the MSS. have <foreign lang="greek"
                            >*eu)/dilkon</foreign>.</note> elected to work for the people.
                    Demosthenes claimed to be his friend. He too was lost. Do not these facts, which
                    you see and know better than I do, give you cause for thought? Do they not make
                    you weigh up your future prospects in the light of the past and reflect in your
                    own minds that this man is of no use except to our enemies, against the
                    interests of the city<gap/>? <milestone n="34" unit="section"/><gap/>to raise
                    such another force as we had in the time of Agis,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">While Alexander was in the East, Agis the Third of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> rose against <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> with the help of Darius in <date
                            value="-333">333</date> B.C. In 331 he headed an army raised by various
                        Greek states but was refused the support of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName>, on the advice of Demosthenes. Defeated near
                            <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> by
                        Antipater he was killed in battle &lpar;<bibl n="Diod. 17.48">Dio. Sic.
                            17.48</bibl> and <bibl n="Diod. 17.62">Dio. Sic.
                        17.62</bibl>&rpar;.</note> when the Spartans took the field together and
                    Achaeans and men of <placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> were taking
                    their part in the campaign with ten thousand mercenaries also; when Alexander
                    was in <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Alexander was, in fact, in <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
                            >Persia</placeName>.</note> according to report, and the whole of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, owing to the traitors in
                    every city, was dissatisfied with the existing state of things and hoped for
                    some release from the misfortunes that beset her. In that hour,&mdash;for I
                    need not dwell on other crises,&mdash; <milestone n="35" unit="section"
                    />what was the behavior of this Demosthenes who had the power to give advice and
                    make proposals, who will shortly tell you that he hates our present
                    circumstances? On these matters, Demosthenes, did you offer any proposal, any
                    advice? Did you contribute money? Were you of the smallest value to the men
                    safeguarding us all? Not the least; you went round suborning speechwriters. He
                    wrote a letter at home, defiling the city's honor, <milestone n="36"
                        unit="section"/>and walked about dangling it from his finger ends, living in
                    luxury during the city's misfortunes, travelling down the road to the <placeName
                        key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> in a litter and reproaching the
                    needy for their poverty. Is this man then going to prove useful to you on future
                    occasions, when he has let slip every opportunity in the past? By our lady
                    Athena and Zeus the Savior, I could wish that the enemies of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had lighted upon counsellors and
                    leaders like him and never better. <milestone n="37" unit="section"/><milestone
                        ed="P" unit="para"/>Let me remind you, gentlemen, of the conduct of your
                    forbears, who, at a time when many grave perils beset the city, faced danger in
                    the interests of the people, in a manner worthy of their country and their
                    well-earned reputation, as befitted free men. Time does not permit me to deal
                    with those figures of the past, Aristides and Themistocles: the men who built
                    the city's walls and carried up to the Acropolis the tribute paid by the willing
                    and even eager Greeks. <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>But you will recall
                    what was done, shortly before our own time, by Cephalus the orator, Thrason of
                    Herchia, Eleus and Phormisius and other fine men, some of whom are still alive
                        today.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cephalus assisted in the overthrow of
                        the Thirty in <date value="-403">403</date> B.C. His reputation as an orator
                        is acknowledged by Demosthenes &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 18.219">Dem.
                            18.219</bibl>&rpar;. Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.76">Din. 1.76</bibl>. Of
                        the other three men little is known. Thrason is mentioned as a Theban
                        proxenus by Aeschines &lpar;<bibl n="Aeschin. 3.139">Aeschin.
                            3.139</bibl>&rpar;; Eleus is perhaps the trierarch &lpar;c.
                        323&rpar; whose name appears in an inscription &lpar;I.G. 2.812, b.
                        14&rpar;; Phormisius is a mere name. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 34.3">Aristot. Const. Ath. 34.3</bibl>.</note>
                    Some of them, when the Cadmea was garrisoned by Spartans, assisted the exiles
                    who returned to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and at their
                    own risk set free a neighboring city, long enslaved.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">In <date value="-382">382</date> B.C. Thebes was betrayed to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and many leading men
                        were exiled. These took refuge at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName>, with whose help in 378 they soon overthrew the new
                        government and ejected the Spartan garrison from the city &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Diod. 15.25">Dio. Sic. 15.25</bibl>&rpar;.</note>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>Others lent aid when your ancestors were
                    persuaded to take the field by Cephalus, who proposed the decree and who,
                    undaunted by the might of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and
                    regardless of the risks either of military or political action, moved that the
                    Athenians should march out to help the exiles who had taken Thebes. Your fathers
                    did march out and in a few days the commander of the Spartan garrison was
                    expelled, the Thebans had been freed and your city had acted worthily of your
                    ancestors. <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>They were counsellors, Athenians,
                    they were leaders such as yourselves and the state deserve. How different from
                    rogues like this who neither have done nor will do the city any service but
                    watch over their own safety and treat everything as a source of income. They
                    have made the city more infamous than themselves, and now, convicted of taking
                    bribes against you, they deceive you and presume, after conduct such as this, to
                    talk to you about their own aggrandizement. They ought, by the terms of their
                    own decree, to have been put to death long ago for doing such things. <milestone
                        n="41" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Are you not ashamed,
                    Athenians, that you should think our speeches the only evidence you have on
                    which to determine the punishment of Demosthenes? Do you not know yourselves
                    that this man is open to bribes and is both a robber and a traitor to his
                    friends that neither he nor the fortune which has gone with him is fit for the
                    city? Are there any decrees or any laws which have not brought him money?
                        <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>Are there any people in the court who were
                    among those included in the three hundred when Demosthenes brought in his law
                    concerning the trierarchs?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the trierarch law
                        see note on <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 43">Hyp. frag. 43</bibl>.</note> Then tell
                    your neighbors that he accepted three talents and used to alter and re-draft the
                    law for every sitting of the Assembly, in some cases taking money over points
                    for which he had been paid already, in others failing to honor the sales which
                    he had made. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>Really, gentlemen, tell me: do
                    you think he got nothing for proposing that Diphilus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Little is known of the various men mentioned in this section.
                        Diphilus was perhaps the son of Diopithes, trierarch in 325/4 and <dateRange
                            from="-323" to="-322">323</dateRange>/2 B.C. &lpar;CIA 2.809 d, 53
                        and 811 b, 104&rpar;. For Chaerephilus, a dealer in salt fish, compare
                            <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 34">Hyp. frag. 34</bibl> and <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 35"
                            >Hyp. frag. 35</bibl>. The three names following his are those of his
                        sons. All four were evidently put in the deme of Paeania, Pamphilus and
                        Phidippus being mentioned as members of it in inscriptions &lpar;CIA
                        2.172 and CIA 2.811 d, 142&rpar;. Cf. also <bibl n="Ath. 3.119">Athen.
                            3.119</bibl> sq. and <bibl n="Ath. 8.339">Athen. 8.339 d</bibl>.
                        Berisades is probably the same man as Paerisades, a king of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> to whom Demosthenes refers
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 34.8">Dem. 34.8</bibl>&rpar;; Satyrus was
                        his son.</note> should have meals at the Prytaneum or for that statue to be
                    put up in the market? Nothing for conferring Athenian citizenship on
                    Chaerephilus, Phidon, Pamphilus, and Phidippus, or again on Epigenes and
                    <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> the bankers? Nothing for
                    putting up in the market bronze statues of Berisades, Satyrus and Gorgippus the
                    tyrants from the <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, from whom he
                    receives a thousand medimni of wheat a year&mdash;this man who will
                    presently tell you that there is nowhere for him to take refuge. <milestone
                        n="44" unit="section"/>Did he get nothing for proposing that
                        Taurosthenes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Dinarchus, like Aeschines, is
                        distorting the facts. &lpar;Cf. <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.85">Aeschin. 3
                            85</bibl> sq. and schol. ad loc.&rpar;. The cities of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> had entered the Athenian alliance
                        in <date value="-357">357</date> B.C., but in 348 they revolted, probably
                        owing to the intrigues of Philip with whom <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> was now at war over <placeName
                            key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>. Taurosthenes and Callias
                        commanded the army of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>
                        and the Athenians lost control of the island. In 343 however they
                        transferred the allegiance of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis"
                            >Chalcis</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName>, and a few years later-the exact date is not
                        certain-were made Athenian citizens on the motion of Demosthenes
                        &lpar;cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col. 20</bibl>&rpar;, whom
                        Aeschines says they bribed.</note> should become an Athenian, though he had
                    enslaved his fellow citizens and, with his brother Callias, betrayed the whole
                    of <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> to Philip? Taurosthenes whom
                    the laws forbid to set foot on Athenian soil, providing that if he does so he
                    shall be liable to the same penalties as an exile who returns after being
                    sentenced by the Areopagus. This was the man who Demosthenes the democrat
                    proposed should be your fellow citizen. <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>Is
                    there any need then for me to call up witnesses for you so far as these men are
                    concerned or any of the others whom he has proposed as proxeni or citizens? I
                    ask you in Athena's name: do you imagine that when he gladly accepts silver he
                    would refuse twenty talents of gold? Do you think that though he takes money in
                    dribblets, he would not accept as a lump sum so great a fee, or that the
                    Areopagus, which spent six months inquiring over Demosthenes, Demades, and
                        Cephisophon,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This is probably the same
                        Cephisophon, a politician of the time, as is mentioned by Demosthenes
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 18.21">Dem. 18.21</bibl> and <bibl
                            n="Dem. 19.293">Dem. 19.293</bibl>&rpar;.</note> has been unjust
                    over the reports submitted to you? <milestone n="46" unit="section"/><milestone
                        ed="P" unit="para"/>Gentlemen, you have very many witnesses, as I said
                    before, among citizens and other Greeks, watching to see how you will judge this
                    trial; are you, they wonder, going to bring within the scope of the courts the
                    venal actions of other men, or will there be complete freedom to accept bribes
                    against you? Will the things which so far have been held trustworthy and sure
                    now cease to be so on account of the trial of Demosthenes? On his past record he
                    ought to have been put to death, and he is liable to all the curses known to the
                    city, <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>having broken the oaths he took on the
                    Areopagus, in the names of the holy goddesses and the other deities by whom it
                    is customary to swear there, and making himself accursed at every sitting of the
                    Assembly. He has been proved to have taken bribes against <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, has cheated the people and the
                    council in defiance of the curse, professing views he does not hold, and in
                    private has recommended to Aristarchus a course both cruel and unlawful.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.30">Din. 1.30</bibl> and
                        note.</note> For these misdeeds, if there is any power to exact a just
                    punishment from perjurers and criminals&mdash;as there surely
                    is&mdash;this man shall pay today. Gentlemen of the jury, listen to the
                        curse.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the curse pronounced by the
                        herald before each sitting of the Council and Assembly on all who might be
                        acting treasonably against the state compare <bibl n="Lyc. 1.31">Lyc.
                            1.31</bibl>.</note><quote type="Curse">
                        <title>Curse</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Despite this,
                    gentlemen of the jury, Demosthenes is so ready with his lies and utterly unsound
                    assertions, so oblivious of shame, exposure, or curse, that he will dare to say
                    of me, I gather, that I too was previously condemned by the council. According
                    to him I am behaving with the utmost inconsistency, because in the past I
                    opposed the council's report and pleaded my own case, whereas I am now serving
                    as its advocate and accusing him over the report before us today. <milestone
                        n="49" unit="section"/>This is a story of his own invention, not based on
                    fact, and he is impudent enough to lie to you. So to make sure that, if he
                    embarks upon this story, you will pay no attention to him but will realize fully
                    that the council did not report me and was in no danger of doing
                    so,&mdash;the truth being that I suffered at the hands of a man of low
                    character who has been convicted before you,&mdash;let me explain briefly.
                    Then I will come back to Demosthenes. <milestone n="50" unit="section"
                        /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The council of the Areopagus is bound,
                    gentlemen, to follow one of two methods in making all its reports. What are
                    these methods? Its inquiry is made either on its own initiative or in obedience
                    to the people's instructions.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See note on <bibl
                            n="Din. 1.6">Din. 1.6</bibl>.</note> Apart from these two, there is no
                    other procedure it could follow. If then you tell us, you abominable brute, that
                    the council followed the people's instructions in making its inquiry and
                    publishing the report on me, <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>show me the
                    decree and tell me who were my accusers after the report was made. Compare the
                    present case, where you have both: a decree which authorized the council's
                    inquiry, and accusers, elected by the people, who are now giving the jury an
                    account of the crimes. If your story is true, I am prepared to die. But if you
                    claim that the council took the initiative in reporting me, produce the
                    Areopagites as witnesses, just as I myself shall produce them to show that I was
                    not reported, <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>to show in fact that, after
                    impeaching one rogue and traitor who, like you, had maligned the council and
                    myself, I proved before two thousand five hundred citizens that he had hired
                    himself to Pythocles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Pythocles was an Athenian
                        orator who, in company with Aeschines, attacked Demosthenes unsuccessfully
                        after <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.285">Dem. 18.285</bibl>.</note> in making this attack upon
                    me, and so avenged myself with the help of those then serving on the jury.
                    Clerk, please take the deposition. I laid it before the jury previously as
                    evidence and no one questioned its veracity. So I will produce it now. Read the
                        deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Is it not an
                    anomaly, Athenians, that on that occasion, because one man, Pistias an
                        Areopagite,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Nothing else is known of Pistias
                        except that Dinarchus composed a speech against him, the title of which
                        appears in the list of his genuine public orations preserved by
                        Dionysius.</note> told lies against the council and myself and said that I
                    was a criminal, falsehood would have prevailed over truth, if through my
                    weakness and isolation at the time the trumped up lies against me had been
                    believed; whereas now, when the fact is admitted by the whole Areopagus that
                    Demosthenes has taken twenty talents of gold against your interests, and is
                    therefore a criminal, and that your popular leader, in whom some men place their
                    hopes, <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>has been caught in the act of taking
                    bribes, the customs of the Areopagus and truth and justice are going to prove
                    weaker than Demosthenes' word? Truth will be overridden by the slanderous
                    statement he intends to make against the council, namely that many of those
                    reported by it as a menace to the people have, on coming into court, been
                    acquitted, in some cases the council failing to secure a fifth part of the
                    votes. There is an explanation for this which you will easily follow. <milestone
                        n="55" unit="section"/>The council, gentlemen, has its own method of
                    inquiring into the cases which you assign to it and the crimes committed within
                    its own body. Unlike yourselves,&mdash;and you need not take offence at
                    this,&mdash;who are sometimes apt when judging to give more weight to mercy
                    than to justice, it simply reports anyone who is liable to the charges in
                    question or has broken any traditional rule of conduct believing that if a
                    person is in the habit of committing small offences he will more easily involve
                    himself in serious crimes. <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>Consequently when
                    one of its number robbed the ferryman of his fare it fined him and reported him
                    to you. Again, when someone claimed the five drachma allowance<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">It appears from Hyperides &lpar;<bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5
                            col. 26</bibl>&rpar;, who seems to be referring to the same case,
                        that Dinarchus is here alluding to the dole made to Athenians to enable them
                        to attend the theater. The normal price of a seat was one-third of a drachma
                        only, but as the fund was apparently drawn upon for other purposes also, it
                        is perhaps not surprising that the sum mentioned here is larger. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Lib. Arg.D. 1">Libanius arg. ad Demosthenem 1</bibl>. The portion
                        mentioned in the following sentence was an allowance of sacrificial meat
                        made to members of the Areopagus.</note> in the name of an absentee, it
                    reported him also to you. Similarly it fined and expelled the man who presumed
                    to break the rule and sell the Areopagite portion. <milestone n="57"
                        unit="section"/>You tried these men and acquitted them. You were not thereby
                    convicting the Areopagus of error but you were more concerned with sympathy than
                    justice, and thought the punishment too severe for the offence which the
                    defendants had committed. Do you imagine then, Demosthenes, that the council
                    made a false report? Of course it did not. Nevertheless, gentlemen, you
                    acquitted these men and others like them, though the council reported that they
                    were guilty of breaking its rules. <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>In the case
                    of Polyeuctus of Cydantidae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For Polyeuctus of
                        Cydantidae, the accuser of Euxenippus, cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 4.4">Hyp.
                            4.4</bibl>, Introduction.</note> when the people instructed the council
                    to inquire whether he was accompanying the exiles to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> and to report back after the
                    investigation, it reported that he was doing so. You chose accusers as the law
                    prescribes: Polyeuctus came into court and you acquitted him, on his admitting
                    that he was going to <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> to
                    Nicophanes who, he said, was married to his mother. So you did not consider that
                    he was doing anything strange or reprehensible in keeping in touch with his
                    mother's husband who was in difficulties, or in assisting him, so far as he
                    could, while he was banished from the country. <milestone n="59" unit="section"
                    />The report of the council, Demosthenes, was not proved false; it was quite
                    true, but the jury decided to acquit Polyeuctus. The council was instructed to
                    discover the truth, yet, as I say, the court decided whether it was a case for
                    pardon. Is that any reason for distrusting the council over the present reports
                    in which it has stated that you and your confederates are in possession of the
                    gold? That would be disgraceful. <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>Convince the
                    jury now, Demosthenes, that any of those crimes ranks with yours and that to
                    take bribes against one's country is a pardonable act which would justify these
                    men in acquitting you. For other pecuniary offences the laws prescribe damages
                    twice as great as the sum involved,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A misleading
                        statement. Cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col. 24</bibl>, where the contrast
                        made is between a simple and a tenfold fine. A fine was doubled only if it
                        had not been paid before a specific date. Cf. <bibl n="Din. 2.17">Din.
                            2.17</bibl> and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 54">Aristot. Const. Ath.
                            54</bibl>.</note> but in cases of bribery they have laid down two
                    penalties only: either death, to ensure that by meeting with this punishment the
                    guilty man is an example to others, or a fine for bribery ten times as great as
                    the original bribe, so that men who dare to commit this offence shall not gain
                    by it. <milestone n="61" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Perhaps
                    you will not attempt to argue thus, Demosthenes, but will say that of those whom
                    the council has reported up till now the rest have admitted that the penalty
                    which it imposed was deserved, whereas you alone have protested against it. But
                    you alone, of all those ever reported, asked these men of your own accord to be
                    your judges and court of inquiry. You proposed the decree against yourself and
                    made the people witness of the agreement, defining the penalty for yourself as
                    death, if the council should report that you had taken any of the money brought
                    into the country by Harpalus. <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>And yet in the
                    past, Demosthenes, you proposed that the council of the Areopagus should have
                    power over all these men, and the rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> too, to enforce the laws of the land and punish any who
                    transgressed them. It was you who surrendered the whole city into the hands of
                    this council which you will presently tell us is oligarchic. By the terms of
                    your decree the death sentence has been inflicted on two citizens, a father and
                    a son, who were given over to the executioner. <milestone n="63" unit="section"
                    />One of the descendants of Harmodius was imprisoned in pursuance of your order.
                    These gentlemen, acting on the council's report, tortured and killed
                        Antiphon.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Demosthenes &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.132">Dem. 18.132</bibl>&rpar; confirms this and says that
                        Antiphon promised Philip that he would burn the dockyards in the <placeName
                            key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>. Demosthenes caught him there
                        and brought him before the people, who at first acquitted him. But the
                        Areopagus intervened and he was later executed.</note> You expelled
                        Charinus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Charinus, a figure of little
                        importance, is mentioned as a traitor in the speech against Theocrines,
                        which was attributed by Dionysius to Dinarchus but has survived among the
                        works of Demosthenes &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 58.38">Dem.
                        58.38</bibl>&rpar;.</note> from the city for treason on the strength of
                    the council's reports and punishments. After proposing this treatment for
                    yourself also, are you now overriding the decree of your own accord? Surely that
                    is neither just nor lawful. <milestone n="64" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>I summon as my witnesses, Athenians, the awful goddesses and
                    their abode, the heroes of the land, Athena Polias, and those other gods who
                    have obtained our city and countryside as their home, to show that when the
                    people has consigned to you for punishment one who, against his country's
                    interests, has accepted a part of the &lt;imported money&gt;,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense of this passage is clear, though the
                        Greek wording leaves room for doubt.</note> one who has defiled and ruined
                    the city's prosperity and betrayed that country which he claimed to have
                    fortified by his diplomacy,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">An allusion to some
                        words of Demosthenes in the speech on the Crown &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.299">Dem. 18.299</bibl>&rpar;.</note>
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>enemies, and those who bear the city ill will,
                    would wish him alive, counting this a disaster for <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; but all who favor your concerns and
                    hope that with a turn of fortune the city's prospects may improve wish that this
                    man may die and pay the penalty merited by his conduct, and such is the burden
                    of their prayers. I also join in praying the gods to save our country, which I
                    see to be in danger of forfeiting its safety, its women and children, its honor,
                    and every other thing of worth. <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>What shall we
                    say to the bystanders, Athenians, when we come out of the court, if you are
                    deceived, as I pray you may not be, by the wizardry of this man? What will be
                    the feelings of you all, when, on your return, you presume to look upon your
                    fathers' hearths, after acquitting the traitor who first brought into his own
                    home the gold of bribery; after convicting as utterly false, in both its inquiry
                    and its conclusion, the body which all men hold in the greatest awe? <milestone
                        n="67" unit="section"/>What hopes, Athenians,&mdash;picture for
                    yourselves,&mdash;what hopes shall we have if some danger overtakes the
                    city, when we have made it a safe thing to take bribes against one's country and
                    have robbed of its status the body which kept watch over the city in such times
                    of crisis? <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>Or again,&mdash;let us suppose
                    this to happen,&mdash;what if Alexander, in pursuance of Demosthenes'
                        decree,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Demosthenes had proposed that the
                        money should be kept on the Acropolis until Alexander sent for it.</note>
                    sends and asks us for the gold brought into the country by Harpalus, and, over
                    and above the fact that the council has made a report, sends down here the
                    slaves which have now been returned to him and asks us to find out the truth
                    from them; what in Heaven's name shall we say, gentlemen? <milestone n="69"
                        unit="section"/>Will you propose, Demosthenes, that we go to war, in view of
                    your success with the previous wars? Suppose the rest of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> decides on this, which is fairer:
                    for your gold to be available for war along with other people's or for others to
                    contribute from their own property, melting down the personal ornaments of their
                    wives, the cups and all the country's store of offerings to the gods, as you
                    said you would suggest, though you yourself paid in fifty drachmas from your
                    houses in <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> and the city?
                    That has been your contribution under the last levy though now you have twenty
                    talents. <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>Perhaps you will not advocate war but
                    advise us to follow out the decree which you proposed and give back to Alexander
                    the gold brought to us? If so, it will be for your sake that the people have to
                    restore it. It is surely neither just nor fair nor democratic that those who
                    work should contribute, while you plunder and steal; that some should make no
                    secret of the property they hold and make contributions proportionate to it,
                    while you who have received more than a hundred and fifty talents, either from
                    the King's money<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See note on <bibl n="Din. 1.10"
                            >Din. 1.10</bibl>.</note> or from your association with Alexander, have
                    no declared property in the city but have fortified yourself against the people
                    as though you had no confidence in your own conduct of affairs. <milestone
                        n="71" unit="section"/>Is it right, when the laws demand that the orator or
                    general who expects to get the people's confidence shall observe the laws in
                    begetting children, shall own land within our boundaries, shall give all the
                    lawful pledges and only thus lay claim to be the people's leader, that you
                    should have sold the land inherited from your father or be claiming as yours
                    children which are not your own, thus breaking the laws which govern oaths in
                        court,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">A reference to the oath whereby a man
                        called down imprecations on his children, swearing that he was not guilty of
                        a certain action. Demosthenes had lost his only child, a daughter, in 336
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Aeschin. 3.77">Aeschin. 3.77</bibl>&rpar;; and if
                        he had other children now, they were adopted or by a hetaera. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Ath. 13.592">Athen. 13.592 e</bibl>.</note> and be ordering others to
                    fight when you deserted the citizens' ranks yourself? <milestone n="72"
                        unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What do you think it is,
                    Athenians, that makes cities vary between good and evil fortunes? You will find
                    only one cause: the counsellors and leaders. Take Thebes. It was a city; it
                    became supreme. Under what leaders and generals? All the older men, on whose
                    authority I shall give you the story, would admit that it was when
                        Pelopidas,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Pelopidas and Epaminondas were
                        the chief Theban generals during their city's period of greatness
                            &lpar;<dateRange from="-371" to="-362">371</dateRange>-<date
                            value="-362">362</date> B.C.&rpar;. In 371 they defeated <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> at Leuctra and, in response to
                        an appeal from the Arcadians who then rose against <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, entered the <placeName
                            key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> in 370. Here they refounded
                        the town of <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> which the
                        Spartans had destroyed at the end of the 8th century B.C. &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Diod. 15.56">Dio. Sic. 15.56</bibl> and <bibl n="Diod. 15.62">Dio.
                            Sic. 15.62-66</bibl>&rpar;. Epaminondas conducted three further
                        invasions of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>,
                        penetrating <placeName key="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName>, but never
                        actually taking <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. It was
                        probably during the second of these that he founded <placeName
                            key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>, the new capital of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>; in the third he was
                        killed at <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName>
                        &lpar;362 B.C.&rpar;.</note> so they have it, <milestone n="73"
                        unit="section"/>led the Sacred Band<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The
                        Sacred Band was a company of 300 picked soldiers maintained by the state.
                        They first attracted attention by defeating a Spartan force in <date
                            value="-375">375</date> B.C. and played a large part in the victory of
                        Leuctra. At <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> they fought
                        to the last man and were buried by the highway from <placeName
                            key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName> to Thebes with the figure of a lion
                        over their tomb.</note> and Epaminondas and their compeers were in command.
                    It was then that Thebes won the battle of Leuctra, then that they invaded the
                    Spartans' country which, it was thought, could not be ravaged. During that
                    period they accomplished many fine achievements: founded <placeName
                        key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> in the four hundredth<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><placeName key="tgn,7011369">Messenia</placeName>
                        was first conquered about the year <date value="-700">700</date> B.C., so
                        that the figure 400th is a very rough estimate; 300th would be nearer. Cf.
                            <bibl n="Lyc. 1.62">Lyc. 1.62</bibl> and note.</note> year after its
                    fall, gave the Arcadians self-government, and won a universal reputation.
                        <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>On the other hand when was their
                    achievement despicable and unworthy of their spirit? When Timolaus,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The three men mentioned in this sentence were
                        Theban generals at the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                            >Chaeronea</placeName>.</note> the friend of Demosthenes, was corrupted
                    and took bribes from Philip, when the traitor Proxenus commanded the mercenaries
                    enlisted at <placeName key="perseus,Amphissa">Amphissa</placeName> and Theagenes
                    was placed in command of the phalanx, a man of ill luck and, like the defendant
                    here, open to bribes. Then, because of the three men whom I have mentioned, the
                    whole city was destroyed and blotted from the face of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. Far from being false it is only too
                    true that leaders are responsible for all the citizens' good fortunes and for
                    the reverse. <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>Think again, this time of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, with the same points in
                    mind. Our city was great, renowned in <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>, and worthy of our forbears, apart from the well-known
                    exploits of the past, at the time when <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> triumphed, as our elders tell us, in the naval battle at
                        <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>; when Iphicrates destroyed
                    the Spartan company, when Chabrias defeated the Spartan triremes at sea off
                        <placeName key="tgn,7003909">Naxos</placeName>, when Timotheus won the sea
                    battle off <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">For the exploits of <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> and Timotheus compare <bibl n="Din. 1.14">Din.
                            1.14</bibl> and note. In <date value="-391">391</date> B.C. the Athenian
                        general Iphicrates, on going to the relief of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, surprised and almost
                        annihilated a Spartan company. The defeat of the Spartan fleet by Chabrias
                        took place in 376 and won supremacy in the <placeName key="tgn,7002675"
                            >Aegean</placeName> for <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> for over fifty years &lpar;<bibl
                            n="Xen. Hell. 5.4.61">Xen. Hell. 5.4.61</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 20.77"
                            >Dem. 20.77</bibl>&rpar;.</note>
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>That was the time, Athenians, when the
                    Spartans, once famous through the leaders in whose ways they had been schooled,
                    came humbly to our city and begged our ancestors to save them; and the democracy
                    which they had overthrown was made by the counsellors, whom we then had, the
                    first power in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> again:
                    deservedly, in my belief; for they had found generals of the type I have just
                    mentioned and had as advisers Archinus and Cephalus of Collytus.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Like Cephalus, who is mentioned above
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 1.38">Din. 1.38</bibl>&rpar;, Archinus took
                        a leading part in the overthrow of the Thirty in 403.</note> For the only
                    salvation of a city or a nation is to find brave men to lead it and wise
                    counsellors. <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>It follows then, Athenians, that
                    if you fully recognize this fact you should not surely be parties in future to
                    Demosthenes' corruption and ill-luck or rest your hopes of security on him; you
                    need not think that you will lack brave men or wise advisers. Let the anger of
                    your forefathers be yours. Put to death this robber taken in the act, this
                    traitor who does not withhold his hands from the gold brought into <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> but has cast the city into the
                    direst misfortunes, this arch-criminal of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>. Have his body cast beyond the city's borders, give her
                    fortunes a chance to mend, and then, with this accomplished, expect a happier
                    lot. <milestone n="78" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I want you
                    also, Athenians, to hear that other decree moved by Demosthenes,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">One of the several decrees relating to defence
                        proposed by Demosthenes after <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                            >Chaeronea</placeName>; the oracle is mentioned in the speech on the
                        False Embassy &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 19.297">Dem. 19.297</bibl>
                        sq.&rpar;.</note> the decree which this democratic statesman proposed
                    when the city was in disorder after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                        >Chaeronea</placeName>, and also the oracle sent from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> from Dodonian Zeus; for it has long
                    been warning you clearly to beware of your leaders and advisers. Read the oracle
                        first.<quote type="Oracle">
                        <title>Oracle</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>Read that splendid decree of his.<quote
                        type="Part of the Decree">
                        <title>Part of the Decree</title>
                    </quote><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A fine democrat indeed who arranges for
                    himself, being a brave and courageous man, to remain in arms, while he orders
                    the citizens whom he rejects for service to go off to their work or to do
                    anything else he thinks is called for. Read the rest.<quote
                        type="Rest of the Decree">
                        <title>Rest of the Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>Listen to that, gentlemen of the jury. The
                    decree says that the chosen embassies shall set out. When, after the battle of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, he heard that Philip
                    intended to invade our country he appointed himself an envoy, so as to escape
                    from the city, and went off,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Dinarchus is
                        perhaps referring to the fact that after Chaeronea Demosthenes was appointed
                        a commissioner for corn &lpar;<foreign lang="greek"
                        >sitw/nhs</foreign>&rpar; and went abroad to procure it &lpar;cf.
                            <bibl n="Dem. 18.248">Dem. 18.248</bibl>&rpar;. Alternatively when
                        appeals for help were made by <placeName key="tgn,7001393"
                            >Athens</placeName> to some of the islands &lpar;cf. <bibl
                            n="Lyc. 1.42">Lyc. 1.42</bibl>&rpar; Demosthenes may have served as
                        an envoy.</note> after scraping together eight talents from the treasury,
                    without a thought about the plight we were in, at a time when everyone else was
                    contributing from his own money to ensure your protection. <milestone n="81"
                        unit="section"/>That is the character of your adviser. Demosthenes has made
                    only these two journeys abroad in his life<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This
                        statement is wholly incorrect and Dinarchus appears to be contradicting
                        himself, since in <bibl n="Din. 1.12">Din. 1.12</bibl> of this speech he
                        does not attempt to refute Demosthenes' claim to have served on many
                        embassies. By excluding the words &ldquo;in his life&rdquo; and
                        placing a colon after &ldquo;battle&rdquo; Maetzner would alter the
                        sense to: &ldquo;Demosthenes has made only these two journeys abroad
                        since the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                        >Chaeronea</placeName>.&rdquo;</note>: one after the battle when he ran
                    away from the city, and another just recently to <placeName key="tgn,7013967"
                        >Olympia</placeName> when he wanted to use the presidency of the sacred
                    embassy as a means of meeting <placeName key="tgn,2540820"
                        >Nicanor</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Demosthenes was the
                        chief Athenian religious envoy at the Olympic games in <date value="-324"
                            >324</date> B.C. when <persName><surname>Nicanor</surname></persName>
                        presented Alexander's decree demanding that exiles should be allowed to
                        return to all Greek cities except Thebes. Cf. <bibl>Dio. Sic. 18.8</bibl>;
                            <bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col. 18</bibl>.</note> A right thing indeed to
                    entrust the city to this man's charge, when danger confronts us! When it was
                    time to fight against the enemy, side by side with his fellows, he left his post
                    and made for home; yet when he should have stayed at home to face danger with
                    them, he offered himself as an envoy and ran away and left the city. <milestone
                        n="82" unit="section"/>When ambassadors were needed for the peace he said he
                    would not move a foot to leave the city; yet when it was reported that Alexander
                    was restoring the exiles and <persName><surname>Nicanor</surname></persName>
                    came to <placeName key="tgn,7013967">Olympia</placeName> he offered himself to
                    the council as president of the sacred embassy. These are the parts he plays: on
                    the field of battle he is a stay-at-home, when others stay at home he is an
                    ambassador, among ambassadors he is a runaway.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now
                    read the<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">That some words have dropped out of the
                        text here is evident from the fact that two decrees are to be read and
                        compared; moreover the executions mentioned in <bibl n="Din. 1.83">Din.
                            1.83</bibl> could have no connection with the decree relating to the
                        money of Harpalus, since in this case Demosthenes himself was the first to
                        be tried &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 1.106">Din. 1.106</bibl>&rpar;.</note>
                    and the decree relating to the inquiry over the money proposed by Demosthenes
                    for the Areopagus and affecting both himself and you. I want you by comparing
                    them together to realize that he is demented.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>Did you propose this, Demosthenes? You did;
                    you cannot deny it. Was the council given authority on your motion? It was. Have
                    some of the citizens been executed? They have. Did your decree have power over
                    them? You cannot deny that it did.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read the decree
                    again which Demosthenes proposed against Demosthenes. Let me have your
                    attention, gentlemen.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="84" unit="section"/>The council has found Demosthenes guilty. Need
                    we enlarge on this? It has made its report on him, Athenians. Justice demanded
                    that, having been self-condemned, he should immediately be put to death. But now
                    that he has fallen into the hands of you who have been assembled by the people
                    and have sworn to obey the laws and the people's decrees, what will you do? Will
                    you ignore the claims of piety towards the gods and the justice recognized by
                    the world? No, Athenians, do not do so. <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>It
                    would be an utter disgrace if, when others no worse, and even less guilty, than
                    Demosthenes have been destroyed by his decrees, he, with his contempt for you
                    and the laws, should be at large unpunished in the city, when by his own motion
                    and the decrees which he proposed he has been convicted. The same council,
                    Athenians, the same place, the same rights have been in question. <milestone
                        n="86" unit="section"/>The same orator was responsible for the misfortunes
                    which overtook them and those which will soon overtake him. He himself in the
                    Assembly instructed this council to judge his case, after calling on you as his
                    witnesses. He made an agreement with the people and proposed the decree against
                    himself, to be kept by the mother of the gods,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                        >Dinarchus is alluding to the Metroon, in which the state archives were
                        kept. Cf. <bibl n="Lyc. 1.66">Lyc. 1.66</bibl> and note.</note> who is the
                    city's guardian of all written contracts. It would thus be impious for you to
                    invalidate this or, after swearing by the gods in the present trial, to give a
                    vote which did not conform with the actions of the gods themselves. <milestone
                        n="87" unit="section"/>When Poseidon lost his suit against Ares over
                    Halirrothius he abode by the decision.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">According
                        to tradition, Halirrothius, son of Poseidon, was killed by Ares for trying
                        to seduce his daughter Alcippe. Poseidon accused Ares before the Areopagus
                        but failed to secure his conviction. Cf. <bibl n="Apollod. 3.14.2">Apollod.
                            3.14.2</bibl>.</note> The awful goddesses too, in their case against
                        Orestes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Orestes, pursued by the Furies, was
                        said to have been given protection by Athena, who allowed the Areopagus to
                        try his case and herself gave the casting vote which acquitted him. Cf.
                            <bibl n="Aesch. Eum. 443">Aesch. Eum. 443</bibl> sq.; <bibl
                            n="Paus. 1.28.5">Paus. 1.28.5</bibl>.</note> abode by the judgement of
                    this council, associating themselves for the future with its reputation for
                    truth. How will you act with your claim to unrivalled piety? Will you annul the
                    decision of the council and follow the bad example of Demosthenes? You will not,
                    Athenians, if you remain in your senses. <milestone n="88" unit="section"/>This
                    is no small or incidental matter that you are deciding today; the question at
                    issue is the safety of the whole city and also bribery, an evil habit and a
                    practice which is harmful to you and has always brought men to ruin. If you do
                    everything in your power to rid the city of this vice and to suppress those who
                    gladly take bribes against you, we shall be saved, with Heaven's consent. But if
                    you allow the orators to sell you, you will stand by and see them wreck the
                    city. <milestone n="89" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
                    />Demosthenes himself proposed in the Assembly, clearly implying that it was a
                    just step to take, that we should keep for Alexander the money brought into
                        <placeName key="tgn,2022058">Attica</placeName> with Harpalus.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">See <bibl n="Din. 1.68">Din. 1.68</bibl> and
                        note.</note> Tell me, sir: are we going to keep it under present conditions,
                    when you have taken twenty talents for personal use, someone else fifteen,
                    Demades six thousand gold staters, and the others the various sums that have
                    been credited to them? For sixty-four talents have already been traced, for
                    which, you must conclude, gentlemen, that these men are to be held responsible.
                        <milestone n="90" unit="section"/>Which is the more honorable alternative,
                    which the more just: that all the money should be kept in the treasury until the
                    people has reached some fair decision, or that the orators and certain of the
                    generals should seize and keep it? Personally I think that to keep it in the
                    treasury is the course which all would admit to be just, while no one would
                    consider it fair for these men to retain it. <milestone n="91" unit="section"
                        /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The statements made by the defendant,
                    gentlemen, have been numerous and very varied but never consistent. For he
                    realizes that all along you have been cheated by him with empty hopes and lying
                    assertions and that you remember his promises only so long as they are being
                    uttered. If then the city must go on enjoying the fruits of Demosthenes'
                    wickedness and ill-fortune, that we may still be plagued by an evil
                    genius,&mdash;I can find no other word for it,&mdash;we should acquiesce
                    in the present state of affairs. <milestone n="92" unit="section"/>But if we
                    have any regard for our country, if we hate wicked and corrupt men and want our
                    fortune to change for the better, you must not surrender yourselves, Athenians,
                    to the prayers of this accursed juggler or lend an ear to his laments and
                    quackeries. You have had enough experience of him, his speeches, his actions,
                    and his luck. <milestone n="93" unit="section"/>Which of you is so hopeful,
                    Athenians, or so irrational, which of you is so unversed in past or present
                    history, as to expect that a man who reduced the city, through whatever fault or
                    fortune,&mdash;I am not concerned with that,&mdash;from such great
                    prosperity to such utter disgrace, will save us now by serving as a counsellor
                    and administrator? For besides the other difficulties and dangers which beset us
                    we have now corruption also, of men right in the city, and are one and all
                    striving to clear ourselves of a shameful charge, lest the people be thought to
                    hold in their own name the money which certain individuals are keeping for
                    themselves. <milestone n="94" unit="section"/>I am not citing other instances of
                    his continual change of policy or of the pernicious speeches which he has
                    consistently made. At one time he made a proposal forbidding anyone to believe
                    in any but the accepted gods and at another said that the people must not
                    question the grant of divine honors to Alexander<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                        >Demosthenes had merely said: &ldquo;Let him be the son of Zeus and
                        Poseidon too if he likes.&rdquo; Cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col.
                            31</bibl>.</note>; and again when he was on the point of being tried
                    before you, he impeached Callimedon for consorting with the exiles<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"><placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>,
                        unlike most Greek cities, refused to obey Alexander's order for the
                        restoration of exiles &lpar;cf. note on <bibl n="Din. 1.81">Din.
                            1.81</bibl>&rpar;. Callimedon, a politician with pro-Macedonian
                        sympathies, nicknamed the Crab, is mentioned several times by Plutarch
                        &lpar;e.g. <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 27">Plut. Dem.
                        27</bibl>&rpar;.</note> in <placeName key="tgn,7017133"
                        >Megara</placeName> with intent to overthrow the democracy, <milestone
                        n="95" unit="section"/>and directly after countermanded the impeachment and
                    brought forward at the recent sitting of the Assembly a false witness whom he
                    had primed to say that there was a plot afoot threatening the docks. In all this
                    he offered no proposals but simply furnished us with charges for the present
                    trial, since on all these points you are witnesses against him. This man is a
                    juggler, Athenians, and a blackguard, not entitled to be a citizen of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, either by virtue of his birth or of
                    his political record. <milestone n="96" unit="section"/>Where are the triremes
                    which Demosthenes, like Eubulus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">For the
                        confidence inspired by Eubulus, son of Spintharus, who controlled Athenian
                        finances from 354 to <date value="-350">350</date> B.C., and perhaps for a
                        further period also, compare <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.25">Aeschin.
                        3.25</bibl>.</note> in his time, has supplied to the city? Where are the
                    dockyards built under his administration? When did he improve the cavalry either
                    by decree or law? Despite such opportunities as were offered after the battle of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, did he raise a single
                    force either for land or sea? What ornament for the goddess has he carried up to
                    the Acropolis? What building has Demosthenes put up, either in your exchange, or
                    in the city, or anywhere else in the country? Not a man could point to one
                    anywhere. <milestone n="97" unit="section"/>Very well; if a person has proved
                    untrustworthy in military matters and useless in the business of the city, if he
                    has idly watched his opponents accomplish everything they wished, changing his
                    own position and neglecting to pursue the people's interests, will you wish to
                    preserve him? <milestone n="98" unit="section"/>Not if you are prudent and make
                    the right decision for yourselves and <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>. No; you will welcome the good fortune which gave up to
                    you for punishment those orators who, through their own bribery, have humiliated
                    the city, and will beware, as the gods have often cautioned you in oracles,
                    against the leaders and counsellors of this type. Listen to the oracle itself.
                    Read the oracle.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.78">Din.
                            1.78</bibl>.</note><quote type="Oracle">
                        <title>Oracle</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="99" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>How then shall
                    we be of one mind, Athenians? How shall we agree upon the interests of the state
                    when our leaders and demagogues take bribes and betray their country's
                    interests, when you yourselves and the whole people are in danger of losing the
                    very foundations of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, together
                    with your fathers' temples and your wives and children, while they have
                    conspired together, so that in the assemblies they purposely abuse and lose
                    their tempers with each other, though in private they are united and thus
                    deceive you, who are so ready to lend an ear to what they say. <milestone
                        n="100" unit="section"/>What is the duty of a democratic orator, hating
                    those who menace the city by speech or bill? What are we told, Demosthenes and
                    Polyeuctus, about your predecessors? What did they always do, even though no
                    danger threatened the city at the time? Did they not summon each other for
                    trial; bring in impeachments? Did they not indict each other for illegal
                    proposals? Have you, who profess to have the people at heart, and maintain that
                    your safety rests upon this jury's vote, done a single one of these things?
                        <milestone n="101" unit="section"/>Have you denounced a decree, Demosthenes,
                    despite the many outrageous and illegal measures which Demades has proposed?
                    Have you prevented any political step among those which he has taken on his own
                    initiative against the interests of the state? Not a single one. Have you
                    impeached this man who has often acted contrary to the decrees of the people and
                    the laws? Never. You allowed him to have his statue set up in bronze in the
                    market and to share entertainment in the Prytaneum with the descendants of
                    Harmodius and Aristogiton.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">These honors were
                        paid to Demades about <date value="-335">335</date> B.C. in recognition of
                        his mission to Alexander after the destruction of Thebes. Cf. Life of
                        Demades</note>
                    <milestone n="102" unit="section"/>In what way then did the people sample your
                    goodwill, where did we see proof of the orator's protecting power? Or will you
                    all maintain that herein lie your powers: to cheat these men by persisting that
                    you cannot leave the country, that you have no other refuge than our goodwill?
                    You ought first to have made it clear that in speech and action you opposed the
                    decrees brought forward against the people's interests and then sought to
                    convince these men that your claim to have no means of safety but the assistance
                    offered by the people was true. <milestone n="103" unit="section"/>But you place
                    your hopes abroad and compete in flattery with those who admit that they are
                    serving Alexander and have taken bribes from the same sources as those from
                    which you are reported by the council to have received them. And you,
                    Demosthenes, after conversing with Nicanor in front of all the Greeks and
                    settling everything you wanted, now make yourself out to be in need of pity,
                    traitor though you are and a receiver of bribes; as if these men will forget
                    your wickedness, as if you will not pay the penalty for the crimes at which you
                    have been caught. You are acting more boldly than Demades to this extent,
                        <milestone n="104" unit="section"/>that though he has given warning in the
                    Assembly of his desperate character and admits that he accepts money and will
                    continue to do so, still he has not dared to show his face before these men and
                    did not presume to dispute the council's report; moreover he did not propose
                    that the council should have authority over him or lay down the death penalty if
                    he should be proved to have taken bribes. But you have such complete confidence
                    in your own arguments and such a contempt for these men's simplicity that you
                    expect to persuade the jury that in your case only has the council's statement
                    been false and that you alone of those whom it reported have not accepted the
                    gold. Who could believe that? <milestone n="105" unit="section"/><milestone
                        ed="P" unit="para"/>Let me explain, Athenians, what you are going to do. You
                    have taken over the case from the people, who know the facts; and to undergo the
                    punishment, due to those whose names appear in the reports, Demosthenes is
                    brought in first. We have made our accusation and have allowed no private
                    interest on the part of any to stand in the way of common justice. <milestone
                        n="106" unit="section"/>Will you disregard all that has passed and acquit
                    the first man up before you? Will you, with full power at your command, reject
                    what seemed just both to the people and the Areopagus, and indeed to everyone,
                    and take upon yourselves these men's depravity? <milestone n="107"
                        unit="section"/>Or will you, for the city's sake, give a demonstration to
                    all alike of the hatred you bear towards traitors and those who, through love of
                    gain, betray the people's interests? All this now lies in your control, and the
                    fifteen hundred of you hold the city's safety in your hands. Your verdict of
                    today will either bring to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                    great security, if you are willing to make a just decision, or else, if you
                    endorse such practices as this, drive all men to despondency. <milestone n="108"
                        unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>You must not be cowed,
                    Athenians, or by losing your self-control give up the city's just defence, which
                    touches all alike, in deference to Demosthenes' entreaties. For none of you
                    compelled this man to take the money, to which he had no right, against your own
                    interests, when he has acquired, with your assistance, much more than enough
                    besides, nor to defend himself now when the crimes have been acknowledged and he
                    has proposed the death penalty for himself. But the avarice and wickedness,
                    fostered in him by his whole mode of life, have brought this on his head.
                        <milestone n="109" unit="section"/>So do not be concerned when he weeps and
                    laments. You might, with far more justice, pity the country, which this man is
                    exposing to danger by behaving as he has, and which is begging you, who are its
                    sons, in the names of your wives and children, to take vengeance on the traitor
                    and save it: the land which your ancestors, after facing many noble combats for
                    it, have handed on to you free in which many noble examples have been left us of
                    the courage of those who gave their lives. <milestone n="110" unit="section"/>It
                    is this land, Athenians, the sacrifices traditional in it, and its ancestral
                    sepulchres to which right-thinking men must turn their thoughts when they give
                    their vote. And when Demosthenes wishes to cheat you and cunningly turns
                    pathetic, shedding tears, you must think of the city's person, and the glory
                    which it once possessed, and judge between two alternatives: which has become
                    the more deserving of pity: the city because of Demosthenes or Demosthenes
                    because of the city? <milestone n="111" unit="section"/>You will find that this
                    man has become famous since he entered politics; that from being a speechwriter
                    and a paid advocate, in the service of Ctesippus, Phormio and many others,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Demosthenes was acting in the interests of
                        Ctesippus, son of Chabrias, when he attacked the Law of Leptines in <date
                            value="-355">355</date> B.C. The Phormio referred to is possibly the
                        freedman of the banker Pasion whom he defended in 350. Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 20"
                            >Dem. 20</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 36">Dem. 36</bibl>.</note> he has
                    become the richest man in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>;
                    that after being an unknown figure, inheriting no family honor from his
                    ancestors, he is now famous, while the city has reached a pass unworthy of
                    herself or the honor of our forbears. Therefore ignore this man's entreaties and
                    deceptions, bring in the verdict that is just and right, having regard for your
                    country's interest, as befits an honorable jury, not the welfare of Demosthenes.
                        <milestone n="112" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And
                    whenever anyone comes forward to speak for him, bear in mind that he who does
                    so, even if not involved in the reports we are about to hear, is hostile to the
                    constitution, unwilling to see punished those who take bribes against the people
                    and anxious that the general protection of your persons, for which the Areopagus
                    is responsible, should be abolished and every right in the city overwhelmed;
                    whereas, if it is some orator or general, one of those participating in the
                    defence because they wish to discredit the report, which they expect will
                    reflect against themselves, you must give their arguments no credence, knowing
                    as you do that all these men collaborated over the landing of Harpalus and his
                    release. <milestone n="113" unit="section"/>You must realize then, Athenians,
                    that when these men come forward, they do so against your interests, being
                    enemies alike of the laws and the entire city. Do not tolerate them; insist that
                    their defence answers the charges. And do not countenance his own fury either;
                    for he prides himself on his powers as an orator and, since he is known to have
                    taken bribes against you, has been proved an even greater fraud. No, punish him
                    in a manner befitting yourselves and the city. If you do not, by one verdict and
                    at one trial you will release all who have been reported, and all who ever will
                    be, and will bring these men's corruption upon yourselves and upon the people,
                    even though, afterwards, you may prosecute those who acquitted them, when it
                    will avail you nothing. <milestone n="114" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>I have now played my full part in assisting the prosecution and
                    have shown regard for nothing but justice and your interests. I have not
                    deserted the city or given more weight to personal favor than to the people's
                    vote. With an appeal to you to show the same spirit I now hand over the water to
                    the other prosecutors.</p>
            </div1>

            <div1 n="2" type="speech">
                <head>Against Aristogiton</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>There is
                    nothing, it appears, Athenians, which we must not expect either to hear or see
                    in connection with the reports which have been made; but the most remarkable
                    fact of all, in my opinion, confronts us now. The worst character in the city, I
                    should say in the whole world, Aristogiton, has come to pit himself in law
                    against the Areopagus on the subject of truth and justice; and the council which
                    has made the report is now in greater danger than this man who takes bribes
                    against you and who sold for twenty minas the right of free speech in the cause
                    of justice. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>It will be no new or alarming
                    experience for the defendant if he is convicted, for he has committed in the
                    past many other crimes meriting the death penalty and has spent more time in
                    prison than out of it. While he has been in debt to the state he has prosecuted
                    men with citizen rights, though not entitled to do so, and has committed
                    numerous other offences of which you have a more exact knowledge than I. It is a
                    most shameful and monstrous thing for this council to be suspected of making a
                    false report against Aristogiton and for him to be considered among you as
                    having more justice on his side than it has. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    />For this reason, Athenians, thinking that the trial holds no dangers for him,
                    this man is coming forward, I believe, to test your attitude. He has often
                    undergone all sorts of suffering short of death, which, if God so wills it and
                    you are wise, he will undergo today. For you must assume, by Heracles, that
                    there will be no improvement in him if he is pardoned by you now, and that in
                    future he will not abstain from taking bribes against you if you now acquit him.
                    For when wickedness is in its infancy perhaps it can be checked by punishment,
                    but when it has grown old and has sampled the usual penalties, it is said to be
                    incurable. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>If therefore you wish depravity to
                    grow up ingrained in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you
                    should preserve Aristogiton and allow him to act there as he pleases. But if you
                    hate the wicked and accursed and can recall with resentment what this man has
                    done in the past, kill him, for he dared to take money from Harpalus, who he
                    knew was coming to seize your city. Cut short his excuses and deceptive
                    arguments, on which he now depends when he appears before you. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Do you realize that, awkward
                    though the arrival of Harpalus was, it has been an advantage to the city in one
                    respect, because it has given you a sure means of testing those who give up
                    everything to the enemies of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                    for a payment of silver or gold? Do not be lax, Athenians, or weary of punishing
                    the guilty; purge the city of bribery to the utmost of your ability. Do not ask
                    for arguments from me when you see that the crimes have been plainly attributed
                    to those whom the council has reported. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    />&lsqb;Or ought you to spare the defendant on account of his ancestry and
                    his moderation, or because he has done you many public and private
                        services?&rsqb;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This sentence was
                        excluded from the text by Bekker. It is out of place in the argument here
                        and its substance is given at the beginning of <bibl n="Din. 2.8">Din.
                            2.8</bibl>.</note> What information do you lack that makes you ask for
                    arguments against the defendant here before you? What if we, the accusers, all
                    ten of us, use up all the water in our clocks and proclaim that it is a terrible
                    thing to release men who have been caught with bribes against the city in their
                    very hands; will that make the council's report against Aristogiton true and
                    just? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Or suppose that each of us assumes that
                    you are just as well aware as we on which side justice lies in the present
                    trials, and so leaves the platform after a short speech; will the report then be
                    a false one, unjustly made by the Areopagites? Or don't you realize that to take
                    bribes in order to betray the city's interests is one of the greatest crimes
                    causing the most irreparable harm to cities? <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>No doubt I shall be told that the defendant
                    is himself a man of sober character coming of a good family, that he has done
                    you many noble services in private and in public life and that therefore you are
                    justified in sparing him. You must all have often heard that, when Aristogiton's
                    father Cydimachus was condemned to death and fled from the city, this admirable
                    son allowed his own father to lack the bare necessities of life, while he
                    survived, and do without a proper burial when he died: a fact for which evidence
                    was often brought against him; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>or again, that
                    the man himself, on being taken to prison for the first time,&mdash;no doubt
                    you realize that he has often been imprisoned&mdash;dared to behave in such
                    a way there that the inmates voted that no one should either light a fire for
                    him or sit at meals or share the usual sacrifices with him. Reflect, Athenians;
                    what sort of character must we suppose this man to have, who was thrown into
                    prison for criminal conduct <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>and when he was
                    there, among those who had been segregated from the rest of the world as felons,
                    was looked upon as so debased that even there he was not thought worthy of the
                    same treatment as the rest? It is said, in fact, that he was caught thieving
                    among them and that, if there had been any other place more degraded where they
                    could have isolated men who stole in prison, this monster would have been
                    conducted there. These facts, as I said just now, were established by evidence
                    against Aristogiton, as is well known, when the lot fell to him to be custodian
                    of the exchange but he was rejected by those who then decided the appointment to
                    that office.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The custodians of the exchange were
                        responsible for seeing that the laws governing import and export trade were
                        observed. Like most magistrates, they were appointed by lot but were
                        submitted to an examination in court &lpar;<foreign lang="greek"
                            >dokimasi/a</foreign>&rpar; before taking office and could be
                        rejected if unsuitable.</note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Do you then feign ignorance among yourselves
                    and give way to pity when the man concerning whom you are about to vote is
                    Aristogiton, who did not pity his own father when reduced to starvation? Do you
                    still wish to hear us talk about the damages he must pay, when you know quite
                    well that his whole life, as well as his recent conduct, justifies the extreme
                    penalty? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>Was it not Aristogiton, Athenians,
                    who made in writing such lying assertions about the priestess of Artemis
                        Brauronia<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The shrine of Artemis at
                            <placeName key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> in <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> was supposed to contain the image
                        of the goddess brought from the Tauri by Iphigenia. There was also a temple
                        of Artemis Brauronia, called <foreign lang="greek">to\ i(ero\n
                            kunhge/sion</foreign>, on the Acropolis &lpar; cf. arg. ad
                        Demosthenem 25.; <bibl n="Paus. 1.23.7">Paus.
                        1.23.7</bibl>&rpar;.</note>and her relatives, that when you discovered
                    the truth from his accusers, you fined him five talents, a sum equal to the fine
                    set down in an indictment for illegal proposals? Has he not persisted in
                    maligning every one of you he meets, though he has not yet paid up, and in
                    speaking and proposing measures in the Assembly, regardless of all the penalties
                    against wrongdoers which the laws prescribe? <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    />And finally, when an information was lodged against him by Lycurgus,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Lyc. Fr. 13">Lyc. frag. 13</bibl>
                        and note.</note>and he was convicted, a debtor to the state without the
                    right to speak in public, when he had been handed over to the Eleven in
                    accordance with the laws, &lt;was he not seen&gt;<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes"> Reiske's emendation is followed here.</note>walking about in
                    the front of the lawcourts, and used he not to sit on the seat of the Prytanes?
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then,
                    Athenians, if a man has often been committed to you lawfully for punishment,
                    condemned on information lodged by citizens, if neither the Eleven nor the
                    prison have been able to restrain him, will you want to use him as a counsellor?
                    The law demands that the herald shall first pray, amid dead silence, before he
                    surrenders to you the task of deliberating on public affairs. Will you then
                    allow an impious wretch, who has proved wicked in his dealings with everyone,
                    and in particular his own father, to share in citizenship with you, with your
                    families and kinsmen? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>After rejecting all
                    thought of pardon for Demades and Demosthenes, because they were proved to have
                    been taking bribes against you, and punishing them,&mdash;quite rightly,
                    though you knew that they had served you during their administration, certainly
                    in many respects if not in everything,&mdash;will you acquit this accursed
                    man who has not done you a service ever since he has been in politics but has
                    been the greatest possible menace? Would not everyone reproach you if you
                    accepted such a person as your adviser? For when you are addressed by a man
                    whose wickedness is both notorious and undeniable and a byword among all
                    Athenians, the bystanders will wonder whether you who listen to him have no
                    better advisers or whether you enjoy hearing such people. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/>Like the early lawgivers, Athenians, who made laws to deal
                    with those addressing your ancestors in the Assembly, you too should try, by
                    your behavior as listeners, to make the speakers who come before you better.
                    What was the attitude of the lawgivers to these men? In the first place, at
                    every sitting of the Assembly they publicly proclaimed curses against
                    wrongdoers, calling down destruction on any who, after accepting bribes, made
                    speeches or proposals upon state affairs, and to that class Aristogiton now
                    belongs. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>Secondly, they provided in the laws
                    for indictments for bribery, and this is the only offence for which they imposed
                    a payment equal to ten times the assessment of damages,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Cf. note on <bibl n="Din. 1.60">Din. 1.60</bibl>. Aristotle
                            &lpar;<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 54">Aristot. Const. Ath.
                        54</bibl>&rpar; states that theft was punished in the same way.</note>in
                    the belief that one who is ready to be paid for the opinions which he is going
                    to express in the Assembly has at heart, when he is speaking, not the interests
                    of the people but the welfare of those who have paid him. Now the council has
                    reported Aristogiton as guilty of this. Moreover, when choosing a man for public
                    office they used to ask what his personal character was, whether he treated his
                    parents well, whether he had served the city in the field, whether he had an
                    ancestral cult or paid taxes. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Aristogiton
                    could not claim one of these qualifications for himself. So far from treating
                    his parents well this man has ill-treated his own father. When you were all
                    serving in the army he was in prison; and, far from being able to point to any
                    memorial of his father, Athenians, he did not give him a proper funeral even in
                        <placeName key="perseus,Eretria">Eretria</placeName> where he died.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 25.54">Dem.
                        25.54</bibl>.</note> While other Athenians are contributing from their own
                    purses this man has not even paid up all the money to defray the public debts
                    which he incurred. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>In fact he has never ceased
                    to contravene all the laws, and his is the one case of those on which the
                    Areopagus has reported where you had inquired yourselves and already knew the
                    answer. For your knowledge that this man is a rogue and a criminal was not
                    gained from the council; you are all very well aware of his wickedness, and
                    hence the statement so often made applies here also, namely that, while you are
                    passing judgement on the defendant, the bystanders and everyone besides are
                    passing judgement on you. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>Therefore it is your duty as a sensible jury, Athenians, not to
                    vote against yourselves or the rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>; you should sentence him unanimously to be handed over
                    to the executioners for the death penalty. Do not be traitors and fail to give
                    the honest verdict demanded by your oath. Remember that this man has been
                    convicted by the council of taking bribes against you, convicted of ill-treating
                    him, to use the mildest term, by his father during his life and after his death,
                    condemned by the people's vote and handed over to you for punishment. <milestone
                        n="21" unit="section"/>Remember that this man has caused a deal of harm and
                    has now been caught doing wrong in circumstances which make it shameful for you,
                    his judges, to release him unpunished. For if you do so, how are you going to
                    vote on the other reports, Athenians? What justification will you give for
                    having condemned those men whom you have already tried? What reason will you
                    have, when you were clearly anxious for the council to report those who had
                    taken the money, for failing obviously to punish the men whose names they
                    submit? <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>You must not imagine that these trials
                    are private issues concerning no one but the men reported; they are public and
                    concern the rest of us as well. A case of bribery and treason tried before you
                    will affect others in the future in two possible ways: either it will make them
                    accept bribes against you unhesitatingly in the knowledge that they will not be
                    brought to justice, or it will make them afraid to take them, since they will
                    know that those who are caught will be punished in a manner suited to the crime.
                        <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>Do you not know that now the fear of what
                    you will do restrains those who are grasping for the money offered for use
                    against you and often makes them turn their backs on the bribe, and that the
                    people's decree, ordering the council to inquire about this money, has prevented
                    even those who brought the gold into the country from admitting their action?
                        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>It was a noble decree, Athenians, a noble
                    decree of your ancestors on this question, providing for a pillar on the
                    Acropolis at the time when Arthmius, son of Pithonax, the Zelite, is said to
                    have brought the gold from the Persians to corrupt the Greeks.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="yes">Demosthenes &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 9.42">Dem. 9.42</bibl>
                        and <bibl n="Dem. 19.271">Dem. 19.271</bibl>&rpar; refers to this
                        pillar. Arthmius of Zelea was an Athenian proxenus. He was sent by
                        Artaxerxes to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>,
                        probably in 461, to stir up war against the Athenians, who had been
                        assisting a revolt in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>.
                        &lpar;Cf. <bibl n="Thuc. 1.109">Thuc. 1.109</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Diod. 11.74.5">Dio. Sic. 11.74. 5</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.258"
                            >Aeschin. 3.258</bibl>.&rpar;</note> For before anyone had accepted
                    it or given proof of his character they sentenced the man who had brought the
                    gold to exile and banished him completely from the country. This decision, as I
                    said, they engraved on a bronze pillar and set up on the Acropolis as a lesson
                    for you their descendants; for they believed that the man who accepted money in
                    any way at all had in mind the interests of the donors rather than those of the
                    city. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>His was the only case in which they
                    added the reason why the people banished him from the city, explicitly writing
                    on the pillar that Arthmius, son of Pithonax, the Zelite, was an enemy of the
                    people and its allies, he and his descendants, and was exiled from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> because he had brought the Persian
                    gold to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>. And yet if the
                    people regarded the gold in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                        >Peloponnese</placeName> as a source of great danger to <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, how can we remain unmoved at the sight
                    of bribery in the city itself? Please attend to the inscription on the
                        pillar.<quote type="Inscription">
                        <title>Inscription</title>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now what do you
                    think those men would have done, Athenians, if they had caught a general or an
                    orator, one of their own citizens, accepting bribes against the interests of
                    their country, when they so justly and wisely expelled a man who was alien to
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in birth and character? That
                    is the reason why they faced danger against the barbarian worthily of the city
                    and their ancestors.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The conclusion of the
                        speech is lost.</note></p>
            </div1>

            <div1 n="3" type="speech">
                <head>Against Philocles</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>What in Heaven's name are we to say about such
                    men as this? How will you deal with the wickedness of Philocles, who has been
                    convicted by the Areopagus not once only but three times, as you all know, and
                    as you were recently informed in the Assembly? He has lied before all the
                    Athenians and the surrounding crowd, saying that he would prevent Harpalus from
                    putting into the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, when he
                    had been appointed by you as general in command of Munichia and the dockyards,
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>and he dared to take bribes against you
                    all, against your country and your wives and children; he has broken the oath
                    which he swore between the statue of Athena and the table; and he proposed a
                    decree against himself imposing the death penalty on him if he had accepted any
                    of the money which Harpalus brought into the country. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>Yet despite this he dared to come and show himself to you
                    when you knew that he had been proved answerable on all these counts. It is not
                    justice on which he is relying, Athenians; for what has he to do with justice?
                    No, it is audacity and effrontery, in virtue of which he has seen fit to take
                    bribes in the past, to the utter disregard of yourselves and the course of
                    justice in the city, and has now come forward to explain that he is guilty of
                    none of these things. So complete has been his contempt for your apathy.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>The law of the city, which binds us all,
                    lays it down that if anyone breaks an agreement made in the presence of one of
                    the citizens he shall be liable as an offender. Shall this man, who has deceived
                    every Athenian, betrayed the trust which he did not deserve to receive from you,
                    and so done everything in his power to ruin all the city's institutions, claim
                    that he is coming to make his defence against the charge laid against him?
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>It is my personal opinion, Athenians, if I
                    am to speak the truth,&mdash;as I must,&mdash;that there is no question
                    whether the reports bearing on Philocles are true or false; you have simply to
                    consider now the punishment mentioned in the decree and to decide whether you
                    ought to fine a man who has done the city so much harm or sentence him to
                    death,&mdash;as he proposed in the decree against
                    himself,&mdash;confiscating the property which he has amassed from
                    perquisites like this. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>Do you think that this question of the gold is the first
                    occasion when Philocles has shown his dishonesty and that he has never taken
                    bribes against you before? You are wrong. He has been like this a long time,
                    though you did not notice it; indeed you have been fortunate not to have met
                    with his venality on more important occasions; for there is no greater menace
                    than a man whose dishonesty passes unobserved. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    />Athenians, will you not all unite in killing one who has plunged many of our
                    citizens into such deep disgrace and guilt, who first opened the way for the
                    gold that has been distributed, exposing the whole of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to blame? Or will you consent to
                    hear this man, who has done so much to harm you, argue that the council of the
                    Areopagus has falsified the reports and that, while he is just and upright and
                    incorruptible, it has published all this in return for favors or bribes?
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Do you realize that, although in the case
                    of other offences you must first consider critically and with deliberation,
                    discovering the truth, and only then administer punishment to the offenders,
                    nevertheless, in cases of obvious and unquestioned treason, you should give
                    first place to anger and the vengeance that goes with it? <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>Do you think this man would refrain from selling any one of
                    the things most vital in the city, when you, relying on his loyalty and honesty,
                    had placed him in charge of it? Do you think that there are any triremes in the
                    dockyards which he would not let go, or that he would trouble to keep anything
                    safe, if there was a prospect of escaping detection and receiving double the
                    amount of gold which he has now received? Nothing, gentlemen, is beyond a man of
                    this type. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>For if anyone values silver and
                    gold more highly than his loyalty to you and has no more regard for an oath or
                    for honor and right than he has for making money, then that man, in so far as he
                    is able, will sell Munichia if he has a buyer; he will signal to the enemy and
                    reveal your secrets, he will betray your army and your fleet. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Therefore, Athenians, do not
                    imagine that, in assessing the penalty, you are merely going to judge of the
                    crimes which Philocles has actually committed; you will bear in mind those which
                    he would have committed, had it been in his power. Thank the gods, now that you
                    know the defendant's character, that you have suffered no more grievous harm at
                    his hands, and punish him as your duty and his baseness demand. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/>This man, Athenians, has held a cavalry command,
                    three or four times, over reputable men; he has been appointed a general by you
                    more than ten times, unworthy though he was, and has enjoyed honor and aroused
                    emulation because of his reputation for loyalty towards you. Yet he sold and
                    betrayed the dignity of a command conferred by us, reducing himself to the level
                    of Aristogiton and changing from a general into a hireling and a traitor.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Is this a reason why you, the injured
                    parties, should give way to feelings of consideration for such a person when he
                    himself showed no consideration in treating you and your fellows as he did?
                    Those who could justly claim your pity, Athenians, are not the like of
                    him,&mdash;far from it,&mdash;they are those whom Philocles would have
                    betrayed if he had had the chance of a good price; and among them are the
                    promontory and harbors, and the dockyards which your ancestors built and left
                    you. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>You must remember these, Athenians, and
                    not make light of the reports published by the council. &lt;Treat this
                        case&gt;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The sense of this passage is
                        evident, though it is not clear whether Dinarchus is expressing himself
                        loosely or whether, as Blass suggests, a few words have dropped out of the
                        text.</note> as you treated those on which you have already passed
                    judgement. For it is shameful to grow weary of punishing men who have proved
                    traitors to the city, and shameful that any lawbreakers and reprobates should
                    survive, when the gods have exposed them and surrendered them to you for
                    punishment, having seen that the whole people had accused Philocles and handed
                    him over first of all to meet with his deserts before you. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>By Zeus the Savior, I am
                    ashamed that you should need us to encourage you and goad you on before you
                    proceed to punish the defendant now on trial. Are you not eyewitnesses of the
                    crimes he has committed? The whole people considered that it was not safe or
                    right to trust him with their children and so rejected him as Supervisor of the
                    Ephebi. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>Will you, the guardians of democracy
                    and law, spare a man who has behaved like this; you to whom the fortune of lot
                    has entrusted &lt;the protection&gt;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes"
                        >Some such meaning seems called for as is presumed by Reiske, but the actual
                        Greek words supplied by him make the future participle <foreign lang="greek"
                            >dika/sontas</foreign> rather awkward.</note> of the people by means of
                    the judgement you will give? You are the supreme court of justice in the city.
                    Will you acquit a man guilty of taking bribes and every other crime, who, as I
                    said just now, is unique among criminals in that he has been reported not once
                    merely but three times and might already have been rightly made liable three
                    times to the death penalty by his own decree. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                    />Then why will you wait, Athenians? What further crimes do you wish to hear of
                    greater than those we have mentioned? Was it not you and your ancestors who made
                    no allowance for Timotheus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">This passage
                        corresponds almost word for word with <bibl n="Din. 1.14">Din. 1.14</bibl>.
                        See note on that.</note> though he had sailed round the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and beaten the Spartans in the
                    sea-fight at <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName>, though his father
                    was Conon who liberated <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and he
                    himself had taken <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Pydna"
                        >Pydna</placeName>, Potidaea, and twenty cities besides? You did not take
                    this record into consideration at all, or allow such services to outweigh the
                    case before you or the oaths which you swear before giving your verdict, but
                    fined him a hundred talents, because Aristophon said he had been bribed by the
                    Chians and Rhodians. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>&lt;Will you then
                        acquit&gt;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">An apodosis conveying some
                        such meaning as this, which is needed to complete the sense of the sentence,
                        seems to have dropped out of the Greek text.</note> this abominable man,
                    reported not by one individual but by the whole council of the Areopagus, after
                    an investigation, to be holding bribes against you; who, though he has ample
                    means and no male heirs and lacks nothing else that a normal man could need, did
                    not withhold his hand from the bribes offered against his country or suppress
                    his natural depravity, but destroyed entirely his reputation for loyalty towards
                    you, by ranging himself with those whom he once professed to oppose and proving
                    that his counterfeited honesty was sham? <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                        /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let every one of you bear these points in
                    mind, Athenians, and remember the present circumstances, which call for good
                    faith, not corruption. You must hate the wicked, wipe out such monsters from the
                    city, and show the world that the mass of people have not been corrupted with a
                    few orators and generals and are not cowed by their reputation; for they realize
                    that with integrity and agreement among ourselves we shall easily triumph, by
                    the grace of the gods, if anyone unjustly attacks us, but that with bribery and
                    treason and the allied vices practiced by men like this no city could survive.
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>Therefore, Athenians, do not admit any
                    request or plea for pity; do not &lt;condone&gt; the guilt which you
                    have seen fastened upon the defendants in the plain light of facts, &lt;or
                    invalidate the council's report&gt;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">Some
                        words have clearly dropped out from this passage. No certain restoration is
                        possible, although the general sense is not difficult to conjecture. The
                        restoration of Sauppe is followed in the translation.</note>; but one and
                    all assist your country and the laws, since both are now on trial against this
                    man's iniquity. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>The whole country will be
                    affected by the verdict you are about to give: the shrines which have been
                    erected in it, the agelong traditions, and the constitution which your ancestors
                    have handed down to you. It is not a question of Philocles alone; for he has
                    condemned himself to death long ago. In addressing these entreaties to you I am
                    urging a far juster plea than the men who have committed these shameful acts: I
                    am asking you not to desert the things for which your ancestors faced many
                    dangers, not to turn the city's honor into utter shame, and not to let personal
                    regard for the defendants override your respect for the laws, the people's
                    decrees, and the reports of the council. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>For
                    let me make it quite clear to you, Athenians, quite clear, that you are being
                    applauded universally in consequence of the inquiries held upon this money, and
                    that men who have been convicted of taking bribes against their own country are
                    regarded as wicked and injurious, haters of democracy, professing, as they do,
                    to be your friends and to work for the city's interests, and having made their
                    reputation thanks to you.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes">The concluding
                        sentences of the speech are lost.</note></p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
