<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [ 
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE"> 
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" > 
%PersProse; 
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
	<title type="work" n="Inst.">Institutio Oratoria, books 4-6: notes</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
<author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
<editor role="editor" n="Butler">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.AnnCPB;
</titleStmt>
<extent>About 100Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<author>Quintilian</author>
<title>With An English Translation</title>
 <editor role="editor" n="Butler">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
<publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
<date>1921</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
	<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
		<state unit="book"/>
		<state unit="chapter"/>
		<state unit="section"/>
	</refsDecl>
	
	<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
		<state unit="page"/>
	</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date>2006</date>
<respStmt><name>GRC</name><resp>tagging</resp></respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<pb id="p.523"/>

	<body>
	<head>Notes</head>

<div1 type="book" n="4"><milestone unit="chapter" n="2"/><milestone unit="section" n="28"/>
	<p>IV. II. 28, <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">secundo partis suae loco.</hi></foreign> There seems to have
been nothing in the schools of rhetoric which corresponded
with the mock trials employed to-day for the training of law
students. It would have needed little to adapt the <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">controversiae</hi></foreign> to this more practical form, but it seems not to have
been done. The declaimer dealt both with the case for the
prosecution and that for the defence, as stated in section 29.
But more than one declamation might be made on the
same theme. The declamation which is described as being
delivered <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">secundo loco</hi></foreign> would appear to be, not a declamation
for the defence, though this is conceivable, but rather a
second speech in answer to the defence. The declaimer
refutes the arguments which he alleges have been made by
the defence, but that he may not miss the opportunity of
practice in making a statement of facts, preludes his refutation with a statement of facts, inserted in the usual position
immediately following the exordium. For the whole of this
obscure passage <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi> v. xiii. 50.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="book" n="5">
	<milestone unit="chapter" n="13"/><milestone unit="section" n="49"/>
<p>V. XIII. 49. An alternative interpretation is that certain
depositions have been communicated to the prosecution by
the defence and are used to supply material for <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">contradictionea</hi></foreign> after discussion among the prosecutor's <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">advocati.</hi></foreign></p>

<milestone unit="chapter" n="13"/><milestone unit="section" n="50"/>
<p>V. XIII. 50. The reading is uncertain. Cod. Bern. reads
<foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">et</hi></foreign> * *<foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">et;</hi></foreign> Cud. Bamb. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">et et;</hi></foreign> Cod. Ambr. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">enaribus.</hi></foreign> It is
clear that something is lost. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">propositionibus</hi></foreign> is a harmless
rather than a probable emendation. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">propositionibus</hi></foreign> and
<foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">coutradictionibus</hi></foreign> have been translated as datives. It would
also be possible to treat them as ablatives: <quote>meet our
imaginary opponent's case both by statements and by
objections.</quote></p>

<pb id="p.524"/>

<milestone unit="chapter" n="14"/>
<p>V. XIV. 1 <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi> I am indebted for this note to my colleague, Dr. A. Wolf, Reader in Logic and Ethics in the
University of London.</p>

<milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
<p>&sect; 1. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">ex conseqnentibus.</hi></foreign> If S is M, it is P; S is not P;
therefore S is not M (a Destructive syllogism). The
argument is: [If Caesar's cause were not superior the
gods would not support it;] the gods have supported
Caesar's cause; therefore our cause is superior. The Major
is omitted, thereby converting the syllogism into an
enthymeme. The conclusion is stated, though it does
<hi rend="italics">not</hi> follow the premise, as it should <hi rend="italics">formally.</hi></p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
<p>&sect; 2. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">ex pugnantibus.</hi></foreign> The usual form would be: It would be
inconsistent for S to be M and not also to be P; S is M;
therefore S is also P. Quintilian's form of Minor and
Conclusion is: S is not P; therefore S is not M. The
argument is: [It would be inconsistent to hold that
someone's death should be avenged and not also that his
life should be restored, if possible;] you hold that his
life was not worth restoring, even if possible; therefore
you cannot hold that his death should be avenged. The
Major is omitted.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
<p>&sect; 3. The argument is: [It would be inconsistent to hold
that a man would commit a murder under unfavourable
circumstances, and not to hold that he would do so
under favourable circumstances;] but you know that lie
did not commit murder under favourable circumstances
therefore, you cannot hold that he did so under unfavourable circumstances.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>
<p>&sect; 4. The original argument is: If a man is guilty of an
illegality which others have committed with impunity,
he should not be punished; S is guilty of such an
illegality; therefore he should not be punished. The
counter-argument (in the text) uses the same reason
(<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the fact that the illegality in question has been
frequently committed with impunity) to establish a
contrary conclusion (<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> that special punishment should
be administered).</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
<p>&sect; 5. The epicheireme is a syllogism in which either premise
is supported by a reason. The reason is a premise of
another syllogism, so that the reason taken together
with the premise which it supports is really an enthymeme;<hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> M is P, because it is Q [and Q is P];

<pb id="p.525"/>

S is M, because it is R (and R is M]; therefore
S is P.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>
<p>&sect; &sect; 7&ndash;9. The argument is confused. It may be expressed
thus: <hi rend="italics">Major.</hi> [If the universe were not controlled by
reason, something could be found better governed than
it is.] <hi rend="italics">Reason.</hi> Because things that are governed by
reason are better governed than those which are not.
<hi rend="italics">Minor.</hi> But nothing is better administered than the
<hi rend="italics">universe. Conclusion.</hi> Therefore the universe is governed
by reason. (The argument is at once an enthymeme
(<foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">ex consequentibus</hi></foreign>)and an epicheireme.)</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>
<p>&sect; 10. The <hi rend="italics"> (Conclusion</hi> here is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> identical with the <hi rend="italics">Major,</hi> it
is only expressed in the same sentence: viz. <hi rend="italics">Major.</hi>
Whatever derives its motion from itself is immortal.
<hi rend="italics">Minor rand Conclusion.</hi> The soul derives its motion from
itself; therefore the soul is immortal.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="11"/>
<p>&sect; 11. The proposition is doubtful because it is a hasty
inference based on mere enumeration of instances.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="12"/>
<p>&sect; 12. 1st <hi rend="italics">Ex.</hi> The argument is: <hi rend="italics">Major.</hi> That which is
devoid of feeling is nothing to us. <hi rend="italics">Minor</hi> (omitted).
Death is a state devoid of feeling. <hi rend="italics">Reason.</hi> Because
a state of dissolution is a state devoid of feeling. Here
we have an epicheireme with <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> substituted for
<hi rend="italics">Minor,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Major</hi> is misunderstood as in &sect; 10 (<hi rend="italics">q. v.</hi>).
2nd Ex. <hi rend="italics">Major</hi> (omitted). If the universe were not
animate, there would be something better. <hi rend="italics">Reason.</hi>
Because all animate things are better than inanimate.
<hi rend="italics">Minor.</hi> But there is nothing better than the universe.
<hi rend="italics">Conclusion.</hi> Therefore the universe is animate. The
<hi rend="italics">Major</hi> is really omitted as Quintilian suspects.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="13"/>
<p>&sect; 13 (last sentence). What he calls the <hi rend="italics">Minor</hi> is only its
Reason.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="17"/>
<p>&sect; 17. The argument is: <hi rend="italics">Major.</hi> If in the midst of arms laws
were not silent, then he who would await their sanction
is certain to be the victim, etc. <hi rend="italics">Minor</hi> (omitted). But
he who awaits their sanction should not he the victim,
etc. <hi rend="italics">Conclusion.</hi> Therefore in the midst of arms laws
are silent. Here we have an enthymeme <hi rend="italics">ex</hi> <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">consequentibus.</hi></foreign> There is still no <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> for either premise. The
<hi rend="italics">Major</hi> is the <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> for the <hi rend="italics">Conclusion,</hi> which is a
different matter.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="18"/>
<p>&sect; 18. <hi rend="italics">Major</hi> (omitted). If the Twelve Tables permit the
killing of a man under certain circumstances, it cannot

<pb id="p.526"/>

be maintained that a slayer must be killed whatever
the circumstances. <hi rend="italics">Minor.</hi> The Twelve Tables do
permit the killing, etc. <hi rend="italics">Conclusion.</hi> Therefore it cannot be maintained that a slayer, etc. Here also what is
given is a <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> for the <hi rend="italics">Conclusion</hi> (i.e. itself a premise)
and not for the <hi rend="italics">Premise.</hi></p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="19"/>
<p>&sect; 19. The Real argument is: <hi rend="italics">Major.</hi> If it were wrong to kill
robbers, etc., we should not be allowed escorts and
swords. <hi rend="italics">Reason.</hi> For escorts and swords are intended
to enable us to fight robbers. <hi rend="italics">Minor.</hi> But we are
allowed escorts and swords. <hi rend="italics">Conclusion.</hi> Therefore it
is not wrong to kill robbers, etc.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="20"/>
<p>&sect; 20. <hi rend="italics">Major.</hi> If a man confesses, etc., he should he condemned. <hi rend="italics">Objection</hi> If a man confesses that he has
killed someone who lay in wait for him he should <hi rend="italics">not</hi>
be condemned.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="21"/>
<p>&sect; 21. The <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> is one of the premises for the proposition.
If the other <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> be false, the proposition will be
false, but the first <hi rend="italics">Reason</hi> will still he true.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="23"/>
<p>&sect; 23. The doctrine is false. If both premises are true, the
conclusion, <hi rend="italics">if valid,</hi> is true, while if both premises or
either be false, the conclusion may still be true. <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
Ar. An. Pr. ii. 2.</p>

	<milestone unit="section" n="25"/>
<p>&sect; 25. <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italics">Enthymema ex consequentibus . . . ex puqnantibus</hi></foreign> See
on &sect; 10. Both these enthymemes omit the major
premise.</p>
</div1>
		
<div1 type="book" n="6">
	<milestone unit="chapter" n="1"/><milestone unit="section" n="20"/>
	<p>VI. I. 20. Servium Sulpicium Messala is the reading of
	Scholl. The MSS. give Servius Sulpicius.</p>
</div1>

<pb id="p.529"/>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
