<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="work">The Art of Poetry:  To the Pisos</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
<author n="Hor.">Q. Horatius Flaccus (Horace)</author>
<editor role="transl">C. Smart</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.NEH;
</titleStmt>
<extent>about 112Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<author>Horace</author>
<title>The Works of Horace</title>
<editor role="transl">C. Smart</editor>
<editor role="revise">Theodore Alois Buckley</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
<date>1863</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state n="chunk" unit="card"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="xgreek">transliterated Greek</language>
<language id="de">German</language>
<language id="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change><date> 9-Jun-00</date>
<respStmt><name>AEM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
<item>
$Log: hor.ap_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-11-24 20:08:27  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/06/18 21:06:46  student
fixed Pl. Men. references - zr

Revision 1.5  2009/05/19 20:56:44  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 21:23:21  lcerrato
fixed author name for consistent sorting

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 20:50:23  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 16:12:23  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:10  packel
Converted to XML

Revision 1.7  2005/07/21 21:42:22  packel
added a milestone at the beginning of the text

Revision 1.6  2003/07/01 22:17:02  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.5  2003/02/04 21:34:43  lcerrato
fixed typo line 54 missing a in Plautus

Revision 1.4  2002/06/24 19:12:37  amahoney
fix minor typo in the Greek in a footnote

Revision 1.3  2000/06/13 21:37:34  amahoney
card breaks for the satires, continue proofreading

Revision 1.2  2000/06/12 21:37:33  amahoney
start fixing up refs to text

Revision 1.1  2000/06/09 21:34:04  amahoney
new texts (they parse but haven't been proofread yet)

</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text lang="en">
<body>
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<p>If a painter<note anchored="yes" n="1" resp="Hurd"><p>All that our poet says here may be referred, in general, to three heads, the fable, the manners, and the diction. We should take notice that this piece particularly regards epic and dramatic poetry, and that our author only occasionally mentions any other kind. The most important precept for the composition of a poem is unity and simplicity of design. There should be only one action, to which all the incidents ought to refer; and this point of perfection, every regular work requires. To show the necessity of this rule, Horace compares an irregular poem to pictures formed by a wild assortment of many parts entirely unlike each other. Every part, considered in itself, may have its proper, natural perfection, while their union produces nothing but what is monstrous and ridiculous. FRAN. The critic's rules must be taken either, 1. from the general standing laws of composition; or, 2. from the peculiar ones, appropriated to the kind. Now the direction to be fetched from the former of these sources will of course precede, as well on account of its superior dignity, as that the mind itself delights to descend from universals to the consideration of particulars. Agreeably to this rule of nature, the poet, having to correct, in the Roman drama, these three points, 1. a misconduct in the disposition; 2. an abuse of language; and, 3. a disregard of the peculiar characters and colorings of its different species, hath chosen to do this on principles of universal nature; which, while they include the case of the drama, at the same time extend to poetic composition at large. These prefatory, universal observations being delivered, he then proceeds, with advantage, to the second source of this art, viz., the consideration of the laws and rules peculiar to the kind.</p></note> should wish to unite a horse's neck to a human head, and spread a variety of plumage over limbs [of different animals] taken from every part [of nature],<note anchored="yes" n="2" resp="TAB"><p>But Orelli more rightly treats <cit><quote lang="la">collatis membris</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 3"></bibl></cit> as the ablative absolute.</p></note> so that what is a beautiful woman in the upper part terminates unsightly in an ugly fish below; could you, my friends, refrain from laughter, were you admitted to such a sight  Believe, ye Pisos, the book will be perfectly like such a picture, the ideas of which, like a sick man's dreams, are all vain and fictitious: so that neither head nor foot can correspond to any one form. "Poets and painters [you will say] have ever had equal authority for attempting any thing." We are conscious of this, and this privilege we demand and allow in turn: but not to such a degree, that the tame should associate with the savage; nor that serpents should be coupled with birds, lambs with tigers.
</p>
<p>In pompous introductions,<note anchored="yes" n="3" resp="Hurd"><p>These preparatory observations, concerning the laws of poetic composition at large, have been thought to glance more particularly at the epic poetry which was not improper: for, 1. the drama which he was about to criticise, had its rise and origin from the <foreign lang="xgreek">epos</foreign>. Thus we are told by the great critic, that Homer was the first who invented dramatic imitations <quote lang="greek">mo/nos &mdash; o(/ti mimh/seis dramatika\s e)poi/hse</quote>. 2. The several censures, here pointed at the epic, would bear still more directly against the tragic poem; it being more glaringly inconsistent with the genius of the drama to admit of foreign and digressive ornaments, than of the extended, episodical <foreign lang="xgreek">epopaeia</foreign>. For both these reasons, it was altogether pertinent to the poet's purpose, in a criticism on the drama, to expose the vicious practice of the epic models. Though, to preserve the unity of his piece, and for a further reason (see note on v. 1), he hath artfully done this under the cover of general criticism.</p></note> and such as promise a great deal, it generally happens that one or two verses of purple patch-work, that may make a great show, are tagged on; as when the grove and the altar of Diana and the meandering of a current hastening through pleasant fields, or the river <placeName key="tgn,7012611">Rhine</placeName>, or the rainbow is described. But here there was no room for these [fine things]: perhaps, too, you know how to draw a cypress:<note anchored="yes" n="4" resp="Fran"><p>Boughs of cypress were carried in funeral processions, and placed before the houses of the great, upon particular occasions of sorrow, <cit><quote lang="la">Et non plebeios luctus testata cupressus.</quote> <bibl>Lucan.</bibl></cit> From hence, perhaps, this tree was usually drawn in votive tablets; in pictures carried by beggars, to excite charity; and in those used by lawyers in courts of justice, to raise the compassion of the judges, by representing the distresses of their clients. A painter might, by frequent practice, excel in drawing a tree for which there was such demand; and he therefore absurdly determines to show his skill upon all occasions, even by painting it in the middle of the ocean, and making it overshadow the storm. The commentators understand this passage in a different manner.</p></note> but what is that to the purpose, if he, who is painted for the given price, is [to be represented as] swimming hopeless out of a shipwreck? A large vase at first was designed: why, as the wheel revolves, turns out a little pitcher? In a word, be your subject what it will, let it be merely simple and uniform.
</p>
<p>The great majority of us poets, father, and youths worthy such a father, are misled by the appearance of right. I labor to be concise, I become obscure: nerves and spirit fail him, that aims at the easy: one, that pretends to be sublime, proves bombastical: he who is too cautious and fearful of the storm, crawls along the ground: he who wants to vary his subject in a marvelous manner,
<note anchored="yes" n="5" resp="Hurd"><p>The word <foreign lang="la">prodigialiter</foreign> apparently refers to that fictitious monster, under which the poet allusively shadows out the idea of absurd and inconsistent composition. The application, however, differs in this, that, whereas the monster, there painted, was intended to expose the extravagance of putting together incongruous parts, without any reference to a whole, this prodigy is designed to characterize a whole, but deformed by the ill-judged position of its parts. The former is like a monster, whose several members as of right belonging to different animals, could by no disposition be made to constitute one consistent animal. The other, like a landscape which hath no objects absolutely irrelative, or irreducible to a whole, but which a wrong position of the parts only renders prodigious. Send the boar to the woods, and the dolphin to the waves; and the painter might show them both on the same canvas.</p>
<p>Each is a violation of the law of unity, and a real monster: the one, because it contains an assemblage of natural incoherent parts; the other, because its parts, though in themselves coherent, are misplaced and disjointed.</p></note> paints the dolphin in the woods, the boar in the sea.  The avoiding of an error leads to a fault, if it lack skill.</p>
<p>A statuary about the Aemilian school shall of himself, with singular skill,<note anchored="yes" n="6" resp="Orelli"><p><quote lang="la">Unus</quote> = <foreign lang="la">praeter caeteros</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">melius quam reliqui omnes</foreign>.</p></note> both express the nails, and imitate in brass the flexible hair; unhappy yet in the main, because he knows not how to finish a complete piece. I would no more choose to be such a one as this, had I a mind to compose any thing, than to live with a distorted nose, [though] remarkable for black eyes and jetty hair.</p>
<p>Ye who write, make choice of a subject suitable to your abilities; and revolve in your thoughts a considerable time what your strength<note anchored="yes" n="7" resp="TAB"><p>Literally, "shoulders," a phrase derived from wrestlers. The reading before <placeName key="tgn,7010699">Bentley</placeName> was <foreign lang="la">imus</foreign>. </p></note> declines, and what it is able to support. Neither elegance of style, nor a perspicuous disposition, shall desert the man, by whom the subject matter is chosen judiciously.
</p>
<p>This, or I am mistaken, will constitute the merit and beauty of arrangement, that the poet just now say what ought just now to be said, put off most of his thoughts, and waive them for the present.

<milestone ed="p" n="44" unit="card"/></p>
<p>In the choice of his words, too, the author of the projected poem must be delicate and cautious, he must embrace one and reject another: you will express yourself eminently well, if a dexterous combination should give an air of novelty to a wellknown word. If it happen to be necessary to explain some abstruse subjects by new invented terms; it will follow that you must frame words never heard of by the old-fashioned<note anchored="yes" n="8" resp="McCaul"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Cinctutis.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 50"></bibl></cit> Having the tunic tightened by the cinctus, or wearing the cinctus instead of the tunic, as appears to have been the custom of the ancient Romans. This was a vest which passed round the waist, and extended down to the feet. That it was an ancient vesture may appear from its being used by the Luperci. Comp. <bibl n="Ov. Fast. 5.101">Ovid. Fast. v. 101</bibl>. As it did not embarrass the motion of the arms, even after the tunic became part of the dress, it was sometimes substituted for it by those who had occasion to use much bodily exertion. Hence <foreign lang="la">cinctutis</foreign> is supposed by some to have a meaning here similar to that of <foreign lang="la">succinctus</foreign>, "active, industrious." Others explain the word as referring to that arrangement of the toga called <foreign lang="la">cinctus Gabinus.</foreign></p></note> Cethegi: and the license will be granted, if modestly used: and new and lately-formed words will have authority, if they descend from a Greek source, with a slight deviation. But why should the Romans grant to Plautus and Caecilius a privilege denied to Virgil and Varius? Why should I be envied, if I have it in my power to acquire a few words, when the language of Cato and Ennius has enriched our native tongue, and produced new names of things It has been, and ever will be, allowable to coin a word marked with the stamp in present request. As leaves in the woods are changed with the fleeting years; the earliest fall off first: in this manner words perish with old age, and those lately invented flourish and thrive, like men in the time of youth. We, and our works, are doomed to death: whether Neptune,<note anchored="yes" n="9" resp="San"><p>Agrippa opened a communication between the Lucrine and Avernian Lakes in 717, and built a magnificent haven there, which he named Portius Julius, in honor of Augustus, who was at that time only called Julius Octavianus.</p></note> admitted into the continent, defends our fleet from the north winds, a kingly work; or the lake, for a long time unfertile and fit for oars, now maintains its neighboring cities and feels the heavy plow; or the liver, taught to run in a more convenient channel, has changed its course which was so destructive<note anchored="yes" n="10" resp="TAB"><p>The Scholiast informs us, that Agrippa opened a canal to receive the waters of the <placeName key="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>, which had overflowed the country.</p></note> to the fruits. Mortal works must perish: much less can the honor and elegance of language be long-lived. Many words shall revive,<note anchored="yes" n="11" resp="Hurd"><p>This revival of old words is one of those niceties in composition, not to be attempted by any but great masters. It may be done two ways: 1. by restoring such terms as are grown entirely obsolete; or 2. by selecting out of those which have still a currency, and are not quite laid aside, such as are most forcible and expressive. These choice words, among such as are still in use, I take to be those which are employed by the old writers in some peculiarly strong and energetic sense, yet so as with good advantage to be copied by the moderns, without appearing barbarous or affected. (See <bibl n="Hor. Ep. 2.2.115">Hor. lib. ii. ep. ii. v. 115.</bibl>) The other use of old terms, i. e. when become obsolete, he says, must be made parce, more sparingly.</p></note> which now have fallen off; and many which are now in esteem shall fall off, if it be the will of custom, in whose power is the decision and right and standard of language.

<milestone ed="p" n="73" unit="card"/></p>
<p>Homer has instructed us in what measure the achievements<note anchored="yes" n="12" resp="Hurd"><p>The purport of these lines (from v. 73 to 86), and their connection with what follows, hath not been fully seen. They would express this general proposition, "That the several kinds of poetry essentially differ from each other, as may be gathered, not solely from their different subjects, but their different measures; which good sense, and an attention to the peculiar natures of each, instructed the great inventors and masters of them to employ." The use made of this proposition is to infer, "That therefore the like attention should be had to the different species of the same kind of poetry (v. 89, etc.), as in the case of tragedy and comedy (to which the application is made), whose peculiar differences and correspondences, as resulting from the natures of each, should, in agreement to the universal law of decorum, be exactly known and diligently observed by the poet."</p></note> of kings, and chiefs, and direful war might be written.</p>
<p>Plaintive strains originally were appropriated to the unequal numbers [of the elegiac]:<note anchored="yes" n="13" resp="Torr"><p>Elegy was at first only a lamentation for the death of a person beloved, and probably arose frem the death of Adonis. It was afterward applied to the joys and griefs of lovers.</p></note> afterward [love and] successful desires were included. Yet what author first published humble<note anchored="yes" n="14" resp="Dac"><p>The pentameter, which <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> calls <cit><quote lang="la">exiguum,</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 77"></bibl></cit> because it has a foot less than the hexameter. For the same reason he says, <cit><quote lang="la">versibus impariter junctis.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 75"></bibl></cit></p></note> elegies, the critics dispute, and the controversy still waits the determination of a judge.
</p>
<p>Rage armed Archilochus with the iambic of his own invention. The sock and the majestic buskin assumed this measure as adapted for dialogue, and to silence the noise of the populace, and calculated for action.</p>
<p>To celebrate gods, and the sons of gods, and the victorious wrestler, and the steed foremost in the race, and the inclination of youths, and the free joys of wine, the muse has allotted to the lyre.</p>
<p>If I am incapable and unskillful to observe the distinction described, and the complexions of works [of genius], why am I accosted by the name of "Poet?" Why, out of false modesty, do I prefer being ignorant to being learned?</p>
<p>A comic subject will not be handled in tragic verse:<note anchored="yes" n="15" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Indignatur item &hellip; Coena Thyestae.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 90"></bibl></cit> <quote lang="fr">"Il met le souper de Thyeste pour toutes sortes de tragedies,"</quote> says M. Dacier, with whom agrees the whole band of commentators: but why this subject should be singled out, as the representative of the rest, is nowhere explained by any of them. We may be sure, it was not taken up at random. The reason was, that the Thyestes of Ennius was peculiarly chargeable with the fault here censured; as is plain from a curious passage in the Orator, where Cicero, speaking of the loose numbers of certain poets, observes this, in particular, of the tragedy of Thyestes, <quote lang="la">Similia sunt quaedam apud nostros: velut in Thyeste, <quote lang="la"><l>Quemnam te esse dicam? qui tarda in senectute,</l></quote> et quae sequuntur: quae, nisi cum tibicen accesserit, oratione sunt solutae simillimae</quote>: which character exactly agrees to this of Horace, wherein the language of that play is censured, as flat and prosaic, and hardly rising above the plain narrative of an ordinary conversation in comedy. This allusion to a particular play, written by one of their best poets, and frequently exhibited on the Roman stage, gives great force and spirit to the precept, at the same time that it exemplifies it in the happiest manner. It seems further probable to me, that the poet also designed an indirect compliment to Varius, whose Thyestes we are told (<bibl n="Quint. 10.1">Quinctil. l. x c. 1</bibl>) was not inferior to any tragedy of the Greeks. This double intention of these lines well suited to the poet's general aim, which is seen through all his critical works, of beating down the excessive admiration of the old poets, and of asserting and advancing the just honors of the deserving moderns. It may further be observed, that the critics have not felt the force of the words <quote lang="la">exponi</quote> and <quote lang="la">narrari</quote> in this precept. They are admirably chosen to express the two faults condemned: the first implying a kind of pomp and ostentation in the language, which is therefore improper for the low subjects of comedy; and the latter, as I have hinted, a flat, prosaic expression, not above the cast of a common narrative, and therefore equally unfit for tragedy.</p></note> in like manner the banquet of Thyestes will not bear to be held in familiar verses, and such as almost suit the sock. Let  each peculiar species [of writing] fill with decorum its proper place. Nevertheless sometimes even comedy exalts her voice, and passionate Chremes rails in a tumid strain: and a tragic writer generally expresses grief in a prosaic style. Telephus and Peleus, when they are both in poverty and exile, throw aside their rants and gigantic expressions if they have a mind to move the heart of the spectator with their complaint.
<milestone ed="p" n="99" unit="card"/></p>
<p>It is not enough that poems be beautiful;<note anchored="yes" n="16" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Non satis est pulchra</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 99"></bibl></cit>, etc. <placeName key="tgn,2046166">Bentley</placeName> objects to <foreign lang="la">pulchra</foreign> because this, he says, is a general term including under it every species of beauty, and therefore that of <foreign lang="la">dulcis</foreign> or the affecting. As if general terms were not frequently restrained and determined to a peculiar sense by the context. But the great critic did not sufficietly attend to the connection, which, as F. Robertellus, in his paraphrase on the epistle, well observes, stands thus: "It is not enough, that tragedies have that kind of beauty which arises from a pomp and splendor of diction, they must also be pathetic or affecting."</p></note> let them be tender and affecting, and bear away the soul of the auditor whithersoever they please. As the human countenance smiles on those that smile, so does it sympathize with those that weep. If you would have me weep you must first express the passion of grief yourself; then, Telephus or Peleus, your misfortunes hurt me: if you pronounce the parts assigned you ill, I shall either fall asleep or laugh.</p>
<p>Pathetic accents suit a melancholy countenance; words full of menace, an angry one; wanton expressions, a sportive look; and serious matter, an austere one. For nature forms us first within to every modification of circumstances; she delights or impels us to anger, or depresses us to the earth and afflicts us with heavy sorrow: then expresses those emotions of the mind by the tongue, its interpreter. If the words be discordant to the station of the speaker, the Roman knights and plebians will raise an immoderate laugh. It will make a wide difference, whether it be Davus that speaks, or a hero; a man well-stricken in years, or a hot young fellow in his bloom; and a matron of distinction, or an officious nurse; a roaming merchant, or the cultivator of a verdant little farm; a Colchian, or an Assyrian; one educated at <placeName key="tgn,7011071">Thebes</placeName>, or one at <placeName key="tgn,7010720">Argos</placeName>.</p>
<p>You, that write, either follow tradition,<note anchored="yes" n="17" resp="Hurd"><p>The connection lies thus: language must agree with character; character with fame, or at least with itself.</p></note> or invent such fables as are congruous to themselves. If as poet you have to represent the renowned Achilles; let him be indefatigable, wrathful, inexorable, courageous, let him deny that laws were made for him, let him arrogate every thing to force of arms Let Medea be fierce and untractable, Ino an object of pity, Ixion perfidious, Io wandering, Orestes in distress.

<milestone ed="p" n="125" unit="card"/></p>
<p>If you offer to the stage any thing unattempted, and venture to form a new character; let it be preserved to the last<note anchored="yes" n="18" resp="Hurd"><p>The rule is, as appears from the reason of the thing, and from Aristotle, "Let a uniformity of character be preserved, or at least a consistency": i. e. either let the manners be exactly the same from the beginning to the end of the play, as those of Medea, for instance, and Orestes; or, if any change be necessary, let it be such as may consist with, and be easily reconciled to, the manners formerly attributed, as is seen in the case of Electra and Iphigenia.</p></note> such as it set out at the beginning, and be consistent with itself. It is difficult to write with propriety<note anchored="yes" n="19" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Difficile est proprie communia dicere.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 128"></bibl></cit> Lambin's comment is, <quote lang="la">Communia hoc loco appellat Horatius argumenta fabularum a nullo adhuc tractata: et ita, quae cuivis exposita sunt et in medio quadammodo posit, quasi vacua et a nemino occupata.</quote> And that this is the true meaning of <foreign lang="la">communia</foreign> is evidently fixed by the words <foreign lang="la">ignota indictaque</foreign>, which are explanatory of it.</p></note> on subjects to which all writers have a common claim; and you with more prudence will reduce the Iliad into acts, than if you first introduce arguments unknown and never treated of before. A public story will become your own property,<note anchored="yes" n="20" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Publica materies</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 131"></bibl></cit> is just the reverse of what the poet had before styled <foreign lang="la">communia</foreign>: the latter meaning such subjects or characters as, though by their nature left in common to all, had yet, in fact, not been occupied by any writer; the former, those which had already been made public by occupation. In order to acquire a property in subjects of this sort, the poet directs us to observe the three following cautions: 1. Not to follow the trite, obvious round of the original work; i. e. not servilely and scrupulously to adhere to its plan of method. 2. Not to be translators, instead of imitators, i. e. if it shall be thought fit to imitate more expressly any part of the original, to do it with freedom and spirit, and without a slavish attachment to the mode of expression. 3. Not to adopt any particular incident that may occur in the proposed model, which either decency or the nature of the work would reject.</p></note> if you do not dwell upon the whole circle of events, which is paltry and open to every one; nor must you be so faithful a translator, as to take the pains of rendering [the original] word for word; nor by imitating throw yourself into straits, whence either shame or the rules of your work may forbid you to retreat. Nor  must you make such an exordium, as the Cyclic<note anchored="yes" n="21" resp="McCaul"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Scriptor cyclicus.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 136"></bibl></cit> Some author of the <foreign lang="la">cyclus</foreign>, described above, 1, 132. The chief Cyclic poems are the following: 1. <foreign lang="greek">ta\ *Ku/pria</foreign>, of Stasinus or Hegesinus. 2. The <foreign lang="greek">*Ai)qiopi/s</foreign> of Arctinus. 3. The <foreign lang="greek">*)Ilia\s mikra/</foreign>, by Lesches. 4. The <foreign lang="greek">*)Ili/ou pe/rsis</foreign> of Arctinus. 5. The <foreign lang="greek">*No/stoi</foreign> attributed to Agias. 6. The <foreign lang="greek">*Thlegoni/a</foreign> of Eugammon. These were collected, more for the sake of philology than poetry, by the Alexandrine grammarians.</p></note> writer of old: "I will sing the fate of Priam, and the noble war."  What will this boaster produce worthy of all this gaping?  The mountains are in labor, a ridiculous mouse will be brought forth. How much more to the purpose he, who attempts nothing improperly  "Sing for me, my muse, the man who, after the time of the destruction of <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>, surveyed the manners and cities of many men." He meditates not [to produce] smoke from a flash, but out of smoke to elicit fire, that he may thence bring forth his instances of the marvelous with beauty, [such as] Antiphates, Scylla, the <placeName key="tgn,2236678">Cyclops</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,2233588">Charybdis</placeName>. Nor does he date Diomede's return from Meleager's death, nor trace the rise of the Trojan war from [Leda's] eggs: he always hastens on to the event; and hurries away his reader in the midst of interesting circumstances, no otherwise than as if they were [already] known; and what he despairs of, as to receiving a polish from his touch, he omits; and in such a manner forms his fictions, so intermingles the false with the true, that the middle is not inconsistent with the beginning, nor the end with the middle. Do you attend to what I, and the public in my opinion, expect from you [as a dramatic writer]. If you are desirous of an applauding spectator, who will wait for [the falling of] the curtain, and till the chorus calls out "your plaudits"; the manners of every age must be marked by you, and a proper decorum assigned to men's varying dispositions and years. The boy, who is just able to pronounce his words, and prints the ground with a firm tread, delights to play with his fellows, and contracts and lays aside anger without reason, and is subject to change every hour. The beardless youth, his guardian being at length discharged, joys in horses, and dogs, and the verdure of the sunny <placeName key="tgn,7014001">Campus Martius</placeName>; pliable as wax to the bent of vice, rough to advisers, a slow provider of useful things, prodigal of his money, high-spirited, and amorous, and hasty in deserting the objects of his passion. [After this,] our inclinations being changed, the age and spirit of manhood seeks after wealth, and [high] connections, is subservient to points of honor; and is cautious of committing any action, which he would subsequently be industrious to correct.  Many inconveniences encompass a man in years; either because he seeks [eagerly] for gain,<note anchored="yes" n="22" resp="TAB"><p><quote lang="la">Quaerit</quote> = <foreign lang="la">quaestus facit,</foreign> as in <cit><bibl n="Verg. G. 1.127">Virg. Georg. i.</bibl> <quote lang="la">In medium quaerebant.</quote></cit></p></note> and abstains from what he has gotten, and is afraid to make use of it; or because he transacts every thing in a timorous and dispassionate manner, dilatory, slow in hope, remiss, and greedy of futurity. Peevish, querulous, a panegyrist of former times when he was a boy, a chastiser and censurer of his juniors. Our advancing years<note anchored="yes" n="23" resp="Dac"><p>He returns to his first division of human life into two parts. <quote lang="la">"Anni venientes,"</quote> the years preceding manhood; <quote lang="la">"anni recedentes,"</quote> the years going back toward old age and death. The ancients reckoned the former by addition: the latter by subtraction. The French have an expression like this of <quote lang="la">"recedentes anni."</quote> They say, <foreign lang="fr">"il est sur son retour,"</foreign> "he is upon his return," when a person is declining in years.</p></note> bring many advantages along with them. Many our declining ones take away. That the parts [therefore] belong ing to age may not be given to youth, and those of a man to a boy, we must dwell upon those qualities which are joined and adapted to each person's age.<note anchored="yes" n="24" resp="TAB"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Semper in adjunctis.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 178"></bibl></cit> <foreign lang="la">"Adjuncta aevo,"</foreign> every thing which attends age; <foreign lang="la">"apta aevo,"</foreign> every thing proper to it.</p></note></p>
<p>An action is either represented on the stage, or being done elsewhere is there related.  The things which enter by the ear affect the mind more languidly, than such as are submitted to the faithful eyes, and what a spectator presents to himself.  You must not, however, bring upon the stage things fit only to be acted behind the scenes: and you must take away from view many actions, which elegant descrition<note anchored="yes" n="25" resp="Dac"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Facundia praesens.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 184"></bibl></cit> The recital of an actor present, which ought to be made with all the pathetic; <foreign lang="la">facundia</foreign>; or a recital instead of the action, <foreign lang="la">facundia facti vicaria, quae rem quasi oculis praesentem sistit.</foreign></p></note> may soon after deliver in presence [of the spectators]. Let not Medea murder her sons before the people; nor the execrable Atreus openly dress human entrails: nor let Progne be metamorphosed into a bird, <placeName key="tgn,2078692">Cadmus</placeName> into a serpent. Whatever you show to me in this manner, not able to give credit to, I detest.

<milestone ed="p" n="189" unit="card"/></p>
<p>Let a play which would be inquired after, and though seen, represented anew, be neither shorter nor longer than the fifth act. Neither let a god interfere, unless a difficulty worthy a god's unraveling should happen; nor let a fourth person be officious to speak.<note anchored="yes" n="26" resp="Rodell"><p>The poet does not forbid a fourth person to speak, but would have him say very little, as the Scholiast understands the precept. Indeed, a conversation of three people is most agreeable, because it is less confused and less divides the attention of an audience.</p></note></p>
<p>Let the chorus<note anchored="yes" n="27" resp="Fran"><p>The chorus was not introduced between the acts, merely to relieve the audience, but had a part in the play, and concurred with the other actors to carry on the plot, and support the probability of it. The Choriphaeus, or first person of the chorus, entered in the acts, and spoke for all those of whom the chorus was composed; <cit><quote lang="la">officiumque virile defendat.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 193"></bibl></cit>  The chorus filled up the intervals of the acts with their songs, which were composed of reflections upon what was past, or their apprehensions of what might happen.</p></note> sustain the part and manly<note anchored="yes" n="28" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Officiumque virile</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 193"></bibl></cit>. Heinsius takes <foreign lang="la">virile</foreign> adverbially, for <foreign lang="la">viriliter</foreign>. But this is thought harsh.  What hinders, but that it may be taken adjectively? And then, agreeably to his interpretation, <quote lang="la">"officium virile"</quote> will mean a strenuous, diligent office, such as becomes a person interested in the progress of the action. The precept is leveled against the practice of those poets who, though they allow the part of a <foreign lang="la">persona dramatis</foreign> to the chorus, yet for the most part make it so idle and insignificant a one, as is of little consequence in the representation; by which means the advantage of probability, intended to be drawn from this use of the chorus, is, in great measure, forfeited.</p></note> character of an actor: nor let them sing any thing between the acts which is not conducive to, and fitly coherent with, the main design. Let them both patronize the good,<note anchored="yes" n="29" resp="Hurd"><p>The chorus, says the poet, is to take the side of the good and virtuous; i. e. (see note on v. 193), is always to sustain a moral character. But this will need some explanation and restriction. To conceive aright of its office, we must suppose the chorus to be a number of persons, by some probable cause assembled together, as witnesses and spectators of the great action of the drama. Such persons, as they can not be wholly uninterested in what passes before them, will very naturally bear some share in the representation. This will principally consist in declaring their sentiments, and indulging their reflections freely on the several events and distresses as they shall arise. Thus we see the moral attributed to the chorus, will be no other than the dictates of plain sense; such as must be obvious to every thinking observer of the action, who is under the influence of no peculiar partialities from affection or interest. Though even these may be supposed, in cases where the character toward which they draw is represented as virtuous. A chorus, thus constituted, must always, it is evident, take the part of virtue: because this is the natural, and almost necessary determination of mankind, in all ages and nations, when acting freely and unconstrained.</p></note> and give them friendly advice, and regulate the passionate, and love to appease thou who swell [with rage]:<note anchored="yes" n="30" resp="TAB"><p>I read <foreign lang="la">pacare tumentes</foreign>, with <placeName key="tgn,1013077">Bentley</placeName>, Orelli, and others.</p></note> let them praise the repast of a short meal, the salutary effects of justice, laws, and peace with her open gates; let them conceal what is told to them in confidence,<note anchored="yes" n="31" resp="Dac"><p>The Choriphaeus was present through the whole play, and was often necessarily intrusted with the secrets of the persons of the drama. To preserve the probability, the poets chose a chorus, that was obliged by their own interest to keep those secrets, and without acting contrary to their duty. Euripides hath greatly offended against this precept.</p></note> and supplicate and implore the gods that prosperity may return to the wretched, and abandon the haughty.</p>
<p>The flute,<note anchored="yes" n="32" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Tibia non ut nunc orichalco</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 202"></bibl></cit>, etc. (From v. 202 to v. 220.) This is one of those many passages in the epistle about which the critics have said a great deal, without explaining any thing. In support of what I mean to offer, as the true interpretation, I observe,</p>
<p>I. That the poet's intention certainly was, not to censure the false refinements of their stage music; but, in a short digressive history (such as the didactic form will sometimes require), to describe the rise and progress of the true. This I collect, 1. From the expression itself, which can not, without violence, be understood in any other way. For, as to the words <foreign lang="la">licentia</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">praeceps</foreign>, which have occasioned much of the difficulty, the first means a freer use, not a licentiousness properly so-called; and the other only expresses a vehemence and rapidity of language, naturally productive of a quicker elocution, such as must of course attend the more numerous harmony of the lyre: not, as M. Dacier translates it, <quote lang="fr">"une eloquence temeraire et outr&eacute;e,"</quote> an extravagant straining and affectation of style. 2. From the reason of the thing, which makes it incredible that the music of the theater should then be most complete, when the times were barbarous, and entertainments of this kind little encouraged or understood. 3. From the character of that music itself; for the rudeness of which, <placeName key="tgn,2077718">Horace</placeName>, in effect, apologizes, in defending it only on the score of the imperfect state of the stage, and the simplicity of its judges. This then being clear, I observe,</p>
<p>II. That those two verses, 
<cit><quote lang="la"><lg type="hexameter"><l>Indoctus quid enim saperet liberque laborum,</l>
<l>Rusticus urbane confusus, turpis honesto?</l></lg></quote> <bibl n="Hor. Ars 211">(212-213)</bibl></cit>
are, as they now stand, utterly inexplicable. This hath appeared long since, from the fruitless labors of the critics, and, above all, of Lambin, one of the best of them, who, after several repeated efforts to elucidate this place, leaves it just as dark and unintelligible as he found it. The interpretation, without them, stands thus: "The tibia," says the poet, "was at first low and simple. The first, as best agreeing to the then state of the stage, which required only a soft music to go along with and assist the chorus, there being no large and crowded theaters to fill in those days. And the latter, as suiting best to the then state of the times, whose simplicity and frugal manners exacted the severest temperance, as in every thing else, so in their dramatic ornaments and decorations. But, when conquest had enlarged the territory and widened the walls of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, and, in consequence thereof, a social spirit had dispelled that severity of manners, by the introduction of frequent festival solemnities, then, as was natural to expect, a freer and more varied harmony took place. And thus it was, that the <foreign lang="la">tibicen</foreign>, the musician who played to the declamation in the acts, instead of the rude and simpler strain of the old times, gave a richness and variety of tone; and instead of the old inactive posture, added the grace of motion to his art. Just in the same manner," continues he, "it happened to the lyre, i. e. the music in the chorus, which originally, as that of the <foreign lang="la">tibia</foreign>, was severe and simple; but, by degrees, acquired a quicker and more expressive modulation, such as corresponded to the more elevated and passionate turn of the poet's style, and the diviner enthusiasm of his sentiment."</p></note> (not as now, begirt with brass and emulous of the trumpet, but) slender and of simple form, with few stops, was of service to accompany and assist the chorus, and with its tone was sufficient to fill the rows that were not as yet too crowded, where an audience, easily numbered, as being small and sober, chaste and modest, met together. But when the victorious Romans began to extend their territories, and an ampler wall encompassed the city, and their genius was indulged on festivals by drinking wine in the day-time without censure; a greater freedom arose both to the numbers [of poetry], and the measure [of music].<note anchored="yes" n="33" resp="TAB"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Accessit numerisque modisque licentia major.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 211"></bibl></cit> M. Dacier is out again, when he takes <quote lang="la">licentia major</quote> in a bad sense, as implying <foreign lang="fr">lascivet&eacute;</foreign>, a culpable and licentious refinement. The license here spoken of, with regard to numbers and sounds, like that in another place, which respects words <bibl n="Hor. Ars 51">(l. 51)</bibl>, is one of those which is allowed, when <foreign lang="la">sumpta pudenter</foreign>. The comparative <foreign lang="la">major</foreign>, which is a palliative, shows this; and is further justified by a like passage in <placeName key="tgn,2239742">Cicero</placeName> de Oratore <bibl n="Cic. de Orat. 1.3.48">(I. iii. c. 48)</bibl>, where, speaking of this very license in poetry, he observes, that out of the heroic and iambic measure, which was at first strictly observed, there arose by degrees the anapaest, <quote lang="la">"procerior quidam numerus, et ille licentior et divitior dithyrambus"</quote>; evidently not condemning this change, but opposing it to the rigorous and confined measures of the elder poet. But the expression itself occurs in the piece entitled "Orator," in which, comparing the freedoms of the poetical and oratorical style, <quote lang="la">"in ea"</quote> (i. e. <foreign lang="la">poetica</foreign>), says he, <quote lang="la">"licentiam statuo majorem esse, quam in nobis faciendorum iungendorumque verborum."</quote> The poet says this license extended <quote lang="la">"numeris modisque,"</quote> the former of which words will express that license of meter spoken of by <placeName key="tgn,2239742">Cicero</placeName>, and which is further explained, <bibl n="Hor. Ars 256">v. 256</bibl>, etc., where an account is given of the improvement of the iambic verse. <placeName key="tgn,2407583">HURD</placeName>.</p></note> For what taste could an unlettered clown and one just dismissed from labors have, when in company with the polite; the base, with the man of honor? Thus the musician added<note anchored="yes" n="34" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Sic priscae &hellip; arti tibicen</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 215"></bibl></cit>, etc. &mdash; <cit><quote lang="la">Sic etiam fidibus</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 216"></bibl></cit>, etc. This is the application of what hath been said, in general, concerning the refinement of theatrical music to the case of tragedy. Some commentators say, and to comedy. But in this they mistake, as will appear presently. M. Dacier hath I know not what conceit about a comparison betwixt the Roman and Greek stage. His reason is, that the lyre was used in the Greek chorus, as appears, lie says, from Sophocles playing upon this instrument himself in one of his tragedies. And was it not used too in the Roman chorus, as appears from <placeName key="tgn,2538429">Nero</placeName>'s playing upon it in several tragedies? But the learned critic did not apprehend this matter. Indeed, from the caution with which his guides, the dealers in antiquities, always touch this point, it should seem that they too had no very clear conception of it. The case I take to have been this: the tibia, as being most proper to accompany the declamation of the acts, <quote lang="la">cantanti succinere</quote>, was constantly employed, as well in the Roman tragedy as comedy. This appears from many authorities. I mention only two from <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>. <cit><bibl n="Cic. Luc. 7">(Acad. 1. ii. 7)</bibl> <quote lang="la">"Quam multa quae nos fugiunt in cantu, exaudiunt in eo genere exercitati: Qui, primo inflatu tibicinis, Antiopam esse aiunt aut Andromachem, cum nos ne suspicemur quidem."</quote></cit> The other is still more express. In his piece entitled "Orator," speaking of the negligence of the Roman writers in respect of numbers, he observes, that there were even many passages in their tragedies, which, unless the tibia played to them, could not be distinguished from mere prose: <quote lang="la">"quae nisi cum tibicen accesserit, orationi sint solutae simillima."</quote> One of these passages is expressely quoted from Thyestes, a tragedy of Ennius, and, as appears from the measure, taken out of one of the acts. It is clear, then, that the tibia was certainly used in the declamation of tragedy. But now the song of the tragic chorus, being of the nature of the ode, of course required <foreign lang="la">fides</foreign>, the lyre, the peculiar and appropriated instrument of the lyric muse. And this is clearly collected, if not from express testimonies, yet from some occasional hints dropped by the ancients. For, 1. The lyre we are told (<bibl n="Cic. Leg. 2.9">Cic. de Leg. ii. 9 and 15</bibl>), and is agreed on all hands, was an instrument of the Roman theater; but it was not employed in comedy. This we certainly know from the short accounts of the music prefixed to Terrence's plays. 2. Further, the <foreign lang="la">tibicen</foreign>, as we saw, accompanied the declamation of the acts in tragedy. It remains, then, that the proper place of the lyre was, where one should naturally look for it, in the songs of the chorus; but we need not go further than this very passage for a proof. It is unquestionable, that the poet is here speaking of the chorus only, the following lines not admitting any other possible interpretation. By <foreign lang="la">fidibus</foreign>, then, it is necessarily understood the instrument peculiarly used in it. In this view, the whole digression is more pertinent and connects better. The poet had before been speaking of tragedy. All his directions, from l. 100, respect this species of the drama only. The application of what he had said concerning music is then most naturally made, 1. To the <foreign lang="la">tibia</foreign>, the music of the acts; and, 2. To <foreign lang="la">fides</foreign>, that of the choir: thus confining himself, as the tenor of this part required, to tragedy only. Hence is seen the mistake, not only of M. Dacier, whose comment is in every view insupportable; but, as was hinted, of Heinsius, Lambin, and others, who, with more probability, explained this of the Roman tragedy and comedy. For, though <foreign lang="la">tibia</foreign> might be allowed to stand for comedy, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">tragoedia</foreign> (as, in fact, we find it in <bibl n="Hor. Ep. 2.1.98">II. Ep. 1. 98</bibl>), that being the only instrument employed in it; yet, in speaking expressly of the music of the stage, <foreign lang="la">fides</foreign> could not determinately enough, and in contradistinction to <foreign lang="la">tibia</foreign>, denote that of tragedy, it being an instrument used solely or principally in the chorus, of which the context shows, he alone speaks. It is further to be observed, that in the application here made, besides the music, the poet takes in the other improvements of the tragic chorus, these happening, as from the nature of the thing they must, at the same time.</p></note> new movements and a  luxuriance to the ancient art, and strutting backward and forward, drew a length of train over the stage; thus likewise new notes were added to the severity of the lyre, and precipitate eloquence produced an unusual language [in the theater]: and the sentiments [of the chorus, then] expert in teaching useful things and prescient of futurity, differ hardly from the oracular <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Delphi</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" n="35" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Sententia Delphis.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 219"></bibl></cit> <foreign lang="la">Sententia</foreign> is properly an aphorism taken from life, briefly representing either what is or what ought to be the conduct of it: <cit><quote lang="la">"Oratio sumpta de vita, quae aut quid sit aut quid esse oporteat in vita, breviter ostendit."</quote> <bibl n="Rhet. Her. 1.4">(Ad Herenn. Rhet. 1. iv.)</bibl></cit> These aphorisms are here mentioned, as constituting the peculiar praise and beauty of the chorus. This is finely observed, and was intended to convey an oblique censure on the practice of those poets, who stuff out every part of the drama alike with moral sentences, not considering that the only proper receptacle of them is the chorus, where indeed they have an extreme propriety, it being the peculiar office and character of the chorus to moralize.</p></note>

<milestone ed="p" n="220" unit="card"/></p>
<p>The poet, who first tried his skill in tragic verse for the paltry [prize of a] goat, soon after exposed to view wild satyrs naked,<note anchored="yes" n="36" resp="Nan"><p>There was a kind of tragic comedies among the Greeks, which they called Satyrs, because the chorus was formed of Satyrs, who sung the praises of Bacchus between the acts, and said a thousand low pleasantries. The only piece of this kind remaining to us is the <placeName key="tgn,2236678">Cyclops</placeName> of Euripides, in which Ulysses is the principal actor. The Romans, in imitation of the Greek Satyrs, had their <foreign lang="la">Atellanae</foreign>, so called from <placeName key="perseus,Atella">Atella</placeName>, the city where they were first played.</p></note> and attempted raillery with severity, still preserving the gravity [of tragedy]: because the spectator on festivals, when heated with wine<note anchored="yes" n="37" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Potus et exlex.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 224"></bibl></cit> The lines, 
<cit><quote lang="la"><lg type="hexameter"><l>Indoctus quid enim saperet liberque laborum </l>
<l>Rusticus urbane confusus, turpis honesto</l></lg></quote> <bibl n="Hor. Ars 212">(212-213)</bibl></cit>
were, I observed, certainly misplaced. They should, I think, come in here, where their sense is extremely pertinent. The poet had been speaking of the satyric drama, which, says he, was added to the tragic, 
<cit><quote lang="la"><lg type="hexameter"><l part="F">eo quod </l>
<l>Illecebris erat, et grata novitate morandus </l>
<l>Spectator, functusque sacris, et potus, et exlex.</l></lg></quote> <bibl n="Hor. Ars 223">(223-225)</bibl></cit> 
But why, it might be asked, this compliance, in so false a taste, with a drunken, lawless rabble? The answer is natural and to the purpose. "Because their theaters necessarily consisted of a mixed assembly, every part of which was to be considered in the public diversions." The question then hath an extreme propriety, <quote lang="la">"Indoctus quid enim saperet liberque laborum, Rusticus urbane confusus, turpis honesto?"</quote> The <foreign lang="la">rusticus</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">turpis</foreign> demanded the satyric piece. It was the necessary result of this mixutre; as, to gratify the better sort, the <foreign lang="la">urbanus</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">honestus</foreign>, the tragic drama was exhibited. It is some prejudice in favor of this conjecture, that it explains to us, what would otherwise appear very strange, that such gross ribaldry, as we know the Atellanes consisted of, could ever be endured by the politest age of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. But scenical representations being then intended, not as in our days, for the entertainment of the better sort, but on certain great solemnities, indifferently for the diversion of the whole city, it became necessary to consult the taste of the multitude, as well as of those, <cit><quote lang="la">quibus est equus et pater et res.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 248"></bibl></cit></p></note> and disorderly, was to be amused with captivating shows and agreeable novelty. But it will be expedient so to recommend the bantering, so the rallying satyrs, so to turn earnest into jest; that none who shall be exhibited as a god, none who is introduced as a hero lately<note anchored="yes" n="38" resp="Fran"><p>This proves that the same actor, as M. Dacier observes, who had been an Orestes or Ulysses in the tragic part, played the same chraracter in the comic or <foreign lang="la">Atellanae.</foreign> Thus Plautus in the prologue to his Menechmes, <cit><quote lang="en">"this town, during this play, shall be Epidamnum, and when it has been acted, it may be any other city. As in a company of players, the same person shall, at different times, be a pander, a youth, an old man, a beggar, a king, a parasite, a soothsayer."</quote> <bibl n="Pl. Men. prologue.0">(72-76)</bibl></cit> St. Jerome hath finely imitated this passage: <quote lang="en">"our vices oblige us to play many characters, for every vice wears a different mask. Thus in a theater, the same person plays a robust and nervous Hercules, a dissolute Venus, and a furious <placeName key="tgn,2236678">Cyclops</placeName>."</quote></p></note> conspicuous in regal purple and gold, may deviate into the low style of obscure, mechanical shops; or, [on the contrary,] while he avoids the ground, affect cloudy mist and empty jargon.  Tragedy<note anchored="yes" n="39" resp="Dac"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Indigna tragoedia versus.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 231"></bibl></cit> Horace means the <foreign lang="la">Atellanae</foreign>, which were in so much esteem, that the persons, who acted in them, were not ranked with the comedians, nor were obliged to unmask on the stage when they played ill, as others were; and, as a peculiar honor, they were allowed to enlist in the army. Therefore low and trivial verses were beneath the dignity of the <foreign lang="la">Atellanae.</foreign></p></note> disdaining to prate forth trivial verses, like a matron commanded to dance on the festival days,<note anchored="yes" n="40" resp="Dac"><p>Young women were usually chosen to dance in honor of the gods, but in some festivals, as in that of the great goddess, the pontiffs obliged married women to dance. Hence the poet says <foreign lang="la">iussa.</foreign></p></note> will assume an air of modesty, even in the midst of wanton satyrs. As a writer of satire, ye Pisos, I shall never be fond of unornamented and reigning terms:<note anchored="yes" n="41" resp="Fran"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Dominantia verba.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 234"></bibl></cit> What the Greeks call <foreign lang="greek">ku/ria</foreign>, as if they were masters of the thing they would express; as we say in English, "calling things by their proper names."</p></note> nor shall I labor to differ so widely from the complexion of tragedy, as to make no distinction, whether Davus be the speaker. And the bold Pythias, who gained a talent by gulling Simo; or Silenus, the guardian and attendant of his pupil-god [Bacchus]. I would so execute a fiction<note anchored="yes" n="42" resp="Hurd"><p>This precept (<bibl n="Hor. Ars 240">from v. 240 to 244</bibl>) is analogous to that before given (<bibl n="Hor. Ars 129">v. 129</bibl>) concerning tragedy. It directs to form the Satyrs out of a known subject. The reasons are, in general, the same for both. Only one seems peculiar to the Satyrs. For, the cast of them being necessarily romantic, and the persons those fantastic beings called satyrs, the <foreign lang="greek">to\ o(/moion</foreign>, or probable, will require the subject to have gained a popular belief, without which the representation must appear unnatural. Now, these subjects which have gained a popular belief, in consequence of old tradition, and their frequent celebration in the poets, are what Horace calls <foreign lang="la">nota</foreign>; just as newly invented subjects, or, which comes to the same thing, such as had not been employed by other writers, <foreign lang="la">indicta</foreign>, he, on a like occasion, terms <foreign lang="la">ignota</foreign>.  The connection lies thus. Having mentioned Silenus in <bibl n="Hor. Ars 239">v. 239</bibl>, one of the commonest characters in this drama, an objection immediately offers itself; "But what good poet will engage in subjects and characters so trite and hackneyed?" The answer is, <cit><quote lang="la">ex note fictum carmen sequar</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 240"></bibl></cit>, i. e. however trite and well known this and some other characters, essential to the Satyr, are and must be; yet will there be still room for fiction and genius to show itself. The conduct and disposition of the play may be wholly new, and above the ability of common writers, <cit><quote lang="la">tantum series iuncturaque pollet.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 242"></bibl></cit></p></note> taken from a well-known story, that any body might entertain hopes of doing the same thing; but, on trial, should sweat and labor in vain. Such power has a just arrangement and connection of the parts: such grace may be added to subjects merely common. In my judgment the Fauns, that are brought out of the woods, should not be too gamesome with their tender strains, as if they were educated in the city, and almost at the bar; nor, on the other hand, should blunder out their obscene and scandalous speeches. For [at such stuff] all are offended, who have a horse,<note anchored="yes" n="43" resp="Dac"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Quibus est equus</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 248"></bibl></cit>, etc., the knights who have a horse, kept at public expense; <cit><quote lang="la">quibus est pater,</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 248"></bibl></cit> people of birth, patricians; <cit><quote lang="la">quibus est res</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 248"></bibl></cit>, they who have wealth, and are therefore distinguished from knights and patricians.</p></note> a father, or an estate: nor will they receive with approbation, nor give the laurel crown, as the purchasers of parched peas and nuts are delighted with.</p>
<p>A long syllable put after a short one is termed an iambus, a lively measure, whence also it commanded the name of trimeters to be added to iambics, though it yielded six beats of time, being similar to itself from first to last. Not long ago, that it might come somewhat slower and with more majesty to the ear, it obligingly and contentedly admitted into its paternal heritage the steadfast spondees; agreeing however, by social league, that it was not to depart from the second<note anchored="yes" n="44" resp="Dac"><p>The iambic yields only the odd places to the spondee, the first, third, and fifth, but preserves the second, fourth, and sixth for itself. This mixture renders the verse more noble, and it may be still trimeter, the second foot being iambic. The comic poets, better to disguise their verse, and make it appear more like common conversation, inverted the tragic order, and put spondees in the even places.</p></note> and fourth place. But this [kind of measure] rarely makes its appearance in the notable<note anchored="yes" n="45" resp="TAB"><p>Ironically spoken.</p></note> trimeters of Accius, and brands the verse of Ennius brought upon the stage with a clumsy weight of spondees, with the imputation of being too precipitate and careless, or disgracefully accuses him of ignorance in his art.</p>
<p>It is not every judge that discerns inharmonious verses, and an undeserved indulgence is [in this case] granted to the Roman poets. But shall I on this account run riot and write licentiously? Or should not I rather suppose, that all the world are to see my faults; secure, and cautious [never to err] but with hope of being pardoned? Though, perhaps, I have merited no praise, I have escaped censure.</p>
<p>Ye [who are desirous to excel,] turn over the Grecian models by night, turn them by day. But our ancestors commended both the numbers of Plautus, and his strokes of pleasantry; too tamely, I will not say foolishly, admiring each of them; if you and I but know how to distinguish a coarse joke from a smart repartee, and understand the proper cadence, by [using] our fingers and ears.

<milestone ed="p" n="275" unit="card"/></p>
<p>Thespis<note anchored="yes" n="46" resp="McCaul, Wheeler"><p>Thespis. A native of Icarius, a village in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, to whom the invention of the drama has been ascribed. Before his time there were no performers except the chorus. He led the way to the formation of a dramatic plot and language, by directing a pause in the performance of the chorus, during which he came forward and recited with gesticulation a mythological story. Comp. note <bibl n="Hor. Ep. 2.1.163">Epist. ii. 1. 163</bibl>.  The date is thus given by the Par. Chron. Boeckh.: <quote lang="greek">*)Af' ou)= *Qe/spis o( poihth\s e)fa/nh, prw=tos o(\s e(di/dace dra=ma e)n a)/stei kai\ e)te/qh o( tra/gos a)=qlon e)/th *H*H*P*D*D, a)/rxontos *)Aqh/nhsie &hellip; nai/ou tou= prote/rou.</quote>  <quote lang="la">Quod ad annum attinet, consistendum sane in Olymp. 61, eiusque tribus prioribus annis.</quote> Boeckh. in Chr.</p></note> is said to have invented a new kind of tragedy, and to have carried his pieces about in carts, which [certain strollers], who had their faces besmeared with lees of wine, sang and acted. After him Aeschylus, the inventor of the vizard mask and decent robe, laid the stage over with boards of a tolerable size, and taught to speak in lofty tone, and strut in the buskin. To these succeeded the old comedy, not without considerable praise: but its personal freedom degenerated into excess and violence, worthy to be regulated by law; a law was made accordingly, and the chorus, the right of abusing being taken away, disgracefully became silent.</p>
<p>Our poets have left no species [of the art] unattempted; nor have those of them merited the least honor, who dared to forsake the footsteps of the Greeks, and celebrate domestic facts; whether they have instructed us in tragedy, or comedy.<note anchored="yes" n="47" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Vel qui praetextas, vel qui docuere togatas.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 288"></bibl></cit> There hath been much difficulty here in settling a very plain point. The question is, whether <foreign lang="la">praetextas</foreign> means tragedy or a species of comedy. The answer is very clear from Diomedes, whose account is, in short, this: "<foreign lang="la">Togatae</foreign> is a general term for all sorts of Latin plays adopting the Roman customs and dresses; as <foreign lang="la">Palliatae</foreign> is for all adopting the Grecian. Of the <foreign lang="la">Togatae</foreign>, the several species are, 1. <foreign lang="la">Praetexta</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">praetextata</foreign>, in which the Roman kings or generals were introduced, and is so called because the <foreign lang="la">praetexta</foreign> was the distinguishing habit of such persons; 2. <foreign lang="la">Tabernaria</foreign>, frequently called <foreign lang="la">Togata</foreign>, though that word, as we have seen, had properly a larger sense. 3. <foreign lang="la">Atellana</foreign>. 4. <foreign lang="la">Planipedis</foreign>."  He next marks the difference of these several sorts of the <foreign lang="la">Togatae</foreign> from the similar corresponding ones of the <foreign lang="la">Palliatae</foreign>, which are these: 1. "<foreign lang="la">Tragoedia</foreign>, absolutely so styled. 2. <foreign lang="la">Comoedia</foreign>. 3. <foreign lang="la">Satyri</foreign>.  4. <foreign lang="greek">Mi=mos</foreign>." (These four sorts of the <foreign lang="la">Palliatae</foreign> were also probably in use at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; certainly, at least, the two former.) It appears then from thence, that <foreign lang="la">praetextata</foreign> was properly the Roman tragedy. But he adds, <quote lang="la">"Togata praetextata a tragoedia differt"</quote> and it is also said, "to be only like tragedy, <quote lang="la">tragoediae similis</quote>." What is this difference and this likeness? The explanation follows. "Heroes are introduced into tragedy, such as Orestes, Chryses, and the like. In the <foreign lang="la">praetextata</foreign>, Brutus, Decius, or Marcellus." So then we see when Grecian characters were introduced, it was called simply <foreign lang="la">tragoedia</foreign>; when Roman, <foreign lang="la">praetextata</foreign>; yet both, tragedies. The sole difference lay in the persons being foreign or domestic. The correspondence in every other respect was exact. The same is observed of the Roman comedy; when it adopted Greek characters, it was called <foreign lang="la">comoedia</foreign>; when Roman, <foreign lang="la">togata tabernaria</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">togata</foreign>, simply.</p></note>  Nor would <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> be raised higher by valor and feats of arms, than by its language, did not the fatigue and tediousness of using the file disgust every one of our poets. Do you, the descendants of Pompilius, reject that poem, which many days and many a blot have not ten times subdued to the most perfect accuracy. Because Democritus believes that genius is more successful than wretched art, and excludes from Helicon all poets who are in their senses, a great number do not care to part with their nails or beard, frequent places of solitude, shun the baths. For he will acquire, [he thinks,] the esteem and title of a poet, if he neither submits his head, which is not to be cured by even three Anticyras, to Licinius the barber. What an unlucky fellow am I, who am purged for the bile in spring-time! Else nobody would compose better poems; but the purchase is not worth the expense. Therefore I will serve instead of a whetstone, which though not able of itself to cut, can make steel sharp: so I, who can write no poetry myself, will teach the duty and business [of an author]; whence he may be stocked with rich materials; what nourishes and forms the poet; what gives grace, what not; what is the tendency of excellence, what that of error.

<milestone ed="p" n="309" unit="card"/></p>
<p>To have good sense, is the first principle and fountain of writing well. The Socratic papers will direct you in the choice of your subjects; and words will spontaneously accompany the subject, when it is well conceived. He who has learned what he owes to his country, and what to his friends; with what affection a parent, a brother, and a stranger, are to be loved; what is the duty of a senator, what of a judge; what the duties of a general sent out to war; he, [I say,] certainly knows how to give suitable attributes to every character. I should direct the learned imitator to have a regard to the mode of nature and manners, and thence draw his expressions to the life.<note anchored="yes" n="48" resp="Hurd"><p>Truth, in poetry, means such an expression as conforms to the general nature of things; falsehood, that which, however suitable to the particular instance in view, doth yet not correspond to such general nature. To attain to this truth of expression in dramatic poetry two things are prescribed: 1. A diligent study of the Socratic philosophy; and, 2, A masterly knowledge and comprehension of human life. The first, because it is the peculiar distinction of this school <cit><quote lang="la">"ad veritatem vitae propius accedere."</quote> <bibl n="Cic. de Orat. 1.51">(Cic. de. Or. i. 51.)</bibl></cit> And the latter as rendering the imitation more universally striking.</p></note> Sometimes a play, that is showy with common-places,<note anchored="yes" n="49" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Interdum speciosa locis</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 319"></bibl></cit>, etc. The poet's science in ethics will principally show itself in these two ways: 1. in furnishing proper matter for general reflection on human life and conduct; and, 2, in a due adjustment of the manners. By the former of these two applications of moral knowledge a play becomes, what the poet calls, <quote lang="la">speciosa locis</quote>, i. e. (for the term is borrowed from the rhetoricians) striking in its moral topics: a merit of the highest importance on the ancient stage, and which, if prudently employed in subserviency to the latter more essential requisite of the drama, a just expression of the manners, will deserve to be so reputed at all times, and on every theater. The danger is, lest a studied, declamatory moral, affectedly introduced, or indulged to access, should prejudice the natural exhibition of the characters, and so convert the image of human life into an unaffecting, philosophical dialogue.</p>
<p><cit><quote lang="la">Moratque recta fabula</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 319"></bibl></cit>, etc. This judgment of the poet, in regard of the superior efficacy of manners, is generally thought to be contradicted by Aristotle; who, in treating this subject, observes, <cit><quote lang="en">"that let a piece be ever so perfect in the manners, sentiments, and style, it will not so well answer the end and purpose of tragedy, as if defective in these, and finished only in the fable and composition."</quote><bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1450a"></bibl></cit> M. Dacier thinks to clear this matter by saying, "that what Aristotle remarks holds true of tragedy, but not of comedy, of which alone Horace is here speaking." But granting that the artificial contexture of the fable is less necessary to the perfection of comedy than of tragedy, yet, the tenor of this whole division, exhorting to correctness in general, makes it unquestionable that Horace must intend to include both. The case, as it seems to me, is this. The poet is not comparing the respective importance of the fable and manners, but of the manners and diction, under this word including also numbers. He gives them the preference not to a good plot, nor even to fine sentiments, but to <cit><quote lang="la">versus inopes rerum nugaeque canorae</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 322"></bibl></cit>. The art he speaks of, is the art of expressing the thoughts properly, gracefully, and harmoniously: the <foreign lang="la">pondus</foreign> is the force and energy of good versification. <foreign lang="la">Venus</foreign> is a general term including both kinds of beauty.  <foreign lang="la">Fabula</foreign> does not mean the fable (in distinction from the rest), but simply a play.</p></note> and where the manners are well marked, though of no elegance, without force or art, gives the people much higher delight and more effectually commands their attention, than verse void of matter, and tuneful trifles. To the Greeks, covetous of nothing but praise, the muse gave genius; to the Greeks the power of expressing themselves in round periods. The Roman youth learn by long computation to subdivide a pound into an hundred parts. Let the son of Albinus tell me, if from five ounces one be subtracted, what remains? He would have said the third of a pound. Bravely done! you will be able to take care of your own affairs. An ounce is added: what will that be? Half a pound.</p>
<p>When this sordid rust<note anchored="yes" n="50" resp="Hurd"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Aerugo et cura peculi cum semel imbuerit</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 330"></bibl></cit>, etc. This love of gain, to which Horace imputes the imperfect state of the Roman poetry, hath been uniformly assigned, by the wisdom of ancient times, as the specific bane of arts and letters. Longinus and Quinctilian account, from hence, for the decay of eloquence, Galen of physic, Petronius of painting, and Pliny of the whole circle of the liberal arts. For being, as Longinus calls it, <foreign lang="greek">no/shma mikropoi=on</foreign>, a disease which narrows and contracts the soul, it must, of course, restrain the generous efforts and expansions of genius; cramp the free powers and energies of the mind, and render it unapt to open itself to wide views, and to the projection of great, extensive designs. It is so in its consequences. For, as one says elegantly, when the passion of avarice grows general in a country, the temples of honor are soon pulled down, and all men's sacrifices are made to fortune.</p></note> and hankering after wealth has once tainted their minds, can we expect that such verses should be made as are worthy of being anointed with the oil of cedar, and kept in the well-polished cypress?<note anchored="yes" n="51" resp="Nan"><p>To preserve their books, the ancients rubbed them with oil of cedar, and kept them in cases of cypress, because these kinds of wood were not liable to corruption.</p></note></p>
<p>Poets wish either to profit or to delight; or to deliver at once both the pleasures and the necessaries of life. Whatever precepts you give, be concise; that docile minds may soon comprehend what is said, and faithfully retain it. All superfluous instructions flow from the too full memory. Let whatever is imagined for the sake of entertainment, have as much likeness to truth as possible; let not your play demand belief for whatever [absurdities] it is inclinable [to exhibit]: nor take out of a witch's belly a living child that she had dined upon. The tribes of the seniors rail against every thing that is void of edification: the exalted knights disregard poems which are austere. He who joins the instructive with the agreeable, carries off every vote,<note anchored="yes" n="52" resp="TAB"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Omne tulit punctum.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 343"></bibl></cit> Alluding to the manner of voting at the comitia by putting a point over the name of a candidate.</p></note> by delighting and at the same time admonishing the reader. This book gains money for the Sosii; this crosses the sea, and continues to its renowned author a lasting duration.

<milestone ed="p" n="347" unit="card"/></p>
<p>Yet there are faults, which we should be ready to pardon: for neither does the string [always] form the sound which the hand and conception [of the performer] intends, but very often returns a sharp note when he demands a flat; nor will the bow always hit whatever mark it threatens. But when there is a great majority of beauties in a poem, I will not be offended with a few blemishes, which either inattention has dropped, or human nature has not sufficiently provided against. What therefore [is to be determined in this matter]? As a transcriber, if he still commits the same fault though he has been reproved, is without excuse; and the harper who always blunders on the same string, is sure to be laughed at; so he who is excessively deficient becomes another Choerilus; whom, when I find him tolerable in two or three places, I wonder at with laughter; and at the same time am I grieved whenever honest Homer grows drowsy  But it is allowable, that sleep should steal upon [the progress of] a long work.</p>
<p>As is painting, so is poetry: some pieces will strike you more if you stand near, and some, if you are at a greater distance: one loves the dark; another, which is not afraid of the critic's subtle judgment, chooses to be seen in the light; the one has pleased once the other will give pleasure if ten times repeated. 0 ye elder of the youths, though you are framed to a right judgment by your father's instructions, and are wise in yourself, yet take this truth along with you, [and] remember it; that in certain things a medium and tolerable degree of eminence may be admitted: a counselor and pleader at the bar of the middle rate is far removed from the merit of eloquent Messala, nor has so much knowledge of the law as Casselius Aulus, but yet he is in request; [but] a mediocrity in poets<note anchored="yes" n="53" resp="Hurd"><p>This judgment, however severe it may seem, is according to the practice of the best critics. We have a remarkable instance in the case of Apollonius Rhodius, who though, in the judgment of Quinctilian, the author of no contemptible poem, yet on account of that equal mediocrity which every where prevails in him, was struck out of the list of good writers by such sovereign judges of poetical merit as Aristophanes and Aristarchus. (<bibl n="Quint. 10.1">Quinct. L. x. c. 1.</bibl>)</p></note> neither gods, nor men, nor [even] the booksellers' shops have endured. As at an agreeable entertainment discordant music, and muddy perfume, and poppies mixed with Sardinian<note anchored="yes" n="54" resp="Nan"><p><placeName key="tgn,7003121">Sardinia</placeName> was full of bitter herbs, from whence the honey was bitter. White poppy seed, roasted, was mingled with honey by the ancients.</p></note> honey give offense, because the supper might have passed without them; so poetry, created and invented for the delight of our souls, if it comes short ever so little of the summit, sinks to the bottom.
</p>
<p>He who does not understand the game, abstains from the weapons of the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName>: and the unskillful in the tennis-ball, the quoit, and the troques keeps himself quiet; lest the crowded ring should raise a laugh at his expense: notwithstanding this, he who knows nothing of verses presumes to compose. Why not! He is free-born, and of a good family; above all, he is registered at an equestrian sum of moneys, and clear from every vice. You, [I am persuaded,] will neither say nor do any thing in opposition to <placeName key="tgn,2070580">Minerva</placeName>:<note anchored="yes" n="55" resp="TAB"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Invita &hellip; Minerva</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 385"></bibl></cit>. <bibl n="Cic. Off. 1.31">Cicero, de Off. i. 31</bibl>, explains this phrase: <quote lang="la">"adversante et repugnante natura."</quote> And yet the meaning here is not very evident. Does <placeName key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName> say that young <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName> will neither do nor say any thing contrary to his natural endowments; implying that he will not attempt poetry, as his abilities are inadequate? Or does he mean to compliment him on his capabilities, by saying that there is nothing which he will attempt, in which genius will not favor and assist him? The latter appears to be the correct interpretation. Thus the obvious meaning of <quote lang="la">invita <placeName key="tgn,2516788">Minerva</placeName></quote> is &mdash; Minerva refusing her assistance, or discountenancing the attempt; and the interpretation-natural endowments refusing their assistance, or marring the effort.</p></note> such is your judgment, such your disposition. But if ever you shall write any thing, let it be submitted to the ears of Metius [Tarpa], who is a judge, and your father's, and mine; and let it be suppressed till the ninth year, your papers being laid up within your own custody. You will have it in your power to blot out what you have not made public: a word once sent abroad can never return.

<milestone ed="p" n="391" unit="card"/></p>
<p>Orpheus, the priest and interpreter of the gods, deterred the savage race of men from slaughters and inhuman diet; hence said to tame tigers and furious lions: <placeName key="tgn,2132474">Amphion</placeName> too, the builder of the Theban wall, was said to give the stones motion with the sound of his lyre, and to lead them whithersoever he would, by engaging persuasion. This was deemed wisdom of yore, to distinguish the public from private weal; things sacred from things profane; to prohibit a promiscuous commerce between the sexes; to give laws to married people; to plan out cities; to engrave laws on [tables of] wood. Thus honor accrued to divine poets, and their songs. After these, excellent Homer and Tyrtaeus animated the manly mind to martial achievements with their verses. Oracles were delivered in poetry, and the economy of life pointed out, and the favor of sovereign princes was solicited by Pierian<note anchored="yes" n="56" resp="TAB"><p>i. e. strains of the muses, surnamed Pierides</p></note> strains, games were instituted, and a [cheerful] period put to the tedious labors of the day; [this I remind you of,] lest haply you should be ashamed of the lyric muse, and Apollo the god of song.</p>
<p>It has been made a question, whether good poetry be derived from nature or from art. For my part, I can neither conceive what study can do without a rich [natural] vein, nor what rude genius can avail of itself: so much does the one require the assistance of the other, and so amicably do they conspire [to produce the same effect]. He who is industrious to reach the wished-for goal, has done and suffered much when a boy; he has sweated and shivered with cold; he has abstained from love and wine; he who sings the Pythian strains,<note anchored="yes" n="57" resp="TAB"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Pythia cantica</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 414"></bibl></cit>, songs like the hymns which were sung in honor of Apollo, by the chorus in some comedies. A player, called Pythaules, played during the intervals when the chorus left off singing.</p></note> was first a learner, and in awe of a master. But [in poetry] it is now enough for a man to say of himself:&mdash; "I make admirable verses: a murrain seize the hindmost: it is scandalous for me to be outstripped, and fairly to acknowledge that I am ignorant of that which I never learned."

<milestone ed="p" n="419" unit="card"/></p>
<p>As a crier who collects the crowd together to buy his goods, so a poet rich in land, rich in money put out at interest, invites flatterers to come [and praise his works] for a reward. But if he be one who is well able to set out an elegant table,<note anchored="yes" n="58" resp="TAB"><p>But compare MCCAUL's note: "<foreign lang="la">Unctum</foreign>. A savory dish, a delicacy. Comp. note, <bibl n="Hor. Ep. 1.15.44">Epist. i. 15, 44</bibl>, and <bibl n="Hor. Ep. 1.17.12">17, 12</bibl>. Thus <cit><bibl n="Pers. 1.50">Pers. Sat. i. 50:</bibl> <quote lang="la"><lg type="hexameter"><l part="F">'Calidum scis ponere sumen,</l>
<l>Scis comitem horridulum trita donare lacerna,'</l></lg></quote></cit> etc., where <foreign lang="la">scis</foreign> is a kind of comment on <foreign lang="la">possit</foreign> here as <foreign lang="la">calidum sumen</foreign> on <foreign lang="la">unctum</foreign>. Comp. also <cit><bibl n="Pers. 6.15">Sat. vi. 15:</bibl> <quote lang="la">'aut coenare sine uncto.'</quote></cit> <placeName key="tgn,2348207">Gesner</placeName> and Doering, however, explain <foreign lang="la">unctum</foreign> as used for <foreign lang="la">convivam</foreign> (note, <bibl n="Hor. Ep. 1.17.12">Epist. i. 17, 12</bibl>), and <foreign lang="la">ponere</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">collocare</foreign>, to place at table on a couch."</p></note> and give security for a poor man, and relieve him when entangled in gloomy law-suits; I shall wonder if with his wealth he can distinguish a true friend from a false one. You, whether you have made, or intend to make, a present to any one, do not bring him full of joy directly to your finished verses: for then he will cry out, "Charming, excellent, judicious," he will turn pale; at some parts he will even distill the dew from his friendly eyes; he will jump about; he will beat the ground [with ecstasy]. As those who mourn at funerals for pay, do and say more than those
 that are afflicted from their hearts; so the sham admirer is more moved than he that praises with sincerity. Certain kings are said to ply with frequent bumpers, and by wine make trial of a man whom they are sedulous to know, whether he be worthy of their friendship or not. Thus, if you compose verses, let not the fox's concealed intentions impose upon you.</p>
<p>If you had recited any thing to Quintilius, he would say, "Alter, I pray, this and this:" if you replied, you could do it no better, having made the experiment twice or thrice in vain; he would order you to blot out, and once more apply to the anvil your ill-formed verses: if you choose rather to defend than correct a fault, he spent not a word more nor fruitless labor, but you alone might be fond of yourself and your own works, without a rival. A good and sensible man will censure spiritless verses, he will condemn the rugged, on the incorrect he will draw across a black stroke with his pen; he will lop off ambitious [and redundant] ornaments; he will make him throw light on the parts that are not perspicuous; he will arraign what is expressed ambiguously; he will mark what should be altered; [in short,] he will be an Aristarchus:<note anchored="yes" n="59" resp="Fran"><p>Aristarchus was a critic, who wrote above four score volumes of comments on the Greek poets. His criticisms on Homer were so much esteemed, that no line was thought genuine until he had acknowledged it. He was surnamed the prophet or diviner, for his sagacity.</p></note> he will not say, "Why should I give my friend offense about mere trifles?" These trifles will lead into mischiefs of serious consequence, when once made an object of ridicule, and used in a sinister manner.

<milestone ed="p" n="453" unit="card"/></p>
<p>Like one whom an odious plague or jaundice, fanatic phrensy or lunacy, distresses; those who are wise avoid a mad poet, and are afraid to touch him; the boys jostle him, and the incautious pursue him. If, like a fowler intent upon his game, he should fall into a well or a ditch while he belches out his fustian verses and roams about, though he should cry out for a long time, "Come to my assistance, 0 my countrymen;" not one would give himself the trouble of taking him up. Were any one to take pains to give him aid, and let down a rope; "How do you know, but he threw himself in hither on purpose?" I shall say: and will relate the death of the Sicilian poet. Empedocles, while he was
 ambitious of being esteemed an immortal god, in cold blood leaped into burning <placeName key="tgn,1013057">Aetna</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" n="60" resp="San"><p><cit><quote lang="la">Ardentem frigidus Aetnam insiluit.</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 465"></bibl></cit> "In cold blood, deliberately." Horace, by playing on the words <quote lang="la">ardentum frigidus</quote>, would show that he did not believe the story, and told it as one of the traditions, which poets may use without being obliged to vouch the truth of them. The pleasantry continues, when he says, it is murder to hinder a poet from killing himself; a maxim, which could not be said seriously.</p></note>  Let poets have the privilege and license to die [as they please]. He who saves a man against his will, does the same with him who kills him [against his will]. Neither is it the first time that he has behaved in this manner; nor, were he to be forced from his purposes, would he now become a man, and lay aside his de sire of such a famous death. Neither does it appear sufficiently, why he makes verses: whether he has defiled his father's ashes, or sacrilegiously removed the sad enclosure<note anchored="yes" n="61" resp="Fran"><p><cit><quote lang="la">An triste bidental</quote><bibl n="Hor. Ars 471"></bibl></cit>. What crime must that man have committed whom the gods in vengeance have possessed with a madness of writing verses? <foreign lang="la">Bidental</foreign> was a place struck with lightning, which the aruspices purified and consecrated with a sacrifice of a sheep, <foreign lang="la">bidental</foreign>. It was an act of sacrilege ever to remove the bounds of it, <foreign lang="la">movere bidental</foreign>.</p></note> of the vindictive thunder: it is evident that he is mad, and like a bear that has burst through the gates closing his den, this unmerciful rehearser chases the learned and unlearned. And whomsoever he seizes, he fastens on and assassinates with recitation: a leech that will not quit the skin, till satiated with blood.<note anchored="yes" n="62" resp="TAB"><p>In concluding the annotations on the Art of Poetry, I must beg to recommend to the reader's notice my translation of <bibl n="Aristot. Poet.">Aristotle's Poetics</bibl>, with a collection of notes, as the two treatises contribute to each other's illustration in the fullest extent.</p></note></p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
