<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
 <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="work">The Works of Horace</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Hor.">Q. Horatius Flaccus (Horace)</author>
    <editor role="transl">C. Smart</editor> &responsibility; &fund.FIPSE; </titleStmt>
   <extent>about 112Kb</extent> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>Horace</author>
      <title>The Works of Horace</title>
      <editor role="transl">C. Smart</editor>
      <editor role="revise">Theodore Alois Buckley</editor>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
       <date>1863</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>

  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
    <step refunit="book" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)"/>
    <step delim="." refunit="poem" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" n="chunk"/>
    <step refunit="line" from="DESCENDANT (1 L N %3)"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
    <state n="chunk" unit="card"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>

  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="en">English</language>
    <language id="la">Latin</language>
    <language id="greek">Greek</language>
    <language id="de">German</language>
    <language id="fr">French</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>

  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date> 7-Jun-00</date>
    <respStmt>
     <name>AEM</name>
     <resp>ed.</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <item> 
    	$Log: hor.sat_eng.xml,v $
    	Revision 1.2  2011-03-21 18:55:05  lcerrato
    	fixed aad to and

    	Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:27  rsingh04
    	moved more xml files around based on copyright status

    	Revision 1.11  2009/06/25 22:16:52  student
    	fixed bibl errors - zr

    	Revision 1.10  2009/06/24 01:26:45  student
    	fixed Ter. An. references - zr

    	Revision 1.9  2009/06/23 22:18:03  student
    	fixed Ter. Ad. references - zr

    	Revision 1.8  2009/06/22 14:10:56  student
    	fixed Pl. Per. references - zr

    	Revision 1.7  2009/02/27 19:05:12  rsingh04
    	trying to fix $log tag

  	 	Revision 1.6  2009/02/04 19:53:54  lcerrato
   		fixed bad bibls
     	Revision 1.5 2008/11/14 21:23:21 lcerrato 
     	fixed author name for consistent sorting 
     Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:21 packel 
     fixed date tags 
     Revision 1.3
     2006/02/10 20:50:23 packel 
     places/dates now actually tagged 
     Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 16:12:23 packel 
     removed stray item tags 
     Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:37:22 packel 
     Converted to XML
     Revision 1.6 2003/07/01 22:17:03 yorkc 
     Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor
     cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.) 
     Revision 1.5 2002/06/10 14:03:59 amahoney 
     mark
     one Plautine word as Latin 
     Revision 1.4 2000/09/25 21:45:18 amahoney 
     begin inserting line
     numbers 
     Revision 1.3 2000/06/13 21:37:35 amahoney 
     card breaks for the satires, continue
     proofreading 
     Revision 1.2 2000/06/12 20:45:06 amahoney 
     fix up the Greek and Latin, and make
     references explicit where the notes say "Plautus says..." or the like 
     Revision 1.1 2000/06/09 21:34:04 amahoney 
     new texts (they parse but haven't been proofread yet) </item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text lang="en">
  <body>
   <div1 type="book" n="1">
    <div2 type="poem" n="1">
     <head>That all, but especially the covetous, think their own condition the hardest.</head>

     <p>How comes it to pass, Maecenas, that no one lives content with his condition, whether reason
      gave it him, or chance threw it in his way; [but] praises those who follow different pursuits?
      "O happy merchants!" says the soldier, oppressed with years, <milestone ed="p" n="5"
       unit="line"/>and now broken down in his limbs through excess of labor. On the other side, the
      merchant, when the south winds toss his ship [cries], "Warfare is preferable;" for why? the
      engagement is begun, and in an instant there comes a speedy death or a joyful victory. The
      lawyer praises the farmer's state <milestone ed="p" n="10" unit="line"/>when the client knocks
      at his door by cockcrow. He who, having entered into a recognizance,<note anchored="yes" n="1"
       resp="McCaul">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Datis vadibus.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.1.11"/>
        </cit> In some suit, the farmer had given bail for his attendance on the day appointed for
        the trial. The persons who had bound themselves as bail for his appearance, are called
         <foreign lang="la">vades</foreign>. The derivation of the word is supposed to be <foreign
         lang="la">vadere</foreign>, "to go," because the person who procures such persons to answer
        for his appearance, is allowed to go until the day of the trial.</p>
      </note> is dragged, from the country into the city, cries, "Those only are happy who live in
      the city." The other instances of this kind (they are so numerous) would weary out the
      loquacious Fabius;<note anchored="yes" n="2" resp="McCaul">
       <p>It is not known to whom Horace alludes. The Scholiast informs us that there was a knight
        of this name, a partisan of Pompey's, who had written some treatises on the doctrines of the
        Stoics, and who, he says, argued sometimes with Horace for the truth of the principles of
        that sect.</p>
      </note> not to keep you in suspense, hear to what an issue I will bring the matter. <milestone
       ed="p" n="15" unit="line"/>If any god should say, "Lo! I will effect what you desire: you,
      that were just now a soldier, shall be a merchant; you, lately a lawyer [shall be] a farmer.
      Do ye depart one way, and ye another, having exchanged the parts you are to act in life. How
      now! Why do you stand?" They are unwilling; and yet it is in their power to be happy.
       <milestone ed="p" n="20" unit="line"/>What reason can be assigned, but that <placeName
       key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName> should deservedly distend both his cheeks in
      indignation, and declare that for the future he will not be so indulgent as to lend an ear to
      their prayers? But further, that I may not run over this in a laughing manner, like those [who
      treat] on ludicrous subjects (though what hinders one being merry, while telling the truth?
       <milestone ed="p" n="25" unit="line"/>as good-natured teachers at first give cakes to their
      boys, that they may be willing to learn their first rudiments: raillery, however, apart, let
      us investigate serious matters) lie that turns the heavy glebe with the hard plowshare, this
      fraudulent tavern-keeper,<note anchored="yes" n="3" resp="Orelli">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Hic</foreign> = <foreign lang="la">cuiusmodi quotidie vides.</foreign>
        See the other commentators.</p>
      </note> the soldier, and the sailors, <milestone ed="p" n="30" unit="line"/>who dauntless run
      through every sea, profess that they endure toil with this intention, that as old men they may
      retire into a secure resting-place, when once they have gotten together a sufficient
      provision.</p>
     <p>Thus the little ant (for she is an example), of great industry, carries in her mouth
      whatever she is able, and adds to the heap which she piles up, <milestone ed="p" n="35"
       unit="line"/>by no means ignorant and not careless for the future. Which [ant, nevertheless],
      as soon as Aquarius saddens the changed year, never creeps abroad, but wisely makes use of
      those stores which were provided beforehand: while neither sultry summer, nor winter, fire,
      ocean, sword, can drive you from gain. <milestone ed="p" n="40" unit="line"/>You surmount
      every obstacle, that no other man may be richer than yourself. What pleasure is it for you,
      trembling to deposit an immense weight of silver and gold in the earth dug up by stealth?<note
       anchored="yes" n="4" resp="TAB">
       <p>i. e. to hide it.</p>
      </note> Because, if you should lessen it, it may be reduced to a paltry farthing.</p>
     <p>But unless that be the case, what beauty has an accumulated hoard? <milestone ed="p" n="45"
       unit="line"/>Though your thrashing-floor should yield<note anchored="yes" n="5" resp="McCaul">
       <p>Literally, "wear," "rub." There is an ellipse of <foreign lang="la">si</foreign>, as in
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.1.3">Sat. i. 3</bibl>; <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.4.292">ii. 4, 292</bibl>;
         <bibl n="Verg. A. 6.31">Virg. Aen. vi. 31</bibl></p>
      </note> a hundred thousand bushels of corn, your belly will not on that account contain more
      than mine: just as if it were your lot to carry on your loaded shoulder the basket of bread
      among slaves, you would receive no more [for your own share] than he who bore no part of the
      burthen. Or tell me, what is it to the purpose of that man, who lives within the compass of
      nature, <milestone ed="p" n="50" unit="line"/>whether he plow a hundred or a thousand acres?
      "But it is still delightful to take out of a great hoard."</p>
     <p>While you leave us to take as much out of a moderate store why should you extol your
      granaries, more than our cornbaskets? As if you had occasion for no more than a pitcher or
      glass of water, and should say, "I had rather draw [so much] from a great river, than the very
      same quantity from this little fountain." Hence it comes to pass, that the rapid <placeName
       key="tgn,1128017">Aufidus</placeName> carries away, together with the bank, such men as an
      abundance more copious than what is just delights. But he who desires only so much as is
      sufficient, <milestone ed="p" n="60" unit="line"/>neither drinks water fouled with the mud,
      nor loses his life in the waves. <milestone ed="p" n="61" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>But a great majority of mankind, misled by a wrong desire, cry, "No sum is enough; because
      you are esteemed in proportion to what you possess." What can one do to such a tribe as this?
      Why, bid them be wretched, since their inclination prompts them to it. As a certain person is
      recorded [to have lived] at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, <milestone
       ed="p" n="65" unit="line"/>covetous and rich, who was wont to despise the talk of the people
      in this manner: "The crowd hiss me; but I applaud myself at home, as soon as I contemplate my
      money in my chest." The thirsty Tantalus catches at the streams, which elude his lips. Why do
      you laugh? The name changed, the tale is told of you. <milestone ed="p" n="70" unit="line"
      />You sleep upon your bags, heaped up on every side, gaping over them, and are obliged to
      abstain from them, as if they were consecrated things, or to amuse yourself with them as you
      would with pictures. Are you ignorant of what value money has, what use it can afford? Bread,
      herbs, a bottle of wine may be purchased; to which [necessaries], <milestone ed="p" n="75"
       unit="line"/>add [such others], as, being withheld, human nature would be uneasy with itself.
      What, to watch half dead with terror, night and day, to dread profligate thieves, fire, and
      your slaves, lest they should run away and plunder you; is this delightful? I should always
      wish to be very poor in possessions held upon these terms.</p>
     <p><milestone ed="p" n="80" unit="line"/>But if your body should be disordered by being seized
      with a cold, or any other casualty should confine you to your bed, have you one that will
      abide by you, prepare medicines, entreat the physician that he would set you upon your feet,
      and restore you to your children and dear relations?</p>
     <p>Neither your wife, nor your son, desires your recovery; <milestone ed="p" n="85" unit="line"
      />all your neighbors, acquaintances, [nay the very] boys and girls hate you. Do you wonder
      that no one tenders you the affection which you do not merit, since you prefer your money to
      every thing else? If you think to retain, and preserve as friends, the relations which nature
      gives you, without taking any pains; <milestone ed="p" n="90" unit="line"/>wretch that you
      are, you lose your labor equally, as if any one should train an ass to be obedient to the
      rein, and run in the Campus [Martius]. Finally, let there be some end to your search; and, as
      your riches increase, be in less dread of poverty; and begin to cease from your toil, that
      being acquired which you coveted: <milestone ed="p" n="95" unit="line"/>nor do as did one
      Umidius (it is no tedious story), who was so rich that he measured his money, so sordid that
      he never clothed himself any better than a slave; and, even to his last moments, was in dread
      lest want of bread should oppress him: but his freed-woman, <milestone ed="p" n="100"
       unit="line"/>the bravest of all the daughters of Tyndarus,<note anchored="yes" n="6"
       resp="Watson">
       <p>As if she had been another Clytemnestra, the daughter of Tyndarus, who cut off her
        husband's head with an ax. <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Fortissima Tyndaridarum</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.1.100"/>
        </cit>, from the accusative of <foreign lang="la">Tyndaris</foreign>, viz. <foreign
         lang="la">Tyndarida</foreign>, comes the noun <foreign lang="la">Tyndarida</foreign>,
         <foreign lang="la">Tyndaridae</foreign> etc.</p>
      </note> cut him in two with a hatchet. "What therefore do you persuade me to? That I should
      lead the life of Naevius, or in such a manner as a Nomentanus?"</p>
     <p>You are going [now] to make things tally, that are contradictory in their natures.<note
       anchored="yes" n="7" resp="McCaul">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Pugnantia frontibus adversis</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.1.103"/>
        </cit> means what we express by "diametrically opposite." The allusion in <foreign lang="la"
         >frontibus adversis</foreign> is to a fight between bulls or rams, who butt each other with
        their heads. </p>
      </note> When I bid you not be a miser, I do not order you to become a debauchee or a prodigal.</p>
     <p><milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="line"/>There is some difference between the case of
       <placeName key="tgn,1123466">Tanais</placeName> and his son-in-law Visellius: there is a mean
      in things; finally, there are certain boundaries, on either side of which moral rectitude can
      not exist. I return now whence I digressed. Does no one, after the miser's example, like his
      own station, but rather praise those who have different pursuits; <milestone ed="p" n="110"
       unit="line"/>and pines, because his neighbor's she-goat bears a more distended udder; nor
      considers himself in relation to the greater multitude of poor; but labors to surpass, first
      one, and then another? Thus the richer man is always an obstacle to one that is hastening [to
      be rich]: <milestone ed="p" n="115" unit="line"/>as when the courser whirls along the chariot,
      dismissed from the place of starting; the charioteer presses upon those horses which outstrip
      his own, despising him that is left behind coming on among the last. Hence it is, that we
      rarely find a man who can say he has lived happy, and content with his past life, can retire
      from the world like a satisfied guest.<note anchored="yes" n="8" resp="TAB">
       <p>Cf. <cit>
         <bibl n="Lucr. 3.951">Lucret. iii. 951,</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">Cur non, ut plenus vitae conviva recedis?</quote>
        </cit> See Orelli. </p>
      </note>
      <milestone ed="p" n="120" unit="line"/>Enough for the present: nor will I add one word more,
      lest you should suspect that I have plundered the escrutoire of the blear-eyed Crispinus. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="2">
     <head>Bad men, when they avoid certain vices, fall into their opposite extremes.</head>

     <p>The tribes of female flute-players,<note anchored="yes" n="9" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ambubaiarum</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.2.1"/>
        </cit>, "Women who played on the flute." It is derived from a Syrian word; for the people of
        that country usually excelled in this instrument. <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Pharmacopolae</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.2.1"/>
        </cit> is a general name for all who deal in spices, essence, and perfumes.</p>
      </note> quacks, vagrants, mimics, blackguards;<note anchored="yes" n="10" resp="Torr,San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Mendici, mimae, balatrones</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.2.2"/>
        </cit>. The priests of Isis and Cybele were beggars by profession, and under the vail of
        religion were often guilty of the most criminal excesses. <foreign lang="la">Mimae</foreign>
        were players of the most debauched and dissolute kind; and <foreign lang="la"
        >balatrones</foreign>, in general, signifies all scoundrels, buffoons, and parasites, who
        had their name, according to the old commentator, from Servilius Balatro. <quote lang="la"
         >Balatrones hoc genus omne</quote>, for <foreign lang="la">omne hoc balatronum
        genus</foreign>, is a remarkable sort of construction.</p>
      </note> all this set is sorrowful and dejected on account of the death of the singer
      Tigellius; for he was liberal [toward them]. On the other hand, this man, dreading to be
      called a spendthrift, will not give a poor friend <milestone ed="p" n="5" unit="line"
      />wherewithal to keep off cold and pinching hunger. If you ask him why he wickedly consumes
      the noble estate of his grandfather and father in tasteless gluttony, buying with borrowed
      money all sorts of dainties; he answers, <milestone ed="p" n="10" unit="line"/>because he is
      unwilling to be reckoned sordid, or of a mean spirit: he is praised by some, condemned by
      others. Fufidius, wealthy in lands, wealthy in money put out at interest, is afraid of having
      the character of a rake and spendthrift. This fellow deducts 5 per cent. interest<note
       anchored="yes" n="11" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Quinas hic capiti mercedes exsecat</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.2.14"/>
        </cit>. <foreign lang="la">Caput</foreign> is the principal; <foreign lang="la"
        >merces</foreign> the interest; and <foreign lang="la">exsecare</foreign> is to deduct the
        interest before the money is lent. For instance, Fufidius lent a hundred pounds, and at the
        end of the month the borrower was to pay him a hundred and five, principal and interest. But
        he gives only ninety-five pounds, deducting his interest when he lends the money, which thus
        increases in twenty months equal to his principal. The laws allowed a usury called <foreign
         lang="la">usura centesima</foreign>, which doubled the capital sum in a hundred months, or
        eight years and four months.</p>
      </note> from the principal [at the time of lending]; <milestone ed="p" n="15" unit="line"
      />and, the more desperate in his circumstances any one is, the more severely he pinches him:
      he hunts out the names<note anchored="yes" n="12" resp="Cruq">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Nomina sectatur</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.2.16"/>
        </cit>. <foreign lang="la">Nomen</foreign> signifies a debt, because the borrower gave the
        lender a note of acknowledgment for the money, signed with his name. The laws forbade
        lending money to minors, or persons under the age of twenty-five years.</p>
      </note> of young fellows that have just put on the toga virilis under rigid fathers. Who does
      not cry out, O sovereign <placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName>! when he has heard
      [of such knavery]? But [you will say, perhaps,] this man expends upon himself in proportion to
      his gain. You can hardly believe <milestone ed="p" n="20" unit="line"/>how little a friend he
      is to himself: insomuch that the father, whom Terence's comedy introduces as living miserable
      after he had caused his son to run away from him, did not torment himself worse than he Now if
      any one should ask, "To what does this matter tend?" To this: while fools shun [one sort of]
      vices, they fall upon their opposite extremes. <milestone ed="p" n="25" unit="line"/>Malthinus
      walks with his garments trailing upon the ground; there is another droll fellow who [goes]
      with them tucked up even to his middle; Rufillus smells like perfume itself, Gorgonius like a
      he-goat. There is no mean. There are some who would not keep company with a lady, unless her
      modest garment perfectly conceal her feet. <milestone ed="p" n="30" unit="line"/>Another,
      again, will only have such as take their station in a filthy brothel. When a certain noted
      spark came out of a stew, the divine Cato [greeted] him with this sentence: "Proceed (says he)
      in your virtuous course. For, when once foul lust has inflamed the veins, it is right for
      young fellows to come hither, in comparison of their meddling with other men's wives."
       <milestone ed="p" n="35" unit="line"/>I should not be willing to be commended on such terms,
      says Cupiennius, an admirer of the silken vail.</p>
     <p>Ye, that do not wish well to the proceedings of adulterers, it is worth your while to hear
      how they are hampered on all sides; <milestone ed="p" n="40" unit="line"/>and that their
      pleasure, which happens to them but seldom, is interrupted with a great deal of pain, and
      often in the midst of very great dangers. One has thrown himself long from the top of a house;
      another has been whipped almost to death: a third, in his flight, has fallen into a merciless
      gang of thieves: another has paid a fine, [to avoid] corporal [punishment]: the lowest
      servants have treated another with the vilest indignities. <milestone ed="p" n="45"
       unit="line"/>Moreover, this misfortune happened to a certain person, he entirely lost his
      manhood. Every body said, it was with justice: Galba denied it.</p>
     <p>But how much safer is the traffic among [women] of the second rate! I mean the freed-women:
      after which Sallustius is not less mad, than he who commits adultery. <milestone ed="p" n="50"
       unit="line"/>But if he had a mind to be good and generous, as far as his estate and reason
      would direct him, and as far as a man might be liberal with moderation; he would give a
      sufficiency, not what would bring upon himself ruin and infamy. However, he hugs himself in
      this one [consideration]; this he delights in, this he extols: "I meddle with no matron."
       <milestone ed="p" n="55" unit="line"/>Just as Marsaeus, the lover of Origo<note
       anchored="yes" n="13" resp="Watson">
       <p>Origo. There lived in Horace's time three famous courtesans at <placeName
         key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; Origo, Cytheris, and Arbuscala, all comedians. The
        poet was probably acquainted with them all. We are at a loss to know who Marsaeus was.</p>
      </note> he who gives his paternal estate and seat to an actress, says, "I never meddle with
      other men's wives." But you have with actresses, you have with common strumpets: whence your
      reputation derives a greater perdition, than your estate. <milestone ed="p" n="60" unit="line"
      />What, is it abundantly sufficient to avoid the person, and not the [vice] which is
      universally noxious? To lose one's good name, to squander a father's effects, is in all cases
      an evil. What is the difference, [then, with regard to yourself,] whether you sin with the
      person of a matron, a maiden, or a prostitute?<note anchored="yes" n="14" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Togata</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.2.63"/>
        </cit>. A prostitute. Women of this kind were obliged, when they went abroad, to wear a
        robe, called toga. The resemblance of it to the robe worn by men, made it a mark of
       infamy.</p>
      </note>
      <milestone ed="p" n="64" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Villius, the son-in-law of Sylla <milestone ed="p" n="65" unit="line"/>(by this title alone
      he was misled), suffered [for his commerce] with Fausta an adequate and more than adequate
      punishment, by being drubbed and stabbed, while he was shut out, that Longarenus might enjoy
      her within. Suppose this [young man's] mind had addressed him in the words of his appetite,
      perceiving such evil consequences: "What would you have? <milestone ed="p" n="70" unit="line"
      />Did I ever, when, my ardor was at the highest, demand a woman descended from a great consul,
      and covered with robes of quality?" What could he answer? Why, "the girl was sprung from an
      illustrious father." But how much better things, and how different from this, does nature,
      abounding in stores of her own, recommend; <milestone ed="p" n="75" unit="line"/>if you would
      only make a proper use of them, and not confound what is to be avoided with that which is
      desirable! Do you think it is of no consequence, whether your distresses arise from your own
      fault or from [a real deficiency] of things? Wherefore, that you may not repent [when it is
      too late], put a stop to your pursuit after matrons; whence more trouble is derived, than you
      can obtain of enjoyment from success. <milestone ed="p" n="80" unit="line"/>Nor has [this
      particular matron], amid her pearls and emeralds, a softer thigh, or limbs more delicate than
      yours, Cerinthus; nay, the prostitutes are frequently preferable. Add to this, that [the
      prostitute] bears about her merchandize without any varnish, and openly shows what she has to
      dispose of; nor, if she has aught more comely than ordinary, <milestone ed="p" n="85"
       unit="line"/>does she boast and make an ostentation of it, while she is industrious to
      conceal that which is offensive. This is the custom with men of fortune: when they buy horses,
      thy inspect them covered: that, if a beautiful forehand (as often) be supported by a tender
      hoof, it may not take in the buyer, eager for the bargain, because the back is handsome, the
      head little, and the neck stately. <milestone ed="p" n="90" unit="line"/>This they do
      judiciously. Do not you, [therefore, in the same manner] contemplate the perfections of each
      [fair one's] person with the eyes of Lynceus; but be blinder than Hypsaea, when you survey
      such parts as are deformed. [You may cry out,] "0 what a leg! O, what delicate arms!" But [you
      suppress] that she is low-hipped, short-waisted, with a long nose, and a splay foot. A man can
      see nothing but the face of a matron, <milestone ed="p" n="95" unit="line"/>who carefully
      conceals her other charms, unless it be a Catia. But if you will seek after forbidden charms
      (for the [circumstance of their being forbidden] makes you mad after them), surrounded as they
      are with a fortification, many obstacles will then be in your way: such as guardians, the
      sedan, dressers, parasites, the long robe hanging down to the ankles, and covered with an
      upper garment; <milestone ed="p" n="100" unit="line"/>a multiplicity of circumstances, which
      will hinder you from having a fair view. The other throws no obstacle in your way; through the
      silken vest you may discern her, almost as well as if she was naked; that she has neither a
      bad leg, nor a disagreeable foot, you may survey her form perfectly with your eye. Or would
      you choose to have a trick put upon you, and your money extorted, before the goods are shown
      you? <milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="line"/>[But perhaps you will sing to me these verses out
      of Callimachus.] As the huntsman pursues the hare in the deep snow, but disdains to touch it
      when it is placed before him: thus sings the rake, and applies it to himself; my love is like
      to this, for it passes over an easy prey, and pursues what flies from it. <milestone ed="p"
       n="110" unit="line"/>Do you hope that grief, and uneasiness, and bitter anxieties, will be
      expelled from your breast by such verses as these? Would it not be more profitable to inquire
      what boundary nature has affixed to the appetites, what she can patiently do without, and what
      she would lament the deprivation of, and to separate what is solid from what is vain? What!
      when thirst parches your jaws, are you solicitous for golden cups to drink out of? <milestone
       ed="p" n="115" unit="line"/>What! when you are hungry, do you despise every thing but peacock
      and turbot? When your passions are inflamed, and a common gratification is at hand, would you
      rather be consumed with desire than possess it? I would not: for I love such pleasures as are
      of easiest attainment. <milestone ed="p" n="120" unit="line"/>But she whose language is, "By
      and by," "But for a small matter more," "If my husband should be out of the way," [is only]
      for petitmaitres: and for himself, Philodemus says, he chooses her, who neither stands for a
      great price, nor delays to come when she is ordered. Let her be fair, and straight, and so far
      decent as not to appear desirous of seeming fairer than nature has made her. <milestone ed="p"
       n="125" unit="line"/>When I am in the company of such an one, she is my <placeName
       key="tgn,5001986">Ilia</placeName> and Aegeria; I give her any name. Nor am I apprehensive,
      while I am in her company, lest her husband should return from the country; the door should be
      broken open; the dog should bark; the house, shaken, should resound on all sides with a great
      noise; <milestone ed="p" n="130" unit="line"/>the woman, pale [with fear] should bound away
      from me; lest the maid, conscious [of guilt], should cry out, she is undone; lest she should
      be in apprehension for her limbs, the detected wife for her portion, I for myself; lest I must
      run away with my clothes all loose, and bare-footed, for fear my money, or my person, or,
      finally my character should be demolished. It is a dreadful thing to be caught: I could prove
      this, even if Fabius were the judge. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="3">
     <head>We ought to connive at the faults of our friends, and all offenses are not to be ranked
      in the catalogue of crimes.</head>

     <p>THIS is a fault common to all singers, that among their friends they never are inclined to
      sing when they are asked, [but] unasked, they never desist. Tigellius, that Sardinian, had
      this [fault]. Had Caesar, who could have forced him to compliance, besought him on account of
      his father's friendship and his own, he would have had no success; if he himself was disposed,
      he would chant Io Bacche over and over, from the beginning of an entertainment to the very
      conclusion of it;<note anchored="yes" n="15" resp="TAB">
       <p>Literally, "from the egg to the apples," for eggs were served first, and fruit last.</p>
      </note> one while at the deepest pitch of his voice, at another time with that which answers
      to the highest string of the tetrachord.<note anchored="yes" n="16" resp="McCaul">
       <p>The four strings of this instrument were called by the Greeks <foreign lang="greek"
         >u(pa/th</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">subsuma</foreign>), <foreign lang="greek"
        >parupa/th</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">subsuma</foreign>), <foreign lang="greek"
        >paranh/th</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">pene ima</foreign>), and <foreign lang="greek"
         >nh/th</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">ima</foreign>). Thus the <foreign lang="la">summa
        vox</foreign>, which answers to the highest string, <foreign lang="la">summa
        chorda</foreign>, must signify the bass, and <foreign lang="la">ima vox</foreign>, that
        strikes the same tone with <foreign lang="la">ima chorda</foreign>, must signify the treble.
         <foreign lang="la">Summa</foreign> should be joined with <foreign lang="la"
        >chorda</foreign>, not <foreign lang="la">voce</foreign>.</p>
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Citaret</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.7"/>
        </cit>. <placeName key="tgn,7010699">Bentley</placeName> remarks that this is a forensic
        word, and can not be put for <foreign lang="la">recitaret</foreign>, besides that <foreign
         lang="la">citare Io Bacche</foreign> is not Latin. He reads <foreign lang="la"
        >iteraret</foreign>. The Librarians wrote <hi>ter</hi>, <hi>cer</hi>, and <hi>ler</hi>, in a
        compendious form thus ~ over its natural place, thus the word &Icirc;TARET, with a
        circumflex over I, and hence <foreign lang="la">CITARET</foreign>.</p>
      </note> There was nothing uniform in that fellow; frequently would he run along, as one flying
      from an enemy; more frequently [he walked], as if he bore [in procession] the sacrifice of
       Juno:<note anchored="yes" n="17" resp="Torr">
       <p>This grave and solemn march, although a religious ceremony in its place, yet, when
        improperly used, is affectation and impertinence. The solemnity of this procession became a
        proverb, <foreign lang="greek">*(Hrai=on badi/zein</foreign>, to walk like Juno.</p>
      </note> he had often two hundred slaves, often but ten: one while talking of kings and
      potentates, every thing that was magnificent; at another &mdash; "Let me have a
      three-legged table, and a cellar of clean salt, and a gown which, though coarse, may be
      sufficient to keep out the cold." Had you given ten hundred thousand sesterces<note
       anchored="yes" n="18" resp="Watson">
       <p>The sestertium among the Romans was about 7l. 16s. of our money, and contained a thousand
        sestertii. Their manner of reckoning was this: when a numeral noun agreed in gender and
        number with <foreign lang="la">sestertius</foreign>, it denoted precisely so many sestertii,
        as <foreign lang="la">decem sestertii</foreign>, just so many; but if the noun was joined to
        the genitive plural of sestertius, it signified so many thousands; as <foreign lang="la"
         >decem sestertium</foreign>, ten thousand sestertii. If the adverb numeral was joined to
        the genitive plural, it denoted so many hundred thousand, as <foreign lang="la">decies
         sestertium</foreign>, ten hundred thousand sestertii. Sometimes they put the adverb by
        itself, and sometimes added the numeral noun to it; as in this place <cit>
         <quote lang="la">decies centena</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.15"/>
        </cit>, ten hundred sestertia, or ten hundred thousand sestertii. WATSON.</p>
      </note> to this moderate man who was content with such small matters, in five days' time there
      would be nothing in his bags. He sat up at nights, [even] to day-light; he snored out all the
      day. Never was there any thing so inconsistent with itself. Now some person may say to me,
      "What are you? Have you no faults?" Yes, others; but others, and perhaps of a less culpable
      nature.</p>
     <p>When Maenius railed at Novius in his absence: "Hark ye," says a certain person, "are you
      ignorant of yourself? or do you think to impose yourself upon us a person we do not know?" "As
      for me, I forgive myself," quoth Maenius. This is a foolish and impious self-love, and worthy
      to be stigmatized. When you look over your own vices, winking at them, as it were, with sore
      eyes; why are you with regard to those of your friends as sharp-sighted as an eagle, or the
      Epidaurian serpent? But, on the other hand, it is your lot that your friends should inquire
      into your vices in turn. [A certain person] is a little too hasty in his temper; not well
      calculated for the sharp-witted sneers<note anchored="yes" n="19" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Acutis naribus</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.29"/>
        </cit>, is the direct opposition to <foreign lang="la">naribus obesis</foreign>, which the
        Latins used to signify a stupid person, who wants the natural quickness and sharpness of the
        senses.</p>
      </note> of these men: he may be made a jest of because his gown hangs awkwardly, he [at the
      same time] being trimmed in a very rustic manner, and his wide shoe hardly sticks to his foot.
      But he is so good, that no man can be better; but he is your friend: but an immense genius is
      concealed under this unpolished person of his. Finally, sift yourself thoroughly, whether
      nature has originally sown the seeds of any vice in you, or even an ill habit [has done it].
      For the fern, fit [only] to be burned, overruns the neglected fields. <milestone ed="p" n="38"
       unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Let us return from our digression. As his mistress's disagreeable failings escape the
      blinded lover, or even give him pleasure (as Hagna's wen does to Balbinus), I could wish that
      we erred in this manner with regard to friendship, and that virtue had affixed a reputable
      appellation to such an error. And as a father ought not to contemn his son, if he has any
      defect, in the same manner we ought not [to contemn] our friend. The father calls his
      squinting boy, a pretty leering rogue; and if any man has a little despicable brat, such as
      the abortive Sisyphus<note anchored="yes" n="20" resp="Watson">
       <p>Sisyphus. The dwarf of Mark Antony the triumvir. He was of a diminutive stature, scarcely
        two feet high, but of a very acute wit; whence he got the name of Sisyphus; for Sisyphus was
        so remarkable for his dexterity and cunning, that <foreign lang="la">Sisyphi artes</foreign>
        came to be a proverb.</p>
      </note> formerly was, he calls it a sweet moppet: this [child] with distorted legs, [the
      father] in a fondling voice calls one of the Vari; and another, who is club-footed, he calls a
       Scaurus.<note anchored="yes" n="21" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Balbutit Scaurum</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.48"/>
        </cit>. Rutgersius informs us that all these names, Strabo, Paetus, Pullus, Varus, and
        Scaurus, are surnames of illustrious Roman families, from whence fathers gave them to their
        children, to cover their defornlties with names of dignity. This is one of many beauties in
        the original, which it is impossible to preserve in a translation.</p>
      </note> [Thus, does] this friend of yours live more sparingly than ordinarily? Let him be
      styled a man of frugality. Is another impertinent, and apt to brag a little? He requires to be
      reckoned entertaining to his friends. But [another] is too rude, and takes greater liberties
      than are fitting. Let him be esteemed a man of sincerity and bravery. Is he too fiery, let him
      be numbered among persons of spirit.</p>
     <p>This method, in my opinion, both unites friends, and preserves them in a state of union. But
      we invert the very virtues themselves, and are desirous of throwing dirt upon the untainted
      vessel. Does a man of probity live among us? he is a person of singular diffidence;<note
       anchored="yes" n="22" resp="TAB">
       <p>But Orelli interprets <foreign lang="la">demissus</foreign> to mean <foreign lang="la"
         >abjectus, pusilli animi.</foreign> See his judicious note.</p>
      </note> we give him the name of a dull and fat-headed fellow. Does this man avoid every snare,
      and lay himself open to no ill-designing villain; since we live amid such a race, where keen
      envy and accusations are flourishing? Instead of a sensible and wary man, we call him a
      disguised and subtle fellow. And is any one more open, [and less reserved] than usual in such
      a degree as I often have presented myself to you, Maecenas, so as perhaps impertinently to
      interrupt a person reading, or musing, with any kind of prate? We cry, "[this fellow] actually
      wants common sense."<note anchored="yes" n="23" resp="Bent">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Communi sensu plane caret</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.66"/>
        </cit>. He wants an understanding that distinguishes the common decencies to be observed in
        addressing the great. Such was the <foreign lang="la">Communis sensus</foreign> among the
        Romans, for which we have no expression in English. <quote lang="la">Sit in beneficio sensus
         communis: tempus, locum, personas observer</quote>. <placeName key="tgn,2652379"
        >Seneca</placeName>. <quote lang="la">Quae versantur in consuetudine rei publicae; in sensu
         hominum communi, in natura, in moribus, comprehendenda esse oratori puto</quote>.
         <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> de Oratore. Lord Shaftesbury explains the
         <foreign lang="la">sensus communis</foreign> in Juvenal, that sense which regards the
        common good, the public welfare. A sense, according to the ingenious author, seldom found
        among the great. <quote lang="la">Raro enim ferme sensus communis in illa &verbar;
         Fortuna</quote>.</p>
      </note> Alas! how indiscreetly do we ordain a severe law against ourselves! For no one is born
      without vices: he is the best man who is encumbered with the least. When my dear friend, as is
      just, weighs my good qualities against my bad ones, let him, if he is willing to be beloved,
      turn the scale to the majority of the former (if I have indeed a majority of good qualities),
      on this condition, he shall be placed in the same balance. He who requires that his friend
      should not take offense at his own protuberances, will excuse his friend's little warts. It is
      fair that he who entreats a pardon for his own fault, should grant one in his turn. <milestone
       ed="p" n="76" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Upon the whole,<note anchored="yes" n="24" resp="Fran">
       <p>The second part of the satire begins here. The Stoics called all vicious people fools,
         <foreign lang="la">stultos</foreign>. <foreign lang="la">Quatenus</foreign> is frequently
        used by our poet for <foreign lang="la">quoniam</foreign>, since that.</p>
      </note> forasmuch as the vice anger, as well as others inherent in foolish [mortals], can not
      be totally eradicated, why does not human reason make use of its own weights and measures; and
      so punish faults, as the nature of the thing demands? If any man should punish with the cross
      a slave, who being ordered to take away the dish should gorge the half-eaten fish and warm
       sauce;<note anchored="yes" n="25" resp="Cruq">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Tepidumque ligurrierit ius</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.81"/>
        </cit>. <placeName key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName>, to excuse the slave, says, that the
        sauce was yet warm, tepidum, and therefore more tempting. For the same reason, he says, the
        fish was half eaten.</p>
      </note> he would, among people in their senses, be called a madder man than Labeo.<note
       anchored="yes" n="26" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Labeone insanior</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.82"/>
        </cit>. The Scholiasts, commentators, and interpreters tell us, that <placeName
         key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName> means Marcus Antistius Labeo, who, in the spirit of
        liberty, frequently opposed Augustus in the senate, when he attempted any alterations in the
        state. <quote lang="la">Agitabat eum libertas nimia et vecors</quote>, says <placeName
         key="tgn,1002882">Seneca</placeName>; which might justly render him odious to Augustus. But
        whatever respect our poet had for his emperor, yet we never find that he treats the patrons
        of liberty with outrage. Nor can we well imagine that he dare thus cruelly brand a man of
        Labeo's abilities, riches, power, and employments in the state; to whom Augustus himself
        offered the consulship. Probably the person here intended was publicly known to have been
        guilty of some folly not unlike what our poet mentions. Dr. Bentley hath found a Labienus in
        the time of Augustus, whose character fits this passage extremely well; and whom he
        therefore recommends to a place in the text.</p>
      </note> How much more irrational and heinous a crime is this! Your friend has been guilty of a
      small error (which, unless you forgive, you ought to be reckoned a sour, ill-natured fellow),
      you hate and avoid him, as a debtor does <placeName key="tgn,2077983">Ruso</placeName>;<note
       anchored="yes" n="27" resp="McCaul">
       <p>The alternative with <placeName key="tgn,2077983">Ruso</placeName> was either ruin from
        extortion, or misery from listening to his writings. If his wretched creditors could not pay
        him, then they were condemned to hear him read his works. Perhaps some might prefer
        considering <foreign lang="la">historias</foreign> used in the sense of "tedious narration,"
        and refer it to the long schedule of the items in his account. <foreign lang="la"
        >Audit</foreign>. Asinius Pollio first introduced the custom of reciting one's own
        compositions at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>.</p>
      </note> who, when the woeful calends come upon the unfortunate man, unless he lrocures the
      interest or capital by hook or by crook, is compelled to hear his miserable stories with his
      neck stretched out like a slave. [Should my friend] in his liquor water my couch, or has he
      thrown down a jar carved by the hands of <placeName key="tgn,2319904"
       >Evander</placeName>:<note anchored="yes" n="28" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Evandri manibus tritum</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S.1.3.91"/>
        </cit>. &mdash; <foreign lang="la">Tornatum, caelatum, fabricatum</foreign>. <quote
         lang="la">Hinc radios trivere rotis</quote>, <placeName key="tgn,1015191"
        >Virgil</placeName>. <quote lang="la">Vitrum aliud flatu figuratur, aliud torno
        teritur</quote>, <placeName key="tgn,2588096">Pliny</placeName>. But as the Latins used the
        word <foreign lang="la">toreumata</foreign> to signify any works, either turned or wrought
        by the chisel, because they were made by the same workmen, Sanadon thinks the poet probably
        means, that this plate was engraved with an instrument. The Scholiast tells us, that this
         <placeName key="tgn,2319904">Evander</placeName> was carried from <placeName
         key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> by
        Mark Antony, and that he excelled in sculpture and engraving. They who believe that
         <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> means king <placeName key="tgn,2319904"
         >Evander</placeName>, would not only persuade us that this plate must have been preserved
        so many ages by some uncommon good fortune, but have unluckily placed a vessel so valuable
        on a monarch's table, whose palace was a cottage, his throne a chair of ordinary wood, his
        beds made of leaves or rushes, and his tapestry the skins of beasts. <foreign lang="la">Res
         inopes Evandrus habebat</foreign>. Dr. Bentley denies that the Latins ever used <foreign
         lang="la">tritum</foreign> to signify <foreign lang="la">caelatum, perfectum</foreign>, and
        he therefore recommends <foreign lang="la">tortum</foreign> to us, on the authority of an
        ancient manuscript.</p>
      </note> shall he for this [trifling] affair, or because in his hunger he has taken a chicken
      before me out of my part of the dish, be the less agreeable friend to me? [If so], what could
      I do if he was guilty of theft, or had betrayed things committed to him in confidence, or
      broken his word. They who are pleased [to rank all] faults nearly on an equality, are troubled
      when they come to the truth of the matter: sense and morality are against them, and utility
       itself,<note anchored="yes" n="29" resp="San">
       <p><placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> endeavors to prove, according to the
        doctrine of Epicurus, that justice and injustice arise only from laws, and that laws have no
        other foundation than public utility, by which he means the happiness of civil society. On
        the contrary, the Stoics asserted, that justice and injustice have their first principles in
        nature itself, and the first appearance of reason in the mind of man.</p>
      </note> the mother almost of right and of equity.</p>
     <p>When [rude] animals, they crawled<note anchored="yes" n="30" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Cum prorepserunt</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.99"/>
        </cit>. This expression is extremely proper for the system of Epicurus, who believed that
        the first race of men rose out of the earth, in which they were formed by a mixture of heat
        and moisture.</p>
      </note> forth upon the firstformed earth, the mute and dirty herd fought with their nails and
      fists for their acorn and caves, afterward with clubs, and finally with arms which experience
      had forged: till they found out words and names, by which they ascertained their language and
      sensations: thenceforward they began to abstain from war, to fortify towns, and establish
      laws: that no person should be a thief, a robber, or an adulterer. For before Helen's time
      there existed [many] a woman who was the dismal cause of war: but those fell by unknown
      deaths, whom pursuing uncertain venery, as the bull in the herd, the strongest slew. It must
      of necessity be acknowledged, if you have a mind to turn over the aeras and annals of the
      world, that laws were invented from an apprehension of the natural injustice [of mankind]. Nor
      can nature separate what is unjust from what is just, in the same manner as she distinguishes
      what is good from its reverse, and what is to be avoided from that which is to be sought: nor
      will reason persuade men to this, that he who breaks down the cabbage-stalk of his neighbor,
      sins in as great a measure, and in the same manner, as he who steals by night things
      consecrated to the gods. Let there be a settled standard, that may inflict adequate
      punishments upon crimes; lest you should persecute any one with the horrible thong, who is
      only deserving of a slight whipping. For I am not apprehensive, that you should correct with
      the rod one that deserves to suffer severer stripes; since you assert that pilfering is an
      equal crime with highway robbery, and threaten that you would prune off with an
      undistinguishing hook little and great vices, if mankind were to give you the sovereignty over
      them. If he be rich, who is wise, and a good shoemaker, and alone handsome, and a king, why do
      you wish for that which you are possessed of? You do not understand what Chrysippus,<note
       anchored="yes" n="31" resp="Torr">
       <p>Chrysippus is here pleasantly called father, because he was the first who explained, in
        this absurd manner, these excellent precepts of <placeName key="tgn,2786860"
        >Zeno</placeName> which teach us, that wisdom sets above kings; and that the throne she
        offers to us is preferable to that of the greatest monarchs.</p>
      </note> the father [of your sect], says: "The wise man never made himself shoes nor slippers:
      nevertheless, the wise man is a shoemaker." How so? In the same manner, though Hermogenes be
      silent, he is a fine singer, notwithstanding, and an excellent musician: as the subtle
      [lawyer] Alfenus,<note anchored="yes" n="32" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Alfenus Varus, a shoemaker of Cremona, who, growing out of conceit with his employment,
        quitted it, and came to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>; where attending the
        lectures of Servius Sulpicius, a celebrated professor of law, he made so great proficience
        in that science, that he soon came to be esteemed one of the ablest lawyers of his time, and
        his name often occurs in the Pandects. He was afterward advanced to the highest honors of
        the empire; for we find him consul in the year of the city 755.</p>
      </note> after every instrument of his calling was thrown aside, and his shop shut up, was
      [still] a barber; thus is the wise man of all trades, thus is he a king. O greatest of great
      kings, the waggish boys pluck you by the beard; whom unless you restrain with your staff, you
      will be jostled by a mob all about you, and you may wretchedly bark and burst your lungs in
      vain. Not to be tedious: while you, my king, shall go to the farthing bath, and no guard shall
      attend you, except the absurd Crispinus; my dear friends will both pardon me in any matter in
      which I shall foolishly offend, and I in turn will cheerfully put up with their faults; and,
      though a private man, I shall live more happily than you, a king. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="4">
     <head>He apologizes for the liberties taken by satiric poets in general, and particularly by
      himself</head>

     <p>THE poets Eupolis, and Cratinus, and Aristophanes, and others, who are authors of the
      ancient comedy,<note anchored="yes" n="33" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Comoedia prisca</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.2"/>
        </cit>. Comedy was divided into ancient and modern. In the first, the subject and the names
        of the actors were real. In the second, the drama was formed on history, but the names of
        the actors were invented. In the third, both the story and actors were formed by the
       poet.</p>
      </note> if there was any person deserving to be distinguished for being a rascal or a thief,
      an adulterer or a cut-throat, or in any shape an infamous fellow, branded him with great
      freedom. Upon these [models] Lucilius entirely depends, having imitated them, changing only
      their feet<note anchored="yes" n="34" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Mutatis pedibus</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.8"/>
        </cit>. Ennius and Pacuvius had written satires before Lucilius. He was rather the restorer
        than inventor of this kind of poetry; he formed himself upon the Grecian comedy, and only
        changed the measure of his verse, hexameter for iambics.</p>
      </note> and numbers: a man of wit, of great keenness,<note anchored="yes" n="35" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Emunctae naris</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.8"/>
        </cit>. Of a sagacious, penetrating genius, to discover the follies of mankind, and of an
        agreeable, spirited, raillery, to turn them into ridicule, <foreign lang="la"
        >facetus</foreign>. Such is the character of Lucilius by <placeName key="tgn,2068515"
        >Cicero</placeName> and Quintilian: <foreign lang="la">perurbanum</foreign> and <foreign
         lang="la">abunde salis</foreign>.</p>
      </note> inelegant in the composition of verse: for in this respect he was faulty; he would
      often, as a great feat, dictate two hundred verses in an hour, standing in the same position.
      As he flowed muddily, there was [always] something that one would wish to remove; he was
      verbose, and too lazy to endure the fatigue of writing-of writing accurately: for, with regard
      to the quantity [of his works], I make no account of it. See! Crispinus challenges me even for
      ever so little a wager.<note anchored="yes" n="36" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Minimo me provocat</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.14"/>
        </cit>. We should understand <foreign lang="la">pignore</foreign> or <foreign lang="la"
         >pretio</foreign>; nor is there any instance in the Latin tongue of <foreign lang="la"
         >provocare minimo digito</foreign>, as the commentators explain it. A man well assured of
        the truth of what he asserts, is willing to bet a large wager against a small one, which
         <placeName key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName> means by minimo provocare.</p>
      </note> Take, if you dare, take your tablets, and I will take mine; let there be a place, a
      time, and persons appointed to see fair play: let us see who can write the most. The gods have
      done a good part by me, since they have framed me of an humble and meek disposition, speaking
      but seldom, briefly: but do you, [Crispinus,] as much as you will, imitate air which is shut
      up in leathern bellows, perpetually puffing till the fire softens the iron. Fannius is a happy
      man, who, of his own accord, has presented his manuscripts<note anchored="yes" n="37"
       resp="Dac,San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ultro delatis capsis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.21"/>
        </cit> When a poet was generally esteemed, his works and his statue were placed in the
        public libraries. But <placeName key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName> congratulates Fannius
        upon the happiness of finding a method of immortalizing his name, without being obliged to
        pass through the usual forms. He thought he had a right to take an honor, which he was
        conscious he deserved, and perhaps imagined it a proper manner of resenting the public
        insensibility of his merit.</p>
      </note> and picture [to the Palatine Apollo]; when not a soul will peruse my writings, who am
      afraid to rehearse in public, on this account, because there are certain persons who can by no
      means relish this kind [of satiric writing], as there are very many who deserve censure.
      Single any man out of the crowd; he either labors under a covetous disposition, or under
      wretched ambition. One is mad in love with married women, another with youths; a third the
      splendor of silver captivates: Albius is in raptures with brass; another exchanges his
      merchandize from the rising sun, even to that with which the western regions are warmed: but
      he is hurried headlong through dangers, as dust wrapped up in a whirlwind; in dread lest he
      should lose any thing out of his capital, or [in hope] that he may increase his store. All
      these are afraid of verses, they hate poets. "He has hay on his horn,<note anchored="yes"
       n="38" resp="ed. Dubl">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Faenum habet in cornu.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.34"/>
        </cit> A metaphorical expression taken from a custom of tying hay on the horns of a
        mischievous bull. The laws of the Twelve Tables ordered, that the owner of the beast should
        pay for what damages it committed, or deliver it to the person injured. <quote lang="la">Si
         quadrupes pauperiem faxit, dominus sarcito, noxaeve dedito.</quote></p>
      </note> [they cry;] avoid him at a great distance: if he can but raise a laugh for his own
      diversion, he will not spare any friend: and whatever he has once blotted upon his paper, he
      will take a pleasure in letting all the boys and old women know, as they return from the
      bakehouse or the lake." But, come on, attend to a few words on the other side of the question.
       <milestone ed="p" n="39" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>In the first place, I will except myself out of the number of those I would allow to be
      poets: for one must not call it sufficient to tag a verse: nor if any person, like me, writes
      in a style bordering on conversation, must you esteem him to be a poet. To him who has genius,
      who has a soul of a diviner cast, and a greatness of expression, give the honor of this
      appellation. On this acount some have raised the question, whether comedy be a poem or not;
      because an animated spirit and force is neither in the style, nor the subject-matter: bating
      that it differs from prose by a certain measure, it is mere prose. But [one may object to
      this, that even in comedy] an inflamed father rages, because his.dissolute son, mad after a
      prostitute mistress, refuses a wife with a large portion; and (what is an egregious scandal)
      rambles about drunk with flambeaux by day-light. Yet could Pomponius, were his father alive,
      hear less severe reproofs! Wherefore it is not sufficient to write verses merely in proper
      language; which, if you take to pieces, any person may storm in the same manner as the father
      in the play. If from these verses which I write at this present, or those that Lucilius did
      formerly, you take away certain pauses and measures, and make that word which was first in
      order hindermost, by placing the latter [words] before those that preceded [in the verse]; you
      will not discern the limbs of a poet, when pulled in pieces, in the same manner as you would
      were you to transpose ever so [these lines of Ennius]: <quote lang="en">
       <lg type="pentameter">
        <l>When discord dreadful bursts the brazen bars,</l>
        <l>And shatters iron locks to thunder forth her wars.</l>
       </lg>
      </quote>
      <note anchored="yes" n="39" resp="TAB">
       <p>Literally, "After that dreadful discord burst asunder the iron bound doors and gates of
        war."</p>
      </note>
      <milestone ed="p" n="63" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>So far of this matter; at another opportunity [I may investigate] whether [a comedy] be a
      true poem or not: now I shall only consider this point, whether this [satiric] kind of writing
      be deservedly an object of your suspicion. Sulcius the virulent, and Caprius hoarse with their
      malignancy, walk [openly], and with their libels too [in their hands]; each of them a singular
      terror to robbers: but if a man lives honestly and with clean hands, he may despise them both.
      Though you be like highwaymen, Coelus and Byrrhus, I am not [a common accuser], like Caprius
      and Sulcius; why should you be afraid of me? No shop nor stall holds my books, which the
      sweaty hands of the vulgar and of Hermogenes Tigellius may soil. I repeat to nobody, except my
      intimates, and that when I am pressed; nor any where, and before any body.</p>
     <p>There are many who recite their writings in the middle of the forum; and who [do it] while
      bathing: the closeness of the place, [it seems,] gives melody to the voice. This pleases
      coxcombs, who never consider whether they do this to no purpose, or at an unseasonable time.
      But you, says he, delight to hurt people, and this you do out of a mischievous disposition.
      From what source do you throw this calumny upon me? Is any one then your voucher, with whom I
      have lived? lie who backbites his absent friend; [nay more,] who does not defend, at another's
      accusing him; who affects to raise loud laughs in company, and the reputation of a funny
      fellow who can feign things he never saw; who can not keep secrets; he is a dangerous man: be
      you, Roman, aware of him. You may often see it [even in crowded companies], where twelve sup
      together on three couches; one of which shall delight at any rate to asperse the rest, except
      him who furnishes the bath;<note anchored="yes" n="40" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Praeter eum, qui praebet aquam.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.88"/>
        </cit> Their host, who provided water for the bath; a part of their entertainment to express
        the whole.</p>
      </note> and him too afterward in his liquor, when truth-telling <placeName key="tgn,2097807"
       >Bacchus</placeName> opens the secrets of his heart. Yet this man seems entertaining, and
      well-bred, and frank to you, who are an enemy to the malignant: but do I, if I have laughed
      bccause the fop Rufillus smells all perfumes, and Gorgonius, like a he-goat, appear invidious
      and a snarler to you? If by any means mention happen to be made of the thefts of Petillius
       Capitolinus<note anchored="yes" n="41" resp="Fran">
       <p>The ancient commentator tells us, that Petillius was governor of the Capitol, from whence
        he was called Capitolinus; that he was accused of stealing a golden crown of <placeName
         key="tgn,2075298">Jupiter</placeName>, and acquitted by the favor of Augustus. If there be
        any truth in this story, for we know not where the commentator found it, he was more
        probably surnamed from his theft, than for his government of the Capitol.</p>
      </note> in your company, you defend him after your manner: [as thus,] Capitolinus has had.me
      for a companion and a friend from childhood, and being applied to, has done many things on my
      account: and I am glad that he lives secure in the city; but I wonder, notwithstanding, how he
      evaded that sentence. This is the very essence of black malignity,<note anchored="yes" n="42"
       resp="TAB">
       <p>Properly, "the juice of the cuttle-fish."</p>
      </note> this is mere malice itself: which crime, that it shall be far remote from my writings,
      and prior to them from my mind, I promise, if I can take upon me to promise any thing
      sincerely of myself. If I shall say any thing too freely, if perhaps too ludicrously, you must
      favor me by your indulgence with this allowance. For my excellent father inured me to this
      custom, that by noting each particular vice I might avoid it by the example [of others]. When
      he exhorted me that I should live thriftily, frugally, and content with what he had provided
      for me; don't you see, [would he say,] how wretchedly the son of Albius lives? and how
      miserably Barrus? A strong lesson to hinder any one from squandering away his patrimony. When
      he would deter me from filthy fondness for a light woman: [take care, said he,] that you do
      not resemble Sectanus. <milestone ed="p" n="113" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>That I might not follow adulteresses, when I could enjoy a lawful amour: the character,
      cried he, of Trebonius, who was caught in the fact, is by no means creditable. The philosopher
      may tell you the reasons for what is better to be avoided, and what to be pursued. It is
      sufficient for me, if I can preserve the morality traditional from my forefathers, and keep
      your life and reputation inviolate, so long as you stand in need of a guardian: so soon as age
      shall have strengthened your limbs and mind, you will swim without cork. In this manner he
      formed me, as yet a boy: and whether he ordered me to do any particular thing: You have an
      authority for doing this: [then] he instanced some one out of the select magistrates:<note
       anchored="yes" n="43" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Unum ex iudicibus selectis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4.123"/>
        </cit> The most eminent, and of greatest authority, among the senatorial order; an order
        called Sanctissimus. Torrentius thinks the poet means the judges, whom the pretor chose out
        of all degrees of the magistracy, to relieve and assist him in his office. But this good
        father would probably have taken his examples out of a more numerous, yet not less venerable
        order.</p>
      </note> or did he forbid me [any thing]; can you doubt, [says he,] whether this thing be
      dishonorable, and against your interest to be done, when this person and the other is become
      such a burning shame for his bad character [on these accounts]? As a neighboring funeral
      dispirits sick gluttons, and through fear of death forces them to have mercy upon themselves;
      so other men's disgraces often deter tender minds from vices. From this [method of education]
      I am clear from all such vices, as bring destruction along with them: by lighter foibles, and
      such as you may excuse, I am possessed. And even from these, perhaps, a maturer age, the
      sincerity of a friend, or my own judgment, may make great reductions. For neither when I am in
      bed, or in the piazzas, am I wanting to myself: this way of proceeding is better; by doing
      such a thing I shall live more comfortably; by this means I shall render myself agreeable to
      my friends; such a transaction was not clever; what, shall I, at any time, imprudently commit
      any thing like it? These things I resolve in silence by myself. When I have any leisure, I
      amuse myself with my papers. This is one of those lighter foibles [I was speaking of]: to
      which if you do not grant your indulgence, a numerous band of poets shall come, which will
      take my part (for we are many more in number),<note anchored="yes" n="44" resp="TAB">
       <p>See Orelli.</p>
      </note> and, like the Jews, we will force you to come over to our numerous party. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="5">
     <head>He describes a certain journey of his from <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>
      to <placeName key="tgn,7004094">Brundusium</placeName> with great pleasantry.</head>

     <p>HAVING<note anchored="yes" n="45" resp="San">
       <p>Octavius and Antony, both aspiring to the sovereign power, must necessarily have had
        frequent quarrels and dissensions. Their reconciliations were of short continuance, because
        they were insincere. Among many negotiations, undertaken by their common friends to
        reconcile them, history mentions two more particularly. The first in the year <date
         value="-39">714</date>, the other in 717, which was concluded by the mediation of Octavia,
        and to which our poet was carried by Maecenas.</p>
      </note> left mighty <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, <placeName
       key="perseus,Aricia">Aricia</placeName> received me in but a middling inn: Heliodorus the
      rhetorician, most learned in the Greek language, was my fellow-traveler: thence we proceeded
      to Forum-Appi, stuffed with sailors and surly landlords. This stage, but one for better
       travelers<note anchored="yes" n="46" resp="McCaul">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Praecinctis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.6"/>
        </cit> Prepared for traveling, i. e. <foreign lang="la">altius praecincis</foreign>, "to
        those who were better travelers than we were." <foreign lang="la">Praecinctus</foreign>
        means having the dress tucked up, that it may not prevent exertion. Hence used for
        "diligent," "active." Compare <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.8.10">Sat. ii. 8, 10.</bibl></p>
      </note> than we, being laggard we divided into two; the Appian way is less tiresome to bad
      travelers. Here I, on account of the water, which was most vile, proclaim war against my
      belly, waiting not without impatience for my companions while at supper.</p>
     <p>Now the night was preparing to spread her shadows upon the earth, and to display the
      constellations in the heavens. Then our slaves began to be liberal of their abuse to the
      watermen, and the watermen to our slaves. "Here bring to." "You are stowing in hundreds; hold,
      now sure there is enough."</p>
     <p>Thus while the fare is paid, and the mule fastened, a whole hour is passed away. The cursed
      gnats, and frogs of the fens, drive off repose. While the waterman and a passenger,
      well-soaked with plenty of thick wine, vie with one another in singing the praises of their
      absent mistresses: at length the passenger being fatigued, begins to sleep; and the lazy
      waterman ties the halter of the mule, turned out a-grazing, to a stone, and snores, lying flat
      on his back. And now the day approached, when we saw the boat made no way; until a choleric
      fellow, one of the passengers, leaps out of the boat, and drubs the head and sides of both
      mule and waterman with a willow cudgel. At last we were scarcely set ashore at the fourth
       hour.<note anchored="yes" n="47" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Quarta hora.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.23"/>
        </cit> The Romans during more than four hundred and fifty years never had names for the
        hours of the day. The twelve tables divided it into three parts; the rising sun, the setting
        sun, and mid-day. The hours of night and day were equal in number through the year; but from
        spring to autumn, those of the day were longer than those of the night, and from September
        to March the hours of night were longest.</p>
      </note> We wash our faces and hands in thy water, O Feronia. Then, having dined, we crawled on
      three miles; and arrive under <placeName key="tgn,7006704">Anxur</placeName>, which is built
      upon rocks that look white to a great distance. Maecenas was to come here, as was the
      excellent Cocceius, both sent embassadors on matters of great importance; having been
      accustomed to reconcile friends at variance.<note anchored="yes" n="48" resp="Masson">
       <p>Three particulars demonstrate that this journey was to the second conference at <placeName
         key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName>. Fonteius is here joined with Maecenas and
        Cocceius, but was not engaged in the first. The poet says, that Maecenas and Cocceius had
        been before employed to reconcile Octavius and Antony, <foreign lang="la">soliti</foreign>,
        which must necessarily suppose the first congress in 714, when Horace had not been
        introduced to Macenas.</p>
      </note> Here, having got sore eyes, I was obliged to use the black ointment. In the mean time
      came Macenas and Cocceius, and Fonteius Capito<note anchored="yes" n="49" resp="Watson">
       <p>Fonteius Capito. Probably the father of him who was consul two years before the death of
        Augustus. he was here of the party of Antony, and Maecenas on the side of Augustus. Cocceius
        was by way of an arbitrator between them, to settle their differences. <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Homo factus ad unguem,</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.32"/>
        </cit> a complete man, every way accomplished.</p>
      </note> along with them, a man of perfect polish,<note anchored="yes" n="50" resp="Erasmus">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ad unguem factus homo.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.32"/>
        </cit> This figurative expression is taken from engravers in wood or marble, who used to
        pass their nail over the work, to know whether it were well polished.</p>
      </note> and intimate with Mark Antony, no man more so.</p>
     <p>Without regret we passed <placeName key="perseus,Fundi">Fundi</placeName>, where Aufidius
      Luscus was praetor,<note anchored="yes" n="51" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Praetore.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.34"/>
        </cit> The colonies and municipal towns had the same dignities and magistracies as the city
        of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; senators, praetors, quaestors, and
        aediles. It is difficult to know whether <placeName key="perseus,Fundi">Fundi</placeName>
        had a praetor chosen out of her own citizens, or whether he was sent from <placeName
         key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</p>
      </note> laughing at the honors of that crazy scribe,<note anchored="yes" n="52" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Praemia scribe.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.35"/>
        </cit> Horace calls these robes <quote lang="la">praemia scribae</quote>, because the
        secretaries in colonies and municipal towns were frequently raised to the dignity of the
        praetorship. The <foreign lang="la">toga praetexta</foreign> was a robe bordered with
        purple. <foreign lang="la">Tunica clavata</foreign> was a vest with two borders of purple
        laid like a lace upon the middle or opening of it, down to the bottom; in such a manner as
        that when the vest was drawn close or buttoned, the two purple borders joined and seemed to
        be but one. If these borders were large, the vest was called <foreign lang="la">latus
        clavus</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">tunica laticlavia</foreign>; if they were narrow,
        then it was named <foreign lang="la">angustus clavus, tunica angusticlavia</foreign>. These
        two sorts of tunics were worn to distinguish the magistrates in their employments, and were
        very different from those worn by the common people, <foreign lang="la">tunicato
        popello</foreign>, which were closed before, and without any purple border. They were called
         <foreign lang="la">tunicae rectae.</foreign></p>
      </note> his praetexta, laticlave, and pan of incense.<note anchored="yes" n="53"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Prunaeque batillum.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.36"/>
        </cit> A pan for incense, frequently carried before the emperors, of those possessed of the
        sovereign authority.</p>
      </note> At our next stage, being weary, we tarry in the city of the Mamurrae,<note
       anchored="yes" n="54" resp="Torr">
       <p>The stroke of satire here is of a delicate and almost imperceptible malignity. <placeName
         key="perseus,Formiae">Formiae</placeName>, the city which Horace means, belonged to the
        Lamian family, whose antiquity was a great honor to it. But our poet paraphrases it by the
        name of a person, who was born there, and who has made his country famous in a very
        different manner. Mamurra was a Roman knight, who was infamous for his rapine, luxury and
        debauchcry. Catullus calls him <foreign lang="la">Decoctor Formianus.</foreign></p>
      </note> Murena complimenting us with his house,<note anchored="yes" n="55" resp="Fran">
       <p>Murena was brother of Licymnia, married afterward to Maecenas. He was condemned to death
        for conspiring against Augustus. Varius and Plotius Tucca were the persons to whom Augustus
        intrusted the correction of the Aeneid, after Virgil's death, but with an order not to make
        any additions to it.</p>
      </note> and Capito with his kitchen. <milestone ed="p" n="39" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>The next day arises, by much the most agreeable to all: for Plotius, and Varius, and Virgil
      met us at <placeName key="tgn,7009927">Sinuessa</placeName>; souls more candid ones than which
      the world never produced, nor is there a person in the world more bound to them than myself.
      0h what embraces, and what transports were there! While I am in my senses, nothing can I
      prefer to a pleasant friend. The village, which is next adjoining to the bridge of <placeName
       key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>, accommodated us with lodging [at night]; and the
      public officers<note anchored="yes" n="56" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Parochi</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.46"/>
        </cit>. Before the consulship of Lucius Posthumius, the magistrates of <placeName
         key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> traveled at the public charge, without being
        burthensome to the provinces. Afterward commissaries were appointed in all the great roads
        to defray all expenses of those who were employed in the business of the state. They were
        obliged, by the <foreign lang="la">Lex Julia de provinciis</foreign>, to provide lodging,
        fire, salt, hay, straw, etc.</p>
      </note> with such a quantity of fuel and salt as they are obliged to [by law]. From this place
      the mules deposited their pack-saddles at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>
      betimes [in the morning]. Maecenas goes to play [at tennis]; but I and Virgil to our repose:
      for to play at tennis is hurtful to weak eyes and feeble constitutions.</p>
     <p>From this place the villa of Cocceius, situated above the Caudian inns, which abounds with
      plenty, receives us. Now, my muse, I beg of you briefly to relate the engagement between the
      buffoon Sarmentus and Messius Cicirrus; and from what ancestry descended each began the
      contest. The illutrious race of Messius-Oscan:<note anchored="yes" n="57" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Osci</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.54"/>
        </cit> is a nominative case, and we must construe it, <foreign lang="la">Osci sunt clarum
         genus Messii</foreign>. The Oscans gave to Messius his illustrious birth, a sufficient
        proof that he was an infamous scoundrel. The people who inhabited this part of <placeName
         key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName> were guilty of execrable debaucheries.</p>
      </note> Sarmentus's mistress is still alive. Sprung from such families as these, they came to
      the combat. First, Sarmentus: "I pronounce thee to have the look of a mad horse." We laugh;
      and Messius himself [says], "I accept your challenge:" and wags his head. "O!" cries he, "if
      the horn were not cut off your forehead, what would you not do; since, maimed as you are, you
      bully at such a rate?" For a foul scar has disgraced the left part of Messius's bristly
      forehead. Cutting many jokes upon his Campanian disease, and upon his face, he desired him to
      exhibit Polyphemus's dance:<note anchored="yes" n="58" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Saltaret uti Cyclopa. </quote>
         <bibl n="HOr. S. 1.5.63"/>
        </cit> The raillery is founded on his gigantic size, and the villainous gash that Messius
        had on his forehead, which made him look so like a Polyphemus, that he might dance the part
        without buskins or a mask. To dance a <placeName key="tgn,2236678">Cyclops</placeName>, a
        Glaucus, a Ganymede, a Leda, was an expression for representing their story by dancing.</p>
      </note> that he had no occasion for a mask, or the tragic buskins. Cicirrus [retorted] largely
      to these: he asked, whether he had consecrated his chain<note anchored="yes" n="59" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Donasset iamne catenam.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.5.65"/>
        </cit> Only the vilest slaves, or those who worked in the country, were chained. It appears
        by an epigram of Martial, that when they were set at liberty, they consecrated their chains
        to Saturn, because slavery was unknown under his reign. But when Messius asks Sarmentus
        whether he had dedicated his chain to the <quote lang="la">Dii Lares</quote>, he would
        reproach him with being a fugitive. These gods were invoked by travelers, because they
        presided over highways, from whence they were called <quote lang="la">viales</quote>. They
        themselves were always represented like travelers, as if they were ready to leave the house;
         <quote lang="la">succincti</quote>. Or Sarmentus was a slave so vile that he knew no other
        gods, but those who stood on the hearth, and which it was his employment to keep clean.</p>
      </note> to the household gods according to his vow; though he was a scribe, [he told him] his
      mistress's property in him was not the less. Lastly, he asked, how lie ever came to run away;
      such a lank meager fellow, for whom a pound of corn [a-day] would be ample.<note
       anchored="yes" n="60" resp="Turnebus">
       <p>By the laws of the twelve tables, a slave was allowed a pound of corn a day. <quote
         lang="la">"Qui eum vinctum habebit, libras farris in dies dato."</quote></p>
      </note> We were so diverted, that we continued that supper to an unusual length.</p>
     <p>Hence we proceed straight on for <placeName key="tgn,7004393">Beneventum</placeName>; where
      the bustling landlord almost burned himself, in roasting some lean thrushes: for, the fire
      falling through the old kitchen [floor], the spreading flame made a great progress toward the
      highest part of the roof. Then you might have seen the hungry guests and frightened slaves
      snatching their supper out [of the flames], and every body endeavoring to extinguish the fire.</p>
     <p>After this <placeName key="tgn,7010380">Apulia</placeName> began to discover to me her
      well-known mountains, which the Atabulus scorches [with his blasts]: and through which we
      should never have crept, unless the neighboring village of Trivicus had received us, not
      without a smoke that brought tears into our eyes; occasioned by a hearth's burning some green
      boughs with the leaves upon them. Here, like a great fool as I was, I wait till midnight for a
      deceitful mistress: sleep, however, overcomes me, while meditating love; and disagreeable
      dreams make me ashamed of myself and every thing about me. <milestone ed="p" n="86"
       unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Hence we were bowled away in chaises twenty-four miles, intending to stop at a little town,
      which one can not name in a verse, but it is easily enough known by description.<note
       anchored="yes" n="61" resp="McCaul">
       <p>This (as the Schol. informs us) was Equotuticum. The reason that it can not occur in
        dactylics is, that the first is short, and the next two syllables long, while the
        penultimate is short. Were the first long, thero could be no difficulty about introducing
        it. MCCAUL.</p>
      </note> For water is sold here, though the worst in the world; but their bread is exceeding
      fine, inasmuch that the weary traveler is used to carry it willingly on his shoulders; for
      [the bread] at <placeName key="perseus,Canusium">Canusium</placeName> is gritty; a pitcher of
      water is worth no more [than it is here]: which place was formerly built by the valiant
      Diomedes. Here Varius departs dejected from his weeping friends.</p>
     <p>Hence we came to Rabi, fatigued: because we made a long journey, and it was rendered still
      more troublesome by the rains. Next day the weather was better, the road worse, even to the
      very walls of Barium that abounds in fish. In the next place <placeName key="tgn,7008311"
       >Egnatia</placeName>, which [seems to have] been built on troubled waters, gave us occasion
      for jests and laughter; for they wanted to persuade us, that at this sacred portal the incense
      melted without fire. The Jew Apella may believe this, not I. For I have learned [from
      Epicurus], that the gods dwell in a state of tranquillity; nor, if nature effect any wonder,
      that the anxious gods send it from the high canopy of the heavens.</p>
     <p><placeName key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName> ends both my long journey, and my
      paper. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="6">
     <head>Of true nobility.</head>

     <p>NOT Maecenas, though of all the Lydians<note anchored="yes" n="62" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Lydorum quicquid Etruscos.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.1"/>
        </cit> Mr. Dacier, upon the single authority of Dionysius Halicarnassensis, asserts that the
        Tuscans were not descended from the Lydians. Yet Horace had a poetical right to the
        tradition, as it was generally believed, although it might possibly be false. But it is
        supported by Herodotus, <placeName key="tgn,4011419">Tully</placeName>, Virgil, Strabo,
        Servius, Pliny, Tacitus, Velleius, <placeName key="tgn,2652379">Seneca</placeName>,
        Plutarch, Valerius Maximus, Silius, and Statius.</p>
      </note> that ever inhabited the Tuscan territories, no one is of a nobler family than
      yourself; and though you have ancestors both on father's and mother's side, that in times past
      have had the command of mighty legions; do you, as the generality are wont, toss up your nose
      at obscure people, such as me, who had [only] a freed-man<note anchored="yes" n="63"
       resp="San">
       <p>In the first ages of the republic <foreign lang="la">libertinus</foreign> and <foreign
         lang="la">liberti filius</foreign> had the same signification; but some time before Cicero,
        as we are informed by Suetonius, the manner of speaking was changed, and from thence
         <foreign lang="la">libertus</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">libertinus</foreign> were used
        as synonymous terms to signify a man who was made free.</p>
      </note> for my father: since you affirm that it is of no consequence of what parents any man
      is born, so that he be a man of merit. You persuade yourself, with truth, that before the
      dominions of Tullius, and the reign of one born a slave, frequently numbers of men descended
      from ancestors of no rank, have both lived as men of merit, and have been distinguished by the
      greatest honors: [while] on the other hand Laevinus, the descendant of that famous Valerius,
      by whose means Tarquinius Superbus was expelled from his kingdom, was not a farthing more
       esteemed<note anchored="yes" n="64" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Licuisse.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.14"/>
        </cit> Laevinus is here pleasantly set up to auction, for <foreign lang="la"
        >licere</foreign> was the term used to signify raising the sale.</p>
      </note> [on account of his family, even] in the judgment of the people, with whose disposition
      you are well acquainted; who often foolishly bestow honors on the unworthy, and are from their
      stupidity slaves to a name: who are struck with admiration by inscriptions and statues. What
      is it fitting for us to do, who are far, very far removed from the vulgar [in our sentiments]?
      For grant it, that the people had rather confer a dignity on Laevinus than on Decius, who is a
      new man; and the censor Appius would expel me [the senate-house], because I was not sprung
      from a sire of distinction: and that too deservedly, inasmuch as I rested not content in in my
      own condition. But glory drags in her dazzling car the obscure as closely fettered as those of
      nobler birth. What did it profit you, O Tullius, to resume the robe that you [were forced] to
      lay aside, and. become a tribune [again] Envy increased upon you, which had been less, if you
      had remained in a private station. For when any crazy fellow has laced the middle of his leg
      with the sable buskins,<note anchored="yes" n="65" resp="Torr">
       <p>The buskins worn by senators were black, and sometimes white; those of the curule
        magistrates were red.</p>
      </note> and has let flow the purple robe from his breast, he immediately hears: "Who is this
      man? Whose son is he?" Just as if there be any one, who labors under the same distemper as
      Barrus does, so that he is ambitious of being reckoned handsome; let him go where he will, he
      excites curiosity among the girls of inquiring into particulars; as what sort of face, leg,
      foot, teeth, hair, he has. Thus he who engages<note anchored="yes" n="66" resp="Cruq">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Sic qui promittit.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.34"/>
        </cit> This was the form of a senator's and a magistrate's oath.</p>
      </note> to his citizens to take care of the city, the empire, and <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
       >Italy</placeName>, and the sanctuaries of the gods, forces every mortal to be solicitous,
      and to ask from what sire he is descended, or whether he is base by the obscurity of his
      mother. What? do you, the son of a Syrus,<note anchored="yes" n="67" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Syri, Damae, aut Dionysi.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.38"/>
        </cit> These three names are the names of slaves. <placeName key="tgn,7002261"
        >Damas</placeName> or <placeName key="tgn,1085129">Dama</placeName> is a contraction of
        Demetrius; Syrus is frequently the slave in comedy.</p>
      </note> a <placeName key="tgn,1085129">Dama</placeName>, or a Dionysius, dare to cast down the
      citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> from the [Tarpeian] rock, or
      deliver them up to Cadmus [the executioner]? But, [you may say,] my colleague Novius sits<note
       anchored="yes" n="68" resp="Torr">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Sedet</foreign> is a law word, properly applied to senators, praetors,
        and other judges when seated on the bench, in execution of their office.</p>
      </note> below me by one degree: for he is only what my father was. And therefore do you esteem
      yourself a Paulus or a Messala? But he (Novius), if two hundred carriages and three funerals
      were to meet in the forum, could make noise enough<note anchored="yes" n="69" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Magna sonabit.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.43"/>
        </cit> Funerals usually passed through the forum, and Novius could pronounce an oration with
        a voice of thunder. Horace laughs at his being made a senator for an accomplishment which
        could only entitle him to the office of a crier.</p>
      </note> to drown all their horns and trumpets:<note anchored="yes" n="70" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Trumpets were used at the funerals of men, and flutes at those of children. The twelve
        tables confined them to ten in number. <quote lang="la">"Decem tibicines adhibeto, hoc plus
         ne facito."</quote></p>
      </note> this [kind of merit] at least has its weight with us. </p>
     <p>Now I return to myself, who am descended from a freedman; whom every body nibbles at, as
      being descended from a freed-man. Now, because, Maecenas, I am a constant guest of yours; but
      formerly, because a Roman legion was under my command, as being a military tribune. This
      latter case is different from the former: for, though any person perhaps might justly envy me
      that post of honor, yet could he not do so with regard to your being my friend! especially as
      you are cautious to admit such as are worthy; and are far from having any sinister ambitious
      views. I can not reckon myself a lucky fellow on this account, as if it were by accident that
      I got you for my friend; for no kind of accident threw you in my way. That best of men,
      Virgil, long ago, and after him, Varius, told you what I was. When first I came into your
      presence, I spoke a few words in a broken manner (for childish bashfulness hindered me from
      speaking more); I did not tell you that I was the issue of an illustrious father: I did not
      [pretend] that I rode about the country on a Satureian horse, but plainly what I really was;
      you answer (as your custom is) a few words: I depart: and you re-invite me after the ninth
      month, and command me to be in the number of your friends. I esteem it a great thing that I
      pleased you, who distinguish probity from baseness, not by the illustriousness of a father,
      but by the purity of heart and feelings. <milestone ed="p" n="65" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>And yet if my disposition be culpable for a few faults, and those small ones, otherwise
      perfect (as if you should condemn moles scattered over a beautiful skin), if no one can justly
      lay to my charge avarice, nor sordidness, nor impure haunts; if, in fine (to speak in my own
      praise), I live undefiled, and innocent, and dear to my friends; my father was the cause of
      all this: who though a poor man on a lean farm, was unwilling to send me to a school under
      [the pedant] Flavius, where great boys, sprung from great centurions, having their satchels
      and tablets swung over their left arm, used to go with money in their hands the very day it
      was due;<note anchored="yes" n="71" resp="McCaul, Wheeler">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Octonis referentes idibus aera.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.75"/>
        </cit> The Romans had many stated times of paying their schoolmasters. Some imagine it was
        at the beginning, others at the end of the year, or at the grand festival of Minerva, called
         <foreign lang="la">quinquatrus</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">quinquatria</foreign>,
        which began the 19th of March. But the Minerval then given to the master was not a salary,
        but a voluntary present. This word has no particular force here. It merely means that the
        Ides were eight days from the Nones. With regard to <foreign lang="la">idibus</foreign>
        comp. <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.3.87">Sat. i. 3, 87.</bibl> It appears from a passage of Martial
        that the Roman youths had full four months' vacation; hence <foreign lang="la">Octonis
         idibus</foreign> denote the period of tuition: trans, "bringing the money for eight months'
        instruction." </p>
      </note> but had the spirit to bring me a child to <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
      >Rome</placeName>, to be taught those arts which any Roman knight and senator can teach his
      own children. So that, if any person had considered my dress, and the slaves who attended me
      in so populous a city, he would have concluded that those expenses were supplied to me out of
      some hereditary estate. He himself, of all others the most faithful guardian, was constantly
      about every one of my prcceptors. Why should I multiply words? He preserved me chaste (which
      is the first honor of virtue) not only from every actual guilt, but likewise from [every] foul
      imputation, nor was he afraid lest any should turn it to his reproach, if I should come to
      follow a business attended with small profits, in capacity of an auctioneer, or (what he was
      himself) a taxgatherer. Nor [had that been the case] should I have complained. On this account
      the more praise is due to him, and from me a greater degree of gratitude. As long as I am in
      my senses, I can never be ashamed of such a father as this, and therefore shall not apologize
      [for my birth], in the manner that numbers do, by affirming it to be no fault of theirs. My
      language and way of thinking is far different from such persons. For if nature were to make us
      from a certain term of years to go over our past time again, and [suffer us] to choose other
      parents, such as every man for ostentation's sake would wish for himself; I, content with my
      own, would not assume those that are honored with the ensigns and seats of state; [for which I
      should seem] a madman in the opinion of the mob, but in yours, I hope a man of sense; because
      I should be unwilling to sustain a troublesome burden, being by no means used to it. For I
      must [then] immediately set about acquiring a larger fortune, and more people must be
      complimented; and this and that companion must be taken along, so that I could neither take a
      jaunt into the country, or a journey by myself; more attendants and more horses must be fed;
      coaches must be drawn. Now, if I please, I can go as far as <placeName key="tgn,7004100"
       >Tarentum</placeName> on my bob-tailed mule, whose loins the portmanteau galls with his
      weight, as does the horseman his shoulders. No one will lay to my charge such sordidness as he
      may, Tullius, to you, when five slaves follow you, a praetor, along the Tiburtian way,
      carrying a traveling kitchen, and a vessel of wine. Thus I live more comfortably, O
      illustrious senator, than you, and than thousands of others. Wherever I have a fancy, I walk
      by myself: I inquire the price of herbs and bread: I traverse the tricking circus,<note
       anchored="yes" n="72" resp="Turner">
       <p>He calls the circus <foreign lang="la">fallacem</foreign>, deceiving, because diviners,
        fortunetellers, interpreters of dreams, astrologers, and impostors of all sorts usually
        assemble there.</p>
      </note> and the forum often in the evening: I stand listening among the fortune-tellers:
      thence I take myself home to a plate of onions, pulse, and pancakes. My supper is served up by
      three slaves; and a white stone slab supports two cups and a brimmer: near the salt-cellar
      stands a homely cruet<note anchored="yes" n="73" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Echino vilis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.117"/>
        </cit> We can not precisely determine what the <foreign lang="la">guttus</foreign> and
         <foreign lang="la">echinus</foreign> were. Mr. Dacier thinks the first was a little urn,
        out of which they poured water into a basin, <foreign lang="la">echinus</foreign>, to wash
        their hands.</p>
      </note> with a little bowl, earthen-ware from <placeName key="tgn,7003005"
      >Campania</placeName>. Then I go to rest; by no means concerned that I must rise in the
      morning, and pay a visit to the statue of Marsyas,<note anchored="yes" n="74" resp="Torr">
       <p>Marsyas, a satyr, who, challenging Apollo to a trial of skill in music, was overcome and
        flayed alive by the god. A statue was erected to him in the forum, opposite to the rostra
        where the judges determined causes, and the poet pleasantly says, it stood in such an
        attitude as showed its indignation to behold a man who had been a slave, now sitting among
        the magistrates of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. The satyr forgets, in his
        resentment of such a sight, the pain of being flayed alive.</p>
      </note> who denies that he is able to bear the look of the younger Novius. I lie a-bed to the
      fourth hour; after that I take a ramble, or having read or written what may amuse me in my
      privacy, I am anointed with oil, but not with such as the nasty Nacca, when he robs the lamps.</p>
     <p>But when the sun, become more violent, has reminded me to go to baths, I avoid the
       <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName><note anchored="yes" n="75"
       resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Fugio campum, lusumque trigonem.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.6.126"/>
        </cit>
        <foreign lang="la">Campus</foreign> is the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus
        Martius</placeName>, and <foreign lang="la">lusus trigon</foreign> was a game played with a
        ball, otherwise called <foreign lang="la">lusus trigonalis</foreign>, because the players
        stood in a triangle. Martial speaks of it in more than one place</p>
      </note> and the game of hand-ball. Having dined in a temperate manner, just enough to hinder
      me from having an empty stomach, during the rest of the day I trifle in my own house. This is
      the life of those who are free from wretched and burthensome ambition: with such things as
      these I comfort myself, in a way to live more delightfully than if my grandfather had been a
      quaestor, and father and uncle too. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="7">
     <head>He humorously describes a squabble betwixt Rupilius and Persius.</head>

     <p>IN what manner the mongrel Persius<note anchored="yes" n="76" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ibrida Persius</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.7"/>
        </cit>. Persius was a Greek by his father, and an Italian by his mother. The Romans gave the
        name of Ibrida to those whom parents were of different nations, or different conditions.</p>
      </note> revenged the filth and venom of Rupilius, surnamed King, is I think known to all the
      blind men and barbers. This Persius, being a man of fortune, had very great business at
      Clazomenae, and, into the bargain, certain troublesome litigations wtth King; a hardened
      fellow, and one who was able to exceed even King in virulence; confident, blustering, of such
      a bitterness of speech, that he would outstrip the Sisennae<note anchored="yes" n="77"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Cornelius Sisenna being reproached by the senate with the bad conduct of his wife,
        replied, "I married her by the advice of Augustus." Insinuating, Augustus had obliged him to
        marry her, that he might have a more easy commerce with her. Titus Veturius Barras, having
        ruined himself by his extravagance, was put to death for violating a vestal virgin.</p>
      </note> and Barri, if ever so well equipped.</p>
     <p>I return to King. After nothing could be settled betwixt them (for people among whom adverse
      war breaks out, are proportionably vexatious on the same account as they are brave. Thus
      between Hector, the son of Priam, and the highspirited Achilles, the rage was of so capital a
      nature, that only the final destruction [of one of them] could determine it; on no other
      account, than that valor in each of them was consummate. If discord sets two cowards to work;
      or if an engagement happens between two that are not of a match, as that of Diomed and the
      Lycian Glaucus; the worse man will walk off, [buying his peace] by voluntarily sending
      presents), when Brutus held as praetor<note anchored="yes" n="78" resp="San">
       <p>Marcus Brutus and Cassius were praetors of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>
        when Caesar was put to death. In 711 Brutus went to take possession of his Macedonian
        government, and <foreign lang="la">praetor</foreign> may be understood <foreign lang="la"
         >propraetor</foreign>; a manner of speaking of which there are many examples.</p>
      </note> the fertile <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, this pair, Rupilius and
      Persius, encountered; in such a manner, that [the gladiators] Bacchius and Bithus<note
       anchored="yes" n="79" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>The Scholiast tells us, that Bithus and Bacchius were two gladiators, who certainly put to
        death whoever fought with them. They afterward engaged together, and both expired on the
        stage.</p>
      </note> were not better matched. Impetuous they hurry to the cause, each of them a fine sight.</p>
     <p>Persius opens his case; and is laughed at by all the assembly; he extols Brutus, and extols
      the guard; he styles Brutus the sun of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, and his
      attendants he styles salutary stars, all except King; that he [he says,] came like that dog,
      the constellation hateful to husbandman: he poured along like a wintery flood, where the ax
      seldom comes.</p>
     <p>Then, upon his running on in so smart and fluent a manner, the Praenestine [king] directs
      some witticisms squeezed from the vineyard,<note anchored="yes" n="80" resp="Dac">
       <p>Horace means a particular kind of vine, <foreign lang="la">arbustiva</foreign>, that grew
        round trees, in which the people who gathered the grapes stood exposed to the raillery of
        the travelers. In such an attitude our <cit>
         <quote lang="la">durus Vindemiator</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.7"/>
        </cit> had often appeared. All sort of injurious language was allowed during the vintage; a
        custom that still continues in <placeName key="tgn,7004474">Naples</placeName>.</p>
      </note> himself a hardy vine-dresser, never defeated, to whom the passenger had often been
      obliged to yield, bawling cuckoo with roaring voice.</p>
     <p>But the Grecian Persius, as soon as he had been well sprinkled with Italian vinegar, bellows
      out: O Brutus, by the great gods I conjure you, who are accustomed to take off kings,<note
       anchored="yes" n="81" resp="McCaul">
       <p>Lucius Junius Brutus expelled Tarquinius Superbus. Marcus Brutus freed his country from
        the imperial power of Julius Caesar. From the introduction of this, we may conjecture that
         <placeName key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName>, at the time of writing this satire, had
        not yet espoused the side of Augustus.</p>
      </note> why do you not dispatch this King? Believe me, this is a piece of work which of right
      belongs to you. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="8">
     <head>Priapus complains that the Esquilian mount is infested with the incantations of
      sorceresses.</head>

     <p>FORMERLY I was the trunk of a wild fig-tree, an useless log:<note anchored="yes" n="82"
       resp="Schol">
       <p>The wood of a fig-tree was very little used, on account of its brittleness.</p>
      </note> when the artificer, in doubt whether he should make a stool or a Priapus of me,
      determined that I should be a god. Henceforward I became a god, the greatest terror of thieves
      and birds: for my right hand restrains thieves, and a bloodylooking pole stretched out from my
      frightful middle: but a reed fixed upon the crown of my head terrifies the mischievous birds,
      and hinders them from settling in these new gardens.<note anchored="yes" n="83" resp="San">
       <p>Octavius, willing to correct the infection of this hill, which was a common burial-place
        for all the poor of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, got the consent of the
        senate and people to give part of it to Maecenas, who built a magnificent house there with
        very extensive gardens. Hence the poet calls them <cit>
         <quote lang="la">novis hortis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.8"/>
        </cit></p>
      </note> Before this the fellow-slave bore dead corpses thrown out of their narrow cells to
      this place, in order to be deposited in paltry coffins. This place stood a common sepulcher
      for the miserable mob, for the buffoon Pantolabus, and Nomentanus the rake. Here a column
      assigned a thousand feet<note anchored="yes" n="84" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Mille pedes in fronte.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.8"/>
        </cit> Such was the title of the grave-yard, preserved on a pillar of stone, cippus, to show
        its extent, and to declare it was never to return to the heirs of the estate. We have
        numberless inscriptions of this kind, <quote lang="la">ITA NE UNQUAM DE NOMINE FAMILIAE
         NOSTRAE EXEAT HOC MONUMENTUM. HOC MONUMENTUM HEREDES NON SEQUITUR. IN FRONTE LAT. PED. XX.
         ET DIG. II. IN AGR. LONG. PED. XX.</quote>
        <foreign lang="la">In fronte</foreign> signifies to the road: <foreign lang="la">in
        agro</foreign>, to the fields. <foreign lang="la">Dabat</foreign> is for <foreign lang="la"
         >indicabat, testabatur.</foreign></p>
      </note> [of ground] in front, and three hundred toward the fields: that the burial-place
      should not descend to the heirs of the estate. Now one may live in the Esquiliae,<note
       anchored="yes" n="85" resp="Torr">
       <p>The air was afterward so healthy, that Augustus was carried thither when he was ill.</p>
      </note> [since it is made] a healthy place; and walk upon an open terrace, where lately the
      melancholy passengers beheld the ground frightful with white bones; though both the thieves
      and wild beasts accustomed to infest this place, do not occasion me so much care and trouble,
      as do [these hags], that turn people's minds by their incantations and drugs. These I can not
      by any means destroy nor hinder, but that they will gather bones and noxious herbs, as soon as
      the fleeting moon<note anchored="yes" n="86" resp="Torr">
       <p>The moon presided over all enchantments, and was believed to be most favorable when in the
        full, decorum os, because she then infused a stronger spirit into the magical herbs.</p>
      </note> has shown her beauteous face.</p>
     <p>I myself saw Canidia, with her sable garment tucked up, walk with bare feet and disheveled
      hair, yelling together with the elder Sagana. Paleness had rendered both of them horrible to
      behold. They began to claw up the earth with their nails, and to tear a black ewe-lamb to
      pieces with their teeth. </p>
     <p>The blood was poured into a ditch, that thence they might charm out the shades<note
       anchored="yes" n="87" resp="Dac">
       <p>Black victims alone were sacrificed to the infernal gods, nor was any thing supposed more
        delicious to the souls of the departed than blood. They could not foretell any future
        events, or answer any questions, until they had drank of it. <placeName key="tgn,2093866"
         >Ulysses</placeName> was obliged to draw his sword to frighten them away from the blood he
        had poured into the trench for Tiresias.</p>
      </note> of the dead, ghosts that were to give them answers. There was a woolen effigy<note
       anchored="yes" n="88" resp="Watson">
       <p>The image of wool represented the person they were willing should survive the other
        represented by that of wax. It is for this reason that the images were made of different
        materials, that their fates might be different.</p>
      </note> too, another of wax: the woolen one larger, which was to inflict punishment on the
      little one<note anchored="yes" n="89" resp="San">
       <p>This little figure probably represented Darius, who had forsaken Canidia, as we find in
        the fifth epode.</p>
      </note> The waxen stood in a suppliant posture, as ready to perish in a servile manner. One of
      the hags invokes Hecate, and the other fell Tisiphone. Then might you see serpents and
      infernal bitches<note anchored="yes" n="90" resp="Torr">
       <p>The serpents were forerunners of Tisiphone, and the bitches foretold that her infernal
        majesty was coming.</p>
      </note> wander about; and the moon with blushes hiding behind the lofty monuments, that she
      might not be a witness to these doings. But if I lie, even a tittle, may my head be
      contaminated with the white filth of ravens; and may <placeName key="tgn,2008628"
      >Julius</placeName>, and the effeminate Miss Pediatous,<note anchored="yes" n="91" resp="Cruq">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Iulius et fragilis Pediatia.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.8"/>
        </cit> We know not who <placeName key="tgn,2008628">Julius</placeName> was. Pediatius was an
        infamous Roman knight, whom <placeName key="tgn,2399201">Horace</placeName>, for his
        effeminacy, calls Pediatia. Thus Aristophanes calls Cleonymus Cleonyma; Sostratus,
         Sostrata.<bibl n="Aristoph. Cl. 673">(Clouds 673 ff.)</bibl></p>
      </note> and the knave Voranus, come to water upon me, and befoul me. Why should I mention
      every particular? viz. in what manner, speaking alternately with Sagana, the ghosts uttered
      dismal and piercing shrieks; and how by stealth they laid in the earth a wolf's beard, with
      the teeth of a spotted snake; and how a great blaze flamed forth from the waxen image? And how
      I was shocked at the voices and actions of these two furies, a spectator however by no means
      incapable of revenge? For from my cleft body of fig-tree<note anchored="yes" n="92"
       resp="McCaul">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Ficus</foreign>, i. e. I, an image made of the <foreign lang="la"
         >truncus ficulnus</foreign>. The heat made the wood crack with a noise, which put the
        witches to flight.</p>
      </note> wood I uttered a loud noise with as great an explosion as a burst bladder. But they
      ran into the city: and with exceeding laughter and diversion might you have seen Canidia's
      artificial teeth, and Sagana's towering tete of false hair falling off, and the herbs, and the
      enchanted bracelets from her arms. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="9">
     <head>He describes his sufferings from the loquacity of an impertinent fellow.</head>

     <p>I was accidentally going along the Via Sacra, meditating on some trifle or other, as is my
      custom, and totally intent upon it. A certain person, known to me by name only, runs up; and,
      having seized my hand, "How do you do, my dearest fellow?"</p>
     <p>"Tolerably well," say I, "as times go; and I wish you every thing you can desire."</p>
     <p>When he still followed me; "Would you any thing?"<note anchored="yes" n="93"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Numquid vis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.6"/>
        </cit> Donatus tells us in a remark upon a passage in Terence, that it was a polite
        customary manner of speaking among the Romans, that they might not seem to take their leave
        too abruptly, to say at parting, <foreign lang="la">"numquid vis?"</foreign> as in modern
        phrase, "have you any commands?" <quote lang="la">"Abituri, ne id dure facerent,
         &lsquo;numquid vis&rsquo; dicebant his, quibuscum constitissent."</quote></p>
      </note> said I to him.</p>
     <p>But, "You know me," says he: "I am a man of learning."</p>
     <p>"Upon that account," says I: "you will have more of my esteem." Wanting sadly to get away
      from him, sometimes I walked on apace, now and then I stopped, and I whispered something to my
      boy. When the sweat ran down to the bottom of my ankles. 0, said I to myself, Bolanus,<note
       anchored="yes" n="94" resp="McCaul">
       <p>Bolanus was a very irritable person. <placeName key="tgn,2032226">Horace</placeName> then
        pronounces him <cit>
         <quote lang="la">cerebri felicem</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.11"/>
        </cit>; for were he but in this fellow's company, he would break out into a storm of passion
        that would drive him away. It appears more humorous to suppose him a heavy, stupid person,
        so apathetic that not even this fellow would annoy him. Similarly Demea in Terent.
         <placeName key="tgn,2078150">Adelph</placeName>. v. 5, exclaims, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">fortunatus, qui istoc animo sies; &verbar; Ego sentio.</quote>
         <bibl n="Ter. Ad. 5.3"/>
        </cit> Bolanus was a surname of the Vettii derived from Bola, a town of the AEqui.</p>
       <p><quote lang="la">Celebri felicem.</quote> Thus <foreign lang="greek">makari/zw se th=s
         parrhsi/as</foreign>, and <cit>
         <bibl n="Verg. G. 1.277">Virg. Geor. i 277,</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">felices operum dies.</quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> how happy were you in a headpiece!</p>
     <p>Meanwhile he kept prating on any thing that came uppermost, praised the streets, the city;
      and, when I made him no answer; "You want terribly," said he "to get away; I perceived it long
      ago; but you effect nothing. I shall still stick close to you; I shall follow you hence: where
      are you at present bound for?"</p>
     <p>"There is no need for your being carried so much about: I want to see a person, who is
      unknown to you: he lives a great way off across the <placeName key="tgn,1130786"
      >Tiber</placeName>, just by Caesar's gardens."</p>
     <p>"I have nothing to do, and I am not lazy; I will attend you thither." I hang down my ears
      like an ass of surly disposition, when a heavier load than ordinary is put upon his back.</p>
     <p>He begins again: "If I am tolerably acquainted with myself, you will not esteem Viscus or
      Varius as a friend, more than me; for who can write more verses, or in a shorter time than I?
      Who can move his limbs with softer grace [in the dance]? And then I sing, so that even
      Hermogenes may envy."</p>
     <p>Here there was an opportunity of interrupting him. "Have you a mother, [or any] relations
      that are interested in your welfare?"</p>
     <p>"Not one have I; I have buried them all."</p>
     <p>"Happy they! now I remain. Dispatch me: for the fatal moment is at hand, which an old
       <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> sorceress, having shaken her divining
       urn,<note anchored="yes" n="95" resp="Fran">
       <p>The divination was performed in this manner. A number of letters and entire words were
        thrown into an urn and shaken together. When they were well mixed, they were poured out, and
        if any thing intelligible appeared in them, from thence the witch formed her divination and
        answers.</p>
      </note> foretold when I was a boy; &lsquo;This child, neither shall cruel poison, nor the
      hostile sword, nor pleurisy, nor cough, nor the crippling gout destroy: a babbler shall one
      day demolish him; if he be wise, let him avoid talkative people, as soon as he comes to man's
      estate.&rsquo;" <milestone ed="p" n="35" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>One fourth<note anchored="yes" n="96" resp="TAB">
       <p>The first hour of the day among the Romans answered to our sixth. Martial says the courts
        were open at nine o'clock, <quote lang="la">"exercet raucos tertia causidicos;"</quote> it
        was, therefore, more than an hour after their opening, that <placeName key="tgn,2399200"
         >Horace</placeName> passed by the temple of <placeName key="tgn,1016295"
       >Vesta</placeName>.</p>
      </note> of the day being now passed, we came to <placeName key="tgn,1016295"
      >Vesta</placeName>'s temple; and, as good luck would have it, he was obliged to appear to his
      recognizance; which unless he did, he must have lost his cause.</p>
     <p>"If you love me," said he, "step in here a little."</p>
     <p>"May I die! if I be either able to stand it out,<note anchored="yes" n="97" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Aut valeo stare.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.39"/>
        </cit>
        <placeName key="tgn,2399199">Horace</placeName> uses the law terms, <foreign lang="la"
         >respondere, adesse, stare, rem relinquere.</foreign> The first signifies to appear before
        a judge upon a summons; the second was properly to attend on the person who appeared, and to
        support his cause; the third marks the posture in which he stood, and <foreign lang="la"
         >relinquere causam</foreign> to suffer himself to be non-suited for not appearing.</p>
      </note> or have any knowledge of the civil laws: and besides, I am in a hurry, you know
      whither."</p>
     <p>"I am in doubt what I shall do," said he; "whether desert you or my cause."</p>
     <p>"Me, I beg of you."</p>
     <p>"I will not do it," said he; and began to take the lead of me. I (as it is difficult to
      contend with one's master) follow him.</p>
     <p>"How stands it with Maecenas and you?" Thus he begins his prate again. "He is one of few
       intimates,<note anchored="yes" n="98" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Paucorum hominum.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.44"/>
        </cit> "A man of discernment, who does not converse with the multitude," as in Terence,
         <quote lang="la">"hic homo est perpaucorum hominum."</quote>
        <placeName key="tgn,2648579">Scipio</placeName> having engaged three or four friends to sup
        with him, and intending to make some others, who came to see him, stay with him, Pontius
        whispered him, "Consider, <placeName key="tgn,2648579">Scipio</placeName>, what you are
        doing; this is a delicate fish, <foreign lang="la">paucorum hominum</foreign>, and does not
        love a great deal of company."</p>
      </note> and of a very wise way of thinking. No man ever made use of opportunity with more
      cleverness. You should have a powerful assistant,<note anchored="yes" n="99"
       resp="ed. Dubl., Fran">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Adiutor</foreign> was a person who assisted a player either with his
        voice or action, but in what manner is to us inconceivable, as we have nothing like it in
        our stage. <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ferre secundas</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.46"/>
        </cit> may be somewhat better explained by a passage in <placeName key="tgn,2031372"
        >Cicero</placeName>: "He will not exert his utmost eloquence, but consult your honor and
        reputation, by lowering his own abilities and raising yours. Thus we see among the Grecian
        actors, that he who plays the second or third part, conceals his own power, that the
        principal player may appear to the best advantage."</p>
       <p>Our impertinent therefore promises <placeName key="tgn,2028398">Horace</placeName>, that
        far from any design of supplanting him in the favor of Maecenas, he will be contented to
        play the second part, and use his utmost abilities to raise our poet's character, as a
        principal actor. The reader may turn to the note on the twelfth line in the eighteenth
        epistle.</p>
      </note> who could play an underpart, if you were disposed to recommend this man; may I perish,
      if you should not supplant all the rest!"</p>
     <p>"We do not live there in the manner you imagine; there is not a house that is freer or more
      remote from evils of this nature. It is never of any disservice to me, that any particular
      person is wealthier or a better scholar than I am: every individual has his proper place."</p>
     <p>"You tell me a marvelous thing, scarcely credible."</p>
     <p>"But it is even so."</p>
     <p>"You the more inflame my desires to be near his person."</p>
     <p>"You need only be inclined to it: such is your merit, you will accomplish it: and he is
      capable of being won;<note anchored="yes" n="100" resp="Bent">
       <p>The poet says Maecenas was naturally easy to be gained, but that a sense of his own
        weakness obligred him to guard himself against the first addresses of a stranger. <foreign
         lang="la">Eo</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">ideo difficiles aditus primos habet, quia est
         qui vinci possit</foreign> as in Terence, <quote lang="la">eo tibi videtur foedus, quia
         vestem illam non habet.</quote></p>
      </note> and on that account the first access to him he makes difficult."</p>
     <p>"I will not be wanting to myself; I will corrupt his servants with presents; if I am
      excluded to-day, I will not desist; I will seek opportunities; I will meet him in the public
      streets; I will wait upon him home. Life allows nothing to mortals without great labor."</p>
     <p>While he was running on at this rate, lo! Fuscus Aristius comes up, a dear friend of mine,
      and one who knows the fellow well. We make a stop.</p>
     <p>"Whence come you? whither are you going?" he asks and answers. I began to twitch him [by the
      elbow], and to take hold of his arms [that were affectedly] passive, nodding and distorting my
      eyes, that he might rescue me. Cruelly arch he laughs, and pretends not to take the hint:
      anger galled my liver.</p>
     <p>"Certainly," [said I, "Fuscus,] you said that you wanted to communicate something to me in
      private."</p>
     <p>"I remember it very well; but will tell it you at a better opportunity: to-day is the
      thirtieth sabbath.<note anchored="yes" n="1" resp="TAB">
       <p>The Jews began their year the first of September, and celebrated their paschal festival
        the fifteenth of April, in the thirtieth week, from whence <placeName key="tgn,2028398"
         >Horace</placeName> calls it <cit>
         <quote lang="la">tricesima sabbata.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.69"/>
        </cit> It continued eight days, of which the two first and two last were observed with so
        much solemnity, that it was not permitted even to talk of business. Augustus, in imitation
        of Julius Caesar, allowed the Jews uncommon privileges.</p>
      </note> Would you affront the circumcised Jews?"</p>
     <p>I reply, "I have no scruple [on that account]."</p>
     <p>"But I have: I am something weaker, one of the multitude. You must forgive me: I will speak
      with you on another occasion." And has this sun arisen so disastrous upon me! The wicked rogue
      runs away, and leaves me under the knife.</p>
     <p>But by luck his adversary met him: and, "Whither are you going, you infamous fellow?" roars
      he with a loud voice: and, "Do you witness the arrest?"<note anchored="yes" n="2" resp="Fran">
       <p>When a man had given bail in a court of justice, if he neglected the time of appearance,
        he might be taken by force before the praetor. But the person who would arrest him was
        obliged, before he used him with violence, to have a witness of his capture, <foreign
         lang="la">antestari.</foreign> This, however, could not be done without the consent of the
        witnesses; he, therefore, willingly offered the captor his ear to touch, who was liable, if
        these forms were not observed, to an action, <foreign lang="la">iniuriarum
        actionem.</foreign> But thieves and people of infamous characters were not treated with so
        much formality. When a fellow in Plautus cries out, "Will you not call a witness before you
        seize me?" <cit>
         <quote lang="la">nonne antestaris?</quote>
         <bibl n="Pl. Per. 4.9">(Persa 747-748)</bibl>
        </cit> he is answered, "What, shall I touch an honest man's ear for such a scoundrel as you
        are?" <placeName key="tgn,2119609">Pliny</placeName> tells us, the lowest part of the ear is
        the seat of memory, from whence came this form of their laws.</p>
      </note></p>
     <p>I assent.<note anchored="yes" n="3" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Oppono auriculam.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.9.77"/>
        </cit> Such was the law term, which our poet very willingly pronounced, to signify the
        consent of the witness.</p>
      </note> He hurries him into court: there is a great clamor on both sides, a mob from all
      parts. Thus Apollo preserved me.<note anchored="yes" n="4" resp="McCaul">
       <p><placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> ascribes his rescue from the intruder to
        Apollo, as the patron of poets. Perhaps he alludes to the statue of that god, which was in
        the forum, where the courts were held, and as it was a law proceeding that saved him from
        the <foreign lang="la">garrulus</foreign>, he ascribes his preservation to the god, that
        from his vicinity to the courts, was called <quote lang="la">iuris peritus.</quote>
        <bibl n="Juv. 1.113">Juven. i. 113.</bibl> Orellius considers reference to be made to
        Apollo, <foreign lang="greek">a)lecika/kos</foreign> or <foreign lang="greek"
        >a)potropai=os</foreign>, and that the passage is founded on <cit>
         <bibl n="Hom. Il. 20.443">Il. 20. 443</bibl>
         <quote lang="greek">to\n d' e)ch/rpacen *)apo/llw</quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note>
     </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="10">
     <head>He supports the judgment which he had before given of Lucilius, and intersperses some
      excellent precepts for the writing of Satire.</head>

     <p>To be sure I did say, that the verses of Lucilius<note anchored="yes" n="5" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Lucilius had his numerous admirers in <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, who
        were greatly disobliged by the freedom with which our poet had treated him in his fourth
        Satire. <persName>Horace</persName> was determined to support his own
        judgment, and instead of making an apology, confirms what he had said, with his utmost force
        and address. Respecting the eight spurious verses usually prefixed to this satire, see
        Orelli's Excursus. The verses are as follows: <quote lang="la">
         <lg type="hexameter">
          <l>lucili, quam sis mendosus, teste catone,</l>
          <l>defensore tuo, pervincam, qui male factos</l>
          <l>emendare parat versus, hoc lenius ille,</l>
          <l>quo melior vir et est longe subtilior illo,</l>
          <l>qui multum puer et loris et funibus udis</l>
          <l>exoratus, ut esset, opem qui ferre poetis</l>
          <l>antiquis posset contra fastidia nostra,</l>
          <l>grammaticorum equitum doctissimus. ut redeam illuc:</l>
         </lg>
        </quote></p>
      </note> did not run smoothly. Who is so foolish an admirer of Lucilius, that he would not own
      this? But the same writer is applauded in the same Satire,<note anchored="yes" n="6"
       resp="TAB">
       <p>Cf. <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.4">Sat. 4.</bibl></p>
      </note> on account of his having lashed the town with great humor. Nevertheless granting him
      this, I will not therefore give up the other [considerations]; for at that rate I might even
      admire the farces of Laberius,<note anchored="yes" n="7" resp="Fran">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Mimi</foreign> were farces written purely for diversion and laughing.
        Decimus Laberius was made a Roman knight by Julius Caesar. He had long maintained the first
        character in this kind of writing, but Publius Syrus at last became his rival, and carried
        off all the applause of the theater.</p>
      </note> as fine poems. Hence it is by no means sufficient to make an auditor grin with
      laughter: and yet there is some degree of merit even in this. There is need of conciseness
      that the sentence may run, and not embarrass itself with verbiage, that overloads the sated
      ear; and sometimes a grave, frequently jocose style is necessary, supporting the character one
      while of the orator, and [at another] of the poet, now and then that of a graceful rallier
      that curbs the force of his pleasantry and weakens it on purpose. For ridicule often decides
      matters of importance more effectually and in a better manner, than severity. Those poets by
      whom the ancient comedy was written, stood upon this [foundation], and in this are they worthy
      of imitation: whom neither the smooth-faced Hermogenes ever read, nor that baboon who is
      skilled in nothing but singing [the wanton compositions of] Calvus and Catullus.</p>
     <p>But [Lucilius, say they,] did a great thing, when he intermixed Greek words with Latin. O
      late-learned dunces! What! do you think that arduous and admirable, which was done by Pitholeo
      the Rhodian? But [still they cry] the style elegantly composed of both tongues is the more
      pleasant, as if Falernian wine is mixed with Chian. When you make verses, I ask you this
      question; were you to undertake the difficult cause of the accused Petillius, would you (for
      instance), forgetful of your country and your father, while Pedius,<note anchored="yes" n="8"
       resp="Watson">
       <p>Pedius. This is, without doubt, the son of that Q. Pedius whom Julius Caesar made heir to
        the fourth part of his estate, and who was chosen consul with Octavius, in room of Hirtius
        and Pansa.</p>
      </note> Poplicola, and Corvinus'<note anchored="yes" n="9" resp="Watson">
       <p>Corvinus. V. Messala Corvinus, no less distinguished by his eloquence than by his noble
        birth. He was descended from the famed Valerius Poplicola</p>
      </note> sweat through their causes in Latin, choose to intermix words borrowed from abroad,
      like the double-tongued Canusinian.<note anchored="yes" n="10" resp="Fran">
       <p><placeName key="tgn,7004111">Canusium</placeName> was built by Diomede. Its inhabitants,
        originally Greeks, had preserved many words of their first language, which being mixed with
        Latin, made a ridiculous, disagreeable jargon. <placeName key="tgn,2072913"
        >Virgil</placeName> for the same reason, calls the Tyrians, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Tyriosque bilingues.</quote>
         <bibl n="Verg. A. 1.661">(Aen. 1.661)</bibl>
        </cit></p>
      </note> And as for myself, who was born on this side the water, when.I was about making Greek
      verses; Romulus appearing to me after midnight, when dreams are true, forbade me in words to
      this effect; "You could not be guilty of more madness by carrying timber into a wood, than by
      desiring to throng in among the great crowds of Grecian writers."</p>
     <p>While bombastical Alpinus<note anchored="yes" n="11" resp="TAB">
       <p>Alpinus. The most probable conjectures induce us to believe, that Horace means Furius
        Bibaculus, a poet of some reputation, and not without merit. He describes him in another
        Satire <cit>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.40">(2.5.40)</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">pingui tentus omaso</quote>
        </cit>, and here he calls him <foreign lang="la">turgidus</foreign>, not only from the
        fatness of his person but the flatulency of his style. The surname of Alpinus marks his
        being born among the Gauls, who lived on the <placeName key="tgn,2110311">Alps</placeName>;
        or, as Dr. Bentley pleasantly understands it, from a famous line, which our poet laughs at
        in another place: <quote lang="la">"Jupiter hibernas cana nive conspuit Alpes."</quote>
        <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Iugulat dum Memnona</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.10.36"/>
        </cit> is a tone and style of bombast in the true spirit of ridicule.</p>
      </note> murders Memnon, and while he deforms the muddy source of the <placeName
       key="tgn,7012611">Rhine</placeName>, I amuse myself with these satires; which can neither be
      recited in the temple<note anchored="yes" n="12" resp="ed. Dubl&gt;">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Quae nec in Aede sonent.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.10.38"/>
        </cit> The commentator tells that Augustus appointed five judges, of whom Metius Tarpa was
        one, to distribute poetical prizes, and determine what plays should be presented on the
        stage. Vossius believes they were established in imitation of the Sicilians and Athenians.
        Mr. Dacier thinks they were continued under the reign of Domitian.</p>
      </note> [of Apollo], as contesting for the prize when Tarpa presides as judge, nor can have a
      run over and over again represented in the theaters. You, O Fundanius,<note anchored="yes"
       n="13" resp="Watson">
       <p>Fundanius. He is known only by this elogium of Horace. This passage refers to the <bibl
         n="Ter. An.">Andria</bibl> of Terence, where Chremes is deceived by the artifices of
       Davus.</p>
      </note> of all men breathing, are the most capable of prattling tales in a comic vein, how an
      artful courtesan and a Davus impose upon an old Chremes: Pollio sings the actions of kings in
       iambic<note anchored="yes" n="14" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Pede ter percusso.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 1.10.43"/>
        </cit> The tragic Iambics had but three measures, each measure having two feet, from whence
        they were sometimes called <foreign lang="la">senarii</foreign>, and sometimes <foreign
         lang="la">trimetra.</foreign></p>
      </note> measure; the sublime Varius composes the manly epic, in a manner that no one can
      equal: to <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName> the Muses, delighting in rural
      scenes, have granted the delicate and the elegant. It was this kind [of satiric writing], the
      Aticinian Varro and some others having attempted it without success, in which I may have some
      slight merit, inferior to the inventor: nor would I presume to pull off the [laurel] crown
      placed upon his brow with great applause. <milestone ed="p" n="50" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>But I said that he flowed muddily, frequently indeed bearing along more things which ought
      to be taken away than left. Be it so; do you, who are a scholar, find no fault with any thing
      in mighty Homer, I pray? Does the facetious Lucilius make no alterations in the tragedies of
      Accius? Does not he ridicule many of Ennius' verses, which are too light for the gravity [of
      the subject]? When he speaks of himself by no means as superior to what he blames. What should
      hinder me likewise, when I am reading the works of Lucilius, from inquiring whether it be his
      [genius], or the difficult nature of his subject, that will not suffer his verses to be more
      finished, and to run more smoothly than if some one, thinking it sufficient to conclude a
      something of six feet, be fond of writing two hundred verses before he eats, and as many after
      supper? Such was the genius of the Tuscan Cassius, more impetuous than a rapid river; who, as
      it is reported, was burned [at the funeral pile] with his own books<note anchored="yes" n="15"
       resp="McCaul">
       <p>The funeral piles on which dead bodies were burned were made of wood. Cassius had written
        so much, that <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> sportively gives it as a
        rumor, that his books formed his funeral pile. MCCAUL.</p>
      </note> and papers. Let it be allowed, I say, that Lucilius was a humorous and polite writer;
      that he was also more correct than [Ennius], the author<note anchored="yes" n="16" resp="TAB">
       <p>There is a great variation in the interpretation of this passage. They may be found
        collected in MCCAUL's notes. </p>
      </note> of a kind of poetry [not yet] well cultivated, nor attempted by the Greeks, and [more
      correct likewise] than the tribe of our old poets: but yet he, if he had been brought down by
      the Fates to this age of ours, would have retrenched a great deal from his writings: he would
      have pruned off every thing that transgressed the limits of perfection; and, in the
      composition of verses, would often have scratched his head, and bit his nails to the quick.</p>
     <p>You that intend to write what is worthy to be read more than once, blot frequently: and take
      no pains to make the multitude admire you, content with a few [judicious] readers. What, would
      you be such a fool as to be ambitious that your verses should be taught in petty schools? That
      is not my case. It is enough for me, that the knight [Maecenas] applauds: as the courageous
      actress, Arbuscula, expressed herself, in contempt of the rest of the audience, when she was
      hissed [by the populace]. What, shall that grubworm Pantilius<note anchored="yes" n="17"
       resp="watson">
       <p>Pantilius. A buffoon, and a great enemy of Horace, whom he calls Cimex, an insect, out of
        contempt. Fannius is the same of whom he speaks in <bibl n="Hor. S. 4">Satire iv.</bibl></p>
      </note> have any effect upon me? Or can it vex me, that Demetrius carps at me behind my back?
      or because the trifler Fannius, that hanger-on to Hermogenes Tigellius, attempts to hurt me?
      May Plotius and Varius, Maecenas and <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName>, Valgius
      and Octavius<note anchored="yes" n="18" resp="TAB">
       <p>Octavius. An excellent poet and historian. The Visci were two brothers, and both senators.
        Bibulus was the son of him that had been consul in 695, and Servius the son of Servius
        Sulpicius, who corresponded with <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>. Furnius
        was consul in the year <date value="-16">737</date>, and equally master of the pen and the
        sword.</p>
      </note> approve these Satires, and the excellent Fuscus likewise; and I could wish that both
      the Visci would join in their commendations: ambition apart, I may mention you, O Pollio: you
      also, Messala, together with your brother; and at the same time, you, Bibulus and Servius; and
      along with these you, candid Furnius; many others whom, though men of learning and my friends,
      I purposely omit &mdash; to whom I could wish these Satires, such as they are, may give
      satisfaction; and I should be chagrined, if they pleased in a degree below my expectation.
      You, Demetrius, and you, Tigellius, I bid lament among the forms of your female pupils.</p>
     <p>Go, boy, and instantly annex this Satire to the end of my book. </p>
    </div2>
   </div1>
   <div1 type="book" n="2">
    <div2 type="poem" n="1">
     <head>He supposes himself to consult with Trebatius, whether he should desist from writing
      satires, or not.</head>

     <p>THERE are some persons to whom I seem too severe in [the writing of] satire, and to carry it
      beyond proper bounds:<note anchored="yes" n="1" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ultra legem.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.1.1"/>
        </cit> The laws of the twelve tables punished these poetical slanderers with death; but they
        were grown obsolete, and had lost great part of their vigor, when they were renewed by
        Augustus.</p>
      </note> another set are of opinion, that all I have written is nerveless, and that a thousand
      verses like mine may be spun out in a day. Trebatius,<note anchored="yes" n="2" resp="Watson">
       <p>Trebatius. This is C. Trebatius Testa, the most celebrated lawyer of that age, as is
        evident from the letters which <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> wrote to him.
        He was greatly in favor both with Julius Caesar and Augustus. As he accompanied the first in
        his wars in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, thirty years before this Satire
        was written, he must, by this time, have been of an advanced age. <placeName
         key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> applies to him as one of great authority, on account
        of his age and skill in the law. He was further a good judge of raillery, and had often used
        it with delicacy and success.</p>
      </note> give me your advice, what I shall do. Be quiet. I should not make, you say, verses at
      all. I do say so. May I be hanged, if that would not be best: but I can not sleep. Let those,
      who want sound sleep, anointed swim thrice across the <placeName key="tgn,1130786"
      >Tiber</placeName>: and have their clay well moistened with wine over-night. Or, if such a
      great love of scribbling hurries you on, venture to celebrate the achievements of the
      invincible Caesar, certain of bearing off ample rewards for your pains.</p>
     <p>Desirous I am, my good father, [to do this,] but my strength fails me, nor can any one
      describe the troops bristled with spears, nor the Gauls<note anchored="yes" n="3" resp="San">
       <p>The Gauls of Aquitain having rebelled 726, Octavius sent Messala, with the title of
        governor of the province, to reduce them to his obedience. He conquered them in the year
        following, and had the honor of a triumph the 25th of September.</p>
      </note> dying on their shivered darts, nor the wounded Parthian falling from his horse.
      Nevertheless you may describe him just and brave, as the wise Lucilius did Scipio. I will not
      be wanting to myself, when an opportunity presents itself: no verses of Horace's, unless
      well-timed, will gain the attention of Caesar; whom, [like a generous steed,] if you stroke
      awkwardly, he will kick back upon you, being at all quarters on his guard. How much better
      would this be, than to wound with severe satire Pantolabus the buffoon, and the rake
      Nomentanus! when every body is afraid for himself, [lest he should be the next,] and hates
      you, though he is not meddled with. What shall I do? Milonius falls a dancing the moment he
      becomes light-headed and warm, and the candles appear multiplied. Castor delights in
      horsemanship: and he, who sprang from the same egg, in boxing. As many thousands of people [as
      there are in the world], so many different inclinations are there. It delights me to combine
      words in meter, after the manner of Lucilius, a better man than both of us.<note
       anchored="yes" n="4" resp="Rutgers">
       <p>When the Romans mentioned a man of great reputation, and whose example had a sort of
        authority, their usual expression in conversation. was, Who is far better, and more valuable
        than you or me.</p>
      </note> He long ago communicated his secrets to his books, as to faithful friends: never
      having recourse elsewhere, whether things went well or ill with him: whence it happens, that
      the whole life of this old [poet] is as open to the view, as if it had been painted on a
      votive tablet. His example I follow, though in doubt whether I am a Lucanian or an Apulian;
      for the Venusinian farmers plow upon the boundaries of both countries, who (as the ancient
      tradition has it) were sent, on the expulsion of the Samnites, for this purpose, that the
      enemy might not make incursions on the Romans, through a vacant [unguarded frontier]: or lest
      the Apulian nation, or the fierce Lucanian, should make an invasion. But this pen of mine
      shall not willfully attack any man breathing, and shall defend me like a sword that is
      sheathed in the scabbard: which why should I attempt to draw, [while I am] safe from hostile
      villains? 0 Jupiter, father and sovereign, may my weapon laid aside wear away with rust, and
      may no one injure me, who am desirous of peace? But that man who shall provoke me (I give
      notice, that it is better not to touch me) shall weep [his folly], and as a notorious
      character shall be sung through all the streets of <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
      >Rome</placeName>. <milestone ed="p" n="47" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Cervius,<note anchored="yes" n="5" resp="Torr">
       <p>A criminal was acquitted or condemned by the number of votes, which the judges threw into
        a judiciary urn. Virgil tells us this custom was observed among the dead, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">quaesitor Minos urnam movet.</quote>
         <bibl n="Verg. A. 6.432">(Aen. 6.432")</bibl>
        </cit></p>
      </note> when he is offended, threatens one with the laws and the [judiciary] urn; Canidia,
      Albutius' poison to those with whom she is at enmity; Turius [threatens] great damages, if you
      contest any thing while he is judge. How every animal<note anchored="yes" n="6"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName>'s weapon is satire. This he will use
        against his enemies, just as every one, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">quo valet, suspectos terret</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.1.50"/>
        </cit>, and according to the dictates of nature, which prompt her creatures to make use of
        the arms which she has given them, i. e. <quote lang="la">ne longum faciam</quote>, he will
        write.</p>
       <p><quote lang="la">Mirum</quote>, etc. Ironically said, for it is not <cit>
         <quote lang="la">mirum ut neque calce lupus quemquam neque dente petat bos</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.1.55"/>
        </cit>, for <cit>
         <quote lang="la">dente lupus, cornu taurus petit</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.1.52"/>
        </cit>. <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName> means that Scaeva's not polluting
        his right hand with the blood of his mother is no more wonderful than that a wolf does not
        attack a person <foreign lang="la">calce</foreign>, or an ox, <foreign lang="la"
        >dente</foreign>. Bentley's conjecture <foreign lang="la">mirum si</foreign> is specious.
        Similarly we have <cit>
         <bibl n="Ter. An. 4.4">Terent. Andr. iv. 4, 16;</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">Mirum vero, impudentur mulier si facit meretrix.</quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> terrifies those whom he suspects, with that in which he is most powerful, and how
      strong natural instinct commands this, thus infer with me.&mdash;The wolf attacks with his
      teeth, the bull with his horns. From what principle is this, if not a suggestion from within?
      Intrust that debauchee Scaeva with the custody of his ancient mother; his pious hand will
      commit no outrage. A wonder indeed! just as the wolf does not attack any one with his hoof,
      nor the bull with his teeth; but the deadly hemlock in the poisoned honey will take off the
      old dame.</p>
     <p>That I may not be tedious, whether a placid old age awaits me, or whether death now hovers
      about me with his sable wings; rich or poor, at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>
      or (if fortune should so order it) an exile abroad; whatever be the complexion of my life, I
      will write. O my child, I fear you can not be long-lived; and that some creature of the great
      ones will strike you with the cold of death.<note anchored="yes" n="7" resp="Orelli">
       <p>i. e. "lest some one of your powerful friends conceive a coldness toward you, and deprive
        you of his friendship." So <cit>
         <bibl n="Pers. 1.107">Persius i. 107,</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">
          <lg type="hexameter">
           <l>Sed quid opus teneras mordaci radere vero</l>
           <l>Auriculas? Vide sis ne maiorum tibi forte</l>
           <l>Limina et rigescunt.</l>
          </lg>
         </quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> What? when Lucilius had the courage to be the first in composing verses after this
      manner, and to pull off that mask,<note anchored="yes" n="8" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Detrahere pellem.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.1.64"/>
        </cit> A figurative expression taken from the stage. The ancient masks were of skins.</p>
      </note> by means of which each man strutted in public view with a fair outside, though foul
      within; was Laelius, and he who derived a well-deserved title from the destruction of
       <placeName key="tgn,7016143">Carthage</placeName>, offended at his wit, or were they hurt at
      Metellus being lashed, or <placeName key="tgn,2059602">Lupus</placeName> covered over with his
      lampoons? But he took to task the heads of the people, and the people themselves, class by
       class;<note anchored="yes" n="9" resp="Watson">
       <p>The great men, and people of whatever tribe. It is plain from what remains to us of
        Lucilius, that he did not spare the great. Besides Metellus and <placeName key="tgn,2059602"
         >Lupus</placeName> already mentioned, he attacked also Mutius Scaevola, Titus Albutius,
        Torquatus, Marcus Carbo, Lucius Tubulus, Publius Gallonins, Caius Cassius, Lucius Cotta,
        Clodius Asellus, Quintus Opimius, Nomentanus, Caius Cecilius Index, Trebellius, Publius
        Pavus Tuditanus. And not satisfied with this, he run through all the thirty-five tribes. one
        after another.</p>
      </note> in short, he spared none but virtue and her friends. Yet, when the valorous <placeName
       key="tgn,2081795">Scipio</placeName>, and the mild philosophical Laelius, had withdrawn
      themselves from the crowd and the public scene, they used to divert themselves with him, and
      joke in a free manner, while a few vegetables were boiled [for supper]. Of whatever rank I am,
      though below the estate and wit of Lucilius, yet envy must be obliged to own that I have lived
      well with great men; and, wanting to fasten her tooth upon some weak part, will strike it
      against the solid:<note anchored="yes" n="10" resp="TAB">
       <p>In allusion to the fable of the serpent and the file.</p>
      </note> unless you, learned Trebatius, disapprove of any thing [I have said]. For my part, I
      can not make any objection to this. But however, that forewarned you may be upon your guard,
      lest an ignorance of our sacred laws should bring you into trouble, [be sure of this:] if any
       person<note anchored="yes" n="11" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Si mala condiderit.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.1.82"/>
        </cit> Trebatius with much solemnity cites the laws of the twelve tables as his last
        argument. A lawyer could produce nothing more strong, and <placeName key="tgn,2399200"
         >Horace</placeName> being unable to defend himself by a direct answer, finds a way of
        getting out of the difficulty by playing on the words <foreign lang="la">malum
        carmen</foreign>, and giving them a different sense from what they had in the text of the
        law..</p>
      </note> shall make scandalous verses against a particular man, an action lies, and a sentence.
      Granted, if they are scandalous: but if a man composes good ones, and is praised by such a
      judge as Caesar If a man barks only at him who deserves his invectives, while he himself is
      unblamable? The process will be canceled<note anchored="yes" n="12" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Tabulae</foreign> are the process and information laid before the
        judge, which, says the poet, shall be torn in pieces. Dacier observes, that this line is an
        imitation of Aristophanes, where a father dissuades his son from an excess of wine, by
        representing to him a thousand disorders which it occasions; quarreling, breaking houses
        open. No, says the son, this never happens when we converse with men of honor; for either
        they will satisfy the people whom they have offended, or turn the affair into ridicule, and
        by some happy jest make the judges, and even the prosecutors, laugh. The process is
        dismissed, and you escape without being punished.<bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 1251">(Wasps
         1251ff)</bibl></p>
      </note> with laughter: and you, being dismissed, may depart in peace. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="2">
     <head>On Frugality.</head>

     <p>WHAT and how great is the virtue to live on a little (this is no doctrine of mine, but what
      Ofellus the peasant, a philosopher without rules<note anchored="yes" n="13" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Abnormis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.3"/>
        </cit> "A philosopher without rules." Ofellus was an Epicurean without knowing it, but his
        morality was in a medium between the very rigid and very dissolute followers of that
       sect.</p>
      </note> and of a home-spun<note anchored="yes" n="14" resp="McCaul">
       <p><placeName key="tgn,2040321">Minerva</placeName> presides over spinning, hence this
        proverbial expression for "of a thick thread," i. e. of a coarse texture. Thus <cit>
         <bibl n="Cic. Fam. 9.12">Cic. Ep. Fam. ix. 12,</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">Crasso filo</quote>
        </cit>.</p>
      </note> wit, taught me), learn, my good friends, not among dishes and splendid tables; when
      the eye is dazzled with the vain glare, and the mind, intent upon false appearances, refuses
      [to admit] better things; but here, before dinner, discuss this point with me. Why so? I will
      inform you, if I can. Every corrupted judge examines badly the truth. After hunting the hare,
      or being wearied by an unruly horse, or (if the Roman exercise fatigues you, accustomed to act
      the Greek) whether the swift ball, while eagerness softens and prevents your perceiving the
      severity of the game, or quoits (smite the yielding air with the quoit) when exercise has
      worked off squeamishness, dry and hungry, [then let me see you] despise mean viands; and don't
      drink any thing but Hymettian honey qualified<note anchored="yes" n="15" resp="McCaul">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Diluta.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.16"/>
        </cit> This mixture was called <foreign lang="la">mulsum</foreign>, mead. Ofella says: Don't
        drink any thing but mead made of the best honey and the best wine. <foreign lang="la"
         >Diluere</foreign> is applied to those things which are melted by the addition of fluid.
        Thus <cit>
         <bibl n="Verg. g. 1.341">Virg. Geor. i. 341,</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">Cui tu lacte favos et miti dilue Baccho.</quote>
        </cit> And <cit>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.214">Sat. ii. 3, 214,</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">aceto &verbar; Diluit insignem baccam.</quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> with Falernian wine. Your butler is abroad, and the tempestuous sea preserves the fish
      by its wintery storms: bread and salt will sufficiently appease an importunate stomach. Whence
      do you think this happens? and how is it obtained? The consummate pleasure is not in the
      costly flavor, but in yourself. Do you seek for sauce by sweating. Neither oysters, nor scar,
      nor the far-fetched lagois,<note anchored="yes" n="16" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Lagois.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.22"/>
        </cit> We do not find this word in any other author. It was probably a foreign bird, whose
        flesh tasted and looked like that of a hare; a favorite dish among the Romans. <foreign
         lang="la">Ostrea</foreign> is of two syllables, as in <placeName key="tgn,1015191"
        >Virgil</placeName>, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Bis patriae cecidere manus: quin protenus omnia.</quote>
         <bibl n="Verg. A. 6.33">(Aen. 6.33)</bibl>
        </cit></p>
      </note> can give any pleasure to one bloated and pale through intemperance. Nevertheless, if a
       peacock<note anchored="yes" n="17" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Quintus Hortensius was the first who gave the Romans a taste for peacocks, and it soon
        became so fashionable a dish, that all the people of fortune had it at their tables.
         <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName> very pleasantly says, he had the boldness
        to invite Hirtius to sup with him, even without a peacock. <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Sed vide audaciam, etiam Hirtio coenam dedi sine pavone.</quote>
         <bibl n="Cic. Fam. 9.20.2">(Fam. 9.20)</bibl>
        </cit> M. Aufidius Latro made a prodigious fortune by fattening them for sale.</p>
      </note> were served up, I should hardly be able to prevent your gratifying the palate with
      that, rather than a pullet, since you are prejudiced by the vanities of things; because the
      scarce bird is bought with gold, and displays a fine sight with its painted tail: as if that
      were any thing to the purpose. What, do you eat that plumage, which you extol? or has the bird
      the same beauty when dressed? Since however there is no difference in the meat, in one
      preferably to the other; it is manifest that you are imposed upon by the disparity of their
      appearances. Be it so.</p>
     <p>By what gift are you able to distinguish, whether this lupus, that now opens its jaws before
      us, was taken in the <placeName key="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>, or in the sea? whether it
      was tossed between the bridges, or at the mouth of the Tuscan river? Fool, you praise a
      mullet, that weighs three pounds; which you are obliged to cut into small pieces. Outward
      appearances lead you, I see. To what intent then do you contemn large lupuses? Because truly
      these are by nature bulky, and those very light. A hungry stomach seldom loathes common
      victuals. O that I could see a swingeing mullet extended on a swingeing dish! cries that
      gullet, which is fit for the voracious harpies themselves. But O [say I] ye southern blasts,
      be present to taint the delicacies of the [gluttons]: though the boar and turbot newly taken
      are rank, when surfeiting abundance provokes the sick stomach; and when the sated guttler
      prefers turnips and sharp elecampane. However, all [appearance of] poverty is not quite
      banished from the banquets of our nobles; for there is, even at this day, a place for paltry
      eggs and black olives.<note anchored="yes" n="18" resp="Cruq">
       <p>Olives, intended for the table, were gathered when they began to ripen and turn black.</p>
      </note> And it was not long ago, since the table of Gallonius, the auctioneer, was rendered
      infamous, by having a sturgeon [served up whole upon it]. What? was the sea at that time less
      nutritive of turbots?<note anchored="yes" n="19" resp="Dac">
       <p>The fanciful, fashionable taste is but of short continuance; that of nature is
        unalterable. You are now as fond of turbot as Gallonius was of sturgeon. But were there no
        turbots in his time ? Certainly there were; but no coxcomb had made them fashionable, and
        the praetor decided in favor of sturgeon. Another glutton brought turbots and storks into
        vogue, and perhaps we only wait for a third man of taste to assure us, that a roasted
        cormorant is infinitely more delicious than sturgeons, turbots, or storks.</p>
      </note> The turbot was secure and the stork unmolested in her nest; till the praetorian
       [<placeName key="tgn,2072219">Sempronius</placeName>], the inventor,<note anchored="yes"
       n="20" resp="Torr">
       <p>The storks built their nests in safety until the time of Augustus, when your praetor
        taught you to eat them. Asinius Sempronius, or, according to others, Rutilius Rufus, when
        candidate for the praetorship, entertained the people with a dish of storks. But the people,
        according to an ancient epigram, revenged the death of the poor birds by refusing the
        praetorship to their murderer. From this refusal the poet pleasantly calls him praetor.</p>
      </note> first taught you [to eat them]. Therefore, if any one were to give it out that roasted
      cormorants are delicious, the Roman youth, teachable in depravity, would acquiesce in it.
       <milestone ed="p" n="53" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>In the judgment of Ofellus, a sordid way of living will differ widely from frugal
      simplicity. For it is to no purpose for you to shun that vice [of luxury]; if you perversely
      fly to the contrary extreme. Avidienus, to whom the nickname of Dog is applied with propriety,
      eats olives of five years old, and wild cornels, and can not bear to rack off his wine unless
      it be turned sour, and the smell of his oil you can not endure: which (though clothed in white
      he celebrates the wedding festival,<note anchored="yes" n="21" resp="Torr, San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Repotia</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.60"/>
        </cit> was a festival the day after the nuptials, when they drank and ate whatever remained
        of yesterday's entertainment, <foreign lang="la">quia iterum potaretur.</foreign> The
        construction is remarkable, <quote lang="la">alios dierum festos</quote>, for <foreign
         lang="la">alios qui ex diebus festi sunt</foreign>. <quote lang="la">Albatus</quote>,
        white, was usually the color of the Roman robe even at funeral feasts. <quote lang="la"
        >Ipse</quote> is a circumstance that strongly marks the avarice of Avidienus. Afraid that
        his guests or his servants should be too profuse of his oil, he pours it himself. The poet
        tells us, his bottle was of two pounds weight, as if it were his whole store, although he
        was extremely rich; and the vessel was of horn, that it might last a long time. All these
        particulars are in character.</p>
      </note> his birth-day, or any other festal days) he pours out himself by little and little
      from a horn cruet, that holds two pounds, upon his cabbage, [but at the same time] is lavish
      enough of his old vinegar.</p>
     <p>What manner of living therefore shall the wise man put in practice, and which of these
      examples shall he copy? On one side the wolf presses on, and the dog on the other, as the
      saying is. A person will be accounted decent, if he offends not by sordidness, and is not
      despicable through either extreme of conduct. Such a man will not, after the example of old
      Albutius, be savage while he assigns to his servants their respective offices; nor, like
      simple Naevius, will he offer greasy water to his company: for this too is a great fault.</p>
     <p>Now learn what and how great benefits a temperate diet will bring along with it. In the
      first place, you will enjoy good health; for you may believe how detrimental a diversity of
      things is to any man, when you recollect that sort of food, which by its simplicity sat so
      well upon your stomach some time ago. But, when you have once mixed boiled and roast together,
      thrushes and shell-fish; the sweet juices will turn to bile, and the thick phlegm will bring a
      jarring upon the stomach. Do not you see, how pale each guest rises from a perplexing variety
      of dishes at an entertainment. Beside this, the body, overloaded with the debauch of
      yesterday, depresses the mind along with it, and dashes to the earth that portion of the
      divine spirit.<note anchored="yes" n="22" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Divinae particulam aurae.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.79"/>
        </cit> To raise the nobleness of the mind, <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName>
        has borrowed the language of Plato; who says, that it is a portion of the universal soul of
        the world, that is, of the divinity himself.</p>
      </note> Another man, as soon as he has taken a quick repast, and rendered up his limbs to
      repose, rises vigorous to the duties of his calling. However, he may sometimes have recourse
      to better cheer; whether the returning year shall bring on a festival, or if he have a mind to
      refresh his impaired body; and when years shall approach, and feeble age require to be used
      more tenderly. But as for you, if a troublesome habit of body, or creeping old age, should
      come upon you, what addition can be made to that soft indulgence, which you, now in youth and
      in health, anticipate? <milestone ed="p" n="89" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Our ancestors praised a boar when it was stale: not because they had no noses; but with this
      view, I suppose, that a visitor coming later than ordinary [might partake of it], though a
      little musty, rather than the voracious master should devour it all himself while sweet. I
      wish that the primitive earth had produced me among such heroes as these.</p>
     <p>Have you any regard for reputation, which affects the human ear more agreeably than music?
      Great turbots and dishes bring great disgrace along with them, together with expense. Add to
      this, that your relations and neighbors will be exasperated at you, while you will be at
      enmity with yourself and desirous of death in vain, since you will not in your poverty have
      three farthings left to purchase a rope withal. Trausius, you say, may with justice be called
      to account in such language as this; but I possess an ample revenue, and wealth sufficient for
      three potentates. Why then have you no better method of expending your superfluities? Why is
      any man, undeserving [of distressed circumstances], in want, while you abound? How comes it to
      pass, that the ancient temples of the gods are falling to ruin? Why do not you, wretch that
      you are, bestow something on your dear country, out of so vast a hoard? What, will matters
      always go well with you alone? 0 thou, that hereafter shalt be the great derision of thine
      enemies! which of the two shall depend upon himself in exigences with most certainty? He who
      has used his mind and high-swollen body to redundancies; or he who, contented with a little
      and provident for the future, like a wise man in time of peace, shall make the necessary
      preparations for war?</p>
     <p>That you may the more readily give credit to these things: I myself, when a little boy, took
      notice that this Ofellus did not use his unencumbered estate more profusely, than he does now
      it is reduced. You may see the sturdy husbandman laboring for hire in the land [once his own,
      but now] assigned [to others],<note anchored="yes" n="23" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Metato in agello.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.114"/>
        </cit> Ofellus was involved in the same disgrace and ruin as <placeName key="tgn,1015191"
         >Virgil</placeName>, Tibullus, and Propertius. Their estates were given by Octavius to the
        veterans who had served against <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName> and Cassius
        in the battle of <placeName key="tgn,2119567">Philippi</placeName>. That of Ofellus was
        given to Umbrenus, who hired its former master to till the ground for him, <quote lang="la"
         >mercede colonum</quote>. As each soldier had a certain number of acres, the land was
        measured, <quote lang="la">metato agello</quote>, before it was divided.</p>
      </note> with his cattle and children, talking to this effect; I never ventured to eat any
      thing on a work-day except pot-herbs, with a hock of smoke-dried bacon. And when a friend came
      to visit me after a long absence, or a neighbor, an acceptable guest to me resting from work
      on account of the rain, we lived well; not on fishes fetched from the city, but on a pullet
      and a kid: then a dried grape, and a nut, with a large fig,<note anchored="yes" n="24"
       resp="Turn, McCaul, Wheeler">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Duplice</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.2.122"/>
        </cit>, a kind of large fig, called Marisca; or <foreign lang="la">bifida</foreign>; or figs
        were split into two parts, and when dried, served up <foreign lang="la">mensis
        secundis</foreign>. The last is proved to be the correct interpretation from <cit>
         <bibl>Pallad. R. R. iv. 10, 36:</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">Subinde ficus, sicut est divisa, vertatur, ut ficorum coria siccentur et
          pulpae tunc duplicate in cistellis serventur aut loculis.</quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> set off our second course. After this, it was our diversion to have no other
      regulation in our cups, save that against drinking to excess:<note anchored="yes" n="25"
       resp="Turn">
       <p>It was customary with the Romans to appoint some person <foreign lang="la">magister
         bibendi</foreign>, who directed the number of cups to be taken, and the toasts, etc. Ofella
        says there was no such person appointed, but that the only president that they had at their
        table was <foreign lang="la">culpa</foreign>, i. e. "excess." Each person took as much as he
        pleased, restricted only by the feeling that excess was culpable. The ancients had a
         <foreign lang="la">ludus</foreign>, which was intended to prevent the intoxication that
        might arise from being obliged to obey the <foreign lang="la">magister bibendi</foreign> in
        taking the number of cups which he directed. The person who (<foreign lang="la">aliqua in re
         peccarat</foreign>) violated any of the convivial laws or customs, was punished by being
        obliged to drink a cupful, <foreign lang="la">poculo multabatur</foreign>, so that as no one
        drank but those who committed some breach of the laws, <foreign lang="la">bibere poenae et
         dedecoris esset, non invitationis aut magisterii</foreign>. Thus <foreign lang="la"
        >culpa</foreign> was <foreign lang="la">magistra bibendi</foreign>.</p>
      </note> then <placeName key="tgn,2068435">Ceres</placeName> worshiped [with a libation], that
      the corn might arise in lofty stems, smoothed with wine the melancholy of the contracted brow.
      Let fortune rage, and stir up new tumults: what can she do more to impair my estate? How much
      more savingly have either I lived, or how much less neatly have you gone, my children, since
      this new possessor came? For nature has appointed to be lord of this earthly property, neither
      him, nor me, nor any one. He drove us out: either iniquity or ignorance in the quirks of the
      law shall [do the same by] him: certainly in the end his long-lived heir shall expel him. Now
      this field under the denomination of Umbrenus', lately it was Ofellus', the perpetual property
      of no man; for it turns to my use one while, and by and by to that of another. Wherefore, live
      undaunted; and oppose gallant breasts against the strokes of adversity. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="3">
     <head>Damasippus, in a conversation with <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName>,
      proves this paradox of the Stoic philosophy, that most men are actually mad.</head>

     <p>You write so seldom, as not to call for parchment four times in the year, busied in
      reforming your writings, yet are you angry with yourself, that indulging in wine and sleep you
      produce nothing worthy to be the subject of conversation. What will be the consequence? But
      you took refuge here, it seems, at the very celebration of the Saturnalia, out of sobriety.
      Dictate therefore something worthy of your promises: begin. There is nothing. The pens are
      found fault with to no purpose, and the harmless wall, which must have been built under the
      displeasure of gods and poets, suffers [to no end]. But you had the look of one that
      threatened many and excellent things, when once your villa had received you, free from
      employment, under its warm roof. To what purpose was it to stow Plato upon Menander? Eupolis,
      Archilochus? For what end did you bring abroad such companions? What are you setting about
      appeasing envy by deserting virtue? Wretch, you will be despised. That guilty Siren, Sloth,
      must be avoided; or whatever acquisitions you have made in the better part of your life, must
      with equanimity be given up. May the gods and goddesses, O Damasippus, present you with a
      barber for your sound advice! But by what means did you get so well acquainted with me? Since
      all my fortunes were dissipated at the middle of the Exchange,<note anchored="yes" n="26"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>The name of Janus was sometimes given to those great arcades which crossed the streets of
         <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>. Livy tells us there were three of them
        erected in the forum, the middle of which <placeName key="tgn,2028398">Horace</placeName>
        means, and which he distinguishes from the <foreign lang="la">Ianus summus</foreign> and
         <foreign lang="la">Ianus imus.</foreign></p>
      </note> detached from all business of my own, I mind that of other people. For formerly I used
      to take a delight in inquiring, in what vase the crafty Sisyphus might have washed his feet;
      what was carved in an unworkmanlike manner, and what more roughly cast than it ought to be;
      being a connoisseur, I offered a hundred thousand sesterces for such a statue; I was the only
      man who knew how to purchase gardens and fine seats to the best advantage: whence the crowded
      ways gave me the surname of Mercurial.<note anchored="yes" n="27" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Mercuriale.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.25"/>
        </cit> Damasippus, ever in character, boasts of a surname, which was given him in raillery.
        Mercury was the god of commerce, and when a man had an uncommon skill in buying and selling,
        he was usually called <foreign lang="la">Mercurialis</foreign>, or favorite of Mercury. A
        number of merchants, in 259, formed themselves into a body with this title, and dedicated a
        temple to the god.</p>
      </note> I know it well; and am amazed at your being cured of that disorder. Why a new disorder
      expelled the old one in a marvelous manner; as it is accustomed to do, when the pain of the
      afflicted side, or the head, is turned upon the stomach; as it is with a man in a lethargy,
      when he turns boxer, and attacks his physician. As long as you do nothing like this, be it
      even as you please. O my good friend, do not deceive yourself; you likewise are mad, and it is
      almost "fools all,"<note anchored="yes" n="28" resp="Fran">
       <p>It was an absurd and ridiculous maxim among the Stoics, that all vicious people were
        equally fools and madmen. <foreign lang="la">Prope</foreign> does not therefore lessen the
        universality of the proposition, for the Latins frequently use <foreign lang="la"
        >prope</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">fere</foreign> for <foreign lang="la"
        >semper</foreign>. In the next line, <foreign lang="la">si</foreign> is not said in any
        manner of doubt, but has the force of an affirmative.</p>
      </note> if what Stertinius insists upon has any truth in it; from whom, being of a teachable
      disposition, I derived these admirable precepts, at the very time when, having given me
      consolation, he ordered me to cultivate a philosophical beard, and to return cheerfully from
      the Fabrician bridge. For when, my affairs being desperate, I had a mind to throw myself into
      the river, having covered my head<note anchored="yes" n="29" resp="San">
       <p>They who devoted themselves to death for the good of their country, covered their heads
        with their robe; and it is pleasant enough to see Damasippus doing that, in an excess of
        despair and folly, which Decius did in a transport of religion and generosity. This image
        gives rise to the raillery of Stertinius, when he says, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">nil verbi, pereas quin fortiter, addam.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.42"/>
        </cit></p>
      </note> [for that purpose], he fortunately<note anchored="yes" n="30" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Dexter.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.38"/>
        </cit> &mdash; <foreign lang="la">Opportunus, propitius.</foreign> The right was by the
        ancients esteemed the lucky side.</p>
      </note> was at my elbow; and [addressed me to this effect]: Take care,<note anchored="yes"
       n="31" resp="San, Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Cave faxis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.38"/>
        </cit> The Stoics despised death when it was honorable or necessary, but to drown himself in
        despair was a villainous death for a philosopher. But the pleasantry of the scene is, that
        Stertinius is going to convince him he is a fool, and then advises him not to do any thing
        which may dishonor his character.</p>
      </note> how you do any thing unworthy of yourself; a false shame, says he, afflicts you, who
      dread to be esteemed a madman among madmen. For in the first place I will inquire, what it is
      to be mad: and, if this distemper be in you exclusively, I will not add a single word, to
      prevent you from dying bravely. <milestone ed="p" n="43" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>The school and sect of Chrysippus<note anchored="yes" n="32" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Chrysippi porticus.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.44"/>
        </cit> The <foreign lang="la">Porticus</foreign> was a famous gallery at <placeName
         key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, where <placeName key="tgn,2786861">Zeno</placeName>
        held his school, which, from the Greek word <foreign lang="greek">sto/a</foreign>, <foreign
         lang="la">Porticus</foreign>, took the name of Stoic.</p>
      </note> deem every man mad, whom vicious folly or the ignorance of truth drives blindly
      forward. This definition takes in whole nations, this even great kings, the wise man [alone]
      excepted. Now learn, why all those, who have fixed the name of madman upon you, are as
      senseless as yourself. As in the woods, where a mistake makes people wander about from the
      proper path; one goes out of the way to the right; another to the left; there is the same
      blunder on both sides, only the illusion is in different directions: in this manner imagine
      yourself mad; so that he, who derides you, hangs his tail,<note anchored="yes" n="33"
       resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Caudam trahat.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.53"/>
        </cit> A metaphor, as the old commentator well observes, taken from a custom among children,
        who tied a tail behind a person whom they had a mind to laugh at.</p>
      </note> not one jot wiser than yourself. There is one species of folly, that dreads things not
      in the least formidable; insomuch that it will complain of fires, and rocks, and rivers
      opposing it in the open plain; there is another different from this, but not a whit more
      approaching to wisdom, that runs headlong through the midst of flames and floods. Let the
      loving mother, the virtuous sister, the father, the wife, together with all the relations [of
      a man possessed with this latter folly], cry out: "Here is a deep ditch; here is a prodigious
      rock; take care of yourself:" he would give no more attention, than did the drunken
       Fufius<note anchored="yes" n="34" resp="TAB">
       <p>Fufius was an actor who, playing the character of Ilione, was supposed to be asleep, when
        the ghost of her son Polydore called to her, "Dear mother, hear me." Fufius, having drunk
        too much, fell really asleep; and Catienus, who played Polydore, having called to him,
        without waking him, the whole house, as if each of them was a Catienus, cried out, "Dear
        mother, hear me," The number of twelve hundred is a pleasant exaggeration. Accius or
        Pacuvius wrote a tragedy on the story of Ilione, and the whole passage is preserved to us in
         <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>: <quote lang="la">
         <lg type="trimeter">
          <l>Mater, te adpello, tu quae somno curam suspensam levas,</l>
          <l>Neque te mei miseret, surge et sepeli natum</l>
          <l>Priusquam ferae volucresque.</l>
         </lg>
        </quote></p>
      </note> some time ago, when he overslept the character of Ilione, twelve hundred Catieni at
      the same time roaring out, O mother, I call you to my aid. I will demonstrate to you, that the
      generality of all mankind are mad in the commission of some folly similar to this.</p>
     <p>Damasippus is mad for purchasing antique statues: but is Damasippus' creditor in his senses?
      Well, suppose I should say to you: receive this,<note anchored="yes" n="35" resp="Dac">
       <p>Stertinius goes on to prove, not only that Damasippus is not a fool, in buying statues,
        since he does not pay for them, but that he would be a fool indeed, to refuse the favor
        which Mercury offers him, in the credulity of Perillius.</p>
      </note> which you can never repay: will you be a madman, if you receive it; or would you be
      more absurd for rejecting a booty, which propitious Mercury offers? Take bond,<note
       anchored="yes" n="36" resp="McCaul">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Scribere</foreign> is sometimes used in the sense "to acknowledge the
        receipt of a sum borrowed"; hence some have supposed that the meaning here is <foreign
         lang="la">scribe te decem sestertia accepisse a Nerio</foreign>, as said by Damasippus'
        creditor. Thus, Nerius is a banker, with whom Damasippus' creditor (Perillius) had lodged
        his money, and in whose books Damasippus, when drawing the ten sestertia, was required to
        acknowledge (<foreign lang="la">scribere</foreign>) the receipt of so much money. But I
        prefer Gesner's interpretation, <foreign lang="la">scribe decem tabulas a Nerio</foreign>,
        i.e. "draw out ten bonds with all the niceties of Nerius," a usurer, well known for his care
        in wording the bonds, so that there could be no evasion.</p>
      </note> like the banker Nerius, for ten thousand sesterces; it will not signify: add the forms
      of Cicuta,<note anchored="yes" n="37" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Cicuta was an old notary, who knew too well the practice of bonds, to neglect any clauses
        or forms, capable of finding these engagements. Such is the force of <cit>
         <quote lang="la">nodosus</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.70"/>
        </cit>. <foreign lang="la">Tabulae</foreign> are the bonds or contracts, from whence
        notaries were called <foreign lang="la">tabularii</foreign>.</p>
      </note> so versed in the knotty points of law: add a thousand obligations: yet this wicked
      Proteus will evade all these ties. When you shall drag him to justice, laughing as if his
      cheeks were none of his own;<note anchored="yes" n="38" resp="TAB">
       <p>People are not usually too careful of what belongs to others, from whence this kind of
        proverbial expression, "laughing with another man's cheeks." Dacier very well observes, that
        our poet hath translated it from Homer, when he says of Penelope's lovers, <cit>
         <quote lang="greek">*oi)/ d' h)/dh gnaqmoi=si gelw/wn a)llori/oisi</quote>
         <bibl n="Hom. Od. 20.346">ODYSS. lib. xx. v. 346.</bibl>
        </cit></p>
      </note> he will be transformed into a boar, sometimes into a bird, sometimes into a stone, and
      when he pleases into a tree. If to conduct one's affairs badly be the part of a the madman;
      and the reverse, that of a man well in his senses; brain of Perillius (believe me), who orders
      you [that sum of money], which you can never repay, is much more unsound [than yours].
       <milestone ed="p" n="77" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Whoever grows pale with evil ambition, or the love of money: whoever is heated with luxury,
      or gloomy superstition, or any other disease of the mind, I command him to adjust his garment
      and attend: hither, all of ye, come near me in order, while I convince you that you are mad.</p>
     <p>By far the largest portion of hellebore is to be administered to the covetous: I know not,
      whether reason does not consign all Anticyra to their use. The heirs of Staberius engraved the
      sum [which he left them] upon his tomb: unless they had acted in this manner, they were under
      an obligation<note anchored="yes" n="39" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Damnati populo.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.86"/>
        </cit> Alluding to the form of the will, in which the testator required any thing of his
        heir, <foreign lang="la">HERES DAMNAS ESTO.</foreign></p>
      </note> to exhibit a hundred pair of gladiators to the people, beside an entertainment
      according to the direction of Arrius; and as much corn as is cut in <placeName
       key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>. Whether I have willed this rightly or wrongly, it was
      my will; be not severe against me, [cries the testator]. I imagine the provident mind of
      Staberius foresaw this. What then did he mean, when he appointed by will that his heirs should
      engrave the sum of their patrimony upon his tomb-stone? As long as he lived, he deemed poverty
      a great vice, and nothing did he more industriously avoid: insomuch that, had he died less
      rich by one farthing, the more iniquitous would he have appeared to himself. For every thing,
      virtue, fame, glory, divine and human affairs, are subservient to the attraction of riches;
      which whoever shall have accumulated, shall be illustrious, brave, just &mdash; What, wise
      too? Ay, and a king, and whatever else he pleases. This he was in hopes would greatly redound
      to his praise, as if it had been an acquisition of his virtue. In what respect did the Grecian
       Aristippus<note anchored="yes" n="40" resp="Dac, San">
       <p>Aristippus was the chief of the Cyrenaic sect. He held that pleasure was the <foreign
         lang="la">summum bonum</foreign>, and virtue only valuable as it was a means of gaining
        that pleasure. Epicurus was perfectly rigid when compared to his master Aristippus, and by
        our author's manner of mentioning him in many parts of his works, we may believe he was no
        enemy to so convenient a philosophy. Staberius, who was a Stoic, has given an ill-natured
        turn to this story, which is much commended by Cicero; for Aristippus had only one slave,
        whom he commanded to throw away as much of his money as was too heavy to carry.</p>
      </note> act like this; who ordered his slaves to throw away his gold in the midst of
       <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>; because, encumbered with the burden, they
      traveled too slowly? Which is the greater madman of these two? An example is nothing to the
      purpose, that decides one controversy by creating another. If any person were to buy lyres,
      and [when he had bought them] to stow them in one place, though neither addicted to the lyre
      nor to any one muse whatsoever: if a man were [to buy] paring-knives and lasts, and were no
      shoemaker; sails fit for navigation, and were averse to merchandising; he would every where
      deservedly be styled delirious, and out of his senses. How does he differ from these, who
      hoards up cash and gold [and] knows not how to use them when accumulated, and is afraid to
      touch them as if they were consecrated? If any person before a great heap of corn should keep
      perpetual watch with a long club, and, though the owner of it, and hungry, should not dare to
      take a single grain from it; and should rather feed upon bitter leaves: if, while a thousand
      hogsheads of Chian, or old Falernian, is stored up within (nay, that is nothing &mdash;
      three hundred thousand), he drink nothing, but what is mere sharp vinegar: again &mdash;
      if, wanting but one year of eighty, he should lie upon straw, who has bed-clothes rotting in
      his chest, the food of worms and moths; he would seem mad, belike, but to few persons: because
      the greatest part of mankind labors under the same malady. <milestone ed="p" n="122"
       unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Thou dotard, hateful to the gods, dost thou guard [these possessions], for fear of wanting
      .thyself: to the end that thy son, or even the freedman thy heir, should guzzle it all up For
      how little will each day deduct from your capital, if you begin to pour better oil upon your
      greens and your head, filthy with scurf not combed out? If any thing be a sufficiency,
      wherefore are you guilty of perjury [wherefore] do you rob, and plunder from all quarters? Are
      you in your senses? If you were to begin to pelt the populace with stones, and the slaves,
      which you purchased with your money; all the very boys and girls will cry out that you are a
      madman. When you dispatch your wife with a rope, and your mother with poison, are you right in
      your head? Why not? You neither did this at <placeName key="tgn,7010720">Argos</placeName>,
      nor slew your mother with the sword as the mad Orestes did. What, do you imagine that he ran
      mad after lie had murdered his parent; and that he was not driven mad by the wicked Furies,
      before he warmed his sharp steel in his mother's throat? Nay, from the time that Orestes is
      deemed to have been of a dangerous disposition, he did nothing in fact that you can blame; he
      did not dare to offer violence with his sword to Pylades, nor to his sister Electra; he only
      gave ill language to both of them, by calling her a Fury, and him some other [opprobrious
      name], which his violent choler suggested.</p>
     <p>Opimius, poor amid silver and gold hoarded up within, who used to drink out of Campanian
      ware Veientine<note anchored="yes" n="41" resp="TAB">
       <p>This wine was of a very poor kind. See Lamb and Orelli.</p>
      </note> wine on holidays, and mere dregs on common days, was some time ago taken with a
      prodigious lethargy; insomuch that his heir was already scouring about his coffers and keys,
      in joy and triumph. His physician, a man of much dispatch and fidelity, raises him in this
      manner: he orders a table to be brought, and the bags of money to be poured out, and several
      persons to approach in order to count it: by this method he sets the man upon his legs again.
      And at the same time he addresses him to this effect. Unless you guard your money your
      ravenous heir will even now carry off these [treasures] of yours. What, while I am alive? That
      you may live, therefore, awake; do this. What would you have me do? Why your blood will fail
      you that are so much reduced, unless food and some great restorative be administered to your
      decaying stomach. Do you hesitate? come on; take this ptisan<note anchored="yes" n="42"
       resp="McCaul, Wheeler">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ptisanarium.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.155"/>
        </cit> The diminutive from <foreign lang="la">ptsana</foreign>, unhusked barley or rice,
        from <foreign lang="greek">pti/ssw</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">tundo, tundendo
        decortico</foreign>. Here it means a decoction, a kind of gruel made of <foreign lang="la"
         >oryza</foreign>, rice. Rice was not then cultivated in <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
        >Italy</placeName>, but brought from <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. The
        physician purposely uses the diminutive <foreign lang="la">ptisanarium</foreign>, lest he
        should terrify the patient.</p>
      </note> made of rice. How much did it cost? A trifle. How much then? Eight asses. Alas! what
      does it matter, whether I die of a disease, or by theft and rapine?</p>
     <p>Who then is sound? He, who is not a fool. What is the covetous man? Both a fool and a
      madman. What &mdash; if a man be not covetous, is he immediately [to be deemed] sound? By
      no means. Why so, Stoic? I will tell you. Such a patient (suppose Craterus [the physician]
      said this) is not sick at the heart. Is he therefore well, and shall he get up? No, he will
      forbid that; because his side or his reins are harassed with an acute disease. [In like
      manner], such a man is not perjured, nor sordid; let him then sacrifice a hog to his
       propitious<note anchored="yes" n="43" resp="Torr">
       <p>All the good and bad accidents that happened in families were generally attributed to the
        domestic gods, and as these gods were the sons of the goddess of madness, they were
        particularly worshiped by persons disordered in their understanding. Stertinius therefore
        advises the man, who, by the favor of these gods, is neither perjured nor a miser,
        gratefully to sacrifice a swine to them, which was their usual sacrifice. <quote lang="la"
         >Fruge Lares, avidaque porca.</quote>
        <bibl n="Hom. Od. 23.2">Od. xxiii. lib. ii.</bibl><!-- AEM:  surely not the Odyssey? --></p>
      </note> household gods. But he is ambitious and assuming. Let him make a voyage [then] to
      Anticyra. For what is the difference, whether you fling whatever you have into a gulf, or make
      no use of your acquisitions? <milestone ed="p" n="168" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Servius Oppidius, rich in the possession of an ancient estate, is reported when dying to
      have divided two farms at <placeName key="tgn,7004111">Canusium</placeName> between his two
      sons, and to have addressed the boys, called to his bed-side, [in the following manner]: When
      I saw you, Aulus, carry your playthings and nuts carelessly in your bosom, [and] to give them
      and game them away; you, Tiberius, count them, and anxious hide them in holes; I was afraid
      lest a madness of a different nature should possess you: lest you [Aulus], should follow the
      example of Nomentanus, you, [Tiberius], that of Cicuta. Wherefore each of you, entreated by
      our household gods, do you (Aulus) take care lest you lessen; you (Tiberius) lest you make
      that greater, which your father thinks and the purposes of nature determine to be sufficient.
      Further, lest glory should entice you, I will bind each of you by an oath: whichever of you
      shall be an aedile or a praetor, let him be excommunicated and accursed. Would you destroy
      your effects in [largesses of] peas, beans, and lupines,<note anchored="yes" n="44"
       resp="McCaul">
       <p>Distributions of these were frequently made to the people by candidates for offices, or by
        the aediles at the celebration of the games, etc. Oppidius asks whether his son would be so
        mad as to squander his property in largesses, for the sake of obtaining an office in the
        state. Comp. <cit>
         <bibl n="Pers. 5.177">Pers. Sat. v. 177:</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">
          <lg type="hexameter">
           <l part="F">Vigila et cicer ingere large</l>
           <l>Rixanti populo, nostra ut Floralia possint</l>
           <l>Aprici meminisse senes.</l>
          </lg>
         </quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> that you may stalk in the circus at large, or stand in a statue of brass, O madman,
      stripped of your paternal estate, stripped of your money To the end, forsooth, that you may
      gain those applauses, which Agrippa<note anchored="yes" n="45" resp="San">
       <p>This compliment to Agrippa is introduced with great art, as if it escaped accidentally,
        and it is enlivened by a comparison, short but noble. Although Agrippa had been consul in
        717, yet he condescended to accept the office of aedile in 720, when he entertained the
        people with a magnificence and expense beyond what they had ever seen.</p>
      </note> gains, like a cunning fox imitating a generous lion? </p>
     <p>O Agamemnon, why do you prohibit any one from burying<note anchored="yes" n="46" resp="San">
       <p>Here opens another scene, in which a king and a Stoic are engaged, and in which the
        philosopher proves in good form, that this greatest of monarchs is a fool and a madman. The
        debate arises from an incident in a play of Sophocles, in which Agamemnon refuses to let
        Ajax be buried.<bibl n="Soph. Aj. 1223">(Ajax 1223-1375)</bibl></p>
      </note> Ajax? I am a king. I, a plebeian,<note anchored="yes" n="47" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Agamemnon finding his answer, I am a king, a little too tyrannical, adds, our decree was
        just. Perhaps the humility of the philosopher, either ironical or serious, in seeming to
        allow his royal manner of deciding the question, extorted this condescension from the
        monarch.</p>
      </note> make no further inquiry. And I command a just thing: but, if I seem unjust to any one,
      I permit you to speak your sentiments with impunity. Greatest of kings, may the gods grant
      that, after the taking of <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, you may conduct your
      fleet safe home: may I then have the liberty to ask questions, and reply in my turn?</p>
     <p>Ask. Why does Ajax, the second hero after Achilles, rot [above ground], so often renowned
      for having saved the Grecians; that Priam and Priam's people may exult in his being unburied,
      by whose means so many youths have been deprived of their country's rites of sepulture. In his
      madness he killed a thousand sheep, crying out that he was destroying the famous Ulysses and
      Menelaus, together with me. When you at <placeName key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName>
      substituted your sweet daughter in the place of a heifer before the altar, and, O impious one,
      sprinkled her head with the salt cake; did you preserve soundness of mind? Why do you ask?
      What then did the mad Ajax do, when he slew the flock with his sword? He abstained from any
      violence to his wife and child, though he had imprecated many curses on the sons of Atreus: he
      neither hurt Teucer, nor even Ulysses himself. But I, out of prudence, appeased the gods with
      blood, that I might loose the ships detained on an adverse shore. Yes, madman! with your own
      blood. With my own [indeed], but I was not mad. Whoever shall form images foreign from
      reality, and confused in the tumult of impiety,<note anchored="yes" n="48" resp="Orelli">
       <p>i. e. the perturbation of mind leading to the commission of impious deeds.</p>
      </note> will always be reckoned disturbed in mind: and it will not matter, whether he go wrong
      through folly or through rage. Is Ajax delirious, while he kills the harmless lambs? Are you
      right in your head, when you willfully commit a crime for empty titles?</p>
     <p>And is your heart pure, while it is swollen with the vice?<note anchored="yes" n="49"
       resp="TAB">
       <p>i. e. of madness.</p>
      </note> If any person should take a delight to carry about with him in his sedan a pretty
      lambkin; and should provide clothes, should provide maids and gold for it, as for a daughter;
      should call it Rufa and Rufilla, and should destine it a wife for some stout husband; the
      praetor would take power from him being interdicted, and the management of him would devolve
      to his relations, that were in their senses. What, if a man devote his daughter instead of a
      dumb lambkin, is he right of mind? Never say it. Therefore, wherever there is a foolish
      depravity, there will be the height of madness. He who is wicked, will be frantic too:
      Bellona, who delights in bloodshed, has thundered about him, whom precarious fame has
      captivated. <milestone ed="p" n="224" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Now, come on, arraign with me luxury and Nomentanus; for reason will evince that foolish
      spendthrifts are mad. This fellow, as soon as he received a thousand talents of patrimony,
      issues an order that the fishmonger, the fruiterer, the poulterer, the perfumer, and the
      impious gang of the Tuscan alley, sausage-maker, and buffoons, the whole shambles, together
      with [all] Velabrum, should come to his house in the morning. What was the consequence? They
      came in crowds.</p>
     <p>The pander makes a speech: "Whatever I, or whatever each of these has at home, believe it to
      be yours: and give your order for it either directly, or to-morrow." Hear what reply the
      considerate youth made: "You sleep booted in Lucanian snow, that I may feast on a boar: you
      sweep the wintery seas for fish: I am indolent, and unworthy to possess so much. Away with it:
      do you take for your share ten hundred thousand sesterces; you as much; you thrice the sum,
      from whose house your spouse runs, when called for, at midnight."</p>
     <p>The son of Aesopus, [the actor] (that he might, forsooth, swallow a million of sesterces at
      a draught), dissolved in vinegar a precious pearl, which he had taken from the ear of Metella:
      how much wiser was he [in doing this,] than if he had thrown the same into a rapid river, or
      the common sewer? The progeny of Quintius Arrius, an illustrious pair of brothers, twins in
      wickedness and trifling and the love of depravity, used to dine upon nightingales bought at a
      vast expense: to whom do these belong? Are they in their senses? Are they to be marked with
      chalk, or with charcoal?<note anchored="yes" n="50" resp="TAB">
       <p>A proverbial expression. Are they to be acquitted or condemned? Are they wise or
       foolish?</p>
      </note></p>
     <p>If an [aged person] with a long beard should take a delight to build baby-houses, to yoke
      mice to a go-cart, to play at odd and even, to ride upon a long cane, madness must be his
      motive. If reason shall evince, that to be in love is a more childish thing than these; and
      that there is no difference whether you play the same games in the dust as when three years
      old, or whine in anxiety for the love of a harlot: I beg to know, if you will act as the
      reformed Polemon<note anchored="yes" n="51" resp="Fran">
       <p>Polemon was a young Athenian, who, running one day through the streets, inflamed with
        wine, had the curiosity to go into the school of Xenocrates to hear him. The philosopher
        dexterously turned his discourse upon sobriety, and spoke with so much force, that Polemon
        from that moment renounced his intemperance, and pursued his studies with such application,
        as to succeed Xenocrates in his school. Thus, as Valerius Maximus remarks, being cured by
        the wholesome medicine of one oration, he became a celebrated philosopher, from an infamous
        prodigal.</p>
      </note> did of old? Will you lay aside those ensigns of your disease, your rollers, your
      mantle, your mufflers; as he in his cups is said to have privately torn the chaplet from his
      neck, after he was corrected by the speech of his fasting master? When you offer apples to an
      angry boy, he refuses them: here, take them, you little dog; he denies you: if you don't give
      them, he wants them. In what does an excluded lover differ [from such a boy]; when he argues
      with himself whether he should go or not to that very place whither he was returning without
      being sent for, and cleaves to the hated doors? "What shall I not go to her now, when she
      invites me of her own accord? or shall I rather think of putting an end to my pains? She has
      excluded me; she recalls me: shall I return? No, not if she would implore me." Observe the
      servant, not a little wiser: "0 master, that which has neither moderation nor conduct, can not
      be guided by reason or method. In love these evils are inherent; war [one while], then peace
      again. If any one should endeavor to ascertain these things, that are various as the weather,
      and fluctuating by blind chance; he will make no more of it, than if he should set about
      raving by right reason and rule." Whatwhen, picking the pippins<note anchored="yes" n="52"
       resp="Wheeler">
       <p>The allusion is to a habit of determining the good or bad fortune of love by trying to
        strike the ceiling of a room with the pippins of apples. They were raised by pressing them
        between the first two fingers. If they struck the ceiling, it was considered a good
       omen.</p>
      </note> from the Picenian apples, you rejoice if haply you have hit the vaulted roof; are you
      yourself? What-when you strike out faltering accents from your antiquated palate, how much
      wiser are you than [a child] that builds little houses To the folly [of love] add bloodshed,
      and stir the fire with a sword.<note anchored="yes" n="53" resp="Cruq, San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ignum gladio scrutare</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.276"/>
        </cit>, a proverbial precept of Pythagoras, "Do not stir the fire with a sword." Our poet
        uses it. as an easy transition from the folly to the madness of lovers. We shall have
        another proverb in the same sense, <quote lang="la">Oleum adde camino.</quote></p>
      </note> I ask you, when Marius lately, after he had stabbed <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
       >Hellas</placeName>, threw himself down a precipice, was he raving mad? Or will you absolve
      the man from the imputation of a disturbed mind, and condemn him for the crime, according to
      your custom, imposing on things names that have an affinity in signification? <milestone
       ed="p" n="281" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>There was a certain freedman, who, an old man, ran about the streets in a morning fasting,
      with his hands washed, and prayed thus: "Snatch me alone from death" (adding some solemn vow),
      "me alone, for it is an easy matter for the gods:" this man was sound in both his ears and
      eyes; but his master, when he sold him, would except his understanding, unless he were fond of
       law-suits.<note anchored="yes" n="54" resp="TAB">
       <p>For an action would lay against those who gave a false character to a slave.</p>
      </note> This crowd too Chrysippus places in the fruitful family of Menenius.</p>
     <p>O <placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName>, who givest and takest away great
      afflictions, (cries the mother of a boy, now lying sick a-bed for five months), if this cold
      quartan ague should leave the child, in the morning of that day on which you enjoin a
       fast,<note anchored="yes" n="55" resp="Dac, San">
       <p>The Romans had regular fasts in honor of Jupiter, which were usually celebrated on
        Thursday, which was consecrated to that god. They began on the eve; and the next morning,
        which was properly the fastday, was observed with great rigor and austerity. Aristophanes,
        in his Clouds, introduces the chorus, complaining that they had a fast, rather than a
         feast(<bibl n="Aristoph. Cl. 578">Clouds 578</bibl>); which was observed on the third day
        of the festival of <placeName key="tgn,1021155">Ceres</placeName>.</p>
      </note> he shall stand naked in the <placeName key="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>. Should
      chance or the physician relieve the patient from his imminent danger, the infatuated mother
      will destroy [the boy] placed on the cold bank, and will bring back the fever. With what
      disorder of the mind is she stricken? Why, with a superstitious fear of the gods. These arms
      Stertinius, the eighth of the wise men, gave to me, as to a friend, that for the future I
      might not be roughly accosted without avenging myself. Whosoever shall call me madman, shall
      hear as much from me [in return]; and shall learn to look back upon the bag that hangs behind
       him.<note anchored="yes" n="56" resp="Fran">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Respicere ignoto.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.299"/>
        </cit> This passage may be explained by the fifty-third line, <cit>
         <quote lang="la">caudam trahat</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.3.53"/>
        </cit>, or by the fable, which says that <placeName key="tgn,2019952">Jupiter</placeName>
        threw over the shoulder of every mortal two bags; that the faults of his neighbor were put
        into the bag before him, and his own into that behind him.</p>
      </note> 0 Stoic, so may you, after your damage, sell all your merchandise the better: what
      folly (for, it seems,] there are more kinds than one) do you think I am infatuated with? For
      to myself I seem sound. What-when mad Agave carries the amputated head of her unhappy son,
      does she then seem mad to herself? I allow myself a fool (let me yield to the truth) and a
      madman likewise: only declare this, with what distemper of mind you think me afflicted. Hear,
      then: in the first place you build; that is, though from top to bottom you are but of the
      two-foot size you imitate the tall: and you, the same person, laugh at the spirit and strut of
       <placeName key="tgn,1024049">Turbo</placeName> in armor, too great for his [little] body: how
      are you less ridiculous than him? What-is it fitting that, in every thing Maecenas does, you,
      who are so very much unlike him and so much his inferior, should vie with him? The young ones
      of a frog being in her absence crushed by the foot of a calf, when one of them had made his
      escape, he told his mother what a huge beast had dashed his brethren to pieces. She began to
      ask, how big? Whether it were so great? puffing herself up. Greater by half. What, so big?
      when she had swelled herself more and more. If you should burst yourself, says he, you will
      not be equal to it. This image bears no great dissimilitude to you. Now add poems (that is,
      add oil to the fire), which if ever any man in his senses made, why so do you. I do not
      mention your horrid rage. At length, have done &mdash; your way of living beyond your
      fortune &mdash; confine yourself to your own affairs, Damasippus &mdash; those
      thousand passions for the fair, the young. Thou greater madman, at last, spare thy inferior.
     </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="4">
     <head>He ridicules the absurdity of one Catius, who placed the summit of human felicity in the
      culinary art.</head>

     <p>WHENCE, and whither, Catius? I have not time [to converse with you], being desirous of
      impressing on my memory some new precepts; such as excel Pythagoras, and him that was accused
      by Anytus,<note anchored="yes" n="57" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Anytique reum</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.4.3"/>
        </cit>. <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName>, when Anytus and Melitus
       accused.</p>
      </note> and the learned Plato. I acknowledge my offense, since I have interrupted you at so
      unlucky a juncture: but grant me your pardon, good sir, I beseech you. If any thing should
      have slipped you now, you will presently recollect it: whether this talent of yours be of
      nature, or of art, you are amazing in both. Nay, but I was anxious, how I might retain all
      [these precepts]; as being things of a delicate nature, and in a delicate style. Tell me the
      name of this man; and at the same time whether he is a Roman, or a foreigner? As I have them
      by heart, I will recite the precepts: the author shall be concealed.</p>
     <p>Remember to serve up those eggs that are of an oblong make, as being of sweeter flavor and
      more nutritive than the round ones: for, being toughshelled, they contain a male yelk. Cabbage
      that grows in dry lands, is sweeter than that about town: nothing is more insipid than a
      garden much watered. If a visitor should come unexpectedly upon you in the evening, lest the
      tough old hen prove disagreeable to his palate, you must learn to drown it in Falernian wine
      mixed [with water]:<note anchored="yes" n="58" resp="TAB">
       <p>But Bentley is doubtless right in reading <foreign lang="la">musto</foreign> for <foreign
         lang="la">misto.</foreign></p>
      </note> this will make it tender. The mushrooms that grow in meadows,<note anchored="yes"
       n="59" resp="Torr,Dac">
       <p>Nothing is more false. The best mushrooms, generally speaking, are those gathered in
        woods, heaths, or downs. They are more wholesome and better flavored than those of
       meadows.</p>
      </note> are of the best kind: all others are dangerously trusted. That man shall spend his
      summers healthy who shall finish his dinners with mulberries<note anchored="yes" n="60"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>The ancients had only one meal, but they who could not wait for supper usually eat bread,
        figs, grapes, or mulberries in the morning. But our doctor, who loved to dine in form,
        taught another method, and in contradiction to <placeName key="tgn,2099233"
        >Galen</placeName> and the faculty, would have his disciples eat mulberries after
       dinner.</p>
      </note> black [with ripeness], which he shall have gathered from the tree before the sun
      becomes violent. Aufidius used to mix honey with strong Falernian injudiciously; because it is
      right to commit nothing to the empty veins, but what is emollient: you will, with more
      propriety, wash your stomach with soft mead. If your belly should be hard bound, the limpet
      and coarse cockles will remove obstructions, and leaves of the small sorrel; but not without
       <placeName key="tgn,2246284">Coan</placeName> white wine. The increasing moons swell the
      lubricating shell-fish. But every sea is not productive of the exquisite sorts. The Lucrine
      muscle is better than the Baian murex: [The best] oysters come from the Circean promontory;
      cray-fish from <placeName key="tgn,7010130">Misenum</placeName>: the soft <placeName
       key="tgn,7004100">Tarentum</placeName> plumes herself on her broad escalops. Let no one
      presumptuously arrogate to himself the science of banqueting, unless the nice doctrine of
      tastes has been previously considered by him with exact system. Nor is it enough to sweep away
      a parcel of fishes from the expensive stalls, [while he remains] ignorant for what sort stewed
      sauce is more proper, and what being roasted, the sated guest will presently replace himself
      on his elbow. Let the boar from <placeName key="tgn,7003125">Umbria</placeName>, and that
      which has been fed with the acorns of the scarlet oak, bend the round dishes of him who
      dislikes all flabby meat: for the Laurentian<note anchored="yes" n="61" resp="Dac">
       <p>All people of taste have ever esteemed boars fed in marshy ground as of higher flavor,
        although Catius is of another opinion.</p>
      </note> boar, fattened with flags and reeds, is bad. The vineyard does not always afford the
      most eatable kids. A man of sense will be fond of the shoulders of a pregnant hare. What is
      the proper age and nature of fish and fowl, though inquired after, was never discovered before
      my palate. <milestone ed="p" n="47" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>There are some, whose genius invents nothing but new kinds of pastry. To waste one's care
      upon one thing, is by no means sufficient; just as if any person should use all his endeavors
      for this only, that the wine be not bad; quite careless what oil he pours upon his fish. If
      you set out Massic<note anchored="yes" n="62" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Pliny advises, that all the best Campanian wines should be exposed night and day to the
        sun, moon, rain, and winds.</p>
      </note> wine in fair weather, should there be any thing thick in it, it will be attenuated by
      the nocturnal air, and the smell unfriendly to the nerves will go off: but, if filtrated
      through linen, it will lose its entire flavor. He, who skillfully mixes the Surrentine. wine
      with Falernian lees, collects the sediment with a pigeon's egg: because the yelk sinks to the
      bottom, rolling down with it all the heterogeneous parts. You may rouse the jaded toper with
      roasted shrimps and African cockles; for lettuce after wine floats upon the soured stomach: by
      ham preferably, and by sausages, it craves to be restored to its appetite: nay, it will prefer
      every thing which is brought smoking hot from the nasty eating-houses. It is worth while to be
      acquainted with the two kinds of sauce. The simple consists of sweet oil; which it will be
      proper to mix with rich wine and pickle, but with no other pickle than that by which the
      Byzantine jar has been tainted. When this, mingled with shredded herbs, has boiled, and
      sprinkled with Corycian saffron, has stood, you shall over and above add what the pressed
      berry of the Venafran olive yields. The Tiburtian yield to the Picenian apples in juice,
      though they excel in look. The Venusian grape is proper for [preserving in] pots. The Albanian
      you had better harden in the smoke. I am found to be the first that served up this grape with
      apples in neat little side-plates, to be the first [likewise that served up] wine-lees and
      herring-brine, and white pepper finely mixed with black salt. It is an enormous fault to
      bestow three thousand sesterces on the fish-market, and then to cramp the roving fishes in a
      narrow dish. It causes a great nausea in the stomach, if even the slave touches the cup with
      greasy hands, while he licks up snacks, or if offensive grime has adhered to the ancient
      goblet. In trays, in mats, in sawdust, [that are so] cheap, what great expense can there be?
      But, if they are neglected, it is a heinous shame. What, should you sweep Mosaic pavements
      with a dirty broom made of palm, and throw Tyrian carpets over the unwashed furniture of your
      couch! forgetting, that by how much less care and expense these things are attended, so much
      the more justly may [the want of them] be censured, than of those things which can not be
      obtained but at the tables of the rich?</p>
     <p>Learned Catius, entreated by our friendship and the gods, remember to introduce me to an
      audience [with this great man], whenever you shall go to him. For, though by your memory you
      relate every thing to me, yet as a relater you can not delight me in so high a degree. Add to
      this the countenance and deportment of the man; whom you, happy in having seen, do not much
      regard, because it has been your lot: but I have no small solicitude, that I may approach the
      distant fountain-heads, and imbibe the precepts of [such] a blessed life. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="5">
     <head>In a humorous dialogue between Ulysses and Tiresias, he exposes those arts which the
      fortune hunters make use of, in order to be appointed the heirs of rich old men.</head>

     <p>BESIDE what you have told me, O Tiresias, answer to this petition of mine: by what arts and
      expedients may I be able to repair my ruined fortunes-why do you laugh? Does it already seem
      little to you, who are practiced in deceit, to be brought back to <placeName key="tgn,1007519"
       >Ithaca</placeName>, and to behold [again] your family household gods? 0 you who never speak
      falsely to any one, you see how naked and destitute I return home, according to your prophecy:
      nor is either my cellar, or my cattle there, unembezzled by the suitors [of Penelope]. But
      birth and virtue, unless [attended] with substance, is viler than seaweed.</p>
     <p>Since (circumlocutions apart) you are in dread of poverty, hear by what means you may grow
      wealthy. If a thrush, or any [nice] thing for your own private [eating], shall be given you;
      it must wing way to that place, where shines a great fortune, the possessor being an old man:
      delicious apples, and whatever dainties your well-cultivated ground brings forth for you, let
      the rich man, as more to be reverenced than your household god, taste before him: and, though
      he be perjured, of no family, stained with his brother's blood, a runaway; if he desire it, do
      not refuse to go along with him, his companion on the outer side.<note anchored="yes" n="63"
       resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Comes exterior.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.17"/>
        </cit> In walking with a companion, the side which is most exposed was called the outer
        side. When three people walk together, the middle is, for the same reason, the most
        honorable place, and is therefore always given to the person of most distinction, interior
        comes.</p>
      </note> What, shall I walk cheek by jole with a filthy <placeName key="tgn,7002261"
      >Damas</placeName>? I did not behave myself in that manner at <placeName key="perseus,Troy"
       >Troy</placeName>, contending always with the best. You must then be poor. I will command my
      sturdy soul to bear this evil; I have formerly endured even greater. Do thou, O prophet, tell
      me forthwith how I may amass riches, and heaps of money. In troth I have told you, and tell
      you again. Use your craft to lie at catch for the last wills of old men: nor, if one or two
      cunning chaps escape by biting the bait off the hook, either lay aside hope, or quit the art,
      though disappointed in your aim. If an affair, either of little or great consequence, shall be
      contested at any time at the bar; whichever of the parties live wealthy without heirs, should
      he be a rogue, who daringly takes the law of a better man, be thou. his advocate: despise the
      citizen, who is superior in reputation, and [the justness of] his cause, if at home he has a
      son or a fruitful wife. [Address him thus:] "Quintus, for instance, or Publius<note
       anchored="yes" n="64" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Quinte, puta, aut Publi.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.32"/>
        </cit> A slave was no sooner made free, than he qualified himself with a surname, such as
        Marcus, Quintus, Publius, which carried a sort of dignity with it. The Romans saluted each
        other by their surnames.</p>
      </note> (delicate ears delight in the prefixed name), your virtue has made me your friend. I
      am acquainted with the precarious quirks of the law; I can plead causes. Any one shall sooner
      snatch my eyes from me, than he shall despise or defraud you of an empty nut. This is my care,
      that you lose nothing, that you be not made a jest of." Bid him go home, and make much of
      himself. Be his solicitor yourself: persevere, and be steadfast: whether the glaring dog-star
      shall cleave the infant statues; or Furius, destined with his greasy paunch,<note
       anchored="yes" n="65" resp="Wheeler">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Pingui tentus omaso.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.40"/>
        </cit> Furius, in a poem on the Gallic war, had said, <quote lang="la">Iupiter hibernas cana
         nivo conspuet Alpes.</quote> Horace applies it to the author himself; adding <quote
         lang="la">pingui tentus omaso</quote> in ridicule of his appearance. <quote lang="la"
         >Furius poeta immanis ventris, qui nivem spumam (sputum) Iovis dixit. Ideo hoc ejus persona
         dedit, tanquam ipse spuat.</quote>: Sch. Acr. Orelli considers three several passages of
        Furius to be referred to: <quote lang="la">rubra canicula findit infantes statuas,</quote>
        is a passage in which Furius describes a statuary, and thought he had a happy expression in
        infantes, since statues are <foreign lang="greek">a)glw/ttoi</foreign>. By <quote lang="la"
         >pingui tentus omasi</quote>, some general opposed to Caesar is described as a voracious
        barbarian. <quote lang="la">Hibernas</quote>, etc., formed the first line of his poetical
        history of Caesar.</p>
      </note> shall spue white snow over the wintery <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName>.
      Do not you see (shall some one say, jogging the person that stands next to him by the elbow)
      how indefatigable he is, how serviceable to his friends, how acute? [By this means] more
      tunnies shall swim in, and your fish-ponds will increase.</p>
     <p>Further, if any one in affluent circumstances has reared<note anchored="yes" n="66"
       resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Sublatus</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.46"/>
        </cit>. A word taken from a Roman custom of laying their new-born infants on the ground, and
        educating only those the father took up.</p>
      </note> an ailing son, lest a too open complaisance to a single man should detect you, creep
      gradually into the hope [of succeeding him], and that you may be set down as second heir; and,
      if any casualty should dispatch the boy to Hades, you may come into the vacancy. This die
      seldom fails. Whoever delivers his will to you to read, be mindful to decline it, and push the
      parchment from you: [do it] however in such a manner, that you may catch with an oblique
      glance, what the first page<note anchored="yes" n="67" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Prima cera</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.53"/>
        </cit> signifies the first page of the will, in which the testator's name was written.
         <quote lang="la">Secundo versus</quote> was the second line, which contained the names of
        the heirs and co-heirs.</p>
      </note> intimates to be in the second clause: run over with a quick eye, whether you are sole
      heir, or co-heir with many. Sometimes a well-seasoned lawyer, risen from a Quinquevir,<note
       anchored="yes" n="68" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>The <foreign lang="la">quinqueviri</foreign> were a kind of tip-staff or bailiff, in the
        colonies and municipal towns. A man who had passed through these little offices may well be
        supposed to be sufficiently knowing in what we call the practice, and from this body public
        notaries and registers were chosen. Horace therefore means, by <quote lang="la">scriba
         recoctus</quote>, a notary sufficiently refined in tricks and cunning of the law. <foreign
         lang="la">Recoctus</foreign> is properly double-dyed, that hath fully taken its color.</p>
      </note> shall delude the gaping raven; and the fortunehunter Nasica shall be laughed at by
      Coranus. <milestone ed="p" n="58" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>What, art thou in a [prophetic] raving; or dust thou play upon me designedly, by uttering
      obscurities? 0 son of Laertes, whatever I shall say will come to pass, or it will not:<note
       anchored="yes" n="69" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Quidquid dicam, aut erit, aut non.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.59"/>
        </cit> It is well disputed, whether these words be spoken in jest by Tiresias, to rally the
        monarch who consults him, or whether he too carelessly discovers his real opinion of his
        art. There is an acknowledged ambiguity and double meaning in his expression, under which,
        perhaps, the poet disguises his own sentiments of the skill of these diviners, and the
        frequent ambiguity of their answers.</p>
      </note> for the great Apollo gives me the power to divine. Then, if it is proper, relate what
      that tale means.</p>
     <p>At that time when the youth dreaded by the Parthians, an offspring derived from the noble
      Aeneas, shall be mighty by land and sea; the tall daughter of Nasica, averse to pay the sum
      total of his debt, shall wed the stout Coranus. Then the son-in-law shall proceed thus: he
      shall deliver his will to his father-in-law, and entreat him to read it; Nasica will at length
      receive it, after it has been several times refused, and silently peruse it; and will find no
      other legacy left to him and his, except leave to lament. </p>
     <p>To these [directions I have already given], I subjoin the [following]: if haply a cunning
      woman or a freedman have the management of an old driveler, join with them as an associate:
      praise them, that you may be praised in your absence. This too is of service; but to storm
      [the capital] itself excels this method by far. Shall he, a dotard, scribble wretched verses?
      Applaud them. Shall he be given to pleasure? Take care [you do not suffer him] to ask you: of
      your own accord complaisantly deliver up your Penelope to him, as preferable [to yourself].
      What-do you think so sober and so chaste a woman can be brought over, whom [so many] wooers
      could not divert from the right course? Because, forsooth, a parcel of young fellows
       came,<note anchored="yes" n="70" resp="Dac">
       <p>Although Tiresias gives <placeName key="tgn,2037257">Ulysses</placeName> no better reason
        for his wife's virtue than the avarice of her lovers, yet the monarch hears him patiently,
        since even this reason proves her sufficiently virtuous. Our poet probably took the hint of
        this passage from homer, who makes Penelope reproach her wooers with their want of
        generosity, and never having made her any presents. The next line is almost a translation
        from the Odyssey.</p>
      </note> who were too parsimonious to give a great price, nor so much desirous of an amorous
      intercourse, as of the kitchen. So far your Penelope is a good woman: who, had she once tasted
      of one old [doting gallant], and shared with you the profit, like a hound, will never be
      frighted away from the reeking skin [of the new-killed game].</p>
     <p>What I am going to tell you happened when I was an old man. A wicked hag at <placeName
       key="tgn,7011071">Thebes</placeName> was, according to her will, carried forth<note
       anchored="yes" n="71" resp="TAB">
       <p><quote lang="la">Elata.</quote> Carried out to the funeral pile. <cit>
         <bibl n="Ter. An. 1">Ter. Andr. i.</bibl>
         <quote lang="la">Effertur, Imus.</quote>
        </cit></p>
      </note> in this manner: her heir bore her corpse, anointed with a large quantity of oil, upon
      his naked shoulders; with the intent that, if possible, she might escape from him even when
      dead: because, I imagine, he had pressed upon her too much when living. Be cautious in your
      addresses: neither be wanting in your pains, nor immoderately exuberant. By garrulity you will
      offend the splenetic and morose. You must not, however, be too silent. Be Davus in the play;
      and stand with your head on one side, much like one who is in great awe. Attack him with
      complaisance: if the air freshens, advise him carefully to cover up his precious head:
      disengage him from the crowd by opposing your shoulders to it: closely attach your ear to him,
      if chatty. Is he immoderately fond of being praised? Pay him home, till he shall cry out, with
      his hands lifted up to heaven, "Enough:" and puff up the swelling bladder with tumid speeches.
      When he shall have [at last] released you from your long servitude and anxiety; and being
      certainly awake, you shall hear [this article in his will]? "Let Ulysses be heir to one fourth
      of my estate:" "is then my companion <placeName key="tgn,7002261">Damas</placeName> now no
      more? Where shall I find one so brave and so faithful?" Throw out something of this kind]
      every now and then: and if you can a little, weep for him. It is fit to disguise your
      countenance, which [otherwise] would betray your joy. As for the monument, which is left to
      your own discretion, erect it without meanness. The neighborhood will commend the funeral
      handsomely performed. If haply any of your co-heirs, being advanced in years, should have a
      dangerous cough; whether he has a mind to be a purchaser of a farm or a house out of your
      share, tell him, you will [come to any terms he shall propose, and] make it over to him gladly
      for a trifling sum.<note anchored="yes" n="72" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Nummo addicere.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.5.109"/>
        </cit> When a counterfeit sale was made of any thing left by will, the forms of law were to
        be observed. The buyer and seller went to a public officer called <foreign lang="la"
         >Libripens</foreign>, or keeper of the scales; and the purchaser, in the presence of
        witnesses, put a piece of money into the scales, which the seller took out, and the sale was
        afterward deemed legal. <foreign lang="la">Nummo addicere</foreign> means here "to sell for
        nothing."</p>
      </note> But the imperious Proserpine drags me hence. Live, and prosper. </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="6">
     <head>He sets the conveniences of a country retirement in opposition to the troubles of a life
      in town.</head>

     <p>This was [ever] among the number of my wishes: a portion of ground not over large, in which
      was a garden, and a founain with a continual stream close to my house, and a little woodland
      besides.The gods have done more abundantly, and better, for me [than this]. It is well: 0 son
      of <placeName key="tgn,1049816">Maia</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" n="73" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Maia nate.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.5"/>
        </cit> He addresses his prayer to Mercury, not only because this god was a patron of poets
        in general, and that our poet, as we find in his Odes, was particularly obliged to his
        protection, but because he presided over industry and merchandise, as Hercules did over any
        sudden, accidental increase of riches. Besides, he was a rural deity, from whence, as Dacier
        observes, the poet recommends the preservation of his cattle to him, in the fourteenth
        verse.</p>
      </note> I ask nothing more save that you would render these donations lasting to me. If I have
      neither made my estate larger by bad means, nor am in a way to make it less by vice or
      misconduct; if I do not foolishly make any petition of this sort"Oh that that neighboring
      angle, which now spoils the regularity<note anchored="yes" n="74" resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Denormat.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.8"/>
        </cit> We do not find this word in any other author.</p>
      </note> of my field, could be added! Oh that some accident would discover to me an urn [full]
      of money! as it did to him, who having found a treasure, bought that very ground he before
      tilled in the capacity of an hired servant, enriched by Hercules' being his friend;" if what I
      have at present satisfies me grateful, I supplicate you with this prayer: make my cattle fat
      for the use of their master, and every thing else, except my genius:<note anchored="yes"
       n="75" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Et caetera praeter ingenium.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.14"/>
        </cit> The Latins, in speaking of style, have expressions not unlike this, <quote lang="la"
         >pingue et adipatum dicendi genus; poetae pinguae quiddam sonantes.</quote> This playing on
        the double meaning of the word is much in our author's manner. Besides, Mercury was a good
        humored god, who understood raillery, <quote lang="la">de Dis non tristibus.</quote> Yet,
        for fear the deity should understand the word <foreign lang="la">caetera</foreign> in its
        full extent, and without any exception, the petitioner pleasantly guards against the fatness
        of his understanding.</p>
      </note> and, as you are wont, be present as my chief guardian. Wherefore, when I have removed
      myself from the city to the mountains and my castle,<note anchored="yes" n="76" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">In arcem.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.16"/>
        </cit> He considers his country-house as a citadel inaccessible to the cares that besieged
        him at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</p>
      </note> (what can I polish, preferably to my satires and prosaic muse?<note anchored="yes"
       n="77" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Musaque pedestri.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.17"/>
        </cit> The muse of satire, if such an expression may be allowed, is a muse on foot. She
        borrowed nothing from poetry but the measures of her verses, tho, only particular in which
        she differs from prose.</p>
      </note>) neither evil ambition destroys me, nor the heavy<note anchored="yes" n="78"
       resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Plumbeus.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.18"/>
        </cit> This epithet very well expresses the weight of air in autumn, when the south wind was
        usually attended at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> with pestilential
        disorders. Our poet's country-house was covered by mountains, in such a manner, that he had
        nothing to fear from its bad effects.</p>
      </note> south wind, nor the sickly autumn, the gain of baleful Libitina.</p>
     <p>Father of the morning,<note anchored="yes" n="79" resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Matutine pater.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.20"/>
        </cit> The satire properly begins here, and all before this line is a kind of preface. Janus
        presided over time, and therefore Horace calls him god of the morning, as if time seemed to
        be renewed every morning.</p>
      </note> or Janus, if with more pleasure thou hearest thyself [called by that name], from whom
      men commence the toils of business, and of life (such is the will of the gods), be thou the
      beginning of my song. At <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> you hurry me away to
      be bail; "Away, dispatch, [you cry,] lest any one should be beforehand with you in doing that
      friendly office"<note anchored="yes" n="80" resp="Dac">
       <p>To show that all his distresses begin with the morning, the poet introduces Janus, the god
        of the morning, pressing them upon him, <quote lang="la">Urge sive Aquilo</quote>, etc.</p>
      </note>: I must go, at all events, whether the north wind sweep the earth, or winter contracts
      the snowy day into a arrower circle.<note anchored="yes" n="81" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Interiore diem.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.26"/>
        </cit> The northern part of the circle which the sun describes in summer is more distant
        from our earth than the southern part, which he describes in winter. From hence our days are
        shorter in winter than in summer, and he may therefore be poetically said to drive the day
        in a smaller course. Horace calls this circle <quote lang="la">interiorem gyrum</quote>, by
        a figure taken from chariot races, in which the driver who turned nearest the goal marked a
        narrower circle, and was therefore called <quote lang="la">interior quadriga</quote>, with
        regard to those who were obliged to take a larger compass, <quote lang="la"
        >exteriores.</quote></p>
      </note> After this, having uttered in a clear and determinate manner [the legal form], which
      may be a detriment to me, I must bustle through the crowd; and must disoblige the tardy. "What
      is your will, madman, and what are you about, impudent fellow?" So one accosts me with his
      passionate curses. "You jostle every thing that is in your way, if with an appointment full in
      your mind you are posting away to Maecenas." This pleases me, and is like honey: I will not
      tell a lie. But by the time I reach the gloomy Esquiliae, a hundred affairs of other people's
      encompass me on every side: "Roscius begged that you would be with him at the court-house<note
       anchored="yes" n="82" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Ad Puteal.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.35"/>
        </cit> He describes a part of the forum by a monument erected there to show that the place
        had been struck with thunder. Some of the proctors held a kind of sessions there to decide
        private causes.</p>
      </note> to-morrow before the second hour." "The secretaries<note anchored="yes" n="83"
       resp="Torr">
       <p>Horace had purchased an employment of register or secretary to the treasury; from whence
        he is desired to return early from Maecenas to consult about some important affair that
        concerned the whole body.</p>
      </note> requested you would remember, Quintus, to return to-day about an affair of public
      concern, and of great consequence." "Get Maecenas to put his signet<note anchored="yes" n="84"
       resp="TAB">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Imprimat his, cura.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.38"/>
        </cit>
        <placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName> informs us, that Maecenas was intrusted with
        the great seal of the Roman Empire, and was a kind of Lord High Chancellor to Augustus.</p>
      </note> to these tablets." Should one say, "I will endeavor at it:" "If you will, you can,"
      adds he; and is more earnest.</p>
     <p>The seventh year approaching to the eighth is now elapsed, from the time that Maecenas began
      to reckon me in the number of his friends; only thus far, as one he would like to take along
      with him in his chariot, when he went a journey, and to whom he would trust such kind of
      trifles as these: "What is the hour?" "Is Gallina, the Thracian, a match for [the gladiator]
      Syrus?" "The cold morning air begins to pinch those that are ill provided against it;"
      &mdash; and such things as are well enough intrusted to a leaky ear. For all this time,
      every day and hour, I have been more subjected to envy. Our son of fortune here, says every
      body, witnessed the shows in company with [Maecenas], and played with him in the <placeName
       key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName>. Does any disheartening report spread from the
      rostrum through the streets, whoever comes in my way cousults me [concerning it]: "Good sir,
      have you (for you must know, since you approach nearer the gods) heard any thing relating to
      the Dacians?"<note anchored="yes" n="85" resp="San">
       <p>The Dacians had engaged in Antony's army at the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010713"
         >Actium</placeName>, in 723, and Octavius had disobliged them by refusing some favors which
        they demanded by their embassadors. He was obliged to send Marcus Crassus against them the
        year following. SAN.</p>
      </note> "Nothing at all for my part," [I reply]. "How you ever are a sneerer!" "But may all
      the gods torture me, if I know any thing of the matter." "What? will Caesar give the
       lands<note anchored="yes" n="86" resp="Dac, San">
       <p>Octavius promised the soldiers who had served under him in reducing <placeName
         key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, that he would divide some of the conquered lands
        among them. But the war in which he was engaged against Antony obliged him to defer the
        division, and immediately after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010713"
        >Actium</placeName>, the troops, which he had sent to <placeName key="perseus,Brundusium"
         >Brundusium</placeName>, mutinied on this occasion.</p>
       <p>He went himself to stop the beginning of a revolt, which might have been attended with
        most dangerous consequences. This affair was all the news at <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
         >Rome</placeName> when our poet wrote the present Satire.</p>
       <p><placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> was called Triquetra from its triangular
        figure, and in some ancient coins it is represented under the figure of a woman with three
        legs.</p>
      </note> he promised the soldiers, in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, or in
       <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>?" As I am swearing I know nothing about it,
      they wonder at me, [thinking] me, to be sure, a creature of profound and extraordinary
      secrecy. <milestone ed="p" n="59" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Among things of this nature the day is wasted by me, mortified as I am, not without such
      wishes as these: 0 rural retirement, when shall I behold thee? and when shall it be in my
      power to pass through the pleasing oblivion of a life full of solicitude, one while with the
      books of the ancients, another while in sleep and leisure? 0 when shall the bean related to
       Pythagoras,<note anchored="yes" n="87" resp="McCaul">
       <p>It was one of Pythagoras' precepts, that beans should not be used as food by any of his
        disciples, lest in the course of transformation the soul of some relative should be placed
        therein, and thus the impiety (as Lucian, Micyll., represents it) be as great as that of
        eating human flesh. Hence Horace humorously calls the bean <cit>
         <quote lang="la">Pythagorae cognata.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.6.62"/>
        </cit> There are various reasons assigned for the origin of this precept.</p>
      </note> and at the same time herbs well larded with fat bacon, be set before me? O evenings,
      and suppers fit for gods! with which I and my friends regale ourselves in the presence of my
      household gods; and feed my saucy slaves with viands, of which libations have been made. The
      guest, according to every one's inclination, takes off the glasses of different sizes, free
      from mad laws: whether one of a strong constitution chooses hearty bumpers; or another more
      joyously gets mellow with moderate ones. Then conversation arises, not concerning other
      people's villas and houses, nor whether Lepos dances well or not; but we debate on what is
      more to our purpose, and what it is pernicious not to know-whether men are made happier by
      riches or by virtue; or what leads us into intimacies, interest or moral rectitude; and what
      is the nature of good, and what its perfection. Meanwhile, my neighbor Cervius prates away old
      stories relative to the subject. For, if any one ignorantly commends the troublesome riches of
      Aurelius, he thus begins: "On a time a countrymouse is reported to have received a city-mouse
      into his poor cave, an old host, his old acquaintance; a blunt fellow and attentive to his
      acquisitions, yet so as he could [on occasion] enlarge his narrow soul in acts of hospitality.
      What need of many words? He neither grudged him the hoarded vetches, nor the long oats; and
      bringing in his mouth a dry plum, and nibbled scraps of bacon, presented them to him, being
      desirous by the variety of the supper to get the better of the daintiness of his guest, who
      hardly touched with his delicate tooth the several things: while the father of the family
      himself, extended on fresh straw, ate a spelt and darnel, leaving that which was better [for
      his guest]. At length the citizen addressing him, &lsquo;Friend,&rsquo; says he,
      &lsquo;what delight have you to live laboriously on the ridge of a rugged thicket? Will
      you not prefer men and the city to the savage woods? Take my advice, and go along with me:
      since mortal lives are allotted to all terrestrial animals, nor is there any escape from
      death, either for the great or the small. Wherefore, my good friend, while it is in your
      power, live happy in joyous circumstances: live mindful of how brief an existence you
      are.&rsquo; Soon as these speeches had wrought upon the peasant, he leaps nimbly from his
      cave: thence they both pursue their intended journey, being desirous to steal under the city
      walls by night. And now the night possessed the middle region of the heavens, when each of
      them set foot in a gorgeous palace, where carpets dyed with crimson grain glittered upon ivory
      couches, and many baskets of a magnificent entertainment remained, which had yesterday been
      set by in baskets piled upon one another. After he had placed the peasant then, stretched at
      ease, upon a splendid carpet; he bustles about like an adroit host, and keeps bringing up one
      dish close upon another, and with an affected civility performs all the ceremonies, first
      tasting of every thing he serves up. He, reclined, rejoices in the change of his situation,
      and acts the part of a boon companion in the good cheer: when on a sudden a prodigious
      rattling of the folding doors shook them both from their couches. Terrified they began to
      scamper all about the room, and more and more heartless to be in confusion, while the lofty
      house resounded with [the barking of] mastiff dogs; upon which, says the country-mouse,
      &lsquo;I have no desire for a life like this; and so farewell: my wood and cave, secure
      from surprises, shall with homely tares comfort me.&rsquo;" </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="7">
     <head>One of Horace's slaves, making use of that freedom which was allowed them at the
       Saturnalia,<note anchored="yes" n="88" resp="Dac, San">
       <p>The particular design of the Saturnalia was to represent that equality, which reigned
        among mankind in the reign of Saturn, when they lived according to the laws of nature,
        without distinction of conditions. Horace here introduces a slave, asserting that a wise man
        alone is free, and that real liberty consists in not obeying our passions, or being enslaved
        to vice. He boldly reproaches his master with his faults and follies. His reasoning is so
        natural, sensible, and pressing, that Horace, not being able to answer him, at last loses
        his temper, and is obliged to make use of menaces to silence him.</p>
      </note> rates his master in a droll and severe manner.</head>

     <p>I HAVE a long while been attending [to you], and would fain speak a few words [in return;
      but, being] a slave, I am afraid. "What, Davus?" Yes, Davus, a faithful servant to his
       master<note anchored="yes" n="89" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Frugi quod sit satis; hoc est.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.3"/>
        </cit> The common people have always imagined that persons of eminent merit do not live so
        long as others. From thence the proverb, "Too witty to live long."</p>
      </note> and an honest one, at least sufficiently so: that is, for you to think his life in no
      danger. "Well (since our ancestors would have it so), use the freedom of December: speak on."</p>
     <p>One part of mankind are fond of their vices with some con. stancy and adhere to their
      purpose: a considerable part fluctuates; one while embracing the right, another while liable
      to depravity. Priscus, frequently observed with three rings, sometimes with his left hand
       bare,<note anchored="yes" n="90" resp="Bond">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Laeva Priscus inani.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.9"/>
        </cit> Before the time of Horace it was infamous to wear more than one ring, and when they
        began to wear more, they carried them only on the left hand, which was less exposed to
        public view, as if they would seem ashamed of such marks of effeminacy.</p>
      </note> lived so irregularly that he would change his robe every hour; from a magnificent
      edifice, he would on a sudden hide himself in a place, whence a decent freedman could scarcely
      come out in a decent manner; one while he would choose to lead the life of a rake at
       <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, another while that of a teacher at <placeName
       key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; born under the evil influence of every
       Vertumnus.<note anchored="yes" n="91" resp="Bond, San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Vertumnis natis iniquis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.14"/>
        </cit> Vertumnus presided over the regular seasons of the year, established by the laws of
        nature. Priscus was therefore born in despite of the god, because all his changes were an
        effect of oddness and whim. Horace multiplies this god, Vertumni, from the different forms
        under which he was represented.</p>
      </note> That buffoon, Volanerius, when the deserved gout had crippled his fingers, maintained
      [a fellow] that he had hired at a daily price, who took up the dice and put them into a box
      for him: yet by how much more constant was he in his vice, by so much less wretched was he
      than the former person, who is now in difficulties by too loose, now by too tight a rein.
      "Will you not tell to-day, you varlet, whither such wretched stuff as this tends?" "Why, to
      you, I say." "In what respect to me, scoundrel?"</p>
     <p>You praise the happiness and manners of the ancient [Roman] people; and yet, if any god were
      on a sudden to reduce you to them, you, the same man, would earnestly beg to be excused;
      either because you are not really of opinion that what you bawl about is right; or because you
      are irresolute in defending the right, and hesitate, in vain desirous to extract your foot
      from the mire. At <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, you long for the country;
      when you are in the country, fickle, you extol the absent city to the skies. If haply you are
      invited out nowhere to supper, you praise your quiet dish of vegetables; and as if you ever go
      abroad upon conpulsion, you think yourself so happy, and do so hug yourself, that you are
      obliged to drink out nowhere. Should Maecenas lay his commands on you to come late, at the
      first lighting up of the lamps, as his guest; &lsquo;Will nobody bring the oil with more
      expedition? Does any body hear?&rsquo; You stutter with a mighty bellowing, and storm with
      rage. Milvius, and the buffoons [who expected to sup with you], depart, after having uttered
      curses not proper to be repeated. Any one may say, for I own [the truth], that I am easy to be
      seduced by my appetite; I snuff up my nose at a savory smell: I am weak, lazy; and, if you
      have a mind to add any thing else, I am a sot. But seeing you are as I am, and perhaps
      something worse, why do you willfully call me to an. account, as if you were the better man;
      and, with specious phrases, disguise your own vice? What, if you are found out to be a greater
      fool than me, who was purchased for five hundred drachmas? Forbear to terrify me with your
      looks; restrain your hand and your anger, while I relate to you what Crispinus' porter taught
      me. <milestone ed="p" n="46" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Another man's wife captivates you; a harlot, Davus: which of us sins more deservingly of the
      cross? When keen nature inflames me, any common wench that picks me up, dismisses me neither
      dishonored, nor caring whether a richer or a handsomer man enjoys her next. You, when you have
      cast off your ensigns of dignity, your equestrian ring and your Roman habit, turn out from a
      magistrate a wretched <placeName key="tgn,1085129">Dama</placeName>,<note anchored="yes"
       n="92" resp="Dac">
       <p>Davus calls his master a judge, because Augustus had granted him the privilege of wearing
        a ring and a robe, called <foreign lang="la">Angusticlavium</foreign>. Thus he was in some
        measure incorporated into the body of Roman knights, whom Augustus appointed to determine
        civil causes. By "Dama" he means a mere slave.</p>
      </note> hiding with a cape your perfumed head: are you not really what you personate? You are
      introduced, apprehensive [of consequences]; and, as you are altercating with your passions,
      your bones shake with fear. What is the difference whether you go condemned [like a
      gladiator], to be galled with scourges,<note anchored="yes" n="93" resp="Torr">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Uri virgis.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.58"/>
        </cit> The people who sold themselves to a master of gladiators, engaged in a form or bond,
        called <foreign lang="la">auctoramentum</foreign>, to suffer every thing, sword, fire,
        whips, chains, and death. They were then received into the profession, and styled <foreign
         lang="la">auctorati</foreign>. From thence the terms came to be used for all kinds of
        infamous engagements.</p>
      </note> or slain with the sword; or be closed up in a filthy chest, where [the maid],
      conscious of her mistress' crime, has stowed you? Has not the husband of the offending dame a
      just power over both; against the seducer even a juster? But she neither changes her dress,
      nor place, nor sins to that excess [which you do]; since the woman is in dread of you, nor
      gives any credit to you, though you profess to love her. You must go under the yoke knowingly,
      and put all your fortune, your life, and reputation, together with your limbs, into the power
      of an enraged husband. Have you escaped? I suppose, then, you will be afraid [for the future];
      and, being warned, will be cautious. No, you will seek occasion when you may be again in
      terror, and again may be likely to perish. 0 so often a slave! What beast, when it has once
      escaped by breaking its toils, absurdly trusts itself to them again? You say, "I am no
      adulterer." Nor, by Hercules, am I a thief, when I wisely pass by the silver vases. Take away
      the danger, and vagrant nature will spring forth, when restraints are removed. Are you my
      superior, subjected as you are, to the dominion of so many things and persons,, whom the
      prsetor's rod,<note anchored="yes" n="94" resp="TAB">
       <p><foreign lang="la">Vindicta</foreign> was a rod, which the lictor laid on the head of a
        person whom the praetor made free. Plautus calls it <quote lang="la">festuca</quote>. <bibl
         n="Pl. Mil. 961">(Mil. 961)</bibl></p>
      </note> though placed on your head three or four times over, can never free from this wretched
      solicitude? Add, to what has been said above, a thing of no less weight; whether he be an
       underling,<note anchored="yes" n="95" resp="San">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Nam sive vicarius.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.89"/>
        </cit> The Romans generally had a master-slave in every family, <foreign lang="la">servus
         atriensis</foreign>, and all other slaves were called by one common name, <foreign
         lang="la">vicarii</foreign>. The first, who commands, is not less a slave than those who
        obey.</p>
      </note> who obeys the master-slave (as it is your custom to affirm), or only a fellow slave,
      what am I in respect of you? You, for example, who have the command of me, are in subjection
      to other things, and are led about, like a puppet movable by means of wires not its own.
       <milestone ed="p" n="83" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>Who then is free? The wise man, who has dominion over himself; whom neither poverty, nor
      death, nor chains affright; brave in the checking of his appetites, and in contemning honors;
      and, perfect in himself, polished and round as a globe,<note anchored="yes" n="96"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Teres atque rotundus.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.86"/>
        </cit> The metaphor is taken from a globe, and our vices are those inequalities which stop
        us in our course of virtue.</p>
      </note> so that nothing from without can retard, in consequence of its smoothness; against
      whom misfortune ever advances ineffectually. Can you, out of these, recognize any thing
      applicable to yourself? A woman demands five talents of you, plagues you, and after you are
      turned out of doors, bedews you with cold water: she calls you again. Rescue your neck from
      this vile yoke; come, say, I am free, I am free. You are not able: for an implacable master
      oppresses your mind, and claps the sharp spurs to your jaded appetite, and forces you on
      though reluctant. When you, mad one, quite languish at a picture by Pausias;<note
       anchored="yes" n="97" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Pausias was a famous flower-painter. Lucullus gave a thousand crowns for a picture, in
        which he drew his mistress Glycera sitting, and making a wreath of flowers. He was a
        contemporary of Apelles.</p>
      </note> how are you less to blame than I, when I admire the combats of Fulvius and Rutuba and
      Placideianus, with their bended knees, painted in crayons<note anchored="yes" n="98"
       resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Masters of gladiators hung the pictures of their best champions, such as Fulvius, Rutuba,
        or Placideianus, at the door of the house where they fought.</p>
      </note> or charcoal, as if the men were actually engaged, and push and parry, moving heir
      weapons? Davus is a scoundrel and a loiterer; but you have the character of an exquisite and
      expert connoisseur in antiquities. If I am allured by a smoking pasty, I am a good-for-nothing
      fellow: does your great virtue and soul resist delicate entertainments? Why is a tenderness
      for my belly too destructive for me? For my back pays for it. How do you come off with more
      impunity, since you hanker after such dainties as can not be had for a little expense? Then
      those delicacies, perpetually taken, pall upon the stomach; and your mistaken feet refuse to
      support your sickly body. Is that boy guilty, who by night pawns a stolen scraper for some
      grapes? Has he nothing servile about him, who in indulgence to his guts sells his estates? Add
      to this, that you yourself can not be an hour by yourself, nor dispose of your leisure in a
      right manner; and shun yourself as a fugitive and vagabond, one while endeavoring with wine,
      another while with sleep, to cheat care-in vain: for the gloomy companion presses upon you,
      and pursues you in your flight. "Where can I get a stone?" "What occasion is there for it?"
      "Where some darts?" "The man is either mad, or making verses." "If you do not take yourself
      away in an instant, you shall go [and make] a ninth laborer<note anchored="yes" n="99"
       resp="Dac">
       <p><cit>
         <quote lang="la">Accedes opera.</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.7.118"/>
        </cit>
        <foreign lang="la">Opera</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">servus</foreign>. Slaves who were
        employed in tilling their lands were generally chained, so that the threat was enough to
        alarm Davus, and end the conversation.</p>
      </note> at my <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> estate." </p>
    </div2>
    <div2 type="poem" n="8">
     <head>A smart description of a miser ridiculously acting the extravagant.</head>

     <p>How did the entertainment of that happy fellow Nasidienus please you? for yesterday, as I
      was seeking to make you my guest, you were said to be drinking there from mid-day.<note
       anchored="yes" n="100" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Nasidienus, to give himself an air of a rake, dines three or four hours before the usual
        time; or perhaps Fundanius would insinuate that this was too solemn a feast for vulgar
        hours.</p>
      </note> [It pleased me so], that I never was happier in my life. Say (if it be not
      troublesome) what food first calmed your raging appetite.</p>
     <p>In the first place, there was a Lucanian boar, taken when the gentle south wind blew,<note
       anchored="yes" n="1" resp="ed. Dubl.">
       <p>Either by buying it cheap, or keeping it too long, the boar was tainted; but our host
        would insinuate that it had a particular flavor, by being taken when the wind was south,
        which made it delicate and tender.</p>
      </note> as the father of the entertainment affirmed; around it sharp rapes, lettuces,
      radishes; such things as provoke a languid appetite; skirrets, anchovies, dregs of Coan wine.
      These once removed, one slave, tucked high with a purple cloth,<note anchored="yes" n="2"
       resp="Dac">
       <p>The table was made of maple, a cheap and common wood; but Nasidienus, in an air of polite
        extravagance, makes the slaves wipe it with a purple napkin.</p>
      </note> wiped the maple table, and a second gathered up whatever lay useless, and whatever
      could offend the guests;<note anchored="yes" n="3" resp="Dac">
       <p>This was the pretense, that nothing might offend his guests, but his design was that
        nothing might be lost. </p>
      </note> swarthy <placeName key="tgn,7002541">Hydaspes</placeName> advances like an Attic maid
      with <placeName key="tgn,7010621">Ceres</placeName>' sacred rites, bearing wines of Caecubum;
      Alcon brings those of <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>, undamaged by the
       sea.<note anchored="yes" n="4" resp="Lamb">
       <p>It was customary to mix sea-water with the strong wines of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
         >Greece</placeName>; but Fundanius, when he tells us that the wine Alcon carried had not a
        drop of water in it, would have us understand that this wine had never crossed the seas, and
        that it was an Italian wine which Nasidienus recommended for Chian.</p>
      </note> Here the master [cries], "Maecenas, if <placeName key="tgn,1031727">Alban</placeName>
      or Falernian wine delight you more than those already brought, we have both."</p>
     <p>Ill-fated riches! But, Fundanius, I am impatient to know, who were sharers-in this feast
      where you fared so well. I was highest, and next me was Viscus Thurinus, and below, if I
      remember, was Varius; with Servilius Balatro, Vibidius, whom Maecenas had brought along with
      him, unbidden guests. Above [Nasidienus] himself was Nomentanus, below him Porcius, ridiculous
      for swallowing whole cakes at once. Nomentanus [was present] for this purpose, that if any
      thing should chance to be unobserved, he might show it with his pointing finger. For the other
      company, we, I mean, eat [promiscuously] of fowls, oysters, fish, which had concealed in them
      a juice far different from the known: as presently appeared, when he reached to me the
      entrails of a plaice and of a turbot, such as had never been tasted before. After this he
      informed me that honey-apples were most ruddy when gathered under the waning moon. What
      difference this makes you will hear best from himself. Then [says] Vibidius to Balatro; "If we
      do not drink to his cost, we shall die in his debt;" and he calls for larger tumblers. A
      paleness changed the countenance of our host, who fears nothing so much as hard drinkers:
      either because they are more freely censorious; or because heating wines deafen the subtle
      [judgment of the] palate. Vibidius and Balatro, all following their example, pour whole casks
      into Alliphanians;<note anchored="yes" n="5" resp="schol">
       <p>Large cups, so called from <placeName key="perseus,Allifae">Allifae</placeName>, a town of
        Samnium.</p>
      </note> the guests of the lowest couch did no hurt to the flagons. A lamprey is brought in,
      extended in a dish, in the midst of floating shrimps. Whereupon, "This," says the master, "was
      caught when pregnant; which, after having young, would have been less delicate in its flesh."
      For these a sauce is mixed up; with oil which the best cellar of <placeName
       key="perseus,Venafrum">Venafrum</placeName> pressed, with pickle from the juices of the
      Iberian fish, with wine of five years old, but produced on this side the sea, while it is
      boiling (after it is boiled, the Chian wine suits it so well, that no other does better than
      it) with white pepper, and vinegar which, by being vitiated, turned sour the Methymnean grape.</p>
     <p>I first showed the way to stew in it the green rockets and bitter elecampane: Curtillus, [to
      stew in it] the sea-urchins unwashed, as being better than the pickle which the sea shell-fish
      yields. <milestone ed="p" n="54" unit="card"/></p>
     <p>In the mean time the suspended tapestry made a heavy downfall upon the dish, bringing along
      with it more black dust than the north wind ever raises on the plains of <placeName
       key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>. Having been fearful of something worse, as soon as we
      perceive there was no danger, we rise up. Rufus, hanging his head, began to weep, as if his
      son had come to an untimely death: what would have been the end, had not the discreet
      Nomentanus thus raised his friend! "Alas! 0 fortune, what god is more cruel to us than thou?
      How dost thou always take pleasure in sporting with human affairs!" Varius could scarcely
      smother a laugh with his napkin. Balatro, sneering at every thing, observed: "This is the
      condition of human life, and therefore a suitable glory will never answer your labor. Must you
      be rent and tortured with all manner of anxiety, that I may be entertained sumptuously; lest
      burned bread, lest ill-seasoned soup should be set before us; that all your slaves should
      wait, properly attired and neat? Add, besides, these accidents; if the hangings should tumble
      down, as just now, if the groom slipping with his foot should break a dish. But adversity is
      wont to disclose, prosperity to conceal, the abilities of a host as well as of a general." To
      this Nasidienus: "May the gods give you all the blessings, whatever you can pray for, you are
      so good a man and so civil a guest;" and calls for his sandals.<note anchored="yes" n="6"
       resp="Torr">
       <p>That he might rise from table. The guests laid their slippers at the end of the bed when
        they went to supper.</p>
      </note> Then on every couch you might see divided whispers buzzing in each secret ear. I would
      not choose to have seen any theatrical entertainments sooner than these things. But come,
      recount what you laughed at next. While Vibidius is inquiring of the slaves, whether the
      flagon was also broken,<note anchored="yes" n="7" resp="Cruq, Dac">
       <p>Vibidius asks whether the groom had broken the bottle at the same time that he broke the
        dish, for <foreign lang="la">quoque</foreign> certainly refers to <cit>
         <quote lang="la">patinam lapsus frangat agaso</quote>
         <bibl n="Hor. S. 2.8.72"/>
        </cit>. He seems to insinuate that Nasidienus had given orders to his slaves not to be in
        too much haste to supply the guests with wine, but to let them call for it more than
       once.</p>
      </note> because cups were not brought when he called for them; and while a laugh is continued
      on feigned pretences, Balatro seconding it; you, Nasidienus, return with an altered
      countenance, as if to repair your ill-fortune by art. Then followed the slaves, bearing on a
      large charger the several limbs of a crane besprinkled with much salt, not without flour, and
      the liver of a white goose fed with fattening figs, and the wings of hares torn off, as a much
      daintier dish than if one eats them with the loins. Then we saw blackbirds also set before us
      with scorched breasts, and ringdoves without the rumps: delicious morsels! did not the master
      give us the history of their causes and natures: whom we in revenge fled from, so as to taste
      nothing at all; as if Canidia, more venomous than African serpents, had poisoned them with her
      breath.</p>
    </div2>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>
