<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Against Apion</title>
	<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	<author>Flavius Josephus</author>
	<editor role="translator">William Whiston, A.M.</editor>
      &responsibility;
      &fund.Tufts;
      </titleStmt>
	&Perseus.publish;
      <sourceDesc>
	<biblStruct>
	  <monogr>
	    <author>Flavius Josephus</author>
	    <title>The Works of Flavius Josephus</title>
	    <respStmt><resp>Translated by</resp>
	      <name>William Whiston, A.M.</name></respStmt>
	    <imprint>
	      <pubPlace>Auburn and Buffalo</pubPlace>
	      <publisher>John E. Beardsley</publisher>
	      <date>1895</date>
	    </imprint>
	  </monogr>
	</biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
	<state delim="." unit="book"/>
	<state unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
	<state delim="." unit="book"/>
	<state n="chunk" unit="Whiston section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language id="en">English
	</language><language id="la">Latin
	</language><language id="xhebrew">Transliterated Hebrew
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>29 February 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: j.ap_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-11-24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:30  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 16:16:03  packel
removed stray item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:54  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.6  2005/03/30 20:29:09  packel
fixed milestone units

Revision 1.5  2003/07/01 22:17:10  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.4  2000/03/08 16:40:17  dasmith
Funded by Tufts, not NEH.

Revision 1.3  2000/03/04 20:34:45  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.2  2000/03/01 02:25:22  dasmith
Added Niese sections at Whiston section breaks.

Revision 1.1  2000/03/01 02:17:04  dasmith
Added to repository.


</item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="Book" n="1">
<head>BOOK I</head>
<milestone n="1" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><p><note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This first book has a wrong title. It is not written against Apion, as
is the first part of the second book, but against those Greeks in general
who would not believe Josephus's former accounts of the very ancient state
of the Jewish nation, in his 20 books of Antiquities; and particularly
against Agatharelddes, Manetho, Cheremon, and Lysimachus. it is one of
the most learned, excellent, and useful books of all antiquity; and upon
Jerome's perusal of this and the following book, he declares that it seems
to him a miraculous thing "how one that was a Hebrew, who had been
from his infancy instructed in sacred learning, should be able to pronounce
such a number of testimonies out of profane authors, as if he had read
over all the Grecian libraries," Epist. 8. ad Magnum; and the learned
Jew, Manasseh-Ben-Israel, esteemed these two books so excellent, as to
translate them into the Hebrew; this we learn from his own catalogue of
his works, which I have seen. As to the time and place when and where these
two books were written, the learned have not hitherto been able to determine
them any further than that they were written some time after his Antiquities,
or some time after A.D. <date value="93">93</date>; which indeed is too obvious at their entrance
to be overlooked by even a careless peruser, they being directly intended
against those that would not believe what he had advanced in those books
con-the great of the Jewish nation As to the place, they all imagine that
these two books were written where the former were, I mean at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; and
I confess that I myself believed both those determinations, till I came
to finish my notes upon these books, when I met with plain indications
that they were written not at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, but in <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, and this after the third
of Trajan, or A.D. <date value="100">100</date>.</note>
I SUPPOSE that by my books of the Antiquity of the Jews, most excellent
Epaphroditus, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Take Dr. Hudson's note here, which as it justly contradicts the common
opinion that Josephus either died under Domitian, or at least wrote nothing
later than his days, so does it perfectly agree to my own determination,
from Justus of <placeName key="tgn,7017529">Tiberias</placeName>, that he wrote or finished his own Life after the
third of Trajan, or A.D. <date value="100">100</date>. To which Noldius also agrees, de Herod, No.
383 [Epaphroditus]. "Since Florius Josephus," says Dr. Hudson,
"wrote [or finished] his books of Antiquities on the thirteenth of
Domitian, [A.D. <date value="93">93</date>,] and after that wrote the Memoirs of his own Life,
as an appendix to the books of Antiquities, and at last his two books against
Apion, and yet dedicated all those writings to Epaphroditus; he can hardly
be that Epaphroditus who was formerly secretary to Nero, and was slain
on the fourteenth [or fifteenth] of Domitian, after he had been for a good
while in banishment; but another Epaphroditas, a freed-man, and procurator
of Trajan, as says Grotius on Luke 1:3.</note>
have made it evident to those who peruse them, that our Jewish nation is
of very great antiquity, and had a distinct subsistence of its own originally;
as also, I have therein declared how we came to inhabit this country wherein
we now live. Those Antiquities contain the history of five thousand years,
and are taken out of our sacred books, but are translated by me into the
Greek tongue. However, since I observe a considerable number of people
giving ear to the reproaches that are laid against us by those who bear
ill-will to us, and will not believe what I have written concerning the
antiquity of our nation, while they take it for a plain sign that our nation
is of a late date, because they are not so much as vouchsafed a bare mention
by the most famous historiographers among the Grecians. I therefore have
thought myself under an obligation to write somewhat briefly about these
subjects, in order to convict those that reproach us of spite and voluntary
falsehood, and to correct the ignorance of others, and withal to instruct
all those who are desirous of knowing the truth of what great antiquity
we really are. As for the witnesses whom I shall produce for the proof
of what I say, they shall be such as are esteemed to be of the greatest
reputation for truth, and the most skillful in the knowledge of all antiquity
by the Greeks themselves. I will also show, that those who have written
so reproachfully and falsely about us are to be convicted by what they
have written themselves to the contrary. I shall also endeavor to give
an account of the reasons why it hath so happened, that there have not
been a great number of Greeks who have made mention of our nation in their
histories. I will, however, bring those Grecians to light who have not
omitted such our history, for the sake of those that either do not know
them, or pretend not to know them already.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="6" unit="section"/><p>And now, in the first place, I cannot but greatly wonder at those
men, who suppose that we must attend to none but Grecians, when we are
inquiring about the most ancient facts, and must inform ourselves of their
truth from them only, while we must not believe ourselves nor other men;
for I am convinced that the very reverse is the truth of the case. I mean
this, - if we will not be led by vain opinions, but will make inquiry after
truth from facts themselves; for they will find that almost all which concerns
the Greeks happened not long ago; nay, one may say, is of yesterday only.
I speak of the building of their cities, the inventions of their arts,
and the description of their laws; and as for their care about the writing
down of their histories, it is very near the last thing they set about.
However, they acknowledge themselves so far, that they were the Egyptians,
the Chaldeans, and the Phoenicians (for I will not now reckon ourselves
among them) that have preserved the memorials of the most ancient and most
lasting traditions of mankind; for almost all these nations inhabit such
countries as are least subject to destruction from the world about them;
and these also have taken especial care to have nothing omitted of what
was [remarkably] done among them; but their history was esteemed sacred,
and put into public tables, as written by men of the greatest wisdom they
had among them. But as for the place where the Grecians inhabit, ten thousand
destructions have overtaken it, and blotted out the memory of former actions;
so that they were ever beginning a new way of living, and supposed that
every one of them was the origin of their new state. It was also late,
and with difficulty, that they came to know the letters they now use; for
those who would advance their use of these letters to the greatest antiquity
pretend that they learned them from the Phoenicians and from Cadmus; yet
is nobody able to demonstrate that they have any writing preserved from
that time, neither in their temples, nor in any other public monuments.
This appears, because the time when those lived who went to the Trojan
war, so many years afterward, is in great doubt, and great inquiry is made,
whether the Greeks used their letters at that time; and the most prevailing
opinion, and that nearest the truth, is, that their present way of using
those letters was unknown at that time. However, there is not any writing
which the Greeks agree to he genuine among them ancienter than Homer's
Poems, who must plainly he confessed later than the siege of <placeName key="tgn,7002329">Troy</placeName>; nay,
the report goes, that even he did not leave his poems in writing, but that
their memory was preserved in songs, and they were put together afterward,
and that this is the reason of such a number of variations as are found
in them. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">The preservation of Homer's Poems by memory, and not by his own writing
them down, and that thence they were styled Rhapsodies, as sung by him,
like ballads, by parts, and not composed and connected together in complete
works, are opinions well known from the ancient commentators; though such
supposal seems to myself, as well as to Fabricius Biblioth. Grace. I. p.
269, and to others, highly improbable. Nor does Josephus say there were
no ancienter writings among the Greeks than Homer's Poems, but that they
did not fully own any ancienter writings pretending to such antiquity,
which is trite.</note>
As for those who set themselves about writing their histories, I mean such
as Cadmus of <placeName key="tgn,7002386">Miletus</placeName>, and Acusilaus of <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, and any others that may be
mentioned as succeeding Acusilaus, they lived but a little while before
the Persian expedition into <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. But then for those that first introduced
philosophy, and the consideration of things celestial and divine among
them, such as Pherceydes the Syrian, and Pythagoras, and Thales, all with
one consent agree, that they learned what they knew of the Egyptians and
Chaldeans, and wrote but little And these are the things which are supposed
to be the oldest of all among the Greeks; and they have much ado to believe
that the writings ascribed to those men are genuine.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="15" unit="section"/><p>How can it then be other than an absurd thing, for the Greeks to
be so proud, and to vaunt themselves to be the only people that are acquainted
with antiquity, and that have delivered the true accounts of those early
times after an accurate manner? Nay, who is there that cannot easily gather
from the Greek writers themselves, that they knew but little on any good
foundation when they set to write, but rather wrote their histories from
their own conjectures? Accordingly, they confute one another in their own
books to purpose, and are not ashamed. to give us the most contradictory
accounts of the same things; and I should spend my time to little purpose,
if I should pretend to teach the Greeks that which they know better than
I already, what a great disagreement there is between Hellanicus and Acusilaus
about their genealogies; in how many eases Acusilaus corrects Hesiod: or
after what manner Ephorus demonstrates Hellanicus to have told lies in
the greatest part of his history; as does Timeus in like manner as to Ephorus,
and the succeeding writers do to Timeus, and all the later writers do to
Herodotus <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">The preservation of Homer's Poems by memory, and not by his own writing
them down, and that thence they were styled Rhapsodies, as sung by him,
like ballads, by parts, and not composed and connected together in complete
works, are opinions well known from the ancient commentators; though such
supposal seems to myself, as well as to Fabricius Biblioth. Grace. I. p.
269, and to others, highly improbable. Nor does Josephus say there were
no ancienter writings among the Greeks than Homer's Poems, but that they
did not fully own any ancienter writings pretending to such antiquity,
which is trite.</note>
nor could Timeus agree with Antiochus and Philistius, or with Callias,
about the Sicilian History, no more than do the several writers of the
Athide follow one another about the Athenian affairs; nor do the historians
the like, that wrote the Argolics, about the affairs of the Argives. And
now what need I say any more about particular cities and smaller places,
while in the most approved writers of the expedition of the Persians, and
of the actions which were therein performed, there are so great differences?
Nay, Thucydides himself is accused of some as writing what is false, although
he seems to have given us the exactest history of the affairs of his own
time. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">It well deserves to be considered, that Josephus here says how all the
following Greek historians looked on Herodotus as a fabulous author; and
presently, sect. 14, how Manetho, the most authentic writer of the Egyptian
history, greatly complains of his mistakes in the Egyptian affairs; as
also that Strabo, B. XI. p. 507, the most accurate geographer and historian,
esteemed him such; that Xenophon, the much more accurate historian in the
affairs of Cyrus, implies that Herodotus's account of that great man is
almost entirely romantic. See the notes on Antiq. B. XI. ch. 2. sect. 1,
and Hutchinson's Prolegomena to his edition of Xenophon's, that we have
already seen in the note on Antiq. B. VIII. ch. 10. sect. 3, how very little
Herodotus knew about the Jewish affairs and country, and that he greatly
affected what we call the marvelous, as Monsieur Rollin has lately and
justly determined; whence we are not always to depend on the authority
of Herodotus, where it is unsupported by other evidence, but ought to compare
the other evidence with his, and if it preponderate, to prefer it before
his. I do not mean by this that Herodotus willfully related what he believed
to be false, (as Cteeias seems to have done,) but that he often wanted
evidence, and sometimes preferred what was marvelous to what was best attested
as really true.</note></p>
<milestone n="4" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="19" unit="section"/><p>As for the occasions of so great disagreement of theirs, there may
be assigned many that are very probable, if any have a mind to make an
inquiry about them; but I ascribe these contradictions chiefly to two causes,
which I will now mention, and still think what I shall mention in the first
place to be the principal of all. For if we remember that in the beginning
the Greeks had taken no care to have public records of their several transactions
preserved, this must for certain have afforded those that would afterward
write about those ancient transactions the opportunity of making mistakes,
and the power of making lies also; for this original recording of such
ancient transactions hath not only been neglected by the other states of
<placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, but even among the Athenians themselves also, who pretend to be
Aborigines, and to have applied themselves to learning, there are no such
records extant; nay, they say themselves that the laws of Draco concerning
murders, which are now extant in writing, are the most ancient of their
public records; which Draco yet lived but a little before the tyrant Pisistratus.
<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">About the days of Cyrus and Daniel.</note>
For as to the Arcadians, who make such boasts of their antiquity, what
need I speak of them in particular, since it was still later before they
got their letters, and learned them, and that with difficulty also. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">It is here well worth our observation, what the reasons are that such ancient
authors as Herodotus, Josephus, and others have been read to so little
purpose by many learned critics; viz. that their main aim has not been
chronology or history, but philology, to know words, and not things, they
not much entering oftentimes into the real contents of their authors, and
judging which were the most accurate discoverers of truth, and most to
be depended on in the several histories, but rather inquiring who wrote
the finest style, and had the greatest elegance in their expressions; which
are things of small consequence in comparison of the other. Thus you will
sometimes find great debates among the learned, whether Herodotus or Thucydides
were the finest historian in the Ionic and Attic ways of writing; which
signify little as to the real value of each of their histories; while it
would be of much more moment to let the reader know, that as the consequence
of Herodotus's history, which begins so much earlier, and reaches so much
wider, than that of Thucydides, is therefore vastly greater; so is the
most part of Thucydides, which belongs to his own times, and fell under
his own observation, much the most certain.</note></p>
<milestone n="5" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="23" unit="section"/><p>There must therefore naturally arise great differences among writers,
when they had no original records to lay for their foundation, which might
at once inform those who had an inclination to learn, and contradict those
that would tell lies. However, we are to suppose a second occasion besides
the former of these contradictions; it is this: That those who were the
most zealous to write history were not solicitous for the discovery of
truth, although it was very easy for them always to make such a profession;
but their business was to demonstrate that they could write well, and make
an impression upon mankind thereby; and in what manner of writing they
thought they were able to exceed others, to that did they apply themselves,
Some of them betook themselves to the writing of fabulous narrations; some
of them endeavored to please the cities or the kings, by writing in their
commendation; others of them fell to finding faults with transactions,
or with the writers of such transactions, and thought to make a great figure
by so doing. And indeed these do what is of all things the most contrary
to true history; for it is the great character of true history that all
concerned therein both speak and write the same things; while these men,
by writing differently about the same things, think they shall be believed
to write with the greatest regard to truth. We therefore [who are Jews]
must yield to the Grecian writers as to language and eloquence of composition;
but then we shall give them no such preference as to the verity of ancient
history, and least of all as to that part which concerns the affairs of
our own several countries.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="28" unit="section"/><p>As to the care of writing down the records from the earliest antiquity
among the Egyptians and Babylonians; that the priests were intrusted therewith,
and employed a philosophical concern about it; that they were the Chaldean
priests that did so among the Babylonians; and that the Phoenicians, who
were mingled among the Greeks, did especially make use of their letters,
both for the common affairs of life, and for the delivering down the history
of common transactions, I think I may omit any proof, because all men allow
it so to be. But now as to our forefathers, that they took no less care
about writing such records, (for I will not say they took greater care
than the others I spoke of,) and that they committed that matter to their
high priests and to their prophets, and that these records have been written
all along down to our own times with the utmost accuracy; nay, if it be
not too bold for me to say it, our history will be so written hereafter;
- I shall endeavor briefly to inform you.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="30" unit="section"/><p>For our forefathers did not only appoint the best of these priests,
and those that attended upon the Divine worship, for that design from the
beginning, but made provision that the stock of the priests should continue
unmixed and pure; for he who is partaker of the priesthood must propagate
of a wife of the same nation, without having any regard to money, or any
other dignities; but he is to make a scrutiny, and take his wife's genealogy
from the ancient tables, and procure many witnesses to it. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Of this accuracy of the Jews before and in our Savior's time, in carefully
preserving their genealogies all along, particularly those of the priests,
see Josephus's Life, sect. 1. This accuracy. seems to have ended at the
destruction of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> by Titus, or, however, at that by Adrian.</note>
And this is our practice not only in <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, but wheresoever any body of
men of our nation do live; and even there an exact catalogue of our priests'
marriages is kept; I mean at <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and at <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, or in any other place
of the rest of the habitable earth, whithersoever our priests are scattered;
for they send to <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> the ancient names of their parents in writing,
as well as those of their remoter ancestors, and signify who are the witnesses
also. But if any war falls out, such as have fallen out a great many of
them already, when Antiochus Epiphanes made an invasion upon our country,
as also when Pompey the Great and Quintilius Varus did so also, and principally
in the wars that have happened in our own times, those priests that survive
them compose new tables of genealogy out of the old records, and examine
the circumstances of the women that remain; for still they do not admit
of those that have been captives, as suspecting that they had conversation
with some foreigners. But what is the strongest argument of our exact management
in this matter is what I am now going to say, that we have the names of
our high priests from father to son set down in our records for the interval
of two thousand years; and if any of these have been transgressors of these
rules, they are prohibited to present themselves at the altar, or to be
partakers of any other of our purifications; and this is justly, or rather
necessarily done, because every one is not permitted of his own accord
to be a writer, nor is there any disagreement in what is written; they
being only prophets that have written the original and earliest accounts
of things as they learned them of God himself by inspiration; and others
have written what hath happened in their own times, and that in a very
distinct manner also.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="38" unit="section"/><p>For we have not an innumerable multitude of books among us, disagreeing
from and contradicting one another, [as the Greeks have,] but only twenty-two
books, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Which were these twenty-two sacred books of the. Old Testament, see the
Supplement to the Essay of the Old Testament, p. 25-29, viz. those we call
canonical, all excepting the Canticles; but still with this further exception,
that the book of apocryphal Esdras be taken into that number instead of
our canonical Ezra, which seems to be no more than a later epitome of the
other; which two books of Canticles and Ezra it no way appears that our
Josephus ever saw.</note>
which contain the records of all the past times; which are justly believed
to be divine; and of them five belong to Moses, which contain his laws
and the traditions of the origin of mankind till his death. This interval
of time was little short of three thousand years; but as to the time from
the death of Moses till the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, who reigned
after Xerxes, the prophets, who were after Moses, wrote down what was done
in their times in thirteen books. The remaining four books contain hymns
to God, and precepts for the conduct of human life. It is true, our history
hath been written since Artaxerxes very particularly, but hath not been
esteemed of the like authority with the former by our forefathers, because
there hath not been an exact succession of prophets since that time; and
how firmly we have given credit to these books of our own nation is evident
by what we do; for during so many ages as have already passed, no one has
been so bold as either to add any thing to them, to take any thing from
them, or to make any change in them; but it is become natural to all Jews
immediately, and from their very birth, to esteem these books to contain
Divine doctrines, and to persist in them, and, if occasion be willingly
to die for them. For it is no new thing for our captives, many of them
in number, and frequently in time, to be seen to endure racks and deaths
of all kinds upon the theatres, that they may not be obliged to say one
word against our laws and the records that contain them; whereas there
are none at all among the Greeks who would undergo the least harm on that
account, no, nor in case all the writings that are among them were to be
destroyed; for they take them to be such discourses as are framed agreeably
to the inclinations of those that write them; and they have justly the
same opinion of the ancient writers, since they see some of the present
generation bold enough to write about such affairs, wherein they were not
present, nor had concern enough to inform themselves about them from those
that knew them; examples of which may be had in this late war of ours,
where some persons have written histories, and published them, without
having been in the places concerned, or having been near them when the
actions were done; but these men put a few things together by hearsay,
and insolently abuse the world, and call these writings by the name of
Histories.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="47" unit="section"/><p>As for myself, I have composed a true history of that whole war,
and of all the particulars that occurred therein, as having been concerned
in all its transactions; for I acted as general of those among us that
are named Galileans, as long as it was possible for us to make any opposition.
I was then seized on by the Romans, and became a captive. Vespasian also
and Titus had me kept under a guard, and forced me to attend them continually.
At the first I was put into bonds, but was set at liberty afterward, and
sent to accompany Titus when he came from <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> to the siege of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>;
during which time there was nothing done which escaped my knowledge; for
what happened in the Roman camp I saw, and wrote down carefully; and what
informations the deserters brought [out of the city], I was the only man
that understood them. Afterward I got leisure at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; and when all my
materials were prepared for that work, I made use of some persons to assist
me in learning the Greek tongue, and by these means I composed the history
of those transactions. And I was so well assured of the truth of what I
related, that I first of all appealed to those that had the supreme command
in that war, Vespasian and Titus, as witnesses for me, for to them I presented
those books first of all, and after them to many of the Romans who had
been in the war. I also sold them to many of our own men who understood
the Greek philosophy; among whom were Julius Archelaus, Herod [king of
<placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>], a person of great gravity, and king Agrippa himself, a person
that deserved the greatest admiration. Now all these men bore their testimony
to me, that I had the strictest regard to truth; who yet would not have
dissembled the matter, nor been silent, if I, out of ignorance, or out
of favor to any side, either had given false colors to actions, or omitted
any of them.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="53" unit="section"/><p>There have been indeed some bad men, who have attempted to calumniate
my history, and took it to be a kind of scholastic performance for the
exercise of young men. A strange sort of accusation and calumny this! since
every one that undertakes to deliver the history of actions truly ought
to know them accurately himself in the first place, as either having been
concerned in them himself, or been informed of them by such as knew them.
Now both these methods of knowledge I may very properly pretend to in the
composition of both my works; for, as I said, I have translated the Antiquities
out of our sacred books; which I easily could do, since I was a priest
by my birth, and have studied that philosophy which is contained in those
writings: and for the History of the War, I wrote it as having been an
actor myself in many of its transactions, an eye-witness in the greatest
part of the rest, and was not unacquainted with any thing whatsoever that
was either said or done in it. How impudent then must those deserve to
be esteemed that undertake to contradict me about the true state of those
affairs! who, although they pretend to have made use of both the emperors'
own memoirs, yet could not they he acquainted with our affairs who fought
against them.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="57" unit="section"/><p>This digression I have been obliged to make out of necessity, as
being desirous to expose the vanity of those that profess to write histories;
and I suppose I have sufficiently declared that this custom of transmitting
down the histories of ancient times hath been better preserved by those
nations which are called Barbarians, than by the Greeks themselves. I am
now willing, in the next place, to say a few things to those that endeavor
to prove that our constitution is but of late time, for this reason, as
they pretend, that the Greek writers have said nothing about us; after
which I shall produce testimonies for our antiquity out of the writings
of foreigners; I shall also demonstrate that such as cast reproaches upon
our nation do it very unjustly.</p>
<milestone n="12" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="60" unit="section"/><p>As for ourselves, therefore, we neither inhabit a maritime country,
nor do we delight in merchandise, nor in such a mixture with other men
as arises from it; but the cities we dwell in are remote from the sea,
and having a fruitful country for our habitation, we take pains in cultivating
that only. Our principal care of all is this, to educate our children well;
and we think it to be the most necessary business of our whole life to
observe the laws that have been given us, and to keep those rules of piety
that have been delivered down to us. Since, therefore, besides what we
have already taken notice of, we have had a peculiar way of living of our
own, there was no occasion offered us in ancient ages for intermixing among
the Greeks, as they had for mixing among the Egyptians, by their intercourse
of exporting and importing their several goods; as they also mixed with
the Phoenicians, who lived by the sea-side, by means of their love of lucre
in trade and merchandise. Nor did our forefathers betake themselves, as
did some others, to robbery; nor did they, in order to gain more wealth,
fall into foreign wars, although our country contained many ten thousands
of men of courage sufficient for that purpose. For this reason it was that
the Phoenicians themselves came soon by trading and navigation to be known
to the Grecians, and by their means the Egyptians became known to the Grecians
also, as did all those people whence the Phoenicians in long voyages over
the seas carried wares to the Grecians. The Medes also and the Persians,
when they were lords of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, became well known to them; and this was especially
true of the Persians, who led their armies as far as the other continent
[<placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>]. The Thracians were also known to them by the nearness of their
countries, and the Scythians by the means of those that sailed to <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>;
for it was so in general that all maritime nations, and those that inhabited
near the eastern or western seas, became most known to those that were
desirous to be writers; but such as had their habitations further from
the sea were for the most part unknown to them which things appear to have
happened as to <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> also, where the city of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, that hath this long
time been possessed of so much power, and hath performed such great actions
in war, is yet never mentioned by Herodotus, nor by Thucydides, nor by
any one of their contemporaries; and it was very late, and with great difficulty,
that the Romans became known to the Greeks. Nay, those that were reckoned
the most exact historians (and Ephorus for one) were so very ignorant of
the Gauls and the Spaniards, that he supposed the Spaniards, who inhabit
so great a part of the western regions of the earth, to be no more than
one city. Those historians also have ventured to describe such customs
as were made use of by them, which they never had either done or said;
and the reason why these writers did not know the truth of their affairs
was this, that they had not any commerce together; but the reason why they
wrote such falsities was this, that they had a mind to appear to know things
which others had not known. How can it then be any wonder, if our nation
was no more known to many of the Greeks, nor had given them any occasion
to mention them in their writings, while they were so remote from the sea,
and had a conduct of life so peculiar to themselves?</p>
<milestone n="13" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="69" unit="section"/><p>Let us now put the case, therefore, that we made use of this argument
concerning the Grecians, in order to prove that their nation was not ancient,
because nothing is said of them in our records: would not they laugh at
us all, and probably give the same reasons for our silence that I have
now alleged, and would produce their neighbor nations as witnesses to their
own antiquity? Now the very same thing will I endeavor to do; for I will
bring the Egyptians and the Phoenicians as my principal witnesses, because
nobody can complain Of their testimony as false, on account that they are
known to have borne the greatest ill-will towards us; I mean this as to
the Egyptians in general all of them, while of the Phoenicians it is known
the Tyrians have been most of all in the same ill disposition towards us:
yet do I confess that I cannot say the same of the Chaldeans, since our
first leaders and ancestors were derived from them; and they do make mention
of us Jews in their records, on account of the kindred there is between
us. Now when I shall have made my assertions good, so far as concerns the
others, I will demonstrate that some of the Greek writers have made mention
of us Jews also, that those who envy us may not have even this pretense
for contradicting what I have said about our nation.</p>
<milestone n="14" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="73" unit="section"/><p>I shall begin with the writings of the Egyptians; not indeed of
those that have written in the Egyptian language, which it is impossible
for me to do. But Manetho was a man who was by birth an Egyptian, yet had
he made himself master of the Greek learning, as is very evident; for he
wrote the history of his own country in the Greek tongue, by translating
it, as he saith himself, out of their sacred records; he also finds great
fault with Herodotus for his ignorance and false relations of Egyptian
affairs. Now this Manetho, in the second book of his Egyptian History,
writes concerning us in the following manner. I will set down his very
words, as if I were to bring the very man himself into a court for a witness:
"There was a king of ours whose name was Timaus. Under him it came
to pass, I know not how, that God was averse to us, and there came, after
a surprising manner, men of ignoble birth out of the eastern parts, and
had boldness enough to make an expedition into our country, and with ease
subdued it by force, yet without our hazarding a battle with them. So when
they had gotten those that governed us under their power, they afterwards
burnt down our cities, and demolished the temples of the gods, and used
all the inhabitants after a most barbarous manner; nay, some they slew,
and led their children and their wives into slavery. At length they made
one of themselves king, whose name was Salatis; he also lived at <placeName key="tgn,7001186">Memphis</placeName>,
and made both the upper and lower regions pay tribute, and left garrisons
in places that were the most proper for them. He chiefly aimed to secure
the eastern parts, as fore-seeing that the Assyrians, who had then the
greatest power, would be desirous of that kingdom, and invade them; and
as he found in the Saite Nomos, [Sethroite,] a city very proper for this
purpose, and which lay upon the Bubastic channel, but with regard to a
certain theologic notion was called <term lang="xhebrew">Avaris</term>, this he rebuilt, and
made very strong by the walls he built about it, and by a most numerous
garrison of two hundred and forty thousand armed men whom he put into it
to keep it. Thither Salatis came in summer time, partly to gather his corn,
and pay his soldiers their wages, and partly to exercise his armed men,
and thereby to terrify foreigners. When this man had reigned thirteen years,
after him reigned another, whose name was Beon, for forty-four years; after
him reigned another, called Apachnas, thirty-six years and seven months;
after him Apophis reigned sixty-one years, and then Janins fifty years
and one month; after all these reigned <placeName key="tgn,1020714">Assis</placeName> forty-nine years and two months.
And these six were the first rulers among them, who were all along making
war with the Egyptians, and were very desirous gradually to destroy them
to the very roots. This whole nation was styled HYCSOS, that is, <gloss rend="ital">Shepherd-kings</gloss>:
for the first syllable HYC, according to the sacred dialect, denotes <gloss rend="ital">a
king</gloss>, as is SOS <gloss rend="ital">a shepherd</gloss>; but this according to the ordinary
dialect; and of these is compounded HYCSOS: but some say that these people
were Arabians." Now in another copy it is said that this word does
not denote <gloss rend="ital">Kings</gloss>, but, on the contrary, denotes <gloss rend="ital">Captive Shepherds</gloss>,
and this on account of the particle HYC; for that HYC, with the aspiration,
in the Egyptian tongue again denotes Shepherds, and that expressly also;
and this to me seems the more probable opinion, and more agreeable to ancient
history. [But Manetho goes on]: "These people, whom we have before
named kings, and called shepherds also, and their descendants," as
he says, "kept possession of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> five hundred and eleven years."
After these, he says, "That the kings of <placeName key="tgn,4011135">Thebais</placeName> and the other parts
of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> made an insurrection against the shepherds, and that there a terrible
and long war was made between them." He says further, "That under
a king, whose name was Alisphragmuthosis, the shepherds were subdued by
him, and were indeed driven out of other parts of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, but were shut
up in a place that contained ten thousand acres; this place was named <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>."
Manetho says, "That the shepherds built a wall round all this place,
which was a large and a strong wall, and this in order to keep all their
possessions and their prey within a place of strength, but that Thummosis
the son of Alisphragmuthosis made an attempt to take them by force and
by siege, with four hundred and eighty thousand men to lie rotund about
them, but that, upon his despair of taking the place by that siege, they
came to a composition with them, that they should leave <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and go,
without any harm to be done to them, whithersoever they would; and that,
after this composition was made, they went away with their whole families
and effects, not fewer in number than two hundred and forty thousand, and
took their journey from <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, through the wilderness, for <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>; but that
as they were in fear of the Assyrians, who had then the dominion over <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>,
they built a city in that country which is now called <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, and that large
enough to contain this great number of men, and called it <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Here we have an account of the first building of the city of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>,
according to Manetho, when the Phoenician shepherds were expelled out of
<placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> about thirty-seven years before Abraham came out of Harsh.</note>
Now Manetho, in another book of his, says, "That this nation, thus
called Shepherds, were also called Captives, in their sacred books."
And this account of his is the truth; for feeding of sheep was the employment
of our forefathers in the most ancient ages <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Genesis 46;32, 34; 47:3, 4.</note>
and as they led such a wandering life in feeding sheep, they were called
Shepherds. Nor was it without reason that they were called Captives by
the Egyptians, since one of our ancestors, Joseph, told the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>
that he was a captive, and afterward sent for his brethren into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> by
the king's permission. But as for these matters, I shall make a more exact
inquiry about them elsewhere. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">In our copies of the book of Genesis and of Joseph, this Joseph never calls
himself "a captive," when he was with the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, though
he does call himself "a servant," "a slave," or "captive,"
many times in the Testament of the Twelve Patriarchs, under Joseph, sect.
1, 11, 13-16.</note></p>
<milestone n="15" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="93" unit="section"/><p>But now I shall produce the Egyptians as witnesses to the antiquity
of our nation. I shall therefore here bring in Manetho again, and what
he writes as to the order of the times in this case; and thus he speaks:
"When this people or shepherds were gone out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>,
Tethtoosis the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, who drove them out, reigned afterward twenty-five
years and four months, and then died; after him his son Chebron took the
kingdom for thirteen years; after whom came Amenophis, for twenty years
and seven months; then came his sister Amesses, for twenty-one years and
nine months; after her came Mephres, for twelve years and nine months;
after him was Mephramuthosis, for twenty-five years and ten months; after
him was Thmosis, for nine years and eight months; after him came Amenophis,
for thirty years and ten months; after him came Orus, for thirty-six years
and five months; then came his daughter Acenchres, for twelve years and
one month; then was her brother Rathotis, for nine years; then was Acencheres,
for twelve years and five months; then came another Acencheres, for twelve
years and three months; after him Armais, for four years and one month;
after him was Ramesses, for one year and four months; after him came Armesses
Miammoun, for sixty-six years and two months; after him Amenophis, for
nineteen years and six months; after him came Sethosis, and Ramesses, who
had an army of horse, and a naval force. This king appointed his brother,
Armais,, to be his deputy over <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>." [In another copy it stood thus:
After him came Sethosis, and Ramesses, two brethren, the former of whom
had a naval force, and in a hostile manner destroyed those that met him
upon the sea; but as he slew Ramesses in no long time afterward, so he
appointed another of his brethren to be his deputy over Egypt.] He also
gave him all the other authority of a king, but with these only injunctions,
that he should not wear the diadem, nor be injurious to the queen, the
mother of his children, and that he should not meddle with the other concubines
of the king; while he made an expedition against <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>,
and besides against the Assyrians and the Medes. He then subdued them all,
some by his arms, some without fighting, and some by the terror of his
great army; and being puffed up by the great successes he had had, he went
on still the more boldly, and overthrew the cities and countries that lay
in the eastern parts. But after some considerable time, Armais, who was
left in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, did all those very things, by way of opposition, which his
brother had forbid him to do, without fear; for he used violence to the
queen, and continued to make use of the rest of the concubines, without
sparing any of them; nay, at the persuasion of his friends he put on the
diadem, and set up to oppose his brother. But then he who was set over
the priests of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> wrote letters to Sethosis, and informed him of all
that had happened, and how his brother had set up to oppose him: he therefore
returned back to <placeName key="tgn,6004608">Pelusium</placeName> immediately, and recovered his kingdom again.
The country also was called from his name <mentioned rend="ital"><placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName></mentioned>; for Manetho says,
that Sethosis was himself called Egyptus, as was his brother Armais called
Danaus."</p>
<milestone n="16" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="103" unit="section"/><p>This is Manetho's account. And evident it is from the number of
years by him set down belonging to this interval, if they be summed up
together, that these shepherds, as they are here called, who were no other
than our forefathers, were delivered out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and came thence, and
inhabited this country, three hundred and ninety-three years before Danaus
came to <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>; although the Argives look upon him <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Of this Egyptian chronology of Manetho, as mistaken by Josephus, and of
these Phoenician shepherds, as falsely supposed by him, and others after
him, to have been the Israelites in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, see Essay on the Old Testament,
Appendix, p. 182-188. And note here, that when Josephus tells us that the
Greeks or Argives looked on this Danaus as "a most ancient,"
or "the most ancient," king of <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, he need not be supposed
to mean, in the strictest sense, that they had no one king so ancient as
he; for it is certain that they owned nine kings before him, and Inachus
at the head of them. See Authentic Records, Part II. p. 983, as Josephus
could not but know very well; but that he was esteemed as very ancient
by them, and that they knew they had been first of all denominated "Danai"
from this very ancient king Danaus. Nor does this superlative degree always
imply the "most ancient" of all without exception, but is sometimes
to be rendered "very ancient" only, as is the case in the like
superlative degrees of other words also.</note>
as their most ancient king Manetho, therefore, hears this testimony to
two points of the greatest consequence to our purpose, and those from the
Egyptian records themselves. In the first place, that we came out of another
country into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>; and that withal our deliverance out of it was so ancient
in time as to have preceded the siege of <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> almost a thousand years;
but then, as to those things which Manetbo adds, not from the Egyptian
records, but, as he confesses himself, from some stories of an uncertain
original, I will disprove them hereafter particularly, and shall demonstrate
that they are no better than incredible fables.</p>
<milestone n="17" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="106" unit="section"/><p>I will now, therefore, pass from these records, and come to those
that belong to the Phoenicians, and concern our nation, and shall produce
attestations to what I have said out of them. There are then records among
the Tyrians that take in the history of many years, and these are public
writings, and are kept with great exactness, and include accounts of the
facts done among them, and such as concern their transactions with other
nations also, those I mean which were worth remembering. Therein it was
recorded that the temple was built by king Solomon at <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, one hundred
forty-three years and eight months before the Tyrians built <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>; and
in their annals the building of our temple is related; for Hirom, the king
of <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, was the friend of Solomon our king, and had such friendship transmitted
down to him from his forefathers. He thereupon was ambitious to contribute
to the splendor of this edifice of Solomon, and made him a present of one
hundred and twenty talents of gold. He also cut down the most excellent
timber out of that mountain which is called Libanus, and sent it to him
for adorning its roof. Solomon also not only made him many other presents,
by way of requital, but gave him a country in <placeName key="tgn,7000250">Galilee</placeName> also, that was called
Chabulon. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Authentic Records, Part II. p. 983, as Josephus could not but know very
well; but that he was esteemed as very ancient by them, and that they knew
they had been first of all denominated "Danai" from this very
ancient king Danaus. Nor does this superlative degree always imply the
"most ancient" of all without exception, but is sometimes to
be rendered "very ancient" only, as is the case in the like superlative
degrees of other words also.</note>
But there was another passion, a philosophic inclination of theirs, which
cemented the friendship that was betwixt them; for they sent mutual problems
to one another, with a desire to have them unriddled by each other; wherein
Solomon was superior to Hirom, as he was wiser than he in other respects:
and many of the epistles that passed between them are still preserved among
the Tyrians. Now, that this may not depend on my bare word, I will produce
for a witness Dius, one that is believed to have written the Phoenician
History after an accurate manner. This Dius, therefore, writes thus, in
his Histories of the Phoenicians: "Upon the death of Abibalus, his
son Hirom took the kingdom. This king raised banks at the eastern parts
of the city, and enlarged it; he also joined the temple of Jupiter Olympius,
which stood before in an island by itself, to the city, by raising a causeway
between them, and adorned that temple with donations of gold. He moreover
went up to Libanus, and had timber cut down for the building of temples.
They say further, that Solomon, when he was king of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, sent problems
to Hirom to be solved, and desired he would send others back for him to
solve, and that he who could not solve the problems proposed to him should
pay money to him that solved them. And when Hirom had agreed to the proposals,
but was not able to solve the problems, he was obliged to pay a great deal
of money, as a penalty for the same. As also they relate, that one&middot;Abdemon,
a man of <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, did solve the problems, and propose others which Solomon
could not solve, upon which he was obliged to repay a great deal of money
to Hirom." These things are attested to by Dius, and confirm what
we have said upon the same subjects before.</p>
<milestone n="18" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="116" unit="section"/><p>And now I shall add Menander the Ephesian, as an additional witness.
This Menander wrote the Acts that were done both by the Greeks and Barbarians,
under every one of the Tyrian kings, and had taken much pains to learn
their history out of their own records. Now when he was writing about those
kings that had reigned at <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, he came to Hirom, and says thus: "Upon
the death of Abibalus, his son Hirom took the kingdom; he lived fifty-three
years, and reigned thirty-four. He raised a bank on that called the Broad
Place, and dedicated that golden pillar which is in Jupiter's temple; he
also went and cut down timber from the mountain called Libanus, and got
timber Of cedar for the roofs of the temples. He also pulled down the old
temples, and built new ones; besides this, he consecrated the temples of
Hercules and of Astarte. He first built Hercules's temple in the month
Peritus, and that of Astarte when he made his expedition against the Tityans,
who would not pay him their tribute; and when he had subdued them to himself,
he returned home. Under this king there was a younger son of Abdemon, who
mastered the problems which Solomon king of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> had recommended to
be solved." Now the time from this king to the building of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>
is thus calculated: "Upon the death of Hirom, Baleazarus his son took
the kingdom; he lived forty-three years, and reigned seven years: after
him succeeded his son Abdastartus; he lived twenty-nine years, and reigned
nine years. Now four sons of his nurse plotted against him and slew him,
the eldest of whom reigned twelve years: after them came Astartus, the
son of Deleastartus; he lived fifty-four years, and reigned twelve years:
after him came his brother Aserymus; he lived fifty-four years, and reigned
nine years: he was slain by his brother Pheles, who took the kingdom and
reigned but eight months, though he lived fifty years: he was slain by
Ithobalus, the priest of Astarte, who reigned thirty-two years, and lived
sixty-eight years: he was succeeded by his son Badezorus, who lived forty-five
years, and reigned six years: he was succeeded by Matgenus his son; he
lived thirty-two years, and reigned nine years: Pygmalion succeeded him;
he lived fifty-six years, and reigned forty-seven years. Now in the seventh
year of his reign, his sister fled away from him, and built the city <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>
in <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>." So the whole time from the reign of Hirom, till the building
of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, amounts to the sum of one hundred fifty-five years and eight
months. Since then the temple was built at <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> in the twelfth year
of the reign of Hirom, there were from the building of the temple, until
the building of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, one hundred forty-three years and eight months.
Wherefore, what occasion is there for alleging any more testimonies out
of the Phoenician histories [on the behalf of our nation], since what I
have said is so thoroughly confirmed already? and to be sure our ancestors
came into this country long before the building of the temple; for it was
not till we had gotten possession of the whole land by war that we built
our temple. And this is the point that I have clearly proved out of our
sacred writings in my Antiquities.</p>
<milestone n="19" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="128" unit="section"/><p>I will now relate what hath been written concerning us in the Chaldean
histories, which records have a great agreement with our books in oilier
things also. Berosus shall be witness to what I say: he was by birth a
Chaldean, well known by the learned, on account of his publication of the
Chaldean books of astronomy and philosophy among the Greeks. This Berosus,
therefore, following the most ancient records of that nation, gives us
a history of the deluge of waters that then happened, and of the destruction
of mankind thereby, and agrees with Moses's narration thereof. He also
gives us an account of that ark wherein Noah, the origin of our race, was
preserved, when it was brought to the highest part of the Armenian mountains;
after which he gives us a catalogue of the posterity of Noah, and adds
the years of their chronology, and at length comes down to Nabolassar,
who was king of <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, and of the Chaldeans. And when he was relating
the acts of this king, he describes to us how he sent his son Nabuchodonosor
against <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and against our land, with a great army, upon his being
informed that they had revolted from him; and how, by that means, he subdued
them all, and set our temple that was at <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> on fire; nay, and removed
our people entirely out of their own country, and transferred them to <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>;
when it so happened that our city was desolate during the interval of seventy
years, until the days of Cyrus king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>. He then says, "That
this Babylonian king conquered <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,1012700">Arabia</placeName>,
and exceeded in his exploits all that had reigned before him in <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>
and Chaldea." A little after which Berosus subjoins what follows in
his History of Ancient Times. I will set down Berosus's own accounts, which
are these: "When Nabolassar, father of Nabuchodonosor, heard that
the governor whom he had set over <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and over the parts of Celesyria
and <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>, had revolted from him, he was not able to bear it any longer;
but committing certain parts of his army to his son Nabuchodonosor, who
was then but young, he sent him against the rebel: Nabuchodonosor joined
battle with him, and conquered him, and reduced the country under his dominion
again. Now it so fell out that his father Nabolassar fell into a distemper
at this time, and died in the city of <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, after he had reigned twenty-nine
years. But as he understood, in a little time, that his father Nabolassar
was dead, he set the affairs of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and the other countries in order,
and committed the captives he had taken from the Jews, and Phoenicians,
and Syrians, and of the nations belonging to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, to some of his friends,
that they might conduct that part of the forces that had on heavy armor,
with the rest of his baggage, to <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylonia</placeName>; while he went in haste, having
but a few with him, over the desert to <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>; whither, when he was come,
he found the public affairs had been managed by the Chaldeans, and that
the principal person among them had preserved the kingdom for him. Accordingly,
he now entirely obtained all his father's dominions. He then came, and
ordered the captives to be placed as colonies in the most proper places
of <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylonia</placeName>; but for himself, he adorned the temple of Belus, and the
other temples, after an elegant manner, out of the spoils he had taken
in this war. He also rebuilt the old city, and added another to it on the
outside, and so far restored <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, that none who should besiege it afterwards
might have it in their power to divert the river, so as to facilitate an
entrance into it; and this he did by building three walls about the inner
city, and three about the outer. Some of these walls he built of burnt
brick and bitumen, and some of brick only. So when he had thus fortified
the city with walls, after an excellent manner, and had adorned the gates
magnificently, he added a new palace to that which his father had dwelt
in, and this close by it also, and that more eminent in its height, and
in its great splendor. It would perhaps require too long a narration, if
any one were to describe it. However, as prodigiously large and as magnificent
as it was, it was finished in fifteen days. Now in this palace he erected
very high walks, supported by stone pillars, and by planting what was called
a <term rend="ital">pensile paradise</term>, and replenishing it with all sorts of trees,
he rendered the prospect an exact resemblance of a mountainous country.
This he did to please his queen, because she had been brought up in Media,
and was fond of a mountainous situation."</p>
<milestone n="20" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="142" unit="section"/><p>This is what Berosus relates concerning the forementioned king,
as he relates many other things about him also in the third book of his
Chaldean History; wherein he complains of the Grecian writers for supposing,
without any foundation, that <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName> was built by Semiramis, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This number in Josephus, that Nebuchadnezzar destroyed the temple in the
eighteenth year of his reign, is a mistake in the nicety of chronology;
for it was in the nineteenth. The true number here for the year of Darius,
in which the second temple was finished, whether the second with our present
copies, or the sixth with that of Syncellus, or the tenth with that of
Eusebius, is very uncertain; so we had best follow Josephus's own account
elsewhere, Antiq. ;B. XI. ch. 3. sect. 4, which shows us that according
to his copy of the Old Testament, after the second of Cyrus, that work
was interrupted till the second of Darius, when in seven years it was finished
in the ninth of Darius.</note>
queen of Assyria, and for her false pretense to those wonderful edifices
thereto buildings at <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, do no way contradict those ancient and relating,
as if they were her own workmanship; as indeed in these affairs the Chaldean
History cannot but be the most credible. Moreover, we meet with a confirmation
of what Berosus says in the archives of the Phoenicians, concerning this
king Nabuchodonosor, that he conquered all <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>; in which
case Philostratus agrees with the others in that history which he composed,
where he mentions the siege of <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>; as does Megasthenes also, in the fourth
book of his Indian History, wherein he pretends to prove that the forementioned
king of the Babylonians was superior to Hercules in strength and the greatness
of his exploits; for he says that he conquered a great part of <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>, and
conquered <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Iberia</placeName> also. Now as to what I have said before about the temple
at <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, that it was fought against by the Babylonians, and burnt
by them, but was opened again when Cyrus had taken the kingdom of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>,
shall now be demonstrated from what Berosus adds further upon that head;
for thus he says in his third book: "Nabuchodonosor, after he had
begun to build the forementioned wall, fell sick, and departed this life,
when he had reigned forty-three years; whereupon his son Evilmerodach obtained
the kingdom. He governed public affairs after an illegal and impure manner,
and had a plot laid against him by Neriglissoor, his sister's husband,
and was slain by him when he had reigned but two years. After he was slain,
Neriglissoor, the person who plotted against him, succeeded him in the
kingdom, and reigned four years; his son Laborosoarchod obtained the kingdom,
though he was but a child, and kept it nine mouths; but by reason of the
very ill temper and ill practices he exhibited to the world, a plot was
laid against him also by his friends, and he was tormented to death. After
his death, the conspirators got together, and by common consent put the
crown upon the head of Nabonnedus, a man of <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, and one who belonged
to that insurrection. In his reign it was that the walls of the city of
<placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName> were curiously built with burnt brick and bitumen; but when he
was come to the seventeenth year of his reign, Cyrus came out of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>
with a great army; and having already conquered all the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, he
came hastily to <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylonia</placeName>. When Nabonnedus perceived he was coming to attack
him, he met him with his forces, and joining battle with him was beaten,
and fled away with a few of his troops with him, and was shut up within
the city Borsippus. Hereupon Cyrus took <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, and gave order that the
outer walls of the city should be demolished, because the city had proved
very troublesome to him, and cost him a great deal of pains to take it.
He then marched away to Borsippus, to besiege Nabonnedus; but as Nabonnedus
did not sustain the siege, but delivered himself into his hands, he was
at first kindly used by Cyrus, who gave him Carmania, as a place for him
to inhabit in, but sent him out of <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylonia</placeName>. Accordingly Nabonnedus spent
the rest of his time in that country, and there died."</p>
<milestone n="21" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="154" unit="section"/><p>These accounts agree with the true histories in our books; for in
them it is written that Nebuchadnezzar, in the eighteenth year of his reign,
laid our temple desolate, and so it lay in that state of obscurity for
fifty years; but that in the second year of the reign of Cyrus its foundations
were laid, and it was finished again in the second year of Darius. I will
now add the records of the Phoenicians; for it will not be superfluous
to give the reader demonstrations more than enough on this occasion. In
them we have this enumeration of the times of their several kings: "Nabuchodonosor
besieged <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName> for thirteen years in the days of Ithobal, their king; after
him reigned <placeName key="tgn,1038302">Baal</placeName>, ten years; after him were judges appointed, who judged
the people: Ecnibalus, the son of Baslacus, two months; Chelbes, the son
of Abdeus, ten months; Abbar, the high priest, three months; Mitgonus and
Gerastratus, the sons of Abdelemus, were judges six years; after whom Balatorus
reigned one year; after his death they sent and fetched Merbalus from Babylon,
who reigned four years; after his death they sent for his brother Hirom,
who reigned twenty years. Under his reign Cyrus became king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>."
So that the whole interval is fifty-four years besides three months; for
in the seventh year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar he began to besiege
<placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, and Cyrus the Persian took the kingdom in the fourteenth year of
Hirom. So that the records of the Chaldeans and Tyrians agree with our
writings about this temple; and the testimonies here produced are an indisputable
and undeniable attestation to the antiquity of our nation. And I suppose
that what I have already said may be sufficient to such as are not very
contentious.</p>
<milestone n="22" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="161" unit="section"/><p>But now it is proper to satisfy the inquiry of those that disbelieve
the records of barbarians, and think none but Greeks to be worthy of credit,
and to produce many of these very Greeks who were acquainted with our nation,
and to set before them such as upon occasion have made mention of us in
their own writings. Pythagoras, therefore, of <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, lived in very ancient
times, and was esteemed a person superior to all philosophers in wisdom
and piety towards God. Now it is plain that he did not only know our doctrines,
but was in very great measure a follower and admirer of them. There is
not indeed extant any writing that is owned for his <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This is a thing well known by the learned, that we are not secure that
we have any genuine writings of Pythagoras; those Golden Verses, which
are his best remains, being generally supposed to have been written not
by himself, but by some of his scholars only, in agreement with what Josephus
here affirms of him.</note>
but many there are who have written his history, of whom Hermippus is the
most celebrated, who was a person very inquisitive into all sorts of history.
Now this Hermippus, in his first book concerning Pythagoras, speaks thus:
"That Pythagoras, upon the death of one of his associates, whose name
was Calliphon, a Crotonlate by birth, affirmed that this man's soul conversed
with him both night and day, and enjoined him not to pass over a place
where an ass had fallen down; as also not to drink of such waters as caused
thirst again; and to abstain from all sorts of reproaches." After
which he adds thus: "This he did and said in imitation of the doctrines
of the Jews and Thracians, which he transferred into his own philosophy."
For it is very truly affirmed of this Pythagoras, that he took a great
many of the laws of the Jews into his own philosophy. Nor was our nation
unknown of old to several of the Grecian cities, and indeed was thought
worthy of imitation by some of them. This is declared by Theophrastus,
in his writings concerning laws; for he says that "the laws of the
Tyrians forbid men to swear foreign oaths." Among which he enumerates
some others, and particularly that called <term rend="ital">Corban</term>: which oath can
only be found among the Jews, and declares what a man may call "A
thing devoted to God." Nor indeed was Herodotus of <placeName key="tgn,7016142">Halicarnassus</placeName> unacquainted
with our nation, but mentions it after a way of his own, when he saith
thus, in the second book concerning the Colchians. His words are these:
"The only people who were circumcised in their privy members originally,
were the Colchians, the Egyptians, and the Ethiopians; but the Phoenicians
and those Syrians that are in <placeName key="tgn,7004540">Palestine</placeName> confess that they learned it from
the Egyptians. And for those Syrians who live about the rivers Thermodon
and Parthenius, and their neighbors the Macrones, they say they have lately
learned it from the Colchians; for these are the only people that are circumcised
among mankind, and appear to have done the very same thing with the Egyptians.
But as for the Egyptians and Ethiopians themselves, I am not able to say
which of them received it from the other." This therefore is what
Herodotus says, that "the Syrians that are in <placeName key="tgn,7004540">Palestine</placeName> are circumcised."
But there are no inhabitants of <placeName key="tgn,7004540">Palestine</placeName> that are circumcised excepting
the Jews; and therefore it must be his knowledge of them that enabled him
to speak so much concerning them. Cherilus also, a still ancienter writer,
and a poet, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Whether these verses of Cherilus, the heathen poet, in the days of Xerxes,
belong to the Solymi in <placeName key="tgn,7016774">Pisidia</placeName>, that were near a small lake, or to the
Jews that dwelt on the Solymean or Jerusalem mountains, near the great
and broad lake Asphaltitis, that were a strange people, and spake the Phoenician
tongue, is not agreed on by the learned. If is yet certain that Josephus
here, and Eusebius, Prep. IX. 9. p. 412, took them to be Jews; and I confess
I cannot but very much incline to the same opinion. The other Solymi were
not a strange people, but heathen idolaters, like the other parts of Xerxes's
army; and that these spake the Phoenician tongue is next to impossible,
as the Jews certainly did; nor is there the least evidence for it elsewhere.
Nor was the lake adjoining to the mountains of the Solvmi at all large
or broad, in comparison of the Jewish lake Asphaltitis; nor indeed were
these so considerable a people as the Jews, nor so likely to be desired
by Xerxes for his army as the Jews, to whom he was always very favorable.
As for the rest of Cherilus's description, that "their heads were
sooty; that they had round rasures on their heads; that their heads and
faces were like nasty horse-heads, which had been hardened in the smoke;"
these awkward characters probably fitted the Solymi of Pisidi no better
than they did the Jews in <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>. And indeed this reproachful language,
here given these people, is to me a strong indication that they were the
poor despicable Jews, and not the Pisidian Solymi celebrated in Homer,
whom Cherilus here describes; nor are we to expect that either Cherilus
or Hecateus, or any other pagan writers cited by Josephus and Eusebius,
made no mistakes in the Jewish history. If by comparing their testimonies
with the more authentic records of that nation we find them for the main
to confirm the same, as we almost always do, we ought to be satisfied,
and not expect that they ever had an exact knowledge of all the circumstances
of the Jewish affairs, which indeed it was almost always impossible for
them to have. See sect. 23.</note>
makes mention of our nation, and informs us that it came to the assistance
of king Xerxes, in his expedition against <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. For in his enumeration
of all those nations, he last of all inserts ours among the rest, when
he says," At the last there passed over a people, wonderful to be
beheld; for they spake the Phoenician tongue with their mouths; they dwelt
in the Solymean mountains, near a broad lake: their heads were sooty; they
had round rasures on them; their heads and faces were like nasty horse-heads
also, that had been hardened in the smoke." I think, therefore, that
it is evident to every body that Cherilus means us, because the Solymean
mountains are in our country, wherein we inhabit, as is also the lake called
Asphaltitis; for this is a broader and larger lake than any other that
is in <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>: and thus does Cherilus make mention of us. But now that not
only the lowest sort of the Grecians, but those that are had in the greatest
admiration for their philosophic improvements among them, did not only
know the Jews, but when they lighted upon any of them, admired them also,
it is easy for any one to know. For Clearchus, who was the scholar of Aristotle,
and inferior to no one of the Peripatetics whomsoever, in his first book
concerning sleep, says that "Aristotle his master related what follows
of a Jew," and sets down Aristotle's own discourse with him. The account
is this, as written down by him: "Now, for a great part of what this
Jew said, it would be too long to recite it; but what includes in it both
wonder and philosophy it may not be amiss to discourse of. Now, that I
may be plain with thee, Hyperochides, I shall herein seem to thee to relate
wonders, and what will resemble dreams themselves. Hereupon Hyperochides
answered modestly, and said, For that very reason it is that all of us
are very desirous of hearing what thou art going to say. Then replied Aristotle,
For this cause it will be the best way to imitate that rule of the Rhetoricians,
which requires us first to give an account of the man, and of what nation
he was, that so we may not contradict our master's directions. Then said
Hyperochides, Go on, if it so pleases thee. This man then, [answered Aristotle,]
was by birth a Jew, and came from Celesyria; these Jews are derived from
the Indian philosophers; they are named by the Indians <term rend="ital">Calami</term>, and
by the Syrians <term rend="ital">Judaei</term>, and took their name from the country they
inhabit, which is called <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>; but for the name of their city, it is a
very awkward one, for they call it <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>. Now this man, when he was
hospitably treated by a great many, came down from the upper country to
the places near the sea, and became a Grecian, not only in his language,
but in his soul also; insomuch that when we ourselves happened to be in
<placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> about the same places whither he came, he conversed with us, and with
other philosophical persons, and made a trial of our skill in philosophy;
and as he had lived with many learned men, he communicated to us more information
than he received from us." This is Aristotle's account of the matter,
as given us by Clearchus; which Aristotle discoursed also particularly
of the great and wonderful fortitude of this Jew in his diet, and continent
way of living, as those that please may learn more about him from Clearchus's
book itself; for I avoid setting down any more than is sufficient for my
purpose. Now Clearchus said this by way of digression, for his main design
was of another nature. But for Hecateus of Abdera, who was both a philosopher,
and one very useful ill an active life, he was contemporary with king Alexander
in his youth, and afterward was with Ptolemy, the son of Lagus; he did
not write about the Jewish affairs by the by only, but composed an entire
book concerning the Jews themselves; out of which book I am willing to
run over a few things, of which I have been treating by way of epitome.
And, in the first place, I will demonstrate the time when this Hecateus
lived; for he mentions the fight that was between Ptolemy and Demetrius
about <placeName key="tgn,7001390">Gaza</placeName>, which was fought in the eleventh year after the death of Alexander,
and in the hundred and seventeenth olympiad, as Castor says in his history.
For when he had set down this olympiad, he says further, that "in
this olympiad Ptolemy, the son of Lagus, beat in battle Demetrius, the
son of Antigonus, who was named Poliorcetes, at <placeName key="tgn,7001390">Gaza</placeName>." Now, it is
agreed by all, that Alexander died in the hundred and fourteenth olympiad;
it is therefore evident that our nation flourished in his time, and in
the time of Alexander. Again, Hecateus says to the same purpose, as follows:
"Ptolemy got possession of the places in <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> after that battle at
<placeName key="tgn,7001390">Gaza</placeName>; and many, when they heard of Ptolemy's moderation and humanity, went
along with him to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and were willing to assist him in his affairs;
one of whom (Hecateus says) was Hezekiah <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This Hezekiah, who is here called a high priest, is not named in Josephus's
catalogue; the real high priest at that time being rather Onias, as Archbishop
Usher supposes. However, Josephus often uses the word high priests in the
plural number, as living many at the same time. See the note on Antiq.
B. XX. ch. 8. sect. 8.</note>
the high priest of the Jews; a man of about sixty-six years of age, and
in great dignity among his own people. He was a very sensible man, and
could speak very movingly, and was very skillful in the management of affairs,
if any other man ever were so; although, as he says, all the priests of
the Jews took tithes of the products of the earth, and managed public affairs,
and were in number not above fifteen hundred at the most." Hecateus
mentions this Hezekiah a second time, and says, that "as he was possessed
of so great a dignity, and was become familiar with us, so did he take
certain of those that were with him, and explained to them all the circumstances
of their people; for he had all their habitations and polity down in writing."
Moreover, Hecateus declares again, "what regard we have for our laws,
and that we resolve to endure any thing rather than transgress them, because
we think it right for us to do so." Whereupon he adds, that "although
they are in a bad reputation among their neighbors, and among all those
that come to them, and have been often treated injuriously by the kings
and governors of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, yet can they not be dissuaded from acting what
they think best; but that when they are stripped on this account, and have
torments inflicted upon them, and they are brought to the most terrible
kinds of death, they meet them after an extraordinary manner, beyond all
other people, and will not renounce the religion of their forefathers."
Hecateus also produces demonstrations not a few of this their resolute
tenaciousness of their laws, when he speaks thus: "Alexander was once
at <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, and had an intention to rebuild the temple of Belus that was
fallen to decay, and in order thereto, he commanded all his soldiers in
general to bring earth thither. But the Jews, and they only, would not
comply with that command; nay, they underwent stripes and great losses
of what they had on this account, till the king forgave them, and permitted
them to live in quiet." He adds further, that "when the Macedonians
came to them into that country, and demolished the [old] temples and the
altars, they assisted them in demolishing them all <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">So I read the text with Havercamp, though the place be difficult.</note>
but [for not assisting them in rebuilding them] they either underwent losses,
or sometimes obtained forgiveness." He adds further, that "these
men deserve to be admired on that account." He also speaks of the
mighty populousness of our nation, and says that "the Persians formerly
carried away many ten thousands of our people to <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, as also that
not a few ten thousands were removed after Alexander's death into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>
and <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>, by reason of the sedition that was arisen in <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>."
The same person takes notice in his history, how large the country is which
we inhabit, as well as of its excellent character, and says, that "the
land in which the Jews inhabit contains three millions of arourae, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This number of arourae or Egyptian acres, 3,000,000, each aroura containing
a square of 100 Egyptian cubits, (being about three quarters of an English
acre, and just twice the area of the court of the Jewish tabernacle,) as
contained in the country of <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, will be about one third of the entire
number of arourae in the whole land of <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, supposing it 160 measured
miles long and 70 such miles broad; which estimation, for the fruitful
parts of it, as perhaps here in Hecateus, is not therefore very wide from
the truth. The fifty furlongs in compass for the city <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> presently
are not very wide from the truth also, as Josephus himself describes it,
who, Of the War, B. V. ch. 4. sect. 3. makes its wall thirty-three furlongs,
besides the suburbs and gardens; nay, he says, B. V. ch. 12. sect. 2, that
Titus's wall about it at some small distance, after the gardens and suburbs
were destroyed, was not less than thirty-nine furlongs. Nor perhaps were
its constant inhabitants, in the days of Hecateus, many more than these
120,000, because room was always to be left for vastly greater numbers
which came up at the three great festivals; to say nothing of the probable
increase in their number between the days of Hecateus and Josephus, which
was at least three hundred years. But see a more authentic account of some
of these measures in my Description of the Jewish Temples. However, we
are not to expect that such heathens as Cherilus or Hecateus, or the rest
that are cited by Josephus and Eusebius, could avoid making many mistakes
in the Jewish history, while yet they strongly confirm the same history
in the general, and are most valuable attestations to those more authentic
accounts we have in the Scriptures and Josephus concerning them.</note>
and is generally of a most excellent and most fruitful soil; nor is <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>
of lesser dimensions." The same man describe our city <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> also
itself as of a most excellent structure, and very large, and inhabited
from the most ancient times. He also discourses of the multitude of men
in it, and of the construction of our temple, after the following manner:
"There are many strong places and villages (says he) in the country
of <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>; but one strong city there is, about fifty furlongs in circumference,
which is inhabited by a hundred and twenty thousand men, or thereabouts;
they call it <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>. There is about the middle of the city a wall of
stone, whose length is five hundred feet, and the breadth a hundred cubits,
with double cloisters; wherein there is a square altar, not made of hewn
stone, but composed of white stones gathered together, having each side
twenty cubits long, and its altitude ten cubits. Hard by it is a large
edifice, wherein there is an altar and a candlestick, both of gold, and
in weight two talents: upon these there is a light that is never extinguished,
either by night or by day. There is no image, nor any thing, nor any donations
therein; nothing at all is there planted, neither grove, nor any thing
of that sort. The priests abide therein both nights and days, performing
certain purifications, and drinking not the least drop of wine while they
are in the temple." Moreover, he attests that we Jews went as auxiliaries
along with king Alexander, and after him with his successors. I will add
further what he says he learned when he was himself with the same army,
concerning the actions of a man that was a Jew. His words are these: "As
I was myself going to the <placeName key="tgn,7016791">Red Sea</placeName>, there followed us a man, whose name
was Mosollam; he was one of the Jewish horsemen who conducted us; he was
a person of great courage, of a strong body, and by all allowed to be the
most skillful archer that was either among the Greeks or barbarians. Now
this man, as people were in great numbers passing along the road, and a
certain augur was observing an augury by a bird, and requiring them all
to stand still, inquired what they staid for. Hereupon the augur showed
him the bird from whence he took his augury, and told him that if the bird
staid where he was, they ought all to stand still; but that if he got up,
and flew onward, they must go forward; but that if he flew backward, they
must retire again. Mosollam made no reply, but drew his bow, and shot at
the bird, and hit him, and killed him; and as the augur and some others
were very angry, and wished imprecations upon him, he answered them thus:
Why are you so mad as to take this most unhappy bird into your hands? for
how can this bird give us any true information concerning our march, who
could not foresee how to save himself? for had he been able to foreknow
what was future, he would not have come to this place, but would have been
afraid lest Mosollam the Jew should shoot at him, and kill him." But
of Hecateus's testimonies we have said enough; for as to such as desire
to know more of them, they may easily obtain them from his book itself.
However, I shall not think it too much for me to name Agatharchides, as
having made mention of us Jews, though in way of derision at our simplicity,
as he supposes it to be; for when he was discoursing of the affairs of
Stratonice, "how she came out of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> into <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, and left her
husband Demetrius, while yet Seleueus would not marry her as she expected,
but during the time of his raising an army at <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, stirred up a sedition
about <placeName key="tgn,7002354">Antioch</placeName>; and how, after that, the king came back, and upon his taking
of <placeName key="tgn,7002351">Antioch</placeName>, she fled to <placeName key="tgn,6005333">Seleucia</placeName>, and had it in her power to sail away
immediately yet did she comply with a dream which forbade her so to do,
and so was caught and put to death." When Agatharehides had premised
this story, and had jested upon Stratonice for her superstition, he gives
a like example of what was reported concerning us, and writes thus: "There
are a people called Jews, and dwell in a city the strongest of all other
cities, which the inhabitants call <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, and are accustomed to rest
on every seventh day <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">A glorious testimony this of the observation of the sabbath by the Jews.
See Antiq. B. XVI. ch. 2. sect. 4, and ch. 6. sect. 2; the Life, sect.
54; and War, B. IV. ch. 9. sect. 12.</note>
on which times they make no use of their arms, nor meddle with husbandry,
nor take care of any affairs of life, but spread out their hands in their
holy places, and pray till the evening. Now it came to pass, that when
Ptolemy, the son of Lagus, came into this city with his army, that these
men, in observing this mad custom of theirs, instead of guarding the city,
suffered their country to submit itself to a bitter lord; and their law
was openly proved to have commanded a foolish practice. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Not their law, but the superstitious interpretation of their leaders which
neither the Maccabees nor our blessed Savior did ever approve of.</note>
This accident taught all other men but the Jews to disregard such dreams
as these were, and not to follow the like idle suggestions delivered as
a law, when, in such uncertainty of human reasonings, they are at a loss
what they should do." Now this our procedure seems a ridiculous thing
to Agatharehides, but will appear to such as consider it without prejudice
a great thing, and what deserved a great many encomiums; I mean, when certain
men constantly prefer the observation of their laws, and their religion
towards God, before the preservation of themselves and their country.</p>
<milestone n="23" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="213" unit="section"/><p>Now that some writers have omitted to mention our nation, not because
they knew nothing of us, but because they envied us, or for some other
unjustifiable reasons, I think I can demonstrate by particular instances;
for Hieronymus, who wrote the History of [Alexander's Successors, lived
at the same time with Hecateus, and was a friend of king Antigonus, and
president of <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>. Now it is plain that Hecateus wrote an entire book
concerning us, while Hieronymus never mentions us in his history, although
he was bred up very near to the places where we live. Thus different from
one another are the inclinations of men; while the one thought we deserved
to be carefully remembered, as some ill-disposed passion blinded the other's
mind so entirely, that he could not discern the truth. And now certainly
the foregoing records of the Egyptians, and Chaldeans, and Phoenicians,
together with so many of the Greek writers, will be sufficient for the
demonstration of our antiquity. Moreover, besides those forementioned,
Theophilus, and Theodotus, and Mnaseas, and Aristophanes, and Hermogenes,
Euhemerus also, and Conon, and Zopyrion, and perhaps many others, (for
I have not lighted upon all the Greek books,) have made distinct mention
of us. It is true, many of the men before mentioned have made great mistakes
about the true accounts of our nation in the earliest times, because they
had not perused our sacred books; yet have they all of them afforded their
testimony to our antiquity, concerning which I am now treating. However,
Demetrius Phalereus, and the elder Philo, with Eupolemus, have not greatly
missed the truth about our affairs; whose lesser mistakes ought therefore
to be forgiven them; for it was not in their power to understand our writings
with the utmost accuracy.</p>
<milestone n="24" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="219" unit="section"/><p>One particular there is still remaining behind of what I at first
proposed to speak to, and that is, to demonstrate that those calumnies
and reproaches which some have thrown upon our nation, are lies, and to
make use of those writers' own testimonies against themselves; and that
in general this self-contradiction hath happened to many other authors
by reason of their ill-will to some people, I conclude, is not unknown
to such as have read histories with sufficient care;for some of them have
endeavored to disgrace the nobility of certain nations, and of some of
the most glorious cities, and have cast reproaches upon certain forms of
government. Thus hath Theopompus abused the city of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Polycrates
that of Lacedemon, as hath he hat wrote the Tripoliticus (for he is not
Theopompus, as is supposed bys ome) done by the city of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. Timeils
also hath greatly abused the foregoing people and others also; and this
ill-treatment they use chiefly when they have a contest with men of the
greatest reputation; some out of envy and malice, and others as supposing
that by this foolish talking of theirs they may be thought worthy of being
remembered themselves; and indeed they do by no means fail of their hopes,
with regard to the foolish part of mankind, but men of sober judgment still
condemn them of great malignity.</p>
<milestone n="25" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="223" unit="section"/><p>Now the Egyptians were the first that cast reproaches upon us; in
order to please which nation, some others undertook to pervert the truth,
while they would neither own that our forefathers came into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> from
another country, as the fact was, nor give a true account of our departure
thence. And indeed the Egyptians took many occasions to hate us and envy
us: in the first place, because our ancestors had had the dominion over
their country? and when they were delivered from them, and gone to their
own country again, they lived there in prosperity. In the next place, the
difference of our religion from theirs hath occasioned great enmity between
us, while our way of Divine worship did as much exceed that which their
laws appointed, as does the nature of God exceed that of brute beasts;
for so far they all agree through the whole country, to esteem such animals
as gods, although they differ one from another in the peculiar worship
they severally pay to them. And certainly men they are entirely of vain
and foolish minds, who have thus accustomed themselves from the beginning
to have such bad notions concerning their gods, and could not think of
imitating that decent form of Divine worship which we made use of, though,
when they saw our institutions approved of by many others, they could not
but envy us on that account; for some of them have proceeded to that degree
of folly and meanness in their conduct, as not to scruple to contradict
their own ancient records, nay, to contradict themselves also in their
writings, and yet were so blinded by their passions as not to discern it.</p>
<milestone n="26" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="227" unit="section"/><p>And now I will turn my discourse to one of their principal writers,
whom I have a little before made use of as a witness to our antiquity;
I mean Manetho. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">In reading this and the remaining sections of this book, and some parts
of the next, one may easily perceive that our usually cool and candid author,
Josephus, was too highly offended with the impudent calumnies of Manethe,
and the other bitter enemies of the Jews, with whom he had now to deal,
and was thereby betrayed into a greater heat and passion than ordinary,
and that by consequence he does not hear reason with his usual fairness
and impartiality; he seems to depart sometimes from the brevity and sincerity
of a faithful historian, which is his grand character, and indulges the
prolixity and colors of a pleader and a disputant: accordingly, I confess,
I always read these sections with less pleasure than I do the rest of his
writings, though I fully believe the reproaches cast on the Jews, which
he here endeavors to confute and expose, were wholly groundless and unreasonable.</note>
He promised to interpret the Egyptian history out of their sacred writings,
and premised this: that "our people had come into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, many ten
thousands in number, and subdued its inhabitants;" and when he had
further confessed that "we went out of that country afterward, and
settled in that country which is now called <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, and there built <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>
and its temple." Now thus far he followed his ancient records; but
after this he permits himself, in order to appear to have written what
rumors and reports passed abroad about the Jews, and introduces incredible
narrations, as if he would have the Egyptian multitude, that had the leprosy
and other distempers, to have been mixed with us, as he says they were,
and that they were condemned to fly out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> together; for he mentions
Amenophis, a fictitious king's name, though on that account he durst not
set down the number of years of his reign, which yet he had accurately
done as to the other kings he mentions; he then ascribes certain fabulous
stories to this king, as having in a manner forgotten how he had already
related that the departure of the shepherds for <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> had been five
hundred and eighteen years before; for Tethmosis was king when they went
away. Now, from his days, the reigns of the intermediate kings, according
to Manethe, amounted to three hundred and ninety-three years, as he says
himself, till the two brothers Sethos and Hermeus; the one of whom, Sethos,
was called by that other name of Egyptus, and the other, Hermeus, by that
of Danaus. He also says that Sethos east the other out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and reigned
fifty-nine years, as did his eldest son Rhampses reign after him sixty-six
years. When Manethe therefore had acknowledged that our forefathers were
gone out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> so many years ago, he introduces his fictitious king
Amenophis, and says thus: "This king was desirous to become a spectator
of the gods, as had Orus, one of his predecessors in that kingdom, desired
the same before him; he also communicated that his desire to his namesake
Amenophis, who was the son of Papis, and one that seemed to partake of
a divine nature, both as to wisdom and the knowledge of futurities."
Manethe adds, "how this namesake of his told him that he might see
the gods, if he would clear the whole country of the lepers and of the
other impure people; that the king was pleased with this injunction, and
got together all that had any defect in their bodies out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>; and
that their number was eighty thousand; whom he sent to those quarries which
are on the east side of the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>, that they might work in them, and might
be separated from the rest of the Egyptians." He says further, that
"there were some of the learned priests that were polluted with the
leprosy; but that still this Amenophis, the wise man and the prophet, was
afraid that the gods would be angry at him and at the king, if there should
appear to have been violence offered them; who also added this further,
[out of his sagacity about futurities,] that certain people would come
to the assistance of these polluted wretches, and would conquer <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>,
and keep it in their possession thirteen years; that, however, he durst
not tell the king of these things, but that he left a writing behind him
about all those matters, and then slew himself, which made the king disconsolate."
After which he writes thus <foreign lang="la">verbatim</foreign>: "After those that were
sent to work in the quarries had continued in that miserable state for
a long while, the king was desired that he would set apart the city <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>,
which was then left desolate of the shepherds, for their habitation and
protection; which desire he granted them. Now this city, according to the
ancient theology, was Typho's city. But when these men were gotten into
it, and found the place fit for a revolt, they appointed themselves a ruler
out of the priests of Hellopolis, whose name was Osarsiph, and they took
their oaths that they would be obedient to him in all things. He then,
in the first place, made this law for them, That they should neither worship
the Egyptian gods, nor should abstain from any one of those sacred animals
which they have in the highest esteem, but kill and destroy them all; that
they should join themselves to nobody but to those that were of this confederacy.
When he had made such laws as these, and many more such as were mainly
opposite to the customs of the Egyptians, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This is a very valuable testimony of Manetho, that the laws of Osarsiph,
or Moses, were not made in compliance with, but in opposition to, the customs
of the Egyptians. See the note on Antiq. B. III. ch. 8. sect. 9.</note>
he gave order that they should use the multitude of the hands they had
in building walls about their City, and make themselves ready for a war
with king Amenophis, while he did himself take into his friendship the
other priests, and those that were polluted with them, and sent ambassadors
to those shepherds who had been driven out of the land by Tefilmosis to
the city called <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>; whereby he informed them of his own affairs,
and of the state of those others that had been treated after such an ignominious
manner, and desired that they would come with one consent to his assistance
in this war against <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. He also promised that he would, in the first
place, bring them back to their ancient city and country <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>, and provide
a plentiful maintenance for their multitude; that he would protect them
and fight for them as occasion should require, and would easily reduce
the country under their dominion. These shepherds were all very glad of
this message, and came away with alacrity all together, being in number
two hundred thousand men; and in a little time they came to <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>. And
now Amenophis the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, upon his being informed of their invasion,
was in great confusion, as calling to mind what Amenophis, the son of Papis,
had foretold him; and, in the first place, he assembled the multitude of
the Egyptians, and took counsel with their leaders, and sent for their
sacred animals to him, especially for those that were principally worshipped
in their temples, and gave a particular charge to the priests distinctly,
that they should hide the images of their gods with the utmost care he
also sent his son Sethos, who was also named Ramesses, from his father
Rhampses, being but five years old, to a friend of his. He then passed
on with the rest of the Egyptians, being three hundred thousand of the
most warlike of them, against the enemy, who met them. Yet did he not join
battle with them; but thinking that would be to fight against the gods,
he returned back and came to <placeName key="tgn,7001186">Memphis</placeName>, where he took Apis and the other
sacred animals which he had sent for to him, and presently marched into
<placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>, together with his whole army and multitude of Egyptians; for
the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName> was under an obligation to him, on which account he
received him, and took care of all the multitude that was with him, while
the country supplied all that was necessary for the food of the men. He
also allotted cities and villages for this exile, that was to be from its
beginning during those fatally determined thirteen years. Moreover, he
pitched a camp for his Ethiopian army, as a guard to king Amenophis, upon
the borders of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. And this was the state of things in <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>. But
for the people of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, when they came down together with the polluted
Egyptians, they treated the men in such a barbarous manner, that those
who saw how they subdued the forementioned country, and the horrid wickedness
they were guilty of, thought it a most dreadful thing; for they did not
only set the cities and villages on fire but were not satisfied till they
had been guilty of sacrilege, and destroyed the images of the gods, and
used them in roasting those sacred animals that used to be worshipped,
and forced the priests and prophets to be the executioners and murderers
of those animals, and then ejected them naked out of the country. It was
also reported that the priest, who ordained their polity and their laws,
was by birth of Hellopolls, and his name Osarsiph, from Osyris, who was
the god of Hellopolls; but that when he was gone over to these people,
his name was changed, and he was called Moses."</p>
<milestone n="27" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="251" unit="section"/><p>This is what the Egyptians relate about the Jews, with much more,
which I omit for the sake of brevity. But still Manetho goes on, that "after
this, Amenophis returned back from <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName> with a great army, as did his
son Ahampses with another army also, and that both of them joined battle
with the shepherds and the polluted people, and beat them, and slew a great
many of them, and pursued them to the bounds of <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>." These and
the like accounts are written by Manetho. But I will demonstrate that he
trifles, and tells arrant lies, after I have made a distinction which will
relate to what I am going to say about him; for this Manetho had granted
and confessed that this nation was not originally Egyptian, but that they
had come from another country, and subdued <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and then went away again
out of it. But that. those Egyptians who were thus diseased in their bodies
were not mingled with us afterward, and that Moses who brought the people
out was not one of that company, but lived many generations earlier, I
shall endeavor to demonstrate from Manetho's own accounts themselves.</p>
<milestone n="28" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="254" unit="section"/><p>Now, for the first occasion of this fiction, Manetho supposes what
is no better than a ridiculous thing; for he says that" king Amenophis
desired to see the gods." What gods, I pray, did he desire to see?
If he meant the gods whom their laws ordained to be worshipped, the ox,
the goat, the crocodile, and the baboon, he saw them already; but for the
heavenly gods, how could he see them, and what should occasion this his
desire? To be sure? it was because another king before him had already
seen them. He had then been informed what sort of gods they were, and after
what manner they had been seen, insomuch that he did not stand in need
of any new artifice for obtaining this sight. However, the prophet by whose
means the king thought to compass his design was a wise man. If so, how
came he not to know that such his desire was impossible to be accomplished?
for the event did not succeed. And what pretense could there be to suppose
that the gods would not be seen by reason of the people's maims in their
bodies, or leprosy? for the gods are not angry at the imperfection of bodies,
but at wicked practices; and as to eighty thousand lepers, and those in
an ill state also, how is it possible to have them gathered together in
one day? nay, how came the king not to comply with the prophet? for his
injunction was, that those that were maimed should be expelled out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>,
while the king only sent them to work in the quarries, as if he were rather
in want of laborers, than intended to purge his country. He says further,
that" this prophet slew himself, as foreseeing the anger of the gods,
and those events which were to come upon <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> afterward; and that he left
this prediction for the king in writing." Besides, how came it to
pass that this prophet did not foreknow his own death at the first? nay,
how came he not to contradict the king in his desire to see the gods immediately?
how came that unreasonable dread upon him of judgments that were not to
happen in his lifetime? or what worse thing could he suffer, out of the
fear of which he made haste to kill himself? But now let us see the silliest
thing of all: - The king, although he had been informed of these things,
and terrified with the fear of what was to come, yet did not he even then
eject these maimed people out of his country, when it had been foretold
him that he was to clear <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> of them; but, as Manetho says, "he
then, upon their request, gave them that city to inhabit, which had formerly
belonged to the shepherds, and was called <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>; whither when they were
gone in crowds," he says, "they chose one that had formerly been
priest of Hellopolls; and that this priest first ordained that they should
neither worship the gods, nor abstain from those animals that were worshipped
by the Egyptians, but should kill and eat them all, and should associate
with nobody but those that had conspired with them; and that he bound the
multitude by oaths to be sure to continue in those laws; and that when
he had built a wall about <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>, he made war against the king." Manetho
adds also, that "this priest sent to <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> to invite that people
to come to his assistance, and promised to give them <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName>; for that it
had belonged to the forefathers of those that were coming from <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>,
and that when they were come, they made a war immediately against the king,
and got possession of all <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>." He says also that "the Egyptians
came with an army of two hundred thousand men, and that Amenophis, the
king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, not thinking that he ought to fight against the gods, ran
away presently into <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>, and committed Apis and certain other of their
sacred animals to the priests, and commanded them to take care of preserving
them." He says further, that" the people of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> came accordingly
upon the Egyptians, and overthrew their cities, and burnt their temples,
and slew their horsemen, and, in short, abstained from no sort of wickedness
nor barbarity; and for that priest who settled their polity and their laws,"
he says," he was by birth of Hellopolis, and his name was Osarsiph,
from Osyris the god of Hellopolis, but that he changed his name, and called
himself Moses." He then says that "on the thirteenth year afterward,
Amenophis, according to the fatal time of the duration of his misfortunes,
came upon them out of <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName> with a great army, and joining battle with
the shepherds and with the polluted people, overcame them in battle, and
slew a great many of them, and pursued them as far as the bounds of <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>."</p>
<milestone n="29" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="267" unit="section"/><p>Now Manetho does not reflect upon the improbability of his lie;
for the leprous people, and the multitude that was with them, although
they might formerly have been angry at the king, and at those that had
treated them so coarsely, and this according to the prediction of the prophet;
yet certainly, when they were come out of the mines, and had received of
the king a city, and a country, they would have grown milder towards him.
However, had they ever so much hated him in particular, they might have
laid a private plot against himself, but would hardly have made war against
all the Egyptians; I mean this on the account of the great kindred they
who were so numerous must have had among them. Nay still, if they had resolved
to fight with the men, they would not have had impudence enough to fight
with their gods; nor would they have ordained laws quite contrary to those
of their own country, and to those in which they had been bred up themselves.
Yet are we beholden to Manethe, that he does not lay the principal charge
of this horrid transgression upon those that came from <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, but says
that the Egyptians themselves were the most guilty, and that they were
their priests that contrived these things, and made the multitude take
their oaths for doing so. But still how absurd is it to suppose that none
of these people's own relations or friends should be prevailed with to
revolt, nor to undergo the hazards of war with them, while these polluted
people were forced to send to <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, and bring their auxiliaries from
thence! What friendship, I pray, or what relation was there formerly between
them that required this assistance? On the contrary, these people were
enemies, and greatly differed from them in their customs. He says, indeed,
that they complied immediately, upon their praising them that they should
conquer <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>; as if they did not themselves very well know that country
out of which they had been driven by force. Now had these men been in want,
or lived miserably, perhaps they might have undertaken so hazardous an
enterprise; but as they dwelt in a happy city, and had a large country,
and one better than <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> itself, how came it about that, for the sake
of those that had of old been their enemies, of those that were maimed
in their bodies, and of those whom none of their own relations would endure,
they should run such hazards in assisting them? For they could not foresee
that the king would run away from them: on the contrary, he saith himself
that "Amenophis's son had three hundred thousand men with him, and
met them at <placeName key="tgn,6004608">Pelusium</placeName>." Now, to be sure, those that came could not
be ignorant of this; but for the king's repentance and flight, how could
they possibly guess at it? He then says, that "those who came from
<placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, and made this invasion, got the granaries of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> into their
possession, and perpetrated many of the most horrid actions there."
And thence he reproaches them, as though he had not himself introduced
them as enemies, or as though he might accuse such as were invited from
another place for so doing, when the natural Egyptians themselves had done
the same things before their coming, and had taken oaths so to do. However,
"Amenophis, some time afterward, came upon them, and conquered them
in battle, and slew his enemies, and drove them before him as far as <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>."
As if <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> were so easily taken by people that came from any place whatsoever,
and as if those that had conquered it by war, when they were informed that
Amenophis was alive, did neither fortify the avenues out of <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName> into
it, although they had great advantages for doing it, nor did get their
other forces ready for their defense! but that he followed them over the
sandy desert, and slew them as far as <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>; while yet it is rot an easy
thing for an army to pass over that country, even without fighting.</p>
<milestone n="30" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="278" unit="section"/><p>Our nation, therefore, according to Manetho, was not derived from
<placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, nor were any of the Egyptians mingled with us. For it is to be supposed
that many of the leprous and distempered people were dead in the mines,
since they had been there a long time, and in so ill a condition; many
others must be dead in the battles that happened afterward, and more still
in the last battle and flight after it.</p>
<milestone n="31" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="279" unit="section"/><p>It now remains that I debate with Manetho about Moses. Now the Egyptians
acknowledge him to have been a wonderful and a divine person; nay, they
would willingly lay claim to him themselves, though after a most abusive
and incredible manner, and pretend that he was of <placeName key="tgn,7002856">Heliopolis</placeName>, and one of
the priests of that place, and was ejected out of it among the rest, on
account of his leprosy; although it had been demonstrated out of their
records that he lived five hundred and eighteen years earlier, and then
brought our forefathers out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> into the country that is now inhabited
by us. But now that he was not subject in his body to any such calamity,
is evident from what he himself tells us; for he forbade those that had
the leprosy either to continue in a city, or to inhabit in a village, but
commanded that they should go about by themselves with their clothes rent;
and declares that such as either touch them, or live under the same roof
with them, should be esteemed unclean; nay, more, if any one of their disease
be healed, and he recover his natural constitution again, he appointed
them certain purifications, and washings with spring water, and the shaving
off all their hair, and enjoins that they shall offer many sacrifices,
and those of several kinds, and then at length to be admitted into the
holy city; although it were to be expected that, on the contrary, if he
had been under the same calamity, he should have taken care of such persons
beforehand, and have had them treated after a kinder manner, as affected
with a concern for those that were to be under the like misfortunes with
himself. Nor ;was it only those leprous people for whose sake he made these
laws, but also for such as should be maimed in the smallest part of their
body, who yet are not permitted by him to officiate as priests; nay, although
any priest, already initiated, should have such a calamity fall upon him
afterward, he ordered him to be deprived of his honor of officiating. How
can it then be supposed that Moses should ordain such laws against himself,
to his own reproach and damage who so ordained them? Nor indeed is that
other notion of Manetho at all probable, wherein he relates the change
of his name, and says that "he was formerly called Osarsiph;"
and this a name no way agreeable to the other, while his true name was
Mosses, and signifies a person who is preserved out of the water, for the
Egyptians call water Moil. I think, therefore, I have made it sufficiently
evident that Manetho, while he followed his ancient records, did not much
mistake the truth of the history; but that when he had recourse to fabulous
stories, without any certain author, he either forged them himself, without
any probability, or else gave credit to some men who spake so out of their
ill-will to us.</p>
<milestone n="32" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="288" unit="section"/><p>And now I have done with Manetho, I will inquire into what Cheremon
says. For he also, when he pretended to write the Egyptian history, sets
down the same name for this king that Manetho did, Amenophis, as also of
his son Ramesses, and then goes on thus: "The goddess Isis appeared
to Amenophis in his sleep, and blamed him that her temple had been demolished
in the war. But that Phritiphantes, the sacred scribe, said to him, that
in case he would purge <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> of the men that had pollutions upon them,
he should be no longer troubled. with such frightful apparitions. That
Amenophis accordingly chose out two hundred and fifty thousand of those
that were thus diseased, and cast them out of the country: that Moses and
Joseph were scribes, and Joseph was a sacred scribe; that their names were
Egyptian originally; that of Moses had been Tisithen, and that of Joseph,
Peteseph: that these two came to <placeName key="tgn,6004608">Pelusium</placeName>, and lighted upon three hundred
and eighty thousand that had been left there by Amenophis, he not being
willing to carry them into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>; that these scribes made a league of friendship
with them, and made with them an expedition against <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>: that Amenophis
could not sustain their attacks, but fled into <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>, and left his wife
with child behind him, who lay concealed in certain caverns, and there
brought forth a son, whose name was <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, and who, when he was grown
up to man's estate, pursued the Jews into <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, being about two hundred
thousand, and then received his father Amenophis out of <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>."</p>
<milestone n="33" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="293" unit="section"/><p>This is the account Cheremon gives us. Now I take it for granted
that what I have said already hath plainly proved the falsity of both these
narrations; for had there been any real truth at the bottom, it was impossible
they should so greatly disagree about the particulars. But for those that
invent lies, what they write will easily give us very different accounts,
while they forge what they please out of their own heads. Now Manetho says
that the king's desire of seeing the gods was the origin of the ejection
of the polluted people; but Cheremon feigns that it was a dream of his
own, sent upon him by Isis, that was the occasion of it. Manetho says that
the person who foreshowed this purgation of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to the king was Amenophis;
but this man says it was Phritiphantes. As to the numbers of the multitude
that were expelled, they agree exceedingly well <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">By way of irony, I suppose.</note>
the former reckoning them eighty thousand, and the latter about two hundred
and fifty thousand! Now, for Manetho, he describes those polluted persons
as sent first to work in the quarries, and says that the city <placeName key="tgn,7001450">Avaris</placeName> was
given them for their habitation. As also he relates that it was not till
after they had made war with the rest of the Egyptians, that they invited
the people of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> to come to their assistance; while Cheremon says
only that they were gone out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and lighted upon three hundred and
eighty thousand men about Pelusium, who had been left there by Amenophis,
and so they invaded <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> with them again; that thereupon Amenophis fled
into <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>. But then this Cheremon commits a most ridiculous blunder
in not informing us who this army of so many ten thousands were, or whence
they came; whether they were native Egyptians, or whether they came from
a foreign country. Nor indeed has this man, who forged a dream from Isis
about the leprous people, assigned the reason why the king would not bring
them into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. Moreover, Cheremon sets down Joseph as driven away at
the same time with Moses, who yet died four generations <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Here we see that Josephus esteemed a generation between Joseph and Moses
to be about forty-two or forty-three years; which, if taken between the
earlier children, well agrees with the duration of human life in those
ages. See Antheat. Rec. Part II. pages 966, <date value="1019">1019</date>, <date value="1020">1020</date>.</note>
before Moses, which four generations make almost one hundred and seventy
years. Besides all this, Ramesses, the son of Amenophis, by Manetho's account,
was a young man, and assisted his father in his war, and left the country
at the same time with him, and fled into <placeName key="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>. But Cheremon makes him
to have been born in a certain cave, after his father was dead, and that
he then overcame the Jews in battle, and drove them into <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, being in
number about two hundred thousand. O the levity of the man! for he had
neither told us who these three hundred and eighty thousand were, nor how
the four hundred and thirty thousand perished; whether they fell in war,
or went over to Ramesses. And, what is the strangest of all, it is not
possible to learn out of him who they were whom he calls Jews, or to which
of these two parties he applies that denomination, whether to the two hundred
and fifty thousand leprous people, or to the three hundred and eighty thousand
that were about <placeName key="tgn,6004608">Pelusium</placeName>. But perhaps it will be looked upon as a silly
thing in me to make any larger confutation of such writers as sufficiently
confute themselves; for had they been only confuted by other men, it had
been more tolerable.</p>
<milestone n="34" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="304" unit="section"/><p>I shall now add to these accounts about Manetho and Cheremon somewhat
about Lysimachus, who hath taken the same topic of falsehood with those
forementioned, but hath gone far beyond them in the incredible nature of
his forgeries; which plainly demonstrates that he contrived them out of
his virulent hatred of our nation. His words are these: "The people
of the Jews being leprous and scabby, and subject to certain other kinds
of distempers, in the days of Bocchoris, king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, they fled to the
temples, and got their food there by begging: and as the numbers were very
great that were fallen under these diseases, there arose a scarcity in
<placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. Hereupon Bocehoris, the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, sent some to consult the
oracle of [<placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName>] Hammon about his scarcity. The god's answer was this,
that he must purge his temples of impure and impious men, by expelling
them out of those temples into desert places; but as to the scabby and
leprous people, he must drown them, and purge his temples, the sun having
an indignation at these men being suffered to live; and by this means the
land will bring forth its fruits. Upon Bocchoris's having received these
oracles, he called for their priests, and the attendants upon their altars,
and ordered them to make a collection of the impure people, and to deliver
them to the soldiers, to carry them away into the desert; but to take the
leprous people, and wrap them in sheets of lead, and let them down into
the sea. Hereupon the scabby and leprous people were drowned, and the rest
were gotten together, and sent into desert places, in order to be exposed
to destruction. In this case they assembled themselves together, and took
counsel what they should do, and determined that, as the night was coming
on, they should kindle fires and lamps, and keep watch; that they also
should fast the next night, and propitiate the gods, in order to obtain
deliverance from them. That on the next day there was one Moses, who advised
them that they should venture upon a journey, and go along one road till
they should come to places fit for habitation: that he charged them to
have no kind regards for any man, nor give good counsel to any, but always
to advise them for the worst; and to overturn all those temples and altars
of the gods they should meet with: that the rest commended what he had
said with one consent, and did what they had resolved on, and so traveled
over the desert. But that the difficulties of the journey being over, they
came to a country inhabited, and that there they abused the men, and plundered
and burnt their temples; and then came into that land which is called <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>,
and there they built a city, and dwelt therein, and that their city was
named <name rend="ital">Hierosyla</name>, from this their robbing of the temples; but that
still, upon the success they had afterwards, they in time changed its denomination,
that it might not be a reproach to them, and called the city <name rend="ital"><placeName key="tgn,7001371">Hierosolyma</placeName></name>,
and themselves <name rend="ital">Hierosolymites</name>."</p>
<milestone n="35" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="312" unit="section"/><p>Now this man did not discover and mention the same king with the
others, but feigned a newer name, and passing by the dream and the Egyptian
prophet, he brings him to [<placeName key="tgn,1125260">Jupiter</placeName>] Hammon, in order to gain oracles about
the scabby and leprous people; for he says that the multitude of Jews were
gathered together at the temples. Now it is uncertain whether he ascribes
this name to these lepers, or to those that were subject to such diseases
among the Jews only; for he describes them as a people of the Jews. What
people does he mean? foreigners, or those of that country? Why then' dost
thou call them Jews, if they were Egyptians? But if they were foreigners,
why dost thou not tell us whence they came? And how could it be that, after
the king had drowned many of them in the sea, and ejected the rest into
desert places, there should be still so great a multitude remaining? Or
after what manner did they pass over the desert, and get the land which
we now dwell in, and build our city, and that temple which hath been so
famous among all mankind? And besides, he ought to have spoken more about
our legislator than by giving us his bare name; and to have informed us
of what nation he was, and what parents he was derived from; and to have
assigned the reasons why he undertook to make such laws concerning the
gods, and concerning matters of injustice with regard to men during that
journey. For in case the people were by birth Egyptians, they would not
on the sudden have so easily changed the customs of their country; and
in case they had been foreigners, they had for certain some laws or other
which had been kept by them from long custom. It is true, that with regard
to those who had ejected them, they might have sworn never to bear good-will
to them, and might have had a plausible reason for so doing. But if these
men resolved to wage an implacable war against all men, in case they had
acted as wickedly as he relates of them, and this while they wanted the
assistance of all men, this demonstrates a kind of mad conduct indeed;
but not of the men themselves, but very greatly so of him that tells such
lies about them. He hath also impudence enough to say that a name, implying
"Robbers of the temples," <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">That is the meaning of Hierosyla in Greek, not in Hebrew.</note>
was given to their city, and that this name was afterward changed. The
reason of which is plain, that the former name brought reproach and hatred
upon them in the times of their posterity, while, it seems, those that
built the city thought they did honor to the city by giving it such a name.
So we see that this fine fellow had such an unbounded inclination to reproach
us, that he did not understand that robbery of temples is not expressed
By the same word and name among the Jews as it is among the Greeks. But
why should a man say any more to a person who tells such impudent lies?
However, since this book is arisen to a competent length, I will make another
beginning, and endeavor to add what still remains to perfect my design
in the following book.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="Book" n="2">
<head>BOOK II</head>
<milestone n="1" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><p>IN the former book, most honored Epaphroditus, I have demonstrated
our antiquity, and confirmed the truth of what I have said, from the writings
of the Phoenicians, and Chaldeans, and Egyptians. I have, moreover, produced
many of the Grecian writers as witnesses thereto. I have also made a refutation
of Manetho and Cheremon, and of certain others of our enemies. I shall
now <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">The former part of this second book is written against the calumnies of
Apion, and then, more briefly, against the like calumnies of Apollonius
Molo. But after that, Josephus leaves off any more particular reply to
those adversaries of the Jews, and gives us a large and excellent description
and vindication of that theocracy which was settled for the Jewish nation
by Moses, their great legislator.</note>
therefore begin a confutation of the remaining authors who have written
any thing against us; although I confess I have had a doubt upon me about
Apion <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Called by Tiberius Cymbalum Mundi, The drum of the world.</note>
the grammarian, whether I ought to take the trouble of confuting him or
not; for some of his writings contain much the same accusations which the
others have laid against us, some things that he hath added are very frigid
and contemptible, and for the greatest part of what he says, it is very
scurrilous, and, to speak no more than the plain truth, it shows him to
be a very unlearned person, and what he lays together looks like the work
of a man of very bad morals, and of one no better in his whole life than
a mountebank. Yet, because there are a great many men so very foolish,
that they are rather caught by such orations than by what is written with
care, and take pleasure in reproaching other men, and cannot abide to hear
them commended, I thought it to be necessary not to let this man go off
without examination, who had written such an accusation against us, as
if he would bring us to make an answer in open court. For I also have observed,
that many men are very much delighted when they see a man who first began
to reproach another, to be himself exposed to contempt on account of the
vices he hath himself been guilty of. However, it is not a very easy thing
to go over this man's discourse, nor to know plainly what he means; yet
does he seem, amidst a great confusion and disorder in his falsehoods,
to produce, in the first place, such things as resemble what we have examined
already, and relate to the departure of our forefathers out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>; and,
in the second place, he accuses those Jews that are inhabitants of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>;
as, in the third place, he mixes with those things such accusations as
concern the sacred purifications, with the other legal rites used in the
temple.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="8" unit="section"/><p>Now although I cannot but think that I have already demonstrated,
and that abundantly more than was necessary, that our fathers were not
originally Egyptians, nor were thence expelled, either on account of bodily
diseases, or any other calamities of that sort; yet will I briefly take
notice of what Apion adds upon that subject; for in his third book, which
relates to the affairs of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, he speaks thus: "I have heard of
the ancient men of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, that Moses was of <placeName key="tgn,7002856">Heliopolis</placeName>, and that he thought
himself obliged to follow the customs of his forefathers, and offered his
prayers in the open air, towards the city walls; but that he reduced them
all to be directed towards sun-rising, which was agreeable to the situation
of <placeName key="tgn,7002856">Heliopolis</placeName>; that he also set up pillars instead of gnomons, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This seems to have been the first dial that had been made in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and
was a little before the time that Ahaz made his [first] dial in <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>,
and about anno 755, in the first year of the seventh olympiad, as we shall
see presently. See 2 Kings 20:11; Isaiah 38:8.</note>
under which was represented a cavity like that of a boat, and the shadow
that fell from their tops fell down upon that cavity, that it might go
round about the like course as the sun itself goes round in the other."
This is that wonderful relation which we have given us by this grammarian.
But that it is a false one is so plain, that it stands in need of few words
to prove it, but is manifest from the works of Moses; for when he erected
the first tabernacle to God, he did himself neither give order for any
such kind of representation to be made at it, nor ordain that those that
came after him should make such a one. Moreover, when in a future age Solomon
built his temple in <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, he avoided all such needless decorations
as Apion hath here devised. He says further, how he had "heard of
the ancient men, that Moses was of Hellopolis." To be sure that was,
because being a younger man himself, he believed those that by their elder
age were acquainted and conversed with him. Now this grammarian, as he
was, could not certainly tell which was the poet Homer's country, no more
than he could which was the country of Pythagoras, who lived comparatively
but a little while ago; yet does he thus easily determine the age of Moses,
who preceded them such a vast number of years, as depending on his ancient
men's relation, which shows how notorious a liar he was. But then as to
this chronological determination of the time when he says he brought the
leprous people, the blind, and the lame out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, see how well this
most accurate grammarian of ours agrees with those that have written before
him! Manetho says that the Jews departed out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, in the reign of
Tethmosis, three hundred ninety-three years before Danaus fled to <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>;
Lysimaehus says it was under king Bocchoris, that is, one thousand seven
hundred years ago; Molo and some others determined it as every one pleased:
but this Apion of ours, as deserving to be believed before them, hath determined
it exactly to have been in the seventh olympiad, and the first year of
that olympiad; the very same year in which he says that <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> was built
by the Phoenicians. The reason why he added this building of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> was,
to be sure, in order, as he thought, to strengthen his assertion by so
evident a character of chronology. But he was not aware that this character
confutes his assertion; for if we may give credit to the Phoenician records
as to the time of the first coming of their colony to <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, they relate
that Hirom their king was above a hundred and fifty years earlier than
the building of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>; concerning whom I have formerly produced testimonials
out of those Phoenician records, as also that this Hirom was a friend of
Solomon when he was building the temple of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, and gave him great
assistance in his building that temple; while still Solomon himself built
that temple six hundred and twelve years after the Jews came out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>.
As for the number of those that were expelled out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, he hath contrived
to have the very same number with Lysimaehus, and says they were a hundred
and ten thousand. He then assigns a certain wonderful and plausible occasion
for the name of Sabbath; for he says that "when the Jews had traveled
a six days' journey, they had buboes in their groins; and that on this
account it was that they rested on the seventh day, as having got safely
to that country which is now called <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>; that then they preserved the
language of the Egyptians, and called that day the Sabbath, for that malady
of buboes on their groin was named Sabbatosis by the Egyptians." And
would not a man now laugh at this fellow's trifling, or rather hate his
impudence in writing thus? We must, it seems, fake it for granted that
all these hundred and ten thousand men must have these buboes. But, for
certain, if those men had been blind and lame, and had all sorts of distempers
upon them, as Apion says they had, they could not have gone one single
day's journey; but if they had been all able to travel over a large desert,
and, besides that, to fight and conquer those that opposed them, they had
not all of them had buboes on their groins after the sixth day was over;
for no such distemper comes naturally and of necessity upon those that
travel; but still, when there are many ten thousands in a camp together,
they constantly march a settled space [in a day]. Nor is it at all probable
that such a thing should happen by chance; this would be prodigiously absurd
to be supposed. However, our admirable author Apion hath before told us
that "they came to <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName> in six days' time;" and again, that
"Moses went up to a mountain that lay between <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1012700">Arabia</placeName>, which
was called <placeName key="tgn,7001247">Sinai</placeName>, and was concealed there forty days, and that when he
came down from thence he gave laws to the Jews." But, then, how was
it possible for them to tarry forty days in a desert place where there
was no water, and at the same time to pass all over the country between
that and <placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName> in the six days? And as for this grammatical translation
of the word Sabbath, it either contains an instance of his great impudence
or gross ignorance; for the words <foreign lang="xhebrew">Sabbo</foreign> and <foreign lang="xhebrew">Sabbath</foreign> are widely
different from one another; for the word Sabbath in the Jewish language
denotes rest from all sorts of work; but the word Sabbo, as he affirms,
denotes among the Egyptians the malady of a <term rend="ital">bubo</term> in the groin.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="28" unit="section"/><p>This is that novel account which the Egyptian Apion gives us concerning
the Jews' departure out of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and is no better than a contrivance of
his own. But why should we wonder at the lies he tells about our forefathers,
when he affirms them to be of Egyptian original, when he lies also about
himself? for although he was born at Oasis in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, he pretends to be,
as a man may say, the top man of all the Egyptians; yet does he forswear
his real country and progenitors, and by falsely pretending to be born
at <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, cannot deny the <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">The burial-place for dead bodies, as I suppose.</note>
pravity of his family; for you see how justly he calls those Egyptians
whom he hates, and endeavors to reproach; for had he not deemed Egyptians
to be a name of great reproach, he would not have avoided the name of an
Egyptian himself; as we know that those who brag of their own countries
value themselves upon the denomination they acquire thereby, and reprove
such as unjustly lay claim thereto. As for the Egyptians' claim to be of
our kindred, they do it on one of the following accounts; I mean, either
as they value themselves upon it, and pretend to bear that relation to
us; or else as they would draw us in to be partakers of their own infamy.
But this fine fellow Apion seems to broach this reproachful appellation
against us, [that we were originally Egyptians,] in order to bestow it
on the Alexandrians, as a reward for the privilege they had given him of
being a fellow citizen with them: he also is apprized of the ill-will the
Alexandrians bear to those Jews who are their fellow citizens, and so proposes
to himself to reproach them, although he must thereby include all the other
Egyptians also; while in both cases he is no better than an impudent liar.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="33" unit="section"/><p>But let us now see what those heavy and wicked crimes are which Apion
charges upon the Alexandrian Jews. "They came (says he) out of <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>,
and inhabited near the tempestuous sea, and were in the neighborhood of
the dashing of the waves." Now if the place of habitation includes
any thing that is reproached, this man reproaches not his own real country,
[<placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>,] but what he pretends to be his own country, <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>; for all
are agreed in this, that the part of that city which is near the sea is
the best part of all for habitation. Now if the Jews gained that part of
the city by force, and have kept it hitherto without impeachment, this
is a mark of their valor; but in reality it was Alexander himself that
gave them that place for their habitation, when they obtained equal privileges
there with the Macedonians. Nor call I devise what Apion would have said,
had their habitation been at Necropolis? and not been fixed hard by the
royal palace [as it is]; nor had their nation had the denomination of Macedonians
given them till this very day [as they have]. Had this man now read the
epistles of king Alexander, or those of Ptolemy the son of Lagus, or met
with the writings of the succeeding kings, or that pillar which is still
standing at <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, and contains the privileges which the great [Julius]
Caesar bestowed upon the Jews; had this man, I say, known these records,
and yet hath the impudence to write in contradiction to them, he hath shown
himself to be a wicked man; but if he knew nothing of these records, he
hath shown himself to be a man very ignorant: nay, when lie appears to
wonder how Jews could be called Alexandrians, this is another like instance
of his ignorance; for all such as are called out to be colonies, although
they be ever so far remote from one another in their original, receive
their names from those that bring them to their new habitations. And what
occasion is there to speak of others, when those of us Jews that dwell
at <placeName key="tgn,7002351">Antioch</placeName> are named Antiochians, because Seleucns the founder of that
city gave them the privileges belonging thereto? After the like manner
do those Jews that inhabit <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName>, and the other cities of <placeName key="tgn,6002765">Ionia</placeName>, enjoy
the same name with those that were originally born there, by the grant
of the succeeding princes; nay, the kindness and humanity of the Romans
hath been so great, that it hath granted leave to almost all others to
take the same name of Romans upon them; I mean not particular men only,
but entire and large nations themselves also; for those anciently named
Iberi, and Tyrrheni, and Sabini, are now called Romani. And if Apion reject
this way of obtaining the privilege of a citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, let him
abstain from calling himself an Alexandrian hereafter; for otherwise, how
can he who was born in the very heart of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> be an Alexandrian, if this
way of accepting such a privilege, of which he would have us deprived,
be once abrogated? although indeed these Romans, who are now the lords
of the habitable earth, have forbidden the Egyptians to have the privileges
of any city whatsoever; while this fine fellow, who is willing to partake
of such a privilege himself as he is forbidden to make use of, endeavors
by calumnies to deprive those of it that have justly received it; for Alexander
did not therefore get some of our nation to <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, because he wanted
inhabitants for this his city, on whose building he had bestowed so much
pains; but this was given to our people as a reward, because he had, upon
a careful trial, found them all to have been men of virtue and fidelity
to him; for, as Hecateus says concerning us, "Alexander honored our
nation to such a degree, that, for the equity and the fidelity which the
Jews exhibited to him, he permitted them to hold the country of <placeName key="tgn,7016998">Samaria</placeName>
free from tribute. Of the same mind also was Ptolemy the son of Lagus,
as to those Jews who dwelt at <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>." For he intrusted the fortresses
of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> into their hands, as believing they would keep them faithfully
and valiantly for him; and when he was desirous to secure the government
of <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>, and the other cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>, to himself, he sent a party of
Jews to inhabit in them. And for his successor Ptolemy, who was called
Philadelphus, he did not only set all those of our nation free who were
captives under him, but did frequently give money [for their ransom]; and,
what was his greatest work of all, he had a great desire of knowing our
laws, and of obtaining the books of our sacred Scriptures; accordingly,
he desired that such men might be sent him as might interpret our law to
him; and, in order to have them well compiled, he committed that care to
no ordinary persons, but ordained that Demetrius Phalereus, and <placeName key="tgn,1043060">Andreas</placeName>,
and Aristeas; the first, Demetrius, the most learned person of his age,
and the others, such as were intrusted with the guard of his body; should
take care of this matter: nor would he certainly have been so desirous
of learning our law, and the philosophy of our nation, had he despised
the men that made use of it, or had he not indeed had them in great admiration.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="48" unit="section"/><p>Now this Apion was unacquainted with almost all the kings of those
Macedonians whom he pretends to have been his progenitors, who were yet
very well affected towards us; for the third of those Ptolemies, who was
called Euergetes, when he had gotten possession of all <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> by force,
did not offer his thank-offerings to the Egyptian gods for his victory,
but came to <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName>, and according to our own laws offered many sacrifices
to God, and dedicated to him such gifts as were suitable to such a victory:
and as for Ptolemy Philometer and his wife Cleopatra, they committed their
whole kingdom to the Jews, when Onias and Dositheus, both Jews, whose names
are laughed at by Apion, were the generals of their whole army. But certainly,
instead of reproaching them, he ought to admire their actions, and return
them thanks for saving <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, whose citizen he pretends to be; for
when these Alexandrians were making war with Cleopatra the queen, and were
in danger of being utterly ruined, these Jews brought them to terms of
agreement, and freed them from the miseries of a civil war. "But then
(says Apion) Onias brought a small army afterward upon the city at the
time when Thorruns the Roman ambassador was there present." Yes, do
I venture to say, and that he did rightly and very justly in so doing;
for that Ptolemy who was called Physco, upon the death of his brother Philometer,
came from <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>, and would have ejected Cleopatra as well as her sons
out of their kingdom, that he might obtain it for himself unjustly. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Here begins a great defect in the Greek copy; but the old Latin version
fully supplies that defect.</note>
For this cause then it was that Onias undertook a war against him on Cleopatra's
account; nor would he desert that trust the royal family had reposed in
him in their distress. Accordingly, God gave a remarkable attestation to
his righteous procedure; for when Ptolemy Physco <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">What error is here generally believed to have been committed by our Josephus
in ascribing a deliverance of the Jews to the reign of Ptolemy Physco,
the seventh of those Ptolemus, which has been universally supposed to have
happened under Ptolemy Philopater, the fourth of them, is no better than
a gross error of the moderns, and not of Josephus, as I have fully proved
in the Authentic. Rec. Part I. p. 200-201, whither I refer the inquisitive
reader.</note>
had the presumption to fight against Onias's army, and had caught all the
Jews that were in the city [<placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>], with their children and wives,
and exposed them naked and in bonds to his elephants, that they might be
trodden upon and destroyed, and when he had made those elephants drunk
for that purpose, the event proved contrary to his preparations; for these
elephants left the Jews who were exposed to them, and fell violently upon
Physco's friends, and slew a great number of them; nay, after this Ptolemy
saw a terrible ghost, which prohibited his hurting those men; his very
concubine, whom he loved so well, (some call her <placeName key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>, and others <placeName key="tgn,2413588">Irene</placeName>,)
making supplication to him, that he would not perpetrate so great a wickedness.
So he complied with her request, and repented of what he either had already
done, or was about to do; whence it is well known that the Alexandrian
Jews do with good reason celebrate this day, on the account that they had
thereon been vouchsafed such an evident deliverance from God. However,
Apion, the common calumniator of men, hath the presumption to accuse the
Jews for making this war against Physco, when he ought to have commended
them for the same. This man also makes mention of Cleopatra, the last queen
of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, and abuses us, because she was ungrateful to us; whereas
he ought to have reproved her, who indulged herself in all kinds of injustice
and wicked practices, both with regard to her nearest relations and husbands
who had loved her, and, indeed, in general with regard to all the Romans,
and those emperors that were her benefactors; who also had her sister <placeName key="tgn,7016892">Arsinoe</placeName>
slain in a temple, when she had done her no harm: moreover, she had her
brother slain by private treachery, and she destroyed the gods of her country
and the sepulchers of her progenitors; and while she had received her kingdom
from the first Caesar, she had the impudence to rebel against his son:
<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Sister's son, and adopted son.</note>
and successor; nay, she corrupted Antony with her love-tricks, and rendered
him an enemy to his country, and made him treacherous to his friends, and
[by his means] despoiled some of their royal authority, and forced others
in her madness to act wickedly. But what need I enlarge upon this head
any further, when she left Antony in his fight at sea, though he were her
husband, and the father of their common children, and compelled him to
resign up his government, with the army, and to follow her [into <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>]?
nay, when last of all Caesar had taken <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, she came to that pitch
of cruelty, that she declared she had some hope of preserving her affairs
still, in case she could kill the Jews, though it were with her own hand;
to such a degree of barbarity and perfidiousness had she arrived. And doth
any one think that we cannot boast ourselves of any thing, if, as Apion
says, this queen did not at a time of famine distribute wheat among us?
However, she at length met with the punishment she deserved. As for us
Jews, we appeal to the great Caesar what assistance we brought him, and
what fidelity we showed to him against the Egyptians; as also to the senate
and its decrees, and the epistles of Augustus Caesar, whereby our merits
[to the Romans] are justified. Apion ought to have looked upon those epistles,
and in particular to have examined the testimonies given on our behalf,
under Alexander and all the Ptolemies, and the decrees of the senate and
of the greatest Roman emperors. And if Germanicus was not able to make
a distribution of corn to all the inhabitants of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, that only
shows what a barren time it was, and how great a want there was then of
corn, but tends nothing to the accusation of the Jews; for what all the
emperors have thought of the Alexandrian Jews is well known, for this distribution
of wheat was no otherwise omitted with regard to the Jews, than it was
with regard to the other inhabitants of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>. But they still were
desirous to preserve what the kings had formerly intrusted to their care,
I mean the custody of the river; nor did those kings think them unworthy
of having the entire custody thereof, upon all occasions.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="65" unit="section"/><p>But besides this, Apion objects to us thus: "If the Jews (says
he) be citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, why do they not worship the same gods with
the Alexandrians?" To which I give this answer: Since you are yourselves
Egyptians, why do you fight it out one against another, and have implacable
wars about your religion? At this rate we must not call you all Egyptians,
nor indeed in general men, because you breed up with great care beasts
of a nature quite contrary to that of men, although the nature of all men
seems to be one and the same. Now if there be such differences in opinion
among you Egyptians, why are you surprised that those who came to <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>
from another country, and had original laws of their own before, should
persevere in the observance of those laws? But still he charges us with
being the authors of sedition; which accusation, if it be a just one, why
is it not laid against us all, since we are known to be all of one mind.
Moreover, those that search into such matters will soon discover that the
authors of sedition have been such citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> as Apion is;
for while they were the Grecians and Macedonians who were ill possession
of this city, there was no sedition raised against us, and we were permitted
to observe our ancient solemnities; but when the number of the Egyptians
therein came to be considerable, the times grew confused, and then these
seditions brake out still more and more, while our people continued uncorrupted.
These Egyptians, therefore, were the authors of these troubles, who having
not the constancy of Macedonians, nor the prudence of Grecians, indulged
all of them the evil manners of the Egyptians, and continued their ancient
hatred against us; for what is here so presumptuously charged upon us,
is owing to the differences that are amongst themselves; while many of
them have not obtained the privileges of citizens in proper times, but
style those who are well known to have had that privilege extended to them
all no other than foreigners: for it does not appear that any of the kings
have ever formerly bestowed those privileges of citizens upon Egyptians,
no more than have the emperors done it more lately; while it was Alexander
who introduced us into this city at first, the kings augmented our privileges
therein, and the Romans have been pleased to preserve them always inviolable.
Moreover, Apion would lay a blot upon us, because we do not erect images
for our emperors; as if those emperors did not know this before, or stood
in need of Apion as their defender; whereas he ought rather to have admired
the magnanimity and modesty of the Romans, whereby they do not compel those
that are subject to them to transgress the laws of their countries, but
are willing to receive the honors due to them after such a manner as those
who are to pay them esteem consistent with piety and with their own laws;
for they do not thank people for conferring honors upon them, When they
are compelled by violence so to do. Accordingly, since the Grecians and
some other nations think it a right thing to make images, nay, when they
have painted the pictures of their parents, and wives, and children, they
exult for joy; and some there are who take pictures for themselves of such
persons as were no way related to them; nay, some take the pictures of
such servants as they were fond of; what wonder is it then if such as these
appear willing to pay the same respect to their princes and lords? But
then our legislator hath forbidden us to make images, not by way of denunciation
beforehand, that the Roman authority was not to be honored, but as despising
a thing that was neither necessary nor useful for either God or man; and
he forbade them, as we shall prove hereafter, to make these images for
any part of the animal creation, and much less for God himself, who is
no part of such animal creation. Yet hath our legislator no where forbidden
us to pay honors to worthy men, provided they be of another kind, and inferior
to those we pay to God; with which honors we willingly testify our respect
to our emperors, and to the people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; we also offer perpetual sacrifices
for them; nor do we only offer them every day at the common expenses of
all the Jews, but although we offer no other such sacrifices out of our
common expenses, no, not for our own children, yet do we this as a peculiar
honor to the emperors, and to them alone, while we do the same to no other
person whomsoever. And let this suffice for an answer in general to Apion,
as to what he says with relation to the Alexandrian Jews.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="79" unit="section"/><p>However, I cannot but admire those other authors who furnished this
man with such his materials; I mean Possidonius and Apollonius [the son
of] Molo, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Called more properly Molo, or Apollonius Molo, as hereafter; for Apollonins,
the son of Molo, was another person, as Strabo informs us, lib. xiv.</note>
who, while they accuse us for not worshipping the same gods whom others
worship, they think themselves not guilty of impiety when they tell lies
of us, and frame absurd and reproachful stories about our temple; whereas
it is a most shameful thing for freemen to forge lies on any occasion,
and much more so to forge them about our temple, which was so famous over
all the world, and was preserved so sacred by us; for Apion hath the impudence
to pretend that" the Jews placed an ass's head in their holy place;"
and he affirms that this was discovered when Antiochus Epiphanes spoiled
our temple, and found that ass's head there made of gold, and worth a great
deal of money. To this my first answer shall be this, that had there been
any such thing among us, an Egyptian ought by no means to have thrown it
in our teeth, since an ass is not a more contemptible animal than - <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Furones in the Latin, which what animal it denotes does not now appear.</note>
and goats, and other such creatures, which among them are gods. But besides
this answer, I say further, how comes it about that Apion does not understand
this to be no other than a palpable lie, and to be confuted by the thing
itself as utterly incredible? For we Jews are always governed by the same
laws, in which we constantly persevere; and although many misfortunes have
befallen our city, as the like have befallen others, and although Theos
[Epiphanes], and Pompey the Great, and Licinius Crassus, and last of all
Titus Caesar, have conquered us in war, and gotten possession of our temple;
yet have they none of them found any such thing there, nor indeed any thing
but what was agreeable to the strictest piety; although what they found
we are not at liberty to reveal to other nations. But for Antiochus [Epiphanes],
he had no just cause for that ravage in our temple that he made; he only
came to it when he wanted money, without declaring himself our enemy, and
attacked us while we were his associates and his friends; nor did he find
any thing there that was ridiculous. This is attested by many worthy writers;
Polybius of <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>, Strabo of <placeName key="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName>, Nicolaus of <placeName key="tgn,7002261">Damascus</placeName>, Timagenes,
Castor the chronotoger, and Apollodorus; <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">It is great pity that these six pagan authors, here mentioned to have described
the famous profanation of the Jewish temple by Antiochus Epiphanes, should
be all lost; I mean so far of their writings as contained that description;
though it is plain Josephus perused them all as extant in his time.</note>
who all say that it was out of Antiochus's want of money that he broke
his league with the Jews, and despoiled their temple when it was full of
gold and silver. Apion ought to have had a regard to these facts, unless
he had himself had either an ass's heart or a dog's impudence; of such
a dog I mean as they worship; for he had no other external reason for the
lies he tells of us. As for us Jews, we ascribe no honor or power to asses,
as do the Egyptians to crocodiles and asps, when they esteem such as are
seized upon by the former, or bitten by the latter, to be happy persons,
and persons worthy of God. Asses are the same with us which they are with
other wise men, viz. creatures that bear the burdens that we lay upon them;
but if they come to our thrashing-floors and eat our corn, or do not perform
what we impose upon them, we beat them with a great many stripes, because
it is their business to minister to us in our husbandry affairs. But this
Apion of ours was either perfectly unskillful in the composition of such
fallacious discourses, or however, when he begun [somewhat better], he
was not able to persevere in what he had undertaken, since he hath no manner
of success in those reproaches he casts upon us.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="89" unit="section"/><p>He adds another Grecian fable, in order to reproach us. In reply
to which, it would be enough to say, that they who presume to speak about
Divine worship ought not to be ignorant of this plain truth, that it is
a degree of less impurity to pass through temples, than to forge wicked
calumnies of its priests. Now such men as he are more zealous to justify
a sacrilegious king, than to write what is just and what is true about
us, and about our temple; for when they are desirous of gratifying Antiochus,
and of concealing that perfidiousness and sacrilege which he was guilty
of, with regard to our nation, when he wanted money, they endeavor to disgrace
us, and tell lies even relating to futurities. Apion becomes other men's
prophet upon this occasion, and says that "Antiochus found in our
temple a bed, and a man lying upon it, with a small table before him, full
of dainties, from the [fishes of the] sea, and the fowls of the dry land;
that this man was amazed at these dainties thus set before him; that he
immediately adored the king, upon his coming in, as hoping that he would
afford him all possible assistance; that he fell down upon his knees, and
stretched out to him his right hand, and begged to be released; and that
when the king bid him sit down, and tell him who he was, and why he dwelt
there, and what was the meaning of those various sorts of food that were
set before him the man made a lamentable complaint, and with sighs, and
tears in his eyes, gave him this account of the distress he was in; and
said that he was a Greek and that as he went over this province, in order
to get his living, he was seized upon by foreigners, on a sudden, and brought
to this temple, and shut up therein, and was seen by nobody, but was fattened
by these curious provisions thus set before him; and that truly at the
first such unexpected advantages seemed to him matter of great joy; that
after a while, they brought a suspicion him, and at length astonishment,
what their meaning should be; that at last he inquired of the servants
that came to him and was by them informed that it was in order to the fulfilling
a law of the Jews, which they must not tell him, that he was thus fed;
and that they did the same at a set time every year: that they used to
catch a Greek foreigner, and fat him thus up every year, and then lead
him to a certain wood, and kill him, and sacrifice with their accustomed
solemnities, and taste of his entrails, and take an oath upon this sacrificing
a Greek, that they would ever be at enmity with the Greeks; and that then
they threw the remaining parts of the miserable wretch into a certain pit."
Apion adds further, that" the man said there were but a few days to
come ere he was to be slain, and implored of Antiochus that, out of the
reverence he bore to the Grecian gods, he would disappoint the snares the
Jews laid for his blood, and would deliver him from the miseries with which
he was encompassed." Now this is such a most tragical fable as is
full of nothing but cruelty and impudence; yet does it not excuse Antiochus
of his sacrilegious attempt, as those who write it in his vindication are
willing to suppose; for he could not presume beforehand that he should
meet with any such thing in coming to the temple, but must have found it
unexpectedly. He was therefore still an impious person, that was given
to unlawful pleasures, and had no regard to God in his actions. But [as
for Apion], he hath done whatever his extravagant love of lying hath dictated
to him, as it is most easy to discover by a consideration of his writings;
for the difference of our laws is known not to regard the Grecians only,
but they are principally opposite to the Egyptians, and to some other nations
also for while it so falls out that men of all countries come sometimes
and sojourn among us, how comes it about that we take an oath, and conspire
only against the Grecians, and that by the effusion of their blood also?
Or how is it possible that all the Jews should get together to these sacrifices,
and the entrails of one man should be sufficient for so many thousands
to taste of them, as Apion pretends? Or why did not the king carry this
man, whosoever he was, and whatsoever was his name, (which is not set down
in Apion's book,) with great pomp back into his own country? when he might
thereby have been esteemed a religious person himself, and a mighty lover
of the Greeks, and might thereby have procured himself great assistance
from all men against that hatred the Jews bore to him. But I leave this
matter; for the proper way of confuting fools is not to use bare words,
but to appeal to the things themselves that make against them. Now, then,
all such as ever saw the construction of our temple, of what nature it
was, know well enough how the purity of it was never to be profaned; for
it had four several courts <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">It is remarkable that Josephus here, and, I think, no where else, reckons
up four distinct courts of the temple; that of the Gentiles, that of the
women of <placeName key="tgn,1000119">Israel</placeName>, that of the men of <placeName key="tgn,1000119">Israel</placeName>, and that of the priests; as
also that the court of the women admitted of the men, (I suppose only of
the husbands of those wives that were therein,) while the court of the
men did not admit any women into it at all.</note>
encompassed with cloisters round about, every one of which had by our law
a peculiar degree of separation from the rest. Into the first court every
body was allowed to go, even foreigners, and none but women, during their
courses, were prohibited to pass through it; all the Jews went into the
second court, as well as their wives, when they were free from all uncleanness;
into the third court went in the Jewish men, when they were clean and purified;
into the fourth went the priests, having on their sacerdotal garments;
but for the most sacred place, none went in but the high priests, clothed
in their peculiar garments. Now there is so great caution used about these
offices of religion, that the priests are appointed to go into the temple
but at certain hours; for in the morning, at the opening of the inner temple,
those that are to officiate receive the sacrifices, as they do again at
noon, till the doors are shut. Lastly, it is not so much as lawful to carry
any vessel into the holy house; nor is there any thing therein, but the
altar [of incense], the table [of shew-bread], the censer, and the candlestick,
which are all written in the law; for there is nothing further there, nor
are there any mysteries performed that may not be spoken of; nor is there
any feasting within the place. For what I have now said is publicly known,
and supported by the testimony of the whole people, and their operations
are very manifest; for although there be four courses of the priests, and
every one of them have above five thousand men in them, yet do they officiate
on certain days only; and when those days are over, other priests succeed
in the performance of their sacrifices, and assemble together at mid-day,
and receive the keys of the temple, and the vessels by tale, without any
thing relating to food or drink being carried into the temple; nay, we
are not allowed to offer such things at the altar, excepting what is prepared
for the sacrifices.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="109" unit="section"/><p>What then can we say of Apion, but that he examined nothing that
concerned these things, while still he uttered incredible words about them?
but it is a great shame for a grammarian not to be able to write true history.
Now if he knew the purity of our temple, he hath entirely omitted to take
notice of it; but he forges a story about the seizing of a Grecian, about
ineffable food, and the most delicious preparation of dainties; and pretends
that strangers could go into a place whereinto the noblest men among the
Jews are not allowed to enter, unless they be priests. This, therefore,
is the utmost degree of impiety, and a voluntary lie, in order to the delusion
of those who will not examine into the truth of matters; whereas such unspeakable
mischiefs as are above related have been occasioned by such calumnies that
are raised upon us.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="112" unit="section"/><p>Nay, this miracle or piety derides us further, and adds the following
pretended facts to his former fable; for be says that this man related
how, "while the Jews were once in a long war with the Idumeans, there
came a man out of one of the cities of the Idumeans, who there had worshipped
Apollo. This man, whose name is said to have been Zabidus, came to the
Jews, and promised that he would deliver Apollo, the god of <placeName key="tgn,1079507">Dora</placeName>, into
their hands, and that he would come to our temple, if they would all come
up with him, and bring the whole multitude of the Jews with them; that
Zabidus made him a certain wooden instrument, and put it round about him,
and set three rows of lamps therein, and walked after such a manner, that
he appeared to those that stood a great way off him to be a kind of star,
walking upon the earth; that the Jews were terribly affrighted at so surprising
an appearance, and stood very quiet at a distance; and that Zabidus, while
they continued so very quiet, went into the holy house, and carried off
that golden head of an ass, (for so facetiously does he write,) and then
went his way back again to <placeName key="tgn,1079507">Dora</placeName> in great haste." And say you so, sir!
as I may reply; then does Apion load the ass, that is, himself, and lays
on him a burden of fooleries and lies; for he writes of places that have
no being, and not knowing the cities he speaks of, he changes their situation;
for Idumea borders upon our country, and is near to <placeName key="tgn,7001390">Gaza</placeName>, in which there
is no such city as <placeName key="tgn,1079507">Dora</placeName>; although there be, it is true, a city named <placeName key="tgn,1079507">Dora</placeName>
in <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>, near <placeName key="tgn,7001405">Mount Carmel</placeName>, but it is four days' journey from Idumea.
<note anchored="yes" resp="ed"><placeName key="tgn,7001407">Judea</placeName>, in the Greek, by a gross mistake of the transcribers.</note>
Now, then, why does this man accuse us, because we have not gods in common
with other nations, if our fathers were so easily prevailed upon to have
Apollo come to them, and thought they saw him walking upon the earth, and
the stars with him? for certainly those who have so many festivals, wherein
they light lamps, must yet, at this rate, have never seen a candlestick!
But still it seems that while Zabidus took his journey over the country,
where were so many ten thousands of people, nobody met him. He also, it
seems, even in a time of war, found the walls of <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> destitute of
guards. I omit the rest. Now the doors of the holy house were seventy <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Seven in the Greek, by a like gross mistake of the transcribers. See of
the War, B. V. ch. 5. sect. 4.</note>
cubits high, and twenty cubits broad; they were all plated over with gold,
and almost of solid gold itself, and there were no fewer than twenty <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Two hundred in the Greek, contrary to the twenty in the War, B. VII. ch,
5. sect. 3.</note>
men required to shut them every day; nor was it lawful ever to leave them
open, though it seems this lamp-bearer of ours opened them easily, or thought
he opened them, as he thought he had the ass's head in his hand. Whether,
therefore, he returned it to us again, or whether Apion took it, and brought
it into the temple again, that Antiochus might find it, and afford a handle
for a second fable of Apion's, is uncertain.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="121" unit="section"/><p>Apion also tells a false story, when he mentions an oath of ours,
as if we "swore by God, the Maker of the heaven, and earth, and sea,
to bear no good will to any foreigner, and particularly to none of the
Greeks." Now this liar ought to have said directly that" we would
bear no good-will to any foreigner, and particularly to none of the Egyptians."
For then his story about the oath would have squared with the rest of his
original forgeries, in case our forefathers had been driven away by their
kinsmen, the Egyptians, not on account of any wickedness they had been
guilty of, but on account of the calamities they were under; for as to
the Grecians, we were rather remote from them in place, than different
from them in our institutions, insomuch that we have no enmity with them,
nor any jealousy of them. On the contrary, it hath so happened that many
of them have come over to our laws, and some of them have continued in
their observation, although others of them had not courage enough to persevere,
and so departed from them again; nor did any body ever hear this oath sworn
by us: Apion, it seems, was the only person that heard it, for he indeed
was the first composer of it.</p>
<milestone n="12" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="125" unit="section"/><p>However, Apion deserves to be admired for his great prudence, as
to what I am going to say, which is this," That there is a plain mark
among us, that we neither have just laws, nor worship God as we ought to
do, because we are not governors, but are rather in subjection to Gentiles,
sometimes to one nation, and sometimes to another; and that our city hath
been liable to several calamities, while their city [<placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>] hath been
of old time an imperial city, and not used to be in subjection to the Romans."
But now this man had better leave off this bragging, for every body but
himself would think that Apion said what he hath said against himself;
for there are very few nations that have had the good fortune to continue
many generations in the principality, but still the mutations in human
affairs have put them into subjection under others; and most nations have
been often subdued, and brought into subjection by others. Now for the
Egyptians, perhaps they are the only nation that have had this extraordinary
privilege, to have never served any of those monarchs who subdued <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>
and <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>, and this on account, as they pretend, that the gods fled into
their country, and saved themselves by being changed into the shapes of
wild beasts! Whereas these Egyptians <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This notorious disgrace belonging peculiarly to the people of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, ever
since the times of the old prophets of the Jews, noted both sect. 4 already,
and here, may be confirmed by the testimony of Isidorus, an Egyptian of
<placeName key="tgn,6004608">Pelusium</placeName>, Epist. lib. i. Ep. 489. And this is a remarkable completion of
the ancient prediction of God by Ezekiel 29:14, 15, that the Egyptians
should be a base kingdom, the basest of the kingdoms," and that "it
should not exalt itself any more above the nations."</note>
are the very people that appear to have never, in all the past ages, had
one day of freedom, no, not so much as from their own lords. For I will
not reproach them with relating the manner how the Persians used them,
and this not once only, but many times, when they laid their cities waste,
demolished their temples, and cut the throats of those animals whom they
esteemed to be gods; for it is not reasonable to imitate the clownish ignorance
of Apion, who hath no regard to the misfortunes of the Athenians, or of
the Lacedemonians, the latter of whom were styled by all men the most courageous,
and the former the most religious of the Grecians. I say nothing of such
kings as have been famous for piety, particularly of one of them, whose
name was Cresus, nor what calamities he met with in his life; I say nothing
of the citadel of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, of the temple at <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName>, of that at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>,
nor of ten thousand others which have been burnt down, while nobody cast
reproaches on those that were the sufferers, but on those that were the
actors therein. But now we have met with Apion, an accuser of our nation,
though one that still forgets the miseries of his own people, the Egptians;
but it is that Sesostris who was once so celebrated a king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> that
hath blinded him. Now we will not brag of our kings, David and Solomon,
though they conquered many nations; accordingly we will let them alone.
However, Apion is ignorant of what every body knows, that the Egyptians
were servants to the Persians, and afterwards to the Macedonians, when
they were lords of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, and were no better than slaves, while we have
enjoyed liberty formerly; nay, more than that, have had the dominion of
the cities that lie round about us, and this nearly for a hundred and twenty
years together, until Pompeius Magnus. And when all the kings every where
were conquered by the Romans, our ancestors were the only people who continued
to be esteemed their confederates and friends, on account of their fidelity
to them.<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">The truth of which still further appears by the present observation of
Josephus, that these Egyptians had never, in all the past ages since Sesostris,
had one day of liberty, no, not so much as to have been free from despotic
power under any of the monarchies to that day. And all this bas been found
equally true in the latter ages, under the Romans, Saracens, Mamelukes,
and Turks, from the days of Josephus till the present ago also.</note></p>
<milestone n="13" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="135" unit="section"/><p>"But," says Apion, "we Jews have not had any wonderful
men amongst us, not any inventors of arts, nor any eminent for wisdom."
He then enumerates Socrates, and Zeno, and Cleanthes, and some others of
the same sort; and, after all, he adds himself to them, which is the most
wonderful thing of all that he says, and pronounces <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> to be happy,
because it hath such a citizen as he is in it; for he was the fittest man
to be a witness to his own deserts, although he hath appeared to all others
no better than a wicked mountebank, of a corrupt life and ill discourses;
on which account one may justly pity <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, if it should value itself
upon such a citizen as he is. But as to our own men, we have had those
who have been as deserving of commendation as any other whosoever, and
such as have perused our Antiquities cannot be ignorant of them.</p>
<milestone n="14" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="137" unit="section"/><p>As to the other things which he sets down as blameworthy, it may
perhaps be the best way to let them pass without apology, that he may be
allowed to be his own accuser, and the accuser of the rest of the Egyptians.
However, he accuses us for sacrificing animals, and for abstaining from
swine's flesh, and laughs at us for the circumcision of our privy members.
Now as for our slaughter of tame animals for sacrifices, it is common to
us and to all other men; but this Apion, by making it a crime to sacrifice
them, demonstrates himself to be an Egyptian; for had he been either a
Grecian or a Macedonian, [as he pretends to be,] he had not shown any uneasiness
at it; for those people glory in sacrificing whole hecatombs to the gods,
and make use of those sacrifices for feasting; and yet is not the world
thereby rendered destitute of cattle, as Apion was afraid would come to
pass. Yet if all men had followed the manners of the Egyptians, the world
had certainly been made desolate as to mankind, but had been filled full
of the wildest sort of brute beasts, which, because they suppose them to
be gods, they carefully nourish. However, if any one should ask Apion which
of the Egyptians he thinks to he the most wise and most pious of them all,
he would certainly acknowledge the priests to be so; for the histories
say that two things were originally committed to their care by their kings'
injunctions, the worship of the gods, and the support of wisdom and philosophy.
Accordingly, these priests are all circumcised, and abstain from swine's
flesh; nor does any one of the other Egyptians assist them in slaying those
sacrifices they offer to the gods. Apion was therefore quite blinded in
his mind, when, for the sake of the Egyptians, he contrived to reproach
us, and to accuse such others as not only make use of that conduct of life
which he so much abuses, but have also taught other men to be circumcised,
as says Herodotus; which makes me think that Apion is hereby justly punished
for his casting such reproaches on the laws of his own country; for he
was circumcised himself of necessity, on account of an ulcer in his privy
member; and when he received no benefit by such circumcision, but his member
became putrid, he died in great torment. Now men of good tempers ought
to observe their own laws concerning religion accurately, and to persevere
therein, but not presently to abuse the laws of other nations, while this
Apion deserted his own laws, and told lies about ours. And this was the
end of Apion's life, and this shall be the conclusion of our discourse
about him.</p>
<milestone n="15" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="145" unit="section"/><p>But now, since Apollonius Molo, and Lysimachus, and some others,
write treatises about our lawgiver Moses, and about our laws, which are
neither just nor true, and this partly out of ignorance, but chiefly out
of ill-will to us, while they calumniate Moses as an impostor and deceiver,
and pretend that our laws teach us wickedness, but nothing that is virtuous,
I have a mind to discourse briefly, according to my ability, about our
whole constitution of government, and about the particular branches of
it. For I suppose it will thence become evident, that the laws we have
given us are disposed after the best manner for the advancement of piety,
for mutual communion with one another, for a general love of mankind, as
also for justice, and for sustaining labors with fortitude, and for a contempt
of death. And I beg of those that shall peruse this writing of mine, to
read it without partiality; for it is not my purpose to write an encomium
upon ourselves, but I shall esteem this as a most just apology for us,
and taken from those our laws, according to which we lead our lives, against
the many and the lying objections that have been made against us. Moreover,
since this Apollonius does not do like Apion, and lay a continued accusation
against us, but does it only by starts, and up and clown his discourse,
while he sometimes reproaches us as atheists, and man-haters, and sometimes
hits us in the teeth with our want of courage, and yet sometimes, on the
contrary, accuses us of too great boldness and madness in our conduct;
nay, he says that we are the weakest of all the barbarians, and that this
is the reason why we are the only people who have made no improvements
in human life; now I think I shall have then sufficiently disproved all
these his allegations, when it shall appear that our laws enjoin the very
reverse of what he says, and that we very carefully observe those laws
ourselves. And if I he compelled to make mention of the laws of other nations,
that are contrary to ours, those ought deservedly to thank themselves for
it, who have pretended to depreciate our laws in comparison of their own;
nor will there, I think, be any room after that for them to pretend either
that we have no such laws ourselves, an epitome of which I will present
to the reader, or that we do not, above all men, continue in the observation
of them.</p>
<milestone n="16" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="151" unit="section"/><p>To begin then a good way backward, I would advance this, in the
first place, that those who have been admirers of good order, and of living
under common laws, and who began to introduce them, may well have this
testimony that they are better than other men, both for moderation and
such virtue as is agreeable to nature. Indeed their endeavor was to have
every thing they ordained believed to be very ancient, that they might
not be thought to imitate others, but might appear to have delivered a
regular way of living to others after them. Since then this is the case,
the excellency of a legislator is seen in providing for the people's living
after the best manner, and in prevailing with those that are to use the
laws he ordains for them, to have a good opinion of them, and in obliging
the multitude to persevere in them, and to make no changes in them, neither
in prosperity nor adversity. Now I venture to say, that our legislator
is the most ancient of all the legislators whom we have ally where heard
of; for as for the Lycurguses, and Solons, and Zaleucus Locrensis, and
all those legislators who are so admired by the Greeks, they seem to be
of yesterday, if compared with our legislator, insomuch as the very name
of a law was not so much as known in old times among the Grecians. Homer
is a witness to the truth of this observation, who never uses that term
in all his poems; for indeed there was then no such thing among them, but
the multitude was governed by wise maxims, and by the injunctions of their
king. It was also a long time that they continued in the use of these unwritten
customs, although they were always changing them upon several occasions.
But for our legislator, who was of so much greater antiquity than the rest,
(as even those that speak against us upon all occasions do always confess,)
he exhibited himself to the people as their best governor and counselor,
and included in his legislation the entire conduct of their lives, and
prevailed with them to receive it, and brought it so to pass, that those
that were made acquainted with his laws did most carefully observe them.</p>
<milestone n="17" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="157" unit="section"/><p>But let us consider his first and greatest work; for when it was
resolved on by our forefathers to leave <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and return to their own
country, this Moses took the many tell thousands that were of the people,
and saved them out of many desperate distresses, and brought them home
in safety. And certainly it was here necessary to travel over a country
without water, and full of sand, to overcome their enemies, and, during
these battles, to preserve their children, and their wives, and their prey;
on all which occasions he became an excellent general of an army, and a
most prudent counselor, and one that took the truest care of them all;
he also so brought it about, that the whole multitude depended upon him.
And while he had them always obedient to what he enjoined, he made no manner
of use of his authority for his own private advantage, which is the usual
time when governors gain great powers to themselves, and pave the way for
tyranny, and accustom the multitude to live very dissolutely; whereas,
when our legislator was in so great authority, he, on the contrary, thought
he ought to have regard to piety, and to show his great good-will to the
people; and by this means he thought he might show the great degree of
virtue that was in him, and might procure the most lasting security to
those who had made him their governor. When he had therefore come to such
a good resolution, and had performed such wonderful exploits, we had just
reason to look upon ourselves as having him for a divine governor and counselor.
And when he had first persuaded himself <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This language, that Moses, "persuaded himself" that what he did
was according to God's will, can mean no more, by Josephus's own constant
notions elsewhere, than that he was "firmly persuaded," that
he had "fully satisfied himself" that so it was, viz. by the
many revelations he had received from God, and the numerous miracles God
had enabled him to work, as he both in these very two books against Apion,
and in his Antiquities, most clearly and frequently assures us. This is
further evident from several passages lower, where he affirms that Moses
was no impostor nor deceiver, and where he assures that Moses's constitution
of government was no other than a theocracy; and where he says they are
to hope for deliverance out of their distresses by prayer to God, and that
withal it was owing in part to this prophetic spirit of Moses that the
Jews expected a resurrection from the dead. See almost as strange a use
of the like words, "to persuade God," Antiq. B. VI. ch. 5. sect.
6.</note>
that his actions and designs were agreeable to God's will, he thought it
his duty to impress, above all things, that notion upon the multitude;
for those who have once believed that God is the inspector of their lives,
will not permit themselves in any sin. And this is the character of our
legislator: he was no impostor, no deceiver, as his revilers say, though
unjustly, but such a one as they brag Minos <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">That is, Moses really was, what the heathen legislators pretended to be,
under a Divine direction; nor does it yet appear that these pretensions
to a supernatural conduct, either in these legislators or oracles, were
mere delusions of men without any demoniacal impressions, nor that Josephus
took them so to be; as the ancientest and contemporary authors did still
believe them to be supernatural.</note>
to have been among the Greeks, and other legislators after him; for some
of them suppose that they had their laws from <placeName key="tgn,2075298">Jupiter</placeName>, while Minos said
that the revelation of his laws was to be referred to Apollo, and his oracle
at <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Delphi</placeName>, whether they really thought they were so derived, or supposed,
however, that they could persuade the people easily that so it was. But
which of these it was who made the best laws, and which had the greatest
reason to believe that God was their author, it will be easy, upon comparing
those laws themselves together, to determine; for it is time that we come
to that point. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This whole very large passage is corrected by Dr. Hudson from Eusebius's
citation of it, Prep. Evangel. viii. 8, which is here not a little different
from the present MSS. of Josephus.</note>
Now there are innumerable differences in the particular customs and laws
that are among all mankind, which a man may briefly reduce under the following
heads: Some legislators have permitted their governments to be under monarchies,
others put them under oligarchies, and others under a republican form;
but our legislator had no regard to any of these forms, but he ordained
our government to be what, by a strained expression, may be termed a Theocracy,
<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This expression itself, that "Moses ordained the Jewish government
to be a theocracy," may be illustrated by that parallel expression
in the Antiquities, B. III. ch. 8. sect. 9, that "Moses left it to
God to be present at his sacrifices when he pleased; and when he pleased,
to be absent." Both ways of speaking sound harsh in the ears of Jews
and Christians, as do several others which Josephus uses to the heathens;
but still they were not very improper in him, when he all along thought
fit to accommodate himself, both in his Antiquities, and in these his books
against Apion, all written for the use of the Greeks and Romans, to their
notions and language, and this as far as ever truth would give him leave.
Though it be very observable withal, that he never uses such expressions
in his books of the War, written originally for the Jews beyond <placeName key="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName>,
and in their language, in all these cases. However, Josephus directly supposes
the Jewish settlement, under Moses, to be a Divine settlement, and indeed
no other than a real theocracy.</note>
by ascribing the authority and the power to God, and by persuading all
the people to have a regard to him, as the author of all the good things
that were enjoyed either in common by all mankind, or by each one in particular,
and of all that they themselves obtained by praying to him in their greatest
difficulties. He informed them that it was impossible to escape God's observation,
even in any of our outward actions, or in any of our inward thoughts. Moreover,
he represented God as unbegotten, <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">These excellent accounts of the Divine attributes, and that God is not
to be at all known in his essence, as also some other clear expressions
about the resurrection of the dead, and the state of departed souls, etc.,
in this late work of Josephus, look more like the exalted notions of the
Essens, or rather Ebionite Christians, than those of a mere Jew or Pharisee.
The following large accounts also of the laws of Moses, seem to me to show
a regard to the higher interpretations and improvements of Moses's laws,
derived from Jesus Christ, than to the bare letter of them in the Old Testament,
whence alone Josephus took them when he wrote his Antiquities; nor, as
I think, can some of these laws, though generally excellent in their kind,
be properly now found either in the copies of the Jewish Pentateuch, or
in Philo, or in Josephus himself, before he became a Nazarene or Ebionite
Christian; nor even all of them among the laws of catholic Christianity
themselves. I desire, therefore, the learned reader to consider, whether
some of these improvements or interpretations might not be peculiar to
the Essens among the Jews, or rather to the Nazarenes or Ebionites among
the Christians, though we have indeed but imperfect accounts of those Nazarenes
or Ebionite Christians transmitted down to us at this day.</note>
and immutable, through all eternity, superior to all mortal conceptions
in pulchritude; and, though known to us by his power, yet unknown to us
as to his essence. I do not now explain how these notions of God are the
sentiments of the wisest among the Grecians, and how they were taught them
upon the principles that he afforded them. However, they testify, with
great assurance, that these notions are just, and agreeable to the nature
of God, and to his majesty; for Pythagoras, and Anaxagoras, and Plato,
and the Stoic philosophers that succeeded them, and almost all the rest,
are of the same sentiments, and had the same notions of the nature of God;
yet durst not these men disclose those true notions to more than a few,
because the body of the people were prejudiced with other opinions beforehand.
But our legislator, who made his actions agree to his laws, did not only
prevail with those that were his contemporaries to agree with these his
notions, but so firmly imprinted this faith in God upon all their posterity,
that it never could be removed. The reason why the constitution of this
legislation was ever better directed to the utility of all than other legislations
were, is this, that Moses did not make religion a part of virtue, but he
saw and he ordained other virtues to be parts of religion; I mean justice,
and fortitude, and temperance, and a universal agreement of the members
of the community with one another; for all our actions and studies, and
all our words, [in Moses's settlement,] have a reference to piety towards
God; for he hath left none of these in suspense, or undetermined. For there
are two ways of coining at any sort of learning and a moral conduct of
life; the one is by instruction in words, the other by practical exercises.
Now other lawgivers have separated these two ways in their opinions, and
choosing one of those ways of instruction, or that which best pleased every
one of them, neglected the other. Thus did the Lacedemonians and the Cretians
teach by practical exercises, but not by words; while the Athenians, and
almost all the other Grecians, made laws about what was to be done, or
left undone, but had no regard to the exercising them thereto in practice.</p>
<milestone n="18" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="173" unit="section"/><p>But for our legislator, he very carefully joined these two methods
of instruction together; for he neither left these practical exercises
to go on without verbal instruction, nor did he permit the hearing of the
law to proceed without the exercises for practice; but beginning immediately
from the earliest infancy, and the appointment of every one's diet, he
left nothing of the very smallest consequence to be done at the pleasure
and disposal of the person himself. Accordingly, he made a fixed rule of
law what sorts of food they should abstain from, and what sorts they should
make use of; as also, what communion they should have with others what
great diligence they should use in their occupations, and what times of
rest should be interposed, that, by living under that law as under a father
and a master, we might be guilty of no sin, neither voluntary nor out of
ignorance; for he did not suffer the guilt of ignorance to go on without
punishment, but demonstrated the law to be the best and the most necessary
instruction of all others, permitting the people to leave off their other
employments, and to assemble together for the hearing of the law, and learning
it exactly, and this not once or twice, or oftener, but every week; which
thing all the other legislators seem to have neglected.</p>
<milestone n="19" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="176" unit="section"/><p>And indeed the greatest part of mankind are so far from living according
to their own laws, that they hardly know them; but when they have sinned,
they learn from others that they have transgressed the law. Those also
who are in the highest and principal posts of the government, confess they
are not acquainted with those laws, and are obliged to take such persons
for their assessors in public administrations as profess to have skill
in those laws; but for our people, if any body do but ask any one of them
about our laws, he will more readily tell them all than he will tell his
own name, and this in consequence of our having learned them immediately
as soon as ever we became sensible of any thing, and of our having them
as it were engraven on our souls. Our transgressors of them are but few,
and it is impossible, when any do offend, to escape punishment.</p>
<milestone n="20" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="179" unit="section"/><p>And this very thing it is that principally creates such a wonderful
agreement of minds amongst us all; for this entire agreement of ours in
all our notions concerning God, and our having no difference in our course
of life and manners, procures among us the most excellent concord of these
our manners that is any where among mankind; for no other people but the
Jews have avoided all discourses about God that any way contradict one
another, which yet are frequent among other nations; and this is true not
only among ordinary persons, according as every one is affected, but some
of the philosophers have been insolent enough to indulge such contradictions,
while some of them have undertaken to use such words as entirely take away
the nature of God, as others of them have taken away his providence over
mankind. Nor can any one perceive amongst us any difference in the conduct
of our lives, but all our works are common to us all. We have one sort
of discourse concerning God, which is conformable to our law, and affirms
that he sees all things; as also we have but one way of speaking concerning
the conduct of our lives, that all other things ought to have piety for
their end; and this any body may hear from our women, and servants themselves.</p>
<milestone n="21" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="182" unit="section"/><p>And, indeed, hence hath arisen that accusation which some make against
us, that we have not produced men that have been the inventors of new operations,
or of new ways of speaking; for others think it a fine thing to persevere
in nothing that has been delivered down from their forefathers, and these
testify it to be an instance of the sharpest wisdom when these men venture
to transgress those traditions; whereas we, on the contrary, suppose it
to be our only wisdom and virtue to admit no actions nor supposals that
are contrary to our original laws; which procedure of ours is a just and
sure sign that our law is admirably constituted; for such laws as are not
thus well made are convicted upon trial to want amendment.</p>
<milestone n="22" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="184" unit="section"/><p>But while we are ourselves persuaded that our law was made agreeably
to the will of God, it would be impious for us not to observe the same;
for what is there in it that any body would change? and what can be invented
that is better? or what can we take out of other people's laws that will
exceed it? Perhaps some would have the entire settlement of our government
altered. And where shall we find a better or more righteous constitution
than ours, while this makes us esteem God to be the Governor of the universe,
and permits the priests in general to be the administrators of the principal
affairs, and withal intrusts the government over the other priests to the
chief high priest himself? which priests our legislator, at their first
appointment, did not advance to that dignity for their riches, or any abundance
of other possessions, or any plenty they had as the gifts of fortune; but
he intrusted the principal management of Divine worship to those that exceeded
others in an ability to persuade men, and in prudence of conduct. These
men had the main care of the law and of the other parts of the people's
conduct committed to them; for they were the priests who were ordained
to be the inspectors of all, and the judges in doubtful cases, and the
punishers of those that were condemned to suffer punishment.</p>
<milestone n="23" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="188" unit="section"/><p>What form of government then can be more holy than this? what more
worthy kind of worship can be paid to God than we pay, where the entire
body of the people are prepared for religion, where an extraordinary degree
of care is required in the priests, and where the whole polity is so ordered
as if it were a certain religious solemnity? For what things foreigners,
when they solemnize such festivals, are not able to observe for a few days'
time, and call them Mysteries and Sacred Ceremonies, we observe with great
pleasure and an unshaken resolution during our whole lives. What are the
things then that we are commanded or forbidden? They are simple, and easily
known. The first command is concerning God, and affirms that God contains
all things, and is a Being every way perfect and happy, self-sufficient,
and supplying all other beings; the beginning, the middle, and the end
of all things. He is manifest in his works and benefits, and more conspicuous
than any other being whatsoever; but as to his form and magnitude, he is
most obscure. All materials, let them be ever so costly, are unworthy to
compose an image for him, and all arts are unartful to express the notion
we ought to have of him. We can neither see nor think of any thing like
him, nor is it agreeable to piety to form a resemblance of him. We see
his works, the light, the heaven, the earth, the sun and the moon, the
waters, the generations of animals, the productions of fruits. These things
hath God made, not with hands, nor with labor, nor as wanting the assistance
of any to cooperate with him; but as his will resolved they should be made
and be good also, they were made and became good immediately. All men ought
to follow this Being, and to worship him in the exercise of virtue; for
this way of worship of God is the most holy of all others.</p>
<milestone n="24" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="193" unit="section"/><p>There ought also to be but one temple for one God; for likeness
is the constant foundation of agreement. This temple ought to be common
to all men, because he is the common God of all men. High priests are to
be continually about his worship, over whom he that is the first by his
birth is to be their ruler perpetually. His business must be to offer sacrifices
to God, together with those priests that are joined with him, to see that
the laws be observed, to determine controversies, and to punish those that
are convicted of injustice; while he that does not submit to him shall
be subject to the same punishment, as if he had been guilty of impiety
towards God himself. When we offer sacrifices to him, we do it not in order
to surfeit ourselves, or to be drunken; for such excesses are against the
will of God, and would be an occasion of injuries and of luxury; but by
keeping ourselves sober, orderly, and ready for our other occupations,
and being more temperate than others. And for our duty at the sacrifices
<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">We may here observe how known a thing it was among the Jews and heathens,
in this and many other instances, that sacrifices were still accompanied
with prayers; whence most probably came those phrases of "the sacrifice
of prayer, the sacrifice of praise, the sacrifice of thanksgiving."
However, those ancient forms used at sacrifices are now generally lost,
to the no small damage of true religion. It is here also exceeding remarkable,
that although the temple at <placeName key="tgn,7001371">Jerusalem</placeName> was built as the only place where
the whole nation of the Jews were to offer their sacrifices, yet is there
no mention of the "sacrifices" themselves, but of "prayers"
only, in Solomon's long and famous form of devotion at its dedication,
1 Kings 8.; 2 Chronicles 6. See also many passages cited in the Apostolical
Constitutions, VII. 37, and Of the War, above, B. VII. ch. 5. sect. 6.</note>
themselves, we ought, in the first place, to pray for the common welfare
of all, and after that for our own; for we are made for fellowship one
with another, and he who prefers the common good before what is peculiar
to himself is above all acceptable to God. And let our prayers and supplications
be made humbly to God, not [so much] that he would give us what is good,
(for he hath already given that of his own accord, and hath proposed the
same publicly to all,) as that we may duly receive it, and when we have
received it, may preserve it. Now the law has appointed several purifications
at our sacrifices, whereby we are cleansed after a funeral, after what
sometimes happens to us in bed, and after accompanying with our wives,
and upon many other occasions, which it would be too long now to set down.
And this is our doctrine concerning God and his worship, and is the same
that the law appoints for our practice.</p>
<milestone n="25" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="199" unit="section"/><p>But, then, what are our laws about marriage? That law owns no other
mixture of sexes but that which nature hath appointed, of a man with his
wife, and that this be used only for the procreation of children. But it
abhors the mixture of a male with a male; and if any one do that, death
is its punishment. It commands us also, when we marry, not to have regard
to portion, nor to take a woman by violence, nor to persuade her deceitfully
and knavishly; but to demand her in marriage of him who hath power to dispose
of her, and is fit to give her away by the nearness of his kindred; for,
says the Scripture, "A woman is inferior to her husband in all things."
<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">This text is no where in our present copies of the Old Testament.</note>
Let her, therefore, be obedient to him; not so that he should abuse her,
but that she may acknowledge her duty to her husband; for God hath given
the authority to the husband. A husband, therefore, is to lie only with
his wife whom he hath married; but to have to do with another man's wife
is a wicked thing, which, if any one ventures upon, death is inevitably
his punishment: no more can he avoid the same who forces a virgin betrothed
to another man, or entices another man's wife. The law, moreover, enjoins
us to bring up all our offspring, and forbids women to cause abortion of
what is begotten, or to destroy it afterward; and if any woman appears
to have so done, she will be a murderer of her child, by destroying a living
creature, and diminishing human kind; if any one, therefore, proceeds to
such fornication or murder, he cannot be clean. Moreover, the law enjoins,
that after the man and wife have lain together in a regular way, they shall
bathe themselves; for there is a defilement contracted thereby, both in
soul and body, as if they had gone into another country; for indeed the
soul, by being united to the body, is subject to miseries, and is not freed
therefrom again but by death; on which account the law requires this purification
to be entirely performed.</p>
<milestone n="26" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="204" unit="section"/><p>Nay, indeed, the law does not permit us to make festivals at the
births of our children, and thereby afford occasion of drinking to excess;
but it ordains that the very beginning of our education should be immediately
directed to sobriety. It also commands us to bring those children up in
learning, and to exercise them in the laws, and make them acquainted with
the acts of their predecessors, in order to their imitation of them, and
that they might be nourished up in the laws from their infancy, and might
neither transgress them, nor have any pretense for their ignorance of them.</p>
<milestone n="27" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="205" unit="section"/><p>Our law hath also taken care of the decent burial of the dead, but
without any extravagant expenses for their funerals, and without the erection
of any illustrious monuments for them; but hath ordered that their nearest
relations should perform their obsequies; and hath showed it to be regular,
that all who pass by when any one is buried should accompany the funeral,
and join in the lamentation. It also ordains that the house and its inhabitants
should be purified after the funeral is over, that every one may thence
learn to keep at a great distance from the thoughts of being pure, if he
hath been once guilty of murder.</p>
<milestone n="28" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="206" unit="section"/><p>The law ordains also, that parents should be honored immediately
after God himself, and delivers that son who does not requite them for
the benefits he hath received from them, but is deficient on any such occasion,
to be stoned. It also says that the young men should pay due respect to
every elder, since God is the eldest of all beings. It does not give leave
to conceal any thing from our friends, because that is not true friendship
which will not commit all things to their fidelity: it also forbids the
revelation of secrets, even though an enmity arise between them. If any
judge takes bribes, his punishment is death: he that overlooks one that
offers him a petition, and this when he is able to relieve him, he is a
guilty person. What is not by any one intrusted to another ought not to
be required back again. No one is to touch another's goods. He that lends
money must not demand usury for its loan. These, and many more of the like
sort, are the rules that unite us in the bands of society one with another.</p>
<milestone n="29" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="209" unit="section"/><p>It will be also worth our while to see what equity our legislator
would have us exercise in our intercourse with strangers; for it will thence
appear that he made the best provision he possibly could, both that we
should not dissolve our own constitution, nor show any envious mind towards
those that would cultivate a friendship with us. Accordingly, our legislator
admits all those that have a mind to observe our laws so to do; and this
after a friendly manner, as esteeming that a true union which not only
extends to our own stock, but to those that would live after the same manner
with us; yet does he not allow those that come to us by accident only to
be admitted into communion with us.</p>
<milestone n="30" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="211" unit="section"/><p>However, there are other things which our legislator ordained for
us beforehand, which of necessity we ought to do in common to all men;
as to afford fire, and water, and food to such as want it; to show them
the roads; not to let any one lie unburied. He also would have us treat
those that are esteemed our enemies with moderation; for he doth not allow
us to set their country on fire, nor permit us to cut down those trees
that bear fruit; nay, further, he forbids us to spoil those that have been
slain in war. He hath also provided for such as are taken captive, that
they may not be injured, and especially that the women may not be abused.
Indeed he hath taught us gentleness and humanity so effectually, that he
hath not despised the care of brute beasts, by permitting no other than
a regular use of them, and forbidding any other; and if any of them come
to our houses, like supplicants, we are forbidden to slay them; nor may
we kill the dams, together with their young ones; but we are obliged, even
in an enemy's country, to spare and not kill those creatures that labor
for mankind. Thus hath our lawgiver contrived to teach us an equitable
conduct every way, by using us to such laws as instruct us therein; while
at the same time he hath ordained that such as break these laws should
be punished, without the allowance of any excuse whatsoever.</p>
<milestone n="31" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="215" unit="section"/><p>Now the greatest part of offenses with us are capital; as if any
one be guilty of adultery; if any one force a virgin; if any one be so
impudent as to attempt sodomy with a male; or if, upon another's making
an attempt upon him, he submits to be so used. There is also a law for
slaves of the like nature, that can never be avoided. Moreover, if any
one cheats another in measures or weights, or makes a knavish bargain and
sale, in order to cheat another; if any one steals what belongs to another,
and takes what he never deposited; all these have punishments allotted
them; not such as are met with among other nations, but more severe ones.
And as for attempts of unjust behavior towards parents, or for impiety
against God, though they be not actually accomplished, the offenders are
destroyed immediately. However, the reward for such as live exactly according
to the laws is not silver or gold; it is not a garland of olive branches
or of small age, nor any such public sign of commendation; but every good
man hath his own conscience bearing witness to himself, and by virtue of
our legislator's prophetic spirit, and of the firm security God himself
affords such a one, he believes that God hath made this grant to those
that observe these laws, even though they be obliged readily to die for
them, that they shall come into being again, and at a certain revolution
of things shall receive a better life than they had enjoyed before. Nor
would I venture to write thus at this time, were it not well known to all
by our actions that many of our people have many a time bravely resolved
to endure any sufferings, rather than speak one word against our law.</p>
<milestone n="32" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="220" unit="section"/><p>Nay, indeed, in case it had so fallen out, that our nation had not
been so thoroughly known among all men as they are, and our voluntary submission
to our laws had not been so open and manifest as it is, but that somebody
had pretended to have written these laws himself, and had read them to
the Greeks, or had pretended that he had met with men out of the limits
of the known world, that had such reverent notions of God, and had continued
a long time in the firm observance of such laws as ours, I cannot but suppose
that all men would admire them on a reflection upon the frequent changes
they had therein been themselves subject to; and this while those that
have attempted to write somewhat of the same kind for politic government,
and for laws, are accused as composing monstrous things, and are said to
have undertaken an impossible task upon them. And here I will say nothing
of those other philosophers who have undertaken any thing of this nature
in their writings. But even Plato himself, who is so admired by the Greeks
on account of that gravity in his manners, and force in his words, and
that ability he had to persuade men beyond all other philosophers, is little
better than laughed at and exposed to ridicule on that account, by those
that pretend to sagacity in political affairs; although he that shall diligently
peruse his writings will find his precepts to be somewhat gentle, and pretty
near to the customs of the generality of mankind. Nay, Plato himself confesseth
that it is not safe to publish the true notion concerning God among the
ignorant multitude. Yet do some men look upon Plato's discourses as no
better than certain idle words set off with great artifice. However, they
admire Lycurgus as the principal lawgiver, and all men celebrate <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Sparta</placeName>
for having continued in the firm observance of his laws for a very long
time. So far then we have gained, that it is to be confessed a mark of
virtue to submit to laws. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">It may not be amiss to set down here a very remarkable testimony of the
great philosopher Cicero, as to the preference of laws to philosophy:
"I will," says he, "boldly declare my opinion, though the whole
world be offended at it. I prefer this little book of the Twelve Tables
alone to all the volumes of the philosophers. I find it to be not only
of more weight, but also much more useful." Oratore.</note>
But then let such as admire this in the Lacedemonians compare that duration
of theirs with more than two thousand years which our political government
hath continued; and let them further consider, that though the Lacedemonians
did seem to observe their laws exactly while they enjoyed their liberty,
yet that when they underwent a change of their fortune, they forgot almost
all those laws; while we, having been under ten thousand changes in our
fortune by the changes that happened among the kings of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, have never
betrayed our laws under the most pressing distresses we have been in; nor
have we neglected them either out of sloth or for a livelihood. <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">we have observed our times of rest, and sorts of food allowed us [during
our distresses].</note>
if any one will consider it, the difficulties and labors laid upon us have
been greater than what appears to have been borne by the Lacedemonian fortitude,
while they neither ploughed their land, nor exercised any trades, but lived
in their own city, free from all such pains-taking, in the enjoyment of
plenty, and using such exercises as might improve their bodies, while they
made use of other men as their servants for all the necessaries of life,
and had their food prepared for them by the others; and these good and
humane actions they do for no other purpose but this, that by their actions
and their sufferings they may be able to conquer all those against whom
they make war. I need not add this, that they have not been fully able
to observe their laws; for not only a few single persons, but multitudes
of them, have in heaps neglected those laws, and have delivered themselves,
together with their arms, into the hands of their enemies.</p>
<milestone n="33" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="232" unit="section"/><p>Now as for ourselves, I venture to say that no one can tell of so
many; nay, not of more than one or two that have betrayed our laws, no,
not out of fear of death itself; I do not mean such an easy death as happens
in battles, but that which comes with bodily torments, and seems to be
the severest kind of death of all others. Now I think those that have conquered
us have put us to such deaths, not out of their hatred to us when they
had subdued us, but rather out of their desire of seeing a surprising sight,
which is this, whether there be such men in the world who believe that
no evil is to them so great as to be compelled to do or to speak any thing
contrary to their own laws. Nor ought men to wonder at us, if we are more
courageous in dying for our laws than all other men are; for other men
do not easily submit to the easier things in which we are instituted; I
mean working with our hands, and eating but little, and being contented
to eat and drink, not at random, or at every one's pleasure, or being under
inviolable rules in lying with our wives, in magnificent furniture, and
again in the observation of our times of rest; while those that can use
their swords in war, and can put their enemies to flight when they attack
them, cannot bear to submit to such laws about their way of living: whereas
our being accustomed willingly to submit to laws in these instances, renders
us fit to show our fortitude upon other occasions also.</p>
<milestone n="34" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="236" unit="section"/><p>Yet do the Lysimachi and the Molones, and some other writers, (unskillful
sophists as they are, and the deceivers of young men,) reproach us as the
vilest of all mankind. Now I have no mind to make an inquiry into the laws
of other nations; for the custom of our country is to keep our own laws,
but not to bring accusations against the laws of others. And indeed our
legislator hath expressly forbidden us to laugh at and revile those that
are esteemed gods by other people? on account of the very name of God ascribed
to them. But since our antagonists think to run us down upon the comparison
of their religion and ours, it is not possible to keep silence here, especially
while what I shall say to confute these men will not be now first said,
but hath been already said by many, and these of the highest reputation
also; for who is there among those that have been admired among the Greeks
for wisdom, who hath not greatly blamed both the most famous poets, and
most celebrated legislators, for spreading such notions originally among
the body of the people concerning the gods? such as these, that they may
be allowed to be as numerous as they have a mind to have them; that they
are begotten one by another, and that after all the kinds of generation
you can imagine. They also distinguish them in their places and ways of
living as they would distinguish several sorts of animals; as some to be
under the earth; as some to be in the sea; and the ancientest of them all
to be bound in hell; and for those to whom they have allotted heaven, they
have set over them one, who in title is their father, but in his actions
a tyrant and a lord; whence it came to pass that his wife, and brother,
and daughter (which daughter he brought forth from his own head) made a
conspiracy against him to seize upon him and confine hint, as he had himself
seized upon and confined his own father before.</p>
<milestone n="35" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="242" unit="section"/><p>And justly have the wisest men thought these notions deserved severe
rebukes; they also laugh at them for determining that we ought to believe
some of the gods to be beardless and young, and others of them to be old,
and to have beards accordingly; that some are set to trades; that one god
is a smith, and another goddess is a weaver; that one god is a warrior,
and fights with men; that some of them are harpers, or delight in archery;
and besides, that mutual seditions arise among them, and that they quarrel
about men, and this so far, that they not only lay hands upon one another,
but that they are wounded by men, and lament, and take on for such their
afflictions. But what is the grossest of all in point of lasciviousness,
are those unbounded lusts ascribed to almost all of them, and their amours;
which how can it be other than a most absurd supposal, especially when
it reaches to the male gods, and to the female goddesses also? Moreover,
the chief of all their gods, and their first father himself, overlooks
those goddesses whom he hath deluded and begotten with child, and suffers
them to be kept in prison, or drowned in the sea. He is also so bound up
by fate, that he cannot save his own offspring, nor can he bear their deaths
without shedding of tears. These are fine things indeed! as are the rest
that follow. Adulteries truly are so impudently looked on in heaven by
the gods, that some of them have confessed they envied those that were
found in the very act. And why should they not do so, when the eldest of
them, who is their king also, hath not been able to restrain himself in
the violence of his lust, from lying with his wife, so long as they might
get into their bedchamber? Now some of the gods are servants to men, and
will sometimes be builders for a reward, and sometimes will be shepherds;
while others of them, like malefactors, are bound in a prison of brass.
And what sober person is there who would not be provoked at such stories,
and rebuke those that forged them, and condemn the great silliness of those
that admit them for true? Nay, others there are that have advanced a certain
timorousness and fear, as also madness and fraud, and any other of the
vilest passions, into the nature and form of gods, and have persuaded whole
cities to offer sacrifices to the better sort of them; on which account
they have been absolutely forced to esteem some gods as the givers of good
things, and to call others of them averters of evil. They also endeavor
to move them, as they would the vilest of men, by gifts and presents, as
looking for nothing else than to receive some great mischief from them,
unless they pay them such wages.</p>
<milestone n="36" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="250" unit="section"/><p>Wherefore it deserves our inquiry what should be the occasion of
this unjust management, and of these scandals about the Deity. And truly
I suppose it to be derived from the imperfect knowledge the heathen legislators
had at first of the true nature of God; nor did they explain to the people
even so far as they did comprehend of it: nor did they compose the other
parts of their political settlements according to it, but omitted it as
a thing of very little consequence, and gave leave both to the poets to
introduce what gods they pleased, and those subject to all sorts of passions,
and to the orators to procure political decrees from the people for the
admission of such foreign gods as they thought proper. The painters also,
and statuaries of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, had herein great power, as each of them could
contrive a shape [proper for a god]; the one to be formed out of clay,
and the other by making a bare picture of such a one. But those workmen
that were principally admired, had the use of ivory and of gold as the
constant materials for their new statues [whereby it comes to pass that
some temples are quite deserted, while others are in great esteem, and
adorned with all the rites of all kinds of purification]. Besides this,
the first gods, who have long flourished in the honors done them, are now
grown old [while those that flourished after them are come in their room
as a second rank, that I may speak the most honorably of them I can]: nay,
certain other gods there are who are newly introduced, and newly worshipped
[as we, by way of digression, have said already, and yet have left their
places of worship desolate]; and for their temples, some of them are already
left desolate, and others are built anew, according to the pleasure of
men; whereas they ought to have their opinion about God, and that worship
which is due to him, always and immutably the same.</p>
<milestone n="37" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="255" unit="section"/><p>But now, this Apollonius Molo was one of these foolish and proud
men. However, nothing that I have said was unknown to those that were real
philosophers among the Greeks, nor were they unacquainted with those frigid
pretensions of allegories [which had been alleged for such things]; on
which account they justly despised them, but have still agreed with us
as to the true and becoming notions of God; whence it was that Plato would
not have political settlements admit to of any one of the other poets,
and dismisses even Homer himself, with a garland on his head, and with
ointment poured upon him, and this because he should not destroy the right
notions of God with his fables. Nay, Plato principally imitated our legislator
in this point, that he enjoined his citizens to have he main regard to
this precept, "That every one of them should learn their laws accurately."
He also ordained, that they should not admit of foreigners intermixing
with their own people at random; and provided that the commonwealth should
keep itself pure, and consist of such only as persevered in their own laws.
Apollonius Molo did no way consider this, when he made it one branch of
his accusation against us, that we do not admit of such as have different
notions about God, nor will we have fellowship with those that choose to
observe a way of living different from ourselves, yet is not this method
peculiar to us, but common to all other men; not among the ordinary Grecians
only, but among such of those Grecians as are of the greatest reputation
among them. Moreover, the Lacedemonians continued in their way of expelling
foreigners, and would not indeed give leave to their own people to travel
abroad, as suspecting that those two things would introduce a dissolution
of their own laws: and perhaps there may be some reason to blame the rigid
severity of the Lacedemonians, for they bestowed the privilege of their
city on no foreigners, nor indeed would give leave to them to stay among
them; whereas we, though we do not think fit to imitate other institutions,
yet do we willingly admit of those that desire to partake of ours, which,
I think, I may reckon to be a plain indication of our humanity, and at
the same time of our magnanimity also.</p>
<milestone n="38" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="262" unit="section"/><p>But I shall say no more of the Lacedemonians. As for the Athenians,
who glory in having made their city to be common to all men, what their
behavior was Apollonius did not know, while they punished those that did
but speak one word contrary to the laws about the gods, without any mercy;
for on what other account was it that Socrates was put to death by them?
For certainly he neither betrayed their city to its enemies, nor was he
guilty of any sacrilege with regard to any of their temples; but it was
on this account, that he swore certain new oaths <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">See what those novel oaths were in Dr. Hudson's note, viz. to swear by
an oak, by a goat, and by a dog, as also by a gander, as say Philostratus
and others. This swearing strange oaths was also forbidden by the Tyrians,
B. I. sect. 22, as Spanheim here notes.</note>
and that he affirmed either in earnest, or, as some say, only in jest,
that a certain demon used to make signs to him [what he should not do].
For these reasons he was condemned to drink poison, and kill himself. His
accuser also complained that he corrupted the young men, by inducing them
to despise the political settlement and laws of their city: and thus was
Socrates, the citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, punished. There was also Anaxagoras, who,
although he was of Clazomente, was within a few suffrages of being condemned
to die, because he said the sun, which the Athenians thought to be a god,
was a ball of fire. They also made this public proclamation," That
they would give a talent to any one who would kill Diagoras of <placeName key="tgn,7010922">Melos</placeName>,"
because it was reported of him that he laughed at their mysteries. Protagoras
also, who was thought to have written somewhat that was not owned for truth
by the Athenians about the gods, had been seized upon, and put to death,
if he had not fled away immediately. Nor need we at all wonder that they
thus treated such considerable men, when they did not spare even women
also; for they very lately slew a certain priestess, because she was accused
by somebody that she initiated people into the worship of strange gods,
it having been forbidden so to do by one of their laws; and a capital punishment
had been decreed to such as introduced a strange god; it being manifest,
that they who make use of such a law do not believe those of other nations
to be really gods, otherwise they had not envied themselves the advantage
of more gods than they already had. And this was the happy administration
of the affairs of the Athenians! Now as to the Scythians, they take a pleasure
in killing men, and differ but little from brute beasts; yet do they think
it reasonable to have their institutions observed. They also slew Anacharsis,
a person greatly admired for his wisdom among the Greeks, when he returned
to them, because he appeared to come fraught with Grecian customs. One
may also find many to have been punished among the Persians, on the very
same account. And to be sure Apollonius was greatly pleased with the laws
of the Persians, and was an admirer of them, because the Greeks enjoyed
the advantage of their courage, and had the very same opinion about the
gods which they had. This last was exemplified in the temples which they
burnt, and their courage in coming, and almost entirely enslaving the Grecians.
However, Apollonius has imitated all the Persian institutions, and that
by his offering violence to other men's wives, and gelding his own sons.
Now, with us, it is a capital crime, if any one does thus abuse even a
brute beast; and as for us, neither hath the fear of our governors, nor
a desire of following what other nations have in so great esteem, been
able to withdraw us from our own laws; nor have we exerted our courage
in raising up wars to increase our wealth, but only for the observation
of our laws; and when we with patience bear other losses, yet when any
persons would compel us to break our laws, then it is that we choose to
go to war, though it be beyond our ability to pursue it, and bear the greatest
calamities to the last with much fortitude. And, indeed, what reason can
there be why we should desire to imitate the laws of other nations, while
we see they are not observed by their own legislators <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Why Josephus here should blame some heathen legislators, when they allowed
so easy a composition for simple fornication, as an obligation to marry
the virgin that was corrupted, is hard to say, seeing he had himself truly
informed us that it was a law of the Jews, Antiq. B. IV. ch. 8. sect. 23,
as it is the law of Christianity also: see Horeb Covenant, p. 61. I am
almost ready to suspect that, for, we should here read, and that corrupting
wedlock, or other men's wives, is the crime for which these heathens wickedly
allowed this composition in money.</note>
And why do not the Lacedemonians think of abolishing that form of their
government which suffers them not to associate with any others, as well
as their contempt of matrimony? And why do not the Eleans and Thebans abolish
that unnatural and impudent lust, which makes them lie with males? For
they will not show a sufficient sign of their repentance of what they of
old thought to be very excellent, and very advantageous in their practices,
unless they entirely avoid all such actions for the time to come: nay,
such things are inserted into the body of their laws, and had once such
a power among the Greeks, that they ascribed these sodomitical practices
to the gods themselves, as a part of their good character; and indeed it
was according to the same manner that the gods married their own sisters.
This the Greeks contrived as an apology for their own absurd and unnatural
pleasures.</p>
<milestone n="39" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="276" unit="section"/><p>I omit to speak concerning punishments, and how many ways of escaping
them the greatest part of the legislators have afforded malefactors, by
ordaining that, for adulteries, fines in money should be allowed, and for
corrupting <note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Or "for corrupting other men's wives the same allowance."</note>
[virgins] they need only marry them as also what excuses they may have
in denying the facts, if any one attempts to inquire into them; for amongst
most other nations it is a studied art how men may transgress their laws;
but no such thing is permitted amongst us; for though we be deprived of
our wealth, of our cities, or of the other advantages we have, our law
continues immortal; nor can any Jew go so far from his own country, nor
be so aftrighted at the severest lord, as not to be more aftrighted at
the law than at him. If, therefore, this be the disposition we are under,
with regard to the excellency of our laws, let our enemies make us this
concession, that our laws are most excellent; and if still they imagine,
that though we so firmly adhere to them, yet are they bad laws notwithstanding,
what penalties then do they deserve to undergo who do not observe their
own laws, which they esteem so far superior to them? Whereas, therefore,
length of time is esteemed to be the truest touchstone in all cases, I
would make that a testimonial of the excellency of our laws, and of that
belief thereby delivered to us concerning God. For as there hath been a
very long time for this comparison, if any one will but compare its duration
with the duration of the laws made by other legislators, he will find our
legislator to have been the ancientest of them all.</p>
<milestone n="40" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="280" unit="section"/><p>We have already demonstrated that our laws have been such as have
always inspired admiration and imitation into all other men; nay, the earliest
Grecian philosophers, though in appearance they observed the laws of their
own countries, yet did they, in their actions, and their philosophic doctrines,
follow our legislator, and instructed men to live sparingly, and to have
friendly communication one with another. Nay, further, the multitude of
mankind itself have had a great inclination of a long time to follow our
religious observances; for there is not any city of the Grecians, nor any
of the barbarians, nor any nation whatsoever, whither our custom of resting
on the seventh day hath not come, and by which our fasts and lighting up
lamps, and many of our prohibitions as to our food, are not observed; they
also endeavor to imitate our mutual concord with one another, and the charitable
distribution of our goods, and our diligence in our trades, and our fortitude
in undergoing the distresses we are in, on account of our laws; and, what
is here matter of the greatest admiration, our law hath no bait of pleasure
to allure men to it, but it prevails by its own force; and as God himself
pervades all the world, so hath our law passed through all the world also.
So that if any one will but reflect on his own country, and his own family,
he will have reason to give credit to what I say. It is therefore but just,
either to condemn all mankind of indulging a wicked disposition, when they
have been so desirous of imitating laws that are to them foreign and evil
in themselves, rather than following laws of their own that are of a better
character, or else our accusers must leave off their spite against us.
Nor are we guilty of any envious behavior towards them, when we honor our
own legislator, and believe what he, by his prophetic authority, hath taught
us concerning God. For though we should not be able ourselves to understand
the excellency of our own laws, yet would the great multitude of those
that desire to imitate them, justify us, in greatly valuing ourselves upon
them.</p>
<milestone n="41" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="287" unit="section"/><p>But as for the [distinct] political laws by which we are governed,
I have delivered them accurately in my books of Antiquities; and have only
mentioned them now, so far as was necessary to my present purpose, without
proposing to myself either to blame the laws of other nations, or to make
an encomium upon our own; but in order to convict those that have written
about us unjustly, and in an impudent affectation of disguising the truth.
And now I think I have sufficiently completed what I proposed in writing
these books. For whereas our accusers have pretended that our nation are
a people of very late original, I have demonstrated that they are exceeding
ancient; for I have produced as witnesses thereto many ancient writers,
who have made mention of us in their books, while they had said that no
such writer had so done. Moreover, they had said that we were sprung from
the Egyptians, while I have proved that we came from another country into
<placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>: while they had told lies of us, as if we were expelled thence on
account of diseases on our bodies, it has appeared, on the contrary, that
we returned to our country by our own choice, and with sound and strong
bodies. Those accusers reproached our legislator as a vile fellow; whereas
God in old time bare witness to his virtuous conduct; and since that testimony
of God, time itself hath been discovered to have borne witness to the same
thing.</p>
<milestone n="42" unit="Whiston section"/><milestone n="291" unit="section"/><p>As to the laws themselves, more words are unnecessary, for they
are visible in their own nature, and appear to teach not impiety, but the
truest piety in the world. They do not make men hate one another, but encourage
people to communicate what they have to one another freely; they are enemies
to injustice, they take care of righteousness, they banish idleness and
expensive living, and instruct men to be content with what they have, and
to be laborious in their calling; they forbid men to make war from a desire
of getting more, but make men courageous in defending the laws; they are
inexorable in punishing malefactors; they admit no sophistry of words,
but are always established by actions themselves, which actions we ever
propose as surer demonstrations than what is contained in writing only:
on which account I am so bold as to say that we are become the teachers
of other men, in the greatest number of things, and those of the most excellent
nature only; for what is more excellent than inviolable piety? what is
more just than submission to laws? and what is more advantageous than mutual
love and concord? and this so far that we are to be neither divided by
calamities, nor to become injurious and seditious in prosperity; but to
contemn death when we are in war, and in peace to apply ourselves to our
mechanical occupations, or to our tillage of the ground; while we in all
things and all ways are satisfied that God is the inspector and governor
of our actions. If these precepts had either been written at first, or
more exactly kept by any others before us, we should have owed them thanks
as disciples owe to their masters; but if it be visible that we have made
use of them more than any other men, and if we have demonstrated that the
original invention of them is our own, let the Apions, and the Molons,
with all the rest of those that delight in lies and reproaches, stand confuted;
but let this and the foregoing book be dedicated to thee, Epaphroditus,
who art so great a lover of truth, and by thy means to those that have
been in like manner desirous to be acquainted with the affairs of our nation.</p>
</div1>
</body></text></TEI.2>
