<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Epidemics, introduction</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb id="p.141"/><p/>
			<div1 type="chapter" n="intro"><head>INTRODUCTION</head>
				<p>T<hi rend="sc">HESE</hi> two books manifestly form one work, and
					that the most remarkable product of Greek science.</p>
				<p>Pretensions to literary form it has none, yet no
					Greek writer, with the possible exception of Thucy-dides,
					has used language with better effect. Often
					ungrammatical, sometimes a series of disconnected
					words, the narrative is always to the point, and
					always conveys the impression that the writer's sole
					object is to express observed facts in the fittest and
					shortest way.</p>
				<p>The composition shows violent dislocations. There
					come first two "constitutions,"<note>"Constitution" is the traditional translation of <foreign lang="greek">KATA/S1TAS1IS2</foreign>,
						climatic conditions of such a marked type as to give
						a distinguishing character to a period of time. The word is
						also used of diseases, and so on, to denote a fixed type prevalent
						at any particular time.</note> then two short
					paragraphs on the duty of the physician and on
					certain symptoms respectively, then another constitution,
					then a few paragraphs on fevers, then
					fourteen clinical histories. The third book begins
					with twelve more histories, which are followed by
					a fourth constitution, at the end of which is another
					disconnected paragraph, and the book closes with
					sixteen histories.</p>
				<p>Dislocations due to the ancient methods of copying
					manuscripts are common enough in classical authors,
					but startling changes like the above are not such as</p>
				<pb id="p.142"/>
				<p>can be ascribed to the vagaries or the carelessness of
					scribes. Combined with the broken grammar they
					seem to point to the work having never been prepared
					for publication. The writer probably jotted down
					his remarks as a series of notes in an order which
					happened to suggest itself, and never went on to
					edit them. Several of the shorter "interpolations"
					would have been in a modern book footnotes or
					appendices.</p>
				<p>This theory is supported by the fact that a
					very great number of the histories have no connection
					at all with the constitutions. The first
					three constitutions refer to Thasos ; the place of
					the fourth is unnamed. The medical cases belong
					to Thasos, Larisa, Abdera, Cyzicus, and Meliboea,
					while many others have no locality attached to
					them. The nature, too, of the diseases bears no
					great likeness to those of the constitutions. They
					are all "acute," some exhibit abnormal symptoms
					and some are ordinary cases of remittent malaria.
					They illustrate <hi rend="ital">Prognostic</hi> far better than they do
					the constitutions. "What do symptoms portend ?"
					is the subject of <hi rend="ital">Prognostic</hi>, and the clinical histories
					give the <hi rend="ital">data</hi> from which many of its generalizations
					may well have been framed. On the whole, it is
					probable that <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> was never published by its
					author.</p>
				<p>The subject matter of the <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi>, including the
					five books universally attributed to authors other
					than Hippocrates, namely, II and IV, V, VI, VII,
					present several interesting problems. For the
					present I will confine myself to I and III.</p>
				<p>What are the diseases described in the <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> ?
					This question has interested physicians for centuries,</p>
				<pb id="p.143"/>
				<p>and each medical reader will enjoy the task of
					diagnosing them for himself. Several cases are
					difficult, but the section on Hippocratic diseases in
					the General Introduction should enable even a layman
					to identify many. Perhaps the most fascinating
					problem is whether the constitution in Book III
					refers to the plague year of Thucydides II.</p>
				<p>Another interesting point is the <hi rend="ital">client&eacute;le</hi> of the
					writer and the scenes of his practice.<note>It is worth noticing that Greek physicians, like the
						Sophists, often passed from city to city, staying a longer or
						shorter period according to the demand for their services.
						It was for such <foreign lang="greek">PERIODEUTAI/</foreign> that <hi rend="ital">Airs Waters Places</hi> was
						written, to enable them to know what diseases were likely
						to occur in a city they had never visited before.</note> The latter
					have already been referred to ; the names of the
					patients, and their position in life, are worth a
					moment's consideration.<note>See Littr&eacute;, VIII. vii-xxix, where Meineke is considered.</note> None of the clinical
					histories has a date, but most give the name and
					address of the sick person. Occasionally the name
					is given without the address, or the address is given
					without the name. In a few instances at the end
					of Book III the town is named but neither the
					patient nor his address is specified. In two cases
					(I, case 12, and III, case 4, of second series) name,
					address and locality are all omitted. The patients
					are sometimes householders, sometimes members of
					their families, sometimes slaves. Several seem to
					have been lodgers.<note>See on these points Littr&eacute;, X. pp. xxix-xxxii, where
						Rossignol's views are given and criticised. There seem to
						have been large boarding-houses in some places.</note></p>
				<p>The variety in the descriptions of patients seems
					to show that the writer attached no importance to
					them, but simply wrote in his note-book enough to</p>
				<pb id="p.144"/>
				<p>enable him to identify a patient for himself. In
					fact he rarely appears to be writing for a public ;
					in the clinical histories especially one feels that the
					only object is private information.</p>
				<p>If the clinical histories are rough notes of this
					character it becomes plain why they vary in fulness
					of detail. The plan generally adopted is to give a
					daily bulletin, or at least to notice the critical days,
					but if the patient was not visited every day and
					the attendants did not report anything striking,
					gaps would occur such as we actually do find. An
					editor writing for a public would either have made
					these gaps less obvious or else have explained them.</p>
				<p>But the most striking feature of this work is its
					devotion to truth. The constitutions are strictly
					limited to descriptions of the weather which preceded
					or accompanied certain epidemics ; the clinical
					histories are confined to the march of diseases to a
					favourable or a fatal issue. Nothing irrelevant is
					mentioned ; everything relevant is included.</p>
				<p>Of the forty-two cases, twenty-five end in death,
					very nearly 60 per cent. The writer's aim is not to
					show how to cure--treatment is very rarely mentioned--but
					to discover the sequences of symptoms, to set
					down the successes and failures of Nature in her
					efforts to expel the disease. The physician is acting,
					not <hi rend="ital">qua</hi> physician but <hi rend="ital">qua</hi> scientist ; he has laid aside
					the part of healer to be for a time a spectator looking
					down on the arena, exercising that <foreign lang="greek">QEWRI/A</foreign> which a
					Greek held to be the highest human activity.</p>
				<p><hi rend="center">MSS. <hi rend="sc">AND</hi> E<hi rend="sc">DITIONS</hi></hi></p>
				<p>The chief MSS. for <hi rend="ital">Epidemics I.</hi> are A and V,
					and for <hi rend="ital">Epidemics III.</hi>, V and D, supplemented for</p>
				<pb id="p.145"/>
				<p>both books by the interesting commentaries of
					Galen.</p>
				<p>Editions were common in the sixteenth, seven-teenth,
					and eighteenth centuries,<note>See Littr&eacute;, II. 593-596.</note> but none are of
					outstanding merit. There is an English translation
					of no merit by Samuel Farr (London, 1780), and the
					books are included in Adams' first volume.</p>
				<p><hi rend="center">A<hi rend="sc">DDITIONAL</hi> N<hi rend="sc">OTES</hi></hi></p>
				<p>1. The word <foreign lang="greek">O)CU/S2</foreign>, "acute," "sharp," is applied to fever,
					and to such diseases (pleurisy, pneumonia, remittent
					malaria, etc., <hi rend="ital">Regimen in Acute Diseases</hi>, v) as are accompanied
					by high fever. The Hippocratic doctrines of crisis,
					coction, etc., apply chiefly to acute diseases, but not to
					them only, as the common cold (<hi rend="ital">Ancient Medicine</hi>, xviii)
					shows coction.</p>
				<p>2. The preposition <foreign lang="greek">PARA/</foreign>, meaning "at the house of," seems
					to be used indifferently with acc., gen., or dat. There are
					probably differences, but I cannot detect them.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>