<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Art of Reading Latin:  How To Teach It</title>
<author>William Gardner Hale</author>
&responsibility;
</titleStmt>
<extent>About 120Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title>The Art of Reading Latin:  How To Teach It.  An address delivered 
before the associated academic principals of the State of New York, 
December 28, 1886.</title>
<author>William Gardner Hale, professor of Latin in Cornell University</author>
<date>1887</date>
<publisher>Ginn and Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
  <state n="chunk" unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change><date>15-Aug-01</date>
<respStmt><name>Anne Mahoney</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
<item>
$Log: hale.art.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-12-08 20:46:34  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status.  renamed terence files to follow the abbreviations and split up minora_lat.xml into separate files

Revision 1.3  2009/07/10 21:51:17  student
fixing citations - ad

Revision 1.2  2005/08/16 17:18:03  packel
ARRGGH item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:04:09  packel
Converted to XML

Revision 1.7  2003/10/10 18:32:34  amahoney
fix a couple of typos

Revision 1.6  2003/07/01 22:18:11  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.5  2003/02/04 21:11:45  lcerrato
fixed typo section 5 book you never say to book you never saw

Revision 1.4  2003/02/04 21:10:54  lcerrato
fixed typo section 8 object or verb to object of verb

Revision 1.3  2002/03/11 22:19:23  amahoney
tweak a few things to improve display

Revision 1.2  2002/03/11 21:38:06  amahoney
finish basic markup

Revision 1.1  2002/03/01 22:38:53  amahoney
new text:  needs to be here, some day

</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text lang="en">
<body>

<div1 type="section" n="1">
<head>Preface</head>

<p>The method of teaching
herein advocated started, many years ago, from a desire to know Latin literature,
and an impatience with the actual amount of reading power attained by a
college course.  At the outset there existed a conviction that the
modern mind could not be so degenerate as to be incapable of reading Latin
as the Romans read it, that is to say, in the Roman order, in the Roman
medium, and at a rate of speed which would not be intolerably slow in the
reading of a modern tongue.  The nature of the aim dictated the method
to be employed;  and the employment of the method proved the soundness
of the original conviction.
</p>
<p>The writer has for some years intended to publish an account of this
method, as it has shaped itself in practical experience with successive
classes.  First, however, he desired to present it orally before a
number of gatherings of teachers.  As a beginning, accordingly, the
address with which the pamphlet opens was read before the Holiday Conference
of the Associated Academic Principals of the State of New York, held in
Syracuse in December last.  The interest with which the paper was
received was so kindly, and the requests that it be published without further
delay were so pressing, that it seemed best not to hold to the former intention.
</p>
<p>The pamphlet has not the form which was first intended, namely, that
of plain exposition;  for in spite of the iteration of the personal
pronoun, the form of direct appeal and explanation natural to an address
proved to have its advantages.  It has been necessary, however, to
add to the address a considerable supplement.
</p>
<p>Though no explicit suggestions will be found in regard to the teaching
of Greek, the substance of the method of course applies alike to either
language.
</p>
<p>I am under a debt to many of my students of recent years, whose support
of the method, though it was taken up by them under the sore necessity
of an entire revolution of confirmed mental habits, has supplied me with
the confidence that comes from concrete results.  But I am under especial
obligations to my sister, Miss Gertrude Elisabeth Hale, both for suggestions
made earlier as a result of her own experience (the device mentioned on
page 13 originated, so far as my own case goes, with her) and for a searching
criticism of the proof of the present pamphlet, from the point of view
of a preparatory teacher.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="2">
<p>The attacks which
have been made of late upon the study of Greek and to some extent upon
the study of Latin have had at their backs the conviction that the results
obtained are very much out of proportion to the years of labor spent upon
these languages by the schoolboy and the college student.  The danger
which threatens classical study to-day in this country is due in large
part to the fact that this conviction is a sound one.  If the case
were different, if the average college graduate were really able to read
ordinary Greek and Latin with speed and relish, the whole matter would
be on a very different footing from that on which it now lamely stands.
</p>
<p>To learn to read Greek and Latin with speed and relish, and then, if
one's tastes turn towards literature or art of any kind, to proceed to
do so;  to come to know familiarly and lovingly that great factor
in the record of the thinking and feeling of the human race, the literatures
of Greece and Rome, &mdash; that is an aim which we should all set before our
students.  But, speaking generally, our students, yours and mine,
do not come to love those literatures.  Perhaps they tolerate them,
perhaps they respect them.  But to love them and to make them a substantial
part of the intellectual life, &mdash; that is a thing which many a student,
fitted therefor by natural taste and ability, fails to accomplish, and
never so much as knows his loss.  This seems to me, looking at the
long years of study given to Greek and Latin, and the great emphasis put
upon them in the requirements for admission to our colleges, a very sad
business.
</p>
<p>Now the blame of it all must be divided among three parties, &mdash; the Greek
and Latin languages themselves, the teachers in the preparatory schools,
and the teachers in the universities.  The first of these guilty parties
are out of our reach.  They are difficult languages;  but difficult
languages they must remain.  That leaves the practical whole of the
responsibility to be divided between the teachers in the preparatory schools
and the teachers in the universities, or, to take concrete examples, for
the purpose of our conference, between you and me.
</p>
<p>Which of us is the more to blame, I will not attempt to say.  But
so much I will say, and from my sure observation:  that the influence
upon the formation of intellectual character by the teachers who prepare
young men for college is nearly ineffaceable.  The boy who comes to
college with a thinking habit is capable of learning to read Latin (for
I must now confine myself to that topic, though the whole substance of
what I have to say applies with equal force to the teaching of Greek) with
ease and speed;  the boy who comes without the habit has faults that
a college course can rarely cure.  That the boy should be taught to
think before he comes to college is, then, from the point of view of the
study of Latin, the one indispensable thing.  That it is so from every
other point of view as well, makes our case so much the stronger.
</p>
<p>But one thing more is also indispensable sooner or later for a high
success (and there is in Latin but one success), namely, that the method
which the boy is taught to use in his thinking be the right one, &mdash; the
result of the most careful observation of the practical difficulties to
be overcome, and the most careful study of the best ways of overcoming
them.
</p>
<p>As we group these difficulties, placing them in the order in which they
would be felt by a beginner, we find them to be: &mdash;
<list type="simple">
<label>1.</label> <item>The vocabulary</item>
<label>2.</label> <item>The system of inflections.</item>
<label>3.</label> <item>The elaborate use of this system
of inflections to express meaning, in place of our simpler modern methods
of using prepositions, auxiliaries, and the like:  or, in a single
word, <emph>syntax</emph>.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>I suppose the beginner would think that these three difficulties covered
the whole ground, and that if he had his vocabulary and his inflections
secured, and understood what is called syntax, he could then read Latin
with great ease.  But he would be very wrong.  The most formidable
difficulty has not been mentioned.  The Latin sentence is constructed
upon a plan entirely different from that of the English sentence. 
Until that plan is just as familiar to the student as the English plan,
until, for page after page, he takes in ideas as readily and naturally
on the one plan as on the other, until, in short, a single steady reading
of the sentence carries his mind through the very same development of thought
that took place in the mind of the writer, he cannot read Latin otherwise
than slowly and painfully.  So, then, an absolutely essential thing
to a man who wants to read Latin is: &mdash;
<list type="simple">
<label>4.</label> <item>A perfect working familiarity with the Latin ways of constructing sentences.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Now we teach the first three things more or less effectively, &mdash; vocabulary,
inflection, syntax.  Do we teach the last?

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="3">
<p>I turn to the "First Latin Books," in order to find what is said to
students at that most critical period in their study of the language, &mdash;
the beginning.  I remember well how I was taught at Phillips Exeter
Academy &mdash; of revered memory &mdash; to attack a Latin sentence.  "First
find your verb, and translate it," said my teacher.  "Then find your
subject, and translate it.  Then find the modifiers of the subject,
then the modifiers of the verb,"  etc., etc.  Well, I had got
more than four years beyond Exeter before I learned to read Latin with
any feeling but that it was a singularly circuitous and perverted way of
expressing ideas, which I could not expect to grasp until I had reformed
my author's sentences and reduced them to English.  Since my time,
however, better ways may have come into vogue.  So I turn to the books
of two scholarly gentlemen of my acquaintance, &mdash; practical teachers, too,
&mdash; namely, Mr. Comstock, of Phillips Andover Academy, and Dr. Leighton,
of the Brooklyn Latin School.   On page 233 of Mr. Comstock's
"First Latin Book," and pages 211 and 212 of Dr. Leighton's "First Steps
in Latin," I find distinct rules, essentially the same, for the operation
in question.  The former begin as follows: &mdash;

<quote lang="en"><p>a. In every simple sentence, find and translate
<list type="simple"><item>(1) The subject.</item>
<item>(2) The predicate.</item>
</list></p>
</quote>
</p>
<p>Here is a new departure, an entire revolution since my day.  I
was taught to find first the <emph>predicate</emph>.  A change so radical,
a method so exactly the opposite of the old one, ought to lead to results
the opposite of the old;  namely, to the power to read Latin easily
instead of with difficulty.  So, with a cheerful heart, I take up
a simple sentence in the fourth oration against Catiline, <bibl n="Cic. Catil. 4.3.5">3.5</bibl>, and try
my new method.
</p>
<p><foreign lang="la">Haec omnia indices detulerunt</foreign>.  I look for my subject. 
Fortunately, it lies right at hand.  It is <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign>, nom. pl. 
Next I translate it, <gloss rend="ital">these</gloss>;  or, since it is neuter, <gloss rend="ital">these
things</gloss>.  Then I proceed to find the verb, which, again is obvious,
viz., <foreign lang="la">detulerunt</foreign>, in 3d person pl., agreeing with the subject <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign>. 
Perhaps I have caught from somewhere the happy idea of not looking words
up in the dictionary until I have tried my hand at them.  So, very
properly, I set out with the simplest meaning I can think of, viz., <gloss rend="ital">brought</gloss>. 
Now I am well started:  <gloss rend="ital">These things brought</gloss>.  Next I
look for the modifiers of the subject, and find <foreign lang="la">omnia</foreign>.  I build
it on, and have now "all these things" for my subject, &mdash; <gloss rend="ital">all these things
brought</gloss>.  Next I look for the modifiers of the predicate, and
I find <foreign lang="la">indices</foreign>, <gloss rend="ital">witnesses</gloss>, acc. pl., object of the verb. 
Everything is straight.  <gloss rend="ital">All these things brought the witnesses</gloss>. 
I pass on, and when I come to the class-room, and the teacher calls on
me, I read out, <gloss rend="ital">All these things brought the witnesses</gloss>, prepared
to parse it to the last word, &mdash; only to be told that I am <emph>entirely
wrong</emph>.<note anchored="yes">If the example chosen is not a happy one, any
teacher of young pupils &mdash; any college teacher even, I fear &mdash; could, with
a few days' watching of a class, come up on examples that will satisfy
him that the habitual method, no matter how high the teacher's aims, tends
to bring about a laxity of scrutiny which constantly leads into blunders
as bad as the example here given.</note> 
</p>
<p>Now, a Roman boy of my age, and much less clever than I, if he could
have smuggled himself into the senate that day, would have understood what
those four words meant the instant Cicero uttered the last of them, <foreign lang="la">detulerunt</foreign>. 
What is the difference between us?  Each of us, he and I, knew substantially
the meaning of each word, each of us could inflect, each of us knew all
the syntax required.  Yet I missed the idea, while he got it. 
Wherein did he beat me?  Why, simply here:  I, following the
direction of my teachers, first found my subject, and settled on <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign>. 
The Roman boy did not know whether <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign> was subject or object. 
He only knew it as <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign>.  I knew that <foreign lang="la">detulerunt</foreign> was
the verb, and so did he when it arrived.  I knew that <foreign lang="la">omnia</foreign>
agreed with the subject <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign>, while he only surmised that it belonged
with <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign>, whatever that might prove to be.  I knew that <foreign lang="la">indices</foreign>
was the object, while he only felt that <foreign lang="la">indices</foreign> was subject or object,
and that it was the opposite of <foreign lang="la">haec omnia</foreign> (apposition being out
of the question), being object if that should turn out to be subject, and
subject if that should turn out to be object.  Then he heard <foreign lang="la">detulerunt</foreign>,
and with that word everything dropped into place as simply as, in Milton's
sentence following,

<cit><quote lang="en"><lg type="iambic-pentameter"><l part="F">&hellip; the moon, whose orb</l>
<l>Through optic glass the Tuscan artist views,</l></lg></quote><bibl></bibl></cit>

the last word resolves our momentary suspense in regard to the relation
of orb and artist;  which relation would have been precisely reversed,
had we found such a word, e.g., as "glads."
</p>
<p>Let us try the method further.  Mr. Comstock goes on (the italics
are in part my own): &mdash;
<list type="simple"><label>b.</label><item>In a Compound Sentence translate
each principal clause as though it were a Simple Sentence.  If there
are Subordinate Clauses, translate them <emph>in the order of their importance</emph>. 
A Subordinate or Dependent Clause is one which, just as in English, limits
some part of the Principal Clause (as described in 42, page 12). 
A clause introduced by a Latin word meaning <gloss>if, who, which, because,
since, although, when, after, while</gloss>, etc., is Dependent, and should
be left until the meaning of the Principal Clause has been obtained.</item>

<label>c.</label><item>In a Complex Sentence, first
translate the Principal Clause as a Simple Sentence;  then translate
the Dependent Clauses according to directions given above (b).</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>But what is the order of their importance, and how am I to start? 
With the connective, I presume.  We will suppose it to be <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>. 
But how shall I translate it?  There are some half-dozen or more "meanings": 
<gloss>in order to, so that, when, as, considering, although</gloss>.  Which
does it have here?  I cannot tell.  <emph>No
more could a Roman</emph>.  But the difference is, that a Roman
did not want to tell which one of its forces <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> had here, but waited
until something in the rest of the sentence, perhaps twenty, perhaps fifty,
words away, informed him;  while I am bidden, so to speak, to toss
up a cent, and start off upon a meaning, with the odds heavily against
me;  possibly to find my mistake and go back and correct it, more
probably to add error on error in order to "make sense," and so to get
the whole thing into a hopeless muddle.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="4">
<p>Now, <emph>all this is wrong</emph>.  It is a frightful
source of confusion to prowl about here and there in the sentence in a
self-blinded way that would seem pathetic to a Roman, looking at things
without the side-lights afforded to him by the order;  and, further,
it is a frightful waste of time.  Take a sentence such as often occurs,
e.g., the opening of the third oration against Catiline, delivered before
the people.  Imagine, now, two scenes:  on the one hand the Roman
Forum, on <date value="-63-12-03">Dec. 3, 63 BC</date>, with a mass of men and boys listening to Cicero
as he tells the story of the entangling of the conspirators remaining in
Rome;  on the other, a modern schoolroom, say in the Syracuse High
School (though I hope I am about to slander Dr. Bacon), <date value="1886-12-03">Dec. 3, 1886 AD</date>. 
In the former case  Cicero has the floor, as we say;  in the
latter case, Dr. Bacon's assistant, book in hand, his pupils before him. 
Both audiences want to get at the same thing, &mdash; what Cicero has to say. 
In the first scene, Cicero proceeds: &mdash;
</p>
<p><cit><quote lang="la">Rem publicam, Quirites, vitamque omnium vestrum, bona, fortunas,
coniuges liberosque vestros, atque hoc domicilium clarissimi imperi, fortunatissimam
pulcherrimamque urbem, hodierno die deorum immortalium summo ergo vos amore,
laboribus consiliis periculis meis, e flamma atque ferro ac paene ex faucibus
fati ereptam et vobis conservatam ac restitutam videtis.</quote> <bibl n="Cic. Catil. 3.1">(Catil. 3.1)</bibl></cit>
</p>
<p>When he has said that, every soul that has heard him knows precisely
what he means.  Now change to the Syracuse High School.  The
teacher says, "first find your subject."  So we run on, scenting out
a subject: &mdash;
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Rem publicam, Quirites, vitamque omnium vestrum, bona, fortunas,
coniuges liberosque vestros, atque hoc domicilium clarissimi imperi, fortunatissimam
pulcherrimamque urbem, hodierno die deorum immortalium summo ergo vos amore,
laboribus consiliis periculis meis, e flamma atque ferro ac paene ex faucibus
fati ereptam et vobis conservatam ac restitutam videtis.</quote>
</p>
<p>Well, we are through with the entire sentence, and there is no subject! 
Of course, then, it is implied in the verb, and that is the 2d person pronoun,
in the plural.  Next we find our verb.  That is, as it happens,
the last word, <foreign lang="la">videtis</foreign>.  Then we go back, do we, and find the
modifiers of the subject, and then the modifiers of the verb?  <emph>No</emph>,
I say to all that.  <emph>We have already</emph>,
if we have been rightly brought up, <emph>understood
everything in that sentence by the time we reach the last syllable of it,
without having thought meanwhile of a single English word;  and we
are as ready in 1886 to go on immediately with the next sentence as we
should have been if we had been Romans in the Roman Forum on that day in
63 BC</emph>.  Or, to put it another way, the boy who, reaching
that oration in the course of his preparation for college, cannot understand
that particular sentence, and a great many much more difficult sentences
in the oration, from reading it straight through once in the Latin, nay,
<emph>from merely hearing his teacher read it straight
through once in the Latin</emph>, has been wrongly trained, is wasting
time sadly, out of a human life all too short, and, so far from being on
the direct way to read Latin with speed and relish, and then to proceed
to do so, is on the direct way to drop it just as soon as the elective
system of his particular college will allow, and, if he cares for literature,
to go into some language in which it is not necessary, first to find the
subject, and then the predicate, and then the modifiers of the subject,
and then the modifiers of the predicate, and then to do the same thing
for the subordinate sentence, or, if there are several subordinate sentences,
to do the same thing for each one of them in the order of their importance,
and then to put these tattered bits together into a patchwork.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="5">
<p>Now, it will not do to say that students, by beginning in this way,
get, quite early, beyond the need of it.  At any rate, I can testify,
from my own experience, that, in spite of the admirable efforts of the
schools in "sight-reading," they do not, when they come to Harvard or Cornell. 
I allow myself in my class-room &mdash; keeping well inside of what is said to
be customary among college professors &mdash; one jest a year.  When I first
meet the new Freshman class (for I could not bear to leave such precious
material wholly to the most perfect assistant), I question them:</p>
<p>"Suppose, now, you are set, as you were at the examination for admission
the other day, to tell me the meaning of a sentence in a book you never
saw, &mdash; say an oration of Cicero, &mdash; how do you proceed to get at the writer's
meaning?"</p>
<p>There is at once a chorus of voices (for they are crammed
for that question, having learned printed directions, as we have seen,
in the first books they studied), "First find the &mdash; SUBJECT," three-quarters
of them say;  "PREDICATE," the other quarter.</p>
<p>"Now here," I say to them, "is an unhappy difference of opinion about first principles
in a matter of everyday practice, and of very serious importance. 
Which is right?"  They do not know.  "Which do you suppose the
Romans who heard the oration delivered in the Forum first hunted up, the
subject or the predicate?"  That little jest, simple as it is, always
meets with great success;  for it not only raises a laugh (of no value
in itself), but it shows at once, even to a Freshman, the entire absurdity
of trying to read Latin by a hunting-up first of either his subject or
his predicate;  and so enlists his sympathy in favor of trying some
other way, if any can be shown him.  But, at the same time, it proves
to me that the method taught at the most critical of all periods, the beginning,
is still wrong.  Only in late years, and very rarely, does some student
answer my question with:  "First read the first Latin word without
translating it, then the second, then the third, and so on to the end,
taking in all the possible constructions of every word, while barring out
at once the impossible, and, above all, erring, if anywhere, in the direction
of keeping the mind in suspense unnecessarily long, waiting, at least,
until a sure solution has been given by the sentence itself."
</p>
<p>Yet this is the one method that should everywhere be rigorously used,
from the day of the first lesson to the last piece of Latin that the college
graduate reads to solace his old age.  <emph>Only,
the process which at first is at every point conscious and slow</emph>,
as it was not with the Romans, <emph>becomes, in Latin
of ordinary difficulty, a process wholly unconscious and very rapid</emph>,
precisely as it was with the Romans.  Just when the process would
become easy for ordinarily simple Latin, if the training were right from
the beginning, I cannot say.  In my own experience with college students,
all whose habits have to be changed, I find a striking difference to be
produced in a single term.  And at the end of two years, when the
elective work begins, I now find it entirely practicable for the class
to devote itself to the study of the Latin literature in the Latin alone,
having nothing to do with version into English except at the examinations; 
and I never had so good and so spirited translation, whether at sight or
on the reading of the term, as last week, when, for the first time, I held
such an examination at the end of a term spent without translation.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="6">
<p>To bring the matter into a definite and practical shape, I can best
indicate what it seems to me you ought to direct your teachers of Latin
to do, <foreign lang="la">mutatis mutandis</foreign>, by telling you what I myself do from the
time when I first meet my Freshmen to the end of the Sophomore year.
</p>
<p>After my little jest about the Romans hunting up first the subject and
then the predicate as Cicero talked to them, or first the predicate and
then the subject, whichever one thinks the Roman method may have been,
I assure them that "<emph>what we have to do is to learn
to understand a Roman sentence precisely as a Roman understood it as he
heard it or read it</emph>, say in an oration, for example.  Now the
Roman heard, or read, first the first word, then the second, then the third,
and so on, through sentence after sentence, to the end of the oration,
with no turning back, with no hunting around.  And in doing this he
was so guided all the time, by indications of one kind or another in some
way strown through each sentence, that, when the last word of that sentence
had been spoken or read, the whole of the meaning had reached his mind. 
The process of detecting these indications of meaning was to him a wholly
unconscious one.  We moderns, however, of course cannot begin so far
along.  What we are to reach finally is precisely this unconsciousness
of processes;  but we shall be obliged, for the first few years, explicitly
to study the indications, until we come to know them familiarly, one after
another.  We must for some time think out, at every point, as the
sentence progresses (and that without ever allowing ourselves to look ahead),
all those conveyings of meaning, be they choice of word, or choice of order,
or choice of case, or choice of mode, or choice of tense, or whatsoever
else which at that point sufficed for the Roman mind.  And when these
indications &mdash; which after all are not so many in number &mdash; have come to
be so familiar to us that most of them are ready to flash before the mind
without our deliberately summoning them, we shall be very near the point
at which, in Latin graded to our growing powers, we shall interpret indications
unconsciously.  And the moment we do that, we shall be reading Latin
by the Roman's own method."

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="7">
<p>I take up now &mdash; all books being closed &mdash; a sentence of very simple structure,
of which every word and every construction are familiar, say a certain
passage in Livy.<note anchored="yes"><cit><bibl n="Liv. 1.41">1.41, </bibl><quote lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui
circa erant excepissent, illos fugientes lictores comprehendunt.</quote></cit></note>
I tell the story of the context:  Two assassins have got admission,
on the pretext of a quarrel to be decided, into the presence of Tarquin. 
One of them diverts the attention of the king by telling his tale, and
the other brings down an axe upon the king's head;  whereupon they
both rush for the door.
</p>
<p>In order that the interpretation shall be done absolutely in the order
in which a Roman would do it, without looking ahead, I write one word at
a time upon the board (as I will again do upon the board before you), and
ask questions as I go, as follows : &mdash;<note anchored="yes">The sentence grows upon the board by the addition
of one word after another.&nbsp; To obtain the same result in print, with
each new word the whole of the sentence thus far given will be repeated.&nbsp;
And, for the sake of greater clearness, answers will be distinguished from
questions by the use of italics.&nbsp;<note anchored="yes" place="inline" resp="aem">[Nowadays, some teachers find it
convenient to write the sentence on a transparency and uncover one word
at a time.]</note></note>
</p>
<p><foreign lang="la">Tarquinium</foreign>.  "What did Livy mean by putting that word at
the beginning of the sentence?"</p>
<p>"That the person mentioned in it is at this point of conspicuous importance."</p>
<p>"Where is <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium</foreign> made?"</p>
<p>"In the accusative singular."</p>
<p>"What does that fact mean to your minds?"
</p>
<p>Here most of them are somewhat dazed, not being used to that word <emph>meaning</emph>,
the very word that ought constantly to be used in dealing with syntax,
or so-called "parsing." So I very probably have to say, "May it mean the
duration of time of the act with which it is connected?"</p>
<p>They say, "No."</p>
<p>I ask, "Why not?"</p>
<p>Somebody says, "Because the name of a person cannot indicate time."</p>
<p>I say, "Give me some words that might indicate time."  They give me <foreign lang="la">dies, noctes, aetatem,</foreign>
etc.  Then I ask, "May it mean extent of space?"</p>
<p>They say, "No," give me similar reasons for their answer, and, upon my asking for words
that might indicate extent of space, they give me, perhaps, <foreign lang="la">mille passuum,
tres pedes</foreign>, etc.</p>
<p>Then I ask, "May it indicate the extent of the
action of the verb, the degree to which the action goes?"  They say,
"No," for a similar reason.  But when I ask for words that might
mean the degree of the action, they commonly cannot tell me, for the reason
that, strange to say, the grammars do not recognize such a usage; 
though sentences like "he walks a great deal every day" (<foreign lang="la">multum cottidie
ambulat</foreign>) are even more common than sentences like "he walks three miles
every day" (<foreign lang="la">cottidie tria milia passuum ambulat</foreign>), and the accusatives
mean essentially the same thing in both sentences.</p>
<p>Then I ask, "May
it mean that in respect to which something is said, &mdash; <emph>as regards Tarquin</emph>,
&mdash; the accusative of specification?"  To a question like that, I am
sorry to say that a great many always answer yes, for students get very
vague notions of the real uses of the accusative of specification. 
Somebody, however, may be able to tell me that the name of a person is
never used in the accusative of specification, and that in general the
use of the accusative of specification, in the days of Cicero and Virgil,
was mostly confined to poetry.  "What words were used in the accusative
of specification in prose?"  Here I never get an answer, although
the list is determinate, short, and important.  So I have to say,
"I must add to your working knowledge a useful item;  write in your
note-books as follows:  <foreign lang="la">partem, vicem, genus</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">omne</foreign>
or a pronoun (<foreign lang="la">quod, hoc, id</foreign>), <foreign lang="la">sexus</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">virile</foreign> or
<foreign lang="la">muliebre</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">hoc</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">id</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">aetatis</foreign>, the relative
<foreign lang="la">quod</foreign> and the interrogative <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign>, are used in Latin prose
in all periods as accusatives of specification.  Here, then, is a
bit of definite information which may enable you, when you first meet one
of these words again (you will do so quite early in your first book of
Livy), to walk without stumbling through a sentence where you would otherwise
trip."  Then I go back to Tarquinium.  "May it be," I ask, "an
accusative of exclamation?"</p>
<p>They say, "Possibly so." </p>
<p>I say, "possibly yes, though in historical narration you would hardly expect
such an exclamation from the historian."  Next I ask, "May it be a
cognate accusative?" </p>
<p>To that they answer, "No";  telling
me, perhaps with some help, that "the name of a person cannot be in any
sense a restatement of an act, &mdash; cannot mean an activity."</p>
<p>"Well, then, what does this accusative case mean?"</p>
<p>By this time a good many
are ready to say:  "Object of a verb, or in apposition with the
object."  But I ask if one thing more is possible, and some one
says:  "Subject of an infinitive."</p>
<p>"Yes," I answer;  "and one thing more yet?"  </p>
<p>"Predicate of an infinitive," someone suggests.
</p>
<p>"Now," I ask, "what have we learned from all this?  Given the name
of a person or persons in the accusative with no preposition, how many
and what constructions are possible?"  All are ready now to answer,
<emph>Object of a verb, or subject or predicate of an infinitive</emph>. 
"Good," I say.  "Keep those possibilities always fresh in your mind,
letting them flash through it the moment you see such a word;  and
that having been done, <emph>WAIT</emph>, and <emph>NEVER
DECIDE</emph> which of these possible meanings was in the mind of the Roman
speaker or writer until the rest of the sentence has made the answer to
that question perfectly clear.  Now tell me what constructions are
possible for an accusative like <foreign lang="la">hiemem</foreign>."</p>
<p>They answer, "duration of time, apposition, object of verb, subject or predicate of an infinitive."</p>
<p>"For an accusative like <foreign lang="la">pedes</foreign>?"</p>
<p>They answer, "extent of space, apposition, object of verb, or subject or predicate of an infinitive."</p>
<p>"For an accusative like <foreign lang="la">multum</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"Extent of action, apposition, object of verb, or subject or predicate of an infinitive."  </p>
<p>"For an accusative like <foreign lang="la">vitam</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"Cognate accusative, apposition, object of verb, or subject or predicate of an infinitive."</p>
<p>Now I ask, "Can any one tell me what constructions we may expect if the verb
turns out to be some word like <foreign lang="la">doceo</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">celo</foreign>?"  They
all give the answer, and therewith I have already passed in rapid review
practically the whole matter of the accusative constructions;  and,
what is more, &mdash; and this is vital, &mdash; I have done it <emph>from
a very practical standpoint</emph>.  I have not asked a student
to "parse" a word <emph>after seeing its full connection in the sentence</emph>
(an exercise which loses four-fifths of its virtue by this misplacement),
but I have demanded <emph>anticipatory parsing</emph>,
&mdash; I have put my questions in such a way that my students have learned for
all accusatives what instantaneous suggestions of the possible parts a
word is playing in the sentence they may get, at first sight of the word,
from the very nature of the word.
</p>
<p>Then I pass on.  "We have our King Tarquin before our eyes, as
the person on whom the interest of the sentence centres, and we know that
he is the object of an action, or the subject or predicate of an infinitive
action;  or, possibly, in apposition with such an object, subject,
or predicate.  To proceed, the next word, <foreign lang="la">moribundum</foreign>, is what
and where made?"  </p>
<p>"Adjective, nom. sing. neut., or acc. sing. masc. or neut."</p>
<p>Don't smile at all this.  The habit of getting a young student to think all these things out, even where he could not
go astray if they were not asked of him, saves many a getting lost in difficult
places.  "What is probable about <foreign lang="la">moribundum</foreign>, as we have it
in this particular sentence?"</p>
<p>"That it belongs to Tarquinium."</p>
<p>"Right.  Now keep that picture in mind:  <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum</foreign>,
<emph>the King, breathing his last, acted upon or acting</emph>. 
Now for the next word:  <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum</foreign>.  What
is <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>?"  Some say, with perfect readiness, "preposition,"
some say "conjunction."<note anchored="yes">The fact that it is possible for students,
without a moment's reflection, to plunge at things in this sadly well-known
way shows how thoroughly ineffective the prevailing method of teaching
beginners is in developing a sharp and self-suspicious observation.&nbsp;
That charge, it will be seen, cannot be brought against the method advocated
in this paper.</note></p>
<p>"But," I answer, "if you are used to the right spelling, you know with
an instant's thought that no Roman that ever lived could tell at this point
whether it was preposition or conjunction.  In order to tell, you
must wait for &mdash; what?"</p>
<p>"Ablative or verb," they answer. </p>
<p>Then we go on, "<foreign lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui</foreign>.  What does <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign>
at once tell us about <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"Conjunction."</p>
<p>"Right.  What do we know now, with almost absolute certainty, about <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium</foreign>? 
What part of the sentence does it belong to?"</p>
<p>Here, I grieve to say, a chorus of voices always answers, "Main verb";  for, in some
mysterious way, students arrive at the universities without having learned
that the Romans delighted to take out the most important word, or combination
of words, from a subordinate introductory sentence, and put it at the very
start, before the connective, &mdash; a bit of information worth a great deal
for practical reading.  That habit of expression I now tell them,
and then ask, "Given a sentence beginning with <foreign lang="la">mors si</foreign>, what do
you know?"</p>
<p>"That mors is the subject or predicate of the verb introduced by si."</p>
<p>"Given a sentence introduced by <foreign lang="la">Hannibali victori cum
ceteri</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"That Hannibali depends on something in the cum-sentence."
</p>
<p>Now we go back to our sentence, and the word <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign>.  "What
part of speech is it?"</p>
<p>"Relative," they say.</p>
<p>"Or what else?"  I ask.</p>
<p>"Interrogative."</p>
<p>"Where is it made?" </p>
<p>"Nom. sing. or plur., masc." </p>
<p>"If it is a relative, where in the sentence as a whole does its antecedent lie?"  
They should answer, "Inside the cum-clause."  The <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> serves as the first of two brackets
to include the <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign>-clause.</p>
<p>"If, on the other hand, it is an interrogative, what kind of a question is alone here possible?"  </p>
<p>"Indirect, and in the subjunctive," they answer.</p>
<p>"In that case, what kind of a meaning, speaking generally, must the verb introduced by <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> have?"  </p>
<p>"It must be able to imply asking of some kind."</p>
<p>"Rightly said;  perhaps we may have such a sentence as, <quote>"When everybody inquired who these men were"</quote> 
&mdash; <foreign lang="la">Cum qui essent omnes quaererent</foreign>; 
or perhaps we shall find that <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign> is relative.  The next word
is <foreign lang="la">circa</foreign>, &mdash; <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui circa</foreign>.  What
part of speech is it?"</p>
<p>"Adverb."</p>
<p>"What then may it do?" </p>
<p>"It may modify a verb, an adjective, or another adverb."
</p>
<p>We proceed:  <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui circa erunt</foreign>. </p>
<p>"What, now, about <foreign lang="la">circa</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"It modifies <foreign lang="la">erant</foreign>."</p>
<p>"What was the number of <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"Plural."</p>
<p>"Was it relative or interrogative?"</p>
<p>"Relative."</p>
<p>"How do you know?" </p>
<p>"Because erant is not subjunctive."</p>
<p>"Right.  Now <foreign lang="la">qui circa erant</foreign> is as good as a noun or a pronoun, &mdash; an indeclinable noun
or pronoun, in the plural.  Think of it in that way, as we go on.  <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui circa erant excepissent</foreign>.  I don't
ask to-day the meaning of the mode of <foreign lang="la">excepissent</foreign>, because the world
is in so much doubt about the question of the history and force of the
<foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>-constructions.  But what was Livy's meaning in writing
the accusative <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"Object of <foreign lang="la">excepissent</foreign>."</p>
<p>"Yes, and what was the subject of <foreign lang="la">excepissent</foreign>?"</p>
<p>"The antecedent of <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign>."</p>
<p>"Yes;  or, looking at the matter more generally,
the subject was <foreign lang="la">qui circa erant</foreign>."
</p>
<p>"Before going on, what picture have we before us?  What has the
sentence thus far said?  This:  
<quote rend="blockquote"><emph>See Tarquin, dying!  See the bystanders!  See them pick him up!</emph></quote></p>
<p>Our curiosity is stimulated by the very order.  The next word is <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign>,
&mdash; <quote lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui circa erant excepissent</quote> ... 
What does the position of <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign>, first in the main sentence proper,
tell us?"</p>
<p>"That the people meant by it are of special prominence at this point."  </p>
<p>"Who do you suppose these <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign> are, these
more distant persons, thus set in emphatic balance against <foreign lang="la">Tarquinium</foreign>,
each leading its clause?  </p>
<p>"The assassins," the whole class say. </p>
<p>"What do we know about Livy's meaning from the case?"</p>
<p>Now they all answer in fine chorus and completeness, "Apposition, object of main verb,
or subject or predicate of an infinitive."
</p>
<p>We proceed:  <quote lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui circa erant excepissent,
illos fugientes</quote> ...  "What part of speech is <foreign lang="la">fugientes</foreign>?" </p>
<p>"Participle."</p>
<p>"Which one?"</p>
<p>"Present active." </p>
<p>"Then you see a running-away going on before your eyes.  What gender?" </p>
<p>"Masc. or fem."</p>
<p>"What number?"</p>
<p>"Plural."  </p>
<p>"Then you see some two or more men or women running away.  What case?" </p>
<p>"Nom. or acc."</p>
<p>"On the whole, do you feel sure you know the case?"</p>
<p>"Yes;  accusative."</p>
<p>"Belonging to what?" </p>
<p>"<foreign lang="la">Illos</foreign>."</p>
<p>"Why?"</p>
<p>"Because of course the assassins, the <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign>, would run away."</p>
<p>"Yes," I say;  "but it cannot possibly
mislead you to wait until there isn't a shadow of a doubt.  We will
go on:  <quote lang="la">Tarquinium moribundum cum qui circa erant excepissent, illos
fugientes lictores</quote> ...  Here you have another set of people, the
king's body-guard.  In what case?"</p>
<p>"Nom. or acc. plural." </p>
<p>"Which?"  They do not know.  "Well, then, can <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign> agree
with <foreign lang="la">lictores</foreign>, if you consider forms alone?"</p>
<p>"Yes."</p>
<p>"In that case, <foreign lang="la">fugientes</foreign> would have to go with <foreign lang="la">illos lictores</foreign>, wouldn't it?"</p>
<p>"Yes."</p>
<p>"But would the lictors run away?" </p>
<p>"No."</p>
<p>"Would the assassins?"</p>
<p>"Yes."</p>
<p>"Certainly. Then <foreign lang="la">fugientes</foreign> does not belong with <foreign lang="la">lictores</foreign>, and does belong
with <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign>;  and <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign> seems to be, just as we suspected
at first sight of it, the assassins.  However, we must ask ourselves
one more question, Is apposition possible between <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">lictores</foreign>?" </p>
<p>"No;  for they are very different people."</p>
<p>"Is any relation of a predicate possible between them?  Can the one be the predicate
of an infinitive of which the other is the subject?"</p>
<p>"No; because, as before, they are very different people."</p>
<p>"Still it is possible that <foreign lang="la">lictores</foreign> is accusative.  If it is, it may
be object, in which case <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign> is necessarily subject, for, as we
have seen, they cannot be in apposition;  or, it may be subject, in
which case, for the same reason, <foreign lang="la">illos</foreign> must be object.  In
either case, they must be in <emph>direct opposition</emph> to each other, one
of them (we don't yet know which) being subject, the other, object; 
while, if <foreign lang="la">lictores</foreign> is nom., you still have the same relation, only
you know which is subject and which is object.  In any event, you
see they are set over against each other, together making subject and object. 
Now keep the results of this reasoning ready for the countless cases in
which such combinations occur.  Given two nouns like <foreign lang="la">bellum Saguntum</foreign>: 
what are the constructions?"</p>
<p>"One is the subject of a verb, and the other the object, and we can't yet tell which."</p>
<p>"Right. Now I will give you a still more involved combination, but of a very commonly
occurring kind, &mdash; <foreign lang="la">quae nos materiem</foreign>.  What do you make out
of that?"</p>
<p>Some clever boy will say, "<foreign lang="la">Nos</foreign> must be the subject of
a verb, either finite or infinitive, and <foreign lang="la">quae</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">materiem</foreign> are object and
predicate-object."</p>
<p>"Good.  Then what kind of meaning does the verb probably have?"</p>
<p>"One of calling."</p>
<p>"Right. The words are from Lucretius, and the verb he used was <foreign lang="la">vocamus</foreign>. 
Treasure up that combination and the meaning of it."
</p>
<p>"Now we go back to the assassins who are running away, and the king's
body-guard.  I will inform you that there is just one more word in
the sentence.  What part of speech is it?"</p>
<p>"Verb."</p>
<p>"Active or passive?"  </p>
<p>"Active."</p>
<p>"Right.  What does it tell?"  </p>
<p>"Tells what the lictors do to the assassins."</p>
<p>"What mode, then?"</p>
<p>"Indicative."</p>
<p>"What two tenses are possible?"</p>
<p>"The perfect and the historical present."</p>
<p>"Right.  Now the situation is a pretty dramatic one.  Which of these two tenses
should you accordingly choose, if you were writing the story?"  </p>
<p>"The present."  </p>
<p>"So did Livy.  Now tell me what you think the verb is."</p>
<p>"<foreign lang="la">Interficiunt</foreign>," somebody says.  "<foreign lang="la">Capiunt</foreign>," says
another, hitting the idea but not the right word, which is <foreign lang="la">comprehendunt</foreign>,
get hold of them well, &mdash; "nab 'em";  or, as our tamer English
phrase might put it, "secure them."
</p>
<p>"Now let us render into English the sentence as a whole, translating
not merely Livy's words, but the actual development of the thought in his
mind.
<quote rend="blockquote"><foreign lang="la">Tarquinium</foreign>, there's
Tarquin;  <foreign lang="la">moribundum</foreign>, he's a dying man;  
<foreign lang="la">cum qui circa erant</foreign>, you see the bystanders about to do something;  
<foreign lang="la">excepissent</foreign>, they have caught and supported the king;  
<foreign lang="la">illos</foreign>, you turn and look at the assassins;  
<foreign lang="la">fugientes</foreign>, they are off on the run;  
<foreign lang="la">lictores</foreign>, there are the king's body-guard;  we hold our breath in suspense; 
&mdash; <foreign lang="la">comprehendunt</foreign>, <emph>THEY'VE GOT 'EM!</emph></quote>  
</p>
<p>So, then, <emph>that Latin order,
which looks so perverted to one who is trained to pick the sentence to
pieces and then patch it together again, gives us the very succession in
which one would see the actual events</emph>;  weaves all the occurrences
together into a compact whole, yet keeping everywhere the <emph>natural</emph>
order;  while any order that we may be able to invent for a corresponding
<emph>single sentence</emph> in English will twist and warp the natural order
into a shape that would greatly astonish a Roman."
</p>
<p>"Finally, with the understanding and sense of the dramatic in the situation,
which we have got by working the sentence out as Livy wrote it, compare
the perversion of it, which we get by working it out correctly on the first-find-your-subject-of-the-main-sentence-and-then-your-predicate,
etc., method:</p>
<p><gloss>the lictors secure the assassins
as they run away, when those who were standing by had caught and supported
the dying Tarquin</gloss>.</p>
<p>The facts are all there, but the <emph>style</emph>, the <emph>soul</emph>, is gone."

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="8">
<p>Then I at once bring what we have learned to bear by giving a piece
of blank paper to each student and starting out upon a new sentence, which
shall involve what we have just seen, together with some fresh matter. 
The questions are carefully studied and written out in advance, and the
place of each is indicated to me, in my prepared manuscript, by a number
attached to the Latin word concerned, as if for a footnote.  As each
question is put, the number is at once written down by each student and
his answer written out.  Afterwards my assistant carefully goes through
every paper, and with a colored paper marks every error, for my own guidance,
and for the subsequent study, penitence, and profit of the writer. 
The following is an example actually used, from <bibl n="Liv. 21.53">Livy 21.53</bibl>.  The answer
that should be written is given with each question.
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Hannibal <gloss id="s8g1" lang="en" n="question">Construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g1">Subject of a verb, either subordinate or main.</gloss>
cum <gloss id="s8g2" lang="en" n="question">Part of speech?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g2">Preposition or conjunction</gloss>
quid <gloss id="s8g3" lang="en" n="question"><foreign lang="la">Cum</foreign> was what part of speech?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g3">Conjunction</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g4" lang="en" n="question">Construction of <foreign lang="la">Hannibal</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g4">Subject or predicate nominative of verb introduced by <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g5" lang="en" n="question"><foreign lang="la">Quid</foreign> is what part of speech?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g5">Interrogative</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g6" lang="en" n="question">Construction of the verb to which <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign> belongs?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g6">Subjunctive of indirect question</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g7" lang="en" n="question">General nature of meaning of verb introduced by <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g7">Some meaning that can imply a question</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g8" lang="en" n="question">Case of <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g8">Nom. or acc. neut. sing.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g9" lang="en" n="question">Construction of <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g9">Subject, predicate, or object of finite verb or infinitive;  or acc. of specification, the so-called adverb.</gloss>
optimum <gloss id="s8g10" lang="en" n="question">Case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g10">Nom. neut. sing., or acc. masc. or neut. sing.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g11" lang="en" n="question">Construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g11">If neut., agreeing with subject or object of verb, or in predicate.  If masc., agreeing with object of verb, or with subject or predicate of an infinitive.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g12" lang="en" n="question">What constructions may follow to complete the meaning of <foreign lang="la">optimum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g13">Dat. of the person for whom something is <foreign lang="la">optimum</foreign>, or abl. of that with respect to which something is <foreign lang="la">optimum</foreign>.  (It is worthwhile to have those two possibilities pat, for the great class of words of which <foreign lang="la">optimum</foreign> is a specimen.)</gloss>
foret <gloss id="s8g13" lang="en" n="question">Where made?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g13">Imperfect subjunctive.  (Reason already given under <ref target="s8g6" targOrder="U">6.</ref>)</gloss>
hosti <gloss id="s8g14" lang="en" n="question">Construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g14">Dative after <foreign lang="la">optimum</foreign>.  (Reason given under <ref target="s8g12" targOrder="U">12.</ref>)</gloss>
cerneret, <gloss id="s8g15" lang="en" n="question">Where made, and introduced by what?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g15">Imperfect subjunctive, introduced by <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g16" lang="en" n="question">Construction of <foreign lang="la">Hannibal</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g16">Subject of <foreign lang="la">cerneret</foreign></gloss>
vix <gloss id="s8g17" lang="en" n="question"><foreign lang="la">Vix</foreign>, <gloss lang="en">hardly</gloss>, has a negative feeling.  In such a connection, what would be the pronoun meaning "any," and what the adjective?  (Probably nobody knows.)</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g17"><foreign lang="la">Quisquam, ullus</foreign></gloss>
ullam spem <gloss id="s8g18" lang="en" n="question">Construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g18">Acc. sing., object of verb, or subject or predicate of infinitive.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g19" lang="en" n="question"><foreign lang="la">Spes</foreign>, just as much as <foreign lang="la">spero</foreign>, indicates a mental activity, and we shall probably find something else, completing its meaning, the object of the <foreign lang="la">spes</foreign>.  What will be the case (a) if the completing word is a noun? (b) if the completing word is a verb?</gloss>  <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g19">Objective genitive of a noun;  of a verb, objective genitive of gerund or of gerundive with noun, or future infinitive.</gloss>
habebat <gloss id="s8g20" lang="en" n="question">Subject is what?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g20">A pronoun, repeating <foreign lang="la">Hannibal</foreign>.</gloss>
temere <gloss id="s8g21" lang="en" n="question">Part of speech, and simplest meaning?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g21">Adverb, meaning <gloss lang="en">blindly</gloss>.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g22" lang="en" n="question">Bearing in mind that, in the ordinary Roman habit, words were placed in anticipation of those which they modify, not after them, what do you feel about <foreign lang="la">temere</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g22">That it modifies the expected object of <foreign lang="la">spem</foreign>, which, consequently, is a verb.</gloss>
atque <gloss id="s8g23" lang="en" n="question">Probably introduces what?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g23">Another adverb, corresponding to <foreign lang="la">temere</foreign>.</gloss>
<seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s8g24" lang="en" n="question">Write an adverb to mean 'not looking ahead.'</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g24"><foreign lang="la">Improvide</foreign></gloss>
<seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s8g25" lang="en" n="question">Write nom. or acc. neut. sing. meaning 'anything' (in one word).</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g25"><foreign lang="la">Quicquam</foreign>.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g26" lang="en" n="question">In what case is that word here, and with what verb is it connected?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g26">Acc., connected with a verb, which verb must depend on <foreign lang="la">spem</foreign>.</gloss>
consules <gloss id="s8g27" lang="en" n="question">Where made, without reference to context?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g27">Nom. or acc. plur.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g28" lang="en" n="question">Where made, with reference to context, and how do you know?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g28">Acc., because <foreign lang="la">habebat</foreign> is sing.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g29" lang="en" n="question">Meaning of this accusative?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g29">That <foreign lang="la">consules</foreign> is subject, object, or predicate of an infinitive.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g30" lang="en" n="question">Relation of <foreign lang="la">quicquam</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">consules</foreign> to each other?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g30">One the object, the other the subject, of the infinitive.</gloss>
<seg type="cloze">---</seg><gloss id="s8g31" lang="en" n="question">Complete the sentence, using a verb meaning 'do.'</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s8g31"><foreign lang="la">Acturos</foreign>, with or without <foreign lang="la">esse</foreign>.</gloss>
<gloss id="s8g32" lang="en" n="question">Write, in the best English you have at your command, a translation of the sentence.</gloss>
</quote>

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="9">
<p>"Now," I go on to say to my students, "you are to commit this sentence
to memory, and be ready to give it fluently in the Latin when we meet next. 
And in the same way you will commit to memory every passage we so use in
the year;  and at each term examination you will find yourselves called
upon to write one of these passages, still from memory.  Further,
and still more important than this, never again pick out your subject,
your predicate, etc.;  but, in preparing your daily lessons, do just
what we have been doing this morning, except that <emph>you
are not to translate any sentence, or any part of any sentence, until you
have gone through the whole lesson in the Latin, and got all the meaning
in your power out of it</emph>.  I give you a short lesson, and I
shall call upon one man and another to take up a sentence and go rapidly
through it as Latin, word after word, as we have just now done, telling
us precisely how it should be thought out.  In preparing your lesson,
in order to be sure that your eye does not stray and run ahead, cut out
a piece of flexible pasteboard, or, until you can get pasteboard, a piece
of stiff writing-paper, as long as twice the width of your printed text,
and two or three inches wide.  Cut a strip from the top, running along
half the length, and deep enough to correspond to precisely one line of
your text, including the space that belongs with it.<note anchored="yes">At the meeting of the Philological Association
at Ithaca last summer, Professor Gildersleeve, in the course of some remarks
upon the reading of Greek and Latin, expressed himself with great severity
in regard to the habitual way of doing the thing, and suggested that it
would be desirable, in order to force students to accept the order of the
original, to require them to read through a hole in a piece of paper, or
with a notched card.&nbsp; The method urged in the present pamphlet is
practically so identical with the results that would flow from Professor
Gildersleeve's suggestion, that nothing but the fact that this method was
already substantially in print in the Cornell University Register for 1885-6,
and in the special announcement of courses in the classics, could save
this pamphlet from the suspicion of being merely an expansion of Professor
Gildersleeve's hint.&nbsp; The same thing holds in regard to the admirable
injunction in the preface to the new edition of the Allen and Greenough
Cicero, published in May, 1886.&nbsp; As it is, however, it appears that
the essential aim of the method of this pamphlet (not necessarily, of course,
its details) has strong and express confirmation.</note>
Use this piece of paper in such a way as to expose just one word at a time,
together with which, of course, will also be seen all the words preceding; 
that is to say, as you think about one word after another, pushing your
paper on, you will constantly see all of the sentence thus far traversed,
without being able to look ahead."
</p>
<p>At the next meeting, the class, thus prepared, recites as described,
a number of students attempting to show precisely what mental processes
one should go through in taking up the sentences of the lesson.  At
the next but one, and thereafter throughout the Freshman year, all books
being closed, the instructor reads the review lesson aloud, with all the
effectiveness possible to him, one sentence at a time, calling for a translation
of it from one and another student.<note anchored="yes">For this very helpful feature of the work under
description, I owe my thanks to my assistant, Dr. A. C. White.&nbsp; I
know of no piece of work more charming and cheering to listen to, excepting
the translation of a new piece of Latin in the same way.</note>
As a preparation for this exercise, each student is urged to read the review
aloud a number of times in his own room, doing his author as much justice
as possible.
</p>
<p>At every exercise during the year, except the special weekly exercise,
a number of sentences, prepared by the instructor, and based upon the text
under reading at the time, are given out to students, to be written upon
the board, in the English and in Latin, while the rest of the class are
engaged upon translating the review as the instructor reads it;  and
when the work upon the review is over, these Latin sentences upon the board
are criticised by the class.  I touch upon a very serious defect in
most of our preparatory schools when I say that from beginning to end there
should never be a recitation in a foreign language without written or oral
translation into that language.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="10">
<p>For the special weekly exercise described above, there can be no considerable
preparation beyond incessant faithfulness in the daily work.  The
time thus left free is utilized in the preparation of a considerable piece
of English based upon the Latin recently read.  (It will be seen that
no textbook in composition is employed.)  The exercise handed in by
each student is afterwards looked through, and returned to him at the next
meeting of the class, with all errors marked.
</p>
<p>The writing of the Latin sentence, one word at a time, upon the board
in the special weekly exercise which has been described above, gives place
in a few weeks to the corresponding dictation of one word at a time, to
be written upon his paper by the student, the questions being, of course,
given as before.  The exercise changes constantly in character by
the dropping of questions with which the students have become familiar,
and the bringing in of questions involving new principles.  Meanwhile,
the examination of the papers written shows, from week to week, just where
each student's weakness lies.  In no long time all the constantly
recurring constructions have become familiar as practical, working affairs. 
Then (and this time properly comes somewhere near the end of the first
third of the year) I cease entirely to have the Latin written, and give
my passage (which may now be of respectable length) orally, still asking
occasional questions for written answers, here and there, at points dangerous
or otherwise instructive.  After the whole of the passage has been
gone through in this way, it is taken up again, one sentence at a time,
and a written translation is made by each student.  The passages are
commonly selected from the book which the class is reading, and not very
far in advance of the place reached in the other lessons of the week. 
The attempt is always made to select a passage with a dramatic or otherwise
striking close.  Each week, as already said, the whole of the exercise
of the previous week is memorized, and repeated by several students, with
great attention to the effective conveying of the meaning, by the throwing
together, as in all spoken languages, of a number of words making a group
in the sentence as a whole, by the careful balancing, in the delivery,
of words clearly meant to be balanced, etc., etc.
</p>
<p>All this time each student is gaining a working knowledge of syntax
regarded from the true standpoint for the first purposes of college work,
namely, as a mechanism for conveying meaning from one mind to another; 
is learning to bring that knowledge of syntax to bear at the most economical
point;  is gaining familiarity with Roman tricks of order;  and
is laying up a steadily growing vocabulary.<note anchored="yes">To vary the exercise, a continuous story of
several pages in length is occasionally read through without stopping and
without repetition, and each student then writes as complete a r&eacute;sum&eacute;
of it as he can produce.</note>
And throughout, in order to keep constantly in sight the idea that <emph>the
aim of the whole business is to learn to read Latin</emph>, occasional
examinations in translation new passages from a text or printed paper are
held during the term (as of course they should be upon any system), and
at the end of each term the first exercise at the final exam is translation
at hearing, the second exercise is translation at sight, the third exercise
is translation at sight from English to Latin, the fourth is the writing
of one of the passages memorized during the term;  and not until this
is done does the student proceed to an exercise in translating and commenting
upon passages read during the term.  Moreover, the greater part of
the grammatical questions of the paper are set, not upon passages read
during the term, but upon the passages given for the first time at the
examinations;  namely, the passages to be translated at hearing and
at sight.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="11">
<p>In the second year,  the aim of gaining in power to read at sight
is constantly held up before the students, and occasional written exercises
in reading at sight are given through the term, while the first exercise
set at the examination at the end of the term is always translation at
sight.  A proper supplement to this is an elective in the speaking
and writing of Latin.  In the second and third terms of the second
year, which are now devoted to Horace, considerable quantities can be read,
with a good deal of memorizing;  and the treatment can be made almost
wholly literary.  That carries us through the Sophomore year, and
to the beginning of the elective work, taken by Juniors and Seniors together. 
Here translation at the daily lesson ends, except in those rare cases where
the meaning of a difficult passage cannot be given by explaining the grammatical
structure, or by turning the passage into some other form in Latin.<note anchored="yes">The preparation indicated has been leading
for some years toward the dropping of translation at the daily recitations,
and, indeed, I have always endeavored to secure time toward the end of
the hour in which to read on in advance to my students, without translating.&nbsp;
But I should not have had the courage in the present year to break with
translation in the class-room in advanced reading, had it not been for
the assurances given me by Professor Greenough, founded upon his own experiments
in doing this precise thing.&nbsp; My experience in the past term has been
so gratifying as to lead me to desire greatly that Professor Greenough
might set forth, in accessible form, the great advantages of the system
for students properly trained for it.&nbsp; Meanwhile, let me premise that
the delight of this method of dealing with a literature &mdash; the charm of
direct communication with the author, of feeling, in fact, the very untranslatableness
of diction and style &mdash; cannot be fancied by one who has not made the experiment;&nbsp;
always supposing, of course, that the class has been trained in advance
and brought to the point at which such reading is made possible.</note>
Translations are written at occasional exercises held for that purpose
during the term, and always make a part of the final examination, so that
every student feels bound to understand his author.  But <emph>the
students are urged not to have anything to do with English in preparation
for their daily lessons or for the final examination</emph>, but to read
the Latin <emph>as literature</emph>, with the utmost skill in rendering their
author that they can acquire.
</p>
<p>In all my teaching, two exercises stand out from the rest, as giving
me special delight through the interest and mental activity of my students: 
first, the exercises with the Freshmen, which I have described as carried
on weekly by myself;  secondly, an exercise such as I carried on with
an elective class recently, when, at the end of a term spent upon Plautus,
I read a new play straight through in the Latin (the students following
me in their texts), without translation, and with very little comment,
moving at about the rate at which one would move if he were reading a new
play of Shakespeare in a similar way;  and felt my audience responsive,
even to the extent of occasional laughter that checked us for a moment,
to nearly everything in our author that would have been intelligible, without
special explanation, in an English translation.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="12">
<p>Finally, if you ask me whether this method which I have been describing
does not take a great deal of time, I shall answer that the amount of Latin
read in the first term is much smaller than in the ordinary way, but that
the power to read increases rapidly, and that the total quantity read in
the first year is somewhat greater than on the common system, considerably
greater in the second year, and in the elective years absolutely greater; 
to say nothing of the much juster understanding of, and more intimate feeling
for, his original, and the much keener delight in reading, gained by the
student who pursues this method.  But there is one thing more to be
said about this kind of work, this training of the student to read Latin
rapidly. <emph>It is not the work of the universities at all.</emph>  In
the universities, men should not learn how to read Latin, but should read
it.  It should be my office, for instance, to make them acquainted
with the body of the literature, to make them know it, at any rate, and
love it, if possible.  But the office of preparing them to do this
by training them to read ordinary Latin with ease and speed belongs to
no college instructor, but to the schools of which you have charge. 
I wholly believe that the application, from the very first day of reading
a Roman sentence of one word, of the method here described, would, without
adding a day to the length of time given to preparation for college, make
a young student able, at the beginning of his Freshman year, to read Latin
with more ease and speed than are my students at the end of it, &mdash; to say
nothing of the greater pleasure which they would have in their work. 
And I am not judging from my experience in university teaching alone; 
for this very method of teaching has been used by students of my own upon
young pupils, of varying ability, in preparation for college, and with
results that fully confirm my belief.  Nor are the young pupils the
only gainers.  The teacher himself will be surprised to see how much
more pleasure he feels in his work;  and, if he keeps up his reading
of the Latin literature, as all teachers of course endeavor to do, he will
be surprised to find how his rate of speed will increase.  And the
method itself will give him no trouble to learn;  for in the very
act of preparing papers for examinations of this sort, or, at the worst,
of conducting oral exercises without preparation, the teacher will very
soon have taught himself the whole art.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="13">
<head>Supplement</head>

<p>To the preceding address
&mdash; long, and yet too brief &mdash; I wish to add two things:  further specimens
of papers actually employed by myself with a Freshman class, and suggestions
for the application of the method in the preparatory schools.
</p>
<p>At this point, I should advise the wearied reader, if he feels some
confidence in the method, to lay the pamphlet aside and make experiment
himself with a class, returning to the reading after he has come to feel
an interest in further suggestions of detail.  As for the wearied
reader that does not feel this confidence, he will readily lay the pamphlet
down unadvised.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="14">
<head>Specimens of papers</head>

<p>In giving in this way details of the system on which my own work is
conducted, I do not feel that I owe an apology.  One who proposes
a method must have a very solid basis for his proposal.  This basis
must be an experience of the efficacy of that which he is urging; 
and this experience should be given with the greatest clearness and definiteness. 
It is to be wished, indeed, that teachers of a given subject throughout
the country, in colleges and schools, might regard themselves as forming
one body with a common purpose, and that a constant interchange of experience
and opinion might go on among them, alike in matters of investigation and
matters of pedagogy.
</p>
<p>It should be remembered that the papers printed below were used, early
in the Freshman year, with students who had prepared for college upon the
familiar and thoroughly un-Roman system.  If students were prepared
upon the right method, not one in ten of the questions here indicated would
need to be asked, and the exercise of translating at hearing would be a
rapid and attractive affair.
</p>
<p>These papers were given to the Freshman class in succession, at intervals
of a week, in the autumn of 1885;  at which time the work of the other
recitations of the week was in Livy.  The constant aim &mdash; and the class
were so informed &mdash; was to find for these papers, as given week after week,
passages which would demand of them a practical power of handling constructions
which had been discussed in the other exercises of the week, so that their
progress should be one of constant acquisition without loss;  and
it was promised them that in this way they should in a short time possess
a ready and <emph>available</emph> familiarity with all the commonly recurring
constructions of the language.  I further told them that, since I
should not give them at these exercises in translation the meaning of any
word which they had ever seen before, they had a very strong reason for
laying up for themselves a vocabulary through securing in their memory
every Latin word occurring in their daily work, and a very strong reason
for paying extremely careful attention, both at and after the other recitations
of the week, to any explanations of meaning of this or that word, alone,
or in connection with others related to it in meaning (e.g. to <foreign lang="la">alius</foreign>,
in connection with <foreign lang="la">alter</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">ceteri</foreign>), which might similarly
be given to them at the ordinary recitations.  Nor was I content with
this;  for, in order that there might be no escape, I prepared a partial
syllabus of definable points emphasized in the work of the term; 
and one of these was purchased, from the office that printed it, by each
student in the class.
</p>
<p>At the beginning of the term, the work of the advance lesson was largely
done in the class-room, instructor and instructed working together. 
It will be rightly inferred from this that the class moved slowly at the
outset.  I am a devout believer in the reading of large quantities
of the classics;  indeed, that is, in this present business, my particular
and precise aim;  but I am also a believer in what is called "the
long run," and "in the long run" only a soundly trained man gets very far. 
In the preliminary training, it is necessary at first to take a good deal
of time in probing to the quick, sometimes with considerable distress to
the would-be athletes, a class of new students who have been carefully
trained to distort and mangle the Latin sentence;  who have necessarily
failed to acquire the alert and self-watchful habits of thought and of
suspended judgment to which the received method, with its resulting impatience
to "make sense," is practically strongly opposed;  whose knowledge
of syntax is of a back-handed kind, good for very little except to "parse"
with, more or less mechanically and ineffectually, after the whole sentence
has been dug out, but worth nothing as yet for the current interpretation
of the syntax of word after word <foreign lang="la">in situ</foreign> in the progress of the
sentence;  and, finally, some of whom have been trained to pronounce
Latin on the English method, others on the Continental, and others on one
or another of that great variety of methods passing current under the general
appellation of "Roman," and many of whom, accordingly, find it very difficult
to understand a word of one syllable as pronounced by my assistant or myself,
&mdash; to say nothing of a word of two syllables.
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="15">
<p>Up to the fourth week inclusive, the Latin was written upon the board
at these weekly exercises, one word at a time, the questions being put,
as indicated by the footnotes in the papers given below, at one point and
another as the sentence progressed.  For several weeks after that
time, the Latin sentence was written by each student, one word at a time,
as pronounced by the instructor, the questions being set and answered as
before.  After this, the writing of the Latin was forbidden, and the
passages used were interpreted only as <emph>heard</emph> from the instructor's
reading.
</p>
<p>At the first interview, the class had worked out, as it was put upon
the board, one word at a time, the sentence in <bibl n="Liv. 1.1.5">Livy I.1.5.</bibl>
</p>
<p><cit><quote lang="la">Ibi egressi Troiani, ut quibus ab immenso prope
errore nihil praeter arma et naves superesset, cum praedam ex agris agerent,
Latinus rex Aboriginesque, qui tum ea tenebant loca, ad arcendam vim advenarum
armati ex urbe atque agris concurrunt.</quote> <bibl n="Liv. 1.1.5">(1.1.5)</bibl></cit>
</p>
<p>As we reached the point <foreign lang="la">...ut quibus</foreign>, they had made out, under
questioning, that <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> might be (1) a
conjunction, in which case <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign> could be (a)
an interrogative introducing an indirect question depending on the <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>-verb,
or (b) a relative referring to something connected
with the <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>-verb;  or that, on the other hand, <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> might
be (2) an adverb, in which case the <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign>-clause
must be substantially an adjective modifying <foreign lang="la">Troiani</foreign>;  in other
words, a <emph>characterizing</emph> clause. 
In this connection, they had been told, for the sake of having the whole
matter secured for their repertory of combinations of this kind, that what
was essential in this latter case was the characterizing clause itself,
and that in strictness no introductory word was necessary;  if one
was used, however, it might be either <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">utpote</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">quippe</foreign>; 
and it was also pointed out that, while there were three possibilities
for a combination like <foreign lang="la">ut quibus</foreign>, there was only one possibility
for a combination like <foreign lang="la">utpote quibus</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">quippe quibus</foreign>.
</p>
<p>As we reached <foreign lang="la">superesset</foreign>, it was pointed out, <emph>against
the practical habit of thought of nearly all the class</emph>, that, since
in Latin the common practice was to put a modifying clause or phrase before
the thing modified, the chances were that the <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign>-clause, if
it should turn out to be a characterizing clause, would bear, not upon
<foreign lang="la">egressi</foreign>, but upon something which we were still to wait for. 
(This something turned out to be <foreign lang="la">cum ... agerent</foreign>, &mdash; <gloss>the natural
thing for destitute men to do</gloss>.)
</p>
<p>As we reached <foreign lang="la">...cum praedam</foreign>, at which stage it was sure that
<foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> was a conjunction, the point was made, though again against
the sentiments of the class, that <foreign lang="la">Troiani</foreign> was the subject of the
verb introduced by <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>, since the Romans were fond of taking out
a conspicuous word or phrase belonging to an introductory temporal sentence,
and putting it before the connective.<note anchored="yes">It must already be apparent that I do not regard
the "Sauveur method" as sufficient in dealing with a language so difficult
as the Latin, and in a community where no amount of exertion will make
Latin the habitual medium of daily speech.&nbsp; But I feel, nevertheless,
that we owe a great debt of gratitude to Dr. Sauveur and his followers
for their insistence that the language should be treated as living, and
as intelligible to the ear.</note>
</p>
<p>The passage chosen for the first written exercise turned out to be a
little too difficult in the reasoning at the <foreign lang="la">et cui</foreign> point, though
it had a certain and considerable usefulness in displaying to the class
a sentence of which some of them, though knowing the meaning of each word,
and though able to "parse" it from beginning to end if it were once translated
to them, would yet fail to comprehend the meaning, through a lack of a
working knowledge of the constructions involved.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="16">
<head>First Exercise <bibl n="Liv. 1.34.7">(Livy 1.34.7)</bibl></head>

<p>[Tanaquil has been urging upon Lucumo, who lives
in Tarquinii, that he would have better hopes of rising in some new city,
and points out that Rome has special advantages.]
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Facile<gloss id="s16g1" lang="en" n="question">May be either of what possible parts of speech;  and where made?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g1">Adj. in nom. or acc. neut. sing.;  or adverb.</gloss> 
 persuadet<gloss id="s16g2" lang="en" n="question">In what way will the person who is persuaded, if there is one, be expressed?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g2">By the dative.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g3" lang="en" n="question">In what way will that to which the person is persuaded be expressed, if it proves to be (a) a pronoun?  (b) a verbal idea?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g3">(a) By the accusative. (b) By the infinitive, if it is a statement of belief, etc.; by a substantive purpose clause, if it be an act desired to be brought about.</gloss> 
 ut<gloss id="s16g4" lang="en" n="question">The suspense about <foreign lang="la">facile</foreign> is now probably how resolved?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g4">The writer meant it as adverb, modifying persuadet.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g5" lang="en" n="question">What constructions will probably follow <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>, if it is meant (a) as conjunction?  (b) as adverb?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g5">(a) A substantive purpose clause. (b) A noun (appositive), adjective, or adjectival phrase, belonging to the personal subject or object of <foreign lang="la">persuadet</foreign>, and so nom. or dat.</gloss> 
cupido<gloss id="s16g6" lang="en" n="question">May be either of what possible parts of speech, and, in either case, in what construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g6">Noun, nom., subject of substantive final clause introduced by the conjunction <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>;  or, adjective, dat., agreeing with personal object of <foreign lang="la">persuadet</foreign> and introduced by the adverb <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g7" lang="en" n="question">Does it call for anything to complete its meaning, and, if so, what?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g7">An objective genitive.</gloss> 
 honorum et<gloss id="s16g8" lang="en" n="question">What three uses has the word <foreign lang="la">et</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g8">(1) Connecting two words, = and;  (2) as the first of two <foreign lang="la">et</foreign>s = both ... and;  or (3) as bearing upon a single word, = also, even.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g9" lang="en" n="question">What uses may <foreign lang="la">et</foreign> have, in each case, in the present passage?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g9">It may connect <foreign lang="la">cupido</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">honorum</foreign>, to something yet to come;  or it may be the first of two balanced <foreign lang="la">et</foreign>s;  or it may emphasize a word or phrase to follow.</gloss> 
 cui<gloss id="s16g10" lang="en" n="question">What is now the probable meaning of <foreign lang="la">et</foreign>, what its office, and what light does it throw upon <foreign lang="la">cupido</foreign>? Mark the quantity of the <foreign lang="la">i</foreign> in the last.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g10">And;  connecting the <foreign lang="la">cui</foreign>-sentence to <foreign lang="la">cup&icirc;do</foreign>, which is an adjective.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g11" lang="en" n="question">If this surmise is right, then what part of speech will the <foreign lang="la">cui</foreign>-sentence be equivalent to, and by what mode will this meaning be expressed?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g11">An adjective;  expressed by the characterizing mode, the subjunctive.</gloss> 
Tarquinii<gloss id="s16g12" lang="en" n="question">Is name of town in nom. pl.?  What three possibilities of construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g12">Subject, predicate, or in apposition with the one or the other.</gloss> 
 materna<gloss id="s16g13" lang="en" n="question">Part of speech and possible cases?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g13">Adjective, nom. sing. fem., abl. sing. fem., nom. or acc. neut. pl.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g14" lang="en" n="question">Meaning of its position before its noun?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g14">That it is emphatic.</gloss> 
tantum<gloss id="s16g15" lang="en" n="question">Possible parts of speech, and corresponding meanings?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g15">Adjective, meaning so great, or adverb, meaning to such a degree, or to such a degree and no further, i.e. only.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g16" lang="en" n="question">In the last sense, what are its synonyms?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g16"><foreign lang="la">Solum</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">modo</foreign>.</gloss> 
 patria<gloss id="s16g17" lang="en" n="question">What part of speech was <foreign lang="la">tantum</foreign>, and what did it modify?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g17">Adverb, modifying <foreign lang="la">materna</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g18" lang="en" n="question">Probably construction of <foreign lang="la">patria</foreign> and of <foreign lang="la">Tarquinii</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g18"><foreign lang="la">Tarquinii</foreign> is probably subject of the <foreign lang="la">cui</foreign>-verb, and <foreign lang="la">patria</foreign> is its predicate.</gloss> 
 <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s16g19" lang="en" n="question">Write the verb.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g19"><foreign lang="la">Esset</foreign>.</gloss> 
sublatis<gloss id="s16g20" lang="en" n="question">Where made?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g20">Participle, dat. or abl. pl.</gloss> 
 itaque rebus<gloss id="s16g21" lang="en" n="question">Possible cases?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g21">Dat. or abl.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g22" lang="en" n="question">Probable construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g22">Ablative absolute with <foreign lang="la">sublatis</foreign>.</gloss>
 commigrant <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s16g23" lang="en" n="question">The place they go to is Rome.  Complete the sentence in two ways, using <foreign lang="la">urbs</foreign> in one, and <foreign lang="la">Roma</foreign> in the other.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s16g23"><foreign lang="la">Ad urbem</foreign>;  <foreign lang="la">Romam</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s16g24" lang="en" n="question">Translate the passage.</gloss>
</quote>
.</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="17">
<head>Second exercise <bibl n="Liv. 1.9.1">(Livy 1.9.1)</bibl></head>

<p>[Romulus has enclosed a great space with his fortifications,
and gathered a crowd of refugees into his new city.]
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Iam res<gloss id="s17g1" lang="en" n="question">Possible cases?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g1">Nom. sing., nom. or acc. pl.</gloss> 
 Romana<gloss id="s17g2" lang="en" n="question">Probable case and construction of <foreign lang="la">res</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g2">Nom., subject of main verb.</gloss> 
 adeo<gloss id="s17g3" lang="en" n="question">Commonest meaning of <foreign lang="la">adeo</foreign>?  and how must its meaning, if completed, be completed?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g3">To such a degree;  by consecutive <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>-sentence.</gloss> 
erat<gloss id="s17g4" lang="en" n="question">Meaning of the tense?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g4">State of affairs at the point at which the story has reached.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g5" lang="en" n="question">What two parts of speech are capable of completing the sentence?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g5">Adjective and participle.</gloss> 
 valida, ut cuilibet<gloss id="s17g6" lang="en" n="question">Part of speech?  what other word is substantially equivalent?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g6">Indefinite pronoun;  <foreign lang="la">cuivis</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g7" lang="en" n="question">How are we to think of the meaning of case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g7">As some aspect of the indirect object.</gloss> 
 finitimarum<gloss id="s17g8" lang="en" n="question">Suggests the beginning of what construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g8">Partitive genitive.</gloss> 
civitatum bello<gloss id="s17g9" lang="en" n="question">Possible cases and possible constructions?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g9">Dative of some aspect of the indirect object, or ablative in some instrumental aspect.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g10" lang="en" n="question">Can <foreign lang="la">cuilibet</foreign> go with <foreign lang="la">bello</foreign>, and why?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g10">No;  for the partitive genitive shows that <foreign lang="la">cuilibet</foreign> refers to a <foreign lang="la">civitati</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g11" lang="en" n="question">Then is <foreign lang="la">bello</foreign> more likely to turn out to be a dative, or an ablative?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g11">An ablative.</gloss> 
 par<gloss id="s17g12" lang="en" n="question">What suspense about Livy's meaning is now resolved?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g12"><foreign lang="la">Cuilibet</foreign> is the dative of the indirect object to which the quality of <foreign lang="la">par</foreign> is directed, and <foreign lang="la">bello</foreign> is the ablative of respect for <foreign lang="la">par</foreign>.</gloss> 
 <seg type="cloze">---</seg><gloss id="s17g13" lang="en" n="question">Write the predicate from <foreign lang="la">sum</foreign>.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g13"><foreign lang="la">Esset</foreign>.</gloss> 
sed penuria<gloss id="s17g14" lang="en" n="question">Possible cases?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g14">Nom. or abl.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g15" lang="en" n="question">If the idea is completed, by what case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g15">Objective genitive.</gloss> 
 mulierum hominis aetatem<gloss id="s17g16" lang="en" n="question">Possible meanings of the case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g16">Duration of time, appositive, object of a verb, or subject or predicate of an infinitive.</gloss> 
duratura<gloss id="s17g17" lang="en" n="question">Probable meaning of <foreign lang="la">aetatem</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g17">Duration of time.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g18" lang="en" n="question">What two possibilities for the government of <foreign lang="la">duratura</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g18">That it belongs (1) to <foreign lang="la">penuria</foreign>,</gloss> 
 magnitudo<gloss id="s17g19" lang="en" n="question">What do we now feel about the case of <foreign lang="la">penuria</foreign>, and the meaning of that case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g19">That it is an ablative, expressing the cause of <foreign lang="la">duratura</foreign>.</gloss> 
 <seg type="cloze">---</seg>, <gloss id="s17g20" lang="en" n="question">Write predicate from sum, choosing the tense with care.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g20"><foreign lang="la">Erat</foreign>.</gloss> 
quippe<gloss id="s17g21" lang="en" n="question">Conceive of <foreign lang="la">quippe</foreign> as an adverb, meaning <gloss>indeed, in fact</gloss>.</gloss>
 quibus <gloss id="s17g22" lang="en" n="question">What is the probable nature of the <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign>-sentence, and what its construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g22">Adjectival, i.e., a characterizing sentence in subjunctive.</gloss>
<gloss id="s17g23" lang="en" n="question">What must be the underlying relation between the condition of affairs which we shall find expressed in the <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign>-sentence, and the condition of affairs expressed in the main sentence?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g23">Causal.</gloss>
<gloss id="s17g24" lang="en" n="question">What is the antecedent of <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g24">The people to whom the <foreign lang="la">magnitudo</foreign> belonged, the inhabitants of the town.</gloss>
<gloss id="s17g25" lang="en" n="question">Possible cases?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g25">Dat. or abl.</gloss>
<gloss id="s17g26" lang="en" n="question"><foreign lang="la">Quibus</foreign> indicates persons. How does that narrow the possibilities of an ablative construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g26">It can be only abl. absolute, or ablative dependent on a comparative or some word like <foreign lang="la">fretus</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">contentus</foreign>, or ablative of source with some word like <foreign lang="la">genitus, ortus, natus</foreign>.</gloss>
nec<gloss id="s17g27" lang="en" n="question">What is sure about <foreign lang="la">nec</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g27">That it balances a later <foreign lang="la">nec</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">et</foreign>.</gloss> 
 domi<gloss id="s17g28" lang="en" n="question">Construction?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g28">Locative.</gloss> 
 spes<gloss id="s17g29" lang="en" n="question">What must follow?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g29">Objective genitive or future infinitive.</gloss> 
prolis nec cum finitimis conubia  <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s17g30" lang="en" n="question">Complete the sentence by writing the proper form from the verb <foreign lang="la">sum</foreign>.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s17g30"><foreign lang="la">Essent</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s17g31" lang="en" n="question">Translate.</gloss>
</quote>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="18">
<head>Third exercise <bibl n="Liv. 1.24.2">(Livy 1.24.2)</bibl></head>

<p>[The Alban and Roman kings have proposed that
the war between the two peoples shall be settled by a battle between the
Horatii and Curiatii.]
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Nihil recusatur.  Tempus et locus convenit.  Priusquam<gloss id="s18g1" lang="en" n="question">What ideas may one have in mind when he writes <foreign lang="la">antequam</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">priusquam</foreign>, and by what mode will these ideas be respectively expressed?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g1">He may mean to give the idea of an act anticipated &mdash; i.e., looked forward to from the time of the act of the main clause &mdash; by some person mentioned in that sentence;  and he will express this by the idea-mode, the subjunctive.  Or he may mean to state the actual occurrence of an event, as a boundary point beyond which the main event took place;  and he will express this by the fact-mode, the indicative.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s18g2" lang="en" n="question">In the light of the situation, which of the two ideas is it more probable that Livy is going to express?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g2">The former.</gloss> 
dimicarent, foedus ictum<gloss id="s18g3" lang="en" n="question">Is anything sure yet about the case of <foreign lang="la">foedus</foreign>, or the part of speech of <foreign lang="la">ictum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g3">No.</gloss> 
 inter Romanos et Albanos est his<gloss id="s18g4" lang="en" n="question">What should be kept in mind as possibilities for all demonstrative pronominal words, like <foreign lang="la">is, hic, ille, ita</foreign>, etc.?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g4">That they look backward to something already mentioned, or forward to something which is yet to be mentioned.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s18g5" lang="en" n="question">Which is the case here?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g5">The latter.</gloss> 
 legibus<gloss id="s18g6" lang="en" n="question">What construction do you think is coming?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g6">A substantive final clause, telling what the <foreign lang="la">his legibus</foreign> were.</gloss> 
, ut cuius<gloss id="s18g7" lang="en" n="question">In general, what have we found to be the two possibilities when one meets the combination of <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> and the relative?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g7">Either (1) that <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> is the conjunction, and the <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign>-clause looks forward to an antecedent to be given laterin the <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>-clause;  or (2) that <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> is the adverb, the <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign> looking backward, and the relative statement forming a characterizing clause which stands in a causal relation to the main clause.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s18g8" lang="en" n="question">Bearing in mind <foreign lang="la">his legibus</foreign>, which of the two possible meanings of the combination <foreign lang="la">ut cuius</foreign> do you suppose to have been in Livy's mind in this particular case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g8">The former.</gloss> 
populi cives<gloss id="s18g9" lang="en" n="question">Probable meaning of case of <foreign lang="la">populi</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g9">Possessive, depending on <foreign lang="la">cives</foreign>.</gloss> 
 eo certamine vicissent<gloss id="s18g10" lang="en" n="question">Meaning of tense?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g10">Future perfect from a past point of view.</gloss>
is alteri<gloss id="s18g11" lang="en" n="question">Probable nature of combination?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g11">Subject and indirect object.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s18g12" lang="en" n="question">Differs how in meaning from <foreign lang="la">alius</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g12">Refers to the one other out of two, while <foreign lang="la">alius</foreign> means another out of any number.</gloss> 
 populo cum bona pace <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s18g13" lang="en" n="question">Surmise, if possible, what the final verb is;  and at any rate tell where it must be made.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s18g13">Imperfect subjunctive;  <foreign lang="la">imperaret</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">imperaret</foreign> is likely to be written rather than Livy's frequentative <foreign lang="la">imperitaret</foreign>;  but the word is admissible).</gloss> 
<gloss id="s18g14" lang="en" n="question">Translate.</gloss>
</quote>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="19">
<head>Fourth exercise <bibl n="Liv. 22.38.1">(Livy 22.38.1)</bibl></head>

<p>[The year following the defeat at the Trasumene
lake.  Dissatisfaction with the policy of Fabius.  The people
have carried the election of one consul, Varro, the nobility of the other,
Aemilius Paullus.  The two are about to march out for the summer campaign.]
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Contiones<gloss id="s19g1" lang="en" n="question">Possible meanings?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g1">Meeting, and speech made before a meeting.</gloss> 
 priusquam<gloss id="s19g2" lang="en" n="question">What meanings may follow, and by what constructions indicated?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g2">Action anticipated at the time of the main act, expressed by the subjunctive;  or actual event, back of which the main act lies, expressed by the indicative.</gloss> 
 ab urbe signa moverentur<gloss id="s19g3" lang="en" n="question">What was the special shade of meaning in <foreign lang="la">priusquam ... moverentur</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g3">That the <foreign lang="la">contiones</foreign> were held, or made, in anticipation of the expected marching.</gloss> 
 consulis<gloss id="s19g4" lang="en" n="question">What is it now clear that <foreign lang="la">contiones</foreign> means?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g4">Means speech, language.</gloss> 
 Varronis multae ac feroces fuere, denuntiantis<gloss id="s19g5" lang="en" n="question">Belongs with what?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g5"><foreign lang="la">Consulis</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s19g6" lang="en" n="question"><foreign lang="la">Denuntiare</foreign> means to make an announcement. How will the object be expressed if it is (a) a noun or pronoun? (b) a verb, conveying a statement of fact?  (c) a verb, conveying action desired?</gloss>  <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g6">(a&gt; Accusative.  (b) Infinitive.  (c) Substantive final clause.</gloss>
 bellum<gloss id="s19g7" lang="en" n="question">What construction occurs to you at once for <foreign lang="la">bellum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g7">Object of <foreign lang="la">denuntiare</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s19g8" lang="en" n="question">Is there any certainty that this is what Livy meant?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g8">No.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s19g9" lang="en" n="question">What else may Livy have in mind?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g9">A subject or an object for an infinitive depending on <foreign lang="la">denuntiantis</foreign>.</gloss> 
arcessitum<gloss id="s19g10" lang="en" n="question">What possibilities for <foreign lang="la">arcessitum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g10">Participle agreeing with <foreign lang="la">bellum</foreign>, or part of an infinitive perfect (with <foreign lang="la">esse</foreign> to come) or future (with <foreign lang="la">iri</foreign> to come) having <foreign lang="la">bellum</foreign> for its subject.</gloss> 
 in<gloss id="s19g11" lang="en" n="question">What case do you expect to find following, and why?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g11">Accusative, because <foreign lang="la">arcessitum</foreign> includes the idea of motion.</gloss> 
 Italiam ab nobilibus mansurumque<gloss id="s19g12" lang="en" n="question">What is the only thing that you know surely about <foreign lang="la">mansurum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g12">That its construction is the same as that of <foreign lang="la">arcessitum</foreign>.</gloss> 
 in<gloss id="s19g13" lang="en" n="question">What case do you expect to find following, and why?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g13">Ablative, because <foreign lang="la">mansurum</foreign> includes the idea of rest.</gloss> 
 visceribus reipublicae, si<gloss id="s19g14" lang="en" n="question">What indication have you of the probable nature of the condition, and how will it be expressed?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g14">It looks as if it were the condition for <foreign lang="la">mansurum</foreign>.  In that case it will be a future or future prefect from the past standpoint, expressed by the so-called imperfect or pluperfect subjunctive.</gloss> 
 plures Fabios imperatores haberet, se<gloss id="s19g15" lang="en" n="question">Probable construction of <foreign lang="la">bellum</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">arcessitum</foreign>, and grounds of your opinion?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g15"><foreign lang="la">Se</foreign> is acc. or abl.  It cannot be abl. absolute, since it refers to the subject of the sentence;  and it is probably not the ablative of source, for we are not likely to find a word meaning <gloss>born of</gloss> here.  It is therefore probably accusative.  In that case, <foreign lang="la">bellum</foreign> is either the subject or object of an active infinitive which we are to have, and of which <foreign lang="la">se</foreign> is object or subject.  <foreign lang="la">Arcessitum</foreign>, which is passive, is therefore not an infinitive, but a participle; and, besides that, <foreign lang="la">mansurum</foreign>, which is in the same construction with <foreign lang="la">arcessitum</foreign>, is not transitive.</gloss> 
quo die<gloss id="s19g16" lang="en" n="question">Where is the antecedent of <foreign lang="la">quo die</foreign>, and what do you know about it?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g16">Yet to come, and in some way connected with the coming infinitive which we have found to depend on <foreign lang="la">denuntiantis</foreign>.</gloss> 
 hostem vidisset<gloss id="s19g17" lang="en" n="question">Meaning of tense and mood?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g17">Future perfect from past point of view, in indirect discourse.</gloss> 
 perfecturum.<gloss id="s19g18" lang="en" n="question">What suspended constructions are now resolved?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s19g18"><foreign lang="la">Perfecturum</foreign> is infinitive, <foreign lang="la">se</foreign> is its subject, <foreign lang="la">bellum</foreign> its object, with attached participles <foreign lang="la">arcessitum</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">mansurum</foreign>, the latter having a future condition dependent upon it.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s19g19" lang="en" n="question">Translate.</gloss>
</quote>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="20">
<head>Fifth exercise <bibl n="Liv. 21.53.1">(Livy 21.53.1)</bibl></head>

<p>[The passage here used was employed in the address. 
It is given again in its place among the present set of papers, partly
to show that the minute questioning with which a teacher of an untrained
Freshman class must begin may give place early to a more rapid movement,
after the habit of watchfulness and a willingness to hold the mind in suspense
have been established.]
</p>
<p><quote lang="la">Hannibal cum quid<gloss id="s20g1" lang="en" n="question">What must be the construction of the verb of the <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign>-sentence, and why?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g1">Subjunctive of indirect question of fact, or of indirect deliberative question.</gloss> 
 optimum foret hoste cerneret, vix<gloss id="s20g2" lang="en" n="question">In such a connection, what would be the pronoun meaning any, and what the adjective?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g2"><foreign lang="la">Quisquam, ullus</foreign>.</gloss> 
 ullam spem<gloss id="s20g3" lang="en" n="question">What would be the completing construction (a) if nominal?<note anchored="yes">It would be a practical convenience if there were an adjective bearing the same relation to the words "noun" and "pronoun" that "verbal" bears to "verb."&nbsp; For my own use I have employed the adjective "nominal" in this sense.</note> (b) if verbal?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g3">(a) Genitive.  (b) Genitive of gerund or of gerundive, or future infinitive.</gloss> 
 habebat temere<gloss id="s20g4" lang="en" n="question">Does <foreign lang="la">temere</foreign>, judging by the order, probably modify <foreign lang="la">habebat</foreign>, or something yet to come?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g4">The latter.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s20g5" lang="en" n="question">Then what do you surmise about the completing construction for <foreign lang="la">spem</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g5">That it is a verbal construction.</gloss> 
 atque improvide  <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s20g6" lang="en" n="question">Write the neuter pronoun meaning <gloss>anything</gloss>, in nom. or acc. form.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g6"><foreign lang="la">Quicquam</foreign>.</gloss> 
consules<gloss id="s20g7" lang="en" n="question">General construction hereby indicated, and construction of <foreign lang="la">consules</foreign> and of the word you have just written?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g7">The verbal for <foreign lang="la">spem</foreign> is an infinitive, with <foreign lang="la">quicquam</foreign> for subject and <foreign lang="la">consules</foreign> for object, or vice versa.</gloss> 
 <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s20g8" lang="en" n="question">Write the infinitive, meaning <gloss>to do</gloss>.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g8"><foreign lang="la">Acturos</foreign>.</gloss> 
cum alterius ingenium, fama<gloss id="s20g9" lang="en" n="question">Case?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g9">Nom. or abl.</gloss> 
 prius deinde re<gloss id="s20g10" lang="en" n="question">Case of <foreign lang="la">fama</foreign>, and proof.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g10">Abl., because the phrase <foreign lang="la">prius deinde</foreign> makes it parallel with <foreign lang="la">re</foreign>.</gloss> 
 cognitum, percitum ac ferox sciret  <seg type="cloze">---</seg>, <gloss id="s20g11" lang="en" n="question">Write verb required to complete the clause.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g11"><foreign lang="la">Esse</foreign>.</gloss>
ferociusque factum prospero cum praedatoribus<gloss id="s20g12" lang="en" n="question">What is indicated by a combination like <foreign lang="la">prospero cum praedatoribus</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s20g12">That <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> connects with <foreign lang="la">praedatoribus</foreign> a noun, yet to come, to which <foreign lang="la">prospero</foreign> belongs.</gloss> 
 suis certamine crederet, adesse gerendae rei fortunam haud diffidebat.<gloss id="s20g13" lang="en" n="question">Translate.</gloss>
</quote>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="21">
<head>Sixth exercise <bibl n="Liv. 22.40.1">(Livy 22.40.1)</bibl></head>

<p><quote lang="la">Adversus<gloss id="s21g1" lang="en" n="question">What part of speech is <foreign lang="la">adversus</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g1">Participle or preposition.</gloss> 
 ea<gloss id="s21g2" lang="en" n="question">What is possible for <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g2">Object of preposition <foreign lang="la">adversus</foreign>, or agreeing with an abl. sing. or acc. pl.</gloss> 
 oratio<gloss id="s21g3" lang="en" n="question">What do you know now about <foreign lang="la">adversus</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign>, and how?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g3"><foreign lang="la">Oratio</foreign> is nom. fem., so that <foreign lang="la">adversus</foreign> is not participle, but preposition, <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign> being its object.</gloss> 
 consulis haud sane laeta fuit, magis fatentis<gloss id="s21g4" lang="en" n="question">Construction to follow (a) if nominal?  (b) if verbal?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g4">(a) Accusative. (b) Infinitive statement in indirect discourse.</gloss> 
 ea<gloss id="s21g5" lang="en" n="question">Possible constructions?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g5">Object of <foreign lang="la">fatentis</foreign>, or subject or predicate of an infinitive depending on it.</gloss> 
 quae diceret vera quam facilia <seg type="cloze">---</seg> <gloss id="s21g6" lang="en" n="question">Write Latin for <gloss>to do</gloss>, completing the idea of <foreign lang="la">facilia</foreign>.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g6"><foreign lang="la">Factu</foreign>.</gloss> 
 <seg type="cloze">---</seg><gloss id="s21g7" lang="en" n="question">Write in Latin whatever is still necessary to complete the sentence.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g7"><foreign lang="la">Esse</foreign>.</gloss> 
dictatori magistrum<gloss id="s21g8" lang="en" n="question">Meaning of the position of <foreign lang="la">dictatori</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">magistrum</foreign>?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g8">Sharp contrast.</gloss>
<gloss id="s21g9" lang="en" n="question">Probable general construction of sentence?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g9">Indirect statement, in the infinitive, <foreign lang="la">magistrum</foreign> being its subject, and <foreign lang="la">dictatori</foreign> being the indirect object of the infinitive, or of a predicate adjective.</gloss>
 equitum intolerabilem fuisse;  quid<gloss id="s21g10" lang="en" n="question">In the present construction, what modes possible after <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign>, and with what meanings respectively?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g10">Subjunctive of indirect question, either deliberative or seriously asking for information, or infinitive, in rhetorical question practically amounting to an assertion.<note anchored="yes">It is of course unadvisable, for class-work of this sort, to cover at the beginning all the possibilities of the indirect interrogative sentence.&nbsp; I have given such of them as are easily grasped and are most important.</note></gloss> 
<gloss id="s21g11" lang="en" n="question">If a partitive genitive is to follow, in what part of the clause have we learned that we are likely to find it?</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g11">As far removed from the word on which it depends as the other points of style will allow.</gloss> 
 consuli adversus collegam seditissum ac temerarium verium atque auctoritatis  <seg type="cloze">---</seg>? <gloss id="s21g12" lang="en" n="question">Decide, in the light of the whole passage, what kind of a sentence this necessarily is, and write the Latin for <gloss>would there be</gloss>.</gloss> <gloss lang="en" n="answer" target="s21g12"><foreign lang="la">Fore</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">futurum esse</foreign>.</gloss> 
<gloss id="s21g13" lang="en" n="question">Translate.</gloss>
</quote>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="22">
<head>Application of the Method in Preparatory Work</head>

<p>It will be convenient
to refer, in these suggestions, to some one of the books commonly employed
by beginners in Latin;  e.g. Dr. Leighton's "First Steps in
Latin."  The application can of course be made with ease to any other
book of the same scope.
</p>
<p>First and most important is it that the beginner should accustom himself
<emph>from the very outset</emph> to the sound of the Roman
language.  In Lesson XIII, e.g., the learner, having prepared
himself upon the sentences <foreign lang="la">regina laudat</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">scribae portant</foreign>,
<foreign lang="la">puellae laudant</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">laudas</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">laudamus</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">reginae donant</foreign>,
etc., should not open his book to translate them.  <emph>His
book should be closed</emph>, and he should give the meaning of <foreign lang="la">regina
laudat</foreign>, etc., as his teacher delivers the sentence to him.  To
translate <foreign lang="la">regina laudat</foreign> <emph>at hearing</emph>,
after having studied it, <emph>is not beyond the mental
power of the modern boy</emph>.  Neither is it beyond his power,
with possibly a trifle of patience on the part of his teacher, to translate
at hearing a new sentence of the same scope, e.g. <foreign lang="la">laudo</foreign>; 
<foreign lang="la">scriba laudat</foreign>;  <foreign lang="la">scriba donat</foreign>;  <foreign lang="la">scribae donant</foreign>. 
But if this is true, a very important truth at once follows.  There
is, it will be admitted, no greater jump in any first Latin book than that
from nothing at all to the first lesson in Latin sentences of one and two
words.  If, in taking that step, the boy can successfully prepare
himself to translate the set lesson at hearing, and to translate in the
same way new sentences of the same vocabulary and the same scope, then
<emph>he can prepare himself</emph>, as he progresses
by carefully graded steps, in any of the books in common use, <emph>to
translate any previously studied Latin at hearing, and to translate at
hearing any new sentences of the same scope, framed for him by the invention
of his teacher</emph>.  Before the book is opened by any one but
the teacher, the exercises of the class-room should be 
<list type="simple">
<item>(1) the translation at hearing of the review, </item>
<item>(2) the translation at hearing of the advance, and </item>
<item>(3) the translation at hearing of new sentences of the same scope.</item>
</list>  And no one will venture to say that a boy who had been carried in this way
through an introductory book would not begin Caesar as a better Latinist
than a boy who had not been so started.
</p>
<p>In Lesson XIII, as we have seen, the boy has learned that the subject
of a verb is expressed by the nominative.  In the next lesson he is
told that the direct object of a transitive verb is expressed by the accusative. 
For the present, that is the sum total of his knowledge about accusatives. 
Of course the teacher will narrow his own knowledge to his pupil's horizon. 
Accordingly, he will start upon a sentence beginning with an accusative,
e.g. <foreign lang="la">scribas</foreign>, and ask the learner what, without hearing the rest
of the sentence, he learns from the case, with regard to the relation of
the <gloss>clerks</gloss> to the rest of the sentence;  in a word, what the
<emph>meaning</emph> of the case is.  The boy will answer "object of
the verb," and the teacher will accept the answer.  Then he will
give the beginning of another sentence, containing a nominative and an
accusative, say <foreign lang="la">regina scribam</foreign>, and ask the learner what the two
cases mean to him.  The learner will answer "subject" and "object." 
The teacher will then give a number of combinations of subject and object,
e.g. <foreign lang="la">scriba puellam</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">nauta agricolam</foreign>, employing the full
vocabulary provided in the lesson.  Then, retracing his steps, he
will give complete sentences of which the combinations just used may be
supposed to be the beginning, repeating each of these combinations in connection
with as many as possible of the various verbs provided;  e.g. 
<foreign lang="la">regina scribam laudat</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">regina scribam vocat</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">regina scribam
exspectat</foreign>.  Then another combination, e.g. <foreign lang="la">scriba puellam</foreign>,
should similarly be repeated with various verbs.  In all this, the
Latin should be given deliberately,<note anchored="yes">The teacher who uses the Roman method should
be fastidious in his pronunciation, for his own example will tell far more
than precept.&nbsp; Now that every method-book has every syllable marked,
there is no possible justification for incorrectness.&nbsp; Yet many teachers,
coming to <foreign lang="la">r&ecirc;gina</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">am&icirc;citiam</foreign> in Lesson XIV,
will pronounce them <foreign lang="la">reg&icirc;na</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">amicitiam</foreign>;&nbsp; not a
few will read <foreign lang="la">vocant</foreign> as <foreign lang="la">v&ocirc;cant</foreign>;&nbsp; and, I sadly
fear, nearly all, while teaching their students that final <foreign lang="la">-a</foreign> is
long in the ablative and short in the nominative, etc., will pronounce
<foreign lang="la">f&acirc;ma</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">f&acirc;m&acirc;</foreign> precisely alike, namely as
ablative, &mdash; though the sound of short final <emph>-a</emph> is very well represented
to us in English in such familiar words as "California," "Nevada,"
"Cuba".</note>
so that the pupil may be able to form his mental pictures easily, as he
hears one word after another.  He should be urged, too, to form these
pictures <emph>without thinking of the English word</emph>. 
The word <foreign lang="la">regina</foreign> should bring a <foreign lang="la">regina</foreign> before his mental vision,
instead of bringing, first the <emph>word</emph> "queen," and then a mental
vision of a queen.<note anchored="yes">I find teachers to be sceptical about the
possibility of doing this.&nbsp; But it is not even difficult, if the young
student begins rightly and is rightly helped throughout.&nbsp; The apparent
difficulty goes back to the false habits of mind produced by making translation
the constant method of getting at the meaning of the author, and, so to
speak, the ultimate end of study;&nbsp; whereas <emph>the
true end of study, precisely as in the case of modern languages, is to
get the power to read the original</emph>.&nbsp; It is to be feared, even,
that, in the pressure produced by the long hours of their working day,
many teachers in the preparatory schools do not themselves read the authors
they teach, but only make preparations to correct the students' translations
at the recitations.&nbsp; If they would devote five minutes a day to reading
their Caesar, Virgil, and Cicero aloud, as before an imaginary audience,
and five minutes more to doing the same thing before a real audience in
their class-room, they would find their faith to grow apace.</note>
</p>
<p>In these exercises <emph>there should be no translation
into English</emph> (it will be remembered that the Latin of the review
and the Latin of the advance have already been translated at hearing). 
Next should come an exercise like the following:</p>
<p>"How, in Latin, can you present to my mind a queen as acting upon somebody?"  </p>
<p>"By saying <foreign lang="la">regina</foreign>."</p>
<p>"How a girl as being acted upon?" </p>
<p>"By saying <foreign lang="la">puellam</foreign>."</p>
<p>"How a clerk?"</p>
<p>"By saying <foreign lang="la">scribam</foreign>."</p>
<p>"How a letter?"</p>
<p>"By saying <foreign lang="la">epistulam</foreign>." </p>
<p>"Now put before me a queen as acting, and a girl as being acted upon." </p>
<p><foreign lang="la">Regina puellam</foreign>.</p>
<p>"A farmer as acting, and a sailor as being acted upon."</p>
<p><foreign lang="la">Agricola nautam</foreign>.</p>
<p>After a number of these combinations have been given, "Now tell me in Latin that the queen is waiting
for the clerk," then "that the queen is waiting for the letter," etc.,
etc.  Variations of the tense of the verb should also be employed. 
I must confine myself, however, to showing the method of dealing with the cases.
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="23">
<p>In the next lesson, XVI, the pupil will learn one of the simple uses
of the genitive.  He should then be asked what the cases tell him
in <foreign lang="la">liber pueri</foreign> (being made, of course, to see that, though <foreign lang="la">pueri</foreign>
might be nom. pl. so far as form goes, it cannot be so here, since <foreign lang="la">liber</foreign>
must be subject), in <foreign lang="la">magister reginae filiam</foreign>, etc.;  and should
then be carried through various exercises similar to those suggested in
connection with the previous lesson.  He will also learn in Lesson
XVI about apposition, of which more anon.  In Lesson XVII he will
learn about the way of expressing the indirect object of a verb, and should
now be asked what the cases mean in combinations like <foreign lang="la">agricolae nautis
viam</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">nauta agricolis viam</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">scriba puero librum</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">scriba
pueris reginae libros</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">agricola puero scribae viam</foreign>, etc.; 
and should then have whole sentences given him, and English combinations
and sentences to be put into Latin, as already described.
</p>
<p>So constructions are taught one after another, the simplest meaning
of each case being alone given when the case is first dealt with. 
Later, other uses of these same cases are taught, and the certainty which
the pupil at first felt in regard to the speaker's meaning when he heard
a given case (say the accusative) now passes away.  As early as Lesson
XVI he learned, as we saw, that "a noun used to describe another noun or
pronoun, and meaning the same thing, is put in the same case."  At
this point, consequently, he recognizes that there is a double possibility
for a given accusative.  Supposing us to take up a sentence beginning
(say) with <foreign lang="la">legatum</foreign>, the accusative word may turn out to be either
of two things, namely, the <emph>object</emph> of the verb, or in <emph>apposition</emph>
to the object of the verb.  These two possibilities, and these alone,
should, for a number of weeks, flash through the beginner's mind at sight
or hearing of an accusative.  Later, however (Lessons LI and LII),
he will find that certain verbs are of such a nature as to take <emph>two
objects</emph>, and will have specimens given him.  At this point an
accusative has for him <emph>three</emph> possibilities:  it may be, to
the speaker's thought, <emph>object</emph>, it may be <emph>second object</emph>, or
it may be an <emph>appositive</emph>;  while if the meaning of the words
is such as to exclude all possibility of the last of these, as, e.g., in
a sentence beginning with <foreign lang="la">me fraudem</foreign>, the meaning of the combination
is seen at once to be that <foreign lang="la">me</foreign> is the first object, and <foreign lang="la">fraudem</foreign>
the second object, of some one of the verbs that need two objects to complete
their thought, e.g. <foreign lang="la">celo</foreign>.  Not long afterward, he will learn
(Lesson LXI) about the accusative of <emph>duration of time</emph> and <emph>extent
of space</emph>, and he now must recognize still another possibility for any
accusatives like <foreign lang="la">annos</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">pedes</foreign>, but not for a word like
<foreign lang="la">Caesarem</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">me</foreign>.  Still later, he will add to his repertory
an understanding of the <emph>cognate accusative</emph>, of the <emph>accusative
as subject of an infinitive</emph>, etc.
</p>
<p>The teacher will keep clearly before the learner's mind that, while
any accusative may be a direct object, or the subject or predicate of an
infinitive, only words of a particular meaning can be used in the expression
of duration of time, etc., and only words of another and an equally particular
meaning can play the part of a cognate accusative, etc.  The teacher
would do well to make for himself, as the book progressed, a collection
of short sentences illustrating all the possible kinds of accusatives (as
yet known to the pupil) in which a given word, like <foreign lang="la">Caesarem</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">annos</foreign>,
<foreign lang="la">vitam</foreign>, may occur (and, of course, similar collections for the other
cases);  and to run through one of these collections frequently, perhaps
daily, with the class, using no English.  Throughout this progress,
it will be noted, <emph>nothing has been allowed to
lapse</emph>.  The way described of looking at all the possible
meanings of (say) an accusative, seen or heard, constitutes a continual
review of the sharpest nature, and, furthermore, of that very persuasive
and pressing kind which looks toward immediate and constant practical use.
</p>
<p>Following these methods, the pupil will surely, if the exercises of
translating at hearing and understanding at hearing without translating
are kept up, have obtained, by the time he reaches the end of the book,
the power to catch the force of the accusative constructions, in short
and simple sentences, with correctness and <emph>without conscious operations
of reasoning</emph>.  For his very familiarity with all the possibilities
of accusative constructions for words of one and another meaning will have
brought him into a condition in which, on the one side, he will <emph>WAIT,
OPEN-MINDED</emph>, for the word or words that shall determine which meaning
the speaker had in his own thought (if, as mostly, those words are yet
to come);  and, on the other, will, by a tact now grown unconscious,
<emph>INSTINCTIVELY APPREHEND</emph>, when the determining
word or words arrive, what that meaning was;  in short, he will have
made a good beginning of understanding the Roman language as it was understood
by Roman hearers and Roman readers.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="24">
<p>The sketch here given for the treatment of the accusative constructions
suggests the way in which any set of constructions should be managed. 
I append a few specimens of the results for this and that class of words
in a number of cases.  I grant that the enumeration for the ablative,
and even for the genitive, is of provoking sweep;  but this is only
equivalent to saying that the number of meanings of the ablative and genitive
cases which a young student must learn, under whatsoever method, is great.
</p>
<p>The genitive of any pronoun may be found to mean the <gloss>possessor</gloss>
of some thing or of some activity (the activity being expressed in a verbal
noun), or the <gloss>object</gloss> of some activity (expressed in a noun, an adjective,
or some one of a certain list of verbs), or the <gloss>whole</gloss> of which some
other word expresses a part, &mdash; may be, then, either <gloss>subjective</gloss>,
or <gloss>objective</gloss>, or <gloss>partitive</gloss>;  or it may simply belong
to some noun, just as an adjective does.  The genitive of any noun
(say <foreign lang="la">civitatis</foreign>) may prove to be either <gloss>subjective</gloss>, or <gloss>objective</gloss>,
or <gloss>partitive</gloss>, or in <gloss>apposition</gloss> with some other genitive. 
The genitive of a noun like <foreign lang="la">periculi</foreign> may prove to be either <gloss>appositive</gloss>,
or <gloss>subjective</gloss>, or <gloss>objective</gloss>, or <gloss>partitive</gloss>, or (if
modified by a noun or participle) <gloss>qualitative</gloss>.  The genitive
of a noun indicating an <gloss>act or mental state of a bad nature</gloss> may
be either <gloss>appositive</gloss>, or <gloss>subjective</gloss>, or <gloss>objective</gloss>,
including <gloss>a crime charged</gloss> or <gloss>a penalty adjudged</gloss>, or may be
<gloss>partitive</gloss>.  A genitive <foreign lang="la">magni</foreign> may agree with a noun,
or may mean the <gloss>value</gloss> of something.
</p>
<p>The dative of any word may mean <gloss>the person or thing indirectly concerned
in an act or state</gloss> expressed by a noun or an adjective or a group of
words.  The dative of the name of a person (say <foreign lang="la">Caesari</foreign>) may
have this general meaning, or, in one or another special phase of it, may
mean <gloss>the person concerned in an obligation</gloss> indicated by a gerundive
(the agent), or the <gloss>possessor</gloss> of something.  The dative of
a word like <foreign lang="la">dolori</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">laudi</foreign>, etc., may mean, in a general way,
<gloss>the thing indirectly concerned</gloss>, or, with a special phase of that
idea, may mean <gloss>the end served</gloss>.
</p>
<p>The accusative we have discussed already.  The vocative takes care
of itself, when the form is unmistakable.
</p>
<p><emph>The ablative is a case to be dreaded</emph>. 
In general, it should, like other cases, be cut up as little as possible. 
Something can be done by proceeding from the three ideas of the <gloss>starting-point</gloss>,
the <gloss>means</gloss>, and the <gloss>place</gloss> (<gloss>true ablative</gloss>, <gloss>instrumental</gloss>,
and <gloss>locative</gloss>), as in Dr. Leighton's table on p. 290, and the table
on p. 254 of the Allen &amp; Greenough Grammar;  but  the best
intentions on the part of grammarians and teachers have not yet made the
matter easy for the learner.  The suggestions to be given here must
go beyond these three divisions.
</p>
<p>Nearly all ablatives can be <gloss>absolute</gloss>, or can <gloss>depend upon a
comparative</gloss>, or on a word like <foreign lang="la">dignus</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">contentus</foreign>. 
Beside this, a proper name (say <foreign lang="la">Caesare</foreign>) may be in the ablative
of source, after some word like <foreign lang="la">genitus</foreign>, though such a form of expression
is naturally rare in the prose read before going to college.  Of course
such a word cannot be in the ablative of <gloss>means</gloss> (in the narrower
sense), or of <gloss>specification</gloss>, or of <gloss>time</gloss>, or of <gloss>degree
of difference</gloss>.  A word like <foreign lang="la">die</foreign>, however, beside the general
possibilities, may indicate <gloss>time</gloss>, or the <gloss>degree of difference</gloss>,
a word like <foreign lang="la">auro</foreign> <gloss>means</gloss> or <gloss>price</gloss>, a word like <foreign lang="la">capite</foreign>
<gloss>description</gloss>, etc.  I shall not attempt here a complete list
of suggestions.  In general, in spite of the complexity of the uses
of the ablative, the learner is less likely to go badly astray in dealing
with this case in actual practice than in dealing with the genitive or
the accusative.
</p>
<p>One point not yet touched upon is of the gravest consequence. 
when a form occurs which may be in either of two cases, or even possibly
in any one of three or four cases, <emph>the pupil should
not allow himself to suppose that he knows the case</emph>, even if a probability
presents itself at once.  E.g., a student reading in <bibl n="Caes. Gal. 1.3">B.G.1.3</bibl>, and
passing by <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">his rebus adducti et auctoritate Orgetorigis permoti
constituerunt ea, quae</foreign>, etc.), may easily suppose <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign> to be the
object of <foreign lang="la">constituerunt</foreign>, instead of waiting until conviction of
some kind is forced upon him by the remainder of the sentence;  which
conviction will prove to be that <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign> was the object, not of <foreign lang="la">constituerunt</foreign>,
but of an infinitive which is not reached until the <foreign lang="la">quae</foreign>-clause
is finished.  The direction to the student should be:  <emph>Have
your eyes open, but keep in doubt as long as possible</emph>;  in a word,
<emph>THINK</emph>, and <emph>WAIT</emph>.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="25">
<p>Verbal constructions should be dealt with in a similar way.  The
possibilities after conjunctions should, in particular, be entirely familiar. 
Given a <foreign lang="la">quamquam</foreign> or a <foreign lang="la">quamvis</foreign>, the student should be able
to tell instantly what is coming.  Given an <foreign lang="la">antequam</foreign>, he should
know precisely what the two ideas are, either one of which may possibly
be in the speaker's mind, and by what mode each was expressed by the Romans. 
Given an <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>, he should know the full range of ideas possible for
the speaker to have when he so begins a clause, and by what construction
each of these ideas is expressed.  And in particular it will be found
useful to set before the class the whole range of verbal constructions
that are capable of serving as the object or the subject or a verb (substantive
clauses), and to ask them which and how many of these a given verb or phrase
may take.  These substantive clauses are as follows: &mdash;

<list type="simple">
<item>The indirect statement of fact (infinitive).</item>
<item>The indirect question of fact.</item>
<item>The indirect deliberative question.</item>
<item>The final clause.</item>
<item>The consecutive clause.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Now give the class a verb, <foreign lang="la">dicit</foreign>, and ask what possible completing
verbal ideas there may be, and what phase of meaning one and another of
these would indicate for the word <foreign lang="la">dicit</foreign> itself.  The answer
should be:  <gloss>the infinitive</gloss>, if dicit means that a statement
is made;  <gloss>the subjunctive introduced by an interrogative</gloss> (including
of course <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>), if <foreign lang="la">dicit</foreign> means the giving of an answer to
a question of fact or a deliberate question;  <gloss>the subjunctive with
<foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">ne</foreign></gloss>, if <foreign lang="la">dicit</foreign> means the giving of a direction. 
The substantive consecutive clause, it is, of course, impossible for <foreign lang="la">dicit</foreign>
to take.  On the other hand, the meaning of a word like <foreign lang="la">effecit</foreign>
is such that it can take the substantive consecutive clause and can take
no other;  so that, unless we find a clear accusative object, we are
sure, upon meeting an <foreign lang="la">efficit</foreign>, that a verbal object introduced by
<foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">ut non</foreign> is sooner or later to come.  A verb like
<foreign lang="la">peto</foreign> can take only a substantive final clause, a verb like <foreign lang="la">quaero</foreign>
only an interrogative substantive clause (either a question of fact, or
a deliberative question), etc.  To look at these matters in this particular
way is of <emph>great usefulness</emph>.  If, for
example, the clas is translating at hearing, in <bibl n="Cic. Sen. 63">Cat. Mai. 63</bibl>, the
anecdote beginning <foreign lang="la">quin etiam memoriae proditum est</foreign>, everybody should
at this point instantly recognize that an infinitive of statement is sooner
or later inevitable, and, knowing the Latin habit of arrangement, should
at once associate with that impending infinitive statement all the intervening
matter, <foreign lang="la">cum Athenis ludis quidam in theatrum</foreign>, etc.  The same
thing is seen, with a much briefer suspense, in Caesar's <cit><quote lang="la">id si fieret,
intellegebat magno periculo, etc.,</quote> <bibl n="Caes. Gal. 1.10">B.G. 1.10.2.</bibl></cit>

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="26">
<p>Most of the things thus far mentioned will be familiar to the student
before he leaves his introductory book and begins Caesar.  At this
point, he takes up sentences more complex, and yet in the main containing
no new principles.  His teacher can now do him a great service by
<emph>reading aloud both familiar and new sentences, in
such a way as to throw the parts into masses</emph>;  and by teaching
the student to do the same in what he has already read.  E.g., in
<bibl n="Caes. Gal. 1.8">B.G. 1.8</bibl>, the words <quote lang="la">ea legione quam secum habebat</quote> form one idea
and should be given without separation;  the words <quote lang="la">militibusque
qui ex provincia convenerant</quote> form another, connected, after a slight
pause, with the former group;  the sentence <foreign lang="la">qui fines Sequanorum
ab Helvetiis dividit</foreign> should be delivered as a single mass, and in such
a manner as to show that it is a piece of parenthetical explanation. 
In this way, the teacher can make his hearers feel that this longish sentence
of five lines, with its verb held up to the last place, is really <emph>entirely
simple</emph>.  He should also call attention to the very common pointings-forward
to an explanatory sentence, which are effected by pronouns and pronominal
adverbs, as, e.g., in <foreign lang="la">id</foreign> in <bibl n="Caes. Gal. 1.31">1.31.2</bibl> (<foreign lang="la">non minus se id contendere</foreign>)
which, as the meaning of <foreign lang="la">contendere</foreign> tells us, must be explained
to us later in a substantive purpose clause;  as in <foreign lang="la">hoc</foreign> in
<bibl n="Caes. Gal. 1.32">1.32.4</bibl> (<foreign lang="la">respondit hoc esse miseriorem et graviorem fortunam</foreign>), which
must be explained later either by a <foreign lang="la">quo</foreign> in a sentence containing
another comparative, or by a <foreign lang="la">quod</foreign>-sentence containing a statement
of fact;  as in <foreign lang="la">haec</foreign> in <cit><bibl n="Caes. Gal. 1.40">1.40.11</bibl> <quote lang="la">(haec sibi esse curae)</quote></cit>,
which must be explained by a substantive final clause, or by an infinitive; 
as in an <foreign lang="la">ita</foreign>, looking forward to an <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>- or <foreign lang="la">si</foreign>-clause,
or an infinitive;  etc., etc.
</p>
<p>The teacher will all the while know very well what things his class
is familiar with, and what it is not familiar with, and will accordingly
drop questions upon the former and continue them upon the latter. 
But up to the very end, there should be stated exercises in translation
at hearing, say once a week, with careful questions upon points critical
for the apprehension of the meaning;  the passages themselves to be
committed to memory later.  This is the most effective engine of the
method, &mdash; the surest way of developing and keeping up the habits of watchfulness
and of willingness to wait.

</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="27">
<p>And now a brief <emph>summary of suggestions</emph>, in which I will address myself directly to the teacher.
</p>
<p>At the outset, make the student feel that the Latin language was once
<emph>an every-day tongue</emph> of men, women, and children;  a tongue
in which people not only wrote books, but dined, and played tennis; 
a language <emph>spoken</emph>, and <emph>understood
as spoken</emph>.  Direct him, therefore, to aim to associate meaning
with the sound of the word, not merely with groups of letters on a page. 
Tell him, as he commits his vocabulary to memory, to lift his eye from
the printed word, and repeat again and again, in imagination, the spoken
word, so that when he hears it from his teacher, he will feel its force
immediately.
</p>
<p>Throughout the introductory lesson-book, conduct the translation of
the review and of the advance at hearing, and, in the same way, have the
student, his book being closed, <emph>put the printed English
sentences into Latin</emph> as you deliver them to him.  If you do
this from the first, he will be able, by the time the lesson-book is finished,
to express a sentence of considerable length in Latin, grasping it as a
whole, instead of turning one word into Latin, and then another, and so
on, in piecemeal fashion.
</p>
<p>If you can get time for preparation, aim at <emph>repetition</emph>,
making for your own use, in connection with each lesson in the book, a
group of sentences which, employing the vocabulary already acquired, shall
proceed from change to change with but a slight difference each time. 
A simple example of what I mean may be recalled from pp. 25-26.<note anchored="yes">I question whether it would not be better
to use a smaller vocabulary in the first few lessons than some of the books
employ, aiming rather, by the varied repetition of a comparatively few
words in the simple constructions of subject, direct object, indirect object,
and predicate, at giving the student a real facility in the grasping of
meanings and the conveying of meanings through inflections.&nbsp; It is
hard for the young mind to get this facility when dealing with things so
new if it is encumbered at the same time with having to handle a large
vocabulary.</note>
In this matter, &mdash; the insisting upon the value of repetition, &mdash; the Sauveur
method is quite right.
</p>
<p>As the student learns one new use after another, say of the accusative,
help him to get a clear and practically serviceable idea of the possibilities
of range of one and another kind of word, as <foreign lang="la">Caesarem, mille passuum,
annum, multum</foreign>.
</p>
<p>In a similar way, help him to classify ideas that are expressed by verbal
constructions, especially in subordinate clauses.  Let him, for example,
know with perfect familiarity what two kinds of adversative ideas exist
in the nature of things, and by what mode these are respectively expressed
in Latin (of the period which he is dealing with), and with what introductory
particles.  Let him know familiarly what two ideas one may have in
mind in using an <foreign lang="la">antequam</foreign>-construction, a <foreign lang="la">dum</foreign>-construction,
and so on, and how these ideas are expressed.
</p>
<p>By the time he has finished the introductory book, he will in this way
have made the <emph>intelligent</emph> acquaintance of
very nearly all the constructions of the language, and should have them
all in working order, like familiar tools.
</p>
<p>When you come to Caesar, do not let your class make the first plunge
alone, but for a number of days carry them through the advance yourself,
avoiding translation on your own part as far as possible, reading the Latin
to them in your very best and most helpful manner, and pointing out order
and construction.  Throughout the Caesar and Cicero (I should say
precisely the same thing of the <title>Anabasis</title>) have the review of each
day prepared to be translated at hearing.  Encourage your students
to learn to deliver the Latin well by appointing a promising reader, from
time to time, to prepare himself in advance to read the review to the class
in your stead.  Let him stand at your side with his eye upon his fellow-students; 
and as he finishes a sentence, or such part of a sentence as shall be best
to give in a lump, do you yourself name the student who shall translate.
</p>
<p>Be sure that you constantly treat constructions as <emph>means of expressing
certain ideas</emph>, not as mere exemplifications of rules.  And, to
enforce this view, as well as for many other reasons, watch constantly
the development of ideas in dealing with sentences which your students
have not seen before, and, in your questioning for written answers, or
for <foreign lang="la">viva voce</foreign> answers, call attention to point after point in the
gradual unfolding of the meaning, demanding all the time what I have elsewhere
called "anticipatory parsing."  And have a good deal of memorizing and reciting of these selected passages.
</p>
<p>Aim to go a little beyond the lesson every day, having your class read
on, not at sight, but at hearing, this additional ground being understood
to form a part of the review at the next meeting.
</p>
<p>The disadvantage of reading on at sight is twofold.  The student
is too apt to look ahead while some one else is up, preparing himself to
make a good showing if he is called upon.  And even if he does not
do this, he is too ready to run his eye to and fro in the sentence, not
really accepting the Latin order, but doing a more or less clever piece
of patchwork.  It often happens to me, in dealing with students who
have been well practised in sight-reading before coming to the University,
to read aloud a sentence containing only familiar words, every one of which
they catch as it is delivered, yet fail to get any meaning from the sentence
as a whole;  and I commonly find that, if I will at once put the sentence
in the very same words, but in the English order, they will comprehend
it instantly and without difficulty.  That experience proves that
one may do a deal of sight-reading, yet never come to know the Latin order
in any practical way.<note anchored="yes">Here lies the answer to the question, What
is the good of going through the extra difficulty of understanding Latin
without seeing it, when all that we aim at is to be able to read the printed
page?&nbsp; Without saying anything about the greater sense of reality,
and the greater interest which this way of dealing with the language brings
with it, one might make the matter clear by supposing the case to be reversed.&nbsp;
If English were a dead language, and Roman boys were learning to read it
under Roman teachers who had mastered it, it would obviously be a very
slow proceeding to pick it all to pieces and rearrange it into the Roman
order as a means of understanding it.&nbsp; The most courteous ghost among
us would laugh in the teacher's face if he were to visit a Roman schoolroom
and find that sort of thing going on;&nbsp; just as undoubtedly the most
courteous of Roman ghosts must laugh &mdash; unless, perhaps, his sense of grief
over the waste of opportunity gets the better of his sense of humor &mdash; if
ever he visits a modern schoolroom when a class is reading an oration of
his great countryman.&nbsp; Just as he would surely say to us that this
was precisely the way never to learn to read Latin, so our English-speaking
ghost would beg the teacher to give all that business up, and to use some
means to make it absolutely inevitable that the student should accept our
English order of expression, to the end that he might really learn to read
the language;&nbsp; and this means would necessarily be the trying to understand
at hearing, first sentences of graded difficulty, then continuous passages
of the literature.</note>
</p>
<p>Finally, <emph>no day should pass without composition</emph>. 
The writing of Latin is one of the most dreary of intellectual occupations,
or one of the most delightful.  Pretty uniformly it is the former
for a boy who has not written a Latin sentence from the time he finished
his elementary book and began his Caesar till, only a few months before
going to college, he took up his special book in composition for the bare
purpose of preparing for the examination in that subject.  <emph>The
object of writing Latin</emph> in the preparatory schools is not to get one's
self ready to pass an examination, but <emph>to get one's self ready to read
Latin</emph>;  and if that aim be intelligently pursued, the examination
in writing Latin will take care of itself.  The pursuit, however,
should be incessant.  Every day a number of sentences based upon the
author in use at the time should be written by various members of the class,
sent to the board for the purpose.  Time can easily be obtained by
having the writing going on while the class is reciting upon the review; 
after which, corrections should be called for from the class in general.
</p>
<p>Throughout the work of the preparatory school, the teacher should insist
upon it that what the pupil is primarily aiming at is to learn to read
in a great literature, with as slight a barrier as possible between him
and his author;  and he should make himself regard cases, modes, and
tenses, and make his students regard them, as <emph>keys to the literature</emph>,
as <emph>direct conveyors of thought from mind to mind</emph>.  How the
last may most effectively and rapidly be done, I have tried to show. 
This is all that strictly falls within the scope of the present pamphlet. 
But I cannot forbear to add that the teacher who is conducting a class
through Caesar, or Cicero, or Virgil, should never lose sight of the fact
that his work is not wholly preparatory, &mdash; that <emph>he
is already dealing with a great literature</emph>.  The more he
can make his students see that it is a great literature, through the virtue
of his own enjoyment of it, and, in particular, through the power with
which he can read it to them in the Latin, and the power with which he
can train them to read it themselves, the easier will be his task, and
the richer its palpable rewards;  and the greater will be his contribution
to the sum total of the classical education.
</p>
<p>This brings us to the university, with its manifold aims, &mdash; the study
of the literature and of the history of its development, the comparative
study of the forms and the syntax, the study of ancient history from the
sources, the study of ancient life, of ancient art, etc.  All these
various pursuits, however, rest ultimately mainly upon <emph>the
power to read Latin with ease and speed</emph>.</p></div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
