<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersDrama PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Drama//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersDrama.dtd" >
%PersDrama;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Eunuch</title>
				<author>P. Terentius Afer (Terence)</author>
				<editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor> &responsibility; &fund.DLI2; </titleStmt> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Comedies of Terence</title>
						<editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Ney York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
							<date>1874</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction method="silent" status="medium">&Perseus.DE;</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="TLN line"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="act"/>
				<state n="chunk" unit="scene"/>
				<state unit="line"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English</language>
				<language id="la">Latin</language>
				<language id="greek">Greek</language>
				<language id="de">German</language>
				<language id="fr">French</language>
				<language id="it">Italian</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>

		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>14-Aug-01</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>AEM</name>
					<resp>markup</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: eu_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2010-08-31 18:43:06  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/12/08 20:46:27 rsingh04 
moved more xml  files around based on copyright status. renamed terence files to follow the
                    abbreviations and split up minora_lat.xml into separate files 

Revision 1.8 2009/06/25 23:08:37 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.7 2009/06/24 15:46:48 student 
fixed Ter. Hau. references - zr 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/22 18:52:12 student 
fixed Pl. Ps. references - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/11/14 21:28:07 lcerrato 
fixed author names for consistent sorting 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:31 packel 
fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:43 packel
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 16:31:41 packel 
removed stray item tags 

Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 15:04:51 packel 
Converted to XML
                    
Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:18:13 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2002/03/13 20:09:06 czietz 
began mark-up 

Revision 1.6 2001/08/29 19:56:38 amahoney 
make the various Dramatis Personae lists independent instead of cross
                    referencing each other 

Revision 1.5 2001/08/21 18:49:51 amahoney 
get translator's name into proper place in meta-data, use same form of author's name
                    as in Latin 

Revision 1.4 2001/08/17 17:32:56 amahoney 
fix headers for TOC
                    
Revision 1.3 2001/08/17 17:24:11 amahoney 
begin marking the Latin 

Revision 1.2 2001/08/17 15:32:08 amahoney 
fix line numbers in the English, pick up a few
                    typos in Latin 

Revision 1.1 2001/08/16 21:11:14 amahoney 
new texts 
				</item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text lang="en">
		<body>

			<castList>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>LACHES,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">lagxu/nw,</foreign>
                            "to obtain by lot" or "heirship."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>an aged Athenian.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castGroup>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>PHAEDRIA,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">faidro\s</foreign>, "cheerful."</note>
						</role>
						<roleDesc>his sons.</roleDesc>
					</castItem>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>CHAEREA<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">xai/rwn,</foreign> "rejoicing."</note></role>
					</castItem>
				</castGroup>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>ANTIPHO,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">a)nti\</foreign>,
                            "opposite to," and <foreign lang="greek">fw=s,</foreign> "light," or
                                <foreign lang="greek">fh=mi</foreign>, "to speak."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a young man, friend of Chaerea.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>CHREMES,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">xremi/zw,</foreign> "to neigh;" delighting in horses.</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a young man, brother of Pamphila.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>THRASO,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">qraso\s,</foreign>
                            "boldness."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a boastful Captain.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>GNATHO,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">gnaqo\s,</foreign>
                            "the jawbone;" a glutton.</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a Parasite.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>PARMENO,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">para\,</foreign>
                            "by," and <foreign lang="greek">me/nw,</foreign> "to remain."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>servant of Phldria.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>SANGA,<note anchored="yes">From
                            Sangia in <placeName key="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName>, his native
                            country.</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>cook to Thraso.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castGroup>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>DONAX,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">do/nu\c,</foreign> "a reed."</note>
						</role>
						<roleDesc>servants of Thraso.</roleDesc>
					</castItem>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>SIMALIO<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">simo\s,</foreign> "flat-nosed."</note></role>
					</castItem>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>SYRISCUS<note anchored="yes">From <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, his country; or from <foreign lang="greek">suri/skos,</foreign> "a basket of figs."</note></role>
					</castItem>
				</castGroup>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>DORUS, </role>
					<roleDesc>a Eunuch slave.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>THAIS,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">qeu/omai,</foreign>
                            "to look at."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a Courtesan.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castGroup>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>PYTHIAS,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">puqome/nh,</foreign> "asking questions."</note></role>
						<roleDesc>her attendants.</roleDesc>
					</castItem>
					<castItem type="role">
						<role>DORIAS<note anchored="yes">From Doris, their country, a part of
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>.</note></role>
					</castItem>
				</castGroup>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>SOPHRONA,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">sw/frwn,</foreign> "prudent."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a nurse.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
				<castItem type="role">
					<role>PAMPHILA,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">pa=n,</foreign>
                            "all" and <foreign lang="greek">filo\s,</foreign> "a friend."</note>
					</role>
					<roleDesc>a female slave.</roleDesc>
				</castItem>
			</castList>

			<p>Scene.--<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; before the houses of
                LACHES and THAIS. </p>
			<div1 type="act" n="introduction">
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<div2 type="scene" n="subject">
					<head>THE SUBJECT.</head>

					<p>A CERTAIN citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had a
                        daughter named Pamphila, and a son called Chremes. The former was stolen
                        while an infant, and sold to a Rhodian merchant, who having made a present
                        of her to a Courtesan of <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>,
                        she brought her up with her own daughter Thais, who was somewhat older. In
                        the course of years, Thais following her mother's way of life, removes to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Her mother dying,
                        her property is put up for sale, and Pamphila is purchased as a slave by
                        Thraso, an officer and an admirer of Thais, who happens just then to be
                        visiting <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>. During the absence
                        of Thraso, Thais becomes acquainted with Phasdria, an Athenian youth, the
                        son of Laches; she also discovers from Chremes, who lives near <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that Pamphila, her former
                        companion, is his sister. Thraso returns, intending to present to her the
                        girl he has bought, but determines not to do so until she has discarded
                        Phaedria. Finding that the girl is no other than Pamphila, Thais is at a
                        loss what to do, as she both loves Phaedria, and is extremely anxious to
                        recover Pamphila. At length, to please the Captain, she excludes Phaedria,
                        but next day sends for him, and explains to him her reasons, at the same
                        time begging of him to allow Thraso the sole right of admission to her house
                        for the next two days, and assuring him that as soon as she shall have
                        gained possession of the girl, she will entirely throw him off. Phaedria
                        consents, and resolves to spend these two days in the country; at the same
                        time he orders Parmeno to take to Thais a Eunuch and an Aethiopian girl,
                        whom he has purchased for her. The Captain also sends Pamphila, who is
                        accidentally seen by Chaerea, the younger brother of Phaedria; he, being
                        smitten with her beauty, prevails upon Parmeno to introduce him into the
                        house of Thais, in the Eunuch's dress. Being admitted there, in the absence
                        of Thais, lie ravishes the damsel. Shortly afterward Thraso quarrels with
                        Thais, and comes with all his attendants to her house to demand the return
                        of Pamphila, but is disappointed. In conclusion, Pamphila is recognized by
                        her brother Chremes, and is promised in marriage to Chaerea; while Thraso
                        becomes reconciled to Phaedria, through the mediation of Gnatho, his
                        Parasite. </p>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="production">
					<head>THE
						TITLE<note anchored="yes">Colman has the following remark on this
                            Play: "This seems to lave been the most popular of all the Comedies of
                            Terence. Suetonius and Donatus both inform us that it was acted with the
                            greatest applause, and that the Poet received a larger price for it from
                            the Aediles than had ever been paid for any before, namely, 8000
                            sesterces, which is about equal to 200 crowns, which in those times was
                            a considerable sum."</note>
						OF THE PLAY.</head>

					<p>PERFORMIED at the Megalensian Games; L. Posthumius Albinus and L. Cornelius
                        Merula being Curule Aediles. L. Ambivius Turpio and L. Atilius Praenestinus
                        performed it. Flaccus, the freedman of Claudius, composed the music to two
                        treble flutes. From the Greek of Menander. It was acted twice,<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Acted twice</lemma> This probably
                            means "twice in one day." As it is generally supposed that something is
                            wanting after the figures II, this is presumed to be "<foreign lang="la">die</foreign>," "in one day," in confirmation of which Suetonius
                            informs us that it really was performed twice in one day. Donatus says
                            it was performed three times, by which he may probably mean, twice on
                            one day and once on another.</note> M. Valerius and C. Fannius being
                            Consuls.<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Being Consuls</lemma>
                            M. Valerius Messala and C. Fannius Strabo were Consuls in the year from
                            the building of the City 591, or B.C. <date value="-162">162</date>.</note>
                    </p>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="summary">
					<head>THE SUMMARY OF C. SULPITIUS APOLLINARIS.</head>
					<p>THE Captain, Thraso, being ignorant of the same, has brought from abroad a
                        girl who used wrongly to be called the sister of Thais, and presents her to
                        Thais herself: she in reality is a citizen of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. To the same woman, Phaedria, an admirer of Thais,
                        orders a Eunuch whom he has purchased, to be taken, and he himself goes away
                        into the country, having been entreated to give up two days to Thraso. A
                        youth, the brother of Phaedria, having fallen in love with the damsel sent
                        to the house of Thais, is dressed up in the clothes of the Eunuch. Parmeno
                        prompts him; he goes in; he ravishes the maiden; but at length her brother
                        being discovered, a citizen of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, betroths her who has been ravished, to the youth,
                        and Thraso prevails upon Phaedria by his entreaties. </p>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="act" n="prologue">
				<div2 type="scene" n="0">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="1" unit="TLN line"/>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THE PROLOGUE.</speaker>
						<p>IF there is any one who desires to please as many good men as possible,
                            and to give offense to extremely few, among those does our Poet enroll
                            his name. Next, if there is one who thinks<milestone n="4" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">If there
                                    is one who thinks</lemma>: He alludes to his old enemy, Luscus
                                Lavinius, the Comic Poet, who is alluded to in the Prologue to the
                                    <title>Andria</title>, and has since
                                continued his attacks upon him.</note> that language too harsh is
                            here applied to him, let him bear this in mind--that it is an answer,
                            not an attack; inasmuch as he has himself been the first aggressor; who,
                            by translating plays verbally,<milestone n="7" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">By translating
                                literally</lemma>: "<foreign lang="la">Bene vertendo, at eosdem
                                    scribendo male</foreign>." This passage has greatly puzzled some
                                of the Commentators. Bentley has, however, it appears, come to the most
                                reasonable conclusion; who supposes that Terence means by "<foreign lang="la">bene vertere</foreign>," a literal translation, word
                                for word, from the Greek, by which a servile adherence to the idiom
                                of that language was preserved to the neglect of the Latin idiom; in
                                consequence of which the Plays of Luscus Lavinius were, as he
                                remarks, "<foreign lang="la">male scriptae</foreign>," written in
                                bad Latin.</note> and writing them in bad Latin, has made out of
                            good Greek Plays Latin ones by no means good. Just as of late he has
                            published the Phasma<milestone n="9" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Has published the
                                Phasma</lemma>: The <foreign lang="greek">fasma/,</foreign>" or
                                "Apparition," was a play of Menander, so called, in which a young
                                man looking through a hole in the wall between his father's house
                                and that next door, sees a young woman of marvelous beauty, and is
                                struck with awe at the sight, as though by an apparition; in the
                                Play, the girl's mother is represented as having made this hole in
                                the wall, and having decked it with garlands and branches that it
                                may resemble a consecrated place; where she daily performs her
                                devotions in company with her daughter, who has been privately
                                brought up, and whose existence is unknown to the neighbors. On the
                                youth coming by degrees to the knowledge that the object of his
                                admiration is but a mortal, his passion becomes sdoviolent that it
                                will admit of no cure but marriage, with the celebration of which
                                the Play concludes. Bentley
                                gives us the above information from an ancient Scholiast, whose name
                                is unknown, unless it is Donatus himself, which is doubtful. It
                                would appear that Luscus Lavinius had lately made a translation of
                                this Play, which, from its servile adherence to the language of the
                                original, had been couched in ungrammatical language, and probably
                                not approved of by the Audience. Donatus thinks that this is the
                                meaning of the passage, and that, content with this slight reference
                                to a well-known fact, the author passes it by in contemptuous
                                silence.</note> [the Apparition] of Menander; and in the Thesaurus
                            [the Treasure] has described<milestone n="10" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And in the Thesaurus has
                                    described</lemma> Cook has the following appropriate remark upon
                                this passage: "In the 'Thesaurus,' or 'Treasure' of Luscus Lavinius,
                                a young fellow, having wasted his estate by his extravagance, sends
                                a servant to search his father's monument: but he had before sold
                                the ground on which the monument was, to a covetous old man; to whom
                                the servant applies to help him open the monument; in which they
                                discover a hoard and a letter. The old fellow sees the treasure and
                                keeps it; the young one goes to law with him, and the old man is
                                represented as opening his cause first before the judge, which he
                                begins with these words:-- <quote lang="la">'Athenienses, bellum cum
                                    Rhodiensibus, Quod fuerit, quid ego praedicem?'</quote>
                                'Athenians, why should I relate the war with the Rhodians?' And lie
                                goes on in a manner contrary to the rules of court; which Terence
                                objects to, because the young man, who was the plaintiff, should
                                open his cause first. Thus far Bentley, from the same Scholiast [as referred to in
                                the last Note]. This Note is a clear explanation of the four verses
                                to which it belongs. Hare concurs with Madame Dacier in her opinion
                                    <foreign lang="la">'de Thesauro,'</foreign> that it is only a
                                part of the Phasma of Menander, and not a distinct Play; but were I
                                not determined by the more learned Bentley, the text itself would not permit me to be
                                of their opinion; for the words <foreign lang="la">'atque in
                                    Thesauro scripsit'</foreign> seem plainly to me to be a
                                transition to another Play. The subject of the Thesaurus is related
                                by Eugraphius, though not with all the circumstances mentioned in my
                                Note from Bentlev." Colman also remarks here: "Menander and his
                                contemporary Philemon, each of them wrote a Comedy under this title.
                                We have in the above Note the story of Menander's; and we know that
                                of Philemon's from the 'Trinummus' of Plautus, which was a
                                Translation of it."</note> him from whom the gold is demanded, as
                            pleading his cause why it should be deemed his own, before the person
                            who demands it has stated how this treasure belongs to him, or how it
                            came into the tomb of his father. Henceforward, let him not deceive
                            himself, or fancy thus, "I have now done with it; there's nothing that
                            he can say to me." I recommend him not to be mistaken, and to refrain
                            from provoking me. I have many other points, as to which for the present
                            he shall be pardoned, which, however, shall be brought forward
                            hereafter, if he persists in attacking me, as he has begun to do. After
                            the Aediles had purchased the Eunuch of Menander, the Play which we are
                            about to perform, he managed to get an opportunity of viewing
                                it.<milestone n="21" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Opportunity of viewing it</lemma> Colman thinks
                                that this means something "stronger than merely being present at the
                                representation," and he takes the meaning to be, that having
                                obtained leave to peruse the MS., he furnished himself with
                                objections against the piece, which he threw out when it came to be
                                represented before the magistrates. Cooke thinks that the passage
                                only means, "that he bustled and took pains to be near enough at the
                                representation to see and hear plainly." The truth seems to be that
                                Lavinius managed to obtain admission at the rehearsal or trial of
                                the merits of the piece before the magistrates, and that he then
                                behaved himself in the unseemly manner mentioned in the text.</note>
                            When the magistrates were present it began to be performed. He exclaimed
                            that a thief, no Poet, had produced the piece, but still had not
                                deceived<milestone n="24" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Produced the piece, but still had not
                                    deceived him</lemma> There is a pun here upon the resemblance in
                                meaning of the words "<foreign lang="la">verba dare</foreign>" and
                                    "<foreign lang="la">fabulam dare</foreign>." The first
                                expression means to "deceive" or "impose upon;" the latter phrase
                                has also the same meaning, but it may signify as well "to represent"
                                or "produce a Play." Thus the exclamation in its ambiguity may mean,
                                "he has produced a Play, and has not succeeded in deceiving us," or
                                "he has deceived us, and yet has not deceived us." This is the
                                interpretation which Donatus puts upon the passage.</note> him;
                            that, in fact, it was the Colax, an old Play of Plautus;<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Colax, an old Play of
                                    Plautus</lemma> Although Nonius Marcellus professes to quote
                                from the Colax of Plautus (so called from the Greek <foreign lang="greek">*kolu\c,</foreign> "a flatterer" or "parasite"),
                                some scholars have disbelieved in the existence of any Play of
                                Plautus known by that name. Cooke says: "If Plautus had wrote a Play
                                under the title of 'Colax,' I should think it very unlikely that it
                                should have escaped Terence's eye, considering how soon he
                                flourished after Plautus, his being engaged in the same studies, and
                                his having such opportunities to consult the libraries of the great;
                                for though all learning was then confined to Manuscripts, Terence
                                could have no difficulty in coming at the best copies. The character
                                of the 'Miles Gloriosus' [Braggart Captain] here mentioned, I am
                                inclined to think the same with that which is the hero of Plautus's
                                Comedy, now extant, and called 'Miles Gloriosus,' from which Terence
                                could not take his Thraso. Pyrgopolinices and Thraso are both full
                                of themselves, both boast of their valor and their intimacy with
                                princes, and both fancy themselves beloved by all the women who see
                                them; and they are both played off by their Parasites, but they
                                differ in their manner and their speech: Plautus's Pyrgopolinices is
                                always in the clouds, and talking big, and of blood and
                                wounds--Terence's Thraso never says too little nor much, but is an
                                easy ridiculous character, continually supplying the Audience with
                                mirth without the wild extravagant bluster of Pyrgopolinices;
                                Plautus and Terence both took their soldiers and Parasites from
                                Menander, but gave them different dresses." Upon this Note Colman
                                remarks: "Though there is much good criticism in the above Note, it
                                is certain that Plautus did not take his 'Miles Gloriosus' from the
                                Colax of Menander, as he himself informs us it was translated from a
                                Greek play called <foreign lang="greek">*ala/zwn,</foreign> 'the
                                Boaster,' and the Parasite is but a trifling character in that play,
                                never appearing after the first Scene."</note> and that from it were
                            taken the characters of the Parasite and the Captain. If this is a
                            fault, the fault is the ignorance of the Poet; not that he intended to
                            be guilty of theft. That so it is, you will now be enabled to judge. The
                            Colax is a Play of Meander's; in it there is Colax, a Parasite, and a
                            braggart Captain: he does not deny that he has transferred these
                            characters into his Eunuch from the Greek; but assuredly he does deny
                            this, that he was aware that those pieces had been already translated
                            into Latin. But if it is not permitted us to use the same characters as
                            others, how can it any more be allowed to represent hurrying
                                servants,<milestone n="45" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Hurrying servants</lemma> On the "<foreign lang="la">currentes servi</foreign>," see the Prologue to the
                                Heautontimorumenos, <bibl n="Ter. Hau. prologue.0">l. 31</bibl>.
                                    <persName>Ovid</persName>, in the Amores, <bibl n="Ov. Am. 1.15">B. i., El. 15, l. 17, 18</bibl>, mentions a very similar
                                combination of the characters of Menander's Comedy: "So long as the
                                deceitful slave, the harsh father, the roguish procuress, and the
                                cozening courtesan shall endure, Menander will exist."</note> to
                            describe virtuous matrons, artful courtesans, the gluttonous parasite,
                            the braggart captain, the infant palmed off, the old man cajoled by the
                            servant, about love, hatred, suspicion? In fine, nothing is said now
                            that has not been said before. Wherefore it is but just that you should
                            know this, and make allowance, if the moderns do what the ancients used
                            to do. Grant me your attention, and give heed in silence, that you may
                            understand what the Eunuch means. </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="act" n="1">
				<div2 type="scene" n="1">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="46" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PHAEDRIA and PARMENO.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What then, shall I do?<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">What,
                                    then, shall I do?</lemma> Phaedria, on being sent for by Thais,
                                breaks out into these words as he enters, after having deliberated
                                upon his parting with her. Both <persName>Horace</persName> and Persius have imitated this passage in
                                their Satires.</note> Ought I not to go, not now even, when I am
                            sent for of her own accord? Or ought I rather so to behave myself as not
                            to put up with affronts from Courtesans? She shut her door against me;
                            she now invites me back. Ought I to return? No; though she should
                            implore me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> l'faith, if indeed you only can, there's nothing better or more
                            spirited; but if you begin, and can not hold out stoutly, and if, when
                            you can not endure it, while no one asks you, peace being not made, you
                            come to her of your own accord, showing that you love her, and can not
                            endure it, you are done for; it's all over with you; you are ruined
                            outright. She'll be jilting you, when she finds you overcome. Do you
                            then, while there's time, again and again reflect upon this, master,
                            that a matter, which in itself admits of neither prudence nor
                            moderation, you are unable to manage with prudence. In love there are
                            all these evils; wrongs, suspicions, enmities reconcilements, war, then
                            peace; if you expect to render these things, naturally uncertain,
                            certain by dint of reason, you wouldn't effect it a bit the more than if
                            you were to use your endeavors to be mad with reason. And, what you are
                            now, in anger, meditating to yourself, "What! I to her?<note anchored="yes">What! I to her?)--Ver. 65. Donatus remarks that this
                                is an abrupt manner of speaking familiarly to persons in anger; and
                                that the sentences are thus to be understood, "I, go to her? Her,
                                who has received him! Who has excluded me!"--inasmuch as indignation
                                loves to deal in Ellipsis and Aposiopesis.</note> Who--him! Who--me!
                            Who wouldn't? Only let me alone; I had rather die; she shall find out
                            what sort of a person I am;" these expressions, upon my faith, by a
                            single false tiny tear, which, by rubbing her eyes, poor thing, she can
                            hardly squeeze out perforce, she will put an end to; and she'll be the
                            first to accuse you; and you will be too ready to give satisfaction to
                            her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> O disgraceful conduct! I now perceive, both that she is perfidious, and
                            that I am a wretched man. I am both weary of her, and burn with passion;
                            knowing and fully sensible, alive and seeing it, I am going to ruin; nor
                            do I know what I am to do.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What you are to do? Why, only to redeem yourself, thus captivated, at
                            the smallest price you can; if you can not at a very small, rate, still
                            for as little as you can; and do not afflict yourself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Do you persuade me to this?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> If you are wise. And don't be adding to the troubles which love itself
                            produces; those which it does produce, bear patiently. But see, here she
                            is coming herself, the downfall of our fortunes,<note anchored="yes">The
                                downfall of our fortunes)--Ver. 79. Colman observes, "There is an extreme elegance in
                                this passage in the original; and the figurative expression is
                                beautifully employed." <foreign lang="la">"Calamitas"</foreign> was
                                originally a word used in husbandry, which signified the destruction
                                of growing corn; because, as Donatus says, <foreign lang="la">"Comminuit calamum et segetem;"</foreign>--"it strikes down the
                                blades and standing corn."</note>--for that which we ought ourselves
                            to enjoy she intercepts.</p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="2">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="81" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THAIS from her house.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to herself, not seeing them.</stage> Ah wretched me! I fear lest
                            Phaedria should take it amiss or otherwise than I intended it, that he
                            was not admitted yesterday. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside to PARMENO.</stage> I'm trembling and shivering all over,
                            Parmeno, at the sight of her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Be of good heart; only approach this fire,<note anchored="yes">Approach this fire)--Ver. 85. <quote lang="la">"Ignem"</quote> is generally supposed to be used figuratively
                                here, and to mean "the flame of love." Eugraphius, however, would
                                understand the expression literally, observing that courtesans
                                usually had near their doors an altar sacred to <persName>Venus</persName>, on which they daily
                                sacrificed.</note> you'll soon be warmer than you need.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>turning round.</stage> Who is it that's speaking here? What, are
                            you here, my Phaedria? Why are you standing here? Why didn't you come
                            into the house at once?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>whispering to PHAEDRIA.</stage> But not a word about shutting you
                            out!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Why are you silent?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Of course, it's because<note anchored="yes">Of course it's
                                because)--Ver. 89. It must be observed that these words, conmencing
                                with <quote lang="la">"Sane, quia vero,"</quote> in the original,
                                are said by Phaedria not in answer to the words of Thais immediately
                                preceding, but to her previous question, <foreign lang="la">"Cur non
                                    recta introibas?"</foreign> "Why didn't you come into the house
                                at once?" and that they are spoken in bitter irony.</note> this door
                            is always open to me, or because I'm the highest in your favor?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Pass those matters by.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> How pass them by? O Thais, Thais, I wish that I had equal affection with
                            yourself, and that it were in like degree, that either this might
                            distress you in the same way that it distresses me, or that I might be
                            indifferent at this being done by you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Prithee, don't torment yourself, my life, my Phaedria. Upon my faith, I
                            did it, not because I love or esteem any person more than you; but the
                            case was such that it was necessary to be done.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>ironically.</stage> I suppose that, poor thing, you shut him out
                            of doors, for love, according to the usual practice.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Is it thus you act, Parmeno? Well, well. <stage>To PHAEDRIA.</stage> But
                            listen--the reason for which I desired you to be sent for hither----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Go on.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> First tell me this; can this fellow possibly hold his tongue?
                                <stage>pointing to PARMENO.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What, I? Perfectly well. But, hark you, upon these conditions I pledge
                            my word to you; the truth that I hear, I'm silent upon, and retain it
                            most faithfully; but if I hear what's false and without foundation, it's
                            out at once; I'm full of chinks, and leak in every direction. Therefore,
                            if you wish it to be kept secret, speak the truth.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> My mother was a Samian; she lived at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> That may be kept a secret.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> There, at that period, a certain merchant made present to my mother of a
                            little girl, who had been stolen away from <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> here.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What, a citizen?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I think so; we do not know for certain: she herself used to mention her
                            mother's and her father's name; her country and other tokens she didn't
                            know, nor, by reason of her age, was she able. The merchant added this:
                            that he had heard front the kidnappers that she had been carried off
                            from Sunium.<milestone n="115" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From Sunium</lemma>: This was a town
                                situate near a lofty Promontory of that name in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. It was famous for a fair
                                which was held there. "Sunium's rocky brow" is mentioned by Byron in
                                the song of the Greek Captive in the third Canto of Don Juan.</note>
                            When my mother received her, she began carefully to teach her every
                            thing, and to bring her up, just as though she had been her own
                            daughter. Most persons supposed that she was my sister. Thence I came
                            hither with that stranger, with whom alone at that period I was
                            connected; he left me all which I now possess----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Both these things are false; out it goes.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> How so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Because you were neither content with one, nor was he the only one to
                            make you presents; for he likewise <stage>pointing to PHAEDRIA</stage>
                            brought a pretty considerable share to you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Such is the fact; but do allow me to arrive at the point I wish. In the
                            mean time, the Captain, who had begun to take a fancy to me, set out to
                                <placeName key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>;<milestone n="126" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Set out
                                    for <placeName key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName></lemma>: This
                                was a country of <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>
                                upon the sea-coast, opposite to the island of <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>.</note> since when, in the
                            interval, I became acquainted with you. You yourself are aware how very
                            dear I have held you; and how I confess to you all my nearest
                            counsels.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Nor will Parmeno be silent about that. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> O, is that a matter of doubt?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Attend; I entreat you. My mother died there recently; her brother is
                            somewhat greedy after wealth. When he saw that this damsel was of
                            beauteous form and understood music, hoping for a good price, he
                            forthwith put her up for sale, and sold her. By good fortune this friend
                            of mine was present; he bought her as a gift to me, not knowing or
                            suspecting any thing of all this. He returned; but when he perceived
                            that I had formed a connection with you as well, lie feigned excuses on
                            purpose that he might not give her; he said that if he could feel
                            confidence that he should be preferred to yourself by me, so as not to
                            apprehend that, when I had received her, I should forsake him, then he
                            was ready to give her to me; but that he did fear this. But, so far as I
                            can conjecture, he has set his affections upon the girl.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Any thing beyond that?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Nothing; for I have made inquiry. Now, my Phaedria, there are many
                            reasons why I could wish to get her away from him. In the first place,
                            because she was called my sister; moreover, that I may restore and
                            deliver her to her friends. I am a lone woman; I have no one here,
                            neither acquaintance nor relative; wherefore, Phaedria, I am desirous by
                            my good offices to secure friends. Prithee, do aid me in this, in order
                            that it may be the more easily effected. Do allow him for the few next
                            days to have the preference with me. Do you make no answer?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Most vile woman! Can I make you any answer after such behavior as
                            this?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Well done, my master, I commend you; <stage>aside</stage> he's galled at
                            last. <stage>To PHAEDRIA.</stage> You show yourself a man.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I was not aware what you were aiming at; "she was carried away from
                            here, when a little child; my mother brought her up as though her own;
                            she was called my sister; I wish to get her away, that I may restore her
                            to her friends." The meaning is, that all these expressions, in fine,
                            now amount to this, that I am shut out, he is admitted. For what reason?
                            Except that you love him more than me: and now you are afraid of her who
                            has been brought hither, lest she should win him, such as he is, from
                            yourself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I, afraid of that? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What else, then, gives you concern? Let me know. Is he the only person
                            who makes presents? Have you found my bounty shut against you? Did I
                            not, when you told me that you wished for a servant-maid from
                                Aethiopia,<milestone n="165" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Servant-maid from Aethiopia</lemma>: No
                                doubt Aethiopian or negro slaves were much prized by the great, and
                                those courtesans whose object it was to ape their manners.</note>
                            setting all other matters aside, go and seek for one? Then you said that
                            you wanted a Eunuch, because ladies of quality<milestone n="168" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Ladies of
                                    quality</lemma>: <quote lang="la">"Reginae,"</quote> literally
                                "queens," here means women of rank and distinction.</note> alone
                            make use of them; I found you one. I yesterday paid twenty
                                minae<milestone n="169" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Paid twenty minoe</lemma>: The "mina" contained
                                one hundred "drachmae" of about 9&frac34;d. each.</note> for
                            them both. Though slighted by you, I still kept these things in mind; as
                            a reward for so doing, I am despised by you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Phaedria, what does this mean? Although I wish to get her away, and
                            think that by these means it could most probably be effected; still,
                            rather than make an enemy of you, I'll do as you request me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I only wish that you used that expression from your heart and
                            truthfully, "rather than make an enemy of you." If I could believe that
                            this was said sincerely, I could put up with any thing.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> He staggers; how instantaneously is he vanquished
                            by a single expression!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I, wretched woman, not speak from my heart? What, pray, did you ever ask
                            of me in jest, but that you carried your point? I am unable to obtain
                            even this of you, that you would grant me only two days.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> If, indeed, it is but two days; but don't let these days become
                            twenty.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Assuredly not more than two days, or----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> "Or?" I won't have it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> It shall not be; only do allow me to obtain this of you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Of course that which you desire must be done.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I love you as you deserve; you act obligingly.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PARMENO.</stage> I shall go into the country; there I shall
                            worry myself for the next two days: I'm resolved to do so; Thais must be
                            humored. Do you, Parmeno, take care that they are brought hither.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Certainly.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> For the next two days then, Thais, adieu.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> And the same to you, my Phaedria; do you desire aught else?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What should I desire? That, present with the Captain, you may be as if
                            absent; that night and day you may love me; may feel my absence; may
                            dream of me; may be impatient for me; may think about me; may hope for
                            me; may centre your delight in me; may be all in all with me; in fine,
                            if you will, be my very life, as I am yours. (Exeunt PHAEDRIA and
                            PARMENO. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to herself.</stage> Ah wretched me!<milestone n="197" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Ah
                                    wretched me!</lemma>: Donatus remarks that the Poet judiciously
                                reserves that part of the plot to betold here, which Thais did not
                                relate to Phaedria in the presence of Parmeno; whom the Poet keeps
                                in ignorance as to the rank of the damsel, that he may with the more
                                probability dare to assist Chaerea in his attempt on her.</note>
                            perhaps now he puts but little faith in me, and forms his estimate of me
                            from the dispositions of other women.<milestone n="198" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From the dispositions of
                                    other women</lemma>: Donatus observes that this is one of the
                                peculiar points of excellence shown by Terence, introducing common
                                characters in a new manner, without departing from custom or nature;
                                since he draws a good Courtesan, and yet engages the attention of
                                the Spectators and amuses them. Colman has the following Note here:
                                "Under the name of Thais, Menander is supposed to have drawn the
                                character of his own mistress, Glycerium, and it seems he introduced
                                a Courtesan of the same name into several of his Comedies. One
                                Comedy was entitled 'Thais,' from which <persName>St. Paul</persName> took the sentence in his Epistle to the
                                Corinthians, 'Evil communications corrupt good manners.'" Plutarch
                                has preserved four lines of the Prologue to that Comedy, in which
                                the Poet, in a kind of mock-heroic manner, invokes the Muse to teach
                                him to depict the character of his heroine.</note> By my troth, I,
                            who know my own self, am very sure of this, that I have not feigned any
                            thing that's false, and that no person is dearer to my heart than this
                            same Phaedria; and whatever in the present case I have done, for this
                            girl's sake have I done it; for I trust that now I have pretty nearly
                            discovered her brother, a young man of very good family; and he has
                            appointed this day to come to me at my house. I'll go hence in-doors,
                            and wait until he comes. <stage>She goes into her house.</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="act" n="2">
				<div2 type="scene" n="1">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="207" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PHAEDRIA and PARMENO.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Mind that those people are taken there, as I ordered.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'll do so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> And carefully.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> It shall be done.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> And with all speed.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> It shall be done.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Have you had sufficient instructions?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Dear me! to ask the question, as though it were a matter of difficulty.
                            I wish that you were able, Phaedria, to find any thing as easily as this
                            present will be lost.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Together with it, I myself am lost, which concerns me more nearly. Don't
                            bear this with such a feeling of vexation.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> By no means; on the contrary, I'll see it done. But do you order any
                            thing else?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Set off my present with words, as far as you can; and so far as you are
                            able, do drive away that rival of mine from her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Pshaw! I should have kept that in mind, even if you hadn't reminded
                            me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I shall go into the country and remain there.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I agree with you. <stage>Moves as if going.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> But hark you!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What is it you want?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Are you of opinion that I can muster resolution and hold out so as not
                            to come back within the time?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What, you? Upon my faith, I don't think so; for either you'll be
                            returning at once, or by-and-by, at night, want of sleep will be driving
                            you hither.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I'll do some laborious work, that I may be continually fatigued, so as
                            to sleep in spite of myself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> When wearied, you will be keeping awake; by this you will be making it
                            worse.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Oh, you talk to no purpose, Parmeno: this softness of spirit, upon my
                            faith, must be got rid of; I indulge myself too much. Could I not do
                            without her, pray, if there were the necessity, even for a whole three
                            days?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Whew! an entire three days! Take care what you are about.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> My mind is made up. <stage>(Exit.)</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Good Gods! What a malady is this! That a man
                            should become so changed through love, that you wouldn't know him to be
                            the same person! Not any one was there<milestone n="226" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Not any one was
                                    there</lemma>: --Ver. 226-7. Very nearly the same words as these
                                occur in the Mostellaria of Plautus, 1. 29, 30: "Than whom,
                                hitherto, no one of the youth of all <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> has been considered more temperate or
                                equally frugal."</note> less inclined to folly than he, and no one
                            more discreet or more temperate. But who is it that's coming this way?
                            Heyday! surely this is Gnatho, the Captain's Parasite; he's bringing
                            along with him the damsel as a present to her. Heavens! How beautiful!
                            No wonder if I make but a sorry figure here to-day with this decrepit
                            Eunuch of mine. She surpasses Thais herself. <stage>Stands
                                aside.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="2">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="232" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter GNATHO at a distance, leading PAMPHILA.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Immortal Gods! how much does one man excel
                            another! What a difference there is between a wise person and a fool!
                            This strongly came into my mind from the following circumstance. As I
                            was, coming along to-day, I met a certain person of this place, of my
                            own rank and station, no mean fellow, one who, like myself, had guttled
                            away his paternal estate; I saw him, shabby, dirty, sickly, beset with
                            rags and years;--"What's the meaning of this garb?" said I; he answered,
                            "Because, wretch that I am, I've lost what I possessed: see to what I am
                            reduced,--all my acquaintances and friends forsake me." On this I felt
                            contempt for him in: comparison with myself. "What!" said I, "you
                            pitiful sluggard, have you so managed matters as to have no hope left?
                            Have you lost your wits together with your estate? Don't you see me, who
                            have risen from the same condition? What a complexion I have, how spruce
                            and well dressed, what portliness of person? I have every thing, yet
                            have nothing; and although I possess nothing, still, of nothing am I in
                            want." "But I," said he, "unhappily, can neither be a butt nor submit to
                                blows."<milestone n="244" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Nor submit to blows</lemma>: It has been
                                remarked in the Notes to the Translation of Plautus that the
                                Parasites had, in consequence of their state of dependence, to
                                endure blows and indignities from their fellow-guests. Their
                                attempts to be <foreign lang="la">"ridiculi"</foreign> or "drolls"
                                were made in order to give some small return to their entertainers.
                                See especially the character of Gelasimus in the Stichus of Plautus,
                                and the words of Ergasilus in the Captivi, 1. 88, 90. Diderot, as:
                                quoted by Colman, observes: "This is the only Scene in Terence which
                                I remember that can be charged with being superfluous. Thraso has
                                made a present to Thais of a young girl. Gnatho is to convey her.
                                Going along with her, he amuses himself with giving the Spectators a
                                most agreeable eulogium on his profession. But was that the time for
                                it? Let Gnatho pay due attention on the stage to the young woman
                                whom he is charged with, and let him say what he will to himself, I
                                consent to it."</note> "What!" said I, "do you suppose it is managed
                            by those means? You are quite mistaken. Once upon a time, in the early
                            ages, there was a calling for that class; this is a new mode of
                            coney-catching; I, in fact, have been the first to strike into this
                            path. There is a class of men who strive to be the first in every thing,
                            but are not; to these I make my court; I do not present myself to them
                            to be laughed at; but I am the first to laugh with them, and at the same
                            time to admire their parts: whatever they say, I commend; if they
                            contradict that self-same thing, I commend again. Does any one deny? I
                            deny: does he affirm? I affirm: in fine, I have so trained myself as to
                            humor them in every thing. This calling is now by far the most
                            productive."</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> A clever fellow, upon my faith! From being fools
                            he makes men mad outright.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself, continuing.</stage> While we were thus talking, in
                            the mean time we arrived at the market-place; overjoyed, all the
                            confectioners ran at once to meet me; fishmongers,<milestone n="257" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Fishmongers</lemma>: <quote lang="la">"Cetarii;"</quote>
                                strictly speaking, "dealers in large fish."</note> butchers,
                                cooks,<milestone n="257" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Cooks</lemma>: The <quote lang="la">"coqui"</quote> were in the habit of standing in the
                                market-place for hire by those who required their services. See the
                                Pseudolus, the Aulularia, and the Mercator of Plautus, and the Notes
                                to Bohn's Translation. See also a remark on the knavish character of
                                the sausage-makers in the Truculentus of Plautus, 1. 110.</note>
                            sausage-makers, and fishermen, whom, both when my fortunes were
                            flourishing and when they were ruined, I had served, and often serve
                            still: they complimented me, asked me to dinner, and gave me a hearty
                            welcome. When this poor hungry wretch saw that I was in such great
                            esteem, and that I obtained a living so easily, then the fellow began to
                            entreat me that I would allow him to learn this method of me; I bade him
                            become my follower<milestone n="262" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Become my follower</lemma>:
                                    <quote lang="la">"Sectari."</quote> In allusion to the manners
                                of the ancient Philosophers, who were wont to be followed by a crowd
                                of their disciples, who were styled <foreign lang="la">"sectatores"</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">"sectae."</foreign> Gnatho intends to found a new school of
                                Parasites, who shall be called the "Gnathonics," and who, by their
                                artful adulation, shall contrive to be caressed instead of being
                                maltreated. Artotrogus, the Parasite in the Miles Gloriosus of
                                Plautus, seems, however, to have forestalled Gnatho as the founder
                                of this new school.</note> if he could; as the disciples of the
                            Philosophers take their names from the Philosophers themselves, so too,
                            the Parasite; ought to be called Gnathonics.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart to the Audience.</stage> Do you see the effects of ease and
                            feeding at another's cost?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to Iimself, continuing.</stage> But why do I delay to take this
                            girl to Thais, and ask her to come to dinner? <stage>Aside, on seeing
                                PARMENO.</stage> But I see Parmeno, our rival's servant, waiting
                            before the door of Thais with a sorrowful air; all's safe; no doubt
                            these people are finding a cold welcome. I'm resolved to have some sport
                            with this knave.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> They fancy that, through this present, Thais is
                            quite their own.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>accosting PARMENO.</stage> With his very best wishes Gnatho
                            greets Parmeno, his very good friend.--What are you doing?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'm standing.<milestone n="271" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I'm standing</lemma>: <foreign lang="la">"Quid agitur?" "Statur."</foreign> The same joke occurs in the <cit>
                                    <bibl n="Pl. Ps. 1.5">Pseudolus of Plautus, l. 457.</bibl>
                                    <quote lang="la">"Quid agitur? Statur hic ad hunc
                                        modum?"</quote>
                                </cit> "What is going on?" or "What are you about?" "About standing
                                here in this fashion;" assuming an attitude. Colman observes that
                                there is much the same kind of conceit in the <cit>
                                    <bibl n="shak. wiv 1.3.30">"Merry Wives of Windsor."</bibl>
                                    <quote lang="en">
                                        <sp>
                                            <speaker>FALSTAFF.</speaker>
                                            <p>"My honest lads, I will tell you what I am
                                                about."</p>
                                        </sp>
                                        <sp>
                                            <speaker>PISTOL.</speaker>
                                            <p>"Two yards or more."</p>
                                        </sp>
                                    </quote>
                                </cit> Cooke has the following note: "'<foreign lang="la">Quid
                                    agitur</foreign>' is to be supposed to have a single meaning as
                                spoken by Gnatho, but Parmeno archly renders it ambiguous by his
                                answer. Our two first English translations, that by Bernard and that
                                by Hoole, make nothing of it, nor indeed any other part of their
                                author. Echard follows Madame Dacier, and perceives a joke; but he
                                does not render '<foreign lang="la">quid agitur</foreign>' as the
                                question ought to be translated. '<foreign lang="la">Quid
                                    agitur</foreign>' sometimes means,' What are you doing?'
                                Sometimes, 'How do you do?' 'How are you?' or 'How goes the world
                                with you?'"</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> So I perceive. Pray, do you see any thing here that don't please
                            you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Yourself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I believe you,--but any thing else, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Why so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Because you are out of spirits.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Not in the least.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Well, don't be so; but what think you of this slave? <stage>pointing to
                                her.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Really, not amiss.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> I've galled the fellow.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside, on overhearing him.</stage> How mistaken you are in your
                            notion!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> How far do you suppose this gift will prove acceptable to Thais?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> It's this you mean to say now, that we are discarded there. Hark you,
                            there are vicissitudes in all things.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> For the next six months, Parmeno, I'll set you at ease; you sha'n't have
                            to be running to and fro, or sitting up till daylight. Don't I make you
                            happy?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Me? O prodigiously!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> That's my way with my friends.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I commend you. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I'm detaining you; perhaps you were about to go somewhere else.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Nowhere.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> In that case then, lend me your services a little; let me be introduced
                            to her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Very well; <stage>GNATHO knocks at the door, which immediately
                                opens</stage> now the door is open for you, <stage>aside</stage>
                            because you are bringing her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>going into the house of THAIS, ironically.</stage> Should you
                            like any one to be called out from here? <stage>Goes in with PAMPHILA,
                                and shuts the door.</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Only let the next two days go by; you who, at
                            present, in such high favor, are opening the door with one little
                            finger, assuredly I'll cause to be kicking at that door full oft, with
                            your heels, to no purpose. <stage>Re-enter GNATHO from the
                                house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Still standing here, Parmeno? Why now, have you been left on guard here,
                            that no go-between might perchance be secretly running from the Captain
                            to her? <stage>(Exit.)</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Smartly said; really they ought to be wonderful things to please the
                            Captain. But I see my master's youngest son coming this way; I wonder
                            why he has come away from the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>,<note anchored="yes">From the Piroeus)--Ver.
                                290. The <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> was
                                the chief harbor of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, at the mouth of the Cephisus, about three
                                miles from the City. It was joined to the town by two walls, one of
                                which was built by Themistocles, and the other by Pericles. It was
                                the duty of the Athenian youth to watch here in turn by way of
                                precaution against surprise by pirates or the enemy.</note> for he
                            is at present on guard there in the public service. It's not for
                            nothing; he's coming in a hurry, too; I can't imagine why he's looking
                            around in all directions.</p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="3">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="292" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHAEREA on the other side of the stage, in haste.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> I'm utterly undone! The girl is nowhere; nor
                            do I know where I am myself, to have lost sight of her. Where to inquire
                            for her, where to search for her, whom to ask, which way to turn, I'm at
                            a loss. I have only this hope; wherever she is, she can not long be
                            concealed. O what beauteous features! from this moment I banish all
                            other women from my thoughts; I can not endure these every-day
                            beauties.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Why look, here's the other one. He's saying
                            something, I don't know what, about love. O unfortunate old man, their
                            father! This assuredly is a youth, who, if he does begin, you will say
                            that the other one was mere play and pastime, compared with what the
                            madness of this one will cause.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself, aloud.</stage> May all the Gods and Goddesses
                            confound that old fellow who detained me to-day, and me as well who
                            stopped for him, and in fact troubled myself a straw about him. But see,
                            here's Parmeno. <stage>Addressing him.</stage> Good-morrow to you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Why are you out of spirits, and why in such a hurry? Whence come
                            you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> What, I? I'faith, I neither know whence I'm come, nor whither I'm going;
                            so utterly have I lost myself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> How, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I'm in love.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>starting.</stage> Ha!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Now, Parmeno, you may show what sort of a man you are. You know that you
                            often promised me to this effect: "Chaerea, do you only find some object
                            to fall in love with; I'll make you sensible of my usefulness in such
                            matters," when I used to be storing up my father's provisions for you on
                            the sly in your little room.<note anchored="yes">In your little
                                room)--Ver. 310. Though <quote lang="la">"cellulam"</quote> seems to
                                be considered by some to mean "cupboard" or "larder," it is more
                                probable that it here signifies the little room which was
                                appropriated to each slave in the family for his own use.
                            </note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> To the point, you simpleton.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith, this is the fact. Now, then, let your promises be made
                            good, if you please, or if indeed the affair is a deserving one for you
                            to exert your energies upon. The girl isn't like our girls, whom their
                            mothers are anxious to have with shoulders kept down, and chests well
                                girthed,<milestone n="314" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Shoulders kept down and chests well
                                    girthed</lemma>: Ovid, in the Art of Love, B. iii., 1. 274,
                                alludes to the "strophium" or "girth" here referred to: "For high
                                shoulders, small pads are suitable; and let the girth encircle the
                                bosom that is too prominent." Becker thinks that the "strophium" was
                                different from the <foreign lang="la">"fascia"</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">"stomacher,"</foreign> mentioned in the Remedy of
                                Love, 1. 338: "Does a swelling bosom cover all her breast, let no
                                stomacher conceal it." From Martial we learn that the "strophium"
                                was made of leather.</note> that they may be slender. If one is a
                            little inclined to plumpness, they declare that she's training for a
                                boxer,<milestone n="315" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Training for a boxer</lemma>: <quote lang="la">"Pugilem."</quote> This means "robust as a boxer," or
                                "athlete." These persons were naturally considered as the types of
                                robustness, being dieted for the purpose of increasing their flesh
                                and muscle.</note> and stint her food; although their constitutions
                            are good, by their treatment they make them as slight as bulrushes; and
                            so for that reason they are admired, forsooth.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What sort of a girl is this one of yours?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> A new style of beauty.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>ironically.</stage> Astounding!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Her complexion genuine,<milestone n="318" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Complexion genuine</lemma>:
                                "Color verus." The same expression is used by Ovid, in the Art of
                                Love, B. iii., 1. 164: <foreign lang="la">"Et melior vero quaeritur
                                    arte color:"</foreign> "And by art a color is sought superior to
                                the genuine one."</note> her flesh firm and full of
                                juiciness.<milestone n="318" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Full of juiciness</lemma>: <quote lang="la">"Succi plenum."</quote> A similar expression occurs in
                                the Miles Gloriosus of Plautus, 1. 787, where Periplecoimenus wishes
                                inquiry to be made for a woman who is <foreign lang="la">"siccam, at
                                    succidam,"</foreign> "sober, but full of juice:" i. e. replete
                                with the plumpness and activity of youth.</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Her age?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Her age Sixteen.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> The very flower of youth.<note anchored="yes">The very flower of
                                youth)--Ver. 319. Ovid makes mention of the <foreign lang="la">"flos"</foreign> or "bloom" of youth, Art of Love, B. ii., 1.
                                663: "And don't you inquire what year she is now passing, nor under
                                what Consulship she was born; a privilege which the rigid Censor
                                possesses. And this, especially, if she has passed the bloom of
                                youth, and her best years are fled, and she now pulls out the
                                whitening hairs." </note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Do you make, it your care to obtain her for me either by force, stealth,
                            or entreaty; so that I only gain her, it matters not how to me. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Well, but to whom does the damsel belong?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> That, i'faith, I don't know.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Whence did she come?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> That, just as much.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Where does she live?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Nor yet do I know that.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Where did you see her?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> In the street.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> How did you come to lose her?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Why, that's what I was just now fretting myself about; and I do not
                            believe that there is one individual to whom all good luck is a greater
                            stranger than to myself. What ill fortune this is! I'm utterly
                            undone!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What's the matter?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask me? Do you know Archidemides, my father's kinsman and
                            years'-mate?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Why not?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> He, while I was in full pursuit of her, met me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Unseasonably, upon my faith.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Aye, unhappily, rather; for other ordinary matters are to be called
                            "unseasonable," Parmeno. It would be safe for me to make oath that I
                            have not seen him for fully these six or seven months, until just now,
                            when I least wanted, and there was the least occasion. Come now! isn't
                            this like a fatality? What do you say?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Extremely so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> At once he came running up to me, from a considerable distance,
                            stooping, palsied, hanging his lip, and wheezing. "Halloo, Chaerea!
                            halloo!" said he; "I've something to say to you." I stopped. "Do you
                            know what it is I want with you?" said he. "Say on," said I. "To-morrow
                            my cause comes on," said he. "What then?" "Be sure and tell your father
                            to remember and be my advocate<note anchored="yes">Be my advocate)--Ver.
                                340. <quote lang="la">"Advocatus."</quote> It must be remembered
                                that this word did not among the Romans bear the same sense as
                                the-word "advocate" does with us. The "advocati" were the friends of
                                a man who accompanied him when his cause was pleaded, and often
                                performed the part of witnesses; those who assisted a person in a
                                dispute or difficulty were also his "advocati," and in this respect
                                distantly resembled the "second" or "friend" of a party in the
                                modern duel. In the Phormio, Hegio, Cratinus, and Crito are
                                introduced as the "advocati" of Demipho. See also the Paenulus of
                                Plautus, and the Notes to that Play in Bohn's Translation. </note>
                            in the morning." In talking of this, an hour elapsed.<note anchored="yes">An hour elapsed)--Ver. 341. <quote lang="la">"Hora"</quote> is here used to signify the long time, that, in
                                his impatience, it appeared to him to be. </note> I inquired if he
                            wanted any thing else. "That's all," said he. I left him. When I looked
                            in this direction for the damsel, she had that very instant turned this
                            way down this street of ours.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> It's a wonder if he doesn't mean her who has just
                            now been made a present of to Thais here.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> When I got here, she was nowhere to be seen.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Some attendants, I suppose, were accompanying the girl?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Yes; a Parasite, and a female servant.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> It's the very same. <stage>To CHAEREA.</stage>
                            It's all over with you; make an end of it; you've said your last.<note anchored="yes">It's all over with you,--you've said your last)--Ver.
                                347. <foreign lang="la">"Ilicet"</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">"conclamatum est,"</foreign> are words of mournful import,
                                which were used with regard to the funeral rites of the Romans.
                                "Ilicet," "you may begone," was said aloud when the funeral was
                                concluded. "Conclamare," implied the ceremony of calling upon the
                                dead person by name, before light was set to the funeral pile; on no
                                answer being given, he was concluded to be really dead, and the pile
                                was set fire to amid the cries of those present: "conclamatum est"
                                would consequently signify that all hope has gone. </note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> You are thinking about something else.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Indeed I'm thinking of this same matter.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Pray, tell me, do you know her, or did you see her?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I did see, and I do know her, I am aware to what house she has been
                            taken.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> What, my dear Parmeno, do you know her, and are you aware where she
                            is?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> She has been brought here <stage>pointing</stage> to the house of Thais
                            the Courtesan.<note anchored="yes">Thais the Courtesan)--Ver. 352. Cooke
                                remarks here, somewhat hypercritically as it would seem: "Thais is
                                not called 'meretrix' here opprobriously, but to distinguish her
                                from other ladies of the same name, who were not of the same
                                profession." </note> She has been made a present to her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> What opulent person is it, to be presenting a gift so precious as
                            this?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> The Captain Thraso, Phaedria's rival. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> An unpleasant business for my brother, it should seem.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Aye, and if you did but know what present he is pitting against this
                            present, you would say so still more.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Troth now, what is it, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> A Eunuch.<milestone n="356" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A Eunuchl</lemma>: Eunuchs formed part of the
                                establishment of wealthy persons, who, in imitation of the Eastern
                                nobles, confided the charge of their wives, daughters, or mistresses
                                to them. Though Thais would have no such necessity for his services,
                                her wish to imitate the "reginae," or "great ladies," would. make
                                him a not unacceptable present. See the Addresses of Ovid to the
                                Eunuch Bagous in the Amours, B. ii., El. 2, 3.</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> What! that unsightly creature, pray, that he purchased yesterday, an old
                            woman?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> That very same.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> To a certainty, the gentleman will be bundled out of doors, together
                            with his present; but I wasn't aware that this Thais is our
                            neighbor.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> It isn't long since she came.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Unhappy wretch that I am! never to have seen her, even. Come now, just
                            tell me, is she as handsome as she is reported to be?<note anchored="yes">As she is reported to be)--Ver. 361. Donatus remarks
                                this as an instance of the art of Terence, in preserving the
                                probability of Chaerea's being received for the Eunuch. He shows
                                hereby that he is so entirely a stranger to the family that he does
                                not even know the person of Thais. It is also added that she has not
                                been long in the neighborhood, and he lias been on duty at the
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>. The
                                meaning of his regret is, that, not knowing Thais, he will not have
                                an opportunity of seeing the girl. </note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Quite.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> But nothing in comparison with this damsel of mine?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Another thing altogether.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Troth now, Parmeno, prithee do contrive for me to gain possession of
                            her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'll do my best, and use all my endeavors; I'll lend you my assistance.
                                <stage>Going.</stage> Do you want any thing else with me?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Where are you going now?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Home; to take those slaves to Thais, as your brother ordered me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Oh, lucky Eunuch that! really, to be sent as a present to that house!
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Why so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask? He will always see at home a fellow-servant of consummate
                            beauty, and be conversing with her; he will be in the same house with
                            her; sometimes he will take his meals with her; sometimes sleep near
                            her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What now, if you yourself were to be this fortunate person?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> By what means, Parmeno? Tell me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Do you assume his dress.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> His dress! Well, what then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'll take you there instead of him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>musing.</stage> I hear you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'll say that you are he.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I understand you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> You may enjoy those advantages which you just now said lie would enjoy;
                            you may take your meals together with her, be in company with her, touch
                            her, dally with her, and sleep by her side; as not one of these women is
                            acquainted with you, nor yet knows who you are. Besides, you are of an
                            age and figure that you may easily pass for a eunuch.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> You speak to the purpose; I never knew better counsel given. Well, let's
                            go in at once; dress me up, take me away, lead me to her, as fast as you
                            can.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What do you mean? Really, I was only joking.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> You talk nonsense.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'm undone! Wretch that I am! what have I done? <stage>CHAEREA pushes
                                him along.</stage> Whither are you pushing me? You'll throw me down
                            presently. I entreat you, be quiet.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Let's be off. <stage>Pushes him.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Do you still persist?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I am resolved upon it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Only take care that this isn't too rash a project.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Certainly it isn't; let me alone for that.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Aye, but I shall have to pay the penalty<note anchored="yes">Have to pay
                                the penalty)--Ver. 381. "In me cudetur faba," literally, "the bean
                                will be struck" or "laid about me;" meaning, "I shall have to smart
                                for it." There is considerable doubt what is the origin of this
                                expression, and this doubt existed as early as the time of Donatus.
                                He says that it was a proverb either taken from the threshing of
                                beans with a flail by the countrymen; or else from the circumstance
                                of the cooks who have dressed the beans, but have not moistened them
                                sufficiently, being sure to have them thrown at their heads, as
                                though for the purpose of softening them. Neither of these solutions
                                seems so probable as that suggested by Madame Dacier, that dried
                                beans were inserted in the thongs of the "scuticae," or "whips,"
                                with which the slaves were beaten. According to others the knots in
                                the whips were only called "fabae," from their resemblance to beans.
                            </note> for this? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Pshaw!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> We shall be guilty of a disgraceful action.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> What, is it disgraceful<note anchored="yes">Is it disqraceful)--Ver.
                                382. Donatus remarks that here Terence obliquely defends the subject
                                of the Play. </note> to be taken to the house of a Courtesan, and to
                            return the compliment upon those tormentors who treat us and our
                            youthful age so scornfully, and who are always tormenting us in every
                            way;--to dupe them just as we are duped by them? Or is it right and
                            proper that in preference my father should be wheedled out of his money
                            by deceitful pretexts? Those who knew of this would blame me; while all
                            would think the other a meritorious act.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What's to be done in such case? If you are determined to do it, you must
                            do it: but don't you by-and-by be throwing the blame upon me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I shall not do so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Do you order me, then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I order, charge, and command you; I will never disavow my authorizing
                            you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Follow me; may the Gods prosper it! <stage>They go into the house of
                                LACHES.</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="act" n="3">
				<div2 type="scene" n="1">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="390" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THRASO and GNATHO.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Did Thais really return me many thanks?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Exceeding thanks.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Was she delighted, say you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Not so much, indeed, at the present itself, as because it was given by
                            you; really, in right earnest, she does exult at that. <stage>Enter
                                PARMIENO unseen, from LACHES' house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I've come here to be on the look-out, that when
                            there is an opportunity I may take the presents. But see, here's the
                            Captain.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Undoubtedly it is the case with me, that every thing I do is a cause for
                            thankfulness.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith, I've observed it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> The most mighty King,<milestone n="397" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The most mighty King</lemma>: It
                                has been suggested that Darius III. is here alluded to, who was a
                                contemporary of Menander. As however Pyrrhus, king of <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>, is mentioned in this Play,
                                there is no necessity to go out of the way to make Terence guilty of
                                an anachronism. Madame Dacier suggests that Seleucus, king of part
                                of <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>, is meant;
                                and as Thraso is called "a stranger" or "foreigner" toward the end
                                of the Play, he probably was intended to be represented as a native
                                of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> and a subject of
                                Seleucus. One of the Seleuci was also favored with the services of
                                Pyrgopolinices, the "Braggart Captain" of Plautus, in the Miles
                                Gloriosus. See 1. 75 in that Play: "For King Seleucus entreated me
                                with most earnest suit that I would raise and enlist recruits for
                                him."</note> even, always used to give me especial thanks for
                            whatever I did; but not so to others.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> He who has the wit that you have, often by his words appropriates to
                            himself the glory that has been achieved by the labor of others.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> You've just hit it.<note anchored="yes">You've just hit it)--Ver. 401.
                                Colman here remarks, quoting the following passage from Shakspeare's
                                "Love's Labor Lost," "That that Poet was familiarly acquainted with
                                this Comedy is evident from the passage, 'Holofernes says, Novi
                                hominem tanquam te. His humor is lofty, his discourse peremptory,
                                his tongue filed, his eye ambitious, his gait majestical, and his
                                general behavior vain, ridiculous, and Thrasonical.'" We may remark
                                that the previous words of Gnatho, though spoken with reference to
                                the King, contain a reproach against the Captain's boastfulness,
                                though his vanity will not let him perceive it. </note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> The king, then, kept you in his eye.<note anchored="yes">In his
                                eye)--Ver. 401. "In oculis" is generally supposed to mean "as dearly
                                in his eyes." As, however, the Satraps of the East were called "the
                                king's eyes," those who suppose that Darius is alluded to, might
                                with some ground consider the passage as meaning that the king
                                ranked him in the number of his nobles. See the Paenulus of Plautus,
                                1. 693, and the Note in Bohn's Translation. </note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Just so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> To enjoy your society.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> True; he intrusted to? me all his army, all his state secrets. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Astonishing!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Then if, on any occasion, a surfeit of society, or a dislike of
                            business, came upon him, when he was desirous to take some recreation;
                            just as though--you understand?<milestone n="405" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">You understand</lemma>: He says
                                this at the very moment when lie is at a loss what to say next; the
                                Parasite obligingly steps in to help him out with the
                                difficulty.</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I know; just as though on occasion he would rid his mind of those
                            anxieties.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> You have it. Then he used to take me aside as his only boon
                            companion.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Whew! You are telling of a King of refined taste.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Aye, he is a person of that sort; a man of but very few
                            acquaintanceships.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> Indeed, of none,<milestone n="410" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Indeed, of none</lemma>:
                                "Immo, nullorum arbitror, si tecum vivit." This expression which is
                                used "aside," has two meanings, neither of which is complimentary to
                                the Captain. It may mean, "he has no society if he associates with
                                you," making the Captain equivalent to nobody; or it may signify,
                                "if he associates with you he'll be sure to drive all his other
                                acquaintances away."</note> I fancy, if he's on intimate terms with
                            you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> All the people envied me, and attacked me privately. I don't care one
                            straw. They envied me dreadfully; but one in particular, whom the King
                            had appointed over the Indian elephants.<milestone n="413" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Over the
                                    Indian elephants</lemma>: Here he shows his lofty position to
                                perfection; he dares to take down the pride of one who commanded
                                even the royal elephants. The Braggart Captain of Plautus comes into
                                collision with the elephants themselves: l. 26. Artotrogus says to
                                him, "In what a fashion it was you broke the fore-leg of even an
                                elephant in <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> with your
                                fist!"</note> Once, when he became particularly troublesome,
                            "Prithee, Strato," said I, "are you so fierce because you hold command
                            over the wild beasts?"</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Cleverly said, upon my faith, and shrewdly. Astounding! You did give the
                            fellow a home thrust. What said he?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Dumfounded, instantaneously.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> How could he be otherwise?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Ye Gods, by our trust in you! a lost and miserable
                            fellow the one, and the other a scoundrel.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Well then, about that: matter, Gnatho, the way in which I touched up the
                            Rhodian at a banquet--did I never tell you? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Never; but pray, do tell me. <stage>Aside.</stage> I've heard it more
                            than a thousand times already.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> There was in my company at a banquet, this young man of Rhodes, whom I'm
                            speaking of. By chance I had a mistress there; he began to toy with her,
                            and to annoy me. "What are you doing, sir impudence?" said I to the
                            fellow; "a hare yourself, and looking out for game?"<milestone n="426" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Lookinq
                                    out for game?</lemma>: "Pulmentum," more strictly speaking, "A
                                nice bit." Patrick has the following Note on this passage: "'Lepus
                                tute es, et pulmentum quaeris?' A proverbial expression in use at
                                that time: the proper meaning of it, stripped of its figure, is,
                                'You are little more than a woman yourself, and do you want a
                                mistress?'" We learn from Donatus and Vopiscus, that Livius
                                Andronicus had used this proverb in his Plays before Terence.
                                Commentators who enter into a minute explanation of it offer many
                                conjectures rather curious than solid, and of a nature not fit to be
                                mentioned here. Donatus seems to think that allusion is made to a
                                story prevalent among the ancient naturalists that the hare was in
                                the habit of changing its sex.</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>pretending to laugh very heartily.</stage> Ha, ha, ha!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> What's the matter?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> How apt, how smart, how clever; nothing could be more excellent.
                            Prithee, was this a saying of yours? I fancied it was an old one.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Did you ever hear it before?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Many a time; and it is mentioned among the first-rate ones.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> It's my own.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I'm sorry though that it was said to a thoughtless young man, and one of
                            respectability.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> May the Gods confound you!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Pray, what did he do?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>. Quite disconcerted. All who were present were dying with laughter; in
                            short, they were all quite afraid of me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> [Not without reason.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> But hark you, had I best clear myself of this to Thais, as to her
                            suspicion that I'm fond of this girl?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> By no means: on the contrary, rather increase her jealousy.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Why so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask me? Don't you see, if on any occasion she makes mention of
                            Phaedria or commends him, to provoke you---- </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> I understand.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> That such may not be the case, this method is the only remedy. When she
                            speaks of Phaedria, do you instantly mention Pamphila. If at any time
                            she says, "Let's invite Phaedria to make one," do you say, "Let's ask
                            Pamphila to sing." If she praises his good looks, do you, on the other
                            hand, praise hers. In short, do you return like for like, which will
                            mortify her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> If, indeed, she loved me,<milestone n="446" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">If, indeed, she loved
                                me</lemma>: Colman has the following Note upon this passage: "I am
                                at a loss to determine whether it was in order to show the absurdity
                                of the Captain or from inadvertence in the Poet, that Terence here
                                makes Thraso and Gnatho speak in contradiction to the idea of
                                Thais's wonderful veneration for Thraso, with which they opened the
                                Scene."</note> this might be of some use, Gnatho.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Since she is impatient for and loves that which you give her, she
                            already loves you; as it is, then, it is an easy matter for her to feel
                            vexed. She will be always afraid lest the presents which she herself is
                            now getting, you may on some occasion be taking elsewhere.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Well said; that never came into my mind.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Nonsense. You never thought about it; else how much more readily would
                            you yourself have hit upon it, Thraso!</p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="2">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="453" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THAIS from her house, attended by PYTHIAS.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>as she comes out.</stage> I thought I just now heard the
                            Captain's voice. And look, here he is. Welcome, my dear Thraso.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> O my Thais, my sweet one, how are you? How much do you love me in return
                            for that music girl?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> How polite! What a beginning he has made on
                            meeting her!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Very much, as you deserve.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Let's go to dinner then. (To THRASO.) What do you stand here for?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Then there's the other one: you would declare that
                            he was born for his belly's sake. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> When you please; I sha'n't delay.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I'll accost them, and pretend as though I had just
                            come out. <stage>He comes forward.</stage> Are you going any where,
                            Thais?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Ha! Parmeno; well done; just going out for the day.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Where?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside, pointing at THRASO.</stage> Why! don't you see him?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> I see him, and I'm sorry for it.
                                <stage>Aloud.</stage> Phaedria's presents are ready for you when you
                            please.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>impatiently.</stage> Why are we to stand here? Why don't we be
                            off?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to THRASO.</stage> Troth now, pray, do let us, with your leave,
                            present to her the things we intend, and accost and speak to her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>ironically.</stage> Very fine presents, I suppose, or at least
                            equal to mine.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> The fact will prove itself. <stage>Goes to the door of LACHES' house and
                                calls.</stage> Ho there! bid those people come out of doors at once,
                            as I ordered. <stage>Enter from the house a BLACK GIRL.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Do you step forward this way. <stage>To THAIS.</stage> She comes all the
                            way from Aethiopia.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>contemptuously.</stage> Here are some three minae in value.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Hardly so much.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Where are you, Dorus? Step this way. <stage>Enter CHAEREA from the
                                house, dressed like the EUNUCH.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> There's a Eunuch for you--of what a genteel appearance! of what a prime
                            age!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> God bless me, he's handsome.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What say you, Gnatho? Do you see any thing to find fault with? And what
                            say you, Thraso? <stage>Aside.</stage> They hold their tongues; they
                            praise him sufficiently thereby. <stage>To THAIS.</stage> Make trial of
                            him in literature, try him in exercises,<milestone n="477" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In
                                    exercises</lemma>: Reference will be found made to the
                                "palaestrae," or "places of exercise," in the Notes to the
                                Translation of Plautus.</note> and in music; I'll warrant him well
                            skilled in what it becomes a gentleman to know.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> That Eunuch, if occasion served,<milestone n="479" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">If occasion
                                    served</lemma>: The Aposiopesis in this line is very aptly
                                introduced, on account of the presence of the female; but it
                                admirably illustrates the abominable turpitude of the speaker, and
                                perhaps in a somewhat more decent manner than that in which Plautus
                                attributes a similar tendency to his Braggart Captain, l.
                                1111.</note> even in my sober senses, I---</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> And he who has sent these things makes no request that you will live for
                            him alone, and that for his own sake others may be excluded; he neither
                            tells of battles nor shows his scars, nor does he restrict you as
                                <stage>looking at THRASO</stage> a certain person does; but when it
                            is not inconvenient, whenever you think fit, whenever you have the time,
                            he is satisfied to be admitted.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO, contemptuously.</stage> It appears that this is the
                            servant of some beggarly, wretched master.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Why, faith, no person, I'm quite sure of that, could possibly put up
                            with him, who had the means to get another.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> You hold your tongue--a fellow whom I consider beneath all men of the
                            very lowest grade: for when you can bring yourself to flatter that
                            fellow <stage>pointing at THRASO</stage>, I do believe you could pick
                            your victuals out of the very flames.<milestone n="491" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Out of the very
                                    flames</lemma>: This was a proverb expressive of the lowest
                                degree of meanness and infamy. When they burned the bodies of the
                                dead, it was the custom of the ancients to throw meat and various
                                articles of food upon the funeral pile, and it was considered the
                                greatest possible affront to tell a person that he was capable of
                                snatching these things out of the flames.</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Are we to go now?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I'll take these in-doors first <stage>pointing to CHAEREA and the
                                AETHIOPIAN</stage>, and at the same time I'll order what I wish;
                            after that I'll return immediately. <stage>Goes into the house with
                                PYTHIAS, CHAEREA, and the SLAVE.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO.</stage> I shall be off. Do you wait for her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> It is not a proper thing for a general to be walking in the street with
                            a mistress.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Why should I use many words with you? You are the very ape of your
                            master. (Exit PARMENO.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>laughing.</stage> Ha, ha, ha! </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> What are you laughing at?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> At what you were mentioning just now; that saying, too, about the
                            Rhodian, recurred to my mind. But Thais is coming out.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> You go before; take care that every thing is ready at home.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Very well. <stage>(Exit.)</stage>
                            <stage>Re-enter THAIS, with PYTHIAS and FEMALE ATTENDANTS.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Take care, Pythias, and be sure that if Chremes should happen to
                                come,<milestone n="513" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">If Chremes should happen to come</lemma>: This is
                                the first allusion to the arrangement which ultimately causes the
                                quarrel between Thais and the Captain.</note> to beg him to wait; if
                            that is not convenient, then to come again; if he can not do that, bring
                            him to me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I'll do so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Well, what else was I intending to say? O, do you take particular care
                            of that young woman; be sure that you keep at home.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Let us begone.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to her attendants.</stage> You follow me. <stage>Exeunt THAIS and
                                THRASO, followed by the Attendants. PYTHIAS goes into the
                                house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="3">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="506" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHREMES.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Why, really, the more and more I think of it,
                            I shouldn't be surprised if this Thais should be doing me some great
                            mischief; so cunningly do I perceive myself beset by her. Even on the
                            occasion when she first requested me to be fetched to her (any one might
                            ask me, "What business had you with her?" Really I don't know.) When I
                            came, she found an excuse for me to remain there; she said that she had
                            been offering a sacrifice,<milestone n="513" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Had been offering a
                                    sacrifice</lemma>: It was the custom to sacrifice before
                                entering on affairs of importance. Thus, too, Jupiter, in the
                                Amphitryon of Plautus, l. 938, speaks of offering sacrifice on his
                                safe return.</note> and that she was desirous to speak upon some
                            important business with me. Even then I had a suspicion that all these
                            things were being done for her artful purposes. She takes her place
                            beside me; pays every attention to me; seeks and opportunity of
                            conversation. When the conversation flagged, she turned off to this
                            point--how long since my father and mother died? I said that it was now
                            a long time ago. Whether I had any country-house at Sunium, and how far
                            from the sea? I suppose that this has taken her fancy, and she expects
                            to get it away from me. Then at last, whether any little sister of mine
                            had been lost from there; whether any person was with her; what she had
                            about her when she was lost; whether any one could recognize her. Why
                            should she make these inquiries? Unless, perhaps, she pretends--so great
                            is her assurance--that she herself is the same person that was formerly
                            lost when a little girl. But if she is alive, she is sixteen years old,
                            not older; whereas Thais is somewhat older than I am. She has sent to
                            press me earnestly to come. Either let her speak out what she wants, or
                            not be troublesome; I assuredly shall not come a third time
                                <stage>knocking at the door of THAIS</stage>. Ho! there, ho! there!
                            Is any one here? It's I, Chremes. <stage>Enter PYTHIAS from the
                                house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> O most charming, dear creature!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I said there was a design upon me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Thais entreated you most earnestly to come again to-morrow.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I'm going into the country.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Do, there's a dear sir.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I can not, I tell you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Then stay here at our house till she comes back.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Nothing less likely.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Why, my dear Chremes? <stage>Taking hold of him.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>shaking her off.</stage> Away to perdition with you!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> If you are so determined about it, pray do step over to the place where
                            she is.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I'll go there. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>calling at the door.</stage> Here, Dorias <stage>DORIAS
                                enters</stage>, show this person directly to the Captain's.
                                <stage>(Exit CHREMES with DORIAS, PYTHIAS goes into the
                                house.)</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="4">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="538" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter ANTIPHO.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Yesterday some young fellows of us agreed
                            together at the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>
                            that we were to go shares today in a club-entertainment. We gave Chaerea
                            charge of this matter; our rings were given<milestone n="541" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Our rings
                                    were given</lemma>: It was the custom of parties who agreed to
                                join in a "symbola," or "club" or "picnic" entertainment, to give
                                their rings as pledges to the "rex convivii," or "getter up the
                                feast." Stakes were also deposited on making bets at races. See
                                Ovid's Art of Love, B. i., l. 168.</note> as pledges; the place and
                            time arranged. The time has now gone by; at the place appointed there
                            was nothing ready. The fellow himself is nowhere to be met with; I
                            neither know what to say nor what to suppose. Now the rest have
                            commissioned me with his business, to look for him. I'll go see,
                            therefore, if he's at home. But who's this, I wonder, coming out of
                            Thais's? Is it he, or is it not? 'Tis the very man! What sort of being
                            is this? What kind of garb is this? What mischief is going on now? I can
                            not sufficiently wonder or conjecture. But, whatever it is, I should
                            like first at a distance to try and find out. <stage>He stands
                                apart.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="5">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="548" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHAEREA from the house of Thais, in the EUNUCH'S dress.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>looking around, then aloud to himself.</stage> Is there any body
                            here? There's no one. Is there any one following me from there? There's
                            not a person. Now am I not at liberty to give vent to these raptures? O
                            supreme <persName>Jupiter</persName>! now assuredly
                            is the time for me to meet my death,<milestone n="550" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To meet my
                                death</lemma>: There is a passage in the Othello of Shakspeare
                                extremely similar to this: <cit>
                                    <quote lang="en">
                                        <l>----"If I were now to die,</l>
                                        <l>I were now to be most happy; for, I fear,</l>
                                        <l>My soul hath her content so absolute,</l>
                                        <l>That not another comfort, like to this,</l>
                                        <l>Succeeds in unknown fate."</l>
                                    </quote>
                                    <bibl n="shak. oth 2.1.201">(act II, scene i)</bibl>
                                </cit></note> when I can so well endure it; lest my life should
                            sully this ecstasy with some disaster. But is there now no inquisitive
                            person to be intruding upon me, to be following me wherever I do, to be
                            deafening me, worrying me to death, with asking questions; why thus
                            transported, or why so overjoyed, whither I'm going, whence I'm come,
                            where I got this garb, what is my object, whether I'm in my senses or
                            whether downright mad?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I'll accost him, and I'll do him the favor which I
                            see he's wishing for. <stage>Accosting him.</stage> Chaerea, why are you
                            thus transported? What's the object of this garb? Why is it that you're
                            so overjoyed? What is the meaning of this? Are you quite right in your
                            senses? Why do you stare at me? What have you to say?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> O joyous day! O welcome, my friend! There's not one in all the world
                            whom I would rather wish to see at this moment that yourself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Pray, do tell me what all this means.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Nay rather, i'faith, I beg of you to listen to me. Do you know the
                            mistress whom my brother is so fond of?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> I know her; I suppose you mean Thais?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> The very same.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> So far I recollect.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> To-day a certain damsel was presented to her. Why now should I extol or
                            commend her beauty to you, Antipho, since you yourself know how nice a
                            judge of beauty I am? I have been smitten by her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Do you say so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> If you saw her, I am sure you would say she's exquisite. What need of
                            many words? I fell in love with her. By good luck there was at our house
                            a certain Eunuch, whom my brother had purchased for Thais, and he had
                            not as yet been sent to her. On this occasion, Parmeno, our servant,
                            made a suggestion to me, which I adopted. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> What was it?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Be quiet, and you shall hear the sooner; to change clothes with him, and
                            order myself to be taken there in his stead.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> What, instead of the Eunuch?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> The fact.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> To receive what advantage, pray, from this plan?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask? That I might see, hear, and be in company with her whom I
                            loved, Antipho. Is that a slight motive, or a poor reason? I was
                            presented to the woman. She, as soon as she received me, joyfully took
                            me home to her house and intrusted the damsel----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> To whom? To you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> To me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>ironically.</stage> In perfect safety, at all events.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> She gave orders that no male was to come near her, and commanded me not
                            to stir away from her; that I was to remain alone with her in the inner
                                apartments.<milestone n="579" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In the inner apartments</lemma>: The
                                "Gynecaea," or women's apartments, among the Greeks, always occupied
                                the interior part of the house, which was most distant from the
                                street, and there they were kept in great seclusion.</note> Looking
                            bashfully on the ground, I nodded assent.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>ironically.</stage> Poor fellow!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>continuing.</stage> "I am going out," said she, "to dinner." She
                            took her maids with her; a few novices of girls<milestone n="582" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A few
                                    novices of girls</lemma>: These "noviciae" were young slaves
                                recently bought, and intended to be trained to the calling of a
                                Courtesan.</note> remained, to be about her. These immediately made
                            preparations for her to bathe. I urged them to make haste. While
                            preparations were being made, the damsel sat in a room looking up at a
                            certain painting,<milestone n="584" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At a certain painting</lemma>:
                                See the story of <persName>Jupiter</persName>
                                and Dana&euml;, the daughter of Acrisius, king of <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, in the Metamorphoses of
                                Ovid, B. iv., l. 610. Pictures of Venus and Adonis, and of
                                    <persName>Jupiter</persName> and Ganymede,
                                are mentioned in the Menaechmi of Plautus; l. 144, and paintings on
                                the walls are also mentioned in the Mostellaria of Plautus, l. 821,
                                where Tranio tries to impose upon Theuropides by pretending to point
                                out a picture of a crow between two vultures.</note> in which was
                            represented how Jove<milestone n="584" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">How Jove</lemma>: Donatus
                                remarks here that this was "a very proper piece of furniture for the
                                house of a Courtesan, giving an example of loose and mercenary Love,
                                calculated to excite wanton thoughts, and at the same time hinting
                                to the young lover that he must make his way to the bosom of his
                                mistress, like <persName>Jupiter</persName> to
                                Dana&euml;, in a shower of gold. Oh the avarice of
                                harlots!"</note> is said once to have sent a golden shower into the
                            bosom of Dana&euml;. I myself began to look at it as well, and as he
                            had in former times played the like game, I felt extremely delighted
                            that a God should change himself into money, and slily come through the
                            tiles of another person's house, to deceive the fair one by means of a
                            shower. But what God was this? He who shakes the most lofty temples of
                            heaven with his thunders. Was I, a poor creature of a mortal,<milestone n="591" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A
                                    poor creature of a mortal</lemma>: "Homuncio." He uses this word
                                the better to contrast his abject nature as a poor mortal with the
                                majesty of <persName>Jupiter</persName>. St.
                                    Augustin refers to this
                                passage. The preceding line is said by Donatus to be a parody on a
                                passage by Ennius.</note> not to do the same? Certainly, I was to do
                            it, and without hesitation. While I was thinking over these matters with
                            myself, the damsel meantime was fetched away to bathe; she went, bathed,
                            and came back; after which they laid her on a couch. I stood waiting to
                            see if they gave me any orders. One came up, "Here, Dorus," said she,
                            "take this fan,<milestone n="595" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Take this fan</lemma>: As to the fans of
                                the ancients, see the Trinummus of Plautus, l. 252, and the Note to
                                the passage in Bohn's Translation. See also the Amours of <persName>Ovid</persName>, B. iii., El. 2, l.
                                38.</note> and let her have a little air in this fashion, while we
                            are bathing; when we have bathed, if you like, you may bathe too." With
                            a demure air I took it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Really, I should very much have liked to see that impudent face of yours
                            just then, and what figure a great donkey like you made, holding a
                            fan!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>continuing.</stage> Hardly had she said this, when all, in a
                            moment, betook themselves off: away they went to bathe, and chattered
                                aloud;<milestone n="600" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Chattered aloud</lemma>: This line bears a
                                strong resemblance to two lines found in Anstey's new Bath Guide:
                                    <quote lang="en">
                                    <l>"And how the young ladies all set up their clacks,</l>
                                    <l>All the while an old woman was rubbing their backs."</l>
                                </quote></note> just as the way is when masters are absent.
                            Meanwhile, sleep overtook the damsel; I slily looked askance<milestone n="601" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I
                                    slily looked askance</lemma>: This way of looking aside,
                                "limis," is mentioned in the Miles Gloriosus of Plautus, where
                                Milphidippa tells Acroteleutium to look at the Captain sideways,
                                "Aspicito limis," l. 1217; also in the Bacchides, l. 1131. Those
                                familiar with the works of Hogarth will readily call to mind the
                                picture of Bedlam in the Rake's Progress, where the young woman is
                                looking askance through her fan at the madman in his cell.</note>
                            through the fan;<milestone n="602" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Through the fan</lemma>: This shows that
                                the fan was probably one made of thin boards, and not of
                                feathers.</note> this way <stage>showing how</stage>: at the same
                            time I looked round in all directions, to see whether all was quite
                            safe. I saw that it was. I bolted the door.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> What then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Eh? What then, you simpleton?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> I own I am.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Was I to let slip the opportunity offered me, so excellent, so
                                short-lived,<milestone n="605" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">So short-lived</lemma>: Colman has the following Note
                                here: "Short indeed, considering the number of incidents, which,
                                according to Chaerea's relation, are crowded into it. All the time
                                allowed for this adventure is the short space between the departure
                                of Thais and Thraso and the entrance of Chaerea; so that all this
                                variety of business of sleeping, bathing, ravishing, &amp;c., is
                                dispatched during the two soliloquies of Antipho and Chaerea, and
                                the short Scene between Chremes and Pythias. The truth is, that a
                                very close adherence to the unities often drives the Poet into as
                                great absurdities as the perfect violation of them."</note> so
                            longed for, so unexpected. In that case, i'faith, I really should have
                            been the person I was pretending to be.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Troth, you certainly are in the right; but, meantime, what has been
                            arranged about the club-entertainment?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> All's ready.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> You are a clever hand; but where? At your house?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> No, at Discus's, our
                            freedman.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> That's a long way off.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Then let's make so much the greater haste.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Change your dress.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Where am I to change it? I'm at a loss; for at present I'm an exile from
                            home; I'm afraid of my brother, lest he should be in-doors: and then
                            again of my father, lest he should have returned from the country by
                            this.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Let's go to my house; there is the nearest place for you to change.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> You say right. Let's be off; besides, I want to take counsel with you
                            about this girl, by what means I may be able to secure the future
                            possession of her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>ANTIPHO</speaker>
						<p> Very well. <stage>(Exeunt.)</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="act" n="4">
				<div2 type="scene" n="1">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="614" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter DORIAS, with a casket in her hand.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to herself.</stage> So may the Gods bless me, but from what I
                            have seen, I'm terribly afraid that this mad fellow will be guilty of
                            some disturbance to-day or of some violence to Thais. For when this
                            young man, the brother of the damsel, arrived, she begged the Captain to
                            order him to be admitted; he immediately began to get into a passion,
                            and yet didn't dare refuse; Thais still insisted that he would invite
                            the man in. This she did for the sake of detaining him; because there
                            was no opportunity just then of telling him what she wanted to disclose
                            about her sister. He was invited in, and took his seat. Then she entered
                            into discourse with him. But the Captain, fancying it was a rival
                            brought before his very eyes, wanted in his turn to mortify her: "Hark
                            you, boy," said he, "go fetch Pamphila, that she may amuse us here." She
                            exclaimed, "At a banquet! Certainly not." The Captain still persisted to
                            a downright quarrel. Meanwhile my mistress secretly took off her golden
                                jewels,<milestone n="627" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Took off her golden jewels</lemma>: This
                                was probably because it was contrary to the laws of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for a Courtesan to appear
                                with gold or jewels in the street. Madame Dacier suggests another
                                reason, in which there is some force, although it is ridiculed by
                                Cooke. Thais may have supposed that the Captain, when irritated,
                                might not have scrupled to take them away from her. Indeed, nothing
                                would be more probable, than that he would be ready to take them by
                                way of security for the return of the slave, whom he had thus, to no
                                purpose, presented to her. In reference to the preceding line, we
                                may remark that it was not customary among the Greeks for females of
                                good character to appear at table with strangers.</note> and gave
                            them to me to take away: this is a sign, I'm sure, that she'll betake
                            herself from there as soon as she possibly can. <stage>Goes into the
                                house.</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="2">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="628" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PHAEDRIA.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> While I was going<milestone n="629" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">While I
                                    was going</lemma>: Donatus remarks that here the Poet artfully
                                finds a reason to bring Phaedria back again; as he at first with
                                equal art sent him out of the way, to give probability to those
                                incidents necessary to happen in his absence.</note> into the
                            country, I began on the road, as it mostly happens when there is any
                            anxiety on the mind, to reflect with myself upon one thing after
                            another, and upon every thing in the worst light. What need of words?
                            While I was musing thus, inadvertently I passed my country-house. I had
                            already got some distance from it, when I perceived this; I returned
                            again, really feeling quite uneasy; when I came to the very turning that
                            leads to the house, I came to a stop, and began to reason with myself;
                            "What! must I stay here alone for two days without her? Well, and what
                            then? It's nothing at all. What? Nothing at all? Well now, if I haven;t
                            the privilege of touching her, am I not even to have that of seeing her?
                            If I may not do the one, at least I may the other. Surely to love at a
                                distance<milestone n="640" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At a distance</lemma>: "Extrem&acirc;
                                line&acirc;." There have been many suggestions offered for the
                                origin of this figurative expression. Some suggest that it alludes
                                to the last or lowest stage of the supposed ladder of love; others
                                that it refers to the first or elementary line traced by the
                                student, when beginning to learn the art of painting. It is however
                                more generally thought to be a metaphor taken from the chariotraces
                                in the Circus, where, in going round the turning-place, he who was
                                nearest was said "currere in prim&acirc; line&acirc;;" the
                                next, "in secund&acirc;;" and so on to the last, who took the
                                widest range, and was said to run "in extrem&acirc;
                                line&acirc;."</note> even, is better than nothing at all." I
                            purposely passed the house. But how's this, that Pythias is suddenly
                            hurrying out in such a fright? <stage>Stands apart.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="3">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="642" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PYTHIAS and DORIAS in haste from the house of THAIS.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aloud.</stage> Where, wretch that I am, shall I find this wicked
                            and impious fellow? Or where look for him? That he should dare to commit
                            so audacious a crime as this! I'm ruined outright!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I dread what this may be.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Besides, too, the villain, after he had abused the girl, rent all the
                            poor thing's clothes, and tore her hair as well.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart, in surprise.</stage> Ha!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> If he were just now in my reach, how eagerly would I fly at that
                            villain's eyes with my nails!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Really I can't imagine what disturbance has
                            happened to us at home in my absence. I'll accost them. <stage>Going up
                                to them.</stage> What's the matter? Why in such haste? Or whom are
                            you looking for, Pythias?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Why, Phaedria, whom should I be looking for? Away with you, as you
                            deserve, with such fine presents of yours.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What is the matter?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> What, do you ask? The Eunuch you gave us, what confusion he has caused.
                            He has ravished the girl whom the Captain made present of to my
                            mistress.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What is it you say?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I'm ruined outright!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> You are drunk.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I wish that they were so, who wish ill to me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> Oh, prithee, my dear Pythias, what a monstrous thing this is!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> You are out of your senses. How could a Eunuch possibly do this?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I know nothing about him: as to what he has done, the thing speaks for
                            itself. The girl is in tears; and when you ask her what's the matter,
                            she does not dare tell. But he, a precious fellow, is nowhere to be
                            seen. To my sorrow I suspect too, that when he took himself off he
                            carried something away from the house.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I can not enough wonder, whither this varlet can possibly have betaken
                            himself to any distance from here; unless perhaps he has returned home
                            to our house.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Pray, go and see whether he is there.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I'll let you know immediately. <stage>Goes into the house of
                                LACHES.</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> Ruined outright! Prithee, my dear, I never did so much as hear of a deed
                            so abominable!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Why, faith, I had heard that they were extremely fond of the women, but
                            were incapable; unfortunately what has happened never came into my mind;
                            otherwise I should have shut him up somewhere, and not have intrusted
                            the girl to him.</p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="4">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="667" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PHAEDRIA from the house of LACHES, with DORUS in CHAEREA'S clothes.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>dragging him out.</stage> Come out, you villain! What, do you lag
                            behind, you runaway? Out with you, you sorry bargain!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>crying out.</stage> Mercy, I do entreat you!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Oh, do look at that! How the villain distorts his face. What means your
                            coming back hither? Why this change of dress? What have you to say? If I
                            had delayed a moment, Pythias, I shouldn't have found him at home: he
                            had just prepared, in this fashion, for flight. <stage>Pointing at his
                                dress.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Have you caught the fellow, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Caught him, why not?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> O well done!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith that really is capital!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Where is he?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask the question? Don't you see him? <stage>Pointing to the
                                EUNUCH.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>staring about.</stage> See whom, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> This fellow, to be sure <stage>pointing</stage>.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> What person is this?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> The same that was brought to your house to-day.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Not one of our people has ever beheld this person with her eyes,
                            Phaedria.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Not beheld him?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Prithee, did you fancy that this was he who was brought to our
                            house?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Why, I had no other. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> O dear! this one really isn't to be compared with the other. He was of a
                            handsome and genteel appearance.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> He seemed so, just then, because he was decked out in party-colored
                                clothes:<milestone n="683" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In party-colored clothes</lemma>: It was
                                the custom to dress Eunuchs in party-colored clothes of bright hue.
                                Most probably it was from them that the "motley" descended to the
                                fools and buffoons of the Middle Ages.</note> now he appears ugly,
                            for this reason--because he hasn't got them on.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Prithee, do hold your tongue; as though indeed the difference was so
                            trifling. A young man was brought to our house to-day, whom, really,
                            Phaedria, you would have liked to look upon. This is a withered,
                            antiquated, lethargic, old fellow, with a speckled complexion.<milestone n="689" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With a speckled complexion</lemma>: "Colore stellionino;"
                                probably having spots or freckles on his face like a "stellio" or
                                "lizard."</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>starting.</stage> Hah! What tale is this? You'll so befool me
                            that I sha'n't know what I bought. <stage>To DORUS.</stage> How now,
                            sirrah, did I not buy you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> You did buy me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Bid him answer me in my turn.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Question him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to DORUS.</stage> Did you come here to-day to our house?
                                <stage>DORUS shakes his head.</stage> He says, no. But it was the
                            other one that came, about sixteen years of age; whom Parmeno brought
                            with him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to DORUS.</stage> Well now, in the first place tell me this,
                            where did you get that dress that you have on? What, are you silent?
                            Monster of a fellow, are you not going to speak? <stage>Shakes
                                him.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Chaerea came.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What, my brother?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Yes.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> When?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> To-day.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> How long since?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Just now.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> With whom?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> With Parmeno. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Did you know him before?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> No.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> How did you know he was my brother?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Parmeno said he was. He gave me these clothes.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I'm undone!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> He himself put on mine; afterward, they both went out together.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Now are you quite satisfied that I am sober, and that we have told you
                            no falsehood? Is it now sufficiently evident that the girl has been
                            ravished?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Avaunt, you beast, do you believe what he says?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> What is there to believe? The thing speaks for itself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart to DORUS.</stage> Step aside a little this way. Do you
                            hear? <stage>DORUS steps aside.</stage> A little further still. That
                            will do. Now tell me this once more; did Chaerea take your clothes off
                            you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> He did.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> And did he put them on?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> He did.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> And was he brought here instead of you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Yes.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Great Jupiter! O wicked and audacious fellow!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Woe unto me! Now at last will you believe that we have been insulted in
                            a disgraceful manner?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> It is no wonder that you believe what the fellow says.
                                <stage>Aside.</stage> What I'm to do I know not. <stage>Aside to
                                DORUS.</stage> Hark you, deny it all again. <stage>Aloud.</stage>
                            Can I not this day extract the truth from you? Did you really see my
                            brother Chaerea?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> No.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> He can't be brought to confess without being punished, I see: follow me
                            this way. At one moment he affirms, at another denies.
                                <stage>Aside.</stage> Ask pardon of me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Indeed, I do entreat you, Phaedria.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>kicking him.</stage> Be off in-doors.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORUS</speaker>
						<p> Oh! oh!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> How in any other fashion to get decently out of
                            this I don't know; for really it's all up with me. <stage>Aloud, with
                                pretended indignation.</stage> Will you be trifling with me even
                            here, you knave? <stage>Follows DORUS into the house.</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I'm as certain that this is the contrivance of Parmeno as that I'm
                            alive.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> So it is, no doubt.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I'faith, I'll find out a method to-day to be even with him. But now,
                            what do you think ought to be done, Dorias?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> Do you mean with regard to this girl?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Yes; whether I ought to mention it or be silent?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> Upon my word, if you are prudent, you won't know what you do know,
                            either about the Eunuch or the girl's misfortune. By this method you'll
                            both rid yourself of all perplexity, and have done a service to
                                her.<milestone n="722" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Have done a service to her</lemma>: Though some
                                would have "illi" here to refer to the damsel, and others again to
                                Phaedria, it is pretty clear that Madame Dacier is right in
                                suggesting that Thais is the person meant.</note> Say this only,
                            that Dorus has run away.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I'll do so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> But don't I see Chremes? Thais will be here just now.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Why so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>DORIAS</speaker>
						<p> Because when I came away from there, a quarrel had just commenced
                            between them.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Take in these golden trinkets; I shall learn from him what's the matter.
                                <stage>DORIAS takes the casket into the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="5">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="726" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHREMES, somewhat drunk.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Heyday! upon my faith, I've been bamboozled: the wine that I've drunk
                            has got the upper hand. But, so long as I was reclining, how extremely
                            sober I did seem to myself to be; when I got up, neither feet nor senses
                            were quite equal to their duty.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Chremes! </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>turning round.</stage> Who's that? What, Pythias; dear me, how
                            much more charming you now seem to me than a short time since!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Troth now, you are much more merry, that's certain.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith, it is a true saying, that "Venus grows cold without
                                <persName>Ceres</persName> and Bacchus." But has
                            Thais got here long before me?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Has she already come away from the Captain's?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> A long time ago; an age since. There has been a most violent quarrel
                            between them.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Did she say nothing about you following her?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Nothing at all; only, on going away, she gave me a nod.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Well now, wasn't that enough?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Why, I didn't know that she meant that, until the Captain gave me an
                            explanation, because I was dull of comprehension; for he bundled me out
                            of the house. But look, here she is; I wonder how it was I got here
                            before her.</p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="6">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="738" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THAIS.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to herself.</stage> I really do believe that he'll be here
                            presently, to force her away from me. Let him come; but if he touches
                            her with a single finger, that instant his eyes shall be torn out. I can
                            put up with his impertinences and his high-sounding words, as long as
                            they remain words: but if they are turned into realities, he shall get a
                            drubbing.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Thais, I've been here some time.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> O my dear Chremes, you are the very person I was wanting. Are you aware
                            that this quarrel took place on your account, and that the whole of this
                            affair, in fact, bore reference to yourself?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> To me? How so, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Because, while I've been doing my best to recover and restore your
                            sister to you, this and a great deal more like it I've had to put up
                            with.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Where is she?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> At home, at my house. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>starting.</stage> Hah!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What's the matter? She has been brought up in a manner worthy of
                            yourself and of her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> What is it you say?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> That which is the fact. Her I present to you, nor do I ask of you any
                            return for her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Thanks are both felt and shall be returned in such way, Thais, as you
                            deserve.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> But still, take care, Chremes, that you don't lose her, before you
                            receive her from me; for it is she, whom the Captain is now coming to
                            take away from me by force. Do you go, Pythias, and bring out of the
                            house the casket with the tokens.<milestone n="752" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Casket with the
                                    tokens</lemma>: It was the custom with the ancients when they
                                exposed their children, to leave with them some pledge or token of
                                value, that they might afterward be recognized by means of them. The
                                catastrophes of the Curculio, the Rudens, and other Plays of
                                Plautus, are brought about by taking advantage of this circumstance.
                                The reasons for using these tokens will be stated in a future
                                Note.</note></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>looking down the side Scene.</stage> Don't you see him,
                            Thais?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to THAIS.</stage> Where is it put?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> In the clothes' chest. Tiresome creature, why do you delay?
                                <stage>PYTHIAS goes into the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> What a large body of troops the Captain is bringing with him against
                            you. Bless me!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Prithee, are you frightened, my dear sir?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Get out with you. What, I frightened? There's not a man alive less
                            so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Then now is the time to prove it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Why, I wonder what sort of a man you take me to be.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Nay, and consider this too; the person that you have to deal with is a
                                foreigner;<milestone n="758" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Is a foreigner</lemma>: And therefore the
                                more unlikely to obtain redress from an Athenian tribunal. See the
                                    <title>Andria</title>, l. 811, and the
                                Note to the passage.</note> of less influence than you, less known,
                            and one that has fewer friends here.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I'm aware of that; but it's foolish to run the risk of what you are able
                            to avoid. I had rather we should prevent it, than, having received an
                            injury, avenge ourselves upon him. Do you go in and fasten the door,
                            while I run across hence to the Forum; I should like us to have the aid
                            of some legal adviser in this disturbance. <stage>Moves, as if
                                going.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>holding him.</stage> Stay.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Let me go, I'll be here presently.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> There's no occasion, Chremes. Only say that she is your sister, and that
                            you lost her when a little girl, and have now recognized her; then show
                            the tokens. <stage>Re-enter PYTHIAS from the house, with the
                                trinkets.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>giving them to THAIS.</stage> Here they are.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>giving them to CHREMES.</stage> Take them. If he offers any
                            violence, summon the fellow to justice; do you understand me?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Perfectly.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Take care and say this with presence of mind.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I'll take care.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Gather up your cloak. <stage>Aside.</stage> Undone! the very person whom
                            I've provided as a champion, wants one himself. <stage>They all go into
                                the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="7">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="770" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THRASO, followed by GNATHO, SANGA, and other Attendants.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Am I to submit, Gnatho, to such a glaring affront as this being put upon
                            me? I'd die sooner. Simalio, Donax, Syriscus, follow me! First, I'll
                            storm the house.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Quite right.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> I'll carry off the girl.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Very good.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> I'll give her own self a mauling.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Very proper.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>arranging the men.</stage> Advance hither to the main body,
                            Donax, with your crowbar; you, Simalio, to the left wing; you, Syriscus,
                            to the right. Bring up the rest; where's the centurion Sanga, and his maniple<milestone n="775" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And his maniple</lemma>: We learn from the Fasti of Ovid, B.
                                iii., l. 117-8, that in early times the Roman armies carried bundles
                                or wisps of hay upon poles by way of standards. "A long pole used to
                                bear the elevated wisps, from which circumstance the manipular
                                soldier derives his name." It appears from this passage, and from
                                other authors, that to every troop of one hundred men a "manipulus"
                                or wisp of hay (so called from "manum implere," to "fill the hand,"
                                as being "a handful"), was assigned as a standard, and hence in time
                                the company itself obtained the name of "manipulus," and the
                                soldier, a member of it, was called "manipularis." The "centurio,"
                                or "leader of a hundred," was the commanding officer of the
                                "manipulus."</note> of rogues? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>SANGA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>coming forward.</stage> See, here he is.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> What, you booby, do you think of fighting with a dish-clout,<milestone n="776" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With a dish-clout</lemma>: "Peniculo." This word meant a sponge
                                fastened to a stick, or the tail of a fox or an ox, which was used
                                as dusters or dish-clouts are at the present day for cleaning
                                tables, dishes, or even shoes. See the Menaechmi of Plautus, ver. 77
                                and 391.</note> to be bringing that here?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>SANGA</speaker>
						<p> What, I? I knew the valor of the general, and the prowess of the
                            soldiers; and that this could not possibly go on without bloodshed; how
                            was I to wipe the wounds?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Where are the others?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>SANGA</speaker>
						<p> Plague on you, what others? Sannio is the only one left on guard at
                            home.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO.</stage> Do you draw up your men in battle order; I'll
                            be behind the second rank;<milestone n="780" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Be behind the second
                                    rank</lemma>: "Post principia." The Captain, with that
                                discretion which is the better part of valor, chooses the safest
                                place in his army. The "principes" originally fought in the van,
                                fronting the enemy, and behind them were the "hastati" and the
                                "triarii." In later times the "hastati" faced the enemy, and the
                                "principes" were placed in the middle, between them and the
                                "triarii;" but though no longer occupying the front place, they
                                still retained the name. Thraso, then, places himself behind the
                                middle line.</note> from that position I'll give the word to all.
                                <stage>Takes his place behind the second rank.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> That's showing prudence; as soon as he has drawn
                            them up, he secures a retreat for himself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>pointing to the arrangements.</stage> This is just the way
                            Pyrrhus used to proceed.<milestone n="782" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pyrrhus used to proceed</lemma>:
                                He attempts to defend his cowardice by the example of Pyrrhus, the
                                powerful antagonist of the Romans, and one of the greatest generals
                                of antiquity. He might have more correctly cited the example of
                                Xerxes, who, according to Justin, did occupy that position in his
                                army.</note>
                            <stage>CHREMES and THAIS appear above at a window.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Do you see, Thais, what plan he is upon? Assuredly, that advice of mine
                            about closing the door was good.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> He who now seems to you to be a hero, is in reality a mere vaporer;
                            don't be alarmed.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO.</stage> What seems best to you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I could very much<milestone n="785" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I could very much</lemma>:
                                Although Vollbehr gives these words to Gnatho, yet, judging from the
                                context, and the words "ex occulto," and remembering that Thais and
                                Chremes are up at the window, there is the greatest probability that
                                these are really the words of Thais addressed aside to
                                Chremes.</note> like a sling to be given you just now, that you
                            might pelt them from here on the sly at a distance; they would be taking
                            to flight.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO.</stage> But look <stage>pointing</stage>, I see Thais
                            there herself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> How soon are we to fall to?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Hold <stage>holding him back</stage>; it behooves a prudent person to
                            make trial of every thing before arms. How do you know but that she may
                            do what I bid her without compulsion?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Ye Gods, by our trust in you, what a thing it is to be wise! I never
                            come near you but what I go away from you the wiser.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Thais, in the first place, answer me this. When I presented you that
                            girl, did you not say that you would give yourself up to me alone for
                            some days to come?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Well, what then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask the question? You, who have been and brought your lover under
                            my very eyes? What business had you with him? With him, too, you
                            clandestinely betook yourself away from me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I chose to do so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Then give me back Pamphila; unless you had rather she were taken away by
                            force.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Give her back to you, or you lay hands upon her? Of all the----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Ha! What are you about? Hold your tongue.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> What do you mean? Am I not to touch my own?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Your own, indeed, you gallows-bird!<milestone n="797" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">You
                                gallows-bird</lemma>: "Furcifer;" literally, "bearer of the
                                furca."</note>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to CHREMES.</stage> Have a care, if you please. You don't know
                            what kind of man you are abusing now.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO.</stage> Won't you be off from here? Do you know how
                            matters stand with you? If you cause any disturbance here to-day, I'll
                            make you remember the place, and day, and me too, for the rest of your
                            life.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I pity you, who are making so great a man as this your enemy.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I'll break your head this instant if you are not off.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Do you really say so, puppy? Is it that you are at?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to CHREMES.</stage> What fellow are you? What do you mean? What
                            business have you with her?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I'll let you know: in the first place, I assert that she is a freeborn
                            woman.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>starting.</stage> Ha!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> A citizen of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Whew!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> My own sister.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Brazen face!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Now, therefore, Captain, I give you warning; don't you use any violence
                            toward her. Thais, I'm going to Sophrona, the nurse, that I may bring
                            her here and show her these tokens.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> What! Are you to prevent me from touching what's my own?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> I will prevent it, I tell you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to THRASO.</stage> Do you hear him? He is convicting himself of
                            theft. Is not that enough for you?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Do you say the same, Thais?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Go, find some one to answer you. <stage>She and CHREMES go away from the
                                window.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to GNATHO.</stage> What are we to do now?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Why, go back again: she'll soon be with you, of her own accord, to
                            entreat forgiveness.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Do you think so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Certainly, yes. I know the disposition of women: when you will, they
                            won't; when you won't, they set their hearts upon you of their own
                            inclination.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> You judge right.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Shall I dismiss the army then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Whenever you like. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Sanga, as befits gallant soldiers,<milestone n="814" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">As befits gallant
                                    soldiers</lemma>: Beaumont and Fletcher not improbably had this scene
                                in view in their picture of the mob regiment in Philaster. The
                                ragged regiment which Shakspeare places under the commend of
                                Falstaff was not very unlike it, nor that which owned the valiant
                                Bombastes Furioso as its Captain.</note> take care in your turn to
                            remember your homes and hearths.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>SANGA</speaker>
						<p> My thoughts have been for some time among the sauce-pans.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> You are a worthy fellow.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>putting himself at their head.</stage> You follow me this way.
                                <stage>(Exeunt omnes.)</stage>
                        </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="act" n="5">
				<div2 type="scene" n="1">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="816" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THAIS from her house, followed by PYTHIAS.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What! do you persist, hussy, in talking ambiguously to me? "I do know;"
                            "I don't know;" "he has gone off;" "I have heard;" "I wasn't there."
                            Don't you mean to tell me plainly, whatever it is? The girl in tears,
                            with her garments torn, is mute; the Eunuch is off: for what reason?
                            What has happened? Won't you speak?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Wretch that I am, what am I to say to you? They declare that he was not
                            a Eunuch.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What was he then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> That Chaerea.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What Chaerea?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> That stripling, the brother of Phaedria.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What's that you say, you hag?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> And I am satisfied of it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Pray, what business had he at my house? What brought him there?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I don't know; unless, as I suppose, he was in love with Pamphila.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Alas! to my confusion, unhappy woman that I am, I'm undone, if what you
                            tell me is true. Is it about this that the girl is crying?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I believe so. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> How say you, you arch-jade? Did I not warn you about this very thing,
                            when I was going away from here?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> What could I do? Just as you ordered, she was intrusted to his care
                            only.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Hussy, I've been intrusting the sheep to the wolf. I'm quite ashamed to
                            have been imposed upon in this way. What sort of man was he?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Hush! hush! mistress, pray; we are all right. Here we have the very
                            man.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Where is he?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Why there, to the left. Don't you see?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I see.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Order him to be seized as quickly as possible.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What can we do to him, simpleton?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> What do to him, do you ask? Pray, do look at him; if his face doesn't
                            seem an impudent one.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Not at all.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Besides, what effrontery he has.</p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="2">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="839" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHAEREA, in the EUNUCH'S dress, on the other side of the stage.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> At Antipho's,<milestone n="839" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At
                                    Antipho's</lemma>: Madame Decier here observes that Chaerea
                                assigns very natural reasons for not having changed his dress; in
                                which the art of Terence is evident, since the sequel of the Play
                                makes it absolutely necessary that Chaerea should appear again
                                before Thais in the habit which he wore while in the house.</note>
                            both of them, father and mother, just as if on purpose, were at home, so
                            that I couldn't any way get in, but that they must have seen me. In the
                            mean time, while I was standing before the door, a certain acquaintance
                            of mine was coming full upon me. When I espied him, I took to my heels
                            as fast as I could down a narrow unfrequented alley; thence again to
                            another, and thence to another; thus have I been most dreadfully
                            harassed with running about, that no one might recognize me. But isn't
                            this Thais that I see? It is she. I'm at a stand. What shall I do? But
                            what need I care? What can she do to me? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PYTHIAS.</stage> Let's accost him. <stage>To CHAEREA.</stage>
                            Good Mister Dorus, welcome; tell me, have you been running away?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Madam, I did so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Are you quite pleased with it?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> No.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Do you fancy that you'll get off with impunity?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Forgive this one fault; if I'm ever guilty of another, then kill me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Were you in fear of my severity?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> No.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> No? What then?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>pointing at PYTHIAS.</stage> I was afraid of her, lest she might
                            be accusing me to you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> What had you done?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> A mere trifle.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Come now, a trifle, you impudent fellow. Does this appear a trifle to
                            you, to ravish a virgin, a citizen?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I took her for my fellow-servant.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Fellow-servant? I can hardly restrain myself from flying at his hair. A
                            miscreant! Even of his own free will he comes to make fun of us.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PYTHIAS.</stage> Won't you begone from here, you mad
                            woman?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Why so? Really, I do believe I should be something in this hang-dog's
                            debt, if I were to do so; especially as he owns that he is your
                            servant.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> We'll pass that by. Chaerea, you have behaved unworthily of yourself;
                            for if I am deserving in the highest degree of this affront, still it is
                            unbecoming of you to be guilty of it. And, upon my faith, I do not know
                            what method now to adopt about this girl: you have so confounded all my
                            plans, that I can not possibly return her to her friends in such a
                            manner as is befitting and as I had intended; in order that, by this
                            means, I might, Chaerea, do a real service to myself.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> But now, from henceforth, I hope, Thais, that there will be lasting
                            good-will between us. Many a time, from some affair of this kind and
                            from a bad beginning, great friendships have sprung up. What if some
                            Divinity has willed this? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I'faith, for my own part I both take it in that view and wish to do
                            so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Yes, prithee, do so. Be sure of this one thing, that I did not do it for
                            the sake of affronting you, but in consequence of passion.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> I understand, and, i'faith, for that reason do I now the more readily
                            forgive you. I am not, Chaerea, of a disposition so ungentle, or so
                            inexperienced, as not to know what is the power of love.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> So may the Deities kindly bless me, Thais; I am now smitten with you as
                            well.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Then, i'faith, mistress, I foresee you must have a care of him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I would not dare----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I won't trust you at all in any thing.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PYTHIAS.</stage> Do have done.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Now I entreat you that you will be my assistant in this affair. I
                            intrust and commit myself to your care; I take you, Thais, as my
                            protectress; I implore you; I shall die if I don't have her for my
                            wife.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> But if your father should say any thing----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Oh, he'll consent, I'm quite sure of that, if she is only a citizen.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> If you will wait a little, the brother himself of the young woman will
                            be here presently; he has gone to fetch the nurse, who brought her up
                            when a little child; you yourself, shall be present Chaerea, at his
                            recognition of her.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I certainly will stay.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> In the mean time, until he comes, would you prefer that we should wait
                            for him in the house, rather than here before the door?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Why yes, I should like it much.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTIH.</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to THAIS.</stage> Prithee, what are you going to do?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Why, what's the matter?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask? Do you think of admitting him after this into your
                            house?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Why not?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Trust my word for it, he'll be creating some new disturbance.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> O dear, prithee, do hold your tongue. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> You seem to me to be far from sensible of his assurance.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I'll not do any thing, Pythias.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith, I don't believe you, Chaerea, except in case you are not
                            trusted.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Nay but, Pythias, do you be my keeper.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith, I would neither venture to give any thing to you to keep,
                            nor to keep you myself: away with you!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Most opportunely the brother himself is coming.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I'faith, I'm undone. Prithee, let's be gone in-doors, Thais. I don't
                            want him to see me in the street with this dress on.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> For what reason, pray? Because you are ashamed?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Just so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Just so? But the young woman----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THAIS</speaker>
						<p> Go first; I'll follow. You stay here, Pythias, that you may show Chremes
                            in. <stage>THAIS and CHAEREA go into the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="3">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="909" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHREMES and SOPHRONA.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to herself.</stage> Well! what now can suggest itself to my mind?
                            What, I wonder, in order that I may repay the favor to that villain who
                            palmed this fellow off upon us?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Really, do bestir yourself more quickly, nurse.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>SOPHRONA</speaker>
						<p> I am bestirring.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> So I see; but you don't stir forward.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to CHREMES.</stage> Have you yet shown the tokens to the
                            nurse?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> All of them.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Prithee, what does she say? Does she recognize them?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHREMES</speaker>
						<p> Yes, with a full recollection of them.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Upon my faith, you do bring good news; for I really wish well to this
                            young woman. Go in-doors: my mistress has been for some time expecting
                            you at home. <stage>CHREMES and SOPHRONA go into THAIS'S house.</stage>
                            But look, yonder I espy that worthy fellow, Parmeno, coming: just see,
                            for heaven's sake, how leisurely he moves along. I hope I have it in my
                            power to torment him after my own fashion. I'll go in-doors, that I may
                            know for certain about the discovery; afterward I'll come out, and give
                            this villain a terrible fright. <stage>Goes into the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="4">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="922" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PAIMENO.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> I've just come back to see what Chaerea has
                            been doing here. If he has managed the affair with dexterity, ye Gods,
                            by our trust in you, how great and genuine applause will Parmeno obtain!
                            For not to mention that a passion, full of difficulty and expense, with
                            which he was smitten for a virgin, belonging to an extortionate
                            courtesan, I've found means of satisfying for him, without molestation,
                            without outlay, and without cost; then, this other point-that is really
                            a thing that I consider my crowning merit, to have found out the way by
                            which a young man may be enabled to learn the dispositions and manners
                            of courtesans, so that by knowing them betimes, he may detest them ever
                            after. <stage>PYTHIAS enters from the house unperceived.</stage> For
                            while they are out of doors, nothing seems more cleanly, nothing more
                            neat or more elegant; and when they dine with a gallant, they pick
                            daintily about:<milestone n="935" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pick daintily about</lemma>: He seems here
                                to reprehend the same practice against which Ovid warns his fair
                                readers, in his Art of Love, B. iii. l. 75. He says, "Do not first
                                take food at home," when about to go to an entertainment.
                                Westerhovius seems to think that "ligurio" means, not to "pick
                                daintily," but "to be fond of good eating;" and refers to the
                                Bacchides of Plautus as portraying courtesans of the "ligurient"
                                kind, and finds another specimen in Bacchis in: the
                                Heautontimorumenos.</note> to see the filth, the dirtiness, the
                            neediness of these women; how sluttish they are when at home, and how
                            greedy after victuals; in what a fashion they devour the black bread
                            with yesterday's broth:--to know all this, is salvation to a young
                            man.&lt; <stage>Enter PYTHIAS from the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart, unseen by PARMENO.</stage> Upon my faith, you villain,
                            I'll take vengeance upon you for these sayings and doings; so that you
                            sha'n't make sport of us with impunity. <stage>Aloud, coming
                                forward.</stage> O, by our trust in the Gods, what a disgraceful
                            action! O hapless young man! O wicked Parmeno, to have brought him
                            here!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What's the matter?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I do pity him; and so that I mightn't see it, wretched creature that I
                            am, I hurried away out of doors. What a dreadful example they talk of
                            making him!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> O Jupiter! What is this tumult? Am I then undone? I'll accost her.
                            What's all this, Pythias? What are you saying? An example made of
                            whom?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask the question, you most audacious fellow? You've proved the
                            ruin of the young man whom you brought hither for the Eunuch, while you
                            were trying to put a trick upon us.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> How so, or what has happened? Tell me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I'll tell you: that young woman who was to-day made a present to Thais,
                            are you aware that she is a citizen of this place, and that her brother
                            is a person of very high rank?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I didn't know that.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> But so she has been discovered to be; he, unfortunate youth, has
                            ravished her. When the brother came to know of this being done, in a
                            most towering rage, he----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Did what, pray?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> First, bound him in a shocking manner.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Bound him?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> And even though Thais entreated him that he wouldn't do so----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What is it you tell me?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Now he is threatening that he will also do that which is usually done to
                            ravishers; a thing that I never saw done, nor wish to.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> With what assurance does he dare perpetrate a crime so heinous?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> How "so heinous?"</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Is it not most heinous? Who ever saw any one taken up as a ravisher in a
                            courtesan's house?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I don't know.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> But that you mayn't be ignorant of this, Pythias, I tell you, and give
                            you notice that he is my master's son.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> How! Prithee, is it he? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Don't let Thais suffer any violence to be done to him. But why don't I
                            go in myself?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Take care, Parmeno, what you are about, lest you both do him no good and
                            come to harm yourself; for it is their notion, that whatever has
                            happened, has originated in you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What then, wretch that I am, shall I do, or how resolve? But look, I see
                            the old gentleman returning from the country; shall I tell him or shall
                            I not? By my troth, I will tell him; although I am certain that a heavy
                            punishment is in readiness for me; but it's a matter of necessity, in
                            order that he may rescue him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> You are wise. I'm going in-doors; do you relate to him every thing
                            exactly as it happened. <stage>Goes into the house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="5">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="970" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter LACHES.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> I have this advantage<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">This advantage</lemma>: Donatus here
                                observes that the Poet introduces Laches, as he has Parmeno just
                                before, in a state of perfect tranquillity, that their sudden change
                                of feeling may be the more diverting to the Audience.</note> from my
                            country-house being so near at hand; no weariness, either of country or
                            of town, ever takes possession of me; when satiety begins to come on, I
                            change my locality. But is not that our Parmeno? Surely it is he. Whom
                            are you waiting for, Parmeno, before the door here?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>pretends not to see him.</stage> Who is it <stage>Turning
                                round.</stage> Oh, I'm glad that you have returned safe.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Whom are you waiting for?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> I'm undone: my tongue cleaves to my mouth through
                            fright.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Why, what is it you are trembling about? Is all quite right? Tell
                            me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Master, in the first place, I would have you persuaded of what is the
                            fact; whatever has happened in this affair has happened through no fault
                            of mine.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> What is it? </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Really you have reason to ask. I ought first to have told you the
                            circumstances. Phaedria purchased a certain Eunuch, to make a present of
                            to this woman here.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> To what woman?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> To Thais.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Bought? Good heavens, I'm undone! For how much?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Twenty minae.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Done for, quite.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Then, Chaerea is in love with a certain music-girl here. <stage>Pointing
                                to THAIS'S house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> How! What? In love? Does he know already what a courtesan means? Is he
                            come to town? One misfortune close upon another.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Master, don't look so at me; he didn't do these things by my
                            encouragement.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Leave off talking about yourself. If I live, you hang-dog, I'll---- But
                            first give me an account of it, whatever it is.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> He was taken to the house of Thais in place of the Eunuch.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> In place of the Eunuch?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Such is the fact. They have since apprehended him in the house as a
                            ravisher, and bound him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Death!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Mark the assurance of courtesans.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>&gt;LACH.</speaker>
						<p> Is there any other calamity or misfortune besides, that you have not
                            told me of?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> That's all.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>LACHES</speaker>
						<p> Do I delay rushing in here? <stage>Runs into the house of
                            THAIS.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> There's no doubt but that I shall have a
                            heavy punishment for this affair, only that I was obliged to act thus.
                            I'm glad of this, that some mischief will befall these women here
                            through my agency, for the old man has, for a long time, been on the
                            look-out for some occasion<milestone n="999" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">For some occasion</lemma>: We
                                learn from Donatus that Menander was more explicit concerning the
                                resentment of Laches against Thais, on account of her having
                                corrupted Phaedria.</note> to do them a bad turn; at last he has
                            found it. </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="6">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="1001" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter PYTHIAS from the house of THAIS, laughing.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to herself, on entering.</stage> Never, upon my faith, for a long
                            time past, has any thing happened to me that I could have better liked
                            to happen, than the old gentleman just now, full of his mistake, coming
                            into our house. I had the joke all to myself, as I knew<milestone n="1003" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">As I knew</lemma>: She enjoyed it the more, knowing that the
                                old man had nothing to fear, as he had just heard the fiction which
                                she had imparted to Parmeno. Donatus observes that the terror of
                                Laches accounts for his sudden consent to the union of Chaerea with
                                Pamphila; for though he could not settle the matter any other way
                                with credit, he was glad to find that his son had made an unequal
                                match rather than endangered his life. Colman, however, observes
                                with considerable justice: "I think Chaerea apologizes still better
                                for this arrangement in the Scene with Thais at the opening of this
                                Act, where he says that he is confident of obtaining his father's
                                consent, provided Pamphila proves to be a citizen; and, indeed, the
                                match between them is rather a reparation of an injury done to her
                                than a degradation of himself."</note> what it was he feared.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Why, what's all this?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Now I'm come out to meet with Parmeno. But, prithee, where is he?
                                <stage>Looking around.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> She's looking for me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> And there he is, I see; I'll go up to him.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> What's the matter, simpleton? What do you mean? What are you laughing
                            about? Still going on?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>laughing.</stage> I'm dying; I'm wretchedly tired with laughing
                            at you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Why so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Do you ask? Upon my faith, I never did see, nor shall see, a more silly
                            fellow. Oh dear, I can not well express what amusement you've afforded
                            in-doors. And still I formerly took you to be a clever and shrewd
                            person. Why, was there any need for you instantly to believe what I told
                            you? Or were you not content with the crime, which by your advice the
                            young man had been guilty of, without betraying the poor fellow to his
                            father as well? Why, what do you suppose his feelings must have been at
                            the moment when his father saw him clothed in that dress? Well, do you
                            now understand that you are done for? <stage>Laughing.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Hah! what is it you say, you hussy? Have you been telling me lies? What,
                            laughing still? Does it appear so delightful to you, you jade, to be
                            making fools of us?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>laughing.</stage> Very much so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Yes, indeed, if you can do it with impunity.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> Exactly so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> By heavens, I'll repay you!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> I believe you; but, perhaps, that which you are threatening, Parmeno,
                            will need a future day; you'll be trussed up directly, for rendering a
                            silly young man remarkable for disgraceful conduct, and then betraying
                            him to his father; they'll both be making an example of you.
                                <stage>Laughing.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'm done for!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PYTHIAS</speaker>
						<p> This reward has been found you in return for that present of
                                yours;<milestone n="1022" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In return for that present of
                                    yours</lemma>: By the present she means Chaerea in the disguise
                                of the Eunuch.</note> I'm off. <stage>Goes into the
                            house.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Wretch that I am; just like a rat, this day
                            I've come to destruction through betrayal of myself.<milestone n="1023" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Through
                                    betrayal of myself</lemma>: Which betrays itself by its own
                                squeaking.</note></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="7">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="1024" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter THRASO and GNATHO.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to THRASO.</stage> Well now? With what hope, or what design, are
                            we come hither? What do you intend to do, Thraso?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> What, I? To surrender myself to Thais, and do what she bids me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> What is it you say?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Why any the less so, than <persName>Hercules</persName> served Omphale.<milestone n="1026" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Hercules
                                    served Omphale</lemma>: He alludes to the story of Omphale,
                                Queen of <placeName key="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName>, and
                                    <persName>Hercules</persName>. Being
                                violently in love with her, the hero laid aside his club and boar's
                                skin, and in the habit of a woman plied the spindle and distaff with
                                her maids. See a curious story of Omphale, <persName>Hercules</persName>, and <persName>Faunus</persName>, in the Fasti of <persName>Ovid</persName>, B. ii. l. 305. As to the
                                reappearance of Thraso here, Colman has the following remarks: "Thraso, says
                                Donatus, is brought back again in order to be admitted to some share
                                in the good graces of Thais, that he may not be made unhappy at the
                                end of the Play; but surely it is an essential part of the poetical
                                justice of Comedy to expose coxcombs to ridicule and to punish them,
                                though without any shocking severity, for their follies."</note>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> The precedent pleases me. <stage>Aside.</stage> I only wish I may see
                            your head stroked down with a slipper;<milestone n="1027" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With a
                                    slipper</lemma>: He doubtless alludes to the treatment of
                                    <persName>Hercules</persName> by Omphale;
                                and, according to <persName><surname>Lucian</surname></persName>,
                                there was a story that Omphale used to beat him with her slipper or
                                sandal. On that article of dress, see the Notes to the Trinummus of
                                Plautus, 1. 252.</note> but her door makes a noise.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Confusion! Why, what mischiefs this? I never saw this person before;
                            why, I wonder, is he rushing out in such a hurry? <stage>They stand
                                aside.</stage></p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="scene" n="8">
					<milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
					<milestone n="1030" unit="TLN line"/>
					<stage>Enter CHAEREA from the house of THAIS, on the other side of the stage.</stage>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself, aloud.</stage> O fellow-townsmen, is there any one
                            alive more fortunate than me this day? Not any one, upon my faith: for
                            clearly in me have the Gods manifested all their power, on whom, thus
                            suddenly, so many blessings are bestowed.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Why is he thus overjoyed?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>seeing PARMENO, and running up to him.</stage> O my dear Parmeno,
                            the contriver, the beginner, the perfecter of all my delights, do you
                            know what are my transports? Are you aware that my Pamphila has been
                            discovered to be a citizen?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I have heard so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Do you know that she is betrothed to me?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> So may the Gods bless me, happily done.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart to THRASO.</stage> Do you hear what he says?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> And then, besides, I am delighted that my brother's mistress is secured
                            to him; the family is united. Thais has committed herself to the
                            patronage of my father;<milestone n="1038" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To the patronage of my
                                    father</lemma>: It was the custom at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for strangers, such as
                                Thais was, to put themselves under the protection (in clientelam) of
                                some wealthy citizen, who, as their patron, was bound to protect
                                them against injury. An exactly parallel case to the present is
                                found in the Miles Gloriosus of Plautus, 1. 799, where the wealthy
                                Periplecomenus says, "Habeo, eccillam, meam clientam, meretricem
                                adolescentulam." "Why, look, I have one, a dependent of mine, a
                                courtesan, a very young woman."</note> she has put herself under our
                            care and protection. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Thais, then, is wholly your brother's.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Of course.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> Then this is another reason for us to rejoice, that the Captain will be
                            beaten out of doors.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Wherever my brother is, do you take care that he hears this as soon as
                            possible.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
						<p> I'll go look for him at home. <stage>Goes into the house of
                                LACHES.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart to GNATHO.</stage> Do you at all doubt, Gnatho, but that I
                            am now ruined everlastingly?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to THRASO.</stage> Without doubt, I do think so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> What am I to make mention of first, or
                            commend in especial? Him who gave me the advice to do so, or myself, who
                            ventured to undertake it? Or ought I to extol fortune, who has been my
                            guide, and has so opportunely crowded into a single day events so
                            numerous, so important; or my father's kindness and indulgence Oh
                            Jupiter, I entreat you, do preserve these blessings unto us!
                                <stage>Enter PHAEDRIA from the house of LACHES.</stage></p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> Ye Gods, by our trust in you, what incredible
                            things has Parmeno just related to me! But where is my brother?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>stepping forward.</stage> Here he is.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I'm overjoyed.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> I quite believe you. There is no one, brother, more worthy to be loved
                            than this Thais of yours: so much is she a benefactress to all our
                            family.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Whew! are you commending her too to me?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I'm undone; the less the hope I have, the more I
                            am in love. Prithee, Gnatho, my hope is in you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> What do you wish me to do?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Bring this about, by entreaties or with money,
                            that I may at least share Thais's favors in some degree.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> It's a hard task.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> If you set your mind on any thing, I know you
                            well. If you manage this, ask me for any present you like as your
                            reward; you shall have what you ask.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> Is it so?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> It shall be so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> If I manage this, I ask that your house, whether
                            you are present or absent, may be open to me; that, without invitation,
                            there may always be a place for me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I pledge my honor that it shall be so.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I'll set about it then.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Who is it I hear so close at hand? <stage>Turning round.</stage> O
                            Thraso----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>coming forward.</stage> Save you both----</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Perhaps you are not aware what has taken place here.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> I am quite aware.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Why, then, do I see you in this neighborhood?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Depending on your kindness.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Do you know what sort of dependence you have? Captain, I give you
                            notice, if ever I catch you in this street again, even if you should say
                            to me, "I was looking for another person, I was on my road this way,"
                            you are undone.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Come, come, that's not handsome.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I've said it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I didn't know you gave yourself such airs.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> So it shall be.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> First hear a few words from me; and when I have said the thing, if you
                            approve of it, do it.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> Let's hear.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Do you step a little that way, Thraso. <stage>THRASO stands
                                aside.</stage> In the firs place, I wish you both implicitly to
                            believe me in this, that whatever I do in this matter, I do it entirely
                            for my own sake; but if the same thing is of advantage to yourselves, it
                            would be folly for you not to do it. </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> What is it?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> I'm of opinion that the Captain, your rival, should be received among
                            you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>starting.</stage> Hah!</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Be received?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PHAEDRIA.</stage> Only consider. I'faith, Phaedria, at the
                            free rate you are living with her, and indeed very freely you are
                            living, you have but little to give; and it's necessary for Thais to
                            receive a good deal. That all this may be supplied for your amour and
                            not at your own expense, there is not an individual better suited or
                            more fitted for your purpose than the Captain. In the first place, he
                            both.has got enough to give, and no one does give more profusely. He is
                            a fool, a dolt, a blockhead; night and day he snores away; and you need
                            not fear that the lady will fall in love with him; you may easily have
                            him discarded whenever you please.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PHAEDRIA.</stage> What shall we do?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> And this besides, which I deem to be of even greater importance,--not a
                            single person entertains in better style or more bountifully.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> It's a wonder if this sort of man can not be made use of in some way or
                            other.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> I think so too.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> You act properly. One thing I have still to beg of you,--that you'll
                            receive me into your fraternity; I've been rolling that stone<milestone n="1084" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Been rolling that stone</lemma>: Donatus thinks that he alludes
                                to the story of Sisyphus, who, in the Infernal Regions, was
                                condemned eternally to roll a stone up a hill, which, on arriving at
                                the summit, immediately fell to the bottom.</note> for a
                            considerable time past.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> We admit you.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> And with all my heart.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> Then I, in return for this, Phaedria, and you, Chaerea, make him over to
                                you<note anchored="yes">Make him over to you)--Ver. 1086.. "Vobis
                                propino." The word "propino" was properly applied to the act of
                                tasting a cup of wine, and then handing it to another; he means that
                                he has had his taste of the Captain, and is now ready to hand him
                                over to them.</note> to be eaten and drunk to the dregs.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>CHAEREA</speaker>
						<p> Agreed.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> He quite deserves it.<note anchored="yes">He quite deserves it)--Ver
                                1087. Cooke has the following appropriate remark: "I can not think
                                that this Play, excellent as it is in almost all other respects,
                                concludes consistently with the manners of gentlemen; there is a
                                meanness in Phaedria and Chaerea consenting to take Thraso into
                                their society, with a view of fleecing him, which the Poet should
                                have avoided."</note>
                        </p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>calling to THRASO.</stage> Thraso, whenever you please, step this
                            way.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> Prithee, how goes it?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p> How? Why, these people didn't know you; after I had discovered to them
                            your qualities, and had praised you as your actions and your virtues
                            deserved, I prevailed upon them.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>THRASO</speaker>
						<p> You have managed well; I give you my best thanks. Besides, I never was
                            any where but what all were extremely fond of me.</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>GNATHO</speaker>
						<p>
                            <stage>to PHAEDRIA and CHAEREA.</stage> Didn't I tell you that he was a
                            master of the Attic elegance?</p>
					</sp>
					<sp>
						<speaker>PHAEDRIA</speaker>
						<p> He is no other than you mentioned. <stage>Pointing to his FATHER'S
                                house.</stage> Walk this way. <stage>To the AUDIENCE.</stage> Fare
                            you well, and grant us your applause. </p>
					</sp>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
