<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersDrama PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Drama//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersDrama.dtd" >
%PersDrama;
]>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Hecyra: The Mother-In-Law</title>
                <author>P. Terentius Afer (Terence)</author>
                <editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor> &responsibility;
                &fund.DLI2; </titleStmt> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>The Comedies of Terence</title>
                        <editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Ney York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
                            <date>1874</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="silent" status="medium">&Perseus.DE;</correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                <state unit="TLN line"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                <state unit="act"/>
                <state n="chunk" unit="scene"/>
                <state unit="line"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="en">English</language>
                <language id="la">Latin</language>
                <language id="greek">Greek</language>
                <language id="de">German</language>
                <language id="fr">French</language>
                <language id="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>14-Aug-01</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>AEM</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item> 
$Log: hec_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2010-07-09 14:48:02  rsingh04
fixed CVS log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/12/08 20:46:27 rsingh04 
moved more xml files around based on copyright status. renamed terence files to follow the
abbreviations and split up minora_lat.xml into separate files 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 23:13:43 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/11/14 21:28:07 lcerrato 
fixed author names for consistent sorting 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:33 packel 
fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:43 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 16:31:41 packel
removed stray item tags 

Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 15:05:03 packel 
Converted to XML                   

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:18:13 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4
extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2001/08/29 19:56:38 amahoney 
make the various Dramatis Personae lists
independent instead of cross referencing each other 

Revision 1.6 2001/08/29 19:38:17 amahoney 
fix incorrect speaker attributions, mark Latin 

Revision 1.5 2001/08/21 18:49:51 amahoney 
get translator's name into proper place in meta-data, use same form of author's name as in Latin 

Revision 1.4 2001/08/17 17:32:56 amahoney 
fix headers for TOC 

Revision 1.3 2001/08/17 17:24:12 amahoney
begin marking the Latin 

Revision 1.2 2001/08/17 15:32:10 amahoney 
fix line numbers in the English, pick up a few typos in Latin 

Revision 1.1 2001/08/16 21:11:14 amahoney 
new texts 
                </item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text lang="en">
        <body>

            <castList>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>LACHES,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">lagxu/nw,</foreign>
                            "to obtain by lot" or "heirship."</note>, </role>
                    <roleDesc>an aged Athenian, father of Pamphilus.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>PHIDIPPUS,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">feidw,</foreign>
                            "parsimony," and <foreign lang="greek">i(ppo\s,</foreign> "a
                            horse."</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>an aged Athenian, father of Philumena.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>PAMPHILUS,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">pa=n,</foreign>
                            "all," and <foreign lang="greek">filo\s,</foreign> "a friend."</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>son of Laches.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>SOSIA,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">sw/zw,</foreign> "to
                            save;" saved in war.</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>servant of Pamphilus.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>PARMENO,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">para\,</foreign>
                            "by," and <foreign lang="greek">me/nw,</foreign> "to remain."</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>servant of Sostrata.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>SOSTRATA,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek">swxw\,</foreign>
                            "to preserve," or "save."</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>wife of Laches.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>MYRRHINA,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek"
                                >mur(r)inh\,</foreign> "a myrtle."</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>wife of Phidippus.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>BACCHIS,<note anchored="yes">From <persName
                                >Bacchus</persName>, the God of Wine.</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>a Courtesan.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>PHILOTIS,<note anchored="yes">From <foreign lang="greek"
                                >filoth\s,</foreign> "friendship."</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>a Courtesan.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>SYRA, <note anchored="yes">From
                                <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, her native
                            country.</note>
                    </role>
                    <roleDesc>a Procuress.</roleDesc>
                </castItem>
            </castList>
            <p>Scene.--<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; before the houses of LACHES,
                PHIDIPPUS, and BACCHIS. </p>
            <div1 type="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <div2 type="scene" n="subject">
                    <head>THE SUBJECT.</head>
                    <p>PAMPHILUS, the son of Laches by his wife Sostrata, being at the time enamored
                        of Bacchis, a Courtesan, chances, one night, in a drunken fit, to debauch
                        Philumena, the daughter of Phidippus and Myrrhina. In the struggle he takes
                        a ring from her, which he gives to Bacchis. Some time afterward, at his
                        father's express desire, he consents to marry. By chance the young woman
                        whom he has ravished is given to him as a wife, to the great joy of her
                        mother, who alone is aware of her misfortune, and hopes that her disgrace
                        may be thereby concealed. It, however, happens otherwise ; for Pamphilus,
                        still retaining his passion for Bacchis, refuses for some time to cohabit
                        with her. Bacchis, however, now rejects the advances of Pamphilus, who by
                        degrees becomes weaned from his affection for her, and grows attached to his
                        wife, whom he has hitherto disliked. Meantime, however, he is suddenly
                        called away from home. During his absence, Philumena, finding herself
                        pregnant, in consequence of her misfortune before her marriage, fearing
                        detection, especially avoids the company of her mother-in-law. At length she
                        makes an excuse for returning to the home of her own parents, where she
                        remains. Sostrata thereupon sends for her, but is answered that she is ill,
                        on which she goes to see her, but is refused admittance to the house. On
                        hearing of this, Laches blames his wife as being the cause of this
                        estrangement. Pamphilus now returns, and it so happens that, on the day of
                        his arrival, Philumena is brought to bed of a child. Impatient to see her,
                        Pamphilus rushes into her room, and to his great distress finds that this is
                        the case. Myrrhina thereupon entreats him to keep the matter secret, and
                        begs him, if he refuses to receive her daughter back again, at least not to
                        ruin her reputation by divulging it. As he now declines either to take back
                        his wife or give his reason for so doing, Laches suspects that he is still
                        enamored of Bacchis, and accordingly sends for her, and expostulates with
                        her. She, however, exonerates herself; on which the old man, supposing that
                        Philumena and her mother are equally ignorant with himself as to his son's
                        motives, begs her to call on them and remove their suspicions. While she is
                        conversing with them, they recognize the ring upon her finger which
                        Pamphilus had formerly taken from Philumena. By means of this it is
                        discovered that Pamphilus himself is the person who has ravished Philumena;
                        on which, overjoyed, he immediately takes home his wife and son. </p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="production">
                    <head>THE TITLE OF THE PLAY.</head>
                    <p>PERFORMED at the Megalensian Games; Sextus Julius Caesar and Cneius Cornelius
                        Dolabella being Curule Aediles. The whole was not then acted. Flaccus, the
                        freedman of Claudius, composed the music to a pair of flutes. It was
                        composed wholly from the Greek of Menander.<note anchored="yes"
                            >Menander)--According to some, this Play was borrowed from the Greek of
                            Apollodorus, a Comic Poet and contemporary of Menander, who wrote
                            forty-seven Plays.</note> It was performed the first time without a
                        Prologue. Represented a second time; Cneius Octavius and T. Manlius being
                            Consuls.<note anchored="yes">Being Consuls)--Cneius Octavius Nepos and
                            T. Manlius Torquatus were Consuls in the year from the building of the
                            City 587, and B.C. <date value="-166">166</date>.</note> It was then
                        brought out in honor of L. Aemilius Paulus, at his Funeral Games, and was
                        not approved of. It was repeated a third time; Q. Fulvius and L. Marcius
                        being Curule Aediles. L. Ambivius Turpio performed it. It was then approved
                            of.<note anchored="yes">It was then approved of)--" Placuit." This is
                            placed at the end, in consequence of the inauspicious reception which
                            had been given to it on the two first representations. See the account
                            given in the Prologues.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="summary">
                    <head>THE SUMMARY OF C. SULPITIUS APOLLINARIS.</head>
                    <p>PAMPHILUS has married Philumena, to whom, when a virgin, he formerly, not
                        knowing who she was, offered violence; and whose ring, which he took off by
                        force, he gave to his mistress, Bacchis, a Courtesan. Afterward he sets out
                        for Imbros, not having touched his bride. Having become pregnant, her mother
                        brings her over to her own house, as though sick, that her mother-in-law may
                        not know it. Pamphilus returns; detects her being delivered; conceals it;
                        but determines not to take back his wife. His father imputes this to his
                        passion for Bacchis. While Bacchis is exculpating herself, Myrrhina, the
                        mother of the injured girl, by chance recognizes the ring. Pamphilus takes
                        back his wife, together with his son. </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="act" n="prologue">
                <div2 type="scene" n="0">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>THE FIRST PROLOGUE.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Prologue</speaker>
                        <p>HECYRA<milestone n="1" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma
                                    targOrder="U">Hecyra</lemma>: The Greek word <foreign
                                    lang="greek">(/*ekura,</foreign> a "step-mother," or
                                "mother-in-law," Latinized.</note> is the name of this Play; when it
                            was represented for the first time, an unusual disaster and
                                calamity<milestone n="3" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">And calamity</lemma>: "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >Calamitas</foreign>." This word is used in the same sense in
                                the first line of the Eunuch. This is evidently the Prologue spoken
                                on the second attempt to bring forward the piece. On the first
                                occasion it probably had none. "<foreign lang="la">Vitium</foreign>"
                                was a word used by the Augurs, with whom it implied an unfavorable
                                omen, and thence came to be used for any misfortune or disaster. He
                                seems to mean the depraved taste of the public, that preferred
                                exhibitions of rope-dancers and pugilists to witnessing his
                                Plays.</note> interrupted it, so that it could not be witnessed
                            throughout or estimated; so much had the populace, carried away with
                            admiration, devoted their attention to some rope-dancing. It is now
                            offered as though entirely a new Play; and he who wrote it did not wish
                            to bring it forward then a second time, on purpose that he might be able
                            again to sell it.<milestone n="7" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Again to sell it</lemma>: See the last
                                Note to the Second Prologue.</note> Other Plays of his<milestone
                                n="8" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U"
                                    >Other Plays of his</lemma>: Madame Dacier informs us that
                                Vossius was of opinion that the second representation of this Play
                                did not take place till after that of the Adelphi. In that case, they had
                                already seen the rest of his Plays.</note> you have seen
                            represented; I beg you now to give your attention to this. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>THE SECOND PROLOGUE.</stage>
                    <note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Second Prologue</lemma>: --Eugraphius
                        informs us that this Prologue was spoken by Ambivius Turpio, the head of the
                        company of Actors.</note>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Prologue</speaker>
                        <p>I COME to you as an envoy from the Poet, in the character of
                            prologue-speaker; allow me to be a successful pleader, that in my old
                            age I may enjoy the same privilege that I enjoyed when a younger man,
                            when I caused new Plays, that had been once rejected, to come into
                            favor; so that his writings might not die with the Poet. Among them, as
                            to those of Caecilius,<milestone n="14" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Coecilius</lemma>: Colman has
                                the following Note: "A famous Comic Poet among the Romans. His chief
                                excellences are said to have been, the gravity of his style and the
                                choice of his subjects. The first quality was attributed to him by
                                Horace, Tully, etc., and
                                the last by Varro. '<foreign lang="la">In argumentis Caecilius
                                    poscit palmam, in ethesi Terentius</foreign>.' 'In the choice of
                                subjects, Caecilius demands the preference; in the manners,
                                Terence.'" Madame Dacier, indeed, renders "<foreign lang="la">in
                                    argumentis</foreign>," "in the disposition of his subjects." But
                                the words will not bear that construction. "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >Argumentum</foreign>," I believe, is uniformly used for the
                                argument itself, and never implies the conduct of it; as in the
                                Prologue to the Andrian, "<foreign lang="la">non tam dissimili
                                    argumento</foreign>." Besides, the disposition of the subject
                                was the very art attributed by the critics of those days to Terence,
                                and which <persName>Horace</persName> mentions
                                in the very same line with the gravity of Caecilius, distinguishing
                                them as the several characteristics of each writer, "<foreign
                                    lang="la">Vincere Caecilius gravitate, Terentius
                                arte</foreign>."</note> which I first studied when new; in some of
                            which I was rejected; in some I kept my ground with difficulty. As I
                            knew that the fortune of the stage was varying, where the hopes were
                            uncertain, I submitted to certain toil. Those I zealously attempted to
                            perform, that from the same writer I might learn new ones, and not
                            discourage him from his pursuits. I caused them to be represented. When
                            seen, they pleased. Thus did I restore the Poet to his place, who was
                            now almost weaned, through the malevolence of his adversaries, from his
                            pursuits and labors, and from the dramatic art. But if I had at that
                            period slighted the writer, and had wished to use my endeavors in
                            discouraging him, so that he might live a life of idleness rather than
                            of study, I might have easily discouraged him from writing others. Now,
                            for my sake, hear with unbiased minds what it is I ask. I again bring
                            before you the Hecyra, which I have never been allowed to act before you
                            in silence; such misfortunes have so overwhelmed it. These misfortunes
                            your intelligence will allay, if it is a seconder of our exertions. The
                            first time, when I began to act this Play, the vauntings of
                                boxers,<milestone n="33" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Vauntings of boxers</lemma>: Horace
                                probably had this passage in his mind when he penned the First
                                Epistle in his Second Book, 1. 185 ; where he mentions the populace
                                leaving a Play in the midst for the sight of a bear, or an
                                exhibition of boxers.</note> the expectation of a
                                rope-dancer,<milestone n="34" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Of a rope-dancer</lemma>: The art of
                                dancing on the tight rope was carried to great perfection among the
                                ancients. Many paintings have been discovered, which show the
                                numerous attitudes which the performers assumed. The figures have
                                their heads enveloped in skins or caps, probably intended as a
                                protection in case of falling. At the conclusion of the performance
                                the dancer ran down the rope. Germanicus and Galba are said to have
                                exhibited elephants dancing on the tight rope.</note> added to
                            which, the throng of followers, the noise, the clamor of the women,
                            caused me to retire from your presence before the time. In this new
                            Play, I attempted to follow the old custom of mine,<milestone n="38"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The old
                                    custom of mine</lemma>: He says that on the second
                                representation he followed the plan which he had formerly adopted in
                                the Plays of Caecilius, of bringing those forward again which had
                                not given satisfaction at first.</note> of making a fresh trial; I
                            brought it on again. In the first Act I pleased; when in the mean time a
                            rumor spread that gladiators were about to be exhibited; the populace
                            flock together, make a tumult, clamor aloud, and fight for their
                                places:<milestone n="41" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Fight for their places</lemma>: This was
                                in consequence of their sitting indiscriminately at the
                                Amphitheatre, where the gladiators were exhibited; whereas at the
                                Theatres there were distinct places appropriated to each "<foreign
                                    lang="la">ordo</foreign>" or class.</note> meantime, I was
                            unable to maintain my place. Now there is no confusion: there is
                            attention and silence--an opportunity of acting my Play has been granted
                            me; to yourselves is given the power of gracing the scenic
                                festival.<milestone n="45" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Gracing the scenic festival</lemma>:
                                Madame Dacier remarks that there is great force and eloquence in the
                                Actor's affecting a concern for the sacred festivals, which were in
                                danger of being deprived of their chief ornaments, if by too great a
                                severity they discouraged the Poets who undertook to furnish the
                                Plays during the solemnity.</note> Do not permit, through your
                            agency, the dramatic art to sink into the hands of a few; let your
                            authority prove a seconder and assistant to my own. If I have never
                            covetously set a price upon my skill, and have come to this conclusion,
                            that it is the greatest gain in the highest possible degree to
                            contribute to your entertainment; allow me to obtain this of you, that
                            him who has intrusted his labors to my protection, and himself to your
                            integrity,--that him, I say, the malicious may not maliciously deride,
                            beset by them on every side. For my sake, admit of this plea, and attend
                            in silence, that he may be encouraged to write other Plays, and that it
                            may be for my advantage to study new ones hereafter, purchased at my own
                                expense.<milestone n="57" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">At my own expense</lemma>: It is generally
                                supposed that "<foreign lang="la">meo pretio</foreign>" means "a
                                price named as my estimate;" and that it was the custom for the
                                Aediles to purchase a Play of a Poet at a price fixed by the head of
                                the company of actors. It is also thought that the money was paid to
                                the actor, who handed over the whole, or a certain part, to the
                                Poet, and if the Play was not received with favor, the Aediles had
                                the right to ask back the money from the actor, who consequently
                                became a loser by the transaction. Pareus and Meric Casaubon think,
                                however, that in case of this Play, the Aediles had purchased it
                                from the Poet, and the performers had bought it of the Aediles as a
                                speculation. What he means at the end of the First Prologue by
                                selling the Play over again, is not exactly known. Perhaps if the
                                Play had been then performed throughout and received with no favor,
                                he would have had to forfeit the money, and lose all right to any
                                future pecuniary interest in it; but he preferred to cancel the
                                whole transaction, and to reserve the Play for purchase and
                                representation at a more favorable period.</note>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="act" n="1">
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PHILOTIS<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Philotis</lemma>:
                            This is a protatic character, or one that helps to introduce the subject
                            of the Play, and then appears no more.</note> and SYRA.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> I' faith, Syra, you can find
                            but very few lovers who prove constant to their mistresses. For
                            instance, how often did this Pamphilus swear to Bacchis--how solemnly,
                            so that any one might have readily believed him--that he never would
                            take home a wife so long as she lived. Well now, he is married.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SYRA</speaker>
                        <p> Therefore, for that very reason, I earnestly both advise and entreat you
                            to take pity upon no one, but plunder, fleece, and rend every man you
                            lay hold of.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> What! Hold no one exempt?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SYRA</speaker>
                        <p> No one; for not a single one of them, rest assured, comes to you without
                            making up his mind, by means of his flatteries, to gratify his passion
                            with you at the least possible expense. Will you not, pray, plot against
                            them in return ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> And yet, upon my faith, it is unfair to be the same to all.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SYRA</speaker>
                        <p> What! unfair to take revenge on your enemies? or, for them to be caught
                            in the very way they try to catch you ? Alas! wretched me! why do not
                            your age and beauty belong to me, or else these sentiments of mine to
                            you? </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="2">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="76" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PARMENO from the house of LACHES.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>at the door, speaking to SCIRTUS within.</stage> If the old man
                            should be asking for me, do you say that I have just gone to the harbor
                            to inquire about the arrival of Pamphilus. Do you hear what I say,
                            Scirtus? If he asks for me, then you are to say so; if he does not, why,
                            say nothing at all; so that at another time I may be able to employ that
                            excuse as a new one. <stage>Comes forward, and looking
                            around.</stage>--But is it my dear Philotis that I see? How has she come
                            here? <stage>Accosting her.</stage> Philotis heartily good-morrow.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> O, good-morrow, Parmeno,</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SYRA</speaker>
                        <p> By my troth, good-morrow, Parmeno.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I' faith, Syra, the same to you. Philotis, tell me, where have you been
                            enjoying yourself so long?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> For my part, indeed, I have been far from enjoying myself, in leaving
                            this place for <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> with
                            a most brutal captain; for two whole years, there, had I to put up with
                            him to my sorrow.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I' troth, I fancy that regret for <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                >Athens</placeName> full oft possessed you, and that you thought but
                            poorly of your foresight.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> It can not be expressed how impatient I was to return hither, get rid of
                            the captain, and see yourselves here, that after our old fashion I might
                            at my ease enjoy the merry-makings among you; for there it was not
                            allowed me to speak, except at the moment prescribed, and on such
                            subjects as he chose.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>sarcastically.</stage> I don't think it was gallant in the
                            captain to place a restraint on your tongue.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> But what is this piece of business that Bacchis has just now been
                            telling me in-doors here? <stage>pointing to her house.</stage> A thing
                            I never supposed would come to pass, that he, in her lifetime, could
                            possibly prevail upon his feelings to take a wife.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> To take, indeed!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> Why, look you, has he not taken one?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> He has; but I doubt whether this match will be lasting.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> May the Gods and Goddesses grant it so, if it is for the advantage of
                            Bacchis. But why am I to believe it is so? Tell me, Parmeno.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> There is no need for its being spread abroad; ask me no more about
                            it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> For fear, I suppose, it may be made public. So may the Gods prosper me,
                            I do not ask you in order that I may spread it abroad, but that, in
                            silence, I may rejoice within myself.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> You'll never speak me so fairly, that I shall trust my back to your
                            discretion.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> Oh, don't say so, Parmeno ;<milestone n="109" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Don't say so, Parmeno</lemma>:
                                She says this ironically, at the same time intimating that she knows
                                Parmeno too well, not to be sure that he is as impatient to impart
                                the secret to her as she is to know it. Donatus remarks, that she
                                pretends she has no curiosity to hear it, that he may deem her the
                                more worthy to be intrusted with the secret.</note> as though you
                            were not much more impatient to tell me this, than I to learn what I'm
                            inquiring about.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> She tells the truth there; and that is my
                            greatest failing. <stage>To PHILOTIS.</stage> If you give me your word
                            that you'll keep it a secret, I'll tell you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> You are now returning to your natural disposition. I give you my word;
                            say on.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Listen.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> I'm all attention.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Pamphilus was in the height of his passion for Bacchis here, when his
                            father began to importune him to take a wife, and to urge those points
                            which are usual with all fathers, that he himself was now in years, and
                            that he was his only son, that he wished for a support for his declining
                            years. He refused at first. But on his father pressing more urgently, he
                            caused him to become wavering in his mind, whether to yield rather to
                            duty or to love. By hammering on and teazing him, at last the old man
                            gained his point; and betrothed him to the daughter of our next-door
                            neighbor here <stage>pointing to the house of PHIDIPPUS</stage>. This
                            did not seem so very disagreeable to Pamphilus, until on the very point
                            of marriage, when he saw that all was ready, and that no respite was
                            granted, but marry he must; then, at last, he took it so much to heart,
                            that I do believe if Bacchis had been present, even she would have
                            pitied him. Whenever opportunity was afforded for us being alone, so
                            that he could converse with me, he used to say: "Parmeno, I am ruined!
                            What have I done! Into what misery have I plunged myself! Parmeno, I
                            shall never be able to endure this. To my misery, I am undone !"</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>vehemently exclaiming.</stage> May the Gods and Goddesses
                            confound you, Laches, for vexing him so !</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> To cut the matter short, he took home his wife. On the first night, he
                            did not touch the girl; the night that followed that, not a bit the
                            more.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> What is it you tell me? A young man go to bed with a virgin, intoxicated
                            to boot, and able to restrain himiself from touching her! You do not say
                            what's likely; nor do I believe it to be the truth.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I suppose it does seem so to you, for no one comes to you unless he is
                            eager for you; but he had married her against his will.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> After this, what followed ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> In a very few days after, Pamphilus took me aside, away from the house,
                            and told me how that the young woman was still untouched by him; and how
                            that before he had taken her home as his wife, he had hoped to be able
                            to endure this marriage: "But, Parmeno, as I can not resolve to live
                            with her any longer, it is neither honorable in me, nor of advantage to
                            the young woman herself, for her to be turned to ridicule, but rather I
                            ought to return her to her relations just as I received her."</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> You tell me of a conscientious and virtuous disposition in
                            Pamphilus.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> "For me to declare this, I consider to be inconvenient to me, but for
                            her to be sent back to her father without mentioning any blame, would be
                            insolent; but I am in hopes that she, when she is sensible that she can
                            not live with me, will go at last of her own accord."</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> What did he do in the mean while ? Used he to visit Bacchis?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Every day. But as usually is the case, after she saw that he belonged to
                            another, she immediately became more ill-natured and more peevish.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> I' faith, that's not to be wondered at.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> And this circumstance in especial contributed to estrange him from her;
                            after he had fairly examined himself, and her, and the one that was at
                            home, he formed a judgment, by comparison, upon the principles of them
                            both. She, just as might be expected from a person of respectable and
                            free birth, chaste and virtuous, patient under the slights and all the
                            insults of her husband, and concealing his affronts. Upon this, his
                            mind, partly overcome by compassion for his wife, partly constrained by
                            the insolence of the other, was gradually estranged from Bacchis, and
                            transferred its affections to the other, after having found a congenial
                            disposition. In the mean time, there dies at Imbros<milestone n="171"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U"
                                    >Imbros</lemma>: An island in the <placeName key="tgn,7002675"
                                    >Aegean Sea</placeName>, off the coast of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>.</note> an old man, a
                            relative of theirs. His property there devolved on them by law. Thither
                            his father drove the love-sick Pamphilus, much against his will. He left
                            his wife here with his mother, for the old man has retired into the
                            country; he seldom comes into the city.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> What is there yet in this marriage to prevent its being lasting ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> You shall hear just now. At first, for several days, there really was a
                            good understanding between them. In the mean time, however, in a strange
                            way, she began to take a dislike to Sostrata; nor yet was there ever any
                            quarrel or words between them.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> What then ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> If at any time she came to converse with her, she would instantly
                            withdraw from her presence,<milestone n="182" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From her presence</lemma>: For
                                the purpose, as will afterward appear, of not letting Sostrata see
                                that she was pregnant.</note> and refuse to see her; in fine, when
                            she could no longer endure her, she pretended that she was sent for by
                            her mother to assist at a sacrifice. When she had been there a few days,
                            Sostrata ordered her to be fetched. She made some, I know not what,
                            excuse. Again she gave similar orders; no one sent back any excuse.
                            After she had sent for her repeatedly, they pretended that the damsel
                            was sick. My mistress immediately went to see her; no one admitted her.
                            On the old man coming to know of this, he yesterday came up from the
                            country on purpose, and waited immediately upon the father of Philumena.
                            What passed between them, I do not know as yet; but really I do feel
                            some anxiety in what way this is to end. You now have the whole matter;
                            and I shall proceed whither I was on my way.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> And I too, for I made an appointment with a certain stranger<milestone
                                n="195" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U"
                                    >With a certain stranger</lemma>: Here Philotis gives a reason,
                                as Donatus observes, why she does not again appear in the Play. The
                                following is an extract from Colman's remarks on this passage: "It
                                were to be wished, for the sake of the credit of our author's
                                acknowledged art in the Drama, that Philotis had assigned as good a
                                reason for her appearing at all. Eugraphius justly says: 'The
                                Courtesan in this Scene is a character quite foreign to the fable.'
                                Donatus also says much the same thing in his Preface, and in his
                                first Note to this Comedy; but adds that 'Terence chose this method
                                rather. than to relate the argument by means of a Prologue, or to
                                introduce a God speaking from a machine. I will venture to say that
                                the Poet might have taken a much shorter and easier method than
                                either; I mean, to have begun the Play with the very Scene which now
                                opens the Second Act.'"</note> to meet him.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> May the Gods prosper what you undertake!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHILOTIS</speaker>
                        <p> Farewell!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> And a kind farewell to you, my dear Philotis. <stage>(Exeunt
                                severally.)</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="act" n="2">
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="199" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter LACHES and SOSTRATA, from the house of the former.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> O faith of Gods and men! what a race is this! what a conspiracy this!
                            that all women should desire and reject every individual thing alike!
                            And not a single one can you find to swerve in any respect from the
                            disposition of the rest. For instance, quite as though with one accord,
                            do all mothers-in-law hate their daughters-in-law. Just in the same way
                            is it their system to oppose their husbands; their obstinacy here is the
                            same. In the very same school they all seem to me to have been trained
                            up to perverseness. Of that school, if there is any mistress, I am very
                            sure that she <stage>pointing at SOSTRATA</stage> it is.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Wretched me! when now I don't so much as know why I am accused!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Eh ! you don't know ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> So may the Gods kindly prosper me, Laches, and so may it be allowed us
                            to pass our lives together in unity!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> May the Gods avert such a misfortune!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> I'm sure that before long you will be sensible that I have been accused
                            by you undeservedly.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> You, undeservedly ? Can any thing possibly be said that you deserve in
                            return for this conduct of yours? You, who are disgracing both me and
                            yourself and the family, and are laying up sorrow for your Son. Then
                            besides, you are making our connections become, from friends, enemies to
                            us, who have thought him deserving for them to intrust their
                                children<milestone n="212" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Intrust their children</lemma>: The plural
                                    "<foreign lang="la">liberos</foreign>," children, is used where
                                only one is being spoken of, similarly, in the Heautontimorumenos,
                                1. 151.</note> to him. You alone have put yourself forward, by your
                            folly, to be causing this disturbance.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> What, I ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> You, woman, I say, who take me to be a stone, not a man. Do you think
                            because it's my habit to be so much in the country, that I don't know in
                            what way each person is passing his life here ? I know much better what
                            is going on here than there, where I am daily; for this reason, because,
                            just as you act at home, I am spoken of abroad. Some time since, indeed,
                            I heard that Philumena had taken a dislike to you; nor did I the least
                            wonder at it; indeed, if she hadn't done so, it would have been more
                            surprising. But I did not suppose that she would have gone so far as to
                            hate even the whole of the family; if I had known that, she should have
                            remained here in preference, and you should have gone away. But consider
                            how undeservedly these vexations arise on your account, Sostrata; I went
                            to live in the country, in compliance with your request, and to look
                            after my affairs, in order that my circumstances might be able to
                            support your lavishness and comforts, not sparing my own exertions,
                            beyond what's reasonable and my time of life allows. That you should
                            take no care, in return for all this, that there should be nothing to
                            vex me!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my word, through no means or fault of mine has this taken
                            place.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Nay, through you in especial; you were the only person here; on you
                            alone, Sostrata, falls all the blame. You ought to have taken care of
                            matters here, as I had released you from other anxieties. Is it not a
                            disgrace for an old woman to pick a quarrel with a girl? You will say it
                            was her fault.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Indeed I do not say so, my dear Laches.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> I am glad of that, so may the Gods prosper me, for my son's sake. I am
                            quite sure of this, that no fault of yours can possibly put you in a
                            worse light.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> How do you know, my husband, whether she may not have pretended to
                            dislike me, on purpose that she might be more with her mother?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> What say you to this? Is it not proof sufficient, when yesterday no one
                            was willing to admit you into the house, when you went to see her?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Why, they told me that she was very ill just then; for that reason I was
                            not admitted to her.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> I fancy that your humors are more her malady than any thing else; and
                            with good reason in fact, for there is not one of you but wants her son
                            to take a wife; and the match which has taken your fancy must be the
                            one; when, at your solicitation, they have married, then, at your
                            solicitation, they are to put them away again. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="2">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="244" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PHIDIPPUS from his house.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>speaking to PHILUMENA within.</stage> Although I am aware,
                            Philumena, that I have the right to compel you to do what I order,
                            still, being swayed by the feelings of a father, I will prevail upon
                            myself to yield to you, and not oppose your inclination.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> And look, most opportunely I see Phidippus; I'll presently know from him
                            how it is. <stage>Accosting him.</stage> Phidippus, although I am aware
                            that I am particularly indulgent to all my family, still it is not to
                            that degree to let my good nature corrupt their minds. And if you would
                            do the same, it would be more for your own interest and ours. At present
                            I see that you are under the control of those women.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Just look at that, now !</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> I waited on you yesterday about your daughter; you sent me away just as
                            wise as I came. It does not become you, if you wish this alliance to
                            continue, to conceal your resentment. If there is any fault on our side,
                            disclose it; either by clearing ourselves, or excusing it, we shall
                            remedy these matters for you, yourself the judge. But if this is the
                            cause of detaining her at your house, because she is ill, then I think
                            that you do me an injustice, Phidippus, if you are afraid lest she
                            should not be attended with sufficient care at my house. But, so may the
                            Gods prosper me, I do not yield in this to you, although you are her
                            father, that you can wish her well more than I do, and that on my son's
                            account, who I know values her not less than his own self. Nor, in fact,
                            is it unknown to you, how much, as I believe, it will vex him, if he
                            comes to know<milestone n="262" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">If he comes to know</lemma>: Donatus
                                observes that the Poet shows his art in here preparing a reason to
                                be assigned by Pamphilus for his pretended discontent at the
                                departure of his wife.</note> of this; for this reason, I wish to
                            have her home before he returns.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Laches, I am sensible of both your carefulness and your good-will, and I
                            am persuaded that all you say is just as you say: and I would have you
                            believe me in this; I am anxious for her to return to you, if I possibly
                            can by any means effect it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> What is it prevents you from effecting it? Come, now, does she make any
                            complaint against her husband?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> By no means; for when I urged it still more strongly, and attempted to
                            constrain her by force to return, she solemnly protested that she
                            couldn't possibly remain with you, while Pamphilus was absent. Probably
                            each has his own failing; I am naturally of an indulgent disposition; I
                            can not thwart. my own family.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>turning to his wife, who stands apart.</stage> Ha!
                                Sostrata!<milestone n="271" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Ha! Sostrata</lemma>: Colman observes on
                                this passage: "This is extremely artful. The answer of Philumena, as
                                related by Phidippus, contains an ample vindication of Pamphilus.
                                What, then, can we suppose could make the house so disagreeable to
                                her in his absence, but the behavior of Sostrata? She declares her
                                innocence; yet appearances are all against her. Supposing this to be
                                the first Act of the Play, it would be impossible for a Comedy to
                                open in a more interesting manner."</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>sighing deeply.</stage> Alas! wretched me!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to PHIDIPPUS.</stage> Is this your final determination ?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> For the present, at least, as it seems; but have you any thing else to
                            say? for I have some business that obliges me to go at once to the
                            Forum.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> I'll go with you. <stage>(Exeunt.)</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="3">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="275" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>SOSTRATA alone.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my faith, we assuredly are all of us hated by our husbands with
                            equal injustice, on account of a few, who cause us all to appear
                            deserving of harsh treatment. For, so may. the Gods prosper me, as to
                            what my husband accuses me of, I am quite guiltless. But it is not so
                            easy to clear myself, so strongly have people come to the conclusion
                            that all step-mothers are harsh: i' faith, not I, indeed, for I never
                            regarded her otherwise than if she had been my own daughter; nor can I
                            conceive how this has befallen me. But really, for many reasons, I long
                            for. my son's return home with impatience. <stage>Goes into her
                                house.</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="act" n="3">
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="282" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PAMPHILUS and PARMENO.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> No individual, I do believe, ever met with more crosses in love than I.
                            Alas! unhappy me! that I have thus been sparing of life! Was it for this
                            I was so very impatient to return home ? O, how much more preferable had
                            it been for me to pass my life any where in the world than to return
                            here and be sensible that I am thus wretched! For all of us know who
                            have met with trouble from any cause, that all the time that passes
                            before we come to the knowledge of it, is so much gain.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Still, as it is, you'll the sooner know how to extricate yourself from
                            these misfortunes. If you had not returned, this breach might have
                            become much wider; but now, Pamphilus, I am sure that both will be awed
                            by your presence. You will learn the facts, remove their enmity, restore
                            them to good feeling once again. These are but trifles which you have
                            persuaded yourself are so grievous.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Why comfort me? Is there a person in all the world so wretched as I?
                            Before I took her to wife, I had my heart engaged by other affections.
                            Now, though on this subject I should be silent, it is easy for any one
                            to know how much I have suffered; yet I never dared refuse her whom my
                            father forced upon me. With difficulty did I withdraw myself from
                            another, and disengage my affections so firmly rooted there! and hardly
                            had I fixed them in another quarter, when, lo! a new misfortune has
                            arisen, which may tear me from her too. Then besides, I suppose that in
                            this matter I shall find either my mother or my wife in fault; and when
                            I find such to be the fact, what remains but to become still more
                            wretched? For duty, Parmeno, bids me bear with the feelings of a mother;
                            then, to my wife I am bound by obligations; with so much temper did she
                            formerly bear my usage, and on no occasion disclose the many wrongs
                            inflicted on her by me. But, Parmeno, something of consequence, I know
                            not what it is, must have happened for this misunderstanding to have
                            arisen between them, that has lasted so long.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Or else something frivolous, i' faith, if you would only give words
                            their proper value; those which are sometimes the greatest enmities, do
                            not argue the greatest injuries; for it often happens that in certain
                            circumstances, in which another would not even be out of temper, for the
                            very same reason a passionate man becomes your greatest enemy. What
                            enmities do children entertain among themselves for trifling injuries!
                            For what reason? Why, because they have a weak understanding to direct
                            them. Just so are these women, almost like children with their fickle
                            feelings; perhaps a single word has occasioned this enmity between them,
                            master.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Go, Parmeno, into the house, and carry word<milestone n="314"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And carry
                                    word</lemma>: It was the custom with the Greeks and Romans, when
                                returning from abroad, to send a messenger before them, to inform
                                their wives of their arrival. See for example Cicero's last <bibl
                                    n="Cic. Fam. 14.20">letter</bibl> to his wife, <date value="-47"
                                    >47</date> BC.</note> that I have arrived. <stage>A noise is
                                heard in the house of PHIDIPPUS.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>starting.</stage> Ha! What means this?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Be silent. I perceive a bustling about, and a running to and fro.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>going to the door.</stage> Come then, I'll approach nearer to the
                            door. <stage>He listens.</stage> Ha! did you hear?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Don't be prating. <stage>He listens.</stage> O Jupiter, I heard a
                            shriek!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> You yourself are talking, while you forbid me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>within the house.</stage> Prithee, my child, do be silent.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> That seems to be the voice of Philumena's mother. I'm undone</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Why so?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Utterly ruined!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> For what reason?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Parmeno, you are concealing from me some great misfortune to me
                            unknown.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> They said that your wife, Philumena, was in alarm about<milestone
                                n="321" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U"
                                    >Was in alarm about</lemma>: "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >Pavitare</foreign>." Casaubon has a curious suggestion here; he
                                thinks it not improbable that he had heard the female servants
                                whispering among themselves that Philumena "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >paritare</foreign>," "was about to be brought to bed," which he
                                took for "<foreign lang="la">pavitare</foreign>," "was in fear" of
                                something.</note> something, I know not what; whether that may be
                            it, perchance, I don't know.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I am undone! Why didn't you tell me of this?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Because I couldn't tell every thing at once.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> What is the malady?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I don't know.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> What! has no one brought a physician to see her?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I don't know.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Why delay going in-doors, that I may know as soon as possible for
                            certain what it is? In what condition, Philumena, am I now to find you?
                            But if you are in any peril, beyond a doubt I will perish with you.
                                <stage>Goes into the house of PHIDIPPUS.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> There is no need for me to follow him into
                            the house at present, for I see that we are all disagreeable to them.
                            Yesterday, no one would give Sostrata admittance. If, perchance, the
                            malady should become worse, which really I could far from wish, for my
                            master's sake especially, they would at once say that Sostrata's servant
                            had been in there; they would invent a story that I had brought some
                            mischief against their lives and persons, in consequence of which the
                            malady had been increased. My mistress would be blamed, and I should
                            incur heavy punishment.<milestone n="335" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Heavy punishment</lemma>:
                                Probably meaning that he will be examined by torture, whether he has
                                not, by drugs or other means, contributed to Philumena's
                                illness.</note>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="2">
                    <stage>Enter SOSTRATA.</stage>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="337" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to herself.</stage> In dreadful alarm, I have for some time
                            heard, I know not what confusion going on here; I'm sadly afraid
                            Philumena's illness is getting worse. Aesculapius, I do entreat thee,
                            and thee, Health,<milestone n="338" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And thee, Health</lemma>: She
                                invokes Aesculapius, the God of Medicine, and "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >Salus</foreign>," or "Health," because, in <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, their statues were always
                                placed near each other; so that to have offered prayers to one and
                                not to the other, would have been deemed a high indignity. On the
                                worship of Aesculapius, see the opening Scene of the Curculio of
                                Plautus.</note> that it may not be so. Now I'll go visit her.
                                <stage>Approaches the door.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>coming forward.</stage> Hark you, Sostrata.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>turning round.</stage> Well.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> You will again be shut out there.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> What, Parmeno, is it you? I'm undone! wretch that I am, what shall I do?
                            Am I not to go see the wife of Pamphilus, when she is ill here next
                            door?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Not go see her! Don't even send any person for the purpose of seeing
                            her; for I'm of opinion that he who loves, a person to whom he is an
                            object of dislike, commits a double mistake: he himself takes a useless
                            trouble, and causes annoyance to the other. Besides, your son went in to
                            see how she is, as soon as he arrived.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> What is it you say? Has Pamphilus arrived?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> He has.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> I give thanks unto the Gods! Well, through that news my spirits are
                            revived, and anxiety has departed from my heart.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> For this reason, then, I am especially unwilling you should go in there;
                            for if Philumena's malady at all abates, she will, I am sure, when they
                            are by themselves, at once tell him all the circumstances; both what
                            misunderstandings have arisen between you, and how the difference first
                            began. But see, he's coming out-how sad he looks! <stage>Re-enter
                                PAMPHILUS, from the house of PHIDIPPUS.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>running up to him.</stage> O my son! <stage>Embraces
                            him.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> My mother, blessings on you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> I rejoice that you are returned safe. Is Philumena in a fair way?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> She is a little better. <stage>Weeping.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Would that the Gods may grant it so! Why, then, do you weep, or why so
                            dejected?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> All's well, mother.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> What meant that confusion? Tell me; was she suddenly taken ill?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Such was the fact.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> What is her malady?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> A fever.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> An intermitting one?<milestone n="357" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">An intermitting one</lemma>:
                                    "<foreign lang="la">Quotidiana</foreign>," literally,
                                "daily."</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> So they say. Go in the house, please, mother; I'll follow you
                            immediately.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Very well. <stage>Goes into her house.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Do you run and meet the servants, Parmeno, and help them with the
                            baggage.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Why, don't they know the way themselves to come to our house?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>stamping.</stage> Do you loiter? <stage>(Exit PARMENO.)</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="3">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="362" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>PAMPHILUS, alone.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I can not discover any fitting commencement of my troubles, at which to
                            begin to narrate the things that have so unexpectedly befallen me, some
                            of which with these eyes I have beheld; some I have heard with my ears;
                            and on account of which I so hastily betook myself, in extreme
                            agitation, out of doors. For just now, when, full of alarm, I rushed
                            into the house, expecting to find my wife afflicted with some other
                            malady than what I have found it to be--ah me! immediately the
                            servant-maids beheld that I had arrived, they all at the same moment
                            joyfully exclaimed, "He is come," from having so suddenly caught sight
                            of me. But I soon perceived the countenances of all of them
                                change,<milestone n="369" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">All of them change</lemma>: This must have
                                been imaginary, as they were not likely to be acquainted with the
                                reason of Philumena's apprehensions.</note> because at so
                            unseasonable a juncture chance had brought me there. One of them in the
                            mean time hastily ran before me to give notice that I had come.
                            Impatient to see my wife, I followed close. When I entered the room,
                            that instant, to my sorrow, I found out her malady; for neither did the
                            time afford any. interval to enable her to conceal it, nor could she
                            complain in any other accents than those which the case itself prompted.
                            When I perceived this: "O disgraceful conduct!" I exclaimed, and
                            instantly hurried away from the spot in tears, overwhelmed by such an
                            incredible and shocking circumstance. Her mother followed me; just as I
                            got to the threshold, she threw herself on her knees: I felt compassion
                            for her. Assuredly it is the fact, in my opinion, just as matters befall
                            us all, so are we elated or depressed. At once she began to address me
                            in these words: "O my dear Pamphilus, you see the reason why she left
                            your house; for violence was offered to her when formerly a maid, by
                            some villain to us unknown. Now, she took refuge here then, that from
                            you and others she might conceal her labor." But when I call to mind her
                            entreaties, I can not, wretched as I am, refrain from tears. "Whatever
                            chance or fortune it is," said she, "which has brought you here to-day,
                            by it we do both conjure you, if with equity and justice we may, that
                            her misfortune may be concealed by you, and kept a secret from all. If
                            ever you were sensible, my dear Pamphilus, that she was tenderly
                            disposed toward you, she now asks you to grant her this favor in return,
                            without making any difficulty of it. But as to taking her back, act
                            quite according to your own convenience. You alone are aware of her.
                            lying-in, and that the child is none of yours. For it is said that it
                            was two months after the marriage before she had commerce with you. And
                            then, this is but the seventh month since she came to you.<milestone
                                n="394" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U"
                                    >Since she came to you</lemma>: There is great doubt what is the
                                exact meaning of "<foreign lang="la">postquam ad te
                                venit</foreign>," here, whether it means, "it is now the seventh
                                month since she became your wife," or, "it is now the seventh month
                                since she came to your embraces," which did not happen for two
                                months after the marriage. The former is, under the circumstances,
                                the most probable construction.</note> That you are sensible of
                            this, the circumstances themselves prove. Now, if it is possible,
                            Pamphilus, I especially wish, and will use my endeavors, that her labor
                            may remain unknown to her father, and to all, in fact. But if that can
                            not be managed, and they do find it out, I will say that she miscarried;
                            I am sure no one will suspect otherwise than, what is so likely, the
                            child was by you. It shall be instantly exposed; in that case there is
                            no inconvenience whatever to yourself, and you will be concealing an
                            outrage so undeservingly committed upon her,<milestone n="401"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Committed
                                    upon her</lemma>: Colman very justly observes here: "It is rather
                                extraordinary that Myrrhina's account of the injury done to her
                                daughter should not put Pamphilus in mind of his own adventure,
                                which comes out in the Fifth Act. It is certain that had the Poet
                                let the Audience into that secret in this place, they would have
                                immediately concluded that the wife of Pamphilus and the lady whom
                                he had ravished were one and the same person." Playwrights have
                                never, in any age or country, troubled themselves much about
                                probability in their plots. Besides, his adventure with Philumena
                                was by no means an uncommon one. We find similar instances mentioned
                                by Plautus; and violence and debauchery seem almost to have reigned
                                paramount in the streets at night.</note> poor thing!" I promised
                            this, and I am resolved to keep faith in what I said. But as to taking
                            her back, really I do not think that would be at all creditable, nor
                            will I do so, although love for her, and habit, have a strong influence
                            upon me. I weep when it occurs to my mind, what must be her life, and
                            how great her loneliness in future. O Fortune, thou hast never been
                            found constant! But by this time my former passion has taught me
                            experience in the present case. The means by which I got rid of that, I
                            must employ on the present occasion. Parmeno is coming with the
                            servants; it is far from convenient that he should be here under present
                            circumstances, for he was the only person to whom I trusted the secret
                            that I kept aloof from her when I first married her. I am afraid lest,
                            if he should frequently hear her cries, he might find out that she is in
                            labor. He must be dispatched by me somewhere till Philumena is
                            delivered. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="4">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="416" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter at a distance PARMENO and SOSIA, with people carrying
                        baggage.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to SOSIA.</stage> Do you say that this voyage was disagreeable to
                            you?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSIA</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my faith, Parmeno, it can not be so much as expressed in words, how
                            disagreeable it is to go on a voyage.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Do you say so?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSIA</speaker>
                        <p> O lucky man! You don't know what evils you have escaped, by never having
                            been at sea. For to say nothing of other hardships, mark this one only;
                            thirty days or more<milestone n="421" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Thirty days or more</lemma>: In
                                his voyage from Imbros to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                    >Athens</placeName>, namely, which certainly appears to have
                                been unusually long.</note> was I on board that ship, and every
                            moment, to my horror, was in continual expectation of death: such
                            unfavorable weather did we always meet with.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> How annoying!.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSIA</speaker>
                        <p> That's not unknown to me: in fine, upon my faith, I would rather run
                            away than go back, if I knew that I should have to go back there.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Why really, but slight causes formerly made you, Sosia, do what now you
                            are threatening to do. But I see Pamphilus himself standing before the
                            door. <stage>To the Attendants, who go into the house of LACHES.</stage>
                            Go in-doors; I'll accost him, to see if he wants any thing with me.
                                <stage>Accosts PAMPHILUS.</stage> What, still standing here,
                            master?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Yes, and waiting for you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> What's the matter?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> You must run across to the citadel.<milestone n="431" unit="TLN line"
                                /><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To the citadel</lemma>:
                                This was the fort or citadel that defended the <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, and being three miles
                                distant from the city, was better suited for the design of
                                Pamphilus, whose object it was to keep Parmeno for some time at a
                                distance.</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Who must?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> You.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> To the citadel? Why thither?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> To meet Callidemides, my entertainer at Myconos, who came over in the
                            same ship with me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> Confusion! I should say he has made a vow that if
                            ever he should return home safe, he would rupture me<milestone n="435"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">He would
                                    rupture me</lemma>: He facetiously pretends to think that
                                Pamphilus may, during a storm at sea, have vowed to walk him to
                                death, if he should return home.</note> with walking.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Why are you lingering?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> What do you wish me to say? Or am I to meet him only?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> No; say that I can not meet him to-day, as I appointed, so that he may
                            not wait for me to no purpose. Fly!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> But I don't know the man's appearance.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Then I'll tell you how to know it; a huge fellow, ruddy, with curly
                            hair, fat, with gray eyes and freckled countenance.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> May the Gods confound him! What if he shouldn't come? Am I to wait
                            there, even till the evening?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Yes, wait there. Run!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I can't; I am so tired. <stage>(Exit slowly.)</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> He's off. What shall I do in this distressed situation? Really, I don't
                            know in what way I'm to conceal this, as Myrrhina entreated me, her
                            daughter's lying-in; but I do pity the woman. What I can, I'll do; only
                            so long, however, as I observe my duty; for it is proper that I should
                            be regardful of a parent,<milestone n="448" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Regardful of a parent</lemma>:
                                    Colman observes here:
                                "This reflection seems to be rather improper in this place, for the
                                discovery of Philumena's labor betrayed to Pamphilus the real motive
                                of her departure; after which discovery his anxiety proceeds
                                entirely from the supposed injury offered him, and his filial piety
                                is from that period made use of merely as a pretense."</note> rather
                            than of my passion. But look--I see Phidippus and my father. They are
                            coming this way; what to say to them, I'm at a loss. <stage>Stands
                                apart.</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="5">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="452" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter, at a distance, LACHES and PHIDIPPUS.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Did you not say, just now, that she was waiting for my son's return?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Just so.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> They say that he has arrived; let her return.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>apart to himself aloud.</stage> What excuse to make to my father
                            for not taking her back, I don't know!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>turning round.</stage> Who was it I heard speaking here?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> I am resolved to persevere in the course I
                            determined to pursue.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> 'Tis the very person about whom I was talking to you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Health to you, my father.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Health to you, my son.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> I am glad that you have returned, Pamphilus, and the more especially so,
                            as you are safe and well.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I believe you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Have you but just arrived?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Only just now.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Tell me, what has our cousin Phania left us?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Why really, i' faith, he was a man very much devoted to pleasure while
                            he lived; and those who are so, don't much benefit their heirs, but for
                            themselves leave this commendation: While he lived, he lived
                                well.<milestone n="461" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma
                                    targOrder="U">He lived well</lemma>: This is living well in the
                                sense used by the "Friar of orders gray." "Who leads a good life is
                                sure to live well."</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> So then, you have brought home nothing more<milestone n="462"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Brought
                                    home nothing more</lemma>: Colman remarks that this passage is taken notice of
                                by Donatus as a particularly happy stroke of character; and indeed
                                the idea of a covetous old man gaping for a fat legacy, and having
                                his mouth stopped by a moral precept, is truly comic.</note> than a
                            single sentiment?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Whatever he has left, we are the gainers by it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Why no, it has proved a loss; for I could have wished him alive and
                            well.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> You may wish that with impunity; he'll never come to life again; and
                            after all I know which of the two you would prefer.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Yesterday, he <stage>pointing to PHIDIPPUS</stage> desired Philumena to
                            be fetched to his house. <stage>Whispers to PHIDIPPUS, nudging him with
                                his elbow.</stage> Say that you desired it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside to LACHES</stage> Don't punch me so. <stage>To
                                PAMPHILUS.</stage> I desired it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> But he'll now send her home again.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Of course.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I know the whole affair, and how it happened; I heard it just now, on my
                            arrival.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Then may the Gods confound those spiteful people who told this news with
                            such readiness!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to PHIDIPPUS.</stage> I am sure that it has been my study, that
                            with reason no slight might possibly be committed by your family; and if
                            I were now truthful to mention of how faithful, loving, and tender a
                            disposition I have proved toward her, I could do so truly, did I not
                            rather wish that you should learn it of herself; for by that method you
                            will be the more ready to place confidence in my disposition when she,
                            who is now acting unjustly toward me, speaks favorably of me. And that
                            through no fault of mine this separation has taken place, I call the
                            Gods to witness. But since she considers that it is not befitting her to
                            give way to my mother, and with readiness to conform to her temper, and
                            as on no other terms it is possible for good feeling to exist between
                            them, either my mother must be separated, Phidippus, from me, or else
                            Philumena. Now affection urges me rather to consult my mother's
                            pleasure.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Pamphilus, your words have reached my ears not otherwise than to my
                            satisfaction, since I find that you post-pone all considerations for
                            your parent. But take care, Pamphilus, lest impelled by resentment, you
                            carry matters too far.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> How, impelled by resentment, could, I now be biased against her who
                            never has been guilty of any thing toward me, father, that I could not
                            wish, and who has often deserved as well as I could desire? I both love
                            and praise and exceedingly regret her, for I have found by experience
                            that she was of a wondrously engaging disposition with regard to myself;
                            and I sincerely wish that she may spend the remainder of her life with a
                            husband who may prove more fortunate than me, since necessity thus tears
                            her from me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> 'Tis in your own power to prevent that.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> If you are in your senses, order her to come back.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> It is not my intention, father; I shall study my mother's interests.
                                <stage>Going away.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Whither are you going? Stay, stay, I tell you; whither are you going?
                                <stage>(Exit PAMPHILUS.)</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> What obstinacy is this?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Did I not tell you, Phidippus, that he would take this matter amiss? It
                            was for that reason I entreated you to send your daughter back.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my faith, I did not believe he would be so brutish; does he now
                            fancy that I shall come begging to him? If so it is that he chooses to
                            take back his wife, why, let him; if he is of another mind, let him pay
                            back her portion,<milestone n="502" unit="TLN line"/><note
                                anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pay back her portion</lemma>: As
                                was universally done on a separation by agreement.</note> and take
                            himself off.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Just look at that, now; you too are getting obstinate and huffish.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>speaking with anger.</stage> You have returned to us in a very
                            ungovernable mood, Pamphilus.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> This anger will depart; although he has some reason for being vexed.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Because you have had a windfall, a little money, your minds are
                            elevated.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Are you going to fall out with me, too?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Let him consider, and bring me word to-day, whether he will or will not,
                            that she may belong to another if she does not to him. <stage>Goes
                                hastily into his own house.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Phidippus, stay; listen to a few words--</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> He's off; what matters it to me? In fine, let them manage it between
                            themselves,just as they please; since neither my son nor he pay any
                            regard to me; they care but little for what I say. I'll carry the
                            quarrel to my wife, by whose planning all these things have been brought
                            about, and against her I will vent all the vexation that I feel. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="act" n="4">
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="517" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter MYRRHINA, from her house.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> I am undone! What am I to do? which way turn myself? In my wretchedness,
                            what answer am I to give to my husband? For he seems to have heard the
                            voice of the child when crying, so suddenly did he rush in to my
                            daughter without saying a word. What if he comes to know that she has
                            been delivered? for what reason I am to say I kept it concealed, upon my
                            faith I do not know. But there's a noise at the door; I believe it is
                            himself coming out to me: I'm utterly undone! <stage>Enter PHIDIPPUS,
                                from the house.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> My wife, when she saw me going to my
                            daughter, betook herself out of the house: and look, there she is.
                                <stage>Addressing her.</stage> What have you to say, Myrrhina? Hark
                            you! to you I speak.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> What, to me, my husband?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Am I your husband? Do you consider me a husband, or a man, in fact? For,
                            woman, if I had ever appeared to you to be either of these, I should not
                            in this way have been held in derision by your doings.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> By what doings?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Do you ask the question? Is not your daughter brought to bed? Eh, are
                            you silent? By whom?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> Is it proper for a father to be asking such a question? Oh, shocking! By
                            whom do you think, pray, except by him to whom she was given in
                            marriage?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> I believe it; nor indeed is it for a father to think otherwise. But I
                            wonder much what the reason can be for which you so very much wish all
                            of us to be in ignorance of the truth, especially when she has been
                            delivered properly, and at the right time.<milestone n="531"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">At the
                                    right time</lemma>: Lemaire observes that, from this passage, it
                                would appear that the Greeks considered seven months sufficient for
                                gestation. So it would appear, if we are to take the time of the
                                Play to be seven, and not nine, months after the marriage; and, as
                                before observed, the former seems to be the more reasonable
                                conclusion.</note> That you should be of a mind so perverse as to
                            prefer that the child should perish, through which you might be sure
                            that hereafter there would be a friendship more lasting between us,
                            rather than that, at the expense of your feelings, his wife should
                            continue with him! I supposed this to be their fault, while in reality
                            it lies with you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> I am an unhappy creature!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> I wish I were sure that so it was; but now it recurs to my mind what you
                            once said about this matter, when we accepted him as our son-in-law. For
                            you declared that you could not endure your daughter to be married to a
                            person who was attached to a courtesan, and who spent his nights away
                            from home.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> Any cause whatever I had rather he should suspect
                            than the right one.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> I knew much sooner than you did, Myrrhina, that he kept a mistress; but
                            this I never considered a crime in young men; for it is natural to them
                            all. For, i' faith, the time will soon come when even he will be
                            disgusted with himself for doing so. But just as you formerly showed
                            yourself, you have never. ceased to be the same up to the present time;
                            in order that you might withdraw your daughter from him, and that what I
                            did might not hold good, one thing itself now plainly proves how far you
                            wished it carried out.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> Do you suppose that I am so willful that I could have entertained such
                            feelings toward one whose mother I am, if this match had been to our
                            advantage?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Can you possibly foresee or judge what is to our advantage? You have
                            heard it of some one, perhaps, who has told you that he has seen him
                            coming from or going to his mistress. What then? If he has done so with
                            discretion, and but occasionally, is it not more kind in us to conceal
                            our knowledge of it, than to do our. best to be aware of it, in
                            consequence of which he will detest us? For if he could all at once have
                            withdrawn himself from her with whom he had been intimate for so many
                            years, I should not have deemed him a man, or likely to prove a constant
                            husband for our daughter.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> Do have done about the young man, I pray; and what you say I've been
                            guilty of. Go away, meet him by yourself; ask him whether he wishes to
                            have her as a wife or not; if so it is that he should say he does wish
                            it, why, send her back; but if on the other hand he does not wish it, I
                            have taken the best course for my child.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> And suppose he does not wish it, and you, Myrrhina, knew him to be in
                            fault; still I was at hand, by whose advice it was proper for these
                            matters to be settled; therefore I am greatly offended that you have
                            presumed to act thus without my leave. I forbid you to attempt to carry
                            the child any where out of this house. But I am very foolish to be
                            expecting her to obey my orders. I'll go in-doors, and charge the
                            servants to allow it to be carried out nowhere. <stage>Goes into the
                                house.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>MYRRHINA</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my faith, I do believe that there is no woman living more wretched
                            than I; for how he would take it, if he came to know the real state of
                            the case, i' faith, is not unknown to me, when he bears this, which is
                            of less consequence, with such angry feelings; and I know not in what
                            way his sentiments can possibly be changed. Out of very many
                            misfortunes, this one evil alone had been wanting to me, for him to
                            compel me to rear a child of whom we know not who is the father; for
                            when my daughter was ravished, it was so dark that his person could not
                            be distinguished, nor was any thing taken from him on the occasion by
                            which it could be afterward discovered who he was. He, on leaving her,
                            took away from the girl, by force, a ring which<milestone n="574"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A ring
                                    which</lemma>: Colman
                                remarks that this preparation for the catastrophe by the mention of
                                the ring, is not so artful as might have been expected from Terence;
                                as in this soliloquy he tells the circumstances directly to the
                                Audience.</note> she had upon her finger. I am afraid, too, of
                            Pamphilus, that he may be unable any longer to conceal what I have
                            requested, when he learns that the child of another is being brought up
                            as his. <stage>Goes into the house.</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="2">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="578" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter SOSTRATA and PAMPHILUS.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> It is not unknown to me, my son, that I am suspected by you as the cause
                            of your wife having left our house in consequence of my conduct;
                            although you carefully conceal your knowledge of it. But so may the Gods
                            prosper me, and so may you answer all my hopes, I have never knowingly
                            deserved that hatred of me should with reason possess her; and while I
                            thought before that you loved me, on that point you have confirmed my
                            belief: for in-doors your father has just now related to me in what way
                            you have preferred me to your passion. Now it is my determination to
                            return you the favor, that you may understand that with me lies the
                            reward of your affection. My Pamphilus, I think that this is expedient
                            both for yourselves and my own reputation. I have finally resolved to
                            retire hence into the country with your father, that my presence may not
                            be an obstacle, and that no pretense may remain why your Philumena
                            should not return to you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Pray, what sort of resolution is this? Driven away by her folly, would
                            you be removing from the city to live in the country? You shall not do
                            so; and I will not permit, mother, any one who may wish to censure us,
                            to say that this has been done through my perverseness, and not your
                            inclination. Besides, I do not wish you, for my sake, to forego your
                            friends and relations, and festive days.<milestone n="592"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And
                                    festive days</lemma>: "<foreign lang="la">Festos
                                dies</foreign>." The days for sacrificing to particular Divinities,
                                when she would have the opportunity of meeting her friends, and
                                making herself merry with them.</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my word, these things afford me no pleasure now. While my time of
                            life permitted it, I enjoyed them enough; satiety of that mode of life
                            has now taken possession of me: this is at present my chief concern,
                            that the length of my life may prove an annoyance to no one, or that he
                            may look forward with impatience to my death.<milestone n="596"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Look
                                    forward with impatience to my death</lemma>: Colman says: "This idea of the
                                long life of a step-mother being odious to her family, is applied in
                                a very beautiful and uncommon manner by Shakspeare: <cit>
                                    <quote lang="en">
                                        <l>Now, fair Hippolyta, our nuptial hour</l>
                                        <l>Draws on apace; for happy days bring in</l>
                                        <l>Another morn; but oh, methinks how slow</l>
                                        <l>This old morn wanes! she lingers my desires</l>
                                        <l>Like to a step-dame, or a dowager,</l>
                                        <l>Long withering out a young man's revenue."</l>
                                    </quote>
                                    <bibl n="shak. mnd 1.1">
                                        <title>Midsummer Night's Dream.</title>
                                    </bibl>
                                </cit></note> Here I see that, without deserving it, I am disliked;
                            it is time for me to retire. Thus, in the best way, I imagine, I shall
                            cut short all grounds of discontent with all; I shall both free myself
                            from suspicion, and shall be pleasing them. Pray, let me avoid this
                            reproach, which so generally attaches on women to their
                            disadvantage.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> How happy am I in other respects, were it not for
                            this one thing alone, in having such a good mother, and her for my
                            wife!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Pray, my Pamphilus, can you not, seeing how each woman is, prevail upon
                            yourself to put up with one matter of inconvenience? If every thing else
                            is according to your wish, and such as I take it to be-my son, do grant
                            me this indulgence, and take her back.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Alas! wretched me!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> And me as well; for this affair does not cause me less sorrow than you,
                            my son. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="3">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="608" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter LACHES.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> While standing just by here, I have heard, wife, the conversation you
                            have been holding with him. It is true wisdom to be enabled to govern
                            the feelings whenever there is necessity; to do at the present moment
                            what may perhaps, in the end, be necessary to be done.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> Good luck to it, i' troth.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Retire then into the country; there I will bear with you, and you with
                            me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> I hope so, i' faith.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Go in-doors then, and get together the things that are to be taken with
                            you. I have now said it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>SOSTRATA</speaker>
                        <p> I'll do as you desire. <stage>Goes into the house.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Father!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> What do you want, Pamphilus?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> My mother go away? By no means.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Why would you have it so?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Because I am as yet undetermined what I shall do about my wife.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> How is that? What should you intend to do but bring her home?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> For my part, I could like, and can hardly forbear it; but I shall not
                            alter my design; that which is most advantageous I shall pursue; I
                            suppose <stage>ironically</stage> that they will be better reconciled,
                            in consequence, if I shall take her back.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> You can not tell. But it matters nothing to you which they do when she
                            has gone away. Persons of this age are disliked by young people; it is
                            right for us to withdraw from the world; in fine, we are now a nice
                            by-word. We are, Pamphilus, "the old man and the old woman."'<milestone
                                n="621" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U"
                                    >The old man and the old woman</lemma>: "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >Senex atque anus</foreign>." In these words he probably refers
                                to the commencement of many of the stories current in those times,
                                which began: "There were once upon a time an old man and an-old
                                woman." Indeed, almost the same words occur in the Stichus of
                                Plautus, 1. 540, at the commencement of a story: "<foreign lang="la"
                                    >Fuit olim, quasi ego sum, senex</foreign>," There was upon a
                                time an old man, just like me."</note> But I see Phidippus coming
                            out just at the time; let's accost him. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="4">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="624" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PHIDIPPUS, from his house.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p>. <stage>speaking at the door to PHILUMENA, within.</stage> Upon my
                            faith, I am angry with you too, Philumena, extremely so, for, on my
                            word, you have acted badly; still there is an excuse for you in this
                            matter; your mother forced you to it; but for her there is none.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>accosting him.</stage> Phidippus, you meet me at a lucky moment,
                            just at the very time.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> What's the matter?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> What answer shall I make them, or in what manner
                            keep this secret?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> (to PHIDIPPUS.) Tell your daughter that Sostrata is going into the
                            country, that the may not now be afraid of returning home.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Alas! your wife has been guilty of no fault in this affair; all this
                            mischief has originated in my wife Myrrhina.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> They are changing sides.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> 'Tis she that causes our disturbances, Laches.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> So long as I don't take her back, let her cause as
                            much disturbance as she pleases.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> I, Pamphilus, could really wish, if it were possible, this alliance
                            between us to be lasting; but if you are otherwise inclined, still take
                            the child.<milestone n="638" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Still take the child</lemma>: In cases of
                                separation it was customary for the father to have the care of the
                                male children.</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> He has discovered that she has been brought to
                            bed. I'm undone!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> The child! What child?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> We have had a grandson born to us; for my daughter was removed from you
                            in a state of pregnancy, and yet never before this day did I know that
                            she was pregnant.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> So may the Gods prosper me, you bring good tidings, and I am glad a
                            child has been born, and that she is safe: but what kind of woman have
                            you for a wife, or of what sort of a temper, that we should have been
                            kept in ignorance of this so long? I can not sufficiently express how
                            disgraceful this conduct appears to me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> This conduct does not vex me less than yourself, Laches.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>aside.</stage> Even if it had just now been a matter of doubt to
                            me, it is so no longer, since the child of another man is to accompany
                            her.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Pamphilus, there is no room now for deliberation for you in this
                            matter.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>. <stage>aside.</stage> I'm undone!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to PAMPHILUS.</stage> We were often longing to see the day on
                            which there should be one to call you father; it has come to pass. I
                            return thanks to the Gods.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>. <stage>aside.</stage> I am ruined!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Take home your wife, and don't oppose my will.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Father, if she had wished to have children by me, or to continue to be
                            my wife, I am quite certain she would not have concealed from me what I
                            find she has concealed. Now, as I find that her mind is estranged from
                            me, and think that there would be no agreement between us in future, why
                            should I take her back?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> The young woman has done what her mother persuaded her. Is that to be
                            wondered at? Do you suppose you can find any woman who is free from
                            fault? Or is it that men have no failings?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Do you yourselves now consider, Laches, and you, Pamphilus, whether it
                            is most advisable for you to leave her or take her back. What your wife
                            may do, is not in my control. Under neither circumstance will you meet
                            with any difficulty from me. But what are we to do with the child?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> You do ask an absurd question; whatever-happens, send him back his child
                            of course, that we: may bring it up as ours.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>. <stage>in a low voice.</stage> A child which the father has abandoned,
                            am I to rear?.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> What was it you said? How--not rear it, Pamphilus? Prithee, are we to
                            expose it, in preference? What madness is this? Really, I can not now be
                            silent any longer. For you force me to say in his presence (pointing to
                            PHIDIPPUS what I would rather not. Do you suppose I am in ignorance of
                            the cause of your tears, or what it is on account of which you are
                            perplexed to this degree? In the first place, when you alleged as a
                            reason, that, on account of your mother, you could not have your wife at
                            home, she promised that she would leave the house. Now, since you see
                            this pretext as well taken away from you, because a child has been born
                            without your knowledge, you have got another You are mistaken if you
                            suppose that I am ignorant of your feelings. That at last you might
                            prevail upon your feelings to take this step, how long a period for
                            loving a mistress did I allow you! With what patience did I bear the
                            expense you were at in keeping her! I remonstrated with you and
                            entreated you to take a wife. I said that it was time: by my persuasion
                            you married. What you then did in obedience to me, you did as became
                            you. Now again you have set your fancy upon a mistress, and, to gratify
                            her, you do an injury to the other as well. For I see plainly that you
                            have once more relapsed into the same course of life.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> What, I?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Your own self, and you act unjustly therein. You feign false grounds for
                            discord, that you may live with her when you have got rid of this
                            witness of your actions; your wife has perceived it too; for what other
                            reason had she for leaving you?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> It's clear he guesses right; for that must be
                            it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I will give you my oath that none of these is the reason.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Oh take home your wife, or tell me why you should not.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> It is not the time at present.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Take the child, for surely that is not in fault; I will consider about
                            the mother afterward.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>apart.</stage> In every way I am wretched, and what to do I know
                            not; with so many troubles is my father now besetting wretched me on
                            every side. I'll go away from here, since I avail but little by my
                            presence. For without my consent, I do not believe that they will bring
                            up the child, especially as on that point my mother-in-law will second
                            me. <stage>(Exit speedily.)</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to PAMPHILUS.</stage> Do you run away? What, and give me no
                            distinct answer? <stage>To PHIDIPPUS.</stage> Does he seem to you to be
                            in his senses? Let him alone. Phidippus, give me the child; I'll bring
                            it up.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> By all means. No wonder if my wife has taken this amiss: women are
                            resentful; they do not easily put up with such things. Hence that anger
                            of hers, for she herself told me of it; I would not mention this to you
                            in his presence, and at first I did not believe her; but now it is true
                            beyond a doubt; for I see that his feelings are altogether averse to
                            marriage.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> What am I to do, then, Phidippus? What advice do you give?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> What are you to do? I am of opinion that first we ought to go to this
                            mistress of his. Let us use entreaties with her; then let us rebuke her;
                            and at last, let us very seriously threaten her, if she gives him any
                            encouragement in future.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> I will do as you advise. <stage>Turning to an ATTEDANT.</stage> Ho,
                            there, boy! run to the house of Bacchis here, our neighbor; desire her,
                            in my name, to come hither. <stage>Exit ATTENDANT.</stage> And you, I
                            further entreat, to give me your assistance in this affair.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Well, I have already said, and I now say again to the same effect,
                            Laches, I wish this alliance between us to continue, if by any means it
                            possibly may, which I trust will be the case. But should you
                                like<milestone n="725" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma
                                    targOrder="U">But should you like</lemma>: Donatus observes that
                                Phidippus utters these words with an air of disinclination to be
                                present at the conference; and, indeed, the characters are well
                                sustained, as it would not become him coolly to discourse with a
                                courtesan, whom he supposes to have alienated Pamphilus from his
                                daughter, although he might very properly advise it, as being likely
                                to conduce to the peace of both families.</note> me to be with you
                            while you meet her?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Why yes; but first go and get some one as a nurse for the child.
                                <stage>(Exit PHIDIPPUS.)</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="act" n="5">
                <div2 type="scene" n="1">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="728" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter BACCHIS attended by her WOMEN.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to her WOMEN.</stage> It is not for nothing that Laches now
                            desires to speak with me; and, i' faith, I am not very far from mistaken
                            in making a guess what it is he wants me for.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> I must take care that I don't, through anger,
                            miss gaining, in this quarter what I otherwise might, and that I don't
                            do any thing which hereafter it would have been better I had not done.
                            I'll accost her. <stage>Accosts her.</stage> Bacchis, good-morrow to
                            you!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Good-morrow to you, Laches!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Troth, now, Bacchis, I suppose you somewhat wonder what can be my reason
                            for sending the lad to fetch you out of doors.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my faith, I am even in some anxiety as well, when I reflect what I
                            am, lest the name of my calling should be to my prejudice; for my
                            behavior I can easily defend.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> If you speak the truth, you will be in no danger, woman, from me, for I
                            am now of that age that it is not meet for me to receive forgiveness for
                            a fault; for that reason do I the more carefully attend to every
                            particular, that I may not act with rashness; for if you now do, or
                            intend to do, that which is proper for deserving women to do, it would
                            be unjust for me, in my ignorance, to offer an injury to you, when
                            undeserving of it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> On my word, great is the gratitude that I ought to feel toward you for
                            such conduct; for he who, after committing an injury, would excuse
                            himself, would profit me but little. But what is the matter?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> You admit my son, Pamphilus, to your house.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Ah!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Just let me speak: before he was married to this woman, I tolerated your
                            amour. Stay! I have not yet said to you what I intended. He has now got
                            a wife: look out for another person more to be depended on, while you
                            have time to deliberate; for neither will he be of this mind all his
                            life, nor, i' faith, will you be always of your present age.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Who is it says this?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> His mother-in-law.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> What! that I</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> That you do: and she has taken away her daughter; and for that reason,
                            has wished secretly to destroy the child that has been born.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Did I know any other means whereby I might be enabled to establish my
                            credit with you, more solemn than an oath, I would, Laches, assure you
                            of this, that I have kept Pamphilus at a distance<milestone n="752"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Kept
                                    Pamphilus at a distance</lemma>: Colman observes, how are we to reconcile this with
                                the words of Parmeno at the beginning of the Play, where he says
                                that Pamphilus visited Bacchis daily; and he inquires whether we are
                                to suppose that Bacchis, who behaves so candidly in every other
                                instance, wantonly perjures herself in this, or that the Poet, by a
                                strange infatuation attending him in this Play, contradicts
                                himself?" To this it may be answered, that as Bacchis appears to be
                                so scrupulous in other instances, it is credible that,
                                notwithstanding his visits, she may not have allowed him to share
                                her embraces.</note> from me ever since he took a wife.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> You are very good. But, pray, do you know what I would prefer that you
                            should do?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> What? Tell me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Go in-doors there <stage>pointing to the house of PHIDIPPUS</stage> to
                            the women, and make the same promise, on oath, to them; satisfy their
                            minds, and clear yourself from this charge.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> I will do so; although, i' faith, if it had been any other woman of this
                            calling, she would not have done so, I am quite sure; present herself
                            before a married woman for such a purpose! But I do not wish your son to
                            be suspected on an unfounded report, nor appear inconstant,
                            undeservedly, to you, to whom he by no means ought; for he has deserved
                            of me, that, so far as I am able, I should do him a service.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Your language has rendered me quite friendly and well disposed toward
                            you; but not only did they think so--I too believed it. Now that I have
                            found you quite different from what I had expected, take care that you
                            still continue the same-make use of my friendship as you please; if
                            otherwise--; but I will forbear, that you may not hear any thing unkind
                            from me. But this one thing I recommend you make trial what sort of a
                            friend I am, or what I can effect as such, rather than what as an enemy.
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="2">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="769" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PHIDIPPUS and a NURSE.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> (to the NURSE.) Nothing at my house will I suffer you to be in want of;
                            but whatever is requisite shall be supplied you in abundance. Still,
                            when you are well fed and well drenched, do take care that the child has
                            enough. <stage>The NURSE goes into his house.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to BACCHIS.</stage> My son's father-in-law, I see, is coming; he
                            is bringing a nurse for the child. <stage>Accosting him.</stage>
                            Phidippus, Bacchis swears most solemnly.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Is this she?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> It is.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Upon my faith, those women don't fear the Gods; and I don't think that
                            the Gods care about them.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>pointing to her ATTENDANTS.</stage> I will give you up my female
                            servants; with my full permission, examine them with any tortures you
                            please. The business at present is this: I must make his wife return
                            home to Pamphilus; should I effect that, I shall not regret its being
                            reported that I have been the only one to do what other courtesans avoid
                                doing.<milestone n="777" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Other courtesans avoid doing</lemma>:
                                Colman has the following quotation from Donatus: "Terence, by his
                                uncommon art, has attempted many innovations with great success. In
                                this Comedy, he introduces, contrary to received prejudices, a good
                                step-mother and an honest courtesan; but at the same time he so
                                carefully assigns their motives of action, that by him alone every
                                thing seems reconcilable to truth and nature; for this is just the
                                opposite of what he mentions in another place, as the common
                                privilege of all Poets, 'to paint good matrons and wicked
                                courtesans.'" Perhaps the same good feeling prompted Terence, in
                                showing that a mother-in-law and a courtesan could be capable of
                                acting with good and disinterested feelings, which caused Cumberland to write his Play of
                                "The Jew," to combat the popular prejudice against that persecuted
                                class, by showing, in the character of Sheva, that a Jew might
                                possibly be a virtuous man.</note></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> We find, Phidippus, that our wives have been unjustly
                                suspected<milestone n="778" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Have been unjustly suspected</lemma>: The
                                words here employed are also capable of meaning, if an active sense
                                is given to "suspectas," "our wives have entertained wrong
                                suspicions;" but the sense above given seems preferable, as being
                                the meaning of the passage.</note> by us in this matter. Let us now
                            try her still further; for if your wife discovers that she has given
                            credence to a false charge, she will dismiss her resentment; but if my
                            son is also angry, by reason of the circumstance that his wife has been
                            brought to bed without his knowledge, that is a trifle: his anger on
                            that account will speedily subside. Assuredly in this matter, there is
                            nothing so bad as to be deserving of a separation.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> I sincerely wish it may be so.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Examine her; here she is; she herself will satisfy you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> Why do you tell me these things? Is it because you have not already
                            heard what my feelings are with regard to this matter, Laches? Do you
                            only satisfy their minds.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Troth now, Bacchis, I do entreat that what you have promised me you will
                            do.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Would you wish me, then, to go in about this business?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p> Go, and satisfy their minds, so as to make them believe it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> I'll go: although, upon my word, I am quite sure that my presence will
                            be disagreeable to them, for a married woman is the enemy of a mistress,
                            when she has been separated from her husband. </p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACH.</speaker>
                        <p> But they will be your friends, when they know the reason of your
                            coming.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PHIDIPPUS</speaker>
                        <p> And I promise that they shall be your friends, when they know the fact;
                            for you will release them from their mistake, and yourself, at the same
                            time, from suspicion.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Wretched me! I'm ashamed to meet Philumena. (To her ATTENDANTS.) Do you
                            both follow me into the house. <stage>Goes into the house with PHIDIPPUS
                                and her ATTENDANTS.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>LACHES</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>to himself.</stage> What is there that I could more wish for,
                            than what I see has happened to this woman? To gain favor without loss
                            to myself, and to benefit myself at the same time. For if now it is the
                            fact that she has really withdrawn from Pamphilus, she knows that by
                            that step she has acquired honor and reputation: she returns the favor
                            to him, and, by the same means, attaches us as friends to herself.
                                <stage>Goes into the house.</stage>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="3">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="801" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PARMENO, moving along with difficulty.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>. <stage>to himself.</stage> Upon my faith, my master does assuredly
                            think my labor of little value; to have sent me for nothing, where I
                            have been sitting the whole day to no purpose, waiting at the citadel
                            for Callidemides, his landlord at Myconos. And so, while sitting there
                            to-day, like a fool, as each person came by, I accosted him:--"Young
                            man, just tell me, pray, are you a Myconian" "I am not.." "But is your
                            name Callidemides?" "No." "Have you any former guest here named
                            Pamphilus?" All said, "No; and I don't believe that there is any such
                            person." At last, i' faith, I was quite ashamed, and went away. But how
                            is it I see Bacchis coming out of our neighbor's? What business can she
                            have there? <stage>Enter BACCHIS, from the house of
                            PHIDIPPUS.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Parmeno, you make your appearance opportunely; run with all
                                speed'<milestone n="809" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Run with all speed</lemma>: Donatus
                                remarks, that Parmeno is drawn as being of a lazy and inquisitive
                                character; and that Terence, therefore, humorously contrives to keep
                                him always on the move, and in total ignorance of what is going
                                on.</note> to Pamphilus.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Why thither?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Say that I entreat him to come.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> To your house?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCH. NO;</speaker>
                        <p> to Philumena.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> What's the matter?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Nothing that concerns you; so cease to make inquiry.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Am I to say nothing else?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Yes; that Myrrhina has recognized that ring as her daughter's, which he
                            formerly gave me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I understand-is that all?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> That's all. He will be here directly he has heard this from you. But do
                            you linger?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Far from it, indeed; for I've not had the opportunity given me to-day;
                            so much with running and walking about have I wasted the whole day.
                                <stage>Goes into the house of LACHES.</stage></p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> What great joy have I caused for Pamphilus by my coming to-day! How many
                            blessings have I brought him! and from how many sorrows have I rescued
                            him! A son I save for him, when it was nearly perishing through the
                            agency of these women and of himself: a wife, whom he thought that he
                            must cast off forever, I restore to him: from the suspicion that he lay
                            under with his father and Phidippus, I have cleared him. This ring, in
                            fact, was the cause of these discoveries being made. For I remember,
                            that about ten months ago, at an early hour of night, he came running
                            home to my house, out of breath, without a companion, and surcharged
                            with wine,<milestone n="824" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">Surcharged with wine</lemma>: Cooke has
                                this remark here: "I suppose that this is the best excuse the Poet
                                could make for the young gentleman's being guilty of felony and rape
                                at the same time. In this speech, the incident is related on which
                                the catastrophe of the Play turns, which incident is a very
                                barbarous one, and attended with more than one absurdity, though it
                                is the occasion of an agreeable discovery."</note> with this ring in
                            his hand. I felt alarmed immediately: "My Pamphilus," I said, "prithee,
                            my dear, why thus breathless, or where did you get that ring?-tell me!"
                            He began to pretend that he was thinking of something else. When I saw
                            that, I began to suspect I know not what, and to press him still more to
                            tell me. The fellow confessed that he had ravished some female, he knew
                            not whom, in the street; and said, that while she was struggling, he had
                            taken that ring away from her. Myrrhina here recognized it just now,
                            while I had it on my finger. She asked whence it came: I told her all
                            the story. Hence the discovery has been made that it was Philumena
                            ravished by him, and that this new-born child is his. I am overjoyed
                            that this happiness hsa befallen him through my agency; although other
                            courtesans would not have similar feelings; nor, indeed, is it to our
                            interest that any lover should find pleasure in matrimony. But, i'
                            faith, I never, for the sake of gain, will give my mind to base actions.
                            So long as I had the opportunity, I found him to be kind, easy, and
                            good-natured. This marriage has fallen out unluckily for me,--that I
                            confess to be the fact. But, upon my word, I do think that I have done
                            nothing for it to befall me deservedly. It is but reasonable to endure
                            inconveniences from one from whom I have received so many benefits. </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="scene" n="4">
                    <milestone n="1" unit="line"/>
                    <milestone n="843" unit="TLN line"/>
                    <stage>Enter PAMPHILUS and PARMENO, from the house of LACHES, on the other side
                        of the stage.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Once more, take care, will you, my dear Parmeno, that you have brought
                            me a faithful and distinct account, so as not to allure me for a short
                            time to indulge in these transient joys.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I have taken care.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> For certain?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p>For certain.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I am quite a God, if it is so!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> You'll find it true.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Just stay, will you; I fear that I'm believing one thing, and you are
                            telling another.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> I am staying.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I think you said to this effect--that Myrrhina had discovered that
                            Bacchis has her ring.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> It is the fact.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> The one I formerly gave to her; and she has desired you to tell me this:
                            is such the fact?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Such is so, I tell you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Who is there happier than I, and, in fact, more full of joyousness? What
                            am I to present you for these tidings? What?--what? I know not.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> But I know.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> What?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Why, nothing; for neither in the tidings nor in myself do I know of
                            there being any advantage to you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> What! am I to suffer you, who have caused me, when dead, to be restored
                            from the shades to life--to leave me unrewarded? Oh, you deem me too
                            thankless! But look--I see Bacchis standing before the door; she's
                            waiting for me, I suppose; I'll accost her.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Save you, Pamphilus!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Oh Bacchis! Oh my Bacchis--my preserver!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> It is a fortunate thing, and gives me great delight.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> By your actions, you give me reason to believe you, and so much do you
                            retain your former charming qualities, that wherever you go, the meeting
                            with you, your company, your conversation, always give pleasure.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> And you, upon my word, possess your former manners and disposition; so
                            much so that not a single man living is more engaging than you.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p>
                            <stage>laughing.</stage> Ha, ha, ha! do you tell me so?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> You had reason, Pamphilus, for being so fond of your wife. For never
                            before to-day did I set eyes upon her, so as to know her: she seems a
                            very gentle person.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Tell the truth.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> So may the Gods bless me, Pamphilus!</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Tell me, have you as yet told any of these matters to my father?</p>
                        <p>BACCH. Not a word.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Nor is there need, in fact; therefore keep it a secret: I don't wish it
                            to be the case here as it is in the Comedies,<milestone n="867"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In the
                                    Comedies</lemma>: Madame Dacier observes on this passage:
                                "Terence here, with reason, endeavors to make the most of a
                                circumstance peculiar to his Play. In other Comedies, every body,
                                Actors as well as Spectators, are at last equally acquainted with
                                the whole intrigue and catastrophe, and it would even be a defect in
                                the plot were there any obscurity remaining. But Terence, like a
                                true genius, makes himself superior to rules, and adds new beauties
                                to his piece by forsaking them. His reasons for concealing from part
                                of the personages of the Drama the principal incident of the plot,
                                are so plausible and natural, that he could not have followed the
                                beaten track without offending against manners and decency. This
                                bold and uncommon turn is one of the chief graces of the
                                Play."</note> where every thing is known to every body. Here, those'
                            who ought to know, know already; but those who ought not to know, shall
                            neither hear of it nor know it.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Nay more, I will give you a proof why you may suppose that this may be
                            the more easily concealed. Myrrhina has told Phidippus to this
                            effect--that she has given credit to my oath, and that, in consequence,
                            in her eyes you are exculpated.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Most excellent; and I trust that this matter will turn out according to
                            our wishes.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Master, may I not be allowed to know from you what is the good that I
                            have done to-day, or what it is you are talking about?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> You may not.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Still I suspect. "I restore him, when dead, from the shades
                                below."<milestone n="876" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"
                                    ><lemma targOrder="U">From the shades below</lemma>: Parmeno
                                says this, while pondering upon the meaning of all that is going on,
                                and thereby expresses his impatience to become acquainted with it.
                                He therefore repeats what Pamphilus has before said in the twelfth
                                line of the present Act, about his having been restored from death
                                to life by his agency.</note> In what way?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> You don't know, Parmeno, how much you have benefited me to-day, and from
                            what troubles you have extricated me.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Nay, but indeed I do know: and I did not do it without design.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> I know that well enough <stage>ironically</stage>.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>BACCHIS</speaker>
                        <p> Could Parmeno, from negligence, omit any thing that ought to be
                            done?</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PAMPHILUS</speaker>
                        <p> Follow me in, Parmeno.</p>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>PARMENO</speaker>
                        <p> Ill follow; for my part, I have done more good to-day, without knowing
                            it, than ever I did, knowingly, in all my life. <stage>Coming
                                forward.</stage> Grant us your applause.<milestone n="881"
                                unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Your
                                    applause</lemma>: We may here remark, that the Hecyra is the
                                only one of the Plays of Terence with a single plot.</note>
                        </p>
                    </sp>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
