<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
	<title>Laelius on friendship</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	<author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
<editor role="editor" n="Falconer">William Armistead Falconer</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.AnnCPB;
</titleStmt>
<extent>About 100Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<author>Cicero: De Senectute De Amicitia De Divinatione</author>
<title>With An English Translation</title>
    <editor role="editor" n="Falconer">William Armistead Falconer</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
<publisher>Harvard University Press; Cambridge, Mass., London, England</publisher>
<date>1923</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
	<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
		<state unit="section"/>
	</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date>2006</date>
<respStmt><name>GRC</name><resp>tagging</resp></respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<pb id="p.109"/>

<head>Laelius on friendship</head>

<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="1"/><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>QUINTUS MUCIUS SCAEVOLA, the augur, used to
relate with an accurate memory and in a pleasing
way many incidents about his father-in-law, Gaius
Laelius, and, in every mention of him, did not
hesitate to call him <quote>the Wise.</quote> Now, I, upon
assuming the <hi rend="italics">toga virilis, </hi><note>If Cicero assumed the <hi rend="italics">toga virilis</hi> when he was sixteen,
as he probably did (or in the year 90 B.C.), and the augur died
in 88 B.C., then Cicero attended his lectures about two years.</note> had been introduced by
my father to Scaevola with the understanding that,
so far as I could and he would permit, I should
never leave the old man's side. And so it came to
pass that, in my desire to gain greater profit from
his legal skill, I made it a practice to commit to
memory many of his learned opinions and many,
too, of his brief and pointed sayings. After his
death I betook myself to the pontiff, Scaevola, who,
both in intellect and in integrity, was, I venture
to assert, quite the most distinguished man of our
State. But of him I shall speak at another time;
now I return to the augur.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Numerous events in the latter's life often recur
to me, but the most memorable one of all occurred
at his home, as he was sitting, according to his
custom, on a semi-circular garden bench, when I
and only a few of his intimate friends were with
him, and he happened to fall upon a topic which,
just about that time, was in many people's mouths.

<pb id="p.111"/>

You, Atticus, were much in the society of Publius
Sulpicius, and on that account are the more certain
to remember what great astonishment, or rather
complaining, there was among the people when
Sulpicius, while plebeian tribune, separated himself
in deadly hatred from the then consul, Quintus
Pompeius, with whom he had lived on the most
intimate and affectionate terms. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>And so, Scaevola,
having chanced to mention this very fact, thereupon proceeded to repeat to us a discussion on
friendship, which Laelius had had with him and
with another son-in-law, Gaius Fannius, son of
Marcus, a few days after the death of Africanus.
I committed the main points of that discussion
to memory, and have set them out in the present book
in my own way; for I have, so to speak, brought
the actors themselves on the stage in order to
avoid the too frequent repetition of <quote>said I</quote> and
<quote>said he,</quote> and to create the impression that they
are present and speaking in person. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>For while
you were pleading with me again and again to write
something on friendship, the subject appealed to
me as both worthy of general study, and also well
fitted to our intimacy. Therefore I have not been
unwilling to benefit the public at your request.
But, as in my <hi rend="italics">Cato the Elder,</hi> which was written to
you on the subject of old age, I represented Cato,
when an old man, as the principal speaker, because
I thought no one more suitable to talk of that
period of life than he who had been old a very
long time and had been a favourite of fortune in
old age beyond other men; so, since we had learned
from our forefathers that the intimacy of Gaius
Laelius and Publius Scipio was most noteworthy,

<pb id="p.113"/>

I concluded that Laelius was a fit person to expound
the very views on friendship which Scaevola remembered that he had maintained. Besides, discourses
of this kind seem in some way to acquire greater
dignity when founded on the influence of men of
ancient times, especially such as are renowned; and,
hence, in reading my own work on <hi rend="italics">Old Age</hi> I am at
times so affected that I imagine Cato is the speaker
and not myself. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>But as in that book I wrote as one
old man to another old man on the subject of old age,
so now in this book I have written as a most affectionate friend to a friend on the subject of friendship. In the former work the speaker was Cato,
whom scarcely any in his day exceeded in age and
none surpassed in wisdom; in the present treatise
the speaker on friendship will be Laelius, a wise
man (for he was so esteemed), and a man who was
distinguished by a glorious friendship. Please put
me out of your mind for a little while and believe
that Laelius himself is talking. Gaius Fannius and
Quintus Mucius Scaevola have come to their father-in-law's house just after the death of Africanus<note>The death of Africanus occurred 129 B.C.</note> ;
the conversation is begun by them and reply is
made by Laelius, whose entire discourse is on friendship, and as you read it you will recognize in it a
portrait of yourself.</p>

<p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="2"/>FANNIUS. What you say is true, Laelius; for
there was no better man than Africanus, and no one
more illustrious. But you should realize that all
men have fixed their eyes on you alone; you it is
whom they both call and believe to be wise. Recently<note>Cato died in 149 B.C., hence Fannius by <quote>recently</quote>
means <quote>twenty years ago.</quote> The date of Cato's imagined
discourse on old age was 150 B.C.</note> 
this title was given to Marcus Cato and we know
that Lucius Acilius was called <quote>the Wise</quote> in our

<pb id="p.115"/>

fathers' time, but each of them in a somewhat
different way: Acilius because of his reputation
for skill in civil law; Cato because of his manifold
experience, and because of the many well-known
instances wherein both in Senate and forum he
displayed shrewdness of foresight, resolution of
conduct, or sagacity in reply; and as a result, by
the time he had reached old age, he bore the title
of <quote>the Wise</quote> as a sort of cognomen. <milestone unit="section" n="7"/>But as to
yourself, men are wont to call you wise in a somewhat
different way, not only because of your mental endowments and natural character, but also because of
your devotion to study and because of your culture,
and they employ the term in your case, not as the
ignorant do, but as learned men employ it. And
in this sense we have understood that no one in
all Greece was <quote>wise</quote> except one in Athens, and
he,<note>The reference is to Socrates. Cicero often quotes this
oracle: <hi rend="italics">infra,</hi> 2. 10; <hi rend="italics">ib.</hi> 4. 13; <hi rend="italics">C.M.</hi> 21. 78; <hi rend="italics">Acad.</hi>
i. 4. 16.</note> I admit, was actually adjudged <quote>most wise</quote>
by the oracle of Apollo&mdash;for the more captious
critics refuse to admit those who are called <quote>The
Seven</quote> into the category of the wise. Your
wisdom, in public estimation, consists in this: you
consider all your possessions to be within yourself
and believe human fortune of less account than
virtue. Hence the question is put to me and to
Scaevola here, too, I believe, as to how you bear
the death of Africanus, and the inquiry is the more
insistent because, on the last Nones,<note>The Augurs regularly met in their college on the Nones
(<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the 7th of March, May, July, and October, the 5th of
other months).</note> when we had
met as usual for the practice<note><hi rend="italics">Commentandi, i.e.</hi> practising the augural art under the
open sky. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cic. <hi rend="italics">N.D.</hi> ii. 11; <hi rend="italics">De rep. i.</hi> 14.</note> of our augural art
in the country home of Decimus Brutus, you were
not present, though it had been your custom always
to observe that day and to discharge its duties with
the most scrupulous care.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>SCAEVOLA. There is indeed a great deal of ques-

<pb id="p.117"/>

tioning, Gaius Laelius, just as Fannius has said,
but I state in reply what I have observed: that
you bear with composure the pain occasioned by
the death of one who was at once a most eminent
man and your very dear friend; that you could
not be unmoved thereby and that to be so was not
consistent with your refined and tender nature and your culture; but as to your not attending
our college on the Nones, that, I answer, was due
to ill-health and not to grief.</p>
<p>LAELIUS. Your reply was excellent, Scaevola, and
it was correct; for no personal inconvenience of
any kind ought to have kept me from the discharge
of the duty you mentioned, and which I have always
performed when I was well, nor do I think it possible
for any event of this nature to cause a man of strong
character to neglect any duty. <milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Now as for your
saying, Fannius, that so great merit is ascribed
to me&mdash;merit such as I neither admit nor claim
&mdash;you are very kind; but it seems to me that your
estimate of Cato is scarcely high enough. For
either no man was wise&mdash;which really I think is the
better view&mdash;or, if anyone, it was he. Putting aside
all other proof, consider how he bore the death of
his son!<note>Cicero admired the stoical parent (<hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Fabius, in <hi rend="italics">C.M.</hi>
12 Cato, here and in <hi rend="italics">C.M.</hi> 84), but on the death of his only
daughter about eighteen months before this essay was written
Cicero's grief was unrestrained.</note> remembered the case of Paulus, and I
had been a constant witness of the fortitude of
Gallus, but their sons died in boyhood, while Cato's
son died in the prime of life when his reputation was
assured. <milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Therefore, take care not to give the precedence over Cato even to that man, whom, as
you say, Apollo adjudged the wisest of men; for
the former is praised for his deeds, the latter for
his words.</p>
<p>Now, as to myself, let me address you both at

<pb id="p.119"/>

once and beg you to believe that the case stands thus:
<milestone unit="chapter" n="3"/>If I were to assert that I am unmoved by grief at
Scipio's death, it would be for <quote>wise</quote> men to judge
how far I am right, yet, beyond a doubt, my assertion
would be false. For I am indeed moved by the
loss of a friend such, I believe, as I shall never have
again, and&mdash;as I can assert on positive knowledge&mdash;
a friend such as no other man ever was to me. But
I am not devoid of a remedy, and I find very great
consolation in the comforting fact that I am free
from the delusion which causes most men anguish
when their friends depart. I believe that no ill
has befallen Scipio; it has befallen me, if it has
befallen anyone; but great anguish for one's own
inconveniences is the mark of the man who loves
not his friend but himself.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>But who would say that all has not gone wonderfully well with <hi rend="italics">him?</hi> For unless he had wished
to live for ever&mdash;a wish he was very far from entertaining&mdash;what was there, proper for a human being
to wish for, that he did not attain? The exalted
expectation which his country conceived of him in
his childhood, he at a bound, through incredible
merit, more than realized in his youth. Though he
never sought the consulship, he was elected consul
twice&mdash;the first time<note>Scipio was elected consul the first time in 147 B.C., at the
age of thirty-eight, when a candidate for the aedileship, and
given command of the war against Carthage. He was elected
again in 134 B.C. (though not a candidate), to conduct the
siege against Numantia and to end a war which had gone
on unsuccessfully for the Romans for eight years.</note> before he was of legal age,
the second time at a period seasonable for him,
but almost too late for the safety of the commonwealth. And he overthrew the two cities that
were the deadliest foes of our empire and thereby
put an end not only to existing wars, but to future
wars as well. Why need I speak of his most affable
manners, of his devotion to his mother, of his generosity to his sisters,<note>Scipio's mother, Papiria, had been divorced by Paulus,
and Scipio gave her the legacy received by him from his
adoptive grandmother, Aemilia, wife of Scipio the Elder.
After his mother's death he gave the same property to his sisters.</note> of his kindness to his relatives,

<pb id="p.121"/>

of his strict integrity to all men? These things are
well known to you both. Moreover, how dear he
was to the State was indicated by the grief displayed
at his funeral. How, then, could he have gained
any advantage by the addition of a few more years
of life? For even though old age may not be a
burden&mdash;as I remember Cato, the year before he
died, maintained in a discourse with Scipio and
myself&mdash;yet it does take away that freshness which
Scipio kept even to the end.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="12"/>Therefore, his life really was such that nothing
could be added to it either by good fortune or by
fame; and, besides, the suddenness of his death
took away the consciousness of dying. It is hard
to speak of the nature of his death; you both know
what people suspect<note>After a violent scene in the Senate, where he opposed
Carbo in the execution of the agrarian law, Scipio was
escorted home in the evening by admiring crowds. The
next morning he was found dead in bed. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Appian, <hi rend="italics">Bell.</hi>
<hi rend="italics">Civ.</hi> i. 20; Vell. Pat. ii. 4. In other works (<hi rend="italics">De or.</hi>
ii. 170; <hi rend="italics">Fam.</hi> ix. 21. 3; <hi rend="italics">Qu. Fr.</hi> ii. 3. 3) Cicero takes
the view that Carbo murdered him; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Cic. <hi rend="italics">De fat.</hi>
18; Livy, <hi rend="italics">Epit.</hi> 59; Plut. <hi rend="italics">C. Grac.</hi> 10.</note> ; yet I may say with truth
that, of the many very joyous days which he saw
in the course of his life&mdash;days thronged to the
utmost with admiring crowds&mdash;the most brilliant
was the day before he departed this life, when, after
the adjournment of the Senate, he was escorted
home toward evening by the Conscript Fathers, the
Roman populace, and the Latin allies, so that from
so lofty a station of human grandeur he seems to
have passed to the gods on high rather than to the
shades below.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="13"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="4"/>For I do not agree with those who have
recently begun to argue that soul and body perish
at the same time, and that all things are destroyed
by death. I give greater weight to the old-time
view, whether it be that of our forefathers, who
paid such reverential rites to the dead, which they
surely would not have done if they had believed
those rites were a matter of indifference to the

<pb id="p.123"/>

dead; or, whether it be the view of those<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Pythagoreans who had a school of philosophy at
Crotona in the fifth century B.C.</note> who
lived in this land and by their principles and precepts brought culture to Great Greece,<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> lower Italy.</note> which now,
I admit, is wholly destroyed, but was then flourishing;
or, whether it be the view of him who was adjudged
by the oracle of Apollo to be the wisest of men,
who, though he would argue on most subjects now
on one side and now on the other, yet always consistently maintained that human souls were of
God; that upon their departure from the body a
return to heaven lay open to them, and that in
proportion as each soul was virtuous and just
would the return be easy and direct.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="14"/>Scipio held this same view, for only a few days
before his death, in the presence of Philus, Manilius
and several others (you were there, too, Scaevola,
having gone with me), he, as if with a premonition
of his fate, discoursed for three days on the commonwealth, and devoted almost all of the conclusion of his
discussion to the immortality of the soul, making use
of arguments which he had heard, he said, from
Africanus the Elder through a vision in his sleep.
If the truth really is that the souls of all good men
after death make the easiest escape from what
may be termed the imprisonment and fetters of
the flesh, whom can we think of as having had an
easier journey to the gods than Scipio? Therefore,
I fear that grief at such a fate as his would be a
sign more of envy than of friendship. But if, on
the other hand, the truth rather is that soul and
body perish at the same time, and that no sensation
remains, then, it follows that, as there is nothing
good in death, so, of a certainty, there is nothing
evil. For if a man has lost sensation the result is

<pb id="p.125"/>

the same as if he had never been born; and yet
the fact that Scipio was born is a joy to us and will
cause this State to exult so long as it shall exist.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="15"/>Wherefore, as I have already said, it has gone
very well with him, less so with me, for, as I was
before him in entering life, it had been more
reasonable to expect that I should have been before
him in leaving it. Still, such is my enjoyment in the
recollection of our friendship that I feel as if my
life has been happy because it was spent with
Scipio, with whom I shared my public and private
cares; lived under the same roof at home; served
in the same campaigns abroad, and enjoyed that
wherein lies the whole essence of friendship&mdash;the
most complete agreement in policy, in pursuits, and
in opinions. Hence, I am not so much delighted by
my reputation for wisdom which Fannius just now
called to mind, especially since it is undeserved, as
I am by the hope that the memory of our friendship will always endure; and this thought is the
more pleasing to me because in the whole range
of history only three or four pairs<note>The three pairs are Theseus and Pirithous, Achilles and
Patroclus, Orestes and Pylades; the fourth, probably in
Cicero's mind (Cic. <hi rend="italics">Off.</hi> iii. 45; <hi rend="italics">Fin.</hi> ii. 79), was Damon and
Phintias (<hi rend="italics">vulg.</hi> Pythias).</note> of friends are
mentioned; and I venture to hope that among such
instances the friendship of Scipio and Laelius will
be known to posterity.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="16"/>FANNIUS. That cannot be otherwise, Laelius.
But since you have mentioned friendship and we
are free from public business, it would be very
agreeable to me&mdash;and to Scaevola, too, I hope&mdash;
if, following your usual practice on other subjects
when questions concerning them are put to you,
you would discuss friendship and give us your
opinion as to its theory and practice.</p>
<p>SCAEVOLA. Indeed it will be agreeable to me, and,

<pb id="p.127"/>

in fact, I was about to make the same request when
Fannius forestalled me. Hence your compliance
will be very agreeable to us both.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="17"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="5"/>LAELIUS. I certainly should raise no objection
if I felt confidence in myself, for the subject is a
noble one, and we are, as Fannius said, free from
public business. But who am I? or what skill<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> readiness acquired by practice in extemporaneous
discussion&mdash;an art practised by sophists and rhetoricians
and by the philosophers of the New Academy; <hi rend="italics">of.</hi> Cic.
<hi rend="italics">De fin.</hi> ii. 1; <hi rend="italics">De or.</hi> i. 102.</note> 
have I? What you suggest is a task for philosophers and, what is more, for Greeks&mdash;that of
discoursing on any subject however suddenly it
may be proposed to them. This is a difficult thing
to do and requires no little practice. Therefore,
for a discussion of everything possible to be said
on the subject of friendship, I advise you to apply
to those who profess that art; all that I can do is
to urge you to put friendship before all things
human; for nothing is so conformable to nature and
nothing so adaptable to our fortunes whether they
be favourable or adverse.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="18"/>This; however, I do feel first of all&mdash;that friendship
cannot exist except among good men; nor do I
go into that too deeply,<note><hi rend="italics">Id ad vivum reseco,</hi> lit. <quote>cut back to the quick.</quote></note> as is done by those<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> those who profess the art of disputation; <hi rend="italics">of.</hi> 17.</note> who,
in discussing this point with more than usual accuracy,
and it may be correctly, but with too little view to
practical results, say that no one is good unless he
is wise. We may grant that; but they understand
wisdom to be a thing such as no mortal man has
yet attained.<note>The perfect <quote>wise man</quote> of the Stoics represents an
ideal, though they allowed that a few men, such as
Socrates, almost realized it.</note> I, however, am bound to look at
things as they are in the experience of everyday
life and not as they are in fancy or in hope. Never
could I say that Gaius Fabricius, Manius Curius, and
Tiberius Coruncanius, whom our ancestors adjudged
to be wise, were wise by such a standard as that.

<pb id="p.129"/>

Therefore, let the Sophists keep their unpopular<note>Lit. <quote>at which everyone looks askance,</quote> as indicating
conceit or arrogance.</note> 
and unintelligible word to themselves, granting only
that the men just named were good men. They
will not do it though; they will say that goodness
can be predicated only of the <quote>wise</quote> man. <milestone unit="section" n="19"/>Let
us then proceed <quote>with our own dull wits,</quote> as the
saying is. Those who so act and so live as to give
proof of loyalty and uprightness, of fairness and
generosity; who are free from all passion, caprice,
and insolence, and have great strength of character
&mdash;men like those just mentioned&mdash;such men let us
consider good, as they were accounted good in life,
and also entitled to be called by that term because,
in as far as that is possible for man, they follow
Nature, who is the best guide to good living.</p>
<p>For it seems clear to me that we were so created
that between us all there exists a certain tie which
strengthens with our proximity to each other.
Therefore, fellow countrymen are preferred to
foreigners and relatives<note><hi rend="italics">Propinquitas</hi> may be applied to <quote>neighbours</quote> or
<quote>fellow-citizens</quote> as well as to <quote>relatives.</quote></note> to strangers, for with them
Nature herself engenders friendship, but it is one
that is lacking in constancy. For friendship excels
relationship<note><hi rend="italics">Propinquitas</hi> may be applied to <quote>neighbours</quote> or
<quote>fellow-citizens</quote> as well as to <quote>relatives.</quote></note> in this, that goodwill may be eliminated
from relationship while from friendship it cannot;
since, if you remove goodwill from friendship the
very name of friendship is gone; if you remove it
from relationship, the name of relationship still
remains. <milestone unit="section" n="20"/>Moreover, how great the power of friendship is may most clearly be recognized from the fact
that, in comparison with the infinite ties uniting the
human race and fashioned by Nature herself, this
thing called friendship has been so narrowed that
the bonds of affection always unite two persons only,
or, at most, a few.</p>

<pb id="p.131"/>

<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="6"/>For friendship is nothing else than an accord
in all things, human and divine, conjoined with
mutual goodwill and affection, and I am inclined
to think that, with the exception of wisdom, no
better thing has been given to man by the immortal
gods. Some prefer riches, some good health, some
power, some public honours, and many even prefer
sensual pleasures. This last is the highest aim
of brutes; the others are fleeting and unstable
things and dependent less upon human foresight
than upon the fickleness of fortune. Again, there
are those who place the <quote>chief good</quote> in virtue and
that is really a noble view; but this very virtue is
the parent and preserver of friendship and without
virtue friendship cannot exist at all. <milestone unit="section" n="21"/>To proceed
then, let us interpret the word <quote>virtue</quote> by the
familiar usage of our everyday life and speech, and
not in pompous phrase apply to it the precise
standards which certain philosophers use; and let
us include in the number of good men those who
are so considered&mdash;men like Paulus, Cato, Gallus,
Scipio, and Philus&mdash;who satisfy the ordinary standard
of life; but let us pass by such men as are nowhere
to be found at all.<note>The ideally perfect men of the Stoics.</note> </p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="22"/>Therefore, among men like those just mentioned,
friendship offers advantages<note>Or more literally <quote>adaptabilities,</quote> <quote>occasions when it
can be fitly used.</quote></note> almost beyond my
power to describe. In the first place, how can life
be what Ennius calls <quote>the life worth living,</quote> if it
does not repose on the mutual goodwill of a friend?
What is sweeter than to have someone with whom
you may dare discuss anything as if you were communing with yourself? How could your enjoyment
in times of prosperity be so great if you did not have
someone whose joy in them would be equal to your

<pb id="p.133"/>

own? Adversity would indeed be hard to bear,
without him to whom the burden would be heavier
even than to yourself. In short, all other objects of
desire are each, for the most part, adapted to a
single end-riches, for spending; influence, for
honour; public office, for reputation; pleasures,
for sensual enjoyment; and health, for freedom from
pain and full use of the bodily functions; but friendship embraces innumerable ends; turn where you
will it is ever at your side; no barrier shuts it out;
it is never untimely and never in the way. Therefore, we do not use the proverbial<note>Proverbial, that is, as representing the prime necessities
of life.</note> <quote>fire and water</quote>
on more occasions than we use friendship. I am
not now speaking of the ordinary and commonplace
friendship&mdash;delightful and profitable as it is&mdash;but of
that pure and faultless kind, such as was that of
the few whose friendships are known to fame.
For friendship adds a brighter radiance to prosperity
and lessens the burden of adversity by dividing and
sharing it.<note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Bacon's <hi rend="italics">Friendship:</hi> <quote>This communicating of a
man's self to his friend worketh two contrary effects; for
it redoubleth Joys and cutteth Griefs in Halves.</quote></note> </p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="23"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="7"/>Seeing that friendship includes very many
and very great advantages, it undoubtedly excels all
other things in this respect, that it projects the
bright ray of hope into the future, and does not
suffer the spirit to grow faint or to fall. Again, he
who looks upon a true friend, looks, as it were, upon
a sort of image of himself. Wherefore friends, though
absent, are at hand; though in need, yet abound;
though weak, are strong; and&mdash;harder saying still&mdash;
though dead, are yet alive; so great is the esteem
on the part of their friends, the tender recollection
and the deep longing that still attends them. These
things make the death of the departed seem fortunate and the life of the survivors worthy of praise.

<pb id="p.135"/>

But if you should take the bond of goodwill out of
the universe no house or city could stand, nor would
even the tillage of the fields abide. If that statement is not clear, then you may understand how
great is the power of friendship and of concord
from a consideration of the results of enmity and
disagreement. For what house is so strong, or
what state so enduring that it cannot be utterly
overthrown by animosities and division?</p>
<p>From this it may be judged how great good there
is in friendship. <milestone unit="section" n="24"/>It is said, at any rate, that a certain
learned man of Agrigentum<note>Empedocles, according to whom <foreign lang="greek">filo/ths</foreign> (friendship)
and <foreign lang="greek">nei=kos</foreign> (strife) are perpetually at war, causing the four
elements to unite or disperse,

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l><foreign lang="greek">a)/llote me\n filo/thti sunerxo/men' ei)s e(\n a(/panta,</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="greek">a)/llote d' au)= di/x' e(/kasta foreu/mena nei/keos e)/xqei.</foreign></l></quote></note> sang in inspired strain
in Greek verse that in nature and the entire universe
whatever things are at rest and whatever are in
motion are united by friendship and scattered by
discord. And indeed this is a statement which all
men not only understand but also approve. Whenever, therefore, there comes to light some signal
service in undergoing or sharing the dangers of a
friend, who does not proclaim it with the loudest
praise? What shouts recently rang through the
entire theatre during the performance of the new
play, written by my guest and friend, Marcus
Pacuvius,<note>The title is uncertain, but the subject was that of
Euripides' <hi rend="italics">Iphigenia in Tauris.</hi></note> at the scene where, the king being
ignorant which of the two was Orestes, Pylades, who
wished to be put to death instead of his friend,
declared, <quote>I am Orestes,</quote> while Orestes continued
steadfastly to assert, as was the fact, <quote>I am
Orestes!</quote> The people in the audience rose to their
feet and cheered this incident in fiction; what, think
we, would they have done had it occurred in real
life? In this case Nature easily asserted her own
power, inasmuch as men approved in another as
well done that which they could not do themselves.</p>

<pb id="p.137"/>

<p>Within the foregoing limits I have, I think, been
able to state my estimate of friendship; if there is
anything more to be said&mdash;and I believe there is a
great deal&mdash;inquire, if you please, of those who
make a business of such discussions.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="25"/>FANNIUS. But we prefer to inquire of you. I
have, it is true, often questioned those men too, and
indeed have not been an unwilling listener, but
the thread of your discourse is of a somewhat different
texture.</p>
<p>SCAEVOLA. You would say so with greater confidence, Fannius, if you had been present recently
in Scipio's country home during the discussion on
the Republic. What an advocate of justice Laelius
was then against the elaborate speech of Philus!</p>
<p>FANNIUS. Ah! but it was an easy thing for the
most just of men to defend justice.</p>
<p>SCAEVOLA. Well, then, would not the defence of
friendship be easy for that man who has preserved
it with the utmost fidelity, constancy, and sense of
justice, and thereby gained the greatest renown?</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="26"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="8"/>LAELIUS. Really you are employing violence;
for what matters it what means you take of forcing
me? Forcing me you certainly are. For it is not
only hard, but not even right, to withstand the
earnest requests of one's sons-in-law, particularly in
a good cause.</p>
<p>The oftener, therefore, I reflect on friendship the
more it seems to me that consideration should be
given to the question, whether the longing for
friendship is felt on account of weakness and want,
so that by the giving and receiving of favours one
may get from another and in turn repay what he
is unable to procure of himself; or, although this

<pb id="p.139"/>

mutual interchange is really inseparable from
friendship, whether there is not another cause,
older, more beautiful, and emanating more directly
from Nature herself. For it is love (<hi rend="italics">amor</hi>), from
which the word <quote>friendship</quote> (<hi rend="italics">amicitia</hi>) is derived,
that leads to the establishing of goodwill. For
while it is true that advantages are frequently
obtained even from those who, under a pretence of
friendship, are courted and honoured to suit the
occasion; yet in friendship there is nothing false,
nothing pretended; whatever there is is genuine
and comes of its own accord. <milestone unit="section" n="27"/>Wherefore it seems to
me that friendship springs rather from nature than
from need, and from an inclination of the soul joined
with a feeling of love rather than from calculation
of how much profit the friendship is likely to afford.
What this feeling is may be perceived even in the
case of certain animals, which, up to a certain time,
so love their offspring and are so loved by them,
that their impulses are easily seen. But this is
much more evident in man; first, from the affection
existing between children and parents, which cannot
be destroyed except by some execrable crime, and
again from that kindred impulse of love, which
arises when once we have met someone whose
habits and character are congenial with our own;
because in him we seem to behold, as it were, a
sort of lamp of uprightness and virtue. <milestone unit="section" n="28"/>For there
is nothing more lovable than virtue, nothing that
more allures us to affection, since on account of
their virtue and uprightness we feel a sort of affection even for those whom we have never seen.
Is there anyone who does not dwell with some
kindly affection on the memory of Gaius Fabricius

<pb id="p.141"/>

and Manius Curius, though he never saw them?
On the other hand, is there anyone who does not
hate Tarquin the Proud, Spurius Cassius, or
Spurius Maelius? Against two leaders we had
bitter struggles for the empire of Italy-Pyrrhus
and Hannibal; for the former, because of his
uprightness, we have no great enmity; for the
latter, because of his cruelty,<note>This was the traditional but unjust view held by the
Romans. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Livy xxi. 4. 9: Hor. <hi rend="italics">Carm.</hi> iii. 6. 361; <hi rend="italics">ib.</hi>
iv. 4. 42; Juv. vii. 161.</note> this State will always
entertain hatred.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="29"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="9"/>Now if the force of integrity is so great that
we love it, whether in those we have never seen, or,
more wonderful still, even in an enemy, what wonder
that men's souls are stirred when they think they
see clearly the virtue and goodness of those with
whom a close intimacy is possible? And yet love
is further strengthened by the receiving of a kindly
service, by the evidence of another's care for us,
and by closer familiarity, and from all these, when
joined to the soul's first impulse to love, there springs
up, if I may say so, a marvellous glow and greatness
of goodwill.</p>
<p>If people think that friendship springs from weakness and from a purpose to secure someone through
whom we may obtain that which we lack, they
assign her, if I may so express it, a lowly pedigree
indeed, and an origin far from noble, and they
would make her the daughter of poverty and want.
If this were so, then just in proportion as any man
judged his resources to be small, would he be fitted
for friendship; whereas the truth is far otherwise.
<milestone unit="section" n="30"/>For to the extent that a man relies upon himself and is so fortified by virtue and wisdom that
he is dependent on no one and considers all his
possessions to be within himself, in that degree is

<pb id="p.143"/>

he most conspicuous for seeking out and cherishing
friendships. Now what need did Africanus have
of me?<note>According to the Stoics the wise man needed nothing,
though there were many things advisable for him to have;
cf. Seneca, <hi rend="italics">Ep. 9;</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Lysis</hi> B.</note> By Hercules! none at all. And I,
assuredly, had no need of him either, but I loved
him because of a certain admiration for his virtue,
and he, in turn, loved me, because, it may be, of
the fairly good opinion which he had of my character; and close association added to our mutual
affection. Although many and great advantages
did ensue from our friendship, still the beginnings
of our love did not spring from the hope of gain.
<milestone unit="section" n="31"/>For as men of our class are generous and liberal,
not for the purpose of demanding repayment&mdash;for
we do not put our favours out at interest, but are
by nature given to acts of kindness&mdash;so we believe
that friendship is desirable, not because we are influenced by hope of gain, but because its entire
profit is in the love itself.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="32"/>From this view those men who, after the manner
of cattle, judge everything by the standard of
pleasure, vigorously dissent; nor is it strange;
for the raising of the vision to anything lofty, noble
and divine is impossible to men who have abased
their every thought to a thing so lowly and so mean.
Therefore let us dismiss these persons from our
conversation and let us for ourselves believe that
the sentiments of love and of kindly affection spring
from nature, when intimation has been given of
moral worth; for when men have conceived a longing for this virtue they bend towards it and move
closer to it, so that, by familiar association with
him whom they have begun to love, they may enjoy
his character, equal him in affection, become readier
to deserve than to demand his favours, and vie with

<pb id="p.145"/>

him in a rivalry of virtue. Thus the greatest advantages will be realized from friendship, and its origin,
being derived from nature rather than from weakness, will be more dignified and more consonant
with truth. For on the assumption that advantage is
the cement of friendships, if advantage were removed
friendships would fall apart; but since nature is
unchangeable, therefore real friendships are eternal.</p>
<p>You now have my views on the origin of friendship, unless you have something to say in reply.</p>
<p>FANNIUS. Pray go on, Laelius, and I answer for
my friend here, as I have the right to do, since he is
my junior.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="33"/>SCAEVOLA. Well said, Fannius. Therefore, let us
hear.</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="10"/>LAELIUS. Then listen, most worthy gentlemen,
to the points very frequently mentioned between
Scipio and me in our discussions of friendship. Now
he, indeed, used to say that nothing was harder than
for a friendship to continue to the very end of life;
for it often happened either that the friendship
ceased to be mutually advantageous, or the parties
to it did not entertain the same political views;
and that frequently, too, the dispositions of men
were changed, sometimes by adversity and sometimes
by the increasing burdens of age. And then he
would draw an illustration of this principle from the
analogy of early life. <quote>For,</quote> said he, <quote>the most
ardent attachments of boyhood are often laid aside
with the boyish dress; <milestone unit="section" n="34"/>but if continued to the time
of manhood, they are broken off, sometimes by
rivalry in courtship or sometimes by a contest for
some advantage, in which both of the parties to the
friendship cannot be successful at the same time.

<pb id="p.147"/>

But should the friendship continue for a longer time,
yet it is often overthrown when a struggle for office
happens to arise; for while, with the generality of
men, the greatest bane of friendship is the lust for
money, with the most worthy men it is the strife
for preferment and glory, and from this source
frequently have sprung the deadliest enmities
between the dearest friends.</quote></p>
<p><quote><milestone unit="section" n="35"/>"Then, too, disagreements of a very serious
nature, and usually justifiable, arise from a demand
upon friends to do something that is wrong, as,
for example, to become agents of vice or abettors
in violence, and when the demand is refused, however honourable the refusal, it is nevertheless
charged by those to whom the compliance was
denied that the laws of friendship have been disregarded; besides, those who dare demand anything
and everything of a friend, by that very demand
profess a willingness to do anything whatever for
the sake of a friend. By their ceaseless recriminations not only are social intimacies usually destroyed,
but also everlasting enmities are produced. So
many dangers of this kind,</quote> he would say, <quote>hover
like evil fates over friendships, that it seems to me
to require both wisdom and good luck to escape
them all.</quote></p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="36"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="11"/>Wherefore, let us first consider, if you please,
how far love ought to go in friendship. Supposing
Coriolanus to have had friends, were those friends
in duty bound to bear arms with him against their
country? Or ought the friends of Vecellinus, or of
Maelius, to have supported them in their attempts
to gain regal power? <milestone unit="section" n="37"/>As to Tiberius Gracchus,
when he began to stir up revolution against the

<pb id="p.149"/>

republic,<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> in 133 B.C.</note> we saw him utterly deserted by Quintus
Tubero and by the friends of his own age. And
yet Gaius Blossius of Cumae, a prot&eacute;g&eacute; of your
family,<note>Cumae did not then possess the Roman franchise.</note> Scaevola, came to me to plead for leniency,
because I was present as adviser to the consuls,
Laenas and Rupilius,<note>Consuls in 132 B.C. when the inquiry into the acts of
Tiberius Gracchus were made.</note> and offered, as a reason for
my pardoning him, the fact that his esteem for
Tiberius Gracchus was so great he thought it was
his duty to do anything that Tiberius requested him
to do. Thereupon I inquired,<quote>Even if he requested
you to set fire to the Capitol?</quote> <quote>He never would
have requested me to do that, of course,</quote> said he,
<quote>but if he had I should have obeyed.</quote> You see
what an impious remark that was! And, by heavens!
he did all that he said he would do, or rather even
more; for he did not follow, but he directed, the
infatuation of Tiberius Gracchus, and he did not
offer himself as the comrade in the latter's fury,
but as the leader. And so, as a result of his madness,
being in fear of the special court of inquiry, he fled
into Asia, joined our enemies, and paid a heavy
and righteous penalty<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> by his suicide after the defeat by the Romans of
Aristonicus whom he had joined.</note> for his crimes against the
Republic.</p>
<p>Therefore it is no justification whatever of your
sin to have sinned in behalf of a friend; for, since
his belief in your virtue induced the friendship, it
is hard for that friendship to remain if you have
forsaken virtue. <milestone unit="section" n="38"/>But if we should resolve that it is
right, either to grant our friends whatever they
wish, or to get from them whatever we wish, then,
assuming that we were endowed with truly faultless
wisdom, no harm would result; but I am speaking
of the friends before our eyes, of those whom we
see, or of men of whom we have record, and who

<pb id="p.151"/>

are known to everyday life. It is from men of this
class our examples should be drawn, but chiefly, I
grant you, from those who make the nearest approach
to wisdom. <milestone unit="section" n="39"/>We read that Aemilius Papus was an
intimate friend of Gaius Luscinus (so we have received
it from our forefathers), that they served together
twice as consuls and were colleagues in the censor
ship.<note>They were consuls together, 282 and 278 B.C. and
censors, 275 B.C.</note> Again the tradition is that Manius Curius
and Tiberius Coruncanius were most closely associated with them and with each other. Well, then,
it is impossible for us even to suspect any one of
these men of importuning a friend for anything
contrary to good faith or to his solemn oath, or
inimical to the commonwealth. What is the need
of asserting in the case of men like these, that if
such a request had been made it would not have
been granted, seeing that they were the purest of
men, and moreover, regarded it equally impious
to grant and to make such a request? But Tiberius
Gracchus did find followers in Gaius Carbo and
Gaius Cato,<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> because they were of a different and less noble
character.</note> and he found a follower also in his
own brother Gaius, who though not very ardent
then is now intensely so.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="40"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="12"/>Therefore let this law be established in
friendship: neither ask dishonourable things, nor
do them, if asked. And dishonourable it certainly
is, and not to be allowed, for anyone to plead in
defence of sins in general and especially of those
against the State, that he committed them for the
sake of a friend. For, my dear Fannius and Scaevola,
we Romans are now placed in such a situation that
it is our duty to keep a sharp look-out for the troubles
that may befall our State. Our political practice
has already swerved far from the track and course

<pb id="p.153"/>

marked out for us by our ancestors. <milestone unit="section" n="41"/>Tiberius
Gracchus tried to obtain regal power&mdash;or rather, he
actually did reign for a few months. Had the Roman
people ever heard of or experienced such a thing
before? What his friends and relatives, who followed him even after his death, did in the case of
Publius Scipio<note>Seyffert and Lahmeyer say that this Scipio is probably
not Africanus the Younger, the friend of Laelius, as contended by Nauck and others, but P. Cornelius Scipio Nasica
Serapis, consul 138 B.C., <hi rend="italics">pontifex maximus,</hi> who led the
Senators in an attack on Tiberius Gracchus when the latter
was killed in 133. Scipio Serapis fled from Rome and died
soon after in Pergamum.</note> I cannot describe without tears.
As for Carbo, because of the short time since the
punishment of Tiberius Gracchus,<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> on account of the recent killing of Tiberius Gracchus
and the consequent excitement of the people.</note> we have borne
with him as best we could. Now what is to be
expected when Gaius Gracchus<note>Gaius Gracchus, though in 129 (the time of the
dialogue) the leader of the popular party, did not become
tribune until 123.</note> becomes tribune,
I am not inclined to prophecy; however, revolution
creeps on imperceptibly at first but once it has
acquired momentum, rushes headlong to ruin.<note>Reid translates, <quote>Affairs soon (<hi rend="italics">deinde</hi>) move on, for
they glide readily down the path of ruin when once they
have taken a start.</quote></note> You
see how much mischief has been caused already
in the matter of the ballot, first by the Gabinian
law,<note>Introduced voting by ballot and so called from its
author, A. Gabinius, plebeian tribune, 139 B.C.</note> and two years later by the Cassian law.<note>The Cassian law extended the ballot to juries in
criminal cases; it was passed in 137 and named from its
author, L. Cassius Ravilla.</note> I
seem now to see the people estranged from the
Senate and the weightiest affairs of state determined
by the caprice of the mob. For more people will
learn how to start a revolution than how to withstand it.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="42"/>Why do I say these things? Because without

<pb id="p.155"/>

associates<note><hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> as in the friendship between Carbo and Tiberius
Gracchus.</note> no one attempts any such mischiefs.
It must, therefore, be enjoined upon good men<note><quote>Good men,</quote> in political parlance were the members
of the aristocratic party.</note> 
that if by any chance they should inadvisedly fall
into friendships of this kind, they must not think
themselves so bound that they cannot withdraw
from friends who are sinning in some important
matter of public concern; for wicked men, on the
other hand, a penalty must be enacted, and assuredly
it will not be lighter for the followers than for the
leaders in treason. Who was more eminent in
Greece than Themistocles, who more powerful?
But he, after having saved Greece from slavery by
his leadership in the war with Persia, and after having
been banished because of his unpopularity, would
not submit to the injustice of an ungrateful country,
as he was in duty bound to do: he did the same
thing that Coriolanus had done among our people
twenty years before. Not one single supporter
could be found to aid these men against their
country; therefore, each took his own life.<note>The treason of Themistocles was in 471 B.C.; that of
Coriolanus in 491. Thucydides, i. 68, says that Themistocles died a natural death at Magnesia, in Asia Minor,
and Livy ii. 40 quotes Pictor as saying that Coriolanus lived
to an advanced age among the Volscians; see also Cic. <hi rend="italics">Att.</hi>
ix. 10. 3; Plut. <hi rend="italics">Them.</hi> 31.</note> <milestone unit="section" n="43"/>Hence
such alliances of wicked men not only should not be
protected by a plea of friendship, but rather they
should be visited with summary punishment of the
severest kind, so that no one may think it permissible
to follow even a friend when waging war against his
country. And yet this very thing, considering the
course affairs have begun to take, will probably
happen at some future time; as for me, I am no
less concerned for what the condition of the commonwealth will be after my death, than I am for its
condition to-day.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="44"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="13"/>Therefore let this be ordained as the first
law of friendship: Ask of friends only what is honourable; do for friends only what is honourable and

<pb id="p.157"/>

without even waiting to be asked; let zeal be ever
present, but hesitation absent; dare to give true
advice with all frankness; in friendship let the
influence of friends who are wise counsellors be
paramount, and let that influence be employed in
advising, not only with frankness, but, if the occasion
demands, even with sternness, and let the advice
be followed when given. <milestone unit="section" n="45"/>I say this because certain
men who, I am informed, are considered sages in
Greece, have approved certain views, which, in my
opinion, are astonishing (but there is nothing that
those men will not pursue with their subtleties).
Some of these men teach that too much intimacy
in friendships should be avoided, lest it be necessary
for one man to be full of anxiety for many; that
each one of us has business of his own, enough and
to spare; that it is annoying to be too much involved
in the affairs of other people; that it is best to
hold the reins of friendship as loosely as possible,
so that we may either draw them up or slacken
them at will; for, they say, an essential of a
happy life is freedom from care, and this the soul
cannot enjoy if one man is, as it were, in travail
for many.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="46"/>Again, there are others, I am told, who, with even
less of human feeling, maintain (and I briefly touched
on this point just now) that friendships must be
sought for the sake of the defence and aid they
give and not out of goodwill and affection; therefore,
that those least endowed with firmness of character
and strength of body have the greatest longing for
friendship; and consequently, that helpless women,
more than men, seek its shelter, the poor more than
the rich, and the unfortunate more than those who are

<pb id="p.159"/>

accounted fortunate. <milestone unit="section" n="47"/>O noble philosophy! Why,
they seem to take the sun out of the universe when
they deprive life of friendship, than which we have
from the immortal gods no better, no more delightful
boon. For of what value is their vaunted <quote>freedom
from care</quote>? In appearance it is indeed an alluring
thing, but in reality often to be shunned. For it is
inconsistent not to undertake any honourable business or course of conduct, or to lay it aside when
undertaken, in order to avoid anxiety. Nay, if we
continually flee from trouble, we must also flee from
Virtue, who necessarily meets with some trouble in
rejecting and loathing things contrary to herself,
as when kindness rejects ill-will, temperance lust,
and bravery cowardice. And so you may see that
it is the just who are most pained at injustice, the
brave at cowardice, the self-restrained at profligacy.
It is, therefore, characteristic of the well-ordered
mind both to rejoice at good deeds and to be pained
at the reverse.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="48"/>Wherefore, if distress of mind befalls a wise man
(as it certainly does unless we assume that human
sympathy has been rooted out of his heart), why
should we remove friendship entirely from our lives
in order that we may suffer no worries on its account?
For when the soul is deprived of emotion, what
difference is there&mdash;I do not say between man and
the beasts of the field, but between man and a
stock or a stone, or any such thing? Nor are we to
listen to those men<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Stoics.</note> who maintain that virtue is
hard and unyielding and is, as it were, something
made of iron; whereas, in many relations of life,
and especially in friendship, it is so pliable and
elastic that it expands, so to speak, with a friend's

<pb id="p.161"/>

prosperity and contracts with his adversity. Wherefore, that mental anguish of which I spoke and which
often must be felt on a friend's account, has no more
power to banish friendship from life than it has
to cause us to reject virtue because virtue entails
certain cares and annoyances.</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="14"/>But, since, as I said before, virtue knits
friendship together, if there should be some exhibition of shining virtue to which a kindred spirit may
attach and adjust itself, then, when that happens,
love must needs spring forth. <milestone unit="section" n="49"/>For is there anything
so absurd as to delight in many inanimate things, like
public office, fame, and stately buildings, or dress and
personal adornment, and to take little or no delight
in a sentient being endowed with virtue and capable
of loving, and&mdash;if I may so term it&mdash;of loving back<note>Cicero coins the word <hi rend="italics">redamare</hi> from the Greek <foreign lang="greek">a)ntifilei=n,</foreign>
but uses it nowhere else.</note> ?
For nothing gives more pleasure than the return
of goodwill and the interchange of zealous service.
<milestone unit="section" n="50"/>And what if I also add, as I may fairly do, that
nothing so allures and attracts anything to itself as
likeness does to friendship? Then it surely will be
granted as a fact that good men love and join to
themselves other good men, in a union which is almost
that of relationship and nature. For there is nothing
more eager or more greedy than nature for what is
like itself. Wherefore, because of this very fact,
I think it should be evident, Fannius and Scaevola,
that the good have for the good, as if from necessity,
a kindly feeling which nature has made the fountain
of friendship. But this same goodness belongs also
to the generality of men. For virtue is not unfeeling,
unwilling to serve, or proudly exclusive, but it is her
wont to protect even whole nations and to plan
the best measures for their welfare, which she

<pb id="p.163"/>

certainly would not do if she disdained the affection
of the common mass.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="51"/>And again, it seems to me at any rate, that those
who<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> those referred to in &sect; 46 <hi rend="italics">ad init.,</hi> the Cyrenaics
followers of Aristippus of Cyrene.</note> falsely assume expediency to be the basis of
friendship, take from friendship's chain its loveliest
link. For it is not so much the material gain procured through a friend, as it is his love, and his love
alone, that gives us delight; and that advantage
which we derive from him becomes a pleasure only
when his service is inspired by an ardent zeal. And
it is far from being true that friendship is cultivated
because of need; rather, is it cultivated by those who
are most abundantly blessed with wealth and power
and especially with virtue, which is man's best
defence; by those least in need of another's help;
and by those most generous and most given to acts
of kindness. Indeed, I should be inclined to think
that it is not well for friends never to need anything at all. Wherein, for example, would my zeal
have displayed itself if Scipio had never been in
need of my advice or assistance either at home or
abroad?<note>But <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> &sect; 30: <hi rend="italics">Quid enim? Africanus indigens mei?</hi></note> It is not the case, therefore, that friendship attends upon advantage, but, on the contrary,
that advantage attends upon friendship.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="52"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="15"/>It will be our duty, then, not to listen to
those besotted men of pleasure<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> Epicureans and Cyrenaics, referred to in &sect; 46</note> when they argue
about friendship, of which they understand neither
the practice nor the theory. For what person is
there, in the name of gods and men! who would
wish to be surrounded by unlimited wealth and to
abound in every material blessing, on condition that
he love no one and that no one love him? Such
indeed is the life of tyrants&mdash;a life, I mean, in which
there can be no faith, no affection, no trust in the

<pb id="p.165"/>

continuance of goodwill; where every act arouses
suspicion and anxiety and where friendship has no
place. <milestone unit="section" n="53"/>For can anyone love either the man whom
he fears, or the man by whom he believes himself
to be feared? Yet tyrants are courted under a
pretence of affection, but only for a season. For
when by chance they have fallen from power, as
they generally do, then is it known how poor they
were in friends. And this is illustrated by the
remark said to have been made by Tarquin as he
was going into exile: <quote>I have learned what friends
of mine are true and what are false, now that I am
no longer able to reward or punish either.</quote></p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="54"/>And yet, such was the haughtiness and perversity
of the man that I wonder if he could have had
anyone as a friend. Now just as the character of
Tarquin could not procure him true friends, so, with
many, their power, if it be very great, is a bar to
faithful friendships. For not only is Fortune blind
herself, but as a rule she even blinds those whom
she has embraced; and thus they are generally
transported beyond themselves by wanton pride
and obstinacy&mdash;nor can anything in the world be
more insufferable than one of Fortune's fools.
Indeed we may observe that men, formerly affable
in their manners, become changed by military rank,
by power, and by prosperity, spurn their old-time
friends and revel in the new. <milestone unit="section" n="55"/>But what is more
foolish, when men are in the plenitude of resources,
opportunities, and wealth, than to procure the other
things which money provides&mdash;horses, slaves, splendid
raiment, and costly plate&mdash;and not procure friends,
who are, if I may say so, life's best and fairest
furniture? And really while they are procuring

<pb id="p.167"/>

those material things, they know not for whom
they do it, nor for whose benefit they toil; for such
things are the prey of the strongest; but to every
man the tenure of his friendships ever remains
settled and sure, so that even if there should be a
continuance of those things which are, so to speak,
the gratuities of fortune, yet life unadorned and
unattended by friends could not be pleasant. But
enough on this point.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="56"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="16"/>We now have to determine in our discussion
of friendship what are the limits and, so to speak,
the boundary lines of affection. On this point I
observe that three views are usually advanced, none
of which I approve: first, <quote>That we should have the
same feeling for our friends that we have for ourselves</quote>; second, <quote>That our goodwill towards our
friends should correspond in all respects to their
goodwill towards us,</quote> and third, <quote>That whatever
value a man places upon himself, the same value
should be placed upon him by his friends.</quote> <milestone unit="section" n="57"/>I do
not agree at all with any of these views. Certainly
the first one is not true which holds that <quote>as a man
feels towards himself, so should he feel towards his
friend.</quote> For how many things we do for our friends
that we never would do for ourselves! At one time
we beg and entreat an unworthy man, and again
we assail another too sharply or too loudly rail upon
him&mdash;things not quite creditable in our own affairs,
but exceedingly so in behalf of our friends; and
there are numerous occasions when good men forgo,
or permit themselves to be deprived of, many conveniences in order that their friends rather than
themselves may enjoy them.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="58"/>The second view limits friendship to an equal

<pb id="p.169"/>

interchange of services and feelings. It surely is
calling friendship to a very close and petty accounting
to require it to keep an exact balance of credits
and debits. I think true friendship is richer and
more abundant than that and does not narrowly
scan the reckoning lest it pay out more than it has
received; and there need be no fear that some bit
of kindness will be lost, that it will overflow the
measure and spill upon the ground, or that more
than is due will be poured into friendship's bin.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="59"/>But worst of all is the third limitation, which is
that <quote>whatever value a man places upon himself,
the same value should be placed upon him by his
friends.</quote> For often in some men either the spirit
is too dejected, or the hope of bettering their
fortune is too faint. Therefore, it is not the province
of a friend, in such a case, to have the same estimate
of another that the other has of himself, but rather
it is his duty to strive with all his might to arouse
his friend's prostrate soul and lead it to a livelier
hope and into a better train of thought. Hence
some other limitation of true friendship must be
fixed, after I have first stated a view which Scipio
used to condemn in the strongest terms. He often
said that no utterance could be found more at war
with friendship than that of the man who had
made this remark: <quote>We should love as if at some
time we were going to hate.</quote> And Scipio really
could not, he said, be induced to adopt the commonly accepted belief that this expression was made
by Bias,<note>Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi> ii. 13 <foreign lang="greek">kata\ th\n Bi/antos u(poqh/khn kai filou=sin w(s mish/sontes kai\ misou=sin w(s filh/sontes.</foreign></note> who was counted one of the Seven Sages;
but he thought that it was the speech of some
abandoned wretch, or scheming politician, or of
someone who regarded everything as an instru-

<pb id="p.171"/>

ment to serve his own selfish ends. For how will
it be possible for anyone to be a friend to a man
who, he believes, may be his foe? Nay, in such a
case it will be necessary also for him to desire and
pray that his friend may sin as often as possible
and thereby give him, as it were, the more handles
to lay hold of; and, again, he will be bound to feel
grief, pain and envy at the good deeds and good
fortune of his friends. <milestone unit="section" n="60"/>Wherefore this maxim, whoever its author, really has the effect of destroying
friendship: rather ought we to have been enjoined
to exercise such care in forming friendships that
we should never begin to love anyone whom we
might sometime hate. Indeed, Scipio thought that,
even if we had been unfortunate in our choice, we
should endure it rather than plan an opportunity
for a breach.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="61"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="17"/>Therefore, these are the limits which I
think ought to be observed, namely: when the
characters of friends are blameless, then there
should be between them complete harmony of
opinions and inclinations in everything without any
exception; and, even if by some chance the wishes
of a friend are not altogether honourable and require
to be forwarded in matters which involve his life or
reputation, we should turn aside from the straight
path, provided, however, utter disgrace does not
follow;<note>This is apparently at variance with &sect; 40 <hi rend="italics">turpis enim excusatio est,</hi> etc.</note> for there are limits to the indulgence which
can be allowed to friendship. Nor indeed ought a
man either to disregard his reputation, or to consider
the goodwill of his countrymen a poor weapon in the
battle of life, though to hunt after it with fawning
and flattery is disgraceful; as to virtue we must by
no means abjure it, for it is attended by regard.</p>

<pb id="p.173"/>

<p><milestone unit="section" n="62"/>But Scipio&mdash;and I often recur to him, my sole
authority for a discourse on friendship&mdash;Scipio used
to complain that men were more painstaking in all
other things than in friendship; that everybody could
tell how many goats and sheep he had,<note><hi rend="italics"> Cf.</hi> Xen. <hi rend="italics">Mem.</hi> ii. 4. 4; <hi rend="italics">ib.</hi> ii. 4. 1.</note> but was
unable to tell the number of his friends; and that
men took pains in getting the former, but were
careless in choosing the latter, and had no certain
signs, or marks, so to speak, by which to determine
their fitness for friendship. We ought, therefore,
to choose men who are firm, steadfast and constant,
a class of which there is a great dearth; and at the
same time it is very hard to come to a decision
without a trial, while such trial can only be made
in actual friendship: thus friendship outruns the
judgement and takes away the opportunity of a trial.
<milestone unit="section" n="63"/>Hence it is the part of wisdom to check the headlong rush of goodwill as we would that of a chariot,
and thereby so manage friendship that we may in
some degree put the dispositions of friends, as we
do those of horses, to a preliminary test. Some men
often give proof in a petty money transaction how
unstable they are; while others, who could not have
been influenced by a trivial sum, are discovered in
one that is large. But if any shall be found who think
it base to prefer money to friendship, where shall we
find those who do not put office, civil and military
rank, high place and power, above friendship, so
that when the former advantages are placed before
them on one side and the latter on the other they
will not much prefer the former? For feeble is the
struggle of human nature against power, and when
men have attained it even by the disregard of friendship they imagine the sin will be forgotten because

<pb id="p.175"/>

friendship was not disregarded without a weighty
cause. <milestone unit="section" n="64"/>Therefore, true friendships are very hard
to find among those whose time is spent in office
or in business of a public kind. For where can you
find a man so high-minded as to prefer his friend's
advancement to his own? And, passing by material
considerations, pray consider this: how grievous
and how hard to most persons does association in
another's misfortunes appear! Nor is it easy to
find men who will go down to calamity's depths
for a friend. Ennius, however, is right when he
says:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>When Fortune's fickle the faithful friend is found;</l></quote>

yet it is on these two charges that most men are
convicted of fickleness: they either hold a friend
of little value when their own affairs are prosperous,
or they abandon him when his are adverse. Whoever, therefore, in either of these contingencies, has
shown himself staunch, immovable, and firm in
friendship ought to be considered to belong to that
class of men which is exceedingly rare&mdash;aye, almost
divine.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="65"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="18"/>Now the support and stay of that unswerving
constancy, which we look for in friendship, is loyalty;
for nothing is constant that is disloyal. Moreover,
the right course is to choose for a friend one who
is frank, sociable, and sympathetic&mdash;that is, one
who is likely to be influenced by the same motives
as yourself&mdash;since all these qualities conduce to
loyalty; for it is impossible for a man to be loyal
whose nature is full of twists and twinings<note><hi rend="italics"> Cf. De nat. deor.</hi> ii. 54. 136 <hi rend="italics">alvus multiplex et tortuosa.</hi></note> ; and,
indeed, one who is untouched by the same influences as yourself and is naturally unsympathetic

<pb id="p.177"/>

cannot be either loyal or steadfast. To this observation
should be added a requirement tending to produce
that steadfastness, which I have been discussing for
some time: a friend must neither take pleasure
in bringing charges against you nor believe them
when made by others. And so, the truth of what
I said in the beginning is established: <quote>Friendship
cannot exist except among good men.</quote><note><hi rend="italics">Supra,</hi> &sect; 18.</note></p>
<p>For it is characteristic of the good man, whom I
may also call the wise man, to maintain these two
rules in friendship: first, let there be no feigning or
hypocrisy; for it is more befitting a candid man to
hate openly than to mask his real thoughts with a
lying face; secondly, let him not only reject charges
preferred by another, but also let him avoid even
being suspicious and ever believing that his friend
has done something wrong. <milestone unit="section" n="66"/>To this should be
added a certain affability of speech and manner,
which gives no mean flavour to friendship. While
unvarying seriousness and gravity are indeed impressive, yet friendship ought to be more unrestrained,
genial, and agreeable, and more inclined to be
wholly courteous and urbane.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="67"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="19"/>But at this point there arises a certain
question of some little difficulty: Are new friends
who are worthy of friendship, at any time to be
preferred to old friends, as we are wont to prefer
young horses to old ones? The doubt is unworthy
of a human being, for there should be no surfeit
of friendships as there is of other things; and, as
in the case of wines that improve with age, the oldest
friendships ought to be the most delightful; moreover, the well-known adage is true: <quote>Men must eat
many a peck of salt together before the claims of

<pb id="p.179"/>

friendship are fulfilled.</quote><note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aristot. <hi rend="italics">Eth. Eudem.</hi> vii. 2; <hi rend="italics">Eth. Nic.</hi> viii. 3. 8.</note> <milestone unit="section" n="68"/>But new friendships are
not to be scorned if they offer hope of bearing fruit,
like green shoots of corn that do not disappoint us
at harvest-time; yet the old friendships must
preserve their own place, for the force of age and
habit is very great. Nay, even in the case of the
horse just now referred to, everybody, nothing
preventing, would rather use one to which he has
grown accustomed than one that is untrained and
new. And habit is strong in the case not only of
animate, but also of inanimate things, since we
delight even in places, though rugged and wild, in
which we have lived for a fairly long time.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="69"/>But it is of the utmost importance in friendship
that superior and inferior should stand on an equality.
For oftentimes a certain pre-eminence does exist,
as was that of Scipio in what I may call <quote>our set.</quote>
But he never affected any superiority over Philus, or
Rupilius, or Mummius, or over his other friends of
a lower rank. For example, his brother Quintus
Maximus, a distinguished man, no doubt, though
by no means his equal, was treated by him as a
superior, because he was older than himself. Indeed
Scipio desired that he might be the cause of enhancing
the dignity of all his friends. <milestone unit="section" n="70"/>And this course every
man should adopt and imitate, so that if he is endowed
with any superiority in virtue, intellect, or fortune
he may impart it to his relatives and share it with
his next of kin; or if, for example, his parents are
of a lowly station and his relatives are less favoured
in mind or estate than himself, he may increase
the means of the one and be the source of honour
and influence to the other; as in legends, men who
have for a long time lived the life of menials, because

<pb id="p.181"/>

their lineage and family were unknown, although
discovered and found to be the sons of gods or of
kings, nevertheless retain affection for the shepherds
whom for many years they regarded as their parents.
And surely such a feeling ought to be much stronger
in the case of real and undoubted parents. For the
fruit of genius, of virtue, and, indeed, of every excellence, imparts its sweetest flavour when bestowed
on those who are nearest and dearest to us.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="71"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="20"/>As, therefore, in the intimacy existing between friends and relatives the superior should put
himself on a level with his inferior, so the latter
ought not to grieve that he is surpassed by the
former in intellect, fortune, or position. But many
of the latter kind are continually uttering some
complaints or reproaches even, especially if they think
that they have done anything which they can speak
of as an act of duty and of friendship, involving a
certain amount of toil. A very disagreeable class
of people, certainly, are those who are ever obtruding
their own services, which ought to be kept in mind
by him for whom they were performed and should
not be mentioned by him who performed them.<note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Seneca, <hi rend="italics">De benef.</hi> ii. 10. 4 <hi rend="italics">haec enim beneficii inter
duos lex est; alter statim oblivisci dati, alter accepti
nunquam, </hi></note> 
<milestone unit="section" n="72"/>As, therefore, in friendship, those who are superior
should lower themselves, so, in a measure, should
they lift up their inferiors. For there are certain
men who render friendships disagreeable by thinking
themselves slighted&mdash;a thing which rarely happens,
except in the case of persons who think that they
really deserve to be slighted; but they ought to
be relieved of such an opinion not by words only
but by action. <milestone unit="section" n="73"/>Now, in the first place, you must
render to each friend as much aid as you can, and,
in the second place, as much as he whom you love

<pb id="p.183"/>

and assist has the capacity to bear. For however
eminent you may be, you cannot lead all your friends
through the various grades to the highest official
rank, as Scipio was able to do when he made Publius
Rutilius consul, though he could not accomplish this
result in the case of his brother, Lucius Rutilius.
But even if you could bestow upon another any
honour you chose, yet you must consider what he is
able to bear.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="74"/>As a rule decisions about friendships should be
formed after strength and stability have been reached
in mind and age; nor should men who in boyhood
were devoted to hunting and games of ball, keep
as their intimates those whom they loved at that
period simply because they were fond of the same
pursuits. For on that principle nurses and the
slaves who attended us to and from school, will, by
right of priority of acquaintance, claim the largest
share of our goodwill. I admit that they are not
to be neglected, but they are to be regarded in an
entirely different way; under no other conditions
can friendship remain secure.<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> only by forming friendships when we are mature
in mind and in age.</note> For difference of
character is attended by difference of taste and it is
this diversity of taste that severs friendships; nor
is there any other cause why good men cannot be
friends to wicked men, or wicked men to good men,
except that there is the greatest possible distance
between them in character and in taste.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="75"/>This rule also may properly be prescribed in
friendship: Let not a sort of ungoverned goodwill
(as very frequently happens) hinder your friends'
advantage in important matters. For indeed, if I
may go back to legends, Neoptolemus could not have
taken Troy if he had been willing to listen to Lyco-

<pb id="p.185"/>

medes, by whom he had been reared and who
endeavoured with many tears to hinder him from
setting out. Often, too, important duties arise
which require the temporary separation of friends;
and he who would hinder the discharge of those
duties because he cannot easily bear his grief at
the absence of his friends, is not only weak and
effeminate, but, on that very account, is far from
reasonable in his friendship. <milestone unit="section" n="76"/>In brief, it is your
duty on every occasion to consider carefully both
what you will demand from a friend and what you
will permit him to obtain when he makes a demand
on you.</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="21"/>Furthermore, there is a sort of disaster in
connexion with breaking off friendships&mdash;for now
our discussion descends from the intimacies of the
wise to friendships of the ordinary kind<note><hi rend="italics"> Cf. &sect; 32 verae amicitiae sempiternae sunt.</hi></note> &mdash;which is
sometimes unavoidable. There are often in friends
outbursts of vice which affect sometimes their actual
friends, sometimes strangers, yet so that the infamy
of the evil flows over on to the friends. Therefore
the ties of such friendships should be sundered by a
gradual relaxation of intimacy, and, as I have heard
that Cato used to say, <quote>They should be unravelled
rather than rent apart,</quote> unless there has been
some outbreak of utterly unbearable wrongdoing,
so that the only course consistent with rectitude
and honour, and indeed the only one possible, is to
effect an immediate withdrawal of affection and
association.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="77"/>But if, on the other hand, as usually happens, a
mere change of disposition and of tastes should
occur, or if a difference in political views should
arise (for I am talking now, as I said a moment ago,

<pb id="p.187"/>

not of friendships existing between wise men, but
of those of the ordinary kind), care must be taken
lest it appear, not only that friendship has been put
aside, but that open hostility has been aroused.
For nothing is more discreditable than to be at war
with one with whom you have lived on intimate
terms. Scipio, as you both know, had severed his
friendship with Quintus Pompeius on my account;<note>He won his election over Laelius by pretending that he
was not a candidate, thus throwing Laelius off his guard.</note> 
and, moreover, because of a disagreement in politics,
was estranged from my colleague, Metellus; he
acted with deliberation and moderation in each
instance, and without any bitter feeling of resentment. <milestone unit="section" n="78"/>Wherefore, in the first place, pains must be
taken that, if possible, no discord should arise
between friends, but in case it does, then our care
should be that the friendships appear to have burned
out rather than to have been stamped out. And you
must indeed be on your guard lest friendships be
changed into serious enmities, which are the source
of disputes, abuse, and invective. Yet even these,
if endurable, are to be borne, and such respect is
to be paid to the old-time friendship that he may
be in the wrong who committed the offence and not
he who suffered it.</p>
<p>In short: there is but one security and one provision against these ills and annoyances, and that is,
neither to enlist your love too quickly nor to fix
it on unworthy men. <milestone unit="section" n="79"/>Now they are worthy of
friendship who have within their own souls the reason
for their being loved. A rare class indeed! And
really everything splendid is rare, and nothing is
harder to find than something which in all respects
is a perfect specimen of its kind. But the majority
of men recognize nothing whatever in human experi-

<pb id="p.189"/>

ence as good unless it brings some profit and they
regard their friends as they do their cattle, valuing
most highly those which give hope of the largest
gain. <milestone unit="section" n="80"/>Thus do they fail to attain that loveliest,
most spontaneous friendship, which is desirable
in and for itself; and they do not learn from their
own experience what the power of such friendship
is and are ignorant of its nature and extent. For
everyone loves himself, not with a view of acquiring
some profit for himself from his self-love, but because
he is dear to himself on his own account; and unless
this same feeling were transferred to friendship,
the real friend would never be found; for he is, as
it were, another self.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="81"/>Now if it is evident in animals, whether of the
air, the water, or the land, and whether tame or
wild, first, that they love themselves&mdash;for this
feeling is born alike in every living creature&mdash;and,
secondly, that they require and eagerly search for
other animals of their own kind to which they may
attach themselves&mdash;and this they do with a longing in
some degree resembling human love&mdash;then how much
more, by the law of his nature, is this the case with
man who both loves himself and uses his reason to
seek out another whose soul he may so mingle with
his own as almost to make one out of two!</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="82"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="22"/>But most men unreasonably, not to say
shamelessly, want a friend to be such as they
cannot be themselves and require from friends what
they themselves do not bestow. But the fair thing
is, first of all, to be a good man yourself and
then to seek another like yourself. It is among
such men that this stability of friendship, of
which I have been treating for some time, may

<pb id="p.191"/>

be made secure; and when united by ties of goodwill, they will first of all subdue those passions to
which other men are slaves; and, next, they will
delight in what is equitable and accords with law,
and will go to all lengths for each other; they will
not demand from each other anything unless it is
honourable and just, and they will not only cherish
and love, but they will also revere, each other. For
he who takes reverence from friendship, takes away
its brightest jewel. <milestone unit="section" n="83"/>Therefore a fatal mistake is
made by those who think that friendship opens wide
the door to every passion and to every sin. Friendship was given to us by nature as the handmaid of
virtue, not as a comrade of vice; because virtue
cannot attain her highest aims unattended, but only
in union and fellowship with another. Such a
partnership as this, whether it is, or was, or is yet
to be, should be considered the best and happiest
comradeship along the road to nature's highest
good. <milestone unit="section" n="84"/>In such a partnership, I say, abide all things
that men deem worthy of pursuit&mdash;honour and fame
and delightful tranquillity of mind; so that when
these blessings are at hand life is happy, and without
them, it cannot be happy.</p>
<p>Since happiness is our best and highest aim, we
must, if we would attain it, give our attention to
virtue, without which we can obtain neither friendship nor any other desirable thing; on the other
hand, those who slight virtue and yet think that
they have friends, perceive their mistake at last
when some grievous misfortune forces them to put
their friends to the test. <milestone unit="section" n="85"/>Therefore, I repeat the
injunction, for it should be said again and again:
you should love your friend after you have appraised

<pb id="p.193"/>

him; you should not appraise him after you have
begun to love him.<note>From Theophrastus, <foreign lang="greek">peri\ fili/as: tou\s a)llotri/ous ou) filou=nta dei= kri/nein, a)lla\ kri/nanta filei=n.</foreign>Seneca also (<hi rend="italics">Ep.</hi>
iii.) quotes the maxim, and describes those neglecting it as
acting <hi rend="italics">praepostere.</hi></note> But we are punished for our
negligence in many things, and especially are we
most grievously punished for our carelessness in the
choice and treatment of our friends; for we deliberate
after the event, and we do what the ancient proverb
forbids&mdash;we argue the case after the verdict is
found. Accordingly, after we have become involved
with others in a mutual affection, either by long
association or by interchange of favours, some cause
of offence arises and we suddenly break the bonds
of friendship asunder when it has run but half its
course.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="86"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="23"/>Therefore carelessness so great in regard
to a relation absolutely indispensable deserves the
more to be censured. For the one thing in human
experience about whose advantage all men with
one voice agree, is friendship; even virtue itself is
regarded with contempt by many and is said to be
mere pretence and display; many disdain riches,
because they are content with little and take delight
in meagre fare and plain dress; political honours, too,
for which some have a burning desire&mdash;how many
so despise them that they believe nothing more
empty and nothing more inane! Likewise other
things, which seem to some to be worthy of admiration, are by many thought to be of no value at all.
But concerning friendship, all, to a man, think the
same thing: those who have devoted themselves to
public life; those who find their joy in science and
philosophy; those who manage their own business
free from public cares; and, finally, those who are
wholly given up to sensual pleasures&mdash;all believe
that without friendship life is no life at all, or at

<pb id="p.195"/>

least they so believe if they have any desire whatever to live the life of free men. <milestone unit="section" n="87"/>For it creeps
imperceptibly, I know not how, into every life, and
suffers no mode of existence to be devoid of its
presence.</p>
<p>Nay, even if anyone were of a nature so savage
and fierce as to shun and loathe the society of men
&mdash;such, for example, as tradition tells us a certain
Timon of Athens once was&mdash;yet even such a man
could not refrain from seeking some person before
whom he might pour out the venom of his embittered
soul. Moreover, the view just expressed might
best be appraised if such a thing as this could happen:
suppose that a god should remove us from these
haunts of men and put us in some solitary place,
and, while providing us there in plenteous abundance
with all material things for which our nature yearns,
should take from us altogether the power to gaze
upon our fellow men&mdash;who would be such a man of
iron as to be able to endure that sort of a life?
And who is there from whom solitude would not
snatch the enjoyment of every pleasure? <milestone unit="section" n="88"/>True,
therefore, is that celebrated saying of Archytas of
Tarentum, I think it was&mdash;a saying which I have
heard repeated by our old men who in their turn heard
it from their elders. It is to this effect: <quote>If a
man should ascend alone into heaven and behold
clearly the structure of the universe and the beauty
of the stars, there would be no pleasure for him in
the awe-inspiring sight, which would have filled
him with delight if he had had someone to whom
he could describe what he had seen.</quote> Thus nature,
loving nothing solitary, always strives for some sort of
support, and man's best support is a very dear friend.</p>

<pb id="p.197"/>

<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="24"/>But though this same nature declares by
so many utterances what she wishes, what she
seeks, and what she ardently longs for, yet we
somehow grow deaf and do not hearken to her voice.
For varied and complex are the experiences of
friendship, and they afford many causes for suspicion
and offence, which it is wise sometimes to ignore,
sometimes to make light of, and sometimes to endure.
But there is one cause of offence which must be
encountered in order that both the usefulness and
loyalty of friendship may be preserved; for friends
frequently must be not only advised, but also
rebuked, and both advice and rebuke should be kindly
received when given in a spirit of goodwill. <milestone unit="section" n="89"/>But
somehow it is true, as put by my intimate friend in
his <hi rend="italics">Andria</hi>:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>Complaisance gets us friends, plain speaking, hate.</l></quote><note>Terence, <hi rend="italics">Andria,</hi> i. 1. 41: <hi rend="italics">obsequium</hi> is chiefly used in a good sense, = the desire to oblige, or fall in with another's taste; but often, as here, it is almost <quote>flattery.</quote></note> 

A troublesome thing is truth, if it is indeed the
source of hate, which poisons friendship; but much
more troublesome is complaisance, which, by showing
indulgence to the sins of a friend, allows him to be
carried headlong away; but the greatest fault is
in him who both scornfully rejects truth and is
driven by complaisance to ruin.</p>
<p>Therefore, in this entire matter reason and care
must be used, first, that advice be free from harshness, and second, that reproof be free from insult.
But in showing complaisance&mdash;I am glad to adopt
Terence's word, <hi rend="italics">obsequium</hi>&mdash;let courtesy be at hand,
and let flattery, the handmaid of vice, be far removed,
as it is unworthy not only of a friend but even of
a free man; for we live in one way with a tyrant
and in another with a friend. <milestone unit="section" n="90"/>Now we must despair

<pb id="p.199"/>

of the safety of the man whose ears are so closed
to truth that he cannot hear what is true from a
friend. For there is shrewdness in that well-known
saying of Cato, as there was in much that he said:
<quote>Some men are better served by their bitter-tongued
enemies than by their sweet-smiling friends; because
the former often tell the truth, the latter, never.</quote>
And furthermore, it is absurd that men who are
admonished do not feel vexation at what ought to
vex them, but do feel it at what ought not; for
they are annoyed, not at the sin, but at the reproof;
whereas, on the contrary, they ought to grieve for
the offence and rejoice at its correction.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="91"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="25"/>As, therefore, it is characteristic of true
friendship both to give and to receive advice and,
on the one hand, to give it with all freedom of
speech, but without harshness, and on the other
hand, to receive it patiently, but without resentment, so nothing is to be considered a greater bane
of friendship than fawning, cajolery, or flattery;
for give it as many names as you choose, it deserves
to be branded as a vice peculiar to fickle and false-hearted men who say everything with a view to
pleasure and nothing with a view to truth. <milestone unit="section" n="92"/>Moreover, hypocrisy is not only wicked under all circumstances, because it pollutes truth and takes away the
power to discern it, but it is also especially inimical
to friendship, since it utterly destroys sincerity,
without which the word friendship can have no
meaning. And since the effect of friendship is to
make, as it were, one soul out of many, how will
that be possible if not even in one man taken by
himself shall there be a soul always one and the
same, but fickle, changeable, and manifold? <milestone unit="section" n="93"/>For

<pb id="p.201"/>

what can be as pliant and erratic as the soul of the
man who changes not only to suit another's humour
and desire, but even his expression and his nod?</p>

<p><quote rend="blockquote">He says <quote>nay,</quote> and <quote>nay</quote> say I; he says <quote>yea,</quote>
and <quote>yea</quote> say I; in fine, I bade myself agree with him
in everything.<note>Terent. <hi rend="italics">Eunuchus,</hi> ii. 2. 21 (1. 250).</note> </quote>

This was said by Terence whom I quoted before, but
he says it in the character of Gnatho; and to have
such a man for a friend on any terms is a mark
of inconstancy. <milestone unit="section" n="94"/>However, there are many like
Gnatho, though his superiors in birth, fortune, and
reputation, who become dangerous flatterers when
their insincerity is supported by their position. <milestone unit="section" n="95"/>But
by the exercise of care a fawning friend may be
separated and distinguished from a true friend,
just as everything pretended and false may be
distinguished from what is genuine and true. A
public assembly, though composed of very ignorant
men, can, nevertheless, usually see the difference
between a demagogue&mdash;that is, a smooth-tongued,
shallow citizen&mdash;and one who has stability, sincerity,
and weight. <milestone unit="section" n="96"/>With what flattering words Gaius
Papirius<note>See &sect;&sect; 37 and 41. The bill referred to was proposed by
him in 130 B.C., and failed to pass, but at some time after
the time of this dialogue (129) was again offered and carried.</note> not long ago insinuated himself into the
favour of the assembly, when he was trying to carry
a law making the people's tribunes eligible for reelection! I spoke against it&mdash;but I will not talk of
myself, it will give me more pleasure to talk about
Scipio. Ye gods! What weight and majesty there
was in his speech on that occasion! One would have
said, without hesitation, that he was the leader of
the Roman people, not their comrade.<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> merely one of them; he was at the time a private
citizen.</note> But you
both were present; besides, his speech is published.
As a result this <quote>people's law</quote> was rejected by
the people's votes.</p>

<pb id="p.203"/>

<p>Again&mdash;and pardon me for referring to myself&mdash;you remember when Lucius Mancinus and Scipio's
brother, Quintus Maximus, were consuls,<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> in 145 B.C.</note> how
popular apparently was the proposed law of Gaius
Licinius Crassus regarding the priestly offices&mdash;for
the right to co-opt to vacancies possessed by the
college was being converted into patronage for the
people. (By the way, Crassus was the first man to
begin the practice of facing towards the forum in
addressing the people.<note>Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Vit. Grac. 5,</hi> makes C. Gracchus the author
of this practice.</note> ) Nevertheless, through my
speech in reply, reverence for the immortal gods
easily prevailed over the plausible oration of Crassus.
And this took place while I was praetor and five
years before I was elected consul. Thus the cause
was won more by its own merit than by the influence
of one holding a very high official rank.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="97"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="26"/>Now, if on the stage, I mean on the platform, where there is the greatest opportunity for
deception and disguise, truth yet prevails, provided
it is made plain and brought into the light of day,
what ought to be the case with friendship which is
wholly weighed in the scales of truth? For in
friendship, unless, as the saying is, you behold and
show an open heart, you can have no loyalty or
certainty and not even the satisfaction of loving
and of being loved, since you do not know what
true love is. And yet this flattery of which I spoke,
however deadly it may be, can harm no one except
him who receives and delights in it. It follows that
the man who lends the readiest ear to flatterers is
the one who is most given to self-flattery and is most
satisfied with himself.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="98"/>I grant that Virtue loves herself; for she best
knows herself and realizes how lovable she is; but

<pb id="p.205"/>

it is not virtue I am talking about but a reputation
for virtue. For many wish not so much to be, as
to seem to be, endowed with real virtue. Such men
delight in flattery, and when a complimentary speech
is fashioned to suit their fancy they think the empty
phrase is proof of their own merits. There is nothing,
therefore, in a friendship in which one of the parties
to it does not wish to hear the truth and the other
is ready to lie. Nor should we see any humour in
the fawning parasites in comedies if there were no
braggart soldiers.<note>Laelius has in mind Thraso in the <hi rend="italics">Eunuch</hi> of Terence,
from which (ii. 1. 1) the following line is taken, and Pyrgopolinices, the braggart soldier in Plautus' <hi rend="italics">Miles Gloriosus.</hi>
The disgust Laelius feels at the fawning of the parasite is
relieved by the humour of the soldier.</note> 

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>In truth did Thais send me many thanks?</l></quote>

It would have been enough to answer, <quote>Many.</quote>
<quote>Millions of them,</quote> said the parasite. The flatterer
always magnifies that which the one for whose
gratification he speaks wishes to be large. <milestone unit="section" n="99"/>Wherefore, although that sort of hollow flattery influences
those who court and make a bid for it, yet even
stronger and steadier men should be warned to be
on their guard lest they be taken in by flattery of
the crafty kind.</p>
<p>No one, to be sure, unless he is an utter fool, fails
to detect the open flatterer, but we must exercise
a watchful care against the deep and crafty one lest
he steal upon us unawares. For he is very hard to
recognize, since he often fawns even by opposing,
and flatters and cajoles by pretending to quarrel,
until at last he gives in, allowing himself to be overcome so that his dupe may appear to have seen further
into the matter than himself. And yet, is there
anything more discreditable than to be made a dupe?
If not, then we should be all the more on our guard
that it does not happen to us to have to confess:

<pb id="p.207"/>

<quote rend="blockquote"><cit><quote><l>To-day, of all old fools that play the comic parts,</l>
<l>You've wheedled me the most and made your greatest dupe.</l></quote> <bibl>Lines from the <title>Epiclerus</title> by Caecilius Statius.<note><title>Cf.</title> Cic.
<title>Cato Maior</title> &sect; 36 <foreign lang="la">nam quos ait Caecilius . . . comicos stultos
senes.</foreign></note></bibl></cit></quote>

<milestone unit="section" n="100"/>For even on the stage the silliest characters take
the parts of old men lacking in foresight and easily
deceived.</p>
<p>But in some unaccountable way I have drifted
away from the friendship of faultless men&mdash;that is,
men of wisdom, such wisdom I mean as is observed
to fall to the lot of man&mdash;and I have rambled on to
a discussion of friendships of the frivolous kind.
Wherefore, let me return to the topic with which I
began and finally put an end even to that.</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="27"/>Virtue, my dear Gaius Fannius, and you,
my dear Quintus Mucius, Virtue, I say, both creates
the bond of friendship and preserves it. For in
Virtue is complete harmony, in her is permanence,
in her is fidelity; and when she has raised her
head and shown her own light and has seen
and recognized the same light in another, she
moves towards it and in turn receives its beams;
as a result love or friendship leaps into flame; for
both words are derived from a word meaning <quote>to
love.</quote><note><hi rend="italics">i.e. amor,</hi> <quote>love</quote>; <hi rend="italics">amicitia,</hi> <quote>friendship.</quote></note> But love is nothing other than the great
esteem and affection felt for him who inspires
that sentiment, and it is not sought because
of material need or for the sake of material
gain. Nevertheless even this blossoms forth from
friendship, although <hi rend="italics">you</hi> did not make it your aim.
<milestone unit="section" n="101"/>Because of this friendly impulse, I, as a young
man, became attached to those old men, Lucius
Paulus, Marcus Cato, Gaius Gallus, Publius Nasica,
and Tiberius Gracchus, father-in-law of my deal
Scipio. And while that feeling is stronger between
men of the same age, as between Scipio, Lucius

<pb id="p.209"/>

Furius, Publius Rupilius, Spurius Mummius, and
myself; yet, in turn, now that I am old, I find
pleasure in the affection of young men, like yourselves and Quintus Tubero; and I find delight also
in social intercourse with still younger men like
Publius Rutilius and Aulus Verginius. And since
it is the law of human life and of human nature
that a new generation is ever coming forth, it is
really most desirable, when you can, to reach the
goal, so to speak, with men of your own age&mdash;those
with whom you began the race of life.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="102"/>But inasmuch as things human are frail and
fleeting, we must be ever on the search for some
persons whom we shall love and who will love us
in return; for if goodwill and affection are taken
away, every joy is taken from life. For me, indeed,
though he was suddenly snatched away, Scipio still
lives and will always live; for it was his virtue that
caused my love and that is not dead. Nor is it only
in my sight and for me, who had it constantly within
my reach, that his virtue lives; it will even shed its
light and splendour on men unborn. No one will
ever undertake with courage and hope the larger
tasks of life without thinking that he must continually
keep before him the memory and example of that
illustrious man.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="103"/>For my part, of all the blessings that fortune or
nature has bestowed on me, there is none which I
can compare with Scipio's friendship. In it I found
agreement on public questions; in it, counsel in
private business, and in it, too, a leisure of unalloyed delight. And, so far as I was aware, I never
offended him in even the most trivial point; nor
did I ever hear a word from him that I could wish

<pb id="p.211"/>

unsaid; there was one home for us both; we had
the same fare and shared it in common, and we
were together not only in our military campaigns,
but also in our foreign tours and on our vacations
in the country. <milestone unit="section" n="104"/>Why need I speak of our constant
devotion to investigation and to learning in which,
remote from the gaze of men, we spent all our
leisure time? If my recollection and memory of
these things had died with him, I could not now by
any means endure the loss of a man so very near and
dear to me. But those experiences with him are
not dead; rather they are nourished and made
more vivid by my reflection and memory; and
even if I were utterly deprived of the power to recall
them, yet my age would of itself afford me great
relief; for I cannot have much longer time to bear
this bereavement; besides, every trial, which is of
brief duration, ought to be endurable, even if it
be severe.</p>
<p>This is all that I had to say about friendship;
but I exhort you both so to esteem virtue (without
which friendship cannot exist), that, excepting
virtue, you will think nothing more excellent than
friendship.</p>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
