<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
	<title>Cato the Elder: on old age</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	<author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
<editor role="editor" n="Falconer">William Armistead Falconer</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.AnnCPB;
</titleStmt>
<extent>About 100Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<author>Cicero: De Senectute De Amicitia De Divinatione</author>
<title>With An English Translation</title>
    <editor role="editor" n="Falconer">William Armistead Falconer</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
<publisher>Harvard University Press; Cambridge, Mass., London, England</publisher>
<date>1923</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>	
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date>2006</date>
<respStmt><name>GRC</name><resp>tagging</resp></respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>
	
<pb id="p.9"/>

<head>Cato the Elder: on old age</head>

<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="1"/><milestone unit="section" n="1"/><quote rend="blockquote">
<l>O Titus, should some aid of mine dispel</l>
<l>The cares that now within thy bosom dwell</l>
<l>And wring thy heart and torture thee with pain,</l>
<l>What then would be the measure of my gain?</l><note>Ennius, <hi rend="italics">Annales,</hi> lib. x., words addressed by an
Epirote shepherd to Titus Quinctius Flamininus, then
(198 B.C.) engaged in war with Philip of Macedon, and here
applied by Cicero to his lifelong friend, Titus Pomponius
Atticus.</note> </quote>

For, my dear Atticus, I may fitly speak to you in
these self-same lines in which,

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l part="F">That man</l>
<l>Of little wealth, but rich in loyalty</l></quote>

speaks to Flamininus. And yet I am perfectly sure
that it cannot be said of you, as the poet said of
Flamininus,

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>You fret and worry, Titus, day and night,</l></quote>

for I know your self-control and the even temper
of your mind, and I am aware that you brought home
from Athens not only a cognomen but culture and
practical wisdom too. Nevertheless I suspect that
you, at times, are quite seriously perturbed by
the same circumstances<note>Referring to the existing political situation. See Introd.
p. 3.</note> which are troubling me;
but to find comfort for them is too difficult a task to
be undertaken now and must be deferred until
another time.</p>

<pb id="p.11"/>

<p>However, at the present, I have determined to
write something on old age to be dedicated to you,<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
for I fain would lighten both for you and for me our
common burden<note>Cicero was then 62, Atticus 65.</note> of old age, which, if not already
pressing hard upon us, is surely coming on apace;
and yet I have certain knowledge that you, at all
events, are bearing and will continue to bear that
burden, as you do all others, with a calm and
philosophic mind. But when I resolved to write something on this theme you continually came before my
mind as worthy of a gift which both of us might enjoy
together. To me, at any rate, the composition of this
book has been so delightful that it has not only wiped
away all the annoyances of old age, but has even
made it an easy and a happy state. Philosophy, therefore, can never be praised as much as she deserves,
since she enables the man who is obedient to her
precepts to pass every season of life free from worry.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Now on other subjects I have said much and shall
often have much to say; this book, which I am
sending to you, is on old age. But the entire discourse I have attributed, not to Tithonus, as Aristo
of Ceos did, (for there would be too little authority
in a myth), but, that I might give it greater weight,
I have ascribed it to the venerable Marcus Cato;
and I represent Laelius and Scipio, while at his house,
expressing wonder that he bears his age so well,
and Cato replying to them. If it shall appear that
he argues more learnedly than he was accustomed
to do in his own books, give the credit to Greek
literature, of which, as is well known, he was very
studious in his later years. But why need I say more?
For from now on the words of Cato himself will
completely unfold to you my own views on old age.</p>

<pb id="p.13"/>

<p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="2"/>SCIPIO. When conversing with Gaius Laelius
here present, I am frequently wont to marvel, Cato,
both at your pre-eminent, nay, faultless, wisdom in
matters generally, and especially at the fact that,
so far as I have been able to see, old age is never
burdensome to you, though it is so vexatious to
most old men that they declare it to be a load
heavier than Aetna.</p>
<p>CATO. I think, my friends, that you marvel at
a thing really far from difficult. For to those who
have not the means within themselves of a virtuous
and happy life every age is burdensome; and, on
the other hand, to those who seek all good from
themselves nothing can seem evil that the laws
of nature inevitably impose. To this class old age
especially belongs, which all men wish to attain
and yet reproach when attained; such is the inconsistency and perversity of Folly! They say
that it stole upon them faster than they had
expected. In the first place, who has forced them
to form a mistaken judgement? For how much
more rapidly does old age steal upon youth than
youth upon childhood? And again, how much
less burdensome would old age be to them if they
were in their eight hundredth rather than in their
eightieth year? In fact, no lapse of time, however
long, once it had slipped away, could solace or soothe
a foolish old age.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Wherefore, if you are accustomed to marvel at
my wisdom&mdash;and would that it were worthy of your
estimate and of my cognomen<note>Cato was called <hi rend="italics">sapiens,</hi> Cic. <hi rend="italics">Lael.</hi> 2. 6.</note> &mdash;I am wise because
I follow Nature as the best of guides and obey her as
a god; and since she has fitly planned the other
acts of life's drama, it is not likely that she has

<pb id="p.15"/>

neglected the final act as if she were a careless playwright. And yet there had to be something final,
and&mdash;as in the case of orchard fruits and crops
of grain in the process of ripening which comes with
time&mdash;something shrivelled, as it were, and prone
to fall. But this state the wise man should endure
with resignation. For what is warring against the
gods, as the giants did, other than fighting against
Nature?</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/>LAELIUS True, Cato, but you will do a thing
most agreeable to us both&mdash;assuming that I may
speak for Scipio, too&mdash;if, since we hope to become
old (at least we wish it), you will, long in advance,
teach us on what principles we may most easily
support the weight of increasing years.</p>
<p>CATO. To be sure I will, Laelius, especially if,
as you say, it is going to prove agreeable to you
both.</p>
<p>LAELIUS. Unless it is too much trouble to you,
Cato, since you have, as it were, travelled the long
road upon which we also must set out, we really do
wish to see what sort of a place it is at which you
have arrived.<note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Rep.</hi> 328 E. Cicero almost translates the
words there addressed by Socrates to the aged Cephalus.</note> </p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="3"/>CATO. I will do so, Laelius, as well as I
can. For I have often listened to the complaints of
my contemporaries (and according to the old adage,
<quote>like with like most readily foregathers</quote>), complaints made also by the ex-consuls, Gaius Salinator
and Spurius Albinus,<note>Both were younger than Cato.</note> who were almost my equals
in years, wherein they used to lament, now because
they were denied the sensual pleasures without
which they thought life not life at all, and now
because they were scorned by the people who had
been wont to pay them court. But it seemed to me

<pb id="p.17"/>

that they were not placing the blame where the
blame was due. For if the ills of which they complained were the faults of old age, the same ills would
befall me and all other old men: but I have known
many who were of such a nature that they bore their
old age without complaint, who were not unhappy
because they had been loosed from the chains of
passion, and who were not scorned by their friends.
But as regards all such complaints, the blame rests
with character, not with age. For old men of self-control, who are neither churlish nor ungracious,
find old age endurable; while on the other hand
perversity and an unkindly disposition render irksome every period of life.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>LAELIUS. What you say is true, Cato; but
perhaps some one may reply that old age seems more
tolerable to you because of your resources, means,
and social position, and that these are advantages
which cannot fall to the lot of many.</p>
<p>CATO. There is something in that objection,
Laelius, but not everything. For example, there is
a story that when, in the course of a quarrel, a certain
Seriphian<note>Seriphos, an island of the Cyclades group, a symbol
of smallness and insignificance.</note> had said to Themistocles, <quote>Your brilliant
reputation is due to your country's glory, not your
own,</quote> Themistocles replied, <quote>True, by Hercules,
I should never have been famous if I had been a
Seriphian, nor you if you had been an Athenian.</quote>
The same may be said of old age; for amid utter
want old age cannot be a light thing, not even to a
wise man; nor to a fool, even amid utmost wealth,
can it be otherwise than burdensome.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Undoubtedly, Scipio and Laelius, the most suitable
defences of old age are the principles and practice
of the virtues, which, if cultivated in every period

<pb id="p.19"/>

of life, bring forth wonderful fruits at the close of a
long and busy career, not only because they never
fail you even at the very end of life&mdash;although that
is a matter of highest moment&mdash;but also because
it is most delightful to have the consciousness of a
life well spent and the memory of many deeds
worthily performed.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="10"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="4"/>I was as fond of Quintus Fabius Maximus,
who recovered Tarentum, as if he had been of my own
age, though he was old and I was young. For
there was in him a dignity tempered with courtesy,
and age had not altered his disposition; and yet
when I began to cultivate him he was not extremely
old, though he was well advanced in life. For he
had been consul for the first time the year after I was
born; and when he was in his fourth consulship I was
a mere lad, and set out as a private soldier with him
for Capua, and five years later for Tarentum; then,
four years after that I became quaestor, which office
I held while Tuditanus and Cethegus were consuls,
and he, at that very time, though far advanced in
age, made speeches in favour of the Cincian law<note>This law was proposed by M. Cincius Alimentus in
204 B.C. and prohibited lawyers from receiving fees from
clients and the rich from receiving gifts from the poor for
services. Cato's irrelevant digression here is a happy
illustration of Cicero's art in impressing us with Cato's age.</note> 
on fees and gifts. Though quite old he waged war
like a young man, and by his patient endurance
checked the boyish impetuosity of Hannibal. My
friend Ennius admirably speaks of him thus:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>One man's delay alone restored our State:</l>
<l>He valued safety more than mob's applause;</l>
<l>Hence now his glory more resplendent grows.</l></quote></p>

<p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>Indeed, with what vigilance, with what skill
he recaptured Tarentum! It was in my own hearing
that Salinator,<note>Cicero blunders here, for it was M. Livius Macatus, a
relation of Salinator, who held the citadel, Livy xxvii. 34. 7.</note> who had fled to the citadel after

<pb id="p.21"/>

losing the town, remarked to him in a boasting
tone: <quote>Through my instrumentality, Q. Fabius, you
have recaptured Tarentum.</quote> <quote>Undoubtedly,</quote> said
Fabius, laughing, <quote>for if you had not lost it I should
never have recaptured it.</quote> But, indeed, he was not
more distinguished in war than in civil life. While
consul the second time, unaided by his colleague
Spurius Carvilius he, as far as he could, opposed
the people's tribune Gaius Flaminius who was
endeavouring to parcel out the Picene and Gallic
lands,<note>Gaius Flaminius was popular tribune in 232 B.C. when
this law was enacted. It provided for the settlement of
citizen farmers on public lands, and resembled somewhat
the American homestead laws. Cicero gives the date
here as in the second consulship of Q. Fabius Maximus,
<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> 228 B.C.</note> contrary to the expressed will of the senate.
And, although an augur, he dared to say that whatever was done for the safety of the Republic was
done under the best auspices, and that whatever
was inimical to the Republic was against the auspices.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="12"/>Many are the remarkable things I have observed
in that great man, but nothing more striking than
the manner in which he bore the death of his distinguished son, a former consul. The funeral oration
delivered by him on that occasion is in general
circulation, and, when we read it, what philosopher
does not appear contemptible? Nor was it merely
in public and under the gaze of his fellow-citizens
that he was great, but he was greater still in the
privacy of his home. What conversation! What
maxims! What a knowledge of ancient history!
What skill in augural law! He had also read much,
for a Roman, and knew by heart the entire history,
not only of our own wars, but of foreign wars as well.
I was, at that time, as eager to profit by his conversation as if I already foresaw what, in fact, came
to pass, that, when he was gone, I should have no
one from whom to learn.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="13"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="5"/>Why, then, have I said so much about

<pb id="p.23"/>

Maximus? Because you surely realize now that it
would be monstrous to call unhappy such an old age
as his. And yet, not every one can be a Scipio
or a Maximus and call to mind the cities he has
taken, the battles he has fought on land and sea,
the campaigns he has conducted, and the triumphs
he has won. But there is also the tranquil and
serene old age of a life spent quietly, amid pure
and refining pursuits&mdash;such an old age, for example,
as we are told was that of Plato, who died, pen
in hand,<note>Not necessarily to be taken literally; but meaning that
he had not abandoned the writing of books. Plato is said
to have died at a marriage-feast (Diog. Laert. iii. 2).</note> in his eighty-first year; such as that of
Isocrates, who, by his own statement, was ninety-four when he composed the work entitled <hi rend="italics">Panathenaicus,</hi> and he lived five years after that. His
teacher, Gorgias of Leontini, rounded out one
hundred and seven years and never rested from his
pursuits or his labours. When some one asked him
why he chose to remain so long alive, he answered:
<quote>I have no reason to reproach old age.</quote> <milestone unit="section" n="14"/>A noble
answer and worthy of a scholar!</p>
<p>For, in truth, it is their own vices and their own
faults that fools charge to old age; but Ennius, of
whom I spoke a while ago, did not do this, for he says:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>He, like the gallant steed that often won</l>
<l>Olympic trophy in the final lap,</l>
<l>Now takes his rest when weakened by old age.</l></quote></p>

<p>He is comparing his old age to that of a brave
and victorious horse. You both may recall him distinctly,<note>Laelius and Scipio, at the death of Ennius, were respectively seventeen and sixteen years old.</note> for it was only nineteen years from his death
until the election of the present consuls, Titus
Flamininus and Manius Acilius, and he did not pass
away until the consulship of Caepio and Philip
(the latter being in his second term), at a time when
I, at sixty-five, spoke publicly for the Voconian

<pb id="p.25"/>

law,<note>This law, named from its author, Voconius Saxa,
tribune of the plebs, passed in 169 B.C., provided (1) that no
one enrolled as having 100,000 <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> (about $1,000) should
make a woman his heir; or (2) leave to another a sum
greater than the heirs would receive.</note> with loud voice and mighty lungs. But
he at seventy&mdash;for Ennius lived that long&mdash;was
bearing the two burdens which are considered the
greatest&mdash;poverty and old age&mdash;and was bearing
them in such a way that he seemed almost to take
a pleasure in them.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="15"/>And, indeed, when I reflect on this subject I
find four reasons why old age appears to be unhappy:
first, that it withdraws us from active pursuits;
second, that it makes the body weaker; third, that
it deprives us of almost all physical pleasures; and,
fourth, that it is not far removed from death. Let
us, if you please, examine each of these reasons
separately and see how much truth they contain.</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="6"/><quote>Old age withdraws us from active pursuits.</quote>
From what pursuits? Is it not from those which
are followed because of youth and vigour? Are
there, then, no intellectual employments in which
aged men may engage, even though their bodies are
infirm? Was there, then, no employment for
Quintus Maximus? And none, Scipio, for your
father Lucius Paulus, the father-in-law of that
best of men, my son? And those other old men, like
Fabricius, Curius, and Coruncanius&mdash;were they
doing nothing, when by their wisdom and influence
they were preserving the state?</p>
<p>To the old age of Appius Claudius was also added
blindness; <milestone unit="section" n="16"/>yet when the sentiment of the senate was
inclining towards peace and an alliance with Pyrrhus,
he did not hesitate to say what Ennius has thus put
into verse:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>Your minds that once did stand erect and strong,</l>
<l>What madness swerves them from their wonted course?</l></quote>

&mdash;and so on, in most impressive style. But you are

<pb id="p.27"/>

familiar with the poem, and, after all, the actual
speech of Appius is still extant. It was delivered
seventeen years after his second consulship, although
ten years had intervened between the two consulships and he had been censor before he was consul.
Hence, it is known that he was undoubtedly an old
man at the time of the war with Pyrrhus, and yet
such is the story as we have it by tradition.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="17"/>Those, therefore, who allege that old age is devoid
of useful activity adduce nothing to the purpose, and
are like those who would say that the pilot does
nothing in the sailing of the ship, because, while
others are climbing the masts, or running about the
gangways, or working at the pumps, he sits quietly in
the stern and simply holds the tiller. He may not be
doing what younger members of the crew are doing,
but what he does is better and much more important.
It is not by muscle, speed, or physical dexterity that
great things are achieved, but by reflection, force of
character, and judgement; in these qualities old age
is usually not only not poorer, but is even richer.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="18"/>But perhaps it seems to you that I who engaged
in various kinds of warfare as private, captain,
general, and commander-in-chief, am unemployed
now that I do not go to war. And yet I direct the
senate as to what wars should be waged and how;
at the present time, far in advance of hostilities, I
am declaring war on Carthage, for she has long been
plotting mischief; and I shall not cease to fear her
until I know that she has been utterly destroyed.
And I pray the immortal gods to reserve for you,
<milestone unit="section" n="19"/>Scipio, the glory of completing the work which your
grandfather left unfinished! Thirty-three years have
passed since that hero's death, but each succeeding

<pb id="p.29"/>

year will receive his memory and pass it on. He
died in the year before I was censor, nine years
after I was consul; and while I was holding the
latter office he was elected consul for the second
time. If, then, he had lived to his hundredth year,
would he be repenting of his old age? No, for he
would not be employing his time in running and in
leaping, or in long-distance throwing of the spear,
or in hand-to-hand sword-play, but he would be
engaged in using reflection, reason, and judgement.
If these mental qualities were not characteristic of
old men our fathers would not have called their
highest deliberative body the <quote>senate.</quote><note><hi rend="italics">Senatus,</hi> an assembly of <hi rend="italics">senes,</hi> or elders.</note> Among
the Lacedaemonians, for example,<milestone unit="section" n="20"/> those who fill
their chief magistracies are called <quote>elders,</quote> as they
are in fact. And indeed, if you care to read or hear
foreign history, you will find that the greatest states
have been overthrown by the young and sustained
and restored by the old.

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>How lost you, pray, your mighty state so soon?</l></quote>

for such is the question put in a play entitled the
<hi rend="italics">Wolf,</hi> by the poet Naevius. Several answers are
given, but the one chiefly in point is this:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>Through swarms of green, declaiming, silly lads.</l></quote>

True enough, for rashness is the product of the
budding-time of youth, prudence of the harvest-time of age.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="21"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="7"/>But, it is alleged, the memory is impaired.
Of course, if you do not exercise it, or also if you
are by nature somewhat dull. Themistocles had
learned the names of all the citizens of Athens <note>The citizens of Athens (native males, over 20, having
the franchise) were then probably about 20,000.</note> by
heart; do you think, then, that after he became

<pb id="p.31"/>

old he was wont to address as Lysimachus one who
in fact was Aristides?<note>Lysimachus was the father of Aristides the bitter enemy
of Themistocles; hence there is pointed humour in the
question.</note> I, for instance, know not
only the people who are living, but I recall their
fathers and grandfathers, too; and as I read their
epitaphs I am not afraid of the superstition that,
in so doing, I shall lose my memory; for by reading
them I refresh my recollection of the dead. I
certainly never heard of any old man forgetting
where he had hidden his money! The aged remember everything that interests them, their
appointments to appear in court, and who are their
creditors and who their debtors.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="22"/>And how is it with aged lawyers, pontiffs, augurs,
and philosophers? What a multitude of things
they remember! Old men retain their mental
faculties, provided their interest and application
continue; and this is true, not only of men in exalted
public station, but likewise of those in the quiet
of private life. Sophocles composed tragedies to
extreme old age; and when, because of his absorption in literary work, he was thought to be neglecting
his business affairs, his sons haled him into court
in order to secure a verdict removing him from the
control of his property on the ground of imbecility,
under a law similar to ours, whereby it is customary
to restrain heads of families from wasting their
estates. Thereupon, it is said, the old man read
to the jury his play, <hi rend="italics">Oedipus at Colonus,</hi> which he
had just written and was revising, and inquired:
<quote>Does that poem seem to you to be the work of an
imbecile?</quote> <milestone unit="section" n="23"/>When he had finished he was acquitted
by the verdict of the jury. Think you, then, that
old age forced him to abandon his calling, or that
it silenced Homer, Hesiod, Simonides, Stesichorus, or

<pb id="p.33"/>

Isocrates, and Gorgias (whom I have mentioned
already), or any of those princes of philosophy
Pythagoras, Democritus, Plato, and Xenocrates,
or Zeno and Cleanthes of a later time, or Diogenes
the Stoic, whom you both have seen at Rome?
Rather, did not activity in their several pursuits
continue with all of them as long as life itself?</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="24"/>But come now&mdash;to pass over these divine pursuits
&mdash;I can point out to you Roman farmers in the Sabine
country, friends and neighbours of mine, who are
scarcely ever absent from the field while the more
important operations of husbandry, as sowing,
reaping, and storing the crops, are going on. Although this interest of theirs is less remarkable in
the case of annual crops,&mdash;for no one is so old as to
think that he cannot live one more year&mdash;yet these
same men labour at things which they know will
not profit them in the least.

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>He plants the trees to serve another age,</l></quote>

as our Caecilius Statius says in his <hi rend="italics">Young Comrades.</hi> <milestone unit="section" n="25"/>And if you ask a farmer, however old, for
whom he is planting, he will unhesitatingly reply,
<quote>For the immortal gods, who have willed not only
that I should receive these blessings from my
ancestors, but also that I should hand them on to
posterity.</quote></p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="8"/>And the same Caecilius, in writing of the
old man making provision for a future generation,
spoke to better purpose than he did in the following lines:

<quote rend="blockquote"><cit><quote><l>In truth, Old Age, if you did bring no bane</l>
<l>But this alone, 'twould me suffice: that one,</l>
<l>By living long, sees much he hates to see.</l></quote> <bibl>From Caecilius's comedy, <title>Plocium.</title></bibl></cit></quote>

<pb id="p.35"/>

Possibly, also, many things he likes; and as for things
one does not wish to see, even youth often encounters them. However, this other sentiment from
the same Caecilius is worse:

<quote rend="blockquote"><cit><quote><l>But saddest bane of age, I think, is this:</l>
<l>That old men feel their years a bore to youth.</l></quote> <bibl>From the play called <title>Ephesio.</title></bibl></cit></quote>

<milestone unit="section" n="26"/>A pleasure, rather than a bore, say I. For just as
wise men, when they are old, take delight in the
society of youths endowed with sprightly wit, and
the burdens of age are rendered lighter to those who
are courted and highly esteemed by the young,
so young men find pleasure in their elders, by whose,
precepts they are led into virtue's paths; nor
indeed do I feel that I am any less of a pleasure to
you than you are to me. But you see how old
age, so far from being feeble and inactive, is even
busy and is always doing and effecting something&mdash;
that is to say, something of the same nature
in each case as were the pursuits of earlier years.
And what of those who even go on adding to their
store of knowledge? Such was the case with Solon,
whom we see boasting in his verses that he grows
old learning something every day.<note>Quoted by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Sol.</hi> 31 <foreign lang="greek">ghra/skw d' a)ei\ polla\ didasko/menos.</foreign></note> And I have
done the same, for in my old age I have learned
Greek, which I seized upon as eagerly as if I had
been desirous of satisfying a long-continued thirst,
with the result that I have acquired first-hand the
information which you see me using in this discussion by way of illustration. And when I read
what Socrates<note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Menexenus, 235</hi> E; id. <hi rend="italics">Euthydemus,</hi> 272 c.</note> had done in the case of the lyre, an
instrument much cultivated by the ancients, I should
have liked to do that too, if I could; but in literature
I have certainly laboured hard.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="27"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="9"/>I do not now feel the need of the strength

<pb id="p.37"/>

of youth&mdash;for that was the second head under the
faults of old age&mdash;any more than when a young man
I felt the need of the strength of the bull or of the
elephant. Such strength as a man has he should use,
and whatever he does should be done in proportion
to his strength. For what utterance can be more
pitiable than that of Milo of Crotona? After he
was already an old man and was watching the
athletes training in the race-course, it is related that,
as he looked upon his shrunken muscles, he wept
and said: <quote>Yes, but they now are dead.</quote> But not
as dead as you, you babbler! For you never gained
renown from your real self, but from brute strength
of lungs and limb. Of a far different stamp were
Sextus Aelius and Titus Coruncanius of ancient
times, and Publius Crassus of a later date, by
whom instruction in jurisprudence <note>By the old Roman custom these lawyers gave audience
in the early hours of the day to all who chose to consult
them on legal questions.</note> was given to
their fellow-citizens, and whose skill in law continued
to the very last gasp.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="28"/>The orator, I fear, does lose in efficiency on account
of old age, because his success depends not only
upon his intellect, but also upon his lungs and
bodily strength. In old age, no doubt, the voice
actually gains (I know not how) that magnificent
resonance<note><hi rend="italics">Canorum . . . splendescit</hi> is a mixed metaphor-the first
word appeals to the ear, the second to the eye; literally,
<quote>a clarion-like ring which gives it brilliancy.</quote></note> which even I have not lost, and you see
my years; and yet the style of speech that graces
the old man is subdued and gentle, and very often
the sedate and mild speaking of an eloquent old man
wins itself a hearing. And although one cannot
himself engage in oratory, still, he may be able to
give instruction to a Scipio or a Laelius! For what
is more agreeable than an old age surrounded by the
enthusiasm of youth? <milestone unit="section" n="29"/>Or do we not concede to
old age even strength enough to instruct and train

<pb id="p.39"/>

young men and equip them for every function and
duty? And what more exalted service can there
be than this? For my part, Scipio, I used to consider Gnaeus and Publius Scipio and your two grandfathers, Lucius Aemilius and Publius Africanus,
fortunate in being attended by throngs of noble
youths; and no teachers of the liberal arts should
be considered unhappy, even though their bodily
vigour may have waned and failed.</p>
<p>And yet, even that very loss of strength is more
often chargeable to the dissipations of youth than
to any fault of old age; for an intemperate and
indulgent youth delivers to old age a body all worn
out. <milestone unit="section" n="30"/>For example, Cyrus,<note>Cyrus the Elder, Xen. <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia,</hi> viii. 7. 6. But other
authorities (Herod. i. 24, Lucian, <hi rend="italics">Charon,</hi> 30) say that
Cyrus died in battle with the Scythians.</note> in Xenophon, in that
discourse which he delivered when he was very
old and on his death-bed, says that he had never
felt that his old age was any less vigorous than his
youth had been. I remember that in my boyhood I
saw Lucius Metellus, who, four years after his second
consulship, became Chief Pontiff and held that
sacred office for twenty-two years, and I recall
that he enjoyed such great vigour of body to the end
of his days that he did not feel the loss of youth.
I need say nothing of myself in this connexion,
though to do so is an old man's privilege and permitted to one of my age.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="31"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="10"/>Do you not observe in Homer how, time and
again, Nestor proclaims his own merits? <note><hi rend="italics">e.g. Iliad,</hi> i. 260; vii. 124; xi. 668.</note> For he,
at that time, was looking on the third generation of
men,<note><hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi> i. 247.</note> yet he did not fear that, in speaking the truth
about himself, he would appear to any great extent
either odd or loquacious. For as Homer says,
<quote>Speech sweeter than honey flowed from his
tongue</quote>;<note><hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi> i. 249.</note> and this sweetness had no need of

<pb id="p.41"/>

physical strength; and yet the illustrious Grecian
chief<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> Agamemnon, <hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi> ii. 371.</note> never prays for ten men like Ajax. but for
ten like Nestor, and he doubts not that, if he had
them, Troy would speedily be destroyed.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="32"/>But I return to myself. I am in my eighty-fourth
year and would that I myself could boast as Cyrus
did; but still I can say this much: that while I
am not now, indeed, possessed of that physical
strength which I had as a private soldier in the
Punic War, or as a quaestor in the same war, or as
commander-in-chief in Spain, or when as military
tribune four years later I fought the war out at
Thermopylae under the command of Manius Acilius
Glabrio;<note>For these events in Cato's life and their dates see
Introduction.</note> yet, as you see, old age has not quite
unnerved or shattered me. The senate and the
popular assembly never find my vigour wanting,
nor do my friends, my dependents, or my guests;
for I have never assented to that ancient and much quoted proverb, which advises: <quote>Become old early
if you would be old long.</quote> For my part I would
rather not be old so long than be old before my
time. Accordingly, I have so far never refused an
audience to anyone who wished to consult me.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="33"/>But it may be said that I have less strength than
either of you; but I reply that you, for your part,
have not the strength of the centurion Titus Pontius<note>This was some man famous for his strength in Cato's
day, but of whom we know nothing more.</note> ;
is he, for that reason, more excellent than you?
Only let every man make a proper use of his strength
and strive to his utmost, then assuredly he will have
no regret for his want of strength. It is said that
Milo walked the length of the race-course at Olympia,
carrying an ox on his shoulders. Which, therefore,
would you prefer should be given to you&mdash;the
physical powers of Milo, or the mental powers of

<pb id="p.43"/>

Pythagoras? In short, enjoy the blessing of strength
while you have it and do not bewail it when it is
gone, unless, forsooth, you believe that youth must
lament the loss of infancy, or early manhood the
passing of youth. Life's race-course is fixed;
Nature has only a single path and that path is run
but once, and to each stage of existence has been
allotted its own appropriate quality; so that the
weakness of childhood, the impetuosity of youth,
the seriousness of middle life, the maturity of old
age&mdash;each bears some of Nature's fruit, which must
be garnered in its own season.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="34"/>I think, Scipio, that the news reaches you of the
daily activities of your grandfather's friend and host
Masinissa, now ninety years old; that when he
begins a march on foot, he never mounts a horse,
and when he sets out on horseback he never dismounts; that no rain or cold, however great, can
induce him to cover his head; and&mdash;such is the
extreme wiriness of his body&mdash;that he in person
performs all the duties and functions of his kingly
office. It is possible, therefore, for a man by
exercise and self-control, even in old age, to preserve
some of his original vigour.</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="11"/>But, grant that old age is devoid of strength;
none is even expected of it. Hence both by law and
by custom men of my age are exempt from those
public services which cannot be rendered without
strength of body. Therefore, we are not only
not required to do what we cannot perform, but
we are not required to do even as much as we
can. <milestone unit="section" n="35"/>Yet, it may be urged, many old men are so
feeble that they can perform no function that duty
or indeed any position in life demands. True, but

<pb id="p.45"/>

that is not peculiar to old age; generally it is a
characteristic of ill-health. Note how weak, Scipio,
was your adoptive father, the son of Publius
Africanus! What feeble health he had, or rather
no health at all! But for this he would have shone
forth as the second luminary <note>Scipio Africanus, the Elder, was the first luminary.</note> of the state; for to
his father's greatness of intellect he had added
a more abundant learning. What wonder, then, that
the aged are sometimes weak, when even the young
cannot escape the same fate?</p>
<p>But it is our duty, my young friends, to resist
old age; to compensate for its defects by a watchful
care; to fight against it as we would fight against
disease; to adopt a regimen of health; <milestone unit="section" n="35"/>to practise
moderate exercise; and to take just enough of food
and drink to restore our strength and not to overburden it. Nor, indeed, are we to give our attention
solely to the body; much greater care is due to the
mind and soul; for they, too, like lamps, grow dim
with time, unless we keep them supplied with oil.
Moreover, exercise causes the body to become heavy
with fatigue, but intellectual activity gives buoyancy
to the mind. For when Caecilius speaks of <quote>the
old fools of the comic stage,</quote><note>From his lost play <hi rend="italics">Epiclerus.</hi> For the line in full see
<hi rend="italics">De amicitia</hi> 99.</note> he has in mind old
men characterized by credulity, forgetfulness, and
carelessness, which are faults, not of old age generally,
but only of an old age that is drowsy, slothful, and
inert. Just as waywardness and lust are more often
found in the young man than in the old, yet not
in all who are young, but only in those naturally base;
so that senile debility, usually called <quote>dotage,</quote>
is a characteristic, not of all old men, but only of
those who are weak in mind and will.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="37"/>Appius, though he was both blind and old, managed

<pb id="p.47"/>

four sturdy sons, five daughters, a great household,
and many dependents; for he did not languidly
succumb to old age, but kept his mind ever taut,
like a well-strung bow. He maintained not mere
authority, but absolute command over his household; his slaves feared him, his children revered him,
all loved him, and the customs and discipline of his
forefathers flourished beneath his roof. <milestone unit="section" n="38"/>For old age
is honoured only on condition that it defends itself,
maintains its rights, is subservient to no one, and to
the last breath rules over its own domain. For just
as I approve of the young man in whom there is a
touch of age, so I approve of the old man in whom
there is some of the flavour of youth. He who
strives thus to mingle youthfulness and age may
grow old in body, but old in spirit he will never be.</p>
<p>I am now at work on the seventh volume of my
<hi rend="italics">Antiquities.</hi> I am collecting all the records of our
ancient history, and at the present moment am revising all the speeches made by me in the notable causes
which I conducted. I am investigating the augural,
pontifical, and secular law; I also devote much of
my time to Greek literature; and, in order to exercise my memory, I follow the practice of the Pythagoreans and run over in my mind every evening
all that I have said, heard, or done during the day.
These employments are my intellectual gymnastics;
these the race-courses of my mind; and while I
sweat and toil with them I do not greatly feel the
loss of bodily strength. I act as counsel for my
friends; I frequently attend the senate, where,
on my own motion, I propose subjects for discussion
after having pondered over them seriously and long;
and there I maintain my views in debate, not with

<pb id="p.49"/>

strength of body, but with force of mind. But even
if I could not perform these services, nevertheless,
my couch<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="italics">lectulus lucubratorius,</hi> used when reading or
the like.</note> would afford me delight while reflecting
on the very things that I lacked the strength to do.
However, the fact that I can do them is due to the
life that I have led. For the man who lives always
amid such studies and pursuits as mine is not aware
of the stealthy approach of age. Thus employed
his life gradually and imperceptibly glides into old
age, and succumbs, not to a quick assault, but to a
long-continued siege.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="39"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="12"/>We come now to the third ground for abusing
old age, and that is, that it is devoid of sensual
pleasures. O glorious boon of age, if it does indeed
free us from youth's most vicious fault! Now
listen, most noble young men, to what that remarkably great and distinguished man, Archytas of
Tarentum, said in an ancient speech repeated to me
when I was a young man serving with Quintus
Maximus at Tarentum: <quote>No more deadly curse,</quote>
said he, "has been given by nature to man than
carnal pleasure, through eagerness for which the
passions are driven recklessly and uncontrollably
to its gratification. <milestone unit="section" n="40"/>From it come treason and the
overthrow of states; and from it spring secret and
corrupt conferences with public foes. In short,
there is no criminal purpose and no evil deed which
the lust for pleasure will not drive men to undertake. Indeed, rape, adultery, and every like
offence are set in motion by the enticements of
pleasure and by nothing else; and since nature&mdash;
or some god, perhaps&mdash;has given to man nothing
more excellent than his intellect, therefore this
divine gift has no deadlier foe than pleasure; <milestone unit="section" n="41"/>for

<pb id="p.51"/>

where lust holds despotic sway self-control has no
place, and in pleasure's realm there is not a single
spot where virtue can put her foot.</p>
<p><quote>Imagine,</quote> he begged, to make his meaning
clearer, <quote>imagine a person enjoying the most
exquisite bodily pleasure to be had. No one will
doubt, I think, that such a man, while in the midst
of this enjoyment, is incapable of any mental action,
and can accomplish nothing requiring reason and
reflection. Hence there is nothing so hateful and
so pernicious as pleasure, since, if indulged in too
much and too long, it turns the light of the soul into
utter darkness.</quote> My Tarentine host Nearchus, who
remained steadfast in his friendship to the Roman
people, told me that, according to tradition, Archytas
uttered these words while conversing with Pontius the
Samnite, father of the man who defeated the consuls
Spurius Postumius and Titus Veturius at the Caudine
Forks.<note>321 B.C.</note> Indeed he further told me that Plato the
Athenian was present and heard Archytas deliver this
discourse, and, upon investigation, I find that Plato
did come to Tarentum in the consulship of Lucius
Camillus and Appius Claudius.<note>That is, in 349 B.C. when Plato was 79 years old and too
old, it is thought, to have visited Italy. The date of his last
visit is usually given as 361.</note> </p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="42"/>Now, why did I quote Archytas? To make you
realize that if reason and wisdom did not enable us
to reject pleasure, we should be very grateful to old
age for taking away the desire to do what we ought
not to do. For carnal pleasure hinders deliberation,
is at war with reason, blindfolds the eyes of the mind,
so to speak, and has no fellowship with virtue.</p>
<p>It was a disagreeable duty that I performed in
expelling<note>This was done while Cato and L. Valerius Flaccus were
censors, in 184 B.C. Titus Flamininus was consul in 192, hence seven years intervened between the consulship and the
expulsion of Lucius Flamininus from the senate.</note> Lucius Flamininus from the senate, for

<pb id="p.53"/>

he was a brother of that most valiant man, Titus
Flamininus, and had been consul seven years before;
but I thought that lust merited the brand of infamy.
For, when in Gaul during his consulship, at the
solicitation of a courtesan at a banquet, he beheaded
a prisoner then under condemnation for some
capital offence.<note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Livy xxxix. 42. 7, xxxix. 43. 2.</note> While his brother, my immediate
predecessor, was censor, Lucius escaped punishment,
but Flaccus and I could by no means approve of
conduct so flagrant and abandoned, especially when
to his crime against an individual he added dishonour
to the state.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="43"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="13"/>I often heard from my elders&mdash;who, in turn,
said they, when boys, had heard it from old men&mdash;
that Gaius Fabricius used to marvel at the story told
him, while an envoy at the headquarters of King
Pyrrhus, by Cineas of Thessaly, that there was
a man<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> Epicurus, who claimed to be not only <foreign lang="greek">filo/sofos</foreign> but <foreign lang="greek">sofo/s.</foreign></note> at Athens who professed himself <quote>wise</quote>
and used to say that everything we do should be
judged by the standard of pleasure. Now when
Manius Curius and Tiberius Coruncanius learned
of this from Fabricius they expressed the wish that
the Samnites and Pyrrhus himself would become
converts to it, because, when given up to pleasure,
they would be much easier to overcome. Manius
Curius had lived on intimate terms with Publius
Decius who, in his fourth consulship, and five years
before Curius held that office, had offered up his
life for his country's safety; Fabricius and Coruncanius also knew him, and they all were firmly
persuaded, both by their own experience and
especially by the heroic deed of Decius, that assuredly
there are ends, inherently pure and noble, which
are sought for their own sake, and which will be

<pb id="p.55"/>

pursued by all good men who look on self-gratification with loathing and contempt.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="44"/>Why then, do I dwell at such length on pleasure?
Because the fact that old age feels little longing
for sensual pleasures not only is no cause for reproach,
but rather is ground for the highest praise. Old
age lacks the heavy banquet, the loaded table, and
the oft-filled cup; therefore it also lacks drunkenness, indigestion, and loss of sleep. But if some
concession must be made to pleasure, since her
allurements are difficult to resist, and she is, as Plato
happily says, <quote>the bait of sin,</quote><note><foreign lang="greek">kakou= de/lear,</foreign> <hi rend="italics">Timaeus,</hi> 69D.</note> &mdash;evidently because
men are caught therewith like fish&mdash;then I admit
that old age, though it lacks immoderate banquets,
may find delight in temperate repasts. Gaius
Duellius, son of Marcus, and the first Roman to win a
naval victory over the Carthaginians, was often seen
by me in my childhood, when he was an old man,
returning home from dining out, attended, as was
his delight, by a torch-bearer and flute-player&mdash;an
ostentation which as a private citizen he had assumed,
though without precedent: but that much licence
did his glory give him.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="45"/>But why speak of others? Let me now return
to myself. In the first place I have always had my
club companions. Moreover, it was in my quaestorship <note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> in 204 B.C.</note> that clubs in honour of Cybele were organized,
when the Idaean worship was introduced at Rome,
and therefore I used to dine with these companions&mdash;
in an altogether moderate way, yet with a certain
ardour appropriate to my age, which, as time goes
on, daily mitigates my zest for every pleasure. Nor,
indeed, did I measure my delight in these social
gatherings more by the physical pleasure than by

<pb id="p.57"/>

the pleasure of meeting and conversing with my
friends. For our fathers did well in calling the
reclining of friends at feasts a <hi rend="italics">convivium,</hi> because it
implies a communion of life, which is a better
designation than that of the Greeks, who call it
sometimes a <quote>drinking together</quote> and sometimes
an <quote>eating together,</quote><note>Cicero thus translates <foreign lang="greek">sumpo/sion</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">su/ndeipnon.</foreign></note> thereby apparently exalting
what is of least value in these associations above
that which gives them their greatest charm.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="46"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="14"/>For my own part, because of my love of
conversation, I enjoy even <quote>afternoon banquets,</quote><note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> banquets which began early and shortened the
business day; the phrase usually suggests something of a
debauch.</note> 
not with my contemporaries only, very few of whom
now remain, but also with you and with those of
your age; and I am profoundly grateful to old age,
which has increased my eagerness for conversation
and taken away that for food and drink. But if there
are any who find delight in such things (that I may by
no means seem to have declared war on every kind
of pleasure, when, perhaps, a certain amount of it
is justified by nature), then I may say that I am
not aware that old age is altogether wanting in
appreciation even of these very pleasures. Indeed
I find delight in the custom established by our
forefathers of appointing presidents<note>Referring to the <hi rend="italics">arbiter bibendi,</hi> or <hi rend="italics">rex-also</hi> called
<hi rend="italics">magister-convivi.</hi> The word <quote>toast-masters</quote> as used in
the United States is the exact equivalent of the Latin. They
were appointed with due ceremony even at public banquets.</note> at such gatherings; and in the talk, which, after that ancestral
custom, begins at the head of the table when the
wine comes in; and I enjoy cups, like those described
in Xenophon's <hi rend="italics">Symposium,</hi><note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Xen. <hi rend="italics">Symp. 2. 26.</hi></note> that are small in size, filled
with dew-like drops, cooled in summer, and, again, in
winter, warmed by the heat of sun or fire. Even
when among the Sabines <note>Noted for their simple habits.</note> I keep up the practice of
frequenting such gatherings, and every day I join my
neighbours in a social meal which we protract as late
as we can into the night with talk on varying themes.</p>

<pb id="p.59"/>

<p><milestone unit="section" n="47"/>But it may be urged that, in old men, <quote>pleasure's
tingling,</quote><note><hi rend="italics">Titillatio</hi> is Cicero's rendering of the Epicurean word <foreign lang="greek">gargalismo/s.</foreign></note> if I may so call it, is not so great. True,
but neither is their yearning for pleasures so great,
and, moreover, nothing troubles you for which you
do not yearn. It was an excellent reply that
Sophocles made to a certain man who asked him,
when he was already old, if he still indulged in the
delights of love. <quote>Heaven forbid!</quote> he said.
<quote>Indeed I have fled from them as from a harsh
and cruel master.</quote><note>Plato, <hi rend="italics">Rep.</hi> 329 B <foreign lang="greek">a)smene/stata au)to\ a)pe/fugon w(/sper luttw=nta/ tina kai\ a)/grion despo/thn a)pofugw/n.</foreign></note> For to those who eagerly desire
such things the want of them is perhaps an annoyance and a trouble; but to those who are sated
and cloyed with them it is more pleasant to be in
want of them than to possess them; though, indeed.
a man cannot <quote>want</quote> that for which he has no
longing, and therefore I assert that the absence of
longing is more pleasant.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="48"/>But granting that youth enjoys pleasures of that
kind with a keener relish, then, in the first place,
as I have said, they are petty things which it enjoys;
and, in the next place, although old age does not
possess these pleasures in abundance, yet it is by
no means wanting in them. Just as Ambivius
Turpio gives greater delight to the spectators in the
front row at the theatre, and yet gives some delight
even to those in the last row, so youth, looking on
pleasures at closer range, perhaps enjoys them more,
while old age, on the other hand, finds delight enough
in a more distant view.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="49"/>But how blessed it is for the soul, after having, as it
were, finished its campaigns of lust and ambition,
of strife and enmity and of all the passions, to
return within itself, and, as the saying is, <quote>to live
apart</quote>! And indeed if it has any provender, so to

<pb id="p.61"/>

speak, of study and learning, nothing is more enjoyable than a leisured old age. Scipio, I used to see
your father's intimate friend, Gaius Gallus, engaged
in the task of measuring, almost bit by bit, the heavens
and the earth. How often the morning sun has
surprised him working on some chart which he had
begun at night! and how often night has surprised
him at a task begun at the break of day! How
much joy he took in telling us, long in advance,
of eclipses of the sun and moon! <milestone unit="section" n="50"/>And what
of those men occupied in studies which, though not
so exacting, yet demand keenness of intellect?
How Naevius used to revel in his <hi rend="italics">Punic War!</hi>
and Plautus in his <hi rend="italics">Savage</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Cheat!</hi> I myself
saw Livius Andronicus when he was an old man,
who, though he brought out a play in the consulship
of Cento and Tuditanus, six years before I was born,
yet continued to live until I was a young man.</p>
<p>Why need I speak of the zeal of Publius Licinius
Crassus in pontifical and civil law, or of that of
the present Publius Scipio, who was elected Chief
Pontiff only a few days ago? And yet I have seen
all these men whom I have mentioned, ardent in
their several callings after they had grown old. Then
too, there was Marcus Cethegus, whom Ennius
justly styled <quote>the marrow of eloquence.</quote><note>Cf. Cic. <hi rend="italics">Brutus</hi> 58.</note> What
enthusiasm I saw him also display in his public
speeches, although he Was an old man! Therefore,
how can the pleasures of feasting, plays, and brothels
be compared with the pleasures which these men
enjoyed? But theirs was a zeal for learning, and
this zeal, at least in the case of wise and well-trained
men, advances in even pace with age; so that there
is truth in what Solon says in a certain bit of verse,

<pb id="p.63"/>

already mentioned, that, as he grew old, he learned
many things every day; and surely there can be no
greater pleasure than the pleasures of the mind.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="51"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="15"/>I come now to the pleasures of agriculture
in which I find incredible delight; they are not one
whit checked by old age, and are, it seems to me,
in the highest degree suited to the life of the wise
man. For these pleasures have an account in the
bank of Mother Earth who never protests a draft,
but always returns the principal with interest added,
at a rate sometimes low, but usually at a high per
cent. And vet what I enjoy is not the fruit
alone, but I also enjoy the soil itself, its nature and
its power. It takes the scattered grain of wheat
within its soft, upturned breast, hides it from sight
at first&mdash;(it is hidden by harrowing,<note>The real derivation is from <hi rend="italics">occa</hi> = <hi rend="italics">rastrum,</hi> <quote>a hoe.</quote></note> derived from
a word meaning <quote>to hide</quote>)&mdash;then, having warmed
it with the heat of its embrace, expands it and from
it brings forth a verdant blade, which, supported by
fibrous roots, and maturing by degrees, stands erect
upon its jointed stalk, enfolded in a sheath, when
now, so to speak, it has arrived at man's estate; and,
when it has emerged from the sheath, the ear comes
to view with its grain in ordered rows and protected
by a palisade of spikes against the attacks of the
smaller birds.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="52"/>Why should I mention the origin, cultivation, and
growth of the vine? But, that you may know what
affords the recreation and delight of my old age,
I will say that vine-culture gives me a joy of which
I cannot get too much. For I pass over the inherent
force of all those things which are generated from
the earth&mdash;a force that, from the tiny fig-seed, or
grape-stone, or from the smallest seeds of other

<pb id="p.65"/>

fruits and plants, can produce such mighty trunks
and boughs. Are not the results obtained from
mallet-shoots, sprouts, cuttings, divisions, and layers
enough to afford wonder and delight to any man?
The vine which droops by nature and falls to the
ground unless it has support, raises itself by its
finger-like tendrils and enfolds in its embrace the props
that hold it up; and as it turns and twists with
many a varying course the skilful gardener with his
pruning knife checks its growth lest it run to wood
and spread too far. <milestone unit="section" n="53"/>So, in early spring, the branches
which are left at every joint bring forth a bud, from
which the grape, offspring of this bud, appears,
growing with the moisture of the earth and the
heat of the sun; and though at first it is very bitter
to the taste, it afterwards becomes sweet as it
ripens; and, enwrapped in foliage, it has no lack of
tempered warmth and turns aside the more ardent
glances of the sun. What, I ask, can be more
delicious to the taste or more alluring to the eye?</p>
<p>Indeed it is not only the utility of the vine, as I
said before, that gives me joy, but I find joy also
in its culture and very nature; in the even-spaced
rows of stakes, with strips across the top; in the
tying up of the branches; in the propagating of
the plants; in the pruning of some branches (to
which I have already referred), and in the leaving
of others to grow at will.</p>
<p>Why need I allude to the irrigation, ditching, and
frequent hoeing of the soil, whereby its productiveness is so much enhanced? Why need I discuss
the advantage of manuring, already dealt with in my
book on agriculture? <milestone unit="section" n="54"/>This is a matter about which
the learned Hesiod, though he wrote on agriculture,

<pb id="p.67"/>

has not one word to say. But Homer, who, I believe,
lived many generation earlier, represents La&euml;rtes
as soothing his sorrow at the absence of his son
in cultivating his farm and in manuring it, too. Nor
does the farmer find joy only in his cornfields,
meadows, vineyards, and woodlands, but also in
his garden and orchard, in the rearing of his cattle,
in his swarms of bees, and in the infinite variety of
flowers. And not only does planting delight him,
but grafting also, than which there is nothing in
husbandry that is more ingenious.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="55"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="16"/>I might enlarge upon all the many charms
of country life, but I realize that I have already said
too much. However, forgive me if I go on, for my
farmer's zeal has carried me away; besides, old age
is naturally inclined to talk too much&mdash;and this I
say in order not to acquit it of every fault. Well,
then, it was in this sort of life that Manius Curius
passed his remaining years after he had triumphed
over the Samnites, the Sabines, and Pyrrhus; and,
as I gaze upon his country house (for it is not far
from mine), I cannot sufficiently admire the frugality
of the man or the spirit of the age in which he
lived. <milestone unit="section" n="56"/>When the Samnites had brought him a great
mass of gold as he sat before the fire, he declined
their gift with scorn; <quote>for,</quote> said he, <quote>it seems to me
that the glory is not in having the gold, but in ruling
those who have it.</quote> Think you that such a mighty
soul could not make old age happy?</p>
<p>But, lest I wander from my subject, I return to the
farmers. In those days senators (that is, <hi rend="italics">senes</hi> or
<quote>elders</quote>) lived on farms&mdash;if the story is true that
Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus was at the plough when
he was notified of his election to that dictatorship

<pb id="p.69"/>

in which, by his order, his master of the horse
Gaius Servilius Ahala, seized Spurius Maelius and
put him to death for attempting to secure regal
power. It was from the farmhouse that Curius and
other old men were summoned to the senate, and
for that reason those who notified them were called
<hi rend="italics">viatores,</hi> or travellers. Well, then, was there cause
to pity the old age of these men who delighted in
the cultivation of the soil? For my part, at least,
I am inclined to think that no life can be happier
than that of the farmer, not merely from the standpoint of the duty performed, which benefits the
entire human race, but also because of its charm
already mentioned, and the plenty and abundance
it gives of everything that tends to the nurture of
man and even to the worship of the gods; and since
certain people delight in these material joys, I have
said this that I may now make my peace with
pleasure. For the provident and industrious proprietor always has his store-room and cellars well
filled with oil and wine and provisions; his entire
farmhouse has an air of plenty and abounds with
pork, goat's meat, lamb, poultry, milk, cheese, and
honey. And there is his garden, which the farmers
themselves term <quote>the second flitch.</quote> Hawking
and hunting, too, in leisure times, furnish the sauce
for these dainties.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="57"/>Of the verdure of the meadows, the even rows of
trees and the beauty of the vineyards and olive
groves why should I speak at length? I will be
concise. Nothing can be more abounding in usefulness or more attractive in appearance than a well-tilled farm, and to its enjoyment old age not merely
offers no obstacle, but even entices and allures.

<pb id="p.71"/>

For where else can the old man find more genial
warmth of sun or fire, and, on the other hand,
where, in summer time, can he more healthfully
cool himself with shade and running streams?
Let others, then, have their weapons, <milestone unit="section" n="58"/>their horses
and their spears, their fencing-foils, and games of
ball, their swimming contests and foot-races, and
out of many sports leave us old fellows our dice and
knuckle-bones. Or take away the dice-box, too,
if you will, since old age can be happy without it.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="59"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="17"/>Xenophon's writings are very instructive
on many subjects and I beg you to go on reading
them with studious care. With what copious
eloquence agriculture is lauded in his book entitled
<hi rend="italics">The Householder,</hi> which treats of the management
of estates! To show you that Xenophon regarded
nothing more befitting royalty than zeal in husbandry,
let me recall the incident<note>Xen. <hi rend="italics">Oecon. 4. 20.</hi></note> in the same book, related
by Socrates in a conversation with Critobulus.
Cyrus the Younger, a Persian prince, eminent
for his intelligence and the glory of his rule, was
visited at Sardis by Lysander the Spartan, a man
of the highest virtue, who brought presents from the
allies Among other courtesies to Lysander while his
guest, Cyrus showed him a certain carefully planted
park. After admiring the stateliness of the trees,
regularly placed in quincunx rows,<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> arranged thus. . . . <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Virg. <hi rend="italics">Georg.</hi> ii. 277.</note> the clean and
well-cultivated soil, and the sweet odours emanating
from the flowers, Lysander then remarked: <quote>I marvel
not only at the industry, but also at the skill of the
man who planned and arranged this work.</quote> <quote>But
it was I,</quote> Cyrus answered, <quote>who planned it all;
mine are the rows and mine the arrangement, and
many of those trees I set out with my own hands.</quote>


<pb id="p.73"/>

After gazing at the prince's purple robe, the beauty
of his person, his Persian costume adorned with
much gold and many precious stones, Lysander said:
<quote>With good reason, Cyrus, men call you happy,
since in you good fortune has been joined with
virtue.</quote></p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="60"/>And this good fortune, therefore, we old men
may enjoy; nor does age offer any hindrance to
our pursuit of other activities, and especially the
cultivation of the soil, even to the very end of old
age. For example, there is a tradition that Valerius
Corvinus, after passing the ordinary span of life,
lived on his farm and cultivated it, and continued
his pursuit of agriculture to his hundredth year.
Forty-six years intervened between his first and
sixth consulships. Thus, so much space of time as
by our forefathers' reckoning marked the beginning
of old age, just that space was the course of his
public honours; and the last period of his life was
happier than the middle span, because his influence
was greater and his labours were less.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="61"/>But the crowning glory of old age is influence.
How great was the influence of Lucius Caecilius
Metellus! How great, too, was that of Aulus Atilius
Calatinus, for whom this epitaph was made:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>All peoples say of him who lieth here:</l>
<l>He was his country's very foremost man.</l></quote>

But the entire epitaph is known because it is inscribed upon his tomb. Deservedly weighty, then,
was his influence, since all men united in his praise.
What heroic qualities I saw not long ago in Publius
Crassus, the chief pontiff, and in Marcus Lepidus,
his successor in that priestly office! And what shall

<pb id="p.75"/>

I say of Paulus, and of Africanus, and of Maximus,
of whom I have spoken before? These men had
power, not only in their speech, but in their very
nod. Surely old age, when crowned with public
honours, enjoys an influence which is of more account
than all the sensual pleasures of youth.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="62"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="18"/>But bear well in mind that in this entire
discussion I am praising that old age which has its
foundation well laid in youth. Hence it follows&mdash;
as I once said with the approval of all who heard it&mdash;
that that old age is wretched which needs to defend
itself with words.<note><hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> instead of being able to refer to the actions of earlier
years.</note> Nor can wrinkles and grey
hair suddenly seize upon influence; but when the
preceding part of life has been nobly spent, old age
gathers the fruits of influence at the last. <milestone unit="section" n="63"/>For
those very things, that seem light and trivial, are
marks of honour&mdash;the morning visit, being sought
after, being made way for, having people rise at one's
approach, being escorted to and from the forum,
being asked for advice&mdash;civilities most scrupulously
observed among us and in every other state in
proportion as its morals are good. Moreover,
Lysander, the Spartan, of whom I just now spoke,
is reported to have said more than once that in
Sparta old age has its most fitting abode; because
nowhere else is so much deference paid to age and
nowhere else is it more honoured. For example,
there is a story that when an old man entered the
theatre at Athens during the dramatic performances,
not one of his countrymen in that vast crowd offered
him a place; but when he came to the special seats
occupied by the Lacedaemonians and assigned to
them because they were ambassadors, all of them
arose, it is said, and invited him to sit down. <milestone unit="section" n="64"/>After

<pb id="p.77"/>

this action had been greeted by the whole audience
with repeated applause, one of the Spartans
remarked: <quote>These Athenians know what politeness
is, but they won't practise it.</quote></p>
<p>There are many noteworthy customs in our college
of augurs, but especially in point is the one whereby
each has precedence in debate according to his age,
and the oldest is preferred, not only to those of higher
official rank, but even to those having <hi rend="italics">imperium.</hi><note>Only the consuls, praetors, dictators, masters of horse,
and provincial governors, while in office, had <hi rend="italics">imperium.</hi></note> 
What physical pleasures, then, are comparable to
the distinction which influence bestows? The men
who have put these distinctions to noble use are, it
seems to me, like skilful actors who have played
well their parts in the drama of life to the end, and
not like untrained players who have broken down in
the last act.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="65"/>But, the critics say, old men are morose, troubled,
fretful, and hard to please; and, if we inquire, we
shall find that some of them are misers, too. However, these are faults of character, not of age. Yet
moroseness and the other faults mentioned have
some excuse, not a really sufficient one, but such
as it may seem possible to allow, in that old men
imagine themselves ignored, despised, and mocked
at; and besides, when the body is weak, the lightest
blow gives pain. But nevertheless all these faults
are much ameliorated by good habits and by education, as may be seen in real life, and particularly
on the stage in the case of the two brothers in
the play of that name.<note><hi rend="italics">Adelphi,</hi> a play of Terence.</note> What a disagreeable
nature one of them has, and what an affable disposition has the other! Indeed the case stands thus:
as it is not every wine, so it is not every disposition,
that grows sour with age. I approve of some

<pb id="p.79"/>

austerity in the old, but I want it, as I do everything
else, in moderation. Sourness of temper I like
not at all. As for avariciousness in the old, what
purpose it can serve I do not understand, <milestone unit="section" n="66"/>for can
anything be more absurd in the traveller than to
increase his luggage as he nears his journey's end?</p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="19"/>It remains to consider now the fourth
reason&mdash;one that seems especially calculated to
render my time of life anxious and full of care&mdash;the
nearness of death; for death, in truth, cannot be
far away. O wretched indeed is that old man who
has not learned in the course of his long life that
death should be held of no account! For clearly
death is negligible, if it utterly annihilates the soul,
or even desirable, if it conducts the soul to some place
where it is to live for ever. Surely no other alternative can be found. <milestone unit="section" n="67"/>What, then, shall I fear, if after
death I am destined to be either not unhappy or
happy? And yet is there anyone so foolish, even
though he is young, as to feel absolutely sure that he
will be alive when evening comes? Nay, even
youth, much more than old age, is subject to the
accident of death; the young fall sick more easily,
their sufferings are more intense, and they are cured
with greater difficulty. Therefore few arrive at old
age, and, but for this, life would be lived in better
and wiser fashion. For it is in old men that reason
and good judgement are found, and had it not been
for old men no state would have existed at all.</p>
<p>But I return to the question of impending death.
What fault is this which you charge against old
age, when, as you see, it is one chargeable likewise
to youth? <milestone unit="section" n="68"/>That death is common to every age
has been brought home to me by the loss of my

<pb id="p.81"/>

dearest son, and to you, Scipio, by the untimely
end of your two brothers, when they were giving
promise of attaining to the highest honours in the
State. But, you may say, the young man hopes
that he will live for a long time and this hope the
old man cannot have. Such a hope is not wise,
for what is more unwise than to mistake uncertainty
for certainty, falsehood for truth? They say, also,
that the old man has nothing even to hope for.
Yet he is in better case than the young man, since
what the latter merely hopes for, the former has
already attained; the one wishes to live long,
the other has lived long.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="59"/>But, ye gods! what is there in human nature
that is for long? For grant the utmost limit of
life; let us hope to reach the age of the Tartessian
king&mdash;for at Cadiz there was, as I have seen it
recorded,<note>Herod. i. 163.</note> a certain Arganthonius, who had reigned
eighty and had lived one hundred and twenty years&mdash;,
but to me nothing whatever seems <quote>lengthy</quote> if it
has an end; for when that end arrives, then that
which was is gone; naught remains but the fruit
of good and virtuous deeds. Hours and days, and
months and years, go by; the past returns no more,
and what is to be we cannot know; but whatever
the time given us in which to live, we should therewith be content.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="70"/>The actor, for instance, to please his audience
need not appear in every act to the very end; it is
enough if he is approved in the parts in which he
plays; and so it is not necessary for the wise man
to stay on this mortal stage to the last fall of the
curtain.<note>Literally until (the words) <quote>now applaud</quote> (are spoken).
All the plays of Terence and most of those of Plautus
close with <hi rend="italics">plaudite.</hi></note> For even if the allotted space of life be
short, it is long enough in which to live honourably

<pb id="p.83"/>

and well; but if a longer period of years should be
granted, one has no more cause to grieve than the
farmers have that the pleasant springtime has passed
and that summer and autumn have come. For
spring typifies youth and gives promise of future
fruits; while the other seasons are designed for
gathering in those fruits and storing them away.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="71"/>Now the fruit of old age, as I have often said, is the
memory of abundant blessings previously acquired.
Moreover, whatever befalls in accordance with
Nature should be accounted good; and indeed,
what is more consonant with Nature than for the
old to die? But the same fate befalls the young,
though Nature in their case struggles and rebels.
Therefore, when the young die I am reminded
of a strong flame extinguished by a torrent;
but when old men die it is as if a fire had gone out
without the use of force and of its own accord, after
the fuel had been consumed; and, just as apples
when they are green are with difficulty plucked
from the tree, but when ripe and mellow fall of
themselves, so, with the young, death comes as a
result of force, while with the old it is the result
of ripeness. To me, indeed, the thought of this
<quote>ripeness</quote> for death is so pleasant, that the nearer
I approach death the more I feel like one who is in
sight of land at last and is about to anchor in his
home port after a long voyage.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="72"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="20"/>But old age has no certain term, and there
is good cause for an old man living so long as he can
fulfil and support his proper duties and hold death
of no account. By this means old age actually becomes more spirited and more courageous than youth.
This explains the answer which Solon gave to the

<pb id="p.85"/>

tyrant Pisistratus who asked, <quote>Pray, what do you
rely upon in opposing me so boldly?</quote> and Solon
replied, <quote>Old age.</quote> But the most desirable end
of life is that which comes while the mind is clear
and the faculties are unimpaired, when Nature herself
takes apart the work which she has put together.
As the builder most readily destroys the ship or
the house which he has built, so Nature is the agent
best fitted to give dissolution to her creature, man.
Now every structure when newly built is hard to
pull apart, but the old and weather-beaten house
comes easily down.</p>
<p>Hence, it follows that old men ought neither to
cling too fondly to their little remnant of life, nor
give it up without a cause. <milestone unit="section" n="73"/>Pythagoras<note>Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo 6;</hi> Cic. <hi rend="italics">Somn. Scip. 3;</hi> Cic. <hi rend="italics">Tusc. i. 20.</hi></note> bids us
stand like faithful sentries and not quit our post
until God, our Captain, gives the word. Solon the
Wise has a couplet in which he says that he does
not want his death to be free from the grief and
mourning of his friends.<note>Plutarch in his comparison of Solon and Publicola
gives these lines.</note> He wishes, no doubt
to make out that he is dear to his friends, but I am
inclined to think that Ennius has expressed it
better when he says:

<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>I do not wish the honour of a tear,</l>
<l>Or any wailing cries about my bier.</l></quote>

He does not think that death, which is followed by
eternal life, should be a cause of grief.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="74"/>Now, there may be some sensation in the process
of dying, but it is a fleeting one, especially to the old;
after death the sensation is either pleasant or there
is none at all. But this should be thought on from
our youth up, so that we may be indifferent to death,

<pb id="p.87"/>

and without this thought no one can be in a tranquil
state of mind. For it is certain that we must die.
and, for aught we know, this very day. Therefore,
since death threatens every hour, how can he who
fears it have any steadfastness of soul? <milestone unit="section" n="75"/>No very
extended argument on this point seems necessary
when I recall&mdash;not the conduct of Lucius Brutus,
who was killed in liberating his country; nor that
of the two Decii who rode full speed to a voluntary
death; nor that of Marcus Atilius Regulus, who set out
from home to undergo torture and keep the faith
pledged to his foe; nor that of the two Scipios, who
with their bodies sought to stay the Punic march;
nor that, Scipio, of your grandfather Lucius Paulus
who, in the shameful rout at Cannae, gave his life to
atone for his colleague's folly; nor that of Marcus
Marcellus, to whom not even his most pitiless foe
denied the honours of a funeral&mdash;but rather when
I recall, as I have noted in my <hi rend="italics">Antiquities,</hi> how our
legions have often marched with cheerful and
unwavering courage into situations whence they
thought they would never return. Then shall wise
old men fear a thing which is despised by youths,
and not only by those who are untaught, but by
those also who are mere clowns?</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="76"/>Undoubtedly, as it seems to me at least, satiety
of all pursuits causes satiety of life. Boyhood has
certain pursuits: does youth yearn for them?
Early youth has its pursuits: does the matured or
so-called middle stage of life need them? Maturity,
too, has such as are not even sought in old age, and
finally, there are those suitable to old age. Therefore as the pleasures and pursuits of the earlier
periods of life fall away, so also do those of old age;

<pb id="p.89"/>

and when that happens man has his fill of life and
the time is ripe for him to go.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="77"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="21"/>Really I do not see why I should not
venture to tell you what I, myself, think of death;
for it seems to me that I apprehend it better as I
draw nearer to it. It is my belief, Scipio, that your
father, and yours, Laelius&mdash;both of them most
illustrious men and very dear to me&mdash;are living yet,
and living the only life deserving of the name.
For while we are shut up within these frames of
flesh we perform a sort of task imposed by necessity<note>Or <quote>fate.</quote></note> 
and endure grievous labour; for the soul is celestial,
brought down from its most exalted home and
buried, as it were, in earth, a place uncongenial
to its divine and eternal nature. But I believe that
the immortal gods implanted souls in human bodies
so as to have beings who would care for the earth
and who, while contemplating the celestial order,
would imitate it in the moderation and consistency
of their lives. Nor have I been driven to this belief
solely by the force of reason and of argument, but
also by the reputation and authority of philosophers
of the highest rank.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="78"/>I used to be told that Pythagoras and his disciples,
&mdash;who were almost fellow-countrymen of ours, inasmuch as they were formerly called <quote>Italian
philosophers,</quote>&mdash;never doubted that our souls were
emanations of the Universal Divine Mind. Moreover, I had clearly set before me the arguments
touching the immortality of the soul, delivered on the
last day of his life by Socrates, whom the oracle of
Apollo had pronounced the wisest of men. Why
multiply words? That is my conviction, that is what
I believe&mdash;since such is the lightning-like rapidity of

<pb id="p.91"/>

the soul, such its wonderful memory of things that
are past, such its ability to forecast the future, such
its mastery of many arts, sciences, and inventions,
that its nature, which encompasses all these things,
cannot be mortal; and since the soul is always
active and has no source of motion because it is
self-moving, its motion will have no end, because
it will never leave itself; and since in its nature the
soul is of one substance and has nothing whatever
mingled with it unlike or dissimilar to itself, it
cannot be divided, and if it cannot be divided it
cannot perish. And a strong argument that men's
knowledge of numerous things antedates their
birth is the fact that mere children, in studying
difficult subjects, so quickly lay hold upon innumerable things that they seem not to be then learning
them for the first time, but to be recalling and
remembering them. This, in substance, is Plato's
teaching.<note><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi> 72 E-73 B, 78&ndash;80; <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus 245</hi> c.</note> </p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="79"/><milestone unit="chapter" n="22"/>Again, in Xenophon,<note>Xenophon, <hi rend="italics">Cyropaedia,</hi> viii. 7. 17&ndash;22.</note> Cyrus the Elder
utters the following words as he is dying: <quote>Think
not, my dearest sons, that, when I have left you,
I shall cease to be. For while I was with you you
did not see my soul, but you knew that it was in
this body from the deeds that I performed. Continue to believe, therefore, that it exists as before,
even though you see it not. <milestone unit="section" n="80"/>Nor, indeed, would
the fame of illustrious men survive their death if
the souls of those very men did not cause us to retain
their memory longer. I, for my part, could never
be persuaded that souls, which lived while they were
in human bodies, perished when they left those
bodies; nor, indeed, that the soul became incapable
of thought when it had escaped from the unthinking

<pb id="p.93"/>

corpse, but rather that, when it had been freed from
every admixture of flesh and had begun to exist
pure and undefiled, then only was it wise. And
even when man is dissolved by death it is evident
to the sight whither each bodily element departs;
for the corporeal returns to the visible constituents
from which it came, but the soul alone remains
unseen, both when it is present and when it departs.
Again, you really see nothing resembling death
so much as sleep; <milestone unit="section" n="81"/>and yet it is when the body sleeps
that the soul most clearly manifests its divine nature;
for when it is unfettered and free it sees many
things that are to come.<note>But cf<hi rend="italics">. De divinatione,</hi> ii. 58. 119 ff.. where Cicero refutes
and derides this theory.</note> Hence we know what the
soul's future state will be when it has been wholly
released from the shackles of the flesh. Wherefore,
if what I have said be true, cherish me as you would
a god. But on the other hand, if my soul is going
to perish along with my body, still you, who revere
the gods as the guardians and rulers of this beautiful
universe, will keep me in loving and sacred memory.</quote></p>
<p><milestone unit="chapter" n="23"/>This was the view of the dying Cyrus. Let
me, if you please, give my own.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="82"/>No one, my dear Scipio, will ever convince me that
your father Paulus, or your two grandfathers,
Paulus and Africanus, or the latter's father and
uncle, or many other illustrious men, unnecessary
now to name, would have attempted such mighty
deeds, to be remembered by posterity, if they had
not known that posterity belonged to them. Or,
to boast somewhat of myself after the manner of
the old, do you think that I should have undertaken
such heavy labours by day and by night, at home and
abroad, if I had believed that the term of my earthly
life would mark the limits of my fame? Would

<pb id="p.95"/>

it not have been far better for me to spend a leisured
and quiet life, free from toil and strife? But
somehow, my soul was ever on the alert, looking
forward to posterity, as if it realized that when it
had departed from this life, then at last would it be
alive. And, indeed, were it not true that the soul
is immortal, it would not be the case that it is ever
the souls of the best men that strive most for immortal
glory. And what of the fact that the wisest men
die with the greatest equanimity, <milestone unit="section" n="83"/>the most foolish
with the least? Is it not apparent to you that it
is because the soul of the one, having a keener
and wider vision, sees that it is setting out for a
better country, while that of the other, being of
duller sight, sees not its path?</p>
<p>Really, Scipio, I am carried away with the desire
to see your father, and yours too, Laelius, both of
whom I honoured and loved; and, indeed, I am
eager to meet not only those whom I have known,
but those also of whom I have heard and read and
written. And when I shall have set out to join
them, assuredly no one will easily draw me back.
or boil me up again, as if I were a Pelias.<note>Cicero here confuses Pelias with his half-brother Aeson,
whom Medea restored to youth by cutting him up and
boiling him in a cauldron.</note> Nay, if
some god should give me leave to return to infancy
from my old age, to weep once more in my cradle, I
should vehemently protest; for, truly, after I have
run my race I have no wish to be recalled, as it were,
from the goal to the starting-place. <milestone unit="section" n="84"/>For what
advantage has life&mdash;or, rather, what trouble does it
not have? But even grant that it has great
advantage, yet undoubtedly it has either satiety or
an end. I do not mean to complain of life as many
men, and they learned ones, have often done; nor
do I regret that I have lived, since I have so lived

<pb id="p.97"/>

that I think I was not born in vain, and I quit life
as if it were an inn, not a home. For Nature has
given us an hostelry in which to sojourn, not to abide.</p>
<p>O glorious day, when I shall set out to join the
assembled hosts of souls divine and leave this world
of strife and sin! For I shall go to meet not only
the men already mentioned, but my Cato, too,
than whom no better man, none more distinguished
for filial duty, was ever born. His body was burned
by me, whereas, on the contrary it were more
fitting that mine had been burned by him; but
his soul, not deserting me, but ever looking back,
has surely departed for that realm where it knew
that I, myself, must come. People think that I
have bravely borne my loss&mdash;not that I bore it
with an untroubled heart, but I found constant
solace in the thought that our separation would
not be long.</p>
<p><milestone unit="section" n="85"/>For these reasons, Scipio, my old age sits light
upon me (for you said that this has been a cause of
wonder to you and Laelius), and not only is not
burdensome, but is even happy. And if I err in
my belief that the souls of men are immortal, I
gladly err, nor do I wish this error which gives me
pleasure to be wrested from me while I live. But
if when dead I am going to be without sensation
(as some petty philosophers think), then I have no
fear that these seers, when they are dead, will have
the laugh on me! Again, if we are not going to
be immortal, nevertheless, it is desirable for a man
to be blotted out at his proper time. For as Nature
has marked the bounds of everything else, so she
has marked the bounds of life. Moreover, old age
is the final scene, as it were, in life's drama, from

<pb id="p.99"/>

which we ought to escape when it grows wearisome
and, certainly, when we have had our fill.</p>
<p>Such, my friends, are my views on old age. May
you both attain it, and thus be able to prove
by experience the truth of what you have heard
from me.</p>

</body>

</text>
</TEI.2>
