<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersDrama PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Drama//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersDrama.dtd" >
%PersDrama;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Poenulus, or The Young Carthaginian</title>
<author>T. Maccius Plautus</author>
<editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.DLI2;
</titleStmt>
&Perseus.publish;

<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>The Comedies of Plautus</title>
<editor role="transl">Henry Thomas Riley</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>G. Bell and Sons</publisher>
<date>1912</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction method="silent" status="medium">&Perseus.DE;</correction>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="act"/>
<state n="chunk" unit="scene"/>
<state unit="line"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="de">German</language>
<language id="fr">French</language>
<language id="it">Italian</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change><date>1-Jun-01</date>
<respStmt><name>AEM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
<item>
$Log: pl.poen_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-12-07 18:50:30  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/06/22 16:22:31  student
fixed Pl. Poen. references - zr

Revision 1.5  2009/06/17 20:57:56  rsingh04
don't chunk by TLN line cause they don't seem to be correct and cause problems

Revision 1.4  2009/01/27 19:01:45  lcerrato
fixed some speaker confusion

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 20:50:27  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 16:22:23  packel
new XML version

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:59:36  packel
Converted to XML

Revision 1.13  2003/07/01 22:17:32  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.12  2001/08/21 18:49:31  amahoney
get translator's name into correct place in meta-data, use same form of author as in Latin

Revision 1.11  2001/08/08 17:55:29  amahoney
get rid of the silly italics (marking words that "don't occur" in the Latin)

Revision 1.10  2001/08/03 20:53:28  amahoney
fix stage directions at end of scenes (which had unmatched parentheses
in the original -- very nasty)

Revision 1.9  2001/08/03 20:50:02  amahoney
fix spurious italics in lemmata

Revision 1.8  2001/08/02 21:22:40  amahoney
add header to introduction stuff, to tidy up the tocs

Revision 1.7  2001/08/01 21:34:11  amahoney
use full speaker names

Revision 1.6  2001/08/01 19:16:31  amahoney
get the tln lines in place;  correct funder

Revision 1.5  2001/07/05 21:23:35  amahoney
correct citations so we can use both schemes (the one with fewer slots
must always be first), and drop page breaks

Revision 1.4  2001/07/03 18:21:29  amahoney
fix the broken characters

Revision 1.3  2001/06/29 19:04:20  amahoney
tidy up line numbers, making citation scheme match the Latin

Revision 1.2  2001/06/21 17:39:36  amahoney
put in rudimentary line numbers, based on the footnotes

Revision 1.1  2001/06/19 21:34:35  amahoney
now they all parse, and the scenes are correctly identified

</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text lang="en">
<body>

<castList>
<castItem type="role"><role><placeName key="tgn,1080049">HANNO</placeName>, </role><roleDesc>a Carthaginian.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>AGORASTOCLES, </role><roleDesc>a young Carthaginian, living at Calydon.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>ANTHEMONIDES, </role><roleDesc>a Captain.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>MILPHIO, </role><roleDesc>servant of Agorastocles.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>COLLYBISCUS, </role><roleDesc>bailiff of Agorastocles.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>LYCUS, </role><roleDesc>a Procurer.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>SYNCERASTUS, </role><roleDesc>servant of Lycus.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>A BOY.</role></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>SOME ASSISTANTS. [ADVOCATI.]</role></castItem>
<castGroup>
<castItem type="role"><role>ADELPHASIUM, </role><roleDesc>sisters, Courtesans.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>ANTERLASTYIS,</role></castItem>
</castGroup>
<castItem type="role"><role>GIDDENEME, </role><roleDesc>their Nurse.</roleDesc></castItem>
<castItem type="role"><role>A MAID-SERVANT.</role></castItem>
</castList>

<stage>Scene--Calydon, a city of &AElig;tolia. Before the houses of AGORASTOCLES and LYOUS, and the Temple of Venus.</stage>

<div1 type="act" n="intro">
<head>Introduction</head>
<div2 type="scene" n="subject">
<head>THE SUBJECT</head>

<p>THERE were two cousins, citizens of Carthage; the daughters of one of them named Hanno, were stolen in their childhood, and being carried off to Calydon, were there purchased by Lycus, a Procurer. In the same place there is living Agorastocles, the son of the cousin of Hanno, who, having been stolen in his infancy, was sold to a wealthy old man, and finally adopted by him. Here, without knowing their relationship, Agorastocles falls in love with Adelphasium, the elder of the sisters, while Anthemonides, a military officer, entertains a passion for Anterastylis, the younger sister. The Procurer being at enmity with Agorastocles, the latter, with the assistance of his servant Milphio, devises a plan for outwitting him. Collybiscus, the bailiff of Agorastocles, is dressed up as a foreigner, and, a sum of money being given him for the purpose, pretends to take up his abode in the house of Lycus. On this being effected, by previous arrangement Agorastocles comes with witnesses, and accuses the Procurer of harbouring his slave, and encouraging him to rob his master. At this conjuncture, Hanno arrives at Calydon in search of his daughters. He discovers them, and finds that Agorastocles is the son of his deceased cousin. The play ends with the removal of the damsels from the house of Lycus, who is brought to task for his iniquities; and Adelphasium is promised by her father in marriage to Agorastocles.
</p></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="argument">
<head>THE ACROSTIC ARGUMENT. <note anchored="yes" place="inline">[Supposed to have been written by Priscian the Grammarian.]</note></head>
<p>A BOY (<foreign lang="la">Puer</foreign>), seven years old, is stolen at Carthage. An old man, a hater (<foreign lang="la">Osco</foreign>) of women, adopts him when bought, and (<foreign lang="la">Et</foreign>) makes him his heir. His two kinswomen and their nurse (<foreign lang="la">Nutrix</foreign>) are <foreign lang="la">also</foreign> carried off. Lycus buys them and torments (<foreign lang="la">Vexat</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">Agorastocles</foreign> in love. But he palms off his bailiff with some gold upon the Procurer (<foreign lang="la">Lenoni</foreign>), <foreign lang="la">and</foreign> so convicts him of theft. Hanno, the Carthaginian, comes (<foreign lang="la">Venit</foreign>), discovers him <foreign lang="la">to be</foreign> the son of his cousin, and recognizes his own (<foreign lang="la">Suas</foreign>) daughters whom he had lost.

</p></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="prologue">
<div2 type="scene" n="0">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1" unit="TLN line"/>
<sp><speaker>PROLOGUE</speaker>
<p>I HAVE a mind<note anchored="yes">Title <lemma targOrder="U">The young Carthaginian</lemma>:  Cicero uses the word "P&oelig;nulus," as signifying merely "a Carthaginian." It is difficult to say whether the Play is so styled in reference to Hanno, merely as a citizen of Carthage, or whether the word refers to the young man Agorastocles, in the sense of the "young Carthaginian." From an expression used in the Fifth Act, "a man's great toe," it would appear that Hanno was represented on the stage as a person of diminutive stature; in consequence of which, it has been suggested that the meaning is "the little Carthaginian." Lipsius thinks that this Prologue was not written by Plautus, and indeed some scholars suspect the whole Play to be spurious.</note> to imitate the Achilles of Aristarchus<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Achilles of Aristarchus</lemma>:  Aristarchus was a Tragic Poet, the contemporary of Euripides, and flourished about 250 years before the time of Plautus. His Tragedy of Achilles no longer exists. We are informed by Festus that it was translated into Latin by the Poet Eunius.</note> from that Tragedy I'll take for myself the opening: "Be silent, and hold your tongues, and give attention." The head-manager it is who bids you listen, that with a good grace they may be seated on the benches, both those who have come hungry and those <hi rend="ital">who have come</hi> well filled. You who have eaten, by far the most wisely have you done: you who have not eaten, do you be filled with the Play. But he who has something ready for him to eat, 'tis <hi rend="ital">really</hi> great folly in him, for our sakes, to come here to sit fasting. Rise up, cryer! bespeak attention among the people: I'm now waiting <hi rend="ital">to see</hi> if you know your duty. Exercise your voice, by means of which you subsist and find your clothes; for unless you do cry out, in your silence starvation will be creeping upon you. Well, now sit down again, that you may earn double wages. Heaven grant success<milestone n="16" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Heaven grant success</lemma>:  "Bonum factum est." Literally, "it is a good deed." This was a stated form, placed at the commencement of Roman edicts and proclamations, as ensuring a good omen.</note>! do you obey my commands. Let no worn-out debauchee<milestone n="17" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Worn-out debauchee</lemma>:  "Scortum exoletum." As the word "scortum" may apply to either sex, it is not improbable that this is intended as a notice to the old and battered debauchees, that they are not to take the liberty of occupying the front of the stage, as perhaps, in their effrontery, they had lately been in the habit of doing.</note> be sitting in the front of the stage, nor let the lictor or his rods<milestone n="18" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Or his rods</lemma>:  These "virg&aelig;" were used by the lictors for the purposes of punishment, and if stiff and hard, would be likely to make a noise when struck against any object.</note> be noisy in the least; and let no seat-keeper<milestone n="19" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">No seat-keeper</lemma>:  "Designator." It was the duty of this officer to point out to persons their seats.</note> be walking about before <hi rend="ital">people's</hi> faces, nor be showing any to their seats, while the actor is on the stage. Those who have been sleeping too long at home in idleness, it's right for them now to stand contentedly, or else let them master their drowsiness. Don't let slaves be occupying the seats<milestone n="23" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Occupying the seats</lemma>:  It has been previously remarked that only standing room was provided in the theatres for the slaves.</note>, that there may be room for those who are free; or else let them pay down the money for their places<milestone n="24" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The money for their places</lemma>:  "&AElig;s pro capite." The meaning of this term, as here used, is not exactly known. Some think that it means, that if the slaves want seats, let them pay down money for their freedom, on which they will be entitled to them. It is not improbable that the phase means, "let them pay money for their seats;" and Muretus supposes that the right of letting out certain seats was reserved by the actors as their own perquisite.</note>; if that they cannot do, let them be off home, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> escape a double evil, lest they be variegated both here with scourges, and with thongs at home, if they've not got things in due order when their masters come home. Let nurses keep children, baby-bantlings, at home, and let no one bring them to see the Play; lest both they themselves may be athirst<milestone n="30" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">May be athirst</lemma>:  This is not the only place where Plautus refers to the love which the Roman nurses had for the bottle.</note>, and the children may die with hunger; and that they mayn't be squealing about here, in their hungry fits, just like kids. Let the matrons see the piece in silence, in silence laugh, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> let them refrain from screaming here with their shrill voices; their themes for gossip let them carry off home, so as not to be an annoyance to their husbands both here and at home. And, as regards the managers of the performance, let not the palm <hi rend="ital">of victory</hi> be given to any player wrongfully, nor by reason of favour let any be driven out of doors, in order that the inferior may be preferred to the good ones. And this, too, besides, which I had almost forgotten: while the performance is going on, do you, lacqueys, make an onset on the cookshops; now, while there's an opportunity, now, while the tarts<milestone n="43" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">While the tarts</lemma>:  "Scriblit&aelig;." These were a kind of tarts or cakes which had letters stamped upon them, and were probably so called from <foreign lang="la">scribo</foreign>, "to write."</note> are smoking hot, hasten there. These injunctions, which have been given as the manager's command, Heaven prosper them! troth now, let every one remember for himself. Now, in its turn, I wish to go back to the plot, that you may be equally knowing with myself. Its site, its limits, its boundaries I'll now lay down; for that purpose have I been appointed surveyor. But, unless it's troublesome, I wish to give you the name of this Comedy: but if it is an annoyance, I'll tell you still, since I have leave from those who have the management. This Comedy is called the "Carthaginian<milestone n="53" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The Carthaginian</lemma>:  "Carchedonius," the old Roman name for "Carthaginian," from <foreign lang="greek">*karxhdw\n,</foreign> the Greek for "Carthage."</note>;" in the Latin, Plautus has called it "the Pulse-eating Kinsman<milestone n="54" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pulse-eating Kinsman</lemma>:  "Patruus pultiphagonides." The Roman "puls," or "pottage," was composed of meat, water, honey, cheese, and eggs. There was a particular sort of "puls," called "puls Punica," or "Punic pottage." As this Play was written at the period of the second Carthaginian war, Plautus would not object to hold their enemies up to contempt as mere "porridge-eaters."</note>." You have the name, then; now hear the rest of the story; for here will this plot be judged of <hi rend="ital">by you.</hi> Its own stage is the <hi rend="ital">proper</hi> place for every plot; you are the critics; I pray you lend attention. There were two cousins-german<milestone n="59" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Two cousins- german</lemma>:  "Fratres fratrueles." "Sons of brothers." This clears up all the confusion that otherwise seems to exist in the Play, by reason of Agorastocles continually calling Hanno his "patruus," which Warner (to avoid confusion, as he says) translates "uncle." It is pretty clear that "patruus" was a term extending not only to uncles, but to other collateral relatives of the father; not only father's brothers, but father's cousins.</note>, Carthaginians, of a very high and very wealthy family. One of them is <hi rend="ital">still</hi> alive, the other's dead. The more confidently do I inform you <hi rend="ital">of this,</hi> because the undertaker<milestone n="62" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The undertaker</lemma>:  "Pollinctor." This was properly the servant of the "libitinarius," or "undertaker." See the Asinaria, l. 916, and the Note.</note> told me so, who anointed him <hi rend="ital">for the pile.</hi> But the only son there was of that old man who died, being separated from his father, was stolen at Carthage when seven years old, six years, in fact, before his father died. When he saw that his only son was lost to him, he himself, from grief, fell sick; he made this cousin-german of his his heir; he himself departed for Acheron without taking leave<milestone n="71" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Without taking leave</lemma>:  "Sine viatico." Literally, "without provisions for the journey." This, probably, simply means that he died suddenly and unexpectedly. Some think that it refers to the ceremony of placing a piece of money in the mouths of the dead, for payment to Charon, on ferrying them over the Styx. If so, the allusion here appears to be very purposeless.</note>. The person who stole the child, carried him off to Calydon, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> sold him here to a certain rich old man for his master, one desirous of children, <hi rend="ital">but</hi> a hater of women. This old man, without knowing it, bought the son of his host, that same child, and adopted him as his own son, and made him his heir when he himself departed this life. This young man is dwelling here in this house. <stage>Pointing to the house of AGORASTOCLES.</stage> Once more do I return to Carthage. If you want to give any commission, or <hi rend="ital">anything</hi> to be managed--unless a person<milestone n="86" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Unless a person</lemma>: --<bibl n="Pl. Poen. prologue.0">Ver. 81-2</bibl>. These two lines also occur almost verbatim in the Men&aelig;chmi, l. 54-5.</note> gives the money, he will be mistaken; but he who does give it will be very much more <hi rend="ital">mistaken.</hi> But this father's cousin of his at Carthage, the old man who is still alive, had two daughters. The one when in her fifth year, the other in her fourth, were lost, together with their nurse, from the walks in the suburbs<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">In the suburbs</lemma>:  "Magalia," or "magara," was a name given to the huts or cottages peculiar to the neighbourhood of Carthage. The word, probably, here means a suburb of that city, which received its name from these huts, and was used by the inhabitants as a public walk.</note>. The person who kidnapped them, carried them off to Anactorium<milestone n="87" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Anactorium</lemma>:  This was a town of Acarnania, in Greece.</note>, and sold them all, both nurse and girls, for ready money, to a man (if a Procurer is a man) the most accursed of men, as many as the earth contains; but do you yourselves now form a conjecture what sort of man it is whose name is Lycus<milestone n="92" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Name is Lycus</lemma>:  From the Greek word <foreign lang="greek">luko\s,</foreign> "a wolf."</note>. He removed, not long ago, from Anactorium, where he formerly lived, to Calydon<milestone n="94" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To Calydon</lemma>:  Calydon was a city of &AElig;tolia, which was situate in the centre of Greece.</note> here, for the sake of his business. Be dwells in that house. <stage>Pointing to the house of LYCUS.</stage> This young man is dying distractedly in love with one of them, his kinswoman, not knowing that fact; neither is he aware who she is, nor has he ever touched her (so much does the Procurer hamper him); neither has he hitherto ever had any improper connexion with her, nor <hi rend="ital">ever</hi> taken her <hi rend="ital">home to his house;</hi> nor has that <hi rend="ital">Procurer</hi> been willing to send her <hi rend="ital">there.</hi> Because he sees that he is in love, he wishes to touch <hi rend="ital">this</hi> man for a <hi rend="ital">good</hi> haul. A certain Captain, who is desperately in love with her, is desirous to buy this younger one to be his mistress. But their father, the Carthaginian, since he lost them, has been continually seeking them in every quarter, by sea and land. When he has entered any city, at once he seeks out all the courtesans, wherever each of them is living; he gives <hi rend="ital">her</hi> gold, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> prolongs the night <hi rend="ital">in his enquiries;</hi> after that he asks whence she comes, of what country, whether she was made captive or kidnapped, born of what family, who her parents were. So diligently and so skilfully does he seek for his daughters. He knows all languages, too; but, though he knows them, he pretends not to know them: what need is there of talking? He is a Carthaginian all over<milestone n="113" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A Carthaginian all over</lemma>:  This is intended as a reflection upon the proverbial faithlessness of the Carthaginians. "Punica fides," "Punic faith,' was a common proverb with the Romans.</note>. He, in the evening of yesterday, came into harbour here on board ship. The father of these girls, the same is the father's cousin of this young man. Now d'ye take<milestone n="116" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">D'ye take</lemma>:  There seems to be an equivocal meaning here in the word "tenetis," which may mean either "to understand," or "to take hold with the hand." "Dirumpatis" also may mean either "break off" a rope or cord, or "interrupt." Though Lambinus thinks that some indecent allusion is intended, this much more probable that Scaliger is right in supposing that allusion is made to the boyish diversion of two parties pulling at the ends of a rope till it either breaks, or one side lets go.</note> this? If you do take it, draw it out: take care not to break it asunder; pray, let it proceed. <stage>Moving as if to go.</stage> Dear me! I had almost forgotten to say the rest. He who adopted this <hi rend="ital">young man</hi> as his own son, the same was the guest of that Carthaginian, this <hi rend="ital">old man's</hi> father. He will come here to-day, and discover his daughters here, and this person, his cousin's son, as indeed I've learnt. He, <hi rend="ital">I say,</hi> who'll come to-day, will find his daughters and this his cousin's son. But after this, farewell!--attend; I'm off; I now intend to become another man<milestone n="125" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Become another man</lemma>:  He will go to dress for a part in the Play; that of Agorastocles, as some have suggested.</note>. As to what remains, some others remain who'll explain <hi rend="ital">all to you.</hi> I'll go <hi rend="ital">and</hi> dress. With kindly feelings do you <hi rend="ital">then</hi> recognize me. Farewell! <hi rend="ital">and</hi> give me your aid, that Salvation may prove propitious to you.
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="1">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="129" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter, from his house, AGORASTOCLES, followed by MILPHIO.</stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Full oft have I entrusted many matters to you, Milphio, <hi rend="ital">matters</hi> of doubt <hi rend="ital">and</hi> necessity, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> standing in need of good counsel, which you wisely, discreetly, cleverly, and skilfully have by your aid brought to completion for me. For which services I do confess that <hi rend="ital">both</hi> your liberty and many kind thanks are due unto you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> An old adage, if you timely introduce it, is a clever thing: but your compliments are to me what are wont to be called sheer nonsense, and, upon my faith, mere bagatelles<milestone n="138" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Mere bagatelles</lemma>:  <foreign lang="greek">*lh=roi.</foreign> This word almost exactly answers to the word "bagatelles," or "kickshaws," borrowed by us from the French. As to the origin of the word "gerr&aelig;," in the sense of "trifles," or "nonsense,' Festus gives the following anecdote:--"Osier-twigs, in bundles, were called 'gerr&aelig;.' When the Athenians were besieging the Syracusans, and were often calling aloud for these fascines, the besieged, in ridicule, used to cry out, 'gerr&aelig;, on which account that word came in use, to signify, in contempt,&gt; anything trifling."</note>. Just now, you are full of kind speeches towards me; yesterday, without hesitation, upon my back you wore out three bulls' hides  <hi rend="ital">with flogging.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> But if, being in love, I did anything by reason of my distraction, Milphio, it's <hi rend="ital">only</hi> reasonable that you should pardon me for it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I've seen nothing more <hi rend="ital">reasonable.</hi> I, too, am now dying for love; allow me to thrash you just as you did me, for no fault <hi rend="ital">at all;</hi> and then, after that, do you pardon me being <hi rend="ital">thus</hi> in love.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If you have a mind for it, or it gives you pleasure, I do permit it; tie me up, bind me, scourge me; I recommend you, I give you my permission.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> If, hereafter, you should revoke your permission, when you are unloosed, I myself should be hung up<milestone n="148" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Be hung up</lemma>:  "Pendeam." He alludes to the practice of tying slaves up by the hands for the purpose of being flogged.</note> <hi rend="ital">for punishment.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And would I venture to do that, to yourself espercially? On the contrary, if I see you but struck, it gives me pain immediately.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> To me, indeed, i' faith.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> No, to me. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I could prefer that <hi rend="ital">to be the case.</hi> But what now do you wish?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why need I tell a lie to you? I am desperately in love.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> My shoulder-blades feel that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> But I mean with this damsel, my neighbour Adelphasium, the elder Courtesan that belongs to this Procurer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> For my own part, I've heard that from yourself already.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'm on the rack with love for her. But than this Procurer Lycus, her master, not dirt <hi rend="ital">itself</hi> is more dirty.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Do you wish now to present him with some mischief?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I should like it. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why look <hi rend="ital">then,</hi> present him with me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Go and be hanged! </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> But tell me seriously, do you wish to present him with a plague?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I should like it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Well then, present him with this selfsame me; I'd cause him to be having both a mischief and a plague.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You are joking. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Should you like this very day, without risk to yourself, to make her free<milestone n="164" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To make her free</lemma>:  "Tuam libertam." "Your freed-woman;" you being the one to give her her liberty.</note>?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I should like it, Milphio.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'll manage for you to make her so. You have indoors three hundred golden Philippean pieces<milestone n="166" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Philippean pieces</lemma>:  The Philippean piece had the head of Philip of Macedon on it, and was in value about two guineas of our money.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Six hundred even. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Three hundred are enough.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> To do what <hi rend="ital">with them?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Hold your peace. This day I'll make you a present of the Procurer, whole, with all his household.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What to do? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You shall soon know. Collybiscus, your bailiff, is in the city just now. The Procurer doesn't know him. Do you fully understand?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I' faith, I understand <hi rend="ital">that;</hi> but what you are driving at I know not.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You don't know? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Not <hi rend="ital">I,</hi> faith.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> But I'll soon let you know. The gold shall be given him, for him to take to the Procurer, and say that he's a stranger from another city; that he's amorously inclined, and wishes to gratify his inclinations; that he wants free range to be found him, where he may secretly indulge his appetite, so that there may be no overlooker. The Procurer, greedy for the gold, will at once take him into his house; he'll conceal the man and the gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> The design pleases me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Do you <hi rend="ital">then</hi> enquire of him whether your slave hasn't come to him. He'll think that I am being sought for; immediately he'll say no to you. Have you any doubt but that the Procurer will at once have to double the gold for you, and be <hi rend="ital">considered</hi> to have stolen the man? Neither has he the means of raising it. When he comes to trial, the Pr&aelig;tor will award<milestone n="186" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pr&aelig;tor will award</lemma>:  In consequence of his being unable to pay the penalty or damages decreed against him.</note> his whole household to you. Thus with a pitfall shall we deceive the Procurer Lycus.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> The design pleases me. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Aye, when I've polished it up, you'll then say so still more even; now it's but in the rough.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'm going to the Temple of Venus, unless, Milphio, you wish for anything. It's the Aphrodisia<milestone n="191" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The Aphrodisia</lemma>:  The Aphrodisia were festivals periodically celebrated in honor of Venus or Aphrodite, in most of the towns of Greece. The worshippers were, however, mostly of the class of courtesans.</note> to-day.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I know.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I wish to amuse my eyes with the harlot finery.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Let's first proceed to this, the plan we have resolved upon. Let's go in-doors, that we may instruct Collybiscus, the bailiff, how to plant this cheatery.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Although Cupid has the sway in my heart, still I'll listen to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'll cause you to be glad it's done. <stage>AGORASTOCLES goes into his house.</stage> There is a speck of love upon this man's breast, which cannot by any means be washed out without great harm; this Lycus, too, the Procurer, is such a wicked person, against whom the engine of mischief is now well aimed, which before long I shall discharge from my battery<milestone n="202" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From my battery</lemma>:  "Balistario." According to Lipsius, "balistarium" was the same as the balista itself; while Turnebus thinks it was the place where the 'balista" was mounted.</note>. But see, here's Adelphasium coming out, and Anterastylis. The first is the one who renders my master distracted. But I'll call him out. <stage>Goes to the door and calls.</stage> Hallo! Agorastocles, come out of doors if you would see most joyous sports!
<stage>in haste, from the house.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What's this bustle, Milphio?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to the door of LYCUS'S <hi rend="ital">house</hi></stage>. Why, here's your mistress, if you'd like to see her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> O may the Gods bestow many a blessing on you, for having presented to me a sight so charming as this! <stage>They stand apart.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="210" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter ADELPHASIUM, ANTERASTYLIS, and an ATTENDANT.</stage>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> The man who wants to find abundance of employment for himself--a woman and a ship, these two things, let him procure; for no two things do produce more trouble, if, perchance, you begin to equip them; neither are these two things ever equipped enough, nor is the largest amount of equipment sufficient for them. And as I mention these things, from experience at home do I now say thus; for we two, even from daybreak up to the present hour of the day, have never ceased either washing, or scrubbing, or rubbing, or dressing, smoothing, polishing, painting, trimming, with all our might, and at the same time the two maid-servants, that have been provided for each of us, have been giving us their assistance in washing <hi rend="ital">and</hi> cleaning; and in carrying water two men have become quite weary. Fie upon it! how great a plague there is in one female. But if <hi rend="ital">there are</hi> two, I know full well that they are able to give to any one, the mightiest nation whatsoever, more trouble than enough, in being night and day, always, at all hours, dressing, washing, rubbing, polishing. In fine, there's no moderation in women, nor do we understand how ever to set a limit to washing and scrubbing. But she who is washed clean, unless she is thoroughly dressed, in my notion at least, is just as though she were dirty.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> I really wonder, sister, that you talk in this fashion; you who are so knowing, and discreet, and clever; for when with all care we have ourselves in trim, hardly and with difficulty do we find poor pitiful admirers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Such is the fact; but still reflect upon this one thing; a limit is best to be observed in all things, sister; all things in excess give too much trouble to mortals of themselves.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Sister, prithee, do reflect that we are accounted just in the same way as pickled salt-fish<milestone n="240" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pickled salt-fish</lemma>:  "Salsa muriatica." Literally. "the pickle of salt-fish," which is supposed by some to have been the thunny</note> is thought of--without any relish and without sweetness; unless full oft and long it is soaked in water, it smells badly, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> is salt, so that you cannot touch it. Just so are we. Women of this class are utterly tasteless, and devoid of grace, without dress and expense.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. She surely is a cook, Agorastocles, according to my notion; she knows how to soak pickled fish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>pushing him away</stage>. Why <hi rend="ital">are you thus</hi> troublesome?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Sister, do, there's a dear, forbear. It's quite sufficient for others to say that to us, not to be ourselves as well proclaiming our foibles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> I'll have done, then.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I thank you: but now answer me this; are all things here which ought to be provided for propitiating the Gods?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> I've taken care of everything.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. How charming and joyous a day, and full of delight, worthy of Venus, by my troth, whose Aphrodisia are <hi rend="ital">celebrated</hi> to-day!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Any thanks <hi rend="ital">for me,</hi> for calling you out of doors? Oughtn't I now to be presented with a cask of old wine? Say it shall be given. Don't you answer me? His tongue has fallen out, I imagine. What, plague on it, have you been struck with amazement standing here? <stage>He shakes him.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Do let me love on; don't disturb me, and do hold your peace.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I'll hold my peace.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. If you had held your peace, why then that "I'll hold my peace" would not have been in existence.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Let's go, my sister. <stage>She moves.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> How now--why, prithee, are you now hastening that way?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Do you ask me? Because our master is waiting for us at the Temple of Venus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Let him wait, i' faith. Do you stay; there's a crowd just now at the altar. Do you wish yourself to be pushed about among those common prostitutes, the doxies of bakers, the cast-offs of the spelt-bread sellers; wretched creatures, daubed over with grease<milestone n="267" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Daubed over with grease</lemma>:  "Sch&oelig;no." This is, by some, thought to have been a rank oil extracted from rushes. Meursius, however, ridicules the idea of an oil being made from rushes, and reads c&oelig;no, "dirt," in the present passage.</note>, followers of poor slaves, <hi rend="ital">who</hi> stink for you of their stable and stall<milestone n="268" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Of their stable and stall</lemma>:  She seems to refer to the lowest class of courtesans, and their seats in the prostitutes' sheds (mentioned by Ballio in the Pseudolus, l. 214) where they were exposed by the "lenones' to the public gaze.</note>, their seats and very sheds; whom, in fact, not a single freeman has ever touched or taken home <hi rend="ital">with him,</hi> the twopenny strumpets<milestone n="270" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Twopenny strumpets</lemma>:  "Diobolaria." Literally, "hired for a couple of obols."</note> of dirty trumpery slaves?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Away with you to utter perdition! Do you dare, then, to despise the slaves, you hussey? As if she was a beauty, as if kings were in the habit of making her their choice. A monstrosity of a woman! Diminutive as she is, she does spit out such mighty words--seven nights with whom I wouldn't purchase at a cupful of vapour.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Immortal and omnipotent Divinities, what is there among you more beauteous? What have you that I should deem you more immortal than I am myself. in beholding with my eyes these delights so great? But Venus is not Venus; for my own part, her will I worship as Venus; that she may love me and prove propitious. Milphio!--hallo! Milphio, where are you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. See, here I am with you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. But I want you boiled<milestone n="279" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I want you boiled</lemma>:  He puns upon the word "assum," which Milphio uses. He intends it to signify "here am I." But as it may also mean the neuter of the participle "assus," "roasted," Agorastocles chooses to take the sentence in the latter sense, as meaning "here I am roasted;" and answers, "I'd rather you were boiled."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why really, master, you are making merry.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why, it was from yourself I learnt all this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. What, even to be in love with her whom you have never touched? Really, that is nonsense.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I' faith, the Gods as well do I love and fear from whom, nevertheless, I keep off my hands.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Alas! upon my word, when I look at the dress of us both, I'm grieved at the way we are dressed out.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Why really, it's quite in a proper style; for our master's gain and our own we are dressed quite well enough. For no profits can result, if the outlay exceeds them, sister; therefore, that is better to be had which is enough, than that which is more than enough.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. So may the Gods love me, may she love me (I had rather she than the Gods), Milphio; why, this woman has it in her power to force a flint-stone to be in love with her.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Upon my faith, in that you certainly tell no lie, for you are more senseless than a flint-stone to be in love with her.&lt;</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. But consider <hi rend="ital">this,</hi> will you; I've never soiled her<milestone n="291" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Never soiled her</lemma>:  There is a puerile and rather Indelicate play in this line and the next two upon the resemblance of the word "limus," "mud," and "limo," "to rub." An attempt has been made to give something analogous in the Translatio"</note> with a kiss. MIL. <stage>apart</stage>. I'll run, then, somewhere to a fish-pond or a pool, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> fetch some soil.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. What need is there of that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I'll tell you; to soil her lips and yours.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. To utter perdition with you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. For my part, I'm there <hi rend="ital">already.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Do you persist?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I'll hold my tongue.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. But I wish you <hi rend="ital">to do so</hi> always.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why really, master, you challenge me at my own game, and <hi rend="ital">still</hi> you make fun of me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> At present, sister, I suppose you think yourself quite well enough drest; but when the instances of other courtesans are compared, then you will be having the heartache, if perchance you should see any one more nicely drest.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Envy was never inbred in me, my sister, nor yet spitefulness: I had rather by far that I was adorned with a good disposition than with gold; gold is met with by luck, a good disposition <hi rend="ital">is found</hi> by nature. I very much prefer for myself to be called good than fortunate. It more befits a courtesan to show modesty than purple; and more does it become a courtesan to show modesty than golden <hi rend="ital">jewels.</hi> Evil habits soil a fine dress more than mud; good manners, by their deeds, easily set off a lowly garb.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart to MILPHIO</stage>. How now, you; would you like to play a merry and a frolicsome prank?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I should like.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Can you, <hi rend="ital">then,</hi> give attention to me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I can.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Be off home, and go hang yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why? AGO. <stage>apart</stage>. Because you'll never again hear so many words as sweet <hi rend="ital">as these.</hi> What need have you to live? Only listen to me, and go hang yourself.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage> Why yes, if, like grapes that are drying<milestone n="311" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Grapes that are drying</lemma>:  "Uva passa" were grapes hung up in the sun to dry, and then scalded, for the purpose of being used as raisins, or for making sweet wine.</note>, you'll hang together with me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. But I do love her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. But I, to eat and drink.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> <stage>to her SISTER</stage>. How now, you? How say you--?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> What is it you ask <hi rend="ital">me?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Do you see? My eyes which were full of dirt, are they clear now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> <stage>looking close at her eyes</stage>. Why, even still there's a little dirt in the middle of the eye.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Lend me your right hand, please.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. And would you really touch or rub her eyes with unwashed hands?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Too great indolence has taken possession of us to-day.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> For what reason, prithee?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Why, because we didn't come long since, before daylight, to the Temple of Venus, to be the first to place fire upon her altar.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> O, there's no need for doing that; those who have faces suited for the night <hi rend="ital">only,</hi> make haste to go and sacrifice by night; before Venus is awake, they are already hurrying with all haste to sacrifice; for if they were to come when Venus is awake, so ugly are they, upon my faith, I do believe they would drive Venus herself away from the Temple.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Milphio! MIL. <stage>apart</stage>. Poor Milphio, i' faith! What do you want with me now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Troth now, prithee, do mark how she speaks honied wine!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>, Nothing at all, except tile- cakes<milestone n="324" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Nothing at all, except tile-cakes</lemma>:  "Laterculi" were sweet cakes on biscuits, shaped like a tile or brick. The things here named were probably articles of homely diet, compared with honied wine.</note>, sesamum, and poppies, wheat and parched nuts.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Do I seem at all <hi rend="ital">to be</hi> in love?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. <hi rend="ital">In love</hi> to your loss, a thing that Mercury is by no means in love with<milestone n="326" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Mercury is by no means in love with</lemma>:  As being the God of Merchandize and Profit.</note>.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why, really, by my troth, it befits no lover to be in love with pelf.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Let's go, my sister. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Do, please, just as you like. Follow <hi rend="ital">me</hi> this way.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> I'll follow. <stage>They move.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. They are going. What if we accost them?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. You accost them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>going towards them</stage>. In the first place, health to you, the elder; and you, the younger, health to you in the second degree of estimation; <stage>to the ATTENDANT</stage> you, the third, health to you, without any place in my estimation.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ATT.</speaker><p> In that case, faith, I've wasted my oil and my labour.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to ADELPHASIUM</stage>. Whither are you betaking yourself?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> What I? To the Temple of Venus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why thither? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> To propitiate Venus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> How now? Is she angry, <hi rend="ital">then?</hi> Upon my faith, she is propitious. I will even answer for her. <stage>Stands before her.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> What are you about? Prithee, why are you annoying me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Thus cruel? Alas! </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Let me go away, I beg of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why in such a hurry? There's a crowd there at present. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I know it; there are other females there whom I wish to see, and <hi rend="ital">by whom</hi> to be seen.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> How can it give you pleasure to look at ugly people, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> to afford one <hi rend="ital">so</hi> beauteous to be looked at?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Because to-day, at the Temple of Venus, there's a fair for the courtesans; there the dealers meet; there I wish myself to be shown.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> To wares unsaleable, its right to entice the buyer of one's own accord; good wares easily meet with a purchaser, although they may be placed in concealment. How say you? When, at my house here <stage>pointing</stage> will you lay your head and side by me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> On the day on which Orcus sends away the dead<milestone n="343" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Orcus sends away the dead</lemma>:  Which, of course, means never.</note> from Acheron. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I've got in-doors I know not how many golden coins in a state of madness.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Bring them to me; I'll make their madness pretty soon come to an end.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>with indignation</stage>. A nice one, upon my word!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Away to utter and extreme perdition with you, and go and be hanged!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>aside to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. The more I look at her, the more insignificant<milestone n="347" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The more insignificant</lemma>:  "Nimbata." According to some Commentators, this word is a substantive here, and signifies a "slight fillet," of the same colour with the hair which the women used to wear upon the forehead; the idea of Turnebus, however, that it is an adjective, signifying "cloud-like," seems more likely to be correct.</note> she is, and a mere bauble.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Keep your prating to yourself; I'm tired of it. <stage>To ADELPHASIUM.</stage> Come, do lift up this outer garment. <stage>Raises it from the ground, and attempts to embrace her.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I'm in a state of purity<milestone n="349" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A state of purity</lemma>:  This she says, probably, because she is especially careful to avoid pollution, by contact with the male sex, when on the eve of worshipping the Goddess in her Temple.</note>; prithee forbear to touch me, Agorastocles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What am I to do, then?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> If you are wise, you may be saving yourself your anxiety.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What? Me not be anxious on your account? What are you about, Milphio? <stage>Beckons to him.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. See now, my aversion, <hi rend="ital">this</hi><milestone n="351" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">My aversion, this</lemma>:  "Odium meum." He forgets that Adelphasium is only the <hi rend="ital">innocent</hi> cause of his master's anxiety.</note>. <stage>Aloud.</stage> What is it you want with me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to ADELPHASIUM</stage>. Why is she angry with me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why is she angry with you? Why should I trouble myself about that? For that is rather your own concern.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> On my word, it's all over with you this very instant, if you don't make her as smooth for me as the sea is at the time when the halcyon<milestone n="355" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">when the halcyon</lemma>: See the note to the Casina, l. 26.</note> is rearing her young ones there.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What am I to do?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Entreat <hi rend="ital">her,</hi> soothe, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> flatter <hi rend="ital">her.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'll do so with all diligence; but see, please, that you don't afterwards be giving this ambassador <hi rend="ital">of yours</hi> a dressing with your fists.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'll not do so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> <stage>to her SISTER</stage>. Let's now begone. <stage>AGORASTOCLES stands before her.</stage> Do you detain me still? You act badly; you make me many fair promises<milestone n="359" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Many fair promises</lemma>:  The semicolon seems to be more appropriately placed before than after "ex multis."</note>; of those many, the whole come to nothing at all. Not once, but a hundred times, have you sworn to give me my freedom. While depending on you, I have neither anywhere procured any other resources for myself, nor is this <hi rend="ital">assistance of yours</hi> at all visible. And thus none the less am I still a slave. Move on, sister. <stage>To AGORASTOCLES.</stage> Get you gone from me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Utterly undone! Come now, Milphio, what are you about? <stage>Points at ADELPHASIUM.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>addressing ADELPHASIUM</stage>. My joy, my delight, my life, my pleasure, apple of my eye, my little lip, my health, my <hi rend="ital">sweet</hi> kiss, my honey, my heart, my biestings, my cream-cheese----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. Am I to allow these things to be said in my presence? I'm quite distracted, wretch that I am, if I don't order him at full speed to be hurried off to the executioner in a chariot and four!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>to ADELPHASIUM</stage>. Prithee, for my sake, don't be angry with my master. I'll make----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Let me alone. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You are too cross. He'll pay the money for you, and make you a citizen of Attica<milestone n="371" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A citizen of Attica</lemma>:  Plautus evidently makes a slip here, forgetting that Calydon was in &AElig;tolia, and not in Attica.</note>, and a free woman.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> <stage>to MILPHIO, <hi rend="ital">who is standing before her</hi></stage>, But why don't you let me go away? What is it you want? Just as he wishes me well, in like manner do you wish me well.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> If, indeed, he has deceived you before, from this time forward he shall be truthful to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Get you gone hence, will you, <hi rend="ital">you</hi> trepanner.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'll obey <hi rend="ital">you.</hi> But on what terms--do you understand? Do let me prevail upon you; do let me take you by <hi rend="ital">those</hi> little ears<milestone n="375" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">By those little ears</lemma>:  It was a common practice to take hold of the ears of the person kissed. The Greeks called this practice <foreign lang="greek">xutra\,</foreign> because it resembled the mode of taking up a kind of jug, which was so called, by its ears.</note>; do let me give you a kiss. By my troth, I shall now set him a&gt; weeping, if I don't make you kind; and (unless I do make you kind he  <hi rend="ital">certainly</hi> will do it) I'm dreadfully afraid lest he should beat me. I know the harsh manners of this crabbed man. Wherefore, my delight, pray do let me prevail upon you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. I'm not a man worth threepence<milestone n="380" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Woth threepence</lemma>:  "Trioboli." Literally, "of three obols"</note>, if I don't tear out the eyes and teeth of that whip-scoundrel. <stage>He beats MILPHIO.</stage> There's your delight for you! There's your honey! There's your heart! There are your biestings<milestone n="382" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Your biestings</lemma>:  "Colostra." This is the first milk after a cow has calved. It is much esteemed for its richness.</note>! There's your health! There's your <hi rend="ital">sweet</hi> kiss! <stage>Giving him a blow at each sentence.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Master, you are rendering yourself guilty of impiety! You are beating an ambassador.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> More than that even still. <stage>Beating him again.</stage> I shall now add the apple of the eye, the little lip too, and the tongue.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> When will you be making an end?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Was it in that fashion I requested you to plead <hi rend="ital">for me?</hi> </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> How then was I to plead?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you ask me <hi rend="ital">that?</hi> Why thus you should have said, you scoundrel: "his" delight, I do entreat of you, "his" honey, "his" heart, "his" little lip, "his" tongue, "his" <hi rend="ital">sweet</hi> kiss, "his" biestings, "his" sweet cream-cheese, you whip-scoundrel. All these things which you spoke of as yours, you should have mentioned as mine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>addressing ADELPHASIUM</stage>. By my troth, I do entreat you, his delight and my own aversion; his full-bosomed mistress, my enemy and evil-wisher; his eye, my eyesore; his honey, my gall--don't you be angry with him; or, if that cannot be, do take a rope and hang yourself, with your master and your household: for I see that henceforth, on your account, I shall have to live upon sighing; and as it is, I've already got my back about as hard with weals as an oyster-shell, by reason of your amours.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Prithee, do you wish me to hinder him from beating you, rather than that he should not prove untrue towards me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> <stage>to her SISTER</stage>. Do answer him in somewhat kindly terms, there's a dear, that he mayn't be annoying to us; for he's detaining us from our purpose.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> That's true. This one fault more will I pardon you for, Agorastocles. I am not angry.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You are not? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I am not.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> That I may believe you, give me a kiss then.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I'll give you one by-and-by, when I return from the sacrifice. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Be off, then, in all haste.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Follow me, sister. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And do you hear too? Pay all compliments to Venus in my name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I'll pay them. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Listen to this, too----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> What is it? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Perform the ceremony in few words. And do you hear? Look back <hi rend="ital">at me.</hi> <stage>She looks back.</stage> She did look back. By my troth, I trust that Venus will do the same for you. <stage>ADELPHASIUM, ANTERASTYLIS, and ATTENDANT go into the Temple of Venus.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="3">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="410" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>AGORASTOCLES and MILPHIO.</stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What now do you advise me <hi rend="ital">to do,</hi> Milphio?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> To give me a beating, and <hi rend="ital">then</hi> have an auction<milestone n="409" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Have an auction</lemma>:  Some Commentators have fancied that a play is intended upon the resemblance of the word "auctio" in this line and "anctor" in the preceding one.</note>; for <stage>pointing to the house</stage> really, upon my faith, with utter impunity you might put up this house for sale.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why so? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> For the greater part you make your dwelling in my mouth<milestone n="411" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Dwelling in my mouth</lemma>:  He says that his master may sell his own house, for he seems to have taken up his abode in his (Milphio's) mouth m reference to his having continually to speak of him or to him.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do have done with those expressions.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What now do you wish?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I just now gave three hundred Philippeans to the bailiff Collybiscus, before you called me out of doors. I now adjure you, Milphio, by this right hand, and by this left hand its sister, and by your eyes, and by my passion, and by my own Adelphasium, and by your liberty<milestone n="418" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">By your liberty</lemma>:  His liberty being a thing non-existent.</note>----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why, now you adjure me by nothing at all.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> My dear little Milphio, my <hi rend="ital">kind</hi> occasion, my safeguard, do what you promised me you would do, that I may prove the ruin of this Procurer.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why, that's very easy <hi rend="ital">to be done.</hi> Be off, bring here with you your witnesses; meanwhile, in-doors I'll forthwith provide your bailiff with my disguise and stratagems. Make haste and be off.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I fly. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> That's more my part<milestone n="425" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">More my part</lemma>:  He alludes to the common trick of slaves taking to flight.</note> than yours.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Should I not, should I not, if you effect this adroitly<milestone n="426" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Effect this adroitly</lemma>:  Plautus designedly makes Agorastocles talk in this disjointed and unintelligible manner, both for the purpose of showing his own distraction and teasing Milphio. He does not, however, seem likely to hurt his own interest by his promises. Given connectedly, his words stand thus (as given in a Note to Warner's Translation): "Should I not give you your liberty to-day, if you do what you have promised--if you impose upon the pander, and deliver Adelphasium to me--I do not deserve so many Philippeans of gold as there are dead men in the shades, waves in the sea, or star in the sky."</note>----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Only do begone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Ought I not this very day----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Only do be off. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> To give you freedom</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Only do begone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> By my troth, I should not deserve-ah!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Bah! Only do be off.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> As many as are the dead in Acheron----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Will you, then, move off?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Nor yet as many as there are waves in the sea----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Are you going to move off?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Nor as many as there are clouds----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Do you persist in going on <hi rend="ital">this way?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Nor as there are stars in heaven----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Do you persist in dinning my ears?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Neither this thing nor that; nor yet, indeed, seriously speaking--nor, by my faith, indeed. What need is there of words? And why not?--a thing that in one word--here we may say anything we please--and yet, i' faith, not seriously in reality. D'ye see how 'tis? So may the Gods bless me!--do you wish me to tell you in honest truth? A thing that here we may between ourselves--so <hi rend="ital">help</hi> me Jupiter---- Do you see how? Look you--do you believe what I tell you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> If I cannot make you go away, I shall go away myself: for really, upon my faith, there's need of an &OElig;dipus<milestone n="441" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Need of an &OElig;dipus</lemma>:  Juno, in her displeasure against the city of Thebes, sent the Sphinx, in order to wreak her vengeance against the inhabitants. This was a monster with the face and speech of a woman, the wings of a bird, and the rest of the body resembling that of a dog or a lion. The monster proposed enigmatical questions to all with whom it met, and those who could not explain them it devoured. On the Oracle being consulted, they were informed that they would not get rid of the monster unless they could find out the meaning of a certain enigma, which was, "What is that animal that has four feet in the morning, two at noon, and three at night?" &OElig;dipus, at length, explained this as meaning a man, who crawls on all-fours during infancy, during manhood stands on two legs, and, when old, makes use of a stick as a third leg to support him. On hearing this, the monster, in despair, knocked out its brains against a rock.</note> as a diviner for this speech <hi rend="ital">of yours, him</hi> who was the interpreter to the Sphinx. <stage>He goes into the house of AGORASTOCLES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He has gone off in a passion; now must I beware, lest, through my own fault, I place an impediment in the way of my love. I'll go and fetch the witnesses, since love commands me, a free man, to be obedient to my own slave. <stage>(Exit.)</stage>
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="2">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="449" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYCUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. May all the Gods render him unfortunate, should any Procurer, after this day, ever immolate any victim to Venus, or should any one sacrifice a single grain of frankincense. For wretched I, this day, have sacrificed to my most wrathful Deities<milestone n="450" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">My most wrathful Deities</lemma>:  These, probably, were Mercury, the God of Profit. and Venus, the Goddess of Lust.</note> six lambs, and still I could not manage to make Venus to be propitious unto me. Since I could not appease her, forthwith I departed thence in a passion; I forbade the entrails to be cut, and would not examine them. Inasmuch as the soothsayer pronounced them not propitious, I deemed the Goddess not deserving. By these means I fairly played a trick upon the greedy Venus. When, that which was enough, she would not have to be enough, I made a pause. 'Tis thus I act, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> thus it befits me <hi rend="ital">to act.</hi> I'll make the other Gods and Goddesses henceforth more contented, and less greedy, when they know how the Procurer put a trick upon Venus. The soothsayer, in manner right worthy of him, a fellow not worth threepence, said that in all the entrails misfortune and loss were portended to me, and that the Gods were angry with me. In what matter either divine or human is it right for me to put trust in him? Just after that, a mina of silver was given me. But where, pray, has this Captain stopped just now, who gave it me, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> whom I've invited to breakfast? But look! here he comes.
<stage>ANTHEMONIDES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> So, as I began to tell you, <hi rend="ital">you</hi> sorry pimp, about that Pentethronic battle<milestone n="471" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pentethronic battle</lemma>:  Much learning and discussion have been wasted on this word, which probably is only intended as coined by the Captain, as a high-sounding word without any meaning.</note>, in which, with my own hands, in one day, I slew sixty thousand flying men.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Heyday! Flying men? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Certainly I do affirm it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Prithee, are there anywhere men that fly?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> There were; but I slew them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> How could you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> I'll tell you. I gave birdlime and slings to my troops; beneath it they laid leaves of coltsfoot<milestone n="478" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Leaves of coltsfoot</lemma>:  The hairy surface of the leaves of coltsfoot would serve to keep the pellets of birdlime together at the moment of being nurled from the sling.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> For what purpose?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> That the birdlime mightn't adhere to the slings.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Proceed. <stage>Aside.</stage> I faith, you do lie most egregiously. <stage>Aloud.</stage> What after that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> They placed pretty large pellets of birdlime in their slings: with which I ordered them to be taken aim at as they flew. Why many words? Each one did they hit with the birdlime-they fell to the ground as thick as pears. As each one dropped, I straightway pierced him through the brain with his own feathers, just like a turtle-dove.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> By my troth, if ever this did take place, then may Jupiter make me to be ever sacrificing, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> never propitiating him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> And don't you.believe me in this?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I do believe, in the same degree that it is proper that I should be believed. Come, let's go in-doors, until the entrails are brought home.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> I wish to relate to you a single battle more.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I don't care about it. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Do listen.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Upon my faith, no.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Why then I'll break your head this distant, if you don't listen, or else be off to utter perdition!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'd sooner go to utter perdition!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Are you determined <hi rend="ital">then?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Determined. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> In that case, do you, then, upon <hi rend="ital">this</hi> lucky day, the Aphrodisia, make over to me the younger one of your courtesans.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> The sacred ceremony has <hi rend="ital">by its omens</hi> been to me today of such a nature--I put off all serious matters from today until another day. I am resolved to make it really a holiday. Now let's go hence in-doors. Follow me this way.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> I follow. For this day, then, I'm out on hire to you. <stage>They go into the house of LYCUS.</stage>
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="3">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="504" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter AGORASTOCLES, and several ASSISTANTS walking behind him.</stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> So may the Deities love me, there's nothing more annoying than a tardy friend, especially to a man in love, who's in a hurry in everything that he does; just as I'm leading on these assistants, fellows of most crawling step; they are more slow than merchant-ships in a calm sea. And upon my faith, I really did on purpose wave my aged friends; I knew they were too slow through their years; I apprehended delay to my passion; in vain I selected for myself these <hi rend="ital">young</hi> fellows on their preferment, timber-legged, most tardy <hi rend="ital">chaps.</hi> Well <stage>turning round to them</stage>, if you are going to come to-day, get on, or get off hence to utter perdition! Is this the way it befits friends to give their assistance to a person in love? Why sure, this pace was bolted through a fine floursieve<milestone n="511" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Fine fiour-sieve</lemma>:  He probably alludes to the time that the fine hour takes before it gets down to the holes of the sieve through which it has to pass. Some Commentators, however, fancy that it is a general allusion to the handmill, and that he means to tell them that surely they must have lost all their activity by their punishment at the mill.</note>; unless you have been practising in fetters to creep along thus with this step.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Hark you! although we seem to you of the commonalty and poor, if you don't speak us fair, <hi rend="ital">you</hi> rich man of highest rank, we are in the habit of boldly playing the mischief with the rich man; we are under no engagement to you, about what it is that you love or hate. When we paid money for our freedom<milestone n="516" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Paid money for our freedom</lemma>:  This passage shows that they had formerly been slaves. It is not improbable that numbers of liberated slaves Were always to be found in the Forum, ready for money to offer their services as witnesses of any transaction, without reference to its morality. They are here called "advocati;" which literally means, "persons summoned to one's assistance." Slaves were not allowed to give evidence against freemen.</note>, we paid our own, not yours; it's right that we should be under no restraint. We value you at nought; don't you fancy that we've been made over as slaves to your passion. It's proper for free men to go through the city at a moderate pace; I deem it like a slave to be running along in a bustle. Especially when the state is at peace and the enemies are slain, it is not decent to make a tumult. But if you were for making greater haste, you ought to have brought us here as assistants the day before. Don't you fancy it--not any one of us will this day be running through the streets, nor yet shall the people pelt us with stones for madmen.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> But if I had said that I was taking you to a Temple<milestone n="527" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To a Temple</lemma>:  He refers to the practice of worshippers inviting their friends to the Temples, to join them in eating the portions that were left after the sacrifice. See the Rudens, where this practice is more fully referred to "In &aelig;dem" may, however, possibly mean "to my house."</note> to breakfast, you would have surpassed a stag in speed, or a man on stilts in your steps. Now, because I have said that I am taking you as my assistants and witnesses, you are gouty, and in the slowness of your pace have been outdoing the snail.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Why, really, is there not good cause for running swiftly, where you are to drink <hi rend="ital">and</hi> eat at another man's expense as much as you please, until you are full, what you need never return against your will to your host, at whose expense you have been eating? But still,in some way or other, although we are poor men, we have at home something to eat; don't you browbeat us in such a contemptuous way. Whatever that very little is, that <hi rend="ital">little</hi> of ours is all at home; we neither dun any one ourselves, nor does any one dun us. Not one of us is going to burst the veins of his lungs for your sake.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You are too warm; really, I said this to you in joke.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Consider it said in joke as well what we have said to you in answer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Troth now, prithee, do give me this aid of yours <hi rend="ital">like</hi> a fly-boat, not a merchant-ship. Do hobble along at least, for I do not ask you to hurry.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> If you wish to do anything quietly and leisurely, we lend our aid; if you are in a hurry, it would be better for you to hire runners<milestone n="544" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To hire runners</lemma>:  Cursores. See the Notes to the Trinummus, l. 1023.</note> <hi rend="ital">as your</hi> assistants.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You understand (the matter I've informed you of), that I have need of your assistance with regard to this Procurer, who has so long trifled with me in my amour; that a scheme is to be planned against him about the gold and. my servant.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> All that we know already, if these Spectators know. For the sake of these Spectators it is that this Play is now being acted. 'Twere better for you to inform them, that when you do anything, they may know what it is you are doing. Don't you trouble about us; we know the whole matter; since we all learnt it together in company with yourself, so that we can answer you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Such really is the fact; but come, that I may be sure then that you know it, repeat the matter at length, and tell me what I told you just now.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Are you trying in this way whether we know? Do you suppose we don't remember how you have given three hundred Philippeans to Collybiscus your bailiff, for him to bring here to the Procurer, your enemy, and to pretend that he is a foreigner from a distance, from another city? When he has brought them, you'll go there to seek your servant together with the money.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You remember it by heart; you have saved me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> He'll be for denying it; he'll suppose your Milphio is being looked for. He'll have to pay double all the money stolen; the Procurer will be adjudged to you. In this matter you wish us to be your witnesses.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You've got the matter <hi rend="ital">fast.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> I' faith, hardly with the tips<milestone n="564" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Hardly with the tips</lemma>:  He plays upon the two meanings of "rem"--"the business in hand," or "money" or "property." Agorastocles means it in the former sense, but the assistants take it in the latter, and probably allude to the smallness of their pay.</note> of our fingers, indeed; it is so very small a one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> This must be done quickly and with expedition. Make as much haste, then, as you can.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <stage>moving as though going</stage>. Kindly fare you well, then; it's better for you to provide some active assistants, we are <hi rend="ital">but</hi> slow ones.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You move very well<milestone n="567" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">You move very well</lemma>:  "Optume itis, pessume--dicitis." Rost suggests that the meaning of these words is, "You'll do well in going away, for you are very abusive." The passage has puzzled many of the Commentators.</note>. <stage>Aside.</stage> <hi rend="ital">But</hi> very badly do you speak me, faith. <stage>Aloud.</stage> Moreover, I could wish your thighs to fall down into your ankles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> And, i' faith, we that your tongue <hi rend="ital">had fallen</hi> into your loins, and your eyes upon the ground.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Heyday! it's not for you to be angry at what I said in joke. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Nor for you, indeed, to be speaking ill to your friends in joke.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Drop this. What I want to do, you understand.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We know full well: to undo the perjured Procurer, it's that you wish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You've got the matter right. See, Milphio and the bailiff are opportunely coming out together. He's coming rigged out like a nobleman, and appropriately, for the plot.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="578" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter MILPHIO and COLLYBISCUS, from the house of AGORASTOCLES, dressed as a person of quality.</stage>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Have you now got your instructions by heart?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Nicely.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Take care you understand them, please.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> What need is there of talking? I won't let my own legs understand<milestone n="577" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">My own legs understand</lemma>:  "Callum aprugnum callere &aelig;que non sinam." For a literal translation of this pun, see the Persa, l. 306, and the Note to the passage.</note> as well. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Only take you care that your speeches are learnt by heart for this plot.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Why, upon my faith, I am more perfect than tragic or comic actors <hi rend="ital">are.</hi> </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You are a capital fellow.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to the ASSISTANTS</stage>. Let's go nearer <hi rend="ital">to them.</hi> <stage>Accosting MILPHIO and COLLYBISCUS.</stage> Here are the witnesses.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. Really you could not have brought as many men better suited for this purpose; for not one of them is tongue-tied <hi rend="ital">as a witness</hi><milestone n="582" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Tongue-tied as a witness</lemma>:  "Nefastus," forbidden to give evidence as witness, either through incompetency as being slaves, or through infamy of character.</note>; they are genuine men of the law-courts; there they take up their abode; there you may see them more frequently than the Pr&aelig;tor. At this very time there are no better cookers-up of a lawsuit<milestone n="584" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Cookers-up of a lawsuit</lemma>:  "Juris coctiores." "Jus" means, according to the context, "law" or "justice." As the same word also means "broth," Milphio puns upon this double meaning, in conjunction with the word "coctior," "better versed in."</note>, to stir up litigation, than are these men; for they, if there is no litigation, sow litigation.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> May the Gods confound you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You I really do commend, inasmuch as, whoever you are, still you act both worthily and kindly in giving your aid to my master <hi rend="ital">thus</hi> in love. <stage>To AGORASTOCLES.</stage> But do they now know what the business is?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> The whole matter, <hi rend="ital">all</hi> in its order.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> In that case, do you, then, give me your attention. Do you know this Procurer Lycus? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Perfectly.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> But, upon my faith, I don't know him, of what appearance he is. I wish that you would point this fellow out to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We'll take all care: we've been instructed quite enough. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to COLLYBISCUS</stage>. He has got three hundred pieces counted out.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Then it's right, Agorastocles, that we should see this gold, that we may know what to say by-and-by as our testimony.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Come <hi rend="ital">and</hi> look at it. <stage>Opens the bag which COLLYBISCUS <hi rend="ital">holds in his hand.</hi></stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to the AUDIENCE</stage>. Undoubtedly it's gold, Spectators--playhouse <hi rend="ital">gold</hi><milestone n="595" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Playhouse gold</lemma>:  He alludes to the practice of using lupines in their purses on the stage, to represent gold. They were probably used for this purpose on account of their yellow colour.</note>; upon this, soaked <hi rend="ital">in water,</hi> in foreign lands, the cattle become fat<milestone n="596" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Cattle become fat.</lemma>:  He means, that in other conntries than Greece lupines are used for the purpose on fattening cattle.</note>: but, for the carrying out of this design, 'tis real Philippean <hi rend="ital">gold.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We'll make believe it is so. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> But do you make believe as though I were a foreigner.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Just so; and, in fact, as though you, on your arrival to-day, had asked us to show you a spot for freedom and pleasure; where you might wench, drink, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> live like a Greek.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Dear me! Crafty fellows, upon my faith!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> But it was I who instructed them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <hi rend="ital">And</hi> who you, in your turn?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Come, be of' in-doors, Agorastocles, lest the Procurer should see you together with me, and some accident might befall our plan.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> This person is extremely prudent. <stage>To AGORASTOCLES.</stage> Do as he bids you. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Let's be off. <stage>To the ASSISTANTS.</stage> But you-has enough been said?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Do you be off.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'm off. Immortal Gods, I beg----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Nay, but why don't you be off? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'm off.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> You do wisely. <stage>AGORASTOCLES and MILPHIO go into the house.</stage> Hush! be quiet.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> What's the matter?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> This door <stage>pointing to the door of the house of LYCUS</stage> was guilty of a great indecency just now.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> What indecency is that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> It rumbled aloud. AsSIST. May the Deities confound you! Get you behind us.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Be it so. <stage>Goes behind them.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We'll walk first.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. They do what town-fellows are in the habit of doing: they put <hi rend="ital">worthy</hi> men behind themselves.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to the PROCURER'S <hi rend="ital">house</hi></stage>. That man that's coming out is the Procurer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> He's a <hi rend="ital">real</hi> good one; for he's like a bad man<milestone n="611" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Like a bad man</lemma>:  He means that the worse the man, the better the Procurer.</note>. Even now, as he comes forth, I'll suck out his blood at this distance.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="3">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="615" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYCUS, from his house.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>speaking to ANTHEMONIDES, <hi rend="ital">within</hi></stage>. I'll return here this moment, Captain. I wish to find us some fitting guests, to join us. Meanwhile, they'll bring the entrails; and at the same time, the women, I suppose, will soon be making their appearance at home after the sacrifice. But why are such a number of people coming this way? I wonder what they are bringing? He, too, in the scarf, that's following at a distance, who is he, I wonder? He is not an &AElig;tolian.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We greet you, Lycus. Although against our will, we give you this salutation, and although in a very moderate degree do we entertain good wishes for procurers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> May you all be fortunate--a thing that I know for certain you neither will be, nor will Fortune permit it so to be.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> That is a treasure hoarded in the tongues of fools, to deem it gainful to speak amiss to their superiors.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> He who knows not the road by which to arrive at the sea, him it befits to seek a river as his own companion. I know not the way of speaking abusively to you. Now you are the rivers to me; you I'm resolved to follow. If you speak blessings, along your banks I'll follow you; if you utter curses, along your track I'll go.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> To do good to the bad is a danger just as great as to do bad to the good.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> But why? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> You shall learn. If you do any good to the bad, the benefit is lost: if you do any bad to the good, it lasts for a length of time.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Cleverly said! But what does that matter to me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Because for the sake of your own well-doing we came hither, although in a very moderate degree do we entertain good wishes for procurers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> If you bring anything that's good, I give you thanks.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Of our own, we neither bring nor give you anything that's good, nor do we promise you, nor, in fact, do we wish to give it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I' faith, I do believe yon; such is your kindly feeling. But what now do you wish?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <stage>(pointing to COLLYBISCUS)</stage> This person in the scarf, whom you see, with him Mars is angered.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside, to himself</stage>. <hi rend="ital">May he be</hi> so indeed with your own heads!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We are now bringing him here, Lycus, to you, for tearing asunder<milestone n="645" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">For tearing asunder</lemma>:  "Ad diripiendum." This expression is purposely used, as being susceptible of a double meaning. It may either mean "for you to plunder," or "to plunder you." In the use of the word "dirip o," "to tear to pieces," allusion is made to the wolfish name of Lycus.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside, to himself</stage>. This huntsman, <hi rend="ital">myself,</hi> will be going home to-day with some spoil; the dogs are cleverly driving Lycus into the toils.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Who is this person? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We really don't know who he is, except that some time since, after daybreak, when we went down to the harbour, at the same moment we saw him landing from a merchant-ship. Disembarking, he came up to us at once--he saluted us; we answered him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. The artful fellows! how cleverly they do enter upon the plot!</p>
<p><hi rend="ital">LYC.</hi> What after that? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Then he joined in discourse with us: he said that he was a foreigner, unacquainted with this city: that he wanted a convenient place to be found here, for him to indulge his appetite. We brought the man to you; if the Gods are favourable to you, it's an opportunity for you to ply your trade.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Is he eager to that degree?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> He has got gold. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. That booty is mine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> He wishes to drink <hi rend="ital">and</hi> wench.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'll find him a nice place.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> But still he wants to be quite private, in a quiet way, that no persons may know it, and that there may be no overlookers; for he has been a soldier in Sparta, as, indeed, he himself has told us, with King Attalus<milestone n="663" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">With King Attalus</lemma>:  This is said merely for its absurdity; as Attalus was king, not of Sparta, but of Pergamus in Asia Minor</note>; from there he fled hither, when the town was surrendered.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. Very clever that, about the soldier! about Sparta, most capital!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>in a low voice</stage>. May the Gods and Goddesses bestow many blessings on you, for having given me kindly information, and finding me a choice prey.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Aye, <hi rend="ital">and,</hi> as he himself has told us, that you may receive him the better, he has brought three hundred Philippean pieces as a provision.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'm a king if I can to-day entice this man to my house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Nay but, he really is your own.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> By my troth, prithee, do persuade him to take up his abode at my house, <hi rend="ital">as</hi> the best lodging.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> It befit us neither to persuade nor to dissuade a person who is a foreigner; you'll transact your own business, if you are prudent. We have brought the ringdove for you, even to the trapping-ground; now it's better for yourself to catch him, if you wish him to be caught. <stage>They move as if going.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Are you going now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to the ASSISTANTS</stage>. What about the matters that I commissioned you upon, strangers?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to LYCUS</stage>. It's better for you, young sir, to speak to him about your own concerns; he's clever in those matters which you are enquiring about.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. <hi rend="ital">But,</hi> for my part, I could like you to see when I deliver him the gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. At a distance there we shall be witnesses of that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to the ASSISTANTS</stage>. You've given me kind assistance. <stage>The ASSISTANTS <hi rend="ital">go out of sight.</hi></stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside, so as to be heard</stage>. The profit comes to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>aside, to himself</stage>. <hi rend="ital">Age,</hi> just so, indeed, the way that the ass kicks<milestone n="683" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The way that the ass kicks</lemma>:  Taubmann says that this means that as the ass kicks away from himself, so the gain will go from Lycus, not to him.</note> with his heels.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'll speak the fellow fairly. <stage>To COLLYBISCUS.</stage> A stranger salutes a stranger; I'm glad that you have arrived in safety.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> May the Deities grant you many blessings, since you wish me well.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> They say that you are in search of a lodging.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> I am in search. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> So those persons told me, who left me just now, that you are in search of one that is <hi rend="ital">free</hi> from flies.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> By no means in the world. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Why so?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Because if I had been looking for a retreat from the flies<milestone n="690" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A retreat from the flies</lemma>:  Under this name he refers to envious and mquisitive persons and Parasites.</note>, on arriving here I should have straightway gone to gaol. I'm in search of this kind of lodging, where I may be treated more delicately than the eyes of King Antiochus<milestone n="693" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The eyes of King Antiochus</lemma>:  This is probably not to be taken literally as, according to Suidas, the chief ministers of Antiochus were thus called. Apuleius says that the ministers of the King of Persia were called his "eyes" and "ears."</note> are in the habit of being treated.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Upon my faith, for sure, I can provide you a charming one, if, indeed, you can put up with yourself being in a charming room, on a couch charmingly laid, a charming damsel cuddling you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> You are in the <hi rend="ital">right</hi> road, Procurer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Where, with Leucadian, Lesbian, Thasian, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> Coan wine<milestone n="698" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And Coan wine</lemma>:  The Chian held the first rank among the wines of Greece, while the Lesbian, Thasian, and Coan. ranked next to it.</note>, toothless with old age<milestone n="699" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Toothlees with old age</lemma>:  Having by age lost all its acidity.</note>, you may soak yourself. There I'll quite drench you with the effusion of unguents. Why many words? I'll cause, when you've bathed, the bathkeeper to set up unguent-shop there. But <stage>speaking confidentially</stage> all these things that I have mentioned let out their services for pay.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Why so?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Because they demand ready money.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Why, upon my faith, you are not more ready to receive than I to give. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Why then follow me in-doors.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Lead me in-doors, then; you've got me devoted <hi rend="ital">to your will.</hi> <stage>The ASSISTANTS come forward.  LYCUS and COLLYBISCUS go apart.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <stage>among themselves</stage>. What if we call Agorastocles hither out of doors, that he himself may be his own witness, past all exception? <stage>They go to the door of AGORASTOCLES <hi rend="ital">and call out, in a loud whisper.</hi></stage> Hallo! you that are to catch the thief, come out quickly, that you yourself may witness him giving the gold to the Procurer.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="4">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="711" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter AGORASTOCLES, in haste, from his house.</stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What's the matter? What is it you want, witnesses?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Look to the right hand; your servant is paying gold to the Procurer himself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> <stage>apart to LYCUS</stage>. Come, take this, will you: here are three hundred gold coins, counted out, which are called Philippeans. <stage>Gives him the bay.</stage> With these do you provide for me. I wish these to be spent with all speed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> By my troth, you have found a lavish steward for yourself. Come, let's away in-doors.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> I follow you. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Well, well, walk on; and then we'll talk together about the other matters that remain.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> As for me, I'll tell you about the Spartan affairs.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Why then follow me. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Lead me in-doors; lead me in, you have got me made over to you. <stage>They go into the house of LYCUS.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What do you advise me now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> To be moderate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What if my feelings will not let me be?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <hi rend="ital">Then</hi> be as they will let you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Did you see it, when the Procurer received the money? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We saw it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Did you know that he is my slave?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We knew it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> That it is a thing against the reiterated laws of the people? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We knew it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Well then, all these things I wish you to keep in memory before the Pr&aelig;tor by-and-by, when occasion shall come.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We remember them. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What if, while the matter has so recently happened, I knock at the door?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> I think <hi rend="ital">you ought.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If I do knock, he won't open it<milestone n="729" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">He won't open it</lemma>:  A note of interrogation seems out of place after "recludet."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> <hi rend="ital">Then</hi> break the pannel<milestone n="729" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Break the pannel</lemma>:  "Panem frangite" Literally, "break the bread," meaning the "pannel." He plays upon the resemblance of the verb "pulto," "to knock," and "puls," "pottage."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If the Procurer comes out, do you think I ought to enquire of the fellow whether my slave has come to him or not?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Why not?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> With two hundred golden Philippean pieces?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Why not?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Then the Procurer will be going astray at once.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> About what matter? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you ask? Because a less sum will be named by one hundred pieces.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> You judge rightly. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He'll think that some other person is being looked after.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> No doubt. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He'll be denying it at once.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> On his oath even. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> The fellow will involve himself in the guilt of theft----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Beyond a doubt, it certainly is so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Of however much it is that shall have been brough to him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Why not? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Jupiter confound you<milestone n="739" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Jupiter confound you</lemma>:  For their repeated and tiresome answers of "quippini?" "why not?"</note>!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Why not your own self? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>going towards the door of LYCUS</stage>. I'll go and knock at this door.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Even so. Why not? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> It's time to be quiet, for the door makes a noise. I see the Procurer Lycus coming out of doors; come this way, pray!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> Why not? But, if you please, cover up our heads, that the Procurer mayn't know us, who have been his decoyers<milestone n="745" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">His decoyers</lemma>:  "Illices." "Illex" was a bird-call, quail-pipe, or decoy used by fowlers for catching birds.</note> into so great a calamity. <stage>He throws the lappets of their garments over their heads.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="5">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="746" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYCUS, from his house.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. Let all soothsayers go hang themselves now at once. Why should I believe them in future, as to what they say? For they, just now at the sacrifice, told me that evil and the greatest disaster was portended to me. I have since then amplified my fortune with profit.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>accosting him</stage>. Save you, Procurer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> May the Gods bless you, Agorastocles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You now salute me more kindly than hitherto.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> A calm has come, as though to a ship at sea. Just as the wind is, to that quarter is the sail shifted.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> May those ladies be well in your house, to whom I wish it, but to yourself I do not wish it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> They are well, as you desire; not for you, though.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Send your Adelphasium to my house, to-day, please, upon this celebrated and famous festival, the Aphrodisia.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Have you been breakfasting on a hot breakfast today? Tell me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why so? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Because now you are <hi rend="ital">only</hi> cooling your mouth<milestone n="760" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Cooling your mouth</lemma>:  Because in opening the mouth, the air tends to cool it</note>, when you ask me.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Attend to this, Procurer, will you; I've heard that my slave is at your house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> At my house? You'll find that has never been the fact.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You lie; for he has come to your house, and carried off some gold there. Word has been brought me to that effect, by persons I fully believe. <stage>Pointing to the ASSISTANTS.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> You are an artful fellow: you've come to entrap me with <hi rend="ital">your</hi> witnesses. There's no one of your people in my house, nor anything of yours.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>turning round to the ASSISTANTS</stage>. Remember that, assistants.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> We will remember it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>laughing</stage>. Ha, ha, ha! I now understand how it is, I've this instant seen through it. These persons, who a short time since introduced that Spartan stranger to me, their brain is now fired at it, because I'm going to make a gain of these three hundred Philippean pieces; now, because they knew that this person was an enemy of mine, they have set him on to say that his slave, together with his gold, is in my house. It's a planned contrivance for them to deprive me of it, and to divide it among themselves. They are wanting to get away the lamb from the wolf<milestone n="776" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Lamb from the wolf</lemma>:  In allusion to his own name.</note>. They are wasting their pains.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What, do you deny that either the gold or my slave is at your house?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I do deny it; and, if it's of any use, I make myself hoarse with denying it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> You are undone, Procurer; for that person whom we told you was a Spartan, is his bailiff; who brought you just now the three hundred Philippean pieces; and that same gold, too, is in his purse.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>shaking his fist at them</stage>. Woe unto you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> That, indeed, is close at hand for yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Come, you hang-dog, give up the purse this instant. You are clearly a thief; caught by me in the fact. <stage>(To the ADVOCATI.)</stage> By my troth, I do beg of you, lend me your aid, so as to see me bring my slave out of his house. <stage>He goes into the PROCURER'S <hi rend="ital">house.</hi></stage>
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I' faith, I'm now undone for certain, beyond a doubt! This has been done on purpose that a snare might be laid for me. But why do I hesitate to betake me hence to utter perdition, before I'm dragged off to the Pr&aelig;tor by the throat? Alas! what soothsayers I've been having for my diviners, who, if they promise anything that's fair, it comes to pass but slowly; that which they promise as unfortunate, comes directly. Now I'll be off: I'll consult my friends in what way--they deem it best in especial for me to hang myself. <stage>(Exit.)</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="6">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="796" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter AGORASTOCLES, from the house of LYCUS, driving out COLLYBISCUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Be off you, get out you, that the witnesses may see you coining out from here. Isn't this my servant? <stage>To the ASSISTANTS.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> I' faith, I really am, Agorastocles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> How now, villanous Procurer? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> He, with whom you have the dispute, has made off.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I hope he's gone hence to utter perdition.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> It's proper that we should wish the same.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> To-morrow I'll bring my action against the fellow.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> Anything further with me----?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You may go; put on your own dress.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>COLLYBISCUS</speaker><p> It wasn't for nothing that I turned soldier. I made a little booty in-doors. While the household of the Procurer was asleep, I got myself well filled with the entrails. I'll be off from here in-doors.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to the ASSISTANTS</stage>. 'Twas kindly done by you. Assistants, you have lent me your good services. To-morrow morning I beg you'll meet me at the court of justice. <stage>To COLLYBISCUS.</stage> Do you follow me in-doors. <stage>To the ASSISTANTS.</stage> To you, farewell!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADVOCATI</speaker><p> And you, farewell! <stage>(AGORASTOCLES goes into his house, followed by COLLYBISCUS.)</stage> This fellow wants a thing that's notoriously unfair; he thinks that we are to serve him at our own expense. But such are all these rich people of ours: if you do anything of service, their thanks are lighter than a feather; if there's any offence, they show vengeance like lead. Let's now go to our houses, if you like, forthwith, since we've effected that for which we lent our services, to ruin this corrupter of our fellow-citizens. <stage>(Exeunt.)</stage>
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="4">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="817" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter MILPHIO.</stage>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'm awaiting in what way my plot is to proceed. I'm bent upon ruining this Procurer, since he torments my afflicted master; but he in his turn beats me, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> strikes me with his fist <hi rend="ital">and</hi> heels. It's a misery to be in the service of one who is in love, especially one who is debarred from <hi rend="ital">the object</hi> which he woos. Heyday! I see Syncerastus, the Procurer's servant, betaking himself from the Temple. I'll listen to what he has to say. <stage>He stands aside.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="823" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter SYNCERASTUS, with some cooking utensils, from the Temple of Venus.</stage>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage> It's quite clear that Gods and men neglect the benefit of him who has a master like a person of such character as I have <hi rend="ital">for a master.</hi> There's not another person anywhere in the world more perjured or more wicked than is my master, nor one so filthy or so defiled with dirt. So may the Gods bless me, I'd rather pass my life either in the stone quarries or at the mill, with my sides hampered with heavy irons, than pass this servitude with a Procurer. What a race this is! What corruptors of men they are! Ye Gods, by our hopes in you, every kind of men you may see there, just as though you had come to Acheron --horse <hi rend="ital">and</hi> foot, a freed-man, a thief, or a runaway, <hi rend="ital">if</hi> you choose, one whipped, chained, <hi rend="ital">or</hi> condemned <hi rend="ital">to slavery.</hi> He who has got <hi rend="ital">money</hi> to pay, whatever sort of person he is--all kinds are taken in; throughout all the house, in consequence, are darkened spots <hi rend="ital">and</hi> hiding-places: drinking <hi rend="ital">and</hi> eating are going on, just as though in a cookshop, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> in no less degree. There may you see epistles written in letters inscribed on pottery<milestone n="837" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Inscribed on pottery</lemma>:  He alludes to the marks denoting the age of wine, which were placed upon the "amphor&aelig;" or "cadi," the earthenware casks. These were stopped tight with wood or cork, made impervious to the atmosphere with pitch (as here mentioned), or with clay, or a composition of gypsum. On the outside the title of the wine was either painted, or inscribed in earthenware letters, which are here alluded to. The date of the vintage was denoted by the names of the Consuls then in office. When the vessels were of glass, small tickets, called "pittacia," were suspended from them stating to a similar effect.</note>, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> sealed with pitch: the names are upon them in letters a cubit long; such a <hi rend="ital">perfect</hi> levy on vintners<milestone n="838" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Levy of vintners</lemma>:  He calls the worthless characters who are skulking in his master's house "vinarii," " vintners," from their love for wine, of which the Procurer seems to be in possession of a choice stock.</note> have we got at our house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Upon my faith, it is quite wonderful, if his master doesn't make him his heir; for really, the way he soliloquizes, he's making a speech over him <hi rend="ital">as though</hi> dead and gone. I'd both like to accost the fellow, and yet I listen to him with extreme delight.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. When I see these things going on, I'm vexed that slaves, purchased at the heaviest price, should at our house be robbed of the savings<milestone n="843" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Robbed of the savings</lemma>:  "Expeculiatas." He alludes to those slaves who, having run away from their masters, are lurking in the Procurer's house, where they spend all their savings (peculium), which, by rights, should go to their masters towards the purchase of their freedom.</note> which ought to go to their masters. But at last nothing is left visible: "badly gotten, badly gone."</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. This man goes on talking quite as though he himself were an honest fellow, when, upon my faith, he himself is able to make worthlessness more worthless.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. Now I'm taking home these vessels from the Temple of Venus, where with his sacrifice my master has not been able to propitiate Venus on her festive day.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Charming Venus!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. But our Courtesans, with their first ictims, appeased Venus in an instant.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> O charming Venus, once again!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> <stage>moving</stage>. Now I'll go home.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>coming forward</stage>. Hallo! Syncerastus!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> <stage>looking around</stage>. Who's calling Syncerastus?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Your friend. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> You don't act like a friend, in causing me delay when I've got a burden.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> But in return for this matter I'll lend you my aid, when you please, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> when you give me your commands. Consider the agreement signed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> If so it is to be, I'll give you my services in this----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> In what way? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Why that, when I'm to have a beating, you yourself may substitute your hide.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Get along with you. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I don't understand what sort of person you are.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'm good for nothing.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Be so to yourself, <hi rend="ital">then.</hi> </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I want you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> But my burden is pressing me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Then, do you set it down, and turn your face to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I'll do <hi rend="ital">so,</hi> although I have no leisure. <stage>Putts down his load.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Save you, Syncerastus. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> O Milphio, may all the Gods and Goddesses favour----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What person, pray? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Neither you, nor me, Milphio, nor my own master, in fact.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Whom are they to favour, then?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Any one else they please; for not one of us is de serving of it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You speak wittily. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> It befits me <hi rend="ital">to do so.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What are you doing? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I'm doing that which, clearly, adulterers don't generally do.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What's that? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Bringing all off in safety<milestone n="863" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">All of in safety</lemma>:  There is an indecent allusion in this passage which is modified in the translation.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> May the Gods confound you and your master!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> May they not confound me. I could make them ruin him, if I chose--ruin my master, did I not fear for myself, Milphio.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What is it? Tell me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> You are a bad one. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I am a bad one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> It goes <hi rend="ital">but</hi> badly with me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <hi rend="ital">Just</hi> tell me, <hi rend="ital">then;</hi> you ought to be in quite other plight. Why is it that it goes badly with you, who have at home in superabundance what to eat, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> what to drink? You don't give a single three-obol piece away to a mistress, and have her for nothing.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> May Jupiter so love me----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I' faith, in the degree that you deserve, to wit.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> How I do long for this family to come to ruin.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> If you long for it, lend your aid.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Without feathers it isn't easy to fly: my wings have got no feathers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Troth, <hi rend="ital">then,</hi> don't pluck out <hi rend="ital">any hairs;</hi> then, in the next two months, your arm-pits will be fit for flying.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Away to utter perdition!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Away yourself, and your master!
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> But, really, if a person knew him well, the fellow might soon be ruined.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why so? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> * * * Just as though you could be silent on any matter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I'll keep the matter more strictly secret for you than that which has been told to a dumb woman.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I could easily bring my mind to believe you there, if I did not know you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Trust me boldly at my own peril.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I shall trust you to my cost, and still I will trust you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Don't you know that your master is a mortal enemy of my master?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I know it. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> By reason of the love affair?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> You are losing all your pains.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why so? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Because you are teaching one that has been taught.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why, then, do you doubt that my master will do a mischief to your master with pleasure, so far as he can do, with his deserving it? Then besides, if you lend some assistance, on that account he'll be able to do it the more easily.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> But I'm afraid of this, Milphio----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What is it that you're afraid of?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> That while I'm preparing the plot against my master, I may be betrayed by yourself. If my master knows that I've been talking to any individual, he'll forthwith be making me from Syncerastus into Brokenlegs<milestone n="886" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Brokenlegs</lemma>:  "Crucifragium;" a word coined for the occasion</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> On my word, never shall any mortal be made the wiser by me; only to my master alone will I tell it; and to him, too, <hi rend="ital">in such a way</hi> that he shall not disclose that this matter originated in yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I shall trust you at my peril, and yet I will trust you. But do you keep this a secret to yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> To Faith <hi rend="ital">herself</hi> it is not more safely confided. Speak out boldly (there's room and opportunity); we are here alone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> If your master chooses to act with caution, he'll prove the ruin of my master.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> How can that be? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Easily.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Then let me be acquainted with this "easily,' that he may know it <hi rend="ital">as well.</hi>
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Because Adelphasium, whom your master dotes on is free by birth.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> In what way? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> In the same way that her other sister Anterastylis is.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> But how am I to believe that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> Because he bought them at Anactorium, when little children, of a Sicilian pirate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> For how much? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> For eighteen min&aelig;.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>with an air of surprise</stage>. These two for eighteen <hi rend="ital">min&aelig;</hi><milestone n="898" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">For eighteen min&oelig;?</lemma>:  He asks this question, as thirty min&aelig; was about the average price for a single slave.</note><hi rend="ital">?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> And their nurse for the third. He, too, who sold them told him that he was selling persons who had been kidnapped: he said that they were free-born, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> from Carthage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Ye Gods, by our hopes in you! you mention a most interesting matter; for my master Agorastocles was born in the same place; he was stolen thence when about six years old; after that, the person who stole him brought him here and sold him to my master; that person adopted him <hi rend="ital">as heir</hi> to his wealth, when he departed this life.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> You mention everything that can render it the more easy; let him assert their freedom, his own countrywomen, in an action on their freedom.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Only do keep silence and hold your tongue.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> He certainly will bring the Procurer to a backgammon, if he gets them away.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Nay but, I'll cause him to be ruined before he moves one foot<milestone n="908" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Moves one foot</lemma>:  "Calcem." By some this word is thought to be used for "calculum," a "chessman," and that reference is made to the use of the word "incitas" in the previous line, which was the mate or backgammon in the game of "duodecim scripta" (somewhat similar to our game of backgammon) and in which " calculi," "pieces" or "chessmen," were used</note>; 'tis so contrived <hi rend="ital">already.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> May the Gods grant it so, that I don't continue the slave of this Procurer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> On the contrary, upon my faith, I'll cause you to be a free man with myself, if the Gods are willing.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> May the Gods grant it so! Do you detain me for anything else, Milphio?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Fare you well, and may happiness attend you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I' faith, that lies in the power of yourself and your master. Farewell, and mind that <hi rend="ital">these</hi> things have been told in secrecy.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> This has not been mentioned <hi rend="ital">even.</hi> Farewell.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> But really it's of no use, unless this is done while it is warm.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> You are right in your advice, and so it shall be done.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> There's excellent material, if you provide an excellent workman.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Can't you hold your tongue?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>SYNCERASTUS</speaker><p> I'll hold my tongue and be off.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> A <hi rend="ital">grand</hi> opportunity you've made for me. <stage>SYNCERASTUS goes into the house of LYCUS.</stage> He's gone from here. The immortal Gods do will my master to be preserved, and this Procurer utterly ruined; a mischief so great is impending upon him. Is it not the fact, before one weapon has been launched, then another presses upon him? I'll go in-doors, that I may recount these matters to my master. For if I were to call him out hither before the house, and, what you've <stage>to the AUDIENCE</stage> just heard, if I were now here to repeat the same, it would be folly. I'd rather in-doors be an annoyance to my master singly, than be <hi rend="ital">so</hi> here to all of you. Immortal Gods, what misfortunes, what great calamities do this day await this Procurer. But now there's no reason why I should delay. This business is resolved upon; no pausing is allowed; for both this must be cleverly managed, which has just now been entrusted to me, and that plan as well which was formed at home must be attended to. If there's any delay, he who sends me a heavy mischance will be acting rightly. Now I'll off in-doors; until my master comes from the Forum, I'll wait at home. <stage>Goes into the house of AGORASTOCLES.</stage>
</p></sp></div2></div1>
<div1 type="act" n="5">
<div2 type="scene" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="930" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter HANNO, followed at a distance by his SERVANTS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. Hyth alonim<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Hyth alonim</lemma>:  These eighteen lines (or, at least, the first ten) are in Punic, the native language of Hanno. The following is the meaning of them, as given by Plautus in the next eleven lines: "I worship the Gods and Goddesses who preside over this city, that I may have come hither with good omen as to this business of mine, on which I have come; and, <hi rend="ital">ye</hi> Gods, <hi rend="ital">lend</hi> me your aid, that you may permit me to find my daughters and the son of my cousin; <hi rend="ital">those</hi> who were stolen away from me, and his son from my cousin. But here lived formerly my guest Antidamas. They say that he has done that which he was doomed to do. They say that his son Agorastocles lives here. To him am I carrying with me this token of hospitality. He has been pointed as living in this neighbourhood. I'll make enquiry of these who are coming hither out of doors." The learned Bochart, in his Phaleg, considers that the first ten lines are Punic, and that the other eight are, possibly, Lybic, of which the sense had been previously given in Punic; and, in fact, he quite despaired of translating them His translation of the first ten very nearly agrees with that given by Plautus himself. Samuel Petit, in his Miscellanea, considers the whole to be Hebrew, and translates his version (which consists of sixteen lines) as follows: 1. Give ear and attend, O Gods and Goddesses, under whose protection are the men of this city. 2. Receive as acceptable my prayers and my integrity. TwO daughters did I beget, my strength. 3. Urged on by fate, I caused them on each feast-day of the Gods to go to the gardens. 4. With much rejoicing, and on the day of song, there was a void. 5. The girls, being stolen, forsook me. Whither shall I go, pacing all chambers? 6. Where is he who bore them away? that I may remove the helplessness of my sorrow which he produces for me like fruit, in being the father of, and rearing, children. 7. They have said that here, assuredly, Agorastocles lives. 8. I have a token of hospitality, the likeness of Saturn (I'm carrying it), 9. Between us. May there be some end for my journey, that rest at last may be afforded to my integrity. 10. So that alone and wretched and afflicted I may not wander to and fro but rather that I may meet with my children, and pay my vows and oblations 11. To the Gods and Goddesses whom I've invoked as my advisers and assistants, 12. To purify my house from the griefs with which I was affected when I praised them. But they heard not my words, and I am most afflicted and am despondent in mind. 13. O my hope, come hither, and whatever troubles await me, cause me to endure them. Take courage from the truth of oracles, and of the responses of the God <foreign lang="greek">Ta=v,</foreign> from divinations, and forewarnings, and prodigies. 14. Be thou speedily fulfilled; arouse thyself and pray. Would that they could hear: grief would depart from a devout parent, and I should recognize Aristocles, my brother's son. 15. Attentively hear this lamentation, O God, my power, make haste to the truth of thy promise of my exaltation, O God, and my evil odours shall cease. 16. Lo!  from henceforth will I to the best of my means show honor, sacrificing spelt to all the Gods, and singing praises!!!</note> vualonuth sicorathi si ma com sith, Chi mach chumyth mumys tyal mictibariim ischi, Lipho canet luth bynuthi ad &aelig;din bynuthii. Birnarob syllo homalonin uby misyrthoho Bythym mothym noctothii velech Antidasmachon. Yssidele berim thyfel yth chylys chon, tern, lyphul Uth bynim ysdibut thinno cuth ru Agorastocles Ythe manet ihy * * chyrs&aelig; lycoch sith naso Byuni id chil luhili gerbylim lasibit thym Bodyalyth herayn nyn nuys lym moncoth lusim. [Exalonim volanus succuratim mistim Atticum esse Concubitum a bello cutim beant lalacant chona Enus es huiec silec panesse Athidamascon Alem * * induberte felono * * buthume Celtum comucro lueni, at enim avoso uber Bent hyach Aristoclem et se te aneche nasoctelia Elicos alemus [in] duberter mi comps vespiti Aodeanee lictor bodes jussum limnicolus.]</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="2">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="961" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter AGORASTOCLES, from his house, followed by MILPHIO.</stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>in a loud voice</stage>. Do you say, Milphio, that Syncerastus told you that both of these women were freeborn, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> stolen away from Carthage?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I do say so; and if you were willing to act wisely, you'd at once assert their liberty by an action on their freedom. For it's a disgrace to you for you to allow your own country-people to be slaves before your eyes, who were free women at home.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>overhearing, apart</stage>. O ye immortal Gods, I do entreat your aid! What speech is this that my ears devour! Surely the words of these persons are <hi rend="ital">made of</hi> chalk; how have they cleansed away all the dark spots <hi rend="ital">of woe</hi> from me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If you've got witnesses of this matter, I'll do as you bid me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why <hi rend="ital">speak</hi> you to me about witnesses? Why don't you stoutly insist upon it? Some way or other, Fortune will be your assistant.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> It's much more easy to begin a thing than to bring it about.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>catching sight of HANNO, attended by his SERVANTS</stage>. But what bird is this<milestone n="975" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">What bird is this</lemma>:  The "tunica," or "garment," which Hanno is wearing, has long sleeves, or "manic&aelig;," which causes Milphio to ask if he is a bird, from their resemblance to wings.</note>, pray, that's coming hither with the tunic on? Is he from the baths<milestone n="976" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">From the baths</lemma>:  He alludes to the practice of thieves making off with the cloaks of persons while bathing at the public baths.</note>, I wonder, enveloped in his cloak? I' faith, the countenance is surely Carthaginian. The man's a Gugga<milestone n="977" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A Gugga</lemma>:  Probably a nickname for an African, in ommon use it Rome.</note>. I' faith, he certainly has got some ancient and antiquated servants.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> How do you know? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Don't you see the fellows following, loaded with luggage? And, as I fancy, they've got no fingers on their hands.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why so?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Why, because they go with their rings in their ears<milestone n="981" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Rings in their ears</lemma>:  The Carthaginians, no doubt, borrowed this custom from the Syrians and Ph&oelig;nicians, with whom, as also with the Jews, it was prevalent.</note>. I'll approach them, and address them in the Punic language: if they answer, I'll continue to speak in the Punic tongue if not, then I'll adapt my language to their usage. How say you, do you still remember anything of the Punic language?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Nothing at all, i' faith; for tell me, how could I know, who was but six years old when I was stolen away from Carthage?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. O ye immortal Gods! very many freeborn children have been lost from Carthage after this manner.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> How say you? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What do you want?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Should you like me to address this person in the Punic tongue?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you understand it? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> No Punic man this day is a better Punic than I.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Go and address him, as to what he wants, why he's come, who he is, of what country, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> whence he comes. Don't be sparing <hi rend="ital">of your questions.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>addressing HANNO and his SERVANTS.</stage>Avo! <milestone n="994" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Avo</lemma>:  "Hail."Milphio's knowledge of the Punic dialect was probably but limited, though in the sequel it appears that he does know something of it. The translation of these Punic expressions is from Warner's Translation, where the Punic is given in a form somewhat different from that found in the modern editions of the text.</note>  Of what country are you, or from what city?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Hanno Muthumballe bacha&euml;dreanech.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What does he say?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He says that he is Hanno from Carthage, a Carthaginian, son of Muthumbal.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HAN. Avo! MIL.</speaker><p> He salutes us.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Donni<milestone n="998" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Donni</lemma>:  "My masters." Milphio says he is talking about "gifts," from the resemblance of the word to the Latin " doni," the genitive case of "donum " "a gift."</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He intends to present you with some " donation" out of this; what, I don't know. Don't you hear him promise?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Salute him again in Punic, in my name.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>to HANNO</stage>. "Avo donni" he tells me <hi rend="ital">to say</hi> to you in his name. <stage>Pointing to AGORASTOCLES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Mehar bocca<milestone n="1002" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Mehar bocca</lemma>:  This passage has been rendered, "Oh! what a son of tears!" Milphio says he is talking about his "bucca," or "cheek," being in pain. An attempt has been made in the Translation to preserve in some slight degree the resemblance.</note>! </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Be that for yourself rather than me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What does he say? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He declares that his "box" for his teeth is painful. Perhaps he takes us to be doctors.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If it is so, tell him that we are not; I don't wish a stranger to be mistaken.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>to HANNO</stage>. Hear you. Rufen nuco istam<milestone n="1006" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Rufen nuco istam</lemma>:  "We are no doctors."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> This is my wish, that in fact everything should be explained to him just as it is. Ask him whether he has need of anything.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>to HANNO</stage>. You who have got no girdle<milestone n="1008" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Got no girdle</lemma>:  The Carthaginian tunic flowed loose, and was not fastened with a girdle. Milphio perhaps alludes to his being without a purse, which was generally supported by the girdle, and without which he might think that a stranger had no business in such a wealthy city as Calydon.</note>, why have you come to this city, or what is it you seek?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Muphursa<milestone n="1010" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Muphursa</lemma>:  "Open."</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What is it he says?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Moin lechianna<milestone n="1010" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Moin lechianna</lemma>:  I beg an entrance for Saturn. Milphio plays upon the very slight resemblance of "muphursa" to "mures," "mice." Under the name of "African mice," he probably alludes to "panthers" or "leopards," which had perhaps been recently shown by the &AElig;diles, for the first time.</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why has he come?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Don't you hear? He declares that he is wishful to give African mice to the &AElig;diles as a show at the games.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Lalech lachananim liminichot<milestone n="1013" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Lalech lachananim liminichot</lemma>:  "The messenger who asks a safe abode and kind endurance here."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What does he say now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He says he has brought latchets, water- channels<milestone n="1014" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Latchets, water-channels</lemma>:  Milphio plays upon the resemblance of the words "lalech lachananim," to "ligulos canales," which (if the reading is correct) will mean shoestrings and water-pipes--perfect nousense.</note>, and nuts; he's now begging that you'll lend him your assistance in having them sold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He is a merchant, I suppose?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Is amar binam<milestone n="1016" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Is amar binam</lemma>:  "Us unarmed."</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What is it <hi rend="ital">he says?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Palum erga dectha<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Palum erga dectha</lemma>:  "Naked men."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Milphio, what is he saying now?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He says that he has got spades and forks<milestone n="1018" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Spades and forks</lemma>:  Milphio says he is speaking of "palas" and "mergas," "spades" and "pitchforks," by reason of the resemblance in the sound.</note> given him for sale, for digging the garden and reaping the corn.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What <hi rend="ital">is</hi> that to me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He wishes you to be informed <hi rend="ital">of it,</hi> so that you mayn't suppose that he has taken anything secretly <hi rend="ital">and</hi> by stealth. He has really, I do believe, been sent here to your harvesting.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Muphonium sucoraim<milestone n="1023" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Muphonium sucoraim</lemma>:  "'Tis on account of your Deities before invoked.</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> So there! do take care, please, how you do what he's begging of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What is he saying, or what is he begging? Explain it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> For you to order him to be placed beneath a hurdle<milestone n="1025" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Beneath a hurdle</lemma>:  Milphio says he is speaking of "crates," "a hurdle." This mode of stoning to death was practised among the Carthaginians.</note>, and for many stones to be heaped upon it, so as to put him to death.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Gunebel balsamen ierasan!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Tell me what it is that he's saying.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I' faith, now I really don't at all know.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>speaking in their own language</stage>. But that you may know, now from this moment henceforth will I speak Latin. <stage>To MILPHIO.</stage> Upon my faith, you must be a worthless and bad servant, to be laughing at a person, a foreigner and a stranger.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> But, i' faith, at yourself a person that's both a swindler and a cheat, who have come here to take us in, you half-and-half Lybian, you double-tongue, just like a crawling reptile.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to MILPHIO</stage>. Away hence with your abusiveness! do restrain your tongue. You'll keep it from uttering abuse, if you are prudent; I don't want you to be speaking harshly to my kinsmen. I was born at Carthage; do you remember that.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> O my fellow-countryman, greetings to you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And you, troth, whoever you are; and if you have need of anything, pray mention it, and command me for the sake of our common country.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I return you thanks; but I've got a place of entertainment here; I'm in search of the son of Antidamas; do point me out Agorastocles, if you know him. Do you know any young man here <hi rend="ital">named</hi> Agorastocles?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If, indeed, you are in search of the adopted son of Antidamas, I am the very person whom you are in search of.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>starting</stage>. Hah! what's that I hear?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> That I am the son of Antidamas.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> If so it is, if you would like to compare the token of hospitality<milestone n="1047" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Token of hospitality</lemma>:  As to the "tessera" of hospitality, see the Cistellaria l. 240, and the Note to the passage.</note>, see here, I've brought it. <stage>Shows him the ticket.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Come then, show it here. <stage>He takes it in his hand, and looks at it.</stage> It is exactly true; for I've got <hi rend="ital">the counterpart</hi> at home.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> O my host, hail to you right earnestly; for it was your father, then, Antidamas, that was my own and my father's guest; this was my token of hospitality with him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Then here at my house shall hospitality be shown you; for I don't reject <hi rend="ital">either</hi> Hospitality or Carthage, from which I sprang.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> May the Gods grant you all you may desire. How say you? How could it happen that you were born at Carthage, but had a father of &AElig;tolia here?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I was stolen away from there; this Antidamas, your guest, bought me, and adopted me as his son.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> He himself, likewise, was adopted by Demarchus, But about him I say no more, and return to you. Tell me, de you at all remember the names of your parents?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I remember my father and my mother's <hi rend="ital">name.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Repeat them, then, to me, <hi rend="ital">to see</hi> if I know them, perchance, or if they are relatives of mine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Ampsigura was my mother, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> Iachon my father.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I could wish that your father and mother were alive.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Are they dead?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> So it is, <hi rend="ital">a thing</hi> which I bore with much grief; for your mother Ampsigura was my cousin-german; your father--he was my uncle's son, and when he died he made me his heir; of whom being deprived by death, I am greatly affected. But if it is the fact that you <hi rend="ital">really</hi> are the son of Sachon, there ought to be a mark upon your left hand, a bite which an ape gave you when a child, playing <hi rend="ital">with it.</hi> Show <hi rend="ital">it,</hi> that I may look at it; open <hi rend="ital">your hand.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>opening his hand.</stage> Look, if you like; see, there it is. My kinsman, welcome to you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> And welcome to you, Agorastocles! I seem to myself to be born again, in having found you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> By my troth, I'm delighted that this matter has fallen out <hi rend="ital">so</hi> happily foryou. <stage>To HANNO.</stage> And would you decline to take advice?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Really, I should wish <hi rend="ital">to be advised.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> His father's property ought to be restored to the son; it's fair that he should have the property which his father possessed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I wish no otherwise; everything shall be restored. I'll give his own property to him all safe, when he comes there.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Take care and restore it, will you, even though he should live here still.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Nay but, he shall have my own as well, if anything should happen to me<milestone n="1085" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Anything should happen to me</lemma>:  An Euphemism to avert all omen.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> A pleasant project has just now come into my mind,</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> What's that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> There's need of your assistance.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Tell me what you wish. Really, you shall have my services just as you please. What is the business?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Can you act the cheat?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Towards an enemy, I can; to a friend, it would be <hi rend="ital">mere</hi> folly.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I' faith, it is an enemy of his. <stage>Pointing at AGORASTOCLES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I could do him a mischief with pleasure.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He's in love with a person who belongs to a Procurer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I deem that he acts discreetly.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> This Procurer lives close at hand.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I could do him a mischief with pleasure.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He has two slave girls, courtesans, sisters; one of these he is desperately in love with, nor has he ever taker any liberties with her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> It's an unhappy kind of passion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> The Procurer plays upon him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> He's enhancing his own profits thereby.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He wishes to do him an evil turn.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> He's right, if he does do it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Now I adopt this plan, and prepare this contrivance, that we should. cite you; you are to affirm that they are your daughters, and that they were stolen when little from Carthage, and to maintain the cause of both in an action on their freedom, as though they were both your own daughters. Do you understand?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> On my faith, I do understand; for I likewise did have two daughters who were stolen away when little children, together with their nurse.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Upon my word, you do feign it cleverly. At the very commencement this amuses me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>aside, weeping</stage>. Much more, i' troth, than I could wish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>aside to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. Dear me! a subtle person, upon my word, artful and knowing, both tricky and crafty! How he does whimper, in order that with his gestures he may effect this all the more easily. Even myself, now, the master-workman, does he excel in skill.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> But their nurse<milestone n="1111" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">But their nurse</lemma>:  It did not escape the accurate Schmieder that the fact has not been hitherto communicated to Hanno that the damsels had a nurse who was stolen. This, then, is either an oversight of Plautus, or he must mean that Hanno thinks he has asked the question, and has received an answer in the affirmative.</note>, of what appearance was she? Tell me. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Of stature not tall, of a dusky complexion<milestone n="1112" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Of a dusky complexion</lemma>:  "Aquilo." "Of he hue of deep water."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> 'Tis the very person. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Of agreable form, with a <hi rend="ital">small</hi> mouth, and very dark eyes.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I' faith, you really have depicted her form exactly in your words.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Should you like to see her?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I'd rather <hi rend="ital">see</hi> my daughters. Still, go and call her out of doors. If they are my daughters, if she is their nurse, she'll recognize me at once.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> <stage>knocking at the door of the PROCURER'S <hi rend="ital">house</hi></stage>. Hallo there! is there any one here? Tell Giddeneme to come out of doors; there's a person wants to see her.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="3">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1120" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter GIDDENEME and a BOY, from the house.</stage>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> Who is it that knocks?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> One that's a near acquaintance of yours.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> What do you want?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Come now <stage>pointing to HANNO</stage>, do you know that person in the tunic, who it is?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> Why, whom do I behold? O supreme Jupiter! this sure is my master, the father of my foster-children, Hanno, the Carthaginian!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Now, do see the cunning <hi rend="ital">hussey</hi> this Carthaginian is really a clever juggler; he has brought all over to his own opinion.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> <stage>running up to HANNO</stage>. O my master! welcome to you, Hanno! most unhoped for by myself and your daughters, welcome to you! But look you, don't be wondering, or gazing <hi rend="ital">so</hi> intently upon me. Don't you know Giddeneme, your female slave?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I know <hi rend="ital">her.</hi> But where are my daughters? That I'm longing to know.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> At the Temple of Venus<milestone n="1113" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Temple of Venus</lemma>:  Venus was the tutelar Divinity of Calydon.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> What are they doing there? Tell me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> To-day is the Aphrodisia, the festive day of Venus! they have gone <hi rend="ital">there</hi> to entreat the Goddess to be propitious to them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> I' faith, they've fully prevailed, I'm sure, inasmuch as he has arrived here.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>aside to GIDDENEME</stage>. How now, are these his daughters?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> Just as you say. <stage>To HANNO.</stage> Your kindness has clearly come to our rescue, in your having arrived here to-day at the very time; for this day their names were to have been clanged<milestone n="1139" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Names were to have been changed</lemma>:  The "profess&aelig;," or "courtesans," at. Rome, were registered by the &AElig;diles, and usually adopted some other than their family name for the purposes of their calling.</note>, and they were to have made a livelihood, disgraceful to their station, by their persons.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>A BOY.</speaker><p> Haudones illi<milestone n="1141" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Haudones illi</lemma>:  Shall I not bid him welcome?</note>. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> Havon bene si illi, in mustine. Me ipsi et eneste dum et alamna cestinum<milestone n="1142" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Alamna cestinum</lemma>:  "Child, remember that they are at the Festival of Venus. The time is not proper as yet. Hold your peace at present, and keep the Captain in ignorance of this."</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What is it they are saying among themselves? Tell me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> He's saluting his mother, and she this her son.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Hold your peace, and let alone the woman's gear.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> What gear is that?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Loud talking without limit. <stage>To MILPHIO.</stage> Do you lead these people in-doors <stage>pointing to his SERVANTS</stage>, and bid this nurse to come away together with you to your house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to MILPHIO</stage>. Do as he requests.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> <stage>to HANNO</stage>. But who's to point them out to you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I <hi rend="ital">will,</hi> right skilfully. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>GIDDENEME</speaker><p> I'll go away then.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'd only rather that you would do <hi rend="ital">so,</hi> than say <hi rend="ital">so.</hi> <stage>She goes into the house of AGORASTOCLES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Upon my faith, I do think that this day the very thing that I said by way of joke will be coming to pass both soberly and seriously, that these will be discovered to-day to be his daughters.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Troth, that very thing is quite certain now. Do you, Milphio, take them <stage>pointing to the SERVANTS</stage> in-doors; we'll wait here for these damsels. I wish a dinner to be got ready for my kinsman on his arrival.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>MILPHIO</speaker><p> Lachananim<milestone n="1157" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Lachananim</lemma>:  "Get on with you. and be thankful," according to Petit.</note> you! <stage>aside to the SERVANTS</stage>, whom I'll just now be packing off to the mill-stones, and from there after that to the dungeon and the oaken log<milestone n="1158" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">The oaken log</lemma>:  The "codex" was a heavy log to which slaves were chained, and which they were condemned to drag about with them. It is hard to say why Milphio speaks thus harshly to the servants of Hanno; perhaps however all this is said in a jocular way to show his own importance.</note>. I'll give you reason to praise your treatment here but slightly.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to HANNO</stage>. Do you hear, kinsman? I say, don't you revoke what has been said; promise me your elder daughter in marriage.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Consider the thing as agreed on.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you promise her, then?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I do promise her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> My kinsman, blessings on you! for now you are mine beyond a doubt; now at length shall I converse with her without restraint. Now, kinsman, if you wish to see your daughters, follow me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Why, really, this long time I've been longing for it, and I'll follow you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What if we go and meet them?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> But I'm afraid lest we should pass them on the road. Great Jupiter, do now reinstate my fortunes for me as being certain instead of uncertain!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I trust that my charmer will be my own. But look, I catch sight of them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> What, are these my daughters? How tall from being such little creatures have they now become!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you know how it is? These are Grecian columns<milestone n="1173" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Grecian columns</lemma>:  He seems to allude to their upright way of walking, and the elegance of the Grecian columns, to which he compares them.</note>; they are wont to be erect. <stage>They stand aside.</stage></p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="4">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1174" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter ADELPHASIUM and ANTERBASTYLIS, from the Temple of Venus.</stage>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> 'Twas worth the while, to-day, of him who has a taste for loveliness to afford a feast to his eyes, in coming hither to the Temple this day to see the sights. Upon my faith, I was charmed there to-day with the most elegant offerings of the courtesans, worthy of Venus, the most handsome Goddess; nor did I despise her worship this day; so great an abundance of beauteous objects was there there, each nicely arranged in its own place. The odours of Arabia and of myrrh filled everything. The festive day seemed to be affected with no gloom, Venus, nor did thy Temple; so great a throng of her dependants was there, who had come to Venus of Calydon.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> But certainly, as far indeed as regarded us two, sister, we were all-powerful <hi rend="ital">in our prayers,</hi> beauteous and gainers of her favour; neither were we there held in ridicule by the young men, which, i' faith, sister, happened to all the rest.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I'd rather that it should so appear to other persons, than that you, sister, should praise yourself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Indeed, I trust <hi rend="ital">so.</hi> </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Troth, and <hi rend="ital">so do</hi> I, when I reflect of what breeding we and the others are. We were born in that station, that it befits us to be unblemished by faultiness.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Jupiter, who dost preserve and feed the race of men, through whom we pass this mortal life, in whose hands are the hopes of life in all men, prithee, do grant this day as a prosperous one for my fortunes! Those whom I've missed for many years, and whom when little I lost from their native land, to them restore their liberty, that I may be sure that for an indomitable sense of duty there is a reward.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I'll engage that Jove shall do it all; for to me he is indebted<milestone n="1204" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">To me he is indebted</lemma>:  This impious expression is out of character with Agorastocles, and the latter portion of the line is supposed to be spurious.</note>, and stands in awe of me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Prithee, do hold your peace. <stage>He weeps.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Kinsman, do not weep.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. As it is a pleasure for a man, my sister, if he succeeds in anything, to have the credit of victory, just so did we this day among the rest excel <hi rend="ital">them all</hi> in beauty.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Sister, you are more silly than I could wish. Prithee, do you really think yourself a beauty, if your face has not been besmeared with soot<milestone n="1209" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Besmeared with soot</lemma>:  Douza informs us that it was the custom of the young men to divert themselves at the expense of those courtesans who were not handsome, by daubing their faces with soot and dirt.</note>?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. O kinsman! O kinsman, dearest of all kinsmen<milestone n="1210" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Dearest of all kinsmen</lemma>:  'Patruissime." A word coined by Plautus for the occasion.</note> to me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. What is it, son of my cousin? My son, tell me, what is it you wish?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why, really, I do wish you to attend to this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Why, really, I am attending to it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. Kinsman, kinsman, dearest of all kinsmen to me!
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. What's the matter? AGO. <stage>apart</stage>. She's a clever and a nice girl. How shrewd she is!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. She has her father's disposition in being shrewd.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. How's that? This long time, i' faith, she has surely used up your shrewdness. 'Tis from here <stage>pointing to himself</stage> she now derives her shrewdness; 'tis from here her sense; whatever she does shrewdly, through my love does she act so shrewdly.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> We are not born of that rank, although we are slaves, sister, that it should befit us to do anything which any man may laugh at. Many are the faults of women; but of the many, this one is the greatest, to please themselves too much, and to give their attention too little to pleasing the men.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> It was a very great delight that was portended in our sacrifice of the entrails, sister, and what the soothsayer said about us both----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. I wish he had said something about me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> That we should be free in a few days, in spite of our owner. I don't know why I should hope for that, unless the Gods or our parents do something.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>apart</stage>. 'Twas through confidence in me<milestone n="1226" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Through confidence in me</lemma>:  He surmises that the soothsayer (like most other successful prophets) had learnt the true state of the case beforehand.</note>, kinsman, upon my faith, that the soothsayer promised them liberty, I'm sure <hi rend="ital">of it,</hi> because he knows I'm in love with her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Sister, follow me this way. <stage>Moves as if going.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> I follow. <stage>Moves also.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>stepping forward</stage>. Before you go away<milestone n="1228" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Before you go away</lemma>:  Warner, in his Note on this passage, suggests that Plautus has here forgotten the rules of nature. He says, "It is unnatural to suppose a parent, who has so long been in search of his daughters, should be so near them as to see them, and hear them talk, and not immediately fly into their embraces. And when he does speak to them, he teases and torments them a long time, for no other reason than to divert the Spectators."</note>, I want you both. Unless it's inconvenient, stop.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Who's calling us back?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> One who wishes to do you a kindness.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> There's opportunity for doing it. But who is the person? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> A friend of yours.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> One&gt; who is not an enemy, in fact.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> This is a good man, my love.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I' faith, I should prefer him rather than a bad one.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> If, indeed, friendship must be engaged in, with such a person ought it to be engaged in.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I don't beg for it. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He wishes to do you many services.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Being good <hi rend="ital">yourself</hi> you will be doing good to the good.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I will cause you joy----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> And, i' faith, we pleasure to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> And liberty. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> At that price you'll easily make us your own.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> My kinsman, so may the Gods bless me, if I were Jupiter, upon my faith I'd at once marry her for my wife, and pack Juno out of doors. How quietly did she utter her words, how considerately and becomingly! how modestly did she frame her speech! certainly she is my own!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>apart to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. But how skilfully I accosted her!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Cleverly and becomingly, upon my faith.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Am I still to go on testing them?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Compress it in a few words; the people who are sitting <hi rend="ital">here</hi> are getting thirsty<milestone n="1241" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Sitting here are getting thirsty</lemma>:  He alludes to the Spectators, and means that they must be tired with sitting there and listening to such a long Play.</note>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Well, why don't we proceed to do that which was to be done? <stage>To the WOMEN.</stage> I summon you to justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Seize hold of this one, kinsman, if you are wise. Should you like me to catch hold of her?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Is this person your kinsman, Agorastocles?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I'll soon let you know. Now, by my word, I'll be nicely revenged on you; for I'll make----you my bride.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Come before a court of justice; don't delay!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Summon me as your witness<milestone n="1246" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Summon me as your witness</lemma>:  'Antestare me." See the Note to the Curculio, l. 621.</note>, and take me; I'll be a witness for you; and after that, her <stage>pointing to ADELPHASIUM</stage> will I love and embrace. But 'twas this, indeed, I intended to say--why yes, I did say that which I intended <hi rend="ital">to say.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>to the DAMSELS</stage>. You are lingering. I summon you to justice, unless it is more becoming for you to be dragged <hi rend="ital">thither.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Why do you summon us to justice? What are we in your debt? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He'll tell it there.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Are even my own dogs barking <hi rend="ital">at me?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Then, troth, do you caress me; give me a kiss in place of a piece of meat; present your lips in place of a bone<note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Your lips in place of a bone</lemma>:  The original of this line is somewhat indelicate, and the translation of it has been modified. She expected assistance from Agorastocles, who appears to her to be taking the part of her enemy.</note>: that way I'll render this dog more smooth for you than oil.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Come on, if you are coming. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> What have we done to you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> You are thieves, both of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> What, we, as regards you?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> You, I say. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And I know it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> What theft is this? </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Enquire of him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Because for many years you have been concealing my daughters from me, and, in fact, persons free-born, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> free, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> born of the highest rank.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I' faith, you'll never find that villany to have been committed by us.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Make a bet of a kiss now, if you are not forsworn, which is to give it to the other.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I've nothing to do with you; prithee, get you gone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> But, i' faith, I've got something to do with you; for he is my kinsman; it's necessary for me to be his advocate. And I'll inform him how you are guilty of many a theft, and in what way you have got his daughters <hi rend="ital">as</hi> slaves at your house, whom you know to be free women stolen from their native land.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Where are these, or who are they, prithee?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>aside to HANNO</stage>. They have been teased sufficiently.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. Why not speak out, <hi rend="ital">then?</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>aside</stage>. I' faith, I'm of that opinion, kinsman.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> I'm dreadfully afraid what this business can mean, my sister; so astounded <hi rend="ital">am I,</hi> I stand here without my senses.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Damsels, give <hi rend="ital">me</hi> your attention. In the first place, if it could possibly come to pass, for the Gods not to send upon the innocent what is undeserved, that could I have wished to happen; now for the good the Gods bestow upon me, upon yourselves and upon your nurse<milestone n="1270" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">And upon your nurse</lemma>:  "Matri." This may either mean their own mother, the wife of Hanno, if then living, or their nurse Giddeneme: as "mater" is used in the latter sense by Plautus in the Prologue to the Men&aelig;chmi.</note>, 'tis due that we should give to the Deities our endless thanks, since the immortal Gods approve and reward our piety. You are my daughters, both of you, and this is your relation, Agorastocles, the son of my cousin.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Prithee, are they deluding us with imaginary joys?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Really, so may the Deities preserve me, this is your father. Give <hi rend="ital">him</hi> your hands.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> <stage>embracing him</stage>. Welcome, father! unhoped-for by us, allow us to embrace you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> <stage>embracing him</stage>. Welcome, father! much wished and longed for! We are both your daughters; we both embrace you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Who'll be for embracing me in the next place?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Now am I happy! Now with this delight do I allay the miseries of many a year.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> We hardly seem to believe this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I'll tell you something to make you believe it the more: why, it was your nurse who recognized me first.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> Prithee, where is she?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. She's at his house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to ADELPHASIUM, <hi rend="ital">who is embracing her father</hi></stage>. Pray, why does it please you to clasp his neck so long, before he has betrothed you to me? <hi rend="ital">Dear one,</hi> much longed-for, blessings on you! <stage>He embraces her.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> <stage>struggling</stage>. Do leave off your salutations!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> I will leave off. And you the other one. <stage>To ANTERASTYLIS, <hi rend="ital">whom he embraces.</hi></stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> <stage>struggling</stage>. I don't want that; you torment me to death!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Let us each clasp the other in our arms, than whom is there anything on earth more happy?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Blessings befall the deserving. <stage>Pointing to HANNO.</stage> At last his wishes are realized! O Apelles! O Zeuxis<milestone n="1289" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Apelles! O Zeuxis</lemma>:  Apelles of Cos flourished in the time of Alexander the Great. He was the most celebrated painter of his time. Zeuxis of Heracl&aelig;a flourished about a century before him, and was equally famous as a painter</note> the painter! why did you die too soon? Would that you could paint a subject after this! For I don't care for other <hi rend="ital">common</hi> painters to be treating subjects of this description.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Gods and Goddesses all! I return you deservedly extreme thanks, for having blest me with this gladness so supreme and with these joys so great; as my daughters have returned to me <hi rend="ital">and</hi> into my possession.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> My father, your own piety has clearly come to our aid.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Kinsman, take care and keep it in memory that you've betrothed your elder daughter to me----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I remember it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> The portion, too, that you promised.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="5">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1280" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter ANTHEMONIDES, from the house of LYCUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. If I don't take full revenge for that mina which I gave to the Procurer, then really may the townspeople make a butt of me! This most rascally fellow even brought me to his house to breakfast. He himself went away out of doors, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> left me as his chamberlain<milestone n="1301" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">As his chamberlain</lemma>:  "Atriensi." The duties of this domestic are fully referred to in the Notes to the Asinaria.</note> in the house. When neither the Procurer nor these women came back, nor anything was given me to eat, for the best part of the breakfast I took a pledge<milestone n="1303" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">I took a pledge</lemma>:  It is
 not quite clear what he refers to, but he probably means to say that he has laid hold of something valuable in the Procurer's house, which will, at all events, procure a substitute in part for the prandium" out of which he has been cheated</note>, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> came out of doors. This way I'll pay him. I'll touch up the rascally Procurer in the military way of payment<milestone n="1304" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Military way of payment</lemma>:  By the mention of "&aelig;s militare," some Commentators think that he alludes to his sword, and draws it. He seems to refer, however, to the stipend which the soldiers receive for their services, with full liberty to lay their hands on anything that belongs to the enemy.</note>. He did get hold of a person for him to bamboozle out of a mina of silver! But I wish that my mistress would now come in my way while <hi rend="ital">thus</hi> enraged. Then, by my troth, with my fists I'd make her <hi rend="ital">quite</hi> black all over; I'd cover her so with swarthiness, that she should be much more swarthy than the Egyptians, or <hi rend="ital">than those</hi> who carry the buckets<milestone n="1309" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Carry the buckets</lemma>:  He alludes to the slaves whose duty it was to hold the buckets to the horses in the Circus for them to drink from. Exposure to sun and dust would tend to render them swarthy.</note> at the games in the Circus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> <stage>running to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. Do hold me fast, please, my love; I sadly fear the kites; this is an evil animal--lest perchance he may carry me off, your chick.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> <stage>embracing her FATHER</stage>. I cannot clasp you fast enough, my father!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. I'm delaying. <stage>Looking in his hand.</stage> I can now pretty nearly cater a breakfast for myself with this. <stage>Raising his eyes.</stage> But what's this? How's this? What's this? What's this I see? How now? What means this strange conjunction? What's this coupling together? Who's this fellow with the long skirts, just like a tavern-boy? Do I quite see with my eyes? Isn't this my mistress, Anterastylis? Why, surely it is she. For some time past I've perceived that I'm set at nought. Isn't the girl ashamed to be hugging a tawny fellow in the middle of the street? I faith, I shall give him up forthwith to the executioner to be tortured all over. Surely this is a womanish race<milestone n="1321" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">A womanish race</lemma>:  "Muliersous" generally means "fond of women." It clearly however, in this passage means "womanish," or "womanlike."</note>, with their tunics hanging down to their heels. But I'm determined to accost this African female lover. <stage>To HANNO.</stage> Hallo! you woman, I say, are you not ashamed? What business have you with her, pray? Tell me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Young man, greetings to you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> I don't want <hi rend="ital">them;</hi> that's nothing to you. What business have you to touch her with a finger?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Because I choose. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> You choose?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I say so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Away to utter perdition, you shoe-latchet! What, do you dare to be <hi rend="ital">acting</hi> the lover here, you great toe of a man<milestone n="1328" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">You great toe of a man</lemma>:  From this expression it has been conjectured that Hanno was a man of diminutive stature, and that the Play took its name of P&oelig;nulus, "the little Carthaginian," from that circumstance.</note>, or to be meddling with an object which masculine men are fond of, you skinnea pilchard, you <hi rend="ital">deformed image of</hi> Serapis<milestone n="1330" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Of Serapis</lemma>:  It is not fully known what the meaning of "Sarapis" is, as it occurs nowhere else. It has been conjectured, that, owing to the African features of Hanno, the Captain compares him to the little ugly images of Serapis, which were carried about in harvest-time by the priests of that God, for the purpose of collecting money.</note>, you half-apron, you sheepskin-jacket<milestone n="1331" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">You sheepskin-jacket</lemma>:  This garment, being worn with the wool on, was remarkable for its offensive smell. "Halagoras hama" is supposed to mean the pots of common sea-salt exposed for sale in the market-place.</note>, you pot of <hi rend="ital">stinking</hi> sea-salt; more crammed, too, to boot, with leeks and garlick than the Roman rowers?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Young man, do your jaws or <hi rend="ital">your</hi> teeth itch, that you are annoying this person, or are you in search of a heavy mishap?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Why didn't you use a drum<milestone n="1335" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Use a drum</lemma>:  The priests of Cybele, who were either eunuchs, or persons of effeminate and worthless character, walked in their processions beating a "tympanum." a "drum" or "tambourine." The Captain, by his question, contemptuously implies that Agorastocles is such a character. See the Truer lentus, l. 608, and the Note.</note> while you were saying that? For I take you to be more of an effeminate wretch than a <hi rend="ital">real</hi> man.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you understand what sort of effeminate wretch I am? <stage>Calling aloud.</stage> Servants, come out of doors, bring out some cudgels!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Hark you, if I have said anything in a joke, don't you be for taking it seriously.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Prithee, what pleasure have you, Anthemonides, in speaking rudely to our kinsman and father? For this is our father; he has just now recognized us, and him <hi rend="ital">as</hi> the son of his cousin.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> So may Jupiter kindly bless me, I heartily rejoice that it is so, and I am delighted, if, in fact, any great misfortune befalls this Procurer, and since a fortune awaits you equal to your merits.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> I' faith, he says what's worthy of belief; do believe him, my father. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I do believe him.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And I believe him. But look <stage>pointing</stage>, I espy the Procurer Lycus, the worthy fellow; look, there he is--he's betaking himself homeward.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Who is this?
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> He's which you please, both the Procurer and Lycus. He has been keeping your daughters in servitude, and from myself he has stolen some gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> A pretty fellow for you to be acquainted with!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Let's bring him to justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> By no means. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> For what reason?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Because 'twere better for an action of damages to be brought against him<milestone n="1356" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Action of damages to be brought against him</lemma>:  "Multum dici" has been adopted as the reading, in preference to "multo induci," which seems capable of no translation consistently with sense. The passage may possbly mean that he prefers an action at law to summary proceedings.</note>.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="6">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1338" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>Enter LYCUS.</stage>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to himself</stage>. No one, in my opinion at least, is deceived, who rightly states his case to his friends. But by all my friends the one same thing is agreed upon, that I ought to hang myself, so as not to be adjudged to Agorastocles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>stepping forward</stage>. Procurer, let's away to the court of justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I do entreat you, Agorastocles, that I may be at liberty to hang myself.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I summon you to justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> But what have you to do with me?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> <stage>pointing at his DAUGHTERS</stage>. Because I affirm that both of these are my daughters, free women, and free by birth, who, when little, were kidnapped together with their nurse.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Indeed, I knew that already, and I wondered that no one came to assert their freedom; they really are none of mine, indeed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Procurer, you must come to justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> You are talking about the breakfast; it is owing to you; I'll give it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Twofold <hi rend="ital">compensation</hi> I must have for the theft.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to his neck</stage>. Take it out of this, then.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> And I <hi rend="ital">require</hi> a full satisfaction.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to his neck</stage>. Take out of this whatever you please. ANTH. And I, indeed, a mina of silver.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>pointing to his neck</stage>. Take out of this whatever you please. I'll at once settle the matter for all with my neck, just like a porter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Do you refuse me in any way?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Not a word, in fact.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Go in-doors, then, damsels. But <stage>to HANNO</stage>, my kinsman, betroth me your daughter, as you promised.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I should not venture <hi rend="ital">to do</hi> otherwise.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Kindly farewell! </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And kindly farewell to you!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> <stage>holding up what he has got in his hand</stage>. Procurer, I take this as a pledge with me for my mina.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> By heavens, I am ruined!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Why yes, before very long, when you've come to justice.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Nay but, I own myself your slave. What need of the Pr&aelig;tor have we? But I beseech you that I may be allowed to pay the simple sum<milestone n="1379" unit="TLN line"/><note anchored="yes"><lemma targOrder="U">Pay the simple sum</lemma>:  In lieu of paying double the amount, as he might be forced at law to do, for being an accomplice in the theft.</note>, three hundred Philippeans. I think it can be scraped together; to-morrow I'll have an auction.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> On condition, then, that you shall be in wooden custody at my house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> So be it. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Follow me in-doors, my kinsman, that we may keep this festive day in joyousness, upon his misfortune and our good fortune. <stage>To the AUDIENCE</stage>. Heartily fare you well. To great length have we gone; at last all these misfortunes fall upon the Procurer. Now--that which is the last seasoning for our Play--if it has pleased you, our Comedy asks applause.</p></sp></div2>
<div2 type="scene" n="7">
<milestone n="1" unit="line"/><milestone n="1372" unit="TLN line"/>
<stage>AGORASTOCLES, LYCUS, HANNO, ANTHEMONIDES, ADELPHASIUM, and ANTERASTYLIS.<note anchored="yes">Many of the ancient MSS. contain this additional Scene, which is generally supposed not to have been the composition of Plautus. It is not improbable that at some period the last Scene may have been lost, and that the present one may have been composed to supply its place, as it is evidently not the composition of a person who was aware of the existence of the Scene which precedes it.</note></stage>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> What is it you are about, Captain? Why does it please you to speak rudely to my relative? Don't be surprised that the damsels do follow after him; he has just now discovered that both of them are his own daughters.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>starting</stage>. Hah! what speech was it that reached my ears? Now I am undone! <stage>To AGORASTOCLES.</stage> From what house were these females lost?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> They are Carthaginians.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Then I am ruined. I was always in dread of that, lest some one should recognize them, a <hi rend="ital">thing</hi> which has now come to pass. Woe unto wretched me! My eighteen min&aelig; are lost, I guess, which I paid for them.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> And you yourself are lost, Lycus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Who is this?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Which you please, he's either the Procurer or Lycus. He has been keeping your daughters in servitude, and from myself he has stolen some gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> A pretty fellow for you to be acquainted with!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Procurer, I always deemed you to be avaricious, but they know you to be a thief as well, who know more of you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'll approach him. <stage>He falls on the ground before AGORASTOCLES.</stage> By your knees I do beseech you, and by him <stage>pointing to HANNO</stage>, whom I understand to be your relative; since you are deserving persons, as it befits deserving persons to do, do <hi rend="ital">then</hi> come to the aid of your suppliant! Indeed, already did I know them to be free women, and was waiting for some one to claim their freedom, for really they are none of mine. Then besides, I'll restore your gold that I've got in my house, and I'll make oath that I have done nothing, Agorastocles, with ill intent.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> As it's right for me to do, I shall still consult my own notions. Let go of my knees.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'll let them go, if such is your determination. <stage>He rises from the ground, and retires to a distance.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Hark you! Procurer. </p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> What do you want with a Procurer amid business?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> You to restore me my money before I take you hence to <hi rend="ital">be laid in</hi> fetters.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> May the Gods grant better things!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Even so; you'll be dining away from home. I see Gold, silver, <hi rend="ital">and</hi> your neck, Procurer, the three things are you now owing to me all at once.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> What it befits me to do in this matter, I'm considering with myself. If I should attempt to take vengeance on this <hi rend="ital">fellow,</hi> I shall be engaging in litigation in a strange city. So far as I hear, his disposition and manners, of the nature that they are----</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ADELPHASIUM</speaker><p> My father, do have no dealings with this man, I conjure you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERASTYLIS</speaker><p> Do listen to my sister. Come, put an end to your strife with the rascal.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> Attend to this, will you, Procurer. Although I know that you deserve to come to ruin, I'll not try the matter with you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Nor I, if you restore me my gold; Procurer, when let go from the fetters--you may get thrust into prison.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> What, your old habit still?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Carthaginian, I wish to excuse myself to you. If I have said anything in my passion against the inclination of your feelings, I beg that you will pardon it; and as you have found these daughters <hi rend="ital">of yours,</hi> so may the Deities bless me, it is a pleasure <hi rend="ital">to me.</hi></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I both forgive and believe you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTERLASTYIS</speaker><p> Procurer, do you take care either to find me a mistress, or return me the mina of gold.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> Should you like to have my music-girl?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> I don't care for a music-girl; you don't know which is the greater, their cheeks or their bosoms.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> I'll find one to please you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Mind that,</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>LYCUS</speaker><p> <stage>to AGORASTOCLES</stage>. To-morrow I'll bring back your gold to your house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Take care that you keep that in memory. Captain, follow me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>ANTHEMONIDES</speaker><p> Yes, I'll follow you. <stage>LYCUS goes into his house.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> <stage>to HANNO</stage>. How say you, kinsman? When are you thinking of leaving here for Carthage?--for I'm determined to go together with you.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> As soon as ever I can, that instant I shall go.
</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> It's necessary for you to stop here some days, until I've had an auction.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>HANNO</speaker><p> I'll do just as you wish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>AGORASTOCLES</speaker><p> Come, please, let's be off; let's enjoy ourselves <stage>To the AUDIENCE.</stage> Grant us your applause.]
</p></sp></div2></div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
